Dell Technologies
The internet GPS in the palm of your hand
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA the defense Advanced research projects agency has been a driver
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window Into Darkness
Core
Program manager
Their job
To redefine what is pasa
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host and today I'm pleased to have
With me in the studio linhoss a program manager since 2012 in DARPA's strategic technology
With a background in physics engineering and management
We spent a lot of time at the art of thinking about a world without the global positioning system
Assistant which is all about physics engineering and the management of complex systems
And he thinks about bringing GPS functions
Undersea and two other places where GPS signals cannot now
Ensure
When has become one of the agency's go2guys in a technical area known as
TNT
Which stands for positioning
Navigation
And timing
Thanks for spending time with me today
Well thank you for inviting me
Before we talk about some of your efforts to develop
Plan B for when GPS might not be available or to create
Undersea version of GPS I just interested you I want to find out a little bit
About you your background and maybe something about how that background explains
How you ended up here at DARPA in 2012
Well when I was growing up
I never
Thought about
My grow up I want to be a navigation engineer
That was not something that was at the front of my mind
However when I
Came out of grad school
My first
Job
Was a navigation flight controller
For space shuttle operation
And I fell in love with the Art and Science of navigation
And it's been a Common Thread in my career ever sets exciting entry I mean to be working on the space shuttle
Graham just a little bit more about the
But I was working on the space shuttle program that was before
We had ups and so the navigation
System.of of the
Are the space shuttle used
A variety of sensors
To determine where that
Vehicle was in space
So we are the navigation system was primarily critical on the
Entry portion
Admission that is when it returns from space
To The Landing
Field but also a scent and on orbit operation
And what did you study in grad school
Physics
And then I I quickly learned that
Theoretical physics was not
My forte
But I still love physics so I my graduate degree was in engineering physics
And there's one other thing about your biography of sense that I'm interested in is your name because I believe your
Full first name is
Franklin Co you go buy at Lynn the second syllable for short winners most people who have the name Franklin
We'll go with that for civil Frank so what's up with Lynn
I like to think that my mother has a sense of humor I am a junior
And she did not want to Frank's running around the house
So my father goes by Frank
I go by
It's so that indicates to me that there was a big dose of
Pragmatism in your home address that spilled over into other way you would he work
What's Noah talk about some of your programs I think we'll start with the
Adaptable navigation systems program
As do all programs at DARPA this one goes by an acronym in this case ANS
What intrigues me about this one but I want you to say more about it is that you are
Trying to tap into a huge diversity of signals hear things like signals and cell towers are TV signals that are
Already out there kind of in the constructed environment
But also other kinds of signals in the natural environment the one that does really sticks out for me
Is lightning
Let me stop there and just asked you to tell me in the listener is a little bit about the adaptable navigation
Systems program
Okay ins is actually a portfolio of
Multiple programs
One of those programs on Uranus
It's called Aspen Aspen with short for all source
Positioning in navigate
And IT addresses the topic you you
Reference to we like to think of it as
A developing a navigation
Architecture
An algorithm that can process what we call sensors
Of opportunity that is any sensor that has spatial
Or temporal information
So
Consider an aircraft
Primarily aircraft today
Use GPS
End
Either Standalone mode or they will
Integrate
A GPS receiver with what's called and inertial measurement u
Basically a dead reckoning device
Has sensors in it for work that senses accelerations
And will sense rotational rates and from that you can dead reckon
So the two
GPS and inertial measurement unit combined form a very robust
Solution but
GPS sometimes is not available
And then that system will rely primarily on the IMU
Are the situation under which GPS might be
Become unavailable
Foreground users GPS can become unavailable when
You are in what we call Urban Canyons that is
Idents
Ordinary skyscrapers you think of downtown Chicago
Or downtown
Manhattan where the buildings are at
Obstructing the
Especially in this is all in the context of maintaining very accurate now
Aircraft
Especially military aircraft when they roll over turn upside down now the GPS antenna is pointing to
Is ground
Signals aren't coming from the ground
Okay so we rely on the inertial measurement unit
Do dead reckon until the GPS
Leicester City versus expose
And
Because the GPS signal is so weak
Eye by Design
That it is very easy to
Interfere with
A receivers reception of that City
Okay so actually kind of sets up the problem for us and that Melanie
Get you back to what you were talking about sandwiches
To use some sensors of opportunity out there to
Makeup for whatever what we recognized was that many platforms we have
Have sensors on them
Better providing spatial information
But they're not being used by the navigation system
So the question we asked ourselves
Was
Can we come up with
An algorithm
And an architecture that can be rapidly reconfigure
To use sensors that are already on board
Are platforms to navigate
When GPS is not available
Just as importantly to provide redundancy and hence additional Integrity to the Jeep
PS signals themselves
Cocaine to work through a couple of examples of a kind of sensing signals okay so they might use your want one that we have
Used very successfully
Is imagery
Okay consider aircraft with a camera
Looking at the ground
The Advent of satellite imagery
Think of Google Earth
Are all all those pixels and a Google Earth image
Have an Associated latitude and longitude
And if we can correlate the image
That is
Being observed by the camera on the airplane with
That satellite that what we call a Geo registered satellite image
Frabill to determine
Where that aircraft is
That's part of the
Problem the other part of the problem is not how do I get that into my navigation system
Such that I can continually navigate
And that's what
The Aspen
A program that's where then you you need
That inertial measurement unit in a sense of timing combined with that
Imagery on the ground and you can then start
To keep track of
That where you are now and where you going until
Interesting yet
Button
Foreground users
For example we are being bombarded with radio frequency signals
Where we are sitting right now
But we're not using them for navigation but they have special information in them whether they be
BTV
Signals
Radio signals or if we are outside we would be
Receiving many signals from satellites
And so we call those signals of opportunity and we've shown that you can navigate
Very well with those signal
Drilling a little bit on one of those signals of opportunity
Lightning
How does that fit in a picture that was a very fun signal for us
When lightning strikes
It essentially lights up
The entire
Electromagnetic spectrum from DC to Daylight and Beyond research
Have shown that they're even
X-rays and potentially even gamma rays
Is coming out of a lie
Tremendous amount of energy
For a very short period of time
We're talkin one to several milliseconds
Of duration and time
So
Huge burst of energy
The energy that is in
The spectrum that we call the very low frequency band vlf which is
The Tenkiller region
10 to 20 kilohertz in general
That
Portion of the energy can travel around the world
There's almost like a waveguide right now between the Earth and the ionosphere and then those signals
That is what writer
That is the reason that the waveguide is because
10 kilohertz
Your wavelength
Is now kilometers
1012 15 km
Depending on what exact
The exact freak
Because that there's only a few wavelengths
Between the Earth and the
Bottom of the ionosphere which is depending on the time of day around 80
And you get a wave.
Affect which has
Very low signal attenuation
Cancel the signal
Can be received at very high
Signal
And so the question was
Can we
Navigate with the
So we went outside and put a vlf receiver
On the street or even in in the building you would be picking up
Pens
Of signals per second the the vlf portion of a lightning strike is called a sphere
Short for an atmospheric that's a fairly old term that that's what we call it so you would be receiving
Dozens of spherics
Per second
Answer questions can you navigate
This is amazing to think about that navigating by lightning strikes
You have to know where those lightning strikes are in order for this to to work correct that is absolutely correct and that is
In my opinion one of the hardest
Parts of a lightning navigation system if you will
To detect those
We use a
Einetwork
What we called monitoring station to reference stations
Located around the world
That would
Geo locate those lightning
Yes right and we both seen these on on weather reports where they're showing the lightning strikes from the sky minion minion
Versys have
Lightning detection Network
In place there are commercial products
For getting that information as well yes
Absolutely fascinates let's Segway to another program you're working on which was related to this one
This one is known mercifully in short form as stoic
Sto I see but that actually short
For the long form
Name of the program which is spatial-temporal and orientation information in contested environment
But let's go with store cuz it's easier to say
And this too as a deliverable of a backup UPS of sorts
And it involves a number of interesting sounding components that I hope we can talk about briefly
Two that I mentioned are very low frequency signals which we actually did touch upon already when we were talking about lightning
But another component here
Has the development of optical clocks which rely on quantum mechanical behaviors in atoms
To keep by super
Accurate time and then the clocks are always a part of these kinds of navigation system
We can't go deeply into the Weeds on on these things but
Let's let's try to talk about him a little bit give us a flavor of what Stokes
It's about and what technology we're hoping to develop to make it work
Okay let's talk about the the vlf component
It's interesting to note
That the
First global positioning system was not called
GPS
It was called Omega
It operated back in the from the early 70s
Through the early 90s
And it was a vlf
Broadcast system
And provided Global coverage
With only eight
Transmitters
Located around the world
However it was not accurate
That system generally provided one
To wish
Kilometer levels of positioning accuracy
Whereas GPS is generally below five
So the older Mega System is clearly not accurate for what we now
Depend on today
I from GPS so the primary challenge we have
In-store
For the vlf component
Is
Developing new models
Back can
Accurately replicate
How that vlf signal
Propagates
From a transmitter
To a receiver
I such that we can get our accuracies
To GPS level
In NY the vlf2 very low very good component of the full
Spectrum about it many many choices of frequency bands to use
So you mentioned the waveguide effect
I'm in and we talked about the fact that
Waveguide effect
Has significantly less signal attenuation such that the signal can be received
At longer distances
So in the context of providing a
Backup system to GPS
Oh that has Global range
Clearly we don't want to put a position Beacon if you will
Every few miles around the Earth
So the ability to provide a positioning system with only a few let's say less than
The electrons meters
Is very appealing
Especially when the signals can be received at very high levels
Right in this there's probably pragmatic and cost issues I believe vlf transmitter is rough and very big
So they are
Not only are they very big but they're also very old it's in general
They're using
1950s 1960s technology
And so using
New technology we're looking at ways of making them much smaller
More affordable
And more portable okay and then
Let's talk about the
Clock aspect here in this case Optical clocks
Before we actually talked about this specific
2 quantum mechanical based
Clock technology that you're you're a nurturing here
Just for those who don't know talk a little bit about the role that accurate clock
Play
In systems like GPS another geolocation and navigation
So there is a common phrase used
On the navigation community
Which is thymus position and position is time
That date
All the way back to the
16 hundreds if not sooner in the maritime days when
We navigated
Off of the Sun
When you left the port
Weatherby
And say when you left the port at London
IU wood
Set your clock
At noon
And then as you sailed across
The Atlantic Ocean
You determine how many degrees
Longitude you had traveled
By looking at
The time on your watch on your clock
At the point at which the sun was
Directly overhead and that would you
Correlate
The number of
The hours off of noon your watch that
Watch what your chronometer
Versus
Nunaat
The pat London where you left
So the more accurate Euro and we're confident you could be of your position and determination in the rice acronym
Today's it was very true time as position position is time
With GPS
The same is also true so the key
The GPS
Is indeed the clocks
You're getting a ranging signal off at the GPS satellite
Can you receiver determines rain
You don't measure distance what you are actually measuring is time
How long did it take that signal to travel
From the satellite
To your receiver so the satellite tells you
This signal left my antenna at
Time Warner
You look at your receiver clock
When that signal was received
At time
And time 2 minus time 1 is
The time of travel
Time of travel
Times the speed of light
Gifts test
Netflix that's where the rain comes runs but it all goes back to the
Read speed of light which we know and is constant that sort of
The key here right
O'Brien
Without that
You wouldn't be able to just from a measurement of time
Know what the range
That it that is cracking there are a lot of other things your GPS receiver has to do as well but that's primarily like
It is remarkably complex on sort of every level by any metric you can you can imagine applying to it
So let's move now to 1/3 program this will be the last one I think we talked about this one is known as Poseidon
And that stands for positioning system for deep
Ocean
Navigation so it sounds like you're going for an underwater GPS system
Yes
Bottom Line GPS does not work underwater
Actually you can receive it at very
Shallow depths inches
I'm people have shown that
But that's not relevant to
Where we actually operate we went to
We want to be able to navigate
At much deeper level
Poseidon is about bringing a GPS like positioning capability
Submerged user
So when I think about the submerged users
I don't think about
Radio operation there though I know that there's some other real interesting working trying to bring
Radio with with vlf and ultra-low frequency
So down into into underwater operations but I left I think immediately of acoustic types of signal
So I presume that that's part of why you were correct
The climate research Community has been using low-frequency acoustic signals for several decades
Now
How to monitor the temperature
Of the ocean
As a function
And
By using low frequency signals if you know again
The analogy of just gave earlier
Time is Key here
If you know when the signal left a
Transmitter
Compare that
The time you received it at another location you can get the time of
Flight of that signal
Now for underwater
So you mentioned
For GPS the speed of light is is is constant
That's not quite the case
For underwater the speed of sound
Underwater is a function of many things
Primarily temperature
But also I doubt
And salinity and some other terms as well
So
We have developed models
That
Account fraud
In addition to that the
Acoustic signals underwater
I don't travel in a single line between the transmitter and receiver
Which radio frequencies
Typical acoustic signals will take
Many paths
On the way from the source
To a receiver
Because the signal was getting re
Refracted
Due to temperature profiles in the ocean
Pressure profiles
Things like that's when you hear a signal low-frequency signal at a receiver
That was admitted far away you actually hear
Multiple instances
Like an echo
I'm in the car for a week all that multi
There are multiple paths that a signal will take
So it sounds like
Eyewitness multipath
Phenomenon going on that one of the big
Issues here is going to be sort of
How do you deconvolve all of those
Signals coming in and so that sounds like algorithms it sounds like computational issues
So I just to make sense of what otherwise would be just a morass of
You are correct
And that is exactly what we are focused on in the program
Initially
What is
Can we
Improve
Current models develop new models that can accurately count
For all of those paths that a signal take such that we can extract
An accurate time of flight and hence an accurate distance
Once we get the distance
I from that signal the navigation part
Is is fairly
The hard part
Is the signal
Measurement model
And
Justice GPS depends upon constellations of
Satellites and forgetting the exact number now but
What is a couple of days
Do you know the exact number
What's around 3130 would Poseidon in an undersea GPS system also rely
Ayana constellation of acoustic beacons so distributed through the oceans yes but hopefully not 30
Forgiving Arrow
Also the ocean is there a phenomenon like the one we talked about for very low frequency radio signals
Minnesota
Skirting the Earth through the Earth in the ionosphere and that sort of long-wave guard guide effect
Acoustic sound can travel tremendous distances in the ocean right there where I'm thinking here of how
Whales communicate over greatest
That is correct and within that is the exact
The fact that we were exploding
There is what's called a sound channel
The death of a sound channel
Is in general a function of
Of temperature
But in general in deep oceans it's about a kilometer
Deep
And so
Low frequency
Acoustics
Will travel for very long distances that there was a Seminole
Study in the 90s that showed
Low frequency signals
Could be received in the sound channel
Many thousands of kilometres I believe it was almost 9000 km
Persuade Absol
Who is down.
And it also just brings another question to mine I don't know much about how these beacons work and what their characteristics are
Are there issues of concern for animals living in the ocean
Who are these signals on will be
Propagating absolutely
A key tenet of the program is
We have to develop a system
That complies with all the Federal
Regulation
Protecting
A marine mammal
When I take it one of the things that drives you
Is the concern that we have become utterly dependent
On GPS just the way we were utterly dependent upon the electric
Grid
We all know when the electrical grid goes down that we become frantic even 5 minutes
Power out we are going nuts
ISO
GPS has a similar vulnerabilities tell me about
That aspect of how you think about technology and security
Yeah so there was a phrase that some people use you have
Fail-Safe
And fail operational
Cayo
Your primary system fails
And he's the fail to a
Safe mode use or fail first two you're still operational and then if it fails again you're still safe
Okay so you have that built-in redundancy same into the power grid when the power goes out the building the diesel generators come on
If you need
Continuous levels of power in that building
The same thing as is happening
In the in the navigation
Considera autonomous
Vehicles
Witcher on the horizon
Clearly they can't
Solely depend on GPS
To tell the car where it is located
Because of
Some of the things we talked about earlier such as
The urban Canyon they can't pick up the
GPS signal
So you're already sing
Driverless cars being more dependent on other sensors for
Fighting positioning a
Information weather
Lidar laser radar
Or or imagery
For example
Or even the
The Doppler sensor
High on The View
So you're already seeing redundancy starting to be built into
Systems that are going to be
Depended on navigation
So when we think of the three programs that we just talked about the ANS stoic and Poseidon
And I should point out that you just handed off stewardship this program to a colleague in the Strategic
Technology
Can you give us a sense in each case of what the status of the v20
So ans is wrapping up
Anuses
Is is transitioning
To the end users to the services in various ways
And that's a good thing
Stoic
Is
Almost halfway
Through a
3-phase program so weird
We are in Phase 2
Are the Start program so we've demonstrated
Feasibility
Came up with an initial approach
Generated evidence to support
Support
That approach
And in face to wear now
Implementing that approach
And and
Doing higher fidelity
Data collection
Besides just getting started we are
In the middle of what we call Phase 1 of Poseidon
Just one more question before you lend
I'm and that's
What question do you really wish
I
What about you that I didn't
And if
Such a question comes to mind you can ask
Skip now and answer
So you mentioned Optical clock
Thanks for reminding me I should have pushed you didn't answer that question earlier
So an optical clock
Is it's an atomic clock and we have atomic clocks today
Such as a rubidium clock
Or a cesium
Does if there were cesium beam has been around since
The 50s
Just a winter mean for a second
Simple way of thinking about these things and then why atoms can be clocks is because there are
Vibrations oscillations associated with the nuclei but rather than the the kinds of isolation
Did you think about it and I are kind of old-fashioned clock with a pendulum I mean something to some ways that's what's going on but it's going on at billions
And trillions of oscillations in what we consider duration of reckon
So in the atomic clocks of today we are exploiting signals
Emitted by atoms
Hot in the microwave reach
Gigahertz
Level six
Gigahertz is
Billion x
Per second
An optical clock
Is exploiting
Atomic energy level transitions
That have frequencies
Over 400
Terahertz
Another
Five orders of magnitude
So that that clock is Optical clock ticks five orders a magnet
Faster
Then
Atomic clocks
Today
And by virtue that that's more precise time and
We get
Much improved stability
Out of that
Optical clocks today in general
Are about the size of a small laboratory universities have these Optical clocks
Nest
The National Institute of Standards and technology has the world's most stable
Optical clock
DARPA in the past had a program
That showed by making some trades and size weight and Power
And performance you could reduce the size of that off
Clock down to the size of
A shoebox
From a laboratory size download shoebox
Yes but that clock is still ticking
At Optical frequency
Another DARPA program
I showed how
You could
Make a very small
And robust
Device called a frequency comb that acts like a set of gears
And transfers that very stable
Optical tick in the 400 terahertz
Region
Down to RF
Radio frequency radio
Then you can generate a timing signal that is used to
Systems of day type 1 pulse
Per second in megahertz
So the store Kroger
Is
Integrating
Those separate technologies that DARPA developed
Into a single unit
Such that
I like to say we want to pull out the cesium being clock and plug in the stove top
Clock-in
Your
Time stability has improved by
At least in order
So imagine a clock that is able to keep
GPS level time accuracy
For over a year
With no GPS route
Fastenal
Thanks for 4
Give me the flavor of what an optical clock is I know that its complexities go off the charts but I think you gave us his
Sense of what you up to there so thanks a lot
Nice understand that in in the not-so-distant future you're going to be leaving. You got here in 20
12 will be leaving this year you've got this amazing sort of skill set in mindset particular fifties navigation
Technologies
The clocks assertive whole range of
Of
Of abilities and skills in different areas
Do you imagine that you're going to keep applying that particular set of Interest
In your post. Professional
Absolutely
Positioning in timing
Are built into so many system
We have today
And it's
Because of the success
Of
GPS
Other nations are building their own
Satellite navigation systems
As well
And GPS is in bed in so many
Thanks thanks
You don't you wouldn't even think about
Are the ATM to get cash from
GPS is in there
Electronic trading on the stock market
GPS is in there disappointed in that case it's mostly the timing function right cuz you need to know
When those transactions happen
Agriculture
Precision agriculture
GPS is in
Power distribution
City Electric
GPS
GPS is
Pervasive
I want to continue
To enable
Systems today too
Provide that same level of positioning and timing
With with capabilities that are redundant to GPS
Provide the integrity
Other also going Beyond
Level of position and timing
Florence we get today with g
UPS such that we can enable new capabilities that we can't even imagine
Today if we had
That much more I can
Time in Memphis
So sounds like
Exciting
Frontiers out there and I'm sure you'll have no problem pushing on those Frontier
Linda's has been a fantastically interesting conversation for me
I feel privileged to have spoken with you for awhile
So I want to just thank you for joining me in the studio today
Well thank you this is this has been a lot of fun
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us I hope you join us again for the next
Voices
Kim Darby
For more information about linhoss and his program in about DARPA's other program managers and the Breakthrough
Analogies they're working on
Visit
DARPA. Mil
And to listen to or download this podcast
Go to the Voices from DARPA page on DARPA's website