Dell Technologies
The internet GPS in the palm of your hand
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War DARPA the defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver of Technology
Welcome to
Voices from DARPA
A window onto DARPA score of program managers
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host
Today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Lindsay Millard
A program manager in darkness
Tactical technology office
We're since 2014 she has been
Running the intriguingly named space surveillance telescope where SST program
Welcome NC to Voices from.
Thank you so much
Much for having me I'm really excited
I'm excited to have you
And before we dive in and talk about the space surveillance telescope
Which packs some really amazing technology that I'm
Eager to hear about
Let's talk a little bit
About you
What I'd like to know is something about your background and interests and
How you became a program manager
Sure so a while ago actually started as a photography major
At the University Michigan
What you might think is a little bit odd start for a scientist
I was always inspired by these images I would see and astronomy magazine
And at that time I thought I was that means I should be a
Photography made
But after learning a little bit more my time there I I drifted over to aerospace engineering
I got my undergraduate degree in aerospace engineering there and a masters as well
And I went to Purdue where did some graduate work
Like the naval to NASA mission called the terrestrial planet
Which of the new design for a space
After that I had some work I did in policy
Actually met a fellow program manager here at DARPA who introduced me
To the house charcoal work
And the DARPA program
I was very exciting to me
And that's how I ended up a
And before we do really talk about the
Advanced Technologies that come together into the
Is too low
The space surveillance
Telescope
Maybe you can talk to us a little bit about the problem that really
Beckon the scream 4 something like an SST and what I'm referring to here is
Is the
Relentless growth
A boat
Maggie's human-made and
Cosmos made degree so
I guess that's really the beginning of the Space Age
Yeah absolutely I mean
Where are uses space is becoming increasingly critical to daily life
I think a lot of people don't know
When space is even involved
What's really anymore
And in order to do that we are launching increasing numbers
Man-made objects
Into space
Are there tens of thousands of these objects
In space right now
And so we have to be very careful that they don't come near each other and
And sometimes even collide with each
And on top of that we also have debris
Get some from man-made object
But also just natural
SST is really focused on
Tracking and identifying debris and object
In an orbit called Geo
Geosynchronous orbit
That's about 22000 miles
The Earth
The really far away
Why did I differs from Leo right which is low earth orbit
A lot of satellites are there as well
That's absolutely right
Leo's much closer so it's a little easier
To tusayan
Go has a volume of tens of thousands of ocean
So not only is it far away
It's gigantic
And so building a telescope that can handle both of those challenges seeing things very far away over a very wide
Area
It's really what I see
He is
Okay let I love that kind of image you just gave us
With all of these oceans above that needs
Looked at in
And monitored
So you have that sounds to me like like
You need some old wow
Technology and maybe this is a good time for you to
Talk about
Those boys really Advanced and unique Tech
Help
Nurture to come together
Yeah absolutely still
I think about a digital camera that you have at home
When you use your zoom lens
You see the field of view on your camera narrow in on the thing that you're looking at it as you get closer
And that is
How a traditional telescope works as you change the design that the field of view Narrows
With SST we actually had a Unique Auto
I were use a curved
Focal plane
So again I think about your digital camera there is a small focal point focal plane in your camera call the CCD
And that's dance for
Charge-coupled device if I recall
What does the acronym
Mccd
Thank you
Well as T obtains that very very wide field-of-view but still relatively very high resolution
Is actually instead of having a flat fee CD or a flat vocal play
Eye is curved
An SST had the first working curved book
That we know of in the world
And what what's so special about the curved
Format versus
As liquor format allows you to actually Focus the light
It's a little bit better towards the edges of the
CCD
It's also very very challenging to
Build
In fact mit lincoln Labs who built the
The focal plane had to come up with a completely new process
Unable to
To enable that curvature
Over the over the
Writing for those who might not know the Lincoln lags Labs is a really fascinating place with a
History that goes back really to World War
2 with a task
Skip that time to
Work on what really
Was some of the original
Radar
It's been really involved in objects among other
Who sings ever
Ever since
So it's a really interesting
Partner in this case
What are some of the other Technologies.
The Devon really tough
DARPA DARPA worthy type of Technologies
The processing power
Telescope
Quite impressive
And the speed at which it can scan over the
And so we can actually
View objects / 1/4
Of the entire go belt over
Imagine it is 1/4 of the Earth
I eat tonight
From New Mexico
And that is just incredibly fast drivetrain on the telescope and requires incredibly fast
And those are two things that
But we also develop
Grandma's coming to standing volume
Not to be thinking about
How does in the field of view of this instrument
And it's in a
Kind of an amazing perch right this is at the White Sands
Missile Range
In New Mexico which I guess most people there now is Whismur
But it's on top of a fantastically name
A peak called Adam Peak
Admit you've been there so maybe you can just sort of paint this a little bit of a
A picture what it's like to be there at night by the
Telescoping and while you're doing that
Describe the telescope
Sure did the atom tickets self is very high and very dry
I am in a very dark location
So you can stand up on the peak and actually see the sunset out over the range
Beautiful
And you're also looking right over a site called Trinity
Trinity site is actually where the United States exploded its
First atomic weapon
I was just kind of interesting to be standing on the edge of two areas where technology
He was developed
After Sunset again it's incredibly dark you can actually see the edge of the Galaxy
When you're standing
And after Nightfall
I walk inside the telescope Dome
The facility itself looks like a very flat Square building with a giant Dome on one
Decide
When you get inside that dome which is elevated even higher above Adam Peak and they will open up the door
Off of the telescope down
At and almost every time I've been there at the wind is just blowing
And it's freezing cold but everyone wants to stay in that down because it just so neat
All the stars in the
Telescope
The telescope moving itself is completely silent
They're just sitting there looking at the stars
Give people a sense of the scale of it and how fast it's moving because when you say
This instrument
Is silent and I think about how big it is now
Fastest moving its
Almost impossible
For me to think about
So the telescope itself weighs
Several tons
And it's sitting on it
Top of many different
Gimbels
And what it's doing is the the shape of the
Opening in the dome is rectangular
And so it starts at the top and the telescope movement
Is going up and down
Look up and down in a vertical and
Autocross in a horizontal motion
And again if it can survive the entire sky so 180° around the Dome
In one single night again that you know volumes and volumes of ocean
A quarter of that in one night
Right and some soda literally as it's moving from one spot
Taking a snapshot moving to another
Taking a snapshot
I'd heard that there's some thousands of horsepower worth of
Hydraulic
Piston
Other moving elements
Good actually
Can can
Bring it from one
To the next and yet
The sound of something like
I've heard this maybe you can correct it or will you have another metaphor
About as loud as a microwave oven
I think that's right the only thing you can hear is the clicking of the shutter
On the camera
Over the hum of a micro
Right and then so when the shutter is open and it's gathering this light on with you through that curve.
Element that you talked
Too bad so I can look at such
Huge
Volume of space all at once
The latest cell phone is going onto as I think you might have said Central like that in our cell phone
Can you talk a little bit about that that censor play
Yes I'll start with as the aperture is open the light actually comes in and and
Hit several different mirrors
Summer saying Schmidt
Optical train
And it's about a 3.6 m m e r
So that gives you an idea of a sort of how big the the hole
Old telescope
Stop at several meters
Text larger than that
And so the light will come in and bounce through that that mirror
And actually be focused on to that curved focal plane
Where
You know the light hits
The materials in that focal plane in that turns them into an elect
Signal
Which is then transferred into what we would
Think of it
Pixels
Based on the strength of the Electra
Cycle signal you're either seeing a brighter or fainter
The longer the telescope is open and looking at a spa
Pacific Place in the sky
Defeater the object
Might be able to see just like
If you are doing it at home
Camera okay so now I'm imagining the camera staring out
To geosynchronous
High altitudes roughly what 22000mah
Our heads there
And it's picking out
Perhaps thousands
At one time thousands of even softball-sized
Objects is that right
Yeah that's about right maybe the size of a whiskey bottle
If we focused in on one of those
You waited with you Whiskey Bottle you just said now I'm wondering if there really are whiskey bottles
Whirling around in orbit
One can only guess right we have at astronauts
So let's assume it's not a whiskey bottle but it's some other kind of debris
How many pixels would that single
Object
Keep eye on that
The sensor
Shirts will be very few so SST cannot actually
Take what we would think of as an image of
Something in Chia what SSD doesn't really see
Datsun Street
So it is not resolved imagery of
Of an object in Geo but really an indication of where that object is
And how it's moving
Okay that's really all important you really want another
Trajectory
Cuz then you can map that
Projector onto the trajectories of
What if all the
Satellites that are out there whether it's for.
Or other entities
And you can then
Calculate
Where there might be a
A nun
An unwanted
Intersection of those
Trajectory
Yes that's absolutely right and it also add that
Primaries are the telescope right now is actually NASA
We partnered with NASA to
Try to identify a catalog new
Near-earth
NSS is actually prolific at this
At finding what we call these Neos
Primarily asteroids and comets
Looking at
Right right so that's been serving the test out phase
In these earlier
Years in a way
Fence first light in
2011 if I recalled my reading
Is that when it first went on top of Adam's peak
Where was that somewhere else no that was on
Okay so since then can you get a sense of
Of the catalogue of observation
Since then
We work
At like a mansion with NASA
To look at objects
Near-earth objects
We've also take some images of nebula and supernova
Also for a Partners at NASA
I work very closely with the United States are
Force
For the Air Force we are observing very faint objects
In geosynchronous orbit
And I'm providing them information on that
And that could be anything from a piece of debris to to a small satellite
We also were quite a bit on developing what we call debris models
I still know telescope is strong enough
To see every piece of debris in space
And so what we do is we make estimate
About where that debris might be based on what we know
SOS St can see many more objects than other telescopes
And so we've been using our measurements
To help develop models for what we think the reality of of the debris is
Pangea
Okay that you mentioned many more telescopes and that made me think
Of the larger context to your eye which is the
The largest of the space surveillance Network
Sure so the United States Air Force operates we recall at the SSN everything has
Have an acronym the space surveillance Network
And there are several different types of optical and radar sensors in that Network
SSC is currently not one of those sensors even though we do provide
Data on an ad-hoc basis to the Air Force
I've been very shortly it is going to become
One of the sensors in that Network
SST is going to be transitioning over to you Air Force use
I actually very soon on October 18th
That is a
Important
Kind of success for DARPA
When we think of what we're trying to do here is
Developed
Technologies
To further the cause of of national
Security
We really do want this sort of transition ultimately that happened we do a lot of high risk
Kinds of Technology developments of the transition doesn't always happen but here is a case where a
It is so
Can you talk to me about
Does Baton handoff
Frightened
Where we are now so that we we can make this hand off
To the Air Force and then perhaps
Also take us forward to the sequence of events that will
Over the next few years
Sure so I mentioned SST had for slight in 2011
I was a demonstration system that's a weed developer
Is wonderfully poetic
Term in the telescope
Community
I would really refers to that moment when all of the conception is over in the development in the building
Hanging you finally
Open up this this wonderful instrument to
2 observation and you desperately want to see what that first observation is nuts
Often referred to as
Slight so excited Intrepid that what that was
In February 2011 the first electricity
Yes thank you
So at that time it was a demonstration system in here Darby we try to really push Beyond
The state-of-the-art Yuna revolutionary
Technology
And sometimes you always don't you don't always get it perfect the first time
And so with the camera that we had in there in 2011 we realized there were some improvements
Could be made
And so over the past year or so we've been developing a new
Replacement
Camera for the one that exists
There today
So we're installing we finished the installation of that new camera
And had a guy again first light
On August 18th of this year
And we're currently demonstrated the approach improve capability
Of SST
Once a demonstration is done
And we really a really certain that the technology is complete
We are just really excited to give this
The US Air Force
It represents an order of magnitude
Increasing capability from what they're able to see now with their existing opt
Vehicle sensors
I am so we are very excited to be able to give them that capability and have that actually
Run into operational use
Right so the Air Force will officially take Stewart
Ship of SST in an official
Ceremony that will be happening up on Adam Peak
I'm in
New Mexico
What's going to happen
After that
I asked her that we are actually going to be leaving the United States are actually going to be moving
Telescope to Australia
Are we have some
The planet is not an easy task for a very large telescope
In 2013 the Secretary of Defense
And also the Minister of Defense in Australia signed an agreement
To actually move the telescope from White Sands Missile Range to you Harold e Holt Naval Air Station
In Western Australia
Until once we complete the technology demonstrated and
Transition to the Air Force
The Air Force is going to continue to work with our Australian Partners to physically move it
Over to Western Australia
That will be happening over the next
Maybe two years
I know that sounds like an enormous project
Probably
Worth its own engineering story
Why take the great pains to move this
Telescope
Ihaveplanet
I completely agree the movement is potentially a DARPA hard problem in and of itself
The reason to do it is because that is a part of the world that were very interested in observing
What's going on up in geosynchronous orbit
We have a lot of very important that lives in that area to include communication
I'd also it represents a great partnership with our Australian allies
It's for the really those two reasons why we want to move
We've covered a fair amount for the time that we have
About
The space
A surveillance telescope question that you really wish I would have asked here that I
Did not and if so
You got to ask it now.
Well maybe not a question but I have a statement
My whole life
I've been interested in swerve looking Beyond
You know what we can really see
And I think it's inspiring to work on an instrument
It went to see other galaxies it makes it so real
In a way it's one thing to look sort of at a picture in a magazine
And it's another to be working with an instrument that can actually Imogen nebula and a supernova
I said for me working on the program has
Has been inspiring
Not only from a science perspective but also because we get to contribute to two very important mission for
You're at a place DARPA which is
Kind of all about
Reimagining what is
Possible and actual
Who taking steps to
Change what you
To take what
My previously been considered in Paw
Send a ways to places trying to make science fiction nonfiction I'm just wondering if
You have some
What are now fictional
Technologies in mines
I bet you think
What to be real
So I have a couple
I want is
The universal translator
It might have been on Star Trek series
That is a technology or perhaps a superpower that that I absolutely wish
That that we had
I think the other one is to travel beyond the stars perhaps that's a
That way he could have guessed it's not enough for me to just look I wish we could go there
That's a good place to end I think
Tell Lindsey I just want to thank you for the great conversation
Thank you very
Glad you're here and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again
For the next Voices from DARPA
For more information about DARPA
The program managers
And the Breakthrough Technologies they are developing
Visit us online
At DARPA.