Dell Technologies the internet
Autonomous operation
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding in 19
58 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense
Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver
Technology
Welcome to
Voices from DARPA
A window Into Darkness
Core of programming
Their job
Redefined what
What is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your dork
Host
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio Blake bextine
A new program manager in DARPA's biological
Technologies offer
He arrived in March of 2016 from the University of
Texas at Tyler
And he brings into DARPA particular love for the entomological kind Among Us
Insects that is
And he is betting that a combination of insects and genetics
Techniques
Can open new Pathways to protecting the crops we depend on
From both natural and human perpetrated
Threats
These are things like droughts and storms unintentional introduction of invasive species
Unintentional
Release of plant harming biological warfare agent
He just rolled out his first project
I called insect allies
Which is challenging the research Community to develop
Plant protective viruses that insects
Working at allies with us
Can deliver efficiently to threaten plants and bestow protection on them in a single season time frame
That can Stave off the
The thanks Blake
We're coming to the studio and spending some time with
That's great to be here thanks for having me
Before we talk about the insect allies program let's talk about you your background
And the
What brings you to
I came to DARPA because I saw a fantastic opportunity for my research
Community
The DARPA mission is
Unlike things
That I have done in the past
Because the DARPA mission is to look at
High-risk high-reward
Projects that could benefit
Humanity in
Acer that 2250 year time frame
And it also gives an opportunity to do D risk
Some
Programs and some projects
So that they can act
Play come to widen and
Sia
See you soon
So when the opportunity to come DARPA
Presented itself
I thought it was just
Awesome chants
Do some really great science and
I was encouraged because I was asked to think about things that
Traditionally weren't funded very well
That I think the women just suck you for a second cuz you said went when the opportunity presented itself
Of course it didn't present itself somehow that
That happened
I knew somebody or you you heard about an opportunity in opening so how how did you
Actually yes sure so I was at a meeting and I had moved into an administrative role at the universe
First day of Texas at Tyler until we have an event
Every year we come to DC and we get to meet program managers and I actually talked
Call Jeff Lang Who is the
Director of biologic
Call Technologies
Set the time
And I wasn't sure that darker really had any interest in agriculture
So
But he was such an interest
The person I wanted meet talk to
So I talked to him after he gave his presentation
I said I don't know if we have any overlap and what were interest
And but I would love to work with you at some point you said well actually
We're looking to get into
You know
And that sort of started this journey of
Seeing if I fit with the kind of mindset that
We have a DARPA
Which is
You know these kind of difficult technologies that need to be developed
How that could benefit Humana
And so it was
It was good for Tyler you were a professor biology but you also need another hat on
Which was the assistant vice president for research
Technology transfer
Right so
So those are the two things that that also go on a DARPA
There are similarities there's
You know the people that you work with
And you're directing a team to try to
Achieve an objective
And so we're definitely doing that and working in agriculture
It has a
The professor
You spend a lot of time where you go out and you think about the technologies that are out there in the
You know genetic-based molecular base things that are happening
But you'll have to marry that with
The reality of situation
That's when you go to Central America and you walk in a potato field
How you start to realize that
Technology is great
But how do you get that technology to the field
That's actually get it too
To the finish line
So we'll talk about that with the insect allies program in just a month but there's one more thing I have to ask
That's because
When you read your bio on on the dark web site Mill
The last line is very intriguing it says that you were
On the Discovery
Channel reality TV show called tethered in
2014 so I just I just have to hear this
How did that happen what did you do with and
We were insects
To start off I am interested in Science Education
And so I like the idea of putting a positive spin
In science not just the Bowtie wearing
Geeky professor
You know type person as the
Scientist but instead somebody that
No kids could aspire to be a
Good strong normal
Person and so there is an opportunity that came up to be
Yeah on a reality show and the idea was that
When you're in a survival situation
People that are alone don't do as well as people that are
Paired with somebody else or in a group
And so this took it to the next level where I was literally tethered with a 6-foot
I cord to another human being
And being that it's reality television
The promise was that I was the scientist
And I was actually paired with a shaman
And so we had very different ideas about how the world works
That's all through the episode we had to learn to
I work together and get together on something
We actually became very good friends we survived
Don't want to give the ending away
Have I'm sitting here today so I must have worked out okay everyday
But I'll tell you that that experience was 100% real
They don't give you food they don't give you water so we had to boil all of our water where to find the food that
Could sustain us
And we didn't do really well I was in Alaska
At the end of the summer so there just wasn't a lot of food around
And
We ended up
At one point that logical aspect of this we ended up
Finding a dead moose in the middle of a sandbar on a river
And
I decided that
I had to have that credibility as an entomologist so
We scooped them out of their cut them off and we ate
Carcass maggots out of out of a moose
Well okay that's actually might be a nice segue then to talk about
Are your new program insect allies those maggots where your allies out there helped you survive
Talk about the program here at DARPA what it is what's the program all about and what
So my broad interests
AR
Sustaining agricultural
Capabilities
So as we move forward
In the future when we're going to grow our population to 10 billion people in the neck
Twenty two
50 years
How are we going to sustain the food so
7.3 billion now so were talking about in that period of time and I
Free ride
And our traditional agricultural approach is great and does does a really good job of
Sustaining food supply right now but
Forward-thinking what are we going to do
And a future to innovate and and make things better
And so insect allies really comes out of that born out of that wear
We want to utilize insects to deliver genes in plants
That could benefit
The plant previously
Capabilities were only in tissue culture
And that meant that you had to grow up those plants after genetic modification
And then you only find out if the genes do what you wanted to do
After you've gone through this sort of long pants
Process
In a world where drought and threats from insects and pathogens are always around
How can we actually protect our plants in the fields where they are
And so this mature plant transformation idea came about and then
At that presents a second problem
How do you actually get the genes into the plants where you want them delivered
And so that's where the insect allies come about
Insects
Insect vectors in particular are very good at
Moving
These pieces of
Genetic material into plants
Very efficiently and effectively
Why couldn't we use that natural scenario
To actually move these genes in the plants
Positive character
So that's what we want to do we want to use insects
To deliver genes in the plants that will benefit
Right now
What are our up
Options in case
Crops are threatened somehow
By a pathogen
Or some other threat
What would we do when an app
Well currently what we do is we try to
Contain the outbreak
And so what that usually means that we have to destroy the crops that are in fact
And
You know if you
Don't think too much about the situation that's just you burn some
Unicorn fields or Rogue some trees in an orchard
But the reality is if you
Ruin that seed source for the next year
You also impact the next year's for
And the next year
And so it's not a small problem to have one of these in basic problems come
And then go into a slash-and-burn mode
What to eat to get rid of the disease
So if we could actually recover those crops very quickly
And we could stop those eminent threats
Then we wouldn't lose production
I mean you almost sounds like a little bit
Like a medical model I mean if I go into 2
Doctor's office
That's because I'm not feeling well
Well I might have
I might get some antibiotics and
In a week I'm feeling better I mean in some ways
It sounds a little bit
Like that because your time frame here
Saw the threat to
How to make OVA plant
You know better within very short time is that
All right. That's exactly right and you know it a good example of
That's where this technology could really benefit would be
In a
Tree
Orchard type situation
Mission in Florida right now they're dealing with Citrus Greening
This is a bacterial pathogen that is transmitted by an insect and
Causes trees to decline rather quickly
And the answer is you need to remove the trees and if you find out brakes
The disease you need to get rid of the
And so entry crops
Do you actually lose those trees
Several years
Because trees take awhile to
So those threats are are very bad so if you could actually
Turn on genes that allow them to
Survive
How that would be
Okay because we are here at DARPA defense Advanced research
You're generally is a 1/3 of a national
Security angle on
Our project
EXO
What is that angle here for in technology
Well there is really too far
So the first idea is that we want to protect our domestic
So if there was a threat that came in Weatherby environmental something like drought or
Flooding
Or if it was past that was
Released
Accidentally or
Or on purpose
Would want to be able to handle that challenge so that we don't destroy our food so
Because there's a lot of evidence that shows that
Unstable Foods
Supply
Leads to unstable
And we definitely don't want that
That kind of leads to the second part
Which is international
Food safety
In
Unstable regions in the world
Food stability water stability
Are things that lead to
Even less stable
So if we can have a hand at the beginning of that problem
And provide sustainable food
These population
I think that that
That definitely is a Nash
Security concern and
Not something that
We have the ability to
Address now
Okay let's dive in just
For a little while
On
Biotechnology
You're pushing me to several
Components
2/8 week but we've got the insect allies
But they're they're going to be the ones that are going to deliver
Innocence the
The threat reducing
Agent
A virus that you're going to
Baby talk
What about it
The end result
Components of insect allies
How you're going to maybe move that the state-of-the-art
That's what's broken up into really three areas the virus so taking a virus at in
Why do people think of viruses only in a bad context
But in reality viruses
Can be benign they might move genetic
Material around and
Yunnan dangerous
Swayze and so what we want to do is run identify viruses that
I have very limited negative
Facts on on any host
And then
Remove any
Possibility of naked
And use those hazard
Shuttles to get genetic
Material
Placed into the
And so we're going to use insects which are
Very good
Movers of viruses
If you select the right virus and you select the right insect
I can be a very specific relationship so
I will have the opportunity to safeguard when you say specific
If if there's a certain
Implant that is threatened
It will
Go to those plants specifically antifreeze
10:20 of the species around hopf
They would ignore
There are generalists that will feed from a lot of different house plants those aren't the insects that we would select in this
Are we want to select insects that
Have a very specific relationship with
Maybe a single species
So
If used in this way they're not going to go feed on everything that's out there
So it's a very specific
Okay maybe to make this concrete can you imagine a unit potential Center
A specific crop that has a specific threat
Onnit
And
Then what kind of virus you might
Devise to treat it how you would get that into an incel
Mitigate
All I can think of a lot of ideas
That well but I think what we want to do is ask our our performer Community want to go out and ask the research
Community
What are these major threats what specific relationships do they see that can be utilized in this way at 2
This is very open program and we're going to ask the research community academic
To come to us and tell us
What problems need to be addressed and what are the players
Okay so rather than specifying a
This point you want to keep this open and
Isn't that what you maximize art of the creative
Full potential of your
Performer Bass
Face the research base
Right eye I know so many people out there and Academia other that have great ideas I want to give them a chance to come
Come in and tell us what they need
Need to address that way we can speak a little bit generally though about some of the molecular
Or tools cuz I think probably what
One of the things
Gives you such strength in moving
Forward with what really isn't ambitious
His program
Is because we really been seeing some new remarkable
What kinds of molecular
Atul maybe can just talk about one or two of those
But our listeners a sense
Sure they revolution in molecular biology has been based around the 2012 finding
Crisper cast 9
A new utilization of that tool
And just briefly an odor that's a mouthful
One sentence or two of that what that
Should have done
So crisper cast 9 is a molecular tool that allows you to edit the Genome of a host and it doesn't have it
Specific way
So that
Cuts in the genome
Are based on a
Couple of letters
That's very specific where it will go so
Traditionally when you've done genetic modification you end up
How to putting it into the genome
And hoping that it goes to the
Right place
These new tools allow us to be very specific and and where it's play so it doesn't interrupt
Change that
There are needed
Okay and so so that means that that there's all kinds of threats after
If we know something about the genetic basis of those
Then we can use a tool like crispr cast 9
Going very specifically
And maybe do a kind of genetic fix
And that can happen in in in a single season
And thereby
A new way of
Food supply
Write a lot of these Gene cassettes that we would use to solve
These problems are
Already being looked
And a good example would be flood resistant rice
That's
That's out there a suite of genes is known Rida sweet of genes that would allow it to
Surviving difficult
Situations there's the same type of Technology that's being found
For high salinity
Drought resistant drought
Tolerance
And so if we could actually figure out a way to put those jeans into the crops that were interested in
Then we could get through those bats
Situations
Alright so this this sounds like a great idea we're going you know our population key
It's going up maybe we're going to reach 10 billion
We're going to want
Abundant and safe food supplies
Thing to do
But this is just only one way you are interested in the human insect relationship
But you have some other ideas I think about how well our partnership with insects might
Expand me if you can
Yeah so I've also been interested in alternative protein sources
And so I have a
Program
India sbir program
And that svr that.
We're actually looking at
Delivering high protein sources
From insects
But also
Using technology to improve our ability to do that so
One side of it might be too
Used technology to manage Pest and pathogen
Problems in insect Colony rearing
So could we shutdown viral infections in these colonies that usually cause inside
Claps
So we talkin about the the bee collapse issue for Mor ryde and there's a whole host of
Viruses that cause that same problem in other insects
Species and so
In
Crickets for example which are probably one of the most popular
Edible insects
Producers out there
There's a similar virus that causes collapsed their colonies so if you were one of the companies that was doing this
An invasion of the virus might cause a complete collapse of all of your
Livestock
Small light socket
That's so and then we can go the other direction and actually utilize these insects to also deliver
Anita
Nutrients like vitamin A vitamin C vitamin D
A whole host of
Five different ideas are there there's really no lack and ideas of what it could
The prettiest butt
We could actually develop insects
Edible insects into a
Realm where not only can they feed an Asian but
They can also deliver
Additional
Resources
Now have you already practice what you seem to be preaching here which
To say that insects might be
Comfort of the pantry
So have you eaten absolutely
And you know it's it's funny I realized that people have an aversion to this there's a new version of this in my own family
That's why I understand it very well
However 80% of the world
Eats insects as a stable protein source
And so
You know the Western World were kind of an oddity where we don't utilize the
This sad
Opportunity so
Again
You know there's great sources of protein right now
That everybody enjoys if you like steak
Like if you like chicken
And if you like all these others
Thanks but again we get to a point where our population continues to rise
We're going to need to have alternative sources so we're really thinking into the future
Remembering it
The early out of the conversation you did mention
I thought you found those when they were with maggots
Are maggots is in the moose
So among the various insects that you Pride somehow I imagine you try crickets
Where where do they stand with maggots great where they not as good as something else you know honestly the mag
I guess were relatively tasteless but I cooked them with a little bit of
Different
Locally sourced
Alaskan Fireweed
So they were delicious they it actually took on the flavor of what you cook them with
Blake is there a question that I should have asked you that I didn't or just
That are you wish I hadn't if so
You can even mascot
We should have asked me
Why I'm interested in insects
And all of that question
And the answer is I haven't always been
I didn't grow up as a child wanting to be an entomologist I didn't have inside
Collections
Brother I was interested in the world in general
How things were
And so that Drew me to biology when I was a college student and
Through my college classes I was at the University of Northern Iowa I randomly took an entomology class
And it opened up this idea that we could ask these biological questions
And we could use insect
To answer that
And they're living organisms they are abundant
And I also realize that
Going into my career in as an academic
That we're always going to need to eat
And so funding for agriculture is
There's always going to be around
And so it was a good way to actually marry some of the ideas but I had
Asking questions about the world
And then also working in field that super important because
Food security is going to be a
A big problem going forward
So I ended up as an entomologist out of
Hey this is a great way to ask questions that I want to answer
It's the one of the things that fascinates me
This year at DARPA and having a
Virginity to
Get to know a lot of
Different Technologies in the making potential
These are technologies that have the potential
How to do a lot of good but they're there also
I'll bring in capability
Is that could be used for nefarious
So the case you're of developing new kinds of
Ways of getting getting genetic
Material into live
Who sings this
Plants
That sounds like a great thing when it comes to
To crop protection but it also sounds to me like
Like it could open doors to new kinds of
What's a biologic
What are your thoughts
Well I think that there are potential negatives that could
Come out of
Technology being developed
Yes but I think the overwhelming
Thought is that
This is a
There's much easier ways to cause a large agricultural damage and regions
That certainly wouldn't have to
Tackle this
Level of service
And so
That there's there's definitely much more Bennett
Let them rest
Right I mean to sexually could have go down deep into the
Killer machine
It is probably a lot harder than what
Just going in and spraying chemicals or something from chemicals or identifying viruses or pests
But you know aren't in the region that you could bring in and release
It's a really that's what we want to guard against
There is the potential that technology like this can be used for nefarious
Purposes
You know that
Positive
That can come out of this in the world changing
Abilities that we're going to gain is fizzing
I just want to thank you for like for this great conversation wanted to watch
And thanks for spending
Thanks for having me this is a very exciting
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us I hope you join us again for the next
Voices
From DARPA
For more information about Blake his program to the other breakthrough technology
Is DARPA is working on
Visit
DARPA. Mill
And four links to allow you to download this
Go to the Voices from DARPA page on.