Technology
The internet
Palm of your hand
Autonomous
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver
Technology
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window onto DARPA score of program managers
Their job
To redefine
What is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I am your docker host
And I'm pleased to have with me in the studio today
Troy Olson
A program manager since 2014 in DARPA's Microsystems technology
Troy earned a pair of Bachelors
Degrees 1 in electrical engineering in one in computer engineering
From West Virginia University
And a master's and doctoral degree in electrical engineering from the University of Michigan
Four-decade prior to coming to DARPA
Troy founded and led a series of programs within the Micro electromechanical Systems Technology
Department of Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque New
Rextroy for joining me in the studio today
It's a pleasure to be here
So I'd like to start out or discussion with some
Background about you I'd like you to tell me about
Your education if they were teachers that were important to you as you were
Growing up in that led you in the kinds of engineering direction that you have take
Yeah sure so I grew up in a small town in West Virginia Weston West Virginia to be
Exact
When I was in high school
Had exhausted
At the math classes that were
Available at my local high school so I ended up going part-time to West Virginia Wesleyan College and they said have kind of a class for men
Any students from my high school
Go do that especially
Placer High School
Students at the local
College
And
For that always been good at math but I didn't ever really knew how to apply it
I figured I would go into medicine or something of that nature and it's part of that special class they set up for us
The first half hour
Professor McBride would come in
And he was an engineering physicist
And he would come in and relate all of the calculus we were learning
To physics problem
And I just found that fascinate
That was a junior in high school and from that point forward
I wanted to
So I'd like to hear a little bit about the base of your career where you really worked a lot on memes and again that's dance for me
Microelectromechanical systems
I know you did that even before going to asendia to talk a little bit about that whole love memes
In graduate school at the University of Michigan I work for Professor Ken wise who's one of the founders
Love memes
There I worked on
Analog interfaces for neural recording
So I was developing integrated circuits to be able to
Record
Neural Action potentials from the brain
For doing things like
Restoring function
People who have
Nervous system disa
Sleep paralysis
The things in the stimulation sense
Like blindness or
Hearing loss
I didn't went to Sandia National Laboratories where I switch things a little bit of Michigan I was designing circuit interfaces for Mims
And
At Sandia I started actually designing the mems
Components myself
I let a team of people designing and
Implementing those primarily
We were working on small a
Acoustic devices
You may not know that in your
Phone and RF signal is immediately converted into an acoustic signal biography
I mean radio frequency the radio frequency signal which has a really long wavelength is
Converted into a acoustic signal which is a very small wavelength which allows you to
Filter it in a small form factor before it's
Creed turn back into an electric
Comment so I was working on technologies that
Do that function but more for Department of
Defense Apple
Locations rather than
Cellular phones
Also worked on other things that really at the interface
Vibrational systems and acoustic systems analyst
Brighten and what was the pathway from Sandia
To DARPA
I was a performer doing a lot of the research on those small acoustic Wireless components
Bill Chappell the current director of the Microsystems technology office
Was my program manager and so when he was promoted to you
Called me out of the blue one day I think that was in March of
2014 and said
Hey Troy this is Bill Chappell
How would you like to come the DARPA to be a program manager I think you'd be great at it
Heading to I shared an office
For somebody so that was
Strange conversation
Yeah that the
That sounds like a great opportunity can I call you back in a few minutes
And is that that's all it took for you just a few minutes and then you knew what your decision would be after that
I mean anybody who gets an opportunity to come in
The DARPA
Fantastic
Opportunity of course I had to come
Interview and put together
I tok that outline the programs I would start I had to come in
Have you with the office director but how it all started was from a phone
Speaking about those programs we're going to dive into talking about a number of those you have a very large portfolio larger than most
Program manager that will only talk about a few but they're too
Questions I want to ask you before we do that one has to do with your name Troy I call you Troy
But your official name is Roy and I'm just wondering if you could tell us
The story of your name
Nasso my official name is Roy Harold Olson
The 3rd
Turns out my dad really wanted me to
To be named after him he's
Harold Olson
My mom wasn't the biggest fan of the name Roy so they made a deal
I could be named Roy Harold Olson the third and everyone would call me Troy
And apparently I
Reinforce this
When I was a small child
As Legend has it I would sit in my high chair and if people called me Roy I would throw green beans at them
Impound on the high chair
Nothing like negative reinforcement
What's a move on to just some of your program
Associate with one another we can talk about them together go by the short names of Icarus and Vapor
Speaker stands for inbound controlled air releasable
Unrecoverable systems
And Vapor stands for Vanishing
Programmable resources
I know the vapor paint before Icarus
So up
Why don't you tell us a little bit about the vapor Icarus story I which is an ongoing one
Yasso
In the Department of Defense a lot of times we have problems with electronic leave behind
We don't want to leave things on the battlefield where other people might collect them
So
We came up with the vapor program which is a Vanishing micro-electronics program it's designed to be able to
To make micro Electronics
That have reliability and
Performance
Commiserate with
Was commercial off-the-shelf electronic components that don't vanish
But that
When we want them to can rapidly
Vanish
A&B invisible to the name
Okay and you meet when you say vanish in the most people just think of
It's gone
Talk to me a little bit about the kind of technical Pathways some of your performers which is to say the research groups who have been worth
Working on this the kinds of Pathways they're taking to try to realize this idea vanish ability of
Yes it is really two approaches that have been really prominent in the vapor program I one was developed by the pallet
All the research center Park
And it is
Vanishing glass substrate that basically turns into dust
Like particles
And that glass can be bonded to integrated circuits and other things and causing and tires
To vanish
Mumbai dust like particles the particles are on
Order size of 100 microns which is about the width
So those ones
Vanish to the naked eye but the material itself
Physically
Completely vanish
We did develop a material that
That does that there was work done there at
At the University of
Illinois and Georgia
Protec and Cornell
Many of those materials
Working a way where there
Thermally unstable at room temperature they like to be a monomer or bepis
Gas
Actually make them at very cold temperatures they like - 50 degrees C
Annie's Casey's Banshee materials are polymers
I would like to make a really long polymer chain to get high middle
Molecular weight
Makes the polymer really tough
And then we link it in a certain way at the very cold temperatures so that we will raise it up and temperature it remains
Then in that material will embed
Something that
It's called either a photo acid generator or a thermal acid generator and that works just like you might expect
It does when you put a trigger
When you expose it to a certain wavelength of light
Tell photoacid generator
Creates an acid
If you take the thermal as a generator and exceed a certain temperature it also creates an acid that acid can break
One of the bonds between the polymer chains
And at that point
Then it becomes thermally unstable at room temperature again and the rest of it
Just vanishes
And by vanishes it take
Turns from a solid
Directly into a gas
Mentally disadvantaged right
Before your eyes
The first time you see it it's
Truly amazed
Is actually the second time you see it a truly amazing at everything is amazing and clever
Chemistry to bring into the capability of
Advanced Materials
And this step the program was successful enough in your eyes that you created a follow-on program
That's correct so
We were brainstorming one day
What else Beyond microelectronic
Could we do with these material
We were thinking where else could we push this materials
What else would
Lead the new fundamental Discovery and developments and could be also at the same time useful
Department of Defense and we came up with the idea of Vanishing Edge
For being able to deliver things
In a very precise way into difficult-to-reach locations
And then not having a leave behind
That could either
Destroy the environment
Or
Lead II detection
Of the deliverer
And so the Icarus
Was born
And that program is currently in Phase 1
And
And is developing
Vanishing
Are delivery Platt
Right and I didn't want to be exciting and potential
Locations for lease
Kinds of
Vehicles would be
In sort of Public Health
Disasters disease outbreaks
Tell us a little bit about those kinds of humanitarian
Applications of your
Absolutely so one of the first things when we started brainstorming about the idea Matt Hepburn who's a program manager
Started interacting with me introducing me to
The idea of being able to deliver Medical
Pool supplies used
Exciting
Thinking about things where there's been a humanitarian disaster
And the runways are
How destroyed
Roads are impassable
How can I get
Really critical supplies
Vaccines
Blood medications
Water
Two locations that need it
Work needs to be precisely delivered
And do that in kind of in some cases a massive response
Without having to worry about
Going and collecting all of these
Is air delivery
How do I get
Not only the thing to biodegrade and disappear back into the environment but how do I make the cost low enough
That you can basically have a glider
But you don't care if
If you ever go
This is an exciting time in the life cycle of
The program right because I know that in the coming months you're going to move
Outside
The glimmer of the eye in front of a laboratory work
Battered vehicle
That's correct so we have two things that are going to be coming up that way
Will conclude phase one of the program
A1 is a flight test
Launching from 35000 Ft
Showing a range of 150 km and Landing with 10 m of accuracy
And doing that with a material surrogate
So the glider is made out of a material that has
As exact as possible the same material properties as the vanishing material and the same
Factoring process
These were trying to test out
Can we actually meet
These flight profiles
Using something within the constraints
Some of the material properties in manufacturing
Ava Vanishing with
At the same time we are also building a non flying
Demonstration
Of the vanishing
Material for example we might build not instead of a full airplane
Just the wing of an air
Build that out of the vanishing material and show that we can actually construct a
A complex structure from the vanishing materials
And then one year after those flight test we will do
A flight test of the actual Vanishing
Air delivery
Alright well I will be excited to
Keep track of that and we'll applaud with you when we
We see our first vehicle do a job and then
I want to move to another program this one goes by the
Name in
0 which
Connection with the hour Evermore sensor Layton world and so tell us a little bit about end
Yes on0 is a program that
Designed
To basically take the internet of things and move it right
To the tactic
So today when we think about the Internet of Things
It can't be what we will really want
We can think about applying it to our refrigerator or
Toaster maybe our car
But we're really limited the things that either can be
Plugged into the wall
Or that a human can take in
Plug in the device
Go everyday or every couple days to recharge
And that's because
The Energy Efficiency of our Electronics operating off of small cheap batteries
Today is not high enough
To sit there and monitor the environment all the
All the time
Report back things that it's
So what we're trying to do in in zero is take out of a new paradigm
Where we actually look
Very low power levels are near zero power to me means less than 10 nanowatts
And I chose that value because that's
The leakage of a
Small coin cell battery
What we want to do is be able to sit there
Continuously monitor the environment
Looking for an event
That weird
AR
Specifically tuned to the doesn't happen very often but can't be missed
And then be able to wake up these higher power consumption
Consuming Electronics
When we see
So you can imagine what kind of events could those be
Those could be like
Augmenting Bridges and infrastructure with these types of sensors
Looking for
Specific failure modes
Earthquakes
You could imagine putting these throughout the environment we're thinking about augmenting vehicles to be able to look
4 and find engine failures earlier
How you could imagine dispersing the environment and detecting things like
Forest fires
Chemical leak
Or other things of that nature we were whole class of these types
The censors looking for
Acoustic vibrational infrared
Chemical
And RF
All being developed
All that can sense these very specific profiles
Reject background interference and consume less than 10 nano
They basically sit there
Always active always listening
But consume basically stand by type
Fascinating to think about
The world becoming an innervated with all kinds
Our bodies are
I want to move on now to just one more
Program this goes by the name amoeba that spelled a.m.
EBA
And the one form of that is a mechanically
Based
Antenna and I'm particularly interested in this because I think it reveals sort of the way you
Apply your engineers mine too
This invisible world of
Of radio frequency signals
That's all around us
Talk to us a little bit about
Okay sure so
Amoeba kind of comes from my love of looking at problems and
Thinking about the ways we solve them today and how those are insufficient and if we could just do it this other way
It would be so much better but we have some technology that standing in our way
That's what we're trying to do is be able to communicate from really difficult in fire
Do you like underground or underwater
Pour over very long distances
Without some type of
Repeater network
And finish your point out right through ground and through
Water
Radio signals do not
Travel very well for those media
I would say
High frequency radio signals don't travel very wealthy
Apus media
And
The key then it stopped right at low frequency
And that presents
A very significant challenges that the wavelength
At low frequencies is extremely long
And in fact that's the reason that they propagate well through
Water and ground is because the
Very long and
That allows the signal because of the physics to be able
Propagate
Through those media over much larger dementia
So the way we build antennas today
We basically push current through wires
Either kind of straight wires
How to build things like Alexa
Dipole antenna is or
Do coils and other things
And
It's very very difficult to
The produce a significant amount
Dove in our case magnetic field
When the antenna is very electrically small that means small was
To the wavelength using those techniques
Fabulous at higher frequencies
But when you get the very low frequencies
Where you want to make something then in our case
Would be man-portable
It just
Seems nearly impossible to make an antenna with any type of
Efficiency
At those size scale with the military does have some antenna systems
That can operate in these
Low frequencies but they're in Normal
Yes lyrics either
The size of Hawaii Islands or counties or sometimes they Traverse States
How to communicate these bands in other cases you might
You really a very long wire that's a kilometer in length out of an airplane to communicated these free
Frequencies button
In any case the dimensions are very very large
So it's going to be
Take a lot of interesting physics
To go from
Something of that size
Like to a man
Technology that will
The same
One-way flight
That's correct and so our Insight was that
When we pushing those
Current through those wires what we're doing is work
Creating electric and magnetic
And we're expending energy to create
I'm in and of course we do that at specific rate
To determine the freak
And what we did was we looked and said well what if we just started with something that actually had a high amount of stored magnetic
Wakefield for example like a permanent magnet
And instead of
Then using our power
Create that magnetic
Mayfield we would take advantage of what Nature has given us
Which is this
Permanent magnet
We've created it and and
And machine data but it's a
Natural
Material phenomenon
And instead we created the RF frequency by movie
And then we also had the Insight that
Moving things mechanically becomes very efficient
The lowering
You go so while I mechanical base Nintendo made
Be completely inappropriate
Where your iPhone operates at gigahertz
Hertz frequency
In fact
A very appropriate at a kilohertz type frequency to
Take a magnet
And spinach
Or mechanically move it
To create an oscillating Magna
Medic field course magnets aren't the only things that were looking at their other types of
Materials that
Store
All these types of permanent Fields Electric
Electric dipoles and there are there types of
Materials that are will be looking at in
The program as well
Another Insight that we had
Was that if we just took one really big thing and tried to move it
That the amount of stored mechanical energy there would be very high and that also would be
We do a lot of inefficiency
So one of the really key ideas of the amoeba program is can we break that
Large thing up into a number of
Small synchronize things
That lowers the total stored energy
And lowers
The power can
And the risk
That we're trying to mitigate is
Howell smaller pieces can we break it into butt
Before the interactions between the pieces batik
Kaley the magnetic intellect
Interactions
Queen
Started
Dominate
The overall system
You can imagine two magnets that are closed
Together have a lot of force between them they interact with one another
The trying to manage and control those interact
The risky part
The program that
Okay if you get utopian and you imagine this program being a
How successful do you want to be
Give us a sense of what additional Communications capabilities
It would offer up
Yeah so this is a low frequency transmitter so you're thinking about things like Voice and text
So at these types of frequencies is not really possible to do things like
Video
But it would give you a new capability safe from underground if you were a minor
To be able to
Text or do voice to somebody above ground
Something like a mining accident
How you can tell somebody where you are at and you would have that
Type of communication
Similarly from underwater Maybe
50 to 100 m under water
One could communicate
Text from underwater to the surface
Or to something even flying
What's today is
Is it just not
And there's one other applications
It's quite interesting to me and that's
The way these low frequencies can travel through the atmos
You're an unusual way so that
Potentially could
Enable
A very long distance communication
In between two points
That's correct so
At a slightly higher frequency say around ten kilohertz
There's a waveguide this form between the ion has
Sphere in the surface of the Earth
We often use that waveguide to bounce
Signals off of
In What's called the high freq
Booty band
So things like ham radios
Work based on that
But you have to know the
Location of the receiver to know how to bounce it down to
For sale if you don't know that you'd much rather
Feel that wave God
With the RF and that's what happens at say
Lake Tenkiller
Trying to build something that can actually
Couple
That waveguide and once you couple of that waveguide the propagation physics
Or the loss of the RF as it travels over distance
Is very favorable compared to
Things that don't propagate
And so that's what would enable you to reach these really long range communication
Thinking things again like Voice and text over hundreds of kilometers
From something that you can really hold in the
In the palm of your hand
Just not possible today using other
Technology
We've talked about four different programs and when I think about all the
The different technical
Components
It's rather amazing so
This makes me you don't realize that your engineer's mind really covers a lot of territory
I think we once had a discussion where you telling me that in some ways you think the
Cast of the engineer is quite a creative one
I really kind of a
Connection
Math problem solving engine
And the creativity that we might even see an artist
I'm just wondering if you got some thoughts about that
And how you might comparing
Ways of
Exercising our minds
Yeah so that's actually an idea that I have borrowed from my thesis advisor can wise who
At the University of Michigan
On their North Campus they have centrally located
Art music engineering and I believe architecture
And his point was all day
Basically stuck all of the creative fields
Together this is
Some people might not think that
Music and Engineering would go together but he think that was his Insight that
Becoming an engineer and being an engineer require quite a bit of creativity
I think particularly if you want to make anything more than an incremental Improvement
To the way things are done today
It really requires the type of creativity to look at the way that they're done understand the limitations of the
And then come up with some
Completely new approach
That would allow you to get Beyond those limitations and make
You're the 10x 100x
Jumps in performance
We're all seeking particularly here at DARPA
Creativity
Huge part of
Being able to found new programs particularly in areas that are not obvious
Apps that aren't leading like from one program to another
How do I get off this certain trajectory
And get myself on a different trajectory which
Is the one I want
And I think it's really the creativity
That allows you to make
That kind of
Before we close tribe
Just wondering if there is a science fiction
Technologies
The technology that you might have learned about when you were kids you might have read a great science
Fiction book you saw something in the movie You Came
Up with the sides of yourself
I bet does not exist now but that you really think or two
Well absolutely
I think
Both come from Back to the Future
So I am
Actually optimistic that one day I might get a hover
Car
And I would love to be able to do time travel
Self I'm not too optimistic about that one
But
You never know
Well it's so if you could do time travel would you be more interested in going back
Or forward I would definitely be more interested in going forward in time is
I knew you were going to say that
This has been absolutely amazing we've gone from Vanishing materials and Vanishing vehicles to sensor
Words that use almost
No energy at all but are paying attention to the environment
Are we talked about
Hover vehicle so at this is just been an amazing conversation
Information
And I want to thank you Troy for
Thanks Ivan I really enjoyed it
And thank you listeners for sharing this
Time with us
I hope you
Join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information about Troy Olson
His programs
And the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA. Mill
And four links that enable you to download this pod
And all the other
Go to the Voices from DARPA page
Uncharted