The internet
Your hands
Technology is a driver of our times
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects
She has Benadryl
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window at the DARPA score of program managers
Their job
To redefine
What is possible
My name is Ivan Amato on your DARPA host
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Paul Thomas known since
His day one as Rusty
Because he arrived in the world with
Red hair
Since September 2017
Rusty has been a program manager in the agency
Is Tactical
Technology office
Which has a penchant
For pursuing audacious vehicular Technologies
For the airspace in Oceanic domain
Already Rusty has made it his mission at DARPA to do what he can
To develop new Concepts
App that will deliver more resilient
Global reach
And Network
Connectivity by way of new space
Rusty joints DARPA from
Daiquiri
Daqri
In augmented reality services
Does company even though it does sound like
Where he served as the Executive Vice President for Global operations
He also held positions in a slew of commercial space companies
Among them SpaceX and orbital Sciences has been in on the design and management of an amazing portfolio
Space-related programs including the SpaceX Dragon spacecraft
The DARPA microsatellite technology
Experiment or my texts
The Iridium low earth orbit satellite constellation and the US Air Force geosynchronous
Space situational
Apple wellness program
Is initial training for all of the
Just came in the form of a master science degree
Inner Space Engineering from the University of
Texas Austin
And a Bachelor of Science
5 Degree in Aeronautical and astronautical engineering
From Purdue University
That's why I say wow let me say to you Paul Rusty Thomas welcome to the Voices from DARPA
Studio thinks Islands great to be here today
Thanks for having me
Before we get started on your life Adventure on the Forefront of
Space technology I want
To let listeners in on something that will not come through in your voice
Sir words
At 6 ft 8 in tall you are among the tallest
People at DARPA though remarkably not even the tallest
It does make me wonder though how you manage to fit into those thin shells when you were on the Purdue crew team
And if your fuel cost when you fly your own Piper Dakota plane
Higher than they would be if a 5-foot 8-inch guy like me where the pilot
Well yeah so it does cause me a lot of pain on airplanes
These days that is that is true but I'll tell you
I'll be in tall was great I grew up in Indiana and
I learned to play basketball and for some reason.
Because of that song
BBS x-rays a good thing overall
And and I'll take it
Alright well one of the things I always want to hear
Programmatic
Who are with me in the studio is
Where they got their start
Send their where their interest
Just came from
In going to science
Engineering and Tech
Technology so what to put that question
Into you okay yeah great I will I'm aerospace engineers you said and I'd like a lot of aerospace engineers
Growing up in the 70s and early 80s
Really saw what NASA was doing
My grade school had a special readers
Where you could go in and see the history of what NASA. Even back in the 60
And I remember pulling over those in great detail
When I was a kid
The real kick for me became a
A career day that my schools have an eighth grade where they actually pulled my father in
And I realize that my dad a mechanical engineer and his grandpa is my grandfather his father
A civil engineer I've been doing some pretty interesting things their entire career and they were staying on The Cutting Edge
Of what was going on my dad work for General Electric
Taking the Plastics industry
When I was getting big in the 60s and 70s
Am I grandfathered work for Northwest
And putting all your fields
Never do any Orient
Cathay pacific routes
Through the through the forties and fifties
He also helped design the the guardian of the airport
So how'd it had
Two generations of of of engineering behind me and at that career day
I actually have my my dad was one of the people presenting and he walked through the different types of engineering and
At the bottom of this was Aerosmith
I did not know that was an option
And all the sudden it clicked for me
Aerospace engineering
It's something I could do and I can focus on it and continue on and do what I tell my dad do
Enter the really Innovative idea
New Concepts
So with that I was in state for for Indiana and Purdue is a great School
So I can
Got jumped at the opportunity.
They're so while at Purdue we had
Quite a few amazing professors
I want of them professor andrisani
I would give us talks about
How
You could do no better in your career as an engineer especially
If you stay on The Cutting Edge in an advanced technology advanced what Humanity can do
The back of my head. Those words and run with me for the last 25 years if I
Kept moving to where is the most advanced technology
How can I
Help the most
Well those sound like two great lines of influence I mean you know what Dad and a teacher like that
And wow have you run with it so one of the things I would like you to do here is to take
Our listeners on a kind of
Whirlwind tours you can't really
Dwell too much on any one thing you've done I'm in your CV
Is just one of the most amazing documents I've ever read
But if you can take us for a whirlwind Tour on your
Experiencing in the commercials
Commercial space absolutely so
I didn't internship at a small Engineering Services Company and we've got to I got to work on NASA and with with a space shuttle
Back and lay.
But what really got me going the commercial side was right after grad school
I got the option to go to Motorola
We're firing up the Iridium low earth orbit constellation
Proliferated low earth orbit satellites at work cross-linked and providing Global conductivity than our planet
Constellation very large 66 satellites + Bears fill the goal was to build
1 satellite per week
And launch the entire constellation of of fuel 70-80 satellites including spares
In one year
Never been done before and to do that we would use a large number of launch vehicles
And a Motorola
I never
Design space
So
They put all that together and and Batman and 1890s was happening the Motorola had a really good plan
And they pulled in a lot of experts say pulled in sub subcontractors like
Rockies radio on Hoover expert
Masseria
Put together the team
And we ended up building at a rate of 1
Spacecraft
Every 4.3 days
We launched
3 continents are in just over
In 8 days
14 satellites were launched off all the side like somebody 2 months
And actually before you move on to some more of your commercial
Space
Experience I remember just talking with you at another time when
Impress I think
It was on this project the Iridium project
Took you around the world
To some of the other
Space cultures out there like in China and an in Russia
So I'm just wondering if
You can compare and contrast a little
Better be kind of space cultures
That's that you have experience being part of the
Hours here and then witnessing
Are those elsewhere when you get to any other
Country any other location that's doing
Rocketry or
Spacecraft design
You really grow in the closet
Type of engineer
That
You can relate to earlier
The people that do that or the are very similar no matter what culture they come from
I was very amazed how quickly you can make friends with
The Russians are the Chinese anybody who was
Who actually watches we're launching on the proton rocket 7 at a time on the on the
Iridium
Ever launched into at a time when the Chinese
I-5 a Time on Delta 2 is out
Atwood remain launcher
How to Vandiver
I rotate between the launch bases in California
Baikonur Kazakhstan where the proton rocket was launched
Also go to Moscow for Innovation meetings
Over to Beijing for the Chinese immigration meetings in Taiwan
Launch bases are
We was very interesting program and really I found it
The Russians and the Chinese
Well the Russians invented
Roxy as we know it just the same time we did China was coming up to curb they were getting faster at an incredible rate they were getting better
Had an incredible race and I found it both Russia and China
Their cultures were
Unless analytically an American Heroes
They were very much driven by
Build test build test cycles and I found it really in the commercial
Space here in the US
We're so pretty well we do those
Will you move out of the Analytics
Don't spend a year or two trying to figure out exactly how to optimize a problem
The build something that maybe a sub-optimal test it and then use that result to go to the next phase
Of modeling and use that model activate is that the one thing really really really good
Who died in the u.s. is very good computers and a very good computer algorithms
Analytically
Predict what it what a rock it would do under structural load
Or under guidance navigation control algorithms which is great
But it doesn't really tell you
Everything that could possibly happen during a flight
Rise of flight actually does tell you that
Before we move off of this little a block where you're describing an international framework
Forgetting so many satellite
Share with our listeners kind of funny experience
But you had with the Russian team when
They were trying to figure out what they should act
Actually call you
I'm so
When I started working at Motorola we would have
Every other month we have
Betacular Chase meeting with either the Russian launch Team or the Chinese launched
So you have one each month
When the Russians were
What kind of town or when we go to Moscow
I will have the stereotypical long table
What's with all the Russian someone sign all of us on your side in the trance
When they
Ask
Eminem produced everybody
They got to me and I said my name is Rusty Thomas
They stopped the meeting
Will briefly and MSR talking to translators and it came back and said
Is that your real name and I said well pause my real name
Osborne Paul Thomas
I need my grandfather's but
Not since the second or third day been around
She's been a nickname
At and they and they went back and talked about and they said okay we get it
Paul Pavel that's a good name we're going to call you Paul
And I am
What's find some people to call Paul bit most people your Motorola nomias Rusty
And and they'd end up coming back and saying
Well we're going to call you Paul and the reason is we've discussed it and and we don't have the nickname Rusty here in in Russia
And we don't feel comfortable with
Calling teddy bear
So they decided not to call me corrosion and I was Paul from there at I've been up all on and off
Since since that time
Smooth working team I want to take you back to that whirlwind
A tour of your experience in commercial space that I wanted you to do but I took you in a diversion so let's get back to that you said you talked a lot
Then I moved up to Seattle following where is the most advanced technology
Happening
Seattle in the late 90s was was really happening place
Molottery
They'd also a new company that was founded
Coachella desert
Had some money coming in from built Bill Gates
Craig McCaw
Titans in them
Communication then
Computer Industries
And they wanted to build a global low earth orbit satellite constellation to do broadband
Station call Telugu
We
Got pretty far into that design
But the technology the time was wasn't quite there miniaturization that as we know it today really wasn't there
And the.com crash of 2000-2001
Made it really hard for us to get that financing so we ended up
I'm not going forward to that program
I even though we had gotten FCC license for a lot of spectrum and I and it had a really good chance of
Major success
And it was at its base
I'm a very compelling architect
I moved from there and did Engineering Services
In San Diego
I had a really good time at some of the
Early days of uavs
Predator and Global Hawk
Not to be insulting down there for the early UAV designs
And then move to
Orbital Sciences where I got into the governor
And then after
Keeping a commercial side going
After the orbital Sciences
The curb
I went to space X
Savage in 2011
And I worked as the
Senior director for Dragon production
I building a capsule to go to the space
So it's been 5 years there
And I had just an amazing amazing run
Putting
Putting almost
Those capsules up also
I got to work on the landing legs
And CNN
Play a good part in the
Historic Landing
Most of those first
Right and just weeks really before this
Discussion we're having now
Eight dragon
Captured it arrived at the internet
For May
Resupply mission
When you see that we had it how do you
Feel knowing
Intense Pride absolutely that's that was it a turning point in How We Do
How we do space missions how NASA contract
Four four things how NASA moves forward to technology gets
The Cutting Edge
Develops at
I didn't can move that technology
Two companies like the SpaceX
Pictures of the world
Who can use that to build a commercial
And then allowing NASA to move on to the next
When I was at SpaceX
We went from doing one rocket a year
One Dragon every year to
Dl456
Dragons for year
And and now SpaceX is ramping up to
2030 +
Launches in a given year
It's really been an incredible time to see
That
Approach to how you do commercial space
Turn on and become a reality and then become a success and it
I'm really a major
Okay so you served
Told the story already here if you kind of growing up professionally along with
The commercial
Space sector which
Which is just kind of an amazing thing to think about
But you then
Made a decision
How to say yes it when when the offer came through to become a program manager here
I'd like to hear that the sequence of events that
LED you in this stage of your career from that the end of the commercial activities you've been in
And now here as a
First European
By chance I happened to an early 2000s be talking to some friends of herbal science
And they said there was an
Very interesting program
What's it called Mike
I didn't know much about it it was a DARPA program
It was classified with the experiments were but it was it was
Real I don't know that existed
The time it was just a DARPA experimental program to do a demo
Of this technology
And a little was looking for people who had my type of background little bit of commercial
But also have the right to
Ticket so I could do the work
And and they brought me out for a three-month stint and I was just going to help do some analysis for that space
I did some analysis
And after 3 months
It looks like dark was going to continue the program orbital wanted to keep expanding so they asked me if I would stay on as the Mets
Manager for the for the design that so I got to
I got to run the design of the
Of the spacecraft
And so I stayed in an oral for not three months I end up
Upstand for body
And during that time frame we work through the my text
The bass trap I got to
Do the design and build
We actually
How to get through immigration launched it and I went out to Schriever Air Force Base
As a vehicle engineer
And got to be on Console flight for
So it was a really good experience I wasn't commercial commercial it was government taking
Commercial approach is orbital is very was if there's a commercial company
And and this was experimental process that wasn't
Grit
Performance driven program it was there to prove some key technology that
We could use in space
It was it was successful
And
Is very proud of it
The results there
That kind of got me into what
DARPA
Step into an area work
Where there might not be a
Set nyora set
Set a requirements or asset
Funding line
And say
This is technology that would really help
The Warfighter help
The country
An insignificant ways
And and
And say we're going to prove it
Is it possible that
The proof
Is here if we can actually spend two or three years and some money
Actually get a demonstration of a run
Not open my eyes to what you can really do outside of the commercial world
But still using commercial approaches as much
I'm so follows on from there and and
Become a deputy pm at on the G7
Gsapp program you mentioned earlier
A geostationary space situational awareness program
Is Air Force program of record now that is doing very well
It's up in Geo and
It's acknowledged but
If it'd be very very good capability and and it's doing a lot of good feedback
From the people use it
So the GSAT program
Very successful
And after
Got to the critical design review I happen to have the opportunity to
To go to SpaceX they were just firing up so I already talked about that
It was it was a wonderful five years
At the end of that
I was at
Daiquiri
Doing the operations job
I'm setting up the augmented reality Global operations manufacturing four-footed what's going to become a revolution
I'm my positronic realities can be a very
Very big
And just a two-sentence description for listeners you might not know what you mean by augmented reality augmented reality is the
Ability put on glasses
Is that I will augment the information that you're seeing it real information with
With computer-generated 3D graph
Is that that actually will float in space
You can put tacks you can put Graphics you put anything you want
And it was good to be contextualized around
Natural objects in space
Not virtual reality locks you out and you don't see anything
And augmented reality you actually have
Still see the people in the room you still see all the objects
But it's adding information and I have seen I think a multisyllabic
A phrase for this
Software to find holographic light controller that related to itch
It is in the most advanced versions of
Of augmented reality and Daiquiri had some of the most advanced
Holographic light control
Technology
Okay so now I suspicion is
Confirm that you actually are are going to
Developed is the starch
Enterprise at some point in your career getting back to how you actually
We got to do.
The final turn to get me back as a program manager
Became win
The concept of the
The Blackjack constellation
I did not come up with you is already been formulated by
Experts here in a little bit more about that right after this great
Great salt darpet contacted me
I said we're going to go forward with that proliferated low earth orbit architecture
Start to change How We Do
Space missions right now we do space missions with
Very exquisite
Very cape
Will satellites actually cost a lot of money
So therefore we can't build very many
And end up
Low earth orbit proliferated
Quotes that iridium
With the communications in in the 90s until odesza
I was trying to do
And and other companies have taken
Is a different approach to put
Smaller
Lower cost
And and something to someone
Expendable Expendable is low reliability
The key element is
Small and lower costs
Satellites at bettering very low earth orbit
So you can cover the entire Earth with
Coverage
And like we said earlier was it six or seven satellites will usually do it to give yourself constant coverage
And the end DARPA
Let me know if they were going to move forward
With the experiment
To try to move into Augmentin
What do use x
The satellites can do
With a Leo low earth orbit
Proliferated
Constellation
When that opportunity meant I came in
David tok
And I was a match made in heaven
It's not like there's ten thousand people in the world
I really do think in terms of matching terms of what does DARPA wants to do with the and in what these type of
Constellations can do
In the future in my background if it's a really good match I'm a very excited
Be in this position
This time it's for
Let's talk about blackjack in a little bit more detailed
Tell me a little bit about
You're kind of the elements
Of that
Even before we start that can you tell
Listeners and me
Where the name comes
Sure
The the concept of of the Blackjack is that instead of having
Sensors
In space
That might
Come out of one or two or three
Points at the sky
You could potentially put smaller sensor
Locations
Give the
Destroyers are the
Surface Action Group
Commanders of the world or the Army Commanders
Or Airforce anybody
The ability to look over the horizon with a small number
Of of discrete sensors
That that actually
. the sky in some way
Well if you go to a casino
And you look up
You see on the ceiling
You see all the little domes
Those little dolls real tiny little sensors
And they're making sure that nothing bad's going on
So the concept of blackjack is to follow that
Distributed sensor approached
You see in a casino at work
You don't have one or two large
Systems making sure that everything's work
Okay and make sure that
There's no cheating going on today
Sit in the car and just just for the record for our listeners we do need to point out the garbage does not get all of its ID
Diaz from Las Vegas but probably more than we should maybe yes absolutely
So that the name came from that that someone playing Blackjack would have distributed sensor set around them
So it's kind of a tongue-in-cheek name but but it's a good name and it gets heavy across from that we give our talks
What we're doing
So Blackjack is this just as I said a low earth orbit
Constellation of sensors
That we're going to leverage in a key element of this is leveraging the commercials
How to talk my my career Independence
You can do things
Very quickly you can do things very efficiently
With a commercial approach now that's not to say the government approached
How we prepare things the past is always bad
But in some cases you don't get the optimal solution
And you could do things on a lower cost in it
At a faster
Your schedule
If you tackle indifferent
Why so what did ideal Blackjack is it
Try a different approach
Use
Low earth orbit
Use proliferated
Commercial satellite
Lights out
Especially the buses where we will marry
Military pay loads to those commercial buses
And then start flying a large number of them so you can give that
Proliferated Global constant custody constellation
Can I say constant custody that means
The commander wants to look at a given spot on the Earth
You can point the sensor to a spot immediately
Because it is going to be a satellite overhead any given
Give you the word and in a way I hadn't heard before
Proliferated just want to make sure I understand what that means in this framework
Proliferated means mulch
In the space
Spread out over the surface of your accept
Any person on the on the ground is going to be able to look up to see if Blackjack satellite
350 Campos constellations developed
In the sky at any given
And that's got into the reciprocal approach work
That is
If the Blackjack satellite is always going to be able to any point of the Earth
At any given time
Right so there's there's some aspects of a sort of
GPS like system in the
But you got many satellites working in a clinic coordinator
Fashion
Delivering amazing kinds of in a data that would
Naughty
Impossible
Otherwise
Qxt talking about a lot more than the several dozen writer GPS
Talk just a little bit more about
The various kinds of challenges
That are
Part of this project
One of them
Certainly is is producing almost Mass producing very rapidly a lot of satellites
So you had you talked about your ex
But there's also going to be coordination there going to be command and control
What are some of these other elements
But you can talk to
Absolutely so first of all yes you your analogy to GPS
100%. Is a full up
Consolation
Add a medium or medium high altitude
With Blackjack window very low
500 km to 12in
Arrange that that's just above the Earth's atmosphere
For the satellites
And and the trick is going to be
Building since you're low enough you need more satellites than what I thought.
GPS constellation
So to do that you're going to need math
And do the
Look at the cost right you're going to need to build them
And I'm very short time scales with a minimal amount
Of assembly integration and test
And to do that
We're going to
Bring it as much
Commercial approaches
We've had an industry day
A very positive
Response from
From over a hundred thirty comfy
Signed up for intraday
And we had overturned 75
Folks who you wanted to come in and
And and listen to us
We believe that
That approach
Going with
Discrete
Low-cost nodes in space
Well I'll most Expendable Expendable but almost
It is going to be a terrible and we're going to use
That that commercial
And and commoditized both the buses and bring that to impedance match
The military payload
Still going on
The other key element today
Yes and you and other two that a second ago
That we don't
Launch
Hundreds
Or or more thousands of of the satellite
We don't want to require teams of multiple people per satellite monitoring
Right now the Expos
Satellites
Have X
Excellent teams app
People on the ground who are making sure everything that.
What satellite does his monitor
Are you going to analytically predict
Beforehand
What the response of any new strip the difference in.
What's going to happen
It's an excellent approach but
Really want to get autonomy into the blackjack
And when I say autonomy
I mean how does the mission control work
How does the resource planning work
How does the payload
In terms of what it seen working from
Can you move
It's a raw data down to the people on the ground can you victra
Verizon information
And contextualize it to what's important
Okay one of the other interesting things about
Blackjack program to me is because
You're not putting in a multibillion-dollar jewels up there
Large
Tremendously expensive
Assets
Need to stay over
There for years and years
Here you can do what I guess much more
Frequent
Technology refresh
Ice prism some of that can be done through software
We were always upgrading our
Are various applications on our computers
But this also does give you some opportunity to you know without breaking the bank
Putting up
I actually new generations of
Bellevue small satellite
Lights and still having them work within the black
Yeah yeah yeah
And there's two areas there
Better very important
And we're going to order Chase both of those
Blackjack first is
If your individual nodes right lower Thor bit your life
Is lower than going entire world
Your
Weight is less and the cost of individual satellite
So we're aiming for
A non orbit cost of
6 million dollars
/ node / blackjack
That includes a logic
Which means that if you have
The problem with one of those satellites
It's you can launch another one to replace it
Slot huge amount of money
And in the second piece is
Weather
Ability to do on an orbit over the air updates
The software
We're going to put large process
I called Pit Boss
Once again going with a blackjack
Approach right The Pit Bosses
Rains on each one of the other Blackjack notes
It's going to have
Teraflop
Class processor
On it or more
And
It's going to allow us to put a lot of algorithms
Sunspace and not only put a lot of algorithms in space to do the work up there with those Edge Computers
But it's also going to we're going to launch more process
Hey Billy that we need for the first generation
Because we
Expect to get better and better with her algorithms and now Grim's typically need more more process
So if you can
We talked about I work at SpaceX might
My boss they're also found another company
Call Tesla
And one of the really goldkuhl models of Tesla
What is you have a car and you might come out
And in the morning and it's not an over the air update
And you have a better car the next day to use
Did the prior day
Because they've updated alsop
So
I'm going to follow that type of approach putting a lot of extra
Capacity
For the processor so that as though algorithms get better you get a better spacecraft essential
Free Aloha por
Alabama
In terms of launching satellites
And I imagine you also have to think about
End of service when you're talking about so many
Discrete parts
Battery low earth orbit means it sounds like to me that these are going to deorbit in some way or another
Have you given that
Absolutely given that thought in that goes back all the way to the Motorola
Iridium constellation every iridium satellite
Has the ability to deorbit itself at the end of its life it has a
A small amount of fuel reserves left
Those fuel reserves aren't used for anything else other than a d orbital
And it has enough redundancy and the elect
Sonic soundboard
So bad it's hard to have problems with his primary mission
You can still fire the thruster
And bring us
Top down so that approach
Has been proven successful with the with the iridium in the commercial constellation
Are we going to follow
Same same approach with Blackjack and I believe
FCC filings for Mega constellations
Communication
Inside lights will be out there that'll launch
Even more satellites in blackjack
They're going to be good stewards I believe
Of of low earth orbit also in and put in the ability
So I decided light
Ends its operation like or gets replaced with a better
Tech refresh satellite it will immediately
Turn on defroster
Usually over
The South Pacific
Or somewhere relatively benign
These small satellites don't make it back down they burn up in the atmosphere during reentry
I'll make a wonderful shooting stars You Outta nowhere
And there may be many of them is that you think about him this is amazing to think about just all the peace
Dan Howard
The program it is
Are there one or two things about it that that stand out in your mind is
May be particularly
A reach even we're kind of DARPA program
Absolutely soba the biggest reach I believe is the amount of
Autonomy would like to put on the spacecraft
I've given a metric
If we lose the ground control that say we have a common problem or this some type of interference
And the satellites Orange
Talkin to the ground I want them to be able to operate at least for 24 hours as a consolation
Talking to each other
Do their systems
And and and
Managing their resources managed in the mission
Still providing whatever in defect
Oriental set of information
The Warfighter that
People downrange need
Without background image
So that's going to be interesting to say the metric is one day but
But really my stretch goal is
How to get the 30 days
Continuous operation
Without talking to the constellation while it's still performed
Primary mission
To whoever needs to have that information.
Generating
So putting that in the place is old as a significant Leap Forward
From the current operation
Since we have an operations control center on the ground
You sure the satellite health
A safety and emission is being managed properly
To one where you don't even have a human
In the loop
Removed a man
We go for a man
Man in the loop command on the loop
Work that.
The people doing a management
Are there to make sure and watch
And adjust priorities is necessary Force
But they're not there to make second-by-second, minute-by-minute decisions I have
Spacecraft
And what they do
Rats that's a really hard but fair amount of autonomy always with
Human beings there at Shepherds in an envelope in some way also
Absolutely
So you're a first-year
Program manager typically program manager
We're here for
Adjust a set several years 3 to 5 I have had some people here in the studio who have
Done several tours
Duty as well so p
Like it enough today
They come here they do one tour of Duty that go away then come back
I'm just wondering
If as a first-time program manager
You're with
A program of this
Complexity and size
What do you think this one program is going to be enough for you to satisfy your your technology interest
And just because it's going to be so hard to do or are you already imagining
I taking on additional programs
I'm actually already imagine taking on additional programs that goes back to my theme of how to get to the most cutting-edge element
Whatever you're doing your career
Blackjack has to be a major program ugliest NBA
A huge success and it's going to really lead
A pivot to low earth orbit
But once you start working in the low earth orbit
The regime and and once a DOD and DARPA starts working
And putting these systems in place
I can envision
Many other programs that will leverage this type of architect
Successful
Come out of blackjack
Once we build this
Global mesh Network
Match the internet in space a space arpanet
How can you use it to actually
Benefit the people on the ground
And I think there's a lot of
I just want to point out to listeners
That even though Rusty's
Is talking about a program like that
It does not mean that it is automatically going to become what he's going to have to really jump through a lot of poops and cut its a lot
If people guessing if that's something worth doing
So this really is it essentially glimmer of the eye that may or may not
I come to become a
A program
So so that's what it sounded like you might even have more idea I got a fuse II
I've been spun up with a world of augmented reality on what you can do with light control
Holographic light control is an area of of high-end
Krista me I believe that we are
Approaching that point where
The Holodeck seller will not recontest things after appearing but the ability for
Systems to transmit holographic light
Phase control the light and projecting the way that you are immersed in reality that
That isn't real but it seems real because your eye
Is getting
Baby getting fed the same information that would be
If the object
Was actually there
I believe the type of light controller just around the corner
And there's a good chance it's going to
Revolutionize
How We Do interact
Computer is an interaction with even people
It in the same way that the transistor revolutionized How We Do
And I think that's the coming the next five
10 years
And I really hope you get DARPA
I'm moving into the Edgewood listing the potential applications of that
Training just popped into my eye
My name is a huge not just training but
If you are deployed
If you have military person deployed
And you can have a holographic
Surgery
Show how how to fix somebody in your ear deploy during her very mode area
You can actually train somebody
In real time to how to do something
Because I can see it in 3D fight in front of them as it's happening
Wilder
Rejuv Medical
Training for welders
Training for another industrial applications
Becomes
Becomes much more advanced much more
That they've already done me
Study showing you can train somebody
Anywhere from 2 to 10 times fast
With augmented reality tools and he's all right
Light approaches
If you
Because your brain is
Program to absorb information
3D contacts
Much faster than you are with someone talking to you or reading a book
So when you stop when you see it
You absorb it
I think
Training is going to be an area that's going to Revolution
Another thing is
Came to my what is
Ergonomic
Turn Discovery so you might have
The space you want to figure out the best way to
Arrange things in that
Headspace
With this kind of
Technology Building
The test out a thousand different ways very efficiently cheap
That's right one of my early early
Crip moves was that that internship where I got to work on
NASA projects in we were developing 3D cat
The time in 2D CAD was the standard computer aided design computer aided designer that three-dimensional KitKat
Austin allowed you to mock-up
Engineering parts
God in Evan dufey check
Virtual picture
Make sure the parts wouldn't interfere with each other
And that was a huge boom Ford it really changed how engineering design
Mechanical
I believe the same thing will happen
We start doing this with interactive collaborative
Tools that allow everybody walk in and see
What's happening in 3D space
Without even needed
Computer screen
There's one other kind of Technology project
Does that
You work
This represents to me
How many thousands and thousands of
Of Technology and Engineering issues
Is there are when you're really
Thinking big
So you also were in on the design of
Crane operator
For mating
Satellite
Going into
Too kind of vehicles
Spencer
Components
Just one of the many many app
So this was an interesting invention we work as two or three of us at Motorola weird the problem we had
It was that Motorola was pitching the ship and shoot approaches base
Finish it on the production line
It went into a shipping container sat on the dock until
Where the Russian proton are the Long March rocket Chinese Long March
Or the or the
McDonnell Douglas Delta
Another set
Satellite
And that the launch campaigns were going
The Russians need seven.
And if that was the case we would
Call
FedEx and FedEx to show up at the Sky Harbor airport and we would load two or three satellites at a time
It would fly into Russia would load them up
And would get him out to the launch base and we want to put them on a rocket within a day or two
And and that's obviously not help int
This done right now and it with the salad we were looking for very fast like a
Sometimes very quick process
And to do that we needed to mate
70 satellites are very close to each other
Accurately and quickly
So we put together a
A crane
I think we called the swing and twist Eliminator
Workshop with mounted to the floor of the Russian immigration Hall in baikonur
And
Wherever
Every satellite would be brought in vertical state
Attached to this and then
Russian crane
Normally would swing these around a little bit as it moved in Philly
Didn't have any others
Neighbors you never get a satellite what next
But I'll need to Spencer
I was seven
Like wedges they were all very close to each
She had to control the twist
Swing
We got the point we can meet three
Of the satellites per day
And have all the the entire dispenser
Of seven satellites ready to go after 3 or 4 days
A process in Allendale
Fueled and be ready to lie
Okay so on top of everything else
Your crane guy
So yeah you're working on things that many of us would
Considered to be kind
Science
Fiction technology
Fiction though your go
Real are there non space
Technologies
That you
Just go nuts
Don space well I'm going to
Day of the arrow
Without the space let's go to arrow and I do believe
That
Transport of human beings list planets
It's going to get
When we're going to be able to move
At the hypersonic
A scale and in the knot
It's not an area of research for myself
But I'm I'm I'm exceptionally interesting I just curious
On how we're going to get some of the new technology
Tattoos becoming online worldwide
To the commercial space and how we might start moving people from
From from
What's a New York
Sydney
In an hour's instead of the
A 12 or 14
Plus hours
I think the
Very high-speed transport
I guess I died the Dozen
Hit your mark because you
Probably have to go into space a little bit during part of that flight but I still see some very high-speed flight supersonic
Hi Supersonics
The flight is being an area
Pinterest
I'm up
Significant
Potential
In the next 10 to 15 years
I think there's some teams
Kraken
Fret not open
Interserv ironically thinking big in this way to
To make the world a little smaller
Vicente Ginga from any point at any
That's right Blackjack will give you the mesh Network and communicate it
Red Broadband in
You can actually move the people
Give me the next step
Rusty you are a technology developer
You been doing that your whole life but
You also have taken time
Get into more of the mindset in the setting of The Warfighter
The warfighters
Find a survey
Bringing more
Capability
Can you just share a little bit with blisters back
Absolutely so I've been a reservist
United States Navy scents
And as an intelligence officer or I was
Lucky enough
To be selected
To go to Nichols
Special Warfare Intel School
And actually went out during the surge
Centcom areas
Desert areas
With the whistle
To help do Target
And a high-value
High-value targeting
And we didn't forget for the job we
Move through
Those areas and
And picked up a quite a few of the al-Qaeda
Mid-level operatives
And I
Put put them away
So
I still I still active I drill
A town in a little creek
Library month
Very very important part of my life
Although it's still as a reservist
Secondary
But I also Imagine
That
That booty
It's on the ground experience now as
The program matter
Completes a kind of
Luke for you that not all program manager
I think it does help the area that I think it helps the most in is
When you are down range with
Special Forces operator
The amount of bandwidth amount of sensing you can get
This amount of communication you can do
Is very limited
Are you you're typically moving data to a soda straw
And what I'm trying to do with the program manager here
Christy give those type of.
Floyd
Sailors soldiers Marines whatever they are
The ability to move data
At much higher bandwidth and to get data
From sensors that over the rise I'm not in a sealed organic drone unit
Immediately within second
Back to where they're at without having to go through a ground for
So seeing how it's operated
When I've been down rain
That is really helped shape hell
I'm setting up a technology
Detroit for the future with our
What's the rest of you've taken me and listeners on on an amazing tour of you know someone who has been in the apps
Thickest part of these last couple of decades music
Evolving
Space Tech
Call Jay so I want to
Thank you for doing that
It's really been a pleasure
No thank you it's it's been a bad that a great career I'm happy to be a DARPA and looking forward to the next door to get to break down and
We're going to be going to cut it
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices
From DARPA
For more information about Paul Rusty Thomas
The programs he and his colleagues in the Tactical
Cool technology
And the other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on visit
DARPA. Mil
And four links that enable you to download
Go to the Voices from DARPA page
Underpants