Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding nearly 60 years ago 19
58 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA the defense Advanced research projects
Nancy has been a driver
Welcome to
Voices from DARPA
A window on a door piskor of program manager
Their job
To redefine what is
My name is Ivan Amato when I'm your door post
Today I am pleased to have with me in the studio
Jim galambos
A program manager since 2015 in Darby
Technology office
Guys we will learn in just a few minutes
He's among the DARPA program manager
Overseeing programs
Under the systems of systems cattle
Which is to say
Very complicated technology
Frameworks with lots of
Components of moving parts
Among the Technologies he integrated into
Unprecedented Frameworks of Maritime defense
Include undersea communication
Unmanned vehicles in system
Maritime power and Energy System
Autonomous operation
And networking
Of man
An unmanned systems
Prior to joining
Jim was director of the advanced technology
At the applied research laboratory located at Pennsylvania State University
There
Oversaw
Portfolio
Restart
Including R&D and sonar systems
Undersea Power Systems
Pino's in unmanned
Jim Hearn
A bachelor's degree in physics from the u.s. Naval Academy and then serve Five Years on
Active duty as a nuclear trained surface Warfare off
In the US Navy
Following active duty he join the naval reserves
And earned his master's and doctoral degrees in nuclear engineering and plasma
Physics from the University of wash
Jim galambos
It's so good to have you
It's my pleasure to be here
Let's start by talking about your background
Bachelor's degree in physics when US Naval Academy and that's
Suggest to me
That you arrived at the Academy with some interest in science and the Navy
So where did those interest
Well I think my interest in science and engineering really came from
My father I was raised in a family that had a lot of engineer so that was
It's kind of an expected thing and
And I did pretty well in those subjects
Although I didn't really know what that meant like most students but I was kind of good at it and
One thing about the Naval Academy
80% of everybody was an engineer in those days so it wasn't a hard choice
And I would guess that your interest in plasma physics so that's what you
You studied in your graduate
Which is Central to the process of nuclear fusion somehow emerge from your time serving on a nucleus
Submarine which relies on nuclear fission for its
Propulsion
I think you said to me one time that day
When you did a lot of boiling of water
Tell me about asserted that that connection you have with both fission and fusion
Yeah well it was
I was an interest of mine
Just as I got into engineering the whole
Nuclear industry and and using fission to to make power and of course being in the Navy
The opportunity go on a submarine and
And serve
Was really the attraction that's what got me into it
The diffusion piece
Actually came about from
Experience I had at the Los Alamos in the summertime
I'm and I have to confess
I did that solely to get out of spending a hot summer in Maryland
Yelling at
Freshman
I look for ways to get out of that and one of the options was to do a research assistantship at
At Los Alamos National Lab
And I ended up working with a group in
Plasma physics
Doing Fusion work
And the key piece that was
Just breakthrough for me is
It was the first time that I was in a laboratory and we are trying to do something where we didn't know how it was going to turn out
Previous to that in classrooms Laboratories or those science fairs in high school
You were usually just trying to make something work
But you knew the answer it was just could you make it
Happen
And it was at Los Alamos where I finally
Saw
We were doing experiments and I realized he's really bright people
They hope they knew it was happening but the reality was we did experiments to find out and then we adjusted
And that was very exciting to me was to see this whole idea of
Really doing research
To explore as opposed to just
Just get something right so you could get a grade on a
Hyatt Estero
A lab report
So it was sort of
Excitement about
Discovery release
This morning about nature totally changed my
My whole View and that's what led to me choosing to do that for grads
It's cool I when I got out of the Navy
And then after your service and education you went off into the defense industry for a while you work on
Such things as
Underwater shocks
System
Energy weapons
Encounter rocket armor
And laser-based instrumentation
I also The Fantasticks
Phenomena and Technologies
And then you went into a more academic.
Still defense
Centric setting a
Penn State
And then somewhere along the way you intersect
With DARPA so can you
Intersection haven't actually my intersection happened when I left grad school and I joined the
The small company called Advanced power Technologies
In industry
Which was the small company where you mentioned some of those projects in undersea shock programs
For listening
Who don't. Know what that means how would you describe that
It's by the way I've had more fun than anybody should as far as the kind of range of projects we get to do
What we were looking at was the whole idea of cannae
Create an undersea Shockwave which means basically light off an explosive underwater
But do it in a way that we could shape those shockwaves
All pile up on top of each other
And smash something like
Am I
So we're actually looking at mine clearance doing that
Attend
That was an idea that we we sold to DARPA as something that they would be interested in seeing it
If we could make it work
And that became my introduction to DARPA
So what I'm reading from that thing is that you were what in darkness because you were performers
Yes and performers are those who end up getting research contracts working on some program
So you were a performer work on that particular project and then
I presume that
You met other program managers may be enough director and that led to a discussion
Yeah we we actually did a number of programs
I probably had three or four DARPA programs as a performer during those years
Then when I transition to the applied research lab at Penn State we picked up a couple of more
So I had had an ongoing relationship actually through multiple organizations
Of being a performer doing DARPA program
And exactly as you described is actually a
A former pm and then at the time Deputy office director kind lot
Kind of pulled me aside and wanted to see hey what I be interested in actually
Coming to this side of the table and
Conceiving ideas and being a program manager at DARPA
Okay and you quite evident evidently did come over here if I just go deep to your program manager patient
The website to vim at work
Talk to you more directly I learned that you have
Three programs on
Two of them the blue wolf
Program in the hunter program they both have to do with
Unmanned underwater systems
And then there's one very multisyllabic
Program
The cross domain
Maritime surveillance
And targeting program
Or known in short
As City mask
And that's really a program which
Zeroes in on that systems of systems idea
Of course which the other two programs kind of feed into is
Component systems of those systems of systems
So maybe we can talk about
City Mastin this whole idea of
Systems of systems which really is a
Phim
Throughout
DARPA you'll see that
Kind of category is defining
Many programs throughout the
VI technical office
So tell me
What rhymes with
This concept
Absolutely in a exactly in fact and this is what kind of need about DARPA this is what I talked
Dakine about as she was talking about bringing me in
What's to look at
We have this initiative
To do system of systems we want to look at a maritime version would you do that
Well
First you gotta understand what do we mean by System of systems and
It's really this idea that
As our defense has matured over the last few decades
And we make more and more capable platform
Set a good example would be saying airplane or a submarine
These are becoming very sophisticated platforms
Very capable
But they're also occur
Expensive
They also take a long time to make
And what we're finding is
To make them even better
Cost a lot of money
And time and you don't necessarily get that much more capability than you had
If you will it's kind of creating like an ass and topaz
You put more effort into it it's getting incrementally better
And the horse seems to be a limit of how much yeah yeah that it's it's tipping over
And so
The whole idea that is
Is there a better way to look at things to say if I really want to do with DARPA supposed to do which is
Major
Capability games and big straw
Is there a different way to look at
And one of the ideas is
Well how about if we distribute
Some of the functions that are on this planet
Farm so if you think about a platform
What does it have to do
It has two cents
It has to defend itself
If I platform you might be like that craft aircraft or a submarine
Exactly
So it has these functions I needs to sense it needs to communicate it needs to defend itself
It needs to do data processing
And if I put that all there it's great I concentrate it but now
As I said it's this
Incremental games and each time I make a change it affects the other stuff
What if I
Do the term we call where we disaggregate I take these functions say the sensing
And I
I put it on a lower-cost platform say like an unmanned system
That I can put
Farther away
So now I get an even greater sensing because instead of being stuck on my platform
It's now
Farther away and in broader and maybe I multiple
Or even up in the air so high up in the air exactly so I get high to buy advantages
The key pieces is I still have I have to be able to communicate
But if I can do that and
And handle the networking part to make all these things work together
Well now I'm really, using my adversary a difficulty
Instead of doing what they're doing now which is
Wearing lots of money into being able to go after these
Single platforms that are high value
Now they have to decide she do I go after this sensor thing well if I get that censor well if there's two others or three
3 more
Okay you got a little bit of my sensing but I'm still going and oh by the way the main
Aircraft or ship is still going
And so it forces them to now
Spread their forces
To cover more things
And this whole idea is
Try to do this in a way that
My total cost is less than what I would for
For just a single platform
But my capability is much
Priest
And the problems I caused for the other side or much
It sounds to me that it also add syrup to things like
Versatility and resilience
Answer the versatility now you can
Mix and match all kinds of different things into these systems of system
At the same time
One thing is taken out of the other you still have the
Brazilian swear
You're not thinking of him you're mad absolutely now you've right on because
That whole idea of you know I'll talk about it is adaptability
Maybe I want to change my mix
In real-time which means hey we know what the mission is and we need some better let's say jamming caper
Ability or something
I can put that in the mix
Much easier than
Change it out on the whole platform you kind of get what you get
Well now these are interchangeable parts
And you hit it on the head with resiliency
It means
They have more things to deal with and so if they take care of one or two of them
You know we like to use the term we degrade gracefully as opposed to either I'm all good
Or I'm done I'm done
And the other way it's adaptable is overtime
In the sense of
Hey technology is changing
That's one of the biggest fact
Actors for this
Is
We see it in our commercial world all the time and new iPhones are coming out new capabilities Udo
Web filming a movie I do all this stuff
I want my military systems to be able to adapt on those time scales
As opposed to
Going to be five years before we can build the next airplane
If I'm more discreet and disaggregated
It's easier to change those parts out
So both over long scale and and Realty
That's another thing I've been hearing about you a tarp another
Replaces the technology Cycles or just
Speeding up so much and so there is a century
Person getting much more
Agile in turning that psycho
Faster without
Expensive amount of time
Has taken in the past
Do that to go from version 1 to 2
Before so
I guess this is in the maritime domain
Can you be absolutely it affects all the domains and one of the issues there is you'll hear us use the term
Yeah one of the challenges
Disney faces
Composability
How can I get better
Quickly
Pulling these things in
And making them so that they go to vit gather
Easily and I don't have to do lots and lots of engineering and testing
To put these two things together
And that's part of the system of systems
Challenges is getting good at being able to rapidly compose
Pulley system
Okay so for some reason as you were talking about the desegregation I was I was thinking about a human body
Do you know which is a system of system
System of the liver
That's the system of cells
And if that were desegregated actually weeds
And it would still be a living body would then be just an amazing
Task
Command and communication and integration
Kind of a weird metaphor perhaps
But it seems to pretend you're so if you're taking apart what has been an integral
System like a carrier
And you're now disaggregating this into all kinds of pieces
What about that integration
That sounds like
The hard problem absolutely in and you've done two things and I like the body example because the easiest thing to think of
About is you know your eyes are primary sensor in our nose
How much better could you surveil
If you had a set of eyes that were
Udo
50 yards in front of you and you had an extra nose that you could put out there that's what we're trying to do
But now you hit it on the head is
Well
It works good my body because those nerve endings
You know they only have to go from my brain down to my nose or my eyes that's not too far now I'm putting it out there
So it puts a premium
On being able to set up
Effective communication paths that are reliable
Because otherwise
What good is that knows it's just sitting out there that could smell everything but if it can't get it back to the brain
Its of no value
And so you
Tide in when we talk about the system of systems programs
Sometimes people a squirrel
You're not really developing a lot of new technology you're kind of using existing stuff and they're exactly right
The DARPA hard part that
Challenges
Yeah but I've got to do this now
And make these reliable
Communications
And networking
And and functions you know now I've got instead of two eyes I've got four
Well I've got to have a brain now that can handle that which means
How do I sequence things and do things because I'm getting more information
It's a good analogy to see what we're trying to do with the system assist
Right and again
We talked about.
Eberhard
We're talkin about systems of systems when you are
Entertaining very ambitious
Ideas like this
Word connect
We trying to make them so
What all so then comes in here or issues then of communications
Security I mean
I might want to try to spoof the system or I might want to try to
Jam it and so suddenly
These kinds of considerations
Become part of your overall
Oh absolutely
Becomes a huge
Because
I can't afford to have somebody Co-op
You know
My forward eyeballs and
Turn them to look to the wrong Direct
Now they're no good to me
And so
It's a good example of Technology were taking advantage of things but you always have to then look at what's the counter-move
And
And and do this traitor
And by the way this is why we're doing this at DARPA it's not a hundred percent certain
But this is the way to fight in the future
It's our hypothesis and there's a lot of evidence suggests if you can do it it's a great way
But that's a big if and that's why we're doing the research
To see can we really make the
This work NBC
Secure
And reliable and all these things that
Rice cereal
Probing what is possible in an in
If it is past
Even if it is
Desirable in the Rye
When you do get together with other program managers hear other other profession
Hope you're at DARPA
How to talk about systems of cyst
Who are you talking with what other what are some of the other I guess
Programs that you think of
When the systems of systems category
Yeah and it's fine there's kind of two variants that I do so when I talk to other
What I would call
True systems assistance PM's another program managers who are doing other system assistance program
You know
In the defense Sciences office
John paskewitz
He's really looking at
Hey can I come up with mathematical constructs
To help me do that composition instead of
Hey I think this looks good let's try it and now let's go from there
So we talked a lot about
Hey how can I have machine learning and intelligence help meme
Pull this stuff together
An interesting Lee we almost always end up with
Logistic
Because one of the issues is
Now I've got more things Fredo
Park
How do I get them there and how do I sustain them you know the body works well the eyeballs come with the head
And it's a nice package
Now I've got these two extra eyeballs out there
Who's going to hold on to those and keep them care and fed etcetera
The other way though that I talked to PM's about programs
Is
How does there
Particular technology so maybe they're making a better unmanned aircraft
Or
A better sonar
Where does that fit into the system assist the weird of those systems fitting where do they fit in and that's where we
We've had really fun dialogue because
Often that's one of the big problems for technology
Somebody can come up with a great idea for a better sonar and they'll work on that and they'll develop it
But then it kind of ends up on the
Porch of the Pentagon with
We have this great sonar but
Where do I put it and how should I employ it in an in do I buy 10 of them or do you know
What's interesting in system of systems you're starting to think about the whole
And it helps
Guide some things to say you know what we really need that sonar to do
Is
Be able to look wider not necessarily farther
Or
Different things that might help direct their work but at the same time
We're giving them a great story to say
Here's where it fits in and my gosh
Does it make it
Write something interesting dialect
You're putting out
Potential Technologies
Capabilities
But then you're getting back information
From the field
The Commanders
The Wharf I right
Who actually giving you feedback and saying this is what we
Really need her this is what we've experienced than then
Aviator perhaps in that dynamic
You come up with something
It really does
Further
Absolutely and what's unique in this program that I've done that I've never done in my research
Career before
We actually spent a lot of time working with the Navy and organizations to
To create
A very sophisticated
Warfighting scenario
Very realistic based on
Excerpts from war plans
To guide our research and that's not
Normally done we usually kind of think
Okay I'll look at an engagement and this would help me defeat this aircraft if they came against me
Very rare to look at it in terms of hey what would I do to win the war and that's the phrase We like to eat
Hey this is great and that's a nice technology but does it help me win the war
And that's not usually a question that we ask
You know usually just say doesn't make me
Faster stronger better
Yasso
Bring in some language in here
There's there's another phrase that I've heard
Round DARPA and I think it must
Relate to this mess
Mosaic
Warfare how does that relate to systems of systems
Yeah Mosaic Warfare is it in some sense it's
It is a different name for system a system certainly
Sister Sister
Fits into it
But it's this whole idea of
Bringing lots of pieces together
And no individual piece
Does everything or tells the story but collectively
You now
Get
The picture
And what's interesting is
You can afford to lose a few pieces
And you still get the
The picture
And that's this idea of being able to
To compose
To make your mosaic
Tell a different message or in our case
Do a different function
For the military
And be able to
Put that together make it do that
Rearrange the pieces now.
Does something different tells a different story so to speak
And it can withstand the fact that like I said if a few pieces get knocked out
You're not done
So it's really that same idea but
What I like with the Mosaic is when you talk about this
The imagery of
Hey I can rearrange this tell difference
Stories to me that means
I can recompose and do a
Permission
Right now in a sense that's been
Going on for a long time I will we have
Different military services they different capabilities they working
Any kind of different domains and so you can almost think
You're from from a general point of view there there there has been this kind of mosaic
Thinking but
Here we're also
Bring that downward
Absolutely and there's a little bit
Udoka
Nothing's new but we're trying to take it to a greater limit
And and one of the biggest differences there is is we're really trying to bring in
Unmanned systems with mancis
And and again create this much more
Rapid adaptive
Because yes
Things have changed but usually it would take
Decades to say oh we're going to
Fight this way differently and I'm going to use it
This kind of system differently and in many years it'll come out and we'll put it together
And so you get
Very static
Kind of in how you operate
This is to be much more fluid
So it it's your right it's an extension but really trying to take it to that limit
You have had the
Experience in
Akadema
I'm a student side of things
You had industry experience
Your
Now working in a government setting
In particular therapist I'm just wondering now
How you view
DARPA
And the way it operates
In the overall Innovation ecosystem
I'm aware where does it fit you know we have the services that have more traditional hey we've got
These products and we need to get better so we'll do kind of product Improvement if you will as opposed to
Darp is hay
I'm going to
Create a whole new line of product in terms of
A whole new capability
And so it's the defense department Venture House
And really that's the way we operate
Fairly quickly pull ideas together
You then have an opportunity to make your case you need to baby due
A small project to get some data to
To backup your supposition
But then you go forward
And you meet with the tech Council and in a very
Short
Time
You'll get an answer that says yes let's go forward and now you're Off to the Races
To really make this happen
Bytech cancel you're referring to what I understand here for program managers are sometimes very harrowing experiences
Where you have to go in front of
Leadership and really make the case for why the research is worthy why it could have benefit to taxpayers and Nash
Social Security and I think one of the things I was hearing when you use this
VCR venture-capital kind of
Analogy is that they're all so I think it's
Unusual willingness
Even expectation
That there will be failure along the way
Because if you're going to really move
Forward
Not just incrementally
Big step maybe even leaps that you're going to fail along the way
Tortoise had absolutely
Just like as a venture capitalist
If you show up and say hey I've got a way to get you 10% on your money
They're not interest
They can go to the bank or somewhere and get that what they want to see is
How do I ten-fold my money
Same idea with DARPA
But when you're doing things like that
Hey if it was that easy everybody be doing it so that you have to be taking risk you have to be
Pushing for things that you know haven't been done and you're not sure
100% if they can be
Okay well so weird
Getting toward the end of our time here but for some reason I'm feeling a little mean
And so at gym I'm going to ask you since we've just been talking about the value of
If you've got a failure story to share with us
Well it turns out I probably have several but I'll use one because it actually ties back to an old DARPA
Project this was when we were I mentioned earlier some of that underwater shock
Process we had
Hilton apparatus
With a lot of if you will think of it is
A bunch of little cannons
You know maybe sixteen of them all on a big rack
That we lowered into the water
And then the idea was we would
Shoot these off and and try to do the timing right
Right to make a shock
And
We lured it in the water and we hit the button then we got the first shot and we thought that way
That was great
Nice big bubble in the water
And then we hit the thing again and
Well we didn't notice anything and
Another time and
After a few times you finally decide to guess it's not working and so we asked the guy to
Bring the crane up in
He pulled it up and there was
I think maybe one wire still dangling from the end of it and we had blown this thing completely this
Smithereens
And I think it took divers about 2 weeks to go find all the parts that we had
Sprung all over the bottom of this cory that we were testing in and
That was not a
Completely atypical day of
How test go sometime
Okay but you learn some lessons we did we change the way we
Just another day in technology development
So Jim it's been a pleasure to have spoken with you here for the last half hour or so
I learned a lot and I know that our
Listeners
As well so thanks for sharing this time with me
My pleasure and really enjoyed this
Thanks a lot
And thank you listeners also for joining us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from.
For more information about Jim galambos
The program he has been running
The other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA. Mill
And four links that enable you to download
Go to the Voices from DARPA page
Antarctica