The internet
Your hands
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding a 19
58 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver
Technology
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window onto DARPA score of program manager
Their job
To redefine
What is pasa
My name is Ivan Amato
I'm your DARPA host
And today I'm pleased to have with me in the studio
Wade Shen
Program manager since 2014 in DARPA
Is information Innovation office
Wade earned a bachelor's
Degree in Electra
Google Engineering in
Computer science from the University of
Sanya Berkeley
Event attended the University of Maryland College Park which is
About 20 miles from where we
We are sitting in DARPA headquarters
Where he received his master's
Pseudoscience
And prior to coming to door but wait worked at the MIT Lincoln Laboratory
In the human language technology
You can tell from the portfolio of program to run zadar bus
That he is fascinated by language both
Of the humankind end of the
And you can tell also that is driven by a very DARPA s vision
Of computers and human beings
Working together
In ways that extend what either type of
Computer and tablet
Or human intelligence
Can do on it
It's own so thanks wait for
Joining me in the studio
Thanks Ivan
It would start out by talking about you wait a little bit about you
Background
How you ended up
Sure
So in a DARPA has his long
String of research
In communicating with
Computers in various forms
I've been involved in a number of those programs over many years
From from days of being a graduate student through
Answer my time at Lincoln
And and what sort of natural progression I was working on a program as a
As a pi and then
You know I do the program manager really well and
And you said hey you know you should
Should think about coming to DARPA
This is an opportunity to do things that
You can't possibly do
In the job that you
Currently at
Before we dive into some of the DARPA programs you oversee
I'm hoping you can let us in on some of the overarching ideas you have about human Minds
Computerminds
The language
Press in the context of these times of our time when so much of what we
Do involves
Interactive
You know the sort of the history of this is that
ARROW computers were good at various
Kinds of things that humans weren't good at like doing mathematical calculations without errors
Sina repeatedly and very quickly
But the fact is that we didn't quite know how to harness that
Solve
Problems that we really cared about so any
Serious problem
Like decision-making of any kind
Global scale policy anything that you might think of
Yunnan requiring humidex
Batista do
Yeah that wasn't something that we would engage
Computers in right it's just now that we're thinking about having computers drive car
Right
And that's a very basic function that
We Trust
Large portions of our popular
Yuan to do
And comes naturally to human beings with c
Some practice
But computers are just getting to the point where they can sense the world
Well enough that they can do that and they can make decisions that are
Are commensurate with what human beings can do
On this very basic tasks
And a number of us want computers to be smarter because we want them to be companions I can help
Must do things right
You know we want them to
Help us solve problems that are really really hard
How to make decisions that are much more complicated than
Just driving a car for
Right so let me just
Stop Yuan on this idea
Computer is making
Decisions because
You know for the life of me I
I cannot really
Always parse out how I make my own decisions
I presume that I'm
Bringing in
Different kinds of data different elements and then there's some kind of algorithm going out of my own head
By which I
I make a decision about where I'm going to go today or if I'm going to buy this item versus
That item
So can you talk to me a little bit about
What does it take to
Put that mystery you know into a working in a working way into a computer
The mystery of decision
It isn't necessarily the case that we wanted mimic
Anyway
Human beings aren't always
Great at making decisions
Yeah you know about the study of of children and whether or not they'll take a Snickers bar now versus
Universes waiting for 30 minutes and then getting five Snickers bars and you know they always choose the
Is the satisfaction now
And so we have all sorts of biases in her own decision-making that makes us make decisions that are suboptimal for our own
Outcomes
Right
And this happens at huge scales and happens when we make political decisions that happen to a make economic decisions
And so on and so forth
And what you hope for is the ability to make
Better decisions given an outcome goal
What you have
Iena based on better data and better understanding of
The process is under the hood
And that's why I think computers
All right well I for one would personally like to be in a position where
Where I can make better decisions on my own personal life if we can do that also on
National and geopolitical scales
All the better so all the power to you wait I hope
Going to do now is just
Talk to you little bit about your portfolio of
Program start with the memex program and tell us a little bit about what that is about and
What its status is now it's been used
Yes at the premise behind the next program is
This is really very simple
It's the Thursday de out there on the internet
That we can't quite get a hold of or make sense of for investing
So are our
Our program concept was
How do we
Help people who are doing investigations online and
And we started with human trafficking because human trafficking is something to wear
The point of sale is almost always online at least
For sex trafficking
We started with that particular domain
Because we we noticed that
The date is online
You know people
Buy and sell
Human beings online in ways that are grotesque and and overt at the same time
And yet because of the volume of the date of the South there because it's it's hiding in a huge sea
Even more data
It's actually really hard for investigators to
Explorer
Effectively and it's not just the data that's in the kind of
Most of us think of is the normal web
Which is index by
Binaural search engines baidu
Another places that's right it's in places like the Deep Web and the dark web
Places that commercial search indexes don't spend a lot of time dealing with
And you know our only
Real view into that data is through commercial circuit
We rely on them to index and make available to
Search
The content that's online
And if it's not index
Or available through Google
Is very likely you're never going to see it
And so portions of the darkweb where a lot of crime happens
Portions of the Deep Web where lots of ads for Saxon for prostitution exist
A lot of that isn't fully indexed by our commercial
Search engines
And so the premise of the program was collect the right data
And then automatically organize that data in such a way that we can
Explore that data and most importantly generate leads into
Detect instances of
About activity
And so we have been working for the last almost three years now
To build a system that would help investigators one chase down leads that they have but to also identify
Delete automatically
Potentially
Potentially ads that are associated
It was trafficking so that they can prioritize R&B
Instigations
And so the concept here is sort of back to this team of human machine interaction the concept here is
How do you help the investigator get to the data that
Salient for their particular
Investigation
And then how do you help them analyze data that they can't possibly NY
Lights on their own
You know one of the key findings in that program was that
Pricing behaviors of organizations that are involved in trafficking look different than
Pricing behaviors of
If you don't normal
Independent contractor process
And you can detect those time you can detect those patterns but you can't see that by reading an individual add online
You have to look collectively at a whole bunch of ads
Author by the same person sometimes tens of thousands of them
In order to understand the statistical pattern of how they price
Right do they price risky behaviors differently
Then the average in that Marketplace
That's the kind of question that's
Very very hard for an individual to answer without analytics that help them do that in Alice
And so and Wade have has this tool memex
Letter I guess the kind of deliverable that I imagine we all want which is sort of taking down
Sex trafficking Rings or other criminal activity
Yasso
You know since the beginning of this program we have been engaged with
Law enforcement agencies across the country and really across the world we have users in the UK and Canada and Australia
And other places not just the United States
Who are
Everyday working with these
Tools to arrest people at this point we have hundreds of arrests that have been
Credited to the use of the memex tool
And a number of different convictions
That have happened out of that
Well that sounds like at least a slightly improved world so that's great news what's a Segway
To another one of your programs the data-driven discovery of
Models program so Wade what are you what are you trying to do with this sand and what's the status of this program
Thought in this program is that
You know when we want to construct an empirical model of how the world works
We use data to do that nowadays are stated everywhere
And so the
Omak for us to construct models of how the world works
Isn't the
You know isn't any longer the collection of the data itself necessarily but the actual
Process of
Constructing a model that process is something that's relegated to
People who are typically called data scientist
Machine learning
Are statisticians right
People with that kind of title
Associated with them
And though that the effort involved in constructing those models is
Huge right it's
Hundreds if not thousands of man years of effort
Largely because the data is messy largely because
How they model that data statistically requires lots of x
Expertise in the areas
The statistics of
Machine learning
And so what we've basically said is hey let's
Take that out of the hands of those kinds of experts in automated
But also I want to
Listen to have a little bit more of a concrete set
Have you been talkin and serve in general terms about
Yo models
And and
System
What might be some of the specific
Say phenomena
What you're talking about
Model development
Just to give you a couple of problems that are concrete
The people have been thinking about
One is you know how would you given different kinds of
Genotypes
Various forms of
Wheat
How would you predict the yield
Of those varieties
Sweet in their different environment
That requires a model and if you could do that you could know what to plant any given year depending on what you
Respect for the weather in
The amount of rain
And the particular soil location you could make decisions that were much smarter than we make
Ignou
And so one of the problems that were working on
Is a question of how do we how do we
Predict crappie
Based on data
And that data can come from genotype data can come from environmental observations of sensors
He liked
Taking pictures of crop fields
I'm making come from you know your Farmers Almanac
The tells you
3 months from now what the weather is likely to be
So those kinds of data can build a predictive model of What kinds
Crop yields you can generate
And if you can do that you can you know
Highly affect the outcomes of Accra
That's just one concrete example
We probably can also link
This to
Big mission of DARPA
In enhancing National Security when we
Even when we're talkin about
Food that relates to things like Foods
Security so we can
Really keep our Foods
Supply
Constantine
At the levels we need that
Does that's right
That's right it did helps us to predict political instability
Different states and countries that we care about
So those kinds of models
Are are always important socio-political models are important
Can you predict whether a riot is
Going to work her
Can you predict that unrest political unrest of a certain type is going to result
10 days from now in some kind of bad event
Those are the kinds of things that you'd like to build models over
What is the challenge that I'm getting a kind of
Computer with access
All kinds of data
Generators
Models I don't know where the human mind comes into this
But to generate those models
From the data and imperfect
So they're sort of two real problems that we have to contend with
So first of all we have
Too much data have too many different kind
And so the problem with that is that we don't know which combinations of the data are likely to
Explain a particular outcome
We care about so if we
Care about crop yields
We need to know the temperatures of veto of
Days prior to a particular event or associated with crop yield outcomes 10 days later
Right that's the kind of thing that
You don't require some subject matter expertise
In agriculture to be able to know
Computers don't know that
Symbiosis
That's right
So what computers can do is calculated
Statistics bacon
Estimate how well correlated
Particular variable is worth
Particular kind of data is
Torpedo outcome we care about
And so
Computers can discover patterns that human beings have a hard time
Figuring out on their own
But human beings are also very good at figuring out
That some of these patterns are
Some of these patterns are what we call Chance correlation
And so what we would like to do in order to build a really effective model is to find variables that
Matter factors that affect
The outcome of crappie
Princeton
I'd like to be able to do that automatically
But because some subject matter expertise is involved we need the help of a human being to help
Curate
This process
And so in the d3m program
The goal is to make and that's the data-driven Discovery Model
The goal of that program is to
Fundamentally change the category of Labor from
Statistician in machine learning expert that constructs the model
To machine
Plus subject matter
And so the idea is that we have a machine that automatically tests a whole bunch of
And it does so in an efficient way
And you know general for most of these problems are infinitely many models that could be used
Answer the question is how do you find the right one
The machines are very good at doing that testing in an automated fashion
And if they can work with you and beings to constrain the kinds of models that they
Explorer
They can potentially find models very very quickly very effectively without the
Need for
Expert machine learning
Personnel
Or Davis
Fascinating
So let's move to the third program
Quantitative
Crisis
Response
Again a little bit of it
Description of a program
And what kind of frog
So the goal in like you Ciara quantitative crisis response
Program
West of figure out
How information affects p
+ 2
Build a way to measure that
That's the fundamental goal in our program
So you know with social media and fake news and propaganda being distributed by organizations
Like Isis
Write our goal was to figure out how does that turn into a radicalization
How is it that videos online
Convert people into Fighters
On the battle
So what we've been doing in that program is
Building models again
How human beings respond properly
And how effective
Spitzer propaganda
AR
By looking at measurements of
How people react in place
And so the fundamental goal there is to build what we call a measure of effective
Which is really a way to measure concrete outcomes associated with
Various bits of information that are put out their various bits
So you know the in the last couple of years what we've seen is that organizations like Isis can reach
Millions of people through social media
And they effectively recruit a small number of them but still you know when you can recruit million small
All percentages add up to a lot of Fighters
Answer the question is how do they do that
I want one hand and how effective are we at stopping them or at you know are they at actually
Achieving that outcome
And so what we've been building is essentially a gauge is essentially a meter
That says
Oh today that message that you put out has a higher degree of
Potential for radicalizing people than the one that you
Yesterday
And why that matters is that it allows us
People who are interested in countering radicalization
Estimate how well we're doing at preventing that radical
Causation from
Or Century building a meter that allows us to know whether or not
We're doing well
Or poorly
A1 theme
I seem to apply maybe all of these programs
Is
That idea of
You know how can
Human beings and their machines and their come
Computers and all of their online resources how can all of these things work together
It could have been a symbiotic way
Play so that we drive
Knowledge
Wisdom from all of this interaction
It reminds me of
Really kind of the early days here of DARPA
In particular I'm thinking of
But one of our more famous
Dinnerly
Program managers Joseph Carl robnett licklider most people know him as
Jcr like
I'm who was even back in the 60s
With the program matter
I was articulating the
What's this idea
Forever symbiosis
Between the human beings and
And machine. Just wondering how how does it feel to be a program manager you know kind of working in this long long
Well First Watch Company
When you look at the history of program managers
The DARPA and the various things that are pissed
Produce over its lifespan
We are all humbled by the
Great outcomes that those folks had in
In the program
That they were produced out of here
You know most of us just try to do our job but all of us are thinking bigger than the things that we could have done our
And that's the thing that darpin genders and all of us
It's the opportunity to explore an area of research
It's much larger than anyone
Research organization can do
Before we close out of our conversation
I think this relates a little bit
What you just said
It's going to stand back from any particular
RAM and maybe share with us some of what you've observed
Closest 24
14 as a program out of
About DARPA's
Roll in the overall
Innovation
Ecos
An ecosystem includes many players and stakeholders
Scientists engineers
In academe
Industry
And government lab those are some of the stakeholders entrepreneurs
Venture capitalist
The science policy community
Ecosystem involves
Most players in the commercial
Armetta hold
Other sectors
So where do you think DARPA fits into this
Overall
Innovation
Well it's it's interesting right so there are a lot of obviously even within the US government or number of organization
Oceans of Fun Bass
Define applied research
Define various
Projects along
That continuum
And I think DARPA has a very unique role it's it it's a role that
Spans the gap
Between basic research and applied science
I often times we are looking for the applications that seem impossible
Whether it's you know
Launching drones off of flying aircraft
Or
You know detecting human trafficking online all of these things are things that
Nowhere emerging capabilities three or four years ago but now have proven to be possible
And so dark isn't a very unique place that allows us to
Push the technology
Beyond the theoretical stages
To the point where we can actually
See where the where the applications are going to be
So
We're not
Builders of the ultimate technology right
At the end of the day we found the research and that research eventually becomes productizing other forms
If you look at the progression of Robotics and self-driving cars
All of those AI technology for curated out of DARPA programs early on
And have subsequently you know a 10-year Horizon after that
You have become
Productize mobile
Industry has been able to take it up so we serve a very crucial role
And the reason that we can serve that role is
Twofold one
The program manager
These folks
Come with the ideas
And they can see the horizon
They've been working in the research they understand the basic research is happening in that field and make a noise like a horizon view of lake
Foods you you had
Boots on the ground in particular of Technology
That's right and we don't stay long and part of the reason we can't stay long is that we're going to lose view of the Horizon if we do right wing
I need to be back in in the guts
To that research
And so all of us are here for a temporary. Of time and I think that was a brilliant
Design decision in terms of how we structure DARPA
The other thing I would say is that the
Funding amounts in the Catalyst the DARPA provides in terms of scope of programs
Is at the right levels
To be able to do the kinds of projects
That we can do is technology demonstrators
What is early prototype
Those are things that are really really hard to do without a
High level of envy
Because they often involve
Multiple disc
Coupons for multiple fields
Who are at the edge of something
But that's something requires them to all work together to build it
And build early-stage prototypes of it and to fail multiple times potentially in the process
Doing that
Yeah you bring up for the failure in
The tolerance for failure here
To me that's one of the most interesting things about DARPA
Because they're they're not all that many other
Stakeholders in the in the Innovation ecosystem
That can actually afford to do that if your company
You might be able to feel a little bit but
You've got to be able to deliver a technology you got to be able to deliver these to your to your stockholders eventually
Where is here I guess
Program managers like you can
Probe technology possibilities
And determined
Is this something that
He's had a good likelihood of moving for another word you can take the risk
Down
For others who then might take it to Ryan exactly
So I worked in startup World prior to it going to Lincoln and one of the things I can tell you there is that
Yeah there's actually relatively little tolerance
Risk
The kinds of risks that you can tolerate
Are not the same as
The kinds of risks that we
Tolerate here at DARPA
The concrete idea that you have in a startup better be
Better be actionable as a product in three to four years
Otherwise
You know there's there's no sense in funding that
There's all sorts of business-related risk execution related risk for technology risk camping
The DARPA we can take technology
Science
And I think that's actually the fundamental
To do what we do
Like other program managers you are a technology developer
Review for exercising your
Science engineering and kind of Technology match
How to eat a match
Nocti
So I'm just wondering if there is a a kind of fictional technology
That you might have been
Thinking about food out since you were a kid
But you wish were real
But isn't
Well so that's that's a fun one you know being a language person
The thing that end in one that worked on
Translation
Many years
For years we've been
Striving towards
This kind of Babelfish
Kind of
Capability do you know what I mean though I never read the books by
Douglas Adams Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy
You know it in the various Interstellar spaces right everybody speaks a different language
So the solution to this is the Babel Fish
It's the the fish that you put in your ear and then suddenly eat you can hear in your own language
You know the translation the perfect translation of
Do all of these alien species University translate Universal trans
Play it right is it the exact
Tweet from Star Trek
Well you know this
What's really fascinating is last couple years because of the work that's going on in deep neural networks and
The cool work has been going on
Bo Sinn DARPA funded research
End end
And commercially funded work
We're really getting close to
So there was this paper last year by Google
The described the use of multiple languages
How to do translation translating for multiple languages into a language
I am in training those translators from various different
Forms
And what they discovered is that these neural networks
Learn kind of a universal
Semantic representation of language
As part of
The process of training this emergent
It's an emergent property of
How these neural networks were built
And so what it leads to in long-run is potentially actually having a universal trans
And that is going to be a really
It just give it a shot so if we were to give listeners
What you mean by neural net
Yeah so so we use the term neural network it actually has very little.
Do with neurons as in the cells in your brain
But these are models of
How your neurons work
Start a very primitive models of how your neurons in your brain work
That are composed together to form little small brain like you
And what the Google guys did was they figured out how to build a neural network
That could take information
Drupal multiple languages
Ian
Essentially regular eyes
Into a form
That would allow it to translate in English
And that intermediate form
Which is
Somewhere in the middle of this rather large neural network
You know happens to have properties that looked
The same across multiple language
Is meeting that it's a fact effectively like the shared
Semantics
Different language
Yeah
Fascinating
Well I think so
Sharon that sounds like
Dykema fictional universe
Translator to something that we might
Actually all of us be able to use
Hope all is well with all 7.4 billion of us on the planet might be able to talk to one another that's right in the thousands of languages that we speak
So wait we have covered a lot of
Fascinating ground here and I just want to thank you
For this
Teaching conversation
Well thank you Ivan
Straight talk any
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
For more information that way.
His program than the other brake
Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit DARPA. Mil
And four links that enable you to download this
Podcast go to the Voices from DARPA page on Darkness