Dell Technologies the internet
Palm of your hand operation
Technology is a driver of our time
Since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the
The Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver
Technology
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window at the DARPA score of program manager
Their job
To redefine
What is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your door post
Today I am pleased to have with me in the studio
Justin gallo
A program manager since 2014 and DARPA's biological technology
Justin earned a Bachelor of Science degree in chemistry at the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign
And received his PhD in chemistry from
Caltech
For 14 years prior to arriving at DARPA he was a professor
In the chemistry Department
Is Emory University in Atlanta Georgia
There he led a research program in synthetic biology
We just all about uncovering the rules and genetic programs by which cells
Behaving operate
And then to learn how to manipulate those rules and programs
Tibet bacterial fungal
Plant and animal cells can make drugs fuels coding and other useful molecules in materials
Adura Gallivan continues to be driven by some of Nature's Own most audacious biological feats
Such as the growth of a great Sequoia redwood tree from a seed
What if it were possible to leverage biology own evolutionary on Powers of chemical synthesis
Growth
Self-organization
Self-healing
And reproduction
In the context of our built landscape of buildings
Roads vehicles and other Construction
That is the sort of question just in his ass
Justin thanks for joining me in the studio.
Gladtobehere Ivan
Let's start by talking about your background
How you became interested in science in general and in chemistry and then synthetic biology in particular
I actually started out it was very
Physics
I was inspired by people like Witcher
Fine men
He told these wonderful stories seem like an incredibly interesting guy actually one of the things that brought me to Caltech I thought you know
This is a place where this character could do such
Great science
The place that I want
I quickly realized after about a week in college that I was not going to be a physicist but nevertheless I'll
I like the hard Sciences
So chemistry seems like a good option
And I always liked the idea in chemistry of the ability to create things
Didn't exist
Credit score
Chemistry has an analytical sides we on
Understand the world around us by studying it and also has a synthetic side which means creating new Opera
And that was something I was really drawn to
Interestingly enough
I was sort of put off by biology
My biological education release formerly
Pretty much ended in the 9th grade
But as time went on during graduate school and post. If I went from this time where the word DNA
Hey in a seminar titled mint do not attend
To a point where I really started to respect the
Remarkable
Chemistry that biology does
I ultimately concluded that no matter how good of a chemist I was that biology would always do
Better
So ask a question okay well can we harness the power of biological systems
To essentially do our bidding for us
So how can I reprogram
A system that
Wants to do its own thing and get through the thing
I want it
And that led me into this area of sin
Biology
So we were interested in taking advantage of some of the properties that
Bacteria
Simple
Microbes could do
Their ability to make stuff there
$0.02 stuff
And I got really interested in programming
Before we
Who talked about
The two programs that you're running here at RPI I would like to hear about the sequence of events
That led you from your long experience at Emory as a professor
To darp itself so how did you actually end up here
That was a funny story I was at a meeting in
Cold Spring Harbor New York
Beautiful laboratory famous laboratory on Long Island
Famous for molecular biology molecular biology the structure of DNA
Wait we are meeting right outside of his office we got to see him walk through coming back from his tennis match
And I was there as part of a short course on synthetic biology
Carrizo
Organizers had brought in
Faculty members from around
The country around the world
And about that time DARPA had an ounce
The Living foundries Program
How much is one of the Seminole synthetic biology
Here at DARPA
Can you just tell listeners what was the Crux of that
The Crux of that program was engineering microbes to
Produce new molecules and to reduce the
Time of the design-build
Test learn cycle today
So instead of taking a decade in a billion dollars to generate a product
They wanted to reduce the time
Down to
Baby days weeks and reduce the cost dramatic
DARPA Hedges put out a call
Nearly a hundred million dollars of investment I think
And needless to say people at this meeting who are all in this area got really excited about it
But we also or sort of
Amazed by the
The audacity Of what DARPA was asked
And I was getting really excited about this and I was talking to some of the younger faculty member so these are mostly system
Professors that are organized the meeting and
They had mentioned that
Ann Arbor was
Expanding heavily in
The synthetic biology Arena they were looking
For program managers
And
It's the program manager I was kind of an interesting one in the sense that we're all
Temporary
Stop it doesn't hire permanent
Staff is program managers we have an expiration date on badge
Mine is
30 December 2000
18 Lexi's yourself emergency it certainly does
So in order to come and do this job
You essentially have to leave
What you were doing before with the expectation that this is only going to be at
So for the folks that come from academics
He more or less have to have a tenured position if you enter
Because early in your career
You can't do this and being a sister
The professor at the
I just wouldn't work out but
Since I already had 10 year old lot of my colleagues said you would be great
You know the field
You have the ability to take a break
Ironically after about three years up here
On leave for memory by Dean said are you coming back
And something I never thought I would say is
So I gave up babe
Tenured faculty position a lifetime appointment
Something I worked incredibly hard tour in sawdust or the end-all-be-all of a career
So I am currently
Serving at the pleasure of the DARPA leadership and don't know what I'm going to do
All right but that also is an indication to me that you developed a certain kind of devotion and excitement about the programs
But you are involved with maybe more so than you even expected so let's talk about the two programs the first one
Goes by the short name of bricks brics
Which stands for
Biological robustness and complex settings what is it status now and what do you hope to achieve with it
The origin of that program goes back
Couple of years before I join the agent
Synthetic biologist got good engineering bacteria to do what I would call parlor tricks
Little cute things that work well in the laboratory
Example was
Engineering bacteria such
That when you expose them to light they would change
Color
So you could do
Photography
You take a petri dish
Shine light and a
Shadows and so on and you can take bacterial
You're cute
Kind of demonstrates the possible
The fields but at the end of the day
It's not going to put digital cameras out of business
I myself have been engineering organisms to follow small molecules
With the idea maybe that
You could chase down pollutants in the environment
Once you have a bacterium that
Not only wanted to eat the oil but actually
Could sense the oil and follow it around
And if you wanted to clean up
And in doing all this the question I would inevitably get ass is okay when are you going to
Transition this to the
The field
Am I answer quite honestly was never
Because the systems that we are building
Work fine
37° C
Petri dish
Sterile
Environment
With the presence of antibiotics.
Any competition away
So we were literally
Cuddling
Is bacteria
And they can perform in that environment but if you said Okay I want to take something that I engineered in the laboratory
And I want to put it in this contaminated site
Clean up what was there
It would never work
Because
There microorganisms
Live everywhere they've established there
Niches
I soaked introducing this little week laboratory strain of e-coli
It wouldn't survive
It's just
It wouldn't work
And just on another angle was there even at that time a regulatory framework with that would enable you to go from the lab out into the field
There is it like
Many regulatory Frameworks it's a little bit
Complicated but it does exist but we were so far away from that that even
The notional idea that we would like to
Do that was
Almost out of the question is
Regulation wasn't going to stop us
From being successful here it was the science itself
The challenge has I saw it was we needed to be able to
Engineer organisms that were
Robust enough to
To survive
You of course have to deal with this problem
Of evolution
So when you have large population sizes Evolution occurs by
Mistakes
Okay when DNA
Copied incorrectly
It introduced
Mistakes
Call grateful for billions of years worth of mistakes aren't exactly the process work
The public concern off
So you're going to create a
Superbug
And my concern actually it was at the other end of the spectrum than anything we've is going to break
Just going to be too fragile so we have to be mindful
If you want to engineer microbes that are
Resilient enough to do the job but make sure that they are not innovating
And one of the challenges
There
Is this notion of engineering robustness
Intersystems
If you talk
Too Hardcore Engineers that build things like
Like airplanes
There are many ways to
Make sure that airplanes
Fly safe
Redundant systems
Sensing
Control a
Actuation
And so on so we've gotten to the point now where air travel is
Ratably safe and there's
The entire engineering disciplines that help support
So I would talk to these Engineers who are used to working in
Your microphysics
World's End say
Okay how do you deal with
Uncertainty
In
Say biological
So is an example
If you're thinking about an airplane flying you can make reasonable guesses as to what environment
And it's going to say
The temperature range that is likely to see
I know how high it's
Find a fly I can model the stresses on the wing what kind of ruins it might exactly you can draw a box around
Wright Engineers are very good at saying that within a certain parameter space
Fat
This should operate as expected and then beyond that
I'm all bets maybe off but we've done a pretty good job of drawing up
But in biology it's a lot more complicated than
Because
We don't
Always know
What an environment is going
Be like
Moreover
You have this
Pesky thing of evolution
Whereas
And physically engineered systems
When something breaks
Generally the
Fitness
She's a biological term
Of the object goes down
Okay so let's say
Part of the airplane brakes
The performance of that aircraft is generally not
Where is in biological systems
Breaking is innovation
So it's possible that
Do mutations in an organism acquires a new phone
It grows faster it out competes its
A colleagues
When I talk to the engineer's taking is there a g in
The mechanical are the answers know that the airplane breaks it doesn't start flying twice as fast and twice as high
Performance goes down
So that was sort of
An intellectual barrier there that the people that
Think about
Engineering robust systems
Weren't
As of yet
Thinking about biology and it
Brings new challenge
And I recognize this but I'm not an engineer so I had no idea how to
So when I came to DARPA
I had the convening power of two
The purse haiku
Sculpt
A program that
Basically asked
Can we transition
Synthetic biology from
Laboratory curiosity into
The real world
So one of the great technological advancement
The last
Decade or so
Is
The Dramatics
Reduction
And cost
Of
Dnac
So we can study
The DNA
That's out in the
And there's a lot of
And
Why doing that we started to recognize that there's this in
Credible
Diversity
Of
Microbes
Acroanna Saint Denis
It turns out that
If you were to count up the number of cells in your body that are yours
Should have your DNA
And then compare that to the number of
Cells of bacteria that live
On your skin and in your
Your gut
Those numbers
There's still a little debate about it but they're approximately
Comfortable
So you are being driven by your back
They help you digest your food friend
They affect us in profound ways or just beginning to
Discover
And
So you're essentially telling me
But I am half bacterial
More less more
So this opened up the tantalizing
Impossibility
That by
Manipulating
Those back
Stereo weekend
Therapeutics
For example soda
Treat
Diseases of the gut
An interesting aside
There is a typically Hospital
Derived
Infection
Called c-diff
Common lyrics
Clostridium
Difficile
Essentially what happens in
Hospital settings is that when
People take a strong course of antibiotics
Essentially
Clears the bacteria out of your
L C diff lives
In this very specific locations within your guts that kind of hangs out in between some cells
And normally it's held in check by
Everything else that's
In your gut right and just because some westerns probably have heard the term we are talking about here about the
The microbiome
Right here this year the mybatis biome of the gut
When you were talking about the bacterial over all of us and that's the entire microbiome on our bodies
I hear you're talking about the microbiome of a gaseous specifically in the gut so what
Happens is that after antibiotic treatment
Got clears out
C-diff says
Oh my God this is great you know it's like it's expanding into a
It makes people very very sick
It can be deadly
The observation was made
That
Perhaps by
Repopulating the gut
With
Normal Got Back
Bacteria you might be able to knock down a c-diff in
So where do you get those bacteria to repopulate the gut
Well
The political terms these days are
Intestinal microbiota
What are talking about
Fecal material however correct I am going to be a group
Transplant
It works if you eliminate a microbial community
You can replace it with a different community and restore
No
It's great it works I mean it said something like 95%
Successful
But aside from just the it
Factor
If you had to design a solution to this problem
Is that the best you could come up with
That you would literally
Take somebody's poop and stick it in you
So
Can we start asking this question
Could you
Buildmore Define communities
Scratch that might have the same function
But
Wouldn't carry all the extra baggage so
In that poop there's a lot of other
Real potential viruses and other bacteria that maybe you don't want to
So we've got very interested in this idea of building microbial communities
That can perform a specific function
But have much more to find Copper
This would of course be a tremendous service in a public health sense because so many people have gastrointestinal
Personal issues
That seems to be related to the microbiome so if you can come up with ways that are more palatable any sense to
To treat that would be really Department of Defense specific problem as well so when
Soldiers deploy to place
Iraq and Afghanistan
They are exposed to do microbes
Water and so on
Travelers diarrhea
Many of you out there may have suffered from it
It's not fun
And not only can it ruin a vacation but if you think about from a
DOD perspective
If you're taking young healthy people you're deploying them in theater
With the expectation that they're going to do a job right away
And then they're sick
That's no good
So one way that you could think about maybe solving this problem would be to
Find a way of engineering robust
Community
In the gut
That more closely matches where they're going
And maybe you transition that
Community States
So maybe you get a tummy ache
But you're here
You can be treated
You're fine
And then
You deployed overseas and don't have to worry about being
Knocked out of the game
Right as you are
If you were to characterize the status of
The program Prix
Now how would
AccuWeather
It's going well I'm actually very pleased so when we started that program we
Realize that
The science behind the microbiome
Is changing it
Incredibly rapidly
When we launched the program we didn't say specifically that we were going to solve this
Microbial engineering problem
Because I felt that those problems were
Quite as well defined
As we want
So what we did was we said
What are the tools in
Some technologies that we will have to develop
App that allow us to engineer
Microbial communities or microbiome
That can function in Campo
Text environment
Because we thought that there were going to be some commonality so a microbial community in your
Your gut
Has to deal with
Changing environment
Right one day
I drink a Diet Coke
I had a burrito for lunch
Then I ate a salad
So there's all sorts of different stuff flowing through
Through there so what we said was if you have the ability to engineer a microbial community
Forum 8
Find function
In some suitably complex environment
We figured we would learn enough lessons that we could
Then
Take that to
Maybe a different phone
In a different car
So they're going to be some primitive
Commonalities
In terms of the problems that you would have
The salt
To engineer a community that
Weather I ultimately want to
Re-engineer a gut microbiome
Aura skin microbiome or a soil microbiome
They're probably some commonalities
How many research
Right over on the program is
Probably about a dozen
And
They've come up with some
Truly creative
Solutions to some of the challenges
At the beginning of the program we said
We want you to engineer a community that has an impact
On
An organism
In a rational
Predictable
Safe
Robust
Way
We didn't specify
What
The test case had to be
We left the performers
Folks at
Came with ideas Define their own space
Wewe to find how complex
Could be or needed to be
But we didn't say
Engineer the gut microbiome of
So we got some really Creative Solutions in
Including some that were on XP
So some of the ones that I would I'd say we're a little bit
More in line with
We kind of thought would come in was
We have a group
At
The recents
Attitude at Harvard
Bye-bye
Pam silver
She and her group
Now have engineered a
Microbe
That
Can sense inflammation
And it changes color when
It senses inflammation
Shenzhen Diagnostics a diagnostic
So at
Can reside in the gut of
They're using animals
Freezing a mouse
It can reside in the god of a mouse for
Something like a hundred days
Without mutating
Thanks for this is one of the things that we were worried about I thought this was going to be a huge problem
But the systems were going to meet a wife
That was a pleasant surprise
They've shown that you can detect
Inflammation in the mouse gut
Basically by looking at
Set the color of their poop
Poop if there's inflammation the mice poop blue
So you can imagine ultimately using this as a diagnostic
One of the other more surprising test cases that a group at the University of Texas
Led by Nancy Moran
Came up with
Was the
Microbiome of the
Honey bee
Got so we are definitely not expecting this
But it
It turns out
That the honey bee is a really interesting
Test kit
So unlike you and I who have a lot
Of different microbes in our guts
The honey bee has depending on the day somewhere around 8 or 9
So much simpler
What is the
So it's not
But it's not a thousand so we thought that this was a really
Useful
Test case because it's
Complicated but not irreducibly,
And what also is interesting about the honey bees the honey bee is a social animal
Displays learning and memory so you can train honey bees
To do tasks
And so on so
What the Texas team
Was interested in doing
Was manipulating the
Gut microbiome of the honeybee
To see if we could alter their learning and memory
And it turns out that this actually work
It turns out that there is something that
Antonis the gut
Brain access
So there is any
Credible number of
Neurons
That go from your brain and synapse
Got
If you think about it
You have the gut-brain at
It inside the gut you have all these microbes
Living in there doing
And it turns out that
There's essentially a gut brain microbe axis
So the microbes in your gut can actually tickle your brain
Via the molecules they produce how they interact
Absolutely amazing soda
Potentially opening up a door of engineering my own gut microbiome in a way that might make me a better learner
Okay so that would be cool not there yet but
You know you said you weren't my only told us about 2 I know you said there's about a dozen other groups we cannot get into all of them
Fact I want to move on now to the to the second program which is
Fairly new and this one goes by the acronym Elm and that stands for
Engineered
Living materials and I know in an earlier discussion one of the kind of metaphors that came up as we're talking about this
Beautiful wanna one you think of where I
Forest come from
And then you think of the seeds that are the beginnings of all of those trees of collectively become this incredible LAN
Of a forest
So what would your thinking about that sort of
Biological
Brilliance and Landscape in another way so talk to us about
Elm what it's about
And what the status
One of the Great
Perks of this job is that we get a pretty
High level
View of the
And I had gone to a meeting
Called biofabricate
And I had met a group from a company
In New York called ecova
And what
Ecovative
Was doing it
At the time and what is actually think
The core of their business is they were taking
Fungi
Particular mushroom
And in particular The mycelial Witcher
The parts of mushroom
Set grow under
And if you've ever walked out on your lawn one morning
Where the hell did those come
Front right they grow really
Fast
I would eat oveta was doing
Was they were taking this organism
And mixing it with
The cheapest agricultural waste
We're talkin
Corn stalks that are ground
Apparently there's a market
Paraguay
Futures
Poodle
What they would do if they take the waist
They would take the my Celia they would put it in a mold
A physical mold and after a few days my silly would grow to fill the voids
And it would get a material that
Essentially has many of the properties of polystyrene
Styrofoam head
Material
And they can sell this as a packing Pro
Do my Celia of the fungal system those are more fibrous kinds of parts of a not the mushroom and body the Rye
Ritenour mushrooms button in here it just kind of ends up looking almost like a
So and I thought this was so cool
Cool because polystyrene
Is
Holding a polystyrene cup as we speak
Is one of the most
Useful yet pernicious substances
In the sense that
It is so inexpensive to make
It is cheaper to
Make virgin polystyrene the Nerdist
Recycle it
And it tends not to go away
Where is these mushroom base materials if you throw in a compost
They go away
And so I was really intrigued
By this idea of
Growing
Materials
And
From a
DOD perspective
I was particularly interested in this idea of
Growing materials
On a
Site
And one of the things that
Ecovative Folkston
Show me was that they could
Take
Are mushroom materials that are not particularly dense but if you put them under Heat
Pressure you can get a material that's more or less equivalent
2 fiberboard
I thought this was cool
You can essentially grow
These materials quickly
If you think about the Department of Defense we operate all over the world
If you think about
A rebuilding effort in
Afghanistan
And let's say you need to get a pallet of plywood there
LED ody has the world best Logistics system out there but
Shipping
Heavy
Pallets of plywood
Across the world in the danger zone
Sounds to me seems
If necessary
But silly
Right cost a lot
Crossfuel
It's dangerous
Why couldn't you ship
Accede
Or effectively accede
Starter
And then grow the
So you reduce the logistic burden
What's the cost
You increase safety because you're not
Find a truck inherently low value materials across the
And then if you take this a step further
And say well what are some other remote places we might want to eventually
Priest materials
If we ever decide to live on Mars
There's no Home Depot up there
We're not going to get there by just shipping everything weed
We're going to
Have to be able
How to grow in
So beyond program really gets at this early stage of growing material
Oh and by the way
We want the material
To remain alive
Sew-in packing material it's obvious
Want that to remain alive
But living systems have grapes
Bacon
Self-repair
They can sense and respond to
The environment
So could you imagine having a structure that a pond
Damaged or insult
Repairs itself
In the way that you do if you get a cut
That would be great
Could you have materials that
Change their properties with respect to the
The
Temperature
State
Change the color so that they were become
Reflective or absorptive if you were interested in
So there's something
About maintaining the living properties
Materials that
Takis
Really
Compelling
Try this absolutely amazing this is also reminding me this comes I guess out of a tradition
Summit used to be called
Smart materials
Smart intelligent materials
And idea there I remember being you can you build a building that might have sort of
Reactive porosity the humidity when the meteorological conditions are and so in some
The building itself
Just by changing its microstructure
Can accommodate
Hayden and queen maybe you lose use less energy to heat and less energy
Before AC
Is the thing is amazing about this though is I'm imagining living
Inside of a building that is living I love the thought of it but I also
It also gives me the willies what's makes me feel like I might be living
Inside of a body
And I still might want you to think about that for a second and I'm wondering what should we be concerned about like if I keep food in the refrigerator
Too long
It goes badly so could my house go
Bad in this respect
Yes these are some of the things that we've asked our performers to be thing
Thinking about so
If you have a system
That grows
How do you control that grow
And there's obviously a natural president
For this right
Human beings grow to roughly
Define shapes
In sizes and so on so
So Nature has solved
This problem
Controlled growth
And development
We actually have a
Second
Track of the
Program that is getting it
Just this
So
Can we
Program biological
Systems
To adopt
Specific sizes
Okay I just have to say this is one of the most miraculous things to me
About biology
About a seed about a fertilized egg because it's comes with
Fairly simple shape and I'm looking at you Justin and you have an interesting shape of a human being
I don't know how to take that so what did DARPA s
Audacious idea to actually now try to build that
Morpho genetic function of biology into
Engineered materials
Right so you mentioned the seeds we've been building with
Once alive materials forever right we use would
And how do we get that would we take the single this very very small seed we stick it in
The ground we grow it for
What years we got this beautiful living tree that
Lightshade
Help heal itself all these great properties
I can take CO2 out of the atmosphere and produce oxygen that we need to breathe and then what do we do
We cut the damn thing. And then we put it in a kiln we render it inert we saw it up and it
Dimensional Lumber
So could you think about
Starting with
Essentially like
The tree progenitor cell
And
Grow dimensional Lumber
The cells will keep dividing in a specific developmental pattern
And they would know
They would be programmed
To go to sleep
Dick sizes and shapes
So producing dimensional Lumber without having to
How to grow a tree
Suggesting that was absolutely amazing discussion you taking me on a conceptual a journey that is just pleasing
Camino and
I just want to thank you for engaging me in this conversation
It's been my pleasure Ivan
It's been a lot of fun
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next
Voices from DARPA
The more information about Justin Gallivan
Is bricks and Elm programs any other breakthrough Technologies DARPA is working on
Visit
Dartford. Mill
And four links that enable you to download this podcast
Go to the Voices from DARPA page on doctor's website