Delta technology , the internet GPS in the car of your hand on the most occupation technologies , a driver of our times since its founding a one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , the defence advanced research agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from double a window on the dark as a core of program managers , their job to read the fine .
What is possible , my name is iphone .
A motel went on your dark host today .
I am pleased to be talking with doctor william carter , a program manager .
Since the agencies defense science office , we are recording our conversations from our respective homes as we do our parts to slow the spread of covered nineteen , because we are not in a recording studio .
You met your ambient sounds like traffic and birds .
Party arriving at door 。
But two years ago , bill , as I will refer to him here was the director of the materials and microsystems laboratory at each oil laboratory , which was founded in nineteen forty eight by the famous billionaire heritage in bill's role in natural , he focused on numerous for three deepening , including high strength metals and ceremonies , mechanical systems , for the stabilization of platforms .
Like once you might find in space , scalable approaches to high performance , anti failing and nano material coatings and micro electronic mechanical systems , or for months for position , navigation and timing applications , earning his PHUNapplied physics in nineteen ninety seven from harvard university bills .
Background also includes material science and mechanics , and is more than fifty years of experience managing government and industrial materials research .
And here's an accomplishment that reflects bills neck for innovation .
So far , he is accumulated some one hundred and one issued pants carrying new materials and devices for what amount and aerospace applications .
And now he is contributing his dry for innovation and dropped weighing carter bill , thanks for joining me in this conversation .
Great to be here .
So first , in the interests of transparency , I should let you know that I am a huge , huge fan material science , which I consider to be under appreciated foundation of essentially entire history of technology .
So i'm looking forward to hearing how you are taking materials research in new , and at times , spectacularly fast directions in the programs you are writing here at dark and will get to that in a bit .
But first I would like to know something about the influences and experiences in your life that turns you first for physics and from there into materials , central origin , industry and government.
First really throw that you are a fan of material science .
I think it's one of the most exciting disciplines as very interesting , and it brings books together from all sorts of different perspectives .
And of course , we all have , and I need feels for materials , these engineered or natural materials that make up our world and allows to navigate in terms of my background , probably doesn't hurt that I grew up around the , the world of lost alarm .
Most new mexico .
My father was a physicist at the love .
My mother was a very adventurous person .
She was nursed by background for the year , the public interests in the area , and so I grew up around not only this environment of science , in the public , interest in the public , interest in the national interests , as well as a wonderful adventure of spirit .
I can remember when I was probably seven or eight .
I was gifted a telescope and the skies in new mexico spectacular .
And you are just sitting there wondering and and exploring with that telescope is in relief , ignited it , the desire to go into science for me and spiritually didn't hurt that he was in the female wonderful .
And let's see , in terms of how I got into material central garden d and engaging with the government .
So I hand the opportunity .
And this is , and I don't take the opportunity for granted to do summer jobs at laboratory , and one of those laboratory jobs .
Summer jobs was with doctor , several adults owners .
And he was doing material science at hillary , high pressures and high temperatures in diamond cells .
And so in high school into college , I was doing rose on it , and that connected me with the team of harvard that I joined , and the team at harvard .
Of course , you will allow me to look at that material science in a different way and want to the naval research and switched fields , stone material century , but went from solid state connectives and face transformations into surface and from an.
Again , that stands for naval research lab for those who were not definitely with the epidemic.
The neighborhood , of course , is the corporate research laboratory for the navy and has that culture , and also was really natural transition for me to go to each other , all which was , of course , connected to the huge aircraft companies , and now is covered by boeing , general motors .
And that's essentially wearing my connection to materials for causing your.
Came from well , so that gets me to the next question I have , which is , and I usually ask this of those who joined me in his conversations is , it's the , how did I get the dark story ?
So I know that HRLhas extensive and historic connections with the dark .
But what specifically was your connection ?
There are that , and they are getting new to japan.
There was a particular program manager in defence science , the office about ten years ago , maybe a years ago , doctor , do the gold waster , who , very sadly , just passed away to the pandemic , and a digital doctor was disturbed , a real visionary and wanted to understand how we could really change our world .
We are around materials in searching for the next new hour , the next new way to to pull out of the period of table females , a strong material , adoptable material .
And so far that can surpass themselves .
We have .
And he asked the question , what if we completely inverted that inside , let's try to teach today's materials , new tricks .
And I had been thinking along the same lines I was working with the colleague at the time , doctor alone checkers in thinking about architected materials , essentially poorest materials with designed architecture .
And these two visions were right in line .
And so I started working.
Dark a gold waster .
And just a question about the what you mean by architecture , and in the scale there , so you talking about the liberate structure at the microsoft scale , and which is why sort of the scale elevator cells were below or or millimeter scale of suicides of puppies is what kind of future sizes are you talking about?
Probably the easiest analogy would be to tall buildings if you look as an example is my favorite example .
Architecture is the eiffel tower .
It is an absolutely astonishing structure in three hundred meters tall , and the relative density of that structure is on the order of a tenth of a percent .
What that means is , if I took that three hundred meter tall structure , and I melted it down , but I kept the same footprint .
I would have a solid piece of metal , which about three hundred and fifty .
So that's an astonishing , efficient use of matter .
And when you do it , he looked at the architecture of the iphone tower .
It is organized as hierarchical .
You've got it , of course , the very familiar sweeping structure , but then when you zoom and you see that it is a that is composed itself of trust .
Initial , those trousers are composed of a third layer of process in some cases , and that architecture is what gives that structure , its massification saying , so we thought , okay , could we translate that idea that cool idea from architecture down into the materials level , and so you can look at architecture of many levels within the material nature does this phenomenally well , but when you look kind of where you can get the biggest if it , it is at that , serve micron and microsoft scale , and the key of all materials is that if you can't make enough of that material for an application really does .
And so scalability is absolutely important .
So we were , we have the laboratory or chasing scalability .
How can I make a really big structure that is composed of all these ministers of microsoft scale architectural features ?
That's where we connected , and then through that program , of course , we've got to no doubt the office got to know media so , and we've been engaged to long conversation about when I , and if I felt like I had really done what I could have data out to certainly explore the creative options there , but also to make an impact in different ways , you know , from a scientific , personal management business , engaging with our LC members of the time born in general motors .
And I felt like you , my next , really important , solid step would be to go to the other side of the table and understand from the government's perspective , what the driver , where are the really important opportunities , and how can materials help with those and involve able to come here and start working on some of the hardest and most impact form terrorist problems?
Validation , well and exciting turn .
I would think of a material scientist .
So thanks for sharing that story .
So bill , before we talk about the programs you oversee it doubt , but I want to dig a little bit into those one hundred and one patterns of yours before we know you have your hundred and second already .
But when we call , can only scratch the surface , I wanted to be pretty quick on this .
But please give me and our listeners a worldwide tour of perhaps a few of the patterns you personally think of the course of.
That's actually pretty hard to pick.
Whatever your children do you like them all , what it doesn't matter that they don't really need to.
Was just once you like .
Now , I think the ones are the most passionate about all or in the area of of safety .
And and safety is , it is not negotiable .
That's something that we really try hard to ensure and maximize cost .
You know , you can , you can , for see every contingency , but , but there are things we can do from ontario's perspective .
And this is in particular , safe for for vehicles , for automotive applications .
One really important area that we doubt into about fifteen years ago , ten years ago is smart materials .
And these choose , I can adapt .
And the concept was could be enabled the vehicle to adapt to a , an incident , you know , a potential collision in a penalty and impact that kind of thing to prepare itself to be more effective in providing protection for the people involved , whether the pedestrian has been impacted or a person inside the vehicle of those in in its a category of safety that are most proud of .
And would you look back very finally on is around child safety , there was a particular problem to heart running problem of in our child trapped in a car , and our busy parents who is forgot them .
and if we really looked hard at what are all the technologies solutions we could potentially bring to bear on that problem , and we developed the heartbeat sensor that could hear the heartbeat of a , you know , through all the layers are padding in the seat through the car seat and just meeting the people involved in safety and empty coach , child safety and iraq , and with them and engaging with them was just a 不是。
Homely moving experience , but make my head time for one more pattern comes to mind that you.
For while we worked on , of course , these architect materials , and we developed a process to make ultra light materials .
And this is under a dark program .
And it was really , really fun .
The fundamental question was how , like the material .
And in , of course , we're intentionally putting proposed in , and in that case , we are able to make a material which was significantly later than a error .
jail.
That's what I was just thinking of .
Which would you have a name called silent smoke ?
Yes , do you hold a piece of?
Okay okay , okay , and so we do have a few pounds on that .
That is a very interesting material .
It's potentially very good at a christopher and installation where you really want to have never wait maximum right?
What is the actual sort of material categories of metal loops ?
And we're going to come on , can be anything.
It is more than architecture .
So we were , we used metals .
We also use polymers .
Really , really , really , very flexible concept.
Okay , and then when everything they came up in an earlier discussion , this goes back , actually more toward your earlier years .
And you said that you traveled around the world , I think , often with your mother , like just to describe in a briefly with something about those travels , and maybe what you might be drawing from that even now , in your science engineering device.
Crash , so I think what I draw from that experience just to start on that point is being open to serendipity .
Let me describe what we used to do .
We would buy a ticket to some part of the world and another britain ticket from a very , very distant part of the world and figure out how to get between those two places with no plan .
And it was an apple incredible experience at the first time , my mother and I traveled , we went from hosting .
He fell in to hong kong the hard way through the old soviet union down in the china and pakistan in the , and it was just a profoundly lightning experience in every year , a couple of years , we are able to make a trip like that .
You get a of the world very different people .
And yet you can be in a part of the world where maybe they don't know very much about you .
And yet they are welcoming and engaging and with you as a person .
And so I think being open and interested in engaging with people who are very different from myself , a certainly one major lesson , and another is to really learn , to listen to ideas that may be your outside of my experience and trying to understand them and and figure out how we can take those ideas and go from them.
Well , I mean , I know you got your PHDfrom harvard , but i'm beginning to think of the most valuable .
I learned a new date was , was on those trips with your mother .
why ?
What a gift that she gave you and many kinds of lessons at a merge realm , sure that you put those to use now , well , thanks for sharing .
Now , let us move into a discussion about your really interesting portfolio of programs .
So let's start with a program called metrics , or in its long form , the materials for transaction program , relevant material categories have intriguing names , similar electrics , multiple roads and face change materials .
And the applications also prompted years .
They include control devices and tennis , migrant motors , energy harvesting and even refrigeration , which actually is quite interesting because we need a next generation refrigeration technology to knock down .
What is the major sources of carbon emission ?
But that's probably story we want to get to hear if we tell me about this program , majority , the new materials , you hope it will lead to , and what you hope to achieve it.
Absolutely , so matrix is actually a program that I inherited .
Doctor , gym , gym .
Let start the program of a variety double , but it's really well aligned with my background and smart terrorism and structure .
The core idea of the program was that we've been working on these transparent materials for a long time .
Female actress , female actress are materials that when you put a temperature grading to cross them , you can transduction that into due into electricity .
There's other materials you mentioned .
Faith , change materials , or if they all do this sort of transit doctor process and the frustration in the community for a long time has been , why have these materials benefits in pakistan as we would like them to be .
They have this amazing capability , and you are completely revolutionizing thermal management and energy generation , and the core comes up on the program .
Was maybe it , because we have not called develop the materials along with the application , and you really do need to do that .
You need to think about what the application is .
It's trying to do , provide , and specifically in a private day , a few hundred watts for a four red operating base so that devices can be recharged and do so significantly lower masses of the emphasizing power contemporaries than what we can do today with the generator that you might find it home people .
So that's the core focus of the program , and I think that has really played out in several different aspects .
There's the energy generation that I talked about portable palace .
There are several projects that have been cold , developing some electric and then.
A device to utilize those , those storm electrics just take me through one or two examples that some of the performers are working at the same research groups that are on contract on the metrics program it took to give listeners a sense of of , in fact , you know , what would such material look like .
And what would sort of the signal from the environment ?
I get translucent into something else that is useful.
Let's take the thermal electric example .
So in this case , the device would look something like a horrible gas candidate you might get for your girl , think something on that size .
And inside of that would be a reservoir fulfilled .
So think you can pour in japanese , japanese or some other type , and there is a burner insights , or converts that fill into heat .
There is a hut zone inside of this device around that hot zone would be a placed these thermal electric materials .
And the theological onside it would be exposed to the hot side .
And then there is a heat exchanger or a of a radiator .
Then couples to the outside in our two room temperature or weather temperatures in ambient that sets up the temperature gradient across the material and starts the floor electricity .
And then you can connect all of those their electric elements up to a parking order , and you know that it might have a set plugs like you would see , you know , for USB charging to buy something like that.
On the outside , so it's like just a question about that .
What is the advantage of doing that , you know , with these advanced materials were to say , burning fuel generator .
It's a base of generator .
Lots of people have in the pattern around the background.
I think there are two major ventures .
One is that we would have a significantly lighter device .
So because there's no moving parts or not with a lot of the mechanics and mechanisms , and could also be potentially more reliable , potentially .
But I think the other other drainages is that it would be silent , and so do not generate us a lot .
They are .
There's smelly , we could probably change a lot of that if we were able to.
Categorically , so you can get electricity without screaming .
here .
I am here .
I am out there in a contested environment .
Yeah , great.
And they're potentially good of non natural applications .
Think one of my favorites is actually the media , if you have a portable station , where are you trying to interview somebody ?
The last thing you want is this noise generator said , you interfering with the yet the audio signal.
right ?
Well , i'll have to tell my journalism friends about about this potential new technology for when they're out in the field .
Another deep dive materials program under your wing .
And another one I think you inherited from a program manager , zhang , men who I got to know my first twelve to the european bank , twenty sixteen to twenty eighteen time frame , is called the atoms to protect program , or a to p catch me a briefly on the history of the program .
And where you are taking you.
So this was the program I actually connection to background done was formulating the program .
So as a real , a real pleasure to be alone here at the program and shepherded through its final , the core idea behind atoms to product was scalability of energy technology .
And at the time , john was looking at all of these different new techniques for developing ten materials .
Absolutely amazing properties and asking the question , why did we not then see a lot of applications for them , and one of the problems is that you need to be able to scale , you need to have a large capability for translating that none of material to the microscopic application .
You don't think the side of of a , or , you know , entire airplane , when , how do I get serious animated royal properties at that scale ?
And so he developed.
Program , where you mean , somewhere , you might make a pigging outside sample in a lab .
But if you're gonna actually apply to something like the site of , how are you going to make enough material , ultimately that you can afford is practical.
Absolutely , so that was the core question in the program .
And when you dig into the science , what you realize is that there is , this is beautiful balance of forces at the nano scale that allow us to make these nanomaterials we have in our different , attractive and responsible forces , everything from korea lunch and ionic bonds up to hydrogen bonds up to prevent of all interactions .
And then we have replaced forces in hardware and reactions , materials that that repeat dramatically , and other forces that cause rearrangements like.
Brown , in motion , written in this list of force , I just wanted the leaders know who never heard what band of all forces are , those who just thought of very settle forces between molecules .
So not exactly as strong as they abandoned type of interaction , but a force that does influence the way molecules will interact with one another year.
Yes , I think the most famous , microscopic example of venezuela's interactions is the gago , of course , you know how the gaga actually can stick to the ceiling at the vendors in the russian .
But those forces are those forces kind of stop working about how to animate leaders .
And then we have a hard time then doing things with those materials at sizes greater than , say about my crown until we get a larger sizes where we can start to manipulate things in traditional ways , in a picking place in a different types of other free machining is certainly .
So the program was really about bridging those two worlds and enabling us to take advantage of those netscape properties at the market .
One of the most stunning outcomes of the program is the scalability of college and production , nanoscale college action into a microscope product that could be a replacement , safe for attendant in the body .
There is a company that were working with right now that has received at the approval.
To go into clinical trials , I take it , referring to employee and their work on.
Yeah , CCO , you got .
And what was really cool for them was developing processes that allowed them to have the nanoscale college , and , of course , but make them massively parallel and at scale , they did not.
Is this actually some kind of synthetic goodbye engineer collision , or is it a completely different materialists able to to serve the same function that the ACL normally does that?
They've doubles , so leave they've done a mock accord , composite between biodiversity and a reinforcing fiber , a reinforcing element , which is more synthetic .
But they also have a pure college , important as well .
And these two , I think , are going to be very impactful , and I am a long time square economy filled my knees , my echoes getting ready to.
One one of these , yeah , so there is a some degree of sale ventures in this trajectory of the program , which is really fine as lots of skills and soccer players and many other active people who would love to have a way of repairing of their sales .
So that sounds recorded that i've heard of another one .
I think this is europe's .
Parker is working on something called it by my.
Assembly printer , yeah , they turned an amazing job .
And of course , it looks like this amazing background in printing of all clients .
And they wanted to be able to take their core in one of their correct expertise areas in a skilled , skillful in a laser printing and apply to electronics and be able to produce electronic components.
Easily as you later print , I wanted to talk about one more program bill in this one is , is your materials architectures and acquaintances for hypersonically or mark program .
Very clever agreement , because mark refers to the speed of something , an error , but that hypersonic word in the program title indicates that your working materials for vehicles intended to travel at least five times a speed of sale , maybe ten , maybe of times .
The speed of sound is this sort of thinking about , just have fast ideas .
And so you calculate the LAto new york trip of a marketing vehicle , which would be travelling at seven hundred miles power , which is two miles , a second or so .
Then it would take about twenty two minutes to get two early from the new york .
So what are the materials challenges to building vehicles that can operate at those ?
And what are you doing in the mark program to try to realize those challenges?
Yeah , high personnel is a really fun technology area .
It is the very driven by the capability of the materials .
And there is one feature of hypersonic vehicle that is absolutely dependent on the possibilities of the materials .
And as the leading edge of the vehicle , this is the part of the vehicle .
That means the atmosphere first were flying through the atmosphere is both the space .
And when you're going , the arab thermal heating that occurs when you cross the air ahead of you , and to , fortunately against the vehicle is absolutely intense .
Just give your sense of how the heating rate at the front of vehicle skills as the cube of the volatility of the vehicle and also skills as the australia , the spring freestone pressure divided described of the feature size .
In that case , the sharpness of that leading edge.
But this is basically major to simplify .
This mean that the faster you go , the faster and faster , you know.
You hit up , yes , and it's , it's a really hard wall in a focus in all , as they were developing faster , faster aircraft .
Talk about breaking the sound barrier once you get to about mark fire , we started talking about breaking the heat period .
This is a thorough problem , in addition to a new dynamic leading edge .
It's a very tiny if you want your vehicle to be a dynamically efficient , it has to have a very sharp leading edge , as opposed to what you might see .
Say for an apollo entry caps or something .
You know , we're , we're coming back from space or trying to mediate that heating .
Those look favorite .
Don't know the very blanket , very large and very low coverture .
We're essentially trying to do .
You're cut through the air if you like .
So it's about dealing with that .
And but we've got back in the history as this is wonderful history of incredibly creative engineering solutions to dealing with that heat in the fifties , focused on trying to understand the , and they did not have great materials to work with enthusiasm and a lot of time , adding thermal management to that leading anger to the north column of vehicle , then sometimes in the sixties , we discovered a material rate will be developed material of carbon , carbon , a composite between carbon fivers and a poorest or lower density of north korean metrics .
And this is an absolutely amazing material .
If you are going to imagine a single material for all the properties that you would want , this is that material , and it can handle very high temperatures .
This comes to carbon , so it does degrade in the atmosphere .
You start to oxygen as the carbon thick enough , a glowing cold you would have in your fireplace , and you blow on their clothes , but it keeps the shape leads to some extent , but you can watch it road as your opposite .
That material took us a long way , and when using it in a variety of applications for leading edges in the bleeding edge of the shuttle , really look at the nose , and the black parts of the battle of carbon carbon .
It's again , a really good material , but it only takes you so far that blasted humid car , heat wall .
So what happens when you hit that wall when you start to hit somewhere around me , know twenty , two hundred and fifty and three or four hundred dollars percent of media .
And then what happens is the carbon starts to burn , and that leading it starts to blunt , and they are dynamic efficiency of the vehicle drops .
So you are not able to then have as much range or manufacturers like and switch and solve that problem is , how do we have a leading age , which , and also can take even greater heat , and we've gone back to that history , the pre carbon carbon history , and said , okay , we have new ways of handling heat .
Now you and you know , the cherry engineering industry look at the parallel training industry they're starting to deal with heat foxes that are on this order , but see if we can translate some of their solutions , new high temperature materials that we can produce in network with complex internal architectures going back to our architecture discussion that can allow us to have the structure of strengthens , difficult as well in viewing with thermal management capability .
So you can hit the heat exchanges transporation and face.
I love the way you describe all that , because it really helped me appreciate the role that materials will play in the future of hypersonic vehicles , technologies , weapons , in the sense that there are other huge challenges .
Just what think about proportion , but , but materials will have a certainly an important role in , I guess how one of a flight in any particular kind of vehicle might be expected to withstand .
And then , of course , that has all kinds of biggest technical and strategic consequences .
And another general fascinating that comes down to the way you put items together .
It's an interesting , continuing.
Indeed , it's a wonderful material problem in the community that are working with is really just energized .
This is a really hard problem , and they're bringing your whole variety of potential new solutions and making great progress all about your roughly year into the program , and already showing results were developing new materials , as well as these new phone architectures .
And how many performers you have on us ?
We have nine , nine performance plus patterns of them on sort of on the government side , happens every year .
They stand up partner for us in being able to connect the material developments with platform performance.
Just the fact that you said that there were nine performer groups that reminds me , one of the things about dark , but that I find amazing in the projects .
In that way , AAproject like this , like mark , and that brings together a number of different performers , different research groups .
It sort of a way that that an orange community and innovation community gets created by way of the existence of the project is so fruit .
Yes , yes , absolutely , bill , before we leave mark as we're getting into the sort of the talent of our discussion , whether any other things about that program , or about a hypersonic technology that you like.
Yeah , just wanted to mention there was one vehicle in the deep , darkest called the most blind reentry vehicle , which flu a year before I was born .
And we've had one of these types of technologies on it .
So this is very much back to the future .
It had a nichol's coin , which was using transparent and had a few like twenty or thirty kilograms of water on board .
The hopes to arrive.
Amazing , no , because what that means is that the engineers were stealing from the plant world trees rely on transparency and bring water up from the roots all the way up to the tops of their canopy .
So i'm happy to hear that engineers are honouring the biology to I bring into something even like hypersonic technology that is so cool to hear .
And I guess just one more question is there anything that didn't come up during our conversation ?
Are you apologized me for not asking up and questioned ?
I absolutely shoot up , and if you ask the question like that , let me know , and a new answer , if I was going to.
Add one thing to a conversation is that I have absolutely under the optimism about the potential for science to solve today's most important problems , and I think material science can contribute in others .
There's a feeling that we , beneath material science , history of our species , and we've unlocked as much of the periodic tables .
We can potentially mock .
I don't think that's true at all .
I think we have barely scratched the surface .
We've looked at the one perspective .
How do we put items together ?
We have tried to look at it from another perspective .
How do we have an application drives are up because the performance of the material that that we would like to produce , there's a whole new world of certain artificial intelligence , machine learning .
These new tools can be applied to that very old problem .
I believe we will for fundamental impact for new solutions .
That's , that's one .
I think the other is really about psychological sciences of wonderful field .
It brings people together from chemistry , physics , engineering , the end user community in all the different engineering disciplines in a lot of engineering and engineering support .
And I think we have a honeymoon opportunity to rethink this field .
So instead of having our different silence , we have through some of these new tools , the ability to now get back together and work as the team I always want to leave you with that message that I really have unbounded optimism about the future materials and the future capabilities that will come out .
And the ability of these capabilities to solve.
Are hardest problems .
Well , we so badly need more and more optimism .
So thank you for giving me that that uplifting kind of finale , and I just have to say , love the way you're thinking , the periodic table , every material ever was , is or will be a sort of inheritance in that .
And yet what you say is , we were only minded in a very minor way .
And so by bringing all these the central disciplinary sort of to it , in other news , skills and tools or addressed at the beginning of maybe bringing out materials , I can solve a lot of problems , and that is very optimistic message to me .
I'm really happy that you run it .
You run this task .
A billion , and I think we're all better for it .
Thanks william carter , because i've been calling it for letting me and listeners in on what the future of materials and the advances in technology to enable might look like .
So , just thanks for the discussion.
absolutely expand the expenditure, 大家可以扫码。
And thanks willingness for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from there , thanks also to ban celebrant for his partnership in producing this program .
For more information about doctor william carter , the programs he runs in the agency's defence sizes , office and the other banks through technology dark , is working on visit , darker duck and for links that enable you to download this .