Going to a science or engineering laboratory , close your eyes and listen in a biomedical lab , you might be an ultra central , huge raving up as a separate to the components of assemble in a mysql proportion research facility .
You may hear the aggressive white noise from a test burn of a new experimental jet fuel in a computer simulation center .
You might hear the harm from a variable or*****ra of cooling events in each setting .
You can hear a sonic finger print of what goes on there .
Welcome back to sounds of innovation , a feature of our Voices from darker parkers .
My name is iphone motel on your dark house in each sounds of innovation feature .
You'll hear some of the soundscapes of research and development in the moments they are happening and learn just a little bit about what new capabilities .
Those things my friends go to the doctor , program managers and their teams , as well as to the research performers working under contract for those teams , for help in harvesting the sound , you are about to hear .
In each case , I first will play the sound without telling you what it is as you listen , try to guess where the sound comes from .
Then I will tell you , alright , here we go .
Let me give you a few hints about these first two sound clips .
One hit is that they come from researchers working on dark as persistent a quarter , leaving sensors program , or pales .
Another hint is that you are not about to hear recordings of big fat rain drops slamming onto A.
Now , for the second clip , it sounds little sad.
What is coming to both of those clips is the right of crackling noises .
They derive from a real life's superpower will die .
A common committee and widespread secretary , known as snapping shrimp , turns out that these two cinema cross stations have some specialized cloud enemy , a tightly fitting pegging cup of sorts that can do wonders when the shrimp slams the pig into the cup structure .
It produces a tiny jet water this interim generates .
And I am not making this up a super carbon trading under sea bubble that , in mere microseconds , developed five thousand degree temperatures in midst a flash of light , and then as ocean pressure instantly squeeze the back out of existence , what amounts to an underwater club of thunder , one thousands of the shampoo snapping it sounds like a pumpkin popcorn , a hardware .
Or , as some have described it from.
The energy from these implanting bubbles can stand and even kill nearby prayer , just what the snapping trip need to see the unresilient of another day .
Just a few more specifics on those sounds , the first one you heard was picked up from a hydrophone placed by the peer at town point in north africa , beginner by team of powers , research performers from the government due university and the underwater technology from cold octopus .
The second sound clip was captured six thousand miles away by a set of power's performers from the neighborhood warfare center , based in new port .
In their case , the hydrophone was immersed in the whale friendly waters by her poorer hawaii .
One working , you might be asking yourself why dark cares about all of these snapping shrimp .
Well , because it is possible to think of all those swimming snaps as millions of sooner pinks get a good enough .
Understanding , uphold those pings , bounce of objects and get good enough of gathering and analyzing those are , and you just might be able to create a global partnership with snapping shrimp to improve maritime situation .
Awareness about what is in the water , where things are in the water and what they are .
The next audio clip comes from an engineering research firm in new hampshire , working on a critical technology of interest to program manager steve , comedian of the agency , tactical technology .
Obvious , which you need to know before you listen to is that I had to slice and splace what was originally an eighty second clip into a much shorter version that you would be willing to listen to the progression of towns provides you as a hint about your hearing .
It's a big journey .
So hang in there.
What you heard in the clip is an experimental , compact turban generator system with the microphone , approximately six feet from the test stand , you heard it increasing from a startup speed using an electric start to a speed of over sixty thousand revolutions permitted for RPM.
That's an assumption rate of .
Are you sitting down a thousand revolutions per second and its ultimate rotation speed will be over twice that novel and advanced proportion systems , including ones for unmanned vehicles .
Instrumentally are under his research menu , this potential component , a hybrid electric turbo alternator about the size of a washing machines .
Chamber , is being designed by engineers at britain , energy inhabitant , new at the fantastic rotation speeds .
It can achieve the turbulence .
Compressive developed enough pressure to support stable and extremely efficient computation using a variety of fuels , and then can start generating access electrical power four up to thirty five kilos of power at one hundred and thirty thousand .
The technology is intended for multiple users .
Among them grounded aerial hybrid .
Electric vehicles were man's men and unmanned a , according to the dark team interested in this research , the technology could be enabled for small to medium hybrid electric aircraft platforms , rather than developing proportion itself .
Disturbance concept efficiently converts fuel compulsions into electricity to run the vehicles , electric models , which , in turn can power fans or propellers .
The electricity can also provide sensors .
A terrible alternative like this can shift the design paradigm for aerospace designers by loosening restrictions on engine policemen , the ability of the device to run on various fuels further , as I will close out this sounds of innovation episode with a trio of audio clips .
They're from the so called foundery of a boston based biotechnology research performer , with , especially in requesting bacterial cells into new and useful forms , analysis to the way a traditional foundry cats and requests metal into useful shapes.
Here's the second clip.
Now , for the final clip of the trial.
That first sound , the one with a throne to it , it comes interview to the gingle buyer works .
Researchers used to concentrated bacteria cells into a deco palace .
These cell concentrates become the focus of other experiments and measurements , such as DNA analysis for determining which genes correctly sympathized , were assembled or tests to see if an introduced gene leads to an expected activity at a top speed insurer clip , the central future reached a spinning rate about four thousand two hundred revolutions , the true break inside the central future was well balanced .
That's why the machines thrown , rather than make a wrecker the way of washing machine does when a unbalanced load of clothes enters the state .
The second sound you heard comes from what dingo folks referred to as an integrated workshop is a highly automated robotic workstation .
That , in this case , is preparing thousands of tiny whales in multiple ways that are shaped a bit like naturalized cupcake baking sheets , the machinery and close the robotic arm that retrieves multiple wail place from a holding and then shuttles them to other locations at these locations .
Other automated machinery adds this through that liquid containing cells , cultural media or text chemicals .
Other actions on the workstation include ceiling and unsealing , the world and barcode labelling them .
So a computer contract , each whales contents conditions in the procedures it has undergone or will undergo .
This kind of automation is what makes it possible to screen thousands and even millions of samples in a reasonable amount time .
It's called HTSor high swimming , whose health , health telephone can cause .
Head of the foundry , explains the value of such systems for his HT.
So our HTSteam , rather than setting up these places by hand , use this robotic workshop to set up many hundreds of places , as you see in this , this hotel here , all track by barcode .
And that way , they can be fed to other instrumentation to run different kind of analytical tastes .
And so the idea , the , by doing everything robotically tracked by our custom software , were able to know exactly what is in every plate , and very well that played and then drive that logistics to run really complex work flow .
Those are other other robot cliffords.
The final song clip of the ginger buyer work series comes to another robotic workstation .
This one is preparing one other name .
Ninety six will multiple places by adding cell infused goose rural solutions into the world that have been pre loaded culture medium .
The results in ten thousand , three hundred and sixty eight wells with specific bacterial cells growing under specific medium conditions , will undergo specific measures .
The darby connection here is that ginger buyer works is under contract in a few of the agencies efforts .
One is the revictual program .
Its goal is to engineer bacteria that can temporarily alter the microbial ecosystem or microbial on a war fighter skiing .
Another relevant collaboration between the company is in the programming on the SDtwo .
Let's stands for synergistic discovery and design .
It's all about leveraging large data sets from high school , put to develop data driven models .
These empirical approaches can accelerate scientific discovery and provide guidance for developing technology , especially for domains such as migrants , for which a full theoretical understanding is not yet in hand .
Well , that's it for this episode of sounds of innovation .
Thanks listeners for joining , thanks also to time , short , rich for his partnership in producing this program .
For more information about the programs associated with the sounds , you justify the program managers who run those programs , as well as other breakthrough technologies .