Self technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand alternatives operation technology is a driver of our times since its founding in one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , the defence advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from dark a window , and the dark is core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan , a motto and arm , your DARPA host today .
I am pleased to be talking with .
Doctors , said kung , a program manager in the agency of biological technology service .
He brings to doubt that interests in experience that ranges from a novel materials that can make technologies more capable , new approaches to therapists and medical counter and new strategies for acquiring scarce materials like rare earth elements , which have rolled in many high technologies and even portable water , we are recording our conversation from our respective pounds , as we do our parts to slow the spread of coffee nineteenth , because we are not in a recording studio .
You might hear ambient sounds like trafficking melbourne to tell you a little bit more about safe .
He joins the art of the university of california , sandy ago , where he is a professor in the department of chemistry and biochemistry and former department .
His research has focused on the interface of bail in organic and medicinal chemistry and advanced materials , including middle organic frameworks or maps , which are many among themselves , chemical separations in catalysts .
No stranger to federal science and technology rules that was the triple ASroger reveal fellow in global stewardship in the white house office of science and technology policy known for shorters OSTP.
And he is an alarm .
Owners of the dark responsibility .
Defense science study group says , received a pair of bachelor's degrees from stanford university , one in chemistry and one in political and APHDand chemistry from the university of california , berkeley , which he followed with a post darker fellow position in biochemistry at the massachusetts institute of technology .
Sounds cool , thanks for joining me .
This conversation .
That's my pleasure to try to be here .
So I always like to get a sense of the origin of the scientist specific interests in your case in chemistry .
And as we mentioned in something a specific against frameworks , and you also interested in sort of all that chemistry is going on inside of sales makes me wonder , you know , certainly the chemistry side of your lighting , things on fire in your parents .
Base manager , you have some love at first side when you saw the period go elements , but you tell me where , where did your interests come from?
Managers and science definitely started in childhood .
My father before he became an office .
Telemarketer was a bio georgia teacher for middle of high school , and he was always really passionate about science .
And we spent many and evening together watching novel , or nationally graphic , or even the mutual .
Oh my hair , I think it was.
Oh , wild kingdom , yes , I remembered that.
Wild kingdom , thank you .
Yeah , so shows like this were a staple of our evening .
Things are cosmos as well , of course , and he always just encourage my interest in science .
We would go fossil hunting off a more home bully varied in southern california , always assist without the top of the list .
And really , after my dad , although he didn't go into a longer inquiry , and scientists himself here had a real passion for it and always really inspired my interest in it .
And so even I did not profile interest going in the high school .
I was very involved in speech and debate and student government , and had an interesting law and civilians that core interesting science I just couldn't shake .
Yeah , and it just stuck with me all the way through my current career or.
So fantastic practical influence in sparking the interesting science in general .
But how about chemistry ?
What is it the direct you there?
Yeah , chemistry was AIsort of failing to it , which is probably not a super uncommon story .
I would think I went to college , you know , knowing I was politician .
Science as a major , maybe premature .
I wasn't entirely sure I never really thought about being a chemistry majoring in chemistry .
I was much more interested in the sort of extremes on either side of chemistry , which was either .
I was very interested in biology , probably again , influenced by the TVshows .
I watched .
I was interested , maybe like being a few biologists setting animals like an or the other stream of being an astronomy physicist , inspired by shows that cosmos , I was always really fascinated with space and astronomy , and had a real love for that , but I sort of fell in the chemistry , probably for two reasons , one , as I , my massachusetts , have a strong enough to be a natural physicist , and as much as I loved it , it was very challenging , but probably the bigger influence was actually just a friend in college .
So when I was asking for his undergrad , I was in all freshman dorms there , but I was in the one dormitory of freshmen and started making friends right away .
And one of my closest friends of my closest friend in college was a guarantee , stephen miller , and we became fast friends very early , and he had a real passion for chemistry , and we took those freshmen chemistry classes together and very competitive owls trying to beat each other on the next term of final .
And he thought that kept nudging me towards chemistry , and I was good at it at the time .
At least , you know , I didn't came as classes .
And so as I think , a combination , having some sort of feeling of ethnic ford , but a lot of just urging by this body of mine to say , hey , let's do chemistry together .
And it's really cool .
And you should , you should stick with chemistry .
And I thought of how it ended out .
And the funny is also a professor chemistry at university , foreign games , well , and in our PHTthesis , I credited him for my interest in sticking with chemistry , and he , conversely , credited me , which I thought was ironic because I never thought I put chemistry .
I was out of the other way around , but apparently we sort of self coaches each other in the field.
Love that story , I mean , just how how two friends would influence each other , and also the chemistry degree is near , and due to my heart , because of that , that was my undergraduate degree as well .
Campaign event spring up .
And for what I do is a science communicator , I felt like what that did for me is giving me the language of science , but in a way where I could actually also talk to biologist and go in the other direction and talk to some of the anybody dealing with atoms and molecules .
So so if I think it's a great degree.
Yeah , I strongly agree with that .
And although I can never encourage myself being a chemist as my crude developer , I definitely found it to be a really good film .
I love the a synthetic chemistry training , so making new molecules , although I did have a postcard and biochemistry , but that's idea that the process of discovery and being creative in coming up with new molecules that nobody ever made before and being in the lab and making something that no one , at least on this planet , is ever made before orange and characterising and figuring out what it is and what it does is a spiritual element of creativity there that are not sure everybody appreciates that I found this is kept my passion in science over the years .
I love to that .
I think , you know , people will be excited about and interesting.
Indeed , indeed , and these are hope .
Some young people listening to this and hearing about the way of the excitement of discovery that comes with going into chemistry .
So maybe you actually influence them .
And there are reference in there .
So when a movement tried to coming to dark on taking on the roads , program engineering , biological technologies of office , I was in twenty one thousand nine hundred and twenty years at the university , california , sandy ago , in an academic setting .
Some just wondering what in buyer , the leap two , and how did they come about ?
I think you.
As you mentioned , I have always had a with my colleagues .
Greece , I also had long standing in tuesday and policy and civics .
This goes back to high school as well , where I was involved in a lot of clubs quickly , the genuine station of america , which was a very big civic club .
And so a student government club that I really love and still love , still support .
And so when i've got ten year , uses NDAgo around two thousand and sixty thousand and seven , I had time for a civilization , and it was time for me to sort of scratch that each in terms of policy interests and civic interests .
And so I applied and received that replies , fellowship that he mentioned and went to work at all ATP for a year .
It was actually under both the bush and obama administrations of their own transition .
It was a wonderful experience .
I absolutely loved it .
It was just a totally different world , and it was one of the great benefits of being a professor and academic with that .
You have these opportunities to literally step out of your everyday job and step in doing a timely , different world and do something totally different .
And so those TPIdid advantage of science policy world and got to hang out around and near the white house and and see a change of administration is received today between two two administrations and just a lot of stuff that is acted in a chemistry I would never seen in my life , and I got a pretty open , close and personal view .
It saw it was just great , and after I finished that september twenty nine team , I knew I wanted to come back and was just a matter of where and when .
And so I looked at working at a variety , federal agencies on the national science , on and then dark became a people mentioned above .
I learned about it through the disease , which you mention the defensive study group .
There are a number of prominent people at my university .
This is an eagle who a football program managers at the , including our chancellor and our DNA engineering .
And they have mentioned how much they enjoyed dark on what special places it was , and so that really stimulated my interests .
And so about a decade after I left , DC, Idecided to try to positions in the federal government , particularly with focus on DARPA .
And ultimately , it worked out I am here now , I really like it .
I should say , i'm at dark under a special mechanism .
I am still actually a part of the USDfaculty and ultimately plan on returning there , and I still have a research group that conducts our research .
There is well filled with grassins and post dogs.
Best of both worlds , because many program managers are so moved to come to dark , but that tells you that they know it's just for a couple of years , and they don't know at a time whether they are going to end up afterwards .
So it's great to have .
I would imagine the kind of security that this arrangement does afford you .
So before we talk about a few of what are really amazing sanding programs that you ever see , including ones that help us take on the troubling rise of anti biotic resistance , and also precured .
What are where it is scarce .
I have to ask you about a seminar that you told a few times the UCS d it is called history of the american muscle car death.
Yeah , that was a lot of fun .
So UCS d has a program called freshman seminars .
They tried to incentivize faculty to get to know the incoming freshmen better in a small environment .
And so it hurt it like a large person in chemistry class to get to know your students well , and so they have this christmas .
Women are programmed as limited to twenty students .
It's one hour a week , and you can basically teach any topic you want .
So the first couple of times I did it .
I tried to keep it close to home to chemistry , and I talk classes in forensic chemistry .
It was called by CSIfact infection .
I told a class in archaeological chemistry , archaeological set of which I call two motorcycles , something like that .
And then I realized how much latter to the university would give me on this , because they really were having factory , getting a freshmen .
And so again , inspired by my father , my father , his brother were big motorhead when I was growing up , my dad was always buying and selling cars .
So it is brother that worked in a gas station and own gas station together .
Write new opinion .
Hot dogs , los angeles , growing up together , I always love cars and not as knowledgeable about all mobiles as my father and his brother were , but I, Icertainly love them .
Another history pretty well have only a few class of the years .
And so I just thought , hey , why not learn more about it myself and just have a fun , engaging way with the students in much of my surprise , they approve the class .
We did the class .
About half a twitter of lectures , if you will , are discussions about the history of automobiles , particularly the muscle car period of the nineteen sixties in early seventies .
But then we would do the last five classes as a on one of the places that uses any eagles .
So I would invite the muslim club or invite the shopping club .
I invited the more part club , and those guys love coming out , and they will show off their cars in the students would walk around the place .
A lot of students is , but I would walk around and talk to the owners about their cars and learn about how they were .
They were .
They came from and how they restored them and all the stuff .
So it was a lot , a lot of fun .
It was a lot of fun.
Absolutely love it .
So if you remind me that when I was in high school , my best friend had a sixty five months than you know that he restored , there was a lot of fun to drive around that .
So this makes me wonder what muscle card you have in your driver.
Yeah , so I have owned a couple of years .
I had a couple of muscles , because they will .
They used to be another pretty expensive , the use of the entry level car for a collector .
So I had a seventy three mark one , a mastering gold with a final talk .
It was quite the thing I had that actually back in grass school .
I bought it off that uncle of mine .
Then I had a seventy two mark one .
Then I , when I got ten year , I bought myself a sydney three , mustn't convertible , and then I upgraded to a sixty nine firebird convertible , which I actually that car discovered when I was here at OSTP, my mentor at OCP, her father owner car .
He was the original owner , had had its since nineteen sixty nine , wanted to get rid of it to a good home .
And so I car back with me from my first ten year and DCand restored it and drove that car for a long , long time , is a wonderful car .
And then my most recent acquisition , like I just saw a few years , is there a sixty three quarrel that convert about it was always a dream that was always a dream car .
Mind , yeah , sixty three .
so.
Wrap it , okay , so you know , let's get to the business at hand , which is your experience at the dark .
And so I wanted to start with one of your programs that , gosh , sounds like it would be great to have the , the technology you're invision in the anti viral technology , and it had that in hand .
Now , the , the program , short name is interesting .
It's one name is interfering and coal evolving provincial and therapy programs .
We started actually , by a previous program manager , jim kim lit .
I just would've shared sort of the basic concept of the program , and where it now.
Sure , so it's a fascinating program , and I feel privileged to have inherited it .
When I joined , DARPA was a great introduction agency .
Until you get me up to speed about how to how to learn about the program and manager program , and the program is focused on a class of what will be or could be a novel theraputics for treating viral disease .
And his novel therapeutics are called tips , which stands for therapeutic interfering particle .
So let's say , for example , you have the , now we have a vaccine for the flu , but we have to reinvent that vaccines every year , because the flu mutates and a new strain becomes dominant year after a year .
So what this approach would do that was different , different from our a vaccine , which stimulates the new system or a small molecule , which is sort of your typical drug like aspirin , that which is directly set of attack , the virus is developed .
These tips , the best way I think to describe it is that it's a neutral version of the flu virus .
So it has all the components of the flu virus , but some genetic element is missing or disrupted , or others .
Why is not properly constructed ?
And so what you end up with is this tape , a therapy of kenya particle is viral particle that looks like the virus is how many of the components of the virus , but the key part that is missing province , it from self replicating , and that's really the key .
And so this type can be given to someone it can enter .
The person sells just like a virus .
But once it's in the cell , it just stopped there and can do anything .
However , if that same becomes infected by the live flu virus , the disease causing club virus , it turns the tip on , and what the tip will do is , instead of allowing the virus to replicate itself inside the tip will steal .
The machinery is missing in its noodle genome .
It will steal that machine ray virus and make copies of itself .
And that's really important , because what happens now is , instead of the virus replicating itself , the type replicate itself .
And the tip is not disease causing , nor can the tip replicate once the virus is gone so effectively , the tip competes with the , until the virus is just knocked out .
And in the whole system shuts down , and the virus is stopped , and even if it doesn't stop it on the first path .
So let's say it competes with the virus may be knocked down the number of articles that are produced , but various dealers escapes .
It can escape with it .
And so those viral particles go , in fact , neighboring cells again , the tips can enter themselves as well and continue to come back and compete with until the library was suggested , exhausted and outcompeted .
And then the whole system.
That is an amazing kind of molecular dynamic to imagine , actually , in a sort of pulling off when you work at the performers , which charges say the research , said that of contracts that working under the program .
How would you articulate the farther said any of these researchers have got into the goal?
Well , I am very encouraged .
It's very much your program entering its fourth year now , and the results of the innocent program are very intelligent .
Tips could become a completely new class of therapy of canada measures for treating violence .
We started , or again , gym , gym , look before me .
And the other programming is that the manager program before me started with just saying or looking at , can we make safe and effective tips that can you make a tube that competes with the virus effectively knocks down an infection and isn't harmful to sales or an animal .
And what I can tell you that for a wide range of viral diseases from the flute HIVto others , more exciting ones , you may not have heard of , and even some more current data looking at covered were trying to get for these .
These establishes is like flu , HIV, and others .
There is very good data showing that these researchers can develop tips that the tips are safe in animal models , and as the tips effectively prevent not only infection , but the spread of that infection between animals .
And so I think the program is looking very encouraging .
We are pushing some of our performers to try to get these novel .
Canada measures into a face , one clinical trial .
And i'm hopeful before the programs over , we will do that .
I think that's parliament .
The last major hurdle is that this is an entirely new type of drug .
It's not like vaccines or biologics or small molecules .
The way we normally think of them , and so it will be interesting to see how this moves forward in a clinical setting , how the fta will available a therapy to look like this with a think will be appropriate .
I am very encouraged that we could see tips as a real medical theraputics for dealing with violence in the future.
Yeah , interesting .
I am glad that you are encouraging your performers to really think about the trials and getting the they did there .
Because , as you mention , this is so different from the sort of pharmaceutical mechanism and antibiotic mechanism that it could will be that a regulatory challenge is going to be the dark ahead problem , even more so than the actual sort of chemical and former social and.
Yeah , it very well could be , because it is a really different mechanism for drug .
But if you think about the current code pandemic that were all living in , I mean , if you had a drug that could keep up with that virus and not only stamped out in an individual , but prevent that individual from spreading it to others , it's literally exactly what you would want even more .
So I would say than vaccine , perhaps , in the current situation we have been living in .
You know , having seen what we all lived in experience through the last , almost coming on a year .
Now , I think that , you know , that should provide some real incentive for a tip to be given serious consideration , considering what they.
May you succeed because , as we know and democracy bets will work experiencing that right now , this new technology might not be in hand for this particular round of a pandemic , but hopefully for the next one , let's move on to a summer related program in the sense that it's aiming for a new kind of pharmaceutical techniques .
But in this case , may be dealing more with bacteria and harnessing in the medical activity for life saving remedies , or in a short form .
Hiller at HEALRsaid this one , two as a satisfactory focus on developing new countermeasures , though more focus on sort of looking at the public health communities were concerned about because of the ascent of antibiotic resistant microbes and the potential that we could enter a sort of a post end up at it everywhere we can no longer use these fantastic medicine .
So how might the hero program step in and save the day when it comes to fighting off?
Bacteria , sir , so here is a new program that my team is dark and I developed , but approve that we're pushing for now .
Yeah , anybody resistance is in many ways , the sort of stealth pandemic that's been emerging for over twenty years now .
So people , oh no , that this is a problem that the bacteria that we get infections from are becoming increasingly resistant to the analytics that we have available , that when a new energy is developed , residents emerges much more rapidly , sometimes within a year of the drug being first used .
And so this is a crisis that has been well recognized by , I guess that many people have called the pandemic .
That's been a sort of evolving or emerging for twenty years .
And so the human program is designed to take on this challenge , using a new approach , a different approach that involves harnessing one's own biology to combat the bacterial function .
And so there's a technology that's been about a little less than a decade .
I would say , and it's an approach by which a new class of drugs often referred to his camera drugs .
Camara , referring to the middle article creature that has multiple heads on a single body like fine and a dragon and eagle fuse to one body .
These molecules also have multiple heads and the way they work is one head of the molecule engages your target , so something that is causing or propagating a disease that head is attached to another head that engages some sort of biology within your cell that is designed to either the activate or eliminate that the activators are destroyed .
And so this concept has been widely investigated , as in any inconnue trials currently for addressing cancer , but it has not yet been applied to many other diseases , including bacteria , cross diseases .
And so what the hiller program is largely focused on is taking this protects or climate technology and porting it from its name and face with cancer biology and applying it to bacteria , threats and bacterial talks in such as anthrops toxin , or barcelona , or many patriotic micro organisms .
And so this is a very , very different mechanism , because you're not just sort of poisoning the organism , or directly attacking a component of the organism , but you are buying the impact of what the organism needs to be patagonia , and you're then shadowing it away and just using natural biological processes to damage the activity , or destroy those such as the disease .
And this has never been applied to microbial disease before .
And so we're hopeful that by bringing again , sort of like with tips and entirely new medical camera measure modality or mechanism of action , we can overcome some of the resistance issues that are playing traditional and about development for decades.
Yeah , so the way you describe these agents in it with the multiple heads in each one having a different function .
Absolutely not just fascinating to think of that sort of macro molecular construction participants .
Sounds like anybody , right , because it , I have to have a kind of specificity for one of those as where can go after the troubles and bacteria , but you do not go after everything else .
So headache has specifically , yes , so.
The use of an anybody is is definitely one possible approach .
I'm sure , when hiller begins its research efforts is not actually at that stage yet .
But once it starts , I am , if you look at the scientific literature on this , which you see is that there are actually a variety of that are being pursued in that inclusions at antibodies that also include small molecules or poor small molecule drives , can be very , very specific for a target , includes different kinds of biological or peptide base constructs .
There are many different ways .
One can can address this problem , actually both to develop the head to target the packaging , as well as the head to target the biological system to eliminate the passage .
Both of those require development of very specific groups , and there are variety ways to do that , and actually part of the hill program is to invest in the technology .
How do identify those , what we call leagues ?
How do you identify the best legals ?
What are the best approaches ?
How do you discover them quickly and make sure , like you said , they're specifically so that is actually part of the investment hiller plans to make in developing the technology.
The epidemic will also send it to me , almost like in one agent , you kind of putting together several components about natural music systems .
Do right to anybody might allege onto a passenger particle .
It also is then flagging other cellular parts of the municipal development for the kill .
Where is it seems like you're getting not only your sort of selective identification of a passage in , on this case of microbes , but it is very same particle you've packaged in the killing mechanism .
So it seems almost like a super efficient immune.
Yeah , that I actually went on .
My program .
Manager colleagues made that observation to me .
He said that , oh yeah , so it seems like you're creating an artificial immune system using other biological pathways .
And I think that's a description .
So there are certainly a lot of parallels with this camera approach to the native amusing system .
I think the potential advantage of the approach here is that you can use it to compliment the natural annual system , because you're not necessarily going use the same clearance path with you could use these molecules , help recruit elements of the immune target the packaging .
But again , there are many other passwords that are in signs that would degrade the passage and or an important component of the pathogen , or , as you said , flagged for destruction , which is actually how protects itself works .
So I think , in a sense , we're almost like opening up human biology to see what other processes and human biology can actually , as a type of immune system , if we can honest them.
Okay , when umbrella amazing programs , we have to be learning about themselves .
And I want to talk about one more .
And this one has , and that sounds like to be hard to live up to .
But I love the acquaintance is all spell that you would expect AWEthat stands for atmospheric water extraction .
Now , you know , the availability of fresh water is a big deal , is becoming a bigger and bigger deal .
We had walked with a fresh water if changing weather patterns and roads are making fresh water , a real concern for the future in a world climate change .
So talking about how you imagine the opportunity or program and what you hope to deliver with it to the us .
Bilateral improves as a billion sectors.
The opportunity was the first program I started at darbar , and despite its simple acronym , it was actually one of the more difficult acronyms to come up with , not just because it was my first program , but because I actually am a huge science fiction .
And I was absolutely dead , said on naming the program , something related to taiwan , or lose skywalker or uncle owen , because uncle owen in star wars was the moisture farmers would take out .
So I was very disappointed , but I could not come up with an agreement to fit any of those things , and so ended up with all but the opportunity seeks to take advantage of effect as you mention , what is the scarce resource not only essential to our war fighters , it's essential for humanitarian purposes , and it is literally been the cause of conflict throughout the world .
And so the upper ground would like to produce a device with a relatively low footprint in terms of energy and size and weight that can harvest the naturally occurring moisture that we have in the air all around us , especially leaving here in the washington DCarea , especially in the summer , many of us will complain about how humidity is and a humidity , of course , is a measurement of how much gaseous water there is in the air .
It's a very pure form of water , and it's just sort of sitting there , ready for the taking .
The challenges is , how do you get that water out of the air and energy efficient manner with a small footprint device , so we have ways of capturing water from air ranging from very low energy devices , but that require a very large amount of since called fog nets .
A fog nester used under humanitarian situations , they act almost like a big leaf and capture water , condemning out of the air .
But there are huge installations .
They are not very practical for the department defence , and you can only use them where you have a hundred percent relative humidity , so where you're literally the water is stripping out of the air .
And so that's not always useful .
We are other devices like condensers are the humidity fires that can coolly air such that you can then get the water to liquid fire out of the air , condense out of air .
You can think of this is your home air conditioning unit if you ever run , sort of like a window unit , you'll see the water dripping off of the condensation .
In that case , has been used to call the air , but you can run that device , your air conditioner on a similar way to collect water .
But the issue there is that , as we all know in the summer , especially in place , like the washing in this area , our electric bills go up tremendously when summer hits , because the air conditioning is a very energy intensive process , so that cooling of the air takes a lot of money and makes that kind of water capture likely not useful for the department of defence and not useful for a lot of other , say , humanitarian applications is just too energy intensive in the all program .
We hope to find a happy meal medium of a device that can capture water from the air under a wide range of environmental conditions from very humid conditions to very dry conditions , with a small size , weight and power input in the key to this is two parts .
First is the development of news orbit materials .
So new material that can extract the water from the air efficient , and many of us rescue familiar with these urban materials .
But we need an extraordinary once .
So the everyday familiar example of a zombie is the little silicon package that you might get with a new pair of shoes or a new backpack or piece clothing that little silicon package is designed to absorb water from the air to keep the clothing fresh and not given being damaged by the humidity .
So that material very effectively actually grabs the water from the air .
The challenge was something like silicas is that it doesn't let the water go very easily , take a lot of energy to get the water back out of that material .
And so what we are looking at in odds to the very sophisticated modern materials , next generation that cannot only absorb the water , but then release it under relatively mild conditions , such as that we can make , it advised the harvest water .
So that's the first.
The authorities are questioned or may help make your trigger the release that would have been used from from sort of electrical stimulation .
magnetical .
Meanwhile , the materials actually be stimulated to release it .
There is a number of different possible.
But is there are performers that have just started their work are looking at different options , but it could range from all the above .
You just mention and and others as well .
So you can hit materials , you can potentially do some of the things you mentioned .
You can use a variety of sort of thermal electrical .
Others stimulate to try to get the water back out .
The key is to make sure that the energy required is as as low as possible , right.
You're about to go into the sort of the second big element of the.
right ?
So the second big element is the engineering .
So we do have some new zoo materials that have been described in scientific literature that looks very promising for this , and they have really spectacular water's option and release properties that we can build off of .
But nobody is ever , really , holistically designed the device.
这个时候，我们就可以看到这样的一种情况，在此之前也许会有很多问题。
但是如果我们在这个过程当中有一些问题的时候，guys that maximum employees , these urban materials and the program is divided in the two .
What we call tracks one is called the expansionary , and the other is called the stabilization .
And the expeditionary track is designed to create a device that an individual would carry and would be very small , obviously in size , maybe something the size of the canteen that would harvest water from the air and then fill up that , for example , war fighters , canteen or their camel back or whatever receptacle they have for collecting the water .
So this would be a small device just designed to provide enough water from individual on a daily basis .
And then we have a stabilization approach where this would be a larger device , maybe something on the size of refrigerator , but this will produce a much larger amount of and could supply political drinking water for safety of individuals .
They are one hundred and fifty individuals .
These require very different engineering challenges are present , very different engineering challenges .
And so our performers have to take that under consideration as well , both from the material standpoint and the engineering standpoint , depending on which device they're trying to successfully produce .
But both the next petitionary and stabilization size device could have a number of both commercial and immediately in applications .
We're going to come.
For a learning here , you've been very generous with your time , just couple of quick questions .
Maybe we can be brief here .
One of them is just served trying .
How do you think about your experience and academic team for twenty years and now is the program and a general federal RNDagency , which is to say , darker .
And how would you compare and contrast the role of academic , and you know , agency like that in.
Evolutionary ecosystem , I think they play very different roles in many respects .
First of all , I like both work environments very much , and I have to really say that dark has been as many people told me it would be one of the best places I could ever imagine .
working .
It is a fascinating agency filled with incredibly a smart , motivated people who create a incredibly supportive work environment .
So I am very pleased to an honor to have been part of the arab and continue to be part of the arab .
But I would say that in the role in terms of innovation and the ecosystem , you know , the universities are really sort of the front line , right , so medium in department of defense terms , they are sort of the tip of the sphere .
Right , there are the ones in during the research , you know , with grad students and post dogs and underground and faculty and research staff out there , you know , pushing the boundaries , making the discoveries and and innovating , of course , and coming up with lots of creative ideas are constantly .
I think that the role of dark , as well as you know , other federal agencies that don't have their own research component , like the national science foundation .
We're like dark , but they're just funny research and not performing research themselves .
You know , they are critical part of that industry because that tip of the spear in the elevator is going to happen without federal support and federal funding .
And so a place I doubt not only provides the financial support to allow the research to function and to proceed , but dark , I think , also plays , as well as agencies do a very important point in in pushing those boundaries .
right .
So one thing , having been on both sides of defense here , the academic research and the dark aside , one thing that dark is very well known for is really pushing the boundaries as an academics , historically , you know , sight fatal funding from a variety agencies .
We're often , you can tend to be a little bit more conservative when you are asking for fatal support because you want to make sure that your programs and that the reviewers of your grand believe it's going to work , and that you can show that you don't research along those lines that shows that you are really capable of doing it , and that tends to keep our ambitions in academia .
Sometimes real , temporary , because we have to make sure that we can convince the federal government and these agencies that we can continue to do that work .
And that's a very important function are not knocking it anyway , but there can be a tendency for that , and and people I think , on both sides of the oil go size of the fence , know that .
And so the dark of places are , especially , it is known for being a cutting edge agency .
It's known for pushing the boundaries .
And though our performers are highly qualified and highly skilled individuals , are they done and teams of individuals , they don't necessarily have to assume that they can do this yet .
It is a latest and greatest , and in many ways , can be the most risky as research , and that's an important role in the dark of the fields .
He's pushing that very cutting edge , allowing people to to take chances to try crazy ideas that are still grounded in good science and good concepts , but that might be outside the comfort zone of a lot of other parts of the federal government to find .
And I think that's why you see .
And this has been spoken about for many administrations .
Now , other federal agencies trying to emulate japan .
And I think that's a good thing .
I don't think they should try to emily daughter at the point of their own nonexistence .
I think , you know , funny agencies like the animation and itself in the do e and missed online online .
They play very important roles in the type of research they found in the way they do it , and they have their own emissions that are extremely important , but many of them have taken a nugget of darkness theme and try to incorporate it into the own portfolios .
And that I do think is a good thing .
I probably the most notable examples , arbitrary over the department of energy where they are trying to push , cutting out technology for energy sciences and those applications .
Yeah , I think universities should have tipped the spear certainly idea generating as well , and in dark , a place that sort of super supportive role , and allowing and encouraging those type of researchers to push those boundaries.
Thanks for giving witness a sense of the many parts of the innovation ecosystem where academic fixing were dark with fixing and across the components of the research infrastructures that there was really great .
So now , just before we do close here itself , I wanted to give you an opportunity to bring anything that just didn't come up in the discussion and didn't come about a question I ask like that .
You think there might be interesting films in the snow.
I guess coming from academia , it gives me a different perspective on DARPA and federal service .
Certainly , i'm not the only one of done .
This is many , many , many people before me , but I do think it gives me a perspective that I like to share , and I will share .
two .
Four is darbar and in federal services in general , I think , is a very important and very valuable thing that academic scientists and science from industry , from the private sector , I should consider , we are very , very lucky to live in a country that saw highly values , science , innovation , engineering , and it's valuable , and I think important to take time out of one's own career to be part of medical system on the site and understand how a works .
And you try to make it better .
The other thing I like to highlight is for all those graduate students and post dogs out there .
So it dark bug , just like it at my university job , I am given a small team of ph d level scientists to help support all of these programs that you talk about innocent and healer and all , and they help go through all the technical data .
And how many programs , and they even helped inspire many , many components of these programs , and it's a career opportunity that I think many post dogs and graduate students across the country are probably not aware of , and it is a very , very exciting .
And I think , in reaching korea past to consider .
And so that's the other result of takeaway , but put out there into the either for the grass .
Soon in the post , officer looking at in the weather , next step is.
Great , this was just a really , really fun conversation for me .
We covered a lot , some amazing things when a one program that could bring a new anti viral technologies , another one that could potentially play role in this enormous global concern that antibiotics are becoming less effective , and we can really need new ways of countering bacterial infections .
A program , yanking water out of the air , both for military and civilian users , perhaps down the line .
Or , you know , you talk about the innovation ecosystem .
You did a great recruiting talk at the end here by why one should work , replace like dark , but so I just want to thank you for all of your time , all of you thinking your expertise , thanks for joining me in this Voices from german conversation.
He's been my pleasure .
I went , thanks for having.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dirt .
Thanks also to ban selected for his partnership in producing this program for more information about dark assets called the programs he runs in the agencies , biological technology office and the other breakthrough technologies .