Going to a science or engineering laboratory , close your eyes and listen it a biomedical lab .
You might hear an operation refuge spinning up as a separate the components of sample in a chemical analysis lab .
You might hear the wind of a turban pump as it vacuously the chamber of a mass patronage in a missile proportion research facility .
You might be aggressive , white noise from a test burn of a potential new jet fuel in exciting , you can hear a sonic fingerprint of what goes on there .
Welcome back to sounds of innovation and internal infrastructure of our Voices from dark or podcast .
My name is iphone motel on your dark host , rather than hearing the voices of program managers , which is normally which you get in voices .
Of course , you need a sounds of innovation episode .
You will hear some of the soundscapes of research and development and learn just a little bit about what new capabilities those sounds could lead to in this episode sounds harvested from research efforts under the wings of an fisher , a program manager in the agency's defence sciences office , and stacy williams , who finish her tour of duty as a program manager in the technical technology office at the january .
Let's get right to it with a sound of innovation that stacy sent my way.
Each one of those nothing sounds comes from a laser post .
It's measures into the service of a senior woman and played .
It's just one element of a motivated investigation .
Drop a sponsoring to understand , characterizing , ultimately better defend against lasers using the battlefield .
This is the catalogue captures a few moments of study , which is measuring how laser lights scatters from different media that might be present in a battle situation and improved understanding of such scattering phenomenon should open door to new protective defensive systems that can detect and monitor in real time adversarial use of higher energy lasers .
Either photographic military assets were directly attacking war fighters .
The sound clip comes away from laser scattering .
Field tests conducted by dr richard , president and colleagues with sensing strategy in painting to new jersey .
Now , I would like to treat you to a medley of laboratory sounds , a program manager , and fisher sent to me , given where these sounds are coming from , it would be defensible to say they depict advanced technologies that literally transform our world and elemental levels .
The middle goes on for close to A.
Those were some exhibits of the future of chemistry emerging from the laboratory of league coroner at the university of glass .
His group is working for an official under a research contract with her naked program , as well as her accelerated molecular discovery program .
Together , these programs aimed to expand access to the vast diversity of that could be technological useful , but that we might not know about yet or have yet to figure out how to make efficiently and cheaply to further , these causes .
The chronic group is building digital chemistry .
They call these digital chemical state machines , or , unless finally computers , these combined artificial intelligence of a molecule making algorithms and automated synthesis machinery into systems that by themselves , plan out , execute after my sequences of chemical reactions and procedures to yield valuable new molecules , including drugs for trading , covered nineteenth patients , new and avoided candidates and new pain to name .
But if you , the five computer sounds that , but you heard correspond to a children turning on for a cooling , a chemical reaction to purify a chemical , a digital surround for moving chemicals around the background for the chronic team's computer equipment , occupy fractions , sampler for identifying chemical constituents .
And finally , a mechanical component , it leaves a rotary evaporator or a role of APP and a heating bath into place for concentrating a solution and isolated the products of chemical reaction before final purification .
We will close out this episode with a sound of innovation group .
I saved until last , because it has a bit of that run from the room quality to it .
And I wanted to stay with me to the end .
What you just heard our detections of photos as they had an ultra sensitive obstacle detector in the laboratory of jonathan hobby at the university of southern california 。
These detection events happen on a nano second time scale .
So the USEteam adjusted the sampling frequency of the events to the much slower audio rains so that we can hear them , rather than just see them on laboratory at first , before the researchers turned on their laser , only deemed background letters .
Observe , that's why the detections of photos are spots in the audio texts are low when the researchers fleak on the detection rate skyrocket .
That's when the sound resembles a photographic window scratching across an old vinal record .
The sound comes down again once the lazy returned off , and all that is left is in background .
Hobby's team collects data like this is a developed normal way to detect laser light , even amid statement background , like the first clip you've heard in this sounds of innovation episode .
This last one comes from research overseen by former program manager stacy williams .
She's helping this research will help prepare our world fighters for a future in weapons are ever more present in the battlefield .
There are now a few effective options for detecting , characterizing and locating sources of high energy laser weapons .
Yet that's just kind of technical data , our need to effectively and responsibly to play counter measures .
Thanks for listening to this episode of darkness , sounds of innovation series .
We will be posting more puzzles in the series intermediately as a feature of the Voices from global partners .
Thanks also depends selected for his partnership and producing the program for more information about the programs .