Still of technology , the internet GPS in the palm of your hand are tonight .
Operation technology is a driver of our times .
Since its founding nearly sixty years ago , in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , the defense advanced research projects agency has been a driver of the technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone a motto , and I am your dark post today .
I am pleased to have with me in the studio , gym girl numbers , a program manager since twenty fifteen .
Industrial technology , as we will learn in just a few minutes .
He is among the dark program managers who was oversee programs that fall under the system of systems category , which is to say , very complicated technology frameworks with lots of components and moving parts among the technologies he integrated into unprecedented framework .
Maritime defence include undersea communications on the men , vehicles and systems , maritime power , energy systems or tournament's operation and networking of men and other systems .
Prior to joining double , jim was the director of the advanced technology office at the applied research electoral located a pencil in a state university there , he oversaw a research projects , including our indian solar systems and underestimate power systems for tropical and unmanned vehicles .
Jim earned a bachelor's urine physics from the USneighbourhood academy and then served five years on active duty as a nuclear trained officer in the USnavy following activity .
He joined the neighbor and earned his masters and doctoral degrees , nuclear engineering and plasma physics from the university of washington gym .
globalized .
It's so good to have you in the studio .
It's my pleasure to be here .
Let's start by talking about your background .
You are background physics when you escape academy , and I suggest me that you arrived at the academy with some interests in science and the navy .
So where those interests come from?
Well , I think my interests in the science and engineering really came from a my father .
I was raised in a family that had a lot of engineers , so that was kind of an expected thing .
And and I did pretty well in those subjects , although I didn't really know that man like most students , but I was kind of good at it .
And one thing about the neighborhood made eighty percent of everybody was the engineer nose day , so wasn't a hard.
And I would guess that you're interested in plastic and physics .
That's what you studied in your regular years , which is central to the process of nuclear fusion , somehow emerge from your time serving a nuclear submarine , which relies a nuclear enforced proportion .
I think you said to me one time that you would , you did a lot of boiling of water , but tell me about sort of that that connection you have with position and fusion.
Yeah , well , it was all the interests of mine , just as a garden engineering , the whole world nuclear industry , and using fishermen to make power , of course , being in the navy , the opportunity go on a submarine and and serve was really the attraction .
That's what got meant to it , that the fusion piece actually came about from experience ahead at the last animals in the summer time .
And I have to confess that I did that solely to get out of spending a hot summer and maryland yelling at freshman , I looked for ways to get out of that .
One of the options was to do a research of system .
It blows almost national lab , and I ended up working with the group in a plasma physics , doing fusion work , and the key piece that was just breathy for it was the first time that I was in a laboratory , and we were trying to do something where we did know how it was going to turn out previously that in classrooms and laboratories are those scientists in high .
You were usually just trying to make something work that you knew .
The answer was just , could you make it happen , and it was at last , almost where I finally saw we were doing experiments , and I realized these really bright people , they hope they know it was happening , but the reality was we did experiments to find out , and then we adjusted , and that was very exciting to me was to see this whole really doing research to explore , as opposed to just get something right .
You could get a great on it.
A tester of alabama , poor .
So it was sort of that that excitement about discovery really slowing something you want nature totally.
My , my whole view , and that's what let me choose and do that for grade school , I wanna get out of the navy.
And then after your service and education , you , he went often to the defence industry for a while .
He worked on such things as under water , shark systems directed energy , weapons , counter , rocket armor and laser based instrumentation .
And well , so the fantastic surrounding phenomenon and technologies .
And then you went into a more academic , there's still defence central setting up in state , and then somewhere along the way , you went to sector with dark .
So can you ?
Yeah , that intersection happened actually.
Manufacturing happened when I left grad school , and I joined the small company called vice power technologies in industry , which was the small company where you mention some of those projects and a undersea shark.
Programs for listener rice , who do not know what that mean , what , how would you describe that?
It's by the way , I pad more fun .
One of the anybody should , as far as the kind of range of projects we get to do what we were looking at was the whole idea of , can I create a nursing shock wave , which means basically light , often explosive under water , but do it in a way that we can shape the shock , waste or pile up on top of each other and smash something like a mine .
So we're actually looking at mine clearance , doing that .
And that was an idea that we , we saw the darker as something that they would be interested in seeing if we could make it work .
And that became my introduction to dark.
But so what i'm reading from that , that is that you are , what industry speaks is your performer .
Yes , and performers are those who end up getting research contracts , working on some program .
So you are a performer worker in that particular project .
And then so I presume that my new met other program managers may be enough to director , and that LED to a discussion.
Yeah , we , we actually did a number of programs .
I probably three or four dark pilgrims as a performer during those years .
Then when I transition to the applied research lab , it can stay we , we picked up a couple of more .
So I had a had an ongoing relationship , actually , through multiple organizations of being a performer , doing dark programs , and exactly as you described as actually a former PM.
And at the time that video office structure climb light , can you point me aside and wanted to see , hey , what i'd be interested in , according to the site of the table and conceiving ideas and being a program.
Okay , and you quite evidently did come over here .
If I just go into your program manager page on the website , and or if I am talking more directly , I learned that you have three programs on your wing .
Now , two of them , the blue wealth program and hunter programming both have to do with on men under water systems .
And there is one very multiple program .
It's the cross domain and maritime surveillance and targeting program were known , in short , as city mass , and that's really a program which there was an unexpected systems of systems idea , of course , which the other two programs kind of feeding too is kind of component systems of the systems of systems .
So maybe we can talk about city masks and the whole idea of systems of systems , which really is a theme throughout durable .
You see , that kind of category is defining many programme's wealthy , the six technical offices .
So tell me what you think of with.
This concept of an absolutely an , exactly , in fact , and this is what kind of need about darker .
This is what IItalked to kind about the shoes talking about bringing me and was to look at .
We have this initiative to do system systems .
We want to look at american version .
Would you do that ?
Well , first , you had to understand what we mean by system of systems , and it's really this idea that as our defence has matured over the last few decades , and we make more more capable platforms , and a good example would be saying airplane or a submarine .
These are becoming very sophisticated .
Platforms are very capable , but they also expensive .
They also take a long time to make , and what we're finding is to make them even better , cost a lot of money and time .
And you don't necessarily get that much more capability than you .
If you wear it is kind of creating like an awesome top , is you put more effort into it .
It's getting increasingly.
And nobody seems to be a limited , yeah , just how much.
How much employee , yeah , that is tipping over .
And and so the whole idea that is , is there a better way to look at things to say , if I really want to do what dark is supposed to do , which is major capability gains and big strides .
Is there a different way to look at things , and one of the ideas is what ?
How about if we distribute some of the functions that are on this platform ?
So if you think about a platform , what is it ?
It has the sense.
It has to defend itself and by platform you might.
I entered an aircraft , yeah , aircraft to a submarine exactly the .
So it has this function that needs to sense .
It needs to communicate , it needs to defend itself .
It needs to do data process , I think .
And if I put that , all there is great , I concentrated .
But now , as I said , it is incremental gains .
And at each time I make a change of the facility of the stuff.
What if I.
Do a term we call what we disagree that I take these functions , say the sense in function .
And I put it on a lower class platform , say , like an unmanned system that I can put farther away .
So now I get even greater dancing , because instead of being stuck on my platform , it's now far away , and in broader , and maybe I move forward , even open the earth of the nearest exactly , so I get high advantages .
The key pieces is I still have .
I have to be able to communicate , but if I can do that and handle the networking part to make all these things worked together .
Well , now I really covers in my adversary , a difficulty , instead of doing what they are doing now , which is boring , lots of money , and to be able to go after these single platforms that are high value .
Now they have to decide g do I go after the sensor thing ?
Well , I get that .
What's those two others are three more ?
Okay , you got a little bit of my sensing , but I am still going .
And oh , by the way , the main aircraft or ship is still going , and so it forces them to now spread their forces to cover more .
thanks .
And this whole idea is , I try to do this in a way that my total class is less than what I would for just a single platform , but my capability is much increased , and the problems I cause for the other side are much greater than.
It sounds to me that it also adds two things like versatility and resilience of the versatility .
Now you can mix and match all kinds of different things until these systems of systems at the same time of one , it thinks , taken out of the other .
You still have this resilience .
We are , you're not thinking of shape , you're making so easy.
No , you've written because that whole idea of an all talk about it is a adaptability .
Maybe I want to change my mix in real time , which means , hey , we know what the mission is , and we need some better .
Let's say , jamming capability or something I can put that in the mix , much easier than I can change it out on the whole platform .
We kind of get what you get .
One else is an interchangeable parts , and you hit it on the head with resilience and see it means they have more things to deal with .
And so if they take care of one or two of them , and we like to use the term , we degrade gracefully , as opposed to either , are more .
I am done .
And the other way , it's adaptable is over time , in the sense of hey technologies changing .
That's one of the biggest factors for , yes , we see it in our commercial world all the time , and new iphones are coming out .
New capabilities hit of filming a movie .
I do all I want my military systems to be able to adapt on those time scales , as opposed to it's gonna , be five years before we can build the next airplane if I more disagreed and disagreed and disagree , it is easier to change those parts out .
So both over long scale.
This is another theme i've been hearing about your job in other places .
The technology cycles are just speeding up so much .
And so there is this interest in more editorial in turning that cycle faster without the huge amount of expense in the matter time it has taken the past to do that .
They go from version one to two , to three to four .
I guess this is in the maritime domain.
And absolutely , it affects all the domains .
And one of the issues there is your heroes used to turn .
And one of the challenges with compatibility .
How can I get better and quickly pulling these things in and making them so that they go to it together easily , and I don't have to do lots and lots of engineering and test steam to put these two things together .
And that part of the system system challenges is getting good at being able to rapidly compose and policy.
Systems together , okay , so for some reason , as you were talking about this aggregation , I was thinking about a human body , which is a system of systems that got eyes that the system of get a liver .
That's sure that this system of cells , and if that would disagree with it , actually , we and it will still be a living body with them .
The , it was an amazing task of command and communication and integration .
Kind of aware metaphor , perhaps , but it seems to protect yourself if you taking apart what has been an integral system like carrier , and you know , this , aggregating this into all kinds of pieces , what about that integration ?
And that sounds like a hard problem , it.
Absolutely and and you've done two things .
And I like the body example , because the easiest thing to think about in our eyes , or a primary sensor , and I know how much better could you survive if you had to set the eyes that were yellow fifty yards in front of you , and you had an extra nose that you could put out over trying to do it .
But now you've hit on the head is , well , it works good my body , because those nerve endings you'd only have to go from my brain down to my nose or my eyes .
That's not too far .
Now I put it there .
So we put the prayer on being able to set up effective communication passed that are reliable , because otherwise , what good is that knows that she should sit mouth there that could smell everything .
But if you can get it back to the brain , it's of no value .
And so you've tied in when we talk about these system of systems programs , sometimes people ask , well , you are really developing a lot of new technology .
You kind using existing stuff .
And exactly right , the dark , but hard part , the challenges , yeah , but i've got to do this now and make these reliable communications and networking and functions .
He knew , now i've got instead of two eyes , i've got four , what i've got to have a brain now that can handle that .
Which means how do I sequence things and do things because i'm getting more information .
It's a good analogy to see what we're trying to do with the system of systems from a military stamp , right?
And again , when you talking about dark but hard , we are talking about systems and systems .
When you are entertaining , very ambitious ideas like this , more than entertaining , actually trying to make them .
So what also then comes in here are issues that of communications , security .
And you know what I might want to try to spoof the system .
I might want to try to generate .
And so suddenly these kinds of considerations become part of your above thinking.
Oh , absolutely , becomes a huge deal .
I can't afford to have somebody call up .
You know , my forward eyeballs and turned them to look at the wrong direction to me .
And so it's a good example of technology .
We're taking advantage of things .
But after then , look at what's the counter move and and do this straight off .
And and by the way , this is why we were doing .
This is dark , but it's not a hundred percent certain that this is the way to fight the future .
It's our high politics , and there's a lot of evidence suggests , if you can do it , it's a great way , but that's a big year , and that's why we're doing the research .
So can we really make this work and be secure and reliable , and all these things that happen and.
Right , so you really probably what is possible .
And in , and if it is possible , even if it is desirable in the end , right when you do get together with other program managers here , other other professions here at the top to talk about systems of systems .
Who are you talking with , what are , what are some of the other ways ?
I guess programs that you think of when the systems of systems , categories on your mind.
Yeah , and it is funny .
There's kind of two versions that I do .
So when I talk to other , when I true systems of systems PMand others program managers were doing other systems systems program , you know , in the defence science is office .
John passed with .
He is really looking at .
Hey , can I come up with mathematical constructive to help me do that composition instead of a state of , hey , I think this looks good .
Let's try it now , let's go from there .
So we talk about what about , hey , how can I have machine learning ?
An intelligence helped me pull the stuff together , and interestingly , we almost always end logistics , because one of the issues is , now , i've got more things spread over part .
How do I get on there , and how do I sustain them ?
You know , the body works while the eyebrows come with the head , and it's a nice pack like it .
Now i've got these two extra boards out there .
Who's going to hold on the doors and keep them care and fed it saturday , the other way , though , that I talk to PMabout programs is , how is there particular technology ?
So maybe they're making a better unmanned aircraft , or a better sooner .
Where does that fit?
Under the system of systems where those systems feature.
Where do they fit in ?
And that's where we've had really fun dialogue because of the next one of the big problems for somebody can come up with a great idea for a better sonar .
And I work on that now developed it.
But danny kind ends up.
Porch of the panic on with I will this great sonar , but where do I put it in ?
How should I employ it and enjoy by ten of them , or do you know what I do ?
You know what's interesting in system and systems you started to think about the whole , and it helps guide some things to say , you know what we really need .
That song is be able to look wider , not necessarily farther or different things that might help direct their work .
But at the same time , we're giving them a great story to say a husband fits in .
And my gosh does.
Make a difference , right ?
Such an interesting thing that I elected .
You're putting out potential technologies capabilities , but then you're getting back information from the field where the commanders and work hard , who are exactly giving you feedback and say , you know , this is what we really need is this is what we've experienced in an dynamic .
You come up with something that really does .
Further reino national security.
Absolutely , in what's unique in this program that i've done , that , i've never done in my research career .
We actually spend a lot of time working with the navy and organizations to create a very sophisticated war fighting scenario , very realistic , based on the , except for more to guide our research .
And that's not normally done .
We usually kind of think k or look at an engagement in this would help me defeat this aircraft if they came against me .
Very rare to look at in terms of , hey , what would I do to win the war ?
And that's the phrase we like to use .
Hey , this is great .
That's a nice technology , but doesn't help me win , and that's not usually question that we ask , you know , we usually just say , doesn't make me faster.
Stronger , better yet , so as you bring in some languages in here , like , like music with the work .
There's , there's another phrase I heard roundup , but I think it must relate to this next music or fair had that relate to systems of systems .
yeah.
Music welfare is , in some sense , it is a different name for a system system .
Certainly this system fits into it , but it's this whole idea of the ear of bringing lots of pieces together , and no individual piece does everything tells the story , but collectively get the picture .
And what's interesting is , you can afford to lose a few pieces , and you still get the picture .
And that's this idea of being able to compose to make your music , tell a different message on our case , do a different function for the military and be able to put that together , make it , do that , rearrange the pieces , but does something different .
Tell the different story , so to speak , and it can withstand the fact that , like I said , if a few pieces get knocked out , you're not done .
So it's really that the same idea .
But when I liked with the music is when you talk about this , the imagery of here , I can rearrange these two different stories to me .
That means I can recompose a new , different mission.
Right now , in a sense , that's been going on for a long time , but we have different military services that are different capabilities .
They work in a kind of different domains .
And so you can almost think from a generalized point of view there , there has been this kind of music thinking , but here will also bring that down more on the technology levels.
Absolutely , and there is a little bit , you know , nothing is new , but we're trying to take it to a greater limit .
And one of the biggest differences there is , is , were really trying to bring in I men systems with man's systems and and game , create this much more rapid , adaptive , because yes , things have changed , but usually it would take decades to say , oh , organized this way differently .
And among the user , this kindness system differently in and in many years , it will come out and we'll put it together .
And so you get very aesthetic kind in how you operate .
This is to be much more fluid .
So if you write its an extension , but really trying to take it to that lemon.
I said that you have had experience and academic .
I was more violent on the sudden side .
Thanks , you've had industry experience .
You're networking in the government setting , in particular , darker , some , just wondering how you view double and weight in the overall innovation ecosystem .
Where , where does it fit?
Yeah , we have the services that have more traditional hay .
We've got these products , and we need to get better .
So what do kind of product improvement if you will , as opposed to dark is , hey , i'm gonna create a whole new virus product in terms of a whole new capability .
And so it's the defense department , and really , that's the way we operate fairly quick .
We pull ideas together .
You then have an opportunity to make your case .
You need to baby , do a small project to get some data to tobacco position , but then you go forward and you meet with the tech council , and in a very short time , you'll get an answer that says , yes , let's go forward .
And now you are after the races to really make.
By tech council , you're referring to what I understand here for program managers , or sometimes rehiring experiences where you have to go in front of leadership and really make the case for why the research is worthy , why it could have benefit to tax players and national security .
And I think one other thing I was here when you use this VCeventual camp .
Local analogy is that there , also , I think , is unusual willingness , even expectation that there will be failure along the way .
Because if you are going to really move forward , not just incrementally , but in big steps , maybe you even leaps that you , you are going to fill one way onto his extraordinary , absolutely.
Just like as a venture capitalist , if you show up and say , hey , i've got a way to get to ten percent on your mind .
They're not interested .
They can go to the banker somewhere and get that what they want to see is , how do I tend for my money ?
Same idea with dark , but when you're doing things like that , if it was that easy , everybody be doing it so that you have to be taking risk , you have to be pushing for things that you don't haven't been done .
And you know , a hundred percent of taking amy.
Okay , also , we're getting toward the end of our time here , but for some reason , feeling little mean .
and so a german wouldn't ask you , since we just been talking about the value of failure , if you've got to feel your story to share with 我要。
Turns out I probably have several , but user one , because it exists back to an old , dark project that this was when we were imagined earlier on the shock process .
We had a billion apparatus with a lot of , if you will think of it as a bunch of little cans , and or maybe sixteen of them all on a big rack that we loaded into the , and any idea was we would shoot this often and try to do the timing right to make a shock wave .
And we loaded in the water , and we hit the button , and we got the first shot , and we thought that was , and I speak bubble in water , and then we hit the thing again .
Well , we did not have a sunny singing another time after a few times , we finally decided that it's not working and swiss to get it to bring the crane up .
He pulled it up there .
I think maybe one wire still dangling from the end of it , and we had bonuses and complete the smell of rings .
And I think it took divers about two weeks to go find all the parts that we sprung all over the bottom of this query that we were testing .
And that was not a completely typical day of.
How can I go sometimes ?
Okay , but you learn some lesson .
We did .
We changed the way we ran up for sure , thereby was a kind of just another day in technology directly .
So jimmy , it's been a pleasure to spoken with you here for at least half hour .
So I learned a lot , and I know that our listeners have as well .
So thanks for sharing this time with.
My pleasure and really enjoy this , thanks a lot.
And thank you .
Listeners also for joining us .