Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand on tonight's operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , DARPA , that offends advance research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone , the motto , and I am your dark host .
And today I am pleased to have with me in the studio .
Wen zim , alert , a program manager in tactical technology , where , since twenty fourteen , she has been running the intriguingly named space surveillance telescope .
Where SSTprogram welcomes the two Voices from japan.
Thank you so much for having me .
I am really excited to be here.
Well , i'm excited to have you .
And before we dive in and talk about the space surveillance telescope , which packs some really amazing technology that i'm eager to hear about .
Let's talk a little bit about you .
Um , what I like knows something about your background , how you became a program manager at the.
Sure , so a while ago actually started as a photography major at the university , michigan , which you might think is a little bit odd .
Start for a scientist .
I was always inspired by the images .
I would see you in a strongly magazine .
And at that time , I thought all that means that should be a photographic major .
But after learning a little bit more my time there , I dropped it over to our space engineering .
I got my undergraduate degree in our space engineering there and a masters as well .
And I went on to produce where it is some graduate work that enabled an assumption called the treasury planet finder , which was a new design for a space , total scope .
After that , I had some marketed in policy and actually met a fellow program manager here double , who introduced me to the how double works and the double programs .
And I was really exciting to me , and that's how I ended up a double.
And before we do really talk about the advanced technologies that come together into this tour , the space surveillance .
Maybe you can talk with a little bit about the problem that really backed in the screen for something like an SST.
And when i'm referring to hears is the kind of landless abbott like a human made in cosmos made debris .
So magazines really the beginning , the species.
Yeah , absolutely , a minor .
A user space is becoming increasingly critical to daily .
I think a lot of people don't know when the space is even involved really anymore .
And in order to do that , we are launching increasing numbers of minimum attacks in the space .
There are tens of thousands of these objects in space right now .
And so we have to be very careful that they don't come near each other and sometimes even collide with each other .
And on top of that , we also have debris in space , some from man made objects , but also just natural objects , but also SSTis really focused on tracking and identifying debris and objects in orbit called geo geo synchronized orbit .
That's about twenty two thousand miles about the earth .
So really far away .
Where did I?
From leo rights , which is low authority , that was a lot of satellites .
well.
That's absolutely right .
Leos much closer .
So it's a little easier to see objects there .
Jill has a volume of tens of thousands of oceans .
So not only is it far away , it's gigantic .
And so building a telescope that can handle both of those challenges since it's very far away over a very wide area .
Yeah , I is really what our sister is best.
Okay , I love that kind of image just gave us with with all of these oceans above the same .
You need to be worked out and monitored .
So that sounds to me like , like , you need some oil technology .
And maybe this is a good time for you to talk those , those really advanced , unique technologies that you helped naturally come together into this remarkable.
Yeah , absolutely , so you think about a digital camera that you have home when you use your zoom lens , you see the field of view on your camera , narrow in on the thing that you're looking at it as you get closer .
And that is how a traditional telescope works as you change the design that the field of with SST, we actually had a unique optical design where we use a curved focal plane .
So gone , thinking about your digital camera , there is a small focal plane , focal plant in your camera .
Call the CCD.
That stands for charge .
Couple devices are very cool .
The most of us know is just the academic.
Thank you .
Well , the weather system teams are very , very widespread of view , but still relatively very high resolution is actually , instead of having a flat CCD, Aflat focal plane , it is curved , and SSThad the first working curve to focus design.
That we know over the world , and what was so special about the curved form embrace is a flat one.
So the curve format allows you to actually focus the light a little bit better towards the edges of the CCDitself is also very , very challenging to build .
In fact , I am a telling concludes who built the focal plane has to come up with the , the new process .
I am able to to enable that character.
Over the over the plane , right and philosophy might not know the legal legs are really fascinating place with AAhistory that goes back really to world war two with a task at that time to work on what really was some of the original weight or technology , and it's been really involved in updates , among other things ever ever since .
Those are really interesting in partner , and in this case , what are some of the other technologies that have been really tough , dark , dark awards , the tiger , tiger.
The the processing power of this total scope is quite impressive , and the speedy , which it can scand over the sky .
And so we can actually view objects over one quarter of the entire jail belt over , you can imagine that is one quarter of each night from new mexico , and that is just an incredibly fast drive train on the telescope and requires incredibly fast processing .
And those are two things that that we also developed under the assets to program.
When I was called the standing volume to be thinking about this in the field of view of this instrument and anything , a kind of an amazing portrait writers is that the white sense mister ranges in mexico , which triggered smooth people there know is wismar , but it is on top of a fantastic way .
The name played a pig called adam peak .
Maybe you've been there , so maybe you can just sort of paint as a little bit of a picture .
What is like to buy the telescope ?
And why are you doing that describe the telescope?
Sure , so the autumn peak itself is very high and very dry in a very dark location .
So you can stand up on the peak and actually see the sunset out over the range , which is beautiful , and you are also looking right over a site called trinity sites .
Trinity sites is actually where the united states exploded its first atomic weapon , which is kind of interesting to be standing on the egypt of two areas where technology was after sunset against incredibly dark .
You can actually see the edge of the galaxy when you're standing up there , and after night fall , we can walk inside the telescope down .
The facility itself looks like a very flat square building with a giant dome on one side , and you get inside that dome , which is elevated even higher above autumn peak .
And then we'll open up the door for of the telescope dome .
And almost every time I bend there , the wind is just blowing , and it's freezing cold , but everyone to stand up down because it just so need to see the stars in the toll scope , moving the toll scott movement itself is completely silent as they're just sitting there looking at the stars next to the instrument .
And it was.
Give people a sense of the scale of it , and how fast is moving , because when you say this instrument is silent , and I think about how biggest is and how fast is moving .
It's almost impossible for me to think about it , right?
So the telescope is offered several towns , and it's sitting on the top of many different gambles .
And what is doing is the shape of the opening in the domestic return .
And so it starts at the top .
And the telescope movement is going open down and both open down in the vertical and also crossing the horizontal motion .
And again , it can serve the entire sky , so one hundred and eighty degrees of down the dome in one single nights .
Again , that , you know , volumes and volumes of ocean A.
Quarter , about in one night , right ?
And so , so it literally is moving from one spot , taking a snap shot , moving to another , taking a snap shot .
I, Iheard that there are some thousands of horse power worth of hydraulic piston and other moving elements that that actually can bring it from one spot to the , to the next .
And yet the sound is something like when I heard this , maybe you can correct it , or you another matter about as loud as a microwave of.
I think that's right .
The only thing you can hear is the clicking of the shutter on the camera itself.
Over the half of a microwave open right .
And then so when the shoulder is open , and it's gathering the slide on on that through curved optical element that you talk to battle can look at such a huge volume of space all at once .
The late itself that is going on to , as I think you might have seen essential like that in our cell phones .
Can you talk a little bit?
Yeah , so i'll start with them as the appetizers open the light actually comes in and and hit several different measures .
Similar sense .
Mates article train , and it's about three point six meter mirror , so that gives you an idea of a sort of helping the hotel school visit itself at several meters larger than that .
And so the labour comment in bonds through that that mirror and actually be focused , that occurred focal plane , where , you know , the late hits the materials in the focal plane , and that turns them into an electrical signal , which is an transferred into what we would think of his pixels based on the strength of the electrical signal year at the scene of brighter or a finger pixel .
The longer the telescope is open and looking at a specific place in the sky , the center of the object you might be able to see , just like if you were doing it at home with your digital camera.
Okay , so now i'm imagining the camera is sharing out to jail synchronism altitudes rapidly .
What twenty two thousand ahead there .
And it's picking out perhaps thousands at one time , thousands of even software sized objects that right?
Yeah , that's about right .
Maybe the size of what he bought.
And if we focused on one of those objects , you wait with the whisky bottles , you just in the mountain .
If you really are whisky bottle whirling around in orbit.
One can only guess , right ?
We have add astronauts of.
So let's assume it's not a whisky bottle , but some other kind of debris .
How many pixels with that single object occupy , and the sensor of.
The SSTshirts will be very few , so assets can not actually take what we would think of as an image of something in gear .
What , as I see , does this really see dozen streets ?
So it is not resolved the military of an object in jail , but really an indication of where that object is.
And how it's moving .
Okay , that's really all important when you really want another trajectory , because then you can map that trajectory until the trajectories of all the theme satellites that are out there , whether it's for deal , deal or other analysts , so calculate where there might be an unwanted to intersection of the strategic rate.
Yes , that's absolutely right .
And I also add battle primary user , the toast group , bring out , actually NASA , we partner with NASA to try to identify in catalogue new near earth objects , and as it sees , actually prolific at this , at finding what we call these news , primarily , astronauts are what we're looking at.
Right , right ?
So , so that has been sold in the test out phase in his earlier ten years .
In a way , it has first light in twenty eleven .
If I call my reading is that when it first went on top of item peak , or was that somewhere else ?
No , that was an atomic .
Okay , so since then , can you give the sense of the catalog observations that the associates made?
Since then , I will , we worked , like I mentioned with NASA to look at objects near the objects , astronauts and comets .
We've also takes some images of nebula and supernova , also for a partner's analysis .
I worked very closely with the united states air force for the air force .
We are observing very thing , objects in geosynchronous orbit and providing them information on , and that could be anything from a piece of debris to to a small satellite .
We also work quite a bit on developing what we call the brain models .
So new telescope is strong enough to see every piece of debris in space .
And so what we do is we make estimates about where that debris might be based on what we know .
So SSTcan see many more objects and other telescopes .
And so we've been using our measurements to help develop models for what we think the reality of of the debris of.
Okay , that you mentioned many more telescopes that make me think of the larger context here , which is the , the largest of the space of violence .
And that were.
Sure , so the united states air force operates .
We recognize the assessment .
Everything has to have an agreement , the space network , and there are several different types of optical and radar sensors in that network , as it sees currently , not one of those sensors , even though we do provide data on an attacked basis to the air force , but very shortly , it is going to become one of the sensors in that network , as it is going to be transitioning over to air force use actually very soon .
On october eighteenth of this year.
That is an important kind of a successful drop .
But when we think about , we're trying to do here is in developed technologies to further the cost of we really do what the sort of transition ultimately to happen .
We do a lot of high risk kinds of technology development .
So the transition doesn't always have the material case where it is .
So can you talk to me about this ?
But on hand of right , and where we are now so that we can make the hands off to the your force , and then perhaps also take us for to the sequence of events that will be able to , oh , oh , with the next few years.
Sure , so I mentioned ASSThad first late in twenty eleven .
I was a demonstration system that we developed.
But I am just going to rub the case for those who don't know first letters , just as a wonderfully term in the telescope community , which really refers to that moment when all of the conception is over in the development in the building .
And you finally know , open up with this wonderful instrument to to observation , and you desperately want to see what that first observation is that often referred to his first lights .
So sorry to interpret that was that in february of twenty eleven , first life , respect.
Yes , thank you .
So at that time , it was a demonstration system .
And here are double .
We try to really push beyond the state of the art in a revolutionary technology .
And sometimes you always don't , you don't always get a perfect the first time .
And so it is the camera that we had in there in two thousand and eleven , we realized that there were some improvements that could be made .
And so over the past year , so we've been developing a replacement camera for the wounded exist there today .
So we're installing , we finished the installation of that new camera and had a game first lights on august this year .
We are currently demonstrated the improve , improve capability of assets .
He once that demonstration is done , and we really , really certain that the technology is complete , and we are just really excited to give this to the user force .
It represents an order of magnitude , increasing capability from what they are able to see now with their existing optical sensors .
And so we are very excited to to be able to give them that capability and have that actually run into operational.
Right , so the air force will officially take stewardship of assets , tea and the official ceremony that would be happening up on item in a new mexico .
What can happen?
After that , I , after that , we are actually going to be , we've been united states going to be moving the telescope to australia .
We have software around the planet .
Yes , not an easy task for a very large telescope .
And twenty thirteen , the secretary of defense and also the minister defensive australia , signed an agreement to actually move the top scope from white sands , massachusetts , to hear the whole naval area in western australia .
And so once we complete , the technology demonstrated and transition into the air force , the air force is going to continue to work with our australian partners to physically move over the western australia that will be happening over the next , maybe two years.
And that that sounds like an enormous project , probably worth its own engineering story .
So why take the great pains to move this telescope and.
I have a healthy adult way .
I completely agree .
The movement is potentially a dark problem in itself .
The reason to do it is because that is a part of the world .
They were very interested in observing what's going on up in geosynchronous orbits .
We have a lot of very important settlements in that area to communication , and also , it represents a great partnership with the australian allies .
It's really those two reasons why we want to move it.
We've covered a fair amount for the time we have about the space .
A surveillance health group is a question that you really wish I would have asked here that I did not .
And if so , you get to ask them as well.
Well , maybe not a question , but I have a statements .
Um , my whole life I have been interested in .
So looking beyond , we know what we can really see , and I think it's inspired , trying to work on an instrument that lets us see other galaxies .
It makes it so real .
In a way , it's one thing to look so about a picture in a magazine , and and it's another to be working with an instrument that can actually imagine napoleon and a supernova suffering me .
Working on the program has , has been inspiring , not only from a science perspective , but also because we could contribute to you to our important mission for their fourth.
When is your editor plays darker , which is kind of all about reimagining what is possible and actually taking steps to change what to take , what my previously been considered impossible , making it possible .
So in a way is the place it's trying to make science fiction on fiction .
I am just wondering if you have some water now , fictional technologies in mind that you think what to be real.
So I have a couple .
One is the universal translator .
I think it might be on the the star track series .
Uh , that is the technology of perhaps a superpower that I absolutely wish that we had .
I think the other one is to travel beyond the stars , perhaps that that one you could guess it's not not for me to just look .
I wish we could go there .
and.
That's a good place to end .
I think so lonely .
I just want to thank you for this a great conversation .
Thank you very much .
Gradually here , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dirt .