Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on tournament.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research projects agency has been a driver of welcome to Voices from dark a window on the people behind darker signature mission to redefine what possible my name is iphone a motto , one of your doorpost .
Today's podcast will be a little different from most of the others .
You hear the voices program managers , as you usually do .
But this episode will feature the senior district efforts of several programs that are opening a path way to what I am calling science .
I am referring here to a turbo charged scientific enterprise that could accelerate the pace of scientific discovery and the development of technologies , knowledge and evidence based decision making and policy and other capabilities based on this new knowledge , perhaps heroic catalogue director of SONY computer sciences laboratories , articulated this notion most clearly and boldly .
He suggested the research community should take on a grand to develop artificial intelligence systems that by twenty fifty will be making nobel caliber scientific discoveries .
Scientists have been the primary engine of civilizations advance could have said , so AI tools that can accelerate scientific discovery in general could exert enormous leverage on many friends , important to anticipating the future cut on a rope in twenty sixteen to give a favourite robot he has in mind NIsystems that will make a succession of discoveries that have immediate medical implications , saving millions of lives and told changing the fate , the human race , just a note before proceeding .
I recorded conversations with dark , appropriate managers joshua elliott , jiang , jiang jiabao from our respective home .
So we all could do our parts to slow the spread of coffee .
That's why you may hear some ambient household sounds like trucks and birds , even circuits .
I wanted to start with judge with allied a program manager since twenty seventeen in the agencies , information innovation office , which has a long history in a research , joshua credits researchers evolving reliance on powerful computational tools and the creation and analysis of vast databases with accelerating the pace of science of discovery .
He says the human machine alliance has gotten as closer to a vision of an early and now famous daughter , program manager jessie are legal letter who is credited with formulating the nineteen sixties , are lasting in guiding for how computers and human beings can become teammates in the quest for knowledge and to become more powerful and capable actors in the world.
I guess I would argue that human machine symbols in science that has been that the primary driver is , how do we enable scientists through competition to be data through these things , actually discover more and bigger things faster .
Of course , we've already seen human machines and buses dramatically improved in accelerate science over the last fifty years , but I think there's still a lot more to go .
And that without the modern generation of the , I think that , you know , we can really take that to the the next level of the third of of the legal letter concept , the human emissions in the oceans.
Judge was a program manager colleague ryan jail of the agency's defence scientist office is doing what she can to hate in the day when these symbolizes typified away science is done , consider her artificial intelligence research associate program , or era for short .
We are talking here of developing an AI and artificial intelligence .
It is competent enough to serve as a genuine scientific collaborator with a human scientist , such a human machine team would be a cornerstone of the science .
To when I asked jessie as jane .
And jail is most often about colleagues about that .
I like the way she.
Is it possible for us to develop air technologies that the court , by analyzing scientific data to figure out the fundamental governing laws of the nature ?
So an example , yeah , so everybody probably remember that the newton , you know , by a sitting down under the tree watching the apple falling on the ground , he eventually figured out the law of gravity .
And so the question is that it is possible for the EItechnologies to be developed to the point that they could also have this level of abstraction capabilities .
So the airport is that a reservation to ask , what are the fundamental components that are needed in for the item orders to achieve this kind of scientific discovery?
But jessie , like SONY researcher hero lucky catalogue , is not just talking about artificial intelligence that just week of petroleum by scientifically in client.
This researcher from japan , kazakhstan .
Also , he asked these questions that can the air technology is to be developed , such that the healthy quality of the human science , scientific discovery is worthy of nobel prices , while so that we are talking about new discoveries and new insights of nature.
For her part , inspiring the research community to develop AItools that might perform like artificial scientists as killed the best human scientists .
Jesse error program has two primary objects .
One is to make machine learning a current main state of air .
I underlined such things as speech and immediate recognition , capable of discerning patterns in data with output line on human beings , providing training sets of data .
This is essentially like showing a child , a bunch of individual a chicken , and then telling the computer to then go out and look at every animal picture on the internet .
It labels the ones that are of.
But in the realm of scientific discovery , you typically do not this kind of training examples to teach the system to uncover the parents .
So the question is that the can we develop a technology so that it can explode unknowns on its own and be able to abstract the principles that underlined data and patterns .
The second , and I think it's a harder challenge that it was trying to address is for the aisle to know when it does.
This could not be more important .
Human scientists are always wearing their measurements and observations , their data in the context of hypothesis .
One of the paralysis , the same datasets can currently consistently with multiple .
We're mathematical statements that can look like laws of nature , and yet are wrong , have no foundation reality or even absurd .
It can happen to the best of them when caprica first argued in the sixteenth century , that was the earth that was in the sand enough the other way around , he managed to preserve effectively false future of the then accepted , tolerant economic system that had the plan is following perfectly circular orbits , as specified by a residential area .
This LED to a defence of oddly complicated planetary emotions in which planets are sometimes took up and small , perfectly circular episodes along the overall to account for the actual observations of planet appearing in the sky to sometimes backtrack .
Let's hear jazz explain how AIscientist most likely would fail to see in the astronomical data before the digitalized , the political passwords that your honest capital was able to determine in the early.
We actually had a demonstration of the tendency for the aisle to trying to explain on the phenomenons worse explanations that are perfectly able to explain the observations at hand , but it's incorrect .
So , for example , that done I mentioned in the air program , one of the examples that the making scientific garrett is to discover the law of planned motion , the capitalist laws .
And now one of the performers actually run experiments , and they talk to a person data , turn observation data and add noise to the data of global noise and a round the air system and ask yourself to find equations .
And because the noise , the assistance discovered very complex equations that nothing to do with the loss of the planned movement , but actually , is a benefit of it.
Then the original me , given the data plus the noise , it made sense of that artificial data , said , exactly helping AIscientist do not make such errors by deriving mathematically sound models that fit the date of beautiful while being factory , meaningless , irrelevant or worse , misleading weighs heavily on the mind of joshua .
Earlier , his program , known as asking which is short for automatic scientific knowledge , is by trying to ensure that the model scientists devise about how the world works with managers and commanders rely on for making decisions , actually resigned and sound causally back .
Foundations were , in short , that the foundations for claiming knowledge and taking actions make sense.
The globalization is is really to digging to these black box models that that the scientists used operationalize their knowledge .
There are good leverages for decision support and to develop tools that enabled us to actually do what I call machine assisted cure , ration and modeling and machine assisted insights , so enable to both abstract an extremely knowledge into models , carried those models with AIassistance .
And then also been able to extract inside from those models in rigorous ways using various air approaches and.
Within the dark in do d contexts , joshua is hoping to improve the decision making , a process based on experience , as well as on theories about how people behave and how conflicts unfold .
But right now , he can't help the imagine how his programs could deliver new term capabilities to help accelerate solutions to even the most pleasant global scale threat , the covered nineteen pandemic , the.
And really , there has never been a more obvious and clear need for technologies like this in a biochemical source of human and viral biology .
Tens of thousands of publications that are relevant with hundreds , and maybe now accused of thousands to count preference of new publications with new information as relevant to the story coming out every single day .
And it's just impossible for folks at that in the case of cobbling eighteen , you're trying to extract catholic associations between proteins and between genes and between small molecules that may be drug candidates , for instance , and how those things interrupt at the biochemical , mechanical , mechanistic level so that you can compile that extracted knowledge or model fragments , in some sense , each of those fragments , a sort of a model in itself .
And you want to be able to compile that over , you know , kinds .
Hundreds of thousands of documents , you know , millions , potentially of pieces of knowledge , fragments compile that into a large scale model that you can actually start doing complex foreign simulation and inference.
In some ways , joshua saying it's the sheer size of scientific enterprise and its current productivity that can be a drag on scientific discovery , and something like a complex waves , viruses .
In fact , sales and cost pandemics , they're just too many scientific pixels for anyone .
Human mind was on its own without the assistance of something like AIassistance .
The judge was asking the researchers working on some of his programs to develop the job.
You may have this entire complex cell signaling pathway that actually answers bright questions about complex diseases , but it might be spread out .
The information from it might be spread out over thousands of publications .
And you need to extract each of these pieces of knowledge and pistol together in order to tell the whole story .
So that's a big part of it , the other , the other part of it is trying to extract actually experimental tests where these results have been validated as observations that provides you with the kind of knowledge that you can use to actually validate your model against the real world.
Another one of joshua's programs , data driven discovery of models or death reim is focusing on enough a signature feature of contemporary science .
The generation analysis of huge databases ranging from genomic sequence of thousands of thousands of species to the social media behavior of millions of people dressed without state science can be leveraged way more to accelerate science across many problem areas .
The biggest.
Problem with the science is always been sort of the democratization of it .
It's something that despite a lot of people's preconceptions actually requires quite a lot of both mathematical and just engineering , sort of expertise , and a lot of that is not sort of the dance map .
A lot of it is the kind of needed , greedy stuff that you don't often think of like data cleaning in normalization and future engineering .
And some of this stuff is just working with data is very hard .
And so dictionary is all about machine learning for everyone , data science for everyone , making these advanced methods of data signs that have evolved over the last several years , especially making them two anonymity .
The scientists , and ideally even making them accessible to a domain scientist who might have a different kind of expertise that they could actually apply to further improve the example , for example , to discover the best possible features for a model often requires domain expertise .
But domain experts are often limited in their ability to use that by the fact that they're not either scientists , and they can , for the higher of data science that a hundred twenty years , wherever they're going it now , and so that the tools were developing in deep ream , they broadly go under the category of auto machine learning and also intuitive interfaces , non specialists .
Nonetheless , scientists build to engage with the modern tools of other machine learning in two thousand and really with problems this ranging from traditional capital regression problems to improve classification and the NLP problems are naturally with processing and to graph.
By tabloid regression , joshua is referring to the seminar , scientific challenge , incense of how two different things in the world relate to each other .
increase .
The temperature will contain gas , for example , and as pressure increases in a mathematically love away by graph problems , network phenomena , whether there is a city's communication system or commanders , war fighters and assets , joshua is referring to phenomena that can be represented in graphical , another program manager in the defence sciences of his barrett russell , who is known as barred for short , is also a champion of accelerating science by imposing with AItools that lend them expertise .
They might not otherwise have A.
My general philosophy towards accelerating science , accelerating capability , it comes down to enabling the human in general , no matter how you cut it , the human brain is still the most sophisticated computational system on the planet , right .
And so for all of the advances in AIthat we have , while there is incredible work going on that area , my view and all of the works that I am , I am driving on here are darker .
Is about using those tools to enable the human brain to to enable the human finger to allow that person to do more with less.
She is hoping that one set of tools to enable scientists to eat more discovery out of the research will emerge from a programme that won't put colleagues in the defence sciences , office , office , deputy director , fellow is running .
It's called score short for systematizing confidence in open research and evidence , and it could spare scientists some of the increasing burden of keeping up with the region time of , but also not so good scientific papers that might or might not be relevant to the scientific questions , a particular scientist.
What score is trying to do is help cut through all that uncertainty by assigning essentially a confident score or a quality score , two different studies .
And exactly the question , can you predict a headache when , based on the way the studies put together based on the methods that the researchers have decided to use ?
Can you figure out which ones are likely to replicate after the fact the ideas , if , if we can raise standards , and we have a lot more confidence in the studies that come out on the other end .
And that way , we can know if a study about red wine tells us it's good for our heart is actually good for a heart , or it's more likely to be good for our heart , or if it really is something we have to worry about .
One another study says it's not so that I think really does speak to the one of the underlying principles of science in general that we require science to be reliable .
We needed to be reliable in order to build things from it .
One of the goals of the score is , can you better filter out the really reliable is very good from the , maybe they're always study that somebody did to get publication , but is really not that great .
I think god that itself would greatly advance the speed of innovation when doing a little trivial .
You don't have to go through hundreds of articles .
You can go right to the tennis twelve .
Then , you know , a particularly reliable.
Judgment earlier , innovations applying similar air tools , but to retroactively clean up the scientific literature so that investigators can feel more confident that the evidence , our scientific understanding and decision making protocols are , he sounded , and is not , instead equivalent to house of cards.
How do we take machine technology and where to be able to reverse , first of all , a lot of those now negative consequences go back through the literature for the last twenty decades in the tried to discover papers and findings and things that are , in fact , not reproducible , or perhaps even completely wrong , or perhaps even fortunate .
How do we go back and find errors and models or competition models that have been used to support it ?
You know , multi billion dollar decisions that have been used to support literally life and death decisions within the do d these models are black boxes that are often poorly understood , even by the people who are using them .
They are often , and that needs to be untangled .
And that's one of the biggest goals of the asking is to try and really untangle the answer to the mess that we've got.
Board russell , who was , according to science background and a strong interest in furthering the reliability of social science , also takes the idea of democratizing the practice of science that spoke about in another direction , in her case , to open science and data sites , in particular to non traditional practitioners .
The hypothesis here is that the more minds that are applying themselves to science , the more side of discovery.
All the things that i'm looking at , tackling one of your dark bar really focus on helping a leverage new eye tools to enable human engineering , rather than take the view that we should write the human out of a loop friendship .
My thoughts is , if we empower the human to understand enough about those tools , I don't mean just highly trained humans .
I mean , the every person , then I think we can unlock this base of engineering that we happen as a country in particular , in a way that we haven't yet .
That could provide pretty profound advantages for our economy , as well as for a defense capabilities , one of the very focused efforts i'm looking at here really is about loosely calling at human factors in the egyptian autonomy .
How do we make complex AItools accessible to non data scientists , not just so they can use them , but so they can with them , not an important distinction , because using them and to use them for the purpose they were designed to be used in innovation means that you can use those tools in ways that nobody has thought of before .
And this is where citizen science can be extremely powerful .
So again , rather than writing humans out of the loop and putting in enough safeguards that they could never use that system in off normal situation .
I take the the AI should be instead transparent enough that you don't need to be a data scientist in order to figure out how it's been engineered , but you can understand enough about its capabilities and limitations and those capabilities that you can make calculated risk decisions about how and when you can use it in new ways .
So we can make these airport more accessible to the every person , regardless of their training , it greatly increases the number of people that we can dedicate tomorrow problems , right , because , as it is , i'm now taking a data scientist in attaching them to every team wouldn't be cool if those data scientists are pushing the edge of the eye , rather than helping me with my cognition science problem .
That's one way that has to do with the actual discovery of capabilities in the first place .
The other way is about against the automobile use of the same tool .
Can you increase utility of the new create wildly , because , you know , again , the every person knows how to use it well enough , they can innovate with.
Much like joshua elliot jessie's AI assistance , accelerating science by digesting far more of the available scientific as a means of automatically generating hypothesis that your human scientist partners could then that for potential for their pursuit.
This huge animal publications merely is hard for individual scientists to keep , keep up and to to make sure that the , you know , they , they understand all the latest greatest discoveries will help an idea on research .
But in our imagine wednesday and AIscientists that are able to , I just ordered publications very quickly , very efficiently , and to be able to at least provide hypothesis and possible principles to expand discoveries and and work with human scientists to validate .
And I think that's a , you know , that that's actually a completely different way of doing science .
And as we are doing us in the science of one point , oh , the attack countries are mostly functioned as truth , and they are directed and used by they're not um teammates .
Actually , one of the visions of the doubles , the next campaign is to enable AIto turn from tools , two arm teams.
By AInext jazz is referring to a large portfolio programs and other efforts .
The dark is running to improve AI .
Many friends in the context of the coming year of science to point she would like to see a new amped up collaboration of human scientists with air teammates to help crack notoriously difficult in complex scientific engineering .
Among these is the challenge of fully understanding phenomena like turbulent flows associated with , for example , supersonic flight .
Another is a huge challenge of discovering and designing new and more capable materials , which , in turn , leave the to know and more capable technologies made of those materials.
The design space for the material , new material is extremely complex .
So are the duty domains , for example .
But the interesting is that the weather there is a capabilities for the air technologies that if I state that I want this specific properties in the the reverse engineering , designing the , the right materials that they can satisfy these material properties , and given the possibilities of the material publicity are governed by from low level , by atomic level , by the adams in interactions , and then at the high levels by the apologies and geometries is a journey complex space .
So to find the right design to satisfy , you are your material publics actually extremely complex problem .
And so that's another area of domain .
Domain said that , yeah , technologies are hoping that we be able to help to accelerate this material discovery process.
Jessie says a few ways AItools could help pull up this kind of acceleration , and research is by making otherwise on wealthy simulations far more efficient .
And by reducing the number of actual experiments and observations , scientists need to make to answer their questions.
We are trying to see that whether you are technologies can reduce our reliance on making huge nominations , observations so that we have a huge implications in terms of film , the cost and the ability to adequately model phenomenon can air technologies can help to make these simulations more efficient and to be able to manage .
For example , the infection between multiple different skills , more competition and efficient so that we can explore.
More design space , joshua earlier conquers , and he says , that's where another one of his programs comes in .
If some part of the scientific process can be automated , he thinks it would be.
Yeah , so as intuitive synergistic discovery and design is all about really trying to once again to apply automation to eliminate those battles and victims and problems is throughout the experimental cycle , from design , building , testing , analyzing and impact to designing experiments , and its really is focused on some of the most complex experimental domains .
You can , you can imagine , synthetic biology , both in traditional and in northern organisms , prove skate's chemistry , which is the film chemistry that it looks very promising for the next generation of solar cells .
And also , we are protein design and folding .
You know , this massively complex , competition , intensive , infinite dimensional design spaces .
And how can we create the tools , creative , the protocols and the infrastructure , but the data , occasional infrastructure and the experimental infrastructure be able to automate the key parts of that process , not admitting the process that still quite a way above , you know , not a terrible thing to see the hard , but ultimately , the , the key aspects that can be automated either to increase , reproduce ability for examples .
Technologies being created for lab software and protocols so that an experimental protocol performed in one lab can be ported over and reapplied in another lab rigorously , without any ambiguities of interpretation , so that assign this connection , publish their experimental protocol explicitly , along with the scientific publication.
Part of the challenge to developing AIscientist teammates resigns in the way scientific experimentations and its results , the data or communicated and cultivate joshua , who wants not only to accelerate , but also to develop new means for being confident about making decisions , explains.
Over the last five decades , nearly scientists and many fields have been encoding much of their knowledge into these computational models with often poor documentation , pick assumptions .
And so we can just start a fraction say , from now on , you have to follow this good , satisfactory standards .
We actually have to figure out ways of extracting and organizing and presenting and making that knowledge .
That's really where the eye comes in .
In the case of asking , and the assault of science to point out goals there in order to use the outcomes of this science to point out to actually be able to support the season , making two point out , which is a big part of my objectives .
We really need to rethink the way that we in code apply and communicate the outcomes of our science right now .
For the most part , it's in it has innovates complex opec black box computational models that some experts have .
Trust me , this model is reality , and that it and it's communicated as a set of numbers with very little context , with very little accounting for what were the assumptions and prime ministrations of things that we need to produce those , and that's just not acceptable , and in a time like this , in a time where things are changing very , very rapidly .
Where the best possible information and science is is needed , and where you actually have to understand what the models tell me what.
Jiang xiao says , we have a long way to go before we have artificial scientists and research collaborators of the source that could handle in the early dark operator challenge researchers to develop .
But he says there likely will be great players in the process of getting there.
In the fifteen years or fifty years or five thousand years , until we get to that point where the official intelligence is actually doing the nobel prizes , wondering science argument that intelligence by human human machines and bioscience might actually make that period .
You know , some of the most , the most exciting and most creative and in history.
Jessie can curse in her own way.
The peaceful scientific spirit and technology development has been actually increasing .
I think it for , for an anonymous attribution to tools and and technologies that we have , including AItechnology .
And so if , for example , the AItechnology culture actually becoming a scientist , digital scientists in a standing shoulder to shoulder with a human scientists , we essentially can , you can see a huge force.
But russell uses that artificial scientists will help us solve the kinds of problems for which we always have wanted and needed solutions , including even social science questions that so far been beyond our ability to understand and.
So what does it mean if AIends up being what we hope it is going to be , and what we fear it could be , and if humans really understand well enough to work with it , I think that like so many technologies that we used in the past will probably use it to solve the same problems .
We just had a very hard time solving in the past .
The beauty of it is so things like hunger and efficiency .
We are always working for efficiencies .
I think we're probably applied same problems .
I think the most exciting part , though , are the emergent properties .
None of us can probably anticipate , you know , looking at a social media as an example with , with twitter who knew that the platform just is asking , what are you doing right now and limited dramatically how people could answer that question in terms of language could result in nations dealing with each other in different ways .
I don't think anybody would have anticipated that the speed in the access , but which we have with each other now is very different .
And I anticipate that the most profound things will be on that we cannot protect , and we do not have the imagination to see yet yet.
One mind blowing possibility of jazz points out is an artificial intelligence as the first other kind of intelligence on the planet applied to scientific investigation and could open up entirely new scientific visitors and styles of explanation that will take some doing for humans , even understand.
Potentially is that the eyes might be come up and explanations or discussions of the world has a different form .
How we see it .
And in one way , we could expand our knowledge on our understanding of the universe of nature , and also probably means that we humans party now , maybe one day we have a single two to learn from AIsystem.
It is no surprise of the password AI systems capable of nobel caliber scientific discovery is likely to be a long one along the way researchers had dropped in elsewhere say , we will need to make it a priority that any artificial scientists in the coming year of science .
Two panel does not feature the same kinds of foreigners and pensions for fooling themselves , but always have been part of the utterly human science .
Thanks listeners for sharing this time with me and some of the program managers of dark , who are aiming to weaken , struck the sign of a enterprise .