Self technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on tournament operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , the defense advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to a Voices from dark , a window on the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible to my name is iphone a motto on your dark host .
And I am thrilled to have with me today .
Doctor stayed c williams of program manager since twenty nineteen .
In the agencies technology , we are recording our conversation from our respective homes as we do our parts to slow the spread of coffee nineteenth , because we are not in recording studio .
You might ambient sounds like trucks and trains and birds and secretaries .
The party coming to door , but they see work with the air force office of scientific , where she oversaw research in remote sensing for battlefield monitoring and in space situation , awareness , which will see , applies to her work here , adopt .
Joseph worked on the space situation awareness challenge in mary , hawaii , as the technical adviser for space surveillance systems for the air force research directed energy director at early on thursday , sea chemistry was a thing , earning APHDin physical chemistry from the university of california , santa cruise in nineteen ninety three .
And later , during past breaking work in the world of metallic as a faculty member in the boston university physics department , she soon research leadership positions and guarantees with the entrepreneurial culture in a started company aiming to translate and transition basic RNDinto commercial before pivoting into her air force are in the work they see briefly stepped away from the lab to focus on improving moving science , technology , engineering and math education , stem education .
That is especially in economically disadvantaged schools .
For part of that time , she was a driving force in a gates foundation funded program to deliver innovative , non traditional teaching approaches for high poverty school populations .
She also got directly into the trenches by teaching in the massachusetts department of education system .
Stacy william , thanks for joining in this .
Thanks for having me .
I will appreciate it .
First of all , congratulations on the placement of your new compact telescope demonstration project , getting into orbit just as passionate thirteenth , released from the international space station .
So that is super exciting and will talk about that and other projects in just a bit .
But first , I like to hear a bit about some of the influences in your wife that first thank you into a trajectory and protein science .
But then more and two optical physics and then technology development directions.
I've actually had a lot of people asked me that particularly people developing stamper claims , trying to target women or other under represented groups .
And so I thought about that , I don't really have a hot moment , but I will say that I pad a lifelong love of photonics , even when I did know what photo that's her , that when I was a little girl in the southern my yard in the evening will be full of fireflies .
And I just was so in troll with the bioluminescence , how something so small could make , you know , all that beautiful.
I wanted to introduce framework for listening who might not actually understand what photonic says .
Certainly , the firefly example is a gorgeous one photos coming from the little lanterns of the fireflies into your eyes .
Photonics is sort of a full time analogue to electronics .
right ?
So you're just thinking about light in terms of its wave nature and also expected nature and full towns .
And this , which is sort of understanding those phenomenon and had to manipulate them for a potentially technology.
Yes , but I guess bureaucrats are a little biological photonics , but I also checkers group of kids in my neighborhood to a local natural history museum .
And we went in there .
And you are looking at everything .
I remember the , the mummy , because he doesn't remember their , but then they took us into this room , and there was budget rocks in a display case , and I was , they cannot get rocks in my backyard .
You know , who cares about , look at rocks , but then they turn the light on , turn on a black light .
And the room was just looked up with a racism and foster russians , and I just was just done by that as well .
So I always love science .
I always was very curious .
I think I drove my teacher's crazy .
So when I went to college and I took chemistry class , and I learned about what pluralism is really was what boss versions was .
I just decided that what I wanted to do , I wanted to work with .
I wanted to understand how I, Iwanted to work with lasers totally when I went to graduate school , I worked for a photo chemist , photo biologist , photo , photo physicists study in the universe .
Directions will likely initiate process .
So we use lasers to initiate biologically relevant molecule to understand how that molecule he took in a light and used to do some type of function , you know , for example , in our eyes , we have adopted in that is a lot of zoo being protein that i'm enables us to see the light in dark .
And so in all of my RNDthat i've done since then , has always involved some type of light initiation , or being able to understand what's happening in the system .
That's distant , like a satellite by using a light to.
I entered data , okay , so smith , by light early on , even as I tried looking at the fireflies , and there's developing that that love in throat , your education and career even now at dark , but so cool you .
So now , just before coming to DARPA , you had a similar research management role in the air force office , upside of research .
AFOSare .
So it was the course of events that resulted in your arriving at dark by headquarters here and have to go to start your tools of program manager in the technical technology.
So when I was a day of australia , i'm not actually when I was in malaria for I like , interacted a lot with dark .
Over the years , the technical technology of his TTOfred kennedy was the office structure he really wanted to be able to disrupt ISRsatellites , and by israel .
Just previously , you don't know intelligence , surveillance and recognition .
So those are satellites , typically in the low earth orbit that provide weather information .
They take pictures of years , and they help us can understand , you know , what's going on with your space eye view .
However , those systems are super expensive .
You know , they can cause billions of dollars to put one of those up .
There are very exclusive .
They give beautiful imagery , but they cost a lot of money group at harvard that was actually funded by d so the defense science is official dark to the australian program had developed a plane or length that could operate in the visible and with a romantic , so we could look at a wide range in a visible four hundred and seven hundred and seven hundred dish .
And so thread really wanted to bring that technology to bear on defense needs .
And so they were looking for a program manager .
And so my colleagues , just in the magic , as I have a chemistry background , which not the materials , is very heavily chemistry.
Based we'll explain many material system as well .
yeah.
Yes , and I also have an optic background and a telescope backgrounds , and you know , imaging background .
And so I put together a patch , and that's how I ended up at all about.
Now , what I wanna do is really get back to that on orbit project today alluded to earlier , and it's called damaging short for the formula .
And it's right , as we speak right now .
Roberta , i'm not quite sure where a few hundred miles above in the cube set about what looks to me like the size of of an old desk , top computer .
And so I couldn't tell me about daming .
And what capability gap is intended to fail .
I think you started to talk about a little bit , the technology experiment that is now going on , and what you hope will come out of this working alone.
We're pushing to get lower core systems , and when we have lower call system , typically we give up functionality .
And so you know , cubes that are a lot are very expensive .
We are relative to these being a large , single launch satellite systems .
And so being able to do a proliferated system with that , you know , says a lot of money .
But the problem is that you lose functionality , something that is that small doesn't really typically operate with something , you know , like the really large satellite system , like the size of a truck.
And just when you say preliminary , did you mean like there would be many , many platforms out there with these small platforms?
Right if you dealing with something that cost billions of dollars , you have a few of them to monitor .
But if you wanted to really have wide access , the information over lots of areas , you need to have lots of these guys , and you can just put a million billion dollars systems , or it's just too expensive .
And so we are looking for cheaper ways to be able to do that .
And so but that means the formal mirrors , sixty cubes at .
And so it's turned by twenty by thirty .
Cinema is cute , and daming is demonstrating a micro electric mechanical system .
So it means the formal bomber , the formidable mirrors were actually developed for the ground based telescope systems .
So imagine objects and space from earth is challenging , because you have to go through the atmosphere , the atmosphere , comfortable degree to images.
One confirmation of example of what adaptive optics is supposed to try to deal with .
This is sort of like the twinkling star effect .
Right , you see a star coming through when the atmosphere is the doing things to the latest , it comes to the atmosphere , and that makes it hard to actually do good telescopic imaging , yes , but adoptive objects using , in your case , these kinds of the formal bomber , as there is amazing technology to compensate for.
Exactly , so what happens is your imagine in your with your large air telescope , you'll see something that looks like a cotton ball , and it looks like a cotton ball .
I guess you said , because the atmosphere is blowing out .
And so the formal mirrors are mirrors that the shape could you have actual weathers underneath here ?
And it measures what that blower is .
We call it what the way from it is , and the mirror will deform to have that same , but exactly the opposite .
And so you know , something that looks like a cotton ball , you turn on your reform of a mirror , a compensates for the buller you get.
Image he is almost like two one to make a right.
Exactly , she may ask , why do I need the form of a mirror and space when i'm not looking through the assessment for right ?
What do we need to do that ?
While the formal mirrors can improve other imperfections that from your optical system , so not not just for ambassador blair , but for examples in space , the temperature authorities , you know , dramatically .
And every time that the temperature change material go try to get to equal librarian , so they change a little bit another extortions into your imagine as well .
And so what the system damie will do is it will manager , what those discussions are in the optical system and a compensate for those so that will be able to see clear images will be able to have , for example , if you want to look at a small extra planet next to a broader planet .
You need dynamic range to be able to differentiate those two and so that we will enable us to be able to do that.
So just want to stop your dog .
That's so cool .
In excellent estimate is insane , interesting .
And as far as I know , we haven't really directly imaged and actually planned yet .
I might be wrong there .
I know we detected them with very singularly methods with you are the form of a mirror in sort of distributed mode .
Be able to create a telescopic technology to directly immediately point.
Well , so that would be what the hope would be the people to do that with a smaller satellite .
I'm actually not on the strawberries .
So my motivation is very different for that , but I can talk about that here.
Right , but what you can say is , overall is ISR, which we talk intelligence .
Surveillance recognizes its situation and awareness and space .
So in generalists , like , what's going , what's there , what's happening .
So that's where we're this false and.
Right , so this is the first main system that the exactly working in space , and the students are in my tear , actually communicating with the satellite .
Now they're going through the initialization , getting things started and its go , and actually really well .
And this is a pound finder .
So if this system works , this can help us with many different types of imaging applications .
Maybe you could extend the range of the satellite .
That's imagine other satellites and space , or can you know , extend the range of , you know , objects demographic that we can see also as multiple communications .
It could also improve that .
So any time that you are transmitting and receiving light , this type of system will be able to improve the performance.
Right , and just to give listeners a more sort of kenneth satellite of physical sense of the mean , how biggest it is that the size of my family alerts it , something like that .
Yep , it's about the size of a dime , a size of a dime .
And is that just a chat size ?
What will you need to make larger reform of bombers for the systems ?
univision?
Well , it depends on what your application is right when you collect , lied and to any kind of telescope , you have areas where you focus the lights down on the smaller point , so you don't need to have a jacket .
The formal bomber , you know , it's not the same size of the approach of your telescope and smaller .
But at the football , mayors can all different sizes.
When it comes to article systems like telescopes , lenses and focal length and other issues determine the overall size of the systems .
Other things , of course , is , I know you've been thinking about pushing the of play , the robotics and many of us have some exposure to this technology in the form of those flat magnifying sheets that can help you see small print on the page , but you have.
Grandmother and my team , yes , well , so if you look at at objects in a reflective objects and look at telescopes made from a reflective objects , they are not that much different than the telescope .
The gala developed .
We've , we've made a lot of strides and in being able to tolerate weight , something particularly for a reflective types of telescopes , but we kind of platted out in the last couple of decades , we have made a significant .
And the reason for that is because currently we rely on naturally curriculum materials to manipulate the light in naturally current materials .
The index of perfection is not that there is not that much depressed .
Twin air in glass materials .
And so what we do to be able to manipulate the light as we had a lot of block , and we end up making optical systems , for example , when I working with the telescopes in melbourne , it would have room just fall above decks .
You know , trying to manipulate the light that we collected the people too , you know , understand what we wanted to do about the many materials .
So on the other hand , there are engineered materials and they can manipulate light in ways that you can do naturally , and even the focus of a lot of research investment , particularly had dark , and the fed scientists office , as well as it .
Therefore , officers , scientific research and other places to mature in and develop.
The stacy , before we move on , it is one for people who haven't heard the term engineered materials and services .
You about surfaces that are made from parts , or have textures that are very deliberately designed and produced.
Yes , so what we are doing is we , we have a surface , and we place a microphone vacated subway branch , struck shirts .
And what I mean by that is structures that are slightly smaller than the wavelength of life that is , we identify what functionality doing one from this object .
And then I go in an engineer that and makes that object , that helps that functionality , that that's where we would like to be .
And many materials have the potential to be tuneable , to be able to to change the structure in real times so that I can change what functionality that specific objects at that time .
So that's , you know what I came to double to work on is to take that .
So , so these beneficiaries have been for longer wavelength systems and for single wavelengths systems have matured significantly .
If I wanted to do something and invisible , so like that , it , on the order for hundred and the structure should going to be smaller and to do something that sports band is more challenging too .
Because now I need structures that interact not only with light that four hundred and nine meters , but it's five hundred , six hundred and seven hundred , so it becomes a much more complicated problem .
So i've been collaborating with my DS, so colleagues that would be working on .
And so we have several efforts that were working on together to try to be able to take these manufacturers that have been demonstrated at the millimeter of april suicide .
So the articles of millimetre wide , but to take that and make that larger to make that so that I can have a telescope that doesn't have thirty objects that are ridiculously heavy , really dry .
The cost of my ISRtype system , but they have something .
Maybe the only has a few objects , and those objects are that the way to eat out of the magnifying tones in reference.
Ha , it reminds me a little bit of innovative , dramatic size reduction that we know when history save computing , where you go from a window computer that takes up a room .
And then we have in a again the size of some know something , you know , thousands of times more powerful than that to the same sort of capability , but in much more compact and practical forms .
So let's in some ways , what you moving together.
Yeah , so so yeah , so that we're all working on somewhere .
As I said , my colleagues in the so were also working with some of the other user communities to investigate in a can we make these minimum lessons have large approach ?
Can we make them such a theory of the function the way that we need to function , particularly in the space environment ?
And the other thing , I think that's important to is this is a very challenging problem .
But can I understand what the limits are of this ?
Originally TTLwouldn't be able to make up a meter plus .
I asked our types of light , but maybe , maybe we're not close to being there yet .
Maybe we can make something though that tony summit , which would also still have a huge empire.
That's a very darker .
Asked question in a propart of darkness , mission of courses to sort of matter the landscape of what is possible .
So you might learn from the performers that is to say , the researchers working with you on this project is , is just what are the limits of obsessing the end of the size and extension and complexity that , you know , you can create with these men of material .
So it certainly is spot on with questions and answers .
Starbucks is gone after .
So before we went at a time , now I want to return to another part of your work life .
And this is when working on the same education .
Again , let's see , you know , science , technology , engineering , math , education , and especially in economically disadvantaged schools .
I am just wondering where that that interest came from , and if this , you are continuing to work on.
Yeah , so I could involve in stem education for many years , and it can have started when I was in in college in the chemistry partner .
I was president of our student organization , and we had lots of parents that were calling onion tutors .
And so you know , my fellow chemistry club members , we set up a free tutor .
Senator , that where high school kids could come and and also college kids and move in the weekend , and my chemistry , and and I have to say , I love to working with the high school kid they were had so many questions .
They were so eager to learn .
So I adopted two girls when they were an school , and I wanted to have the same schedule with them .
So I don't always thought about , you know , teaching high schools are , but I made that transition then , and I did that in boston , and I just love them .
And and then I was offered a position at the dictionary college academy , and they know how to be the circular and director for the gates on the school that you mentioned it when I went to the school , it was , it wasn't a second year , and it was an amazing experience working there , the , the first year the folks had started the teachers and administrators and community is leaders that research , lots of different creative solutions for urban education , because at that time , and you know , probably still , we have a lot of children are graduating from high school that are on a great level that are really prepared for college or prepared for life .
And the billion millions of information where to change them , so they find it several extremely schools across .
And one was the data or the european economy , and the idea behind decades duckers sought for dinner ecology academy .
These were first generation college students , the students , ninety five percent of them around for your reduced launch , nineteen five per cent of students were considered minorities to take these students secretary for college , until the model was , first of all , I was early college because a lot of students that graduate , particularly students from launch and families , they go to college , and they can , they don't tested to the the universal thirteen hundred college classes , so they are not taking these remedial classes , but they are paying their college tuitions .
So they are a cruise large dead , but getting zero college and a lot of them get disappointed , and they dropped out .
So this school has the students taking college , whether in high school , to get them ready for that , lots of the college classes were a media classes , but that still helped give them prepared for the college glasses .
It's a very good model .
The school is doing .
We did realize early on that we really need to start young girl , so rather than starting at fourteen each year , the school is added a middle school grade , or elementary .
Now they go k through twelve , but we also did a kind of a different way to approach learning .
When you open up , you know , your classical chemistry textbook .
The first chapter is on measurement , and that is the most worrying chapter in the entire book .
And I don't know why they just limit text , like all of you enthusiasts about it .
This class in this first week .
So what we did was , we took the students on overnight counterpart , and we went to a king up that had a straight , and the students collected waters and balls , collected rock sailboats , leave sailboats , and also , during that time , they had the opportunity bomb with the teachers that there were going to be spending a lot of time work , because relationships .
I think , when you have students in high school to get that really engaged in mind , when we came back to the classroom , we spent the next few weeks under the standing in learning about measurement , learning about water quality , learned about the policies of water , learning about how water affects economics , how that affects you know , where cities are built and to do a cut event in a greedy circular .
Murray , you know , touch all of the.
Stacy , that just sounds absolutely amazing .
And I can tell with the combination of your knowledge and your enthusiasm must be just been a gift to the songs .
I have a prediction that , at some point , me , or maybe not doing your tenures at our program manager , but at some point you are going to get back into each encourage .
Sounds like that's one place .
You know , you want to be at some point .
One more question is , daisy , before we close out here , you know , one of the phrases that often is associated with double , you know , if that is an important part of the opera innovation ecosystem , you know , which goes everywhere from academics and laboratories to entrepreneurs , you had some experience of that already on .
I'm just another group in a darker for a little while .
How do you view its place in the innovation ecosystem?
Oh , well , I think dark is as an amazing , incredible place .
And in one of the things I think that's most powerful .
He said , is that we have technical program managers , coal , located with lots of the end users .
So one of the things that I think is amazing about dark as the services is on when I was in melbourne , we developed technology , but we were very fortunate because we had end users embedded with us at the telescope side .
And it was huge because the end users can really give you some guidance and.
Right , and just let me stop you just for a second soul in africa .
And for listeners who might not know what that phrase service leaves on me so at the door , but many women in uniform , they come from different services who , you know , have boots on the ground and experience in those services so that they can relate to the program managers and contribute to discussions with program managers about the kind of technology really would be valuable for the mission of furthering international security and defence.
Unusually valuable , like , for example , I have a small business innovation research , her gram to develop variable laser detection so that are disappointed soldiers who know if they are being lazed .
Well , I immediately talked to the end users that could potentially use this to understand , if it's , you know , an edge , maybe there's an inch wherever that's too big for them .
They can't help that , you know , they need it if it was a pounder , I can't wait a pound .
It has the way a quarter of .
So these are really key pieces of information that you need when you're designing something .
And so I doubt , but we just have access to , you know , amazing people that you know , have experience in the battlefield .
Then come back and with enthusiasts and share that with us and give us ideas for , for new things that need to be developed .
So I think that's what the most wonderful things about dark.
Called the bring up beginning , it is just one element of many , you know , that make up as some former directors , of course , it is special sauce .
What is it that makes the open such a successful technology development institution , and , you know , a lot of people actually have tried to emulate people from all over the world that come to observe and try to learn what dark has been doing it to see if they can learn lessons .
But at the moment , they're still as just one doctor , as far as I know .
So thank you says , it has been a really cool to talk with you about , you are ongoing science and technology , adventure , and i'm foreign , right here .
And now that dark pass .
So thanks for sharing this time with me .
Oh , thank you .
I will enjoy that chat , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from garbage , thanks also to ban celebrant for his partnership in producing this program for more information about doctor's taxi , williams , the program she runs at the agency , tactical technology office and the other ways with technologies dark is working on visit , dark and for links that enable you to download this podcast .