Stealth technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on this operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since the funding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defensive as research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window , and the dark is core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is , i've been a matter when i'm your daughter host today .
I am pleased to be talking with doctor , witnessing a program manager since twenty seventeen in the agencies microsystems technology , obvious to give you a clue about her focus at the agency .
Let me say for the moments that if I had a question about , say , in for it based technology , I would go to her first , just a context note , we are recording our conversation from our respective locations as we do our parts to slow the spread of copyright team , because we are not in recording studio , you might hear ambient sounds that make it into our microphone .
So now , let me get back to witnesses and tell you a little bit about her .
She brings to dark for her interests and expertise in imaging sensors and making those senses see and do more .
She's currently on detail from the night vision and electronic sensors directorate , which is part of the army communications , electronics research , development and engineering center , or at four billboards , virginia , at that directorate witnesses , most recent job was director of the science and technology division .
In this capacity , she entered and engineers and had their sights on next generation article , materials and designs .
Devices such as focal plane , raise advanced circuitry for converting war imaging signals into useful information and image processing techniques , among other topics .
Her division delivered the technology that underlines the army is most advanced infrastructural and explosive hazard detection technologies , and take some education to get witnesses earned her bachelor of science degree in physics from george town university , and followed that with APHDin physics from the university of oklahoma witnessing , thanks for joining me in this Voices from garbage .
It's great to be here .
Thank you .
So let's get a little bit at the origins of your interest , right ?
So you got hooked on physics , at least in college , and then you got hooked on objects and infrastructure and technology , among other .
So , what are the origins of these interests ?
And if it goes all away back to your childhood , go.
I have always said that scientists are born not made when I was started my childhood .
I was constantly asking why , why is the sky blue , why is concrete hard ?
Why is electricity so expensive ?
right ?
Just curious about things .
And I was fortunate to to have people that would indulge me and help me get resources to try to answer those questions .
You know , I just like science in general , but what suddenly on physics , I think that it's just the root of most of the sciences that we explore today .
But the cool thing about , imagine if you think about it , it's a little bit of everything .
So there is material science .
There's electronics , there's image processing and those biology , right , because all of us , all animals , in fact , have eyes of one form or another.
right ?
And before we leave , that biology point is amazing to think that there even are inferred sensors in the biology world and thinking of things like those pilot organs and snakes .
And there are those other animals and have that ability.
Yeah , that's absolutely true .
And you know , you can take a lot of inspiration from the way animals of all kinds seek to inspire the work that we do here in other places .
Let's move.
Two sort of a question that I asked me to every program manager said , how did you get to dark a story ?
And so you started in twenty seven teen , and just before that , you have been running one of the directors at third deck against the army communications , electronic research , development and engineering center .
So what was the change of our best to catalyze your leap into what is really kind of an extensive , detailed into four years , just about here , it dropped.
I have really been fortunate during my time at the army to have a lot of different things position .
So every four to five years , I have been offered opportunities to do another job , and I was just coming to the end .
About five years is the director of the science technology .
I am jealous , who is done .
The deputy director for microsoft and technology office , called and said , would you consider a tour at dark ?
And of course , I had been fortunate in my career to work very closely with DARPA transition in some of the technologies to us , and no was just an opportunity that was too big to pass up .
And I will say it is , by far , I have a very fun jobs , but this is the funniest.
Okay , and of course , that is one of the characteristics of darkness that anybody comes in there pretty much as a cell by day on the day they come in and you're coming in on detail .
So how long?
So right now , my expiration date is november of this year.
All right , well , so I am .
So please to be speaking with you now before that day arrives , and you go back to third , I presume , examination in pursuit .
Where are you going ?
I, Idon't know .
Okay , which is also another characteristic of DARPA web , where people are willing to take some lips and risk without necessarily knowing what's on the other side of that cell by day , but nearly do the job itself is open and off to take such a risk .
So let's still move into your programs and mean , when I look at the portfolio programs , strong themes of updates and infrared radiation come through , that might even broaden when we get to maybe one of the last programs will talk about at the end of the conversation before we do take brief tours of the programs .
Tell me a little bit generally about , you know , the world from the infrared perspective .
And why should the departure defence wheels , and for that matter , the rest of us , the rest of the same point , billions of us on planter of , why should we care about that information?
就是back to the ，to the animal analogy , you know , any more eyes involved to be the way they are because they are specific tasks .
So you reference the picnic lines in steaks they developed those because they needed to see their pray , of course , humans to be able to see in the visible wavelength , because that is where most of our light comes from .
But you know , people in the deal , do you need to see other than just the day rights of social needs to see at night , or see through dust , or find homemade explosives , or find things really far away , or track thinks.
Right , and witnesses before you continue on that thought of records , the most listeners might not know , sort of what the pit organs are doing biologically for the snake .
And so I will just say very briefly , they're essentially like these , these article centres , but in the infrastructure helps them pick out , say , a moving , a warm , a moving mouse out there .
In addition , if they have the visual contact or not , but the pilot organ will give them that moving heat source , and so it will help them hurt .
Just want to get that little detail in case listeners did no .
And now I wanted to pick up where you.
Thank you .
Until you are a great point , right , because everything emits heat of one source or another .
So , just like any more eyes have evolved to be task dependent .
There is a lot of capability in the infrastructure and a lot of capability in imaging sensors to be able to evolve those sensors to suit soldiers .
So to see all the time , right dynamics says everything in its heat is an important characteristic for a soldier , particularly if he can only carry .
So thermal sensor is create ubiquitous image.
Okay , so despite , let's actually move into your portfolio , programs will step to most of them .
So let's serve you more mature programs once that had their thoughts with program manager , the proceeds of june , and whose research performers and by that , I mean , those who are on contract to do work on the programs that you're not shepherding toward delivering real technology capabilities , one of those programs goes by the figuring .
Imagine or reimagine , tell me in our listeners about the article technology that you hope to deliver with this program and how it would empower war fighters , and perhaps in time civilians.
So if you don't mind , i'm gonna , give you a small tutorial on how infrared images zoo first , there is an absorber material in the visible world that silicon and say , the million foreign that could be a material like indian technique .
This is the material that what color if you will of radiation ?
You were central williams , or in infrastructures , there is also what is called a read out in the greatest circuit .
The absorber material observes the four times and turns those four towns in electrons .
They read out in a greater circuit , collects those electrons and read them out .
And that's what goes into your display or a computer , and both the absorber and the riddle of circuit are pixilated , and that you , for instance , the pixels in your TV, so you put these two things together .
And then you have an infrared football.
Where and I should say , just as you listen to that description of sense , very much .
Oh , right now .
Yeah , we do have young rights and conservatives sanctions , and that gets translated into accountable .
Read out in the form of a normal language , right that is.
That is an excellent point .
So we imagine is really about working on the riddle , integrated circuits , technology and probably forever rhythm in the greatest circuits have been pretty boring .
really .
They have had a storage device that collects the turns out into a current and in recent autumn , and the difference between the currents between one pixel and another pizza is what creates the contrast , and it's as basic as that we and you need a computer then to make sense out of this information .
And they only do one day , right .
So they only absorbed the electrons , or they could count the electronics .
You have sensors that can do what timing analysis only will do one .
What we imagine does is it as the capability first to do more than one thing at one time .
So framework greatest as fast as the your television refreshes , writer as fast as your camera refreshes .
And a traditional occupant rate will frame at one frame rate , typically , sixty , hurts using reimagine .
You can frame with different frame rates across different portions of the foreign rate at the same time , or you can change your special resolution so that you have pixels in one area , then you do in another , or you can actually put some math in there so you can turn the information into signals .
And because it has this computer of capability , it can also plug in algorithms .
You can program this to do algorithm .
So the sensor can be more autonomously .
It doesn't require a user to change the way the focal pilot behaves .
You can use the embedded algorithms to change the way this behaves .
And so this is going to create an enormous amount of opportunity where a lot of platform farms need to do multiple jobs .
And right now , they would have to have multiple sensors .
Now you can just put one to do all of those functions , and it's very much like your brain works , right , your eyebrow combination , where our brain decides we need to fulfill the aid in a place .
So we need to look around broadly , this focal point rate is the start of being able to do that in a system.
Okay , let's just get a bit concrete of weekend .
You know , let's say , we have this versatility to be able to just on the fly , change the framework , as you are referring to work , you know , maybe different parts of the sensor can have higher resolution than the other .
what?
Well , so think about what you would do if you went into a crowd , and you were looking for a specific person , right ?
You would first scan the entire brown looking for something , and then you , I would focus on something that you would focus on something , and you would bring all of your attention into a specific area so that you could identify by a specific person right now that requires two different kinds of sensors to do that , but using reimagine , I can do this simultaneously , and what I can actually keep my attention on the rest of the room while I am trying to determine if it's the person that I am looking for .
So you don't have to lose your situation awareness while you're trying to focus on one specific area of the city.
So well , websites are really between a lot more versatility and into what these kinds of sensors .
Let's move to your program called wild , and that's short for if we're a detector's program .
This one is interesting to me , and that is focusing on the way dramatic cost reduction , you know , as much as a dramatic technology innovation can be what really brings game changing , new capabilities , practical being .
So maybe you can tell me in our listeners what you're hoping that we will do .
And what are the capability gaps are that the programs designed to fill?
If you take a little bit for into the explanation that I gave before on how infrared detectors are made , you take a europe's observer layer , and you make different dye where I die would be the size of your phone around on one waiver when you process that into pixels .
And then you go probably to a different founder , and you make your read up in a greeted circuit .
And you has many die on it as well .
Can you guys up each of these layers separately ?
So you have individual sovereignty and individual world , then you could do what we call hybrid decision .
So you put indian bombs , which are just thinking of this as glue on each of the pixels .
And you put these two layers together , and you see them .
The biggest yield hit in focal point rate is actually , when you're taking these , these small focal panel raise are lessen the cinema on the side .
traditionally , they're very small things when you integrate these 的人，and we lose a lot through this process .
Plus , it is a long process .
You have to paradise each of these , in turn , contrast that with the way we make visible sensors , SONY takes away from , and they put into their foundry , and they make it hundreds of the eye on the waiter , and they cut up .
And then there is your camera you're done .
So what wire does is it says , kennedy leverage the thinking of commercial scale and skip the hypothesis .
So we take away for robots .
We put our absorber material on it .
We create pixels , and then we die them up , and our camera is there .
So we're taking advantage of commercial processes .
Commercial architecture is commercial flight processes , which has only once before been done in the world world , and that is on good detectors that you can actually buy right , right now .
And french teams put it on yourself.
Okay , so I talked to me just a little bit about difference between couldn't uncalled detectors in the infrared technology.
Context , sure , so cool detectors are going to talk about the absolute material season .
Sovereign materials are in the mathematician and the entire ride , or it was exciting materials that most of us don't think about on a given day , because very , very few people actually make this .
So not only is the process expensive , but the cost of use is expensive , and they are based on a very exclusive material quality .
And what is called the photo electoral effect .
So I am four towns , and that turns into a current image is very dependent on what the full tones are .
So the band gap of the material sets the wavelength.
The device , right ?
So I banned capital of tunes into what infrared frequencies it will be sensitive to.
That is exactly right .
You can take up this as red , blue , green , right in your physical camera that is done with filters .
This is done from a material perspective .
Uncle detectors are based on micro bloomy or so .
A bolometer is just something that changes it's resistance as a function of the temperature that isn't pinching on it .
So in this case , I am just detecting heat , so you absorb the interrogation , decorate the current , and you read it out , and it's a very simple device you can be made right now .
It's made in commercial foundations .
It's made a wafer scale .
So you take the read out , and you put this material on .
So it's a low cost .
And I have to say it's kind of medium performance , but that's enough for a lot of low cost applications like on your phone .
You don't need the most exquisite of performance and.
And so what , though , will say , wired deliver to the department of defense , which is interested in enhanced capability , say , for war fighters.
Right now , midwife detectors , are you used a lot in water strategy , you know , on the water , saying navy applications , because it sees very well through hubble environments .
And right now , these sensors are very , very expensive to manufacturer by going to a low cost material or a low cost process .
This is going to enable more of the sensors to be proliferated across , you know , say , ships or planes or forms that operate in.
Human environments , so it falls into the sort of agreement that most people would don't know that we , in our context , we do the swap sea idea , right where , if you can reduce the size , you can reduce the way , reduce the amount of power inquiries , and in this case , reduced the cost .
And maybe some of those other things that in itself brings out more capability , because we can afford to investigate as using other areas where previously , you might not even thought.
That is correct , and I, Ilikely should have mentioned before the primary difference between a high performance infrastructure and an uncle tensor is clearly that an uncle chancellor .
Operating room temperature and high performance sensitively operates at weaker nitrogen temperatures that seven thousand kilometers are about minus two hundred degrees.
Sounds easy and not alone at a world of technical challenges to keep things that .
So it seems like the wild program follows from a previous and now completed manufacturing century programme that was called the low cost symbol imaging manufacturing program .
But in this is a dynamic that happens a lot at dark , or where lessons are learned .
And earlier program applied in the design of a following program .
Some just wondering what lessons from the earlier program or helping with various programs.
So I think there is two things for civilities against leveraging that commercial idea and the commercial processes , looking at manager of commercial scale processes .
The other thing is that you have to set your performance criteria correctly , right ?
So uncle detectors are typically medium format , and it's okay because you are leveraging other things right to swap , save energy , the low cost packaging of these transition in that into a wild , in particular , the other thing we focused on was the , of course , packaging .
So trying to make this work more like an uncle package operating very close to real temperature , but not expecting the very highest performance television.
Witnessed , you know , I agree with you enough , but not quite because I want to talk briefly about your news program .
And i'm referring here to your program called fence .
That's the agreement for fast event based neurologic camera and electronics .
Just want to congratulate you .
First of all , for getting the problem , the victim process , it is hiring and difficult to do that , and you've gone to a place in the lifecycle of the programmer .
You've now identify the research groups who will be working on .
So i'm hoping that you can tell us a little bit about what you hope to achieve with the program and about status.
Sure , so I think that this is the forest .
We have gone .
The imagine community has gone towards approaching the way the eye brain works .
There is a classic sensors called event based sensors .
It appears that the essential is only provides information when something changes , though , if you were looking at a static scene and nothing changed , then you will get no information and the sensors right now operate the visible , and they work just beautifully when there is not a lot of change in this thing , there are some pretty cool videos that you can find on mind of rockets taking off using these sensors , or looking at stars , tracking stars , because not a lot of the background scene is changing and advantages .
They can be very , and they can be extraordinary , low power , but you know , the world is not changing scenes , rather than a lot of information going on all the time .
And so what fence springs is using that event based mentality , but bringing processing to it very much like your eye does .
So we have the equivalent of about one hundred and thirty million pixels in our eye , but your brain only processes about one percent of that information at a time .
There is a lot of preprocessing that goes on actually , in your right .
We always used to think of the camera as the eye and the processor as the brain , but it's a much larger spectrum than that .
Weather is a lot of it processing going on at the front end .
And if you can do that processing in the front end , then you can maintain this very high speed allegations and very low power by putting processing right behind the foreign primary , in fact , right into the pizza so that you are what I can specify the information in real time .
So to that analogy that I said , right , where are you going to a role in your scanning around for people , your brain automatically ignores chairs and.
The floor is the sea link .
Now you're.
Foot feels in your show all of these things , exactly right .
You are focused on the information that is important to you .
That's exactly what these cameras are going to be .
People to do is boil down the same content into information that is relevant to the job ahead and be very low power and very quickly .
So we've just been through source elections when we have selected , the performers were not yet under contract .
I think we will be under contract this summer , and I just couldn't be more excited to get started.
It's gonna be amazing , as you were describing that , and I think it , actually , my related to some work in your other programs .
And in some ways you are striving to do is to , and the capacity of sensor is a kind of pay attention , just the way we do .
It is a kind of amazing that we actually have to ignore .
Ninety nine point nine percent of what is actually available to our own senses in order to really operate in the world .
Because if we pay attention to everything , we would be paralyzed .
You going to a supermarket , and you find that box of syria , which you interested in , you look for the queues of that , and you consider when I undergo that behavior , whereas if you could not distinguish between the ten thousand items in a supermarket , you be lost when it sends you are trying to bring the ability to pay attention to in my contract .
That is exactly it .
So take me out into a kind of setting out there on the world with the kinds of sensors you've developing an imagine football , even a civilian version of this beyond the bye .
What is fun for you to think about being able to do with those?
Here is so one of the examples that I use think about going out on the boat .
And if you're out on the water , particularly you are out on the ocean right , there is a lot of stuff going on .
There is a sunglass of the waves , right , they can play .
There can be boats moving around .
There can be just use .
Moving around .
There could be birds flying around right ?
There is all of this content , but all they think you really want to do is make sure that you don't hit in body , right , and a typical focal point rate , you would have to take in on that information , and eventually your sensor would be able to say it will stop another critical samples .
Is self driving cars right ?
There is released critical information that you need to know .
You don't need to know that the grass is green .
You don't need to know that their stores on the side of you , but you shall be better be able to say that the pedestrian is getting ready to walk across your field of view , or that there is a bicycle , but approaching .
And if we do these sensors , right , eventually , we're going to be able to honeymoon things right where you can start thinking about intent and thinking the way we do great , think about driving along the road .
And you see somebody in their working over their shoulder , and you know , the speakers are going across the road right recently doesn't know that recently has no idea .
But if you can start focusing on the things that are important , you can start to learn about , how do these things work and become more likely?
Our ignorant combination works right .
So it sounds like in the back end , at least for some of the applications who have in mind artificial intelligence techniques will be part of it.
I think that this enables those artificial intelligence techniques to be so much more powerful , absolutely , because you're doing the processing at the beginning .
Take good , rid of information that confuses for the computer.
So when you said earlier that you have had many jobs , and you are adopted as a program manager , just wondering if you can tell me a little bit about what sort of different about this experience you're having as a program manager .
And how do you view it is fitting into the overall innovation ecosystem , isn't it?
Great question , the thing that I think is the most amazing and the most impactful parts about dark is that I get to throw the dirt really hard , right ?
I get to say , i've done some research .
I thought people , I think it's good work , but it might not write feeling fast .
Use an option if you learn something else .
So you really get to explore the space of what might be impactful .
Ten years from now , twenty years from now , thirty years from now , I supposed to having to make sure that it works , which is I was a valuable job , but my technology doesn't have to work it in two years .
It doesn have to go on attack in two years .
It can be way out there and far reaching , and I can change the world.
Right , and this reminds me of just one of the most wonderful aspects of the dark at my opinion in which is this tolerance of failure , and actually not looking at failure in the way many people do , which is sort of like a lost cars .
Instead , failure is valuable , right ?
And that you learn lessons from it , and those lessons often do become the basis of programs down the lights.
That is absolutely true .
There are so many programs in the imaging world and other places that took a lessons learned from a previous program recognized the technology .
But she has advanced and brings that new technology to bear on an old problem to solve its challenges .
So it's much like all of science we are building on the.
You've been very generous with your time .
I just want to give you an opportunity to bring up any other question that you think I should have brought up in the conversation that didn't come up with any other topics that you think just would be interest.
To listeners , they do actually have one other programming is really cool , telling full cycle arranges for curved infrared images , and another place leverages the whole biological scenario .
What you find right now is that infrared cameras can be very small fields , say on the order of twenty degrees .
You can think about that maybe is about a quarter of our future view .
And they're exquisite and they're wonderful .
But when you try to extend the field of you to , well , we see right , which is on the order of one hundred degree field of view .
Then the performance of the cameras around the edges degrees , and it degrades from a resolution , and it degrades from a sensitivity perspective .
There is a concept in objects which is sort of the ideal focuses called the peaceful surface , and it resides on a curve .
And if you curve a foreign minority allows you to have a white field of view in a compact package , you can solve the performance degradation by putting in more and more objects .
But there is a limit to that .
Of course , this makes it very heavy .
It is , in fact , the reason that our eyeball is curved because we have to fit our wide field of view , high resolution into a very small package .
And so football guy is approaching that trying to get focal point rates into a very small package to have up to him a spiritual right half of the circle to make the very smallest.
Vital review .
So very ago , again , just bought me stealing from biology and evolution's brilliance.
Yeah , well , we all see right .
Nature has evolved over thousands of years , and we're trying to evolve much quicker.
And so tell me that the challenge of them bring you what typically is in technology has been kind of flat focal planner can have a rate into these curved formats .
What are some of the technical challenges underneath ?
That is that?
Let me tell you what I did when I was thinking about this program .
Take a piece of paper .
And if you hold it on those things dancing , you've folded up in one dimension .
Writers , perfectly smooth .
So you have an innovative solution that is perfectly smooth .
There is no tears .
There is no anything , anything .
Now take that same piece of paper and try to make it into a circle , and it rigorous rate , or it breaks .
And max obviously know what you in this focal planner rate and focal planter is right to the underlying materialists silicon , which is hard .
It's fun , but it's hard .
So you have to deal with the physics of the material , the current risks of the material to try to reduce the string that is involved in the eastern , where approaching is in the forecast program in two different ways .
In one sense , we say , take a large piece of silicon about four cinemas on the side and folded up to be about a quarter of a circle , but half a himself with no wrinkles and no overlap and no breaking in the other case , were saying to people .
You can have strange relief in there .
You can make cuts , or you can do a say , a soccer ball and fooled it into a shape .
There are particularly in order to get an actual through him is fear , just like our eye , graduates of culture .
The new thing about dark programs , I think , is when you can find farmers that are all approaching the same problem in fundamentally different ways .
So they choose to explore the physics of the problem .
And I always say rising tide raises or ships the lessons that you are .
Those efforts are changes the way you can do.
Right in your leveraging the creativity of many minds this way , instead of specifying this is the way to go about it .
We certainly limits the creative imagination.
The engineering imagination , that's right .
The neighborhood is when somebody comes to you with an idea.
That just makes it so much better , and I could see how that would make a program manager's date when it has been a really fun conversation .
And I just wanna thank you for making this time to be with me in the share with our listeners .
Thank you very much .
This was , and thanks witnesses for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from double thanks also to ban selection for his partnership in producing this program .