Step of technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand are tonight technologies , a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt this offensive best research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window on the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is , I went a motto , and I am your dog by host today .
I am pleased to be talking with mr john francisco margin , though I will call him at the rest of a cyber security technology developer , jail dark as a program manager in the agencies , information invasion office in january twenty twenty , just as the cold front end up with getting under way , his previous job was with raising on BBMtechnologies , where he was chief scientist in a senior racial fellow before that , he worked for a number of companies among the verizon general and SAIC, and roads centered on communications and information management .
I should point out the BBMtechnologies , which was acquired by brazil in two thousand nine as an important historical connection with urban in nineteen sixty nine , is delivered four inch interface message processors , which were pivotal components , enabling the birth of opponent and ultimately the internet .
Moreover , beyond vice president for engineering psychology , from one thousand nine hundred and fifty sixty two , JCare late later , was one of darkest , most visionary research managers and leaders in its early years .
Okay , back to john .
France is back to jail as an undergraduate year university .
He double major in electrical engineering and operations research .
He builds on that foundation by earning a master of science as the green management with the concentration and information systems from m , it is slowing school of management , a few other details to share .
Jail is a private pilot and a ham radio operator , and has more than forty patterns to his name .
They've titles like wireless vehicle , slash journalist and public announcement system , malware and temporary system , computer architecture .
And this one , a bit of an space debris using upper atmosphere and more text generated .
Jia , thanks for joining me in the studio today and to share with me a tale about your ongoing adventure in technology development .
I'm really happy to , so we'll get your life as a program manager soon enough , and also to those patterns at the angels briefly , but let's go straight to those hobbies .
You fly plans , and you are a ham radio .
So just briefly tell me about those interests .
And how is the party of your life now?
Flying has been part of my life about twenty six years .
Here's at this point , my wife came home from a business trip announced that she wanted to learn to fly , and I take along and got my pilot license , along with incidents have gone on to get multi engine and instrument ratings and conflict lighters and seaplanes , well , but so it's a two pilot households , which makes a discussions with the budget committee on changes to the airplane .
Ma said , much easier .
Ham radio has been part of my life for much longer .
I've been a handwritten operator for over fifty years , and during that time , have operated outside the us and really got involved with packet radio when the truth came up.
Written for those who are not in account in that world of hamburger , just give us a little bit of flavor of the kind of content that flows over the .
There are ways when you are buying the controls.
It has jokingly been said that ham radio is one of the few hobbies where you build equipment so you can talk about your hobby .
It's really set into several different communities .
There were experimenters .
There are people who like to do public service and public support , such as emergency communications during floods and hurricanes .
And there those who enjoy handling traffic and.
Just right , actually uses code now , very interesting .
The european european community resilience is becoming so much more important .
And so being a position to really be part of that solution.
And you really get to see and work with first responders , and those who have to deal with with those that get hurt .
And it really affected my whole way of thinking about what the role communications was in our society and what it could do for good in terms of helping people when they are need help.
So i'm beginning to hear it hints from that .
Interesting , what are you doing now ?
And so we'll get to that just a little bit .
And I do like my discussion partners in the partners in the park , some sense of society of the original story of your interest and patients .
And so if there were people or teachers or parents , are some a pipeline or some failure , just whatever in your earlier years , we're important in the development of your interest in the industry , professional integrity.
Whether there were a couple of people I grew up in a university town with , with teaching parents , and my dad was a was a professor yell , and I remembered an early meeting with one with his ph address .
Professor looks , and he would always bring me a trickett of a piece of patrick would have an eggs , something .
And we talk about it .
And I learned a little bit from it , and one day I was really proud .
I had gotten a four hundred power microscope for my birthday , and I wanted to show this to professor louds .
And he said , oh , you know , I can .
The four hundred power microscope because I have , these are techniques magnifier that I wear around my neck , and I can see more through that than I can understand .
I could never understand what comes from a foreign repair microscope .
And I was crushed as a little kid .
I had this thing .
I was really proud of .
And then he gave me the techniques manufacturer , and I still have , it is hanging on a book in my home and what he really made me do was realized .
Observation is incredibly important for doing science , and that the power of tool , the , the speed of a tool is not as important as really thinking about what you're trying to see and what you are trying to see him .
And so that really affected me as I , as I grow up.
HMM , it sounds like a lesson you continued to embrace.
Yeah , it's , it's .
I try to think it's simply about things as I possibly can.
Such transformative .
Yeah , thanks for that story .
So what's now , can I move into your dark experience ?
And let's start from the beginning .
And you have been here for more than you .
You want to be a second europe .
I arrived in january twenty twenty , which was just two months before the world health organization and declared south korea too , in the spirit of it , to have a kind of ascended to pandemic .
So what was the course of events that got you ?
Your job here is an it ULprogram manager .
This is a manager in the information innovation offers one of darkness , executive offices .
And then what was it like ?
Get hearing and just very shortly after , you know , this sort of being this covered status.
Well , i've been a performer , which is the dark of violence for somebody who who executes on the program .
I've been a performer and PIfor daughter for about twenty years on and off through that period of time .
And some of the people like work with headband , explorer managers and another people who I formed good friendships with went off to become program managers , a deputy of structures and obstructors .
So I had a good long affiliation with dark , but doing research , working with the PMto develop new program , ideas and alike .
And it was coming to dark with something I always wanted to do , but I needed to wait for the right time in my career .
I wanted to be sure my son had graduated from college .
I wanted to to achieve certain milestones and also get some people in place at my old employer to make sure that the research could carry out .
And I also wanted to have the right set of ideas for programs I didn't show and went around for a year trying to come up with an idea for a program .
So I had my low basket of program ideas , and I came in the door .
I was all excited .
I started up .
And part of the reason for coming to dark days .
There are several neat things that dark program managers get to do one they get to talk with other people who are , who are in the organization and get their ideas and get them completely unfiltered .
But the other one is , you can tap into researchers all across the globe .
You call up and say , hi , I am from DARPA , and I was wondering what you were thinking about something .
And usually the conversation will run far longer than you ever anticipated , or you ever even planned .
But you're sorry , when it's over , i've been able to talk with a cow attack at my tea , and they'll call back with another idea afterwards .
That is unbelievably exciting .
And for someone having a kind of access is the great destination when I could ever hope for the other big piece about this is you get to go see their lab , and you got to go see stuff happening .
And as you can guess , from being a pilot , from being a ham radio operator , i'd love to touch the technology .
I love to play with that .
I love to do things .
And so two months after I arrive , I cannot go see the lab anymore , and I can't see my coworkers , because it will doing our part to trying , and it be safe and keep other people safe .
And so it was a little bit maddening .
You know , it's sort of like going to a giant technological toy store , but you can only see through the windows.
What's there ?
And it says clothes indefinitely.
Exactly that has been my single big frustration since coming here is I cannot go as fast as the organization normally would let me go .
And i'm seeing a substantial difference with the real.
我不能。
Boys are exciting .
They are interesting to hear , just in the the kind of specific laws that a program manager we can experience in a , in a situation like copyright .
I mean , cooper just brought a thousand million different kinds of losses .
So interesting to hear you express the specific sort of loss that program just loves to be miss the performance of researchers working with you need to be private .
That connection .
Let's now talk about your , the programs that you run , one of them , you develop from scratch and just got the green light will be talking a little bit about that .
What started by talking about one of the programs , jewellery , heritage .
So this was called search late that had been up and running for about a year or more before you check it over from an outgoing program .
Manager is often that often happens the end of the course between program .
So in brief , what absent capability was the importance for the program .
What is the invasion and pointed at this point , and what is it said?
First , I want to comment on the idea of the hand off from one program manager to another .
I was extremely lucky in that I knew the PM , who quite well , who I was taking over from .
And so , and I was bad .
Jonathan smith , james , and he , he has been a visionary in the communications area for a number of years .
I, Iwant to have long double gamest tell you that , but he really does tend to lead in the in the digital networking area , and so is very nice .
I had an understanding of his vision going forward , and I was able to wrap some of my own , my own experiences inside of tokyo to be able to to bring it forward .
So it certainly , yes , he is evolved into is a need solution to a very thorny problem .
And one of the things that I think many people listening to this experience of recovery was live on zoom or life on teams , and occasionally really will have the all I can see your pictures breaking up .
It's getting jealous .
The one of the reasons that this occurs are actually doesn't occur all the time is because of a service on networks called QOSor quality , which allows certain streams of data that are very time critical to be given priority , or to have their cheater , or the variability in a packet delivery reduced , and that allows for good video , good audio .
And if you're doing things like transferring a file or uploading a new version of your system or book , transferring a thousand pictures from your vacation , those can have a little bit of general .
They can have a little bit of bouncing back and forth , but also , fortunately , people are also starting to become more security country .
What that means is they're traffic where the data coming in and out of their houses or another businesses is wrapped in an incredible group .
And what this does is , it prevents the networks from really understanding what the traffic is that they're carrying .
So it'll see upstanding , you .
All the pictures of my .
It was also having a phone conversation over the same network connection .
It's all equipped it .
So therefore our voice gets the same priority as the picture of the fish record , not particularly useful .
So with such like those is one of the things inside the search light is that it's able to understand what those traffic clothes are , even though they are increased , and it lets the network provide priority , and I need to be very careful in explaining how this technology works .
It can understand with the flowers it cannot underscore , cannot be see what the flow is carrying , right or not , examine the content , not examining the content .
It is looking at the behavior of the floor and then moderating the movement of that flow based on the need for priority for that type of traffic .
So what it does is it preserves privacy .
It preserves confident reality , but it also preserves the flow improvement capabilities of the network , so that is really a new way of doing it .
And the other thing that it does is , it allows for moderating other traffic flows , slowing the loading of the fish pictures of access so it can be done not directly in the path .
So it gives carriers a lot more flexibility to use the band with that they have .
And as we saw a journey of it , managing a band with is important mechanism for allowing us to cope with problems .
And the game goes back to how can communications be improved or moderated to make people life better?
If we register to give people a concrete sense of what this technology delivers , I say it fulfills the vision that you had .
The previous program manager had , maybe the access to reach these metrics .
But how does it make life better for either , you know , a civilian , or perhaps in it is offensive.
In any place where there is , let's bend with them could potentially be used .
It provides a better mechanism for sharing APP .
So we get that hi priority gets the high priority .
So i'll use the home example on this , both my wife and I working hard during coffee , both on zoom calls .
I am also downloading a copy of the operating system .
I had to stop downloading the copy of the operating system because I consumed all of the coming into the house , just doing that , that file transfer , if I had a certified enabled system , I wouldn't even thought about it .
Calls would have gone through without any problem .
They would not have been dropped .
They would not have been jealousy or blocky .
And my operating system copy my copy of the would have arrived a minute and half later .
Then it , then the otherwise would have .
So that's an example of how it can make things better .
Another example is uh in telemedicine eye .
And this is important to both do d and civil , because we can get the medical personnel into the field .
Words needed at all time .
So telemedicine is a very important mechanism for first round of care to everyone have no field .
It means that if somebody is downloading a minute manual for truck , it's not , it'll take a little bit longer to get there , but the telemedicine session goes on on in a rapid .
So that's another example of it.
Right you now cannot be , want to be in the middle of either a procedure or giving instructions for seizure .
And you freeze , and then you leave people on the other end wondering what they should do in medical situation.
Exactly , you don't want the media to be seen and be certain too , and then just died.
So now let's move on to another program that you're inherited in this one , actually , really , I think , will be relevant .
Many people who buying more and more internet connected technologies , which is scheduled when you think of all of these things , they are collectively known as the internet of things i'm referring to the program called configuration , security or concept for short , had its beginnings in the twenty seventeen , twenty eighteen time frame .
You took the pattern in twenty twenty again , soon after you start suddenly , unlike many program managers , you , you are shepherding two programs and certainly thinking about the third one that will talk about just a little bit .
So some of this technology already is getting adopted in places as the USnavy and also the federal railroad administration , on other places .
Before we talk about the program in some detail , i'd like just to hear what your definition is of internet things.
Internet of things has a whole bunch of different conditions to it .
In my household .
I have a internet connected rabbits and include internet connected piggy bank , as well as weather stations .
As a matter of fact , several hundred devices are sitting on my home.
Okay , now you don't want to ask the interruption of talking about the definition here , but you just have to explain what is an internet connected rabbit.
This is something called the neighbor's technique out of friends .
It has years that vehicle back and forth .
And right now , all the servers around by volunteers around the world .
But it was a very , very early incentive of what would be something like the amazon legs , and it now evolves too , basically telling you things like you look really good today , or that it's nervous , and people have made , nevertheless attack or*****ras with several hundred of these things .
My son found it when he was studying overseas and and brought it back , and it's become part of a petting zoo of internet of things , devices.
Okay , so I no longer have a very longer animal in mind when you say that , and you will clarify it .
Sometimes it seems a little bit in some homework in character , though you always be so you do have animals in your life.
And and I actually have an internet of things behalf .
I get to limit me back from the behalf that helps me manage and understand .
And health bees are doing .
I can take the temperature of the humidity and away the hive remotely , which gives me some indication , is to changes in the amount of brutal , the amount of money.
Okay , so you are richly connected through various internet of things in your own personal life .
In some ways , you already define maybe what you need to do .
Things is that I didn't rub to you so finish that definition , then talk about concert.
So internet of things is when mechanical or or cyber activators and sensors are connected to the , to the internet versus people .
So we have an internet .
We have a worldwide web , which connects people , internet of things , connects the stuff that were working with , and part of the challenges with doing is these are usually traditionally .
They've been very traditionally ten years .
They're in very simple low , and I had a connected thermostat .
I found out when I was writing software to control the house to energy management , the house that if you asked what temperature more than a few times a minute , you deplete the capacitor that was used to parrot , and it would just give you garbage information back .
So these are dead , very , very simple devices .
And as such , don't have very much protection building to them , so they have to be protected , the networks that they are on have to protect them .
They have to be set in a way that is useful , but not in a way that can be used .
So not as a way that somebody could go in caused my hot water heater to explode , or cause my furnace to shut down , or in industrial setting , cause a certain agreement to be put into a foot supply that shouldn't be .
There should be there in that volume .
So how do you protect these devices that starts to become a really interesting thing ?
Interesting question , and it's also not just preventing them from doing something malicious , but they also can be used as a launch point for another attack .
So if my thermostat not jury brought thermostat , but somebody can connect , and then once they are connected to the thermos that get to all the other devices in my house , that becomes a real issue , because everything on the normally one thinks oil trust that a little bit more than something on the outside , but that may not necessarily be the case .
You can have an insider attack from an internet things device .
So what concept attempts to do is let you use my house as an example hundred plus .
All of them , slightly different , all of them , a little eye ball and a number of rounders , a number of modems to connect all these things up .
How can you configure them in such a way that they will be secure , but they will still work .
And so what concept does is it goes from a human riddle , human britain set of documents that specify how you want to do security .
Francis , if you come to my house , the rule would be , that would be written down , would be your allowed on the gas network .
But i'm allowed on the internal network to make sure that all the access points around the house are configured correctly to do that .
So concept will read documents .
It'll look at the diagrams , look at the drawings of the network and digest them and figure out all these are what the security requirements are .
No little girl is that for the , and it will read the manuals , and this is something I know very few people ever do .
The manual is always something that comes .
You look at it .
This is recycle above , and it's gone .
It concept , what , sit down and read the manuals , figure out what the configurations are based on what the requirements were .
And then it will put play them directly to the.
To the device .
Okay , just let me stop you for me .
And so when you say the concept will read the menu , so it is interesting information .
I presume these are probably identifies that I would like to do some electronic form of of the kind of paper manuals that I have a huge photo of .
And you're right , I didn't read them , but is that how exactly , it just needs to read the PDF , read the PDF.
Read the pdas , and it can read images in the PDF .
So if you can get something skiing in the end , in its in entertaining wish , it will make an attempt to read it .
It doesn't always get it right , and because of that , it will also explain why it can figure something the way it has .
So you get a human riddled document that comes out .
I set up a gas network , because guests need to be on the gasoline at work .
So I, Ican read this .
It's not .
It is not .
It is not hemingway .
It is very much computer generated text , but it is completely reasonable and understandable , and explains why the system elected to configure in the way that it did .
It is really , really cool .
And given that french students today , a variety engine is a connected piece of the internet , its its performance is being monitored .
It's part of the positive train control system .
It is out there getting it .
Configure properly is , is a real challenge and are providing tools to athens is a um same thing you for the navy , a modern naval vessel has thousands of computers on it would be really nice if they were configured in a way , according to guidance that also made them useful .
And the final stabbed concept is when the ship comes back , it can be read , and we can see why the changes occurred , and those can then either be undone or controlled into best practice and incorporated into the next round .
So that's.
Concept in natural , right , and due excellent vision , some of the tools and protocols and practices coming out of concept to be available , said to a whole manner , in addition , because you are , as you are speaking , it became clear to me that you are internet of things in a military setting .
Clearly , there are security concerns there and then , and so consequently , aboriginal there , but the threat space , the vulnerability space is really everywhere , because we can have a railroad system attacked through the internet of things , portals , for example , that that becomes the securities , but as well.
Well , for me , the most exciting trend coming out of concept is one of the performers , and I won't steal their press release under , but they are looking at two product roles for one , which would do automatic configuration of docker containers for virtual machines and moving virtual machines .
And the second is to do automatic configuration of the windows registry , and they're seeing of a strong market and providing this to small and medium sized enterprises as a as a commercial lawfully .
So the answer is , if , if you look , you'll probably see this technology available in a shrink wrapped or download of forms in a year or so , and it should make an difference in and how we can do security and buy small and medium enterprise that also include households that have several hundred internet things.
Quartering that that , and you did you see the example of a inner neighborhood just before , so I on its way , or maybe already has made some transitions into the services.
We're in some clouds right now to understand behavior and to understand reliability , because we don't wanted to play something and then have it blown up .
But we are , we're actually an exercise as we speak.
To see how this overall , okay , i'm sure you are excited to see you the results of those and learn lessons from those that you can take the programme .
I don't know it for a learning .
I don't know how much more time is available for the program .
At this point , we have about six months to six month we have been considered .
And air .
Sounds like if you got some real transitions that you'll be , which they say , that's kind of the trophy for programs is when the technology comes out in action to get sort of views operationally or with its points , companies or something of that kind of those are all kind of positive results .
Actually , an appointment , though , even even failures for doubt , our lessons and we learn from .
So uh , you know , successes and negatively is always good.
And and I just like to comment , there was a system called bomber ring that was a shoulder detection system .
My former employer had developed you and had developed .
It went to be shellfire because it wasn't a need after it was initially developed .
They're suddenly became a great need for it , and it was able to be filled within ninety days because the technology had been ahead of time .
Then when the time came , it was able to be brought out and run.
There are european , european great example , you know , just about how context is all important as to whether or technology makes sense or not at a so fascinating to share that .
thanks .
So now let's talk about one more program , though .
I guess this is sort of still in the innovation phase , in the sense that is just been approved .
You have been received proposals from performers , which is to say the research results will in my work on this .
You call this one learning , interested in control project or a link for short from the little , I know about a sense of director developed a kind of machine learning account of our official intelligence that will enable military assets , whether it was a ground vehicle weapons system to effectively self discover relevant capabilities it might actually have in the context in which it is placed , even though the original designers and might not afford of that .
Initially , I don't know from getting that right .
So I wanted to correct me farming , and this gave me a sense of what you hope to ultimately deliver with this program.
It's actually a little bit broader , in some senses .
It , because it's looking beyond just systems , because there are all for a lot of commercial systems that are needed by the us military , but also infrastructure resilience , operational resilience and ugly addressing climate change are incredibly important issues that were trying to prevent strategic.
God coming to the coming to the documentation right there.
And the idea behind link is systems live a long time , and they're living longer and longer and longer .
If you look at military vehicles , they have lifespans of thirty to fifty years .
Some of the aircraft will have lives of hundred years .
You look at private vehicles .
There are on the road much longer than they have been , and it's because they are good , usable systems through that period .
If one hazard system and lets lets the dream take a pickup truck is an example .
Take a pick up truck .
You put a tunnel and fifty gallon water tank on the back of it and errors not going to do too great with that water can be filled , the water tank paying empty oats can be fine with the water tank half full .
It's unbelievably dangerous.
你是哪个部门？
Thank you for writing。
Exactly exactly .
And so the idea is a modern pickup truck has a platform sensors in a several hundred of them .
It also has a collection of relatively powerful computer sitting in slideshow .
And so the idea is the system is designed , and it's exclusively designed before leaves the factory to encounter the circumstances that are limited in the users handbook , and unlike network configuration manuals , I know everyone reads there , ultimately , a hamburger and nervously did cover to cover .
Where is the fuse ?
That's the first time somebody will open it .
Or where is the tire jack ?
So the idea is cars are modified trucks and modify the laws are different .
Everything is different over the life of the car or over the life of the truck and the ideas to have the control system adapt in correct itself to keep , to keep on going .
And there is a great deal .
Skepticism is to how this actually could work .
But there's , i'll tell you a story of an existence proof that stunned me when I thought there are some researchers who are an imperial college london .
And again , this is the beauty of being a dark PM .
You can call them up and say , hi , can I talk to you , and they will help me talk to , and they were doing some work with hacks upon robots where they would break a leg .
They did naturally break .
It takes turn off the power to it .
And with these old hacks apart , they would sit there and kind of wrapped around for a minute or two , and suddenly they be up and hoping along on just a couple of lakes and be almost as movable as they were before him .
because they, 我想看小猪佩奇第一季的综艺节目有什么好看的电视剧，有什么好看的电视剧吗？
我想要一个美人鱼公主裙子。
And that small child is taking a backpack to school , and they want to take everything they have in the backpack .
They put it on , and they'll stick around the little bit in front , and then they will get their footing .
And thereafter the race , that's what we're trying to get machines to do is to do that same , learning that that small child does when they take on the noon and heavy load and have them be able to make newer , safely , efficiently in a useful way , just by using what they have internally not having to go to a big cloud server , not to have to have some engineer .
We do the design , but rather have them customized how they react to something and handle off .
So that's the idea behind the real benefit that i'm seeing behind .
That is by allowing systems to operate much longer , the energy requirements to manufacturers .
These systems goes down dramatically .
And so that's what i'm saying .
One of the big benefits of.
Oh , maybe one of the million solutions we need for mitigating climate change , and it is effective .
There's also a little thing that I see you with this program and configuration security , in the sense that it seems like you like you are out to help the anonymity world and the , the world of things , world of technologies , whether we're talking about vehicles , but also all like china technology census , the IOT technology .
You want them to be able to learn about themselves and make themselves better , more given.
Exactly right , and a big part of this also comes from growing and reading the golden age of science fiction .
Highline of the camp campbell as a clark , where there was an internal hopelessness that technology could be bent to do good .
And that's really what IIstill am trying to do that .
And if I can have IOT systems internalize doing good stuff , I, Ithink it would just be.
Better place , right ?
Well , jail .
I want you to succeed at that .
And this is a sexy , cool secretary .
To another question I have .
And this is just coming from the forty summer pattern titles of that was some really interesting reading .
So we can talk about all those , obviously , but , but one is certainly just reflect that you can help yourself .
You are an inventor of you been doing in all kinds of ways .
Now you do with your dog .
Are there any of those patterns that just really stand out for you either , because they were most rewarding .
You think the technology , we're a good idea that there would be .
It would do the most good as we are just talking about yet , or just been doing .
It fascinates you for some reason.
Too , that just made me happy when they , when they were all metrics .
So go with those aren't so and dark is all about metrics .
So the , the first one originally had a working title of tooth and come on , or two towns , and um at the time I was involved with the technology board for the natural federation of the blind .
And there was a real question of how electric vehicles , the tournaments vehicles to affect the blind as they navigate throughout a city .
In some respect , economic vehicles would be marvelous .
The black and white , that is just a wonderful thing , but the other side of it is that it was concerned that electric vehicles and hybrid vehicles would sneak up on people .
They wouldn't hear them , and they would cause accidents .
And I noticed this myself , I was driving a hybrid hybrid in the parking lot .
And if you have a car with engine running , people will just transplant walk to the side .
But with the hybrid , they will just keep walking in the center .
And you don't want to blow your heart .
You don't want to be the guy who blows his orange of pedestrian .
And I think it was not right .
And so what I was thinking was , why not a gentle cough .
You know , something .
We're somebody know .
Excuse me , you know , so they know your hair .
And that is that what , why not ?
This was at the time of download of all rain tones .
I thought why I have tones that you can double .
And I went ahead and worked up the system .
The pen was filed , and I very pleased that many states now require supplemental alert exactly to protect those who are sighting paired .
And you're also around the globe .
And because of that , that patterns actually found real .
So that was , that was a fun one.
Sounds like a good technology to get out there .
Oh , I will have patched you here for more time than your party .
Future can be set down here with me .
So I just want to ask you , is there are question that didn't come up .
There's anything that didn't come up to you think , would be eventually.
我是。
What is the thing that worries me the most wonderful here is that we have a clock that is running every dark program manager has a date on their bed .
And that is our final day here , and we feel an incredible urgency to get things done before that date and covered , really make me feel more because I.
Didn't want to lose time .
That is actually one of the most interesting institutional characteristics of dark to me .
And it is that you come in here .
We all do right with that cell by date , as a , you hear the open over again , how that does turn up that dialogue , urgency and is thought to be one of the reasons why darker has such a track record of producing so much so interesting to bring that up .
What out of time may you and your research performers , those who let us to say , the researchers were working on your programs .
May you all succeed and maybe learn much from that work .
Thanks for being with me , my pleasure and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dark thanks also to TOM shortage for his partnership in producing this program .