Stealth technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand on the most operation technology , is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window until dark is cool of program managers .
Their job to we define what is my name is Ivan Amato  , and I'm  your DARPA host today , I am pleased to be talking with that .
Your strategic brought us in twenty eighteen .
The program manager in the agencies , information innovation office in twenty eighteen , he brings in the agency , what you might think of as a six cents for the surnamed of a deeply hidden security vulnerabilities in the oceans of software and the communications practices underlying our civilian and military technologies and systems .
Private coming to dark .
But surgery had been at darkness college , beginning in two thousand as a post doctoral research associate , and most recently as research associate professor in the computer science department , he began his professional career at BBNtechnologies where he worked on natural language processing .
I find that professional element fascinating because the BBMdark connections spend back to one thousand nine hundred and sixty when the two work together on some of the foundations of back to circuit , he received his undergraduate education at the moscow institute of physics and technology and earn his PHTand mathematics from northeastern .
He has published over one hundred technical papers , and his research has received several awards , including the twenty twelve black hat pony award for most innovative research .
That word pony award is a christchurch , one that recognizes achievements of security researchers and security community .
Doctors say *** practice , thanks for making some time to talk with me today about your money and very efforts to increase every safety in the paralysis , cyber domains that we are in .
Merson , thank you for .
Thank you for having hearing .
Let's start with the original story of your interests in computer science and cyber security .
I think one of the things that fascinate the public about scientists and engineers is just where there are sort of in some ways , hybrid specialized interests come from .
So did you grow up in a household ?
Did you encounter an engaging professor at the mask going to do the physics and technology ?
Where did you interest come from?
Oh , computers were a miracle .
I grow up on the soviet union , and we would get a slow trick of imported technology , which is so wonderfully contrasted with the rest of life .
They were something from the future .
And so even though the technology that was available to a school student was perhaps decade behind , it was never less a miracle , and it had an enormous attraction over the executives myself , we wanted to know how it worked , and we wanted to be able to program something like those games that we saw on those computer screens .
And so we did , but as I was growing up in the soviet union , you could see the slow progression of technology being important from the rest , and we were left behind by some people listening ten to fifteen years .
There was a bit of luck in that , because in my age , I go to see the very basics of computing , starting with programming micro calculators , where my appears in the west might have seen , might have been already seen IBMPCXT, which was an incredible miracle of technology.
And circuit just thought the listeners have a sense of timing here .
You say that you , you really encountered computers for the first time when you run middle school .
So what?
But those actually , but we're talking nineteen , seventy eight , ninety and seventies , early , nineteen eighties.
Okay , thank you .
So took your attack or write on back.
So making computers do things was a huge time , think , because where people in california might have had access to storage devices and floppies and food , we actually had to retire our texas instruments .
Kind of a clown APP firms .
Still , it was an incredibly magical experience , but that was my introduction to computers .
My introduction to security came when I was a great student at nothing strong working on my degree , mathematics and lyrics was exploding on the scene .
Everyone wanted to run a little .
The internet was still the wonderful place where you met .
Like minded kicks up wasn't anything else .
And so I set up my LINUX server .
I followed every bit of how to instructions , and it worked , and I was happy .
And then in about two weeks , that sir was compromised and taken over , and I found it a serving up .
I don't know music .
I could not quite understand what pieces of a game are probably pirated , that I knew nothing about .
It got to , as the sea was at the time , a pond compromise taken over as it happened with many university computers in the nineteenth , and I wanted to know how I did everything by the book .
I thought I couldn't stand .
The windows programs were written by that time I was already competent .
She programmer , I thought , and I thought I understood that environment and those programs.
Turned out I did not , and the hackers did right .
So you had a very personal experience with personal violation showing up a right at your own computer station that really got you hooked and concerned about these security issues.
I probably all who ever did that a year.
Right , so now you wanna go find out who that person is and shake their hand , because they essentially were central in the rest of the project will be a career.
I might say that , and so I went down the rabbit hole of a hacking and computer security , rather than being.
One of the quick question just cause i'm serious in the timing of in your educational , professional development and world history .
You got to undergraduate degree in massacre , and then you got your graduate degree north system .
So can you tell me , how is it that you made the transition from the then soviet union than two other states?
I saw the late soviet union .
I grew up with the totally during society that it was , and I wanted out at the time , it was nearly impossible to do in any legal fashion .
But luckily , the soviet power was collapsing .
It collapsed between nineteen ninety one and ninety , ninety three , and so I could , in fact , go out and study if an american university would take me and several offered .
And so I left quite a few people were more enthusiastic about the prospects of persevere , brush and persuade states , unfortunately , they were proven wrong.
All right , well , their losses are our game .
So happy that you did actually make it out and clearly embrace the opportunities that were here .
So get after getting your degrees where you watch first bbm , then you sack waiting to academic darkness where you build the computer science and security program that included the what you have described as a in a coroner called hidden curriculum , this one derived from the mindset and innovations of the hacker community , which is sounds fascinating to bring that account of a computer science program and necessary .
I think the right thing to do surely .
So please talk about how these professional experiences contributes to your approach now desirable security , and how they lead to your job at dark.
Starting in the twenty eighteen , I am very grateful to darkness for letting me do this for taking me on as a research of shoot on one of their cybersecurity efforts .
I started with a machine learning application of a cyber security .
But by that time , I was already interested in how an explanation worked , how exploits were written , how vulnerabilities were discovered and are being in the limitation by education .
I wanted to systematize this .
So I started showing up at the helper conventions , such as the afghan , and what I realized very soon was that there was a curricular there , which the community came up with .
It was distributed and split up between various minds and groups .
But the war , a consistent sets of things that newcomers learned , and even though they had some interaction with how we took computer science and computer programming in kenya , they were not quite the same .
And many aspects are they actually , when deeper on how things worked , and so I started assistant advice in this discipline , which I maintained it has become as of academically nineties .
And I tried to extract that hidden curriculum , and I had from my supervisors of darkness doing that , and I have support to bring in students to the computer hacking conferences and then exposing them to the sydney curriculum .
And it turned out that it translated to impressive undergraded and then graduate additional organizations , all in all , I find that this.
right ?
Well , it causes not done because of innovation going on , both in those were seeking new and more powerful exploits , and those who are worried about that and trying to to come up with canada measures and defenses against that and everybody to be brilliant thoughts , kind of an amazing dynamic going on .
So now , before we talk about your programs , and I think it's scared of a gabriel's out of listeners who might not know about some of the wayne and wait and installed the software we use , and perhaps how they are even contributing to some of the hazards , and in my practices that they engage in the , in , I really want to talk about the way you think about an engaged cyber space in the infrastructure .
We shouldn't be gone to get into that a little bit , but you can have looked over your programs and really try understand where you are coming from , in which you are trying to achieve .
As I looked over your darkness , college page , your lab page , I sort of met a fortune to my mind about you , which is , and maybe one way of thinking about it .
All of us .
Most of us are drivers , and we weren't after driving , we're paying attention to the various hazards of the road in our traditional things .
What's happening with the street lights ?
Are we going to be able to make it through that are their children on the side of the road ?
You know , what's the weather is .
It looks like there's about to be a downpour .
right ?
All of us sort of have a sense of these hazards are their parties coming in the condition of the road .
And so yeah , I imagine that you are looking at the info sphere , kind of driving through that world with that same kind of heads up view on these kind of obvious hazard .
But more than that , I kind of imagine you having almost the sixth sense in being able to see even what might be hidden .
Has , you know , let's say , there's a single , and it's just now , as i'm coming upon it about to open up with my cars going to go in there , something that you could not see from the surface , but somehow you can see through the road .
And you see that single about to start , I get the feeling you have that six cents in the information technology and the cyber spirit to see what we really need to worry about .
Okay , that's me terribly describing your mind .
You know , your mind better than me .
Talk to me about that cognitive framework that you bring in to this.
Rich world that we live in an extra vision of vulnerability is a lot to claim .
I certainly do not claim that what I could claim is a lot of transparency and reluctant using some technology that are not as dependable or as simple as they could be .
I am the person with no personal smart phone .
I am the person who , before engaging with the website tries to see what the website looks like with all the executable bids , a javascript , disabled , disabled , and mostly it looks like nothing , which is too bad .
Because for most of those websites , and for most of those tasks that I want to complete on them , they have no business executing code on my computer and then pulling code from their associates , maybe commercial advertising or analysis associates , and then executing their code on my computer .
And then the coach from their associates as well.
So you consider these all to be almost like nested vulnerabilities .
They are in.
One of the best examples of this is probably the thing that everyone uses every day , the web beneath email .
But when I look at the web browser , I see a for denying the user the understanding of where those are graphic elements in the email were in the overall pain of the browser up come from or where they eat if you click on them , it is the brother's goal to simultaneously blamed all of the content and high directions .
But at the same time , it doesn't let me see what my next action would actually bring about .
Now for me , I can second guess this for a typical user of such a webmail .
This is the tool order .
Imagine we make our trust decisions and based on the province of what we hear and see them directly .
And here we were denied any visual cues or inquiry tool to that province .
Speaking of a portal , this is a very slow process , but some people could see that bottom ten years ago , it was actually hit one of my safe documents deals with another search photo are peaceful of electronic documents that we all exchange , and we are to not click on if we can't really verify where it came from .
But then , of course , see the previous point about to have a male most of the time you are denied any he's to wear .
It actually came from .
But of course , it is our job to click on those documents .
Read them , someone else , any ambiguity in the description of these formats is in security , and that insecurity will hit us ten years or or five years from now , from all from when it was introduced , people might say , well , it is okay .
We have entire virus programs .
We can check , and we have firewalls , and we have other devices that could just check for malaysia .
However , it's typical because of the format , ambiguities for all the readers and and temperatures of electronic documents to disagree about what those documents .
Actually , it's been a hacker's sport to make a file like a PDF document appear differently in different views .
It will simply use a little different to the entire virus or an application firewall .
And so if you can't really agree with all your electronic helps and applications want what is actually in the document , what better way to hide malaysia ?
And again , this is something that fundamental computer science can tell you that will result at in those .
But as we call the passing different shows of those data formats and.
And those documents , i'm glad that you have become time to talk about your programs .
You started with safe documents .
Except that's one of the easier ones of years to say one of the other easier ones is assured .
Micro patching or APP .
I'm actually just gonna read all of the dark names because they are so darker in the darkness known for its names and acronyms just for listeners .
And then we're not gonna acceptably really go through each one , because we would be here for quite a long time .
I would love to , but we can have a five hour particles .
We lose everybody , but let me just read them because they are beautifully multiple .
And they gave some sense of what you are up to .
So here we go , artificial intelligence , medications of emergent execution , or amy AIMEverify , security and performance enhancement of large legacy software or vegetables recovery of symbolic mathematics from cold or three hybrid AI to protect integrity of open source code .
And we will , he already mentioned safeguards and short micro patching , and there's even one more .
I think this is the newest one .
I got approval is called , and that's short for hardening development to change against emergent execution engines .
What a mouth for that is , it sounds like quite an ambitious set of programs too in the queensland vulnerabilities , as we been talking about , but since we can't really go into any depth with these , certainly all of maybe you can pick and choose and sort of walk through your programs you spend , you know , as little or as much times you want on this one , or that it just to give us a sense of what , in fact , you are worried about .
And what kinds of problems you're trying to solve , all the interests of increasing security for our war fighters are also for all the civilians.
Certainly , and I would borrow a phrase from one of the famous security researchers , who are the point of our profession , is making that we could finally trust .
Which , of course , hurricanes to the fact that we cannot trust computers as we make them now .
But , and who , who said that , who is that famous person ?
It is a phillips liner , a research from berlin .
Now we cannot trust computers rebuild today , and we can not trust software rebuilt today .
And part of the reason is , even if we build them exactly the specification .
And even if there is no ambiguity , but all the morsel , if there raised some immigration in that a specific issue , we end up building what we intend , and something else that something else turns to be a lot friendly to the attackers , to the exploiters .
Then we've ever intended to be .
It's as if packaged with your chinese work station for yours .
Server is the kid for exploiting that server .
And this is what I refer to as emergent execution uh , emergent properties of computing systems , properties that we never met them to have needed the hardware and other software , not the combination .
There are all , but yet they emerge , and they allow the to reprogramme computers , reuse existing , while debugged pieces are software before attack purposes .
And this is the aspect of the computers that I would like to reduce , mitigate and eliminate where possible.
Right , so maybe I can ask you to take that another level further .
We have given us kind of the helicopter view .
And then your programs .
I imagine our design to go after a specific categories of vulnerabilities .
So maybe just talk about two of the ones that may be our particular interest in reports.
So here is , a are likely to find save dogs or save documents .
Looks at the information interchange formats , the formats in which data arises at our computers and arrives at our software , and will also sometimes explain them .
Now , how do we build code that can safely intact a data that might be hostile or might have been manipulated ?
How do we make software that agrees on what is in the message between the various computing components that are involved in the the flow of our email of our documents ?
How do we , as we say , a pass , the data security , or how do we intake data security ?
This is a safe , and then , of course , now , that we found some vulnerabilities or ambiguities , we want to fix those vulnerabilities in the date , and very typically , those vulnerabilities are like a single check on the input date that was assumed was down , but was actually never done by the actual software doing the data and take the passer .
So how do we patch ?
Those usually is a simple check , but the problem with a simple change to any binary soccer is that you have to make sure that you are not destroying something else .
You are not damaging the design function , nationality of your device and the methods and tools for sharing.
I just have to say , so , what's fascinating about that description to me is that there is a parallel in genetic engineering .
And well , if you're going to make a change , even a very tiny point , change , changing one of me know accident approaching , or or just one DNA nuclear tide , sometimes that will have a fact , another proteins that you never thought would be involved , given your initial intention .
So it's kind of the same way , right , apache going into legacy software .
You'll , you're after , you know , I fix your channel and create security , but you don't .
Maybe there is another set of changes that are delicious.
That you would would regret , I said , well , each and every one of us , we are computing devices besides , are the things .
So this is a very valid technology .
And then , of course , you might want to check how you could add components or add features to a system without disrupting it .
And this is.
Device spouse program .
So let me just go to one that gets back to your .
I would say earlier interest , you know , your interests as a mathematician is the recovery of symbolic mathematics from code .
So this is sort of working backwards .
It sounds like from the software , two mathematical formulations that the heart of what the programmer was trying to do .
Now , why is this an important ability I.
It is extremely important when you encounter legacy software as you rely more , as we all rely more and more on algorithms controlling our power , power , medical devices and or even our cards , you want to make sure that the intended algorithm are with the engineer planned to put in that device is actually what the device does .
So connecting back the , buying the reform of software to the symbolic form of mechanics that the software and close , it is an extremely important step in making sure that our devices are trust worthy .
Very often , you don't have the source code in legacy software , the company that may , the thing the device went out of business , or it might not have focused on out of business , but it actually lost the source code .
This has happened to companies begin small .
What would like to do is still be answer the question of does this books do , what does what was intended to do , and what was it in control engineering terms?
Interesting question comes to mind now that as you work backwards from software source of the original mathematical formulations and algorithms , does that uniquely to one mathematical formulation was impossible that you , you might have several .
And then you still left with the question of what was the actual original intent in the regional mathematical formulation?
You certainly end up with the several and an effect who continue , because there are many different ways to write down the same as medical formula , and many more to encourage that formula in code .
And of course , not all called a consumer mathematical formulas , but for the well engineering systems , for the so called control processes that control things such as engines or generators .
There is a volunteer symbolic mathematical theory of how they work , and we should be able to disturb , oh , that and cold .
This is , what do you mean?
Athens to the right , if , you know , this is something like embedded processors in the grade .
And there are certain other things you can bring into five candidate mathematical formulations , because you know what it should look like in this particular engineering category.
That's right .
This aims to help the subject .
Never experts .
This aims to put together the specialist in the binary and in the control algorithms.
Or control engineers , when you say binary , what do you mean?
The executable code , as a compiled form of it that finally goes into to the memory of the device on controllers and production.
Only getting started .
I could keep asking questions because what you do fascinates me , and I want to know more and more , but i'm excited and suggest that listener to have the common tree takes to go to your program manager , where page on the , and then to take a chord themselves to get at least some additional taste of all of your programs .
Unless we come to the end of our time , you are and want to get into a couple of just bigger questions .
This is the innovation , ecosystem and technology and society types of what fascinates me about you is that you really have had experience in the three kind of major sectors .
We tend to think about in the innovation ecosystem , rise of you strategic career in industry and expanded you twenty years in academic at a darmon , and you might return to that at the end of your time here .
And then here you are doing government work at dark persons twenty eighteen .
So when you look at those three players , universities and industry and government in the overall innovation ecosystem , specifically when it comes to the to sort of cyber security technology , how do you see each of those?
Contributing it's a great question .
I would say that , of course , the industry looks to display product .
Academia explores new ideas and follows publishing a trends .
The role of dark has been to , at least in the success that I have seen has been to pursue things that could not be immediately made them to protect .
Or the interesting might not believe could be made into products and encourage that kind of exploration , when which you could not justify to your manager , to your shareholders as an industry worker.
You mean , in that case , because there is a sense that there is , there is too much risk to go ahead to do that responsibly in a business context .
But then , if dark comes in and has the benefit managers like you , who can have programs that demonstrate , take the risk down in certain areas , then a company might say , okay , let's take this to a finish line .
That's right now.
Whereas with the canadian , well , you may have heard the phrase of publisher , which means that and academic research or not to have a successful career or any career tool is expected to produce at least several years aimed at a difficult first tear conferences or journals .
Now , those have some idea of which research directions are promising and interesting , but these often fail to encourage significant parts of reality , including industrial reality , or even the parts of the industry , does not think about it has been behind a several diaper successes that have experienced personally to define a new .
Do you find a new trend and puts some are grand funding behind the trend in order to get a kitty meal to listen to .
Well , this is the need that you might be missing .
This is the cool film that might , with time create its own first tier publication value of journalism conferences .
And there are a blue dark has been greatly successful.
Thinking about this , what a great finish line , what a great result is a dark of which is to take a technology .
Neither take the risk down so that someone else will pick it up , the insert transition , but a military service or two industry for additional development , sometimes programs just segway to another program to build on what has accomplished in the prior work when you scanning your own mind , your programs and the many research performers were working on them who wanted to come to you now again , say , circle circuit .
Look what i've can you mention one or two of the maybe the more mature accomplishments that you think have a good chance of transition and becoming actual technologies in our life?
One of the things that really excites me , it is on the safe dog's program we've been working with the PDF association , which is an industry by the united , unites many stakeholders in the portable document format to produce a machine readable , unambiguous specification of the format of the former .
This is the first time i've ever that this has been attempted for a major format , with billions of documents out there .
And of course , you cannot reinvent it that format for that reason , because people would not take kindly to their documents being simply deemed in compliant and not opening .
But I think we are on our way to be forming how the standards process , the international standards process at the international standard organization , a deals with the information into change for months and how we might make our electronic documents much more trust worthy that we would not actually be told to not click on documents and could rely on computers to securely process the data that comes in a documents and communications in the many .
Sensor sheets that surround us.
Okay , and let you spend one more minute on this PDF example that you bring up , and so that listeners who might not be in this world of increasing security , reducing vulnerabilities as they interact with safety of documents .
What is the security game that you get by moving toward that kind of standardization that you just mentioned , and the , this MDUATINIget on the part of the platform on which showing up .
How does that increase their security directly?
Immediately remember the time of your training when I started to use any computing system , when you're told to never click on attachments from people , you do not trust what .
Why is that ?
It's because documents these days are not equivalent of a simple sheet of paper with some passive content that you can read or ignore it to each other .
They're sophisticated programs that interact with the soldiers on your computer , make it do things , trigger emergent properties .
Emergent are parts in that software that no one went there , no one intended to put there in the first place , and that we could locally really know as the exploit .
So when you talk to not click on documents , well , this is the part of the present that I would like to exclude from the future .
It'll take a lot of effort , but unambiguous definitions of what you expect to find there .
And what has been dying and what is expected .
I isn't a three.
Super helpful for for someone like me who sees that I don't click , I don't clicks .
Try to make that my practice .
But now I understand that that in some ways that are hedge against some creative person who might have found one of these emergent executable path with them into my computer.
Yeah , which are typically known as for the regulations.
But because we don't know all of the vulnerabilities that could be in there , the broad brush rock solution of not clicking on it sort of solved a lot of problems .
But you say , without that , that's not really good solution.
Yeah , actually doesn't work .
Whatever your job is , you're intended to read things .
Add them , send them on .
I don't think there is any professional exists that doesn't include some kind of form , feeling or meaning of reading , or any one of those attacks that do take electronic , so you can just not click.
So I often ask of my , my discussion leaders , who I presume our technologies , because here this is dark , right ?
I'm here is the question I, Iwould like to find out if there are technology is that you dreamed about when you were in middle school or later , this don't have to be dark for technologies at all .
But just , you know , when you just sort of look back in your wish for , you say , oh , that technology is just like , are there technologies like that for?
Of course , I mean ，I am the child of the space exploration edge , or they are attaining their up .
And so flying cars that can go to the moon , a rockets that teenagers could violate .
If you look back at some of those novels of highlights and others , that's what you see .
And we are getting some not the flying cars yet , but certainly spacecraft , and that cannot learn vertically , used to be straight.
Hi , I am .
So it was not right .
We do see that I have to say that the idea of millions of teenagers of piloting their own rocket is about the most frightening vulnerability I possibly can imagine , but maybe we can educate the teenagers to operate these things safely , but I just have the image ever I actually do kind of love .
One final question before I show you much to attitude for talking with me .
And that's just , is there something circuit that I should advance you that I did not worth there , just something else that sign your mind that you think would be a venture to our listeners.
If I could say one thing on the technology in general , it is that it is exciting .
But at the same time it brings large and unknown helier modes and vulnerabilities , getting too enthusiastic about technology to the point of mandating its use is hardly ever a great idea in my book , you can call me a technology or a combine technology technology , but a mandating of the use of any particular technology also means amendatory the use of the abilities that come with it .
And so any such decisions , any sessions users should be temporarily by the understanding that this is what happens.
right ?
And so one way I think about what you just said is that a question that has to be there in the technology development process is what could possibly go wrong , right ?
And that all we should be part of the practice that is sort of hygiene for.
That is true , but I would also take it further .
I would say that listening to rejectionists of any particular technology is underrated .
They might , in fact , be right in certain ways that a people more enthusiastic about the technologies might not have forced .
So we must do this question here.
I believe that balanced perspective of being excited in a technology license , but also having that sense of respect and ice wide open and caution and fear of unintended consequences that justified a little bit of a component , as well as you move forward .
So that's really , really interesting to hear .
So I get it out of time .
So let me just thank you for helping me understand a bit more about the cyber security and in security landscapes .
And I have to say , I am really hardened that people with your expertise in it tensions , which is to say , people exactly like you in particular , I am happy around the case .
It was just a real blast for me to talk to.
Thank you for having me and great to meet you.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from DARPA .
Thanks also , the time shortage for his partnership and producing this program , for more information about doctor circuit practice , the programs he and calling in the agency's information innovation office , run and many other breaks through technologies darker , is working on visit , darker , dark and for links that enable you to download this podcast .