[Music]
stealth technology the internet gps in
the palm of your hand autonomous
operation
technology is a driver of our times
since its founding in 1958 in the midst
of the cold war darpa the defense
advanced research projects agency has
been a driver of technology
welcome to voices from darpa a window
onto darpa's core of program managers
their job to redefine what is possible
my name is ivan amato and i'm your darpa
host today i am pleased to be talking
with dr gordon keeler gordon who knew he
wanted to be a scientist by the time he
was in second grade joined darpa as a
program manager in the agency's
microsystems technology office in 2017.
his work is all about exquisite control
and management of electrons and light
within device loaded chips and otherwise
compact systems that can do more
computing more sensing
more decision making more artificial
intelligence
in cheaper smaller lighter and more
energy efficient packages than any
technologies we have had in hand before
to me his deliverables represent a
pinnacle(顶峰) of the entire history of
technology prior to joining darpa gordon
spent 14 years at the department of
energy's sandia national laboratories in
albuquerque new mexico there he became
good friends with semiconductor lasers
modulators and detectors
nanophotonics and plasmonics phenomena
纳米光子学和等离子体现象
semiconductor materials and device physics
radio frequency and ultra fast optics
novel photonics materials and their
integration with existing platforms and
micro scale optoelectronic packaging
technologies
earning his first degree in physics in
Canada where he grew up Gordon in 2013
earned his phd in applied physics from
stanford university
along his career path gordon has
published more than 100 peer-reviewed
publications and has been granted
several patents in the field of
photonics Dr. Gordon Keeler thanks for
making some time to talk with me today
about your ongoing adventure in
technology development
- thanks Ivan it's
great to be here
- I always love to hear
about the origin story of a person's
interests and i think listeners do too
especially when uh those interests are
hyper-specialized in the eyes of most
people i mean i think we agree most
people probably never even heard the
term opto electronics uh you told me in
earlier correspondence that both your
father and mother got you going in the
science and engineering directions uh
that you would ultimately take so i'm
hoping you might share with us a little
bit about what it was like what kind of
encouragement you got in your childhood
household and then also what other
influences you think of when you might
explain why you think the way you do
think now
sure well i grew up in canada like you
mentioned in in a relatively small town
my parents really both loved exposing us
as kids to lots of different things so i
was busy you know doing sports and music
but i really loved academics my mom was
a teacher and a librarian and a nurse my
dad was a university physics professor
and so you know academics was sort of
really important in our family as far as
science
i really loved problem solving when i
was a kid and i also liked building
things
when i was little i used lego blocks and
as i got bigger i used meccano which
here we call erector set and so you know
tiny little uh nuts and bolts and
putting things together was sort of my
my specialty and really that's sort of
what my career looks like i i do a lot
of problem solving and building tiny
little things
yeah fascinating to think about the
erector sets which you know had
macroscopic parts and you could actually
manipulate them with your hands and and
when i think of the
the devices and the parts that you're
working with now on the micrometer and
smaller scales it's just kind of
astonishing
now you spent
14 years at
sandia you know one of our national labs
and i
would guess that
while there and maybe even before you
had heard about DARPA but uh i also do
like to share with listeners the how did
this particular program manager get to
darpa story and so what's that story for
you was it somebody you knew at darpa
did you in a sense let darpa know about
you and your interest how did you get
here
-  yeah you know it's a little bit of
all of those back when i was in grad
school i actually worked on on darpa
programs i guess that was my first
introduction but then i got to sandia i
worked on a lot of different
technologies in this
optical microsystem space and i was
there for like you said 14 years with my
wife who also
studied applied physics and did a lot of
building of small things i got a call
from the MTO microsystem technology
front office saying that the director
wanted to to talk to me and i thought
well that's interesting he's probably
looking for a reference for somebody
that i work with
who's looking to move to darpa
and
it turns out no actually they had seen
some of the work that i was doing and
they wanted to know if i wanted to come
to darpa which you know i was very
familiar with darpa but hadn't really
thought about coming to be a program
manager but you know given that
opportunity i thought about it really
hard really quick in fact we had to make
a decision pretty fast
and came out and interviewed and and
things things moved quick picked up the
family and moved out of new mexico and
came out to the east coast so i've been
at darpa since 2017. so that's a big
decision i mean one thing that always
amazes me about program managers
is that you know you come in knowing
that this is not
almost certainly not a lifelong
appointment you know in fact
you know one of the pieces of the secret
sauce one of the ingredients of the
secret sauce of the organization is that
you know you come in knowing that you're
just going to be here for three four
five years that sort of thing some
people do of course come back for second
tours of duty later but tell me just a
little bit about
you know why you had so much confidence
and sort of excitement about coming to
darpa that you were willing to leave a
place you'd been for 14 years and then
go to one where you might only be there
for a few years
yeah it's a great question i had no
doubt really in my mind darpa was was
clearly sort of the pinnacle of doing
innovative
scientific research and development and
leading the community to go do new
things that had always been my passion
and i didn't go into science and
technology for a a stable long-term
job at one place i wanted to make an
impact and darpa was clearly the way to
do that
what comes next we don't really know but
i feel like my life has been this series
of fortunate events that kind of stack
up and and i'm sure there'll be great
opportunities after i'm done here
well may that good fortune continue
so gordon now let's dive into your
portfolio of programs when i look at the
half dozen or so of the programs you you
have taken on i think one of them has
gone to completion that they're
thematically connected in several ways
one of them has to do with the design
and integration of micro devices that
manipulate and manage electrons and
photons but also connecting all of the
technology work that you're doing is is
a kind of another sort of technology
advancement that i've seen at darpa can
be even more consequential than say an
initial invention and i'm talking here
about a term that we hear uh and you
hear in technology circles called c-swap
that's c-s-w-a-p
it refers to uh the challenge of taking
or transforming what originally are sort
of big expensive power hungry
technologies and making them smaller and
lighter and more energy efficient and
cheaper and this then opens them up to
kind of wider access because say they're
cheaper and not so unwieldy(笨重的) and
essentially you're taking something
that's impractical for many and making
it more practical
so it's those kind of two themes that i
see
and if you keep those in mind and
feel free to bring other themes in
as well
take me and listeners on a tour of your
programs
sure yeah well the
the term c-swap that you you bring up
you know it stands for cost size weight
and power
and it really is a way to quantify
uh the benefits of miniaturization
and
if i look at the portfolio of programs
that i've got i'd say there's sort of
two big themes the first is
generally optical microsystems
and the idea being if we
build systems out of very small
components
integrate them together
then we can make them
low-cost make them mobile deploy them
all over and add new functionality
typically the way we do these optical
microsystems is through another thing
that's sort of a theme of my programs
which is heterogeneous integration
and that means different things to
different people but really it's about
bringing different materials
technologies and functions together into
a
really small package we often
think of many of these programs as
creating some sort of capability in the
size of a sugar cube rather than a beach
ball
one that goes back a ways is
moab let's start with that one
modular optical aperture building blocks
and i remember first encountering this
and thinking
a sort of this remarkable idea of taking
what might be a whole system of lenses
you know think of a telescope or
binoculars or those are more familiar
ones but then uh in a way flattening
those down all into into something like
a more integrated kind of optical system
that would be much less bulky than the
originals you inherited that right and
so tell me a little bit about
what you got where you took it and where
it's at now
yeah great so moab was one of the
programs that i inherited back in 2017
when i arrived at darpa it's a great
example of this optical micro system
integration concept
and the idea is that most of the lidars
that we build today this is a laser for
3d ranging it's become really exciting
and enabling for autonomous vehicle
navigation also used on on your phone
perhaps to recognize you so typically
lidar systems that we use in in the
military are large systems they have a
telescope they have a gimbal
and they're hand assembled
right and so they tend to be big slow
expensive
and so MOABB is a program that looks to
shrink all of that down onto a chip
sort of like a postage stamp
non-mechanical
optical beam steering particularly for
for lidar and other kinds of optical
techniques
and
a lot of this is done through
integrated photonics which allows you to
take discrete
optical functions like modulators or
lasers detectors
and put them into sort of micro scale
and then assemble them together onto a
chip and maybe put thousands or tens of
thousands of components on a chip that
you manufacture in a semiconductor
foundry just like you do with integrated
circuits
the program is now in phase three has
made
enormous progress we've had many world
records over the last few years scaling
this technology and
now it's actually being flight tested
and shows a path for doing things on on
small uavs and other kinds of mobile
systems
okay and do you imagine that those kinds
of systems are the ones where this
technology will see at least its
widest initial application or do you
imagine also that there are some other
very big application areas down the line
yeah that's a good question and you know
i'd say that for most of the integrated
photonics technologies that we look at
there is a very large commercial driver
for most of the things that we pursue
and so
if you think about the the engineering
cost of creating something like MOABB
there's a whole lot of upfront
development cost
eventually though you get to the point
where you can
essentially stamp these
chips out in a foundry
and
it would allow you to scale these to
sort of millions or hundreds of millions
of units
where the
the unit price can be very low and so
for for MOABB the path there is for
commercial automotive where you can see
you know there are hundreds of millions
of cars every year that need
lidar systems that are small compact
and so MOABB might be good for the dod
initially and in certain uh cases but
also there's a path to commercialization
and helping the the broader community
very cool very cool so let me now move
to one another program that i've i've
known about for a while in fact i even
had met the programmator who started
that one dan green so i'm referring here
to chips which is common heterogeneous
integration and ip reuse strategies so
you don't have to actually parse all of
that
those words out there's probably an
easier way just to describe
what the goal of that program is and
where what its status is so chips is a a
program in our eri portfolio electronics
resurgence initiative this is a number
of programs that we're doing here in the
office
to help define what's next for
semiconductor microelectronics
and
chips came about because there is an
observation that you know as moore's law
goes on
and we can put more and more transistors
on a chip
both the cost of fabricating chips at
advanced nodes
and designing them essentially puts the
newest technology out of reach for both
the military and for sort of moderate or
small commercial uses
if you think about
say the most advanced GPUs or CPUs built
by big microelectronics companies and
those are central processing units and
graphics processing units yep that's
right if you think about these they
might cost a couple of hundred dollars
each
but the design time that goes into them
it can be
thousands of engineering years
and so you know if you want to put
something on a on an aircraft we can't
afford to do that every time so instead
chips takes a modular approach
essentially a chiplet integration
approach where you don't need to create
a full
asic or application specific integrated
circuit from the ground up every time
instead you can compose a system out of
smaller pieces
where you really only have to create
maybe a couple small capabilities like
say a machine learning accelerator
chiplet or an rf radio frequency front
end chip
and then assemble it with other things
that are that are also in the the chips
library and put it in a package in fact
chips has been a great success it
actually has transitioned over to osd
where they have
made a
much bigger investment in the in the
navy ship program
to try and make this a commercial
reality
and i will just remind readers that osd
stands for the office of the secretary
of defense
now as we continue the tour of your
programs let's move to pipes which
stands for photonics in the package for
extreme scalability pipes is actually a
really exciting program for me and it's
the first one i started at darpa pypes
is a program that is
about a technology called optical
interconnects
and that really means the technologies
that you would use to
send data from one ship to another with
photons rather than electrons
now i started
working on darpa programs back in in
grad school at stanford with professor
david miller who was an expert at
optical interconnects
optical interconnects were seen as sort
of the future for microelectronics but
microelectronics kept moving forward
without optics for a long time having
said that we've now gotten to a point
where moore's law has sort of put us
into a corner we can do more and more
transistors and compute on a chip but
the wiring or essentially the technology
to move data around doesn't really get
better as you shrink it down
so you've got this bottleneck where you
create all of this data on chip but you
can't move it from one place to another
very efficiently and we've reached a
problem where we're both bottlenecked in
terms of total capacity and the energy
that we use to move data becomes
enormous and and sort of dominates our
system
so instead we have to turn to a
different solution and optics is that
solution
if you think about the internet or data
centers right we've already used
fiber optics to move data around for a
long time 20 or 30 years
and this has gotten meaningful at a
shorter scale as we go forward
PIPES is looking to integrate photonics
into the package like it says in the
title for advanced
microelectronic systems like CPUs and
GPUs which you defined before or or
reconfigurable processors like FPGAs
which are field programmable gate arrays
FPGAs can be really powerful chips but
out of the box they don't really do
anything
they're meant to be programmed by the
customer and so they can really be
applied to different scenarios different
applications this makes it a really good
application for the PIPES program and so
the program has a number of performers
they all have very challenging metrics
given that this this field is is
relatively uh mature
so we're pushing
Intel and Xilinx two of our bigger
performers to put photonics into their
most advanced fpgas they've actually had
great success we're just moving into
phase two
and then we have a number of smaller
companies and academics
working to really improve the the
underlying technologies the integration
the circuits
the photonic components themselves
to help us
as you go forward in time so sort of
five or ten years out these technologies
are going to be particularly important
right and there are so many interesting
technical questions i could ask i'm just
going to sort of go to one just to give
a flavor of the kinds of challenges
you're dealing with you know so like
with optical fiber technology i mean
that all emerged out of out of really
kind of specialty incredibly pure
you know glass i mean that's glass
technology uh here when you talk about
optical interconnects and photonic
components i mean just give us a
just a real short sense of what kinds of
materials that you're actually talking
about sure so we're talking about many
materials but
usually they're at the chip scale and so
we have compound semiconductors like
gallium arsenide or indium phosphide
砷化镓或磷化铟
often integrated with silicon where
silicon might be doing a lot of the
electronics and the compounds might be
doing
emission and detection of light and then
those might be interconnected with glass
fibers or other things that that go
between one source and one detector that
might be a meter apart or a kilometer
apart depending on the on the
application
- great thanks for those
details okay now i would like to
continue and talk about a couple of more
of your programs next let's move to
lumos which i think maybe is one of your
uh newest this stands for lasers for
universal micro scale optical systems
what are you up to with lumos
yeah so lumos is the program that i most
wanted to do when i came to darpa lumos
was
it's a heterogeneous(异构) integration program
that that basically integrates new
materials in sort of a 3d way
onto semiconductor wafers (晶圆) and so
if you look at integrated photonics
today it's moved very fast in the last
decade
because silicon photonics has been very
successful
we use silicon in traditional
electronic circuits
and by leveraging the fabrication
techniques people have moved silicon
photonics forward very fast you can
fabricate
really complex
photonic integrated circuits
however silicon is actually not a great
material for optics
it's really good for fabrication but
it doesn't emit light at least not very
efficiently doesn't really detect most
of the light that we care about and it
doesn't do other effects like nonlinear
effects that we might care about
so LUMOS is about integrating materials
onto silicon or other other low loss
materials
particularly to make lasers so
lasers and amplifiers in the in the
optical space are really foundational
the laser was invented about 60 years
ago around the same time darpa actually
they co-evolved
yes
and you know people
realized really quickly that that lasers
were going to be really important they
shrunk them down to make semiconductor
lasers and you know we keep finding new
applications for for lasers silicon
photonics doesn't really have lasers and
so you need to integrate separate laser
chips to build up a system so LUMOS is
saying how do we put lasers directly
directly on these wafers and so the
teams are doing various things they're
they're growing compound semiconductors
right on top of silicon they're
integrating tiny little chiplets on
silicon they're doing non-linear
wavelength conversion so that we can
create new wavelengths maybe in the
visible for quantum or atomic systems
and looking at how do you amplify light
to get to sort of watts of power on
these on these wafers
well so it sounds like tremendous amount
of versatility both kind of in the
spectrum element and also power
you know when you think of two or three
applications that would just tickle you
if you saw them getting out there in the
in
real life what comes to mind well so i
think that there's going to be a lot of
new applications beyond just moving data
around which is what photonics is used
for today so
so sensors for
positioning navigation and timing that's
a big thing that we care about in in the
dod but understanding where you are and
navigating in the world
often we make precision sensors with
with quantum systems or atomic systems
and you have to interface with atoms
every atom might be different it might
be a rubidium atom or a cesium atom
铷原子或铯原子
and LUMOS is trying to address this by
making a flexible platform that can
create really narrow line width lasers
at just about any wavelength that you
care about on a chip right and is this
where the optical frequency combs come
in which i've been hearing about and
actually had a little bit of a challenge
with a public affairs colleague of mine
uh to see if we could uh just if you
could describe that in a way that most
people would understand
well sure i can i can give it a try so
uh yeah optical frequency combs have
seen sort of a huge explosion of advance
in the last few years the idea is
typically using non-linear techniques we
go from a single optical frequency if
you think of a laser it's sort of one
single color and we create a number of
different frequencies that are all
equally spaced in the frequency spectrum
if you think of them looking like a comb
that you would you know comb your hair
with each one of these tones equally
spaced this essentially becomes a very
precise ruler and it can be used in many
different applications can be used for
frequency metrology it can be used for
spatial metrology
and it's really created a whole new area
of science and applications including
some of my other programs uh like DODOS
and griffin okay we'll get to that just
in one minute but some i was thinking
about these
optical frequency combs the other day
sitting back on my deck and i was
wondering like if in addition to
kind of specifying
this
you know range of frequencies if if you
can individually
also determine and specify the intensity
of each of those frequencies because
with that then you'd be able to kind of
simulate
the
color
experience of any particular thing like
a leaf or wood and the way each of those
absorbs and emits a different
portfolio of light frequencies can you
do that with an optical frequency comb
or are all of those component
frequencies the teeth of the comb as it
were or tones as you refer to them
are they all the same intensity well so
typically they start out maybe similar
in intensity but you can certainly
modulate each one of them and and create
just about any spectrum that you want
and so
you know one of the
clear uses for optical frequency combs
would be for spectral sensing and so you
could imagine creating thousands of of
tones at different frequencies
and sensing maybe a gas plume and
understanding exactly which molecules
are present at what concentration by
detecting the relative intensity of each
one of those we also have
under the pipes program that i talked
about some teams that are using optical
frequency combs
with each each comb tooth being sort of
an independent source almost like
how systems today are built with
individual lasers at different colors
wavelength division multiplexing or wdm
instead you could have one comb laser
that creates hundreds of lines
and then modulate each one and now you
have hundreds of of optical channels
each carrying their own data
yeah astonishing
so let's finish out your
tour of programs with with two that are
related
and one preceded the other i'm referring
here to the two programs known as dodos
and griffin
and i'll let you spell those out and
tell me
the technology trajectory that they
amount to
sure so
dodos is uh the direct on-chip digital
optical synthesizer this is a program i
inherited also when i arrived back in
2017 it's a fantastic program and it's a
little esoteric so for people that
aren't in the optical physics space
it'll take just a minute to explain but
if you're familiar with microwave and
radio frequency technologies the direct
digital synthesizer or dds
is commonplace today in a radio in your
car you no longer have a tuning knob
that you kind of have to tweak and find
the right frequency
instead you just hit a button and your
radio goes there it generates the right
frequency optics today is kind of still
stuck in the microwave world of the 60s
where we build a laser
and then we measure what the output
wavelength is or the frequency you might
be able to lock it to something but you
don't really just tell it where to go
and dodos which is looking to make an
optical analog of the dds
is trying to do that we just finished
dodos this year and made enormous
strides and the idea is if you use
optical frequency combs as your ruler
and some microwave techniques where we
know frequencies very well hopefully you
can create
optical frequencies with incredible
precision and accuracy and so in fact
under DODOS we've we've seen many many
orders of magnitude improvement in the
accuracy of of optical frequencies and
this is all using chip scale
technologies so again trying to to take
technologies that today look like a a
room or a rack and put it into the size
of a sugar cube right and just to help
listeners who might be impressed that
you can get the highest precision on a
frequency might be impressed by that
capability but it doesn't know why what
do we get from that well sort of again
like changing the paradigm(范例) the way that
digital synthesis did for radios we also
use optical frequencies for
communications
and so you could imagine incredible
improvements in
optical communications by having
precision control of frequencies at both
ends
essentially doing coherent communications(相干通信)
where both sides know
what wavelengths are being communicated
very precisely or you could do precision
uh lidar where maybe you have one source
emitting and a different source
receiving it's also important for for
doing optical sensing where you perhaps
know
the precise wavelength of different
transitions for different molecules or
again quantum anatomic sensors
okay and then just one more point on
this one because as you were talking
about you know if i know and can produce
an extremely um you know precise
frequency
for communication and i want my
recipient to be able to do that same
thing or if my recipient can that sounds
like it would open up kind of you know
privacy and security channels
yeah that's a great point you could
certainly do that so DODOS was the prior
program that led into GRYPHON talk about
GRYPHON right so as we got near the end
of DODOS we saw this this great advance
in technology in fact i should say that
under dodos
perhaps the biggest outcome here was
seeing the whole community
get excited about non-linear photonics
we had
from the the performers under DODOS we
had well over a hundred peer-reviewed
journal submissions
and we had more than 25
high impact journals in in the nature
and science suite of journals
this is really changing the field and
there's whole sessions at conferences
now on DODOS's technology
now on to GRYPHON
which stands for generating rf with
photonic oscillators for low noise it's
a little bit of a stretch but we like
the name the GRYPHON  program is a
recognition that if you can make
extremely precise frequencies in the
optical domain
and then divide those frequencies down
from these sort of 100 terahertz
frequencies down to the microwave
you actually reduce noise when you do
that and that means you can get
incredibly
precise low phase noise oscillators in
the microwave regime
so
oscillators
are important in our entire world right
they
they form the clock that drives every
piece of digital electronics your phone
your computer microwave oscillators in
particular are important for
communications and for radar and so the
dod cares a lot about making very
precise microwave oscillators
and they try and make them very low
noise very quiet
essentially a pure tone if you think of
ringing a bell and just maybe you know a
crystal wine glass that's a pure tone at
microwave frequencies
it is something that's sort of an
exquisite oscillator and it gets used in
again exquisite systems but using
GRYPHON kinds of techniques or dodo's
kinds of techniques
you can imagine making these exquisite
oscillators(振荡器) not with RF(射频) electronics
which are often sort of hand-tuned
hand-built
expensive bulky things but putting them
on a chip and you use optics and
photonics on this chip
but it's a case where we don't really
care that there's there's optics inside
the package what we want to do is
generate a microwave signal that
ultimately comes out so griffin again
with sort of this sugar cube idea in
mind has
has goals of making very very quiet rf
or microwave signals with optics inside
the the tiny box
and
the idea would be we make we make better
radars better communication systems
and we can make them small
low power and low cost
there's a lot of commercial applications
as well like
imaging radar say for a autonomous
vehicle or if you make it small enough
maybe it goes in in every cell phone
wow okay well gordon
that was kind of an amazing tour of all
of these programs i mean when i think of
the technical challenges when i think of
the probably dozens of research
performers who are working across these
half dozen or so programs and you
keeping track of all of them and
and seeing how they can all integrate
and synthesize uh you have really got a
lot on your shoulders i uh give you some
pats on the back for doing all that and
it's exciting to think about the
technologies that will move forward so
before we kind of come in for a landing
here i just want to see was there
anything that you thought of afterwards
from any of these programs that you know
you'd like to just share with listeners
before i do take you in for a landing
and liberate you so i think that there's
a whole lot of unknowns as to where this
technology could go and there's a lot of
potential and so you know i worry about
occasionally on our DARPA  programs which
are very focused right we're trying to
solve one particular problem that that
we're missing things there's
there's other things like you know
biosensing or medical applications
and so we need to to kind of look at the
big picture and always keep looking for
new opportunities i would say that one
thing i want to make sure that the
listeners hear
is that
good ideas come from everywhere and
you mentioned the limited tenure that we
have at DARPA we're always looking for
new people and so if you've got ideas i
care a lot about
optical microsystems so for sure come
see me if you've got ideas in this area
but you know get involved DARPA is not
one person or one place it's a
collection of people that are excited
about moving technology forward and so
you know maybe you want to be a program
manager maybe you want to work as a STAEA
maybe you want to be a performer and
keep doing research but uh reach out and
get involved with darpa
all right you hear that listeners it's a
pitch for you guys to get in touch and i
should point out that the acronym aceta
stands for the scientific technical and engineering
assistance
who
work with program managers like you,
Gordon, to take
programs through their entire life
cycles
so as i see it you're kind of in the
business of turning science fiction or
at least sort of visions of technology
into reality we've talked about a num a
number of the ways you're trying to do
that but i'm wondering if as a kind of a
技术狂热
technophile and a technology developer
yourself do you dream about non-existent
technologies
not yet hear technologies that you wish
were real things yeah well
you know right now
time travel
or maybe slowing time down
there's so much
that i want to do
and you know sometimes it's at work
sometimes it's it's being at home with
the family sometimes it's it's going and
doing other things and there's just not
enough time that would be it
right so that would be a technology that
would kind of end the lament(抱怨) that we all
have you know so many books not enough
time you know so so many careers to
pursue not enough somebody might want to
climb not enough time gordon i think if
you can actually solve that problem
that's the one you will be most uh
remembered for though i don't think
that's going to be a darpa program as
far as i know who knows
but you might be able to pitch that to
close i just want to thank you for
taking us on a tour of your life as a
technology developer
as a program manager at darpa
thanks evan it's been a pleasure and
thanks listeners for sharing this time
with us i hope you join us again for the
next voices from darpa
thanks also to Tom Shortridge for his
partnership in producing this program
for more information about Dr. Gordon Keeler
the programs he and his
colleagues in the agency's microsystems
technology office run and the many other
breakthrough technologies DARPA  is
working on visit darpa.mil
and for links that enable you to
download this podcast go to the voices
from darpa page on darpa's website