Step of technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are totally missed.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defense advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan a motto .
And I am you double host today .
I am pleased with me in the studio , rosa , a hundred workers known as alive by her friends and colleagues .
Alan has been a program manager since early twenty seventeen in darkness , defense science office , where program managers take some of the deepest types in the fundamental in search of new foundations for novel technologies , relevant to national security allies , deep dive into fundamental science goes all of the way to electrons in some of the more unusual they can organize and behaviour and certain materials .
And how might be useful to engineer those electronic organizations into new microelectrodes and micromagnetic devices for applications in memory , logic , energy conversion and sensors prior to arriving a dark early was a professor of physics at the college .
William and marine williams burger in before that , she was a member of the physics faculty at the university of the little in ohio .
And yet earlier in her career , she was a research scientist at the argentine national atomic CNEAin venezuela's argentina after finishing her early college training at the university , witnesses ali earned her doctorate in physics from wayne state university and retried michigan , and she completed a postdoctoral fellowship at the university of michigan and albert , I like .
Thanks for joining me in the today.
I'm happy to be here .
Thank you.
So let's start out by talking about how you became interested in science and general .
And then in particularly in physics , and the empty of electrons.
When I guess that , you know me , I started being interested because my father would read to me articles that he was interested in in a magazine that he was getting delivered at home at the time in one of the sidelines , he was getting , some of which was a french man getting involved later .
Discoveries and developments .
And he was reading this to me when I was like seven or eight years old , so I mean , it was a very early start .
So that was the beginning .
And then , well , clearly , a minimum science has always been a billion to me , and we were getting additional languages inside home .
You know , that I was very obviously .
I remember reading once about shredding globalization , and even though I was like they really live in the top , and I didn't know what you mean .
I knew how.
The shrinks , the question you were , you were reading all about the deeper , because parts of economic economics of uncertainty makes me think that your parents were signed , strange and so.
Father was a doctor in engineering , so but yeah , clearly , I mean , I was reading in this magazine .
I said in a minute , didn't understand what it question men I was staying , but I still was able to write it , you know , to draw it if you wish , I was able to draw a disagree with a paper .
And to this day , I remembered it from that day , I was very fascinated by decent , clearly , well , given us a stand went by .
I was greeted my head that I was going to go for a career in science .
I didn't know exactly what I speak to science shortly .
But surely , you know , myanmar began very , very interested in the electronic properties of materials and trust went from their own words right now.
right ?
So the first part of your career you ended up going in an academic direction .
You became a professor at william and mary .
So talk me a little bit about the experience as a professor .
And I wanna hear you are , how did you get to dark story ?
So start with the university.
Okay , so I mean , I have been fascinated by the fact that , you know , me is not about what we are doing is like , you know , where's the spaces , we have to realize that our part resides on the fact that we transfer our knowledge is not .
Our individual knowledge is in knowledge from every generation before us .
Any disabled duty in my mind to buy this along to the next generation , where part of right ?
Correct , correct , so i've been always interested in in being a professional for that same reason , because I wanted to to be able to identify and students that internet , that capacity they've tried to go for scientific research and to try to amend them and help them be the best they could be so that they can , you know , that is no lesson that particular area ever more .
So that's why I went for the candy , of course , you know , when you're going to get the email , one of the things that you need to do in order to be able to to carry out this mother left trying to train grade students , you have to get funding .
And so clearly , I mean , I had to explore all the fountain agencies among them .
I export our bye and gotten funding from the orbit .
And eventually you want to cannot learn .
Okay , what does it take the other side right to understand ?
How do you know , select the best people to do best ?
How is this process being proceeds from the viewpoint of the funding agency ?
So it was particularly intrigued by dark , but because I say , said it was happening by funded by the park in the beginning .
This model of trying to find basic science that has a goal and ultimate goal was really very appealing to me.
Can I just ask your question of that dark in particular , because of as someone in academia , you might have gone to nationalistic to support , you might have gone to national science foundation .
What about that world?
They're doing there .
There are several parts to this particular question of me .
On the one hand , you know , as a senior american , not by birth , but by choice , you know , I have a deep love for this country , the evaluation for this country , in , and a sense of duty regarding , you know , trying to help this country to continue be what it is right now .
And the best way my opinion is to try to see , okay , what are the needs of the people that are they far from difficult from difficulties that will be defended , the armed forces in general , right ?
Is it what is that is going to make that difference in terms of university and technology of analysis and research that can help this dismission , and clearly the advice at the first front of all of these funding agencies and that particular direction .
So I was very , very intrigued and cute years and interested in the impact of this particular organization for that reason.
So did you reach out only two ?
Darpa , was there somebody here that knew about you ?
What was the ?
Those were the final steps that got you onto the ruster programme managers?
I had the collaboration with store wolf , who was at a time when I was a william and murray .
He was at the university of a junior , and he was leading the newspaper in the newspaper .
And and and I took it up on myself to actually introduce my research to him to try to study collaborative effort .
And index did happen , and we actually got a couple of british is going .
And so eventually , what , of course , I knew that he had been a doubtful manager in the past .
So I mentioned him that that I was interested in , like , you know , seeing the others side of the fourth is so he actually told me what we don't give me your CV, and I will buy it alone .
And particularly he told me that he was going to show it the symphony dominance , which was set up down the director of the.
And there are some meaning defense , like software .
Six , a technical officers are.
Correct and the russian history of english .
I guess that she got my CV, and she contacted me to see if I was interested in pursuing a career.
So you mentioned to wolf , and that gives me a little bit of an excuse to maybe dive into your entry press , because it has still worked .
He's a big name in the area of spain , chronics and miss gifts to electronics and materials .
Okay , talk to me just even a little more generally , emotions as the physicists that you are about this arena of that.
So so grab you .
So basically , my , my career in physics here .
And this country has been focused in particularly on spin dependent phenomenon , particular magnetic materials and magnetic phenomena.
And by spin dependent , you mean , depended on the spans of political lecturers , right?
Pretty particularly electrons .
Yes , that is correct .
The electronics being so turns out that would you read the proper manager here , though , super stewart actually was the father of spain journey in the scene that he realized that there were some discoveries that were happening at a time when we were talking like late nine days are , in particular , the giant metal assistance effect , which was particularly driving .
He falls for the explosion in a hard driving city and stories in japan that we have experienced the last twenty years.
Just wanted to accept you .
For many , I realized we kind of just passed by this idea of spin , dependently spin of electrons .
But there's a difference spin of electron , which is little less familiar , as opposed to the charge of electric and the negative charge , which could most people do know about .
So , talking about those different aspects of the electronic and where spin dependence is in the coming into the group.
Great , so the electronics beneath the very difficult quantity to define legal citizens that quantify the electronic world of mechanical effects .
So instead of trying to define what spin is , one is whether or settled by defining what is that being does in general , what you find the election .
Yeah , if you , if you think of it as like a little error pointing in any given direction , what happens is that the accurate spins like to eat a barrel to each other and a bullet to each other , and indicates a magnetic materials .
What happens is that the electrons items in particular areas of the different attempts , they all like each other that , you know , very much attractive to one another , pointing in the same direction .
And and with that gives you some opportunity to give the meaning to this .
And so , for example , you can say , okay , if I have a group of things spins that they are all aligned and given direction , I can associate , that would say , number one , and if they are pointed in the opposite direction , then I can associate this with the numbers .
And then you have the banner language , and you can combine the vitalities language and more complex languages that lead to what we using confutations these days , similar ones in zero of our digital age .
Correct , correct , so spin allows to do this in the advantages of spin in in , are , are that , well , you can actually have these composition of spins to be made really small , which means that you can actually back a lot of these beats of once in zero in space .
Ukraine hands the area , then CDthat you can store the ones and zero they happen to be done by the nature of the materials are protected against radiation , damaging .
And in one of the holy grades , as I was being to try to find out what is that limit , how small can you make the leader amount of spins to store a once in series in a stable manner , so?
And they were sentenced by focusing on spin of the electoral , rather than charge of the electron that you can actually have a smaller area of a piece of semiconductor with all these electrons are , are living that the smaller piece of that that some economics will host a one of our zero is.
It's not just a question of the size , but it is also of the energetic , I mean , you know me , one of the things that matters to use do not to see how , how much power you've gonna be needed in order to have these , these consideration of this and one .
So in general , you know , this is what what we found .
There were several effects associated with these activity of the elections of the involved and dialogue , that code technologies that will enhance the incident without increasing the demands of powerful and making this very stable ceremony , and also on the location , so that makes the entire in a collection of a property that are very , very attractive , not just for storage density .
So car drives , but also for memory , but , and that's basically one of the goods that this benjamin program had the program that stored actually started to be.
Right , let me bring you back now too .
Another big , multi celebrate crazy that you use earlier , which was giant magnetic resistance .
We simply bring that up is because that phenomenon and the technology that it LED to became part of our everyday lives in our hard drive , right in the red heads of the hard drive .
It tells a little bit about that technology , evolution .
And where does it?
So what happened was that what it was found , and this was what letter , the novel of brights in nineteen ninety eight was that when you have layer systems in which you two magnetic layers separated by one layer , that is not magnetic .
And if your best current through this particular contraction , the resistance of this contraction will be different when the spines of parallel with respect when they are under violent .
So that gives you a mechanism to read what is going on in terms of the biggest parallel , and they're valid , because you have now resistance to enable that , that the domination , and that's how you sense .
What is in the hardware.
So you are reading the spends , what are your parallel ?
And I do paralyse , but you are.
Correct , so that is a big power of this .
So that was discovered nineteen ninety eight .
And then later it was discovered , was that if you replaced the intermediate layer , the magnetic layer that goes metallic was done by an insulator layer and insulate , then you have an effective civilization , which means that you have an amazon sensitivity .
What you're doing .
That was this being dependent on the natural systems being done , a independent natural assistance , and that LED to the explosion in , usually in england , that we have a magnetic , random access memory is great .
Yes , I always forget that in a photos of hazardous and the field , this is like everyday language , right?
I have been in some ways and understanding science , and emma is understanding acronyms that some of the battle.
He beginning , the government has been in the end of the country is very single day.
So let's then segregate into your wife's appropriate material and exactly doing this for less than a year .
So you have a kind of perspective of an early program manager , which I think it would be quite interesting .
You already have two programs under your wing .
One of them pause , which stands for a program in ultra fast laser science and engineering , is a program that you inherited .
And the other one , the top logical executions in electronics , or t that's a program that you pitched to the agency leadership and got the green lights of congratulation on that .
Thank you .
Let's start talking post , which seems to be about a new sort of taking our ability to generate and manipulate electoral magnetic graduation in ways that have been .
so .
Tell me what your tickets are important , but you hope to achieve.
Both adjusted , it is a program that I inherited it .
The BCtenant of the program is that it was to use again , some discoveries that have been increased outside by the the community , which is related to the frequency gone .
The frequency gone is something that takes up in .
It can like a separate , specific frequencies and brother ration frequent and use that for a variety of application.
COM comes from right , because if you think of each frequency as a tie of account and rely on them all up , you get something that somebody looks like to come .
You usually brush your hair.
Correct , and so you can select secretary at the end of this reconsidering men .
And so there have been worked that I was particularly interested in because it dies in with the programs that I am going , that I developed , people have been able to user technology , for example , to get a kind of extra behavior that the kind of behavior that you get with a single drum facility , which is a big , large facility and a table dropped type of configuration .
So there has been fascinating to me , people have been able to to achieve these by using frequency comes in the other extreme of it was also that people have been able to probe things in the time domain , and we'd add a second position that is.
Really short duration , right , right ?
I mean , adult second is turned to the minus eighteen seconds .
So if you think of another second , which is tends to the nine seconds , which is one billions of a second , then an adult second is one billion of one billion.
A one second is really , really fast , so that they think about this is that it is going to enable us to actually look at the dynamic dynamics of electrons , because those are the only entities that are going , but not the only , but at the mainland , it is that are going to be moving in that regime .
So that is what you are going to be using this kind.
So in some ways , it is almost like you are trying to create a movie camera that is mapped onto the way electrons live in the speed they live at , which is so much faster , and a minor human.
And not only the human , but are even the things that we have been doing doing so far .
Because I mean , you look at the various ranges in which we got to have been looking at things , yes , we move at some speed , you know , as humans , but then it is , molecules also have a weird moving day .
They translate .
They rotate their vibrate and then seeing those , because those movements are not at the , at the second , they are much slower than that .
So we have been able to see some of those things already , some in your getting the capabilities that we enable us to see .
As I said , in the realm of electrons , which are so much more than the same and move so much faster .
So this is a new capability that would be a good achieved by this programming is due to the album .
This does not exist today.
So let's stand this one for a second before you move over to your tea program .
So this , this sounds like very fundamental science .
And of course , that's why it was in DSof defence science .
His office among the six second glove this year , but on the other hand , we are also in dark up .
And so tell me a little bit about not only sort of where this might push the undeveloped in fundamental science , but how that might actually be of relevance to national security.
But some of the things that , for example , these technologies were enabled and happening , talking to the performance system , for example , provide methodology , for example , for the masks in the battling that have been done a dynamic level for microscopes that are used in the middle makeup of a number of driving systems from each other .
You need microprocessors and micro electronics in a number of of instruments and things that are used by the armed forces that are used by .
So when you reduce the footprint , there are a number of things that can , without the minimum addition to lower weight , obviously reduced the smaller you make a tables so fast , faster , which also enables , you know , faster , read information , but you also may enable lower power consumption , which also enables the acceptability of having this institute .
This is given this cheap to work with less badly , needs so badly also have their own weight and footprint on the soldier's backs .
And in all of this is going into the same direction to try to the possibilities for safe for the soldiers to be more efficient when you have right now , but less bulky and less power hungry .
So the methodology that disconnect will enable gosh in an indirect question , but it goes into that particular.
And by micro logic , we mean some of new ways of measuring films as click case , very , very small claims .
And as you are speaking , it also makes me think that this does perhaps play into the future of progress and micro electronics .
And that is always this , this business concern for many minutes at at some point , we're not gonna , be able to use the techniques we use now to make the next smallest transistor we can actually need very new ideas .
Perhaps here that coming out of posts that will open doors for yet another era of of ministration or not , many transition , increasing capability and.
Of the trip , but at least , you know , more with the same , right , more sensitivity for less powerful beneficiaries are the same size .
So isn't that the addition in each way that you are there , there is a very broad , but I made our space that you have to consider when looking at.
All right , so a lot of opportunity .
There are members , fundamental science and potentially applying an interview to the highest of technologies .
So let them move over to your baby that we can call that your top logical executives in electronics program .
And I know this gets a little bit hurry , because we're using words like top logical , or where you can take our imaginations down to the electronic level .
Talk to me as obama in undergraduate physics , and your introducing some of these ideas for first time.
I tried in the meaning .
One of the things that I mentioned earlier was that one of the holidays that we have had for the obligation of in , say , a storage renewable is , how small can you make this collection of space so that they can keep the information as all aligned meaning and one or all align meaning we've been disturbed by preparations , because in the end of southwestern energetic consideration , if your temperature fluctuations are more than energy than the energy that is contained in this group of a of electrons , then they're not gonna win , and then you lose .
Information is like , I like the day my students , you take your left up to my yummy , and that goes all the information that you started , that would be fun .
So you need something better than that .
And so I have been following the jenny turns out , you know , that we have a new door , our , our disposal for , for blogging , new partnerships , and is what the college brings , which is again , something that has to do with the , they are all the intentional configuration of things.
But not just as a technology comes out of really the deal wrong.
Of geometry , right in a way , yes , like in , in a way .
Yes , it has to do with something that has to do with a special configure .
So in this particular case , that we go to the heart of the method , I mean , I told you that spins like to be barrel and dialogue , but he doesn't say that this is an attempt of the possibility that scientists have discovered .
And he said , they are engineer for them to be candidates that is making some angle between them .
Now , you lock them into discounting , and you try to put them on a surface , you realize , and now they had to arrange themselves in such a fashion that they can accommodate the academic .
And when you try to do this exercises , if you take like , do little , be , do little doing .
And then you went about several of them on a surface , you see that they had to be arranging kind of award exercise , kind of little things to the political experience of regulators are right .
Okay , something like that .
You can put them there right on the surface .
And that is what we got screamings , right .
And why are these interesting ?
Well , because now , because they are counted , if you want to switch them off , pointing in one direction to pointing the opposite direction , now you have to do this with the entire , the entire lot.
And just just for clarity , when you say the word canteen with you , likely these spines are candid , means that they're not parallel or anti parallel , but are actually a certain kind of angle , almost like.
Correct , correct .
And so now , because they are locked into this by some mechanism , right , you just cannot switch one without switching the other , so you have to switch the entire thing because you have to switch the entire that caused you more energy than it will be doing just the individual players , right , so that makes an introduction more.
A little doubt of thermal energy , he is not , is not enough to football correct , so they become stable , correct.
That is what the topology offers you a production , so that if you can like , engineer this in a suitable way , such that we can create a region of spins in this configure multiplication smaller than what we have right now for collecting the ones and diseases .
Then you are in the next generation of media that would be based upon this type of material , and that would push it .
I mean , and there are some metrics that tell us , where can we go ?
What would we achieve me doing that ?
And it is not just size , as I said , that really so , so question about energetics , how much energy you really need to do do this ?
Can you move them around , and you actually do things with them so you can open up several paradigms to use these entities for memory , logic or sensitive applications beyond what we can do with materials , right?
Okay , and this still fall within the tradition of spain , china , accidents and still worth , or is this beyond , is this in some other?
Related , so it will be spiritual in in spirit , right ?
But it is .
It has this added thing , which is the topological protection .
This is top box in double logical spintronics , right , right ?
So that is a new thing .
And that is.
What is gonna ?
Take us ?
Let's talk about where your program is in sort of the general lifecycle of a program .
Here is dark .
So you came , and here you came up with this wonderful idea .
You went through the hiring experience of bringing it to its called tech council , where leadership in your coal program management .
Others are there vetting it ?
So you made it passed all of those obstacles.
我。
Now , what's the status of the purpose ?
So right now , we have passed .
Source selections show a broader announcement was placed for the people and university proposals .
The proposals were evaluated by teams of experts , and then decisions were made in terms of what the most.
Qualified and teach me that by source , select action is that those who can make a past , these obstacles become a source as a where we tell them for.
Correct correct , so right now , that is the states .
And so what we are going on right now will be , you know , the contracting part of , so is that when the money is actually being delivered to the performance , and so we think that we would have the kick of meeting sometime early during the eighteen , and shortly after we'll be reviewed time , right ?
I mean , they have to perform between the art by another agency as well .
Is that there are very strong metrics that have to be satisfied in order to continue with.
Progress , although I certainly miss you , this , you know , this reminds me a little bit of some of the early days here .
I doubt about where , for example , there was a funding of something called the inter disciplinary laboratories , and at least became kind of the , the seeds , but later became known as material science and engineering .
So starbucks had a role .
They are next to the united .
Kind of it is nurturing .
What had was honest way to becoming a new material science is this is this kind of a sense of that kind of possibility where , because you have an idea that organizing groups , these potential performers , do you think this is going to be important for starting a new field?
In fact , it is particularly important to concentrate the efforts of experts that are maybe working on various other areas that may not be related to one another .
But to then focus them under a specific problem with the specific metrics , and that may lead to advances in this particular territory in which we are not even brief , because we don't know what they are going to discover .
I mean , we are thinking that one application would be .
This new generation may modify that we all are needing and wanted to happen , but it so happens in the suspect experience that , you know , prior people in , including school , has mentioned this to me that often thinks what happens is that the performance discovers things that you need and anticipate , and the program can go in a different direction rate and start the new program .
You just don't know what they can take you .
So that's basically what my hope is that because this is basic science , that is all of the best ability of the groups , groups of people to discover something completely non undissipated that would blow our minds away .
We would like , well.
We'll make that happen , as that sounds really like an exciting possibility .
And in some ways , I wonder if I wondered if at a place like dark , or whether such a diversity of skill set , whether there is even more of an opportunity to recognize when really surprising things happens like a sleep , maybe if everything promises , no question , here is another to hear you kind of air dropped in from academy .
You're in the defence science office .
Have you met other program managers or wanted other programs that that , in a sense of blow your mind , and that are , you are now beginning to think of how they relate to your own.
interests .
I'm definitely looking into this , particularly for the m do the manufacturing technological life is the microscope that is correct , because these are the guys that would be perhaps the ones that may take on whatever developments come from the issue , because they are the ones that are going to try to make actual devices out of this if they turn out to be , do living up to the promise that we are hoping .
So yes.
So it looks like an interesting synergy there where you might be on the really fundamental side of things .
And telled .
My system technology officer , even though still fundamentally in engineering site , could take it further the next step toward what ultimately would be the finish line , and , of course , of the way dark it works that would probably be out in industry or some a part of some other lab .
And in the military services.
But there is so easy and expected , because in the sensor technology , you don't know , this may take you to some biology related sensors that we are not even thinking on right now .
And it has happened a lot of in , in particularly in recent times , that a lot of the discoveries have been done , like , for example , taking the indeed of nanotechnology , and in people who are working with analytics for a number of physical application and then and then the biology started thinking .
How about using them as markers for biological , you know.
Rights and by and by nanoparticles were kind of talking about things , viruses , so things that much smaller than sales , more , even smaller than some organisms .
But the suitable one that virus.
Correct , so there are , there are opportunities so that that we just don't know , and we will have the , you know , we will see the performance .
Get there there .
And then , you know , if there is certainly an opportunity , we will really , really explore it in and make the people from between.
Aware of this , so , and BTor game was an excuse to mention that another one of the officers said that the biological technology is correct.
Correct , correct , and so that's that's from the indian , who knows ?
I mean , there might be other things that may be important for doctors .
I mean , we just don't know .
I mean , I know that deeply at the , in STO, you know , maybe interested in , you know , different ways of of of that can come from these programs that to be applicable to specific problems that they're working on.
Right , and again , as tears are going through the entire reporter here , the entire set of others , that strategic technologies of us that could be only when we did mention so far as the technical technologies are not just .
Oh , and I too .
Oh , exactly what is this information innovation occasion ?
There is the entire six.
But again , we don't know where is this political program is gonna .
Take that .
I mean , that is the beauty of working for the issue that you are there for front of science .
We are there by science .
Starbucks , in that regard , you know , that we are working with things that we don't know where they are going to take us .
That is not a specific goal .
We have some idea where we want to go , but we don't know if there are going to be new opportunities arising from them.
From discovery , so are there , are there any questions that you wish I had asked you in the discussion that I.
Didn't get you .
Yes , like where , whether by in the american dessert , I mean , I mentioned this in best , a lot of people like when I was like at an obligation a few years ago , was reading a club gotta novel , and he mentioned at some point , darbar .
And i've got to the science novel , kind of universal digital.
This has to be a hot age to climb custody , the author .
And yes , the dark , we do know a certain kind of mistake , and it is out there in the cultural world , in various ways that is absolutely true .
Yeah , I just want to thank you alive for spending this time with us and letting us know little bit about how you are taking this role as a programmer energy to the future of technology.
Thank you so very much for being here .
I am proud of being adopted member here .
So thank you.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from darker .