Self technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand.
Autonomous operation technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight in the midst of the cold war , the defense advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as a core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan a motto , and I am your daughter host .
And i'm please have with me in the studio today , choosing a program manager since twenty fourteen , industrial systems technology of others try earned a pair of bachelor's degree is one in electrical engineering and one in computer engineering from west virginia university and our masters and doctoral degree and electrical engineering from the university of michigan for a decade prior to coming to DARPA , try founded and LED a series of programs within the micro electric mechanical systems technology department of sandia national laboratories in elbow cookie , new mexico , thanks for a journey in the studio today .
Now the point .
So i'd like to start out of discussion with some background about you .
I'd like to tell me about your education if there are teachers that were important to you growing up , and that let you in the kinds of engineering correction that you have.
Yeah sure , so I grew up in a small town in west virginia , western , western , to be exact when I was in high school , I had exhausted the math classes were available at my local high school , so I ended up going part time to west virginia wesley in college .
And they set up kind of a class for many students from my high school , go to a class for high school students , the local college .
And before that , it was been good mass , but I never really knew how to apply it .
I figured I would go in the medicine or something of that nature , and it's part of that special class they set up for us .
The first half hour professional bride would come in , and he was engineering physicists , and he would come in and relate all of the calculus we were learning to physics problems .
And I just found that fascinating , so that one of the junior high school , and from that point forward , I wanted to be an engineer.
So I like to hear a little bit about the base of your career where you really work a lot on men and get next steps from micro electric mechanical systems .
I know you did that even before going to a sandy as I talk a little bit about that whole man.
Part of your work in graduate school to university , michigan , I worked for a professor .
Canvas is one of the founders of names there .
I worked on analog interfaces for normal recording electorates , so I was developing integrated circuits to be able to record nervously potentials the brain for doing things like restoring function to people who have nervous system disabilities like paralysis .
Could , could be other things in the stimulation sense , like blindness , or are hearing loss or other of that nature .
I didn't went to send the international laboratories , which things a little bit of michigan I was designing circuit in their faces for members .
And sandy , I started exactly designing the max components and let the team of people designing and employment in those .
Primarily , we were working on small acoustic devices .
So you may not know that in your phone and all of signal is immediately converted into an acoustics of.
And I arrived by our female radio frequencies.
Corrector , yeah , yeah , I mean , radio frequency , the radio frequency signal , which has a really long way of linked this converted into a acoustic signal , which has very small wavelength , which allows third in a small form factor before it's create , turned back into an electrical signal .
Uh , my joy was working on technologies that do that function , but more for department of defense applications , rather than the elephant , also worked on other things that really at the interface of the vibrational systems and acoustic systems and electronic systems and.
All right , and then what was the pathway from sandy?
Two drop , I was a performer doing a lot of the research on those small acoustic violence components .
Bill chapel , the current director of microsystem technology office , was my program manager .
And so when he was promoted , he called me out of the blue one day , I think that was in march of the twenty fourteen .
Instead , he tried , this is built chapel .
How would you like to come the dark , but be a program manager ?
I think you be great at it .
And I shared north , as was the bodies that was kind of a strange conversation .
I said , yeah , that that sounds like a great opportunity .
Can I call you back at a few minutes?
And is that that all all it took a few , just a few minutes , and then you know what your.
Oh , of course , i'll mean after that , I mean anybody who is an opportunity to come in to the album is fantastic opportunity .
Of course , I had to come in our view and put together talk that outlined the programs I would start to have to come in a view with the office director , but how it all started was from a phone call from belgium.
Speaking about those programs were gonna die when to talking about a number of those who have a very large portfolio , the most program managers that will only talk about a few , but there are two questions I want to ask you before we do that one has to do with your name .
Try , I call you try , but your official name is roy , and i'm just wondering if you could tell us the story of your name.
Yes , so my fish name is royal herald .
Also , the third turns out my dad really wanted me to be named after him is clearly roy herald's in junior , and my mom wasn't the biggest fan of the name roy , but so they made a deal that I could be named royal holders in the third , and everyone will call me troy and enforced this when I was a small child , as legend has it , I would sit in my high chair .
And if people called me roy , I would throw green wings at them and pound on a high chair , telling them the money in the morning was.
Nothing like negative reinforcement .
And so let some move on to we'll just some of your programs too , that I think our associate with one of those who can talk about them together .
Go by the short names of equals and paper equals stands for inbound controlled air releasable unrecoverable systems and zebra stands were vanishing programmable resources , and the vapor came before equals .
So I wanted to tell us a little bit about the labour across story , which is an ongoing woman.
Yeah , so um , in the department of fans , a lot of times we have problems with electronically behind .
We don't want to leave things on the battlefield where other people might collect them .
We came up with the paper program , which is vanishing micro electronics program , is designed to be able to make micro electronics that have reliability .
Four months , commissioner , with commercial of the shelf electronic components that don't vanish .
But that when we want them to can rapidly vanish and and be invisible to the naked eye.
Okay , and do you mean when you say vanish in the most people to think of puff , it's gone .
Talk to me a little bit about the kind of technical path with some of your performers , which is to say , the research groups have been working on the kinds of pathways they're taking to try to realize this idea of vanished ability.
Yes , it is really too approaches that have been really prominent in the paper program .
A one was developed by the palestinian o'clock , and it is a vanishing glass substrates that basically turns into dust like particles , and that glass can be bound to integrated circuits and other things , and causing an entire system to you to vanish , and by dozens like particles , the part of the order size of one hundred mile crowds , which is about the weight of human hair .
So those ones vanished , but the material himself doesn't know physically completely vanish .
We did develop a material that does that .
There was worked on there at the university of annoying and george attack and cornell .
Many of those materials were walking away where they're thermally unstable room temperature .
They'd like to be a monument or be a guess .
So exactly make them at very cold temperatures , say , like minus fifty degrees .
See , in this case , these vanishing materials of polymers .
And we'd like to make a really long polymer chain to get home like you are right , makes the parliamentary tough .
And then we link it in a certain way at the very cold temperatures that we raise .
The open temperature remains stable , then in that material will in bed , something that called it .
There are photo generator or a thermal laser generator networks , just like you might expect to those when you figure , when you expose it to a certain wavelengths of light , photos of generator criticism , if you take the thermal laser generator and exceed a certain temperature , it also creates an asset that asset can break one of the bonds between the polymer change .
And at that point , then it becomes storming unstable room temperature again , and the rest of it just vanishes and by vanishes .
It take turns from a solid directly into a gas .
Mental illness vanishes right before your eyes .
The first time you see , it is truly amazed , and actually , the second time you see it actually raised.
They're gonna , always be aware , and it really is amazing chemistry to bring into the capability of vanishing materials .
And this , the program was successful enough in your eyes that you created the following program , right?
That's correct .
So we were brainstorming , what else beyond micro electronics , could we do with these materials ?
We were thinking , where else could we push this materials would lead the new fundamental discovery and developments , and could be also at the same , sometimes useful , the permanent defence .
And we came up with the idea of vanishing air delivery vehicles for being able to deliver things in a very precise way into difficult , rich locations and not having a leave behind .
That could either destroy the environment or or lead to detection of the delivery .
And so the exercise program was born , and that program is currently in facebook and is developing vanishing air delivery platforms in the two phase.
Right , and I know one of the exciting potential applications for these kinds of vehicles would be in sort of public health disease outbreaks tells a little bit about those kinds of humanitarian applications of.
Absolutely , so one of the first things we started brainstorming out .
The idea met hepburn , whose program manager started interacting with me , introducing the idea of being able to deliver medical supplies using the technology and how exciting that would be thinking about things where there's many humanitarian disaster and the wrong ways are destroyed .
Roads are impossible .
How can I get really critical supplies , vaccines , blood medications , water to locations that needed or needs to be precisely delivered and do that in kind of , in some cases of massive response without having to worry about going and collecting all of these air delivery vehicles .
How do I get not only the thing to biodegrade and disappear back into the environment , but how do I make the cost low enough that you can basically have a glider that you don't care if you ever go achieve.
This is an exciting time in the lifecycle of the program , writes , because I know that in the coming months , you can move outside of the glimmer and the eye and fundamental europe , but toward vehicle.
That's correct .
So if two things that are going to be coming up , that will conclude face of the program , a one is a flight test launching from thirty five thousand feet , showing a range of one hundred and fifty kilometers , and landing with ten meters of accuracy and doing that with a material search of it .
So the glider is made out of material that has as exact as possible , the same material properties as the vanishing material and the same manufacturing processes were trying to test out .
Can we actually meet these flight profiles using something within the constraints of the material properties and manufacturing of vanishing material , at the same time , we are also building a non flying demonstration of the vanishing material .
For example , we might build nonsense of four the plane , just the wing of an airplane , but build that out of the vanishing material and show that we can extract significantly complex structure from the vanishing with terrorists .
And then one year after those flight test , we will do a flight test of the actual vanishing.
Air delivery vehicle , no right .
Well , I will be excited to a keep track of that and will applaud with you when we see a first vehicle european disappear .
I wanna move to another program .
This one goes by the name zero , which kind of connection with the ever ever more sensor late in world .
And so it tells a little bit better.
Yes , so in the error is a problem designed to basically take the internet of things and move it right to the tactical launch .
So today , when we think about the internet of things , it can't be what we really want to be .
We can take about a plane to our refrigerator or toaster , maybe our car , but we really limited things that either can be plugged into the wall , or that a human can take and plug into the device , or every couple days to recharge the battery .
And that's because the energy efficiency of our electronic cooperating off of small , cheap batteries today is not high enough to sit there and monitor the environment all the time and report back things that it says .
So what we're trying to do in zero is taken of a new paradise .
Well , we actually look at a very low power levels of nearly our power to me means less than ten .
And what and I choose that value , because that's the leakage of a small coins of battery .
What we wanted to be able to set their continuously monitored environment , looking for an event that we are specifically tuned to .
That doesn't happen very often , but can't be missed , and then be able to wake up this higher power consuming electronics when we see that event .
So you can imagine what kind of events could those be .
Those could be like , maintain bridges and infrastructure with these types of sensors looking for a specific failure mode , earthquakes , you could imagine putting these throughout the environment , more thinking about augmenting vehicles to look for and find engine failures earlier , you could imagine dispersing the environment and detecting things like false fires or chemical leagues or other things of that nature .
We will hold class of these types of sensors looking for acoustic vibrational , inferior chemical , and and all of all being developed .
All that can sense these very specific profiles , reject background influences and consume less than ten and a watch .
So they basically said they are always active , always listening , but consume , basically stand by type power.
Consumption right ?
I have fascinated , think about some of the world becoming the innovated with all kinds of sensors , almost aware of our bodies .
Are , I want to move on now too .
Just one more programmers goes by the name of neighborhood , am EVA and one form of that is mechanically based .
And tana , and I particularly interested in this , because I think it revealed , sort of the way you apply your engineers , mine to this invisible world .
A variety of frequency signals that that all around us talk to us a little bit about a member .
Okay , sure .
so.
A member kind of comes from my love of looking at problems and thinking about the ways we solve them today and how those are insufficient .
And if we could just do it this other way , it would be so much better , but we have some technology , the standing in our way of doing that .
So when the people were trying to do is people communicate from really difficult environments , say , like underground or underwater , or over very long distances without some type of repeater network and.
I should point out right through ground and throw water .
Radio signals do not travel very well through those media.
I would say , high frequency radio signals don't travel very well through those media , and the key then is to operate low frequencies , and that presents a very significant challenge .
Is that the wave linked at low frequencies is extremely long , in effect , that is the reason that they propagate water and ground is because the wavelength is very long , and that allows the signal because of the physics to be able to propagate through those media over much larger dimensions .
So the way we build in tennis today , we basically push current through wires , either kind of straight wires to build things like a lecture type of antennas or through coils and other things .
And it's very , very difficult to produce a significant amount of an arcade magnetic field when the antenna is very electrically small .
That means small with respect to the wavelengths , using those techniques of techniques are fabulous at higher frequencies .
But when you get a very low frequency where you want to be main portable , it just seems nearly impossible to make an internal with any type of efficiency at.
Those scientists believe that the military does have some antenna systems that can operate in these low frequencies , but there.
In nervous , yes , they're either the size of whole islands or counties , or sometimes they travel states to communicate these banks .
In other cases , you might real , a very long wire .
That's a column or and link out of an airplane to communicate these frequencies .
In any case , the dimensions are very , very large.
So it's going to take a lot of interesting physics to go from something of that size to amazon portable technology that will generate the same.
Long wavelengths that's correct until our insight was that when we pushing those currents to those wires , what were doing is were creating electric and magnetic fields and were spending energy men .
And of course , we do that specific rate to determine the frequency , and what we did was , we looked in said , well , what if we just started with something that actually had a high amount of store magnetic field , for example , like a permanent , and instead of then using our power to create that magnetic field , we would take advantage of what nature has given us , which is this permanent magnet , of course , we've created and and machine that , but is a natural material phenomenon .
And instead , we created the art of frequency by moving it .
And then we also had the insight that moving things mechanically becomes very efficient , the lower in frequency you go .
So while mechanical based and tanner may be completely inappropriate where your iphone operates at giga hurts frequencies , it's in fact , very appropriate at a killer hurt type frequency to take a magnet and spin it , or mechanically move it to create an authority magnetic field .
Of course , magazine , only .
We're looking at the other types of materials that store these types of permanent fields , electric store , electric types , and there are other types of materials that are will be looking at the problem .
Another insight that we had was that if we should just took one really big thing and tried to move it , that the amount of store mechanical energy there will be very high , and that also would lead to a lot of efficiencies .
So one of the really key ideas , the middle program is , can we break that large thing up into a number of small , synchronized things that lower the total store energy and lower the power consumption and the risk that we're trying to mitigate is how small pieces can we break it into ?
But for the interactions between the pieces , particularly the magnetic and electric interactions between them started dominate the overall system performance .
You can imagine two magnetizer costs together .
I have a lot of force between them , they and around us one .
So trying to manage your controllers in the reaction is the big , risky part of the program that we're trying to overcome here at all.
Okay , and if you get your topic , and you imagine this program being successful , you want to be gives a sense of what additional communications capabilities would offer.
Yes , so this is a low frequency transmitters .
You are thinking about things like voice and test .
So at these types of frequencies is not really possible to do things like video forwards and employees , but will give you a new capability , say , from underground , if you are minor to be able to text or do voice to somebody above grounds , or if there were something like a mining accident , you could tell somebody where you were at , and you would have that type of communications .
Similarly , under water , maybe sixty two , one hundred meters under water , one could communicate text from underwater to the surface or to something even flying overhead , which today is , it is just not really possible.
And there is one other application that is quite interesting to me in that the way these low frequencies can travel through the atmosphere in unusual ways that it potentially could enable very long distance communication between.
Two points , that's correct .
Oh , um , at a slightly higher frequency , save around ten kilograms .
There's a wave guide that formed between the ionosphere and the surface of the earth .
We often that wave guide to bounce signals off .
And what's called the high frequency event .
So things like ham radios work based on that physics , but you have to know the location of the receiver to know how to bounced down to the receiver .
So if you don't know that you much rather feel that wave guide the arrival , and that's what happens as a technique hurt .
So we're trying to build something that can do that wave , guide and want you couple that we've got the propagation physics or the loss of the RFStravels over distance is very favorable compared to things that don't propagate in the wave guide .
And so that's what would enable you to reach these really long range communications , thinking things again , like voice and text over hundreds of kilometers from something that you can really hold in the palm of your hand , just not possible today , using other technologies.
We've talked about four different programs , and when I think about all the different technical components of them is rather amazing .
So this makes me in a realize that your engineers mind really covers a lot of territory .
I think we once had a discussion where you telling me that in some ways , you think the attack of the engineer is quite a great one that there is really kind of connection between the kind of problem solving engineers do , and the creativity that we might even see in the orders .
I'm just wondering if you got some thoughts about that and how you might comparing contrast those kinds of ways of exercising our minds.
Yes , so it takes me an idea that I borrowed from my thesis adviser can wise you at the university of michigan on their north campus .
They have centrally located our music engineering , and I think , believe architecture and his point was all they basically stuck all of the creative fields together .
This is uh some people might not think that music and engineering would go together , but I think that was his insight that becoming an engineer and being an engineer requires quite a bit creativity .
I think , particularly if you want to make anything more than an incremental improvement to the way things are done today .
It really requires the type of creativity to look at the way that they are done , understand patients of that and then come up with some completely new approach that would allow you to get beyond those limitations and make you the ten x hundred x jumps and performance that we are seeking , particularly here adopted .
So creativity is a huge part of being able to found new programs , particularly in areas that are not obvious that are leading in life from one program to another .
How do I get off the certain trajectories and get myself on a different trajectory , which is the one I want to be on .
And I think it's really the creativity that allows you to make that.
That kind of jump before we close tribe , I just wondering if there is a science fiction technologies , technology that you might have learned about when your kid , you might have read a great science fiction book .
You saw something in the movie up with a society yourself that does not exist now , but that you really think well.
Absolutely , I think both come from back the future .
So I am actually optimistic that one day I might get a whole car , and I would love to be able to do time travel .
So I am not so optimistic about that , what , but.
You never know .
Well , so , and if you could do time travel , would you be more interested in going back?
We're forward , I would definitely be more interested in going forward in time .
I was say what.
But I knew you are going to say that this has been absolutely amazing .
We've gone from vanishing materials and managing vehicles to censors that use of almost , but I were paying attention to the environment .
We've talked about harvard vehicle .
So this is just been an amazing conversation for me , and I want to thank you .
Try for spending the time with me.
Thanks , i've been , I really enjoyed.
And thank you listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dirt .