Soft technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand alternative operation technology is a driver of our times .
Since the founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , DARPA , the defense advanced research agency , has been a driver of the technology .
Welcome to a Voices from darker a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone motto , and I am your dark a host today .
I am pleased at with me in the studio at a muscle , a program manager and twenty fifteen and defence sciences of us , sometimes referred to as double starbucks because its programs , they've deeply into fundamental science in search of new foundations for technologies .
Atom stands out of global , partly because he is six feet forgers tall and carries a rugby players , but more importantly , because he isn't anthropologist and social science that makes him a rare bird of the agency with the social sciences have not had a strong presence for decades .
Adam earned his bachelor's agricultural anthropology from university and his daughter philosophy degree in social anthropology from oxford university in england , where he was also a road scholar prior to joining dark .
He was a program manager at the intelligence advanced activity europe , a dark black organization under the office of the director of national intelligence , adapt .
Atmosphere has been taken the agency into anxiety territories with ambitious goals that include fundamentally weak , asking how social science is done so that the questions , experiments , data and conclusions of its practitioners are better , more reliable , more tell and predictive of the human experience than ever in the history of social science .
One worthy .
This new baby girl has been schooling him in ways that institutions of paralleling have been unable to animals so.
Thanks for joining me in the studio today .
Well , thanks for me .
I went.
So let's start up by talking about how you became interested in science in general .
And more specifically , in the social sciences , and even more particularly in cultural anthropology.
My realization of science control million experience is a child .
I mood around a lot as a kid myself as a resident .
Foreign service was in different schools every year for about five , six year straight africa , europe .
And just because there are many cultural contexts , many culture of context , with often times informal education , as you point out , being the , the , the supermarket driver , that the realization quickly , the thirteen year old is not the same in every way we , so it's not been a third year old now moved to an entirely different culture in which expectations , rules , rules change .
Well , you start figuring out first .
Well , that the world doesn't be very differently to different people , but that that is not an introduced boundary that you can actually understand what the worldwide of other people , in some cases , if you're thirteen in the new school , you have to .
And the survivors , in other cases , is really do all the way you benefit to understand how how people think work.
And involved themselves .
So even at the age of thirteen , european , european cultural differences , and evidently you brought that programmes when you get the interview.
College , well , right .
The social scientists are enormous swaths of disciplines we refer to them , often times unfairly , as a regional .
But I wanted the answer .
Politics specifically , I think , because it was obvious that anthropology allowed you to come to be a practice of all trades , but a professional master of none , but you touch the human as user , the human experience , so you can do that apology if you don't also understand something about economics , politics , religion exchanged simple zones .
And what I was particularly focused on which was identity , the concept of identity think really , is what distinguishes humans , human social behavior from other natural physical science.
Identity is a very rich and complex idea .
I mean , they're all kinds of identities that that we can assume .
I want to just talk a little bit about it .
And I know that when you were adults for that , your disruption really focused on the subject.
right ?
Well , so I was focused on what was described .
I think , in summaries of crisis , like danny , and only give you a little context for for that .
So when we talk about danny , what I see when we distinguishing the two kinds of different kinds of enthusiasm , physical anthropology , which is , I explained my , my grandmother , when she was asking .
So we know what I would do with her physically .
The party is really the study , like other natural science of the world that makes us .
However , ocean is likely to us .
Our species of psychological trades and the physics that are played culturing , the poetry really studies the world we make for ourselves .
And so there we were into the room .
Collective fictions raise the economy is the original , and is that the identities that we have and share?
In development , and just wait , when you say collective fictions , just to be clear , because I think of economics for examples are real thing .
But when you say you use the language , a collective fiction , just explain that for a business is.
Well , as though it had a great time from a horror who wrote the spokeswoman , and I think , is right that the RSPis competitive .
Advantage is our ability to sort of believing , actually unreal .
But in the process , as you make them real , and economies are just like that , as you can see , and this is the challenge .
Social is that we want a model , so the financial crisis or crashes the opening , certain fundamental physical laws , perhaps trying to adopt models from physics or other necessaries .
The problem is , is that , by virtue of action model in the phenomenon , you can leave people believe that it , and so you actually created the phenomenon you are trying to understand the first place so that that fiction is , I don't mean to import the fiction doesn't mean for effect , affecting the rules , and we have all that way to do that , because there is great power if we all believe in kind of this , this quite efficient that we can get one , we can solve the coronation problem , which is that , which is a fundamental to complex societies .
But it also needs a source of conflict .
If my quite efficient is different from your quality fishing , we get worse that.
Oh , so let me steer you back , though .
I took you away from the crisis of identity , which was , again , the focus of what you were studying as a graduate.
Expert , right , this is the difference streams that the world makes us .
In the words we make for ourselves , while increasingly , those words are boring , right ?
We have increasing power over the physical material .
And so we talk about christmas , but then we were talking about christians in which the world we made for ourselves no longer fits or explains , or alliance with the network away .
So the categories we use it classify the real world and masculinity .
In this case , uh , in the trees of notion .
What makes a man , well , that doesn't actually work sunny in the world , in which manner not making more money than women work in a convention that has been sort of a cultural stereotype .
Well , when the fundamentals of world identity sometimes rewrap behind how to catch up , and that leads to crisis , because in various scientists , human , I am my identities .
That's that I see myself gives me purpose , gives me role , gives me my behavior .
So the crisis really matter , how do we negotiate these social behaviors and identities when the world is changing , and some people do it more successful than others , and an unusual child crisis .
And this is not the same way to look at refugee crisis , although there are , unfortunately , not unrelated .
Since when you see this , this johnson , you see this description between a social attorney in the world that it wants to explain in our response .
Unfortunately , you know , the nature of our species , sometimes to respond violently to try to post the world back into the category that we think it should be .
Or that wasn't where , you know , we understand things .
Now , now we don't , and that can be really disturbing far from our space in particular.
Right , and just so you can get a good listener , some sense of the kinds of identities that you are probably beginning to think about an impress , investigating a new ways to your programs here .
Yeah , so there , there is , there is , we have a sense of who we are as as individuals , as individuals , with different social context .
We have general identity .
We have belief groups that we want , there are state identities .
There are national identities that are nationalities .
Some of us try to be world's citizens and soldiers .
There are global identity and written me .
That's the kind of mix of things that you're talking about , talking about identity and an identity .
And I.
You are all about ten seconds to identify why social sciences are up against such a hard problem .
You just listed all the things that are probably important and role in for any particular social question .
And so how do you fetch all those things ?
And how do you figure out what's most important ?
How do you understand the dynamics ?
And I walked to , you know , as so , people study animals , for example , where they , they've seen were challenges in the complexity of some times of like champed organization behavior .
But do they know that as far as we know , marxist chimpanzee , james don't themselves , develop new social dynamics and have those identities , you'll be be more as well.
Well , you just give me an excuse to ask you a question can , based on some prior discussions .
We paid , and things are pretty .
You say , which is that social science is harder than , say , physics , which I, Ilove the idea , and I think you've got a good argument , which is what.
Well , it began not my argument , right ?
So nobel pricing physicists , miracle men and farming go ahead .
Name drama .
Yeah , I reached my mind and murray , but his mind , the component , how much harder faces would be if electrons could think in head feelings , and that sorted summarizes .
And I say , I think , will change .
So , so there is open question that I am actually trying tag will hear DARPA through couple programs are potentially more , and ideally with me and support for a future programme .
Andrews interested in this area , and we will get to those in particular later .
And the open question is our , you know , you can see the difference between the billions of dollars that have been invested in physics and the probably millions of millions of millions of labour compared to what's been investing social science .
Are we at the stage where we just need better tools to understand these things like that dynamic employee , or are we able to discover that ?
Well , this is really a different thing .
This is the fine sort of , umm , a status scientific approach we need to think about this in new ways , because there are these other weaker problems waiting for us , one of which is you change the very system you're studying .
So , so that is no open question .
But I do think right now I would .
I would just harder whether that I was .
The case was the function of visual time in the tools , or whether the function of the surgery itself .
I think it is like this is an open question , and one that I think , really we need to ask , understand from even a national security perspective of.
right ?
Well , and one of the things double is charged with doing is not only doing orange that that sort of specifies begins to determine what is possible , but also to get a handle on what are fundamental constraints , invitation .
So , and that's actually an exciting kind of space of uncertainty to be in .
We're gonna move into into a sort of a dark , but segment here in the second .
But before we move away from your schooling and your time and express , one asked you about your rugby career in your rugby experience , because I think in some ways , your experience in that social and cultural context has informed her some of the questions that you are asking in the way you go about thinking about cultural anthropology now , in the kind of darker national security context .
So talking to me about , you know , regularly , and how informs what you think.
Interesting , I probably haven't refused , but it is not upon that that they give you an intelligent answer , so we can give you an intelligence , right ?
That is whether the selection bias prompt , perhaps in that , did I choose rubbish , choose me .
I am not a natural athlete by any means , but I , for some reasons , into quickly out of the sport , and I think part of it is because it is such an hungry social sport .
It really is a team .
What do you degree that we have very few others , frankly , are we said in the weather , weather cohesion is required in teamwork .
This room for everybody in rugby .
And as we often time say , ruby producers seems to be a particularly good building character in the scar tissue , but that career to part , I think , is tested on rare basis , both against other teams , but also even with their own team .
So I became really interested in the empowering robots , as , as some people have described these things like cohesion and teamwork , even frankly , beyond identity commitments , these things are clearly important that clearly , yet the real world , even in any way we have simple rules like rubbish .
But there are really hard measure and remain at this point , almost kind of like a magic .
And we look to the best cost who are able to throw some of this magic and produce performance is from teams that really on paper should have gotten there .
And likewise , you know , this functional dynamics where you can have the best super stars and existence in perform , and then thus far , as remains , like I said , kind of this in ponderable area of heroics and trade craft , and in the wisdom of the ages , what is your science there ?
And that's , that's why I really assume all time studying the rubbish himself , and I am given particularly that uh and dirty , and we , we fight , and we work , and we and they were died in teams that actually prized in excellent target , or focus on which to go after these important books .
No , no.
Yeah , fascinating to just think about you , what is it ?
What is that magic as you call , which maybe is something distribute and something that you want to study , that will take a group of individual as a team and have this team achieved collectively in a human feeds that are often absolutely standing .
So I don't want to talk too much about that now , but I just say that you can have catalyze.
我们我们我们就是按属于as you move a tonight topic on 。
This is an example where I think social science falls down in a way , because there's what on teams .
But the issue worked with the weather chair .
It definitely reflects what done can watch sociologist , makers , of course , the incoherency problem that the way people study teams very tremendously , the measures they use very , tremendous , the often times not highly available .
There is no replication of the studies .
So , so actually , this is part of my frustrations when you turned to where , presumably they would have the answer is this magic .
There's actually very widow that can be drawn confidently from the literature , so that what say I am galaxy , given the opportunity to organize a large group to achieve something different .
What can I draft on the social science literature that helps me get there , and there's not a lot right now that I would consider be reliable , or but enough to really help me drive forward .
And that has been away other ways that we can improve .
The research itself , said that I , as commander , leader , even a programmed or know how better to put my team together to really get the most out.
Advertising to do .
Okay , well , I can tell you you're hinting about some things that will talk about it , just in in the world during your future .
But I wanna move .
Our two men screamed here toward dark , and I had actually get here .
What was the sequence of events where you met somebody to talk to somebody senior , there's always that .
How did I get my job stories so.
From the electric , well , so did you rubbish rugby choose just double double juice .
Me , I can say confidence is a darker juice .
Is you ?
So I was fortunate enough , I think , to having been the iron , but you mentioned been moving in the circle of the appropriate measures and the surveillance research area for financial security .
And I think , getting to know some folks who have done what both with endeavour , and for double , it's hard not to sort of be affected by the cashier in to realize that they will do what they are willing to take these chances and risk investments that other areas might be considered beyond tourist .
Definitely , you know , given what I said , or are you about , you know , the difference , we know the matter of money and times spend on physics and participants , if there's an agency that can actually , you make that we can three , five years over the twenty years , we might need normally enough dropped in nothing .
Well , I mean , how did you not get the opportunity get there ?
So having made a couple of machines with within the building and then mostly have been called in by some leadership , I think , really understood that both these are really important questions , coordination , collaboration , competition .
Ultimately , every national security question we really care about has some fundamental human , social and behavioral aspect to it , but reference mirror comments about the state of the literature , and they sent to which you can run our solutions as problems they realize , I think , and I hope I make people , everyone that things might be changing both culturally , with a new emphasis on reproduce , ability and transparency in the science , which , ultimately , I hope , will improve the quality , but also , technically , so technologically , we now have capabilities to run skills .
We never been able to do before we have the ability to analyze data , new conflicts , ways .
We have the ability to preregister studies that is where I announced my study publicly to out of most community period .
So were reinvesting and reinvestigation regularly the conventional models and double leadership realize , okay , maybe now to take that risky step and see if we can bring that science for a little bit.
Okay , perfect time .
And then this is just talk a little bit about each of your programs .
So let's let's start with the first program , and you manage to get through the difficult wedding and approval process .
You are referring to the next generation social scientist program , which is pretty transparent about what you are trying to do .
Next generation social science , transparent in just the most surface sort of way .
So what do you mean?
Right , so we're trying to accomplish too .
I would take probably in sailing ambitious goals , but that's what we do .
The forces were trying to get after experimentally , those important bosses emerging phenomenon we were referring to earlier , so things like collect , how does that mean you can buy other cells that the meat becomes the way what was most important for that of emerging behavior ?
Well , we know we have a lot of case studies .
We have a lot of people who should the world , but what we don't have is experimental evidence to begin the test , these different mechanisms .
So we're trying to average what we think our advances now , technology to tend to prove out of experimental capability in the process .
And this is second , or we're trying to do it so that we can have greater conference , the reproducibly of the work for itself .
So all the way from testing motorcycle , rather than being married to a single model that I will then try to , i'm actually actually trying to figure which models are more effective than.
And again , these would be models about what about what?
When this is quiet to buy danny , so there's lots in the literature about what leads the media , but we , what they all make .
In many cases , they make very different predictions under similar conditions .
If you can actually get the models to make predictions , by the way , that is another problem is many social science models are , so that is awesome , possible to say what they were predict.
And prediction predictability is a hallmark of what we might consider .
You know , that the hard science is you come up with a , and if you can predict when healthy comedy is gonna , come back around then you say , hey , i've made up of approaching account of scientists.
And I think there's another side that , which is , if you make a petition in your wrong , at least you know that how wrong you are .
And that improvements , but if you never make that position , or you engaging a practice is called hacking , which is a high position after the result are known .
This is very common .
If you , if you collect your data and you analyze them , and no result knows what the question was you are asking .
The first place .
I can always go back and claim I was looking for the answer .
I found the first place .
Then they will give me.
And then rationally we construct a possible story and to make sense of what you've.
And in social science in particular , it's hard to come up with senior in which , no matter what answer you find .
You can't with a postcard story that makes sense , no matter what I find in an experiment in social science , for the most part , I can go back in time and tell the postwar story is like that obvious that they.
Problem , okay , so we get you talking for a minute , and you succeed.
还有多余in these insane ambitions of afghanistan coming up with next generation social science 。
What was social site?
We'll barely mind again in social scientists of architecture , until i'm aware of them paying with very wide brush .
But if what word the question racing right now , backward and extended to other questions , we care about social science .
I am too cool .
Things like determines and cooperation and competition .
The process to me would look very similar , which is people will be mining the volunteer that all exists to come up with different models that make predictions , not just of quality descriptions of how the world , my worst predictions , the thing can be tested imperatively in experiments at scale that is necessary , that are transparent , that there are pretty registered .
And that ultimately , we are replicated .
So the replication process is , is really important , especially with social systems , because the answer you get the next time around will be the same , the world that will change , the participants will change .
It seems to be able to change .
But if you don't do that error process , if you don't replicate , you won't know when your model begins to fail when it doesn't installed right now .
Frankly , in insurance , many ways are just to get published .
I suppose , to get it .
We are trying to figure out how to close those incentives so that getting A.
Alternatives , what gets you published ?
Okay , so you are running another program that really sounds relevant .
What you talking about right now , the ground truth program and the name that really fascinates me because of the first time I ran across that term , actually was related to satellite remote sensing of the snow pack .
And the what would happen is there is natural of cities .
Briefly , the authorities , natural microwave radiation and goes through snow pack this , this , these signals can be picked up by sensors on satellites , and then with a model , the satellite then convert those who are signals into some measure of exactly what the snow packages , and that's important information , for example , farmers who are gonna need to know how much snow is going to be coming off nearby mountains .
So , but in order to be confident about the model , people will go on the ground , you in their snowboards long rulers are actually measured the depths , and that weight could , in a validate that the models were were working well .
So in this context , ground treatment in social science.
Well , so this is a question .
I think the economy asked if the police is dark .
So we do not have that kind of ground of in a social science , partly because the very measures we take from the very beginning of making assumptions that what we're measuring , we can't see the things we really care about .
So we have to use this observed measures and sort of hope there were captured construction of the behavior of at the end of the day .
We actually have very little idea how accurate we can be that when we refresh it , how accurately we are currently .
And then this question of animal limitations , how agriculture we are currently be when faced with these complex systems like social behavior .
So double has given me the chance to serve involved a questionable bit and say , okay , we have these amazing advances in social simulation .
And I think you target on the faults , a programme right to who is very interestingly , there is no nonsense of asian base modeling that while you run lots of little agents and see how they interact and create these emergent and very composed behaviors from fairly simple roles and.
And by agents , you mean.
We could be people doing things , people doing things .
In this case , it would have enough time that I , you give me some rules , those evidence in the right of my computer , and because my computer now , holders in north american political power , I can really start scaling this up .
I can start beyond simulating behaviors on all on the scale , on some cases of nations and international interactions right now , our approaches , we use our simulations to try to understand the royal , where is the question ?
Well , what if we , but that unhopeful moment , and I use the simulations instead as a wind tunnel , right almost that I expect , so that I have caused all truth or ground truth of these simulations .
I know I grew this alternative world and what I am seeing .
Social behavior is that there are also a social behavior , but it's still conflicts .
Now I give that as a win channel two , social scientists and other other areas of researchers .
And as then , can you give me using your method , your best approaches ?
Can you tell me what causing the behavior ?
Can you predict what can happen in the simulation when something happens , like a resource drives up , and can you ultimately help us understand what the premiers that are most important in the behaviors ?
How close can you actually get towards happening , and that tells us a couple of things , one which tools are most appropriate for which consumption is questions too .
What if any other theoretical limitations of being able to understand and predict , and that's really important , people talk about why , why anyone know what you can know .
Well , in my experience , certainly with initial security due the immigration , they're very comfortable with risk .
They have to deal with decisions under incomplete information .
So why do you want to figure out what you cannot know how ?
How is that usual , well , that gives you the boundary of what you can plan for , and if you know , for for that , and theoretically , that you can't know something , you can plan for that too .
It is a much different planning process , but that's really important .
And again , I think your dear , dear , in particular , council has operate in highly uncertain environments .
But being able to say you are so among , this is the end of this situation that we cannot predict .
It was going to have the next you can plan according to that very different from believe in , you know , what can happen being an accurate , but being very confident.
And that leads a bad point .
Okay , but it is a fascinating idea to kind of be a world you can control that world , throwing in a very circumstances has a social behavior unfolded and simulated environmental , and hopefully learn something that you can take out of the box , the computer box and applied to this sort of real world that we , britain , I wanted to talk about one more programming sexy .
Now the program is , it is a preliminary phase .
What could become a program , which are you sent out is what we call in the government speaker request for information , and that is an arrival about what?
I went to this particular quest .
Information was working at the possibility of using some argument tools to give us to help us cooperate .
The confidence we can have a in the social , behavioral science research that already exists .
So NGStwo is still thinking about how we can do social science going in the future of the program is not working at how effective we can actually be in in the evening for a widely successful and individuals .
This , our request information is ignored in that the other tremendous amount of water and research has been done , and on questions that in a deal , the initial security cares about , we just don't know how much confidence we should have in some of those claims , and that is best as examplified by the recent reproduce ability project , which is run ethical , organized by a host of different research scientists .
Santa film science is most famous , but where they actually took connecticut and psychology replicate them , and they do not , in fact , more often than they do not replicate .
And if you know , there is lots of running , of course , and national teeth that happened well.
Private is great as a great name policy to write over the crime.
This is a replacement .
This is a representative , is not now in india is not just , by the way , social sciences , right , but part of it .
Well , part of it is because the science is hard .
Part of it also stems from these , these crystal research practice that are provided by personnel .
Zhang kisses just the enormous degrees of freedom that is , if I am given a large date things I can do with those data .
And if I am only going to publish positive results , don't be surprised when I only tell you about the past results that is our natural human racism .
It's not the people more shares are naturally faking .
This is just a result of healing .
Senator wide , and yet much of the research is solid , right .
There are many things you cancer , bang on if you're building a model about humans behavior insurance , we just don't have a decent tango alone .
And so that the request from ration is asking other new ways of putting the other practice weak signals , signals in her to a study on alcohol , maybe the status of a little bit .
Maybe there's has the study been replicated , has been tested on more than one population .
You know , has anyone else about the reproduced results ?
And then I think , increasingly , there are these other symbols that we have historically neighborhood things like discussions in social media , social media , in some cases , actually an open period process .
And if you look at some more controversial studies of my , I think , you know , the discussions have occurred on this open platform to , I should be very informative .
Yes , some of it is at home and attacks , and they , but a lot of it is , I should be discussed about the other.
So strip tapping into the wisdom of the crowd .
So we.
The hard parties are in the crowd is very busy .
So how do we battle average , those that those signals are to submit the automatic , successful , as you too outcomes .
One is , I can more easily , more rapidly , more confidently , whereas the normal soldiers are the other in the second is , frankly , craig , almost kind of a road map so that if I am a young researcher or i'm a programmed research , I can work at this algorithm or this credit score for lack of bedroom , and I know how I can improve the confidence in my research .
I can work with the things that matter for increasing conference .
I can do the right thing .
I can replicate my study .
I can make my data available so that three bruise by independent parties , I can test on multiple populations .
You know , I can be transparent about my noises where they worked in , where they didn't .
It's settle.
So adam , you know , is engaging you in this conversation .
It also is occurring to me .
There's another reason why spring social science into the dark portfolios .
And it says it's because of the way the vulnerability landscape , the risk and threat landscape has been changing so much .
There are so many more kinds of risks that are inherently in that behavior and cultural behaviour .
Space , i'm just thinking about the wild , wild place of the internet and how identities are made and created and manipulated in global environment .
So maybe just before we close out , talk to me a little bit about that in with respect to the kinds of efforts you making here , your programs.
It doesn't take on to talk to any double program measure before they began to bring in this discussion .
Utility of the social complexity , no matter what platform , no matter what technology or suffering , you've pointed extremely a little bit , and it weighs quickly to this threat landscape , as you said by threat .
Landscape is of your own behavior , the unintended consequences of .
And so , so I think , you know , this is an eye .
Frankly , we have to go to begin to get a better sense of those questions erased .
I think we should be excited about our new capabilities .
We can to try to get there .
We should remain humble as we have to go for , though that it regions to remain execution .
But I , but I do think that if I do nothing other with my time of DARPA , that the idea that we can use these tools to the reengage and try to get after that social complexity that has something to contribute to national security that will have been aware from my perspective of.
Okay , well , maybe we come to know ourselves better at the right .
And with that , I just want to thank you for spending this time with me in the study of no , thank you .
I appreciate and wanna .
Thank you .
Listeners also for spending the time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dr , for more information about item russell , the programs he runs .