Stop technology.
The internet GPS in the column of your hand are tonight with technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window on the darkest core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is , I went a mutual on your dopp a host today .
I am pleased to be talking with that your time roundup , who joined the dark as a program manager in twenty sixteen , first in the microsoft technology before transferring into the strategic technology , is still in may .
We are recording our conversation from our respective homes as we do our part to slow the spread of coffee nineteenth , because we are not in a recording studio .
You made your ambient sounds like trucks or trains .
Let me tell you a little bit earlier in the morning , he collected three electrical engineering degrees from virginia technique , blacksburg , running his ph d in two thousand and eight .
Several years before that , he got seriously involved with a good new radio project .
That's GNU, like animal , which is an open source heaven for radio hackers , makers and others interested in using software models to do a wide range of radio anchor task , communicating with satellites or controlling household drones as a visiting scholar at the university of pennsylvania .
And as a research scientists at the institute for defence center for communications research in prison , new jersey , TOM .
Further those causes , which is work on other things on architectures and algorithms in signal processing for communications and the monitoring and use of the electronic expected .
Thomas is much of a community builder as he is a tech guy .
He has organized many conferences and workshops , and has been spreading the world like an adventurers and new technologies in wireless signal processing , among other radio techniques .
Town's current interest include adapted in weaken figure of radios , improving the development cycle for new single processing techniques and creating general purpose electrical systems .
Tomorrow , thanks for joining mysterious conversation .
Yeah , thanks .
I was excited .
So before we dive into your portfolio group programs , which ranged from software defined radios , and we will explain to a new category of powerful , yet affordable chips for specialty computation , intense applications like signal processing .
Let's give listener some sense of how radio technology became your.
As you mentioned , I, Igot all three degrees from a virgin attack and black spot .
And what happened was an unconvenient intellectual resource .
So I was also getting a little chairman , english literature , one of my english professors think , realized my restlessness , put me in touch with charles boston , who was a professor of electrical engineering .
But his wife , the freedom was a member of the effectively the english department .
So there are chinese connection there .
And I freely just walked into trouble .
His office , a drug , boxing at the time and said he was a software , said he had a panda board later to do more .
Well , you made the most my university career .
I was more involved in my processors and networking , and just kind of how to make computers talk to each other .
And charles is a wireless guy that we can accomplish notes and start to really look at a wireless networking , so we can .
It took me on the test , the song , moreover , a summer period and was impressed enough that it was doing some bluetooth work .
This is back in two thousand so early , early in the bluetooth era in person after it became me on , I kept working on lab .
Do more stuff , higher frequency staff and radio propagation staff in an eventual determined to a massive degree .
And he called me , well funded , well , engaged with wireless stuff followers in my pitch.
Well , beautiful , we should all have such men tools I always love , and I hear about , you know , teachers and individuals , but you know , adults , and I like to really have had transformative effects .
What sounds like you like this profit was that person for you.
Yeah , manager is the right words used for him that the number of things beyond just the skills of researcher .
And as an engineer that I learned from him out of people in our situations just had to behave as a adult in the , in the field as an engineer that is doing more than just the court.
You'd grateful that , okay .
So what happened along this trajectory ?
And as you , this interested your development , pacified as you became very much involved in the coming radio organization .
So what I would , most people , I think listening might not know what that is about .
And so I developed it just say , briefly , what is the good new radio project ?
And then I love to know what catalyze.
Near the dark , the new radio is a free and open source software framework for building software defined radio capabilities .
So desperate , fine radio , it is the ability to program in your computer signal processing technology , appointing mass to signals that manipulate the electronic spectrum .
And so we see here is that electronic spectrum .
Electronic are one of the four fundamental forces of the universe .
And we saw for radio allows us to do is right programs that manipulate one of four fundamental forces of universe .
And once that thought really hit me , and he had a number of business field that was that kind of all moment of all this going .
This is , this is incredible .
This is breaking open and making accessible to us .
And two hundreds of thousands of people around the world , they are beauty to access and control this thing that controls , as you mention drones , sadly , over cell phones or utility systems are now all connected in communication .
Honestly , I usually reach , feel that that is is rude in this .
And google radio is this tool that allows us to make.
That happened in the robot , oh , no time .
So you mentioned the world , you are having a kind of movement is your thinking about the electronic magnetic phenomenon , the world , and how you connect the interact with it .
So this reminds me of something that I know I want to get the timing of you have on your arm or arms tattooed the famous four equations from maximum of four equations to scribe electronically phenomena was at this time that you were moved to get those status.
Yes , it actually wants .
It was thinking about those four equations , but this is an excellent equations , and that shows us as as something that we , as humans have done , which is understand this , this incredible force and what it does for us are qualified in these four , in some senses , relatively simple , but they want to , you break up down the very complicated equations .
And so there are the third attitude I got to reach on on each forum , and I looked down at those every , every day and and have that moment of all of what we believe that we.
I've already to meet you in , that is one of the best metaphors of the kind of devotion you often see to science and technology .
Buy program like you .
So very cool .
The second half of my question here was , so you described the new radio .
What is it then that got you to?
And what happened was in two thousand fifteen , I met bill chapel , who was the director of the microsystem office , and he invited me to a big DARPA , even called weight .
That was showcasing what the dark of capabilities and technology .
And he wanted me to come and talk about this .
Now , this was my first interaction with DARPA as a grassroot in electronic engineering , especially from the school like virginia attack , were well aware of dark .
It's part of our funding source .
It's part of growth in the research community .
So I met bill , and it was always in the back of my head that I love to go to dark .
I love to be the kind of person I can make the contributions to the technology of the country and larger the , that's what darker .
Yeah , I always represented to me is that the most impressive , cutting edge you , this world of the quarter comes from , so it was always the back of my head .
I wanted to do this , but I never felt ready .
I might be able to figure it .
You know , what are not already foreign .
I think I am ready .
It's time to to step up and take the opportunity to see about getting into a position like this .
So I ask bill , and he said , looks like , but the reason why I want to do that back to the real through the question was the elevation of focusing on this , this project in the radio , which is wonderful .
But I had this increase that I wanted to be able to affect more , and that's the opportunity that I saw a dark was to , instead of just coding , I was able to organize and really put real resources behind some of the ideas that were in the back of my head when I wanted to accomplish .
And what I thought technology could become .
And so yeah , so I jumped at an opportunity was made of twenty sixteen when I got to sit down for the first office meeting with crumble .
The program managers and kind of realized out in over my head .
I actually , once , when you , when you meet your fellow peers of dark parts are pretty uninspiring back to that again.
You might have been involved your head for a while , but you shouldn't come to embrace the job and really become quite the PM with quite an amazing portfolio .
That's why I want to get into now .
So let's take a tour of the , in the fascinating programs that you and overseas , initially empty , owned .
And now MSTO, the two , two of the six dark technical offices , let's talk briefly about two programs .
The same related one goes by the name domain specific system on cheap programs , and one of the things related to me .
But you're clarified that goes by the name , software defined hardware .
So talking to me , well , the ocean , yeah , we hope to achieve with them .
And what the status of those programs.
Those who took great programs , I was able to formulate the full domain specific system on chip or DSsock program .
And then I worked closely with the other program manager who crafted the estate for themselves from a fine hardware , but I had been running their program for the past year when he left the agency to people on familiar with software .
It might seem weird that I went to DARPA and started running processor programs , but that's what the software defined in this really means is that what are the radio spectrum ?
And the more you want to do , the more processing power you need in order to to do all those cool , single manipulations that make sadly communications work that make five g technologies .
So new processors are cool to meet in this habitat .
The assault , it was all about trying to understand how to overcome the limitation of general purpose , embedded computing .
What I mean by that is taking your general purpose , install processor , which call about that processor is , it can do almost any mathematical competition .
You can .
It doesn't necessarily do anything particularly well , but we were able to use that as our programming platform for all the general radio work .
So we are , we were you using and slightly miss using this , this great general process .
So , but what we realizes your every generation of a processor coming out , we be able to do more because you can do news if they're faster , the lower power , all those cool things that were coming with more slow as you start to see some of those that no size of the future sizes of these transistors starting to come to to the end of the lines , far is just free processing power in .
You are waiting months or whatever , and so stealing from once in churchill , we realized the months are now .
It's time to think the transition is running out .
It's time to think what we she've LED earlier in our thinking and coming out it from the sino processing rules , like , you know , hazards , a lot of math that we go over and over again .
What if we build a hard work salary that did just that , but then we tied it down to a system on chip .
So lots of these different courts that all work on the same silicon chip package together that we could kind of balance this general purpose processing and special purpose computation to be able to accelerate those core math problems that we kept we keep burning into if we can make use of that , we get to accelerate our ability to control back to the control of the electronic government .
So that was the correspondence .
Now , the second part about the assault that's really important to me .
And one of the key concepts of a new processor to me is , if you give me a new processor without code , without a compiler , without a way to use it from software , you've literally just handed me so little fat sand .
And that is that all is good for .
So coming out from their perspective , the is also about the software tools .
How do you actually make use of with no call in many core hydrogen is computation system , so we can have dozens , of course , each one of them doing different jobs of more effectively than other .
How do you distribute the software down onto a trip like that without it becoming a massive burden to the developer , we couldn't rely on the general purpose processors to give us the speed .
So what kind of balancing knows out by having some special purpose and some general purpose and taking advantage of of the small transistor , no sizes that more slaw has produced , and I see more release .
The hard work is the entire silicon industry is produced for us , and then make a program.
That program sounds like there is really hardware component .
What it might be hard work century and a sense of specific models where software to find hardware sounds like you are using software to get specialized hardware.
Yes , and the core distinction is every engineering problem is a trade off .
And when I go , we're seeing in both the asylum establishes , you can get program ability and high performance in the same trip .
And currently those are are competing objectives , so you only can get both and give high program ability .
And the jump of his processor , highest specialization and efficiency in the athlete , we're saying that you can actually get both , but we're giving up something , so we're not going to replace the entire process or in your work station , or your laptop is create different types of architectures that meet different needs .
In my case , that the assault needs was in better processing and really hipper , specialized math processing on the signals , or or video or image .
There's whatever , what SDAjust asking is a different context of problems of a space of problems , big data , machine learning , large data sets .
You know , talking billions of a of bate of data or billions of trolls of images , or or or social networks , are whatever , whatever we're trying to understand and computer against the challenge with that kind of computational model is moving deeper in and out of the processor .
That's typically a limitation .
Often our processes are bored waiting for data to be delivered to them , and the really fast .
And it takes a military offload that data back into memory , so offered a fine hardware .
Is , how do you stuff software program , ability of the memory access models in order to make sure that you're balancing the data movement and competition , and again , without overburdening , the programmer for , for trying to specialize to this , this new architecture .
So that's the , the , the similarities and the subtle distinctions between the two and the two.
Let's settle it to another program since a little bit like software to find hardware .
So this one is called soccer to find the radio for a point out , and I think that might actually rules to go .
Go back away for you .
So what about that?
Yes , the software , fine radio is still four points on .
This is again thinking about DSS , a new table processing framework and architecture and programming environment for doing things like software , financial processing .
But then you have , we had a good new radio , which was designed to take advantage of general purpose in jail .
Type course , we need to bridge that gap , and so what we're thinking about , what's your four point now is , how do we make a general programming environment like an radio able to target hydrogen year's processors , and in reason , why is because , as imagine general proposed , processors can do anything , just not particularly .
But then you have other procedures like the famous wondering that everybody talks about as AGPwith the graphics processor unit , a lot of machine learning is now done on GPU .
They're good for what we call densely neurological .
There's a lot of problems that are represented as dense , linear , arguable problems and floated to GPU is really well .
Then there's other things like few programmable gatherings or FPGA .
Those are really good for high throughout high eye or input pricing problems .
Each one of these has a role to play in different stages of of processing and entire signal working in radio had no idea how to take advantage of those .
So we've been looking at this problem for a while .
This hydrogen is crushing problem as it will lead , but the assault is coming along , and we're going , frankly , amazing stuff and in , but we also need to suffer programming environment that can take advantage of existing hydrogen users or even future hydro genius type .
So then if I take what you will take a step back , and I think about , because i'm also a history nerd as the maximum equations probably include , but going back to the evening to the seventy people really started to start programming in these digital single processors are DSP , you know , that was kind of the release ages of what became so far radio , and then in the nineties , there was a single speak easy , and this was actually ADODfunded project to create this , this machine called speeches that was like the first soft video .
So that's kind of generation , two of software for one radios when we really qualified what a mental process , all the signals and in computers , and then good news radio , I think , represents today , what the third generation is , which is a small dinner , make flexible processing stage of the singles .
And so we are thinking , what next is , let's , let's do good processing with program ability and mixing those together with ahead of genius processing nature of all the processes .
That's the fourth generation of software video .
That's what china do is make these things both again , flexible and programmable , but also take advantage of efficiencies that different types of.
Elements provide for us .
There are so to to finish out this tour , more of the research that you are overseen , talking about a relatively small , effective .
It is called hatch.
It uses more effort in daughter terms , but he said , it really keeps me in .
My heart .
Is dark .
Program manager .
This is a new embedded device that makes software defined radio practical .
So what I mean by that is to communicate to the audience , radio spectrum , the election background , you need to have the ability to come into to transition between the art of waves .
And as the digital processors.
More programming , like a radio frequency waves in the process.
Yeah , so what we are trying to do with hydrogen is take advantage of dark technology , one that we ran in a program called the r FPGA .
And that program is a lawyer academy .
But I talked about few programmable gatherings before FGA.
Those are digital processors that they can be reprogrammed to do a lot of things .
What are , but we do the same thing with analog signals .
Can we have a programmable array , a signal processing , your amplifiers and mixers and isolators and and futures .
These are important building blocks in the for communicating , transmitting signals into the spectrum or receiving signals and in capturing them .
So I heard of that project when I came to double it , we also worked , were investing in work with zillions to create a new type of embedded of pg processor , which had embedded analytics and digital dynamic converters .
Now , those are how we DHO blocks that moved it between the digital world in the end of the world .
So we thought we could remind these r FPGA s with this in better processor , with the integrated converters .
That is a really amazing package that crazy and bedded software , fine radio platform for us .
Digital operating system on the processor .
It'll do the digital signal processing portion of the FPGA .
And it talks to this r FPGA , not a really interesting thing about us , and why we call the head truck is because it has multiple channels so you could connect sixteen and tennis to a head shock device , and something is , this is in a lecturer electronic world .
This is caught in a ray activity of the strawberries , or there's a lot of talk about that , especially with five g the more and tennis you have , the more it , it becomes an array that you can manipulate .
Well , it turns out that the collective noun for hatches .
So I thought I knew potential .
I was , because I thought that was fun , but the other really cool thing is not only easy in multi channel digital informing system , multi channel , multi function , because every antenna could be doing a different function , one could be scanning the spectrum for , for signals for interference .
One could be communicating to a sort of other could be communicating to satellite frequently .
So I truly call it on the other thing that we're pushing on in the system is the traditional commercial software radio system , the bedrock of all of all we do .
But there are typically limited to about six bigger hurts .
What subsequent hurts is important is that where most tourist real communications happened .
So your TVand over their TVam FM broadcast most cell phone up until fifth generation , all cellphones open to face generation are under the six .
Giga hurts so six times ten to the nine cycles per second .
That's great .
But what's happening now in the world is more people are trying to push into the higher spectrum , higher frequencies in the US.
The five g high band colleague , you'll also care , called no leader wave .
Those are about twenty a gaga hurts thirty seven .
Gaga hurt thirty nine gager hers .
Those are some of the new bands .
Those are well outside of almost people have access to , and so hydrogen is actually pushing up to cover .
forty .
Giggle hurts , so could tune this thing up as high as the high , the high band of five , two .
And why is that important to me ?
This kind of goes back to the kenya radio foundation , what we did in canada , radio was really open this access to the document for people to change how they learn , what singles are , what , what radio waves are .
We teach things differently now because of this type of technology , millimeter wave signals behave differently in the world .
They , they just , they , they bounce off of things .
They don't penetrate things this.
The range of ways of millionaire ways that you are talking about that sort of forty and gigas.
The thirtieth of the four days he had that type of those of these special .
This happens in millimeter ways , so we behave differently , and we don't have the tools to access them , and really , really have that level of engagement that we do with the lower bans .
And so we were hoping that we learn through kind of collective research and and just being able to have more researchers do , and their flexibility of programming the spectrum and and changing the way that they engage the spectrum , maybe hundreds of times per day to tweak , to tune something to to see how things behaved differently .
That's the level , level of access that the device of casualties can give us two to the state of spectrum , this unknown space that works you were trying to operate.
Okay , so what , just a couple of things like one is , it is very interesting to hear you are making a possible .
The crowd source investigation in areas of the electronic expectation that had not really been that accessible to as many this program will open it up to the question now is , then , how do you connect this to say the dark mission?
Which means the complexity of of interacting with the large amount of them is well beyond what we can do with the numbers and resources that we have within the do d and so for us to take advantage of it .
We really have to to engage the wider community and learn from them and build a mass of a research and research body that can help us tease the part .
What's really important , what's not , what's effective .
And what is it ?
So what were were balancing the need for technological superiority in surprise , but with building a better understanding and engagement with this incredibly complicated , but force that we , we use for all of us stuff.
Right , so we're getting to the end here , but you just made me want to ask you a certain question , or someone who has been so mercy in the electronic mechanic phenomenon to the point that you actually tattooed maximum occasions on your arms .
And when you look out at air at the end , you're bringing in a sort of radio sensitivity in a radio kind of mine said , yeah .
So you know how health failed every little millimeter of the air is , so must be a kind of very rich thing to have that understanding emerging industry , in which is your sense of nature.
Yes , I actually think it does , you know , the ultimate force operates on this level of visible late that we see through our radio waves at the community .
As it said , the satellite is the phones to their wireless .
Senators , obviously not .
It is in this sweet spot for us to use , manipulate and in bad information , and so we can move this , how we , we get over information moved around the world is through electronic development force .
That's the decade .
It's not just to play with is for the second playing with ways , but it is connecting information and moving information around us .
So so when I think about that , what you just said , that kind of poverty , sense of the world being surrounded by electronic waves , when I really see is this , this interface of of information , which has been important to us as society , to move our , to move our stories around , to move friendships around to our economies , all that embedded in the fourth in some way .
And again , that's what we are trying to help understand better and expose more people.
We have worked with them .
Nicely said , I just actually met one more question before really close out .
And it has to do with the internet of things .
This , the billions of various gadgets , smaller and large that are striving for .
Since , you know , two of the electoral magnetic spectrum to give a receive signal , sensor , signal , signals in geolocation date and all kinds .
And the second right now , this is probably another ten thousand of these internet of things .
Gadgets such as one online .
So when you think about that explosive growth and the program , so that it seems of your programs , what's the interviewer there?
It's been since the three , geez , like since then , nine days since the world has been this excited about wireless technology for , and part of it is IOT , because all those devices need to communicate over the spectrum .
And I don't go so far to say the special message , scarce resource it is , it is a renewable resource .
It's not like if you one hurts , it is gone forever .
You can use it , but it doesn't become congested .
It does .
They do step on each other that what we call interference in the military campaign jamming .
Though these , these devices communicating this understanding of the automatic spectrum .
So just thinking about it from the ability to see and engage to the automatic is one of the things that cannot be necessary for us to tease apart these challenges of making these billions of devices can work and communicate together .
The second thing is all of the personnel we do the way what I lead to call manuva bill , being manufacturer of changing frequency is changing away forms of avoiding other signals that you can communicate all that the stuff is going to take processing power .
And all these IOT voices are .
Many of them are connected to war power .
They got batteries , so you have to build better , more effective processing capabilities .
The process of so the radios have to be more efficient are programming and applications use of those sources , powers the scarce resource here .
And so that's those two key aspects of how do we use the radio spectrum efficiently , and how do we manage our battery lies on these edge processors .
The edge devices are better powered , both of those who can see themselves in the programs between ideas or program to the heritage program to STR.
Four points out trying to make can combine a lot of.
Well , attempts you usually are on at the four friends of many of the most important technological true jackets of these times .
Really exciting .
So i'm , we're getting gonna add to the end of this .
I just wanted to give you an opportunity to let me know what question I didn't ask in your poll that I didn't ask it .
And if there is a question like that asked answer.
Real quick side and know when the middle of of contracting for new program that we call data protection and virtual environments in this is creating a new process to solve a hard cryptographic problem to allow us to compute on a credit data .
So nothing about all of your , your personal data that exists in the cloud , or on another server somewhere .
If it's always incriminated , then then deeper leaks start to become , I think of the past.
No , that's a gorgeous program , because all of us are super anxious about the integrity of our data .
But we also know that it , we can use this data .
Really , we might be able to really discover important things .
Yeah , yeah.
Until that , in my world of thinking about arrive and processing , and it all coming around to really , it's about controlling that leads me to the ultimate of , how do we protect that information as we're controlling?
TOM were out of time , but I have to thank you for the worldwide of the discussion will recover so much of what you are overseen as the dark program manager , but also just really enjoyed hearing you talk about your views on the history of technology and how it unfolds in all the twists and all is fascinating .
The users as stories of innovation .
So thanks for sharing all the same day.
Thank you .
As you can hear , i'm pretty excited and passionate about this stuff that sounds wonderful to talk to him , and hopefully.
We all benefit from those kinds of passions , and then when you bring the kind of expertise bring to it , the world will potentially pro , quite likely benefit from it too .
So thanks again , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with thomas , and I hope you join us again for the next Voices from the urban , thanks also to bend celebrant for his partnership in producing this program .