Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , double the defence advanced research projects , say , has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window on the dark of the core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan .
A motto , went on your dog by host , and today , and please have with me in the studio , doctor and fisher , a program manager since twenty , in the agencies defense sciences office .
That's where she had her fellow program managers PM , as they were known in house foreign , deeply into the fundamental chemistry , physics , optics , materials and other disciplines in search of new scientific engineering foundations for technologies that can matter for national and is making her market darker as one of the few chemists in the agency after receiving her PHDMchemistry from michigan state university with a catalyst project that relied on electrically conductive government , she did a couple of research stands at the neighbourhood research laboratory , which is the navy's broad based corporate laboratory .
She also got her feet weight in technology world as a at the american association for the advancement of science , publisher of science magazine .
Then in two thousand and nine , she began with continues to be her partnership with dark first as a contract scientists , and since early as a dark program manager , when a purpose accomplishments inspired by her own successful journey to become a woman scientist and a male dominated profession , she created a growth girl , chemistry .
We took out of getting more growth interested in the molecular wonders of the world , darker .
And fisher , welcome to the studio .
That's great to be here .
Thank you .
So before we talk about your sizable portfolio of dark programs with names like make it and molecular informatics .
And this one spectrum comes from ultra violet to terror .
hurts .
You've got to tell me how your interest in chemistry is , because if you will know most people , men or women vote with panic , the incident , you say something like the period of table chemical elements.
Yeah , so , so that actually goes back to elementary school , sitting down at the kitchen table in my house growing up , and my parents bought chemistry , said that things I don't think you could probably buy today .
They wouldn't be in the store today .
It literally had a wreck on it with all sorts of different chemical , very dangerous chemicals that are probably only one of them what they were , and it had experiments and from an early age of very dangerous .
And my , my mom , specifically , my parents , both sort of just encouraged this sort of explorer tour experimental nature , and I just launched on the chemistry then through her high school , sort of all over a science , second , really choosing , and it was really a solidified in my undergraduate education at the cultural western in western higher .
And just there was something about chemistry and the way it was , and that department , that really just kind of catalyzed , essentially the rest enough of the graduate career and postpone work.
Tell me it is a little bit about that distraction project , where you use the electrically conductive diamond.
The group I was in a michigan state was really focused on developing electrically conducting diamond electors for variety of applications .
And I was in the destruction of the lab that was working on paranoid applications .
So we were actually trying to develop a new and ultra stable materials for fuel cells that really was both at credit of chemistry , but with a very practical application , and that was in inner the early two thousand , where there is a lot of our confuse , odd development and a lot of our conservative term of turn of energy .
They continue today .
But that was really the journalism.
For yourself being technology that makes the relies on fields , even something like hydrogen , but maybe hydro carbons and produces.
From that electricity , that's right .
That's right .
And in one of the one of the promise at the time was the the stability of the electrons themselves .
And electors are what converts sort of the fuel of you , all the harder , genuine an example case to electrons , electricity .
And we were trying to enhance the stability of these materials.
Okay , then before you move on to your strength in the research library , I do just wanna confirm that you did not walk with any of those who left.
I love them .
Unfortunately , there are not as beautiful as you might imagine .
There are , there are distant films of.
Really excellent , great .
So tell me about neighbor research webbs in the world , the result in a little bit about that is because I actually worked for an error for a while .
I was hired to write an institutional history for the submitted anniversaries .
I got to know the place pretty well .
It intrigued me to see the june.
Yeah , so I worked there .
I came radar , gorgeous hood to post doctor at naval research lab , working with them double roles .
And they worked on power and energy related applications , not with diamond , but , but with other , the electoral types .
And so I was assembly , taking my interest in insert of power , energy and alternative sources to a group that had a long history of of success in the space of the .
So I spent A.
Two years there , working with them .
Actually , I got to know deborah , when I was , there are the two excellence , very excited to me the year .
And then the funny thing I work at tripolis as well .
The american association for the events of where you've learned a finger to about science and technology policy , that's an interesting turned away from the lab and into this other component of the home scientific reports.
Yeah , so I actually learned about the triples fellowship when I was in graduate school .
And it's , you know , it's a one year potentially to your program .
I'm a , if you renew for a second year where scientists , engineers come to DCand either either serve on a couple of homework for members of congress or congressional committee , or work in executive branch .
And scientists at my time , as a trouble's fellow working at the national science foundation , and that was my first kind of entry .
If you willing to policy by the personal , essentially , how do we sort of change the scientific words by funding specific areas for technology development?
Okay , so I am also realizing there is something weird about .
I guess both of our cbs , because I am swimming you to your experience .
And i've got double on my resume as well .
I think this is practice is that i'm not going to mention it again , but there are some , some.
Parallel , I just I wrote the open to follow you where.
So let us let us turn to your topic experience .
You started as a cedar contract worker , and then you became a program manager in the defense sciences officer , talk about the early city phase .
And and how that kind of sacred into A.
Your program manager face , yes , that's a really interesting thread , because I am eat shapes what my interests are today , all the , all the way back to the first day that I worked at arba , so actually heard about that from a friend who who worked for a company that had see the contract here .
And well , he didn't work at our bodies that hate , there's this opportunity is something that the interesting is was right after my triple leadership was running up with me up .
And I said , you know , that sounds pretty interesting .
And the opportunity was , was working with a mathematician in the defence , signs of his bad man , ben was , is a server , a genius mathematician who wanted to surround himself by people who knew other things , chemistry , biology , physics .
Those are the things , and so he was really looking for someone to come to provide a length to chemistry that sort of he could then think about how to apply mathematics in that space .
And it was probably one of the scariest first days of my life , but I decided to do it anyway .
I am , it was an image , amazing opportunity and realized the sort of the math in the programs that that he had going still again .
As I , as I mentioned , all the impact my thought process today means the programs I have today .
I am AIcomponent machine learning based components .
I'm complexity , those sorts of things , which are things that are he addressed from a fundamental level .
Many years ago , when I started , and I sort of weaved through a meal as I started a girls .
None of us are here for all that long .
And so I am worked for a material scientist , and I came after getting back a little bit closer to my roots , but still being able to bring in those things I learned from banned from his performers and the programs that he had and was developing and.
Right , and just for listeners who might not know how this sort of the basic structure , who works is a program manager , who is in charge of a portfolio of programs .
We're going to talk about that in your case soon , but then each program manager has , has one or several seaters assist .
And so what might be a typical role for a seat on the typical program ?
I mean , when they , when it comes to working with those research groups that become part of the overall program of.
Yes , it really , it really depends on the programmers , often the program manager , but generally speaking , you serve as you can serve the subject matter expert where you have your person in the room with that expertise in chemistry .
And when questions arise about , for example , how to appointment authorities to accomplish related questions , you can then think about , well , you know , if I think about the material , and I think about some structural considerations of that material , those have dimensions associated with them .
How that is that , could that be addressed ?
Mathematical design for material eventually .
So , so it is providing a subject medicines , but then also , how do you bring that perspective of that field in two of the program at hand , because it's always about sort of what the program is exploring and how various disciplines and and approaches can impact that , so subject matter expertise , providing a sort of reviews of literature and things like that in and some help with sort of program strategy , industrial programs are all about how you manage them to function more sufficiently and towards a specific goal .
And so that requires a team of people , I think , really kind of through all the different ways with which that might happen.
Case something was about a year and half when you became APMAprogram manager , most PM and management is a few programs in the several positions .
But you are , as we think you got seven , perhaps even more , or than that , some inherited from previous another program managers and some of the youth pitching , we will get approved through the hearing wedding process here , so we can talk about all reason and debt .
So I would really love to , let's just talk about a few , and let's start with the makeup program , which I actually can tell you .
It was started by former program manager here .
Terrible required , who I have a special , funniest work because he was my first guests here on the Voices from global partners .
So you've taken the time to to one day , make it program so tells little bit the vegetables is .
And what this sadness is.
The primary goal of the makeup program is to fully automate the sentences of small molecules .
And what I mean by that is , is , we have a small molecule like I be proven that that might be some sort of pain medication or a small male to energetic or a small molecule agriculture chemicals are the building block materials for for what we have in it on a daily basis , and we need to to figure out how to make them .
So , by and large , right now , that that that , by hand process and expert cameras were going to a lab and and mix things up in in biggest and testimonies and wrong bottom flasks , and really define , I wrote to a malaysia .
So that round is like a recipe that you might have an introduction to be a cake with a certain taxation of certain flavor .
And you don't know in advance what that route is .
So you going , and you test out very steps to i'll particularly molecule , so molecules might take a five steps in that crash means I need to go from a set of starting materials , and you five different experiments , five different transformations , if you will take it to the extra product to molecule , it takes much longer than you might imagine in your hand to design around to molecule that that noise done before it might take me through .
Afraid for the six months to do so what we try to do with make it actually provide computational tools that can help us define that road , three machine learning , and then build a device that can actually implement that route.
For completely hands free sympathies , and we are just needed to stop here with that machine learning and supply to chemical sympathy , which is very interesting sounding to me .
And if it sounds like like you have to gather a tremendous amount of data from the chemical literature of feed to your machine , and so that it can pull out of that likely series of steps that would work raised to produce the military adventures.
I get that right ?
That's absolutely right .
And there are , there is existing data from the last hundred years ago of chemistry once in the literature , but we actually having to generate a lot of as well , because as , as you might know , the data that you need to train , machine learning algorithms is both what works or the positive results , and you also need what doesn't work .
And it turns out the scientists typically don't publish what doesn't work .
We might have the captured in our levels of books , but we don't publish that information , and it's not available in database , and that's what so that your machine learning doesn't take it on a dead end , right ?
So that's right , it needs to know what doesn't work .
And we actually had to both and generate that computationally , so we generate sort of negative result .
If you and we also built a rapid screening platform that we can rapidly test various reactions , and we're collecting all of the data for the molecules are made , and then those molecules that aren't made .
So these reactions that don't work when we want all of them information to them feed into these machinery and algorithms to them help us understand what's the best path or recipe to get to a certain moment.
Okay , so this machine learning , but also in this , upon a mistake in its machine , making right .
So so this whole thing is really automated .
Your machine learning a song you have to try these intensification that it grows , and then then a bunch of gadgets are going to end right?
Great , so we're trying to accelerate both the , the brain of the chemist in terms of of having to sort through and sit through what route to use and what route to test .
And also then the implementation of that on a device so that there will be a fully automated process and not not only automated from the perspective of making one molecule , but we want one device that can make a lot of many molecules that's.
A pretty complex undertaking .
So as an invasion , the whole system , it is sort of making me think a little bit of sort of like a molecular version of the star trick replicator or something like that .
But where maybe I would bring this , make it gadgetry somewhere under maybe to a to a battlefield where I might .
This is that chemical , mechanical , can you take us through an actual scenario ?
Let's say your successful with make it .
You have these , make it technologies , these gadgets , boxes that you can shift them , or who might want that with.
I think about this in insert of two main ways .
One is , one is from the perspective of if there are times where you might need to generate some , some medicine , for example , remotely in the field , this device would allow you to do that .
It will allow an announcement to come up the device and saying , I want medicine , eggs , and the device would then be able to define the road to that medicine .
What is the most efficient route , most cost effective for out the most environmentally to be able to make that medicine for you .
I also think about it from the perspective of a reproductive and enabling sentences for , for fields , for research , tool for fields that don't house and that it , but teeth .
So , for example , the field of military biology practice , you can have a make a device in their lab , and in the rate small amounts of chemicals that they might need in their research without having to purchase sort of a large , large products , or in a products that are necessarily available commercially .
They built them to navigate the research well.
Interesting okay , well , well , good luck with with , make it me .
You take it to the finish line .
I wanna move to another program , which I find just absolutely fascinating molecular informatics , you know me , we've also gotten familiar with the idea of thinking of the oxygen to click as it as an information containing molecule .
Names contains genetic information .
We often think , say , it sort of it has the genetic or the molecular information blueprint of a person .
But you're taking this idea of multilateral information to entirely different , and whether a dishes places , can you talk about?
Molecular informatics , yeah , sure .
So malaysian informatics is it kind of the crazy institution of a really , what would you do if you could actually store data in the physical form of a molecule ?
So nature does that , as you mentioned in DNA , that's how that's how we store information for our genetic codes .
And there there is worth going on to store actual digital data using ones of our digital in dinner .
So dinner has these four building blocks , and you can essentially code .
The zoo is in ones of our digital data into this for building .
But you know , when we started to think about this in terms of how we could both accelerate ultra dance data storage .
So that's the benefit that molecules providers is from a density perspective .
You can store much , much more data in a very small physical form.
But also then minutes as compared to say , the transition based to the storage on A.
I like to worry , my name is very things like that .
Take memory .
But then if , if , if you do that , there are , there are so two threads here .
One is that nature uses four building blocks for molecules to store our the complex instructions for life .
But there are millions of molecules and and why limit ourselves to those for so we start to think about this from the perspective of if we could actually sort of address and access the richard political chemistry to store data .
What could that then enable from either a density perspective or a computational perspective ?
And that's what we started to see this .
This mix between storing data and are carrying it , which is which um is really good with DNA right now .
You , you write the data until the DNA strength , and you put in refrigerator and for later , but could you actually use that information in the molecular form ?
So could you compute it on that molecule for some functions of computations are , like , you know , you might want to do an additional motivation , or you might want to do .
You might want to a search of a large data set .
So well , a large image set do some sort of machine learning on that image set .
And what molecules offer is not only the ability to store data in a very , very dense way , but also a very highly parallel processing .
And what I mean , you know , chemical reactions have been relatively quickly , and they happen centrally simultaneously .
So if you have a bigger , full of money , you have multiple reaction parts , all happening at the same time , as opposed the sort of cereal processing , or one right after the other processing that that we might think about for today.
And then there are particular kinds of problems where this molecular computation is would be better than than the kind of commercial case.
Exactly what we're exploring .
You know , we have high policies about where that might be true .
We have some approaches that are looking at things like similarity , search for a very large of images .
So can I find all of the images that have a range shirt , and can I do that much , much faster than a conventional computer might be able to do it ?
We're looking at problems and involving signal processing and optimization .
So so how can you optimize our response ?
How can you get rid of the best I am function from that response , and what we're really looking at is , is , can molecules enable us to do things like that , and or can they enable us to do sort of a computation that a conventional computer that sits on your desk cup would not be able to do.
I just want to drilling on one part of this to see if you can help me understand , say , how is the result of a chemical reaction saying this molecular computation , some of our car responds to a red shirt in an image while white shirt in the image .
How does that molecule?
Map to the object , so that depends on how you encode the information .
So I give you an example that kind of easy to grasp .
We'll go back to DNA for a minute .
So DNA again has these , these four base pairs , and we put them together , and and that string we can men with that string in the cold that we use for that string weather is ACTGor GCTAwhenever we design as the cold for a red shirt , we can actually then sympathize those DNA strength and an image that has a red shirt , and it will have that richard code , for example .
So if I have a string of a hundred of the ATCengines , the coach for that red shirt will be embedded within that , and we can actually search with that very quickly from with , in a molecular and and with DNA , we might do that with them complimentary strengths .
So it focus understand that that DNA has is a sort of a double strengthen process .
We're working in the encoding on the encoding and the story with single strength , so we can use that that sort of based pairing and phenomenon that that nature uses in DNA to .
Then , how do we reach in to that sort of liquid steel of of data and only plug out those strengths that have that code?
A red shirt that sounds absolutely amazing .
One thing I think would be interesting to maybe try to give .
This is a sense of is just how dance the storage can be .
I mean , you know , sometimes you hear people talking about storing the entire contents of the library of congress uh in something the size of the sugar queue by the library , congress is becoming an information unit .
So when you talk about DNA as storage me , how much say I mean , this might be difficult , but in indian aid that could pack into a sugar cube , like how much would that?
The one of one of the best kind of images I can provide this , if you took all of the data that have been generated in the history time .
Ubuntu , like twenty , fifteen or twenty sixteen .
If you saw that in DNA , you could pack all of that into something the size of the next UV, absolute standing tip , sort of put an explanation point on that what we're trying to do in electronics is provides for the practical DNA storage solutions that we can compute on , as I mentioned .
But access that brought a pilot of molecules which might provide.
Higher density levels right ?
So in that case , biological evolution leads to DNA with this four building blocks AC, but that doesn't mean we have to stop there if our purposes or something else like data storage , you might have medicinal building works at one thousand different functions that's.
That's right , and it , it allows us a lot more flexibility in our , in our designs .
We think a lot of doubt about not only developing enabling capabilities , but thinking about the ultimates are a scalability and implementation of those capabilities .
And diesel really is looking at things that we might actually realize .
In ten , twenty , thirty years , but we always have that in.
But these are different .
Scientists are up .
That's right .
young .
Okay , so we've just touched on two of your other programs , just briefly , one of them , ACDC, that stands for egg , nasty .
The militarization of chemical agents .
And that just sounds like a great idea.
Yes , it is a wonderful and necessary , necessary thing , unfortunately .
So the ACDCprogram is , is designed to make transport of devices that can destroy chemical religions .
So really what we're headed with this is actually building a device that is almost a conventional diesel .
If you imagine a diesel engine and what we're gonna be doing with the diesel engine is using the commonwealth agent as a fuel .
So just like as you would burn in engine , we're burning chemical warfare agent and destroying it in the process so we can produce energy from the sandwich , but we are also then destroying chemical for region , and ultimately , what we're building is a prototype to pick up truck with an engine in the front that this pickup truck can drive to a site run off of the chemical horrigan to store chemicals or region .
And that we can drive.
Well , that sounds like sorts of pleasures like , I think , okay , maybe you absolutely succeeded .
And if you test this.
Test we've tested the engine concept , and we're right now .
We're developing .
We're building the full system of developing the.
Okay , the rest of your many programs that will talk that right now is scale is because I mentioned earlier in the interior that stands for spectral comes from ottawa .
Harry hurts , and when i'm talking about here about comes that we used to make our hair look nice .
Right , this is something else.
That's right , the scale is , is a focused on developing compact sources for spectroscopy and spread trust pieces , essentially chemical measurements of various species .
So if we want to know what species are present in the air that were breathing , we might expect us to find out , and snow was really designed to take a capability to have been developed at a single wavelength and expanded all the way from ottawa hurts , as you mentioned in the reason that you want to do , that is because molecules behave differently when there are sort of energies .
If you wear weight late in the UVregime than they doing a terrorist regime and different systems respond differently .
So UVis is very good for integrating biological systems and claims , whereas terror hurts might be really good for really complex mixtures like breath analysis .
So people are very interested in using terror space before for those complex mixtures .
Until scott had sort of two threads , when is to develop the materials to miniature , rights are very sort of high fatality for spectro scope across the evidence .
Heritage , swim light sources .
That's right to use for the sort of spectroscopic application .
And the other was um to actually demonstrate , let's say that we can build these things in a laboratory .
What can we actually do with them than in the field , and what we've shown is that that scott offers the ability to do things much , much faster than conventional systems .
So I can take a spectrum um in a matter of middle seconds .
What might have taken me minutes to do before that is very important when you , when you have something that that is a matter of whether you want to know that there's a chemical attack , for example , you wanna know as fast as possible , and you want to know exactly what that agent was , this kind of spectacular tool can tell you that .
And so we've been able to show that we can do the spectroscopy of a large distances , so much link distances , which is really important to monitor larger areas .
This might have implications in oil , gas industry for gas leaks , for example , also for air quality monitoring across the city .
There are a number of different factors that you can , and either all I save .
So , so we don't worry about safety challenges , and we're really looking to find out how we might apply this special topic method uh in a , in a duty and an outside duty contexts.
And you did just mention , along the way , even breath analysis that that begins to sound like a biomedical application going to the husband .
Research indicating that there can be in a really subtle science in the initiative of the chemistry , but of an explanation right that can be indicative of some conditions.
That's right , and and really what we're getting in something like brazil analysis , or any other biological or complex system generally , is you getting a lot of chemical , lot of signals that might change frequently or over time in the concentration might be very , very low .
So developing a technique that can can do both and do both deal with that .
The complexity of the number of different analysts have feared them from different things in that sample , and also do it very quickly and distinguish them from each other is really important.
Okay , then just finally honest that word COM .
Umm , I take it because if you would look at the distribution of wavelengths and so that represent each one of those , then there is many lines in a way , look like the times of come.
That's right , that's exactly right .
So so you get AAlight source that provides many wave links all at once , but they have a very fine spectrum resolution , which is really important again for the sort of complex environments were dealing.
Okay , so we , we've kind of touched on four of your programs , and we will have to leave the other ones for a another time , although our listeners can always go to the dark of website and find out more about those .
So you've been a program manager for about a year and a half .
And that means that you probably have a couple more years to go .
That's typically the case .
So just wondering if you imagine back to your time here at dark , but from advantage of of ten years from now , and you examine what has come of your work of your programs safe .
Scott will make it .
What do you hope you will be able to say at that time?
I really , you know , looking back , we've spent a lot of time here .
I'm spending a lot of time thinking about where my , these things go , and that's a lot of what what are produced is built relationships without organizations to transition the technology that we develop .
And so IODCseats to what that answer might be .
There are some projects I have where it's going to be continued scientific and technical development .
This is going to be a lot of knowledge and might be in a twenty to thirty years before anybody sees anything , and it might not look anything like it does today .
I think , for programming , like , like , make it , we might actually see these systems , and we might actually see some , some generation of the systems that we're building now as the first generation asked michael devices , we might see some of the industry and through the chemical production industry , using some of the , the competition , social tools that were developing .
Um , I think the programs like make it in ACDC, Ican see a very practical sort of field application and more programs like military and dramatics .
I think it's were just the forefront of defining what are the questions we should be asking to really begin to understand the opportunity for molecules in in something like computing.
Written as I gave myself , if I try to be you for a minute , I mean , if I knew , say , ten years from now that the ACDCtechnology that I work on helped to decontaminate time tons and tons and tons of very dangerous chemical warfare regions .
Well , I mean , I would feel like I have come for something like.
Yeah , after saying , even even even being at upon a daily basis is humbling experience .
But then , you know , seeing something that you are working on , and their performers are working really hard to develop , become used in either the dirty or a broader context .
This would be incredible.
Oh , and then , as we're getting towards the end here , but I did just want to touch back on an interest of yours that you express way back when you are graduate student , when you were , you're a woman entering the world of science and in what traditions have been a male dominated kind of world .
But going further , not just getting through that yourself , but also china , inspire young women and girls to do this the same as the girls .
Go to interest , patching chemistry .
I want to say a little bit about that particular experience .
And then , if , but exactly continued that kind of ventures , even later in your.
Yeah , so , so that it just really started in college , college in graduates .
So I was actually part and held leadership bowls .
And in organizations of my undergraduate and graduate institutions , they were really geared towards sort of women scientists .
And we did outrage to , to to young girls and worked at science , personal things like that .
But we also then work community for each other , and the faculty at our institution that is not .
It wasn't something limited to a student population and a sort of professional levels .
And and I learned a lot through a lot of these conversations about explicit bias and implicit bias , and an authority of couldn't cook reasons , you know , that there is an under representation of of both women and other under represented groups .
But for me , it wasn't about finding the answer .
The reason was about sort of empowering those around me .
And that happened at that level .
It still happens today .
But I think I do it a little bit more organically now , as a possibility involved in organization is much more about and trying to fill a hole that other women might have in terms of , you know , having a circle of of people around them , men and women help mentor them and grow the careers .
And that's one thing that that I do try to focus on , and also , then again , make sure that I have that in my own life as well , because it's important for everyone actually took , make sure they build those relationships for folks to the help.
And teaching and learn and grow .
Okay , so we works at a time , but I just wanted to ask you , if there is anything about science , double your careers , chemist or anything I suggested to come up , there would be an interesting thing to listeners.
You do not know how funny songs .
Well , tell me , I have fun .
This one .
Well , this , this big being being the podcast , but also live in january at DARPA .
And and I say that because it interact with amazing top nut scientists on a daily basis , a lot of political times a day , and that's really exciting .
And it is a really fun , and it's amazing opportunity .
And those are the folks that are doing the hard work to employment , all of the ideas that we , i'm really put them to practice .
And and again , from , you know , the perspective of coming to work every day and being humbled by that and being so excited and energized by what they have to bring in terms of various and their talents.
So I just wanna thank you for spending time with me in the studio and getting up to speed on your programs .
Thank you so far , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from DARPA .
We're more information about infrastructure , the programs that she and her colleagues run in the defence science office and the other breakthrough technologies dark is working on visit , darker now .