Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on the most operation , and technology is a driver of our times since its founding a one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , the defence advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window on the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible.
My name is ivan , a motto on your dark post today .
I'm pleased to be talking with mister john waterson , a program manager , sends twenty seventeen in the agency's strategic technology .
We are recording our conversation from our respective homes as we do our parts to slow the spread of covered nineteen , and because we are not in a recording studio , you might hear ambient sounds like traffic , planes and birds prior to arrive in a darker .
John was a senior program manager in SRIinternational advanced technology and systems division over a number of years there , he LED defence research programs in cyber arctic sensing unmanned vehicles , among other technical areas , with his pipeline from SRITEDERBAR.
John brings with him interest in maritime autonomy under distributed sensing and non traditional communications .
John surely developed some of those interested in his twelve years in the navy doing what she lived on three different submarines and learned how to operate in nuclear actor .
He continues his military service as a commander in the USneighbourhoods .
John received the bachelor signs to read electrical engineering from the us naval academy and a master science degree trickle engineering from stanford university , earning that agree in two thousand and one .
John watson , thanks for.
For joining me in this conversation , thank you .
I mean , this is a great opportunity to talk today.
So interesting bit will arrive into some of the programs you are overseeing .
One of these seems like they're hoping to install a century and nervous system into the planet's oceans .
Another one has to do with developing a back up to GPS in case that must have system or two suddenly become unavailable .
Another is about creating a GPS like system networks under water bowl .
Them hugely ambitious .
But before we hear more about those programs , i'd like to know something about the influences and experiences in your life that turned you toward electrical engineering and a career .
At least the first period of the.
One of things has always dreamed .
I wanted to figure out how things work and kind of work at a fundamental level .
And so when I was thinking about going to school , electrical engineering allowed me to understand how computers , phones and all the digital communications are today was working .
So that's kind of what attracted me to electrical engineering is .
I want to lose people who is it satisfied with their son , black box and wanted to get down into the northern boats work with the navy .
I thought it would be a great , great opportunity to see the world and a big believer in making decisions as you move through life to maximize your opportunity while growing up in high school , I was involved with the scott , so I always had kind of a big service component .
My life .
I don't have a military family , although my grandfather served in the navy and two , I went to the neighborhood academic , not knowing what I wanted to do .
I feel like , maybe I don't know what I want to be when I grow up , I probably still want to be when I grow up , and maybe there has been a place where I can explore many areas that interests me and show success .
The navy trains everyone to do a very important national mission .
And so again , I pick submarines , and I think I learned a few things along the way , and it's been very helpful.
You brought up the idea of the black box , and particularly in our electronic realities , we have so many these black boxes in our lives .
And yeah , that's why I have actually always admire the electrical engineer , because that is a profession that some sense of just almost everything about those black boxes , they transistors and other devices that are incredibly manipulating them , how they all look together , how software is interacting with them , how directly creating the capabilities .
So I think you so as well , if you want to know how things work these days , you probably couldn't have done better than an EEtraining .
And I also want to just follow up on your survive experience in the navy and working on submarines .
And if you know , one of the smoke so population out there that actually knows how to brand a nuclear reactor .
But wonder if any of the that experience , and any of those skills that you developed is that setting is helping you in your new role since twenty seventeen , as a program manager.
Well , it still feels new .
That's another thing about life .
A dark book goes by super fast , but getting back to a life on a summary .
Everyone on a submarine is responsible for everyone else , right ?
You have to be an expert in your life job , because the ocean is cool , and chips really shouldn't be able to submerge below the surface of the ocean and survive the basic thing that is taught every summer winner is , you are responsible , and you have to become an expert within your area of influence and know everything about the ship that you are living on so well , it on the summary , and I was more focused on mechanical systems , hydraulic water , the nuclear reactor , and less on the black box is computing .
I still use those tools every day to do in an important mission , and that's what really attracted me to summarize in the first place was , I felt like they always were at the tip of during the coolest missions around the world , and I wanted to work with people who have volunteered to do that .
While I played out my activity.
Okay , because you're one of the few people I know who , who has lived on summaries under water palace for extended periods of time .
Now I know you are in various machines that you just can talk to me about .
You can talk your kids , can talk your wife .
But my guess is that there are some pretty crazy things that probably happened .
Very fascinating , interesting things down there is something that just surprise you , that you actually can tell us about.
There is a lot of great stories on board summary , and my first dive to tested up on the USSto meet carter .
My job was to to check to see if a hatch was going to work at death in the thing is , as I climbed up in this hatch , and I knew the pressure the ocean was pushing down .
There is no way was going to open , but I had to move the mechanical linkages to make sure that it wasn't binding under the extreme pressure in opening towards fully open position and all the scientific knowledge and words , as others , thousands of PSIpressure on the outside of this .
But here you go , you're opening it to the maximum position on the entire , you know , unlocking that wet , and just to make sure it would work .
And boy , that was one of those who got to believe in everything that's like that .
There are similar things like crawling down the end of a torpedo too , but things like that , a very unique experience is that you just want to find in other navy.
Shapes , thank you for give me some sense of some of the moments on the summary .
And so just want to keep moving forward here in your career before we get into talking about your programs and suggest before coming to DARPA , you're at a serious international for number of years , as ryan has had a bunch of touch points with the agency uniform actually decades , including some , historically nowhere , the project scenarios in a library , computer technology about excused machine interface is things that sort of .
But i'm just wondering about you are how you got to starbucks story .
How did you go for mystery to dark?
It's true as a ride .
I mean , I first was introduced as a right in graduate school in parallel .
And when I decided to get out of the active duty navy , I went back to as a ride to connect fuel my intellectual curiosity .
And when they're in melbourne park , you see the first mouse .
You see the cocktail napkin where the internet was kind of sketched out you .
We meet the researchers who built and interfaces like that .
Okay , and all of which have dark connections .
exactly .
And so I was given the charter to build a marathon portfolio that has arrived based on my naval and ended up winning two dark contracts , started performing on those contracts and interacting with the people in the dark of the buildings .
And I realized that I could move from , you know , industry into the government and continue along the strategy of kind of making really interesting solutions for a lot of my neighbor.
Yeah , so you're bringing it also that additional kind of special experience has been a former performer , which has started speak for a researcher on contract , on on a particular program .
And I imagine that is really serving you well .
Now , on the other side of the program manager who is giving contracts out others to work on your programs.
You understand some of the dynamics around what is the business case for this , or what might management be needing from the principle investigator ?
So you understand how this negotiation works between government and industry , and is where all trying to create these interesting technologies.
Now , let's dive in to your programs .
And for the first one , I guess it's more like we're floating into the program , because there isn't a floating sensors are going to be a key component of it .
I'm talking about your ocean of things program .
We join .
I love you to tell me and listeners about this program .
What's the need you are trying to meet with it .
And what have you ?
And the researchers , the performers you're contracted to work with on the project to c you'd so far.
Ocean of things was born of my understanding of the ocean .
Is it in in this realization that it is so amends in recovering seventy percent of the earth's surface , and even with all of the ships , all the aircraft , all the satellites and all the existing centers , we are severely under sampling this environment .
It's a dessert of data , and we need to come up with a new way to sample it .
And then with those new sensors , lisa is things , floats .
What can we do with this new high resolution data to serve existing academic , commercial and military users in the maritime environment .
And and all I seem pretty brought , but to be honest with all the investment that has been done in the commercial space with things like cell phones and microcontrollers , you're able to get very low power , low cost processors that are able to now make decisions while flowing out the ocean in the communicate what those floats found back to cloud storage so that our performers can do data analysis on this .
And that's a game changing.
Paradigm I want listener sexually having their minds , just some sense of cool and vast and motivated .
The system is that during a regional hero , in fact , we are well under way to bring into a realization .
So we'll be good if you could focus on , on on the main component .
So I wanted to do talk a little bit and be described it about those floats .
You talked about how their communicating to a system of satellites , and what is going to happen with the data that the floats are really those satellites to other analytic systems on the ground.
One of our technical areas , and that's how we break down our programs that dark is really delivering this flow hardware in face .
One was we just completed .
We had three performers who are building kind of environmentally friendly flooding sensors , and the sensors were not just traditional maritime scientific measurement devices .
There were more like three year old cell phones , and because they were three old cell phones , they all had the same things you do on your cell phone , you have a microphone and cell campus GPS , and limit the overall causes rises .
We actually had mission centres as well .
Things like higher phones , cameras and suffered fine radios .
And so we're trying to do is in those sensors in to a platform that was lost in the harsh ocean environment , and that is a challenge .
That's really difficult because the ocean marine can look at it so harsh , and these floats are trying to be so low cost .
So we're previously pushing at a dissidents because traditional boys and ocean going platforms are very expensive .
We don't build lots of them .
So we put really exquisite sensors on to abstract the most data .
This is solving the exact opposite corner of the spectrum where we're trying to build lots of sensors , where that are commercial quality , and then put them into the ocean environment .
And my thesis is , if you have hundreds of these lower quality sensors , you can and argument existing sensors and filling the gaps in ocean understanding .
And one of the news things we didn't face , one was really look at the materials and one performer used vacco to cardboard to be environmentally friendly .
One performer used glass , as in capitalism , can be more like another traditional japanese fishing floats , and one performer was more traditional innocence of they used aluminum , but used the word to provide the bonuses .
So these floats are designed to operate for month on their own , often solar powered , and since the environment of their own , and then the only thing is , since they have processes , they can realize when there's a change to that environment and report that change back to me and our servers in santiago .
So right now , we have floats in the pacific , the golf of mexico and even the mediterranean sea .
And we do that the original satellite , so really is more of a medium altitude satellite .
What were using is their small birds .
Data service are floats , sweet .
In essence , three hundred and forty bite messages every fifteen minutes back to our servers , where we can check their status , see what they are and generate a bunch of interesting data products for user community.
I love that the trading energy , because I mean it is pretty good , right , because the original idea of twitter was , you know , it sort of like , what are you doing now , or what you , but you've observing now , when so now we should talk to you better having all of these floats .
You tell me , tens of thousands of thousands of floats throughout the asia.
So this year alone were building over five thousand floats of a design that smaller , lower impact and has more sensors on it .
So we're increasing both in the number domain and in the canada impact , or moderates of something that we can achieve .
So with thousands , now we're going to start to have really tested the thesis that I present a deal where number might be more important.
Right now , it also excites me so much about the ocean of things is the way it actually can be a value to , you know , many of society sectors , of course , we're at dark others at the beginning of DARPA defense advanced research projects agency .
So surely things like situation , awareness and surveillance are part of what you have in mind , what dark hasn't mind .
What do you want to have in mind with the ocean of things , but you also how valuable it can be kind of as a new century system in the ocean for fundamental science and just for monitoring the condition of years.
You've got that exactly right ?
So when we did a survey of the existing censors that are out there in the ocean , we find out that , well , if you're in our whole ocean graphic institute , you build yourself a sensor , great collection data is out there .
You know , some of the new ones are saying , after for four years , at times are great , but it's very similar to the same sense that the neighborhood oceanographic coming and could deploy , or a naval surface ship could deploy to get the situation .
Awareness community member would employ .
And so instead of each of these individual entities pulling up their own stove types of information , I realized , why would we figure out how to build a common platform that generates utility for multiple people ?
It's the same fundamental data , and like you said , doubt with its defense , head on is very interested in understanding the situation that all of its forces will be operating around the world .
The thing is , this is while tracks and figuring out where all the activity is kind of important in that , you still have to build the foundation of the environment to which those activities can be built upon .
So a better understanding of the ocean currents , temperatures , the waves , the atmospheric conditions on the surface , the ocean , all of those things impact the activity layer , and therefore the operations of the military in a specific area of interest.
It's a reasonable thing to to think that you will succeed this , and that we will end time have the vast distributed century system in the ocean when you have your happiest moment about that success , you think about the greatest good that might bring us what comes to mind.
It's weird to say , but improved weather forecasts can have a huge impact around the world .
I know that just recently we had hundreds of floats in the tour of hurting salary in the gulf of mexico , and what we are able to do is we realize that there is a warm core eddy that had kind of broken off from the golf loop current that connects the formation of the ghost stream and was sitting south of mississippi and the ocean models of the current variety being used in geographic and neurological research had this idea in a slightly different location in the last twenty four hours of being assured , sally intensified .
And all of you remember , she has been like category a one hurricane to a category three kind of rapidly right before getting to land .
We think that that intensification was due to the location of this warm set of water , and it's on a scale that wasn't able to be resolved in canada , existing models that are used by researchers today or used by those forecasters today are drifter by drifting on the surface of the ocean .
Their velocities were able to correct them model , and we kind of had an internal thing .
So what we hope to do is a similar flow data into those models .
And the next thing is , mythology is starting to fully couple the ocean with the air , and now understanding , like where it's raining in the ocean , kind of a question that we've never even tried to ask before .
I think we'll be in reach of the sensors , and then we will affect that huge heat transfer between in the water , and similarly from the water to the sky .
In the case of hurricane , other psychological storms control , dressed with value in improving weather forecast .
And that matters the military.
I guess the key here is the granularity of the data , which I think , maybe , perhaps unprecedented for feeding into these large scale ocean at mister type of models.
Exactly , and you've seen it happen on the tourist , real weather forecasting .
Everyone can put a weather station in their back yard connected to the insights like whether underground , whether that comes to using this a harvest data feed to improve their forecast , it doesn't get rid of the national weather service instruments at the airport and a key strategy , music occasions .
And i'm sending whether balloons up into the strategy , but what it does is allows them to make really fine grain forecast of its raining here in vienna versus raining an organ turn right , something four to five miles away , bringing that kind of understanding to the ocean is unprecedented .
There is no way to do that .
So that's at the environmental , what i'm excited in the activity layer , though , is understanding where homering mammals , something again today in twenty twenty , we know where whales live by putting people out in a small boat and looking at them with binoculars , and we record those sensors and kind of get a sense of where they're feeding , where they're migrating and how they interact with , and in their daily life .
And so ocean of things can help automatic and understand where those marine mammals are .
We can have less impact to the those populations , plus , we can also in a formal commerce aspect .
We all have to unnecessarily slow down ships , or we can slow down shapes when we need to protect this .
Remember , so there's a great example of a activity scenario where this ubiquity , distributed sensing can really help improve overall state of the ocean awareness.
We're gonna move to another program and just the second , but just two further questions here .
And once following what you just said , so there were two things that come to my mind when I think about thousands and thousands of floaters , I do think about impacts with out there.
这个时候我们就可以看到这样的一种方式了。
在此之前，也许会有更多的问题，或者是说我们可以通过这样的一个方式来进行分析。
Which means that they will be remaining in the ocean environment 。
And so just talking me a little bit about those aspects of the programme and the environmental.
Yeah , so we've , he has been very sensitive to that trade .
Right , there is no such thing .
As for free , you participate in the environment .
What we have done is spent a lot of time minimizing the amount of plastics that are in each one floats .
We do want to prevent them from interacting with humans and other marine mammals .
They do .
Scott , also , they don't end up on beach or in the morning for technologies where they have kept out fences from those and undersea national parks and international equivalents .
But the thing that i'm trying to do is derive value from the data , they , so that the return that we get from these floats is much , much greater than any environmental impact .
And I think once we have a distributed set of the sensors that is able to be used by many different people in the community , where academic , commercial or military , we all have much , much more value from that .
I look forward to seeing if my thesis holds true .
And as we scale , this have a lot of people involved.
Wet and while it's under your wing , and you still adopt a program manager , as we know program managers , they just a number of years are not travel .
What is still to happen in the program until we.
So it's really the scaling out .
We obviously have a manufacturers working to build five thousand of these here in the second place .
We're also then trying to build more advanced detection and anonymously thinks , so .
Can we put a classifier ?
Can we put something that detects the health of GPS ?
All of these things have really important uses for downstream users and delivering those to military customer and deploying it for their use is something I want to exceed on before we are complete with the program.
Okay , well , thanks for the description of the ocean of things project are .
May you succeed with that ?
Because I think in all of us will benefit from having better and understanding of what's happening in the ocean .
And now I want to move to another one of your programs .
This one , I think you inherited this one is called the special temporal and orientation information and contested environments program , or known for short as still like this one results with a one garbage tradition of pushing precision clark technology forward into new levels of performance .
And the thing about stocks that gets me is that it kind of driven by a fairly alarming question when I think about it , which is what if the global positioning system GPS were to go down and tell me about , so it , what you do have to achieve with it .
And what is it?
Status , yeah , GPS is a victim of its own success .
Right , right ?
Because we now have you picked this positioning on the earth's surface in , and with that positioning , we have very accurate coming from the satellite .
We know , while people use GPS for positioning , many computers today , use GPS for their timing in the relationship between positioning and timing is so tightly coupled .
So when I got this program , I had actually interacted with it in its earlier state at us .
All right .
So I wasn't ignorant of what it was trying to do .
I kinda , I handed it where this idea came from was , are there are of radio frequency sources that are available , kind of in the atmosphere today that can be used for positioning and the signal that stolen , started working from was lightning boats .
And , you know , before I was out of that , how can you use lightning boats around the world ?
We're cheaper aircraft is .
And so the earlier program , which was called , as ben , really worked to try to make a positioning system just from these lightning sources around.
Just to give listeners that said is , if the very low frequency signals that are coming from those lighting bosses and therefore travel great distances that you're looking at .
There was some other part of lenie.
No , it is either they very low frequency signal that occurs is that discharged from the lightning ball .
Weather is cloudy , cloudy or cloud to ground occurs in that travels were tens of thousands of .
And there is a great network of lightning detection systems were wide .
Happens to be that over the amazon rainforest .
There is almost continually lightning storms .
You would know that until you , canada are investigating this , and this wasn't interesting source .
Still , it continued down that path and look for generalized , violent sources to do this localization .
And that was one area .
The other area is building really precise clocks .
So just like we have at the neighbor observatory , which is the master clock for the united states .
How can you transfer time from that clock and have a contained ownership of summary , a plane , and so therefore were always synchronized .
And so the idea for a very precise clocks that will won't drift in time .
I know this is parts per billion types of precision that the class have to maintain was the second kind of main effort here .
And when we ended up looking at laser based clocks and how those would support this precise timing in the stock.
Program , right , and then , ultimately , the idea that this would provide a GPS like capability , even if the GPS system went down .
So this means that the various military assets would have that capability , even in the event , again , that GPS went down .
This means that the us rebellion carry out its military missions , regardless.
Exactly , and so this was the kind of a different program in the sense that we were working on the fundamental services that a military platform needs .
You need to know where you are and what time it is , and you want to build in as many diverse position sources , whether that's in our selection , navigation in the , from ships of all to the story of the story of the elephant navigation to g PS , or things like magnetic navigation , are in other modulates , right ?
That's the overall goal of wear that localization , part of a positive navigation and timing goes the other parties .
Now , if you know , where you are , knowing what time it is , allows you to synchronize operations across the battle space .
So how does the plane above no one to talk when compared to a ship below ?
How do we know when various activities have to occur in the battlespace ?
And how do we know when I sent something ?
It was of this exact event , and so we can all be a moving forward , not a key military capability.
In the context of a life cycle of a double project , where is strike , strike is.
Almost done , we're excited about the results in which transition the capabilities and technology to the navy , so they can put it in on their ships and aircraft .
So this is an exciting thing to see these concepts coming through maturity and dark by those investments showing benefit and then transitioning over to the fly.
You just mentioned it really , what four dark is kind of the finish line that were transitioning .
New youths could stop once doing , investigate all the kinds of technologies that are possible , and that would serve the cause of national offence .
But if it goes , no , where else , then doesn't really do as much as if you hand off to an unusual like , in this case , it could be in the navy.
Yeah , it's exactly in that feedback they get from that informing .
The development is so valuable , both the dark and to the navy , so they know what's possible .
So really , it is informing both sides of the interaction .
It's a win win whenever we get a chance to experiment and go interact with the various military users.
Okay , and since we're on the subject of GPS , I just want to briefly touch on one more of your programs is called president for the positioning system for deep ocean navigation , which essentially sounds like to meet a GPS system for places were used to be like referring to summary , so for summaries and autonomous undersea vehicles GPS for the underwater world .
Tell me a little bit about that programming .
We're that.
That's the exact purpose .
So I went when you underneath the water , GPS isn't available .
So by definition , GPyes , isn't there .
And so traditionally summarized have operated with very precise navigators on board so that they don't need to put a parachute above and come above the surface of the way .
So what it was built , a set of active transparency that would operate an area of interest that would provide a GPS like signal to a summary or a man under water vehicle .
Again , positioning is one of these key enablers for operations in the undersea , and the by providing that as a service like GPS , does everyone on land , it would be very , very valuable .
So we transition this hardware to the navy , and they're working at implementing it into operational systems today it.
To me to hear this from a historical point of view , because the original step toward systems like UPS was , I believe the transit system , which is a navy system .
And the whole point of that was at least one major point , was to reduce the time the nuclear submarines in our defence platform would have to actually surface to get a reading from a satellite and an idea with the minimize .
That's handsome .
The transit system , which was more sort of a double based system , which LED to GPS .
And now you are talking about president , which actually sounds like they choose what was maybe sort of , ultimately , in the minds of the people develop , translate , which is being able to get position under water without actually having a surface.
That's right , and it provides that infrastructure they rely on to understand , stand where you are at all time .
And so if completely implemented , a summary , we've never needed to go about the surface , the ocean to figure out.
Right , and not only to figure out yourself , but this is the reason why I would not want to do .
That is because it comes vulnerable to detection.
By embrace is exactly the most vulnerable , right .
And that is , the summer is advantages itself , and so limiting any opportunity to be detected is a win for a summary mission.
That was quite a worldwide .
John , those three programs .
Still , it president and ocean of things you really do have your hands full .
Have to say .
Now , if someone who has been on the ground in the military or injury case , boots under water , and who also has been in the business of technology development , something of your work at us all .
How would you characterize dark this place in the innovation ecosystem?
So what you don't meant about my background , ivan is , I was a management consultant .
So I had a state postcard back to duty .
Well , I was focused on businesses , improving their overall operations .
And so I feel what we do at dark is being a venture capital fund .
right ?
We are a place where you can bring ideas and measure them so that they have the most impact going forward .
So I don't , we don't have excessive bureaucracy .
We're able to move fast .
We get this advantage that everyone's motivated to succeed in good ideas that have the most impact .
And that's what makes me excited every day that I , it makes every day different .
And those two things kind of keep me pushing in an alpha , almost four.
Yeah , and just following on that a little bit , me , one of the things now that i've been a topic for a while that becomes to my mind , how is it that humanity all can go after some of the incredibly ambitious technology vision is , there are just a part in parcelled dark .
But when you think about a lot of private industry , the risk with dark is doing in the programs like you're running and other PMrunning is to take the risk down right enough .
So ultimately you can get to that transition .
Where is not in the , on the part of we know another part of the military in another military service , like the neighbourhood or even commercial analyst companies , jackson takes the time and take the technology to the finish line .
So is that sense of dew risking technology , I find interesting.
Exactly , and you know , I am not judged on success of my progress .
I am very comfortable operating with a lot of risk .
I've had a lot of failures along the way as APM, Adouble get riddle programs .
Things didn't succeed .
They didn't , what they did to say .
What did we learn from it , and how do we make the next interaction of what we do better so often said to feel fast , and we take those losses , and we turn them into something valuable .
And that that what makes dark of?
Special place nicely said , that sort of winning role of what's on some levels might be considered failure .
But really , what that is is a form of data and understanding that helps you move forward in the end so nicely by one of the question , which is not even a trick question , but it's , what are you a pause that I did ask you?
I always like to tell people that dark doesn't have a secret laboratory in the basement .
We are a business operation .
We're trying to get money out in the hands of researchers every day .
And so I think a lot of people are either afraid to come talk to program managers , bring their ideas to us .
I think most people , what were busy .
We're in the business of ideas .
And if you have an idea in a new way of doing something.
Always interesting talking to jonathan , you know , program managers are at the open for just to find a number of beers could be three for five years .
Sometimes they actually go , come back for a second tour of duty , but you know , you know , therefore , ever so wondering , you know , if you think about the end phase and transitioning out of dark at some point , you imagine in your role in the reserves may be going back into a submarine for another nine deaths .
And are you finished with that sort of service and will think about things?
Once you've been away from submarines from , I think over two years , you have to be require , and they want to take someone and as little like me .
So I proud you never get back on summer inds , i'll stay working hard and reserves and get to figure out what to do when I grow up , whether it's good industry , start my own company or help others continue to innovate .
These are things that are going to nearly deal with my heart , although i'm so busy these days , I don't have time to often think with the next.
Remember , I suspect that you can have a lot of options given all of the experience that you are pattern , what you continue now to acquire a dark .
But when you certainly give it me and also a listeners a lot to think about the imagine with respect to the new ways that we might stand the ocean and what goes on in that vast portion of the planet , which you actually have seen also from within , that is to say , underwater .
And where amazes me to think about that .
Also , we learned about incredibly cool technologies like very low frequency signaling from a lightning and an amazing article , clarks , that can help provide GPS where it is that actually reminds me to resolve the mixed match game of different technological systems , which has been a theme of dolphins innovation style .
So , so called here , about the ways you are putting out of systems of systems together .
And this is a long way i've seen john , and thanks for sharing this time with me and telling such engaging tales of life as a dirty programming.
Thanks , I wanna encourage everyone out in the audience to engage with dark going forward .
Check out the data from my floats .
They are available at the dark website that ocean of things that darker , that meal there is can be more to see in the future .
Look forward to hearing people's thoughts and ideas moving forward.
Okay , you heard it from john listeners get in touch with us , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from garbage , thanks also to bend selection for his partnership in producing this programme .
For more information about mister john washington , the programs he runs in the agencies , strategic technology office and the other breakthrough technologies .