Still , technology , the internet GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight with operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , the midst of the cold war , doubt that offends .
Advance research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker .
A window went to dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone a motto , and i'm your dark host .
And today I am pleased to have with me in the studio for rebel , for rule , a program manager since twenty four , team in dollars , defence office .
Throughout her career , fruit has been working on mathematical innovations and applying them in areas ranging from spacecraft control , vibration control and structures , and even to the vaccine problem of quantifying uncertainty in the mathematical models that scientists use to study complex phenomenon like weather and biological process , and the engineers used to design , simulate , manufacturer and upgrade many of the complex technologies important in military and civilian and settings .
Thanks for your first spending some time with me today and.
Thank you .
Ivan , good to be here.
I'd love to start out freedom and learning a little bit about you about your background , education .
Some of the important thing that happened throughout your area , that ultimately let you hear to dark .
So tell us a little bit.
Well , let me tell you a little bit about my background , and till you that the july my relationship , mathematics has been a developing one , and I have to say that over the years , it has really tipped .
I was born and raised in iraq , which has a long tradition of excellent , rigorous mathematical and technical education .
I received my bachelor degrees boarding , applied math and physics from user birthday .
From then I went the beautiful campus of the university of his concern medicine .
And then I went to brown to get my psd in applied mathematics after getting my PSD, Icame back to uh .
Neighborhood is called the california to naval postgraduate monitoring , and spent several years as a professor in the department of .
And while I was there , I was contacted by a colleague of mine was working in a very similar research .
She suggested whether I would consider getting a job as a program manager for computer israel mathematics that efforts of the scientific research is , for example , it is all intense , makes you feel basic on the same block as I was not even sure what that is , but having my colleague and friend in a position and watching her what she was able to to achieve was actually an inspiration .
And that's when I said , yes.
And how then was did you make a direct connection ?
He was dark , I suppose to be APMelsewhere.
The interesting thing was that about maybe couple years into my job with some program managers from top approach me .
And they said , I interested in going in , coming to dark , and and I have to say , if I thought of getting a position there for a server , scary and kind of out of character , I thought the current job would be the scariest thing to do .
I had become familiar with the research that being supported by dark and dark mission .
And oh , I was having a hard time to see how supporting basic research and mathematics could be of any relevance to what darker was doing and making that a connection.
You certainly have done that with programs which we will talk about it and a little while you really have a discover that it really is a connection between you .
And the programs are adopted before we actually talk about those I wanted to pull back a little bit and find out how you and mathematics became like foreign partners .
And I ask you this , because I can see true for me , i'm sure many listeners that your mathematics just want those bills that from so many of us is , is difficult .
We , we kind of push it away that the earliest time that we can .
And yet you really had this partnership threat .
How did you develop this ?
What I imagine as a kind of love for this discipline.
Some are interested in mathematics , so was not actually from the point of view of being interested in abstract , or just because this , this was the way my mind worked .
I was always interested in problems solving , but it was also interested in gaining better understanding into the physical the world .
so I didn't want to become an engineer , even though at the time , seemed like all the smart kids who , with strong mathematical villages would like to go to engineering , or they would go to mathematical 口。
But then I decided to know I wanted to try to become more of a scientist of thinking of physics .
The only thing is that I started as a physics undergrad , but it only took me taking a semester long course in their scientific realized , I don't have a lot of talent that I realized initially come with a lot of pleasure and enjoy spending my time .
So then I decided that actually , what really gives me a lot of pleasure and steady heart is what is actually the more medical aspect of the physics courses , and I found out that , oh , I can , I do very quickly become a double major in polite mathematics , a language physics .
So that's how it started.
So I wouldn't interest me about applied math .
Is that in that way of engaging mathematics , you are looking at these symbols , working with these symbols that made many of us associated with math , and you are finding out how they related to the real world in pretty dramatic ways .
One way of making this concrete in this conversation might be for you to tell us about how old you applied .
A kind of mathematics is a kind of an innovation for which you now have some mathematical energy named after you .
And how is that lead to operational changes with respect to the international space station ?
So can you tell us that story about the new that math to space station connection?
So the research that are doing during my patient afterwards , have to do with control and optimization of natural systems that.
Model by a person offensively quiz , I bought the natural system.
A sound waves , for example , control of electric magnetic waves structures or any combination of interaction of these are different physical phenomenon .
So in the case of , for example of spacecraft control is that we are looking at the situation .
Where are you looking at complex known near dynamics ?
We're in this case.
So that means little changes can lead to big results .
possibly.
Even even though the senior engineer system , right , this is not necessarily like climate that you would say , well , be necessary .
Don't have any control over the initiative .
Random is of the situation we talking about the engineering system that we would like to perform certain manufacturers in an optimal fashion .
So you are expecting your system in the skype .
He needs to perform certain manufacturers that would lead to minimize a certain objectives .
So in this case , you are trying to do it .
Sometimes it means you trying to do it with minimum energy , your minimum feelings of parents , you are depending.
But so listeners can can understand why that's something to go for is prepared on a spacecraft can cost ten thousand dollars a pound pound .
So you can minimize.
And give that with the analysis , of course , but also cost of , like , in the case of the necessary station , the cost of refueling , it could be a millions of enough that the situation .
So you really have to use everything in the most cost efficient .
I love to OPPO manner .
So in this case , for me , I should have to say that the whole success story here , I owe you .
Basically , my colleagues were able to basically get the theory and the guidance that we developed and basically work really hard to to employment and.
Space station , right ?
And if we would just say simply what the result was , if my reading is correct is that you were able to come up with a way of using certain systems like giraffe scopes on the space station to achieve very dramatic changes like united returns hungry , native relocations without the use of propeller released , minimizing to a great degree , the need for.
Right exactly ?
And if this would not have happened , had been not come up with up an efficient and accurate way of implementing this arm.
Right and , but , but the actual controls that went to those gallery scopes emerge from the mathematical framework that you are able to develop into this sort of drugs , that line all the way from this most abstract way of thinking is mathematics .
All the way .
Million dollar , multimillion dollars savings of how you operate the international space station .
Let me assert a one of the miracles of math in this connection to the real world .
So excellence , lets say the way to you in the upper and two programs that you are working on here .
So one of them goes by the equipment here that stands for enabling quantification of uncertainty in physical systems .
And the other one goes by the acronym model that stems models , dynamics and learning .
So let's start with equips , and again , that stands for enabling quantification of uncertainty in physical systems .
This sounds fascinating .
The idea of quantifying a uncertainty tells about the program what the goals are and what the sadness is not the money.
The goals of the program , after saying a sort of lofty fashion , which is not always my normal state of.
We have a statement .
We were just talking about the international space station , and that's pretty well.
Yes , but I do have to say that I had very lofty goals for the program , and the way in my mind I was thinking of the program , and I still do it is to translate , change the way we go through our modeling and simulation .
Oh , what you are saying , physical world engineering system , we do have a long history , basically , almost all of scientific history of of modelling , physical systems and physical phenomenon , and using mathematics .
And but what I am saying about changing the practice of modeling is , in some ways , taking into account how good or how bad we are as models as some was like bringing such certain level of honesty to our modelling innocence said , we have to consider the fact that it doesn't matter how good we think our models are at the end are just going to be an approximation .
It just going to be sarah guide for the physical reality .
The fact that in in the process , sometimes we are not quite clear about the , let's say , the description of which we are , what the output of our models are and what the physical world is , the it's going to create a lot of issues when we try to analyze the system as far as physical modeling goes .
Probably one of the most successful stories is basically the navy soak secretion.
So you might apply the number of stock succession , for example , if you want to try to describe how the queen , you point to your coffee goes into that fluid .
And you see the beautiful swords , or it might be the way masses of air in the atmosphere are flowing and intermediately unsufferable that the range they were talking.
Yes , exactly , yeah , so error , you know , basically flow a barrel where , you know , the airplane rings are is basically the fundamental love every space in china at the celebrity decreasing .
But the problem with it is that you , then you talk to those people who are looking at basically physical flows , fluid flows , and they do still scratch their head , and it still could say that we are talking in certain situation looks like in hypersonic , but it is not at all clear that this is the question .
Even how would you be talking about ?
You were still talking about fluids , but it's at the scale , and so the physical condition that is not at all clear that this is the right equation to even try to simulate .
Yes , we do have airplanes that fly .
We do have any air space .
The industry has been one of our more successful modern industry is not just twenty century .
It will be even more in twenty years in the future century , but it makes a little worried that some of the work and mathematical work that is being done .
It's based on certain assumptions that are and physical models that may actually not hold.
Crack me from wrong , but as you speaking , i'm realizing , well , we have these technology wish lists .
We want high personnel vehicles and hypersonic technology things that celebrating festival speed of sound .
Were you thinks we've got mathematical equations and traditions , and mathematically roughly in the economic phenomenon that are applicable in designing a hypersonic vehicle .
But we actually don't know .
We don't know if it's an accurate representation of of that.
In a supersonic arena , this need for qualifying are answering to a lack of knowledge and all .
So the kind of error and description set up between the mathematical models and physical reality .
And our engineering system comes from engineers themselves , because one of the things is that they are looking right now in situations that the only way they can , that is a certify that is a design , or whatever they build is by using something right .
And in this case , they'd probably try to do it using well , in certain situation , you can test , and maybe you can , if you do taste some any kind of testing , maybe you can do it , maybe certain components of it , but full testing on the system for examples and play when I certainly have to be done on the entire one is , after you already built .
That's a little too late in order to come up with ways of changing the design or changing the way it's being built , right .
So it would like to be involved in that process as a mathematician and as an engineer little earlier into that .
So the only way to do that , the testing is not going to help festival in certain situation is that it may be too expensive .
It's too late and sometimes impossible to .
It's using simulation .
The whole thing of a simulation is based on having a mathematical model and having the simulation tools , like basically the numerical methods and all that , and the computational tools platform .
So the computers that you can actually do this simulation .
So this is when you see that maths comes in right there , and this is the only way that we can test .
Doubt these .
These new designs are new that are not a bit , but you have basically the elements of the design so you can at least tested out using the simulation before before you build.
So I think I heard you once talk about this is almost like a mathematics of honesty .
Yeah , meaning it is which you and I love the phrase now that you talking about this word of simulation , which is based on mathematics and improves mathematical models operating in the form of computer models of the , but in there , in that kind of abstracted place and abstract , the operation , you're trying to develop a framework with the creeps that is kind of the reality in the man .
exactly .
And how well is this representing , ultimately , the real world technology that we want to emerge out of this mathematics and model?
That yes , that's a very nice accusation .
And what is so fascinating about this is that the fields goes very quickly from some may in the beginning , we think some philosophical ha , a rumination about what is reality .
What is representation of reality ?
What is the relationship of mathematics of physical world , very quickly , two , some beautiful theory , the interesting result that I expect from equips is to see whether it's possible to come up with some common frameworks and common rules that could deal with some of the major challenges within looking at very different application problems .
This is , this is going to be an interesting approaches to to observe and see what results come out of it , because the performance at this point are looking at system as different as possible from each other , from airspace structures to integrated circuits and to chemical networks .
So we'll see whether something a common love.
Come out of the africa , but so maybe that's a nice queue to talk a little bit about model , the models dynamic.
Program , so there is actually a very nice link between the programming creeps and model one issue that I need to emphasize about equips .
Because right now , a funny talked about it , basically , as you mention , it's about trying to capture or make honesty as part of a modeling process .
But I haven't really told you about the challenges that we have enough in our process .
And one of the biggest challenges is that the complex for all that we are looking at the complex system we are looking at.
They are high dimensional when you say high dimension .
What do you mean by the sounds like as many parts we have to think about.
Right , uh exactly so , so , so a lot of times when we think of dimension , and you've heard that you're thinking about that , there are three physical , and then we have a dimension of time .
So we think our physical world is basically like a four dimensional space time , but the way we are using dimension basically , here is what we think exactly , the degree of freedom are basically the number of vegetables that we need in order to build on model .
What repent.
Moreover , the robot with ten jones is that the world , I could think that very simply is a ten dimensional problem.
exactly .
so.
But it could be a thousand.
It could be very cleared out .
Yeah , exactly .
And the interesting part is that you look at the robot , and you look at the , okay , when I wanna write down , basically , when I am thinking about the , the number of variables or modes , whatever that I can express the physical variable that i'm interested , but at the same time , sometimes when I want to do any kind of approximation , right of each of these ten variables or ten dimension for each dimension , I am actually need additional dimensions in order to move approximately .
So this is like at every step of a modeling here and an approximation .
We are introducing more dimensions here .
So starting a tendering attendant what we say , interventional system , and they've been , for example , for each dimension , I made another ten.
Well , just it just a simple way of saying , hell .
Ten dimensions most applies in a robot case that each joint itself has has the three special dimensions and the temperatures of each one has four , so suddenly already.
So sometimes there those dimensions have to do with the physical had relate to the physical representation , but somebody's sometimes dimension comes from a approximation and modeling and mathematical work that we need to do .
so .
It's , it's an extremely good question .
And I slept what when we talk about high dimensionality , what you are saying , and this is what happens with the systems that we are looking at that representation of these physical systems require lots of dimensions , lots of vegetables , lots.
Hi , dimension and and higher the dimensionality , the harder , the harder it is to compute to put into a computer next round simulation.
It goes back to how much computing can we do , and people say , well , right now , we do have extremely good , extremely fast and computing platforms .
And that is true .
And that's why , at this point , we can do computing physical system that twenty years ago was not possible , but the more you do , the higher demand of your analysis tools now about model .
Uh , the model is a sort of an acronym for models , dynamics and learning .
And I would say that the goal of the program is extracting mathematical models from dynamic data sets.
The goal of a program I was so what you stopped when you say , dynamic data said something , a lot of data dynamics makes me think of motion or time that I get .
That writer , would you want to?
Absolutely what I mean by dynamic data set is a data set that you get from dynamical system , which our system , whose behavior changes respect the time for you for your dynamic system player .
Absolutely , I mean it life is dynamic , is a great example of a dynamical system .
One of the reasons that I wanted to have .
This program was also against saying that existing tools that behalf of modeling cannot handle us on the complex dynamical systems that we need to analyze .
We are looking again , very similar , but we're looking , for example , the system , such as whether , you know , if you biological systems , even in general system , like communication networks , or , you know , human social networks , these are all the examples of dynamical systems , but we don't have very good analytical and mathematical models to to express the complex behavior of the systems that if you just look at the data set from something like turbulent floor , it's fascinating because you see these .
These borders sees this horse , this , it is a beautiful pattern.
Learning this is applicable in reverse , but it is also applicable .
And gentleman , exactly.
Exactly , that was so beautiful about these are all these different conflicts phenomena that can be expressed , that when you see it , some communality in there .
And in this case , what we trying to learn is that what are the common patterns that can be learned and basically expressed dynamics of these systems in terms of evolution of these patterns ?
Yeah , I suggest them .
We don't have the mathematical tools yet to deal with the data .
So people say , why , you know , look at us .
We not only be a data , big data , we also the age of lake on machine learning and all these different ways that we can handle date of any size .
But what i'm saying is that the existing techniques cannot handle the fact that data is dynamic and changes , which is expected time .
And I actually not going back and say , look , go back to the beginning of the dynamical system theory and trying to develop different way of modeling , extracting these models from dynamic .
It said.
Give me one example of a phenomenon of a system of technology that cannot really be model .
Well , now that if your model program is successful , will be modeled.
A vast performance motorcycle to start with something that we think we have some grasps both and use the basic as a task case .
I'm going back again to the classical problem of a basic , turbulent flow .
My hope is that they can apply the meteorologist mathematical methods that they develop two systems that are much , and the assistance , for example , is the data .
Did you get , for example , from?
Never science .
So you're talking about things like how brain signals , propaganda , or how patterns of new relativity associate with the century stimuli , or the way we move.
Absolutely , it could be a data that you can get even from a social networks and social systems , and basically two systems for which we really are reluctant , the proper mathematical.
Modelling that strategies before time result here , I just want to one question about being employed .
Mathematician at a place like dark one of the phrases here , a lot here is the innovation ecosystem .
And what that means is it really is referring to come all the players and all the stakeholders that it takes another go from sort of an idea about the technology to technology that you have in hand .
That's that's operational in the field .
So as an applied mathematician , what do you think you can do here , you might not be able to do elsewhere.
I say , darkness , probably the best place to be if you are and applied mathematician , in fact , I just say for your mathematician .
And like to solve problems , one of the greatest thing about dark is that there is a wealth of information , wealth of problems that important .
And I have to say that very , very cool , the coolness factor for problems to solve for a mathematician .
Here is enormous because you feel that not only your solving a problem that has importance , the second modern impact , as far as you know , you solving important problems and national security , but you also feel like the problems are that in some ways , there is , there is so much to contribute the richness of the problem are just as maybe the biggest driver , a motivating factor for anybody , certainly for a mathematician .
And I just wanted to add that is that , and i've been saying that to my , my friends , to my colleagues , anybody who would listen that why mathematics actually very important to to an encouraging to come , future program managers is that when you are encountered by important problems , and you see that your ideas , the rule you have as a mathematician that not only you try to look at these particular problems , but you try to abstract out and coming with different representation .
That would you better solution for these problems .
So you basically see that your ideas are at work .
I mean , what better satisfaction are they?
Well , freedom , it's been a little like for me to talk to you about your love of mathematics is coming out here right now , and to get some sense of of how mathematics that is have that role in the umbrella innovation ecosystem in a particular here at the dark .
So I just want to thank you for spending this time with us.
Thank you ever .
It's been pleasure.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with freedom , and I, Ihope you join us again for the next Voices from dark .