Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight with operation.
Technologies , a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window until the history , people and accomplishments , kind of earned dark membership among the most admired places and cultures of innovation .
My name is iphone a motel and on your dark host in this episode of Voices from DARPA , we will take a tour of an ambitious ten year project to merge biology and engineering into one of the most powerful engines of molecular invention .
The world is known , although some works still remains to be done .
The program now is winding down to a clothes , but not before its research performers already delivered a new adversity of technology platform , whose consequences are begun to revolt .
New companies follow on investments , chemical and materials based technology for the department of defence .
And perhaps one day for the public large , the players already have begun to accumulate.
Biology can do things that no weather technology can come close to doing .
It can replicate itself .
It can adapt , it can above it , can scale from one to millions to billions effortlessly in a day , and its program will fill the genetic code .
Biology is technology.
That's former program manager alicia jackson in twenty fifteen .
She was speaking at a meeting that showcased the mission in projects of the biological technologies office will be to you .
She'd been a group already for several years , and was preparing to hand off stewardship of the living founderies program .
She launched the programme twenty eleven by twenty thirteen and extensive set of academic and industrial performers .
That's researchers in terrorist speaker had begun , or to realize the beauty of vision that biology is living .
Foundations was just one of the more are delicious embodiments of that original .
Jackson argued at the twenty fifteen BTOshowcase that biology is the past way to advance new technologies that will empower us to make useful chemicals and materials like we never have been.
It offers us a chance to combine all the advances that we see now for the past fifty years and electronics and physics and computer science and data analytics , and combine it with the last two decades of advances in genomics and biology and narrow science and come up with the technological capability .
The first phases , anything that we have today , it would be truly astonishing to have a technology that could leverage both of these aspects from the engineering world and from the biological world .
It could offer solutions and capabilities.
But we just don't have today .
Former program manager renewed wages now , with ginger buyer works picked up the pattern on a living foundry is programmed twenty seven in a visit from global .
Parker said the southern twenty eighteen , she showed a status report on the project .
It was a pipeline in the project whose first phase was known as ATthat stands for advanced tools and capabilities for generalizable platforms .
This was the face said , wages in which the living fundraising , occasional program manager li said , intended to bring biology and engineering together in novel and never more in power.
She had the decision to start to create a tool bed where we could destroy biology to an engineering to take something like the design , build , test , learn psychologically engineering and apply that to a biological system like my problem in ecology or a east or other type of bacteria to make products and molecules that would be a value to the dirty .
And I really think that her inspiration came from looking at biology as this incredible system that could make a real diversity of molecules that extends well beyond what we can make through traditional manufacturing and chemical processes .
So when you have access to that diversity of biology , can you start to manipulate that to make new pot molecules , things that have never been made before biology , which is some of the most ambitious goals of the program .
So her foundation of investments really created the tools under each one of those categories that design tools that you can quickly in automated way , design a violence .
And that apparently distinguished teens together to put into a build , said , this is that the DNA sympathizing , an insertion of DNA into a living system testing .
This is the domestic trauma tree .
Other measure falls to look if a product has been made and importantly , learning .
So this is some of the design to make are not going to work and program programming that into your learning cycle to not use that design , make a better design next time is the first phase of the program was to build those individual components and tools .
And now the second phases to really integrate them as a platform to create this foundry type capability that the us , military or our customer , a business customer , could go to a foundery and say , I would like you to make the smaller kill kenny developed about that perfect and organism to do so .
The ultimate demonstration of that capability , that founder capability is to make one thousand unique molecules and where five hundred fifty one molecules.
That was in twenty eighteen , the team performers that were then walking their way up to , and now , beyond the one thousand molecule mark include researchers at the biotechnology firms , emergency and zimmerman , and they're academic colleagues at the m it broader each group , but are different strengthening approaches to the tables as an achiever .
The BTOprogram manager , who is now taking living to the finish line.
So we all have different strength and different approaches .
You know , one of the strength of of the m it broad foundery is in some of the early sort of development and a little girl approach to determines when the bills , and that are catholic .
And so there there goal was never to scale up .
They were not .
There are not a criminal entity , and so they were very good in sort of the very methodical approach to understanding what kind of violence that the population will go into the creating a molecule um , you know , embrace as a commercial entity has been very successful in in scaling some of their projects .
And I think some of the early development under ATCGhas has definitely added in that in that path and an imagination , I would say , in terms of of molecules and their commercial approaches been very good at the building , new materials .
And so using a certain hollywood monuments , for example , and thinking about new material that can be.
At the heart of all this biosynthesis and ultimately larger scale bio manufacturing is the process of fermentation in microbes.
That's the actual sort of liquid tanker .
You put all your microbes and where you make it happy and you feed .
And it could produce a molecule and from there of an university purification of that molecules separating it from that liquid .
And those actual sales that produced.
Justice bureau is in baker's reliant microbes to convert sugar , it alcohol into generate carbon outside to live in bread .
Performers in the living founders program , genetically engineered eastern bacteria to ferment or chemically different kinds of starting molecules and two more useful molecules and materials .
Some of these transformations require the scientists to install a number of genes that govern the insect creation of entire bias athletes , the equipment of a new , tiny factory inside the cell .
That's why the relatively new terms in federal biology applies here , and because it now is possible for researchers to mix and match thousands into an infinite variety of various synthetic passwords , the potential to turn microbes into living foundations for turning out molecules with different trades , and also seems to have vast potential in recent years of the program , researchers have produced , among other useful materials and biotics , drug criticisms , pesticides .
And he still feels filtering materials , mode , inhabitants and churches , catalysts for chemical reactions and article material , such as local crystals .
Synthetic biologist christopher avoid has been a principal investigator on the project at the boston based MIT.
broader .
I asked him as a leader in the synthetic biology and bio manufacturing to record what he saw .
Living founders added to the cause.
Living countries with unique and its focus on improving foundation of capabilities , underlying engineered biology , in other words , getting better a genetic engineering for the sake of genetics engineering without a particular application in mind as a result of these projects that were impossible in two thousand thirteen are trivial .
He said , the fruits of this work across the upper program said it brings specific operational capabilities online from harnessing living cells to build infrastructure to converting plastic waste food to creating new domestic sources for various , as well as counter measures to handle the next pandemic .
The cells being built for these applications , use parts and methods from living countries.
Waiters referring here to a range of dark programs , engineering , living materials were armed .
A program known as resource , one known as amber , which sends for environmental as a bioengineering resource , and one known as the pandemic prevention platform program , all share elements with a living founders programme.
And m it , we use these methods to build over thousands of new molecules in the time period .
These include practice for energetics , monuments for residents in poland .
Targeting attacked microbes , absorbs obstacle coding , subscriptions and so on .
One lesson learned , he said the rapid scale of biological technology remains a critical challenge .
We cannot rapidly ensure yourselves , but moving from a few millions of leaders is challenging and slows and implementation in the world.
When an achiever took the managerial biton over from renewed wages in twenty twenty , she knew it already had taken a lot of work for the program to achieve what it had achieved .
And she knew it would take a lot more to do with still had yet to be done.
So there were a watching sixteen initial performers under ATCG, and they have various projects for wearing links of time , ranges from academic loves , hollywood , institution companies .
And you know , they , they really spend the grounded of approaches , and they all have unique approaches and strength .
But , you know , overall , it was their collective efforts that really kind of substantial hands , that fragmentation process of molecules and set the state occasion for MITamazons .
Imagine to pick that up in one thousand molecules and build a founder infrastructure that we have now.
In the last few years , a piece of microbial design molecule making it by a manufacturing became furious.
Yeah , so by twenty nine team , the goal of making one thousand molecules with biology was met a full year at a schedule of the.
And the molecule count now , at the end of the project is well over sixteen hundred , thanks to the integration of automation machine , machine learning in other tools for scaling up to this kind of productive , the gallery of unique michael .
Malaysia has just been getting richer , and this success has LED to a very dark thing to ask yet more of the research , personal collaborators working on the.
At that point , at twentieth , we were able to pick it and focus on specific molecules that could be developed further and tested for new do d operational capabilities .
So , so this meant that now we are looking to produce molecules for duty testing , evaluation partners at scale , and they saw a kind of testing they need to , so think of going from middle ground to kilogram amounts of a molecule or material , and depending on the application requirements .
And as a result of this , the program objectives in this have predicted away from broad demonstrations of capability , and they focused more on delivery of duty , relevant molecules , insufficient quantity for testing at duty facilities.
Participating in the suspended and face of the project had been performers at emergency emergency and MITroad with collaborators in navy , army and air force service liberty .
They have been taking the molecule , making the material producing technologies , which performers delivered during the ATCGand one thousand molecules faces of the project .
Protest drives .
We are talking here with stuff like tough materials for aircraft parts and higher performing liquid fuels .
Here is some audio evidence that this isn't just talk.
It was manufactured information tanks by east , genetically engineered by researchers and embrace the textbook of the fuel , which normally would have been made with petroleum feet stock .
And that , he says , took place in china in california at the weapons division of the neighborhood center , known as knock WD.
So we are currently actually working with our partners at nowadays , and to advanced testing of some of the molecules that we developed two or three programs.
Senior challenger is head of research and development at armors and oversaw the work that LED to this new fuel.
The bottom line is that knocked wade and air violation , a lot of potential with some of these molecules that will previously not available and meaningful quantities , while , and we have been able to deliver larger and large volumes of these molecules for additional testing in advanced applications .
So , for example , the NOWDteam created a new field that they called by a renewable one or BRone , which is that it goes to nineteen percent , one , nine percent higher volumetric energy density than conventional jet fuel .
In addition to the improved grammar , these improved will result in an increase in the operating range and good efficiency , foreign and increase and.
Believing fundraised program just keeps on giving us an achievement.
From my point of view , this is the most crucial in the most exciting part of the whole program , right , because we are are demonstrating the real potential , all of engineering biological organisms to produce chemical materials , fuels and anything that it really has had a transparency of impact on on both duty needs .
And the writer by the economy .
So , you know , it is a powerful technology platform , and it can be possibly programed .
You can scale it .
You can adapt to changing environs .
Biology can software pair , so in a living foundation is able to address the development of the technology and infrastructures to really take advantage of this.
Key to the ongoing success and ability to keep building value on the new hardware capabilities .
Living factories has delivered , has depended on project collaborators who have been putting their own again.
So the scale up work and the partnerships with those duty teams have been fantastic .
They are facilitated by both a discussion of funding from darker , as well as matching funding from those , the other partners .
I'm so we are working with groups from army , from navy and air force to perform testing the regulation on molecules and english , the goal here is far for duty , test and innovation partners to develop tastes of these prototype models for the udi applications and advanced them to a stage that established military technology development .
Pipelines could then transition the technology and some day.
That , by a sensitive field that knocked WDhas tested is one of the more mature examples to emerge from the living founders programs .
So far , the innovation ecosystem and its , perhaps the now send a great chance of the expanding and diversifying , both within an outside of DARPA.
Yeah , that's been great , because in addition to the m , it broad foundery of their great work , they've published a lot of that work .
We were also fortunate to have two companies as performers , and so they serve as direct commercial transition partners , and they can incorporate technologies developed into their own commercial production pipelines .
And so we see that as a , as a great sort of wind coming out of this program , they're also been some examples of spin of companies , for example , there was one focusing on on violence that it perfectly designed .
And we are also proud to incorporate the embedded onto final initiative to help some of our academic performers look at potential commercial applications for the materials that they developed under living congress.
The embedded entrepreneurial initiative , or EEIis a new dark .
Its mission is to help researchers and innovators with promising , but early stage technology development ideas survive the privilege value of death .
That's the orange phase when most start of efforts fail to get to the finish line before managerial , technical or financial obstacles , dry them up and take them out .
Meanwhile , also helping the cause is a commitment throughout the department of defence to transfer living foundry technologies from the lab to operational status last year for one , during the biotechnology for material and defense symposium , convened online by the national defence industry association .
Michelle rossel , then assistant director for biotechnology at the office , the undersecretary of defence for research engineering , said , quote , the same core competencies that can unlock production capabilities have the potential to transform military systems in ancient spaces.
Yes , there are combined efforts by a wide range of duty , agent , season and service branches to develop technology transition pipelines into the the audience who adopt the these emerging biotechnologies like this .
So I think he added to keep the delivery is developing founderies and really just biologically based platforms .
Uh , I really can be able to will provide new materials and capabilities further for the do DNand the nation , frankly.
For anti river living centuries in its completion.
It is just getting started .
So I think that in a post living foundry is the breath of report of products will only continue to expand , especially since commercial applications of this technology span across the biotech sector .
And for the duty , this will include continuing that development path .
The others can imagine the solutions .
There's been any new enhancements to military means , as well as.
And that sounds like a textbook example of a double win , thanks listeners for sharing this time with me .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dirt up , thanks also to TOM shortage for his partnership and producing this program .
For more information about the programs that dark is biological technologies of the snow is running , as well as about all of darkness .