I've been a model here on the host of the Voices from garbage pakistan .
Please note that in this episode , you might hear ambient noises , such as birds , trucks , even the harm of my refrigerator .
That's because I have had to record my words in a home office as I play my social distancing role in our collective effort to minimize the spread of covered nineteen.
Scott technology , the internet GPS in the column of your hand alternative.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defense advanced research has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from dark , a window until dark is cool of program managers , their job to redefine what is part possible .
My name is , I have an amateur on your dark post .
I've been away since the end of twenty eighteen , and i'm excited to resurrect with this episode .
The Voices from global partners .
However , I do this at one of the most trying times most of us can remember .
Everything seems to have changed .
Nothing feels right .
On march eleventh , one of the days , and which I set down with program managers in our recording studio , the world health organization , WEIZHOUdeclared the infectious spread of the crown advisers as a covered nineteenth , the disease caused by a new corona virus .
That sense is referred to as severe acute respiratory syndrome , coordinate virus too , or sars .
It has been among us at least since late last year , when the first case is showed up in china and our UNIin our seven point eight billion human brazilians are living in pandemic .
The worlds people are in this together.
What we do know is that pandemics come , and pennsylvania , depending on their security in the collective response , they meet out different amounts of human and economic loss as an institution .
Dark has for many years , recognized the enormous threats posed by emerging infectious agents .
It has done so in its very dark away , says , dark as an institution we are going to do something about this .
In twenty sixteen , the bread realized a civil servant working for the department of defence for nearly twenty years , became the deputy director of darkness , biological technology of this BTO.
In june , he upgraded to become BTOdirector .
Now he finds himself heading a team of program managers , or*****rating or portfolio of technology programs that stand the chance of meeting this new coroner buyers on its own molecular biological terms , these program managers are on their way to developing a technology platform that they hope will end the threat of pandemic disease period if they succeed , copyright team could become the last pandemic .
This is not some pen , glassy ambition .
This is hard science and technology that could take the pandemic disease off of humanities already long list of worries .
BTOdirector , bread wing ice.
Darker plays a really important role for the entire government , quite obviously , but specifically for the department , defence and predict what is emerging as threats to both our war fighters and our duty personnel , but also to the country is a whole .
And that has been something that has been persistent to the entire lifetime of darker , but specific to infectious disease and emerging diseases .
This is something over the last two decades .
Dark has been there .
We've learned what is needed and what is required to build the fight , the types of outbreaks and pandemic right now.
Right now , if the new crowd , obviously that is waking the world up to how devastating pandemic diseases can be , it was only a few years ago that we all extremely another wake up call .
That's when dark are double this efforts to investigate and develop for crashing outbreaks of infectious diseases before they can blow up into regional academics or global.
Like a one of the challenges as no back in twenty four team .
There was a new balloon outbreak after we all remember that that was the last last time we really started to to worry about sort of our international pandemic because of sort of the limited transmissibility of that particular virus requirements , or the bottled fluid transferring that seem to not be as contagious as the current current virus that they were seen right now .
But one that process did for a dark for some amazing program managers and amazing for thought that happened back five , ten , even fifteen years ago , program managers started thinking about an ideal world where we can have a rapid response platform where we could insert having to develop back scenes of the course of years , maybe even decades , at at any time .
We would not be grateful at the world where we could reduce that research and development process down to a matter of potentially weeks or months , rather than having to wait on that tremendously long time , from which we know living through or living through right now , it's just too long.
It's a combination of the nature of a new contagion , the speeded , which a disease outbreak is detected , and public health and medical countermeasures to the , it determines just how much and how fast and how far an initial outbreak will grow renewed wickers in a program manager in the biological technology .
Officers , twenty sixteen , now runs several programs that she hopes were produced powerful new entire democrats , at least in time for the next one of those programs , the digit program aims to improve our ability to detect any biological threat known or news , human kind , anytime , anywhere .
Her prepared program aims to liberate natural passage in fighting genes and proteins already in our bodies .
Here is how you can explain the difference between outbreaks and pandemics and pandemic that try for own work .
As a program manager.
The way you think about an outbreak is really just AA, Anormally in the number of diseases in a given region .
Maybe for influenza is an increase in cases or alcohol , seasonality , but something that is inherently different from baseline would , would constitute AAoutbreak beyond an outbreak and epidemic is where you start to see more person to person transmission and a larger geographic region , even multiple regional countries being impacted for something to be declared pandemic .
The three straight criteria that have to be satisfied .
So one is that in most cases , as this is , is , is novel , meaning that is , it is something we have seen before , or it's something that hasn't been around for a very long time .
Nineteen eighty flew is a great example where there is very unlikely that there is a community in the population .
So effectively many , many individuals from that risk of this disease as the first criteria in the second is there is person to person transmission , so it's not just simply animals , certainty people in this , we will not accept , but virginia and personal , personal , and then finally inherited in pandemic as a global is that it's a pen regional outbreak , which is now a pandemic .
And those are , those are the criteria that the WHOhaven't said to declare pandemic .
In effect today .
It was because of the nineteenth declared a pandemic.
That was on march eleventh , and in just a few weeks , the pandemic has terrorized ever more of the world , and it is amplified , darker , sensitive urgency to realize those innovations that will dramatically short from disease detection to delivering countermeasures at large scales .
The agency runs a portfolio programs that hit pandemics and every point possible , including even as dangerous viruses , are mutating with an animal and insect totes in two forms that can lead into people if we could stop disease progression that really says graduating island .
We would not see those upward shooting curves in the news to picking massive spread of infection and the devastation that comes with it.
In the ideal situation , you would really want to be able to move very , very much left of the curve that we are currently experiencing for the coordinating outbreak .
We would want to be able to identify the emergence of diseases from animal populations .
We wanna be able to take those identifications early and detect , maybe even in the animal populations , potentially even give countermeasures to those animal populations to be able to prevent it , the hub , and to humans that we have just witnessed over the last several months .
So we have a program called prevent .
That is exactly trying.
This is where programme manager role heat chitty comes into the picture .
He has been a disease spider for his entire professional life .
Among his credits are called establishing the global disease detection operations at the UScenters for disease control and prevention , and helping to temp down the spread of aids and sales to down .
And now he has focused on all of his experience and knowledge on the challenge of ending pandemic disease.
I hammered the darker in september of twenty ninety , and in november , I inherited a program called preventing emerging passage and threats .
And really , really what some people are double called etheric , but exactly what I think where we need to be going .
It is the type of program that says we looked animals .
We look at insects .
So how can we stop the disease there before it spills over to humans ?
And that idea , there is truly a prevention and public health of all about prevention .
And unfortunately , we like to say that we were successful .
People don't know.
But he says , one of the best ways of achieving these hidden , advancing successes in public health , and with battling pandemics , is to understand how dangerous viruses arise in animals.
There has been a focus of the last one years on the concept of one health , one health brings together human and animal medicine , and says that basically , we know that animals actually are about response for sixty , seventy of human factors threats .
So you know , we think about things like ziggy's yellow favourite chicken gania , a bowler .
These of all , come from animals .
Sars , all three , at least three thousands , and last fifteen twenty , and the last the ground of us , the last fifteen years have come from animals .
More than the idea is that you should have one health concept , says a look at animals so that we can get ahead of spring to humans .
Can we prevent the spillover of a hundred virus or a new crown of hours to people ?
Can we prevent that ?
Keep it in the bats , keep it from coming into the intermediate reservoirs , like the penguins , the civic cats , you know , for example , or the I read that the dogs on the birds in china , for example.
Understanding how the spiller was occurred takes boots on the ground all over the world .
He says , and the performers , the investigators contracted to do research under his prime program are leaving their boot principal.
Far and wide , not healthy to study bets in bangladesh by the gas , car gonna and australia , and there's certain bad ecology .
You can understand , how do you best live ?
What do they feed on ?
When do they get stressed ?
When did they produce more in their europe ?
When did they produce more virus ?
And when does that virus below for starting horses in hydro australia , that name of the town is actually hendry , that's where it was name from the virus .
So looking at where the spiller events have happened and and wear the spiller events have happened for humans.
Once a spill over happens , then detection and diagnostics become pivotal pieces of the public health response , bridging eyes and explains a few of the ways his program manager colleagues have been moving the dialogue and escape one rapidly developing technology .
He points to will quickly identify and say the student were blood of patients .
The presence of molecular science called epigenetic marks in the sales of a patient responding to a viral exposure .
This would be like tracking the earliest footprints left by the viruses and people's bodies , you would know , for example , if and when people with common infection symptoms have been visited , either by influence of viruses or source .
Kobe , tu.
In darker language , we've very much tried to have four sides of the past , two or three years to try to start developing detection platforms that are very easily adaptable to new diseases .
Use genetic technology that there are lots of work that can be done .
Justin , computers to be of the simulate and to be of the identified the exact genetical that you would need , that would be specific to the type of emerging fires that we see now with the source .
Coffee too , too .
So we were able to immediately in january , just with genetic code information that was coming out about this virus .
Some of our performers were able to immediately identify very specific code that would specifically identify the virus , turn that into an essay that could then now be tested .
University of brazil , whether as many of these conversation , patients undergoing treatments in the bicycle , and so that was all done within a two months period of time to rapidly respond to now do the work , but the necessary to be able to get approval of that new essay for detection .
That's one , and the second one I liked to talk about this , a host response diagnostic program we developed about two years ago called echo.
Echo run by program manager error , van diesel is an economic stands for epigenetic characterization , and observation is all about identifying the early signs and a person's that he or she has been exposed to gravely threatening agents , including chemical , radiological and biological weapons , were to natural threats like infectious and passengers .
More than that , the handheld technology that eric has been shepherding through development might be able to identify people who show no symptoms of infection , but nonetheless , our contagious were likely to become .
So it turns out that even early violent exposure , sleep told , tell molecular marks on the DNA and proteins inside the nuclear air bar cells , these are called opportunity marks .
They're a bit like we've feeding tags and walls throughout the city .
The goal of alcohol is a developed health devices that would be able to read those viral tags from easily got , says , eric , the technology should be able to tell us if someone has been exposed to a particular arrivals exactly when and how that person is likely to respond to an exposure again .
BTOdirector breading island.
We are working at the epigenetic response of your own body , and that episode response may occur on day one of the exposure to that virus .
And so your body starts suggesting that starts adapting to that infection , and it starts leaving dynamic marks on your genome , so are very confident that would be able to identify host a patriotic marks that are specific to this new cover , ninety outbreak .
This is opportunity .
We started two years ago .
And again , I started to pay dividends now to be able to get very , very early , maybe even present domestic detection of a disease like this , and again , more working with the university of the press to be able to validate and to be able to test that as a as it develops in emergency , comes online.
We'll hit two toilets and urban decent fellow program manager immediately has called several years working for DARPA , but only last june that she became a program manager in detail .
She didn't expect the ride would be accelerated quite as much so quickly in the mistakes with the claims so high , but she is where she wants to be furthering the power of the public of community .
Can , will against these.
And you always think you are ready until the real world scenario kind of drops itself in your lap .
And then it realized , well , there are a lot of things that we , we have to think about others a lot of coordination that has to go on .
There's a lot of pressure .
Yeah , when you put out a program , this is , we're going to stop pandemic and sixty days .
And you have a declared pandemic on hand , people are looking at us to potentially make.
Abraham is overseen a baby of programs , including an especially comprehensive economic prevention platform program among the deliverables of many programs or anti party base treatments of the to stop infections early and longer enough to buy time for the development of long term protective measures , such as vaccines .
The goal of another wonderful program called now , which is short for nuclear as its undermined world wide , are mobile manufacturing platforms for producing new therapeutics against infectious diseases .
Anywhere , anytime at school.
That matter .
So my portfolio largely consist of , how are we going to respond very quiet quickly to infectious diseases .
And the reason I think we need to respond quickly to infect .
This is because we have seen it .
We saw in two thousand nine with each one anyone we thought with the bowler , even though that was not respiratory and spread across the world , it very easy to make the next connection to save .
We had something that works , friend by a respiratory as a respiratory disease .
How quickly can spread across the world?
Central to amy's portfolio is the quest to dramatically shrink the amount of time it takes to identify the antibiotics and people who recovered from antibodies .
These are broken that our own immune systems in event , when challenged by infectious agents , and that are tailor made to neutralize those agents , amy , in the researchers supported by her pandemic prevention platform program , or developing antibody treatments that could prove pivotal in slowing outbreaks before they can become epidemics and pandemic .
S the technology has made it beyond the concept stage all the way to clinical trials , at least previous knowledge .
Chicken gun , amy says we could have protected antibodies against the new coronal virus in hand this year .
This is our cheap .
Critical is the progress of.
For I am very interesting antibodies and antibodies , technology , and provides specificities .
Antibodies are very , very specific for the passage that you are trying to come back , trying to target .
They're made naturally by your body .
So when you are exposed to say a chicken pocks , when you were a little kid , your body made antibodies , those in two bodies and become memory b cells , and they hang out in your body .
And if you ever see chicken pocks again , they come back to life if you will , and they stop you from getting infected by chicken park .
Well , we are very interested in that same type of technology .
So when it's a person gets sick , they actually make any other bodies .
And so the thought with our programs that you can go in arm to a personnel has recovered , and presumably the body has made antibodies that helped them recover from manufacturers , diseases at passenger .
And we can very rapidly find those antibodies .
So once you find that anybody , it then becomes a matter of , how do you give that thing that protected that one patient , if you are able to find the very good ones and give it back to the rest of the population to protect them and prevent them from getting sick .
And so that is really how we think about the use of antibodies .
In many cases , we think of them as a firebreak .
So you give it to people so that they don't get sick .
So that's the same as a general concept that we want to use here .
The problem that we have when we think about the use of these types of things is that we don't have decades to find that antibody said , and we certainly don't have years or more to manufacturer that antibody .
And so that's where some of our other technologies comment we have , as I mentioned , learned how to very quickly find the antibodies we have certainly shrunk that time line .
The anthropology we also needed to invest in ways to ensure that we can make new factor that anybody much , much faster .
And so traditionally , how their maids are made in giant steamers still buy reactors , said malayan cells traditionally back in a twenty four teenager that outbreak that process could take anywhere from ten to twenty four months to figure out how to get that that those cells to grow in that bioreactor and had to make that protein properly .
That was much too long for rapid response .
And so we begin investing in an DNA or army technology , and the bodies are simply approaching if we have the DNA or the army code for that that DNA or arney , if you injected into your body , should make that protein badly anti body , we demonstrated this was for a variety of different passengers .
So we looked at the bowler we looked at influenza .
We looked at multi drug resistant bacteria passengers .
We looked at chicken glorious , so many different viruses and generally always variable to demonstrate straight that , yes , this is possibility , and animals , we then turn ourselves to humans through a rounds of regular safety testing .
We thought that it was a time to potentially test this humans , and we did do a humans clinical safety trial .
These types of technologies have been tested in fourth safety and face one human clinical safety trial , and it has generally demonstrated the ability to inject , for example , in our name intravenously and to a human patient , that patient , then their cells take up that army and ourselves , then producing up to party the US, the code that you gave it to produce .
And we actually completed that clinical trial with the company called mcdonald as part of the adapt program on in the fall of twenty nine team that was actually for a chicken glorious and antibiotics chicken gloriously .
So we've demonstrated that you can use this genetic code , you can inject that into the person , and the person can become the bioreactor .
So the thought is for the crown virus outbreak , we may be able to actually manufacturer enterprises in anywhere from four to eight months.
As embassy said , this kind of anti body based medical technology can change the pandemic equation in humanity is.
If you think about the fact that we could use antibodies , whether they be traditional protein empathized that we injected , whether we inject the army or the DNA code , all of these , you gave them to healthy people .
Those people are now protected for anywhere from a month to maybe as many as six months from getting disease .
So if you think about this , we should always talk about it in the context of the above outbreak .
I'll talk about it in my context to crowd of others now , because the same thing potentially applies here , you have those people that have to respond .
They are on the front lines .
These are your nurses .
Your daughter is your first responders , the people that can't quarantine , be in hospitals helping patients .
These are the people that are potentially most at risk , so we call them our front line health care workers and disappear population that would make more sense to give this , and naturally , so that they don't get sick so that you keep your health care system functioning in a robust manner , then you can also think about giving this type of if you had another , you could give this type of modernity .
Two people that have been exposed .
So , for example , if you have a family member , potentially all of their contacts could get this .
So this is something that I think even two months ago , people maybe didn't understand the people are now becoming much more comfortable with understanding , contact tracing and what that actually means , and why that's important , if you become second , you tell your public health department .
These are all the people I came in contact with .
Those are potentially now the people that are also going to get sick .
You could then go to peoples people and potentially give them this that they don't become sick .
And now you stop these types of diseases from spreading , and it is , frankly , exactly how we have stopped .
Another worst of all outbreaks in history of a bullet outbreaks in the last four years .
And it's going to be critical in this corona virus spread , as well as just understanding who talked to who , who interacted with her .
And we could certainly a vision , a situation where this type of technology to ensure that those contacts do not get sick.
Amy and her daughter colleagues .
But to solve the research groups already working as performers in the pandemic prevention platform program , also known as the peace reprogram to apply with the already of learned to the new covered nineteen pandemic.
So all of our groups are currently working on this , and we actually have groups that are currently at great , as we speak at this moment , discovering into bodies against this crowd buyers , we're able to obtain samples from our patients that under informed consent , donated their blood to try to find some of these antibodies that helped that person recover .
So several other groups are currently working to try to identify those antibodies .
I will carry out this by saying that this was one person and one person's response .
And so we would typically do this with many people , maybe after ten people , because we just don't know how one person responds versus another .
You wanna have an best shots on goal .
We had one person .
Our groups are working extensively , literally around the clock to try to identify those antibodies from that patient that may be the most useful for trading of broader swarth .
The population .
It is going well .
I am very cautiously optimistic .
We have found initial hits that would indicate that we have some antibodies that do bind the snowball crown , but there is extensive testing that will go on in the next two to three weeks to really characterize and understand those antibodies what we actually want to be able to do is neutralize the virus , or what we call neutralized the , which is prevent the virus from infecting human cells .
So the first thing will do is we will test that in vitro in a petri dish , if you are not exactly a petri dish , but in that , we actually tested and make sure that our antibodies block that passenger from infecting human sets , then the next step would be to then tested in animals , small animals or large animals , or both .
Potentially , so we're talking mice , or potentially all the optimum employments .
And if if it looks like it can protect those animals from getting sick from the crown of virus , the next step would begin to manufacture and and get ready to tested for safety .
And a facebook humanitarian trial.
This means all of the technology stands a chance of helping out , even in this current pandemic .
But it also sets the stage for discerning pandemic threats that humanity assure to face the future , like some of her colleagues , renewed wagers and is running programs that , if successful , could help solve the hard problem of quickly detecting any dangerous passage that might emerge , one of our ambitious programs is digital shot for detected with gene editing technologies .
Imagine , she says , hand held devices that could detect any passenger in the concern , and with just about any biological sample , spit blood or your own , for example , that's what your name wants to make.
Five years now , and when we have all of our digit devices up and running first on the front end , we're going to have unparalleled biotherapeutics where we can look at every patient sample that that comes in and look across a thousand different possible passengers , in fact , in an individual , in every human passenger , that is .
So we just routinely look at that testing that would be our opportunity to to take something very early , potentially even before an outbreak occurs .
Once we have at the bowl's surveillance of then we would want to get a diagnostic in place very quickly so that we could , okay , now we know there is something that is in a normally not rule in a rule out that they know this is person who have this disease or not .
That's very important because you can help make a decision to quarantine somebody , but then also to give them the right medical camera .
So you want to make sure that you're matching treatment with the element .
Of course , that's what about the individual patient level , but then at the decision , make our level , whether it's for a nation or at the polite unit , there needs to be decision making of , you know , how did they respond and move forward ?
Is it rolling out medical calendar measures ?
Is it bringing your call command back in whatever that might be if you actually could have in what we were called actionable information moving forward , so that would have been great if we had this for this current outbreak , potentially , we could contained it before we hit this pandemic state .
That's really where we want to be moving forward.
Bread is olympic and moving forward as fast as possible , with the program managers in BTOand the innovation community they are nurturing .
He feels their efforts really , really could reduce the consequences of future academic.
Threads , so if we step back and think about the the next thread that inevitably is most like , it is going to happen .
I think what you see with the dark of beauty of sweet of programs and sweet of technologies that we're developing is that we really do see a pathway now where we , we won't have to go through the process of all going through right now .
Exponential growth to see the danger of the threat to our.
Bread points out that supervisory board goes like developing practical and deployable technology platforms that will introduce any infectious disease outbreak before it can threaten military readiness .
And large populations .
Takes salad partnerships throughout the system , and it takes an institutional infrastructure that can deliver public health actions and medical countermeasures.
On massive skills , we put a goal out to the community .
We offered funding , research , funding .
Those researchers then go off and do the amazing work , but we can take any of that work from the laboratory to actually used to be able to fight something like without partnerships , and and that's something that in my three years here , darker that I really worked hard at is trying to work with our domestic advanced developers , work with our ages and age as per barrel partners , because there are the ones that are really tasked with the advanced development and ultimately getting these types of products through the fda and being of the actual distribute manufacturer to the population .
And so without those partnerships , I am , we're working with them literally , almost every day during this outbreak to be able to make sure that these new innovations , these rapid response platforms don't just die in laboratory .
They actually make their way into the duty personnel and to offer , protect the USpopulation as well.
So in this moment of shared anxiety and fear , it is a gift to imagine credibly of a not so distant future where no one has to worry about an outbreak of a new disease anywhere we're spreading to a devastating pandemic .
Everywhere is harding to know that there is a team of dark program managers who , with partners around the world are making sure our most innovative researchers and technology develops can take those steps that won't get us there .
Thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next voices for government , thanks also to tongue short ridge , and then celebrate for help in producing this forecast for more information about dark and that many breaks with technologies , the agency is working on visit darkness and for links that enable you to download this and other episodes of the pipeline , go to Voices from dark .