Stop technology , the internet GPS in the column of your hand on the most operation , and technology is a driver of our times .
Since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war in DARPA , the defensive ADS research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window on the darkness , core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone amount on your dark a host today .
I am pleased to be talking without your john book , a program manager since twenty seventeen in agencies microsystems technology , we are recording our conversations from our respective homes as we do our parts to slow the spread of covered nineteenth , the pandemic disease caused by the crowd of our source .
Two , this is also why you might hear ambient sounds like trucks and sirens and birds .
John brings his technology visions to dark up on detail from the air force research laboratory , space vehicles directorate , acquirement air force base in new mexico .
There , he had a research team developing a tonight clocks , a ton of time transfer for secretion applications and ultra precision measurement techniques for use in the global positioning system , other space .
His research interests include the development of next generation sensors for pushing the state of the identity , for example , remote detection and frequency synthesis methods to enable PN, PNTis *** , speak for positioning , navigation and timing .
John earned this pitch in physics in the university , virtually.
John , thanks for joining me .
What are the bigger thanks for inviting me to do this?
Also , I know that one of your interest adopted is to reduce the complexity , costs and size of PNTand other techniques , and to make these usable outside of labour , tories settings , and we'll get to those when we speak about your programs .
But first , I like to hear a little bit about where your interest in science comes from .
If your parents were scientists , repair the amazing teacher , just what is about twenty two?
I think it really started in the youth that , as I suppose it does for many people to sort of a natural curiosity in the world .
And as I grew up and kind of discovered , I was pretty good at math .
I think every person has a good or bad experience with this .
Mine was positive .
And one thing LED to another , and I went to college and a professor talking to taking physics one or one for a general education agreement .
And I did really , really one thing like another in here I am , I can sort of call that that went .
I will say one little thing along the way .
It turned out that my , a great grandfather actually was a physics professor at the college that I went to know .
I knew this a little bit going there , but I didn't really discover this until I was .
So it turns out that of my great grandfather with a physicist name johnny .
Here I am , this is his name and doing the same thing , which I was amazing circle there.
It's the bird dynasty and physics , so that that's really a copy of history next to the school you went to .
So you work at the air force research laboratory in current .
And so my guess is that you knew about DARPA quite well even there .
But how is it that you've got to die ?
Booking manager has a how I got the dark story .
So what's?
When I was in graduate school , we were funded .
I was found as a graduate student by daughter and said , that was my first exposure to it .
The pressure was overwhelming to perform , but it was really rewarding to have some direction to go on and not to sort of float in the english world of questions you might ask .
And physics are in science .
And I saw that kind of when I get interested in being participant and sort of the dark of mission , get all that .
I think that stake with me .
Now I want to air force , as you said , and it doubt there are many folks government that helped double with more context for the problems that there have been .
So then I helped not rule for quite a while before being asked , join the ranks .
And I was very excited.
Okay , and just wanna backtrack a little bit too , that earlier , I think you said the involvement is a graduate student .
And we said , that's right .
What was the program?
It was called the guided , both einstein .
Khan said in a foreign program , which is a mouthful , to be sure.
And what really what we're talking about are tiny in a sort of fundamental particles like atoms that are put into a certain conditions so that they all are sort of like one micros topic want an object that you can manipulate this , that I get that kind of.
That's pretty close to rate .
It is a strange thing that it turns out that the eyes , diana and the physician both figured out that you , you could under certain conditions , would make this way .
They need to be very cold if you can cool particles down to a certain temperature in parliament of box , they would insert a behaving like individual particles being into each , yeah , that they would add more like a super particular .
We all can adapt together and call her fashion the most normal way of talking about this is , I was coming out to say , we are talking about .
This is a comparison to the laser .
You have a light bulb .
You know how that works , and you have a laser pointer , and you , people have experience with those who implemented the capital or whatever .
So that sort of the difference we're talking about yourself , normal particles , and I guess they've been in two children .
I believe one kind of physics .
And then if we do this BCconversation , they act more like a laser .
So it's a whole different set of rules applies that level .
We will reach glory at a time.
The journal , we want to secure it in two , talking about your programs , two of which you inherited and two of which you are going to be rolling out .
Or are , let's go to the inherited programs .
First one is called the atomic clocks with enhanced stability program or aces , and one is actually much more multi celebrate program known short as ambient , but a long form as atomic mechanism of her for biological imaging in earth's native to win .
So let's talk about both programs , starting with asians and and so what's the technology goal basis ?
And how would you describe the status of the program?
So it is , is , is trying to make some of the world's best time clocks and to a package that is actually useful .
And you know , this is a long history , actually darker , trying to do this as a program called suicide crystal , maybe fifteen years ago , trying to do the next four hours earlier .
Thus , the chip scale tonight clock , so to a little more self event , it was trying to do that was really successful program .
And I , you can buy sea sex .
This typical time of collapse in a variety of thanks .
Just mentioned a few of the users share , so automatically general , the main user of them is , is what synchronization visible .
What is the synchronism things like GPS, GPS.
The global positioning system is entirely funded on these atomic clocks .
It went for them .
They wouldn't work at all .
There are also backup for a lot of information technology systems , things like financial markets , data , data centers are all these things when a lot of data is moving around requests in conversation , you find a tomato collapse in all those cancer.
Right , okay and unseen to most of us is just just the role that autonomic clocks play as you change everything from GPS all the way to to the financial transactions .
But so getting back to assist the asset program .
Yeah , again , what's the technology goal ?
And how do you describe the status of the.
But so there's a whole solution of atomic clocks that are out there .
Some are pretty expensive , and you will not see those except specialized circumstances , and some are very inexpensive , like the justice .
Galaxy collectors is rotary and expensive .
But the think you find it like finance networks and GPS systems .
The question was , could we make something as good as that , but at a sizing costume and power low enough that you could actually start thinking about putting them more places .
And so let's deal with the program to try to make an anthony collector you could still buy , but it will cost you seven thousand and fill up a good chunk of of your real statement and save up and develop a talk communications cannon and replaced .
It was something that was more like the size of your fist or millions , and then you guys are putting them in radios , putting them in their planes , putting on a matter of places .
So that's a gold program to to do that .
Is , it turns out every part of these best atom o'clocks that you could buy has to be managed to rise precise dramatically , and that will be enough , and we need to go to the laboratories , whereas some of the best atomic clocks are made and learned some new techniques .
Leaders are calling being one of the english .
Just participants are talking about cold , cold particles and and try to implement those .
It also , it makes us small , so it's a pretty big system challenge of lots of pieces being made small where we are in the program , where we are actually towards into the problem .
And I would like to tell you when I took the program over , it seemed like a very , very difficult challenge was had at the beyond us .
I think it would be unlikely that we would have that for your programmer , so we would succeed at the level we have , but longer holds were about six months out to dinner the program , and we have program types , and they work .
And it's amazing .
It is each little compounded , and there is a little bit of a of a dry story , but there are all kind of amazing when you think about them , vacuum pumps and special lasers , and just just all kinds of little pieces , this has been made to fit in there , but they work , and I think , pretty soon will have asian clocks that.
It is , some people will be able to buy .
Maybe you can just say a little bit about what this does mean when you can mean your choice and make more , more affordable technologies that have been too big or too expensive to use .
And I am thinking of just even the way GPS became a military rise , and and is now in all of our fans , something the job also had a role .
So what happens when we can take , you know , the time of clubs and put them into gadgets they.
So I have not been able to go before .
Well , let's start at the GPS system because that next part of the most important place to start the , you know , a lot of people maybe not realize how important GPS actually is .
It's in practical , everything writers that would make your mobile phones really work as well as they do .
It makes our electrical system work as as reliably .
It's , you know , even to the point of right now .
I don't have to realize this , but the best farming equipment , and actually most of our crops now are dependent on GPS .
They actually recalled each one of the seats were exactly reduced to make a cinema.
And so they can go back to that sea , gratefully into precision farming , precision fertilizer in position .
Application of water were needed to be amazing.
It's amazing , and so GPS is everywhere , but what you might not realize is that if something would happen to GPS , you know , it could be a mammy problem .
There have been several instance of that new york books , basically in the system have been discovered to a natural system problem , some , some way of solar flares have been famously started about it .
Spain very disrupted , and so what I have , and if we didn't have GPS was all those things that depend on , it will always certainly be flowing and not have that time or the location information , and it would be very bad , I think .
So over , for example , how would overwork , or you're right during work if there was no GPS for a day , wouldn't work at all .
It's an important problem .
So the main thing that absolutely the main thing that is that my affordably making a clock at this quality , those kinds of systems that leads those are truth , can put these o'clocks backup in there , and there are systems we know we're planning for on the bad days on day , but that they would be a little less bad .
Now we could have some reasonably priced collapsed in.
right ?
And just because we are talking about dark here , which is part of the department of the fencing .
And we should point out that , of course , one of the concerns and a driving concerns , and we leave GPS becomes available to the military services in the assets that we have to depend on them , right ?
So this is one of the drivers were trying to come up with alternatives to GPS that can kick in their european factor in absolutely some of the recent GPS system becomes unavailable.
That's right , organized asia's clocks .
They are , first , of course , but if we can manage , that , does not think you are seeing in in commercial use all over the place too .
I say one of the most important places you might see this .
It is in our soil and infrastructure .
So it is a reason all of our phones , if you actually prepare phone is about the opportunity , and it's all typed back to GPS through your cell phone to our own .
So at the same thing , if we can make achieve enough that telecom companies wants me a bucket , putting AAreally nice time keeping unit in their base stations in the towers and so on .
Now , awesome , you have a much moral based technology communication system in case of something happens , but also they can make the systems even better .
Right , there's a problem , you know , past five g sixty , whatever is out past that might utilize the timing that these clocks gave the systems more .
So , so , you know , really have a talk communications companies sort of argue outside , like leaning into the timing precision .
They could buy a reasonable price .
They could be really begin changing.
That's because it would help them piece together many more packets of information coming in all different times , because I can time snap those so accurately.
That's right , you're trying to spend very accurately , and it's really important for things like data hand off the festival , driving around .
It's actually had amazing when you think about it , you can drive in your car now .
And the most part , your call doesn't drop .
Where are you going to eternally go into a bridge ?
No problem .
And yet that's why is that it was because of those data packs of things rounded between between different towers all the time .
And it works similar into powerful techniques , synchronized and and just different , different.
Detail activities .
Now let's move to the second program that you inherited in this was from a former program manager , robert , like work .
This one is called atomic magnetos matter for biological imaging in earth's native train or ambient for short .
That's two eyes in there .
What's that program about ?
And where is it it in ?
So in the end of.
As a magazine , it's a management program .
And so first question is asking for what is the magnitude , and it's simply a device that measures magnetic fields .
And you might ask , why would we want to ever handle such a device , but it turns out that lots of things had a magnetic moment through them are like a permitted language .
Does university of a strong one that can be used to find them .
So you see this all the time .
So , for example , you see people using a metal attackers to find , like jury on a beach as a classic example of someone using some of the negative properties of a device of the story of the object trying to find to find it , even though it would be difficult to.
Otherwise , although usually the finding.
Bottle cap misery is , so you have it an important problem , and manufacturers just already .
So the magnetic field made by the object can be actually large enough to find .
The promise is so many things that have a magnetic associated imaginative field that they cannot collaborate each other up so it can be very easy to get lost in all the noise made biological objects that mention the earth has all magnetic field that is actually quite large and scale of any of these things were talking about yet to attract that off .
And so let's hear that the program and earth need to rain .
So the problem we're trying to solve here is , how can make a manufacturer that sort of automatically , you're intrinsically removes that background field and can separate out all the that you from different objects , so you can really hold in on one thing that you care about.
One of the potential applications that has caught my attention is in using these new kinds of magnetic tools as measurement instruments for the brain took to sort of look at the magnetic fields that are associated with all of the kind of movement of electrical charges in the brain .
What we can say about that.
So that's right .
The , it's not just permanent objects that he says anything that makes a current so that your brain does that you have nervous circuits in your brain that are constantly firing , trying to sort out the law around you .
And those currents make many fields , and the many fields can be detected .
They passed right through the score and to the outside world .
Now you , you might imagine that you might , those currents are really , really small , so actually detecting the middle field associated with them is pretty challenging , especially if you get this big earth field trying to wash all of that out the indian program as well .
The first things were trying to do this .
It's just a really hard .
Problem is a very small metic field argument in a number .
It's a honest scale of about ten film to test.
Samples that small , let's stand to remind the fifteen of something.
Turn the minus fifteen of something .
And to put that perspective , that is about so earth's magic feels about a hundred micro tesla .
So we've got about the lesson .
What is the matter ?
But twelve , because the manager , too , would get to keep the cultural in order to see this .
That is a really , really hard problem .
How do you measure something small on the face of something large ?
So we were trying to legislate , measure these tiny manufacturers and the way we want to do that is , instead of measuring a many field itself , we will try to measure the gradient , automatic field .
So instead of measuring the raphia direction , measuring the difference between two manufacturers to reckon .
So the idea you put one manufacturer may be next , you're brain , but it has at your , your skill and the element , tomorrow's a lot of fuel inches away from that , which doesn't sound like a lot .
But I insist in space enough to a sort of measure the separation between what your brains doing and what the earth is doing , and subtract us to and give you back a signal list , hopefully.
What your brain is doing .
I remember talking to rubber .
Let's work about some of the potential biomedical applications you are like , potentially helping to monitor what happening in the nervous system during medical procedures in the weather that some kind of neurosurgery , or , I think , really discussion you mention.
Concussion monitoring , that's right .
The brain is sort of famously difficult to understand and end make any kind of reasonable measurements of , especially in real time .
And we have cats , gangs and things like this .
But do you want to know something about an injury happening to the brain of real time ?
That's very difficult to find .
So let's the kind of thing we might try to go use this for is real time concussion monitoring .
You actually , maybe we all see if the narrow activity your brain is changed from what it was the day before .
So a football player might have a very fast ability to see if they've been concussed .
And if we make it more important than they could do it out in around the side of the field with the earth's field , constantly trying to wash out that there will be one of the we want to do is in the military .
We want to do this too far for , say , soldiers .
They were exposed to an explosion of some kinds .
It's sent to the same problem .
How do you know if that soldiers okay , that could continue?
Just in a more general sense , and just bring me briefly on the assembly , it pushes science whenever you can develop a sensor that just is more capabilities , more sensitive words , more accurate words , tapping into a signal out there on the world that other centuries have not been able to do you open up opportunities for more discovery , right ?
And so I would think these kinds of mcdonald's coming out of ambient might also survivor us.
That's right , it means it's a tool not just to explore magnetic fields or some particular problem , like concussions , but it's a means to see our world with a different sort of abilities .
And we had before .
And this is really fascinating thing .
So we , we are particular problem , and we were looking at , but the larger picture of of , how can you understand in the world around us ?
And anytime we can expand our capability to do that , scientists everywhere and all kinds of applications , engineers , and so we'll find a way to make the best of that and discover new things that make new types of applications capabilities .
So that's really , really exciting parties , figuring out how it happened to that page , then hearing accuracy and and sensitivity these , these kind of sensors can not.
Can give us .
So we've spoken about the two programs that you inherited assets and ambient , but you are in the process of rolling out to other.
Programs sure , so the , the first program of it was briefly mentioned as the atomic photonic integration program .
He added , basically , the problem is for these really high and column sensors .
The existing labor tories , did you look at these things in someone's laboratory at university say you'll instant see this large force of optics and mirrors and lasers , and just all kinds of stuff .
And it's amazing , scientists can do it for all that , but it takes a small army of graduate students to run all that in the symbolic and lot of money , money from taxpayers , mostly too to build .
So the question I had was , could we figure out a way to fabricate the equivalent sort of device that does all that stuff ?
And then we have a means to more quickly iterate on different design concepts to expand the state of the art and also a faster offering offered from a laboratory to a natural , practical advice .
So , for example , asean ambient would be examples of the kind of problem action .
So could you just want to fabricated the standards you just making a more copies of it more quickly released ?
No , so much such a word .
So you're combining fatalities and electronic and circuits , another kinds of devices into a quantum , trying to make it all at once .
And so if we could do that , I will just imagine how much faster we could go if we could do that instead .
So that's an automation , you know , for us in a deal deal , if we saw something that was really going to make a big impact to our national security , we can actually do something about that relatively quickly .
So let's let's go to.
Right , okay , thanks for showing that .
And then there is the second program we rolling out to tell me little about.
So quebec is another manufacturer program .
It saw this , this , we were talking about .
Environment is in the idea of tournament .
and.
And so I get them just before you go to the description for something like this.
Quebec stands for the column imaging of vector electronic creation and emphasize victor , because that's what the key question is .
So these manufacturers that we made in ambient , they are skilled amanda towners , so for for them , initiated with that means that the magnetic field , the authors of actor , you can see this field , but he looked at iron filings around , like a , like , a permanent mag .
Maybe some pictures like that .
Those are showing you the field lines that can occur around themselves since a little bit of a field , and imagine it is a little of an invisible field .
And if you try to measure that the magnitude of that , any point you really get in part of the information .
So instead , the question is , let's make a victor management , they can measure the three different or flag or components that magnetic field .
Victor explains , they say , and they will make those into a smaller way .
Imagine that religious , and then you can measure something called that you copy , and a magnetic field of actual beneficial .
Did you copy in cancer , but to copy an answer , sir , is the mathematical or speaker .
But it's a majority of three by three majors , or each component of the is a derivative of electrical component .
Would respect to a different direction of component .
So , for example , the delivery of domestic field in the extraction was respect a translation in the white direction would be the middle component , say that magic.
Okay , and so what i'm gonna actually have to ask you to do that is maybe translate that.
If you succeed , what's the capability to do , so , what are we talking about this right ?
So there is a magic , right once you have that tensor , you now have all of the relevant information about the magnetic , you'll do to say a premier nan , and with all the information now , this quarter and background field problem is no longer a physics lesson , any more to mathematical lesson is in question , what algorithm can I use on that methodological object to deduce information about the architect looking for ?
And that's very , very powerful , because now you reduce the sensing problem into a computation problem , very easy computation promises to relate at three major magic is not very complicated .
So with that , we hope we can make a very general manager that can see almost anything we have to really make a big impact on the ability of neglect .
Tomatoes to build a final minute field with objects looking for , as I hope it is to the general plan for every name of tomorrow.
Can you concrete is that either an innocent military technology , technology , space for civilian technology , space where that can make a difference ?
Let's say.
You are a civilian .
What is decreased for the moment , and you , you , you have a well ahead that maybe you , your company built has been in the ground in half fifty years old , and you don't aware of this , you know , then a field , maybe , you know , if you've got that far , you get a map somewhere .
You say , okay , that the well had I needed to attach to you to do something is somewhere in this .
This , this handwritten field , as a very common scenario , I am a pipeline could be pipeline , something like this .
Yeah , okay , I want to go find and have been covered with a long ago .
Now you have this unfortunate prompt , just like the person trying to find the hearing on the , on the beach , you have to get take a mangoes on the do you can try to find the involved .
ironic .
Pipe says , as a nice management field .
But if the systematically , you know , a few inches over the ground may be surveyed the entire field , trying to find that welfare , but we've quarrel .
Imagine how to do that if you are just in range .
And so instead of pandas surveyed the whole field systematically and do a big analysis on the whole , management should take days , if not longer to find .
Now you go out to the field of your kind of clothes if you measure your imaginative field , and it tells you there it is , and you go there find it .
Now you're done .
Could you actually put them on a drawing that actually is a good question ?
That's exactly how they actually do it .
They had dropped megacities from drones and do the surveying that way .
But it does very long time .
Nor did you do that.
John , in an email exchange , you wrote something that really intrigued me , here's what you wrote .
I like to make the point that quantum sensors can observe electric , magnetic and inertial forces , or gravitation more accurately than anything else , at least in in laboratory laboratory skills .
And then you said , when you really think about this in compasses , every part of our world , because all about human experience is governed by these forces .
That's amazing to me .
I love thinking about new circumstances .
This way gives me some sense of why we go about it , but we've also been measuring electrical , magnetic inertial forces without some of the sensors you have in mind .
So what are we gained by building one term sensor is like the ones who are pursuing.
It's all about noising .
Sensitivity may be an accuracy .
You know , the original sort of sensors or devices or mechanical clocks , are just sort of a special cases where it is sort of the oldest right at pendulum clock .
You see that on the wall , and you know , kind of that number of accuracy is more of a display piece .
Why is that all we replaced that mechanical device with an electrical one and logical component ?
Where is that ?
All , of course , will be a hospital in your rest watching , that's , let's wait better from an across point of view .
And this is influenced true for , for , like , save a manufacturer , you can make a management with a permanent management on , like some kind attention , right and make an mechanical sort of negative , like a campus actual issue that says the first accomplishes the manufacturers of mechanical one .
So that's all .
That's great , but going to our logical systems .
And finally , now to a quantum systems is really just about improving the accuracy and sensitivity of these kinds of so the wise , that , well as it's simply because that in the quantum world noise and it sort of errors are just the physical properties are driving .
Those sorts of mechanisms are just a lot .
So the and their noise properties are unable to to making the best advice , as we know how to make .
So it in every field .
Luca said , a luxury gravity of magnetic .
We don't get a quantum of nuclear force measurement system yet , but I imagine what could make one in the future .
But the royal economic analysis , because of this inherent accuracy that based on this industrial alone so long , maybe a story that trying to figure out why exactly that is .
But that's the fundamental reason is that the quantum devices , the noise properties that.
Logical organic ones .
So you can reiterating something , but feel free to elaborate us , free flame .
And again , what's so exciting to me about , that is one of the , the new technological opportunities that these kinds of sensing devices would allow , but it also the takes away our otherwise might be a blindness to certain kinds of phenomenon that are out there , but we don't see them because we don't have the essentials that are good enough to detect.
That's right .
I mean , if you , you know , take a little volume in space in your house , or you know , some world , anywhere else in the universe , the fundamental forces are playing a little violent .
Meanwhile , there are what it feels there , the magnetic fields there , there is gravity .
There are four times moving through that space that in a result or radio waves .
It's all there , and our eyes are just special versions that are eyeballs of biological sensor measuring article fields to watch the special case and watching the field in a animals have named towners .
Don't introduce them to take a navigate around the world that takes one time to figure out that even as possible .
But this fundamental forces govern everything so for us to build a peer behind the current and satisfactory to see more and more of what's everywhere around us and understand that bill reproduce that we can all agree or were saying .
That is , I think the ultimate sort of ability to see the.
Well , that was great , fascinating way to think about you to move in the state of the art of sensor .
So thanks for sharing out that now we are running at times .
I wanna ask you one of the question , which is , what question do you wish ?
I had asked that I did not ask in a very such a question .
You should ask it.
I have a question horizon , you know , the question is , why would climb devices be more accurate , and I say , accurate , because sensitivity in being out of the world that really a different question from knowing what you're seeing is truly what the world is gift showing you like that .
We can agree on the same thing .
And that to me , as I should even more powerful still , it's easy to maybe imagine making more sense of devices like you see more signal .
I'll have less noise , but for you .
And I did not agree with that .
I have to do anything in advance that our devices see the same thing means that we can also build upon our mutual measurements and collaborate more easily .
And that's really powerful to have , you know , accurate measurements of the world around us that we can all agree on .
And so quantum devices are especially good if that there are more sensitive tools and that's useful , and whether also more accurate in the reason is because most of these things are based on adults , not all but those in every adam , exactly exactly the same .
try .
You can't manufacturer something to be exactly the same about how hard you drive is always manufacturing train challenges .
These lines were using items , every single items , exactly the same issues has some hydrogen , and attack is the exact same hydrogen that I had in my tech .
And so we can , it means for growing upon our measurements.
It sort of like the ultimate reference by which we can all agree on what we're seeing , and what maybe the numbers from our instruments are telling us .
May you succeed it .
All of these , these efforts adopt , and then beyond that .
So I just want to thank you john , this time with me.
Well , there was a lot of fun .
I hope it turns into something that people really can be kind of learn from it and see a little bit more about doing.
Thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from darker thanks also to bend , celebrate in town shortage for their partnership in producing this program .