Step of technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand are tonight .
Technology is a driver of our times .
Since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from drug a window onto the top is cool of program managers , their job to redefine what possible .
My name is ivan , a motel , and on your dark host today , I am pleased to be talking with us .
Air force lottery cannon children , david lewis , a program manager in the agencies , defense sciences office , just not before we proceed , we are recording our conversations from our respective homes as we do our parts to slow the spread of coffee nineteenth , because we are not in a recording studio .
You might hear ambient sounds like trucks , birds , and at this time of the summer .
Even secretary .
So let me say a few things about david before we talk about programs , and let's just say the david , as is more casual in home , has been immersed in the heart sciences for quite a while after collecting bachelor's degrees in both physics and chemistry here and the physics in twenty eleven from the air force institute of technology , which is located at the right pattern air force base near data , no higher at the institute .
David was an assistant professor of physics where he taught coal graduate , physical and helped usher and mentor more than sixty officers in civilians through graduation prior to coming to their , but they would also took on assignments with the joint special operations command , the defense threat dictionary agency in the air force research laboratories , sensors directorate , instead of a fascination in applying quantum mechanics , the physics of the space environment , plasmas and gravitational physics in unique ways to take on duty changes .
Lu tennis kernel , lewis , david , thanks for joining me in this conversation .
Glad to be here again .
Thanks for having me .
You have a portfolio , five programs to meet astonishing all of the way from the deep math underlying optimization challenges , such as road planning and allocation of resources to finding ways of using untapped signals in the atmosphere as indicators of natural and human activities on the planets surface .
And we're gonna dive into those in just a minute first , though , because I like to think of this part case is potentially inspiration of young people considering stamp careers that is careers in and technology , engineering and math .
I usually ask my conversation partners to get a bit out of biographical first .
So let's do that .
And you were an ambitious undergraduate for one earning group of in both chemistry and physics .
Are you going to chemistry degree myself and italia , that was enough of a challenge for me .
So when I think of you take taken on both chemistry and physics , once I know you were committed and very busy .
So what were the influences in your life that instead you with an interesting science that was so strong that you collected those two degrees as an undergraduate , went on to become a car carrying PHDand physics , and and beyond that , it brought on an entire career in science .
And now.
然后就代表我们，i think that the two major influences in my life were probably one starts at the next generation , number two natural philosophy .
You know , the show that I watched all the time of my father will start at the next generation , and I added that they are joining the forward to their chief engineer .
And zhang looked at the cabinet , the enterprise where my two favorite characters .
And so you know what those type of of shows are , including a science fiction reading .
It really gives an area for us to sort of explore humanity and what it might look like in the future .
And of course , I was always obsessed with the , with the technology , right , you know , how is it possibly go faster than the speed of late in the released , in theory , for this TVshow , when I just all the physics that's incorporated into that show , I think the other big influence in my life has been .
Philosophy is so i've been interested in philosophy , you know , before I knew a philosophy was right in our justice , the young child to ask those questions why and how , when I always just thought I used to look up at the sky when I was the bus stop , when I was really anger , kept woken up .
So we know whether the solar system , then also an effectiveness of the large scale structure , the universe , and it's going to have an essential liberty for trying to understand the natural world , and it is made sense to me that I had to keep going with physics , palestinian chemistry and all the wonderful science is out there to be export.
I know I love those influences , and you know , one being science fiction .
I too , have just loved the entire set of thorough series .
Jordan is an interesting character to me too , because you mean he was sort of a champion in a way at an illustration of optical physics .
You know , when you think of the flies or he had so the hero , instead of just seeing a little rainbow of visible like that , we see , right .
My understanding is right of what that technology was supposed to be able to get gave invasion all the way through the entire electoral magnetic spectrum .
So , and then , just , you know , your boy , who , you know , wonder , just looking up at the stars and allowing yourself just to be so instead , by the mystery and wonderful that , so that's kind of , in some ways , the , the origins of some of your intellectual interests , but you also , one of the few program managers are dark at any particular time , and who goes to work in a military uniform .
So tell me briefly about how you entered into military servicemen and made it clear about.
I know when you younger life is pretty simple .
So going from high school to to undergraduate , the plane was simple , and I was going to join the air force , become a pilot , five hundred and two , and I was going to test pilots go , and then I was going to be an action up so I could be in space , just like starting at the next generation .
But my fresh mania of undergraduate september eleven has happened .
And you know , that variously changed the scope of our nation and where our resources went .
And so , you know , one of the things that sort of alcohol consequence of that is that our space program was no longer a higher priority .
Is it was , of course , because we were involved with everything that happened after september eleventh .
And so that being the case , my sort of sense of duty still to go over , and even though it's naturally join the military for if you will selfish reasons .
I thought it was a good path to be an asian september eleven completely changed my outlook .
And so I have in a cap with the military ever since , and I actually did get my pilots .
And I started undergraduate palestinian UPUT, but in the most I had to , as I called it kill a childhood dream , you know , and working at what fires do and also knowing sort of my own skills .
QIC, when I can do in scientific technology , I told myself , know what if it is probably better , you can do more for the service by being a physicist and developing the next generation of tools , techniques , capabilities , then you can be in a pilot .
Clearly nothing against pilots .
I think they are on the greatest occupations in the world , and I still look in afternoon and two , and after the fires and said in myself , man , I could have been me , but at the same same time , kind of like a third man with grip .
Hair comes great responsibility .
Dessert of being software of my skills , and I told myself , it's probably best that you go be a physicist in the military , and you can probably do more good .
And ever since i've stuck with being in the military at three seconds then.
And thanks for sharing that it always fascinates me to hear those kind of transformed of moments at which someone's life really kind of takes on a different trajectory .
So one more question before we start talking about your programs , I am always interested in .
How did you get to dark story ?
I'd like to hear yours , but.
How I get to double , I will call that work , and bad luck .
I mean , the definition of luck , where preparation with the opportunity , just a quick bit of background .
So when I was going through my PHDprogram , I was supposed to immediately become a professor arrangements , but afterwards , but the air force said , nokia have to do was called intervening operations tour to sort of payback for the education .
We know the time was a lot of the opposite , because I really want to be a professor immediately .
But however , I want to defend threat reduction agency .
Let's write it a whole lot of offensive corner WMDadvanced development , weapons of mass description .
And so it was through the work that I did .
There were a double PMtook notice of it and actually came down to understand the research that I was doing , and that my office was doing that actually invited me up to starbucks for about a month that hope this PM worked on a new start program concept , and I was absolutely enthralled , right , because in a barber has always been a one of my dream , but not sort of .
It always has been one of my dream jobs , so you know , I think I was a cabin at the time .
So , of course , i'm super excited .
I'm going to divert .
I'm helping them all .
This is fantastic in the month past .
And what about natural men ?
And once I finished our deadline assignment , I was then able to go ahead and go back to air force sensitive technology to the , and it was the sort of one on one of those days .
I know , I believe it was at the beginning of two thousand and seventeen , as at my desk , and I got a phone call from this PM , who became an office director .
So hey , how things have been gone ?
I remember working with you .
And would you like to come bring an interview to to be APMand it.
Who was the scheme with it was a technique .
It , an interesting point there .
And I went to the finish to , how did I get to dark a story ?
Taylor required was my first conversion .
He was PMthat I featured in my very first Voices from our proposal .
I was like to find it for him .
So there were even a more of a funders.
So yeah , that was .
So it was , it was kind of shocking to me , because I , at least in my world , that is the equivalent form .
Call of saying , hey , congratulations , you're an astronaut .
And I put on my best military bearing and said yesterday to come from an interview .
What needs to happen , and I remember getting off the phone and going to talk to then adviser .
But now colleague that after day with weeks , I wanted my phd under , I went to his office , told him what happened , and my hands at the level when I said to myself , what if they do not accept me ?
And he says , well , you have the chance of the opportunity go for .
And then I said , what if they do , accept me ?
Hey , and gonna , be APMAdark owners .
Can I be the slope of responsibility so that that's going to help it , and I bring up the lock , the preparation plus opportunity pieces that said , beginning , there's a phrase that we use in the air force all the time , and that is a bloom where you are planted , meaning , of course , being in the military , we don't get to choose where we live all the time .
We don't necessarily get the truth with assignments .
We too , and so that the phrases to say that , no matter where you are , do the best that you can do , because it's going to help out the country , and you always have to be prepared for when opportunity knocks , excellent opportunity , and my opinion shows up at everyone .
store .
Question is , what are you going to prepare for the opportunity when it , it took a lot of preparation ?
Pretty much I think of my entire air force career up until that point to be ready for this opportunity .
And it worked out last.
Now that we have some idea regarding , from once you have come a day , but let's take a tour of where you are now .
And that means let's talk about your dark programs , and let's start with two of them that , to me , share several thematic threads .
And these include sophisticated mathematics , computation and making sense of things in the midst of changing , uncertain and incomplete information .
So one of the programs referring to goes by the name backgrounds , which I think , is not for the eighteen century mathematician joseph lewis playground , and the other goes by the name virtual intelligence process to talk me about those things.
All of these programs are a mathematics programs , and I see said in the midst of changing , uncertain and incomplete information .
So we'll start off with the ground , which is a program all about optimization .
So optimization is everywhere , but the type of optimization were talking about here .
I will put in the difficult arena of trying to solve .
This is not your typical in or take the function .
I said , the reality of equal type of optimization .
This is optimization , where the model changes over the time , but the constraints change over time .
And you get an information that is dreaming , and the sort of the traditional MPhard problem , if you will , an optimization as the traveling sales person problem .
And let's see now , you have a number of locations that you would like to visit that are connected in certain ways , and you want to visit each location and the shortest path possible that actually is an extremely hard problem to do .
And so what the laboratory program looked at was , instead of looking at it from your traditional outbreak point of it , really looked at it from a geometric and top electrical point of view to see we can bring in those tools for most areas of mathematics , and these optimization problems also , wanna say , as well as the , you know , the problem of optimism is probably the problem .
And the department of defence rate , because we want to always optimize for most performance , lowest costs , make sure that we apply our resources correctly , and we don't waste any .
And so some of the interesting things that have come out of grass , what branches has ended , but we're moving until the transition period .
We're getting .
Some of these technologies are into the worldwide .
But I think one of the , the news thinks it came out of algorithms program , according to highlight , is a night to the traveling sales problem called the travelling physicist problem .
So one of our performers , inspired by what NASA had done bargainer the space race .
So when you are trying to , for example , get satellite out to other planets so that you can study those planet if you take your typical travelling sales person , thought brain work to that , then you try to go from planet to planet in a straight line for a lack of better term .
But that doesn't work so well when you have gravitation of potential , because it would cost a lot of energy to go from point to point .
So what else I did at the time instead , was well thinking about orbital transfer manufacturers and orbitals link shots that , you know , have a longer path and figure to the next planet .
I would never try to study , but it cost less energy to do .
And so our performer was inspired by that and applied this type of thinking to an orange tearing problem .
So an orange orange problem is , for example , where you have a platform that's trying .
Uh , ISRintelligence , advanced recognition and has multiple objectives , rather than taking a picture or scanning a certain area , or just being trained on a particular area for a certain amount , you have to combine that with the constraints of the actual platform itself in a platform , being a airplane or a satellite sooner software .
So this is one of those optimization problems , and they are able to reformulate this problem using the language of function , which is sensitively sort of lives in a dollar space of your typical lecture spaces , and was actually able to piece together using some geometric and top logical wait , not just optimized for distance , but optimize for other things that might be of use .
I already discussed a little bit about less energy , but now you can start to bring in sort of those human defined type of musician ideas , like the number of collections you want to take , or the order .
I want to take those collections .
You can start up the machine over time .
Saturday doesn't really , really cool .
Highlight the came out there to A.
Interesting is , okay when i'm hearing is like going at the fundamental mathematical foundations and and really the basics of models that you have to come up with tools and frameworks that then can be applied in many ways to many different kinds of optimization tasks.
Absolutely , and so I thought of trying to explore , sorry , no word else .
Can we use this framework , this methodology , as we are looking at things like rejected redesign is another problem that could be method onto the mathematics are coming out of this particular problem.
So now maybe you can talk me a little bit about the others are a very mathematic heavy program , virtual intelligence.
Yes , the VIP is a fantastic program .
It was conceived and started by michael ali , who has now moved on to the analysis .
But is the idea here for the VIP program is to be inspired by how the rain works and try and manifest that enter new mathematics .
And we were looking to apply all this course .
Is starbucks push for third wave artificial intelligence ?
That's artificial intelligence that is contemporary , aware that is a partner with us .
We know , versus the second way , watches more big data and statistical influences .
So one of the need things about the VIP program is not only looking at new mathematics , but we are also looking at what we call non violent movement computing architectures .
So these are hardware architecture that mimic the way the brain processes .
So we're talking about various types of networks and hardware .
We are also talking about combining computing and memory and one .
And what we call men computing .
And so I think one of the highlights that I like to tell one of the mathematical tools that were using and try to employment here is this idea of using what we call high dimensional factors .
One of the next thing she can do with these very large factors is that if you can find a way to take dance information , say images that you might want to classify and be able to sparse a further information action to these factors .
Others are unique mathematical property and which all these factors are what's called quiz or thug in all .
So there are different , but almost the same in certain areas , and what you can do is you factor those very quickly ?
So what that allows us than to do is to process dance information very quickly , and people to learn on that information very quickly , and it's all been inspired about thinking of , how can we map are a lot of mathematics to the way that the brain processes and functions cause our brains are very good classifying things .
So it is blue at the dog that the cat that threatens not a threat , right ?
We do that very quickly .
So how do we get our machines , if you will our processing to do that , we know hands moving to technologies to get us to the third way of.
Okay , then before we move on , wearing a lifecycle of a program is virtual or just processing.
So it's a slightly month program .
We're finishing up the first year here , and we're right now making decisions to see .
But who is moving on to too .
So we hope that the outcomes of this VIP program for lead and to figure darker programs are surrounding things like unconventional computing.
Now we want to move on to another paragraph programs that also seem to share a thematic threat .
But in this case , the challenge of knowing what is going on , invest volumes of space or monitoring characteristics of those uniquely revealing .
In this case , i'm talking about one of your programs called space environment exploitation , the sea program , and that's reaching tortured capability , accurately forecasting space weather and conditions and ethnically connected to to another program atmosphere as a sensor , or at most sense , that investigating how events on the surface of the earth leave detectable impressions in the vast admit spiritual gray , which thereby conserved , perhaps as a sensor for those earthbound .
If that so talked to me about each of those.
Yeah , so we , we go from the mathematics .
So that is a large scale , at least large scale in terms of our own environment .
right ?
So the space involvement , exploitation has A, Ithink that a fairly fun background .
I said , when I was at an athlete , I just got back from a nine months appointment was the joint special operations command , and as I was getting back , the swing of things be a professor agenda to continue being professional , my , my colleague and my good friends at ten o'clock on an hour walking to my office one day .
And I don't know , just for a few months at the point and asked your question if you take one electron and you inserted into the earth ionosphere , which consists of a bath of electrons , a sea of electrons .
If you will , I , as can you predict how the honest fear is going to respond ?
So I looked at him .
He looked at me .
I looked at him again , and I started laughing .
So anyone who has been through the throws of a statistical mechanics course , or a thermodynamics course .
Just you , you laugh at the almost intractability of that problem on the microscope because they would take a computer , you know , at least half the age of an university to answer that question .
So I started digging a little bit more to what he was asking to understand what the operation we happened to be talking about the second part when we were a bar and did no higher .
So sort of that year , you'll typical in a year at a conference , so you write on the back of an action type of thing .
I started some of the things that I saw during the appointment with what he was looking at and trying to help out some more fires and bring our capability .
So in the end , as we want to go , visit the UK, want to go , visit japan and see what their capabilities were .
Of course , we , we talk to all the relevant organizations within the united .
I started thinking to myself that I don't think we have the right set of capabilities to bring the prediction of the near of space , environmental relevance model being my relevant , that a decision maker , like when we're deployed , would actually take that information into account when I make a decision to assign some degradation of keep bodies , if you will , when we're deployed , that I think I was that , you know , there must be something going on in the space environment , because everything else seems perfect , but we use comes all the time , and those comes you link to a satellite .
So you know , if I could give a prediction to say , you know , this is what the space environments can be doing to us today .
That will be fantastic for the war fighter .
That's all the sea program sort of came to be .
And it was towards the end of that exploration , right at the phone call from DARPA .
And I said , hey , let me tell you what hard problem work on right now .
So that became the sea program .
I am , we're looking to do with this program is we're looking to be able to to predict that near a space environment of the specificity and occasions that's useful for the war fighter .
So if you look at the matrix for the program that I put out as a challenge to the community that challenges to be able to predict every hour on the hour for seven years , what that space environment is going to be like uh over particular area of responsibility .
So , as I saw at the time , there is an opportunity to sort of start over again , right ?
So let's take everything that we , as this community knows .
Her put together worth with current model simulation and delivers simulation .
So let's take all the lessons learned .
Let's start over .
We do the physics representations .
And now what supply things like executive computing , GPU s and TPU , lots of child machine learning techniques , because I think we have a chance to bring this type of prediction to relevance .
And so that were pushing for right now.
One quick question on that , because we , we have had a capability of predicting , forecasting space weather for a while , for a very example of this is a solar flare .
We have some idea what that , what that can mean for the earth environment when that will happen .
Sounds to me like what you're getting out here .
There was a kind of granted of that forecast that we've never heard it .
Someone's like going to the no weather forecast inside and putting music code in the same when he was , what was the weather going on for , here is that kind of idea?
Yeah , that's not a bad way to look at it .
You know , it's one thing to to predict solid players , and all that .
That's important .
But when you look through the literature , and you talk to scientists and engineers , part of the variability from me that we see in the atmosphere actually comes from below .
So let's sort of the neutral atmosphere pushing on and protecting the atmosphere , and in terms of being an operational tool , bringing operation relevance , you know that the commander on the ground and now in space doesn't really , you know , care if you will , if there is a software for our coming , I mean , they do .
But when we look at the kittens , we conduct operations on in a way through sorts , every hour of the power .
So we need that green , you already , as you talked about to understand , I think even more so to maybe exploit certain situations .
You know , one of the things that were taught as officers going through our military education is that you want to be able to understand the environment that you are operating on or with them , so that you can take advantage of it , and or to take advantage of that , be able to predict it and a particular degrees .
Magic and use that information.
So david , you just spoke about the space environment exploitation program .
And now I like you to talk about atmosphere is a sensor or atmospheric program.
Yeah , so that the amazon program is really fun program , the genesis of this program , of course , did come a little bit from a space environment exploitation .
But I think I am also , what sort of my microbiologist wonderment of what we could do , different one trend that we see both the and commercial world is the evolution and building of the slow earth orbit , satellite clusters .
We know , make them distributed , make them your best so that we can better communicate .
We can better do ISR, so and so forth .
I'm so in my head , and I am thinking that is a great idea , but that's going to be a lot of cost , a lot of energy that you have to out there to put into orders , right ?
It's the oscar rotation of potential of the whole schedule .
So I said , what , how else could we maybe think about looking at conducting similar missions , today's layer clusters , or really , I think , more importantly , how can we bolster ?
How can we support those missions ?
So I sit around one day and I said , well , what are the open orbit while the atmospheres are the open orbit .
But when you start looking through the literature , the atmosphere really access an information , results of war , so things like earthquakes and tsunami they push around , or they move the neutral atmosphere , and the mutual atmosphere responds in a way that you think it worked from classical mechanics .
You get AArebounding for a safety ruler , harmonic type revision , and this energy then gets transported through the atmosphere all the way up with the atmosphere .
So we're talking to your column to holding up to a hundred kilometers sweep , and we could attack this if you look at the measurement for GPS.
So from a global positioning system , tolerate on content measures , so the GPS cannot have two different faces available for us to look at .
And since that electronic energy is propagating through AAcharge atmosphere , meaning the honest fear , my different frequencies , you can see different faiths , and so you can back up with those faithfully honest here .
Wave was bouncing packaging fourth , and so those can be correlated to earthquakes and tsunamis .
And so in my head as well , this is a , this is a huge sensor , right .
And so it started then to get me to think about what's the smallest detectable disturbance you might be able to pick up not too different than oats moving an ocean .
Anyone who has ever been selling knows that awake book makes if the speed boat versus a big tankers different , right .
And so I started thinking along those lines , and then , once again , doubt on a literature , and it leads to me and the arguments that made is , there's a lot more basic science that we need to understand about energy propagation in the atmosphere .
So this release is our basic science program to better get a handle of how the whole atmosphere responds that the troops fear , the strategic fear , the mother's fear and ionosphere how energy propagate through the whole atmosphere , because the atmosphere does change , rate .
It changes the density of changes that constituency .
And so reactivity .
And I think that there are six dollars in the atmosphere that we might be able to learn , understand and then try and back out what polluted it so on this way , I think of the atmosphere is a big information .
Reservoir is just right for exploitation .
I love how big.
Thinking this is really a sort of .
Just think about the entire gear system , the entire kind of planet dairy system as having sensory capabilities that we might build .
Who are tapping to when and the certain things that we otherwise might not .
So I love to watch out the program .
Emma , since unfolds as you continue to oversee it , one program of this program is that worker is not going to talk about .
It goes by the short name that stands for quest for undiscovered energy storage and thrust .
And the reason we are not going to talk about it is because I know you can hear that from my city , who I was a program manager in d so , and just recently left , and he was also with me on a package , and we spoke about quests there .
So i'll just direct listeners to the mike fitty podcast to learn about that program .
But it is fascinated , saw that china , you know , apply pretty sophisticated and abstract quantum mechanical ideas and phenomenon to potentially use space itself as as a means of generating thrust in proportion without maybe the need for traditional kinds of fuels .
And , you know , in the sense , taking energy at the vacuum itself , and so I just could not be more interesting .
And so it's , and we must be fun for you to take it up.
Oh , I love it .
I love it so much .
I mean , I really thanked my favorite food that together , I was always with them for a little bit in about some ideas with music formulating it .
So happy to to be able to take that over , but it does not start tracking .
I don't know what it.
That's right , it really happened .
It does not go back to that original inspiration for you .
So now , as we do so to approach the end of our conversation , there is an opportunity I want to take , and I want to squander .
And another I have you talking with me , but also at a time when we're on a society skills , sort of critical look at ourselves regarding systemic ratio and in justice in our history , but also in these current times .
So the under representation , northeastern fields in our science , technology , engineering and mathematics , and that's long been known .
And this shortfall is also apparent when you going to institutions in places like double , we actually have been , I am not beneficial .
Yeah , cell for quite a lot of the pandemic .
But here you are going to do , you know , black scientists of physics professor or technology developer , now it are a program manager .
Just wondering what you can share with us about your experience of being a black person managed to navigate so successfully through the sustainable obstacles and racism that you surely have.
Yeah , so I think this is an important discussion to have , because there are so many different settings that's surrounding this conversation .
So I think I like to sort of start to answer this space , putting up the difference between individual racism and , of course , systematic racism .
I think one of the things that I has been difficult for others to have this conversation with me is the fact that sometimes users , and example to say that racism has disappeared .
You know , people are david , you know , you have APHDERand the air force , like , we really mean those races are still on the world that we could all that you achieved .
On the one hand , I, Ido agree with them was , in fact , that as far as individual racism goes , I can only probably recount , maybe two situations in my whole life .
We're slurs were thrown on my way , or I was denied something because of the color of my skin .
I think the I know it is in my , my world .
The individual racism hasn't a big deal , but what I think has been a really big deal is the systematic racism that exist rounders .
And so I think i'll account myself fortunate , and I think this is probably also serves a template to how our country is .
And she needs to be moved forward .
But when I look back at my life , I have essentially been protected from systematic racism by what are called intersection , airline ship .
So those people are , of course , what the colors who are , who are stewards were allies to protect me from the systematic racism .
And looking back , this is kind of happened .
I almost argued before I was born first out of data to point out my grandparents , who taught my father that you have to be the smartest in the room .
You have to be the best in the room , and you cannot make any mistakes because of you leave one person back in the armor , they'll focus on the fact that you're black .
So you know , my grandparents , in order the right and the sake of all the sovereign's movements that happened in order markets ago .
And so they pass the spots that learning on how to behave even as well to my dad .
And he passed it down to me , I think another example would like to bring up forever , you know , being protected by systematic racism , and ah was actually my father's first boss .
So my father's advertise power engineer , logical engineer , and he told me a story when he got his first race , his boss would give it to my dad's , like when she gave me my raise .
And so my first boss was like already gonna do with this money , and my father really had no answer at the time , right .
And so it was my desk for his boss who said , you know , come back to me .
What's an idea what you can do with this extra money , and then , so you know , let have to point out this first boss , my father's husband and I called my , my , my granddad , because he thought I told my father , at least at the time , song basics about financing and investing , song and so forth .
That was not talk about my grandparents .
They were talk to my grandparents , play their parents who were not talked to because they know they are busy with the sovereign movement .
And so I think that said , it is my dad on a path .
This was what it takes in this information that isn't where I was introduced to people of color .
I think another story that I like to bring up a second of three that I can protect it from sort of systematic racism was with my six grade teacher , you know , and six grade , I thought I had this .
I don't know reputations to the right word , but refugee always thought that was bored in class .
Great cause .
Get the homework assignments .
I do that .
My tunnel man , read all the books sector , and I just kind of bought and moving from sixty seventh grade .
I was going to go into the local high school rape , but my sister teacher actually called my father , and I once again knew his white male and said , I don't think your son should go to the local high school school or the district high school .
And my dad was kind of like , what do you mean like , where should we go there ?
And it was like , I think your son is fairly gifted , and it would be better for him to go to AAprivate , high school so that , you know , and i'll be real so that he doesn't get caught up and sort of the social desperately get caught up in your activities .
That , yeah , they are , you know that I look great upon .
And so my sister , teacher actually helped me get into that school .
and.
Find ways to pay for it .
That's fascinating .
So in a way , without maybe knowing it or having words for recognizing her , the systemic racism in the education system .
And I am happy here that he took a step to try , at least in your case , in the individual case , help you bypass that systemic episode .
yeah.
Yeah , I know it is .
Yes , it is one of the things that you don't realize into to your order .
Much older , right ?
And so I think the , the last thing that I think we're thinking , protected by systemic racism is I have involved , especially in the world college , but more so in a big my fifty years there , I have always tried as best I can to seek out working for women bosses .
And i've done that .
What's the idea that you know what we're talking about right now ?
Races on colorado skin sold in south australia , but these are intersection issues that also cross as well .
You know , we should just all call them human rights issues .
But what I have found with working with women .
Actually , the majority of my boss is healthy , and women , about half of them as a scientist .
So glad that had the other half in .
But you know , women face the same type of issues as well .
And what are they breaking to the glass ceiling , right ?
And so I always found myself that when I work for people who have also become their obstacles , who've broke these glass ceilings that I am more protected from those systematic issues and allowed to .
And so I think my navigation through a workout , this racial atmosphere has been enough .
I'm just so thankful , really , it takes a whole pound .
It takes a whole village to raise .
I've been the , you know , on the advantages end of that , and I also would like to point out that it is comforting , and it was a privilege to serve in the military , within the military .
It is absolutely illegal to discriminate .
I can start protective categories , raise being one of them .
So I have , in the case of the military , not saying that they're perfect , because we're still working on our , our systematic issues , but it's comforting to know that if something happens , I can go to the equal opportunity and file a claim felt like the better term .
And so I think that's a nice safeguard to know that I actually have a legal officer if they could help rule this out .
Yeah , I consider myself thankful i've been the on the advantages and a lot of interested in our allies shape , and I think that's really , really , really four need to go after this country .
So you know , justice is , it has been the benefit of it .
You know , it's my turn to give back .
And so let's wear also for opportunities to mentor , also for opportunities to teach , so on and so forth .
Because let's go to the strength of america .
I think over military is.
Well , not our diversity , just before we leave this subject , which cannot be left and will take years in years , truly work out in good ways .
Let's stand back a bit of , you know , to sort of the technology development context , and , of course , darker is in there .
And just went , you know , if you got some ideas of what will take to close the racial guys , bring more equitable opportunity , not only in a sort of on the same education side of things , but beyond that , into all of the ranks of your program manager there , there is also office directors is all the way to the director of an agency like dark , and it's not just dark , but let's think of the entire in the infrastructure of the country .
What do you think it will take to have equal opportunity and representation through all of those things?
Yeah , that's , that's a difficult one to answer .
On the one hand , you just have to sort of keep pushing , keep fighting against the momentum that was initially established .
I think that education is the great equalizer and terms of my definition of lock rate , preparation plus opportunity .
I think that the stamp issue that were talking about now speaks more than preparation , said , and that is continuing to try and make education less expensive is possible to make education more throw .
I think one thing that this in occur and democracy highlighting is that we need to figure out how to conduct education , virtual means .
And I think we will figure it out , and I think that's going to be another technology and the framework that allow the field , because now you are , the code , does it dictate whatever education you have access to , if it can be done virtually , I think the other part of that announced the opportunity .
I think we just have to continue pushing with our making .
All people of color understand these opportunities are available to them and try and show them release , explain to them in what type of preparation and you need to engage .
And so when the opportunities do come , but you can take hold of them , the opportunities are there .
I actually believe the opportunities and everywhere .
But she had to be prepared to take them .
I think , finally , all evening goes for us .
Get back to days .
The okay .
And in fact , then it was nationally , it was national pride to say , i'm going to go work from asia .
I mean , to go to develop this technology , I mean , because it's going to put our country heads and tails above our evil series of the time , right ?
And so we've got to find a way to get back to a cool idea with , with the , what can you do for your country when you know , the second quarrel back at the air force trade service before yourself ?
So I think that there's a lot of society we need to push back towards the really good america at the world where we are .
And we were going to go .
I still have a lot of hope and confidence in america , where innovators and we actually quite a good friend who.
David was really a bleeding to hear that positive consequences that could come out of our covered nineteen experience and referring to the sense that as we're learning online education , in fact , having to move in that direction , that that could have fascinating consequences of the couple .
In a sense , education from location and potentially having a positive effect in providing more education opportunity in a more egalitarian way .
So we'll see out that unfold .
And I think it is going to take some real attention already on the the part of some people care about this to make that happen , but it ability to meet you hear about the possibility .
So one more question before I let you go .
And it is , this , is there anything that did not come up during the conversation that you think would be important or interesting for our listeners know about?
You know , right now , we're going through in a sort of , and so many lifetime situation with this pandemic , I think one thing that I like to leave our listeners with .
I just think about the opportunity we have the country .
And as the end of vegetables , tit to seize this tough time and making an opportunity out of it to think about what is the future look like .
Where do we want the future to go ?
Okay , it seems like we say in the upper , sometimes , if you want to bring the future , just create yourself , right .
But I think we have an opportunity here to release what a change length .
I thought we do things and variably .
This is going to change .
Our economy is probably going to change aspects of our governance structure .
You know , not saying that we're not going to be capitalists were not going to be democratic .
We're gonna evolve , and it's gonna .
Be interesting to see we'll evolve towards .
And so I think it's important to further for right now to think about what they want the future.
In the beginning of these packages , I save in what do program managers do and the platform that I would say at the beginning , every parker is to read fine was possible , and it shouldn't sound like that's what you're doing as a doctor .
May you be successful in all of your endeavors , your dark .
I just want to say thoroughly , enjoy the conversation and thank you for sharing this time.
That sounds great to talk with you , and thank you once again very much.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dark thanks also to bend , celebrate for his partnership in producing this program .
For more information about returned kernel , david lewis , the programs he runs in the agencies , defence sciences of this and the other breakthrough technologies .