Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight with operation .
Technology is a driver of our times .
Since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defense advanced research has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan , a motto in your dark host today , and please to be with doctor mark , robot , a program manager in the defence sciences of since twenty nine team mark .
And I are recording our conversation from our respective homes as we do our part to slow the spread of coffee nineteenth .
This is also why you might hear some ambient sounds like birds , simply even thunder .
My heart goes out to all of those in the USand around the world .
We're in doing grievous losses , stresses and anxieties due to the bank .
Now , a little bit about mark first adelaide , he has made his primary concern to help develop technologies that can counter weapons of mass destruction , including chemical , biological , radiological and nuclear threat .
Today , we will focus on one of the programs that overseas , the sigma plus program .
We will learn how it quickly arrive as the current copyright nineteen pandemic on falls in the coming months .
And as we learn how to manage the ongoing presence of the all of this devastating new coordinate virus , proud to joining the door .
But mark was a lead program manager for the department of homeland securities , countering weapons of mass destruction office and the former domestic nuclear detection of mark , a retired USair force officer , earned a doctorate and environmental health sciences with the concentration and health physics from the university of mission .
He holds a master degree , nuclear engineering from result , your pilot technique institute , mark , thanks for joining me .
Thank you very much for having me .
I went so before we talk about this program .
I'd like to know something about the urgence of your drive to do something about weapons of mass destruction .
And what will the influence is that like you in that direction?
Well , at growing up with the early sixties and and was kind of that dark and covered error , a little bit , little bit after that , but I was certainly very much growing up during a time of these hiking concerns with respect , nuclear analysis .
And can I stop with me that and the program novel , I was kind of addicted to growing up , and I just got this passion to kind of learn about all things , nuclear .
And so subsequently , when to answer there , my new engineering degree , I had also been an artist sea at the time , and the yarn force in the , in the wisdom , decided to take my new continuing degree and put it towards health , physics community and how physics for those who may not be familiar with the profession is all about protecting people from radiation .
So I did that for twenty two years and year force , and so nuclear and religious threads with something that I , it's kind of steep down during my entire fourth career that LED me to the defensive reduction agency , when I retired from the air force , where then my research focus became , how do I develop new tools and capabilities to control the threat of nuclear terrorism ?
And that then worked it way into the palm of online security , where I focused on nuclear terrorism , and then , through evolution of that organization , we expanded our horizons to the complete coming weapons of mass destruction , threats , so that enhanced with chemical and biological threats .
So it's been kind of fine since just growing up is a little care about this description , what we can do.
So much knowledge or grown up and running the sigma plus program .
I'd like you to tell me and listeners about that program , which is the following to the sigma program , and should point out that earlier program and by former program management in the tank , was all about creating a distributed sensor network for detecting and monitoring nuclear and radiological threats in real time over large areas.
So you know , a little bit about signal plus , it is building on what was done .
So we're adding the capabilities to detect chemical threats and biological threats in a large scale region or in complex environment .
And that in the end of itself , is a significant challenge to taking radiation in urban environmentals , many different sources of the nine radiation that don't care about which we got a train or technology to ignore.
Where is even buildings right to the healthiest geological materials eliminated?
Exactly , and the patients coming out of a hospital who made it , my have had a fun of suitable treatment that had that had radio isolates associated with many different bananas sources .
So we need to have algorithms that are able to differentiate what we care about real threats , forces what we don't in read that that's very manageable .
And you think about a chemical environment , and as city , any city peaker city , there is always these constant emissions coming from businesses , coming from factories , coming from bruise , coming from research facilities , and those create the to very complex chemical background , and weren't again challenged to differentiate all of this benign background material from things that we care about .
What are we care about things that obviously can cause as harm .
Michael li , and this can be chemical offer agents or taxi conductor chemicals , but were trying in similar , plus to move detection to what we call the left boom that before , naturally , when occurs , were trying to be able to detect the threats before they actually are used to cause harm .
So in the chemical space and means trying to detect somebody perhaps cooking and a hazardous compound that could be a homemade explosive , it could be an opportunity .
It could be a natural campaign region and tried to attack the fugitive emissions that would be associated with somebody cooking one or more of these hazardous materials and detecting that in this very complex chemical background , that is what our urban environmental bright stuff .
The same problem exists in the biological front we were trying to collect large firms of air , since in that air are their passengers present in differentiate those potential passages that might be associated while terrorist attack from all the other naturally occurring stuff that in the atmosphere , this could be power , and it could be things are in the environment .
Society with all the natural biological processes go on.
The other region , so things in the environment , including source , could be to the causes of agent .
Okay with one thousand.
That's right , we are actually trying to direct .
This is what you mentioned earlier , some of our research , sea candidates actually detect south korea too , with and generating a unique signature .
Right , that's , that's the key .
We need to be able to see if these technologies can generate things that are unique to south korea tour and current viruses , perhaps more broadly , and and be of the differences that from all the other things that are in the environment.
right ?
So let me just drilling to that a little bit .
I mean , I know of the sigma program .
It delivered kind of hand , health size praps other kind of formats of the radiological sensors that could be distributed all over the place in that data converging into a cloud based and political environment .
Here , i'm wondering what is the signal that a modified or sort of enhanced instrument that also now can look at biological threats .
What is the signal that looking to detect it?
There's one technical approach .
We're doing something called romance , but cross could be where we take a sample from the air .
We eliminate it with a laser and at laser in racks with the molecules that are present in that deposit .
There's those multitudes undergo some play borrowers based on the slight stimulating at this lazy lights , stimulating again as warm and signature .
That thing is measured , and there's a characterization that's done to see .
Does this virus have unique signature in roman space in the spectrum that's been generated , and we're bringing those measurements right now to see if that's the case .
That's one technique , the other technique , that's a little bit further behind .
But we're also thinking about how it may be applied to the space is taking and then analyzing it with actual DNA sequencing .
So taking a large function , assemble , concentrating whatever erasers might be , not simple , and then having that be analysed within several hours , ideally to see , is the packaging person in a serious animal , but based on the orange signature that would be associated with the crown of virus .
What that affords is the ability to look at .
Now , the virus may evolve over time , because the original sequencing is kind of absolute detection of that passage in the environment .
And how that army may change over time.
Okay , it maybe you can talk to me and tell our listeners a little bit about what would happen if if you actually succeed in developing the technology , which I suspect you will .
How will environmental monitoring fit into the overall challenge of sort of managing a new world in which , you know , this crown of viruses is part of our reality.
IIsee crown virus has been subset of what is going to be a continual concern , and it is the threat of either pandemics , such as this .
Maybe that next crown of virus that can pop out somewhere , or the thread associate with your names .
State actual development of passengers using these new tools and capabilities associated with synthetic biology .
So the entire development is trying to do something about that to get as close as we can detect kinds of events from environmental perspective , so that public health measures can be involved .
Countermeasures can be developed as expected as possible for future threats are coming down the line.
Interesting , in your case , you , you started at the top of the program manager in twenty one thousand , nine hundred and one month mark .
When did you start ?
Was much nine months later , covered nineteen begins to take hold in and dry , or maybe even less than nine months .
And then from there goes on its tour of the world .
So does it is now , what was the luck , you know , as cobber nineteenth became a reality when WHOdeclared it a pandemic .
And we had that change the way you thought of yourself as a program moving forward with your particular programs , which we actually do not have potential relevance of.
So we were gone down the pack .
Materials technologies to address as biological space , as was the chemical threats base .
And it was the only one that really kind of came home to us that we think about .
All right , things are getting serious .
Now , what can we do to fight the ?
So we started to till , and at the same time we're trying to till and do so where it makes sense were also focused on that longer term capability .
That's gonna be needed for the next rate .
I think that's the balance that we need to strike .
Let's support where we can and where makes sense , but we have a mission to preventing strategic surprise .
Single plus , we believe , I believe it's going to help address that from potential future events that we need these capabilities to detect an article.
Mark , if we gave out sigma plus such a successful and point where we know how technology that will be able to this kind of environmental monitoring of biological threats , whether there once they emerge naturally , like these sort of analysis , types of events that spill over from animal origins to humanity , or or whether it is not serious origins .
What value is the information that you get from the environmental monitoring ?
How would the knowledge go to decision making in and taking actions?
The concepts of operations for what we're developing within six months , kind of calls for persistent monitoring capabilities .
So this would be a mobile platform s we may think about taking advantage of public transport .
We may think of taking advantage of things like first respond of vehicles that are constantly circulating through a city or region .
He put them with new sensing capabilities .
And I would just constantly be moving through that environment , sampling the year , looking for these threats or precautions to these threats .
That information would then be networked .
So we would constantly be seen what the background environment looked like .
running .
Advanced analytics are no sense of fees and fusing that data with other forms , textual information .
So in the case of both chemical and biological threats , and I may want to know what the local meteorological conditions , where they are going , where is going , I may want to look at a capture of a video associated with when I do get something anonymously .
Is there factory or building there that might be associated with what that anonymous chemical event was ?
So an example of that is , if i'm dragging around the city , and I drive past a news line , and I pick up as a town , well , that can make sense , right .
So if I know where my vehicle is my pop , a map map is providing context to what that sensor is saying , and I can do the same thing and biological space too .
So having this fuse data pulling in these other forms of contextual data and having that all be presented to say , a fusion center or a dispatched operator , somebody who is watched off a surface while who was looking at the data .
The algorithms are helping with sense , making a lot what those sensors are seeing in the environment and were able to then throw this process bill to reduce false alarms , and yet also improve a judiciary , true events and then deploying capabilities as necessary to either improve our confidence that he , this is , this is suspicious .
Let's go send another sense right there to take a second sample and see if its persistency is there , or just say it now , that was a false positive .
We can let that call being able through these advanced analytics to have a smart air jail system that is continuously learning about the environment .
Now we're talking about machine learning techniques that are learning about what's typical for environment .
What's not been able to strike these anonymously detections that could be associated with an actual threatening , detected or bad actors trying to execute , adopting the attack by sympathizing making a capability.
Quite an amazing vision there .
It makes me think about in doubling the constructed landscape with a kind of century system and nervous system and analytics system , specifically enough to certainly be able to monitor in response to rights of weapons of mass destruction , so may make you succeed , because I think a lot of us would benefit from that .
So just last you mentioned earlier that you had great admiration for DARPA before you got here .
And that just picks my interest is to , why , what is it about dark as an institution saying the innovation ecosystem that particularly caught your attention earlier , and you , and now you start bleeding it by being a program.
Dark , but those amazing things and is a federal employee , or on a twelve years , I think , now on activity service members for twenty two years , and a very few places in government .
Do you have the real capacity to make to intervene , to discover and to do amazing things ?
And daughter is one of those places , and it's literally drink control to be your program manager here , and but an awesome year .
And I am hoping for another few years of awesome this before.
I wrapped my teenager , yeah , I wish you a great luck and just having an absolute arsenic experience as a program manager .
So marketing , just personally , thank you for spending this time with me and also for doing what you can do to reduce threats posed by weapons and agents of mass destruction .
I'm awful that .
So , so I owe the power to you so much .
thanks .
Thank you .
I will spend great and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from darker , and thanks also to ban sullivan and TOM shortage for their help in producing this park test .