Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand are tonight with technology is a driver of our times .
Since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defense advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone a motto , and on your dark bowl host until I am pleased to have with me in the studio .
Miss your david gunning , who has been admitted his third tour of duty as a program manager , durban , in this case , with the information innovation office during his previous tour in the early years of the new millennium , david managed the personalized system that learns program paul that lent to the now familiar voice of syria during his first tour and nineteen nineties , he managed to variety of AIprojects artificial intelligence , including the command post of the future , which was later adopted by the USarmy as the command control system for using a regular afghanistan between his institute .
But mister gonna play the variety professional roles , among them , program director for data and lyrics and contextual intelligence at the pale .
Although research center park , a number of funding and managerial roles for test , and as a senior scientist in the air force research lab at white petterson air force base , the synthetic threat threatens career , have been artificial intelligence and human computers in bias .
It's a threat that goes back to his education .
They would hold a pair of master's degrees , one in computer size from stanford university and another and experimental psychology from the university of david gonna .
Thanks for joining me in the studio today .
Yes , glad to do so .
You're a double .
You work at the intersection of different mine sets , skill sets and tall sets .
In your case , intersection seems to focus on humankind , computer kind in the ways these two creatures can work together .
Where do those interests come from and go back as foreign , we need to learn.
Well , I can go back to the original event that started up up , spotted in nineteen fifty eight .
I was eight years old living at my grandfather's house out in the country .
And I can remember him taking me out on the yard night to see the light of the spotlight gets its flying overhead in a kind of conveying what I shocked this world .
But where were you to complete the setting and coming down and talk outside governing kentucky , and so that at the time , also , not only sparked dark , but sparked a huge interest in technology , she might as a huge interest in encouraging young minds to be interested in engineering and science .
So I can remember that is kind of the sport dark .
It started later on .
I was an album college in ohio and late sixties , early seventies , you know , during this kind of rapid change , and a lot of cultural change going on .
I became very interested in psychology .
So there was my first technical entries .
Just , how do people work , right , people , clearly , the issue in most of the problems we have the day .
How does that mind work ?
And what could we do about ?
It was was the starting point , and that I did that would get master's degree in psychology , started to work at the right patterns and air force base as a human factors engineer , which was one of the practical uses of that psychology degree .
I am , and then very quickly , the first jobs I had worked to look at the human factors of how they were introducing electronic displays into the cockpit .
This , in nineteen ninety seven days , can one of the first workplaces to be automated if you want pilots were good in the most advanced technology , they are putting electronic displays in the place of instruments .
Pilots were making submitted microsecond decision , life or decisions you want to make sure they get just the right information and just the right way , you know , to make those decisions , and so that trigger might interest in computer science because quickly became parents that all the important aspects job were in computer software .
And so that prompted my interest in computer science , then went back to school to stand for to get my masters degree in computer science , and especially in AI, that was one of the aisles , summers , if you will , there is a hole in the nineteen eighties , a lot of interest in expert systems in one of the first waves of a and so that captured my interests .
And certainly was a lined with my background in cognitive psychology.
David , as I noted in my introduction , you know , in your third tour as a program management dirt butt , and just the latter will talk about the programs you inherited in this latest tour , communicating with computers and the program that you initiated explaining AI.
But before we get to that , i'd like for you to take us on a brief of your prior two times as a program management .
So let's start with how you and double met for the very first time as APM.
Iguess this was the ninety ninety four in the information systems of us .
What is?
As they started off as a psychologist and switched the computer science in both those roles , I was a research idea for his research lives , right , patterson , so doing a lot of work at the time on the afternoon too .
That was the latest fighter aircraft of the day .
Now , those computer displays that , you know , and nineteen seventies were very advanced , and particularly then I was working on a integrated information mainland system .
So now it was possible for the maintenance technician woke up to a computer , woke up to the aircraft with a portable computer plugged in .
Download information about what files had occurred .
Did all of his tech manual instructions present on the computer , great kind of integrated in a workplace for the maintenance technician.
Do you help him do it , just a question about that , because , you know , you know , when you go into a any garage tent of your own car looked at regard , there is a system very much like that .
Yeah , it is .
But this proceeded.
Proceeded that it was actually the very first prototype of electronic maintenance instructions anywhere the service did that the that time on my program .
And so I was doing at work that gets the attention of the general who was running the afternoon two program .
He pulled me into the afternoon , too .
The kind of managing coordinate model model of his digital technology .
And what I was there , some people from doctor came to visit .
They tried to convince the skeptical of the day he should listen to double and adopt some of their new technology .
So he expressed how skeptical he wasn't photographic way .
Instead , if you're not doing something , going to have twenty two , you need to convince dave going on his , my computers that was with the steve cross , who was deputed record of one of the officers geo video hold , who was a program manager here on long from stanford university , who is doing a project and intelligent integration of the world heat systems using AI.
And so I began to interact with those guys in when jail left , died after his tour was done , then invited me to come to the door , but to be APMand nineteen ninety four , I just , I finally had.
这个是我们这边的一个产品。
然后第二部分就是说呃有些客户可能需要去做什么东西，或者其他方面还有没有什么问题的话，可以bringing a new technology ，which does not have as much of a track record .
But then you were there , as someone really a champion of the.
Yes , can I be in the new year ?
Very conservative environment is not that their technology adverse .
These people are very serious .
Engineers are building the aircraft with the normal life and deaths , and , you know , consequences that we started incorrectly .
So they don't want to put anything in that airplane right unless they really know that they can depend on it , but they may really solid understanding in background where those people are coming from .
When you're try to introduce new technology , you know what you need to do to convince them.
One thing that I noticed regarding your this first tour , beauty is , and naturally , did you come here ?
But you went full mind and body .
And if i'm reading your background correctly .
Overseas , nine programs released in your period of six years , and at first tour.
There were nine programs , and you win , yeah , that's right .
I was starting , wanted to new programs a year and heard at a few , you know , for mother PMS, but I was all in .
I was like younger than had a lot more energy , and but just love the job you mention .
I've been here three times , just to me , is one of the most fascinating job you can have .
You are the panic goal of new technology development .
You have such a broad view was going on , and dark gives you this incredible freedom to pursue what you see is advantage on where they should go.
Now , one of the standards from that first tour is not a command post of the future , and that one actually did get out into the field .
So just briefly , could tell us a little bit about what gold of that program wasn't , in fact , how I was so it unfolded in the field.
Of course , my interests spent AIall along in most of those nine programs .
I ran my first tour had to do with knowledge in reasoning , planning , trying to provide intelligent decision ages to people .
So we created command posts of the future , you know , as a way to save weekend , explore all sorts of vi technologies , see what work packaged that up into a system that army commanders could use out in the future film .
So we started that with a wide variety of technologies of varying degrees of maturity and risk .
And by time we get to the end of the program .
And I had left up by then it was other people were taken it over , but the technology that survive was something that was my call adapted for intelligent visualization .
A lot of the , the more higher risk I techniques that actually kind of following out this two imagery , right , but they had through a lot of virtue with some visionary people from the army , marine , corn , air force and really kind of picked out the knowledge of the new technology .
And they were incredibly valuable , and basically , was that if a commander in his staff could each have their own view , the battlefield in their command post the future screen .
So the operators saw the plans for the attack , the logistics guide , and saw , what did he have to do to support that plan , right ?
The entire guy just got to see what the information was coming in on what the I mean , we do next .
And one of the commanders are army , general korea , who is the one who championed it and took it to back then .
Ashley said that by watching his staff campaign pushed the future screens , he had a better idea of what they were thinking .
Then he did , if they were all in the same room , so it enabled them to one be distributed , which is very important for the battlefield .
The two gave him better insight into what his staff was and wear the battle , the battle.
Was emerging so fascinating this , that is the case where the human machine interaction into something more than the components.
Yes , and partly critical part of that programs where we set it up was the health is consistent interaction between the technologies and the visionary use .
Right , which is it now called edgy development as a lot of names , is pretty much been adopted by silicon valley as religion .
But that strategy was pretty early in those , and they had a lot of exercises where they take researchers from the university .
Send them down the ford pork in the army , initially put on the army gear and run up director sizes , so they get a real sense of what the problem was , but they also had exercises where the visionary military guys would work closely with the technologies to try to sort out what was the most valuable thing the technology could do for user in the field .
And not just let the technologies kind of hypothesize what that might be with somewhat idea of.
But watching it in .
So in two thousand , you leave the article and do other things , and in two thousand reasons , you come back , and this time , you need information processing technology .
Office tells a little bit about the programmes that you , well , they are , including one that I think many listeners will have purple.
Working back , as they say , a tony teller , just comment is the new director around black men as the office cheese of this newly formed officer , though , and ipad was also the name of one of the original dark officers are LED by a legislator is really where the personal computer was created with whole idea .
Yeah , those days , a computer met a large .
I be in range and just.
For listeners who don't know so lick lighter is a giant in the history of dark , but he is now usually as JCRAlegislator actually stands for those in joseph , carl robinet lick later .
And he really brought in an ethic of of this idea that the human machine interaction in the symbolism was going to be a long , long theme of technology from the end of sixties , when he was until now .
And so david , you'll continue in this tradition.
Exactly , and I did before he came in , did what a computer man was an , I be a main frame to took up eyes of a small room , and people would interact with it by sending punch cards and do a punch card reader and getting an answer back on the other side , there was no concept of this being a personal computer .
You sit down with , interact with on a daily basis , and was actually under his program as alan kay , who was that the stanford at the time in later , it park sketched out the first diagrams of what we recognized the day is the personal computer in parking pilot to research in the exactly right and the journey .
So that was it .
So tony teller and run block men , I really wanted to bring that back .
They wanted to reenergize the top to go after the next generation of human computer service .
And the phrase then was cognitive systems , cognitive technology .
And so tony believed in western biggest .
And so we came up with the idea for this program called pile , personalized the system to learn which , even by daughter standards , was a fairly large program , two hundred and fifty million dollars over five years , and it had multiple levels at one level .
It funded twenty some research , universities and agencies around the country to explore a lot of cutting edge technology in AI, in particular , machine learning .
Machine learning is now common place today , with this kind of emerging technology and those days .
So we'd funded a huge amount of basic research on machine learning.
And let me just save you for a second for listening .
You might not really know what that means .
We can go into a full seminar about that .
But what would you find that?
Well , in the earlier days of AI, we try to develop intelligent systems by having program .
Rules are statements into a system that we tell it what the knowledge wasn't later than reason with that .
And the expert systems of expert systems and knowledge bases .
And the terrible tax today is kind of a current incarnation in that time , just playing programs .
Exactly , those ended up being very difficult , very difficult to program , very difficult to maintain its very difficult for people that actually , exactly the logic rules that are behind intelligence .
But over those decades , and especially during this power program , began to realize that if you fed a computer , a lot of data entertained loose with the right machine learning algorithms , which were kind of learning the statistics and probably stick nature of the data and learning a different recognition patterns , the computer could learn its own patterns .
They were not specified by a person , but those patterns were much more effective than doing a lot of jobs than like understanding , speech , recognizing images .
You know , a funny credit card fraud .
And so machine learning was much more effective than the older style , explicit logic.
Basketball , so , in a sense of the computer was doing is taking those , those sort of analyzed signals that that we humans are comfortable with .
But looking them now in their data versions , right , and that's where they are comfortable.
Yes , exactly , until there was a big component of the program , but we also did not work on machine dialogue on , you know how you carry on an intelligent dialogue with a computer .
The speech , understanding to some extent was already being developed .
How would you have a computer that could be an intelligent assistance ?
They would watch what the user is doing , understand his job , then be able to give him assistance at the right time .
And one of the metaphors we used as you wanted to create an assistant that was like a surgery right only on the old TVshow match for those viewed enough to remember already always knew what the kernel needed before the kernel need new himself , right .
So we just followed the context of what the user could anticipate and provide intelligent advice .
So there was the grand vision , and we found it a lot of it very advanced research , and all of those areas .
And in one of our performers was the israel international and how the middle park , california , they were one of the integrators of the state .
They looked at all the research was being tried to create a prototype of this power system that would conductor be used as an intelligent assistance on your laptop.
So that they were looking at many of the component technologies that the other performers were were developing and see.
We put it together exactly , and I was really their job .
Was , how do we interpret the best of all these techniques and put that together , and a real prototype of a cut into a system .
And so they , as long as they were doing that , began to develop a kind of streamlined , more efficient version of the architecture .
And when the pile program , the research version , the book , our program ended around two thousand and eight .
They had several people who worked on power , and some new performers they brought in from the venture called , and they decided they were going to take this technology adapted for the iphone , which was a brilliant new product at the time , and people didn't know quite what to do as a ride was very wisely said , this is the place for , according to the system .
People gonna help this phone .
They won't have a keyboard .
They really going to need an assistance that can help them out .
So they had the adventurer in for two years .
It was just funded as a new start up , darker than without the picture .
They get venture money from silicon valley to develop .
And in two years later , they put their first syrian application on the APP store .
The APP store was brand new .
And I think , was three days later , they got a call from steve jobs himself , who said , in first , they are like what sure this is .
Steve jobs .
He just caused by the trend of phones , you know , in the office after they began to believe it really was steve jobs .
He asked the three founders , he said , wanted to come over to my house tonight for dinner .
I've got a vision for what I wanted to do , and it was some negotiation over selling the company .
Apple boarded , spends several years developing it under the syrian assistant we know today .
And for the first year of that , steve jobs was personally involved in directing it .
He had really seen that as a vision for he wanted to go , but then get.
To continue , okay , so before we move on now to your current in your third tour , which is described your result of the architectural technology development cycle at dark , wanted about successful .
They can get in the u and others here in your performance .
Those works under contract on your programs .
They brought the technology to a point of proving it and then taking the risk down enough that say , other corporate entities , or where the military services can take a hand off and do the final .
Developmentally , we actually have the product technology .
Some of the development goes to that point of a product technology , but it's more to that prototype with a proof of principle .
Here is the case where all of this worth that you did , let do something that now is part of the technology of the world .
So the question I have for you is just , what does that feel like ?
I mean , here you are , you hear right here you all over the place , and you know that you had it a role in the sequences that LED to it .
So I had that film.
We've feels great and was quite a surprise in a way , right , as you say , that starbucks job were always doing .
His advanced technology were always trying to , you know , and we knew a personal assistant had been .
That's been apart of the AI science fiction since two thousand and one and star track , and that's always like what certainty , be able to interact october computer someday .
But we've never quite work , but we've never heard about that.
But now we want , we want the party .
It was all right.
But the idea of a computer that was intelligent enough to carry on a conversation being assistant had been around for a long time , but never employment it when people tried it , it didn't work well enough .
It was always a little bit too close to .
And I think that that power program really brought it to the point the cheap jobs is willing to take a risk and say , yeah , I can make a real product out of this .
And like you say , left up in two thousand and eight , it's two years later that this comes out and renewed .
Apple had bought it , but had no idea what they're going to do , and it suddenly its apple's marketing department is advertising the product , my program , and that was very nice .
My , my children even thought I was a cool guy .
I.
Momentarily , the greatest achievement of all right .
So let's then move now to your current .
You came here in twenty fifteenth , you left until thursday .
You wanna wait , you do other things in an industry .
And you came back in twenty fifteen .
So again , tell me that that approach holders that you were convinced the third time , and it was talking about your two programs.
Well , one is , I said , and it just being a dark is the best job by weather hand .
It is interesting to go out in industry .
It's to be in other places .
But if you enjoy technology and you really want to make an impact , there's nothing like being a darker .
So I was in a headband out for a while in a friday jobs in industry , i'm ready to looking for something to do the other factor of those myself who lives in ruslan nearby just had a first grandchild , and so that convinced my wife it was worth moving from seattle , where our baseball , oh , back to DC, Igot a great job .
My wife got to play with her grandson all day .
So that was A.
That would be a pure justification , right ?
There are no need for anything thing else .
So let's talk about the two programs , one , one you can hurt it .
That's communicating with computers .
See that you see , right , just as tell me a little bit about to go.
Well , innocence is going to do the next generation of earlier alexander and no source of things , or now that technology is there , you know , can understand what you say for the most part , not always , but for the most part , and can provide , you know , assistance .
Consultant alarm can play a song , right ?
Keep you find directions instead of yourself .
We really want to raise the level of intelligence and partnership of the computer .
So it is really an intelligent partner that , you know , I join partner with the human is really human .
Computer sympathize , not human as the manager and computer as a low level of system to that score.
Let's stay here for just one more minute .
What's the kind of question that I might be able to ask after a successful seat of UCcommunicating with computer's program that I can't ask , say , siri.
Let me not use serious , but use one of the examples from the program is the harvard medical school , where they had done some work on a previous dark a program called big mechanism .
Were they trying to add credit system that could read masses of research and biology and an automatically construct models of cancer pathways instead of at the human biology , was having to read thousands of research articles , the computer would do it themselves in great suggestions of new pathways of how cancer behaves in a sale , so the biologists would have that as a suggestion .
So now we see that we see part of it is , can we put a collaborative user interface on top of that ?
So now the biologists can collaborate with a computer to hypothesize how answer works in the sale , the design experiments too , you know , so that the computer is working as a virtual site layout .
The system , if you wear a greatest tune in a biology layout , who's really helping to digest the literature , pull out the important and suggest experiments that should be .
I'm getting this knife.
Think like that , the value added is a farmers scientist in euros , scientists , and we each spend a month in most in , you've read one hundred papers , and I have read one hundred papers , but are found working with the computer .
The computer might have read ten thousand papers were really exact.
You know , what has enough intelligence and has the right kind of dialogue machinery so it can carry on a much more intelligent conversation with you about them today .
It was seriously in a concerned technology might find me , you know , a certain pathway right to find me articles about a certain protein , and a computer could do that , but it is really not gone up .
Sort of bad information integrated , and I am carry on kind of more given.
Conversation with the scientists or so now move on to the program that I suspect is taking up most of your time because of the number of mine might discreet you .
At least eleven performers on this , and this is called explainable artificial intelligence XAI.
So talk about in place for the program .
I guess first and then talk to me about the status and health.
Well , first I said , I came back in two thousand and fifteen yuan , a talk to the an office director , then caught men about the coming back to darker and insurers lessons .
Now my program manager comes to dark with the question is , what revision , what project do you want to do ?
You know that that's kind of job?
And you better do it fast , because you usually have yourself by date on your badge .
You hear for a few years.
And so then he actually suggested this idea of explainable AIIhad just been to a workshop on with a group of intelligence from the OD , and it was a group of machine learning and HIvisualization .
We're trying to convince this group of the great new technology we could provide the help in television analysis and wonderful it is there who was an analysis that one of the deal said , that's not a problem .
Her problem , she already has big data analytics systems that recommending , suggesting patterns or targets are in a suspect to her , but she has to put her name on the recommendation that goes up the chain , and she gets greeted , if not punished , if that recommendation is wrong , and she wanted these systems to explain the horizontal for making the decisions they make.
This was for her , how she was going to trust the machine.
Right , trust it and trust in a win .
When is the machine ?
Winners is a false alarm .
Winners is a positive example .
I and to her , having the explanation was what really needed to make that happen .
And so that resonated is about that time is when the new wave of AI, which is deep learning , is taking off right .
And you hear about this call and a new revolution in AI, that's all about the egg learning techniques .
Where are kind of the most advanced of this machine learning technology we talked about earlier , or takes an huge violence of data , these deep learning systems that are very large , narrow match with millions of neurons .
Well , there are each learning wage that helped build a model of which the correct decision in any situation , electronic versions , of course , yeah , exactly , but they're incredibly opaque and difficult for people to understand .
Collaborators are not quite sure how these systems were making their decisions .
They can be incredibly accurate .
Their federal data and the data fits the world right away .
They can be very effective in our incredible effective at analysis , faces and objects and images and voice recognition , and , you know , and computer games , but they're not very explainable .
It's not very easy for user to understand what these systems are doing .
So for a lot of applications .
That's okay if you find in cat videos on facebook , the nation is not critical , right , but if you are an analyst for DOD, that's picking out targets to investigate , are you running in autonomous ?
And then there were a goal that's going to go off on to a mission on its own .
You really want to get a good explanation of what the standard is thinking .
So it's a very hard problem .
The sum extend this machine learning technology works so well because it learns models that are inherently more difficult , more complex than what person would specify .
But yet , you need to get some explanation out of it so that user can get an integration for what the system is doing .
So that's the problem .
So we lay that out .
There is a typical .
Then a doubt you talk to a lot of researchers , a lot of people in duty about the you craft , your solicitation , and you get in your proposals , and you pick your performers and have you mentioned , i've picked eleven performers or each developing what i'm calling an explainable learning system .
So we still wanted to be a machine learning system .
We don't want to go back to the old version of technology where you're trying to specify the rules , although we know the older versions , they were more more because a human had described the logic it's using .
It was much easier to regard to take that logic to another human , and people could understand what is doing .
But in this case , that's not possible .
So each one , these eleven teams developing two major components , the dark and applied together into a system .
One component is a modified machine learning process , so they're changing the deep process , or they're adding a new learning technique that changing something about the way the system learns its model .
So this is more interpretation , more explainable in the second , going back to my inner background , and AGI and psychology is to have an explanation interface , which is the best combination of visualization , natural language generation , you know , creates just the right explanation that appropriate for the end users , or who understands what the system is doing , even know that the user is not going to be a machine learning expert .
So we have to take the complexity of this machine learning system system , increase the right kind of explanation .
So you're average user can understand what.
Doing so , question about that , and this really comes from the human side .
So I might do something behaved in a certain way , right , and somebody might say , why did you do that with the explanation for your behavior ?
Yes , and I can come up with one after the fact that sounds reasonable to me .
Yes , but I can't really be sure that i'm not fooling myself until just one .
Maybe i've just made up an explanation .
So cannot be happening here .
It , it again at gold rationalization , rationalization , one of the.
Make sure you , we , we could .
Some of the teams are taking a approach , whether going to treat the machine learning systems of black box .
They don't know what's going on , but they can experiment with that .
They can run a million simulation trials with different input and see what the output and and see if they can throw a model of the explains what is doing .
So the test , though we do to avoid the problem you describe it is the text .
Is , does your explanation predict what the machine will do in a new situation .
So if you fool in yourself , the prediction will be wrong , and especially to help the use gaining trust , you know , so the user needs to have a model from the explanation .
So the user knows when in which situation , should they trust it , and when they , so they need to have some model , which , you know , predictive of what the systems gonna do , so they can create this understanding , and even though that understanding may be very different than what's actually going on inside the machine , it is close enough .
This capturing the main features of what the system is doing , so that they can understand and have some faith and understanding what the system will.
Then another fascinating thing to me about explainable AI , and certainly , as I am learning for me right now , is it also seems to be robbing shoulders with some of the great questions of philosophy .
Not , it gets into a piece of technology where a big world which we had had , we come to know things as human things .
And what is an explanation anyway ?
What's the nature of explanation makes me think the philosophers would be quite interested in what you do.
Unfortunately , they are , and our explain that , and we have the eleven teams are actually building the system .
We have one team that is just a group of cognitive psychologists who were digging into what's known about the explanation , not so much from philosophy , but from psychology psychologist for years , have started what explanation is more affected for personal , what explanation leads to learning better than another explanation , what explanations improve decision making .
So their job is suggested to rule that literature and help us out with what's an explanation .
And I mentioned business about philosophers .
Interesting , unfortunate , because it is so easy to get lost in this very deep conversation about what is called .
And what's an explanation ?
And we've had a fair amount of that discussion in the program i'm trying to get around that by using a very practical definition , the test will be , if you create one of these systems , a human user has to use that system to make decisions to manage a non main vehicle or to doing televisions .
Does the explanation enabled him to appropriately trust the system , does the enabled him to predict when the system will be right , and when it will be wrong , and that's our measure .
So I want to try to avoid this philosophical swamp and just get to a practical solution on .
When does an explanation help user do his job ?
And when doesn't it so give you me , you want?
Tools in hand in a relatively short time , I suppose , to a thousand years of discussion.
Exactly right , a thousand years of discussion with no tools at the end.
So we're getting together , and we don't have that much time , but there are few other things that like to adjust the discussion you want them is in looking at the way our official intelligence is is received by the public .
We kind of discussions the public is having .
There is certainly some excitement .
I think the public is leaning toward a positive view on , say , fleets of driverless cars that actually are working out there .
There are still some ways around that , but there also without that disturbing insight that the artificial intelligence is another kind of intelligence , and it's scary , and it might be more powerful , and that this is something to really fear and worry about it .
So you are in the midst of you are one of the , the tool builders , SAIspace .
And how do you think about that , the in the promise and the potential paris.
What's a great question , and one that we mean , we talk about a lot .
I'm so first day , I like any technology can be used for good or evil , right , others , both sides do it , and we have to be careful right to manage that .
And I have overall think it's very positive , right .
I think it's be much easier for us to avoid that , really make it.
Backs of this , this is where someone might press you and say , well , but your technologies , right , and yes .
And so , and you said that in a fairly carefully away , so give me one of two bases for why you , you have an appointment.
What is the level of intelligence were really at an aim ?
So what we have even known that we spent huge advancements , especially in the deep learning technology in the last couple years , were so far away from human intelligence or anything that would be an independent super intelligence that that science fiction to me is like worrying about a media that's gonna hit earth sometime in the next million years , and in life , as we know , right is not imminent , right .
You're not high probability , you know , which nurses should make sure they get telescopes , you know , around the planet .
So we can see that when it's happening , so we need a small number of people worrying about , let's make sure we don't create a super intelligence that gets out ahead .
But I think the current technology today is so far from that.
That's not a big concern .
So the disturbing and point is something , as you said , it's not worth worrying about too much now , but on the other side , then to move forward suggests to me that you think the positive employees are really worth resuming.
What are just like a driver's cars , right ?
There is a lot of issues to be worked out there .
But I have no doubt when that comes , we'll be fewer deaths on the highway .
Then it will be with human drivers , medicine , you know , just huge scientists and applying this medicine , think one of the latest results was one of these deep learning systems can learn to recognize skin cancer events better than human .
You know , so just analyzing the vast amounts of data that we have , and you know , being able to understand it or just creating theory and personal systems that can do a better job .
So many things where AIis going to be.
Useful , right ?
This is making me think of your new grandchild , he or she , she is .
So he is going to grow up any time when AIis part of of the landscape , part of the technique sleep , he will not know what I am with everything I have that kind of.
That tried , I should have a great little video of him at one year old .
His first interaction was serious , and he's learned if he presses this button , the iphone talks to him , and he doesn't even have languages we understand , but he would press this button and have a conversation in his own global language , just fascinating .
So I think we'll be interesting to see how this generation grows.
Well , we have been going to want to see that video at some point .
So we are at the time , and I just want to thank you for engaging with .
And really , what has been an absolutely fascinating start of my morning here .
Lots of things we need to think about for the rest of the day .
So thanks , a lot for priority .
Yeah , thank you .
Certainly enjoyed it .
And thanks listeners for sure .
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dark .
For more information about david gunning , the programs he runs and the other breakthrough technologies dark is working on visit , dark , adopt and for lengths that enabled you to download this .