Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand on tonight's operation technology has a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war dirt , the defence advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from dark , a window under darkness .
Core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone a motel and arm your dark host today , I am pleased to be talking with christian michael baggage since twenty seventeen .
In the agencies , biological technology office would be to you as much as anyone here are doubt .
He embraces biology from its foundations in molecules that are boom cells , like , plus the interactions of these components , which are decidedly full of life , all of the way to like pinnacle manifestations , perception , learning and other categories of christian came to daughter from the european colorado boarder , where he was a research assistant professor in the department of molecular and developmental biology .
His academic studies focused on the molecular mechanisms associated with the way drugs of abuse , toxins and neural developmental disorders protect complex biological systems , such as bodies and minds .
Prior to his faculty appointment at the university of colorado , christian was a postdoctoral fellow in the department of psychiatric at the yale university school medicine and an aluminous of the yale .
Neither narrow property on the center , neither sense for nationalised to the drug abuse .
Christian received his daughter philosophy degree in integrative physiology and graduate certificate in behavioral genetics from the university of not on his official , the arab obey or two areas of applied biology that christian has developed the neck for one is home bureaucracy in which specializes in less familiar .
Bruce , including one called his other DIY approach to apply biology .
Sounds delicious .
He loves to cook .
He tells me , particularly classic , southwestern and northern mexican dishes like current meters intro lotters shi li RUIYANANGpork , green , shirley and purpose fruits with tomato just simply call baggage .
Thanks for joining me today .
But a different matter was pleasured with you .
Well , so a humble in some of your chilly rain sounds , but that will help you wait .
I am sure I will get an invitation at some point , right , absolutely right now .
I want to learn about your extensive port for your programs and their assistant goals among the restoring memory law associated to traumatic brain injury .
And as I have heard , you put it cold , slowing down to save life in cases of severe battlefield injuries .
But first , trust them want to get some sense of the origins of your embrace of science in general and biology , in particular .
In an earlier email exchange , you told me that by the age of seven , you wanted to study biology .
So give me the origin story of of your interesting size.
As many things in your early childhood development , you can draw up a pretty straight line towards printer influence both .
And my parents are PHDscience .
The chalk growing up was not , you know what you want to be when you grow up , but rather , what kind of doctor do you want to be when you grow up ?
And so my mother has heard peace and educational psychology , my dad in electrical engineering .
And so it's actually kind of funny .
If you know , one or the drug , you know , of line of continuing through , you know , the quantitative sciences as someone's life with you , you know , had a psychologist and engineer , end up with the biologists approaching me .
And so he , yeah , when I was relatively young , and I had my first experience with the actual quantitative assessment of the functions of living things of , you know that this was the first experiment .
You know , you do as it as a child in , in science class in school , with , you know , growing plans and monitoring their transition through different faces of development , ultimately leading to the the production of employment of fruit .
I found that entire process absolutely fascinating , because it's spoke to the ability with which systems living systems pursue this sort of self organizing potential .
And ultimately , you know , propaganda and you know , contribute to this , or never ending continuum of existence , and the fact that it is all primary rise , and you know , produced as a result , measurable , quantifiable chemical reactions gives us the opportunity to understand that system in a manner that also allows us to intervene system .
So if we can establish your functional and consequential relationships between you are what happens to a living system when it starts itself organizing and self repairing potential .
What can we do to to bring it back?
Okay , and and we're working against some of that when we developing more deeply into some of your programs like biostatistics , we're very excited to talk about .
But I want sure that we give a shout out to a teacher abuse whenever there's an opportunity to give praise back and give our teachers a part of a back .
I like that happen to know from an emailed .
Strange that there are , you had an important high school teacher that was , you know , kind of catalyze some of.
Oh , absolutely , so that it gives me great pleasure .
Haven't talked to him in the decades , but I assumed to mr tim henson , and I watch a high school , and I watch colorado , which is of the smallest town in between bolder and london .
When I took his course in college preparatory biology at the age fifteen , that was my first real introduction into cloud .
Shall we say the more fundamental molecular nature of life learning about you are the crime cycle about the rules underlying media and genetic scenes .
You know , here , the ability of treats all that came from from college prep biology in mr henson's class .
I also was fortunate enough that you are .
He recognized , and I was probably forceful enough with my interest in the subject that , you know , the school curriculum didn't have live science really much beyond that .
You know , this sort of the junior level science classrooms in chemistry and settlement .
So he sponsored me to do two years of independent study .
So I was the belong independent study biology students who was basically given the opportunity in the access to freely pursue a scientific of lives of topics that I find interesting , so as a consequences that spend the semester recording various features of of global wires around the third of colorado for a branch .
Looking at neutrals of accident content , ph levels in settlement , various positions along rivers in the reporting that information to the court.
The last question .
So I went as before , we get into the programs is how your dark eventually began .
I typically do ask program managers who sit with me for these conversations about you .
How did they get to dark a story ?
And so tell me that story and brief.
So I came to doubt from the academic side .
I , it was a performer on a dark program .
The program was called RTAfor rapid threat assessment .
It was the brain child of an XBTOPM, and in various quarter , who had the vision of saying , well , is there are chemical , biological threatens out that we have never seen before , cannot carry the right .
How would we know how to respond appropriately with containment , with medical countermeasure design all that kind of stuff , what we need is a description of the mechanism of action of the threatened .
What is this thing doing in a complex biological system ?
It is not enough to just describe the chemical structure , the agenda .
So we have to know what did it do and why .
And so that was the challenge in the RTAproblem .
It was now taking an unknown chemical entity , perceiving a biological model system with it , and then interrogating the responses to that production to determine what happened and why .
And that was essentially a program that was , you know , almost taylor made for scientists with my type of of background , I cannot devoted my academic too , explaining the molecular mechanisms underlying yellow chemical prohibitions to biological systems.
right ?
And what years were you working on that program?
So I went on that program from twenty thirteen to the end , thirteen early , twenty fourteen until I came to territory.
Twenty seventeen , oh , I see .
So there's a really a cut newly from you .
You working as a performer that is a researcher on narrative program , and then coming in to the biological technology office as a program manager .
That's a very sort of aggressively secret from performer to the program manager .
And so let's move there .
now .
I mean , when you came in , you may know , for five years later , you got a real handful of programs .
Some of the murray inherited .
We'll get to those , I think toward the end .
Then you got three others that will talk about wisdom is a taste of all of this .
If we can the first one to start with this program that you devised and which launched a blame twenty eighteen , is called the bio states program .
And this has some really fascinating aspects with amazing organisms called territories and then wood frogs .
But I let you sort of leave that into .
You're narrowed to hear of what the buyer says is all about .
And what is.
Okay , so violates this is really a virus to the attempts , and outside it , it would be about trying to buy time .
It is literally attempting to intervene with a complex biological system in a manner that preserves its functionality for a period of time , under which otherwise it would be stronger press , it would start to decay , and we would lose functional capacity and the system .
This has rather direct removals for a number of applications within the department of defense , going all the way from logistical concerns , such as how do we stabilize and protect variable religious things like vaccines , medical countermeasures of settlement that ordinary would require a huge degree of infrastructure support in the form of inner temperature control set up.
Known as the cold chain , right , there is something that we've been talking about with the interviews.
Yes , get that perfect example .
And then also the fact that , you know , there are issues around coaching , even even for molecules that are , you know , well , stable under certain temperatures are not stable indefinitely .
And so you have the issue with , you know , the important resources that , you know , do no fault of their own , just lose activity over time .
And from that all the way up to what are some areas of medical information that have not really been explored yet , largely for no reasons of the fact that the chemical to actually protect the system in that way , just simply doesn't exist .
We don't have molecules in hand that can act as your broad spectrum stabilizers , reversible stabilizers , often complex , the biological machinery , which is not going to have .
So what I wanted to do with file status was basically look at , you know , elements from the natural world where we see this type of functional , actually taking place , learn from those systems .
Or what are the sort of your core guiding principles responsible for that capability , and then translate the more , you know , either logistically minded or human physiology minded application.
Right , and so just tell listeners a little treat with descriptions of two of the primary biological systems to listen I heard about , so that's the wood frog .
And it was amazingly writing free , silent for a long time .
Come out , and it in the target grades , which are just that , you know , insanely interesting .
I almost impossible creatures.
Sure , so I mean , for example , that the work would target rates that was originally done by thomas goods be assigned to sell the university , north carolina , chapel hill , who was wondering performers on biostatistics as america .
He sounds mutual , numerously violent , but he did a lot of work , actually describing what are the biochemical mechanisms by which is the small , you know , small arthur parts .
Can we stand such extraordinary environmental stresses and entire grades , when they're legislature appropriately prepared , they can freeze , they can describe .
They can be almost completely dry out .
And in that state , providing excellent temperature extremes , extreme radiation of accumulated space , and in a white flower , to example that there are other organisms that can also do this .
They enter a state that is not hibernation asian , and it's not torpedo either .
It is in gas clothes .
We can come to crucial BIOS , which is a sort of terminate to find all , you know , the outward appearance of the absence of life .
And yet life can persist and can resume its normal function when , in variety of conditions , we have more conducive return .
And so what will I draw a lot of inspiration for by a status from really looking at the , you know , the molecular mechanisms and of the biology that is , that is responsible in these organisms , and then figuring out what is it all having common , and what can we use from that to help design , you know , our sort of novel .
They are beautiful interventions and then tested .
And so when it comes down to a target risk of our fascinating creatures , because we were , first of all , one of the things that they do is they actually increase the production of a certain class of proteins in their sales when they start experiencing , you know , the changing environment , that's basically a signal that you know what .
What is is leaving , and we need to prepare for a period of pain .
Try and so what they'll do is reduction of these users with class of proteins that the thomas name TDPSwere totally great .
Disordered proteins were a biochemical perspective of their fascinating , because they're at least , you know , so like long spin , intrinsically disordered proteins , the doctor is spontaneously falled into a three dimensional shape .
There is a sort of fraud and what they can do is they actually act inside the soul is almost like a chemical ship they packed in there .
There are produced a great numbers of the assault of fuel of the gaps in spaces in between the south .
Machinery can like packing peanuts .
You understand keeping , not keeping everything where it is , you know .
And then they wrap around , they can actually stabilizing and constrain the inflexibility of social components , and that that appears to be really important for the ability that thousands of experience in the loss of all this work , you know , animals are , but you know , huge domestic reaction of an animals we are , and that goes away .
The tendency is for the biological molecules to lose function as a result .
In a day they did nature , they fall apart when the water goes away .
But if the sale is protected appropriately , well , then it can actually survive .
It can maintain its disturbed structural functionality , while we know that the change in hydration has taken place .
And then when the rehydrated , while it can sort of resume the wrong process .
And so.
Absolutely brilliant at the right , and it sort of keeps the sales in the overall structure .
Former needs to win when the water comes back , maybe , maybe months , and maybe even years later , I think a good way to give listeners a sense of really where you want to go with .
This is in some ways to imagine a battlefield situation .
So what fighter is injured , whether you have some of the tools that you have in visioning and our infector performers are beginning to.
Real what would happen , allowing it , it , we will depend on the nature of the injury , the blue sky concept of operations .
There is a two hundred something that can be administered at a reasonably large volume into the system in order to basically slow down its rate of collapse right after there is a unique life for an injury .
There is a huge shock of that system in manifest in many different ways .
Simultaneously , the analogy would be something it came to lucy a ball , and I love lucy on the chocolate bump on the same way , whether just they're down so quickly and so many different directions .
And she , just , you know , two hands just cannot keep pace with that .
There are too many things happening at the same time , such that , you know , targeted interventions , right , you know , one hand grab in one band band , not a graphic is , it's not going to automatically result in the kind of your control over that , you know , catastrophic runaway system that you would want the appropriate thing to do is to slow the about that if you had that capability , you could reduce the rate at which , in all the events are taking place .
Wouldn't then you have more an opportunity to intervene , and actually , you know.
Care of the system , right , and this .
So this gets back to sort of weighing and introduction when I threw that kind of very teasing lineup , which is slowing life to save , you know , so that's the idea the beneficial situation is that goes an hour right when there's a severe injury you really need to get that word fighter to sophisticated in a medical intervention .
And this is the way that maybe help more injured board fighters survive.
That is the hope , and it basically boils down to and into radically oversimplify .
You know , that the process of life is the living systems from the cell all the way up to in the blue whale are ultimately all they're all supported by giant sets of parallel and interconnected chemical reactions by a chemical , one of the defining features of most biochemical reactions that they do not occur spontaneously .
They have to be capitalized .
They need help to take place their energetically disfavor .
And so what are responsible for those catholic events ?
Are , you know , any of them ?
They're proteins , they're the large bio molecules that , you know , make up a huge portion of , you know , the contents of ourselves .
Well , those things all have rates .
And if you introduce something that slows the rate down , and it's relatively universal will not only have you , you know , slow down that rate , but potentially you slow down the rated , which the system is action .
That's the high professors , right ?
So we can do that to degree right with , with things I call temperature in other reason that there is a cold chain is because called slows things down is slows chemical regions down .
We go back to , you know , everybody's gentlemen class .
We all learn the original situation .
You know , the temperature is a of that equation .
So as you refrigerate food , you are slowing down both competition from my growth rights as their metabolic rate is slowed .
So who doesn't spoil his father due to , you know , the growth of modern victory on the food , and then the , you know , food itself is , you know , in transit copies is worth of saying or integrity .
You know why your careers could wrinkle them and fall apart from that , that is also sold when it is cold .
So that's fine .
But what we want to do is use a more chemical biology solution because of another component in the iranian education is responsible for governing the rate of chemical , and that is the frequency of collisions between the reactions in the appropriate geometric .
You know , how well does that key fit into the walk that then allows the chemical reaction to take place to take , and in a biological systems , and so many of these things are catalyzed by proteins .
If we can control the geometry of the protein , control its three dimensional confirmation of flexibility , we can exert some degree of rate of reactions that it is capitalism .
And if we were able to do that in a very broad spectrum , sort of promiscuous special , you can effectively and act something like warm , freezing .
You know , it is a small room temperature reduction in activity.
Ha , ha , nice report .
Yeah , I could talk to you forever and buy a status right now , and we are just scratching the surface .
I don't want to deprive listeners of getting at least a taste of some of your other programs when you move on from here , tracing out what i'd like to do is talk you about a pair of your programs once called panel's .
Yet here you challenging performers that will be called researchers working on programs that develop to mind the vast reporter , proteins , human bodies , for which dragon adventures , you know , might help or fighters , and the neighbourhood is called focused farmers .
The other goal there in interesting leaders is to develop drug companies for neuropsychiatric conditions among the depression and post substance abuse , but that work with unprecedented specificity and receptor proteins on cells .
The idea is it gets several beauty effects with fewer or no side effects is one tank goal costs in medicinal chemistry and information to go science and medicine .
But talk about those two.
If you want , I can , we can even bring by your spaces , and because they're actually kind of all in a continual , you could basically oil by a , this is done to say , i'm looking for chemicals for which there are reversible and favorable interactions with as many proteins in the service possible .
So looking forward to the views and promise you was drugs that you can imagine where the target for the drug is every protein .
Then in panacea , it's sort of in the middle .
One thing , whereas identify clusters of proteins , clusters of drug targets that we want to interact with with a single molecule , and then all the way in the other end , is focused .
Farmer , we're not only in mind after one specific protein , but i'm after one specific , eagerly impacts way that it impacts .
So we're literally running from the dirty of drugs in the world into the cleaner strikes in the world across.
Whether the interesting thing about panacea is that it sort of does bucket a paradigm of the medicinal chemistry in an industry of farmers who call this career approach , which has to try to malaysia summer lacker intervention that focuses on a single in a protein target might be a receptor might be something else .
But what you're bringing in yourself , acknowledgement of the complexity of the system and say , well , it really might be better to have ten protein targets out there that can give you a better therapeutic responsibility is some way of getting at panacea , right?
Yeah , that's correct .
So I mean , if you really think about a conception in another one of those who are famous , scientists pull early under the bus , but he , in a politics is a claim assigned to the end of many decades ago who had this notion of the magic bullet being the thing that were going to be the most successful drugs that if you can identify the one thing that was wrong in the system that was responsible for this function , you could change that one proteins function with a drug that only targeted that one protein .
Then you would end up , you know , fixing the problem , and you would have a very little taxi girl , you know , our undesired side effect in the problem with that while thinking is that , in many cases , most manifestations of disease , or in a following injury , they're not due to a single disappointment system .
You know , most disorders are motive , patrol and nature .
And so , as you say , yes , we need to accept that there are certain complexities in the system , certain redundancies and certain diverse manifestations , of course , that will otherwise present with something that is connecting very similar .
And so what we need to do is really increase the diversity of our chemical interventions that we have access to this , so that we can do a better job actually plugging into the system that wrapped assortment of promotions in order to get it back on track .
And in many cases , actually in existing , we know the farmer computer , you know , the collection of all the drugs that we have that have , you know , distributions in many cases that drugs that are the most effective act on multiple components of a male functioning system .
They have targets that produce a , you know , either an attitude or a synergistic affected manifest , as , you know , a greater therapeutic index being in the concentration of the drug that is effective before becomes , or a great reminder to the affecting on how much relief do you get from the symptoms associated with this condition when you take this drug that has insert cluster of targets to suppose the other drivers are .
The problem is that in many cases , the identification of , you know , those multi target , I can draw some record on palestinian political activities in mobile phones is that it happens very difficult .
Is it just luck ?
You know , we ended up being in a position where we were looking at the effects and variable to sort march backwards through the targets that could be identified .
And then by applying the appropriate study of physiology , we could say , oh , well , the reason that you know , this drug has a longer lasting effect on this condition is because , well , it turns out that one of its off target effects , something that is was actually beneficial .
Now , will that unlocks now a whole new area of study were reconciliable .
What other you know , contributions are these particular targets making to the manifestation this disease , or rather than leave that kind of discovery , you know , up to chance for the penalty .
I thought , why would we take a more systems biology systems from a college approach to it and actually do political ecology by design in order to do that , what we have to have , there is a very good representation of the malaysian nature of the condition we are trying to improve .
And so in pennsylvania , that's why we're really focusing on the designer my colleagues are getting getting down for one more with you , with multiple targets.
Sounds challenging and wonderful .
May you succeed that , and I want to make sure that we , in touch on one more program that called the targeted neuroplasticity training program , or TNT .
Yeah , this was going up from the molecular scale executive .
Incredibly interesting idea of stimulating the preference of system in order to enhance learning and absolutely amazing idea .
Can you give this new success of it ?
What the goal , that program meals and what is its status?
Yeah , so TNT was originally devised as a throne applied nor engineering program to leverage preferences simulation and promoting in our state that is receptive to burning memory .
And the notion really came from the observation that we are nervous .
System in private .
Define has young , two components , the CNSessential and the PS, the performing resistant CNSis your brain , spinal cord , and then PNSis basically everything else .
This system they talk to return , and since nerves are electrically inside myself , you can deliver electrical stimulation to , you know , accessible branches of the profile , nervous system , and you can see that stimulation result in changes in central nervous system function .
You can appreciate basically what you done is activated .
An african projection , you know , from a disclosure penetration .
Whatever the translates that the electrical imports into a chemical signal in the central nervous system , some pioneering work in the space had been done in empire to the inception of the program , largely in the areas of rehabilitation following a so it was observed that if you paired electrical stimulation of in a large fiber volume of the vaccino , which is known as these big poor phone nerves and sort of wonders down from the brain through the neck , and then ultimately intervals that the visual workers they called the vegas , because it is the vague about nerve , a kind of wonders all over it .
You'd deliver an electrical stimulation to the vegetarian .
You can impact the degree of synaptic plasticity in circumstances , and synthetic plasticity will destroy broadly defined as the phenomenon by region .
Neural activity changes in reaction to various importance in it , one of the , the core physiological components , you know of learning memory .
And so TNT was really looking at , what can we leverage that kind of interface , you know , from an electrical stimulation to approval nerve in order to produce a window of potentially improved synaptic plasticity in order to accelerate the encoding of professional stimuli that would ultimately result in an improved rate of learning that program has ended .
When I think about him , it's not necessarily that , you know , your generating a state that is somehow you augmented in , you know , relation to a statement of the brain could normally achieve , is just changing the likelihood and the temporal dynamics of that state , one of the mechanisms have really came out of the nature has been important for its impact on sanitary questions has largely to do with the phenomenon that delivering electrical stimulation to perform those results in a state that is sort of a generally reminiscent of century arousal .
He said , uh in the brain of novel.
So in general , your sort of dying up , the learning entertainment probability , the fact is kind of a general dilling up means that it might work for whatever , if you try to learn a new language .
If you are trying to mathematics , are trying to learn how to use a new weapons is whatever.
That's the hope .
I think it's important to point out the internet and other thing that we determine is that the timing and the presentation of the nurse to the century input and the , the reaction to the century input is also extremely important that when you are training someone and you deliver a focus performer information to the biggest nerve , and it is temporarily paired with a correct response .
Then the subsequent responses are more likely to be correct .
You essentially the system saturday , you know , there , they were focused on me what the context of century input was at the time that they responded correctly , that increased the likelihood in a subsequent response is , if you pay the stimulus with either rendering or with an incorrect response , you're actually more likely to buyers the system in the opposite direction , so it can be crucially important what the timing and the context in which the training is taking place .
How are you delivering performance nation?
Just finished up on the TNT program .
Have any lessons come out of that , researching from the performers that have been working on that program that are close to being applied in a trading or learning situation.
Also , we have a number of things that they came out on the the basic science side .
I would say that a number of the lessons learned how to do with nerve target engagement , and they need for very specific and atomic interfaces that , you know , for the most part , the physiology that is really responsible for the observable effects of large manufacturers in the program really depends efficient activation of deep branches of the various nerves .
So that is to say that the large fiber volume , nerve that is your couple cinema is bubble the skin , and that try to deliver electricity , you know , through the skin .
Sophistication is bad .
muscle .
Is sarah .
All that stuff is really great insulator .
And so you actually don't end up driving the deep targets of the nerve if you are going to provide electrical stimulation through this .
And so one of the teams are until the university was causing medicine that has had some success in their response of a small company around a proud of political , the inject and injectable lecturers .
So is there is a novel composite polymer that can be introduced .
Nonsensically been a thriller needle to basically provide a direct electrical can do it from the to those these branches of the nurse that you , you know , don't have to go through , you know , but the national invasive , you know , coffee and play a procedure , and you can circumvent that problem .
We're trying to get your reliable , objective activation to a deep branch of the nerve .
That's one of the things that never calling a reasonable success from the problem .
And then the only thing that we learned it was really important is , again , this terms of timing and context , that , in order to , in a really achieve a considerable benefit when it comes to optimizing your , you know , sort of state of arousal .
It is important .
There is a zone in which you want the students to be in order to achieve efficient processing and discrimination .
Incoming century information , whether is , you know , the sound of new words that are being used , or whether it's the presentation of , you know , new objects that the trying to learn how to you will want a specific degree of general riots or present , because two year too little arousal , and they're not an attention too much .
A russell under napping .
And so we have an ongoing study in collaboration with a research laboratory at air , foreign and university of maryland that are working right now with the air force , foreign language , defence , languages to that monetary california , and they are basically applying the innocent of best practices that we generated from the program to see an ecologically valid in a circumstances .
Right , you're dealing with bilateral foreign language winners does hiring , you know , the sort of a finally control performance stimulation of the new language does that in the , in fact , improve their occupy formats .
So that experience is.
Now , I wanted to return just briefly to focus for me , because one thing we did get out .
There was one of the more fascinating aspects of , and this has to do with investigating how valuable drugs like alice d and suicide , and those that are in a famous for their hallucinogenic and capabilities .
Just , what can I also do in clinical settings for conditions like depression and post dramatic stress and anxiety , these sorts of there is a new research feel that really has been emerging and building momentum of investigating these .
Talking me little bit about how focused farmer is looking at these kinds of agents for the kinds of neuropsychiatric issues that the war fighters often.
Basically , focus farmer is an effort to introduce some more chemical diversity and magnetic novelty into the space of north psychiatric medication in a , regardless of target .
The effect of the matter is that a psychiatric drug development has , has really suffered over in over decades from large scale investment that there are your classes of drugs are generally prescribed that are generally safe , new of things like selected search on and reality and evidence in my prosecutors all up to sarah , that do produce , you know , measurable effects for us for a number of people not in anyway .
You have to crying the existence of those compounds , but it is also well appreciated that , for you know , the broad swaths of the population who suffering from anxiety , depression , postman distress at zero , there are a lot of the existing molecules that we have to treat those conditions .
They suffer from a circumstances where they produce a fact that are what it may be statistically significant .
They are what we are politically insignificant .
You can administer because at the individual depression , they will get measurably less depressed , but it doesn't move the needle out of the category .
Being depressed right there is still the pressure just left the press , the phenomenology to know , you know what a lot of pioneering work are by rolling briefs at the chance .
Hawkins , as well as a robin carter heroes , a formally of university college one day .
He just useless .
They really started doing some experiments with the cute doses of innocent classical psychiatric drug , a source event paired with therapy for treatment resistant depression , as well as anxiety and depression associated with end of life and cancer patients .
And one of the things that they found with those experiments with the fact that they could get that in clinical manifestation that affects size , that moved the patient out of being depressed into now , no wonder the press , and then a similar effect size was seen with the sort of large scale , the mass travel and the amazing system cycle therapy for postman express .
That was a multi senator trial that that recently published their their final result showing the dynasty method and fundamental drug , also commonly known as excessive , not a classical psychiatric , by any means .
That mechanism is very different than so asylum , but it's still one of these .
Instead , we call it more brownie modulators of the syrian original transmission that went again , paired with therapy and the amazing society that he could produce giant effect sizes and otherwise treatment , resisting cases of cosmetic stress to the extent that they were no wonder meeting diagnostic criteria for health and cosmological stress .
And , moreover , that that remission was long lasting that it would persist months or more , as opposed to hanging a drug like , you know , personal resolve that you will take every day as part of your regimen , right ?
So having that kind of phenomenal logical evidence , and it really sort of spoke to , okay , there are , in fact , some physiological similarities here that we should be integrated with the eye towards the first fine , the range of their activities are available that may keep on some shared aspects of this physiology , right , because the other truth of the matter is that , you know , classical psychology not spent appropriate therapy with option for a lot of people if we were to live at the criteria for the clinical trials done with so seven .
And you know , you couldn't take it if you had a family history of my poor , if , you know , you know , you know how any family history of your skills africa is that there were a huge exclusion criteria.
You may say , if you could decouple , those are often times difficult manifestations of the use of these substances from the clinical aspects are targeted to say , four depression for a postgraduate stress that that would open up new evidence.
Well , it's more than I am interested in asking the question , right ?
Because first of all , we want with the chemical matter just doesn't exist , right , we don't have in our hands yet .
Molecules that have the same kind of target engaged as the classical psychiatrists , but for which the signaling processes that they , the they stimulate are isolated , most travel , classical psychiatric tend to act as indiscriminate activators of downstream signal .
Sarah , tony receptors , when , in fact , there are multiple downstream signaling pathways .
We need the chemical matter can to selectively activate those different downstream .
Second part is , in order to answer the question , can we , in fact , in due responses that allow us to see whether or not the theoretical facts can , in fact , be uncoupled from the more defused , hallucinatory psychiatric effects , we just the factors we don't have the material in hand to even answer the question , let alone pursue it as a therapy of option .
But it is also fair to say that deserves to be done , because we all do you know that there is a substantial proportion of the population who cannot currently benefit from the psychological?
Psychotherapy , fantastic .
Well , so again , now I wish you a great success with this aspect of focus for my biggest inner could potentially open up in a really new , important or mathematical categorically open up a lot of people we have covered a lot of ground truth in a new bin , blowing my mind all away from the molecular dance going on inside of sales and how you might be older in some ways to spend up to extend a goal now , or in case I , because I am injured in some terrible way , may that not happen .
You're all the way up now to waste of using the powerful nerve system to enhance learning .
And now is we just discuss with focus former new furniture categories for treating psychiatric issues .
Just one more question , before I give you the rest of your day back here , you know , there , anything that did not come up in discussion about your scientific journey .
You're journey as a program manager , a doctor that you think listeners of this package would find interesting.
Yeah , I think in general , how are you going to be expensive that listeners are going to be interested in the end of the culture of darkness and the perception of the culture of dark program managers exist in a approval space .
Right , we are .
We are given a lot of freedom with which to make decisions with which to resource efforts in order to produce research projects that are very nearly due to us .
There is a lot of I, Iwould dare to say that in a program , managers are very personally invested in the programs that they are .
So we know we have a , we have a tendency to take things personally , because there , there is that degree of relationship that exists between the ideas the problems are trying to solve .
The reasons why we're trying to solve , and ultimately how the researchers done .
And I would say they , despite that emphasis on the program manager as the sort with the entity responsible for all of this fantastic research and pushing out near the boundaries of what is incorrectly possible , or I would also say that it has been part of my experience that this is a profoundly collaborative agency that I spent a substantial amount of time in very productive discussions with my colleagues hear the agency getting very different respective on a number of fundamental issues and questions .
And as well as the collaborations that I have both with the other governmental agency , the end users who is ultimately going to take the thing that I try to invent and turn it some real enabling capability for university , for natural security , for meaningful rehabilitation , for treatment , for restoration in a very population.
themselves that part of the job of a dark a program manager is not just coming up with clever ideas and setting things in motion , but also continuing to work and pay to know what the researchers producing .
What does it tell you about your initial hypothesis and any assumptions that you made in which of those things are ultimately going to be rejected ?
You know , we all learn as much from successes we do from failure .
And so sometimes you just have to be mindful and do your best to establish the appropriate balance between things that are practically impossible for a reason versus things that are practically impossible , just due to electronic.
right ?
Well , thanks .
I have .
I always love the agencies embrace of failure as a equally informative and instructive as successes .
So christian , you've taken me on just a fantastic tour of your mind of your programs of where I , you think about science , where you want to take a pilot science until new capabilities , technologies , just achievement as I just have you and your research performers succeed in all of these natural defense mission , for sure , is allowed to gain from these efforts .
But these are the source of ones that also could spill over , you know , just a bit for for everybody .
So thanks so much for joining in the.
Oh , you very welcome and thank you .
Thank you very much for for all the well wishes .
I certainly hope that history and results will educate favourably for the intentions of the efforts that I started working.
Indeed , indeed , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from garbage , thanks also to TOM shortage for his partnership in producing this program .
For more information about christian michael bakery , the program is he and his colleagues in the biological technology is opposed to run in the many other breakthrough technologies .