Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight with operation .
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt that offends advanced research has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA .
A window until dark is core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan a motto .
And I am your doctor host today .
I am pleased to be talking with alexander wallen , a program manager since twenty seventeen in the technical technology , obviously , we are recording our conversations from our respective locations to comply with company restrictions , because we are not in a recording studio .
You might hear everything , sounds like traffic and birds .
And as it so happens , insect noises from this year's brood of seventeen years occasions , which are just everywhere here in my location , alzheimer's agenda , as he is more often known , brought it up , but his interests in developing and demonstrating advanced aircraft , rapid design and prototyping for moving concepts as quickly as possible to operational practicality are also parts of his modest surrounding zenda has had his hands on the challenge of a vertical landing and take off or vital technology and demos of later than aircraft are capable of being navigable and having extended flight at stratospheric altitudes of eleven twelve miles and above that , we have a lot of time .
His main programmatic focus today is with the program known as queen , short for control of revolutionary aircraft , with novel effects .
Before joining japan's team of program managers , zander searched for twenty two years as an officer in the air force , beginning a nineteen ninety five and stretching all the way to twenty seventeen when he began his diaper years just before joining garbage .
Peter is the program manager at the research library , oversaw bright technology portfolio over seventy projects designed for transition to the war fighter .
He also helped positions in the f thirty five joint program office and the combined joint task force parliament , which between two thousand and five and twenty thirteen , helped manage the threat of improvised explosive devices in the war in afghanistan .
He also worked in the office of the assistant secretary of the air force for , and that he will tell you later , he has had quite the adventurer and getting close up looks at aircraft of other nations , including china .
Zenda , has four degrees .
Three of them are in ironic engineering , including a doctor of engineering degree from george washington university .
His first degree is an NBA from the university of massachusetts .
One more thing , zander is a new father with a ten week old baby girl , alexander valley , though I shall call you zander from here on out .
Thank you for joining me in this discussion and a huge congratulations on your new baby gear .
Well , thank you very much .
It's great via the end before we talk about your technology development work at the dark .
But I would like to get some sense of how you became the sort of person ends up as a program manager .
I can tell from your three aeronautical engineering degrees that flying technologies were on your mind by the time you are under graduate of the university and soda , what can you tell me about the influences in your a weather at home or at school ?
And I just think you had met towards that LED to the interest.
Well , thank you that a degree question .
I think I combine this by my father .
So growing up every year , my father's pilots and my three sisters and my brother and the car , when we go to the chicago air and water show and watch the blue angels of thunder bird and watch all the airplanes .
My lesson about the time I was in faith , greater and beyond the only gifts I wanted for christmas on my birthday .
War in cycle , pedia is a military airplanes , so I have always been interested in flight .
My family to take me to go watch the world's land at the local air power when they do fly over the air shows .
And so I really inherited from him a lot of their planes as I graduated high school in the college , I knew I wanted to be an engineer .
And so I just put those two together and starting aircraft and flag in that sort of thing sense.
Now you're doing your education .
You also added in a masters in business administration .
I'm assuming that this is a clue to what you can have had in mind for the wrong holidays , and what you want to do professionally.
As a young officer near force of managing road to be small programs , and I noticed my counterparts and industry , I was always interested in the technology .
But there are all these other concerns that had managed budgets that manage people they had worry about .
And so I actually wanted to understand that side of the business side of it of running a program .
And so I started my NBA and find out a lot of finance about the accounting aspect study economics , my spare time .
now .
So I got into an initially understanding the other side of the table as I was married in programs , and then turned out that I love that part of it as well , and I think it helped inform higher craft programs to the contractor , understanding of what the contract are on .
What my counterpart in industry has to deal with above and beyond just the technology challenges.
When I saw that you had the NBAdegree with thinking , well , you know , that has got to be really hopeful in your world .
Adopt , because in sort of best , i've got no program managers and what that role is emitted is like you're running in a corporate energy of full fledged corporately , where the kinds of issues of just running businesses and staying on budget , and all of the logistics of that are particularly , it's not just finding people who do cool technology , but it's also managing all that .
So the NBA just seems like a perfect addition to the technical training.
I think it is , and also thinks like market research and marketing now is one thing to , I have a great idea , but developers sell it and get people excited about it and market research .
Understanding what else is going on and how you fit into a new weapon or a interesting piece technology to lose the type of things that I strive to learn , as well as the UMS.
And I think i've tried to cooperate that background projects.
So now let's move to your dark adventure .
And I always love to hear the how I got to double a story .
I guess that of almost all of the program managers that have spoken with for this particle .
So let me ask you mean that you seek out a job , a doctor , did someone a doctor seek ?
You will have to get here.
So little bit of boats .
So when I returned from afghanistan in two thousand and nine , it spent ten months corner influences opposed the device work .
We are feeling new technology with long hours with tiring .
It was exciting , and it went back to my old job in the penalty after about a month and went to my boss and said , this job is a learn easier than I remember .
Do you have anything tougher ?
And he just got a call from double looking for a deputy program manager , and so I set up an interview .
And it turns out that david interviews there was a snowstorm .
I have to leave six blocks away from dark at the time .
So I watched six plus in a snowstorm to do an interview with the TTOoffice director .
And at the time it was , I was in interviewer for , but I was excited , and so I ended up being a deputy program manager for two years at the dark of duty transition when the work's mother for assignments finished on my career .
But from that point four , I knew that we want to come back .
So I had the opportunity to reach , in a view as a civilian and get higher line in twenty seventeen after my first dynamic.
Thanks for letting me know about that entry and into the agency .
Love the detail with the snowstorm .
So in twenty seventeen , as you just said , you joined darkness .
Tactical technology of now , more than any office that offers developed technologies that move in a way around the ground and see in the air space .
And in one of the now completed programs you work on .
So let's talk about the past a little bit first before we talk about cream .
You can't program that wants coffee adaptable later than aircraft program or autumn , and it did get some attention at twenty nine team when people across the country war crawling their necks , it and reporting strange white dots high overhead .
The agency posted on facebook in late june of that year , twenty one thousand nine hundred and three test balloons have been to navigate from eastern cross country beginning cabinet maryland , and then ended with safe landings in northern california .
So can you prefer to explain the technology you need that altered was designed to meet and and tell me what you can't about what is achieved in the autumn , piling questions , and you are also interested what you were thinking when mere reports were coming in from around the country about these sightings .
Weight , let's start actually with what the program you know , was about , and what technology needs , you would hope it would deliver .
And then what is it sad is now?
Right to these variety of programming , I was , I was lucky enough to inherit that .
So previous program manager has started that .
And as what is the deputy for a few months and took their program over and what we are trying to do , there is doing a low cost strategic vehicle .
So strategist theoretically , above sixty thousand feet , there are big advantages of you going to get a flying vehicle up there .
Commercial airliners don't fly up there .
And as he gave from sixty to seventy nine thousand feet , you get a good to view a lot of the earth from up there .
So it , we call them suitor , satellites or suitor .
late.
This , for context , were , were probably talking here eleven , twelve miles and above , right?
Absolutely , yes , until the air is very thin upturn it , you build .
These are lighter than their vehicles , almost more like a spacecraft , and you do an aircraft is there is , i'm so for a low cost in the occasion , processing , navigation and timing and a low cost of surveillance platform that was very appealing to the military .
So we , we did this program , and we actually did a test flight about a year before that that graduates , an exercise or full cross country for that flight .
We flew out of utah smaller port enough .
The volunteer going to laugh , and we are taking pictures , and we began to notice that the brand and we appear and disappear based on the song , and there are very large vehicles , hundreds of feet across , but they're very far away .
So it's very disorienting .
And the copy engineers and I looked at each other and said , dramatically , think that you , so we sort of suspect those gonna happen .
So we were very trying to be very forthcoming .
We , we felt with the FA.
We did social media post thing we're gonna do .
And the really , the only bet was how far across the country wouldn't get before the first you are so excited .
I think we made it on the way that they know how before we get our first .
You'll so , so that was fun , but we actually participate in with the army , and that we are ground units to communication exercises while we are gone over the us .
And we are specific points we are navigating from a military technology .
I think we demonstrate a very low cost , reactive way to sort of supplement satellites and build a local network on western world world .
And you believe the flag constellation from one cotton it across .
So I think we are very successful in , and I know about the army in the navy to have activities that are building on our success and.
Great , so some chance of early degree of transition to potential and universe users .
That's always the trophy that dropped ones with its programs .
I wanted to well out just a bit more , because there is one very cool aspect of the , the technology that just wanted to hear a little bit more about .
That's just the navigation aspect , because of I recall one way that you achieve .
Navigation is by changing the of the balloons in order to take advantage of a university of different air currents and conditions at different attitudes .
And I write about that , and if so , just tell us a little bit more headache.
Yes , of the fundamental theory of why you can navigate with these balloons that the winds in the strategic fear are a very catholic and turbulent .
And so winds going one direction .
And at a few thousand fear bowler below , the letter began the other direction .
And so you know what they're doing , you can kind of you can change out to by moving , basically pumping air under the balloon .
And it , you can make it go up or down .
And we got zero mass because we are not actually changing .
The massive vehicle were bringing iran or venting it off .
And then the couple memory piece of advantage where you want to know the window .
So we are .
She also a windsor of sensor , the user laser actually measures the molecule movement of the air at seventy five thousand feet above the .
And to do that , we took a piece of technology that NASA demonstrated that way .
About fifteen hundred pounds and research for dinner or table and shrunk it down to something about the size of a coffee can await fifty pounds .
And we demonstrated a low power satellite thief , lazier to connect three measure wins at three , five thousand feet and above , and the direction that you wanted to figure out if you wanted to assign to send , depending which direction you want to go.
Well , it's amazing to think about the vehicle that says that can remove her up and down in the atmosphere column to take advantage of different wind conditions as they , it's really , truly amazing .
Now , let's move onto another program .
You had worked on this one that had the goal of delivering an aircraft prototype capable of vehicle that is worker takeoff and landing , like it has never been done before .
They know what were you hoping to achieve this program?
Great question .
So we actually had a program called vital eggs or lightning strike that was supposed to be a high speed vertical take off learning aircraft and by high speed three hundred and three hundred and fifty nine , which is about one hundred and fifty , if it is not faster than a helicopter or something like AVtwenty two top roller at the end of the day , that program ended up not going to fly .
We ran into the challenges with electoral higher proportion and an enlightener that actually got a lot of active investment in both commercial government said , I think we , we advanced it to allow you a fair amount of that program , but that's a , that's a great example of a program that didn't end up complaining international media machine , but we actually discovered where the technology needed to events , and we spend the and work with industry to , to push some of the generator technology and some of the , some of the underlying technology that would enable that kind of aircraft in the future .
So , so we continue to work with folks and support the air force in their journey , prime and ever , but high speed fixed wing combines all the attributes like a helicopter , the efficiency of a traditional aircraft , and that's still something that there is altha to go do .
And so we advanced some of the technology , but a legendary was still most of our configuration of what technologies have to mature before already for leaving capability.
Right , and you know what I love to buy your description .
There was that it really is touch upon one of the signature aspects of the dark , but model , which is to take on extremely challenging a technology problems with the hope , you know , that you actually will get to the technology , finish line the generation ahead of time , but also with the understanding that if you don't , you learn all along the way that there is a value to that , and that helps you point in the direction or point away from what others be .
That is so that in the end , it helps to work in accelerate a technology vision to to a good finish line .
Let me know there when on your current program , queen , control of revolutionary aircraft with novel effectives .
In july , the agency and asked the first three words in the program .
And i'm gonna , let you talk about what I think .
In short , the idea is a ploy was called active flow control , such that one can seal an aircraft without the need of movable services .
Tell us the story of the queen program , the problem , need or capability that you invasion it will address .
And what is the set of the program?
When I was starting the cream program and installing it through my leadership , I used the example of an episode five versus award award aircraft .
And I said he took an error in automatic engineer from one thousand nine hundred and forty and seventy five .
He could do all the equations and tell you how to how far the move detail left , right , the rotters , how we control aeroplanes are not fundamentally changed in over one hundred years .
Now that engineer from nineteen fourteen would have no idea how the challenge and work you were understand , right , are in their .
But fundamentally , we are still designing airplanes the same way we did one hundred years ago , and that's by moving little bit of air foil open down or left and right , and that works pretty well .
But what you find is from a design .
It really limits your imagination .
And and so what we wanted to do with crane was take a technology in this case at the flow control , just basically blowing little bit of air over the wind as strategic locations , and that technology between the wire , but in wind tunnels and bring an academy for over thirty years , we wanted to create program that the aircraft designers to think differently and to work on the tools and the methodology to develop new and other ideas and give them the time space to do that .
And so that's what we try to do on crane is , is really given the designers the freedom to think outside the box .
And in one of the ways we did that , as we specifically said at the beginning of the program , don't come to us with an idea what they are planned look like .
We've been the first year doing experiments doing when tunnels doing high power computing , we want to examine in dozens of different ideas , and then , as a group , decide what's the most compelling .
Dama , what should the airplane look like ?
And I , that was unusual .
I had a bit of my leadership to give me more time of friend .
And I said , if we go slow in the beginning , we'll get in much better product , middle faster .
the.
Zenda , so you are really just getting these programs momentum going , and it sounds like it said , the first years can be really gathering IDyes , then bring the teams together , performers together to think about what would be the good next steps it takes .
But as you just sort of game out , the entire program is dramatically what you expect will happen , how to learn for.
Right , let us get a great question .
So what about a year in the program that we're eleven months , and we've had three contractors who have started with over dozen different ideas and concepts of water prices should look like we have spent for last to eleven months doing winter and testing to on high park computing , building brand new tools , and in kind of working as a team to develop this new revolutionary concept of over the next month or so , we're going to start downstairs selecting to one or two ideas , and those who were going from what we are crawling , which we call face zero interface one .
And that is what will actually do the off the flying air vehicle will start doing , drawing your identify subsidies , and then you start to get an idea really of what is your look like , and what demonstrated .
And the things were going to demonstrate us .
We think , with this technology , we can make our plans to lighter .
We can potentially do new interesting and manufacturers , and that we can be changed the way we design them and the way they look , but we can actually show improvements and weight and range and take off capability by thinking outside the box and applying this new technology .
And so what will do that ?
And then , from there were plenty downstairs , single airplane , and they will do that detail .
Design will start construction , and then in three to four years , we actually have flying prototype out of flying in demonstrating some these breathers.
Yeah , you know , this is also reminding me a little bit of hydrodynamics may be air dynamics in nature a little bit , you know of thinking of things like the like sharks .
Can I do that has these little denticles , you know , which are all the best throwing eddie flows and turbulence in a sort of thing .
It makes the shark much more efficient .
Swimmer , biological analogies that some of your performers are bringing into the next.
Yeah , so that's really interesting , because that's one of the one of the things you find earlier on is early in aviation .
We try to mimic birds .
And it was until the right brother's basically broke out proportion suffered from lift that we are able to keep flight and then over the best hundred years where we found is that the projects , you know what they're doing , because they , they can very small changes to the wings , especially storing bird .
We've ever watched hawker eagle .
It are very slight changes .
They can begin to great removals with very , and so we have actually got some concepts that sort of borrow , that idea that that , rather than brute force , you're using big pieces of metal moving up .
But if you effectively just change the way the error appears , you'll make little changes .
The error you can , you can remove .
And what I call more elegant manner .
And so it's go from where we started trying to mimic birds to actually getting back to worry about the technology that computing resources actually model how to do that , because it is much more challenging when you try to try to do that , anyone would think , but there are really energies to the way nature is above that the wrong and how actually be able to sort of.
Okay , just a couple of more questions , and then I will bring our discussion as it were in for lending .
Forgive me with that .
I'm asked to sort of imagining little , and they're forgiving me for that too .
But several decades ago , and you're going to do , these are shows , and you probably screaming things like , well , that's cool to your dad .
And now here you are a dark or manager .
I'm in a seriously cool tech .
She obviously thinks it could have some value in the context of defence , but in a serious idea of a new way of producing or creating navigation .
And but when you allow yourself to sort of imagine the coolest technologies that you dreamt about , even if they're not double related with what comes to mind , like what kind of error and article technologies have you dropped ?
You wish could be so , but not.
For me personally , the most exciting thing out there , the thing that we've all been promised are where our jet packs rate .
And so we actually did a good approval , and we have a small business initiative to look at it will be called battlefield personal mobility .
So the idea is , if I am a soldier , and I want to move five or ten miles is a way I can do that without being and point to point to the air .
And so we're gonna do several smaller words to look at some innovative things to include quiet paragraphers , personal level , helicopters and potentially some version of jet packs in a military context to say , if I need to move five or ten miles , can soldiers get off the road to get a get away from large vehicles and move around freely , so that sort of a really exciting thing and innocent technology .
Let's just now emerging that might make that more practical .
We got a lot of work .
Batteries regard the rebecca is now quite capital or drowned .
Yellow things can scale up , potentially to be something that men portable and transport , so still not there .
But I think if you can do the personal mobility where you basically carry your own little vehicle and are able to move around five or ten miles .
I think that it's a really exciting kind of opportunity to be.
Well , that gets it just well for me , because you know , the jet pack comes up even in a lot of correspondence with dark .
But let's start like , okay , you can do it .
You can do it .
What about the jet pack ?
So as entrepreneur helping to deliver the jet pack , I think your name will go down quite well in the history of dark a party , the history of technology of general .
So may you succeed in helping to deliver the jet pack , shifting direction just a bit .
I'd like to ask you to reflect on your experience as a dark program manager in a place of darker , which is so notable in the overall innovation ecosystem .
And this is kind of an interesting time to ask the question , because there is just tons and tons of discussion , both domestically and in other countries , about trying to emulate dolphin , whether it's an immune energy and intelligence , they are already even in the permanent transportation .
There is a proposal now to create a transportation eccentric arab event research project agency .
So i'm just wondering your opinion , what are some of the institutional and cultural characteristics of that you , we'll be most challenging for others to emulate , replicate.
I am working that i've had the opportunity or adopt work a couple of projects with foreign governments on funding nations who are talking about sending throne garbage .
And they often ask the same elizabeth two things , at least that i've seen that are that are really enabling and motivating the first as poor managers , we know , are a short time when it , typically two to five years , we have to start a project in and get moving in and really do do exciting work .
And then after that , we're going to be basically thinking , have to go find another job in a summer on comment .
And so what that means is one you very motivated to take an idea or find it , and make sure you really ready to go , and you can execute in the time fashion .
And the second thing is to more complicated project , and it's going to take a little blanker .
You really are motivated to to make sure that it turns out footing because the person coming next week behind you to take that program over may not love it as much as you love it right to the gatsby is gonna be compelling and scattered .
Besides a technically the method to release in the second , I think , enabled and seeing the dark it does is one out of free the face .
Well , I was not afraid to basically stop program weight , weight through and say , you know what this was harder than we thought .
Let's take a step back , and when I stop doing this , maybe think about a better way to do it .
And I think we do that in TTOAfair amount of wealth , our big successes .
And so we're willing to to invest in things that that we think are disruptive and wealth willing to take changes that mean that panel , and that's a lot easier said than done and being willing to fail , and knowing that you will be looked as a failure if the program runs in the technology issues that is success .
That you've discovered a new technology , road work.
Thanks for sharing some of your insights and observations about the innovation culture at DARPA , especially like the way to describe the positive value of the agency EX from , you know , both delivering an original technology vision , but also from discovering road blocks that still must be overcome , you know , to reach the finish line .
So very cool about that .
And now , before we do close , I do monitor .
Just we visit a little bit your air force korea before coming to durban .
Can you share a little more about?
Sure , I was in your first officer for twenty two years , primarily engineering focused .
I had a relevant opportunity as my first assignment .
I was sent to the national air and space intelligence center .
And where's a chinese fighter aircraft hour ?
So I got to look at four new aircraft and try to deduce their capabilities and have the opportunity as secondary tenant to attend the first error , chinese public aerial and nineteen ninety six , and that's received a deal that I let you know before I love their planes , and so I got it to look at four aircraft , and they move over and worked at one seventeen .
B two has the opportunity to die during electronics when we lost in the first seventeen got to participate and figure out why that happened and how to avoid .
Since that had the opportunity work on a lot of fixed rain aircraft , some special mission things , and one of the things I think , therefore , is really offered in an opportunity is , I got a new job every three or four years , and I got to take new challenges and work a variety of programs in a variety of the and try to take all of that background , knowledge and pilot into this four year to our doubt , to figure out what went well .
It doesn't go well and where the gaps are capability , so had a great opportunity in their first day .
They gave me a lot of opportunity every three or four years to get a brand new , challenging job , and that's when I think that exciting your bookstore poses , it's very similar .
You got a very fixed window , you got a clear authorities .
Did you take the backing of your boss near your total go ?
Do something amazing.
That would be a great conversation .
You have taken my imagination or laughed .
Thank you so much.
For sharing the time with me , or it's been a pleasure , and there's a few things in life .
I like talking about more than my programs or my new baby girls .
Thank you for the opportunity.
Well , the best of luck to you in your wife and raising this new life you brought into the world .
And I also want to thank you listeners for learning us your ears .
I hope you join it again for the next Voices from the other , thanks .
Also , the time shortage for his partnership , introducing this program , for more information about alexander valley programs , he and his colleagues in the technical technology officer TTO, run in the many other way through technologies dark is working on visit , dark adult mill .