Step of technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are totally missed.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defense advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window on the dark as core of program managers , their job to weed , fine , what is possible , my name is ivan , a motto on your darker host .
And today , and please help with me in the studio , ray waggish , a program manager since early twenty sixteen in darkness , biological technology office renewed her bachelor and doctor degrees in the field of applied biology from the georgia institute of technology and and did post doctor work in molecular biology in hyderabad , germany , as an alexander wang hamburg , fellow , a strategic research driver for her is to apply tools of synthetic biology , which draws from genetic engineering , relax kelly , biology and other runners to support biosecurity and to outpace infectious disease prior to joining doctor as a program manager .
When I was a singer , lead by our technology at buzz alan hamilton , where she LED a team that provided scientific , instituted support in the areas of biodefense biosecurity , disruptive technologies , emerging infectious diseases and neuromodulation and synthetic biology to DARPA and other federal and private institutions should also let research development teams in the biotech industry that focused on the development of a municipal essays and other tools from regular biology and disease diagnostics .
Read it is my pleasure to have you in the studio today .
Thank you .
I will be here .
Let's start with how you got interested in science and technology .
What was was your teacher that transforms you to turn you on the size ?
Did you come from a scientific?
What was it ?
It's hardly to think of a time when I, Ididn't have science in mind , even from a very young age so growing up .
And in florida , we'll attack access to little quitters on the beach shore and little quicks in our backyard that we would play with .
And my sister , who is her , namely soft , she's eleven years older than me , had a career that was really unintroduced to be a scientist until later in life , she switched to be a lawyer .
But in the early days , I got to go to lab with her and can see what that world look like that , that coming really interested in .
So from a very early age in high school , I was a lab assistant to one of the teachers were helped him and bomb simultaneous that we would disappear in classes .
I think I was very elementary school and high school , and then going into college and beyond .
They always had opportunities to be really handsome with the sciences to understand and what types of science I really liked in in what I didn't like .
And I remember in in high school , one of our teachers will take us to it was , I think it was a limestone mine in in florida , where they would pump out a dirt and rocks from really deep into the earth .
And there is many fossils masted on teeth and things like this that you could find not really had an impression on me , because that's where it I first started to learn about evolution , and in an authoritarian school , I didn't take the opportunities to work in the laboratory as an undergraduate .
I draw the technique back to do on APC, because I really heard about it .
You're in half.
And right , and just in for listeners who have never seen and mastered on two , that actually have , I mean , they're like the size of your racist .
They're amazing things to see , obviously for you .
And when I look at your degrees , both of them are an applied biology , which is to say your bachelor degree and your peach design of these masses around the world , but both in the polite biology would tells me that from a very early age , you were looking at biology as technology , perhaps .
So , how did that really inside come to?
It is interesting with it to think about it .
I hadn't thought about it that way , but I did always see biology as a tool and a tool to understand in the world around us , and later than an university .
It's a total understanding the disease and then be integrated , actually , even with a person moving into the medical device world .
The metro detectives in one of the early classes that was working with the bio engineers , they were just launching a bioengineering program at door to tax pack .
So it was really interesting for me to interact with .
The engineers would actually build the device based on things like soiler mechanics and fluid extent .
And that was pretty mind boggling to me that that you could take that information and and actually turned into a device to improve people's lives.
So for some years , he worked as a contractor with booze and hamilton , and the next company does a lot of work with government agencies , including drupa .
Is that actually how you got to no double?
No , actually , I got to know double when I was working about technology appeared in roughly measurement and the sea of a small company I will take out at life .
This is where we are developing diagnostics for neurogenetic diseases based on on protein misflown and indicators of disease and the sea of that company out in route of used to be a dark or program manager .
And and I had not heard about dark before meeting allen , so sometimes ever launched her just casually , he would talk about this magical police called dark at where it really seems that you can have A, A, Awild idea in his hands .
You had a great technical plan to make it happen .
There could be a password to try to implement that in the more I learned about double , the more I really got interested in .
And when I was looking for the next step in my career , I wouldn't knowing , I just asked him , what , what do you think could be something that would be good for me .
I like the piece of a of the start of environment , but jobs quality would be a little bit .
Banger turned up .
Security would would be eventually .
So he suggested that that I looked into different types of contracting and consulting agencies around the DCarea to support agencies like dark buzz of these multiple arbitrated agency's .
And in , luckily , I just found a great position with , with bills , and for quite a few as a theater , not only at DARPA , but other other places like I opened the intelligence advanced research project activity and the billionaire foundation is , well , it helps them with some other early grand challenges.
Right , and you use a little government speaking there , which is seater , but I wanna learn every second that stands for scientific engineering , technical adviser , that's right .
That's actually what we hear , what around here .
There are more seaters here than there are program managers .
You are now a program manager .
So , so you vaccinate one , both heads , and I want to be going to talk a little bit about those two categories of employees here , the theater and the program manager.
As you just mentioned there , there are two categories of employees here .
There is the government employee , which is the program manager and other supporting staff .
And in the theaters .
And we are like to describe that model too to focus in biology , especially their familiar with having APIin the lab and on people that work with them to , to support the distribution by a principal in the laboratory .
They and they have a supporting staff of they could be great students .
They could be umbrella scientists too to help them implement division of that PIand daughter to me that the program manager in sydney roles is very much along those lines .
The program managers responsible for for the vision of the programming in the direction forward in the sea , the team serves various roles .
They can provide technical content .
That's complimentary to the program manager .
They may have strategic guidance .
They may have deep , dark experience , because often times I see the maybe here for for many years longer than than a program manager , who , of course , were here for these short term appointments.
Let's now start getting to your double life a little bit .
Twenty sixteen .
You became a program manager at that time .
You inherited one program called living foundations , which is about engineering the exquisite control that living cells have overtake items and molecules , but in the , in the case for technology , glenn , such as new materials , industrial chemicals from the soda goals and agricultural products .
And then you develop the program called safe genes , which are able to get through the very difficult and approval process here .
And this is all that developing a tool kit to rain limit and even reverse some of the emerging extremely powerful tools and genetics and genomics , and recognizing , I want you to talk about those .
But before we do that , I just want to hear a little bit about how you think biology , because as we look at some of these tools and will talk about them a little bit like christopher last night to meet the sort of more reckless little nanoscale machines .
And it makes me in a sort of look at life with a kind of reference .
And oh , I don't mean to lead you .
that's nice to me , but talking about how you view biology on the sort of molecular 貂蝉。
And even higher skills , the way I think about biology is really from an employed approach in india has a lot to do is , I think , having been brought up scientifically at at the door , detached , always immersed in donald's biology , but surrounded with engineering when I looked at biological system .
I think about how that system can be manipulated in a program of a way looking at some of the tools that since that a biology brings to us , or in a medicine , lake christopher last night , which is christopher , is one of the big circumstances for cluster regularly interspaced short palestinian repeats what this protein dozens is really interesting .
It , the organs are .
It was about to empty system effectively where fade virus would insert its DNA into a bacteria that period .
Victory would would cut up that DNA using christmas systems and take little pieces of that page to the name and put it into its own genome as a memory of that infections , so that if that virus came back again to infect that cell phone , I would say , oh , hey , I have this information that i've seen this before .
I can now neutralize it .
So bacon to any tool of what researchers generate downtown and others recognize , you can actually program what casteno recognizes .
It doesn't have to be a page , but you can provide it with cash on the information to say , okay , go after the specific piece of DNA was very powerful .
I like what I like to think of from the darker perspective as a spotted moment in biology .
So we had a lot of innovation in DNA sequencing and sympathies .
You could look over the decades that we kept improving .
That technology is very power , but all of us , suddenly , we had a tool to be able to edit that DNA , and that that really has changed a lot in the field .
Nowadays , there is very few organisms that can be added.
I love the spotted moment , partly because when you look at some failures , when one is name tea four , they look like a little spacecraft , right ?
So this is where proposal , maybe new.
That's right .
Yeah , there is even microsatellites in DNA sometimes .
So , but for me , that was created an urgency for this new tool in biology that that I think makes that national security connection for.
So let's let's talk about the two programs .
We'll start with one that you can have living .
Founders tell me little bit about the history that in its.
Sir , so that original program manager who launched that affected li xie jackson .
She had to start to create a tool bed where we could disturb biology to an engineering practice like the design and build test , learns psychological engineering and apply that to a biological system like a microbes in ecology or a east or other type of activities to make products and molecules that would be a value .
And I really think that her inspiration came from looking at biology as this incredible system that could make a real diversity of molecules that extends well beyond what we can make traditional manufacturing and chemical processes .
So when you have access to that diversity of biology , can you start to manipulate that to make new pot molecules , things that have never been made before by biology , which is the most ambitious scores of the program .
So her foundation of investments really created the tools under each one of those categories that design tools that you can quickly and admitted weight , design and violence that it partly distributes together to put into a microwave build .
So this is the DNA sympathizing and an insertion of DNA into a testing .
This is the the mass background , a tree and other measurement tools to look at the products being made and importantly learning .
So this is some of the designs you make are not going to work and program that into your learning cycle .
That design makes a better design next time is really important .
So when I took over the program , the living founders , one thousand molecules program was just taking off the first phase of the program was to build those individual components .
And now the second phase is to really integrate them as a platform to create this foundery type capability that the us , military or or customer , a business customer , could go to a foundery , and so I would like you to make the smaller kill , can you the boss , and that perfect and organism to do it ?
So the ultimate demonstration of that capability , that founder capability is to make one thousand unique molecules , and we're five hundred fifty one molecules .
And so our teams , which are among the summer then , and MITburden situation they collectively.
Maybe five hundred and fifty one million kids , can you just give a listener to the sense of the.
The kinds of murray , the kinds of molecules , so they're very diverse .
They can be anything from it .
He saves the coding to a paint .
You might want to put on the crafted all the way to a small molecule from citizens that they could be used for medicines , cannabis , cancer treatments .
You , you name at the whole guarantee of small molecules being developed under that program , and not , we're about two years into for your program .
The final two years is going to prioritize the small subset of those molecules have been produced .
There are very compelling that we like to scale up .
So , so far , we made pretty much detectable amounts , meaning in a very small amount of each one of those molecules , and we like to move to the kilogram level so that this , they're not testable amounts that we can really improve it in larger experiments and testing.
Yeah , absolutely exciting area .
I mean , you just think about biology .
I think of things like a circular foreigner .
And amazon forests mean the the diversity of creatures .
And then all of the tissues that they are made of all the materials they are made of hormones and narrow transmitters .
All these , these powerful kinds .
Since his commander biology , and now he'll bring a different mind set .
But with that same kind of context of sentences.
Kind of an exciting area .
I think they're a great point at that .
You mentioned that biological diversity across the globe , because of many of the teams are doing are , are looking at extreme environment across the global , looking at microbes , looking at plants , even looking at some human animals .
And you can stitch those together a plan and some human and some extremely file microwave enzyme altogether in a , in a worker's organization in the laboratory to make that .
So it is , this program is very much dependent , logical diversity and looking at the enzymes that that can be detected in the wild , doing their normal jobs that they do in the world , that we repurpose them in the.
Tonight , so you also leverage the way evolution has pushed biology to be innovative initiative in its biological context , sort of seeing where you might find useful things .
There were then even further with human technology .
Yeah , so then let's go to safety .
And this is , this was your first baby here , right ?
So talk to us about about that , the origin of in your mind , and what the status of that program is now sure , so.
Sixteenth is a program that that's the program I came to double to to run in for the listeners that they don't know the way that programmers to adopt adopt , is it ?
It is very grassroots type of process where comes from , the program manager , an initial idea or concept that we can bring to our leadership into the director of dark that gets developed and into into a program .
So I came to dark with the idea too , really try to harness the beneficient use of general medical technologies like christopher , kazakhstan , but to prevent their potential for misuse .
So at this point , these tools have really been , it's arguable that probably every military biology love in the world has access cities , tools and is using these tools .
So the genius out of the bottle is out there , and there's a lot of power in these tools for editing genomes .
And and we can do a lot of really tremendous goods with these tools , but their potential for misuse , potential .
Israel vulnerability that the vulnerability that came to the agency to try to address nearly the ability to control editing activity .
If you want to use it in a given system to limit it , only for using that system to counter it at the start of the sixteenth program , there was no cannon measure available , meaning no inhibitor of a genome data that could shut down if it's activity , if it should accidentally be misused , or or in more militia's misuse .
And then if it changes made , how can we restore a dinner back to its baseline state to remediate , any technology , natural changes may be unwanted.
Yeah , it's a remarkable set of tools .
One of them that I heard you talk about reminds me of the kilometre , which takes up how many times the sale has is replicated in this only so many times that cell can do that .
It dies off .
It sounds me like you , something like that , you , that you are your performers .
And by that , I mean , the research groups that did them have contracts under the safety in the program that they might be working on some similar mechanism to limit a genetically edited .
So it's just how long it can be out there.
So that that would definitely be under the category of a controller that that were developing , and we do have some generation counters .
So one thing that I haven't mentioned as a the , there's drivers divisive tools that are major gentlemen drives .
And this is one of the most powerful uses of these technologies , because what team drives do buyers , the outcomes of inheritance , where when momenta gets together , you normally have a fifty fifty chance of a gym in an offspring coming from mom or dad , but through a gene drive , when you couple a general trade with a genome of editor that can force its inheritance to new york hundred percent efficiency .
And so when you can buy ACoutcome to levels that are about that , reach up two hundred percent , you want to be able to have a way to control that if you don't want that spirit of that trade to go on in perpetuity , and so one way you could do that is through a generation counter that if you want to keep it , something like a gene drive local , you may say , okay , after after five generations and reproductive cycles , this can shut down .
So these are some of the technologies were starting to explore.
Right , so clearly you , you are sick in an area of powerful biological technologies , and you know , some of those who were being in from the beginning of i'm thinking here of general doubt who has been in on this from the beginning .
And so she's written a book that I read recently .
And when you read that she is both , you told me and thinking about the power of it , tools like a christopher cast nine in during all kinds of diseases and doing all kinds of good things .
But she is at some point in the books should disturb in you are in the middle of this is when you go , go out to conferences , the promise and the period of these technologies are always part of that discussion .
How are you thinking about that ?
Someone who is in a position direct to some degree , how this research goes?
So somebody's once described me as surprisingly upbeat for someone working on genetic and national security .
But I am really excited about the promise of these tools , not only for addressing inherited negative disorders , but the potential for use of these tools to eliminate infectious disease in a way that superior to our current cannon measures that we use and poor to the opportunity to be able to test those tools .
I think there is a lot to be set for for biodiversity as well in terms of a tool .
Legacy drive is going to have the face of natural about diversity .
A perfect gene drive would only work in a system where an organization of gina is identical all the way across the globe , and that that just doesn't exist in any system .
So I think , in reality , some of the potential for missions .
So these tools is actually going to be very intelligent to achieve .
And as long as we are addressing those risks that while we develop the benefits and use technologies , I think we could be on a good , safe course for.
When you think about the work that you are doing now in the biological technologies oppose in dark as an institution , what you say about dark is place in the overall innovation ecosystem , because you're brought in a number of parts of adequate systems .
So I think you might be interested in.
Having been a dark , and now , in some capacity for about eight years , I can absolutely say darker is is leading agent .
It's a place where you learn about new technologies , new ideas .
We , we have people from industry , from academia , reject to us all the time with , with new concepts .
So I do feel that is a special place where we have really access to these technologies are at least information about these technologies and really responsibility to to look at them and understand .
You know , how could these tools be used for good , use for bad , and and really be ready for it to address both of those in an appropriate weight way?
Yeah , when you think about tools like christopher last night , you spoke about this tool within the context of the programs you working on .
But when you think maybe the best application that you could imagine.
On the one , ha ha , what comes to mind , they entered that question , probably barriers , depending on who you are speaking with .
So had the opportunity to be in meetings with patient advocates for a number of inherent genetic disorders and the ability to create a theoretical for in a doubt individual who has suffered long term from a disease , I think , is it incredibly exciting if we can do something to improve that individuals quality of life , there are desperate for those technologies .
And I think , here's an impact opportunity for a tool to do a lot of good .
So that's one of the things that most excited about , and many diseases that otherwise have no treatment options at all .
The religious treating symptoms , trying to make patients more more .
And the other is , of course , this is one of a lot of people points too far for team drives , but as the ability to eliminate on factors that that carry diseases , things like malaria or danger , or chicken gunnie , as we have more and more urgent diseases that are spread through through insect factors .
This is be an incredible tool to implement to to prevent the thirst.
To humans , right and again , now , where we're talking about such powerful technology , so we have been in the debate here has been in .
Do we get rid of the the mosquitoes at the factors that actually carry these things , which sounds on the surface to be , that sounds like a solution , but on either hand , and I think you talk about this yourself , we are talking about very complex ecological environment .
And so even though we think about mosquitoes is essentially bad , we don't know , we get rid of them.
What would that do ecologically ?
right ?
Yeah , and that's that something that we have to take a very serious close look out , because we could be opening up a new ecological needs , right if we eliminate one species of mosquito , and there are many pieces of mosquitos out there , right ?
So they say you can be inviting on a new mosquito to fill in that ecological niche and potentially bringing a different disease .
And so really , this is a safety , and this is a short term funding for four years .
There's no open release , but we want to start to develop text pads for these systems to understand how they behave over generations .
But I think of how this might work in the environment , in the ecosystem .
It will be answered in the next decade or next decades , until we can really understand how these systems are.
Behind it is , it's interesting .
I, Ioften think about the history of technology um as sort of the solution becomes the problem .
I'm thinking here , things like sea of secret , full carbons , which were a great solution to a refrigeration problem .
Early last century , people were dying from the refrigerants that were user that time .
See if seats come in .
They're not flammable , they're not toxic , and they become these wondering chemicals for that purpose , but then is there made a massive amount that the same stability makes them great , goes up to the strategic students to eat , so they become up the greek , one of the great team of williams , of the of the twentieth century .
When you think about biological technology and this contact , the solution could be , what are the problems that keep you?
But now what if you've got back to the dean drive examples that it is that written ?
What are the long term implications ?
And so this would be a dynamically modified organism released into the environment .
And if we have to be sure that we carefully consider how one might be useful , it's not going to be a silver bullet for every problem we , we shouldn't have fifty different types of mosquitoes engineered where dean drives , which can attend the space drunk type situation where we don't know how these individual and organizations will be interacting with each other .
What is the longer perfect in the environment ?
This is , I know , I know , I agree .
I don't think that a long term solution , and for , for me , part of the safety programming , and just the message that I like to get out there is to have that long term thinking in place where , in the evening , the initial designs of the experiments .
You know , what might this look like in ten years , twenty years , thirty years , well beyond the end of dark program , so we can build in some of those safety switches on early on the inception of technology.
It's hardening to me to know that you , as a program manager here , are thinking about both those provincials , the promise in the parallel of these powerful technologies , and it's going to be exciting to see where you take your existing programs and maybe some other ones that you get in the near future .
Ronnie , is there a question that you wish , I had asked , you wish some of your interviews for mother interviews in the past had asked you that I haven't .
And so you can ask it.
Even answered right now , you know , I one of the questions I, I, if people do , ask me , and I want to put a plug here for the item competitions .
This is the international genetically engineered machine competition .
This is a place where a lot of new researchers and individuals , amateurs interested in synthetic biology get .
This is a pretty low threshold way to get into a competition setting to say it .
What's something cool you can do with with engineering , biology and synthetic biology .
In the organizers of this competition have always , first and foremost , put biosafety and biosecurity as part of these programs .
Each of the teams of his young students is undergraduates , sometimes even high school students have to address safety and security in all of their designs .
And it wouldn't that be a great thing for every lab to be able to do one of the things i've loaded since being a program manager is that people are often blind to the potential misuse of their own technologies .
It takes somebody from the outside to be able to and see where , where those potential vulnerabilities are , not only for just the system of work in my break too well , this could actually become a problem .
You maintain biotechnology , becoming the problem .
I think if we had the really look objectively at each others work and try to identify those vulnerabilities in the immediate , the risk said that are represented .
I've been much more excited about apart forward by your technology.
Okay , well , I think we're about out of time .
So I just wanna thank you for being here .
There was an amazingly interesting discussion for me .
Thanks for sharing .
These stories about came to science .
And what's motivating you hear the program manager , so thanks for being here , thanks ivan's painter , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from urban , for more information about renewed wages in the programs she runs and the other breaks for technologies .