Soft technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand alternative operation technologies , a driver of our , since its founding in one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt that offended that research project agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to voices a window entitled with core of program managers .
Their job to redefine was possible .
My name is taiwan acquainted since two thousand and thirteen , i've been a program manager in darkness .
Defense science is office , and i'm your dark host .
Taylor , elected startup , which is sort of learning a little bit about you as a program manager .
So maybe you could tell us something about your background and how that relates to the kinds of programs you then developing .
And i've been a molecular day , I love molecules I have since I was in high school and even beyond high schools are earlier .
Yeah , i'm a server nova junky .
Because most billions and billions of stars .
Well , I was more interested in the billions of militaries i've always wanted to be an exploring , but the time I got the age , yeah , I might explore something all the year charted .
Plans have been charged , and there were no more uncharted planes .
So I looked at kind of frontiers that did .
Did you couldn't see and molecules fit that look more defined in physics , because you can put it in a bottle all at times , especially in the area that I am very comfortable in organic synthesis .
You can make stuff and insert .
You can test the properties , and you can play with the combination of items that are together .
And in really , it was sorted .
This palette that I could play with .
Then I really like that .
It was exploring the world in a totally different way , always been amazed that have just putting together items and certain geometries , certain bonding patterns and can come together in two materials with all kinds of different properties in a scheme and bonus at the crazy rate .
I mean , you go from having something they can buy to something that explodes to something that makes beautiful colors to something that makes your cookie smell great and taste great events , all chemistry , your molecules .
Guy , no , galaxy are not that many molecules .
People do your double , which is interesting .
So as a wrap of this minority , how are you taking that interesting in the form of programs in the defense scientist office , one of the things that is going on right now , one of the ziggy's is revolutionized .
How do we do science better , and one of the means that is interesting about chemistry , especially when we're talking about the makers , the people who make materials , make medicines .
It is especially slow process .
I really like the idea of reinventing scientists and in chemistry , there is a lot of opportunity to reinvent the science .
So I ask , when you say we invented science , maybe you mean the actual process that we were asking questions that we were trying to answer those questions .
Can you be a little more detailed about , what would you have ?
Men , chemistry is a tough subject .
We have lots of primaries that we don't often know how are controlling them , but if we did all of the chemistry in much more controlled environment , where the environment was being monitored , we might come up with much , much more reproducible chemistry , which will then mean it can be transportation .
So in other words , if I have a machine that is doing the chemical reaction , recording how it does the net code that record can be sent from one love to another , so you could accelerate the same way to the end .
Internet allows you to accelerate how information was transport , what if you could do that with molecules , tell you this might be a good time to talk a little bit about the two of the programs that you're working on , and what I have in mind is the full effect program , and they make it program .
So when we start with full effect , full effects , that's a program , it stands for a full , did non natural with biological function in the photo , fact , program were making polymers that meet natural polymers so that we might biotherapeutics moral bust .
So right now , if you get one of the more modern drugs right now , a good portion of them are made from proteins , and some people like it , I entire bodies .
So , for example , humana or installing those are examples of protein biotherapeutics .
The problems they are not heat stable .
And if something is in heat stable , it's not going to end up in a except .
So our soldiers are a very place , rather than to be most .
Bono's boomer don't have access to the most banks , medicines , as many of them are just gradual , and so we have to transport them back to an environment where you have refrigerators , you have a handling equipment that can allow you to control that the environment around the medicine .
What if you want to make an unnatural ?
There are lots of natural fibers that we used to use , and we've replaced them with non natural fivers , because they're more robust .
Do you mean like silk to ?
So what if he wanted to take the same ?
So the beneficial properties are yet from plastics , and you were emerging with the beneficial properties of the biological balloons , like proteins in DNA .
The full effect program that is a platform .
It's about how we make those in and how we discover them .
So in a way , if you think about all of the possible molecules that one could make the small ones , you know , like , like an aspirin or the below larger ones like these protein based medicines you're talking about , they're really sort of being infinitive to possibilities , like an infinite space that you could possibly search an example which you say here is your trying to develop some tools , even just a few people took to go explore some of the regions of this influenced space .
They just have not been looked at before .
I'm getting on my own track .
Oh , you're so on track .
It gets back to my whole desire to explore that .
I talked about , you know , but it is really about giving researchers a capability to be able to explore these , these universes .
It's almost like a hubble telescope for this particular galaxy or universal regular space .
So that was full of effects .
Young , i'm also interested in the makeup program .
Can you say little bit about what you're doing there make it is a platform technology for making small .
And in this particular case , we're trying to do is we're trying to democratize chemistry .
So what if you could have a system that biologists or any scientists came up and type , and the machine figured out how to make it , even if there was no recipe available so that the machine would figure out a possible set of ways to make something , and then we'll go about testing each one of those ways and tell it on the solution , and it would log that solution in a cloud or in its data bank .
And now that molecule could be made any time .
In addition , the system would also be able to have to make more of so that initially , I would do really small scale sympathies .
That means milligrams .
And then once it figured out a solution , it would also automatically scale it up .
Can you offer to us a concrete example ?
maybe you could think of a, 这个时候我们就可以看到这样的一种方式了。
在此之前也许会有很多不同的东西可能会有interacting with that the receptor in perhaps solving medical or other biological problem .
Yeah , you know , for example , one very popular target for the heart disease is PCSKnine .
And so there's probably many papers that come out every year .
They describe inhibitors that have been discovered against that target .
The structures are available .
Let's say that I am a researcher , and I want to study some aspect of a complex soil system and having access to the PC inhibitor would be really useful .
But maybe I wanted to selective in a certain way that is commercially available , but somebody is reported now , I might contact that researcher who is made it before .
Maybe they ran out , and it can take them three months to make it .
But if I have access to make it device , I could just go tie business structure and half the material , maybe the next day , or at the end of the week .
And in addition to that , I have it memorized .
The machine has kept that in his memory .
Banks , university environment , for example , wants to make that they typed it in a little bit out that day , because the solution would be , it's a way of saying chemistry has been documented since its inception , especially santa chemistry , through what a colleague experimental .
These are documents that the researcher is using to try to capture what they didn't .
A laboratory make something to write a dynamic recipe .
So a lot of times will leave out that we think are not necessary , but are necessary .
And sometimes we didn't even know there were necessary .
So when another researcher comes in and try to read that cookbook like a experimental , it might take the month to reproduce it , and it may never .
Why should we waste our human effort by not making sure that we document that outcome , that experiment in a way that can guarantee production .
So you're talking about capturing procedural knowledge .
Correct , yes , the magic system is not just the artificial intelligence system or a cloud system is archiving .
It's a machine that's doing the chemistry so that the machine will be reproducible .
You'll be able to recreate that machine in any love you want , as long as you replicate that machine faithfully , and it runs the routines that you recorded one lab versus another faithfully , you're going to reproduce chemistry everywhere you want to one of the things that I find fascinating about that , but is that it is perhaps unit in its place in the overall technology development ecosystem .
And as a program manager and someone who has been an academy , I think , also an industry .
And now here a doubt , can you talk to us a little bit about how darker might be playing some interesting or perhaps even unique roles in the overall technology ecosystem .
And yeah , it is a very exciting role .
Darker is that one place where we are thinking about innovation on constraint , like , where can we go ?
No , in my mind , the way remember doing that is because it fits our mission space .
If you want to create a prevent surprise , it's best to get to that new universe of chemistry sooner rather than later .
And so we take innovations from all of the other funding agencies .
In other words , they're seeding it , and we look for one away with the beginning , and we pushed hard and not across .
The fact just double is critical because we are structuring what I consider to be that christian investment , as we are trending towards something amazing , and the internet is an example , and I am really immunity net with , make it .
I want to create the internet of molecules .
How do you change for molecules from one place to another in the same way is a three day printing concept ?
You have a design .
You could put a design and a cloud .
And then if you have three printer , you could transfer that design from one place to .
So they are related .
And I have been no , constantly inspired by what dark has done .
Is there a question , tyler , that you wish I had asked you during the discussion that I didn't , even so ask the question yourself and answer , what's my favorite aspect of chemistry ?
The answer for most cameras ?
What , what's the answer for ?
Most cabinet cameras dive , and you know , I love that the structure of molecule relates to the function .
Now I love them .
Yeah , most of my friends media is for the crowd magnets .
I guess everybody likes explosions , but I actually like the smell of organic chemistry , so pretty much amongst all actors like people going to like one flavors are thinking of , maybe it omit chocolate cheap , but actually smelling all of the esters and wondering , I wonder if that's disaster , or that I strength and tell the fluctuations , and also an astronaut refers to a particular chemical motive .
If I recall of my own organization must be part of it .
There's a carbon with the oxygen job , abandon a few other things we don't have to go into the details , except to say that is a particular kind of molecular motivated and variations .
Yeah , classic compounds .
So I, Ireally like the class of compounds that are associated with flavourings , and I don't mean just not a natural flavorings and natural unnaturally a coconut .
It smells the way it does because of chemistry , and that that always just really makes me excited .
The teller I really enjoyed talking with you today about the your programs by chemistry , by dark .
So thanksgiving , you , I mean , it's always a pleasure to build you , and thanks for having me and really glad to relate my thoughts about chemistry and and thank you listeners for sharing this time with us .
Tony , next time for another voice from double.