Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on tournament technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , the defense advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window at the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is , I have a motto , and I am your daughter host today .
I am pleased to be talking with darker .
Michael fitty , a program manager .
Since defense sciences office , we're recording it our conversation from our respective homes as we do our part to slow the spread of coffee , nineteenth , the pandemic disease caused by the crown by a source .
Two is also what you might hear .
Some ambient sounds like trucks and sirens prior is coming to darbar mike , as it is most often known , was that the university of north carolina at challenger , where he was the founding director of the center for optical , electronic and optical communications , and director of the national science foundations , industry , slash university collaborative research center for materials , which are a class that interact with light in the darkness twice .
Michael urges PHDin physics from the university of london .
And I am just , so please , mike , to join me.
Well , thanks for the introduction .
I went unhappy to be here.
So I know like that your primary interest result in the many ways that , like other forms of electronic energy interact with the matter .
But before we get into those interests , i'd like to hear , how is that you became an interested in science , and ultimately , in particularly article based on oil.
As a kid , I used to play around with phenomenon magnifying in glasses , politician filters .
I was always interested in trying to understand why visible light that we could say would go through some materials like glass .
Oh no , others , I really just try to understand what the difference between the masses are the kid almost going on .
The allowed me to see through a piece of glass .
So I should chelsea causes when I went to college that focused on electric magnetics and light and scattering theory and.
Whether any particular influences that that really in a sort of got to go in , this is a job of fantastic professor , were you parents ?
Scientists have anything of that sort that that really steer you in the direction of a professional science?
Yeah , I think I have to say that my father was using the lazy from mom , very younger age men are away from home to join the navy .
Always had telescopes , and but not killers , are home and magnifying glasses .
I think I picked up he's enthusiasm for image , bringing , bringing scenes up close to inspect them more carefully.
Well , well , very interesting to hear that , and as you are saying that it also is images of the , the end of the sides of the sixteenth and seventy century came to mind because glass objects , you know , both in the form telescopes and microscopes really are kind of at the beginning of the scientific enterprise .
So as the epidemic , I am not quite at all myself , but it shows the connection .
So no , every program manager has a , how do I get to dark a story?
I love you for yours .
Okay , when IIhad some intellectual method of the years , and i've been talking to a program manager in d so who was starting a new very much in the area , which I was interested in being a possible performer .
So I am , I haven't come to the discovered the so day when he talked about it , met with the announced director at that.
我的手机。
And I just wanted to do that .
There are still being defense sciences of us were listening to that .
I could not.
Sorry , I did me with the director of the officer time , and she suggested I might like consider becoming a program management .
Since I had all these ideas that does not know what I could be funded to do , but maybe I could find others I could find to pursue them .
So I am very quickly at the meeting I attended was in june , june .
I think I started a couple of couple months later , september twenty.
You have executed large portfolio of program managers and letterpress by with six different programs , but they focus on really some rather amazing ideas .
And we'll get to this a little while me , one of them really catches my attention , or things like tapping into the energy of the vacuum , perhaps even my level for things like proportion without fuel .
As I said , we'll get that a little bit .
I am kind of interested in at the moment , a more strategic level of your thinking .
You have that informs already efforts in the programs that that you have ended up formulating and running .
Effectives said , and they love this line .
I am interested in electronic waves and their interaction with matter from DCto daylights .
So I think if you explain that to listeners those lessons , you might not know what that means .
I think that they might actually have some handle on where a lot of your thinking comes.
Well , if we really got back to basics , we made up of items of charge particles .
And in principle , if you accelerate a charge , particular , they will radiate .
And so we are completely based by electronic magnetic fields , literally from DCto very high frequency failed .
This is being direct , correct earlier , so is there are frequency .
Think about this is zero frequency .
So and my ，I bet my comment about looking through a piece of glass , how does that happen ?
We have to think about electronic magnetic waves , whether they are very high frequency of the what much lower frequency punch , radio or microwave .
And what are those fields doing , the carrying energy and the moving items around their exciting items as they propagate , and what we might want to detect that radiation , we might want to bend it or steer .
We need to understand what those interactions are at all scales in order to exploit .
It may keep a bit .
And what I am finding is that even though electronic goes back hundred years in the first radio was probably in eighty nine five , that classical picture , which evolved to describe electronic magnetic waves and interactions , is still surprising as when it comes to model the interaction of waves with structures that perhaps of the order of the wavelength in size , or when we try to explain interactions where is strong residencies of what we were called on linear effects .
So the material properties that could be described by earlier electric theory , the classical electronic theory , keep pulling us to test them and stretch them into new rounds .
Well , we are discovering new properties , new physics , new opportunities all the time .
And I think all of the programs are healthy , and my poor , fully of touch on some aspect of the weather , detecting light looking at these nonlinear aren't strongly interacting relationships like half with engineering , matter with it over similar size and the right material properties to the wavelength is interested in to managing electronic waves for bad imagining .
Oh , thank you .
We've got one program we're looking at instead of imaging with frequency , we can see uh you could go to lower frequencies , much lower frequency and start thinking about trying to image through structures with very low service .
The penetrate sounds like glass I can see through .
I don't expect to see through a piece of metal .
Very low frequencies can penetrate the piece of .
So can I extract information from radiation of low frequency , the cost to those materials like my phone and find out what's on the other side.
Right , and so that's that mapping onto your program called , imagine through almost anything , anywhere , right , right?
We've become more sophisticated in how we can model the emission of low frequencies from sources , maintenance and hurricane describe how those who will call narrow or crazy strategic fields with matter , and can provide this information about that matter , not interaction.
Right , so this is reminding me one of your programs which really fascinates me that they all do is , is radio buyer , right ?
So we are talking about , in this case , electronic interactions with biological material .
And in this case , when thank you really looking more on the salary level.
Actually , that was the first program I launched AIIpitched the service by calling to dark , and it was ahead of previous work in north carolina , where I realized for some of these engineered materials have the kind of remarkable new properties the beyond seen before a good metal materials .
It might be convenient to grow them .
So I was looking at chemical methods that myself assemble some of these residents structures , some of these geometric , like shapes that interact very strongly with with light .
And it occurred to me that some of these structures occur in nature .
And I got to thinking about whether nature perhaps is already making use a very sad electronic interactions , but between cells , between organs , between individuals using electronic ways in ways that we haven't really thought about .
It was studied very deeply .
So the program had a , oh , you've trying to determine whether sounds or any scale by our systems , which we knew would be successful to exposure by different frequencies .
We like to magnetic waves , whether these structures might actually be generating electronic magnetic waves , and if there could be some purposeful communication on over large ranges , the man would expect to see with normal chemical signaling by a chemical .
Sydney is usually used to describe as southern bus systems communicate with each other , and the programs still going is a very challenging problem , but it's quite clear that biological structures do eliminate electric magnetic waves across going back to GCto the airline , in fact , but okay , exploiting them for some purpose is , as a question we still try to answer if it turns out there is this network of communication going on in biological systems for some purpose .
We have not understood in the closely opens up the possibility of perhaps being able to intervene and generate similar signals externally for foreign positive purposes to perhaps hill wounds , for example , if there were charges and fields involved in that process in so , I think it is a good area to think more deeply about , because it would be terrible to miss some opportunities for doing good if we just have .
If not thought they played enough about what's going on.
So I wonder if , if any of the performers and that sort of double speak for the research , researchers , research groups that end up getting essentially contracts through program management to work on the programme and try to realize them the goals of the program have any performers .
You're discovered things and published things in this arena that had happened , surprising.
For a number of application areas of interest exampled by our phones , one performing team has established .
But there are a couple of frequency ranges in the terror hurts when there are , which are some attempt to transmit , receive over a couple of bands , a couple of range of frequencies in the terror.
Range range and just a couple of things , just so listeners know a bio film .
I typically think of that as as as a kind of bacterial carpet of some kind.
let's write some via phones of extreme , useful , but they protect 早上的那一天，we have buy a films along with example , and some by a films are a pain to deal with likelihoods that grow on the bottom of shapes .
Now , this great african leaders to collect so much other debris .
If we could identify a communication channel in the territorial regime , which is selected to a particular buyer film that we don't want , we might be able to broadcast a set of frequencies to it in a way that confuses it makes you think practice time and move on .
And it shouldn't continue to form a film there .
That's one of.
Yeah , well , I just say the and fascinated by this idea of imagining is that there could be not knowing , but there could be a kind of whole world of electronic magnetic communication in account of the cellular and go wrong that we certainly have been .
You know , blindness for , for not actually asking the question by asking the question is , then we'll know what to look for , but it will know what was signals to seek and.
Picking up on that , I do like to remind everyone that we all thought the earth was flat for very long time , until we started looking more carefully .
So I am a great believer in the fact that we've been doing science for a few hundred years , and the stone will follow up.
Well , and so that reminds me of another thing that you said , I , this might have been at a dark conference called the sixty , which was in celebration of sixty .
And of course , you might have been somewhere else , but you said that you're looking for a late matter interactions that we have missed , and certainly that's kind of that is what we were talking about radio .
But outside of that program , where else does that stick to play on your programs?
What is there a few , for example , in the end of the program , coal nationwide matter , niceness is supposed to improve intellectuals that we might have missed or not really pretty much we're seeing the materials we'd have a reflective index close to zero , and that's kind of because free space vacuum air has a reflective index , one in the visible glass .
But I like looking through my , haven't reflective in the one point , three , one point five that we can make a material that has a reflective index .
It's close to zero .
And what does that mean ?
What is going to reflect the flag lie in a very unusual way .
But we're finding that by looking more deeply at models for those interactions with the material , having those properties , these materials have very large northern areas .
What does that mean ?
That means if I illuminate the material with frequency , FImight generally frequencies two f or three f , it would generate higher or lower frequencies , depending on how I do it .
But this causes a very important , for example , of a nightmare for a night convert employed wavelength to visible wavelengths to help even on driving sea battery night .
This is a material now because of its structure and thanksgiving me , a much more efficient way of doing that than i've been able to so far with existing night vision technology .
Oh , that's just one example of.
In that one example that you also addressing an another question that I had , which is explaining how , you know , your kind of thinking you , which is to say how to slide and had a lot matter when you write .
How is it that asking questions like that , and developing programs based on that idea , has that related the dark ambition , you know , of furthering national security .
And as actually , you put it , also , at some point that you're trying to avoid a spanish like surprise based on electronic photographic phenomenon .
So you did point directly to the possibility to wanna shake me one more , because you used to have a couple more ready to end.
Yeah , well , the young different scientist office has a mission priorities for the agency .
And one of them is anticipating surprise .
So whenever one comes across some interesting new phenomenon , physics and all electronic magnetic phenomenon is tempting to think about whether there could be a new capability buried in the that could provide the pound of defence has some new capability .
Or is it worth investigating to see whether there is actually nothing there , nothing of any consequences , least for the next ten , twenty , thirty years .
So we will not be surprised by new technology based on this phenomenon .
So a lot of what we do is to investigate as rigorously as we can , these ideas either to see if there is a new capability for national security , or if it's really to be afraid of from nephew story , pursuing this work as long as we can tell , i'm so , you know , one example that has popped up a lot in the last ten years is all that different mechanisms for proportion that we've overlooked .
It might be electronic , magnetic nature that might enable proportion for sample in space , but without fuel , without physically having to have fuel on board .
Some ideas have been floated to this based on electronic magnetic interactions with structured materials , with residents .
Structures are committed materials or with , well , the pennsylvania might be strongly non reciprocal .
Meanwhile , we got one way through it , but not the other way .
And this , some sort of foundational math associated with consuming theory , which says that there are these fluctuations in space of electric fields and magnetic fields , a consequence of quantum theory that these fluctuations occur .
And I have a certain energy associated with now that energy dancing is not something we normally think we can take into , but we cannot rule out entirely whether one of these strongly non reciprocal structures might be able to be reflected just by its sitting learning space , immersed in these naturally occurring background fluctuations .
It's probably highly , unlike we cannot look at this a bit more carefully , just in case.
Right , and it's just one interject that I believe what you are talking about here is the focus of your quest program .
One of the ways I heard that program described which fascinates me , is in some ways , is investigating the possibility of accessing or interacting in some way energies that are also set with the back government.
Space , yes , I think the usual moment even say a common sense view of it is that if you are already at the bottom of a while , you probably cannot go any lower .
And this energy background , the contemporary says very most in , it's a sort of lowest energy state is the ground state .
So how could we can we learn to somehow dip into it or serve across it , or manage it in a way that we could extract the management temporarily and put it back , or extracts a moment of first temporary , uh , it's a challenging problem .
It's a question that's come up many times over the years .
I would say that the time is right now .
Well , we can make structures that , and we can do very exclusive experiments in terms of measuring threats .
We have more drawn theoretical models of these phenomenon .
So the time seeing right to see if we could investigate more thoroughly this possibility , if we find in eighteen months time is really hope of getting any significant energy from this mechanism .
So beyond , we've learned something simple to know whether our adversaries with their pursuing similar of of inquiry .
I can hit the same.
Great , well , and what was the account of to pursue with the reasoning , he said , chance that it could ultimately be realized because one of the greatest burdens to bear right in the space enterprises , holding teenagers of fuel through the atmosphere and into orbit and beyond .
So if there is some authority of doing that nicely , in a sense , looking at this , being in the space where the space itself could become part of the mechanism of proportion .
Well , really nice to know that is possible.
It wouldn't a nearly adopt program ended a few years ago , looked at how nanos rubbish services can manage this energy .
This fact , you managed dancing and by management , I mean , make it very specially across the surface so that is possible , attractive and repulsive .
Forces nearly surfaces .
These are called cosmic forces .
We have some young faculty of all right now , looking at how these forces never surface may be sufficient to change tonight , energy levels and lead to different spectrum , scrappy signatures from items just by being closed to the services .
So if we can understand the forces interacted with matter and are shaped by the presence of matter , we may understand whether we can extract and exploit the energy associated with this phenomenon in some usual way , and that's what the program quest is designed to do .
We're going to look more carefully what possibilities are to do.
June thirtieth is your last day of a graduate .
I forgot four years program manager and nuclear spokeswoman , average , ten year four program managers involved a lot of turnover by design at DARPA .
Some just wondering you , as you finish your tenure here , what you've learned about the dark culture , and yeah , where it fits in kind of the innovation ecosystem.
What a sunny , very innovative place , and it's packed for the very bright , dedicated , and i've been overwhelmed by the college alleged respect , the sense of responsibility , strong sense of belonging to this agency to doubt it really is a wonderful place to work , and the responsibility everyone feels is the .
This is taxpayers money being used to try to anticipate , surprise , come up with a new capabilities .
So we restructure our programs in a way .
But as you step forward through them , months by months , phase , by faith , we always want to fail .
We're learning something a value of towards that poor , the mission of making , making the country a satisfactory place .
So i've really been humbled , trooping the colleagues , and we might know we have service cheap follows to come , and we have our sites where we , we meet with soldiers .
Amen , and we listen to do what's bothering them .
What's what they say is their highest priorities .
And we tried all of this perspective , we get from being adopted into trying to shape , design , plan and manage a program that the is truly beneficial to to our own fighters.
Well , said , thank you for pursuing all of that .
It , it also did .
This makes me one as one following question in the sort of the end of tenured kind of sad questions , which is you had all these programs , you know , a good handful of programs , programs .
This means that you have been working with a probably a large number of research groups over the years .
And I just wanted to do anything particularly memorable , surprising our opinion to know that that do you think listeners might find interesting months of those interactions and.
I think there is something special about the upper in the eyes of our performance , as well as I was fortunate enough to work the agency .
I think that rapid turn over that since we can see the way well organized structure of the doctor has makes performers feel that they are engaged in something special when I get funded , and I want to give it , and I, Ido see a lot of performers who put in really a lot of extra effort to make those deadlines keep us informed style on track .
I understand that we are using an arrangement with them where these program managers were in regular content , and we've been involved months by months , quarter by quarter , with , with what they are doing , and they don't want to disappoint .
I , the program has a goal , and the goal was approved for good reason , because , because it's addressing some needs .
But they are , they?
Hence , why is it interesting that you mention kind of that mission oriented , goal oriented , it is kind of research is supposed to maybe what we might think of this as curiosity driven coming out of the year , the great , endless frontier model science , postwar or two , I do find a dynamic at dark , absolutely fascinating where there is this big goal .
There is a big missioner's , potentially large payout , and becomes this wonderful collaboration between program managers like you .
And as you say , the performers that work on your programs.
The payment of a risk project , and as as we discussed earlier , pursuing a research project based on an idea that there could be something a value if the idea is correct , it is great , but an idea represents foreseeable threats if it's correct , but we establish that the idea was bad was wrong , that we get negative results is also extremely valuable .
It's important to know what doesn't work , and this is something which , in academia is a private industry , I guess not acquired such high value , but for us to know what doesn't work is just as important .
And this is a different mine set , especially to explain to performers that we just want to know .
We want to the best signs , the best engineering we just want to know .
Does this phenomenon occur ?
Does this this idea correct ?
Does this theory predict eggs ?
And if it doesn't ask , fine too , because we've learned something as well .
That's very important , right in this world.
A negative result has nothing to do with failure .
It's actually a success , because it helps us understand the landscape of what is possible .
Precisely , that's exactly right .
Yes , okay , my glass question , you leave in garbage with next.
Well , I have a couple of projects that i've got hooked by .
So I will go back to the university for some of the time I will go back to the teaching focus on one of them , but some are exploring a possibility to stay up in the DCarea and work on one of the others with the , with the government lab .
So nothing's completely firm yet , but it's moving in that direction .
So i'm hoping to have the best and continue to work on some of these projects slide .
I felt very compelling and could have some significant impact.
In the near future , well , I just wanted to thank you for your four years or so of service as a program manager .
Or , but may you have the best suppose world's may have a great next professional adventure , and I just want to thank you for spending the time with.
But thank you .
Algorithms , it's been a pleasure , and I appreciate you asking me to do.
Thank you .
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us .
I hope you join this again for the next Voices from dark thanks also to bend silent for his partnership in producing this program .