Soft technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on tuesday morning .
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defense advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from dirt , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan , a motel on your dark host today .
And please help with me in the sudden doctor , joseph evans , a program manager since twenty fifteen in the agencies , strategic technology offers , that's the office , which focuses on mixing and matching component technologies into networks of cable abilities that can adapt to all kinds of battlefield threats .
And I can voice surprise on adversaries to currently on leave from the university of cancer learns where he is a professional engineering computer signs .
Joe brings to double interests in advance networking and communications technologies , especially as they supply to large scale wire with communications and data links in every more network battle space in everyday living spaces in the private sector , zhou co founded net games , us a and network gaming company acquired by microsoft in two thousand .
He also was a partner and chief scientist that the company assent intelligence , which developed the tactical ground reporting system for darker in the USarmy .
This system was widely deployed in a recent afghanistan to help war fighters with situation awareness .
Zhou is personally unassigned in these conflicts to help refine the system , in addition to many other professional involvements , zhou flies planes skipper's bronze and placed guitar , including many years ago in a band called nasty a british and short , dark joe .
Events will continue to thank you .
Thank before we talk about some of the programs we run with names like geospatial , cloud analytics , shared spectrum access for radar and communications and secure handles are assured , resilient networks at the technical and no more , mercifully , by the acronym share , I would like to know something about where your interest come from .
How did you get interested in science and electrical engineering and the electronic magnetic spectrum , which has a , because your portfolio seems to provide the domestic background of.
Manufacturers may be a rhetoric .
Both granddaughters were like going , and I saw my father , they were involved in various links .
My mock prevailed , my mother's eyebrows involved in large coalition nearing for especially david and no , did smart for three or other agencies back when you couldn't say the names of those agencies .
And the nursery treatment is exactly the and and then on my other side , he was involved in early broadcasting back in the nineteen twenties.
When that's what radio is really a new in becoming a household.
The point exactly , and so oh me , others have been the slaughter , longstanding interest in radio , radio frequency engineering background .
And then we have failed to then exposed to a science fiction star track and things like that in the one thousand nine hundred and sixty , I remember asking my father , and I could remain at something like the communicator in the garage .
No , well , no , that's like too far out there .
You can get the components of all that .
There are that small .
And and I felt forward to the ninety nine years , and suddenly you have a football , and that looks like a starter communicator .
This longstanding interest in those types of wireless communication types of topics , and it's been wonderful to watch through my career .
Hello technologies , really , of all of the point where you can do some of these things that seem the worst inspection of.
Yeah yes , even as a kid , you are really immersed , not just knowing about radio , hearing it using it , but knowing something about it , I wanted .
So what I would love for you to do if you can talk a little bit about the electronic magnetic spectrum , i've always found it to be a kind of miraculous thing .
Right , I mean , it's invisible .
We have no sense of it directly , and yet we can use our cell phones .
We turn the radio on .
All of the stuff is going on there .
So when you think of the electric magnetic section , what is in?
I think of it really as a as a shared resource like the air .
If you move up with that way near the ability to communicator this medium .
And obviously , there is one of technology behind the year how you did build the art of devices and answer for gradual frequency .
Really , in the end , it is a shared resource that we can use for various things like communications .
Radio for sensing raids are so those types of things and is something that I think is the technology is evolved .
We can be more sophisticated about how we use that , that shared resource of nearly half spectrum .
I will say it is pretty serious , but it is one of those things that we have .
You kind of have to visualize how the sharing is going on in the smaller dimension in order to make use of it more , more.
But smart limb well actually gives me a good excuse to to start in on some of your programs , including one called the events of mapping program .
Because in some ways , the technology is the seek .
There is trying to make the invisible visible , trying to make what's going on an electron magnetic spectrum visible .
So can you talk to me a little bit ?
This program , which is at the toilet and writing , transitioning even to the raincoat .
That's what this is a nice example when you can sort of talk about the original idea of the idea it started snow on .
And what you think is going to do for our military capabilities.
A van star of mapping is really known by the name radio map that sets the shortage , and we use the program until the radio map program is really trying to provide that basic spectrum situation awareness .
What's happening in the spectrum , as he says , it's visible , and what we make it visible .
Computer visualization tools and so um is a mix of sensing what's out there is a turning existing radios , things like that into RFsensor .
So you can see what essentially see what it's going on in the spectrum .
You can sample what's going on in this pattern .
You bring that back over a tactical networks , in our case , that the more inquiry is using , but you bring those back to percentage of pcs and give up up , and you run some elderly themselves on it and generate visualization of what's happening in the industrial man in a given area , in a given area .
And so if you might , a military unit is operating in a particular area , there , generally , many of those marines results have radios .
You use those radios as your sensors you bring back , no , all the measurements and from that area to that location , we can run the algorithms and generate what looks like a heat map , a colored visualization of what happened in natural graphic area in the spectrum .
The map shows you how much energy is there by the color of the of the map , kind of the way that you want with signals are in a particular frequency of health room with , if you think of like the weather radar that you see , you know , in the evening news , that type of visualization is the way you look at the spectrum , and you can see here , essentially , what's already eating hot in your area , and that maybe of interesting , maybe curious about what bad is .
Um , so we can , we have a display that shows how kind of here is what happening over all the spectrum .
And then we have a display that shows you okay at this particular frequency of this particular part of the spokeswoman says the frequencies where the wifi networks , you can see where the hot spots are .
You can see healthier radiating away from their their basket.
And you can you go just as sentences a new kind of situation where in this rate , and I can look around and see if there , maybe there are adversaries , I can see a kind of administrative assets that we have an adversary might have .
This has always been sort of invisible , sort of innocent of phenomenon .
So as a war fighter , if I know this now , how can I put that information use?
So so as a war fighter , it is very valuable because you can start to identify maybe signals that you did not expect to be there .
So a particular example that we have from some wrinkle exercises landscape will simply really that they play with the radio map , but display .
And I saw something it was unusual , and it turned out of the sniper team that was out there , hiding and not visible otherwise , other than , or in there are of spectrum emissions that are using their radios .
So there are things like that that allow you to identify what's happening in the spectrum , and then you can decide if that's militarily important or or not , you may decide , well , let's not signal .
Maybe I should send somebody over to take a walk , things like things like that are possible , cross of action that you are present once you can finally see what's happening in the , in the art of spectral.
Why , in our way to your map is getting to what we think of here are doubt as as when the best finish line that a technology development program can get to , which is to say , you're gonna hand this off , in this case , right to the morning course .
What , what the next steps for that happen.
What we're doing with the rainfall is working with them on some of these various exercises and experiments in parallel .
The wrinkles been very followed , leaning in spectrum operations , essentially AEMspectrum operations .
They have been adding it to their doctor .
They have been looking at the techniques , procedures , how they might use the alternative spectrum in a war fighting sense .
And so they've been forward kind of some of these ideas of if they have the technology .
And so what we're doing , darkness , develop the technology , and we are transitioning it to the marines where they can then start to use in exercises first and then in the , in the forces we roll forward .
So they have in identify .
This is a key technology that will be inserted as a royal word in their budget planning and the program planning.
But let's talk about another program that this was not as far along .
It's not about to be the transitioned yet .
This one goes by an acronym spark .
There was two s in the front of that SSPARCthat stands for shared spectrum , access for radar and communication .
This does relate to what we were just talking about , specially in the sense of where there was a very busy electronic magnetic spectrum , which is to say where all people and devices wanna kind of have access to that .
So there you exploring something called spectrum sharing , and maybe we can talk about concept and why that's becoming ever more important.
So one of the issues with spectrum is that it is very heavily used .
You can just think of your cellphone in your cell phones that they are using more and more of the spectrum .
There's why fires millions , millions of the millions , so many , even the billions by now introduced wifi and cell cell phones for shortage .
And so there are , there are , there is a heavy use of the arab that is a new , modern phenomenon .
If you look back in the galaxy sixty seven days , most of the arab spectrum use tended to be governmental and lottery .
And so the advent of cell phones and in laptops and ipads and so forth with life , refrigerators connected to refrigerator .
All of that has started to really be the dominant use of the spectrum , which means that the military has to adapt to having less and less freedom to to move in that spectrum .
And so one of the things that we're doing in the spark program is looking this idea of sharing between communications , technical communications , even maybe commercial communications and military rates .
We have looked at the navy's rate , arts and healthy might interact with or use the same spectrum as ALTcell phones , and in some spectrum bands .
And we've also looked at how military systems can share with military system .
So , for example , leave done some things that have transition to the army , where they're developing a rate are that will use the radar for communications with other sites and soldiers to get improved .
Ray are overall system , and so there are things like that were , let's smarter use of the spectrum enables the military to use less .
And commercial world has its constant pressure that it needs to more spectrum because of use by individuals and , and.
The individual consumer , well , in this , this sounds like it relates to some work that colleagues in the microsystem technology office are working on and referring here to the spectrum collaboration challenge , which also is really all about trying to bring this holiday of spectrum sharing , almost like a new ethic , unhealthy views .
and think about this spectrum into a magnificent , real wide context to know what we , even the radios all have to get smarter and 干嘛干嘛，is it is very good.
Connection absolutely going back on a little little bit in my personal history in two thousand , three , two thousand five , I was a program manager over the national science foundation .
And one of the things that I started there was a program looking at taking smart radios and doing dynamic access of the spectrum .
So they influence.
Listeners who might not appear that term before smart.
Radio , can you just ?
Authorities are so smart radios , really a software defined radio in the sense of the radio characteristics .
It's frequencies that use types of wave forms that sends over the electronic spectrum.
Those are all the most likely to the most like familiar way forms being something like , like AMN.
Academic employee modulation frequency modulation at the lowest level .
Tennis , yeah , you can think of wifi is being having a way form of that you use .
So all of these different types of reforms can be basically implemented using software these days because of the vast increase in computing power available , as well as some improvements in the arab devices themselves .
Already , a great news capable of doing that .
We've think of those , as , yeah , exactly .
And those key bullies are getting smarter and smarter capability is being dragged into , you know , a smaller and smaller hands at , like your cell phone and a technical radios in the military .
So , and when I was at the natural science foundation attendance of started this program on dynamically accessing spectrum that is using different frequency bands , the essentially share the spectrum more intelligence .
It was academic work , a lot of that work is a mature to the point where they're starting to show up in chips and systems that can be used throughout both the commercial world , as well as well .
The military rope MTO , the michael transfer technology authors is helping to to move that wave of technology forward by making better devices and creating better techniques through things like the spectrum , challenges and see two where they are looking at different techniques for sharing the spectrum .
So there's definitely been a movement throughout the academic industry said to try to make that the spectrum access , because I smarter than we've traditionally done the traditional way of accessing the spectrum , or has been the traditional bureaucratic cut down types of ways of mentioning , respectively , accessing federal communications .
We say you get to use.
This frequency at this time , under these conditions , and what we're talking is making is all more fluid .
So , like all of these connected devices , can , can figure out how make best use of this incredible.
Research , the electronic inspector had absolutely , but the excessive and on the government's virus , the NTIAnational information agency think I got the right are looking at these new technologies as a kind of the wave of the of the future .
And we are hoping some of these technologies let the darkness develop will make their job easier , basically in.
In the future on the policy said , okay , so let's just touch on one other of your programs .
So , so I know that some of your programs sent innovative ways of sharing access in whenever and wherever preps , even using things like drawings as temporary , can win a wifi roaders .
That's sort of thing programming .
I want to talk about .
You is called jail special cloud and lyrics by doing a lot more with satellite data that has been done before , things like using data about due special characteristics such as crops in the stress and may be using that sort of data , predict things like a security relevant of anonymous social .
That's true to think so .
Tell me about that me , what kind of data is available that you're hoping to , you know , access in new ways and how that might be valuable.
Some of the genesis of this idea , really , the transaction , the major genocides .
It was the vast amount of new geospatial data that has been created from commercial sources .
So traditionally , the satellite imagery market place was government , special government satellites taking pictures or either military use , or for things like agricultural prediction since like that thinks that from that , some of those types of capabilities that's radically changed in the past couple of years , with the launching of many new commercial satellite .
Some are already , some are uh in various stages of deployment .
And what that's providing is much more data on a daily basis .
One of those ways I like to describe this is , in fact , when dark woods failed at the back of one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , it was really founded in response to sputnik being launched , some wealth of panic in the popular , well , the soviet can see what i'm doing all the time they're flying over with the satellite , and and they can see me in my backyard .
Well , what's interesting now is refinedly getting to a point where there are enough commercial side that they are really arguing over every day and imagine everywhere .
And it's one of those things that unexpected , I think , from a government outside what the impact of that could be , the , the vast amount of new and useful data that might come from the commercial sites .
And this is a pictures of you .
Data say , they say whatever after goal , so they say in the bills , it can be other things .
Are there are satellite cancellations that are collecting graph data is uh they , they forever .
Are there commercial accelerators that are doing radar imaging as well combined ?
All of these are vast new data source to understand what happened in the world .
It is so much data , however , that people can keep up .
It is a fire horse of data to an extent that has never been really seen .
People talk about big data .
This is bigger than bigger data , and just in terms of the amount of data that's being collected from these satellites .
So people can keep up that can look at over the state .
So then you have to do automatic processes , machine learning types of algorithms .
You really have to set up the , the pipelines of of processing the to get useful information out of all that data .
And what are trying to do in the jurisdiction , cloud and little explosion is make use of all that data to set up the architectures to do that , and then essentially business model so that dirty customers can get that information , rather than just the data in a sensible way .
So the GAspecial part is of the GCAand the GS, which was glad I wanted to geospatial partners , all the new satellite constellations , all that new gear , special data .
There is the cloud part , which is , well , you need , you put it in the computing , hear about google cloud and amazon web services , lows widely accessible , and then also can be a widely accessible , and then also can be assess the high speeds in those cloud resources so you can actually crunch through of a data in the cloud in order to produce a result out the back that then a war fighter can purchase the.
And this is what kind of where the analytics come in .
So I imagine that the ideas is to apply any lyrics and various kinds of models where you try to now connect this road data , the things that are even more interesting than raw data , which is what it might have mean .
We are referring to the conditions of crops and how that can lead to food security or insecurity , and that can relate to how , meanwhile , groups people are behaving.
Exactly so so , for example , as you say , one of the thrust we have is looking at full security and understanding what is happening in particular regions of of the world in terms of health profits developing over over the year , and essentially using these new data sources that are so much fresher than it ever before .
Using a new , fresh data that comes in delhi , or maybe weekly , in some cases , but much more frequently than in the past , using that to then crunch these analytics algorithms that predict , you know , that this crap is going to do well this year , or this crop of weed is , is going to report in this part of the world .
And what we've seen over even the past few years is that crap failures can lead to social instability .
The arab spring , excited as one of those examples were that was kind of the spark that lent to the arab spring .
And so if we get a little bit of more events warning , maybe we can improve the dollar by identifying that there may be a need for aid going to a particular parts of the world .
Early steady can position itself so that it's not a surprise .
So that's one of the challenges , problems in the US.
Special analysis of problem , not one of our primaries .
We've , that is some illegal fishing .
There is a real problem in certain parts of the world with illegal , unlicensed fishing .
There's also non governmental organizations looking at this problem , but we're using that as a way to try to identify when vessels may be showing up in particular territorial waters .
Whether I wanted .
So we're trying to use the program to explore that space and really to push the limit of what you can get from the GS, special commercial gear , special data.
Right now , I don't usually think of the defense department is policing in official practices around the world .
So can you just explain a little bit about how that connects to what might be a dark and deal the interest short.
And and so in the case , the bill of fishing , they also a good proxy problem for general maritime situation , awareness types of a problem .
So near the navy may desire assistant understanding of what vessels are in a particular area , and owner , kind of large scale .
I want to know where all of the traffic is in the pacific , and and so these new commercial data sources are providing a way to bring together satellite imagery .
Read or satellite , think such as AIS , which is one of the vegan seats on commercial vessels that say , I am here .
And this is so I am .
There are various things like that can be brought together just to improve overall , the understanding of what happened.
In the marathon , but it's interesting you've been the subject .
Just last night I was looking at at a website that tries as many of the aircraft that are in the air at any one time .
It uses something much like an air system , one of those bacon .
And here I am systems , I was amazed to learn that at the moment I was looking at this real time website that they were fourteen thousand aircraft in the year at at that moment .
So , so listen , some ways is a little bit related more than a year.
Our time kind of contact exactly .
And so in the maritime context , the trick is that if a vessel doesn't want to be seen , it will turn off at the air speaking .
And so then you are interested using some of those other data sources from the the satellite data .
And so for the , yeah , well , the real issue vessel there just turned off its beak and.
Go radio dark , yeah , doesn't mean that you can't be detected exactly exactly .
okay .
So we're kind of getting told the end of our discussion here .
But because you're someone who is experience in academia , you've experience in the government and a safety for coming here , you have experience in the private sector .
Someone who has a kind of interesting view on the overall innovation ecosystem , and some of another to hear a dog , papa .
Just wondering , you know what you are discovering about , where a place like this fits into that overall.
Innovation ecosystem , obviously darker , spent on the leading edge of technology for decades .
In a certainly iphone walking on and around the internet .
For most of my career , and in a darker was about their first international networking technology .
And the so it's both let the way and opened the doors for things happening in the commercial world .
And I mentioned in the spectrum , sharing the same time as I was at an accept working on on that .
There was another program manager over here , a dark of working on similar issues , and we frequently would work together to move that that technology forward .
So it's , it's always been on the leading edge .
One of the interesting things to me coming to the dark has been really the opportunity to understand , even in more deaths than I thought .
I , the specific needs for the military spin , very eye opening .
What problems there are that need to be solved .
One of the things it's been fine as putting together programs that kind of address those , those specific needs .
So we are dropped both those that the kind of move the technology forward .
But the other parties were very interested in me is that double , really , I believe , is the key agency in terms of military innovation for the war fighter , the opportunities to think about the kind of big problems facing the department of defense facing the military as we move forward .
Unnatural world , you do that others in our policy , dark.
You are now , in addition to your work as a program manager as a professor , the invasive cancer .
Imagine the introduction of these other .
So you're a pilot .
I saw a picture of you were looked like you were skippering a boat and actually pretty scary conditions .
You think these kinds of interests have some kind of influence in the way .
Think about , let's cook , engineering about how you do .
Do your program management.
I do think that one of the things that has been helpful from those experiences coming to a place late , like david is that the opportunities offered to a program manager are very much like skippering , a boat or flying in airplane in the sense that you have great freedom to do what , what you want .
You operate within the limits of the technology , whether it is the airplane or the or the sale book , but you have a great freedom that kind of set your course .
And I really do think that that's a wonderful.
我。
Opportunity were given since you've been here in washington , have you been able to get into a plate ?
and.
Why these guys around here not so much a with all the restricted airspace around here , it , this is probably dicing , almost challenging places in the , in the country to adjust the university of her a phone .
Politicians who are also nearly a lot of water , and we're nearly a lot of I have done a little bit better on that new occasional education and.
I have helped you .
So there is one biographical detail that I find , particularly using a mentioned earlier before , when you were student , princeton , you and somebody's weren't a ban called nasty , british and short , which , you know , is , I guess that's a phase of TOM hoped one of the less optimistic .
We're more pessimistic .
Abuse on life .
And I guess a seventeen century century .
So this does not represent european life .
Now , yeah , absolutely not to.
Although it was a pretty full name , maybe it is more distributed school .
But yeah , that was , that was a wonderfully fun band .
At least the characters from the area .
I hope that have ended up .
His university president , a university province , and I think the senior technology leader at a place that does business with darkness .
So I will mention it , but I.
Well , at the dark program and the director manager , exactly , we are , really , you know , disappearance left .
Is there anything about technology in general , about dark about your programs that did not come up doing our discussion , you think , would be a bitter to our listeners.
Just a general thought , and that is that one of the other things that is really been wonderful about being a dark has been using the breadth of new ideas that focusing on in the science and technology industry are working on and bringing and discuss with us .
And it's AAbroad vision that that you don't really get in a lot of others , parts of either the academic world war on the commercial world , and the thing that that really comes through from that use that as much as technology has evolved and as mature as some ideas , there are still enough vast opportunities out there for continued innovation .
It really has been a good experience , seeing that and seeing other the new ideas that talks are still.
Bring forward , yeah , I mean , that just makes me think about , you know , that some hundred program managers here , and when you really think about all of the kind of individual technologies are developing , which we are in this error , now almost account mix a match where you get into a permutation game .
And this is what strategic technology offers this kind of about where all of these existing technologies can come together into amazing diversity of of assembly .
Just right.
Absolutely , and that is one of the wonderful things about being in a sea more the systems officers that are barely global strategic technology offices is that you do get to see these technologies across the board that are helping to and provide a capability that will make the difference for the us .
And for the worldwide is .
So it's really , i'm funny to see how you can put those individual , individual , individual together to grade , and even better in A.
right ?
Well , you've given us a bit a bit of a snap shot about you and the worker doing in the strategic technology official just want to thank you for spending this time.
Okay , well , thank you very much .
Really , really , john.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dark.
For more information about zhou events , the programs he and his colleagues run in the strategic technology office and the other grateful technology is working on visit dropper domino and for links that enable you to download this part .