Self technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on tonight .
Operation technologies , a driver of our times since its founding nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt that defense advanced research projects agency has been a driver of welcome to a Voices from dark , a window on the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My names are in the mutton on the middle of host .
And today I pleased to have with me in the studio .
US.
army .
Curl might happen and active duty army physician , and since twenty thirteen , a program manager in terms biological technologies office kernel happen holds a bachelor science green by medical engineering and a doctor medicine , both from duke university , following all of that education .
He completed an internal medicine residency in an infectious disease fellowship at book army medical center at fourth , sam houston in texas practice .
Joining DARPA met , served as the director of medical preparedness on the white house , national security staff , and additional previous assignments included the chief medical officer at a level two medical facility in iraq , a clinical research director at the USarmy medical research institute for infectious diseases .
And in exchange , officer to the united kingdom , among other positions , matt is one of the doctor's program managers who comes to work in his military tire , in his case , either is army for teeth or address uniform .
Either way , he always wears the smile of someone who find himself in a place he just might be able to realize a dream , and he has said publicly that he wants to stop all infectious diseases from killing people .
Maybe so cool that happens though I will call you mad from that one .
It is my pleasure to have you in the study.
It's fantastic to be here , and thank you .
I went for inviting me to be on the pakistan to tell my story and tell you what I care so deeply.
Yes , I have been greatly looking forward to question , so why do we get ready to it ?
And so you're a medical professional who embraces clinical and field practice , as well as living as research ?
What are the origins of those interests view?
It started pretty young .
I have the childhood memory of being asked at my school .
A catholic score now is meeting with one of the prisoners of what you really want to do .
And I said , I wanted to be a pediatrician , and I said , why , and I said , well , because this wanna take care of people , and I want to take care of children , and I do think it stems from my mom , visitors .
And oh , I think let's so from the influence of being around someone in the medical profession .
But more so just being around someone that cares are deeply about other people .
Again , very early .
I know it , but it's been , it's been sort of a consistent part of my life , and I think it really , aren't you mean I would manage .
This is in fourth grade this whole life .
Yet I wanted to be APDtreasure .
This was , I was on this trajectory , and I didn't know , of course , what I was talking about , you know me , even you make this stations early in your life , but my parents and my family always had this incredibly strong ethic of service and very deeply in fundamentally , because I reflect on this often actually , is like , who am I and what am I supposed to be , and I think what I do is I serve others , and that's that I would find myself , maybe one of the greatest gifts from my parents was that my dad was an activity .
Navy after the RTC and served as a nuclear engine here on a surface warfare ship .
It was activity for five or six years .
Stayed in the navy for another twenty plus retired as a navy captain in the reserves .
You couple , my mom's passion for helping other people in the medical field with my dad's passion of serving our country .
This was almost a girl I knew .
And so that subject for his sort of guided me through all of my decisions and.
Okay , what let's exactly talk a little bit about that , you know , before you can do that .
We spend almost fifteen years in a variety of assignments that took you to , for example , for the military premier facility for infectious disease research , took you to korea to the UKas the republic of georgia as AB, A, J, I, A, N, A, iraq , thailand , other places .
I'm sure what did you learn from all of that global experience?
I would start by saying what a privilege to have those types of life experiences , all in the context of a game , feeling that i'm serving my country and making a difference .
Some of the work that are most proud of , frankly , is what I did in the caucuses with georgiana's arbitration .
And the program was under the officer , was called the cooperative threat reduction program , but really , there was to engage their political communities and their medical research communities to establish the capability of the finding , infectious diseases , diagnosing them and ultimately treating them .
And it was a capability that was those public health systems were all part of the soviet union , but when the soviet union fell , these countries were kind of left their own .
We create a public health infrastructure .
And so the privilege was to work with those experts in the whole country to say that we build that back up again , so that helicopters are now pretty going on .
And then we can collectively work together to respond to that.
But I inserted you bring in models like the descendants of disease control.
We did is we did .
We were closely with the embassy .
We were closely with the state department , closely with the cdc at the end of the day , it was my selfish of my duty colleagues on the ground near rolling or sleeves up , helping these countries develop the systems , developing laboratory capabilities , developing the ability to do clinical research to ethical standards that would be accepted all over the world , and to figure out how to do this .
You know , again , I would bet what a privilege to be on the ground and at this tribe , fairly junior in my career , and to help an entire nation of.
Improve their proper health .
Yeah , now that that sounds like a great privilege .
What is the sequences of a best that resulted in your current position here adopted as a program manager?
Throughout my medical career , I had heard about up , and I had seen amazing technology that it come from doubt that were aimed at a dress .
Manufacturers is easier threats .
So I always admired from a far before I joined .
Darby was over the white house , national security council staff .
And in that row , my job was to identify what capabilities we do not have to respond to pandemics , and then how we can organize ourselves as a government , not just do d but as an entire government towards addressing the escape .
So we're ready for the next one .
And while I was there , I got tapped on the shoulder .
And the concise phrase was , you're doing all of this policy , what we should do as a government .
How would you then like to employment and actually make investments ?
They're going to address this , get.
So met , were you literally tapped on the shoulder ?
This is the end of the world .
Who was that the post?
It was actual jeffrey , who was the deputy director of the so at time .
And here we imagine , for coffee one morning , and he didn't literally actually put his hand on my shoulder , but figuratively , imagine a hand on my shoulder saying that , how would you like to try a darker to actually invest to make a difference for all those things that even talking about international policy words for the last few few years.
Well , and of course , he provided a model of authority because he really took control manners of rogers and prosthetics and other programs really helped the worldwide , one of them secret and into your life is a program manager hearing this tremendous follow you that you've developed .
Which is , I think it would follow you that also reflects some account of all dishes point of view , as is , of course , reflected by that statement earlier that you want to take the lethal power out of infectious disease .
So the names are fantastic .
Some of them like promises in four dialysis , like their reputations in vivo nano platforms , and we'll probably talk more about one of them , particularly the pandemic prevention platform , when i'm hoping to do now is , is , if you could briefly take us for a tour of your programs , we can go in depth about any of them at this point , but take me a little bit of a toronto .
And what was you hoping to see these programs , and there will focus on a little bit more on the open damage.
Prevention platform , yeah , so the tour starts by saying , what , what problems are we trying to solve .
And again , at the white house , national security council staff , I get a chance to say , look for these major outbreaks , pandemics or near pandemics .
How have we done as a government ?
Think about the issue ?
Yeah , two thousand , nine , eight , one and one panda , I think about the west africa .
He evolved a crack in each one , and one matters of each one and one influenza .
Yeah , influenza , think about the west african buller crisis .
Think about how we recently responded to zig at their common things throughout , and some of those common things are .
We need to be much better at diagnosing if someone has an infection , and we need to go a step beyond that in , imagine that if we could figure out if someone is going to be sick or is going to be contagious , we can intervene and stop the upgrade and extract , and that's permissions .
You know , that's the permitted program , but we also need to make vaccine scenes and treatments much faster than we currently can .
And that is a one of the examples of the pandemic prevention platform .
We need alternative ways of how we treat infections and using impossible dialysis , and to filter the blood and remove any type of passage is a good example.
But but so just in that case , is that mean I might have been supposed to some kind of passage in the agent , and it's in my blind certain level .
So with this kind of technology will move that before could take hold and actually look at music with exactly idea of that.
Yes , and the idea would be again , especially for passengers , where we don't have a vaccine , where we don't have a treatment .
Especially think about now with what we're seeing so much time .
And I microbial resistant bacteria , imagine if we can use an apologies .
So if we can filter your blood and remove that passage and what it does ultimately gives a leg up for your own immune response to ultimately make you , well , again , we like that technology , especially in those first days when we need to buy some time to develop a vaccine , and we need to develop new treatments .
And so my point across the portfolio is , we have lots of investments and medical diagnostics .
We're investing in , muddling to forecasts where infectious diseases are going to go .
We have investments and accelerating new treatments , but there are connected together .
They are all linked .
And let me give you an example with our promise .
This program , predicting if someone is going to become contagious will awesome , right if we can do that .
But once we predict and identify that person , we still have to treat them , and so organize treatments as fast as possible with our panda and prevention platform .
And the beauty is that those treatments are probably gonna , be most effective when they're given as early as possible .
So I think of our whole port volume is inner connected that we develop a lot of different specific projects to possibilities , but that they're ultimately going to inner twelve so that we stopped the outbreak and.
Well , when I think of programs you'll drop , i'll have a kind of life cycle to them .
right ?
I mean , they started started a glimmer and the eye of someone like you might .
Program manager , the superior of wedding and working with others here to relate particulate and formulate programmers .
Best can be , so it can be most effective , and then kind of smoke signals go out to the world and seeking people who maybe think that they can pull off .
Some of these are delicious tests that we will put out , because then the research is not , hopefully , in the end , you succeed or fully succeed .
You learn from all the research that that's gonna .
So what is the status in that life cycle of depend?
Prevention platform , the payment democracy platform just launched .
And so.
And by lots of those who might not know what that means in the dark context said.
That means that completing the contracting process so that are performers that was selected in a very rigorous process can now accomplish the goals of the program .
So they are just starting in there for six months as part of the lifestyle .
These are early , early days because the ultimate goal of that programmers so difficult .
We have a lot .
It would , sometimes I feel like we have , we have a long way to go one of the the key points , though , of the petroleum prevention platform is that the goal is incredibly ambitious , but there is foundational scientific evidence that this can be done , and that foundation of scientific governance is derived from a previous starter program .
And that previous star , corporate others.
Prove the accounts at the debt that see a debt program .
Because when I looked over the program , it's fascinating to me because it looks like which were trying to wrap up the whole brilliant molecular world of any bodies .
And so I wanted to let you go through this .
The secret incidents , beginning with this earlier program and depth .
Yeah , but walkers through some of the steps , because when I look at anybody to among my favorite protein , when I look at it , just brilliant things , they just so selective .
And I find the thing that we want our bodies .
And I glom , anyway , you tell us I.
The pieces of the program in the interior economy more , I think all of us that are fascinated by natural , dark arrival .
right ?
That's why our common thing is , we are just amazed by the natural world and what the natural developed antibodies are .
Great example .
I mean , there are millions and millions of these different versions of antibody circulating through your body at all , and the mechanisms are so refined in intricate to select .
Okay , which are the analysis that are most protective when you are exposed to infection , and your body goes through the process of the making .
A lot of those in a short period of time .
I think it's mine boggling how events that system is .
We've learned so much about everybody in less fifty years .
You're absolutely right .
We want to leverage all of that information that we know how they work now , and we know how they , we know about their structure , we know how to make them and big vets .
And why can we use that in your same incredible progress medicine where we are using ?
Were you saying antibodies approved as products now for cancer treatment , for treating auto immune disease with the category biologics in the category of biological ?
So massive explosion in that space ?
And we want , we use all of that knowledge and that technology to solve infectious diseases problems .
What we do at dark of those , the fun parties , we couple different fields together .
As you've correctly pointed out , this extraordinary , powerful tool of antibiotic engineering .
But can we couple that with the revolution that we seen in genetics , and that that started right ?
It's taking two different areas , seeing if we can mix them together again , and anybody specials might not think about the opportunities with genetics to genetics , specials might not think , well , wonder verify can use my use genetic engineering to make an employee .
You bring the two fields together in a more digital of bringing the disappoints together .
We achieve that effect .
And so the proof of concept , which I find exhilarating and choose up and on my spine , is that we can give you a piece of DNA or piece of irony , and we can put that into your muscle cells and that your muscles cells say , okay , got it .
I am going to make this .
anybody that is so protective 我。
That someone's nationalists , and that's encoded by these nuclear cases .
They are in the irony.
He tells that muscle cell to muscle cells do , and what a muscle cell does , but one side arney gets inside that muscles cell , the muscle .
I'm gonna , make a protective antibiotics can protect you from me , buller and do that in a very short period of time .
And that idea would sound crazy .
Ten years ago , too many obstacles can be done .
The foundation of from DARPA prove that concept in many different animal models for many different infections , but because we're darker , we said , we prove the concept that wasn't good enough , wasn't good enough for me .
It was in good enough for the dark , dark leadership said , okay , that's great .
We need to burst the baby if we're going to take pandemics off the table .
That's time here .
We need to be able to put this together as a platform that can go , start to finish from once a passage , and is identified to making thousands of dollars of this miraculous antibody based on bottom based.
An incredibly short period of time , right .
And let's talk about the time skills for minutes .
That's part of the , the big deal here , right ?
What i've seen is within six days by identifying the the passenger agent and actually have these doses right in handling in a distributable form as a correct as correct .
And it appears to what to do to what's the state of the year today today.
The state of the architecture depends on infections , but let you some , some recent examples .
We currently have some zeke of accents in clinical trials , but we've been working now for a , and we don't have a licensed digital vaccine .
You think about our risk when we talk about gaps , you think about all of these recent outbreaks .
And one of the fundamental licenses that we haven't had vaccines and treatments that are ready in time .
And we came up that the sixty day go has been cultural asylum when we talk about our destiny .
You know , I have professional colleagues who left me , and then i've been on panels where a white idea discuss the program , and the other panels joined with the audience laughing at me .
So I knew we were in the the counter argument that I continued to make to the critics is its sixty days is dictated by what we need to respond to petroleum .
So if you don't agree that our approaches the right way , then come up with creative , because we can't negotiate with mother nature and say , what would you like , another six months , if you don't mind , especially when you think about the catastrophic consequences accordingly .
So we have to be , we have to do this with in sixty days .
And I think , again , i'm profoundly excited , because I think we found a way to do it.
So I want to try to make this concrete for a listeners which you've absolutely unfairly , well , just know what I thought of another way we might do this .
And that's by combining in a kind of almost the gaming out of the future .
Let's say you are , and may you be successful with this piece , reprogramming the pandemic prevention platform program .
Let's say that you had that p three ability back in the nineteen eighteenth spanish floor , which i've seen different numbers .
I put fifty million people died during that the pandemic , if this technology existed , back it in the early part of the last century , how would that have unfolded ?
Do you think?
Oh , my , is that fifty million people don't die that we , and again , part of this is , you detect that we have a new virus .
There are a new version of influenza , and we detect very early on in the process when it's for starting out in a given country .
That is that that is happening .
We fought the switch , and we say , for that new virus , we need twenty thousand dollars that have to be ready within sixty days .
And then we go to win that outbreak is we identify who sick we treat those people that are most likely to be contagious , and we stopped the outbreak and its tracks , if we added , we could establish the spanish .
I think , even more importantly , right now today , you and I both know people who are getting very sick with influence , or seeing a severe season .
And we're seeing , unfortunately , children we're seeing , unfortunately , otherwise completely healthy people having nearby hospitalized and influence the doctor to us every year , we imagine a world where this platform could be used to take seasonal influence off the table as well.
Well , and an amazing thought , because I mean this gets back to you to the several times .
You said , what a privilege is to do what you're doing , because if you succeed , you will know , I know you wanna take this .
It is not pumping you like personalities .
It's more for what is doing for , you know , compulsory , but you will know you had a part of potentially saving millions of people's lives by cutting pandemic experiences off before they really get going and spread so quickly .
Quite an amazing.
And I would make two points .
The first is that on dark , my , my part , my team does not do this alone .
Darker does not do this alone .
We , we work incredibly closely with our colleagues and health and human services with other experts and department of defence , US, government , as well as full enterprise , as well as the private sector , and as well as the global community .
Ultimately , a global teamwork .
That's going to take these infectious diseases off the table .
But make no mistake , we can say it's unhardened ambitious , and it's crazy , but I challenge you to say , why not know why .
Why are we as a society putting incredible even more effort into taking these infectious diseases of the table if we have the scientific know how to do so this is.
Ownership focus is a moon shot , but why not go from moon?
And when I go for a moonshot for against something that could kill another fifty million people , why not take a moon shot against infectious diseases like malaria and technologies ?
I mean , we've seen , you know , there's , there's effort in there .
There is global efforts .
That's absolutely .
But why not?
So maybe just a little while going when I were kind of gushing about the molecular beauty in the biological beauty of anti bodies .
And the specifications have to go out and find whatever the health threatening agent might be in kind of the world that plays in our own bodies , fight against the health , compromising exposure .
So I guess I can't wanna ask you , do you have a favorite infectious disease in the sense that you admire what the bacteria was virus ?
Thus , he has learned how to do with the course of evolution.
So I answered in a slightly different way .
I think it's a , when we say we want to take infectious diseases off the table .
In some ways , it is ridiculous , because we're always gonna have , we're always going to have viruses and bacteria that are part of an actual and and we've always seen them as the enemy errors .
Passengers use one of the interesting ways to think about the problem is that a part of it is that there are a passage in a particular is how we respond and modulating , how our own body responds to passengers is a major theme of what we're trying to with the entire party has been one of many examples .
And so you are one of the traditional attitudes of analytics , and about it has been wonderful , certainly preferring impactful in terms of our society as as we , as we come along .
But we also discovered the unintended consequences of giving a broad spectrum and about it , conquering my and microbial resistance and things like that as well , so that the world that I imagine is that there is , I guess , like you said before , an appreciation of packages and appreciation of viruses and bacteria , understanding what they do and what they do not do , and what .
And it's not always wiping them out , but more about rendering them harmless or figuring out ways to kind of call exist with them is where I would like our thinking to go on the twenty first century.
It makes a lot of thanksgiving .
I brought statistics about the number of malaysian cells in me , and the number of bacteria cells .
And there were almost from just the numbers perspective , way more bacteria , mammalian we are .
But there most of the china's , this is a symbol .
This is , this is a mutually beneficial relationship .
And so it really , we should notice , we think about these , these microbes as things to to consider the management we shouldn't consider them.
The trade and the other parties that we learn from them , you know , it's , it's their evolution that also kind of inspires us .
And so it's uh in some ways , there are adversary , but in some ways , there are sort of that yellow in the super hero novels and things like that .
This idea of the the balance between the hero in the william and sort of that strange relative relationships that often in develops between the two and influential appreciation , is that I think that's often petitioned.
So mad , what we're coming towards the end of our time here , but i'm just wondering if there is something that didn't come up during our discussion that you think would be interested to our business , given , you know , your goal here of a privacy of reading us .
Some of some of the concerns we have about the passages in our environment.
One of our matches that doubles this idea of inspiring inspired creativity and new solutions to problems , and often times we say , by sort of recruiting and people who have not traditionally thought about our to help us with those solutions .
And so you know , I would love for the listeners of this podcast to be more inspired to address the province and infectious diseases .
And what I mean by that is , I would say , people like me have to be yellow .
We will invest our entire careers in our life , work into this , and we have deep knowledge , the subject .
But I love the thought of people that have expertise in computer science and mathematics , and what we would say will maybe those fields are necessarily .
Obviously , that's all I think that have worked in a solve the infection .
This is the promise of the twenty first century .
And so when I speak on this , it's almost part .
It's one part recruiting .
It's especially recruiting those that may not have all of the biases of the traditional experts in infectious disease to come up with a creative solution to solve it.
So that makes me think of a terminal europe , or what here are doubt , you know , the innovation ecosystem , because you just mentioned a whole bunch of disciplines that , you know , maybe when you first think about effectiveness , you do not think some of those come together .
So is there something about you and being here at DARPA that is conducive to shut the shaking up that innovation ecosystem in ways that could maybe move towards that you.
The doctor enables me to do that , because , again , they are a program announcements .
We say , okay , we set the requirements .
Solve this problem , make us a treatment in sixty days .
We know that they can do that alone , and it takes a more time to submitting a team .
So if you want funding from dark , but you're going to have to work with people , you're going to have to recruit it .
We designed it so that you will , and people that may not be the traditional subject matter experts .
But furthermore , every time I get a chance to speak and to talk about this problem , like i'm a spider cast , you know , again , I see it as a recruiting is a recruiting tool to inspire those to help , such as season .
Factories is threat.
Well , when i'm realizing that was , I do not want to prevent you for another minute from going out there and realizing your goal of taking the layout of a passage in a disease .
And we are out of time also .
So I just wanted , thank you .
This has been immensely fascinating for me , and I just wanna thank you for sharing stories about your life as a medical professional and how you are expressing your interests .
And girls here at dark.
Well , thank you very much for for allowing me to be parliament.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join it again for the next Voices from garbage .
For more information about kernel might happen .