Stealth technology, the Internet
GPS in the palm of your hand,
autonomous operation
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in
1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA
The defense Advanced research projects agency
Has been a driver of technology
Welcome to Voices from DARPA
A window on to DARPA's core of program managers
Their job
To redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I'm your DARPA host
And today have with me in the studio Carrie Bernstein
A program manager since 2012
In DARPA's Micro Systems Technology
That's the office
among the agency six technical offices that is devoted to
doing more with electrons photons and electromagnetism
It's been possible in the history of Technology
Terry's curiosity and Science and Technology knows no bounds
What is background in the micro lectronics industry has
everything to do with a mission he has taken on a DARPA
More than anyone
He's been pushing Technologies to reduce or even eliminate
The vulnerabilities to are billions of micro Electronics
chips to things like hacking counterfeiting cloning
Tampering and other nefarious actions that are just no good
at all for National Security
Prior coming to DARPA
Carry an electrical engineer by training
Like more than 30 years at IBM where he worked on a dizzying
array of technical subjects including
Microprocessor circuit design
High-performance low-power devices circuits and
architectures
New technologies that could replace the basic logic switches
that underlie almost all of chips today
Three-dimensional chip integration and the ways radiation
can damage chips
Terry has co-authored
Text books on circuit design he holds 155 patents
And is a fellow of the
Institute of electrical and electronics engineers
It's my pleasure to have you in the studio today
That's really mine
I'm always fascinated by the way people get interested in
science and technology if there was some transformative
moment or
Key person in your life that pointed you in that direction
Ivan it's sort of an ax
And if one of the most fortunate.
Accidents I've ever known
So you can it's a little kid I was always
Very interested in astronomy
Astrophysics
And God bless my daddy
He didn't understand any of the lecture
But I'd identify famous
Astronomers
Who's coming to
Lecture at the University
Chicago or University of Illinois and you would take
Was Wonder
And
I went to college anticipating I would
Study apps
Astronomy
And
I come from a family of fairly modest means
It became very apparent that
I needed to
Be able to pick up my
My college cost
And
Astronomers in astro-
Physicist just not in real high command at
What's the time
So I looked around in my credits
Reply to
To electrical engineering
And a normal physic
The night embarked on a career of engineering
And was the most wonderful accident
Let's talk about that move you made that pivot into
electrical
And really electronic engineering as it turned out right so
you can cuz you ended up going to IBM one of the most store
Ohrid companies and organizations when it comes to certain
the entire history of micro Electronics
And I just would be interested in hearing about the numerous
hats that you did wear there and
And what you learned about that
Technology
Timing is so much
And at the time that I graduated college
The technology that we use in current
Computing
CMOS
Was just in its infancy and just for listening to might not
know that that's such a familiar term if you're in that
micro electron
Phonics world the CMOS stands for what, Terry?
I've always wondered
CMOS stands for complementary
Metal-oxide-semiconductor
And this is this is so that the work
Horse technology that underlies pretty much any chip that
any of our listeners might have in their computers were were
Is there a dominant
preceding
CMOS
Field-effect transistors
was the technology called bipolar
The bipolar was very power-hungry
And the power was really limiting
How much you could do
So when I first
Entered
The space
CMOS was just starting out
And I had the great fortune of
Joining IBM
And IBM was leading the field in the development of
Processes
Circuit design
Architecture
For truly high performance computing
It's over a career of 30 years
I enjoyed this
This incredible ride
Bringing through new materials new applications
Producing the technology that went into machines that we
used to play chess
Play Jeopardy
Quite a ride
There's two things about your experience there that fast
they make
One is that you became part of that IBM team
With a bachelor's in electrical engineering right this was
from Washington University in st. Louis and then you've got
several
Phds worth of Education while you were there because you
don't have a Ph.D here Ivan I don't even have a masters
Don't even have a masters but when I see you in action oh my
gosh right it didn't clearly you got everything that that
any of them
Hyper educated people here have
Are you learned it
Kind of insult you in the in the industry
He was
A matter of luck
That
When I entered the field the industry was moving so fast
That for me to take time away to
To take time out
To go for my graduate degree
Was actually putting me behind
Because I was not getting to participate in all the
game-changing
New process
And Chip design
Technologies
that were
being produced
So I did take a few graduate courses
And at that point decided no I really want to
Being on the
The ground floor stuff
(right) I just never look back
I've been very fortunate to be surrounded by just incredible
human beings
There's this notion of a rising tide raises All Ships
And I've been so fortunate throughout my career to be
surrounded by truly incredible
Human beings.. that continues here
There's one other thing that I think emerge probably largely
out of your ID
Am experience
And that's your hundred and fifty-five
Who knows by now maybe this week you got another one
Tell me a little bit about
Some of the ones say that
Sick in your mind most that you're most proud of or that
perhaps had the most consequence
Perhaps the one that sticks out in my mind
The
Foremost
Is general purpose
Registers
for high performance
Computing
At the time and you'll have to explain that for me and what
does that mean
So
Clearly and thread parallel machines
There's simultaneous need for the same data in multiple
locations
In microprocessor
And at the time
The notion was well let's keep
Keep interrogating a memory over and over and
Send its results
To each of the separate place
This is where it might be needed
The GPR
The general purpose register
Invention
How did I develop with her
Allowed us to simultaneously access the same data
And send it to
Different locations
At the same time
And
It it found its way into a lot of very high performance
Which computer application
If I was to this day
And went when did you make this development and get this
patent
Early my career is one of one of my first one said sometime
in the 80s
Yes, late 80s.
Okay so let's not move to your DARPA adventure and another
thing I really like to learn about from PMs
is the mechanism by which you ended up getting here
So some .. a program manager and office director at a
conference
Others just were in love with DARPA for years and years and
they kind of made the initial
I reach out
How how did you actually end up here
So without going Kiki on you
Over the 30 years that I was at IBM
This this happened about seven years ago
About 7 years ago
There was a
I was involved of course in the design and
Fabrication
of high performance
computing elements
And
Became apparent there was a class of
Defects
The class of failures
That were
Exquisitely difficult
to
diagnosis
And  very difficult to image
Or to
Try to Define
But none the less they impacted the yield
Performance
And in some cases
Even had the ability to change
What the
Computer chip was supposed to do
so you're talking about defects that really go all the way
down to sort of the
Micron scale the transistor level element level
Scale of of these chips right?
- You're exactly right and I am not smart enough to be a
high-level
achitect I was very much
A hardware engineer
Very much about the hardware the physical design
And fabrication of the actually
- [..] and again to give the listeners vision of this I
believe we're probably talking
about defects that could be the size of like individual
biological cells 50 microns across
Even smaller
Indeed
Indeed and as technology scale
The size of the defects that were vulnerable to also
Continue
to shrink so
It's essentially
to keep
A very very clean environment
So
It became clear to me that there was a class of defects
That we were vulnerable to
Not just from a yield or functional point of view
But that potentially someone malicious
Could intentionally assert upon a process
Or a pond design
to
Perhaps
Compromise
The component or its function or its reliability its
lifetime
Make a long story short I
Became a
Contractor
Consultant to DARPA
And
- and with this consulting era
Or phase of your intersection with DARPA was that begin to
define the kinds of programs
That you ultimately would end up
Running
With the aim of addressing the concerns that you learned
about when you're ...
- indeed initially it was
To consult an existing program
And
I
Became involved in actually doing things
To computer chips
And then
The DARPA program would hire
Reverse Engineers to try to find
What was done
And
We continue to make progress
At both.
Detecting
Identifying those
Those features which couldn't couldn't be detected
And
One thing led to another and after
After about a year of consulting, DARPA finally said why
aren't
you come to DARPA
So I retired from IBM at that point
Then came to DARPA
To assume
The swim lane, if you will,  the swim lane of
hardware security
Right and released
Three of your programs and the names of them really kind of
Reflect just some of the goal that you have had in mind that
I've been working toward
some referring to Trusted Integrated Circuits which is known
as
In the short form is Trust
Integrity and Reliability of Integrated Circuits known as
IRIC
And the Supply-chain Hardware Integrity for Electronics
Defense
Which
Is .. known in short as SHIELD
Each one has its own individual aspects but together there's
a certain kind of theme
And I'm wondering if you can actually sort of talked about
them
Collectively
And of course diving into each one as you might
Feel so inclined
- indeed
God bless our warfighters
It is critical now
For us
To make sure that
Not just the mission is successful that that were protecting
the warfighters
executing at mission
The electronic components
We used to support that mission
Need to be
Authentic
We need to make sure that those parts do no more and no less
than they're supposed to
But they were built where they claim to be when they were
claimed to be
We have to make sure that they last for the full stated
lifetime
We have to make sure that
There is no
Nothing done to that component during the supply chain
during distribution
But there are no Trojan horses
Or Easter eggs
If you will better built in
And this is challenging right to rebuke because in the
Creation of a chip in the fabrication of a chip
There's so many players
It's so many different places that
And somebody can have your fingers on it
That that you really need some way of tracking ...
That's exactly right
Once Upon a Time
Chain of custody was a sufficient means
Up tracking
The authenticity and integrity of our component
But micro-electronics
Has indeed become global
And right about the time that I warned DARPA
That there could be
An issue in the space
The electronics
Space indeed
Went global
This the design is
We're not the only smart
people in the world
And so
Because of this
It was critical
That we develop those tools necessary
to
To be able to
Confirm the Integrity of the
One of the most audacious trajectory that you've been taking
and I get it just amazes me the progress that you and your
performers have been making
Is
With
Tiny little triplets about the size of
Glitter particles
I don't want to say anything more cuz I want you to
Tell listeners that just what you been up to with your
performers on this task
Before you even go there
I'm reminded that
It's one thing to come up with a challenge
But it's quite another
To go
Execute
to go accomplish
Such a challenge
And to be clear the heroes in the space
Are the performers that DARPA has
hired
Be a contract
To go solve this issue
I'm astounded daily just
the
creativity the amount of themselves that they pour into the
[...]
they skip holidays, they stay home over
they, they work
through Christmas sometimes in order to deliver
Products
such as those
The one that you're referring to , SHIELD
The threat space is large
The threat space
Of micro electronic component begins in design
It goes right through fabrication
And then after fabrication and packaging it goes through
distribution
SHIELD is a taggant
(标签剂, 原意"为了预防不法使用
而在炸药添加的物质,使它在爆炸后能被辨认出来")
Shield
Is is a means of authenticating
The parts that
We
Use it are most sensitive applications they have
To be the correct part
For a number of reasons the existing authentication
technologies were
necessary but not
sufficient
So SHIELD is a microscopic taggant(标签剂)
We hope to get it into the world records here before we are
all done
But it is used to make sure that this is the part
that we intended
to go into
our defenses
It has five special sauces
The first
Is a hardware root of trust
Every single microscopic
Shield
Chip
Has a unique identifier
II
Special Sauce
that each SHIELD die(压模) contains
Is an AES 256-bit
Encryption engine
100000 transistors
On a chip that is 100 microns by odd
Backgrounds
The 3rd
Is sensors that sense
If
The SHIELD ship has been corrupted
Compromised
Could [doucled] any given way
The 4th
Is an antenna
Because it's way too small
Contact
And so because that we have to talk to with RF
- You mean physical contact is just too small
That's correct
V is
Self destruct capability
But if you attempt to remove it
From The Host
Component
It will cease to be functional
The part is powered
By the
By the interrogator
It is completely seperated from
from the host component
The goal is that at any time
At any place
An untrained operator
with no special equipment
in this case being just an iPhone or smartphone
Can test the integrity of their components
At any time and place
And get immediate
Trustworthy
Results
For free
SHIELD cost one tenth of a cent
And the entire operation would cost less than $0.01
Every time
You wished authenticate the part
When you authenticate the part it also reports the GPS
location
And the TCP IP network address
Of where it was tested
In this way
At least for the most
Serious
Over counterfeit(伪造者) in clone threats
We believe we have a very cost effective solution
The goal is to make sure that
Counterfeiting and cloning
Becomes
Too expensive
and takes too long
For the bad guy
Right absolutely amazing description I mean this sounds to
me like a bat
The highest of high technology
A certain length in the synthesis the way you're mixing and
matching
Different kinds of Technologies also is just to me one of
the things that characterizes
A lot of what's going on here at DARPA
- one thing I'm somewhat of a pain in the rear to my
performers about
Because I'm just a knuckle-dragger hardware engineer
Everything we do
You have to be able to hold it in your hand
And this is a program
Especially this program where it's not rainbows coming out
of keyboards are unicorns sleeping over Terminals
and magic will happen
This has to be
Deterministic
Quantitative
Very analytic real engineering
And after the initial technologies were developed
SHIELD
Is about
Good engineering
We've engineered
A beautiful product
All right well since you're all about that kind of ground
truthing
Where are we at with the with this
Program with these tiny little
Triplets how would you characterize the status
SHIELD is a 3-phase program
Phase one was to go develop
Those five core Technologies
Because they really did not exist
At that scale all five
Have been demonstrated to be
Functional
Phase two is the integration of those technologies
Into the shield
Prototype
Phase 3 of the program
Which is the field test
Of Shield
Will begin
Early in 2018
The field testing
Is supported by
Some wonderful companies that we won't identify right now
that have volunteered their supply chain
And we will do things
What's the components
Windshield attached
And use their supply chains
And we will see how effective Shield is
In catching compromises
So Kerry, we've talked about
Shield
I do want to go back to to the other programs that you work
on one of them is completed now and one of them is still in
progress it was
Start with trusted integrated circuits (TRUST)
https://www.DARPA.mil/program/trusted-integrated-circuits
which I believed is
kind of one of the earliest programs you took on.
TRUST was the program that I actually began supporting
before I entered DARPA
Trust was a program
To make sure that we could verify
that a part is doing no more and no less
than it is supposed to do
Trust was a large program
Lots and lots of achievements
We developed microscopes
We develop solutions
For pulling netlist(网表) if you will
the schematic from chips
To make sure that the schematic is what it's supposed to
We look at both COTS
(commercial off-the-shelf) product
As well as Gods parts
Government-owned components
We looked at field programmable gate arrays (FPGA)
As well as ASIC(专用芯片)
The output of that program
Is installed in a number of agencies
All over the country
And still being [...]
Ready when you mentioned ASIC,  field programmable gate
array (FPGA), those are just names for
other kinds of categories of integrated circuits
That have different capabilities
But all of which are used today and all of which we really
need to feel very confident about
- that is correct
So that's TRUST and that completed
A year or two ago when did that ...
- yes, it included
About
18 month ago
So obviously there's parts of the spirit of that program
that are part of SHIELD
And the other program I just wanted to say a little bit
about this one continues
Today and that's the integrity and reliability of integrated
circuits program or IRIS
The question that Iris answered was
If indeed we know that this component
Has not been compromised
In its function
Can we still be assured that it has not been compromised
And its integrity
How do we make sure with
With a low sample size
That this component indeed fulfills
Its lifetime spec
Its reliability
That it is up to the task
A performing
For $20,000 an hour
Or 100000 power in hours
Or whatever the spec is
That mission that is critical
To the defense
That it's installed in
Okay and this is to defend against such things as
counterfeiting practice
where an old chip might be taken out of some unit
it might then be blacktop right where new kind of
packaging is put on with new printing looks new but in fact
it's old and so might not be able to actually live
Up to its
the spec that a user expects
That's correct Ivan
Just like human beings age
In automobiles rust
There's a lifetime to electronic components
And
The lifetime must be ...
we depend on that lifetime when the  system
Is built
For that part to execute its function
Even without the malicious intent
We need to know we need to be able to
Very quickly assess
The reliability
Of a part
and currently
The reliability science
Is is a
Is very involved
Painful
Long-term goal
And so
IRIS
Looked
To try to
Improve the turnaround
and the testing
Reliability
I want to move to a couple of other questions before we we
close out
One of them is really I want you to reflect a little bit
about micro electronics
As a technology in your
roll, your several decades roll in
Pushing that technology forward and doing whatever you can
to ensure the integrity and safety of it
And you know with some programs even moving forward thinking
about
Next generations of micro-electronic devices even in the
nanoscale area
So so that we continue to have a
Progressive technology in micro-electronics
As you think about all of that me what excites you about
this category of technology and, Kerry ,what concerns you
about it
I've been few months ago I had the
Privilege of
Spending a week with a 311th Fighter Squadron
At Holloman Air Force Base
In New Mexico
And after spending a week of them sharing
With me
What they do
I have the opportunity at the end of that week
To describe
To them what I do
And that's when it hit me
My son is training to be an A-10
Fighter pilot
The warthog
And when I
Got in front of the audience
They all look like Mikey
They all look like
My son
And, I mean, it's hard
It's even hard now to talk about it
It's not just
As a DARPA program manager
or as an engineer
As a parent
How many people
Everyone, of course, wishes the best
Our warfighters
How many people actually
are in the position to do something about it
It was one of the greatest
epiphanies (顿悟)
Of my time at DARPA
was to realize that
I've been trusted
With
All this
Resource
And funding
And
Security
Given everything I need
To go do what I know needs
to be done
If I fail it's my fault
Because this
God bless this agency is giving me it's giving me
Everything
I need to succeed and it's all on me
And that's what's driven me and
In front of an audience like that
They deserve no less
Thanks for that.
You've been here since 2012 so you've been here longer than
a lot of program managers and you probably are coming toward
the tail end
When are you leaving
September of
September 18th
I'm not actually sure you're even going to be able to see
SHIELD through all the way to the end I know that that's
you're gonna go
most of the way but I'm I imagine you're going to be handing
off some of the final
Testing
I'm just wondering with six years of of participation in
this agency which is part of the the
Innovation ecosystem
What you have learned about it as an organization and as a
culture in technology
DARPA is a incredible place
Just incredible
Place
Of course it's a human organization so it's given to
All the variation that
Human
Endeavor
Introduces but it's such a rare place
To be given the opportunity
To go
Develop those ideas
Which you know
Can be made to work
Is a once in a life-time
Do you have any thoughts about
a post-DARPA phase of of your professional adventure
There are certain capabilities
This nation urgently needs
And I'm pouring the concrete(混凝土)  in those holes
As quickly as I possibly can
My intent when I complete my DARPA post
Is to be able to move into a position where I will be
allowed to continue
to pour that concrete
Well I for one will be excited to watch you as you take your
programs through to the point that you will be able
Able to end to see what you do
When you leave here now bringing your DARPA experience,
maybe perhaps back into the private sector and industry
whatever you might do
Where was I wish you the best of luck
We are at the end of our time here
for th is podcast I just want to thank you for
Spending this time with me
Oh thank you Ivan
It's been a pleasure
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us
I hope you join us again for the next Voices from DARPA
For more information about Kerry Bernstein
the programs he runs
And the other breakthrough technologies DARPA  but is
working on
visit DARPA.mil
And for links that enable you to download this podcast go to
the Voices from DARPA page
on DARPA's website