我。
Technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand on the most operation technology , is a driver of our times since its founding a one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , double the defence advanced research project has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window at the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine was possible .
My name is iphone a motor on your dark horse .
On this occasion , i've invited my colleague in darkness , public affairs group types to join me as a as we speak to doctor timothy chan , who joined the dark as a program manager in twenty sixteen .
You might hear some ambient sounds like birds or sirens .
That's because recording our conversation from our respective homes , as we do our part to slow the spread of cognizing team , as the pandemic has opened , their daily routines .
Work continues on more than two hundred and fifty programs .
Each was a vision of useful technology that's out of reach at the moment , but I couldn't become less enriched in the future capital , even working closely or doctor tim chang can help get word out about his program .
So when did you take it?
Thank you .
I will I have been looking to have a fruit receipt to the progress on two of programs , often substantial tactics are offset for short and the dark of separate training challenges or safety challenge , for sure for the outset , program , two teams have developed two different storm systems , open architectures in physical text bans .
The program also has what I called swarms printers , organizations competitively selected through contract opportunities to focus on a particular technology grocery up about every six months .
The program hosts a few tests with the spirituals to demonstrate and further develop their solutions .
The safety challenge is a price base challenge , with teams from all over the world competing in the systems , competition with physical platforms , the virtual competition , or in both team score when the robots accurately identified artifacts , a first responder or a war fighter might encounter underground like a backpack draw or a thermal .
Representing a survivor .
Tim , thank you for joining.
To talk about your work.
Yeah , I suppose to be here .
Thank you so much .
I'd like to hear more about your programs and technologies are working toward .
But start with your research , reduction and how you came to dark up .
You have degrees in mechanical and aerospace engineering .
But where did your interest start ?
And are there any significant influence that could be people or events that stand up for you?
Yeah , well , I mean , I think I.
Really appreciated and was curious about how the world works .
And from that perspective , being an engineer means that we not only need to understand how things worked , but also also wants to try to fix them .
If we came out , of course , and come , come up with new ideas .
And so I think a lot of the excitement that goes on around robotics on also touched me , especially as a undergrad where I had a chance to work on the coroner , university robotic cycle team .
And that left whole new experience is really understanding what it means .
The main technology real .
This is granted about playing robots occur , but it meant that people had to come together , share ideas , worked together and then create the sets of robots that were doing , or be something really fun with a soccer , but doing a purpose .
And I really inspired me to continue that line research.
Could you go from that experience with robot soccer to coming to dialogue as a program manager?
The inspiration perhaps comes all the way back when my sister was a software at west points , and I just started my first year in grad school .
And that's when I am eleven hit .
And I knew at that point , my sister being part of that , yang army went to be called upon to action , and it was really hard for me to sit in this supposed every time of egyptian , and think that my kids just would be are fighting , you know , the source and spouted a lot about whether or not to , unless myself pondered what I could do to serve my country in that .
And I remember my mentor at the time said , I totally understand if you want to , I need to understand , you know , go , go , do that .
But remember that there is an opportunity that the worst that you do here , pursuit of your banks agrees , can ultimately , potentially do more and serve more and have deeper impact .
And I think , from that point toward , I saw that my sister went into harm's way , but I remain in grade school , finish .
My degree continues .
I always have in the back of my mind that I wanted to make the world a slightly safer , better place .
And I think that let me to pursue in my position , my factory position as the neighbor's graduate , which allowed me to explore mission relevance , research problems while also engaging with our general officer core , which is incredibly rewarding , and then also ultimately LED to a research portfolio there that brought exposure to the institutional global and from that interaction , was able to find my way ultimately developed to hopefully realize some of that question that wasn't far.
那你们你有这个。
You've given a couple of examples of how your career interacted with dark before you actually join the agency as a principal investigator , and also not honesty .
But knowing the team that was participating in a dark attendant , when you talk a little bit about how those experiences , in addition to those life experience is that I think we're so good , so important to informing your work how they influence the way you shape the programs that you run.
For the agency , it takes me back to think about the double grand challenge .
What was a great student ?
I saw this announcement about this auditor's effort to take robots and driving across the desert and economic special .
And I remember thinking , and I was just a junior red student , but leaning over to my favourite student piercing .
While this is really cool , and then discovered that the contact would be feeling a team largely comprising undergraduates .
But I still remember the inspiration of that challenge offered to me and my fellow graduate students and undergraduate student , and I think that a negative inspiration was something like that continued burning .
I think uh it continues to be there and drives us to go and do sometimes really are these things , and even as opportunities come to double and have the opportunity to go off and do those types of our dishes , things that really inspired the nature of both of my problems .
I think you are also able to work at the next graduate school , which I would really like him to be an incubator .
Really great ideas .
We have general officers who have a lot of fleet experience .
They come to getting their gradual level education they bring with them a lot of experiences that meet academic research .
And boom , you have a really great fusion of meat , and said that you are .
And from my perspective thing , MPSis an incubator .
I view darker as an accelerator of those ideas , really take those ideas and run with a bigger , faster.
This is a good point for us to talk a little bit more about programs in your portfolio said to challenge and offset offensive swarm enabled tactics , the obvious tie between the two is the focus on the autonomy and robotics .
But there are some significant differences in the outcome goes too , for instance , the focus on human swarm , tiny and upset .
Could you talk through some of these common teams , and then also some of the key differentiators for these two programs , and then also some of.
Jerry offset is a program where we seek to discover the swarm system technologies that will allow aborigines of hundreds of two hundred and fifty air ground brown operating in complex urban environments in support of small unit operations .
The subscription in challenge is all about innovative approaches to map , navigate and search complex underground environments .
I think the unifying theme and what drives me is to see robots in the real world , upgrading in complex environments .
I think robotics is one of those fields where you can just only work in theory , or you can only work in in kind of challenge air .
You kindly need to bring both of them together and see robot working in the world .
And so I think that something that really inspires me is obtaining that strict , that something that we were , what is really embrace is seeing robots work until the key emphasis for both of the ancient tea challenge .
It is putting robots in really challenging environments in a field , robotic sense and seeing what they have to do , where the gaps might still be for what they're not yet able to do .
So far offset were interested in those really complex urban environment , specifically those aspects of the urban news that stress a tony today .
And that includes everything from the fact that you might not have a line of sites , because the building in the way you can move this really , because there is a lot of obstacles or things , spoke in your lines , and the fact that you have to look up and around , because you have the superstructures all around this , well .
And so how do you get air grand robots stock in that kind of environment ?
And then on top of that , and because the suburban , we'd like to push young , how do we get hundreds of robots to be able to go often , do those kind of things in a complex environment .
I think the similarity with the supreme challenge is the sense said these underground environments are equally complex .
And not only are they complex , in the sense of , hey , we don't typically spend a lot of time in other environments .
One might argue , but also the fact that the unknown underground , it makes it even dangerous for people to go in .
And so this is an opportunity for again , robots , the , the shine .
And so whether there was are in human mcdonald's environment , such as mines , two urban underground to naturally current cave environments .
This is an opportunity for again , roberts , to understand what the current limitations of autonomy and robotics are today , and really inspired the temporary shelters necessary to congratulate the environments in the future .
I think both of the programs offered the for robotics , but also just brought the researchers , geologists , city planners , even kind of micro climate researchers , can not speak to what impact a holistic systems design .
And when I say systems , i'm not talking just about one robot .
I'm talking about all the robots working together .
The team , the humans supervisor or the humans .
Warm team member , understanding how that holistically comes together to deliver the capabilities at all .
Top civilizing the end.
Could I get you to talk a little bit more about human swarm , teaming at this discovery ?
I wish that looks like.
Yeah , the name of an economic researcher is , is , however , described myself , but in thinking about the economy and swarm attorney , in the sense of having large girl teams of measurement makes iron ground working together .
We can't leave the humanitarian because how we design that economy is impacted by how english , the human swarm commander , working with a technology .
And so the opposite program intentionally focuses on those two pillars of swarm tournament , human .
And in that sense , the author programs about discovering what it means when you have hundreds of robots operating a complex environment and the intense of the program is to kind of understand , you know what works and what work we can't .
We certainly cannot have one hundred and two hundred million round with joysticks in conducting and urban operation .
So what does it mean when we try to cancel it was that team member commander role for large cultural teams ?
Robot , what , what does it mean ?
Does it mean ?
We present information in a different way ?
Does it mean that they have to interact with with the robots at michigan level , and so the way we think about it in the officer program is in the context of translating commanders in tents in two days , machine , understandable swarm techniques .
These warm tactics give us a glimpse as to how we can potentially interact with these large scale teams , and ultimately boils down to understanding with the language because the swarm , intellectual grammar .
What is the language by which the swarm can understand ?
The government is trying to get done commanders intent , and conversely , the commander understanding what the source actually doing is it doing what I asked to do when things are benedict or so , the two way street , and that's why we call it the human swarm team inside is not a human storm control .
It's really the interaction between the human and the swamp .
And so we imagine also that it's not just going to be a screen with a mouse .
That's gonna solve this problem of interacting with these article team .
Yeah , gesture or boys or organized and virtual reality .
Maybe these are other tools that we cannot take advantage of the help inform how we interact .
These are.
For the safety challenge , it's an extended event , so it's over a couple of years .
They are working with these teams .
And you divided it up into circuits .
Could you talk a little bit about your goal for each other and how you divided?
The challenge policy management were really interested across my double portfolio of putting robots in the real world and having them operate in complete environmentals .
And mommy taken out a look at underground environments .
There are so many different types of underground environments that just to solve the problem in once of the men went vienna , really to be able stands and identify what works and what doesn't work in underground environments .
And so what we've done is for the safety challenge we highlighted is underground , environmentally canoes and and minds .
We've articulated their urban underground environments .
They are naturally creative systems and trying to figure out what kind of robotic technologies will allow us to operate relatively across all three of those types of underground environmentals .
So what I bought the spaghetti is , how do we capture all of that ?
And so one way to do that is to focus on each individuals of domain and were doing that in the context of three , namely the tunnel circle , urban circuit and upcoming , we have a gift circuit by , as I highlighted , it's not being the best woman were the best runner .
It's really about being the best here .
And so we want to see how these individual events in form the designs , and even the concept of vibrations for those technologies .
But it's a final event where will be able to merge elements of all three of those of them into the screen .
Finally , epic final course , and understand what it means to have truly adaptive technology , robotic systems that can upgrade across those subjects.
Tim , both of your programs really inspired the imagination to think of all of this kind of interaction with with you are human beings and with machines all trying to work together to a year in new ways .
The subject also comes to my mind as a kind of fascinating and development that it forces you to think about being underground , right in most of the time .
We think about being on the surface when plains all the time .
But it's aware it was your spell longer a cave .
Or do you really think much about being underground , if you are , you know , a metro worker , and you are in tunnels under the city .
Where were girl ?
But i'm just wondering if your experience with some tea has changed the way you think about in some ways , being in the world because your mind so much underground.
Hey , yeah , we'll say everything takes a different lands when you put in the context of each of these programs and safety is no different .
I think everything from when I am , you know , I know about this .
You know what's one of the time , many ways , you know , taking a look every time I go and take a subway into a tunnel , one , i'm driving , or anything like a longer science kind of inspires a little bit of tea .
And I say , for anyone who watches movies quite a lot , there are many occasions where there folks in underground tunnels are , basements are empty malls in sublimes or whatever involves now that they watch the movies with the challenge lengths , i'm often catching out all those a great idea for the subject , but I maybe the other more technical , serious answer here is , I think , thinking about the underground has let me to understand that the challenges are quite severe .
You don't have GPS , and at seven times something we need to get the job done for for a robot .
Communication is horrible , down there .
And so it makes us think a little bit differently about what it means to want to communicate what information do I want to ?
And this isn't just for robots to turn out that this is applicable to human teams that I figured out there as well .
And so that's really even both a stronger , inspirational motivation to pursue boundaries of the technologies , but is also really grieving the appreciation , but also of all the participants of the challenges that resigned underground.
Well , thanks tim , for sharing some of your personal notes from the underground and the challenges of working in separately in settings .
And now let me pass the tongue back to capital.
Thank you .
Ivan , a team .
You talked about your experience , working with graduate students from the safety challenge perspective .
But you worked with students in an earlier challenge when you first came to dark up for the swarm talent , could you describe that program and what you learn from?
I know we talk about how I found my way to dark up earlier , but in fact , I think it was .
The swarm .
Challenge comes up that really feel the deal for bringing me the dark .
And the idea was building on the research and previously of getting large teams of air vehicles .
In this case , my prior research was on getting fifty fixed doing aircraft , the fixing airplane , like grounds are loved and and doing interesting things in the sky .
And we were able to leverage that body of work and the idea that came from it , and what we built out here , desperate upon my arrival with the service academies , swarm challenge that your reference , this was really fun because we wanted to capitalize the momentum of of technology development of getting large numbers of aircraft laughed and also create an opportunity to help frame the next generation of military officer by working with the military services academies .
Name is the neighborhood academy and the military academy at west point and bring those kids and michigan and work with them to understand what it means to work with these types of strong technologies .
And so the phrase that we like the user was , had you go from there to swarm in eight months because of time , the , these credits and michigan head in their capital design projects in their senior year to complete this , this project .
And so that was basically getting a fixed wing in quarter drawings .
I gave each team , and they get to pick their own lineup of twenty five phones on the side .
We set up bounty castles on the opposing sides of the field , and this , in lifeline explanation , until we have bouncy castles and you'll score points by lending your john and the opposing teams .
County castle , but you want to defend your own home , bouncy castle , basically AAsimulated lazy pack in the sky .
And so it was this really great understanding how heady plays , strong offensive players from defense and seeing a heavy gears turned for these categories , really , with the separate technology before and apartment with research engineers and lives and others to make this all happen .
It was incredibly rewarding to kazakhstan , and germany would never thought that they would be part of something that bob , that for leading in their time at the economies , I think , and they walked away , recognizing that their dogs and in the deal deal that is thinking so far in advance that they have the region to , in our twenty twenty one year old , the start , the process of tech revolution , right ?
So I think that again , inspired me .
I think that that experience bothers and enforced my core team of challenge believers as a model for driving technology , and that allowed us to go forward with kind of pitching the supreme challenge as the next board step in driving a tonight member , but acknowledge.
And so let me just follow that with an institutional question , I am in dark .
It is a place where engineers like you .
Tim can develop a technology vision .
And as I see the opening of this package redefine what is possible .
But what is it about dark institutionally , do you think that creates these opportunities?
I definitely barber has a secret toss that it has continued to be able to generate the ideas , but also create an executive realized of ideas .
I think , on the one hand , certainly from the technical technology office , from which I hear , we really love seeing technologies demonstrated so systems being brought together and realize in some sort of fuel test demonstration , and I think that's one end on the other hands .
We're interested in creating honeymoon in a foundation honey .
Areas of research that had really been thought about .
And I think that being of that's backroom and do it in the context of , you know , one hundred years of programming and juice across three hundred programs is a pretty phenomenal .
I say , one other way I describe , therefore , the suicide in a one of my colleagues had previously described research .
This way .
Is there a lot of folks out there that might say some research is impossible .
Digital nation possible .
And michelle at the time said , actually know it's not impossible .
It's rather , it's impossible .
It's just that it hasn't been done yet .
It is not that it can be done .
Benjamin and I like to embrace that philosophy and everything that may I try to touch in the sunset , just because I hadn't been done before .
It is not proof that it can't be done .
In fact , its challenge that maybe everyone who can , who can do it , and doubt we really give us for the tools and inspiration , and the kind of community a day that was the support , but also my , yeah , program manager colleagues , when I see all the amazing things that they are making possible .
The things that once might have been considered impossible , or simply just opportunities.
We're getting towards the end here , but I want to get into a couple of questions that are more about technology in general .
First , I want to ask you about the kinds of technology is developing .
We're talking about humans and machines working together .
There are parts of one long history going back even to nineteen sixties , in thinking about that particular kind of powerful dynamic .
So i'm just wondering what excites you most about these technologies.
The egg said it is the intersection of the human machines and biotics that uh in a lot of groups , genetic code already .
So I am in alleviating a lot of them sending on their shoulders for you .
I think the thing that perhaps excites me a lot about these technologies .
It's the idea that we'll have to look at our robotic teams in thirty different ways .
What I mean by that is a lot of maybe a research has been done .
What means work with a single robot , or maybe a few robots , but we're narrowly pushing what it means to work with multiple , many robots .
And I think this is a really new research to be heard in the science , said the way I would interact with my small team of researchers , or at a start of company , or something like that is very different men , how I would want to interact a larger company or a larger project , team , and vehicles are not obviously with teenager robots .
And so I think how we work with mixed , but physically mixed in terms of your own , but uh mixed as in canada , the functions that these robots will play in a composition of a team .
I think the temporary shells is really going to can open up not only new capabilities , but also plane proceeds for new foundation of research to be done as well .
So I think that cannot be one of the , interestingly , behind that , both of these problems , it is understanding what it means to work when you have high complexity in a robot .
Team is so , and that high complexity , new math , new communication networks , new computer methodologies , new sensing approaches or new algorithms .
And I think both of these programs have started to , there are some other fruit out and lay similar foundations .
So that's been really , really exciting.
And that's a lot of foundation to lay down .
We all know how much it takes for people to work well together .
So i'm not surprised to hear about the enormity and complexity of to realize obedient in which humans and machines were together almost as if they were one hybrid organism , very cold.
It is , and I think it's important to know how that work is continuing .
I've been reference .
This is the beginning of the episode , but there is no doubt copyright team will be an historic marker for all of it would be interesting to know tim how it is affected your work , and perhaps the near term goals in deliverables for some of these programs you're working on.
Yeah , no doubt cabinet in has had its impact in one of the things about drugs that it's all about to be neighborhood and adapted from several , I think , given in the context of challenge , the impact really is felt in the context of , as I mentioned earlier , about trying to get robots in the real world .
And when it's difficult to go to the real world to get those lessons learned and put a robust in those contest , which , which cabinet in this really limited ability to do that , it definitely does impact the type of progressive and lessons learned we can achieve .
But in that same way , both of these problems have assumed of leveraging the virtual environment kind of balance in couple and accelerate the lessons that we learn in the world .
And so , and obviously we have two virtual environments that allow us to explore , test , simulate form , tactics and execution .
And we do that with real environmental attacks , said we will have a three day model of a textile , and we'll replicate what it is that we're testing in a synthetic environment .
And the way the officer from michael was at the robot , whether they're simulated real , don't know that they're politicians to the simulated world friends of we really need to that aspect , the officer programs so that we can still continue to discover new ideas and strengthen the insights that we hope for translate .
The first time he felt tested the officer program for the safety challenge again , that virtual environment plays a huge role for safety and the sense that we virtual competition alongside the system competition .
So words we might be physically putting robots in underground environments for the system competition .
We've created that some tea simulator that allows for teams to not only practice and test , but also compete in advertising environment .
And so nevertheless , environments given us opportunity , and in some ways of relief out for teams , you are constrained and being able to go to the site , the context I can still do some of that development in the simulated contacts to go and and you're keeping the ball rolling forward to his absence of tear , both about keeping up the momentum of a research , just like the rest of the air .
Impacts , of course , is the community a described earlier about getting together and facilitating the exchange of information or or bouncing ideas .
You're seeing what works them and imitating it in my own research , or whatever I mean , each of these teams benefits from the infrastructure is very different , but also in performance faster than since the community , through on my community from , we're being able to open up a collaborative web space for teams to share their software .
Deliverables are always that were trying to live in this new.
Jim , for your time , for your insights into your work with dark bed .
It's been a pleasure .
Thank you so much .
I will encourage everyone to spend some time exploring the safety challenge , play list on darkness , youtube channel , to get an idea of how tackling the underground .
You can see a couple of recent offset field experiments on the youtube channel as well .
And ivan , it's been great during the newspaper holes .
I look forward to seeing you back in the studio.
Yes , and it was my pleasure too to share .
This is a tag team packets with you tapped , and also just to learn so much about what you're doing .
Teams really , really fascinating .
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from darker for more information about doctor timothy chan , his programs and the other breaks who technology is dark , is working on visit darker .