Stealth technology, the Internet,
GPS in the palm of your hand
autonomous operation ...
technology is a driver of our times since its founding
in 1958 in the midst of the Cold War
DARPA the Defense Advanced Research
Projects Agency has been a driver of
technology.
Welcome to Voices from DARPA, a window
onto DARPA's core of program managers.
Their job -- to redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato and I am your
DARPA host. Today I am pleased to have
with me in the studio Dev Palmer, a
program manager and DARPA's
Microsystems Technology Office (MTO) .
Since 2012 he has been in that office overseeing
a portfolio of
projects all of them with the goal of
pushing electronics into smaller, faster
and generally more capable territory. So
welcome Dev to Voices from DARPA.
Thank you, Ivan. - Dev, I'd like to start by just
finding out a little bit about you and
so maybe you can tell us something about
your background and interests and how
you became a program manager at DARPA.
Well, like every red-blooded American
teenage boy I started playing electric
guitar back then you played through an
amplifier that used vacuum tubes and
there was some cachet (威望) with the soft glow
of the vacuum tubes and the warm sound
that you get when you play your guitar through them
but being naturally curious
I started to wonder how they worked and
how does the guitar take the motion of
the strings and turn it into an electric
signal that led me into studying electro-magnetics
ended up pursuing engineering Electrical Engineering as a
career
and started working as a government program manager for the
Army Research Office
about 15 years ago until I ended up here
let's talk a little bit about some of
the programs then since 2012 that you
have been overseeing and I'm thinking
perhaps we can start with the Terahertz (太赫兹, 10的12次方)
electronics program
and I'm gonna sort of steal your thunder
slightly here by telling or listeners
that in 2014 it garnered(获得) a Guinness world record but I'm
gonna let you talk
about the program and and what that
superlative(最好的) moment was when you heard
about that record
Dev: That was a lot of fun indeed you can
think about transistors like you think
about guitar strings the low frequency
guitar strings can be heavy and loose
but as you move up in frequency the
strings get thinner and you have to wind
them tighter it's kind of the same with
transistors when you're working at low
frequencies you can get away with large
dimensions and as you move up in
frequency those dimensions have to
shrink(缩小) so in the Terahertz electronics
program we really took that to an
extreme it's like when you're putting
new strings on your guitar and you're
tuning it up and you're winding(绕) the strings(弦)
tighter(更紧) and tighter you think
they can't get any tighter and they're
about to break but you still keep
winding and finally you hit the note you
want it worked kind of the same way in
the Terahertz electronics progress... - so
let me just stop you a little bit before
you say more about the program because
I'm not sure all of our listeners would
have heard the term Terahertz and I know
the a) above middle C on a guitar
vibrates at 440 Hertz that's 440
vibrations(振动) per second
tell us what 1 terahertz is in
comparison to that 1 terahertz is 10 to the 12th (10的12次方)
vibrations per second which is
1 comma zero zero zero comma zero zero
zero comma zero zero zero comma zero
zero zero cycles per second that's one
trillion that's correct one trillion
cycles per second so that's very hard to
achieve in an electronic circuit right
yes very hard in fact when the program
started none of the performers believed
it could be done and during the program
there were many instances when we were
thinking that maybe we should just
circle the wagons and try to make the
electronics weren't work better at a
lower frequency but one of my colleagues
Bruce Wallace said that
Chuck Yeager didn't get famous for
flying 85% of the speed of sound so if
we were gonna have a terrorist
electronics program we were gonna have
electronics at work that one terahertz
so everybody found a new knobs to twist
and kept working on it and finally we
did hit that mark. right okay and and at
that time that what and perhaps it is
now you can let me know what the status
is but it actually was the fastest
switching electronic circuit on the planet
it's the fastest linear amplifier on the
planet at the time and still is and I
imagine it will be for some time to come
okay so it took you you know you had to
inspire your performers those groups
that worked on this to to actually
achieve this you went through great
pains to do this why what what do you
get by having a terahertz switch
Dev: There's two things you get from moving
transistor performance up in frequency
1. is you access much wider bandwidths
which is like having a bigger pipe to
push your data through in a
communication system and the other is if
you work on a transistor enough to to
make it capable of working at a
terahertz you have to eliminate(消除) all the
parasitic capacitances(寄生电容) resistances(电阻)
inductances(电感) that limit its performance
and then when you take that same
transistor and operate down at lower
frequencies say in the millimeter wave
the performance of the transistor is
much better you get lower noise better
linearity(线性度) better dynamic range(动态范围) and maybe
most importantly better power efficiency
interesting so you get this circuitry(电路系统)
that that can switch it a terahertz that
then has additional benefits
just because you've pushed the
technology for it and you can apply it
elsewhere in the electronic space
exactly right so let's let's move to
another program that I guess really gets
back to what we were talking about
before which is vacuum electronics this
one is called INVEST and that stands for
innovative vacuum electronics science
and technology program so I'd love you
to tell us a little bit about the origin
of that program what problems and or
what technologies is it
is designed to create and what its
status is at the moment
terahertz electronics program pushed solid-state
electronics up to an extremely high
frequency but if you're trying to get
extremely high frequency and extremely
high power at the same time vacuum tubes(真空管)
are pretty much our only option the
problem is that vacuum tubes scale with
operating frequency the dimensions get
smaller and smaller as you go up in
frequency and so at some point you just
can't build them so the INVEST program
is exploring several different areas one
is advanced manufacturing for example
using 3d printing additive manufacturing
the vision there is to be able to draw
the tube in a CAD program ship the CAD
file to the printer and end it end up
with a millimeter wave tube voila
right out of the machines and CAD being
a computer-aided design and the idea
here then is you have to make the
cavities(腔/孔) in which sort of the the the
frequency generation is occurring really
small smaller than ever before for the
frequencies are interested in the area
the cavity(腔体) dimensions get smaller and
the alignment(对准) requirements get more
critical so if you could build the whole
tube at once you'd have the dimensions
and the alignment in one shot there's
another thrust(推力) in the program that's
looking at modeling because as you move
up in frequency, small variations in the
manufacturing process can produce large
variations in device performance and
you'd like to be able to know which of
the dimensional parameters is most
important so you need a modeling program
to do that then there are other
components of the tube the cathode(阴极) and
the beam(波束) wave interaction structure (波束相互作用结构)
where we just went out looking for new
and interesting ideas maybe that would
just blow away the current way of
building tubes and eliminate the problem
with manufacturing altogether okay so
let's say the program ends up being
successful and why shouldn't we think
otherwise
so you end up having a new kind of
family of technologies where you've got
this high frequency and you've got the
high-power
where do you imagine these technologies
finding an important place so you hear a
lot about 5g as the next generation of
cellphone communications
they're talking about using frequencies
that are in the millimeter wave region
of the spectrum but still hard to get
devices that operate in that range
especially with enough power to close a
communications link over a long distance
so that's where the INVEST program comes
in you get millimeter wave operation and
high-power in an affordable power
efficient device and again using your
pipe metaphor(比喻) which I really like you
have you will have bigger pipes on
connecting our cell phones to the system
with this technology that might come out
of the INVEST program yes absolutely
you're not gonna find a vacuum tube in
your handset I'm pretty sure but it
could see some use at base stations and
definitely in military communication
systems all right and so let's talk
about just one more program and this is
one of your latest which is a mouthful
to say one of these short forms I like
is M cubic (M的立方, MMM三个词，后文有提到) if you actually write that
out that's M3 I see but the real long
form I'll say it'll take two seconds or
three magnetic miniaturized and
monolithically integrated components
program did I actually say that right
yes that's exactly alright so I feel
like I've accomplished something
okay well the primary goal of the
program is to be able to hit a great
magnetic materials with the
semiconductor devices that everybody
knows it loves today if you dive a
little deeper into it we've achieved an
incredible degree of integration of
electronic components like resistors (电阻)
transistors (晶体管) and capacitors (电容) largely
because you have a large pallet(托盘) of
materials to work with that have
properties that are relevant to
electronic components with magnetic
components there are only three elements
that have intrinsic(固有的) magnetic properties
so it's been very difficulty to find a
way to integrate those with
semiconductor processes
what we're trying to do with the program
is leverage some work that's been
in material science on magnetic
materials over the last decade or so
with microwave engineering to produce
integrated components where you can
actually access that magnetic physics in
an electronic circuit in a very compact
form factor so let me ask you this
because I'm already amazed by the chips
in our lives right they can do so many
things they have there's part of so many
technologies what more are you gonna get
by taking small magnetic components now
and integrating them into those those
ubiquitous chips from the user point of
view you probably won't see anything
much different but from the
technologists point of view lower
frequency systems use magnetic
components all the time but they're
large and heavy and tend to be difficult
to integrate so you kind of push that
functionality out to the edges of the
circuits and use it in a non-ideal way
so give me an example or two though of a
specific technology where these magnetic
components are central to it even though
they're not yet integrated onto the
chips themselves but they're somehow in
the overall system so what might be an
overall system that again has the
electronics in it and some of these
magnetic components we're talking about
well picture a walkie-talkie for example
you've got a transmitter and a receiver
but you've only got one antenna there's
a magnetic component that isolates the
transmitter from the receiver and
connects both of them through the
antenna at the same time if you didn't
have that you'd have to have two
antennas now I put higher frequencies
you can still do that but the
performance of the components drops off
substantially because they're separate
from the electronics what we're hoping
to do with M cubic (MMM) is bringing that
functionality back into interaction with
the electronic circuits so you can have
that same kind of ease of operation up
at the higher frequencies right now you
have to try to mimic(效仿) that magnetic(磁)
physics with electronic components and
there's really nothing that does quite
the same job right and for those
engineer types
out there who are listening I think the
component you were referring to just now
is that known as a circulator (环形器)
Wow Ivan that's great yes it is yes I
just impressed you Dev, and just you
mentioned three components we're not
going to talk about them but I'm just
now intrigued(引起..好奇心) by what they are so
circulator is one of them and what are
the other two well in the program we're
looking at frequency selective limiter
which can through the natural physical
process cancel out interfering signals
whether they're intentional or not and
also at integrated inductors which have
been kind of a holy grail(圣杯) for millimeter
wave circuits for a long time and just
give me one reason why they're they've
been so coveted(梦寐以求的) well right now since you
don't have access to magnetic materials
on chip the inductors(电感) tend to take up a
substantial(可观的) percentage of the circuit
board space if you have a magnetic
material you can shrink(缩) those down
substantially(可观地) make the whole chip
smaller that means it works better and
It's also cheaper but can you say in a
sentence or two what function the
inductor typically has the inductor
smooths out high frequency signals it
tends to pass lower frequency signals
and stops higher frequency signals so at
very low frequencies they're used to
filter power supplies make those quiet
power supplies at higher frequencies
they're used as part of filter circuits
to select out the frequencies you want
and the frequencies you don't want.
Ivan: so thanks you know for talking about all of
those programs there are others that you
are also overseeing but we're not going
to talk about all of them now but what I
would like to talk about is these
programs and you as a program manager in
a place like DARPA and what I'm getting
at here is you know DARPA is just part
of the overall innovation ecosystem
you've been here since 2012 you you've
got these programs we've talked about so
you know what is it like to be here and
and how do you think DARPA is unique in
the innovation ecosystem coming to DARPA
is like grabbing the nose cone(鼻锥) of a
rocket and holding on for dear life it's
a fast moving place that has a
significant impact on the trajectory(轨迹) of
technology for the nation and being part
of that is an incredible thrill(兴奋, 名词)
the idea that you can
come up with a technical idea that's interesting to you
and create a community to pursue that ideas
is an experience you won't get anywhere else
you can take flyer bets on crazy
things like integrating magnetics with
semiconductors and people will actually
soldier up (挺身而出) and tell you how they're
gonna do it right so what you just said
about creating communities is just
something that that you know I guess
I've observed here too and in the short
time I've been here and I think maybe
perhaps one of the most valuable things
that happens here at DARPA which is is
is that you the program managers do
bring together handfuls of research
groups that otherwise probably would not
have gotten together but in getting
together now create and bring bring
together mindsets skill sets tool sets
ways of doing ways of thinking that are
unique and and therefore can push into
new technological territory did I
overstate(夸大) things or is that about kind
of right no that's about right it's very
exciting can you name one science
fiction technology that you just wish
could become real well Ivan since I
commute weekly between DARPA and my home
in North Carolina that would be
teleportation(瞬间移动) of course but I don't
think we'll ever get there we don't have
any wireless communication technology
that can transfer the amount of
information it would take to completely
disassemble and reconstruct a human in
any reasonable amount of time
imagine having to encode the information
that's in every strand of DNA and every
cell of your body
every memory you've ever had every scene
you've ever seen take that apart turn it
into bits send it somewhere and then
rebuild it in the physical world driving
might be faster well I do hope that
teleportation does become a reality at
some point in the future it's a very
lease to make you're commuting and
traveling around a little bit easier
I've really enjoyed the entire
conversation Dev, I just want to thank
you for coming into the studio Thank You
Ivan it's been a real pleasure and
thanks listeners for sharing this time
with us I hope you join us again for the
next Voices from DARPA
to find this and other episodes of
Voices from DARPA visit us online at
DARPA.mil