Self technology , the internet , GPS in the column of hand on the most operation technology , is a driver of our time since its founding , a nineteen fifty eight in the midst of the cold war darbar , the defence advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window on the dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible.
My name is dan green , since twenty thirteen , i've been a program manager in doubles microsystem technology.
And on your double host , I went motto .
Then tell me a little bit about your background and how it relates to what you hope to accomplish your time here.
A double , I came here to a series .
The fortunate events I got into science , remembering a geological physics at the physics and college got into semiconductor physics so semicon materials that underpin the electronics in all of our commercial technologies today , and really go in over that area at that point time , which was in the nineties , when I started getting into electronics and going after graduate school , who was kind of bad time to be doing electronics , because there is a lot of maturity and what I thought concerned about where was gonna go from there because of the established players like intelligence , we're hitting their hitting the storm .
And along came a new material system called galling nightlights until I was part of brought up looking at going .
I tried and understanding this properties as it applies to transistor technology.
Can you just spend a few seconds talking to us about what is interesting about different kinds of sandwiches?
So when you look at the history of semiconductors , right , the transistors came out from bilateral pools after the , after the second world war .
So it's been around for a long time in the interesting pieces that as dominant as silicon is today , that was not a good , obvious when they started , in fact , we need , and you look at the , the first transistors they are made of germany.
And it looked like crazy little contraction right there were they were the size of.
TOM almost essentially they , they dragged a couple of wires into this block of material and were able to extra money from that very , very rude mentally experiment that , hey , we are really understanding here .
It's obviously translated to many billions dollars of commercial activity , the complexity of luxury conducting today is astonishing .
really .
The key was going from germany of the silicon and a lot of the technical reasons that made work related effectiveness , ethnic combinations with other materials called oxide , very easily .
And so having that outside layer really help control where the electrons flow , the building to manipulate the material structure is really what separated silicon from the other competitors .
That time , an interesting piece that happened with the economic result in the eighties and nineties , was the dramatic expansion of the materials that were able to manipulate that manner .
And so we went from things like silicon to what our knowledge compounds of conductors were used combinations of to create new material sets .
So the first material said that hit the main dream was called gun in arsenide , instead of being a regular crystal just made of silicon items , it has an alternative pattern of gallium and arsenic atoms.
Right , and my understanding is going from silicon to a campaign campaign .
Galaxy night was heard enough that it became AAprogram at dark metro .
That material make a newspaper.
I've already read the dark amateur earlier investment to take what that was the experimental technology of gang martian eye that was useful buyers and really scale it up to make it manufacturer .
Well , because they realized that it was going to enable us to do things like a race factories .
What is a factory factory is , is a combination of amplifiers in a repeated pattern so that you can project electronic waves .
So that means things like retards that gonna are planning .
Internships can leverage that capability to see what's around them to communicate .
And what another company was because of the defense interest in material technology and the ability to bring it to a effectively state .
A lot of people are always that he would be useful for the commercial sector as well .
And so that same gallery , mercy and technology that came out of the really dark memory program in the nineties was really what set off the cellphone revolution because it enabled the amplifiers that let those small handsets that you can run with you to talk to you.
The cell phone towers and that expansion of the same conductor's zoo with we started with germany , and when we talked about silicon , we talked about gallian arsenide .
This might be a good attempt to sort of move into some of the programs that you've been oversee.
Galaxy machine I was was really exceptional because it showed how different method properties can be by moving away from just silicon .
But by no means that that exhausts the period of people were looking around , they realized that there is a lot of other option .
Late nineteen ninety thousand was an individual researcher actually developed the technology to grow high quality galileo , nitrogen material and galin natural materials is special because it , it offers a wider ban .
Get , so that's a characteristic energy , the material , and it enabled devices to be made , which could admit into the blue to many expectations was not available before that sort of a whole wave in terms of lighting , and suggesting that today was our peculators uploads .
And the LED is that we seen out of houses , but the quality that was enable that material to be more widely available and enabled those of us in electronics that we need to use it for other purposes , like a power amplifiers that enable us to look at things like more efficient cell phone towers .
But also higher power arranges for the navy and the army and the air force for the centres and the communications and the electronic work with that we.
Right now , I know that one of your own patients has been to try to look at the strength of these different kinds of semiconductor materials , and then try to put them together .
It makes them match them in ways that might not be so easy to do before , partly because there crystal structures are a little different than they might not stick together .
Well , so these are some of the challenges right that you've been taking on as a program manager.
Part of the interesting piece with gallery nightlight is not so much that it provides all these advantages , but that work , it's a very difficult sector in historical semiconductor .
So it has a mechanical element that's a part of the way operates more than just the weather to move the electronics around .
It has was known as these electrics , and so it actually depends upon being compressed by the community in a certain state to enable the electronics exist where we can use them so we can mix in a little aluminum with our gallery and nitrogen to create a different alley .
And we can grow those crystals right on top of each other so that they maintain their structure from lawyer delier and a lot of the development that happened in the early in development of european neighbouring those techniques where we can control that at the atomic scale , which enables us to create these types of very funny characteristic structural devices over very larger is so we can create very complex circuits that are a structured , athletic topics .
Girl , so well , this goes from here because it has this funny characteristic of mechanical and electrical companies that there's a whole swathes of degrees of freedom that haven't really been exported in nature .
So I entered the field justice .
It was michigan and worked at a competitive , bringing on the initial products to life in terms of high power amplifier for the community .
But my time with darkness has really been about , where do we go from ?
Here comes to leveraging all of these inhabitants of guarantee matter that really haven't been brought the barrier .
So things like scaling the gate links down to be the link .
And what that enables us to do is push up hiring her frequencies .
So how do we understand that ?
Well , the frequency is that we recommend the economy for , like our cell phone is around two giga , and really , because the scaling advantages not what we can do with .
Gallery mayor tried at the higher paradigm cities that we can start to realize the ability to transport in the middle , middle weight .
So that's up toward thirty to three hundred .
Giga hurts and saw the ability to address that higher quantity range really opens up a whole party that we are going to expect them that we have made it .
What do you want to go there , because that will enable things like five g in the commercial sector .
There's a lot of activities right now .
That's going to help us all stream video from everyone , but also enables us to do different things like look at different material properties as we interrogate what's going on with with different materials , with this difficult party like a man , expect them .
So we can see the world in different because using light at different weightings that the possibilities of what we can do .
There are just starting to explore and the capability that we're developing with gun naturally block in a tool that helps get there.
Then how would you imagine the technologies that you are not drawing ?
You spoke , speaking a lot about galaxy when I tried you , how would you imagine that finding traction , both the national security and civilian setting.
So the technologies were developing with gun nightshirt are going to be very important for natural security .
Because it doesn't able to get into this new parts of the electronics circumstances that underpins all of our capabilities when it comes to things like communications or sensing coming from the civilians are getting really understand until I work with some of the military is that we think , why do you need to sense things , and we know what's down the block , and we're walking down the street .
But if you are the navy , and you are in the ship in the middle of you're in a very , very dark place , and you don't know what's wrong in the world until something becomes very important , because you're really out of the middle , nowhere .
And that part of the pieces missing , I think when we think about this context of everyday life that the military is doing , things are very different from our video on the corridor sector .
What we're doing without nicholas , enabling the technologies that will help them other particular missions , and what will happen at the end of the day is that once we have them and people are creative , and they will find ways to use those pieces .
They are more relevant to what we do in our family lives.
So what might be some of the larger society or technology security context in which your programming interests reside?
It's a very interesting kind of right now in electronics .
And because historically the us has such a dominant position of the development of these technologies from the national development of billions through that is the mass rolled out of pcs from intel .
And what we've seen is just in the last decade or so , is the globalization of that technology has spread around the one of the bad products , said , they really going , we're darker , funded a lot of these gunny marginal technologies that rolling to our defence , defence and sensing technologies , was that we are very place in the world where we could make all this components at home and use them in their control manager for our purposes .
And with this globalization , that's taking place because of the event of cell phones and mass consumer electronic , we're seeing now that all of these electronic pieces and these different developments are happening all over the world , and so really challenge the way that we consume electronics in in the permanent funds .
Because now we , we don't necessarily have all of those best components at home , because there's a activity all over the world .
And so there is , there is challenges both to understand what pieces we should develop and can continue to own that .
And what piece is we should leverage in a global marketplace and how to put the best little branch together so that we can confirm competitive.
What you're talking about here , in some ways , is the sort of the technology ecosystem , the genuinely ecosystem innovation ecosystem that makes me think about where dark buffets , until these various ecosystems that.
So dark release is fantastic , and that it has the ability to go and make significant investments to advanced technology said that there are any critical on it can really be a difference maker before instance , in england .
Nightmare , I mentioned the the imports of gang as it came along too , and then I think what we can do in the art of spectrum , and really , that technology was without the world because of the LED marketplace .
But dark became alone and medicine , if any investment in white band gap submitted , accused of transform to push the material that that space for the electronics to win , and because they're really investment darker has created capabilities that have been rolled out to the services in the form radars that are going to the navy and communication systems that are going around the services .
And it also dominated , provided the backbone for industry players that are serving commercial market as.
Then can you describe one science fiction technologies that you read about in the past , you come up on your own .
You woke up in the middle of the night with this dream of a technology that doesn't exist now , but that you really wish could exist.
This is what we do here .
He is explained our time , dreaming about different technology .
So it's such a fascinating time , because a lot of these things that we formally just dreamed about our coming to life around us .
But the one comic book , I, Idid reign .
I was a kid with iron man , and we now have all these are men movies , but what's fascinating is walking around the building and seeing how parts of those technologies are trying to make it look less than less crazy .
You start to see people who are actually working on exercises , people who are working on how we connect the body to electronics , how we actually interface with electrical.
So you're talking here about complex and potentially powerful technologies , which means they could lead to both good and perhaps troublesome results .
How do you think about the potential consequences of the technologies you are helping?
So I think that's a healthiest question that we do struggle with a lot as we continue to expand our capital and project into their electronic spectrum really raises the ability for us to to be always on and always connected .
And it not only does that , you raise all the issues that were seen today , it helps us having yourself and on all the time and being in that santa wei zhang , but also , this is always aware so that there is no way to hide things .
And so it becomes a very open and transparent place to be , which has passed the ministers in terms of how we operate as it .
So I think there is a lot of implications of technology that are yet to be grappled .
But it also a law physics that technology will advance .
We will continue to explore the world , so it doesn't help us to not try to advance what possible the whole point of darkness to prevent surprise and really part of our job .
He was to go out .
Fear was possible , so we can start that process of understanding it early , early.
Well , gonna really enjoyed our conversation here today , thanks for listening and tuning .
Next time to hear another voice from job .