Stealth technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand alternatives operation technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defensive best research project agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window on the darkness .
Core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone a motel on your dark host today .
I am pleased to be talking with rhetoric enforced officer in test pilots scott , where has been asked a program manager since twenty sixteen of the agencies technology offers sky will be fishing a star patriot duty at the end of april .
So i'm really looking forward to hearing how he might some of his experience as a dark .
That is the same program manager .
Now , just to know we are recording our conversation from our respective locations as we do our parts to slow the spread of coffee nineteen , because we're not in a recording studio .
You might hear ambient sounds like traffic in birds .
Now , a little bit of bad scott , in his foreign , healthier is a darker .
Scott has overseen a portfolios that are all about making more in the sky .
One of his programs took on the long subject of building and easily reusable vehicle that can deliver smallish payloads , save several times to space and return to the ground in simple airplane like round trips .
Another has been stepping toward aerial systems in which smaller fleets of unmanned aerial systems think these are scouts deploy from and return to a mothership .
Yet other programs central on bringing more automation into the relationship between wolf fighters and operators , and they're flying assets , in part , by conferring more attorney into among those .
This portfolio makes a lot of sense when you know that scott himself has been a pilot extensively throughout his life , he was a command pilot , was more than two thousand hours , primarily in the f sixteen fighting second and eighty thousand , including fifty combat hours in a racket air space during operation , provide comfort and its successor operation , northern watch .
For twenty years , he served in the USair force as a test , a program manager in advanced weapons systems and in international affairs specialist , prior to joining dark as a program manager , scott , with the executive director for space and advanced technologies at where he helped expand the company's advanced technology , strength and forge collaborations with several organizations , including japan , the department of energy and defence reduction agency .
Scott holds a bachelor of science degree and astronautical engineering from the united states , are forced to academic and aerospace engineering from the u .
Persuade alabama , another MSand systems engineering from the air force and situate technology .
And he is a graduate from the french test pilot school and later letting pronounce name at school .
Scott was beneficial , unhappy to squeeze in this conversation on this mid march , day before you leave the agency in the next month .
So thanks for.
I think you ever is great to be here , and I look forward to this conversation.
Now me too , me too , let's start with your life as an error .
man .
I understand that you are essentially born with the DNA of pilots .
I like for you to share with me and our listeners just what is like to grow up with friends in your 对外说。
Well , thanks .
It is been interesting on the material .
My dad was a test pilot and flew over the other words out for space .
He was known for being the first air force test pilot of the extra nine , and then I got into the air force , and I nationally choose my graduate of nuclear , but all three of us , my brothers , my two younger brothers , jeans and ryan or suppliers , jason , was a test pilot in bombers , and then my youngest brother ran was a assisting pilot .
You could probably go back even a little bit further to my grandfather , who was killed in ABseventeen hundred or two .
So there's there's definitely a history of assad in the military , and then a focus beam pilots , and in some of us being tested.
Well , as such as an amazing vineyard , i'm just wondering how you ever been up in the air at the same time , working pretty much the same location with other family members in plains nearby.
There's a time over and sent on your taxes where I was in structural pilot of eighty three , there's exactly in time that my brother was a tea sixth pilot and instructed pilots .
My youngest brother was coming through , becoming a sixteen touring had become an existing party .
It was during that time that I actually get the final flight with my youngest brother , and there was a , the same time that all three of us , at least , were at the same basis at the same time.
Sounds like some serious symbolic bonding there .
So now , what are catching element of your resumes that you graduated from francisco test pilots school ?
And I can't pronounce the name of the school , so i'm gonna .
Let you do that .
But so tell me the name of the school and tell me about that experience and how it came about.
To share .
So it is lively , known as aparna in the stands for a call to personnel navy gong DIC at the end of the young , which is a long way of saying friends.
So I mean , that sounds familiar with your food and french.
So now it's been , it's been several years since i've actually been able to use it in our working environment .
I still have friends over in france , and I tried to keep it up .
Personally , it's still sad that if you don't use off and it starts to go up to the way , sad , but before hand , you know , I take an friendship in school , but they actually sent me two language training , both over washington , DC.
And and there is more attention in french spirit to the course starting , and I simply to give me an opportunity to try to get cut up because the , the course of french tests politics , of course , it was pretty much all in french , or what they would fly in english most of the time , most of the world we did was inflation .
So you can just take fifty eight points of by trying to seek a lot of language while you're running out of line a different aircraft or crew there.
Right , I just want more question about the french text code experience .
What's the value added for the us , government , for the audit to to send a person like you to a french test?
It suggests that several are too long that we could talk about released .
These are the international relations by being a strange pilot or your other pilots from one side come and extreme views become part of another culture and other military .
And then the whole fact there is , as those relationships built over the course of our career , or you always have the ability to go back to your friends on the outside .
And it helps win .
There may be a mysterium occasion between one countryside and the other , and it was so far as well my time over with the french taste political arms called up several times to go to additional events to help bridge again if you want .
One time , I was an interpreter for the fifth effect of the indeed , and so these types of relationships are meant to be long lasting , and it is not too to help faster follow on relationships at the second reason comes down to the schools themselves .
We all have a desired , instead of teaching our palace to become test pilots , but we all do in different ways of french , the brands in americans who are slightly .
I haven't pilots go to desert schools .
The error bring back different skill sets , and then be able to provide those skills as back to the community that they came from .
It's just a great way to cross the information to be able to get different ways of learning and different perceptions of how different people do different.
That was fascinating , and it just , it's a little window on what it means for two countries to be hours , right , and it comes down to individuals exchanging the kind of experience that you did not ensure that there's been a test pilot from the countries that have been up instructed over here very fast .
And he heard about that bit of what means being alive .
So your portfolio programs dropped a clearly reflect your experience at high altitudes .
Fine , commanding , vast , powerful aircraft .
This is tell me about how your experience in the carpet informed .
Do you think about aerospace?
We started off as a young pilot .
Several years are really spent in in training the individual to come competent .
You could expect at least one year for pilot training , probably another year to two years to become trained in your major weapons system .
Women , probably another , two or four years to build up enough ownership .
And what if we come up a flight leader and structure palate is a huge amount of time in training to provide that to get?
I mean that the equipment to what you would put in if you were getting a dark.
They're very much so very much .
so .
And so when you take a look at the amount of training necessary , I wanted to first questions that they are forcing a navy with asks what we do training because of this very expensive .
And then if you are reducing that , how do you ensure that you keep the same skill set in your pilots in your approval , or even improve upon that to make it possible , because , you know that the airplane are getting more difficult to more complicated in terms of the systems in the sensors , and you don't want to lose their own shifts as as tangles forward .
If you start focusing on the sensors , you don't want to lose their actual , why they are fun .
And so as we started to improve , our computer capabilities are , and that are tonight in general , they became very , very natural person .
How much can we actually bring a tonight into the campaign in order to argument or a component , the earth of the aircraft , and that's one of the biggest process .
So I want to take a look at coming to was that that that partnership , the mathematically , the ability to have computers and systems work in concert with the human enthusiasm that they choose them together , become better than any of them .
so.
I think we're going to return to some of those ideas when we talk about your programs just before we do that , I would like to hear about your experience just prior to coming to drop up .
You're a maintained international cooperation and also what would be good at the end of that is , it tells your headache , gets the story.
So I retired from the reinforcing , trying to health and donate transition .
I had always been looking at trying to become a program manager working at dark men .
Take a national headache , couple of contracts with dark , and it was a way for me to at least gain an understanding of of what it was like , and so actually started as a consultant ford up with romantic .
This lasted on and off over the course of four years ago .
Footman taken a national .
But during that time , additional judge kim and I ended my time over atlantic and nationalized maximum director of charge of multiple contracts throughout the national capital .
But during my time with my technology , I had built up several relationships with program managers , as well as the leadership over at the top of and made a bit to become a program in a jury , which was a long process to convince them to explain to them how I would be a good fit for the organization , how I could bring expertise .
My skill sets too dark or not , to better the young state of all were trying to do from a vision pressure today.
Another question just came to mind that when you were saying you had some sense of dog , but you've heard about it before you got to men text .
It was on your radars , or even before they are wondering how , in fact , it was on your radar when you were your sitting for those thousands of hours in a cockpit , did you have interfaces with dark technology in some?
Nobel , so not as a as a lying pilot has in track pilots or combat pilot doesn't really happen there .
From my experience , it became more parent as a test pilot .
You go , and you take a look at the new technologies that you're going to incorporate into an aircraft you start looking at the research laboratories and other agencies that can bring on those tax technologies .
And that's how the idea of dark came to my .
And when I was given one of my master's degree through the air forces to technology , they haven't exchanged group this war of fellowship with dark .
That is ongoing right now , where we bring in officers from the services two double for summer between three months and a year , let them learn what double is like and then go back to the services , and they are available to do kind of wooden exchange power .
It is greater to bring those that that awareness had information back to other war fighters .
And I had applied to that a couple of times , but was never able to make it worked out due to my job , the way that my , my job had come around .
I think so that I helped him into awareness .
So when I thought that I wasn't going to be able to reach dark through the air force , it was basically afterwards , once I retired from the reform of a traditional programme.
Scott , now take us on a tour of your programs , beginning with the ones that may be a wonder course if it may be beginnings , middles and ends , and then moving onto ones that you can assume hand of the other since you are leaving .
And that sexy , a normal procedure , these are big , complex programs that they often will start in the middle of a program manager , tour of duty .
And then when their program manager leaves , those programs get handed off to program managers that follow .
So maybe chronologically , talk about the programs you took on or develop when you first started drop and then take through to the end.
So was my first boss over in a darbar TTL.
The textbook technologies office that said , when it became a program manager that you can show successes of program manager of you able to programs and a few programs , and be in the middle of several programs .
So you can see the whole game and a life of a program .
And that was definitely true , in my case , the first program I got was alias , which is aircrew labor in cockpit automation system .
And well , is it , it is a mouthful .
The whole intensive was to develop and demonstrate a flexible automation tool kit for existing aircraft that enables safe , crude aircraft operations .
And this was our programmers was initiated from doctor dampen when I came on board .
He had seen that my skills , such a really kind of was in line with what he was trying to do with the nearly as programming .
And so I took that program , and I only took it for about about a year and a half before its transition to another program manager , but it was a great way to get involved with a program here , a dark button .
It was right in my sweet spot in terms of how combined these machines and humans together in this madam and television.
Before you exaggerate , when other programs are not appointed what vaccines , me about alias also is how connected up history , in the sense , one of the most famous stopper program entries , jessica legal letter , the snow goes back to the sixties .
He is all vision .
It was human machine collaboration and partnering , and alias is really all about that .
So it really does connect to to some of the earliest times of darkness.
It does that .
What was really interesting about that one , and then it's still ongoing .
Program is still ongoing right now , two key demonstrations that we had there that I thought were extremely important and lining the first one was where we put it robotic arm into the carpet of a credit aircraft , and was able to do certainly mercy procedures and showed the capability of of these systems being able to take on the role of a pilot .
Pilot became capacitated .
It is not only a rate for prime time , but it sure that that capability was there .
The second window was really interesting as well .
We automated the flight control system of an existing and allowed the sixteen to take control in a very scope of weight , the weapon system , in order to do target tracking of guns in this particular case .
And it was a cold front of effort for that particular project between us and air force research .
It was so good and showed that the keep buildings of the other pilot for tracking a gun towards the target was better than what the pilot actually do , and because it was so air force downstairs , come on to take a look at how we can incorporate these types of capabilities more into programs of record .
And that that work is ongoing right now , wasn't the existing community.
Right , and then this , finally , before we move on to another program , as when you say programs of record , you are really referring to technology , really transitioning into operational settings , you know , which is the great financial line for dark ride and in dark .
Once the this technology is making , it seem like they really can work and then hand it up to those who can take it all the way too .
A full technology and a tune operational settings .
So this sounds like it's really on.
That's , that's very true .
A second program called cold or collaborate operations in a denied environment with another program I took in the end , part of the program .
Jessica day was a program manager , and as he left the assembly , take on a program for the final demonstrations .
It was a software focus program in which will take what types of algorithms can you put together and affordably put them into current systems in order to help make them fly better with , with attorney mind .
So if you think about smart weapons right now , once they are launched , they basically go through a very route path , and they don't normally talk to another what we wanted to do to explore .
Well , if you are going to deny the environment , and you had multiple atom system going into that environment , and we started disconnecting the communications lines and the GPS lines , how those systems work together .
And as very successful , we had several very complex demonstrations , were repeated multiple systems against the complex environment and the system rebels to talk to another and accomplish the mission in a very efficient , it was so successful that neighborhood neighbor had taken that on the transition .
And now they're doing further experience of how to incorporate that into their programs of record.
Okay , so you talk about aliens , you talk about code .
But this is a few others , and you.
There is grandma is looking at how you do safe , effective and efficient aircraft of smaller UAZto a host aircraft .
Now a small UAB, in this case , is something in the range of five hundred to fifteen hundred pounds .
So the relatively large system , or we're looking at is in large system , if we were to go long distances , he holds the aircraft and dropped these systems off .
They were then going to a high threat area , accomplished wherever the mission happens to be , and then given the sensors , or maybe you would not want them to be expensive .
So any of them that survive these attribute vehicles could then be recovered to do it again .
Another day , we are the very blessed part of the program we were doing our final flight tests or final deployments to prove out the air recovery can be safe and effective and efficient .
Assuming that everything goes well , this program will look at transaction opportunities again with the services they are forcing it specifically to bring the skipper notice.
I've seen a couple of videos and been tracking the progress of grammar .
This is really a mean , incredibly ambitious program .
It's also been pretty heroic .
You've got so close to one of the events that you need , which is to actually bring it back into the european , almost got your last time.
That is true .
It's been so close as nearby team , as you're in inside the yet the task control room watching these things happens is completely different .
If you're a test pilot in your flying aircraft , you remember things going on .
You have control of the vehicle , but you , you , it's completely different story when you read the test operator or the program manager , and you are watching this on videos as they get so close for talking with an inches , a vacuum making the final mechanical connection .
It doesn't happen .
Any other african were granted covering it is .
It is what flight tests is hard is dirty work , and your constantly making fixes to change it and and making changes , because the assumptions that initially start off with , or necessarily the exact right ones , which is good about this program , though , is that we have very strong testing , and we are constantly making improvements , such as every time we get back in the flight test , we get damaged closer .
Hopefully , by the end of the summer , we will have have been able to show that that irritability is visible and should be consider part of our future keep today.
Yeah , and you sort of reminding me just have another trade of the dark orange culture , which is that you guys know how these projects are .
Do you really don't go in with an expectation that everything is going to work smoothly , or maybe in the optimum schedule , but that even when things don't work out , that's a win because you learn something , and then it comes back in an education for the next round of born day.
It is true , comes down to the idea that these are high risk , high pay off projects in programs .
The high risk comes to the , to the effect that ages may not work , or it won't work until after the third of the first trial .
So having a program set up in a way that you have multiple task vehicles , or you have understanding that it , it's not going to happen right the first time that you need several literatures to get to a desire , and state is within our mobile operation .
She would love if it works at the first time , but it's not always the case.
So your annual you talk about three programs.
Between our domestic writer , I would get too much .
So the next program is college for more space .
Plane was one that I had taken from another program manager .
Just fundamental is departure from air .
alcohol .
U ad is in the context of a reasonable space launch capability was , was really what we're focused on here .
now .
This program I actually started with just football as a as a see , the contractor , he is supported contractor in very beginning .
And through the first couple of years , supported him as he accomplished the program when he left dropped , he asked me to come on and take on the program management role nationally to and through the program .
Now , in this case , australia must be explained how was not a success in the dinner transition .
We went through several years of design work , only the find out at the end of the day , what we are trying to do was just too difficult given the capabilities that we had at that time .
And again , this is what one of those times were you funny , drug perspective ?
Take a look at what is available or money should be spent , and what is really going to be visible given the time in the budget of schedule .
In this case , we decided to turn it programmers and focus on time , attention on other areas , and that does not mean that useful space launch is in future capability that we want to be able to have , which is different than what you see out of space or exchange blue ocean .
This is more tactically oriented where you could fly responsibility to vehicle , multiple fans and multiple days in order to do different types of nations .
Now what I would expect to happen is as space sex and blue origin , and other companies make sure they may be an ability for the technologist on rap onto a military relevant technicians are on their , we're spacecraft that matter where it disappointed .
It just wasn't being visible.
Yet another theme that comes to mind , there is one of the mandates of job is exactly explore the landscape of the possible , but that also means discovering the innovation , technology domains that , in fact , are not reachable at the moment .
At the moment , though you , again , you may learn lessons now that you pack away for a bit and bring them out down the line when other parts of our technology might become available to change together , and I then ultimately make the regional capability like this case , flying the space and back almost like you do in airplane , make that possible so interesting in your bad access p , as that program was known .
In short , I think you got one more , and this one was just recently announce the job.
Let's write the farmer program that I have is called long shot and spent about four years in coming when I first became a program and ensure that it was exploring activity to start the program of a trusted women .
In this case , we are looking at UAVSthat can work similarly with fighter aircraft , and basically is able to argument with the fleet or with the force of formation .
And you can do over the last four years that has more and more focused on the u ad itself in this ability from a small air launch , you AV perspective to launch air weapons .
It's a program that just started .
We are in face one world's boring , different types of concepts in order to reach these designs.
When you think maybe will you top in you handle the sovereignty to another program manager ?
But let's say that it is a programming transitions .
How would you disagree with the characterize the new capability that will bring to the.
So this program , along with pattern pieces of the other airspace programs of head from cooled to elia's diagram lens , all kind of focus on different capabilities that provide you the ability to distribute .
And at the end of the day , that's really what i'm looking at is , is , how can you take the capabilities of our fourth generation of fifth generation fighters and bombers , which are expensive experience systems that remained that you don't want to throw in hardware , but you absolutely have to .
How do you expand those capabilities by bringing other systems transparency and the capabilities that we show in each of these different programs is just one more tool set , or one more idea that the worldwide can use as they decide what they want this instead to be .
So , for my perspective , at the end of the day , a reusable system that is a man that can actually employ employee , airline weapons or electronic warfare capabilities , or do ISRand have them teamed up with mandela craft work , the UVvisa , the ones are going to the higher area is in the main aircraft once are overseeing this complicated error will happen .
That is what i'm really trying to export.
Right in isaac , that's intelligence , the surveillance in the conditions I asked , yes , ok , that was an amazing week up of five , really ambitious programs .
And we want to think about everything that's gone into these programs , including sort of defining them and then getting worried out about them and making choices of performers too contract to do the actual research .
All the moving pieces I can see that you've been busy since one is sixteen , when you came to dark , and you're now about to finish up your tour of religious or program manager .
And I should point out this is routine .
You're pulling average in the left of four years , and some , which is built into kind of the culture of DARPA .
Many say that the limited state of the program manager is part of the agency's special sauce , which is to say , what helps us gets so much dozens and move so much technology from concept to realization .
But now that you are about to finish up as a program management , interested in whether you think that is true , that that limited time as a program manager is an important part of the culture , and just whatever lessons you learned and expect to bring front door , but to your subsequent professional.
I hold hardly agree that one of the things that makes double a successful organization .
This idea are bringing program hundreds in for a short time , get the work done that the invasion getting done , and they leave in order for new blood coming to the culture into the organization .
And it's important standing that you have a very limited time in a very special place , like darker , it becomes your biology .
You focus all your time , attention , day , night , weekends on whatever this project happens today .
Is it it becomes a passion that becomes your wife , and you could do so for a two to four , five year period , where this is everything that you focused on .
But eventually humanity takes over , and eventually people who can burn out , or they no longer have new or ideas that needs to be brought to there .
And that motivation is in this terry gun .
But it is time for other people to come in with their new ideas , and there's another new ones that happens to you have a program , and you work this program for a couple of years , and you focus on this .
It is successful , but sometimes a program manager will keep advice and by bringing a new blood or a new program manager interrupted workers , they may see in a , and maybe it would make changes that the other program manager didn't wasn't aware of , or maybe just decided that it would be better go down at the past .
It's a double export , but I think in doing so , we bring in new program managers in to take care of programs that are ongoing , as well as bringing their own in is really what makes us such AAgreat store.
One of the interesting things you said , there is one emphasized , is the human natural side and held by cycling program managers just over time , terms of a couple of years .
You actually from the agency , institutional deal , dangerous RNDtechnology development perspective , you hedge against an individual in a way becoming too invested with an idea to win love with a particular by cycling out .
And and then someone else cycling in , you can get a good critical look at previous approaches , and if need , be modify , those which you wear might be harder if a program managers in pretend twenty years or a lifetime.
Agree , if you have a program that is a very good program , then it should be able to stand multiple photograph managers taken over there and try to make changes , or at least refining it to the desires that the NCwants to be able to achieve .
I think it's good to know , though that drug it doesn't normally work off requirements .
They have an essay vision in mind .
They have goals and objectives that they want to achieve , and they may have to bring class in order to get that instead to see whether never truly will be a revolutionary capability that the services will eventually take up.
Ha , ha , nicely said , so thanks scott , for that tour of your programs .
I have to ask you something.
What's next to you ?
So i'll tell you over the next day for six months , english egyptian break is a summer time here .
We're just coming over coffee .
It is time to enjoy life .
Let's not want to be in the sphere and then and then I realized that I can learn to summer , beginning of all my wife , and I are going to be going towards the physical northwest and consider of a new life in the prayer .
And what.
All right , well , the best of luck to you .
And may we be an atlantic october so that , you know , you enough health can begin to move back towards some sort of normal .
So do I want more question ?
And this is there anything that didn't come up to an accomplishment that you would like to share with me and our listeners for future program managers , anything that works.
So yes , it's actually to the future .
Program managers are out there .
I have been blessed in the idea that a beneficial mentor's several individuals coming in either as program managers and here are , or aspiring engineers want to become program engineers and to say that double is a unique , special place is an understatement .
So , given an opportunity of program , manager , darker is a blessing you are giving .
You are given a lot of li wei in terms of regional state , the office expects you to be proactive in order to do what needs to be done in order to get to that instead .
And so for the foreign managers of the aspirin program , managers out there don't give up .
It's , this is a place that you would want to work at .
It's a place where you can achieve the visions that you might not have been able to give in the world of academia or in your offices , a from industry or within the military .
And as those people who want to make a change in world who want to try to make things better , those should attach the people that are good.
Well , great , that was a willing , amazing discussion for me to learn all about your programs , and then to hear about your inspirational pitch to those after who might be thinking about dolphin sounds like your messages .
I suspect a real pleasure , a christmas discussion with you just before you're gonna , say goodbye .
Dark , I just want to thank you for sharing with me and listeners and stories about your wife and times as an airman and as a , the upper program.
Thank you .
I think you are in the third time.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from DARPA .
Thanks also to bend , celebrate for his partnership in producing this program .
For more information about the programs run by the agencies , tactical technology , others until learn about other breaking technologies .