Self technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight with operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research projects agency has been a driver of welcome to Voices from the dark , a window , and the dark is core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone motto on your dog , a host .
today .
I am excited to have with me for a billion uncle appears .
Doctor and fisher , a program manager , since twenty seventeen in the agencies defense sciences office .
I talk with him back in twenty eighteen in a previous Voices from global partner , and and I are recording our conversation from our respective homes as we do our part to slow the spread of cold , with one thousand nine hundred and the pandemic disease caused by the new coronal virus , sars , kobe , too , my heart goes out to all of those in the US, and around the world were doing all kinds of rebels .
Losses , stresses and anxieties due to the pandemic .
Please note that because we are recording outside the studio setting , and on a particular whole new day , you might hear win noises , other ambient sounds , and fisher is a chemist by training with professional experiences that have taken her to the neighborhood research laboratory .
The navy's corporate laboratory , which is just a few years away from its sentences celebration , a benefit of american association for the advancement of science , where she was a science and policy fellow , proud to becoming a dark a program manager in the defense of his , she had been a senior advisor for d so well at the consulting from strategic and and thanks for joining me for the podcast for a second time , it's good to be here .
I am .
Thank you .
In this pad case , I want to focus on the part for you that you have been able to sword into our scientific and technological responses to the coordinate team pandemic .
These programs include your accelerated molecular discovery program , and then make it programme .
And that would stand a chance of circumference of supply chain bono's abilities by enabling low cost fabrication of many important molecules in chemical ingredients that are anywhere , anytime and affordably .
So look for to learn more about where you have been taking that program .
But let's start with AMD , the accelerate delegator discovery program .
What is the goal of it ?
What is it status ?
And how is it relevant to our pandemic response?
Sure , I will thank you so exhilarated .
Military discovery , or MDSis really a program about helping chemist identifying discover new molecules that meet the property demands that we have to .
So we come , we come to the table with challenges .
These challenges could be that I need a new material in the field for some protection measure .
These changes could be that they , there is a new disease on , on on the horizon , and we need to develop a therapeutic for that disease .
And really , instead of using our intuition and our hands and experiment , what AMD is really trying to do is help leverage computational resources , including machine learning , leverage automation , to really help us accelerate the rate at which we can identify new molecules within the vast space of a potential molecules that might meet our capability needs.
Okay , and this is , in contrast to the traditional sort of bench chemistry way of discovering materials , which is a lot of trial and error .
There's a lot of synthesis innovation that has to .
And here you are trying to leverage automation , tools , competition and so far threat .
You had some experience , I think , on the bench to.
Yeah , I did .
And I think this is the situation of the way we do things that we still do them today in a laboratory by hand , and that's not a bad thing .
It just , it doesn't that the time scale at which it takes to do those experiments , and then the limitations of of a chemist who , who has a training in a particular space of molecules or synthetic capabilities , release , sort of hinder innovation and being able to look outside of that sort of space in which we work , which , when you consider the vast possibilities based of , but say something like tender , the sixty of potential molecules that might provide us , the capabilities that they were looking for .
Really , these tools are to help a chemist , automation and laboratory to experiments faster and machine learning and other models to be able to actually understand properties in a really vast array of molecular spaces that we can be more efficient and effective in finding things like cares two to covering a team whether they be antibiotics or identifiers , too .
To start .
ACVTU.
Well , we will need to attend the sixty molecules that , if i'm not mistaken , that's a trillion trillion , truly .
And trillionaire children molecules , which are china , identify in that vast search base are a particular suited for particular purposes .
So , as many as you said , that can be for materials , they can be for farmers suit goals .
They can be for other molecules of interest to the department of defence and military needs .
Let's actually do those zero went on on how you thinking about applying this , or how you already are beginning to with the performers who you have under contract for the program .
How are you swerving that into the european nineteen response?
So that's that's a really great question in .
And what we're trying to do is actually love it .
What capabilities we've developed as far in the program , in the context of community .
And , you know , AMD , exactly relatively young program , we just got kicked off at the very end of last year .
And so from an experimental perspective , or building the capabilities to do the experiments with that with evaluate predictions , but really were worth focused on for covering nineteen right now on the computation outside .
And that's both because that were were most mature , but it's also because of the laboratories are shut down when we think about being able to contribute these capabilities .
What can we leverage today when people are home and want to help in the fight ?
And so one great example of what we're doing that space is some effort at m it right now , which is one of the performers on the program .
They did some early work in the program on developing antibiotics .
So there is actually a paper recently in cell .
They're on the cover of sale in february , and they essentially reported that they searched virtually over a hundred million molecules .
So again , something no cameras could do come in any relevant time frame , searched for molecules that are known to us that might have enterprise activity .
And and what they were able to define is essentially to map these molecules to properties that are relevant for antibiotics activity .
They then even tested these molecules against coastal quarters and bacterial cultures .
Excuse me , and were able to to show molecules that were actually of interest for other things like , like diabetes .
There publics that actually had antibiotic activity against bugs that were relatively resistant to to antibiotics .
So this was , this was actually really critical finding .
It was pretty good .
All of the , the activity now surrounding surnamed korean , nineteen , and united actually interested in the point out this demonstration of an ability of activity .
There are a lot of focus on now finding an entire viral .
So , so we want to be able to do development of iraq for the source .
CUVtwo , but of many of the people that are in the hospital , bacterial infections that is so called secondary effects of of infection of coordinate team bacterial infections are are significant challenge , particularly those that are resistant to to turn and about .
Except we have .
So my teacher is now looking for an advantage for covering using the same tools and and building an argument in the tools that they develop for this paper that was highlight.
So if they were able to connect , achieve this results to say , identify him from the vast search base , michael structures , that would be able to potentially event about the function against secondary infection .
And like the monument faction , what would actually , what would m it actually deliver , and then what would be the next step?
Yesterday actually we , we have a beautiful collaboration between and my tea and walter reed army institute for research so known as rare WRAR.
And essentially what they're gonna be delivering is , here are some candidates molecules that could potentially serve as energy articles in a sort of what we wanted to use and rank ordered them .
What of these molecules are at the FDapproach , so there might be FDapproval , completely different purpose , but we now should competition that they might have in a bacterial activity .
Then there are molecules that can be commercially purchased .
They may not be affected , approved , but they are out there on the market , and then there are multiples that are completely new and novel .
So what we then do is send that list to rare , and we already got some hits in .
And and where is taking a look at this hits now and saying , okay , how can we then build a those into our essays and do the experimental validation?
Sometimes I need , ultimately that we go forward , potentially into animal tests and to clinical trials with people.
That's right .
And we're leveraging all the resources that we have in the department defense , in terms of those SAand animal testing capabilities so that were ready to go when we do identify.
A viable head were in also , because these secondary is infections and conditions like numeral are are common .
This could have lasting effect , even beyond the present.
Dilemma , that's right .
And I think , again , important to emphasize the development of animals that are affected activity against bacteria that are typically resistant to known about exactly how I think listeners , what will know if heard things like I am about a christmas before , you know , where you have been about it .
So stepped .
So we really have to continue to to to innovate and develop new medicines so that we can address these new boxes emerge.
I am , thank you for giving them an update on the accelerated molecular discovery programming .
Congratulations for getting that launch right at the end of last year , which is , of course , exactly when the cobber nineteen outbreak began before it is , the group went to this global configuration of a pandemic .
But another program is relevant here , perhaps in the near term , as well as the long term , is called them .
Make it program .
We spoke about this back in our earlier parties , but I like it till listeners roughly what the makeup program is attempting to do , and again , how it potentially could become relevant in situations like we find ourselves in now.
Well , AMD is , is all about .
Discovery is all about , you know , what molecule do I need to address whatever technological challenging facing make it is about .
How do I produce that molecule ?
So it doesn't matter how many molecules we identify that we might need as an entire violent of material , what really matters .
In addition to that is , how do I make that monkey ?
How do I sympathize it and make it is about developing new capabilities so that we can certainly have devices , which not only can help in adults in the sentences of of america , which is currently done by hand , but also that that can make many , many molecules on a single platform .
So I give you an examples , if you think of an oil refinery where everything is in piping and two billion , we go from what i'm starting with on the front end of that , and then i'm processing it to some final as effectively , what make it devices do , and they allow you to do that fully automated so that you can take raw starting materials and produce many different products .
So is an example over the course of of the last several years and make it with demand straight at the synthesis of over thirty five different drugs from again .
Since it , you can buy a purchase from a chemical company all the way to.
It would have imagined him he was there .
Maybe you campaigned to picture better than me , but this would facilities that are not so big , but that would potentially enable anybody thought of anyway , there are any time to make almost any sympathize of chemical , you know , kind of wherever they are as needed .
But one of you describe how this , for example , could play in a public health situation , where particular kind of safe farmers who was needed , but was hard to get.
He has to imagine your description is actually , really , really good .
And I think it certainly learn itself not to me talking about what the original vision like make it was that instead of having sort of centralized facilities that are producing large amounts of chemicals , arguments of of medicines , we could actually deal with challenges that that are face , whether they're because of work more time , or because we have a supply chain problem , or because there is a pandemic .
Now there is a need for certain medicines .
We can certainly take these devices , which are incredibly flexible and on a single device , then sort of tune to address the needed hand .
So you can imagine them doing that at a single location .
But not only that , because there are essentially the size of be you've done in your table .
You can imagine that they can then have this sort of distributed network of these devices so that we could be now making things at the point of , and that was really always the vision of the making program .
And that's , I think , really highlights that need to thrive .
Think about , we know as as dark , but does what , what I need , maybe ten or twenty years than a line .
And what are the fundamental research investments that I can make today , that can make that a reality , because now that we have the reality that we're facing today , the investment that we made over the last four or five years in this technology , now , a really poisoned potentially can scale them and build them out to make independently that we currently.
Face , okay , so let me paint a picture about the next pandemic thread .
I'm optimistic , and i'm thinking about the other side of covered nineteen already .
I'm thinking about the next pandemic threat and putting your two programs together on imagining accelerated molecular discovery , perhaps identifying from that search space of tend to the sixteen articles , an anti viral that that might work .
And then i'm thinking about thousands of these make it devices distributed around the world that they might get instructions to work to actually make that antiviral at the point where you can be , you know , most easily distributed to those who needed .
And we did that a realistic.
Picture , I think that's absolutely realistic , and what we're trying to do right now is , is really get our thoughts around .
What are the major technical challenges that we need to address to make that right ?
So we have invested in the technology .
We've got the platforms demonstrated that can make many different materials , but the research and development platforms , they are not robust , scalable devices .
And so now we really certainly think of , as we begin to think about transition these capabilities , I have a partnership currently with the department of health and human services .
Assistant secretary for preparative and response , which is much easier to say , expert ASPRto actually straight some of the capabilities that were developed in make it and critical programs that doubt against fundamental research investments that now have built these capabilities and working with aspirin , demonstrate these devices actually for production of an added a superfos in the context of FDAregulatory processes .
So again , now we got the devices next to all we need to think about how we deal with the regulatory aspects who are conclusively hand in hand with that capability.
Very exciting news to hear about both the makeup program and the accelerator molecular discovery program , may you succeed widely in both of those , because not only will that serve the mission of furthering the capabilities of our military patients , but it sounds like it would also do a lot of good for a lot of people in general throughout the world .
So you know , do happen now .
And as we close into the end here , I want to switch here just for a moment , I have a question about the reality of this pandemic for you as the reality of became more clear , you know , in february , march , and we have been hearing about obviously some of its , some of what was happening earlier than that , but i'm just wondering what some of your personal thoughts were as , as it was becoming clear that this was going to be a global public health threat .
And then also how it intersected with your professional role as a dark program manager.
Well , that's such an interesting question .
I think for me that to the biggest thing to look back on was how much changed in such a short period of time .
So there is about , you know , a three week period where I think we , as americans , at least eye , I don't want to speak for everybody in their states .
But we saw the panel far , and as it began to impact our lives very , very quickly , the realities of all that release sort of came to bear .
And I think we know that even before that happened , we were looking to how we could help in the fight .
But it's one thing to , can I see something at a distance and something very different when , when it then is impacting every second of your day , and in a world , all relatively fortunate that I can work from home , you know , my performers are arguing things that don't require them to put themselves in danger outside of any third quarantine or travel ban source type to think so .
We can do our part right now , and that's what we're trying to lower to those capabilities to do our part right now .
But it's struggle .
It's its challenging .
I think everybody who listening has had some sort of personal , whether it's a female member who is sick or or managing kids , which is what i'm doing in a managing kids with two working parents is challenging , but it's so critically important that we all work hard on this .
So that's what we are trying to do .
And that's so many colleagues that are predicted another organizations , which is really.
Encouraging , indeed , work .
We are all in this together .
So thank you for sharing those reflections on what you are doing in this , the reality of pandemic .
So we are about out of time .
But I just wanted to give you an opportunity to share or to ask a question that I should have asked and didn't .
So you can ask that , and as ready for this.
To question , I don't really have a question that follows up on anything in terms of communities .
It's just kind of relates to what you just asked about .
How will this team to be , and in what's next ?
And you mentioned earlier , the next pandemic , what I hope is that that we can all learn in a sort of very important lessons about the response and how an organization like dark is responding , unable to put things out and just really highly again , the importance of the fundamental research investments that we , during , during , along the way that never were intended to influence the magical perspective of addressed the pandemic .
But the way that we can shift that view and focus and still stay true to the main goals program , but build the capability much more rapidly than we would have been able to do under.
Couldn't quote normal circumstances , yeah .
And just the final thought there , and we wanted to think that I, Ilove seeing adult and the programs that program managers like you in your country do overseas that so often the capabilities are powerful in the and general , and not just going for one specific , one of kind of solution , but there are capabilities that can be applied in many ways .
And I think we're seeing that , and you know , both with your AMD and make a program so nice , nice illustration of that , and I just wanna thank you for making time here and for assuring with me and listeners , which dropped to , but thank you , evan , and thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from the airport , thanks also to bend silver and thomas shortage for their help in producing this podcast .