Still , technology , the internet GPS in the palm of your hand , are tonight with operation .
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , doubt the defence advanced research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window on the dark of the core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone , a motel on your dark post today , and please have with me in the studio , major christopher or laughs .
Key , a program manager since twenty fourteen in darkness , technical technology , he comes to drop with an extraordinary combination of academic field and managerial experience and skill sets on the academic .
He is a head trick of engineering degrees , a bachelor's , mechanical engineering , a masters in astronautical engineering and a doctorate in aerospace engineering .
The last one from the university of michigan .
His word time experience includes the deployment to operation record freedom as a tank opportunity .
He has served as the officer in charge and science and technology for the joint robotics of pair detachment at background air field in afghanistan .
There , he planned LED and coordinated personal training and feeling in the statement of thirty five hundred robotic systems before his tour in afghanistan , he served as chief military scientists in engineer for ground vehicle robotics at the USarmy tank , automotive research , development , engineering .
A double all of this previous experience has channeled into a wide range of interest in research efforts , including men and amendment teaming and complex environments , biometric unmanned systems and technologies to improve the capabilities of dismounted war fighters on the ground .
Major christopher laski , thanks for spending some time with me in the studio today .
In the afternoon , I am going to be hurt .
So before we talk about your programs , your adult , but I want to find out a little bit about you and your background , and have you got so interested?
Yes , but I think part of it is a grandfather who he worked as an engineer in a pilot program later in alabama , he used vice president li siller .
So he is always grown up around that type of thing .
He was in the air force .
I want my articles also was an engineer .
So the young age was exposed .
My grandfather is pretty cool .
You let me play with his computer .
Let me work on his workshop .
He let his five year old grandson worked on as a master of computer and tried to figure out of break it and use.
Okay , for for those younger listeners .
So how would you describe my stories?
My best way to describe my own user in new york is on the genetic health .
Is there are not too many people in ways as a command line operating systems of you borders rescued the program instead of cooking and dropped down menu or double cooking at nine hundred and actually had no command lines , and where to find things that I bought all command scripts .
Of course , I think my computer programming skills privately told from about five until I was in grade school.
Right , there is not just a kind of amazing that I think of you to age of five are tapping away at one of these sort of early economic operating systems for some old computers , which took up at that time .
But because half of a desk , so I am wondering , then I , you know how , how did you first learn about DARPA and and and how did you kind of end up here is a program and a tactical.
Technology opposite the person I heard about darfur was actually playing the video game , mentally asylum , where you actually rescued the dark , or director at one point in the game .
I know the idea of darker was , until they did that never got up as I got .
It was pretty cool , but my first little exposure , a previous programming is now a targeted technology , or hit .
It comes to target one of my jobs that target when I figured it , yeah , yeah , yeah , yeah .
A lot of research , development , engineering , santa , when I was there , I went to a legal squad support system review meeting after the last three program review , meeting at a wolf and massachusetts was my first thing when I got out of graduate school , I met with ten o'clock there .
And later he came , and he breathed the new program concept to my organization .
I moved on after that , the robotic system drawing project office knows an existing more , but at the time , it was the primary organization that filled it in programs of record for robots .
And he breathed , and program comes upstairs as my first major experience that have a dark programs in the scope and complex of you , what they do and what their goals are are.
Can you just take us a little bit further along the past way ?
So you would heard about dark from , from the individual .
And then how did you end up getting an offer to even worker?
Yes , I do an additional technical head .
I add up some coworkers in michigan and target who were recommended to talk to another attack on a nationwide moment .
I guess they give you my background , and some of my , I guess what they claim technical expertise and recommended that something I should look into .
So on .
That took up by myself to reach out to both the tenets of women , and ten o'clock had , yeah , there were both two pianos at the time that asked what that golden path , how do you get in double , because I assumed at the time that I was a major storm that you need to be looking at currently takes the position .
And next thing I knew it , I was emailing my resident , hey , what's called the officer brief , within a month , I was on the phone with occasionally whose the technical technology officer director in headphone interview.
Oh , well , i'm sure that the doctor tells me anyone else you spoke with associated with .
That was really impressed by your experience , inquiring the army .
So can you tell me a little bit about that , and you know how you think that might have played a role in getting girls certainly will talk about that , how that played a role in the programs that that you are now running.
Absolutely , I think one of the things that left out earliest we've been told is the experience with robotics , with the army .
So on .
Graduate school , I did some classes while I understanding about the work they move .
I spent some time doing a little bit of time doing research to take a take a lot of research of them in engineering cinema before I went to afghanistan twenty two hours , but about six months , and I did very things .
In addition , the meaning after in charge and being responsible for the people in all the robots I push , they are what we call it during urgent operational needs statement .
So there was a requirement .
Chinese junes are for small robots to support this modern operations .
And so one of my main duties was to support feeling those robots to support what's called the full or of A.
For the operational assessment , and you had to take a class in.
Remembering acronyms , right , but the cousin was before I went through of the same training regimen , or the most the same training regimen that we , at the time , the robotic systems for a project of his data to trained technicians .
So I get trained on how to upgrade all the robots that get trained to fix some of them , which was kind of uncommon for a major to do it .
And it's not typically our jobs , but it gave me a better appreciation of the systems , what the capabilities were with the limitations .
And when I get into theater , and we're supporting operations are as able to make relationships with various units and get the systems out to a wide ride of units , and as much as I could , I will travel around the smaller bases from the larger basis and going to download .
Top soldiers are marines and sellers and asking how they are using their systems , what to keep your bodies .
They saw what limitations are.
And how we could have to improve .
Well , there is absolutely fantastic background .
And one is particularly valuable .
You and our dark , because one of the great challenges of the whole institution is , is to make that connection , you know , the , the orientation of the very verified .
And of course , it gets supply , but then , even when that is successful to know what the issues are , once you run the ground , once your feeling , this kinds of technology is absolutely invaluable .
So it explains what kind of talk about your programs .
Now you have three of them in your portfolio , and all of them associated with imposing war fighters on the ground .
Both his individual war fighters and is elements of on some boards of human robotic and vehicular teams .
So let , let start with your oldest program .
It's called wear web , which means almost sounds like a quest for a full body understood that can enable war fighters to essentially perform sort of like super hero in training capacity .
I know that's a simplifying things .
But how would you describe the worldwide programming and status?
The worldwide program , the goal is to reduce the fatigue , soldiers carrying heavy loads and by reducing fatigue of by doing that , you can implicitly release our goal as I reduce the chances when.
Yeah , and just want to quit me when you say , have you love you?
Really meet , I absolutely mean heavy loss of our soldiers in iraq and afghanistan are carrying loads of up to one hundred and twenty hundred and thirty pounds .
Are there carrying this up heavy ?
They're carrying out of steep slopes and mountains , and it's not something new .
I like a joke .
Now it is not really new ideas anymore , just trying to figure out a better way to do things .
Sometimes i've been to add the opportunity to the chicago in the science and industries , and want to see the difficulties with that was there .
And the other part was used to visit my kids and had an exhibit about the teacher card .
Army from china , and the same thing that they had its same issue .
One soldier , when this man soldiers gonna fight two thousand years ago , they were carrying eighty pounds in the head specific troops of soldiers that were carried .
Lastly , they be faster in last weekend .
You could see the administrator , symbolic of soldiers there will be considered and had signs set up to talk about not surprised to the same .
We said , the same problem today .
So the warrior weapon programs were china's that the same issues were trying to is one approach has been taken on the past .
And what dark did and dark , a funded in exercise and program in the middle , thousands of if I create a parallel scale team , and I could just transfer low to the ground , and then it takes the way off the soldiers , but the challenges with that word .
Now , if you try to try to walk on a metal plate on your foot is very uncontroversial .
Those who actually work hard to operate and increase the material cost of the needed the energy you had to exert to use them .
And so there's they weren't generally accepted for inventory applications .
Researchers are moving one piece of challenging to so that the goal is the .
The program was the shift to lose this look at reducing their fatigue as reduced the energy cost .
And incredibly , they could either walk longer with the same and be the same level of photograph , had the same remaining reserves at a certain point , or they can get to a place and be more physically ready were just directly tied .
How cardinal ready they are to execute .
That's the goal at this point .
The program has been successful .
We've met most of our program goals.
We're at the point where there were two phases .
One was to develop the elements of those .
Now there was them to , I integrate them right ?
So where?
We're the end of the international face actually , so we are done with what we call tsb , which was the beautiful suits .
However , it and the victims to do now , cambridge , massachusetts , was the primary effort that did that .
And we finished testing of those suits with soldiers from foreign injuries are at the average improving ground .
In july , we finish.
Rather than a one early description or vision of what this might look like is something like a wet suit , crafts with a hydrated elements into a book .
When , when you look at what is coming out of the program at this stage , where how would you describe?
I described as good a great first step .
None of those good , great first step towards producing systems in the future that can be integrated into a larger soldiers and samples that can reduce defeating product and the carrier loads over hot , longer distances and make you make them try to run faster , cover the same distance and faster time .
So today , it looks like a bunch of straps and wedding that goes around your legs .
You needs your hips .
There's actual waiters mountain , either under backpack should lower back that poor cables that either connect to your ankle or just behind your head and walk around , then move .
And as it says , the system is , you move , the system traces that sounds like you walk and adapt the best you can to your , your style of walking .
Is everybody different and provide the best systems and.
And no matter , this is my imagine that most of thinking there must accountable , accused the government to eliminate .
So , as you , as you move in , most of things like this.
Yeah , there is , there is quite often in a sound of the actuates pointing in the cable , pulling the cables and and pushed them back out , crackers away .
And this is merely good work that the harvard teenagers in great work actually do standards .
And so to the point where , by the end of the program , there are controls new york complaining about the lack of noise because they used to use the noise as a way to trouble shoot the system .
So when the noise is that studying in a different pitch or different , something was wrong .
Now it's so quiet that they can do that anymore.
Which is a good thing for some answers are getting in the field in a few of the engineers .
It's a personal problem .
I get to be more clever and keeping the improvement moving along .
And there was one of the things that I find interesting about the goals of the program , which was that the host , who would be powered by something like one hundred .
And so in obviously , last week to keep from having to add a battery , wait up and where you alone A.
So we're workloads we're using .
So using batteries like the portable engineering , something like that in backer , soldier , but we did come in a little higher than that , because we are one hundred years ago of twenty five percent about production so often times with the dark program , you set goals , that metrics that you honestly don't know if they achieve it , will you hope they are that we were doing the research to seek the greatest bars and calm down with system traded in the program where we could meet the material reduction of twenty five percent .
We could meet the total system .
A total system must have been less than eight kilograms , but toward john were twenty percent .
So , and I included the batteries .
But the other job was higher than other words , because largely we move to the quiet the quarter .
Actually , at the end , we should not draw more power.
Okay , but I think we're good luck with the continued progression in that program .
So I likely move now to a second program .
This one called the ground experience , go technology or GXPTprogram , and just from the middle of some of the sort of the artist concept images , I can see that this one would have some particular residents for you duty , your experience in the records of tank resolved .
Tell us about the.
GXDTprogram I would like to describe the program as the focus is how to improve the capabilities we know about individual ground combat vehicle , how to make the crew better , how to make the vehicles self better , which explicitly does make data decreases their effectiveness and increases their so primarily focused at this point , I was looking at technologies at argument .
The crew , so to provide them more efficiency or effectiveness in their individual , or improving the mobility , the platform .
So the platform container had access to motoring so that with the same bureaucrats in real or I can actually move faster and safely.
And over the same types of train right now , I think I read you want these vehicles to be of the access upgrade in ninety five percent of the trend they might encounter .
So as a huge range of possibilities , right , right now.
Absolutely , and so there's one of the challenges that we look at three , three main different ways to do that .
So there is , there is an eagle that there is a listens thirty and forty .
There is a concern argument between tracks .
Racist wheels .
What's the best application for even manifested in the worldwide two years alone to have drug vehicles , whether it was in the front .
Well , one year first we looked at this .
We have a reconfigure of a wheel track where you could have a wheel and transform it into a track and back again .
So if you need to drive the road in wheels , if you understand software , snow , those types of train , you can transform in which I can reduce the ground pressure.
I'm trying to get a sense of this is a single kind of vehicle element that that exactly can reform into a wheel and then reform to A.
Yeah , I saw it .
So the , the , the wheel and transforms into a triangle ship track on demand as necessary.
It does actually remind one of the move of the transformer movies above.
Yeah , that was nearly .
Maybe she told my kids that I work on transformers and anything at school .
I have a couple of things working there as we've got a suspension effort to get a result in a full vehicle demonstrator with the goal of driving the standard army test , threatening the vehicle in its classroom .
So , so a hungry , you can take that road at ten months power , we'd like to do it at eighteen and twenty , if possible , while not exceeding the safe driver limits that their standard limits of how much energy can be put into a ever hitting bumps , hitting all is going over after rain .
And so where are goals to go as fast as possible when maintaining?
I understand , also , the program doesn't involve components like censors , other things that will increase the economy situation , awareness of those who might be inside .
Just talk a little bit about some of those important.
The one of the things is the challenge of your goals are the windows tend to be the weapon .
I need to look outside the vehicle to be able to see an operator in windows can provide weaknesses that were usually typically less , less safe or less dancing had less ability to withstand entire army threatening missiles , zebra rounds .
So you can tell me when you get rid of the windows , that's one of the exploration is getting rid of the windows .
Thanks , and I have windows , you know , patient blocks , but you can see a lot out of them .
So two efforts were looked at in harder if you remove the windows as one is looking at driving from a near the air , but has a display that takes in stereo images from around the vehicle and projects them to your eyes and a cool thing about that is , if you ever driven a vehicle by just a screen , others think of the risk of reflects where your eyes expect a certain amount , but the screen doesn't give that to you , and it can make people who are natural .
So some people very successful to what others can kind of train themselves to be less acceptable , but still , over twenty minutes , you can get sick in the ashes and not operate the platforms anymore .
So by now , projecting a stereo image , you can actually reduce that particular and almost eliminate the national , and you can try these things for a long time to add that it will the group , honeywell , with the company that did it modify the player's platform , you drag the completely block out .
And I think I got a lot of thirty five months per hour and.
couple weeks ago , with no nurture, 我到哪去。
Well , well done .
Okay , i'm sure there are many more components that are part of your DGXBtea program we can talk about , but I do want to move on to the third .
We can give business sense of all about you talking about .
The third one is called the squad eggs core technologies program , if no more often , just the squad eggs .
And this one is a systems of systems project , which i'm glad we can be allowed to talk about that dark is doing more and more books , and it just from the sound of it .
You can tell , this is a very complex kind of pursuit by system of systems .
This is a project of many parts , each of them with their own challenges , and but they all intended to come together in ways that infantry squats on the ground would then have unprecedented degrees of situation when awareness and capabilities and ability to adapt to complex and rapidly changing situations .
Again , we went out of time to talk about all of the pieces of scottice , but I would be gratification a little bit of november you may be , but some of those components that are excited to the most so.
Let's start talking about scottish , there's one best way to describe scripts .
You mention the system , the systems we destructed , and sure that it is focusing on the squad as the system as a whole monument , motivating factories for forming that program was experienced , talking to complete manners .
And afghanistan , who asked and for feedback on the robots , we have provided them in training soldiers on .
And one came back to me .
So when I using it , because we've got all the other girl responsibility to carry the throne , all the individual girl , adults , whether it would be mind , provides exposure of device systems , and we just have no soldiers to carry these things that.
So i'm just an interesting point here , because you know , we've earned a kind of a technical philip environments .
We tend to think the technology is a good thing , but hear what we learning is that immediately has to work in the practical , especially for our war fighters , or who have so many things to worry about , so things to carry .
So this was a kind of interesting lesson for you to learn.
I saw that any part of it is , for my least , my viewpoint is in the army more important than a very good job , or especially with fast fifteen players , were of a quickly individual soldiers .
But sometimes we get slaughtered if I threw too much at individuals , soldiers and marines , I don't look at what the impacts to a fire team are squad so on .
The main focus areas of squad access to look at what is the effect on the past performance .
It's the smallest formation in the military that can conduct what we says .
Fire manufacturers that can fire while the other teams newspaper in the target .
And so I just admitted what fighters might have an army squad today has none soldiers , and a morning coastguard has dirty and thank you .
So that's the scientists we're looking at , and we're looking at how we can hold , listed and improve .
So in taking a system supposed to do that , looking at the total waiter , this quarters of votes to tolerate the individual person , the , the effectiveness of the global is the effective of a single person , for example , and well matrix scientists have been done before the holiday , quantity , leisure and improving scott .
And so that I think some of the coolest things are most potential benefits we have is really , truly how funeral , how we can integrate men systems into a scott and providing capabilities don't result in a soldier marine being headed down because of a soldier rings being headed down , trying to control a robot that they're not paying attention .
And that's one last rifle that's in the site .
So a couple things will look at how we can have one main systems of royal ground robots , or a robot move with a squad information .
Sounds very simple .
The military , if we can we manufacturer information , but we have different formations for different missions in different conditions .
So can we get robots that recognize what is doing , and manufacturer without intolerance to do that ?
Can we get robots ?
The municipal scouts , and from the squad to the side of the squad , whatever the most appropriate position would be.
So that they can actually provide support , right ?
And again , this is without the human life , parts of the system worrying about the the robotic ones , raising , thinking that they're just gonna conscience , know what to do almost as a collective kind of energy or going forward.
And as we do that , someone else thinks we're looking into , not just going to robots to move reliably , but then what useful tasks can they do ?
So we have efforts out their techniques so that canadians and systems are cameras carried by design systems gotta , find humans and environment , report back to the square that there may be humans overhear and even trying to get the point , we can distinguish whether another carrying.
And that is quite noted .
So you been here , I think what since twenty fourteen sounds like a tremendous amount of are in the effort .
And yet you're also coming to , and the vietnamese here , as a program manager , that is an interesting aspect of darker , and that the program manager role is a pretty short live one anywhere from two , three , or maybe sometimes five years .
So because you send emergency , but the halloween realized is for the no , right that is my last halloween .
All right .
So you're behind of these programs to your , to your fellow program managers and see if they can take them to the finish line , but because you have the kind of the benefit of remembering the beginning , leaving the middle and now coming to the end of your program manager status , I think you got a kind of a good porch for you , saying a little bit about the whole experience of being a program manager .
What would you you learned about that role , say , as part of the europe innovation ecosystem in the context of national fans.
The biggest thing i've learned that being a program manager is that the innovation in collaboration , it's a team effort I don't do by myself .
There is no way I could begin to find them to manage all these programs and all these efforts that are , rather than by myself .
So I have a great team , a great support team that helps our technical experts in the field , in their fields .
And the ultimate events is not the ones that do .
It is the engineers and scientists at japanese and universities and defence contractors that we found that are the ones that ultimately are going to bend metal and write code and then deliver these capabilities to our fires that can forget the war fighters either , because they are invaluable advice .
Stations are also part of a loop , such a collaborative ecosystem that results new innovation that provides these new capabilities.
No , it was actually beautiful way of connecting what is happening in this dark headquarters , which is mostly kind of a typical building reaching out the researchers record of the performer community .
And in your case , you have several for each of your programs and ensure you multiply three by whatever , i'm sure you got .
Probably , it doesn't know many more than that performers out there , all of your work in your colleagues have to go out and make sure everybody is gonna doing what we all agreed would would happen in these programs .
But then you're taking it all the way out into the fields .
This is really an draws , the , the full line , so is really interesting to hear that .
But because you are leaving on halloween , I have to ask you now also what?
What's next for european ?
So i'll be a scientist , penalty gun and a part of my duty .
There will be to take a lessons , take the lessons I learned and pass assignments , especially the lessons are not going to stand up to others to problems for the army , where we need capabilities in A.
Well , okay , we'll be good to know that this can be someone who is said , a lot of experience .
You are dark and in the field , and now over in the panic and looking at the host of technology equation in context , national advances , thanks for sharing all that .
Chris , you've been here dark .
And I often think of dark as a place where technologies that are for the moment , fictional , sometimes become nonfictional or real .
I am wondering if you are someone who has been inspired by science fiction in your life .
If you've been a science fiction reader of the fictional technologies movies , you've seen some advanced technology in on the field .
Employments is there fictional technologies kind of you find fascinating in my one of our ultimate?
When they see becoming a there is , actually , I have draw quite offensive danger that I go mind OGHOcartoons that I grew up on it for a technologies that geologists had nearly , it is , and use those , they have robots that move to them and have capabilities to protect .
Joseph , take , take the fight to the enemy is necessary .
So do you have your own comic books ?
Sir , I had the old cartoons .
Still , you actually report them much to my wife , grand.
And so kick it , it means amazing to me that you might be able to go back to some of these two images that you saw the child and then compare them to what you are actually doing now.
And happened as a as a dirty program manager , let's be quite fun .
Spent a great , great experience being a double program manager.
What christmas beneficial to help you in the studio , thanks for sharing with us a good part of your experience of dark .
And just before you're about to leave on halloween , so your colleagues are gonna miss you when you go , but thanks for all that service here , I just want to thank you for sharing this time with me and our listeners , my pleasure , thanks for helping me and thanks listeners for ease dropping on us .
I hope you again , boys from dirt .