Self technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand alternatives operation technology is a driver of our times since its founding in one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , DARPA , that offends research projects has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan a motto , and on your dark host today , and please help with me .
Doctor erick , medicine , a program manager since twenty seventeen in the agency's biological technology , we are recording our conversation from our respective homes as we do our part to slow the spread of copyright team .
The pandemic disease caused by the new crowd bars .
Sars could be .
This is pakistan and pandemic times , iraq by a medical engineering by training , is among the number of program managers at drug were trying to accelerate technology development already underway to help out the current pandemic crisis .
The portfolio of his programs covers a broad swar for technologies and capabilities .
Much of this workers about minimizing the impacts of emerging disease threats .
It's what eric has been doing .
He is cool .
Europe , thanks for joining me screwing to be here .
Thank you for having me .
So before we talk about your size of the world for the opera programs with names like electrical , prescription epidemic , characterization and observation , or echo ego and personalized protective biosystems .
I'd like to know something about the origins of your interest in biomedical engineering .
And what like you in that direction.
As I have progressed in my career , but more , more focused , developing technologies and applications that can solve real problems , like the one were facing today.
Write in some president of this interest in your drive to solve problems that really catch my interest .
I just wanted to bring up one of them .
I wanted to hear a little bit of the story of the containerization of bio containment system .
This one hundred award from originally magazine , back in twenty sixteen .
I believe it was .
Can you tell me a little something about that work because it seems to share some of the themes that map onto the programs you are running for now.
Yeah , thanks for asking that question that I really was excited about that project .
It was probably one of the most fascinating and in most challenging engineering efforts that i've ever been a part of , and I was proud to be part of .
It came about when the ebola outbreak began in an early twenty fourteen .
And as we watched the unfold , and in very similarly , a chemically waves kind of like we expect to see cover , and I think we saw that there is going to be a problem .
Had aid workers in africa who needed to come back to the us , or who needed to be transported to other medical facilities because of the fact there was limited capacity in africa itself .
Doctor will waters head of operational medicine at the state department contacted me and said , he , can you build a transport system that can fit into a commercial or a military aircraft and the engineering team ?
And I set out to do that will waters , and I literally draw the design of the CBCSon the back of an afghan .
And then we gave that to the engineering team , and I work with that engineer team nineteen day , and in about thirty days , we had the first prototype built .
And now that system is in the covering nineteen response at maximum capacity , I believe there are four systems out there .
I just heard from the military site that they're gonna , be bringing it more .
So it's really satisfying to see something that you put your heart and soul and to come out many people and so that I hope that we have more stories like that while we get our short time here , dark.
Right , indeed .
Indeed , when you said CBCSthat was at the acquaintance for containerization by our containment system .
So that is very cool , must feel very rewarding to work is now in a kind of getting deployed .
So I also always love to know kind of the , how did I get the dark story ?
Somehow , you met somebody you heard about , you know , opening a dark .
How is it that you actually got yourself a dark?
Well , actually , that goes all the way back to the late eighties for me , when I was in middle school , I would write my over two .
The library influenced her to crash marshall high school in northern virginia , and I was going there , and I republican recognizing and started reading stories about dark .
That was when we were starting to hear about some of the , the computer reading technologies and the networking technologies that were coming out of double as as part of the unveiling the internet , so that got me interested .
And then I did an internship at the navy research libertarian , early nights , working for someone who eventually became a program manager on rudolph , many of the technologies he developed actually , are now being realized as helpful .
And in prosthetics , germany started with his early work , and some of the diagnostics work , for example , that abbott ID now platform and the software platform started from his arms worker DARPA .
For me , I was seeing the potential and the vision that he had , even when I was at the navy research , libertarian manifested itself and the dark , and that got me very excited about the fact that , you know , you can have this burning research passion , and you think you can change the world .
And allen and others with him in his coward really inspired me to to realize that I could do that one day and waited until I not enough of a breath of experience in the , at the real world .
If you wear cotton , cotton industry and in research institutions before I felt like I was ready to come to dark , but now I think about the right point , my area , and I am thinking that it's possible to start making a difference here .
And i've had a really good time so far .
So it takes.
Going out another report , how you became a biomedical engineer and how you ended up the dark .
Let's kind of move on and talk about the programs that you have .
You mean some of them are inherited , and some of them might believe that you , you device and have gotten through the very difficult wedding process to get the approval to move forward .
They also seemed to have a kind of some themes to them .
So wonder if you can talk about the distributed driver , the things that you have most in mind , like what you most want to achieve with just your entire sweet of programs .
And they will talk more specifically about some of them .
And then.
It started actually way back when I started that the naval research separatory , you know , we were always having a hard time measuring the responses of the biological systems we are studying .
I was actually trying to how sales turned into blood vessels that happens in embryonic development and moon healing , and we really are still even to the state still unlocking the mysteries of how blood vessels form and how they adapt the stresses of life .
And one of the things that is really making it hard to understand .
That is the ability to measure at the soil level .
What is going on .
You know , there is this massive network of inner plane between proteins and other bio molecules in the cells , and we need to figure out ways to see that in real time , so that LED me to the formation of the two programs in my portfolio , one is the objective circulation and observation program , or echo and echo .
What we're doing is exactly what exploiting an entirely new landscape .
It's a landscape that people have shut away from .
We've known about the landscape , and that is the opportunity .
And what's crazy about the opportunities that is kind of like a black box ?
It , what happened in your life from days europe , and it even has little hints of recordings .
What happened in your ancestors like , because you can actually pass along the.
And our limit just introduced for a minute to give listeners a sense of what the is , the genome .
That's really kind of the , the entire repertoire of our genius is about twenty two thousand of them is , so the epigenome does not have to do with the genetic letters .
Exactly , ACTNG.
It's above that , just like an episode center of an earthquake as a upward north korea actually happens .
The epigenome is above the genome , above the genetic sequencing essence , but it's where there is all kinds of molecular mechanisms and the signals that can control which genes are expressed , which ones are on , and which ones are silent .
Do I get that right?
Yeah , think about like this .
I mean , that's a great way to describe it .
It's kind of a labeling system on your genome .
Think of your genome as like your ACTGis like , he said , but it's about two meters long in every single cell , and it's also identical , pretty much in every single cell , but it used differently by every single cells .
The appetite , it's really a way that each sale is able to know what parts of the gym to use to live to function .
All the sells in our body function differently .
The point here is , it's a pretty permanent mark , and it responds to the environment when you go outside on a hot day , your opportunity is changing when you go into a inner indoor pool .
You break up crown , that's changing arbitration too .
When you get a viral infection , it definitely is changing your reputation because your body is trying to respond that virus by making anybodies .
Guess how it makes us anybody's try to turn a pigeon to make the antibodies that are very specific for that virus .
And so what we can do is exploit that and say , oh , well , let's just look at the opportunity because that actually happens within an hour or so of exposure to a virus .
So it's a quick response and it happening in millions of thousands in your body .
So there's plenty of cells to assemble , therefore planning a signal to read .
So going back to my quest of reading , what's going on in sales in your body .
This approach , you know , is a really right target for doing that in the context of violent factions , and it opens up a whole new landscape in way , the diagnose infection that no one has been using ever .
And so where were really the first ones doing it when we started this program two years ago , no one thought we could do it .
Now we're able to distinguish people who have infections better than the current state of the art .
We're beating PCR , which is the current state of the art , climate change reaction and and sold .
We're beating that .
But what's also cool is where doing things that our current diagnosis can do , for example , were now in human samples , distinguishing people who have drug resistant infections from the same species of bacteria versus are non drug resistant strength of that .
So this is like anybody criticisms were diagnosing just from your own cells , your own appetite , and rather than taking the blood sample and having a culture of bacteria and figure out of its response of nonresponsive danie badges we're able to show now from your own host response to those bacteria that we can tell you if you have a drug resistant infection or not , and I can get treatment that can make a big difference .
And we can detect it very early in the infection , much sooner than conventional methods .
So that's the echo programming .
It in a nutshell .
And we think we can actually change the game and covered nine team responses .
We think we're gonna get responses days before the current technology for diagnosing or testing for that violent faction .
So I think that's something that's very exciting for me , but hopefully makes a difference in the world.
Right , and that's a very powerful capability , because I was learning with this new crown virus .
People can be contagious .
Well , before they are showing symptoms .
So if you have a tool like echo , when I present , require , as you say , kind of biological samples themselves , that would have responded , perhaps in the even the early hours of initial infection , it might be possible than to identify people who are , in fact , in two days before they shortly symptom something .
Obviously , we would love to have now .
So when expand democrat vehicle could possibly provide us with their capability.
Well , I should even wear in the process right now , going through human samples that we've obtained from multiple clinical sites , and we're building a signature of fuel .
This is what we call this , the opportunity signal that we get from somebody .
We're building a universal epigenetic signature that applies across individuals that we test , but also we've applied it against similar infections to show that it's unique , and where a trying this now to a commercial platform , so that we can actually have an opportunity text that will be relevant in this current outbreak , and we're going to be submitting that for emergency use authorization to the .
So we hope that if everything goes well , we'll be making a difference in this very outbreak .
This is something that we would , we would hope that will change the game and our ability to do testing , testing is going to be important for this covered nineteen outbreak well into the end of twenty , twenty , maybe beyond , because I don't think we're gonna completely radicalized this immediately .
So we hope that this is a tool available to.
Yes , interesting is gonna be the absolute key in getting the economy back , going , knowing when any individual can feel confident about going out into the world and not getting sick themselves for getting other sick .
This is a very exciting thing to hear eric that this work , as you know , you've storming it right into this current lemon wearing .
This also relates science to multiple measuring biological activity to some degree .
Right , yes , or imagine.
Logical aptitude we wanted to , instead of with alcohol , where we were diagnosing things that were harmful to you , like bacteria , viruses .
We had a challenge that was presented to us by some of our military lays on officers and services chiefs , and we know we have a services he felt as program and dark aware people who are actually in the fight , actual war fighters in the military activity .
They wrote it through every three month , and we get to talk to them and hear about what they're facing in the real world , and they're shaping our programs and one of the challenges that day and the military is on one military is an officer particular chief for an officer , neil hermanson , who's a twenty seven year navy seal .
They all brought me the challenge of , how do we diagnose performance ?
And so instead of diagnosing disease , how do we diagnose performance to identify what people need to work on how they could work on it to improve their performance .
And when we talk about performance , we talk about from the context of cognitive , behavioral and physical performance so realized that if you are a navigator , or if you are navy seal , it's physically challenging , absolutely , but it is also and emotionally slash behaviorally challenging , right .
So you have to balance all of these things and hit the switch part of the three elements physical , cognitive behavior to really master your art , or master your specialty in the military , and is there a unique measurement at the molecular level , right there is something we could measure in the opportunity , or maybe we could measure how we express our dreams that the notes , what it is about somebody that is special in a given application .
Maybe your navy sale , maybe your fighter pilot , maybe clinician .
There are a lot of different specialists in the military , and we wanna be able to court on court , diagnose what is unique about that specialty at a gene expression level .
What this is is it measuring how people are currently expressing their genes that on the job doing , you know what they're really good at doing .
And let's figure out what it is that makes them tick at a molecular level that can help us shape people in their .
So , for example , if I know you are expressing a certain protein at higher levels and other people , and you're doing much better at your jobs of fighter pilot .
What I can do is use that in to look at people as they're going through their developmental process early and training , or even in selection or free selection .
And I can look at those molecular markers of performance , and you're low and ease in your higher knees .
But what's cool is because it's not your genome .
You can actually change these things by training .
You can actually change your levels of expression of and gym products , so that you can get to a higher level of performance .
So you know , first , we understand that that was called measuring biological aptitude .
That's the name of the program , so that's building understanding , and you use that understanding to shape the training process .
And this has implications a little bit beyond training and preparation for the clear .
We also think it has implications for maintaining performance levels , because if you can look at jenny expression , which is a very dynamic system , and you can understand that circuit this driving performance for someone who's on the job you can , you can actually capture your own their state of readiness or their state of preparedness for that job .
By looking at now a molecular objective marker , not just asking him how they feel before they get the cockpit of their fighter palace , but actually taking a measurement and saying , you know , these biomarkers are a little bit different .
You should change your diet .
You should change your sleeping.
Right amazing .
So it's sort of like you bring in a molecular biological point of view to try to improve the system of people in the entire kind of military mission .
So you can bring in military biology into that overall picture .
And as you say , bring in either you know , training or or diet , other kinds of things that can tailor that molecular biology to that person and their mission .
Then we begin to , to really enhance what the military mission is capable of overall and absolutely fascinating .
Okay , there is another program that catches my attention .
Actually , all of your programs do .
This one is called personal protective via system , tells a little bit.
Yes , the , the personalized , protected by our system program , is all about using systems that we haven't used before to protect our body from threats .
So you know , i've talking about , you know , the other program , literal about kind of measuring your bodies response with that kind of been my quest , but I wanted to make sure that before I left up , but I put in a program that actually didn't just measure them in report , but also could give you some level of protection against things were worried and ill in this time of covering our team .
This program personalized , protected by the system or PPBBlike ravel , the PPBprogram is about protecting you against viral bacteria and chemical threats , and it's also utilizing a completely new approach .
So number one were building reactive materials that you can wear .
You think of them as almost like skin tight , you know , very , very light weight materials .
We want the whole world system , way less than a pound .
So those materials could put on your body and be protected in your airway , your skin , your eyes and and all over your body from threats , but you really wouldn't know you wearing it because it doesn't add thermal burden really adds almost no weight , and it provides you with protection against the spectrum of known and emerging chemical and threads .
But what was really different about this program is not just the material piece , what we have , another piece of this program , which is using synthetic to protect you by having the synthetic biology living on or annual at your tissue barriers .
So think about this , right , there is a wave of a syn buyer right now .
You know , you heard about this , another podcast and you news .
So it's where we use bacteria and other organisms to make products for us , and that usually happens in a big buyer reactor , or what looks like a beer for mental in a factory or warehouse somewhere , right ?
But what if you could make the projects you need on your body with the same types of bacteria are the same types of organisms there are used in those big for mounting systems or big barrier actor systems that we see um in a typical drug manufacturing or industrial processes .
So , in other words , you become the factory , you become the factory that makes the compounds that we see this happening .
Now , there's a few companies that have started clinical trials where you can actually take , and in just certain types of bacteria that arty can live in your body , and they make products to protect you against toxins or help you deal with your labor disorder , or help you process things that your body , if you have a kitty disorder .
For example , these bacteria are are actually taking the place of your kidney , and they're doing the job of processing your , your talk to buy products that you have in your blood.
This is fantastic , sort of like engineering lead , the bigger microbial.
Exactly , and so for personalized , protected by our system , what we're asking is , can we regenerate on microbiology , or even bring in other types of organisms that can live on you ?
There is a number of different types of live have evolved over millions of years to live on , or within humans in a sympathetic way .
We call a commercial system .
And so they live commentary with , and if we can engineer them with new genetical techniques that are now almost ubiquitous , we can now engineer than to produce things for us and protect us so they can produce , for example , anybodies , or they can produce vaccines , or they can produce compounds that interact with viruses or bacteria , or even chemical agents like anzac and break them down before they can hurt us .
So we essentially circulating , or a constant presence of something to protect us , and all we have to do is take it in an inhaled form or injected , or put it on our skin , or put it on our eyes , or right .
So these are the ways in which the personalized , protected bio system is going to utilize what we call commercial organisms to protect us through a simple application .
The workers were saying in the program , thirty day protection or even corner threats to remove ideal encountered and destroyed them by using answers , using other compounds .
So that's the idea of PPBis that is both a material solution , and it's a biological solution that can live honors and with us.
To protect us , write an article you depend on one thing that really caught my year , which was that you're designing this the third day kind of alteration said in our microbial .
So that sounds like it should be reversible , not a permanent change that you are.
Thinking about you , oh yeah , things bring that up in part of the critical components of this program are on and off switch .
So we're gonna from the very beginning of the program to five year program .
We planned habits in humans by the end of five years , and that this year , but in the very beginning , we want there are performer teams .
People were funding to do this work to demonstrate that they can turn off the bio system if you will within one hour .
So , for example , take an anniversary and you shut it off , or you take an effective cleared compound that safe to use has no side effects .
And that turns off the protection immediately .
You need to turn it off , but you also need to turn it on quickly .
So I saying , you know , within an hour , you need to be able to take you know , in hell and adjust or apply this bio system .
And it needs to be active within an hour.
One of the programs that you inherited has acquired an intriguing name is called the electrical prescription program .
What's the status of that programme?
Will the electrical prescription program or electrics is about , I say , in its last six months , I say it's been a very phenomenal , very successful program .
I think it has the capacity to change how it medicine works in the country .
I think its its inception was to control and organ function through very focused , specific interactions with the preferred nervous system .
Dog weber started that program , and I think it was really a visionary concept , a lot of the work , and exactly comes from a gentleman name , calm tracy , out of the institute .
And you know , he published some early work showing that you could actually control overall information of your body through interacting with the biggest nerve , which is a big nerve that runs outside of your spinal , from your brain to various organizations in your body , and it has really kind of unique control and feedback .
It has a really unique relationship between the organs and your body and your .
So can you stimulate that nerve in all of its branches to have therapeutic effects ?
And it turns out with electric can , and we are actually entering into five different clinical studies , treating a wide variety of conditions .
And this is how dark program , you know , you , you prove it out .
And over the past four years , people to prove it out that we can actually control things like your body's locals levels for type two diabetes .
We can control earlier about this water in the animals , and we now show we can block pain and animals through performance .
Damn , if we can do things like control information .
So control roommate toward authorities or or maybe information associated with joint injury .
And then what's also very interesting as post dramatic stress , we're entering the clinical study where we can interact with the vages nerve to combine that with a certain type of therapy called exposure therapy to stop the symptoms associated with postgraduates , which I think is a very powerful application .
And we were very excited about that one point mute perspective.
So remarkable , transformative idea , in the sense that for many melodies , and it sounds like this is where you're going .
You might be .
The move patients off of a medicinal and a former suitable type of approach and move more into this kind of intervention with the biggest nerve.
The teams on this program have done a phenomenal job characterising the underlying mechanisms until we had publications , well respected journals , and and it's seen a lot of accurate , even from journalistic journal of american medical association .
Where were really threatening their whole paradigm .
We're threatening the paradigm and using surgery , you know , now we're saying , look , you may not need those things .
We could actually modulate organ function through very precise interactions with the performance system , and this is actually spawned an entire industry .
We just seemed just recently a glacial partner with one of our performers at jiang's occasions to roll out an error about this order , clinical results that showed the variable control are euro about this water through circle discrimination .
This is very exciting for.
In every connection was that a face one just perceived , it was actually an ethics effective.
No , that was an ethical study .
So now , yeah.
Ah , so so that's really exciting that moving toward potentially a actual clinical use.
Right in a municipal condition , this chronic , you have to stand a drug course .
That's not one hundred percent effective , and usually in in the late stages , you end up having surgical innovation .
This is a very powerful thing .
If we can actually stop yourself about this , you know , we think that we can get to a point of changing the game for , for those patients and to putting them back in normal life without drugs or surgery.
Yeah , yeah , people suffer in such difficult ways with that disease .
And so if you could move this for that , you are a lot of good for a lot of people .
And so may you succeed.
One more thing , you know , may not sound like a militarily relevant problem , but that is a disease that is thirty percent higher in the military population .
Then in the rest of the population .
So it's a very militarily relevant disease .
And I just want to make sure that's clear that , you know , we're helping , you know what happened .
Our folks are troops , in addition to helping the rest of the world .
Let's the , that's the goal of the departure program.
In a week , spoken about four programs epigenetic characterization and observation , measuring biological aptitude and personalized protective equipment in electrical prescriptions .
We've talked about how echo is perhaps on a sweet being , even a part of the set of solutions we need to ultimately manage the current pandemic , but are other other places in your portfolio where you are solving what really worth longer term technology development goes right into this copyright nineteen challenge.
You know , we're really focused on just making sure alcohol is entering the male .
You know , I think once the personalized , protected bio system program gets up and running , because it hasn't started yet .
Just to be clear that that program starts in the we think , want to get up running if the outbreak is still creating changes for us , we may be able to bring in online some early solutions from commercial systems that may offer protection , in effect , meaning one of the things were thinking about utilizing the microbial men and the commercial systems , taxi produce , vaccine products .
You know , you may hear that , you know , where ear plus out from a vacation particular outbreak .
But again , if we could produce that product in a commenced organism and have the , the person just in just or apply this organism and in the body that production could happen on site , and that has been shown in an animal stroke very well , and protecting gets a number of different infectious disease and talks and threads .
So we think that it's possible that we could bring that online , and that would be a sword that I would apply if we needed , if we don't see a good vaccine or therapy candidate for this.
I'll break now , one of the things I like to ask .
Program managers is in , is there something special institutionally about double how it institutionally can help you persuasions of important technology.
Well , it was great about dark .
It is , you know , there is a lot of freedom to be creative , but there's also a lot of rigger that goes into creating a program and making that idea a reality .
And I think that has opened the door for a lot of success in the biotechnology space , because biotechnology is requires an enormous amount of discipline and underlying knowledge for you to make a product that's going to be worthwhile in the commercial space , or in the military application , because those who end up being wanting the same .
And i'll say , I say that because of the fact that for any product to me know , help the military from , you know , that scene with their putis or diagnostic standpoint , those products have to go through the same regulatory evaluation with the FDGas as any commercial products .
So they have to follow the same long articles , just pass to make sure that they are safe and effective .
And so what dark allows us to do is , is really apply the level of discipline you need to apply to a new product right from the beginning .
Now , the opportunity only last four to five years .
So we need to be creative and engaging the commercial space early on with our ideas and our programs , so that the commercial space can can help carry them through the the material process .
Then on the tail end of that maturation , the military can come back to and utilize those products and those products with them already have a manufacturing pipeline and allegedly exchange that can support the needs of the military.
Right , erick is one way , and maybe you could just kind of consciously react one about to say that one of the things that I think darker does best is to take what really is a very risky technology idea and find ways of the risking of doing a hard work .
The validation is needed , sometimes foundational research , but then sometimes more on the development site to take a risk down enough that it can then hand off the bottom to other players in the innovation ecosystem , otherwise would not take it on , because the risk was too high .
Do you think that's one way of thinking about a major role of the.
Perfect place , but I think you said perfectly , and I think one thing dark is doing that help us also be on that .
Is there now starting to embed entrepreneurs with people we found so on the second half of several funding cycle with the company or university , we're putting embedded entrepreneurs .
The dark is paying for our own pocket into the companies to help those companies succeed .
And I have been a huge advocate and adapter , and we're already seeing benefits from those relationships with new investments from the private sector into our programs and performers that we , we started here doubt.
There are , thanks a lot for sharing all this time with me and our listeners .
It was just amazing to hear about the programs you're working on .
Couldn't be happier .
Dolphins have been hard pursued to be some of the solutions to the copyright team pandemic , and also working on problems that will potentially have really great consequences in many areas of medicine .
As you mentioned , even in areas like diabetes and irritable bells and drums , so it just released australia .
Amazing here about.
Again , thanks for being with us .
Thank you .
I am and thank you for the opportunity.
And thanks witnesses for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from dark thanks also to ban silver and TOM shortage for their help in producing this pakistan .