Going to a science engineering laboratory , close your eyes and listen in a biomedical lab , you might hear an operation tribute as it separates the components of assembled in a chemical analysis lab .
You might hear the wind of a turban pump as a evacuates , the chamber of a , in a missile proportion research facility , you may hear the aggressive white noise from a textbook of a new jet fuel in each setting .
You can hear a sonic fingerprint .
What goes on .
Welcome to a new periodic feature of our Voices from darker pipelines .
We are calling it sounds of innovation .
My name is , I have a matter on your dog host , rather than hearing the voices of program managers , which is normally what you get enough Voices from doctor parkers in each sounds of innovation episode , you will hear a few snippets of research escapes .
They're part of jobless world and learn just a little bit about what new capabilities those songs could lead to .
Let's get right to.
That's a signal with a set of towns just a tad above the highest piano generated by an underwater modem for sending and receiving data through water .
This is the sort of communications and networking component that researchers in darkness , timely information for marijuana engagement program , timely for short , are working toward as they strive to realize a strategic framework known as music warfare .
Think you have many discribed military assets in the and on and under the ocean , as though there are music tiles of a logical hearing to picture .
Now think about dynamically integrating and reintegrating those towels into the most effective military action possible , and in any given situation and moment for that to become possible with assets across all military developments , including ones under water motors and signals like the one you just heard , probably will be part of the museum .
Brace yourself for the next sound of innovation.
That intense white noise is coming from a new experimental bioscience eclipse of you made with the help of genetically engineer as a campus and creates thrust in the first of its kind ground test of a liquid fuel rampage at the weapons division of the neighborhood center in china .
Lake , california , in the mix of hydrocarbons in the fuel , which normally derived from petroleum , distributes not e sales , is just one of the many deliverables emerging from doctors living founders program .
In this case , from the biotechnology emmas a performer on the program based in memory of california , notable here is a gallon for gallon , the spiral synthetic fuel , dubbed by amazon as bio renewable one packs energy comparable to jet fuel , JPten , the current go to synthetic for missile platforms like the thomas hawk , says an achiever program manager for the living founders program , biologically produced fuels can have advantages in costs and performance over comfortable synthetically produced and could be an additional source of military grade fuels during times of great demand .
Here's the sound of another kind of jet.
What you just heard was a laboratory test of a drilled that relies on high pressure drafts of water .
In this case , at one hundred and twenty five pounds per square range , jet out of another to cut through soil .
The clip captures just a few seconds of the workers that researchers at the colorado school of mines are doing for their part in darkness under minor project , the goal of under miner is to develop new , new , two more than techniques and to adapt ones from oil and gas , utility , geological , environmental and other industries for quickly borrowing tunnels to open new technology .
Such a preposition in supplies in advance of military operation were providing ongoing resupply channels as troops move through an area , the ability to rapidly bore tunnels also could be helpful in rescue mission .
Here's a partial spoiler alert , the next sound of innovation is also from the other minor program.
That sound clip was harvested by the engineering team from general electric , which is developing an earth warm , inspired tunnel , boring robot under contract with under minor program , rather than the size of saying toronto earth's warming your backyard , the robotic earthworm is six feet long and two inches wide .
The robot snows will the boring tools penetrates earthly environments as a series water activated chambers mimicked the rising motion of an earthward .
As a result , the system boats boards forward as the segments have come back and stable as the walls of the fresh brown , the sounds in the clip derives from inlet and exhaust files as they managed the water in fleeting and exhausting from the robots , bladder , like artificial muscles .
The GEteam hopes to live over about account .
They'll be able to borrow tonight more than five football fields in land in a time it takes to watch .
Thanks for listening to this first episode of darkness , sounds of innovation series .
We will be posting more episodes in the series intimately as a feature of the boys is from darker parkers , thanks to benjamin for his partnership and producing this problem for more information about the programs , which sounds you just heard , as well as about other breaks of technologies .