Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand.
Autonomous operation.
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding a nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , DARPA , the defense advanced research projects agency , has been a driver of welcome to Voices from DARPA , a window onto dark as core a program managers their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is ivan , a matter when I am your dark host , and today I am pleased to have with me in the studio .
Lin horse , a program manager since twenty twelve in darkness , strategic technology offers with a background and physics .
Lin spends a lot of this time .
I doubt thinking about a world without the global position system , a system which is all about physics , engineering and the management of complex systems .
And he thinks about bringing GPS functions under sea into other places where GPS signals cannot reach , in short , wednesday become one of the agencies go to guys in a technical area known as PNT, which stands for positioning , navigation .
And thank you for your spending some time with me today .
Well , thank you for inviting me .
So before we talk about some of your efforts to develop plan b for when GPS might not be available or to create a and underestimate version of GPS .
I just interested you .
I want to find a little bit about you , your background , and maybe something about how that background explains how you ended up .
Your read .
Start in twenty twelve .
Well , when I was growing up , I never.
Thought about when I grow up , I won't be a navigation engineer .
That was not something that was at the front of my mind .
However , when I came out of grade school , my first job was a navigation flight controller for special operations , and I fell in love with the art and science of navigation , and it's been a common threat of my career ever said.
What are an exciting entry , I mean to be working on the special program to say little bit more about that.
But I was working on the space shuttle program that was we had GPS and saw the navigation system of the , the space shuttle used a variety of sensors to determine a vehicle was in space .
So we are , the navigation system was primarily critical on the introduction of the mission that is when it returns from space to the learning field , but also accent and or on.
One word with operations , you can .
And what did you study in great school?
Physics and then I, Iquickly learn that theoretical physics was not my forty , but I still love physics .
So I , my graduate degree was an engineering.
Physics and is one of the things about your biography and sensor and interested in .
This is your name , because I believe full first name is franklin .
Cool , you go by lin , the second ceiling bowl for short , when most people who have the name franklin and shortage will go with the first of all , frank , so what's up?
I think that my mother has a sense of humor .
I am a junior , and she did not want to , frankly running around the house .
So my father goes by frank.
My girlfriend is so that indicates to me that there was a big dose of pregnancy in your home , and practice spilled over into where you work .
So let , let us know , talk about some of your programs .
I think we'll start with the adaptable and navigation systems programme , as do all programs that double this one goes by the acronym , in this case , ANSwhat intrigues me about this one , but I want you to say more about it is that you are trying to tap into a huge diversity of signals here , things like signals and cell towers or TV signals that are already out there candidates in constructed environment , but also other kinds of signals in the natural environment .
The one that just really stands out for me is lightning .
So let me stop there , just as you to tell me and listeners a little bit about the adaptability of navigation systems program.
Okay , ANSis actually a portfolio of multiple programs .
One of those programs under NShas called aspen ASPN, which is short for all sorts , positioning , navigation , and it addresses the topic you , you are reference to .
We like to think of it as developing a navigation , architecture and algorithm that can process what we call sensors of opportunity .
That is any sensor that has special or temporary information .
So consider an aircraft , primarily aircraft today use GPS are , and a either stand alone mode , or they will integrate a GPS receiver with what's called an initial measurement unit as basically a dead reckoning device has sensors in effort .
That sense , accelerations and will sense rotational rates .
And from that you can debt reckon .
So the two GPS in an initial measurement unit combined for my very robust solution , but GPS sometime just not .
And then that system will rely primarily on the IMU.
And then let me just stop you there .
What are the situations under which serve GPS might become unavailable?
For ground users , GPS can become unavailable when you are in what we call urban canyons that is dense , ordinary skyscrapers constantly , you think of downtown chicago or downtown manhattan were the buildings are obstructing the signals , especially .
And this is on the context of maintaining very accurate navigation .
The aircraft is specially military aircraft when they roll over , turn upside down .
Now , the GPS santa has pointed to the ground signals are coming from the ground in case , or rely on the initial measurement unit to debt .
Reckon until the GPS reservoirs is exposed .
And because the GPS signal is so weak by design that it is very easy to interfere with a receivers of.
That's signal , okay .
So I should actually concept up the problem for us .
And let me get you back to what you're talking about , which is to use some senses of opportunity out there to make up for the school.
So what we recognized was that many platforms we have have centres owned them that are providing special information , but there are not being used by the navigation system .
So the question we asked ourselves , let me come up with an algorithm and an architecture that can be rapidly reconfigured to use sensors that are already on board are platforms to navigate .
When GPS is not available , or just as importantly , to provide redundancy and hence additional integrity to the GPS themselves.
Okay , it's worth for a couple of examples of the kinds of sensing.
Okay , so one , one that we have used very successfully .
This injury , okay , consider aircraft with a camera looking at the ground with the advantage of satellite imagery .
Think of google earth , all all those pixels and image had have an associated ladder to the launch .
And if we can correlate the image that is being observed by the camera on the airplane with that satellite that will be called geo registered satellite were able to determine whether aircraft is that's part of the problem .
The other part of the promise .
Now , how do I get them to my navigation system such that I can continue and navigate with that , and that's what uh the.
Progress , that's where that you need that initial measurement unit and a sense of timing , combined with that imagery on the ground , you can then start to keep track of where you are now .
And where are you going on , software , interesting here.
But in for ground users , for example , we are being bombarded with radio frequency signals where we're sitting right now , but we're not using them from navigation , but they have special information in them , whether they be TV circumstances , radio signals , or if we were outside receiving many signals from satellites .
And so we call those signals of opportunity .
And we've shown that you can navigate very well with those signals , as well as well.
So just drilling a little bit , and one of those signals of opportunity , white things .
So how , how does that finish?
That was a very fun signal for us when lightning strikes , it essentially lights up the entire electoral magnetic spectrum from DCto daylight and beyond .
Researchers have shown that they're even extraordinary potential event gamely is coming out of a lightning strike christmas for a very short period of time , were talking one to several million seconds of duration in time .
So huge positive energy that is in the spectrum that we call the very low frequency band , the elephant , which is the oil .
The ten killer hurts region tender .
Tony killers in general , that portion of the energy can travel around the world.
It is almost like a wave guide right at between the earth and the ironic sphere , and those signals that tolerate.
That is correct in the reason that's the wave guide is because it ten killer hurts .
Your wave is now , oh columns .
Okay , ten , twelve , fifteen kilometers are depending on what exactly exact frequency is , because there is only a few wave links between the yours and the bottom of the ionosphere , which is depending on the time of the around eighty coal , and you get a wave god effect , which has very low signal technologies , so the signal can be received at very high signal strength .
And so the question of us , can we navigate with us ?
So we went outside and put a violent receiver on the street , or even in in the building , you would be picking up the tens of signals .
Prosecutor , the violent portion of a lightning strike is holiday spirit short for an atmosphere .
That's a fairly old term , but that's what we call it .
You would be receiving dozens of physics per second.
Answer the questions , can you navigate with those ?
This is amazing to think about navigating by lightning strikes .
You have to know where those lightning strikes are in.
For this tool tool correct , that is absolutely correct .
And that is , in my opinion , one of the hardest parts of a lightning navigation system to detect those , we use a network of what we called monitoring stations or references located around the world that would geology .
Those lightning strikes , yes.
Right , and we've all seen .
These are on whether reports were also shown in the lightning strikes from these.
Many of the many universities have lightning detection networks in place .
There are commercial products for getting that information as well.
No , I have applied fascinating .
So let's say the way okay to another program you are working on which was related to this one .
This one is no , mercifully , in short form .
STOIC, but directly short for the long form , a name of the program , which is a special temporal and orientation information in contested environments .
But let's go with because it sees you to say , and this two is a deliverable of a backup GPS of sorts .
And it involves a number of interesting sounding components that I hope we can talk about briefly to that .
I mentioned our very low frequency signals , which we actually did touch upon already when we were talking about lightning .
But another component here is the development of optical clocks , which rely on a quantum mechanical behaviors , and adams to keep a super accurate time and making the clocks are always a part of of these kinds of navigation systems .
We can go deeply into the weeds on these things , but let's , let's try to talk about a little bit , gives a flavor of what stocks about and what technologies you are hoping develop to make.
Okay , let's talk about the the real life component .
First , it's interesting to note that the first global positioning system was not called GPS.
It was called omega .
It operated back in the from the early seventies through the early ninth , and it was a real life broadcast system and provide a global coverage with only eight transmits located around the world .
However , it was not accurate .
That system generally provided one tourist column levels of positioning accuracy , where , as GPS is generally below five meters .
So the automatic system is clearly not accurate for what we now depend on today from GPS.
So the primary challenge we have in stroke for the violent component ears , developing new models that can accurately replicate how that we all have signal , propagate from a transmit to receive .
Can I suggest that we can get our accuracies to?
Levels and and why the video left a very low , very exciting component of the full spectrum , many , many choices of frequency band steels.
So you mentioned the wave guide effect , and we talked about the fact that the wave got a fact has significantly less signal attenuation such that the signal can be received at longer distances .
So in the context of providing aim backup system to GPS that has global range .
Clearly , we don't want to put a position begin , if you will , every few miles around the earth .
So the ability to provide a positioning system with only a few , let's say , less than ten video of transmitters is very appealing , especially when the signals can be received at very high levels of.
Right in this , thursday's pragmatic and cost issues that I believe we all have transmits often.
So they are not only are they very big , but they're also very old is , in general , they're using nineteen , fifty , ninety , sixty technology .
And so oh , using new technology , we are looking at ways of making them much smaller.
More football and more portable .
Okay , and then let's talk about the clock aspect during this case , obstacle clocks .
And before you actually talk about this specific .
So a quantum mechanical based collective technology , the europe , and here , just for those who do not talk a little bit about the role that accurate clocks play in systems like GPS , another geolocation and navigation systems.
So there is a common phrase used in the navigation community , which is time as position and position , is time that data is all the way back to the sixteen hundreds of not sooner the maritime days when we navigated , offered the SUN when you left the .
Whether we have to say , when you left the portrait london , you would such a clock at noon , and then add sailed across the atlantic ocean .
You determine how many degrees launched to you had travelled by looking at the time on your watch , on at the point at which the song was directly overhead .
In that way , you could quarrel the number of the hours off of new york said , when you like your watch , but your coroner , in this case , versus noon at the at london , where you.
From there , get your degrees .
So the more accurate you'll flag , the more competition you could be of your position and determination , and the rest accurate , more , more than all days .
It was very true.
Position position is time with GPS , the same as also choose .
So the key to GPS is indeed the clocks you're getting arranging .
So in love for the GPS satellite , can you receive determines you don't measure distance what you are actually measuring is time .
How long did it take that signal to travel from the satellite to receiver ?
So the satellite tells this signal left my eye , and tonight , at time , one , you look at a receiver clock when that singer was received at two and time to manage time , one is the time of travel , time of travel times .
The speed of light gives distance of transactions .
The key that is where the range comes from , but it all goes back to the clock.
Let's speed of light , which we know in this concept , that sort of a kid here , right , all right .
Without that , you would be able to just from a measurement.
No , with the range was that that is correct , and there are a lot of other things .
Your GPS receiver has been.
To do as well , but that primarily drilling to it is remarkably complex and sort of every level by an image or cute .
You can imagine applying to it .
So let's move now to a third program is with the last one .
I think we talk about .
This one is known as president , and that stands for positioning system for deep ocean navigation .
So sounds like you're going for an underwater.
A GPS system , yes , the bottom line , GPS does not work under water .
Actually , you can receive it very shallow depth in people have shown that , but that's not relevant to where we actually operate .
We want , we want to be able to navigate at much deeper levels .
Personnel about bringing a GPS like positioning capability.
Submerge users .
So when I think about the emerged users , I don't think about radio operation there , though I know there are some other real , interesting work in trying to bring radio with with violence and ultra low frequencies are down into into a underworld operation .
But I hope I think of immediate , believe acoustic types of signals .
So I presume that that's part of what you are correct.
Climate research community has been using low frequency acoustic signals for several decades now to monitor the temperature of the ocean as a functional time in and by using low frequency signals .
If , you know , again , the knowledge of justice , value of the time is key here , if you know , when the signal lefty transmitter and compared that to the time you received it at another location , you can get the time of flight of that signal .
Now , for underwater is so important for GPS .
The speed of lighters is , is constant .
That's not quite the case for under water , the speed of the sound of the underwater is a function of many things are primarily temperature , but also a depth and solidarity and some other terms as well .
So we have developed models that account for all that , in addition that the acoustic signals underwater don't travel in a single line between the transmitter and receiver , which radio frequencies typically occur signals , will take many pets on the way from the source to a receiver , because the signal is getting reflected due to temperature profiles uh in the ocean .
Pressure profile and things like that , when you hear in signal , low frequency signal at receiver that was admitted far away , you actually hear multiple instances of that is like an echo .
And there are four we call that multipass .
There are multiple paths that is going to take.
So it sounds like with this multi path phenomenon going on that one of the big issues here is , is gonna .
Be had you been digging by all those signals coming in , and so that sounds like algorithms , that sounds like computational issues are just to make sense of what otherwise would be just my arrests of acoustic signals.
You're correct , and that is exactly what we're focused on in the program initially is , can we improve current models , develop new models that can accurately account for all those pads that a signal take such that we can extract an accurate time of flight , and hence and accurate distance measurement .
Most we get the distance from that signal .
The navigation part is , is fairly easy , the hard part.
Is the signal measurement model , and just the GPS depends upon consultations of satellites and forgetting the number now .
But as a couple of dozen , generally exact number as regular general is around thirty year , around thirty would perceive an undersea GPS system also rely on a consolidation of acoustic biggest distributed to the oceans .
Yes , falling out thirteen for a given area also in the ocean .
Is there a phenomenon like when we talked about for a very low frequency radio signals in the silver skirt in the air through the earth and the ironic spirit , that sort of long wave guide effect acoustic sounds can travel from many distances in the ocean , right , the wheat on taking care of how wealth communicate of great businesses.
That is cracking with , and that is the exact effect we're exploding .
There is what is called a sound channel , the depth of a sound channel is in generally function of of temperature , but in general and depositions , it's about a columna deep and so low frequency acoustics will travel for very long distances .
There is a seminar study in the nineties that showed a low frequency signals could be received in the sound channel , many thousands of kilometers .
I believe it was almost nine thousand kilometers.
Absolutely standing , and it also just brings another question to mind .
I don't know much about how these weekends working with their characteristics are other issues of concern for animals living in the ocean , where these signals will be will be a propaganda.
Absolutely , a key tenant of the program is we have to develop a system that complies with all the federal regular relations , protecting memory , memory , wife.
So when I take it , one of the things that drives you is the concern that we have become utterly dependent upon GPS , just the way we are utterly dependent on electrical grade .
We all know when electrical grid goes down that we become friends , given five minutes of power out .
We are going not .
So GPS has similar problem .
rebellion .
Tell me about that aspect of how you think about technology and security.
Yeah , so there was a phrase that some people used to have fail , safe and fail operational and create your primary system fails , and is the failed to a safe models , or it fail first to , you are still operational .
And then if it fails again , you are still safe .
Okay , so you have that built and redundancy so much in the paragraph one of the power goes down the building .
Come on , if you need to continue as well as a power in that building .
The same thing is , is happening in the navigation community .
The consider tonight's vehicles , which are on the horizon .
Clearly , they can't solely depend on GPS to tell the car where it is located , because some of the things we talk about , others , such as they're in urban canyon .
The campaign of the GPS signal .
So the artist , seeing more dependent on the other sensors for providing positioning information , whether the layer lazer raid are or or imagery , for example , or even the doubled sensors you have on the vehicle security scene , redundancy , starting to be built in two systems that are going to be dependent on navigation.
In the future .
So when we think of the three programs that we've just talked about , and as so , I can decide , and I should point out that you just handed off the witch of this program to a colleague in the strategic technology offers , can you give us a sense of what the status of the victim is?
So analysts is ripping up .
Analysis is transitioning to the end users to the services are in various ways , and that's a good thing .
Storage is almost halfway through a three phase programs .
We're in faith to the store programs that we've demonstrated feasibility came up with an initial approach generated evidence to support that approach .
And in fact , we are now employment in that approach and doing higher federal data collection , but scientists just getting started .
We are in the middle of what we call.
One of the sudden , just one more question for you , and that's what question do you really wish ?
I would assume that I didn't .
And if such a question comes to mind , you can ask it.
Answer yourself , so you mention the article clerks.
Thanks for reminding me , I, Ishould push it as you like question earlier.
So enough to go clock , this is an atomic clock .
We have a thoma clocks today , such as a rebellion clock or a season being clocked both of the racism beam has been around since the fifteenth of the night.
Senior just one intermediate for a second , a simple way of thinking about these things when white atoms can be , clocks is because there are vibrations isolations associated with nuclear .
But rather than that , the kinds of association do you think about it in our accountable fashion ?
Clark , with a pendulum , I mean , some ways that was going on , but it's going on a billions and trillions , and of isolation is in what we consider duration of the second.
So in the atomic clocks of today , we are exploiting signals immediately by atoms in the microwave region .
Giga hurts level signals .
Okay , google hurts is billion times per second .
An optical clock is exploiting a time of energy level transition that have frequencies over four hundred .
Terror hurts another five waters of magnitude so that the clock at the ottawa clock takes five words of management faster than the atomic clocks of today .
And by virtue that that's more precise time , and we get much improved stability out of applicable clocks a day in general , are about the size of a small laboratory .
Universities had the optical clarks .
At least the nationalism to for standards and technology has the world most table optical clock double in the past headache program that showed by making some trades in sized , weighing power and performance , you could reduce the size that optical clock down to the size of a shoe box from a laboratory sized down to a shoe box .
Yes , but that clock is still taking adult to call frequencies .
Another doctor program , should , you could make a very small and robust device colleagues , frequency come .
That acts like a set of years and transfers that very stable obstacle took in the four hundred terror hurts region down to all of frequencies , very frequently frequency .
Okay , then you can generate a timing .
Second , that is systems of the data , one post per second , ten mega hurts , referenced on one hundred meter hurt reference systems .
So the story project is integrating those separate technologies that develop into a single unit , such that I like to say , we want to pull out the season , being clock and plugging the stock obstacle clock , and your time stability has improved by , at least in order of one hundred and eighty .
So imagine by clock that they would keep GPS level time accuracy for over a year.
With no GPS research , the best name , the thanks for giving us a favourite vote in africa .
O'clock is , I know that its complexities go up the church , but I think it gave us a sense of what you have to do .
So , thanks a lot .
And then I started to understand that in another suggestion future , you're going to be .
You've got him in twenty twelve , you'll be leaving this year .
You've got this amazing sort of skill set in mind , said , particularly with the navigation technologies .
We've been talking about a time , a clock , a lot of of abilities and skills in different areas .
Are you imagine that you're going to keep applying that particular set of interests in your post or professional life?
Absolutely , positioning and timing are built into so many systems we have today .
And it's because of the success of GPS .
Other nations are building their own satellite navigation systems as as well .
And GPS is embarrassed .
So many things , things you , you would even think about the eighteen young google cash from GPS is in there , but like trying to trading on the stock.
GPS is , then I just occurred in that case .
It's mostly the timing function like , as you need to know when those transactions have happened.
Agricultural precision agriculture GPS is under power distribution to the electrical credit .
GPS and GPS is provinces .
I want to continue to enable systems today to provide that same level of positioning in timing with , with cafe villages that are redundant to GPS providing integrity , but also going beyond the level of positioning , attempting performance we get today with GPS such that we can enable new capabilities that we can even imagine today if we .
That much more accurate timing and position.
Information it sounds like exciting frontiers out there .
I'm sure you have no problem pushing on those frontiers when this has been a fantastically interesting conversation for me .
I feel probably should spoken with you for a while .
So I wanted to thank you for.
Joining me in the studio today .
Well , thank you .
This is , this is a lot of fun.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from doubt .