Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the palm of your hand on tournament operation technology is a driver of our times since its founding and nineteen fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , durban , the defence advanced research projects agency has been a driver of technology .
Welcome to Voices from darker a window on toddler's core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is iphone a motto on your dark host today .
I am pleased to have with me in the studio .
Justin gallery , a program manager since twenty fourteen in dark is biological technology .
Justin , on the bachelor of science degree in chemistry at the university of illinois , urbana champagne and aged in chemistry from kale tech for fourteen years prior to arriving at dark , he was a professor in the chemistry department at emory university and inland georgia there , he LED a research program in synthetic biology , which is all about uncovering the rules and genetic programs by which sales behavior upgrade and to learn how to manipulate those rules and programs so that bacterial , fungal plant , animal cells can make drugs , fuels , coatings and other useful molecules .
Materials at DARPA , government continues to be driven by some of natures own most or dishes , biological feeds , such as the growth of a great soccer redwood tree from a seat .
What if it were possible to leverage biologist own evolutionary home powers of chemical growth , cellphone organization , self healing and reproduction in the context of our build landscape of buildings , road vehicles and other constructions .
That is the first question .
Just asking johnson , thanks for joining me in the studio today .
Glad to hear everyone .
Let's start by talking about your background and how you became interested in science in general and in chemistry and a synthetic biology in.
I actually started out .
It was very interesting physics .
I was inspired by a people like richard firemen , and he told these wonderful stories seem like an incredibly interesting guy , sexual , one of the things that promise a cow tag .
I thought , you know , if this character could do such a great scientist was placed that I wanted to be .
I quickly realized after about a week in college that I was not going to be a physicist whenever the less I like .
So chemistry seems like a good option .
And I always like the idea in chemistry of the ability to create things didn't exist before it is core chemistry as an analytical size .
We understand the world around us by studying browser is a synthetic site , which means creating new opportunities .
And that was something I was really wrong .
Interestingly enough , I sort of put off biology , my biological education that is formally pretty much handed in the night grade .
But it's time when , on , during a graduate school in post dog , I went from this time where the word DNA and a architect owners do not attend to appoint where I really start to respect the remarkable chemistry that biology does .
I ultimately concluded that no matter how good of chemist I was that biology do better .
So asked the question , okay , well , can we harness the power of biological systems to essentially do our beating for us ?
So how can I reprogram a system that wants to do with one thing and get to the thing that I wanted to do , and that let me into the serious antarctic biology .
So we were interested in taking advantage of some of the properties that bacteria , simple microbes could do .
They are really to make stuff .
They are really to send stuff .
And I got really interested in.
Ramming that before we talk about the two programs that you're running here dark , but I would like to hear about the sequence of events that let you from your own experience .
And emery , as a professor to develop itself .
So how do you and appear?
So it's a funny story .
I was at a meeting in cold spring harbor , new york , which is beautiful laboratory family's laboratory and long island , female for molecular biology .
and 真的是sure of DNA 。
That's , we're meeting right outside of his office .
We got to see him walk through , coming back from his tennis matches .
And I was , there was part of a short course on synthetic biology .
So the organizers had brought faculty members from around the country , around the world .
And about that time , double had announced .
The living foundry is programmed , which is one of the seminars in that biology programs .
Here are dark.
And then just tell listeners what was the cracks of that.
So the cracks of that program was engineering groups to produce new molecules and to reduce the time of the design billow test learn cycle to do that .
So instead of taking a decade in a billion dollars to generate , they wanted to reduce the time down to maybe days or weeks , and reduce the cost dramatically .
Dropped her .
Just put out a call on early hundred million dollars of investment , and I think , and he likes to say people at this meeting , who are all in this area , got really excited about it .
But we also were sort of amazed by the insults in the authority of a DARPA was asking , and I was getting really excited about this , and I got talking to the younger faculty members of these mostly sister professors that organize the meeting .
And they had mentioned that in a darker was expanding heavily in the senate biology , they were looking for program managers , and it's the program manager .
I was kind of interesting one in the sense that we're all temporary , dark .
It doesn't hire permanent staff .
This program , we have an exploration date on our badge minus thirty december twenty eighteen , like , is yourselves , emergency of it .
It certainly does .
So in order to come to this job , you essentially have to leave what you are doing before , with the expectation that this is only going to be a temp job .
So for the folks that come from academics , you more or less have to have a tenure position if you intend to go back because early in your career , you cannot do this and be an assistant professor at the same time .
It just wouldn't work out .
But since I already had ten year , a lot of my colleagues that you would be great , you know , the field , you have the ability to take a break .
Ironically , after about three years appear , uh , I leave for memory , my team said , are you coming back something I never thought I would say is said , no .
So I gave up a ten year faculty position , a lifetime appointment , something I worked incredibly hard for .
And scientists , or the end of the bill of a career .
And I gave up .
So I am currently have been observing at the pressure of the traffic leadership.
And don't know what i'm gonna do next hurry , but that also is an indication to me that you develop the certain kind of devotion and excitement about the programs that are involved with maybe more than you even expected .
So let's talk about the two programs .
The first one goes by the short name of breaks .
BRICS, which stands biological robustness and complex settings .
What is it that is now and what you hope to achieve.
The origin of that program goes back couple of years before I join the agency .
Santa biologists got good engineering bacteria to do what I would call parallel tricks , little cute things that work well in the latter example , engineering bacteria is such that when you expose them to light , they would change color so you could do photography .
You could take a patriot that she could shine light and shadows and so on , and you could take back photographs .
You'll cube kind of demonstrates the possibility for the field , but at the end of the day , you know , it's not going to put digital cameras .
So I myself have been engineering organisms to follow small molecules with the idea .
Maybe that you could chase down pollutants in the environments , you would have a bacterium that not only wanted to eat the oil , but actually could sense the oil and follow the road around if you wanted to clean up the environment .
And in doing all this , the question , I would inevitably get asked as okay when you can have transition this to the field .
And my answer , quite honest , because the systems that we are building work fine at thirty seven degrees .
Sales in a petri dish in a stereo environment with the presence of energy , alex , to keep any competition away .
So we were literally following these bacteria , and they could perform in that environment .
But if you said , okay , I want to take something that I engineered and laboratory , and I wanna put it in this contaminated site to clean up with them , it would never work because their microorganism is live everywhere .
They establish their own .
Nicholas , okay , so introducing this little weak laboratory strain of equality , it won't survive.
It wouldn't work , and just another angle was there , even at that time of regulatory framework that I would enable you to?
So from the lab out into the field , there is it like many regulator framework , sets a little bit complicated , but it does exist .
But we were so far away from that that even the national idea that we would like to do , that was almost crashes in regulation wasn't going to stop us from being successful here .
It was the science itself was going to stop the challenge , as I thought was we needed to be able to engineer organisms that for robust enough to survive , of course , have to deal with this problem of evolution .
Large population sizes .
Evolution occurs by mistakes .
Okay , when DNA could be copied and correctly and introduced his mistakes .
And it.
And we are all grateful for billions of years and worth the mistakes , are we?
Exactly the process works .
The public concern offenders who are going to create a superbug .
And my concern .
Actually , it was at the other end of the spectrum than anything we built this kind of break , just gonna , be too fragile .
So we have to be mindful of both if we want to engineer my crops that are resilient enough to do the job , but make sure that they are not innovating on the fly .
And one of the challenges there is this notion of engineering robustness into systems .
If you talk to hard core engineers , build things like airplanes , there are many ways to make sure that airplanes fly safely .
Can we have multiply reduced systems ?
We have lots of sensing control , activation and so on .
We've got at the point now where air travellers incredibly safe , and there's entire engineering disciplines that help support that .
So I will talk to these engineers who are used working in the micro physical and say , okay , how do you deal with uncertainty and say a biological system , so is an example if you're thinking about an airplane flying , you can make reasonable guesses to what environment is .
Yeah , I know the temperature range that's likely to see .
I know how highest going to fly .
I can model the stresses on the wind .
Examples you could draw box around it .
Right , nature , you are very good thing that within a certain space that this should operate as expected .
And then beyond that , all bets may be off , but we've done a pretty good job during a box around the problem , but in biology , it's a lot more complicated .
We don't always know what an environment is going to be like .
Moreover , you have this past few thing of evolution , where is in physically engineered systems when something breaks generally , the fitness fertilized biological term of the object goes down .
Okay , so let's say , part of the airplane breaks the performance of that aircraft is generally not going .
Where is in biological systems breaking is innovation .
So it is possible that the reputation and organism acquires a new function .
It grows faster , now completes its colleagues when I talk to the engineers they go , is there an alliance of the world ?
The mechanical organizers know that the airplane breaks , it doesn't start flying twice as fast and twice as high as performance goes down .
So so there was a lot of intellectual barrier there that people thinking about engineering robust systems work as of yet thinking about she .
And it brings new challenges .
And I recognize that , but i'm not an engineer .
So I had no idea how to solve this .
So when I came to dark , I had the convenient power of the purse , I could sculpt .
A program basically asked , can we transition synthetic biology from electoral curiosity into the real world ?
So one of the great technological advancements of the last decades , so is the dramatic reduction in cost of DNA sequencing .
So we can study the DNA that's out in the world .
And there is a lot of , and by doing that , we started to recognize that there is this incredible diversity of microbes that grow honors and enough .
It turns out that if you are account up , the number of sales in your body that are yours , that have your DNA , and then compare that to the number sales of bacteria that live on your skin in your gut , those numbers , there's still a little debate about it , but there are approximately comparable and okay , so you are being driven by your bacteria .
They help you digest your food .
For instance , they affect us in profound ways .
We're just beginning to discover the and.
But you should eliminate the straight .
So you essentially telling me that I am have bacteria.
More or less , more or less .
So this opens up the tunnel is impossible .
They're by manipulating those bacteria .
We can develop their are politics , for example .
So the trade diseases of god .
Interesting , there's a typically hospital derived infection called ACDF.
Commonwealth cluster .
Divorce is essentially what happens in hospital settings is that when people take a strong , so in a biotics essentially clears the bacteria out of your gut .
Now see if lives in this very specific locations within your guards , that kind of hangs out in between some cells , and normally it's held and checked by everything else that's.
In your guy , right ?
And just because some with owners probably approve the term we are talking about to hear about the , the microbiome right here , the microscope of the god , when you are talking about the bacteria over all of us , and that's the entire microbial amount of body .
I see you talking about the microbiology .
Yes , so specifically.
And I got .
So what happens is that after and about a trip that got clears out , see if says , oh , my god , this is great .
You know , it's like it's expanding into a vacuum , and it makes people very , very sick that can be deadly .
The observation was made that perhaps by repopulating , the god with a normal gut bacteria , you might be able to knock down the city of infection .
So where do you get those bacteria repopulate ?
Well , the pilot terms these days are intentional microbiota transplant。
But you are talking about vehicle material .
However , correct that i've been appeared , and the place you prove this is a transport.
So in it works , if you eliminate a microbial community , you can replace it with a different community and restore function .
Now it's great work .
Some , it's something like ninety five percent successful .
But as I felt just the egg factor , if you had to design a solution to this problem is that the best you could come up with that , you would take somebody's pope and stick on him .
So if we started asking this question , could you build more to find communities from scratch , that might have the same function , but wouldn't carry all the extra packages .
So in that pope , there is a lot of other potential viruses and other bacteria that maybe you don't want to reintroduce into the cut .
So we , we , you've got very interesting this idea of building microbial communities that can perform a specific function , but have much more composition.
This would cause be a tremendous service in a public health sense , because so many people , the astronaut testimony issues that seems to be related to the microbiome .
So you can come up with ways that are more political and to.
To treat that , there would be religion , but it is also a department of defence specific problem as well .
So when soldiers deploy the place , reckon afghanistan , they're exposed to know my crops , whether something in the water and so on .
Traveler's diary , many of your other way of suffer from it .
It's not fun .
And not only can it ruin a vacation , but if you think about from a deep respective , if you're taking young , healthy people , you're deploying them in theater with the expectation that they're going to do in job , right , and then the sick , that's no good .
So one way that you could think about , maybe solving this problem would be to find a way of engineering robust community .
The god that more closely matches where they're going , and maybe your transition , that community state said , so maybe you get a tony , but you can be treated .
You're fine .
And then you deploy our season .
Don't have to worry about being not out of the game.
Right , as you arrive , if you were to characterize the status , the program breaks .
Now , how would you describe?
It's going well actually , very pleased .
So when we started that program , we realize that the science behind the microbiome is changing incredibly rapidly when launch the program , we didn't say specifically that we were going to solve this microbial engineering problem , because I felt that those problems were quite as well defined as we wanted .
So what we did was , what are the tools and technologies that we will have to develop that allow us to engineer microbial communities or microbiology that can function in complex environments , because we thought that there were gonna be some commonality .
So a microbial community in your god has to deal with changing environment .
Right , one day I drank a diet coke , and I had a breeder for lunch .
Then I ate a salad .
So there is all sorts of different stuff falling through there .
So what we said was , if you have the ability to engineer microbial community to perform a define function in some suitably complex environment , we figured we would learn enough lessons that we could then take that to maybe a different function in a different complex environment .
So certainly some primitives , commonalities in terms of the problems that you would have to solve to engineer community , that's going to function , whether I ultimately want to reach near a got microbiome or skip microbiome , or soil microbial .
There are probably some common allies to the solutions there .
You can have any research groups developing on this one , right it overall , the program is probably about a dozen , and they've come up with some truly creative solutions to some of the challenges that we give them is the beginning of the program .
But we want you to engineer community that has an impact on an organism in a rational , predictable , safe , robust way .
It wouldn't specify what the test case had to be , whether the performers who focus on came with ideas to find their own space .
We , we define how complex could be or needed to be .
But we didn't say engineer to get microbial of eggs , so we got some really creative solutions , including some that we're unexpected .
So some of the ones that I say were a little bit more online with what we kind of thought would come in .
Was we have a group at the vincent statuted harvard LED by pam solar in her group now have engineered a microbes that concerns information , and it changes color when it senses information takes a diagnostic soap , it can result in the god of they're using animals .
So using a mouse , it can resign the god of mouse for something like a hundred days without mutating .
So this is one of the things that we are worried about .
I thought this was going to be that the systems were gonna muted .
Waitress that they don't .
Actually , I am so as a pleasant surprise , they show that you can detect information in the bowl .
Scott , basically by looking at the pool .
So if there's information that might spot blue , so you can imagine , ultimately , using this is a diagnostic , one of the other more surprising test cases that agree with the university of texas LED by nancy .
Marian came up with was the microbiome of the honeybee .
Got , so we were definitely not expecting this , but it turns out that the honeybees are really interesting test case .
So unlike you and I , who have a lot of different microbes and architects , the honey bee has , depending on they , somewhere around eight or nine different species of bacteria .
So much simplified web satisfied .
So it was not one , but is not a thought .
So we thought that this was a really useful test case , because it's complicated , irreducibly complex .
And what also is it to think about the honeybee is the honey bee is a social animal .
It displays learning in memories .
You can train honey bees to do tasks and so on .
So what the text team was interested in doing was manipulating the gut microbial of the honey bee to see if we could alter their learning memory .
And it turns out that this actually works .
It turns out that there is something that known as the good brain access .
So there is an incredible number of nervously backwards from your brain and send up onto the god .
If you think about it , you have the god brain axis and inside the gut , you have all these microbes living , and they're doing something .
And it turns out that there's essentially , you got brain microbic .
So the microbes in your gut can actually tackle your brain .
We are the molecules they produce how to interact with the cells in the gut.
So for absolutely amazing .
So the potentially opening up the door of engineering my own god microbial , and a way that might make me a okay .
So you know , we were , you know , that would be very cool .
So you are there yet , but you know , so you went by up to you only told us about two , and the user is about a dozen other groups .
We cannot get into all of them .
In fact , I wanna move on now to the , to the second program , which is fairly new .
And this one goes by the acronym , and that stands for engineered living materials , and I know , and earlier discussion , none of the kind of metaphors that came up as we were talking about this result of a really beautiful one of when you think of where our thoughts come from , and then you think of the seeds that are the beginnings of all of those trees that collectively become the incredible landscape .
So , but you are thinking about that sort of biological brilliance and landscape in another way .
So talk was about what is and what the settings , what is.
Great parts of these jobs that we get a pretty high level of view of the technology landscape .
And I got to a meeting called by a fabricate .
And I admit a group of a company , and you are called economic .
And what economy was doing at the time .
What is actually going to call their business is they were taking fundamental particulars of mushrooms , and in particular , the mycelia , which of the parts of mushrooms are grown underground .
And if you ever walked out on your one one morning , and so yeah , you see mushrooms like where they heard of those comfort , right ?
They grow really fast .
Okay , I want economic was doing was they were taking this organism and mixing it the cheapest agricultural waste they could find .
So we're talking in corn stocks that are ground up .
Apparently there is a market for agriculture who , what they would do is they take the the waste .
They would take the michelle year .
They were put it in a mode , a physical mode , and after a few days , the mystery would grow to feel the voice , and they were getting material that essentially has many of the properties of policy styrenes of style , phone pack material .
And they can sell this as a packing.
The material of the fungal system , those are more fibrous kinds of parts of enough mushrooming bodies are right now , right thinking about.
Mushrooms , but in in here , it just kind of ends up looking almost like a film .
Okay , so and I thought this was so cool because palestinian is pulling a pilot styling of cups , as we speak is one of the most useful yet prisoner's substances on earth , and that it is so inexpensive to make it is cheaper to make virgin palestinians to recycle it .
And it turns out to go away .
Where is these mushroom based materials ?
If you throw on a composition , the golden way .
And so I was really intrigued by this idea of growing material from a perspective , I was particularly interested in this idea of growing materials on a specific site .
And one of the things that the egyptian folks had shown me was that they could take .
There are mushroom materials that are not particularly dense , but if you put them under heat and pressure , you can get a material that's more or less equivalent to fiber board .
I thought this is cool .
You can essentially grow these materials .
Now , if you think about the department of defense , we operate all over the world .
If you think about a rebuilding effort in afghanistan , and let's say , you need to get a pilot point there .
And the delhi has the world's best logistics system out there , but shipping heavy pilots of private across the world in the dangerous ones to me seems it's necessary , but silly , right .
It costs a lot of costs .
Fuel is dangerous .
Why couldn't you see it or effectively a seed like star and then grow the materials that you want on sight , so you reduce the logistic burden , you reduce the cost , you increase safety because you're not trying to truck inherently low value materials across the industry .
And then if you take this step further and say , well , what are some other remote places we might want to eventually produce materials if we ever decide to live on mars , there's no home people out .
We're not going to get there by just shipping everything we need .
We're going to have to be able to grow in for structure .
So the own program really gets at this early stage of growing materials .
Oh , and by the way , we want the materials to remain alive .
So in packing materials , obviously , you may not want that to remain alive , but living systems have great properties right , they can sell for pair .
They can certainly respond the environment .
So could you imagine having a structure that upon damaging soil repairs in south marginal way that you do if you get a cut , that would be great .
Could you have that that new changes are properties with respect to the , the environment , so temperature , they may change the color , so they'll become reflective or absorptive .
If you were in general properties .
So there's something about maintaining the living properties of materials that I think it's really.
Compelling , like this absolutely makes the successful reminding me .
This comes , I guess , I guess that of a tradition of something easy because of smart materials , smart material , an idea there I remember being , you can you build AAbuilding that might have a reactive process , it , depending on what humidity , what the media logic conditions are insulted in some ways of the building itself , just by changing its microstructure can accommodate .
And so maybe you use less energy to heat and less energy for AC.
The thing is amazing about this dose is i'm imagining living inside of a that is living .
I love the thought of it , but I also , you all suggest me , the village with it makes me feel like I might be living inside of a body , and I like some money to want you to think about that for second , and I wanted , what should we be concerned about ?
I keep food and refrigerator too long .
It goes bad .
And so could my house go bad and respect?
Yes , these are some of the things that we've asked our performers to be thinking about .
So if you have a system that grows , how do you control that growth ?
And there's obviously a natural president for this right human beings go to roughly define shapes and sizes and so on .
So , so nature has solved this problem of controlled growth and development .
We have AAsecond track of the own program that is getting it just this question .
So can we program biological systems in the to adopt specific sizes and shape?
So can I just have to say so , this is one of the most more regular things to me about biology , about a seat , about a fertilized egg , because it comes fairly simple shape .
And i'm looking at you , justin , and you have an interesting shape of human beings with all kinds of shoes .
You know how to take that .
I went in the best of ways .
So what a dog descriptions idea too , actually , now try to build that more full genetic function of biology into.
Engineering materials , right ?
So you mention the seats , even building with once a live material forever .
Right , we use would .
And how do we get that , what we take this single piece , very , very small seat with digital in the ground .
We grow it for twenty years .
We get this beautiful living tree that you provide .
Shade can be on help here it .
So all these great properties can see you too out of the atmosphere and produce oxygen that we need to breathe .
And then what we do , we cut the dancing , and then we put in the killing .
We rendered an earth .
We saw it up in the dimensional number .
So could you think about starting with essentially a tree progenitor cell and grow dimensional number ?
So the sales would keep dividing a specific developmental pattern , and they would know they would be programmed to go to specific sizes and shapes .
So producing the national number without go to grow a trip.
So jessica , that was absolutely amazing discussion of taking me on a conceptual journey that is just pleasing me now .
And I just want to thank you for engaging in this conversation.
It's been my pleasure .
I wouldn't spend a lot of.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join us again for the next Voices from double for more information about justin galab and his breaks and own programs and the other break through technology is dark .