Stuff technology , the internet , GPS in the column of your hand are tonight with technologies , a driver of our times since its founding a one thousand nine hundred and fifty eight , in the midst of the cold war , DARPA , the defence advanced research projects agency , has been a driver .
Welcome to Voices from DARPA a window onto dark as core of program managers , their job to redefine what is possible .
My name is , I have an motto , one of your doctor host .
And today I am pleased to have with me in the studio with the paul thomas , known since his day one as rusty , because he arrived in the world with since september twenty seventeen , rusty has been a program manager in the agency's tactical technology officers , which has a pension for pursuing all delicious vehicular technologies for the air , space and oceanic domains .
Already , russia has made his mission a doctor to do what he to develop new concept that will deliver more resilience , global reach and network to connectivity , by way of new space systems .
Rusty , join starbucks from decorate DAQRI, an organized this company , even though it doesn't like a cocktail where he served as the executive vice president for global operations .
He also held positions in a slew of commercial space companies , among them spaces and verbal sciences has been in on the design management of an amazing portfolio of space related programs , including the space x dragon spacecraft , the dark of micro satellite technology experiment , or my text , the original law earth or but satellite constellation and the US, air force jail sydney's space situational awareness program .
His initial training for all claim in the form of a master science degree in our space engineering from the university of texas , austin , and a bachelor of scientific degree in iran , astronaut engineering from , after I say , well , let me say to you .
Paul , rusty thomas , welcome to the Voices from the opportunity of thanks .
I was great to bear today .
Thank you for helping me before we get started on your life adventure , on the forefront of space technology .
I want nursing on something that will not come through in your voice or words .
At six feet , eight inches tall , you are among the toilets .
People at dark , though we are markedly not even the toilets .
It does make me wonder though , how you managed to fit into those seen shows when you were on the producer crew team .
And if your fuel costs , when you find your own paper to code , a plane are higher than it would be if a five foot ANGguy like me were the balance.
Well , yeah , so it does cause me a lot of pain on their planes these days .
That is , that is true .
But ottawa being taught was greater group in the game , and I learned to play basketball for some reasons , kind of good at it because of that .
So baby is a good thing of raw , and i'll take it.
All right , well , one of the things I always want to hear from program managers who are with me in the studio , where they got their start .
And they're whether interest came from in science , engineering and technologies .
I would put that question to you.
Okay yeah , great , I will love my own space engineering .
She said , and like a lot of our space engineers , grown up in the seventies , nearly eighties , really saw what NASA was doing my great school ahead .
That has special readers who are equal and see the history of what NASA don't even back in sixties .
And I remember the point of those in great detail when I was a kid .
But the real kick for me became a career day that my schools have been made great , where they actually pulled my father , and I realized my dad , mechanical engineer and his grandfather , his , my grandfather , his father , a civil engineer , had been doing some pretty interesting things are entire career , and they were staying on the cutting edge of of what was going on my desk network for general electric in the plastic industry when that was getting bigger than sixties and seventies , and my grandfather had worked for northwest and put in all year fields .
And when they are doing it , pacific growth through the , through the four weeks in fifties , he also helped design the regarding at the airports , so had two generations of of insurance behind me in a career day .
I actually have my dad was one of the people presenting , and he wanted to the different types of engineering , and at the bottom of a list was error space .
I did not know that was an option and always on click for that .
The aerospace engineering is something I could do , and I could focus on it and continue on and do our lives on my dad doing in terms of , in terms of really innovative idea .
If things are in new concepts that could be suffering .
So with that , I was installed for for indiana and produced a great school .
So I jumped at the opportunity to accept that there .
So while I prove we had quite a few amazing professors , I wanted them .
Professor and sunny give us talks about how you could do no better new career as an engineer , especially if you stay on the coordination and advanced technology advanced what humanity can do .
Look back my head .
Those words are wrong with me .
Feel at twenty , keep moving to .
Where is the most of this technology ?
How can I help the most?
Well , those sound like two great lines of influence .
I mean , you know , we died in a teacher like that .
And where have you went with so one of the things that I would like you to hear is to take on our listeners on a kind of worldwide tories , you can really do well too much on any one thing you done .
I mean , you're CVis just one of the most amazing documents i've .
But if you can take us for a worldwide tour on your experience in the commercial space.
Commercial space absolutely so I didn't internship at a small engineering services company , and we've got to work on NASA with with a special technology .
It is .
But what really got me going to commercial side was right after graduate school , I got the opportunity to go tomorrow was firing up the radium lowest orbit .
Constellation proliferated , lowest orbit satellites that were crossed , linked and providing global connectivity .
And her plan .
And this was a large , constantly , very large , sixty six adults of plus papers .
So the goal was to build one satellite per week and launched the entire consultation of of young seventy excellence , including the spare in one year .
Never been done before .
And to do that , we're going to use a large number of , and motorola and never designed to spacecraft before .
So they put all that together and and background .
Eighty nineties was happening .
The of the motorola had really good plan .
They pulled in a lot of experts .
They pulled in some contractors .
Lucky and written on who were experts in this area .
They put together the team , and we ended up building at a rate of one spacecraft every four point three days .
We launched from three containers on this , and in eight days , fourteen satellites , we wash off all the satellite and but it.
And exactly before you move on to some more of your commercial space experience , I remember just talking with you at another time when I am proposed to use on this project , you really in project which took around the world to some of the other space cultures out there , like in china and an in russia .
So i'm just wondering if you can compare and contrast a little bit of the kind of space cultures , and that , you know that that you have experience being part of the hours here , and then witnessing those elsewhere.
Absolutely what the first analysis , when you get in the other country , any other location is doing a rocket tree or space represent you really grow up across it as type of engineering that you can really do really well if the people that do that are , there are very someone who matter what culture they come from .
I was very amazed how quickly you make friends .
The russians are the chinese , anybody who was who are actually launched as we will launch in on the protons rocket seven at a time on the patriot , and we launched two of the time on the chinese rockets at five times on delhi , that which is the main launcher advantage , I would rotate between the lunch bases in california , bike nor kazakhstan , where the rock was launched , also go to mask of integration meetings over two of our beijing for the chinese english meetings in taiwan for lunch based there .
We was very interesting program , and really , I found it , the russians and chinese , while russians invented rockery , as we know , just the same time we did , china was coming up to curb .
They're getting faster as an incredible rate .
They're getting better at an incredible rate .
And I found both russia in china .
Their cultures were less analytical in the american aerospace culture .
They were very much driven by test , build , test , build , test cycles .
And I found it really in the commercial space here in us .
We'll serve pretty wonderful videos type of things when you move out of the analytics .
Don't spend year to trying to figure out exactly how to optimize .
It may be a sub optimal tested in the news that resort.
faith and so we see analytics , I think of of, 妈的，我应该牛仔裤加厚的。
Is that so one thing we really wanna , really , really , really good at in the USis very good computers and a very good computer algorithms that that let us analytically be predict what a rocket would do under structural load or under guidance , navigation control hours , which is great .
But it doesn't really tell you everything that could possibly happen during the flight .
Where is the flight actually does tell you that?
Before we move off of this little a black weird describing , you need this international framework for getting so many satellites up in such a short time share with every listeners kind of funny experience that you had with the russian team when they were trying to figure out what.
They should actually call you as a great joy .
Thank you .
So , so when I started working at motorola , we would have every other month .
We would have a technology changes .
We need to see the russian launch team or the chinese launch team .
So you have one when the russians would come to tunnel when we've got a mascot , we would have the stereotypical long tables with all the russian , someone's side , all of us on your side in the trains when they asked , and we introduced everybody , they got to me .
And I said , when I was rescued , thomas , they stopped the meeting .
Robert briefly , and they started talking to translators , and they came back .
And is that your real name , and I said , well , pulls my real name .
I was born paul thomas anniversary grandfathers , but since the second , third day and around russia's benignant name , and they went back and talk about this .
It , okay , we get paul , paul , that is a good name .
We're gonna .
Call you paul .
And and as it was fine , some people who can call you power , but most people are more over .
No musician , and they came back and saying that , well , we're going to call it palm , and the reasons we've discussed it , and and we don't have a nickname rusty here .
And in russia , we don't feel comfortable calling .
So , so they decided not to come in corruption .
And I was paul from there .
I had been a poll on.
Since since , like , okay , because of that , it was smooth working team yesterday .
So now I want to take you back to that will win the tour of marshall space .
Like , what is you to do ?
But I took him on a diversion .
So let's get back to that .
You , you talk to live it about the model experience now moved from the world.
Great , then I then I moved up to see out of following words , the most important technology , seattle , in late nineties , was , was really happening place for a lot of reasons .
They are also a new company that was found that cottage has the money convenient from field bill gates of criminal call for tightens in the communication and computer industries .
And they wanted to build a global lower football .
Saturday , said , like constellation , to do broad bank communication , we got pretty fun that design , but the technology , the time was , was , wasn't quite their military session , as we know today really wasn't there .
And the dotcom crash of two thousand two made it really hard for a secret of financing .
So he ended up not going forward that program , even though we had got no CClicense for a lot of spectrum .
And I had really good chance to be AAman major success .
And it was at the space of a very compelling architecture and moved from there and did engineering services in santiago had a really good time of some of the early days of UAVis prejudging .
Global hawk got to be consulted down there for the early UAVdesign , and then moved to orbital sciences , where I got into the government side .
And then after it keeping the commercials are going after the orbital sciences occur , I went to space six hours in two thousand and eleven and worked as a senior director for driving , building the capsules go to the space station .
So i've spent five years there and had distant , amazing , amazing run , putting on those .
Those capsules up also got to work on the lining legs and the and see and and play a good party of christopher claimed in those of.
First data , right , and just weeks really before this discussion are having now , a dragon capital did arrive at the international space station for a resupply mission .
So when you see that the media had , you feel now when the two.
Parliament intense pride , absolutely , that that was at a turning point in how we do it , how we do space missions , how NASA contracts for for things , how NASA moves forward , the technology gets the cutting edge , develops it and then can move that technology .
Two companies like the space exists of the world , who can then use that to build a commercial case and then allow enough to move on to the next place .
When I was at space x , we went from doing one rocket year , one dragon every year , two to four , five , six dragons per year .
And now the spacecraft was rapped up to twenty thirty plus launches in the given year .
It's really been an incredible time to that approached how you do commercial space turn on and become reality and then become a success , and then become really a major success.
Where is that right now ?
Okay , so you serve told the we are already here .
If you kind of growing up professionally , along with the commercial space sector , which is just kind of amazing thing to think about you then made a decision to say yes , when , when the officer came through to become a program , yeah , I like to hear that the secrets of events that let you in this stage of your career from that the united commercial activities you been in .
And now here , as a first year PM absolute program manager and.
By chance I happened to in the early two thousand and be talking to some friends at robert sciences .
And they said , there was a very interesting program was found that called my tax .
I did no .
Materiality was a dark program .
It was classified what the experiment's war battles was will never know that existing the time it was used to dark .
The experimental program to do a demo of the technology and orbital was looking for people who had my type of background , a little bit of commercial , but also had the right tickets so they could do , do the work .
And and they brought me out for three months then , and I would just gonna help do some analysis for that spacecraft .
I did some analysts , and after three months , look like dark was going to continue the program overall wanted to keep expanding .
So they asked me if I stay on as a manager for the , for the design that so I got to run the design of the of the michael spacecraft .
And so I stayed in an overall , for now three months , I ended up to everybody years .
And during that time frame , we work through the middle spacecraft .
I got to do the design and build .
We actually took the integration , launched it .
And I went out to shiver for space as a vehicle engineer and got to be on council on flight for about year .
And f , so it was a really good experience .
I, Iwasn't commercial commercially , but it wasn't government .
Taking commercial approach is all about .
It was a very commercial company .
And and this was an experimental process that wasn't a strict requirements remain program .
It was there to prove some key technology that we could use in space .
It was was successful , and I , as very proud of the of the results there , that kind of got me into what dark can do , dark can step into an area where , where there might not be a set need , or a set said requirements are a set funding line and say this is technology .
It would really help .
The wolf fire helped the country and in significant ways , and and say , rogan , rogen do a democratic proof that this is possible , that the proof is here , if we can actually spend two or three years and some money , the actually good demonstration of a running that opened my eyes to what you could really do outside the commercial world , but still using commercial approach as much as possible , so followed on foreign and became a deputy pyongyang met on the GSAprogramme mentioned earlier .
Geostationary special awareness program is air force programming record .
Now that is doing very well .
It's up in jail , and it is acknowledged that it is very , very , very good capability , and it is doing in a lot of good from the people using .
So the GSAprogram are very successful .
And after it got to the critical scientific review , I happened to have the opportunity to to go to a space , except they were just found out we talked about that it was .
It was a wonderful five years at the end of that .
I was at degree during the operation job of setting up the owner , reality global operations , manufacturing for the what's going to become AArevolution .
I'm a positive argument .
Reality can be a very , very big.
And just a two sentenced description for listeners , you might not know what you mean by augmented.
The home in the reality is the ability put on glasses that will organize the information in real information with , with computer generated three d graphics that that actually will float in space .
You can put text , you can put graphics , you can put anything you want .
And it was is going to be contextual .
Natural objects in space was not virtual reality where locks you out , and you don't see anything and algorithm , you actually still see the people in the room .
We still see all the objects.
But it's adding information , and I have seen , I think , a motorcyclist phrase for this software defined holographic , like control that related to what you talking about.
The advanced versions of argument rarely and degree had some of the most advanced holographic , like control technology.
Okay , so now my suspicion is confirm that you actually are are going to develop this district enterprise at some point .
And how that example is that it gets , yes , so getting back to how you actually got the two drop.
That final turn to get me back as program manager became when he concept of the blackjack consultation , which I did not come up with .
It was already been formulated by expertise .
And i'll talk a little bit more about that right after this great , so dark , contacted me and said , we're going to go forward with a proliferated , lower , thorough architecture to start to change how we do space missions right now .
We do space mission varieties with very capable satellite , exactly caused a lot of money , so therefore we can't build very many of them .
And the lawyers are preferred to approach that already indeed , but with the communications and in the nineties , and television was trying to do .
And other companies have taken weight forward is a different approach to put smaller , lower costs and and sometimes expandable , but not expendable , slow reliability .
But the key element , small and lower costs satellites that are in very lower orbits so that you can cover the entire earth with coverage , and likely satellite was a six year semi .
Satellites will usually do it to give yourself constant coverage over the and and double .
Let me know if they were going to move forward with an experiment to try to move into organizing what these eggs with satellite can do with a lower storm proliferated constellation when that opportunity came in , I came in , gave a talk .
It was a match made november day because it sounds like this ten thousand people in the world that seems to have made this kind of idea .
I really do think in terms of match , in terms of what the job wants to do with the and in what these type of consolations can do in the future .
And in my background is , it's a really good match on .
I'm very excited to be in this position .
This is time is perfect.
Let's talk about black jack in a little bit more detail , tell me a little bit about , you know , the kind of the elements of that .
And even before we started , can you tell listeners and me where the name comes from?
Sure , the concept of of a black jacket that instead of having sensors in space that might come out of wonder to with this points of the sky , you could potentially put smaller sensors in many locations .
Give the destroyers or the surface action group commanders of the world or the army commanders or air force .
Anybody they build it look over the rising with a small number of description source that they actually doubt the sky in some ways , while we go to a casino , and you look up , you see on the ceiling , you see all the little domes , those little dorms roll , tiny little sensors , and then making sure that nothing bad is going on , right .
So the concept of black jack is to follow that distributed sensor approaches to see an excellent .
You don't have one or two large systems making sure that everything is working okay and making sure that there are no cheating going on in the , in the excel.
And just just for the record for our listeners , we do need to point out the dark .
It does not get all of its ideas from us.
Biggest , we don't look at all , but probably more than we should .
It maybe , yes , absolutely .
So the name came from the summer playing blackjack would have the distributed sensor said , so it is kind of a tongue and cheap name , but , but it was a good name and a good idea .
crossings .
We give our talks and what we're doing .
So black jackets , this yesterday said a lower storage consultation of some , sir said , we're going to leverage and key elementaries leveraging the commercial space as they talk my grandpa in the past is , you can do things very quickly .
You can do things very efficiently with a commercial approach .
Now , let's not to say the government approach , however , it occurred things .
The best is always bad , but in some cases , you don't get the optimal solution , and you could do things in a lower cost and a faster schedule if you tackle in a different way .
So what the ideal black jack is a try different approach .
You use lower orbit , use proliferated commercial satellites , especially the buses where we will marry military payloads to those commercial buses and then start flying a large number of them .
So you can give that proliferated global custody consultation , and I say , consequently , that means for a commander wants to look at a given spot on earth .
He can point the sensor to that spot immediately , because it could be a satellite operation.
Okay , and you use the words that , in a way had been here before proliferated is one of my transition .
What that means?
In this framework , proliferating means multiple points of in the space and spread out over the surface of the other sector of the space , of course .
So any person on the , on the ground is going to be able to look up , see a black with the council confliction developed in the sky any given time , and that's the end of the reciprocal approach works that if the black jack satellite is always going to be also any point of the earth.
At any given time , right so century since there is there some aspects so sort of of GPS like system , and that you got many satellites working in a kind of coordinated fashion , delivering amazing kinds of inner data that would not be possible .
Otherwise , he reacts to talking about a lot more than the several dozen rider GPS talk just a little bit more .
The various kinds of challenges that are part of this project , one of them certainly is , is producing almost mass , producing very rapidly .
A lot of satellites .
And so you had to talk about your experience there , but there's also going to be coordination .
There's going to be command and control .
What are some of these other elements that you.
Talk is about absolutely so first , while yesterday's analogy , the GPS is honest person .
That is a preliminary conclusion , but it's about at a medium or medium , high altitude with black jack won't go very low , five hundred kilometers to twelve hundred columns , so arranged that that's just about the earth's atmosphere for these outlet .
And and the trick is going to be building such a low enough .
You can need more satellites and what a GPS satellite would GPS consolation would need .
So to do that , you're going to need mass production and to do that , you have the cost right ?
You going to need to build them , and on very short time skills with a minimal amount of a simply immigration and test and do that , we're going to bring it as much commercial approaches .
We , we've had an injury day , a very positive response from from over one hundred and thirty companies signed up for the industry day .
And we had overturned seventy five folks who want to comment and let them just .
So we believe that that approach of going with discreet , low cost notes in space that are almost expendable , not expensive , but almost is going to be achievable , and we're going to that that commercial and commodities approached the buses and bring that to impose match to the , the , the military pilots that will go on those buses .
Also , the other key element of this .
And I knew a little bit of that second ago is that we don't , if we're gonna , launch hundreds or or more thousands of of the satellite , we don't want to require teams of multiple people per satellite monitoring .
And right now the exit have excellent teams of people on the ground who are making sure everything that that satellite does is monitored .
They're gonna inevitably predict beforehand what the response of any new script .
It's an excellent approach , but we really want to get a tournament into the black jack architecture .
And when I say economy , I mean , how does the mission control work ?
How does resource planning work ?
How does the payload in terms of what it seem work in terms of , can you move instead of raw data down to the people on the ground ?
Can you recognize the information and could actually , it was important.
Okay , when the other interesting thinks about the blackjack program to me is because you're not putting in a multiple billion dollar jewels up their large juice , expensive assets that need to stay up there for years .
Nearly here , you can do what I guess , much more frequent technology refresh , as presumes somewhat I can be done through software .
Now you can just wait or with upgrade .
Reading are various applications on our computers , but this also does give you some opportunity to , you know , without breaking the bank putting up actually , new generations of these small satellites and still having the work within the black jack consolation.
Yeah , yeah .
And and they're too early there that are very important and organized both of those on black jack first is , if your individual lawyers orbit your large costs is lower than going at higher rabbits , you're waited less , and the cost of individual satellite is less .
So we're aiming for an orbit six million dollars per note per black jet note that includes a launch cost , which means that if you have a problem with one of those satellites , you can launch another one replaced flood huge amount of money .
And in the second piece , is there the the ability to do on our own orbit over the air of days of the software working about large , I call a pit boss once again going with a black jack approach .
Tried the pit boss is the brains on each one of the of a black jack notes .
It's going to have a terrific class processor on it or more , and it's going to allow us to put a lot of algorithms on space and normally put a lot of allegations and space to do the work up there with the authentic computers .
But it's also gonna run a launch , more process , repeat building than we need the first generation , because we expect to get better .
That was our algorithms and algorithms typically need more processor .
So if you can , we talk about our work to basics , my , my boss , there also found another company called tesla , and one of the really girl called models of tesler .
It is , you have a car , and you might come out and in the morning , and I started over there update , and you have a better car the next day , and you did the priority , because if i've had a lot of work , so i'm going to follow that type of approach , putting a lot of extra capacity for the processor , so that as the algorithms get better , you get a better spacecraft essentially for free .
Although , of course , you have to pay for algorithm update , but in terms of launching , you said that , you know.
and I imagine you also have to think about end of service when you talking about so many discrete parts that are in lower therapy means , sounds like to me the desk and deal with some 沐浴露。
那都是。
Have you given that thought , absolutely , given that thought , and that goes back over the motorola radium consolation every year , rhythmic has the ability to deal with itself .
But the end of his life , it has a small amount of fuel reserves left that those few reserves are used for anything else other than the orbit , and has enough redundancy and electronics on board , so that it starts to have problems with it can still far the thrusters and bring itself down , so that approach has improved , successful with with the original in the commercial consultations .
We're going to follow the same approach of object , and I believe there are numerous FCCviolence for mega consultations of communication .
Satellite is not the other that have launched even more satellites and black jack , they're going to be good of lawyers , or , but also , and put in the ability .
So as a satellite ends its operation , like organic , replace with a better technique for satellite , it will immediately turn on infrastructure and do usually over the south .
This africa summarized relatively bunny , the small cell lights don't make a pack down .
They burn up in the high and the spirit during the story .
I haven't nobody else , and there may be many of 这没得说。
So as you think about it , this is amazing to think about this is all the pieces , and you can have additions of a program .
It is either one or two things about it that stands out in your mind , as maybe , particularly a rich , even working on the dark program in technology .
Speaking , yes , we are.
Absolutely , so that the biggest rich , I believe , is the amount of atomic we'd like to put on this spacecraft .
I've given a metric that if we lose the ground control , as if we have a comes problem , or the some type of influence and satellites are arranged talking to the ground .
I want them to be able to operate this for twenty four hours as a consumer talking to each other through their systems and and and managing the resources .
Managing the mission is still providing whatever in the fact or our set of information , the worldwide that the people downrange without that ground infrastructure , so that could be interesting when I learned that I say the matter is one day , but really , my stretch goal is to get thirty days universal operations without talking to the consultation , while it still performs its primary mission to whoever needs to have that information that is generating .
So putting that in the place is also significantly for from the current operations .
We have an operations controls in our ground , making sure the satellite health and safety and the mission is being managed properly to one , or you don't even have a human being in the loop .
You moved the man pregnant for men , men in the loop to men on the loop , poor that the people do in the management are there to make sure and adjusted priorities as necessary course , but not there to make a second by second minute , by many decisions .
I have the spacecraft operating , and what they do that is really hard , but.
So a fireman for tonight be always with human beings .
They're as shepherds and in the loop , and somewhere absolutely so you're a first year program manager .
Typically , program managers are here for just to three to five .
I have people here in the study of whoever is done .
Several tories of duty as well .
So people like it enough to say they come here .
They do want to reduce the go away .
They come back .
I'm just wondering if , as the first time program and energy with a program of this complexity and science , what you think this one program is going to be enough for you to satisfy your , your technology interest , and just because it's going to be so hard to do .
Or are you already imagining are taken on additional programmes?
I'm actually early , imagine taken on .
It does not bargain that goes back to my theme of how to get to the most cutting that gentleman of whatever you do in a career , but like text of a major program , because it could be AAhuge success , and it's gonna really lead a pilot to lower the orbit .
But once you start working in a lower orbit regime and once a duty and dark , start working and putting these systems in place , I can introduce many other programs that will leverage this type of architecture and and a successful command object once we build this global message network , this , this message is space , a space open at .
How can you use it to actually benefit the people on the ground ?
And I think.
A lot of programmer and I just , I just want to point out to listeners that , even though restless , is talking about a program like that , it is , it does not mean that it is automatically going to become what he's gonna have to really jump through a lot of hopes , and it is a lot of people that something worth doing .
So this really is essentially glimmer on the eye .
Mayor may not come to become AAso that's one immediate .
Sounds like you.
I didn't have more idea .
Yeah , I, I, I, I, Ihave been spun up with a world above in the reality on what you can do is like control hollywood graphic , like controls in area of high interest to me .
I believe that we are approaching that point where the holidays are allowed , not reconduct things that appearing , but the ability for systems to a transmit holographic light phase , control the light and project in a way that you are emerged in a reality that that isn't real , but it's seen the real , because your eye is getting fed the same information .
It would be if the object was actually there .
I believe that type of light control just drawn the corner , and there is a good chances going to revolutionary how we do interaction with computers and interaction with even people in the same way that the transistor revolutionized how we do computers .
And I think that's are coming the next five , twenty years , and I really hope you get dark.
Movement and as you released in the potential applications of that training , just.
And to my , my meaning is a huge , but not destroying .
But the if , if you are deployed a , if you have multiple person to ploy , and you can have a holographic surgery .
So how , how to fix somebody in your deployed , or in a very mode , you can actually train somebody in real time and how to do something , because I can see it in three day , right in front of them .
Has it happening while the reducing american procedure , training for welfare , training for other industrial applications becomes , becomes much more advance .
Or thus , they very done me .
Study showing you can train somebody anywhere from two to ten times faster with algorithm is all in his olympic light approaches .
If you , because your brain is , is , is programmed to absorb information from three day context , much faster than you are with someone talking to you or reading in a book .
So you said , you see it .
You have a robot factor .
So I think training is going to be an area that could be revolutionized.
Another thing just came to mind , what is economic sort of discovery .
So you might have a space you want to figure out the best way to arrange things in that space with this kind of technology .
Build a text out of those different ways , very efficiently , cheaply.
One of my early early crew moves was that the internship will work out , work on on as a project .
And we will would well be three day cat at a time when two d cat was the standard computer redesign , and that three dimensional cat and allowed you to mark up engineering parts , and and then do photographic , virtual photographic , make sure the parts would learn through with each other .
And that was a huge boom for it really designed with a mechanical design .
I believe the same thing will happen .
Owners are doing this with the interactive , collaborative tools allow everybody who want to see what's happening in three days without even.
Computer screen are selling for them , and then there is one other kind of technology project that you work , which also just represents to me , just how many thousands of thousands of technology engineering issues there are when you really thinking big .
So you also were in on the design of the crane operation for meeting satellites , going to connect vehicle dispenser components right after just one of the many , many.
So this was an interesting invention .
We worked as two or three of us at motorola , where the we had it was that motorola was pitching the ship and shoot approach a spacecraft you finished on the production line .
It went into a shipping container , said on a dog until where the russian protesters under the landmark rush , chinese landmarks , or the , or the , the mechanism that was said of two folks needed another set of satellites , and that those launched campaigns were going .
The russians lead seven .
And that was the case .
We would call photographs and photographs showed up at the sky harbor airport .
We will load two or three side .
They would fly in the russia .
We looked up , and then we get them out to the large base , and we wanna put them on a rocket within a day or two .
And and that's always do not help .
I entered this done right now , and it was the salad we were looking for very fast , like our times , very quick process flow and do that .
We needed to make seventy salaries are very close to each other , actually and quickly .
So we put together a crane , so I think we call the swing and tourist eliminator , which mounted to the floor of the russian integration hall in bike north .
And we , every satellite would be brought in vertical state attached to this .
And then it is the russian , korean , normally with swimming is around a little bit as a model , because you didn't have a neighborhood of salad transaction , but on the disposal , like wages , there are all very close to each other .
She had to control the twist in the swing .
We are at the point .
We can make three of the satellites per day and have all the entire dispenser of seven satellites ready to go after three or four days of processing , and then they would be filled and be.
Okay , so on top of everything else , you are right , right ?
So you know , you're working on things .
And many boss would work , consider to be kind of science fiction , technology fiction , though you can make these things really are there non's space technologies that you just go about?
Down's space will almost daily error space without the space , or as good error .
And I do believe that the transport of human beings of planets is going to get to the point organ a bit more at the hypersonic scale , and in the not to distant futures , not in the area of research for myself , but i'm exceptionally interested .
I guess , curious on how we're going to get some new technology that seems becoming online right to the commercial space and how we might start moving people from , from , from , say , new york to sydney and an hours instead of the two of the fourteen plus hours , take right .
I think the very high speed transport , which I guess that it doesn't hit your mark , because you will probably have to go in space a little bit during part of that flight , but I still see some very high speed flight , supersonic , high supersonic speed flight has been a narrow of of interest of of significant potential , and the next ten to fifteen years .
And I think there's the museum teams that are cracking dragon that would be.
And so sort of , ironically , thinking bigger than this way to make the world a little smaller in the sense of english , for many points at any point , be in a much shorter time than as right.
Black jack will give you the message .
Networking communicated red broad band and connection with the people.
That's going to be the next step up .
So rusty .
You are technology developer .
You been doing that your whole life .
But you also have taken time to get into the mall of the mine said in the setting of the war fighter , the wonderfully the war fighters who are not trying to serve more capability .
Can you just share a little bit with listeners about your experience?
Complex , absolutely so i've been a reserved for united states navy since two thousand four , and as an intelligence officer , I was lucky enough to be selected to go to naval special offer and and actually went out during the search to synchronized desert areas with the whistle teams that help do targeting and how value how are you talking ?
We did the pregnant job .
We got to go to move , move through are those areas and picked up , but quite a few of the alcohol may love , love , produce and and then put them away .
So for I feel , I feel , I feel like if I draw it down in a little greek on every , every month , very , very important part of my life , although it as a reserve is secondary.
But I also imagine that that boots on the ground experience now , as a program manager , completes the kind of liu prove that not all program managers can add .
I think it does help.
The area that it helps the most tennis when you're downrange with a special force , special operators , the amount of band with the amount of sensing you can get the distant amount of communication you can do is very limited .
You're typically moving that if you are so destroyed .
And what i'm trying to do , the program manager here is to give those type of point .
Sailor , soldiers , marines , whatever they are , the ability to move data at a much higher brand , with indicated data from sensors at all with the rise and not necessarily organic or unit immediately within seconds back to where they were without help , go through a grounded for structure .
So seeing how it is operated when I have been , downrange is really helped shape homes , set up the technology to for the future of a dark .
We can help you international nation.
What's the recipe you've taken me and listeners on an amazing tour of in the summer , who has been the absolutely the last couple of decades , which is involved in space technology .
so I wanna thank you for 会员。
It's really been a pleasure .
Well , thank you .
It's been a bit of a great career .
I'm happy to be a darker and looking forward to the next doorstep to break down .
And where we're going to be going to get next year.
And thanks listeners for sharing this time with us , I hope you join this again for the next Voices from the urban , for more information about called rusty thomas , the programs he and his colleagues in the technical technology office runs and the other breakthrough technologies dark , is working on visit , dark that no.