WNYC Studios
Leadership support for more perfect
Is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Hey I'm Jared I'm rod and today
Not an entire more perfect story just something that you need to know right now
Supreme Court's about to hear a case that apparently could turn the country's legislative map
Upside down
More perfect sean rameswaram
Kentucky from here
Hello Jad
Hello America
So what's up with some contacts Republicans controlled a lot of legislators in 2010
And there was also a sense of
Does that year
Which meant that a whole lot of Republicans
Got to redraw a whole lot of legislative Maps
And a lot of those Mavs benefited
Republican
Democrats do this to
But today's case Gill V Whitford
Is about a Republican
A map in Wisconsin where for example in 2012
Democrats got 53% of the vote
But only 39% of the
Republican made that happen
Buy packing Democrats
Into Super Democratic districts
Weather Boats were essentially wasted
And also by
Kraken Democrats
Into mostly Republican districts
Weather boats
We're essentially wasted
In a move that could have a huge bearing on the future of American politics this
Supreme Court on Monday agreed to take off Annex
Explosive cake
Whether lawmakers in Wisconsin's republican-led legislature went too far in 2011 when they read through the snow
State electoral map to make it harder for Democrats to win legislative races
I will make the Supreme Court case all the bigger a big deal right now
Is
The timer
This is the first time in more than a decade
But it's going to take up the question of drawing lines
Partisan game
And this is Justin Levitt he teaches bought at Loyola in Los Angeles
It's going to do that right on the eve of
Everybody redrawing lines everywhere
Local District State District's congressional districts
After the census in 2020 all sorts of different bodies will redraw all sorts of different lines and this case
Will help decide
How and where
And if the court can crack this nut it'll be solving one of the biggest
Baddest
And oldest abuses of power
In our democracy
It goes back to before there was an America
So there were problems with rotten boroughs in England
I wish were Century districts with no people in them
The nevertheless elected representatives
In this country in America
The allegations going these fees are also contested all the way back
The allegations are that Patrick Henry tried to gerrymander James Mattis
Out of
The very first Congress
Hemp seeds in Virginia
Because he was so upset with
The Constitution
The word itself
Comes from in 1812 attempt
Change the lines in Massachusetts
It is named after a governor mess
Elbridge Gerry
I meant if you go to
Northeastern Massachusetts they will tell you passionately that is called the gerrymandering out of Jerry Mannix
That's something that people actually argue about it over Massachusetts
To the allegations were that did Elbridge Gerry created a district that snake
Around the northern cape and suburbs essentially
I it was ridiculed in a political cartoon of time is looking more like a salamander than a district
And the portmanteau is born
I gerrymander
And since that moment we've been living with this unfortunate word
And it's unfortunate problem
And it turns out it's a really hard problem to solve
Leavitt says you can't just
Hit reset
Draw some rectangles and call it a day
That's not the way people live
Nobody is ever bought a house because it fit the last perfect spot on the last perfect square grid and last perfect develop
In a square City in a square County in a square state
The way we live is sloppy and messy
And organic
See that I find an interesting cuz one of the one of the conversation people have about districts a lot of times it's like
Look at this District
The truth is like if you look at it like
Voting rights.
He'll do that to try and keep
Exactly since together
Right
Totally I think the best example to look at here is
Illinois's 4th Congressional
It looks like this weird jaw the skeletal job trying to eat like
Lake Michigan
People actually called the ear
Ida chemist because
Horizontal so
If you put it that way we look like you're much too big trunk
Connected by basically this
Straightener
Looks really tacky it's running up a highway
But
This was drawn by democrats
So United
Similar
But geographically you know
Apart
Latino District right
How to create a cohesive
Block
And it's actually if you look at it that way
It's a very
Good
Helpful
This is it gives a community voice
Right so in the end the question is
How do you
Distinguish between what's giving a community of voice
And what's
Straight up
Scandalous
Cheating
It all starts with designing districts around real communities that have something in common with each other
It turns out that's really hard to
Do
When your legislator
Focused intently on the next election
And that's my time and time again
Gerrymandering has ended up in front of the Supreme Court's of the United States
The nine justices in DC have to do what
Congress doesn't really care to
The Constitution does not require the
Cigar
This is Justice Stevens back in 2004
Partisan gerrymandering
English
Enables representatives to choose
Undemocratic
Constitution
Malpractice
The case was beef vs Jubilee as the last time the Supreme Court
Dealt with partisan gerrymandering
And just as Kennedy in the first
The Jubilee year
Basically said
You legal community of America need to solve this for us
Or we are in big trouble
Weekly Standard
Now we have in our own Jersey
Geographical
Compactness
But I just don't think we have
Numbers
One person one vote
But beyond that
And the Justice of the deathly looked at Sea trying to fix this invite versus juvelier
These are people who love rules they love test
So they came up with a whole bunch and no one could agree on any of them
They're looking at the big Statewide picture versus the local little
Sure they were
Using racial standards from the Voting Rights Act and not it was like a hot mess
Of socialist
And Kennedy could see this
And what he said is
Sitting in the middle
As he often is
The most powerful man in the country by many stretches
The courts
Should be in this business
Yes
But I haven't heard a standard that lets us decide how much is
Is too much yet
So give me some
It was as public a plea to
Lawyers
To bring cases to help him work through the appropriate test
As I think anybody's ever
I'm sort of like this
Public
Challenge
Who out there can solve this
And and now
May finally have a solution
Allow me to introduce the efficiency Gap
The efficiency Gap efficiency Gap is essentially this
Relatively simple math equation for measuring Parts in jail
The idea is if the justices want to know was its districts fairly drawn
Or are some legislators up to no good
All we have to do is grab a calculator plug in a few numbers and Ben
They get there
To political scientist came up with it
And then a bunch of mathematicians weighed in on it
And one of them was Professor Moon duchin
You can call me moon or Professor teaching she works for Tufts University in Boston
I do geometry topology
Group Theory and Dynamics so little bit of everything across the mask
Just as a heads up with all is dust
Acknowledge the existence of a maths
Moon co-authored a paper titled a formula goes to court which is essentially What's Happening Here
Supreme Court's going to consider
Weather this efficiency Gap formula passes muster
Is this equation a
Reasonable standard
From measuring partisan German
The efficiency Gap formula does that in a couple of different ways most importantly by measuring what
Called wasted vote
And wheezing votes by definition
They are
The number of votes that you got
Minus 50%
If you want
In other words there's a voice that you wasted while winning
So if Republicans got 60% in a district
Wastage would be tempered
Okay okay so if I got 10 volts but only in five I wasted
But
Or
They're all the votes if you lost
So in that same district the Democrats got 40%
And so that was 40% wasted because I didn't go towards electing a Democrat
Okay so wasted for the losing side is basically
All of the votes
In a race where you lost
Yeah that's a waste
And then the efficiency Gap
Is quite simply
You take
All the ways to vote for a
Across the entire state
All the wasted votes for b u takes a difference
As a proportion of the total turnout
Efficiency
Subtraction
It's party a wasted votes - party B's wasted votes
Divided
By the total number of people who voted
That gives you a number that measures
Gerrymandering
It's is addition and subtraction
With a smattering of division it is so not scary
So Republican wasted vote - Democrat wasted votes
/ the
Total number of
Of overall volume
That's that's the that's what we're trying to measure
Here yeah
Why would that work as a measuring of gerrymandering
So
Take a look a purple State like Wisconsin where you know you have Democrats winning and you have Republicans winning and they're both wasting
Boats
They're both winning elections losing elections and
And every one of those races
They're wasting both because I wasted vote as anything over 50
If you want 80%
And
Anything you lost if you lost right so wasted Just Happening across the board
But theoretically it's happening on both side so all the wasted should
Do canceling out in Wisconsin have this picture where
Democrats won 53% of the vote
But only one 39% of the sea
It's a Democrat for wasting a lot more the Republic
Tons more
And that might mean
That they're sort of this
Pattern
Of wasted votes
Across the entire state
The entire map might have been drawn
To favor one side
Is that like if you plug in the numbers in the equation you if you got a big number that means lots of ways to get a little number that means
0 is that is that essentially it or is it
Something like that
Really yeah
That's cool
It literally is like
Is it like that
There's actually a way that we don't need that
Moon's got even easier way
To understand this
A shortcut
I can tell you what it is
Do you want notice right now
No effort
This is my perfect I'm Jared I'm right here with Shaun Robbins firm we're talking about the ancient problem of gerrymandering
A solution may be about to fly into the
The Supreme Court on the gleaming wings
Matt
You mentioned that there was a there's a short
Truck yeah you know if you don't like the math that we were doing a little deficient scab
Professor duchin gave me this
Disorder handiwork around
That'll probably make it a lot easier to understand the whole wasted vote
It just involves comparing how many votes you got in the race
How many seats you got in that same race
All you have to do
Is Teak
Your vote margin
And double it
Efficiency Gap tells you that should be your seat March
So you got 53% of the votes
So that's a margin of 3% over. Why
Doublet
You should get 56% of the sea
If you get
Try this with me now
You get 60% of votes
So how many seats should you get
Okay so
I got 60% of
I need 50% to win
Size of track that off I got
10% left
And doubled
That's 20%
And then I add back the original 50%
I won
And that's
70% of the seats
You got it
The one I just went to 60% why do I double it
So that's an excellent question
And what's
Because of a kind of complicated answer to that
Interesting
This a well if you look at elections
Don't believe the margin is what actually tends to happen
Okay so these guys Professor duchin mean Stephanopoulos and McGee
The dude who came up with the efficiency Gap
What they say is when you look at elections across the country and compare how many votes the winning party gets to have
How many seats the winning party gets
The winners tend to get some extra seats
This idea is called the seat bonus
The idea that if you win by a little you should get a cushion
In your governing majority
So it's like what are systems kind of funky let's let's roll with it and here we baked the funk into the into the formula we baked in
In the funk I love it that should be the subtitle
His genius of Brandon
Grateful they're taking something descriptive this is what actually happened
Turning around do something normative which says this is what should
So well let's look at
Waupaca Wisconsin
The courts of the gerrymandering quotes
Did in fact prevent Wisconsin Democrat
From being able to
Translate their vote into seat as affect
Is Wisconsin Republican
So Wisconsin in
Dems get
57% of the vote
So
What percent of seats should they get
This is according to the Matthew just did you can do it
Okay 57 650
I got 7 * 2 is 14
+ the original 50
WhatsApp
84% of the seats you got it exactly God
I have this
Instead in 2008 they get 52%
Cancel that suggests that
View through lines of efficiency Gap things are stacked against them by quite a bit
Right in Seoul
That's how this works it becomes
Only a way to compare
You vote margin to see margin
Not moons feeling about all this deficiency Gap the shortcut
It's a good start
But it's just
The start
You know I really respect the effort to take
Something so complicated and boiled down into a single number but
It fundamentally can't beat
Done that simply because
People are way more complicated than just
What number we are
We are geography we our history our race were so many things
You're going to need a few different
Metrics at once
The fear is that that's what the courts been allergic to is
You have several different metrics how do you combine them and how do you decide when enough is enough
By Good Fortune we're now finally in a position with been a long time that partisan gerrymandering
Rendering keeps peeing
But you can keep seeing take down the road by the court
Good news is
They may have some postponed and delayed just long enough
But now we have some really good alternative
Most promising things this coming down the pike is
The use of computers
Dreamed of this for decades but computing power just hasn't been
Nearly ready
To contend
With the big data of
The three District
Problem
That's because
We're doing some
Phenomenally complicated, notorious we've got
This, that's what matters
Accounting
Supreme Court isn't quite at combinatorics but if Justice Kennedy likes the efficiency Gap
The Court's decision could dramatically change the way
State Street
And if the court can Embrace this standard moons hoping it will go for others down the road
Ones that more fully consider all the kinds of connections
That make up a community
They're just
Phenomenally many ways to break down
Millions of people
Into
Doesn't exist
If you just enumerate all the possibilities
So that's the biggest day that you're going to find
Bigger than medical problems bigger than
Astronomical
Asking a computer to really understand all the possibilities has been Out Of Reach
But what's happened recently is both
Computing power and the algorithms used to study this have been getting better and better
Forecastle understood how to constrain that search space more
What we're moving towards is a Time
I won't be able to cut down the space of possibilities that you have to search
And at the same time computers will be getting more powerful until those meet in the middle
In computers can really see all about
So what numbers are
You're too big for mathematicians to even wrap their heads around when you can
Computers oh no other way around
Applications are very comfortable
Infinity is the computers that have had to catch up
Computer need to catch up
How do we expect 9th Supreme Court Justice
What happens when computers can really explore
The space of possibilities
Is it they can build
A bell curve of the properties of all the different Maps
Soap computers are going to do it for us
Create Maps app on maps
Zapata maps that
Together will give us an idea of what a disc
Scripture look like
And then you look at Wisconsin's actual plans legislature enacted
You'll see where it falls on the bell curve
Is it in the nice meaty part in the middle
Or is it an outlier that's
Just out along the tail of bell curve
Pretty
Persuasive enough
Kind of outlier analysis
It should be pretty comfortable for court because they do this all the time for other kinds of
Legal standards
What is
Perfect this
Look like
What is something that is just
Anyone
Regardless
Political ideology could look at it and say
Oh yeah.
Yahoo questions
It's fun to do the Rorschach blot
Version of detecting gerrymandering
One of the things that my group is working on is like
A swipe left swipe right
Promoting District Uganda C District
Little bit of information and decide if you think it was hot or not that's hilarious that's great you have that can I play
Coming up coming up for congressional district
Is that were calling a gerrymander
Great so I mean that's always going to be fun but
Just that Contour isn't always showing you what's really going on
It's not just the outline is also where the people are and how they're split
Wright cuts of the district and not just its boundary
That's got a lot of information about its legitimacy
We're trying to throw a lot of
20th and 21st century math
At the district render does a graph for a network
I think that's going to produce some new insight
Before that happens does the Supreme Court have to say in this Kilby Whitford case
Hey partisan gerrymandering is is wicked unconstitutional
Wilkes the court has already told us
That partisan gerrymandering is is just a symbol that they can they can throw out plans of partisan gerrymandering
They just don't know how yet
Right and so
This case
Came up
With efficiency Gap as its centerpiece
In the future
Cases may come up with a outlier analysis
As their centerpieces 30 there going to be more than one
A bite at the sample
I regard efficiency Gap as a great
Stop
Towards convincing courts not to be scared
Adjudicating partisan gerrymandering
It's a really good opening Salvo
Great well
Thank you so much for all your time I can't wait to download gerrymander
And meet my next
Favorite sister
Great great talking to you
John Rumsfeld
Supreme Court audio in the show is from Oye a free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Leadership support for more perfect
Provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
I'm Chad Ivan rod
More perfect will be back next week