WNYC Studios
This is more perfect time Chad have him ride as you probably know if you've listened to any of the previous episodes of the Season that we have Des
Decided
To make an album
Call 27 the most perfect album we reached out to a bunch of
Musicians
Create songs in
Inspired by the amendments to the US Constitution
Which there are 27
And on the podcast
And by the way if you wanna hear all the music
You can go to the Moon
Album. Org all the songs are there
On the podcast
We are
Creating little
Liner notes
For the songs leak little
Small tape
Houses Amendment
Came to be
What they mean to us now
We're marching right along we are getting close to the end
Today we have
2 amendments
Allergan start with
25th Amendment
If you've been paying attention to the news recently you know that the 25th Amendment
Has been having a moment
Officials have considered attempts to remove him from office
Fifth amendment number
To vote out President Trump to remove him is totally irrelevant to what's going on
This is the Amendment that deals with
How do you remove a
Sitting president from office
Who may not be fit to serve
Section 4 whenever the vice president and the majority of either the principal officers of the executive
Or of such other body as Congress May by law provide
Transmit
To the president pro tempore of the
Send it
And the Speaker of the House of Representatives there written declaration
Can the president
Is unable to do
Discharge the powers
It goes on
I bet I mean it really says if you don't
Pick the president up to
Snuff here's how you
Here's how you get them
It's very contentious and very hotly debated thing
We're not going to talk about the current Administration
We can actually go back
To a Time
Way before the 20th
5th Amendment when the whole question of
Succession
Far less
And we're going to tell the story of
Another Administration
Hello
Hi William
Yes High
How are you
I'm doing great
It is an amazing story
And it came out of a conversation that producer Tracy hunt
Had with
A writer and author William hazelgrove
Okay William so
Used Wilson
Why do we start with
Who are you what's your name what's your job
You know my name is William hazelgrove
Written 15 bucks
Manifest
Like number 12
How did you become interested in this since you know I've been working and you know fiction and then other kind of town
Actually I was reading Scott Burns biography on Wilson and had a really interesting line where he said we'll see
She was almost the president
Almost a president
Wilson by the way is Woodrow Wilson
20th president United States 1913 to 1921
Is she being referred to here
Is his wife Edith
And I thought
Almost a president
So I started a little research and what I found out was that
He was totally incapacitated
From a stroke in 1990
And that she has second wife only 42 years old
Took over and
Absolutely was the first woman president
So why don't we start with just like some kind of biographic
You know how did they meet okay okay
Okay so what do I
Skinny depressed is first wife
He switches his
Kidney disease a lot of women died of at that time
This is 1915 by the way and his first wife is only 54 when she died
And I actually want to resign the presidency
And Doctor Grayson who was his personal physician said me and let's go for a drive
He just wanted to get him out of the White House
To driving along
And
Edith Wilson is rather is Galt is walking along the road
They drive
Woodrow Wilson turned around and said
Who's that beautiful woman
See who is Edith Galt
Well she was born in Wytheville Virginia
1872 El Prado was a judge and after the Civil War they lost all their land
Beavis one-off
To the two different girl skulls both were bad experiences so she only had three years of schooling
But her whole thing was she wanted to get out of with the again I understand that I've been to Wytheville
She eventually married a man named Norman Fell to the jeweler in Washington DC
And then Norman died and she inherited his Jewelry Company
Was not doing well at all and everybody said we'll sell it sell it
Glimmer Edith is a very different person she keeps the jewelry company
And makes it profitable
Biosource off the first electric car and the District of Columbia get the first driver's license for a woman
And basically becomes a woman about town and if she's doing very well
And then of course on a fateful day Woodrow Wilson Drive past
Who's that beautiful woman
Now his buddy he was with him that day that's a Grayson he actually knew eat if they had friends in common and so he's like
She like wow I can get this present out of this funk
I'm going to
Arrange this dinner
Dr. Grayson actually got Woodrow Wilson's cousin to invite Edith over 40 at the White House
And so that's how they they met the very first time as if so this arranged in her butt
The motivation was for Grayson was
This is the first time that Wilson that's sorta perked up after his wife died
So
Two beautiful one according to Woodrow Wilson what does she look like when she was young
Pictures of Jojo
She has agreed
Junoesque
Figure out which is in a cheese sauce
Voluptuous
And Wilson by the way was a very sensual man we don't get this from history but he was
Houston to sex
And
G58 you know she has a very pleasant sort of round face
But here's the thing
Edith Wilson was very
Quick on the draw
She would had a photographic memory
And
Wilson love that he loved women who had
And we're able to banter with him
His wife birthwise Ellen could not do that
That she was
Very cultured barrier fine an artist in her own right
But you going to have this sort of Snappy repartee that
He has had and Wilson love
What years was not as taking first of all either
Was not looking to marry a sitting president
I said a very good life
She had her own money
If you could travel the world
She's an independent woman every time she had her own company
And so you know the
The marionette
President
Did not really appeal to her but how did he win her over I guess
Otwell Woodrow Wilson then started
To do what he always does
He started to write
Lots and lots
Lots of love letters
Did you bring a copy of one of these love letters me see if I can pull it up here
The off
Phone
I had it and now
I hear you guys ready
Don't actually like what is this like when they're still dating or are they married
Actually I this is
The Lusitania was just sunk
Quick note here that was a penia was an ocean liner that was attacked by a German U-Boat back in 1915
Massive massive loss of life
Something like a thousand people died more than a hundred of them Americans and
This is actually one of the things that helps bring the us into World War 1
President Woodrow Wilson
The proclamation
Any help as The Story Goes
Right after the Lusitania was sunk
People rush into Woodrow Wilson's office
Tell him they got to go mr. president the Lusitania was just on
What are we know well things are coming let me know and it goes back into a study
And you write a love letter
So this is what he wrote
Redis
Lusitania song
My darling my darling
If ever again I have to be with you for an hour and a half with only two stolen glasses to express my all but
Irresistible desire to take you in my arms
Smother you with kisses
I'm sure she'll crack an artery
Are you go
He lays it on thick I think yeah purple prose is the word here
Auburn water park
Now how did they date
Here's how they did something interesting
Get a big Pierce Arrow
And it would take this car way out into the country
And pull the curtain your head like that
Agent Starling one Secret Service guy
Any basically make out in the back of the car
While they're taking me through to absolutely absolutely
I didn't think it did it go out and stop
Field they recite poetry
They were modern couple in that they would have fun
So few months after they start dating Woodrow really wants to marry Edith
And this is a problem for some of the people in his Circle he's advisors Colonel house
Is one main advisor did not want this to happen he thought of
Terrible for the 19th
16 election
Because
As it turns out
Woodrow Wilson actually had an affair when he was married to his first
He had an affair
Was another woman named Mary pack
And he wrote Mary pack
A bunch of Love Letters as he does everybody
Okay so no one is going to marry this
Is advisor Colonel house who doesn't want this marriage to happen start to Rumours at these letters going to be
Published
And so Wilson freaks out
And sent a letter to eat
Basically saying
I had an affair
I'm sure you don't want to be with me
And delivered by doctor Grace
Anto
Even sits there
Cheap she thinks about it all night long by the morning
You know what the past is the past
Writing back a letter she doesn't hear from for 3 days
And then Grayson appears that our door and says You must come with me to the White House
They go to Lighthouse go up to the bedroom
Wilson is in bed
And she's like 10 you get my letter and he saw the knot
I 3 months later he goes I have a confession
She says what's that
I had your letter but I never opened
I couldn't bear to open
So they opened it together
But think about that a sitting president has gone to bed because his girlfriend is about to Gilton
So
You know this guy
Skinny guy. He's he's a mess
So what's up fast
Forward a bit
When did
When did he start getting
Sick so 1919
Alright well one is ended
At this point
You didn't Woodrow have been married about four years comes home with the League of Nations to try and get it
President Wilson's League of Nations
The First Assembly of the League of Nations was held in the League of Nations as part of the peace deal that ended World War 1
And it was Woodrow Wilson idea actor
Out of this war that killed an estimated 20 million people you wanted to create an organization that would keep the world
Going to war again but
It didn't look like Congress is going to support it and retirement Lodge Republicans are like no
And that's because of article acts provision that would have committed American troops to help a member Nation
Under attack
We are not going to commit to sending troops around the world
Enter Wilson says you know what I'm going to
Take it to the
At this point
Because on a Whistle Stop
Car 10000 miles
22 days
Whistle Stop tour is a berry
Cupping for a healthy person
Fresh Outlast you're giving all these speeches it's brutal
And welcome isn't well
Wilson had history of stroke
Migraines
Depression go outside of Pueblo Colorado
Wilson has a stroke and he called the EU
Ethan says can you come here he can't move his right arm his head is pounding me from these
Excruciating high blood pressure so they quickly decide to stop
The Whistle Stop tour
Head back to Washington
Washington Wilson seems to get better
He goes to bed and then in the middle of the night uses up she hears this thump in the bathroom
Goes in
And finds Woodrow Wilson
Laying on the floor with his head bloody
Out
Grayson Thompson
Says the immortal words my God the presents paralyzed so what happened to him was he had a thrombosis a blood clot
And his brain
Stroke
The paradise entire left side of them
He couldn't talk
Speak
He ebase was very close to death
At this point
So
Then what happens is they bringing only specialist and they all come and examine
And then they decide
Only chance
Did they hide them away
Can you get the rest
Which is basically
What year was for anything they couldn't solve
Heart ailments
Anything girl
Until
They all turned to eat
They said
Any stress will kill it
Kill him
You got to take
Takeover will help
You have to
To take over
And keep all the problem from him
And that's the moment earlier an inauguration
What about vice-president Marsh
No
You can do this
I'm we need you
To do this and from then on
Edith Wells
Depressant
So that's
That seems bananas to me that nobody is like
Should the president resign
Should he like it isn't it that's just not even like really
Mucc does ask about the vice president but like
Why is why is it automatically like he should stay president in
You know technically
While she runs a company why do you think everybody in this kind of Rush
That that was
The perfect solution
Well because of this
The League of Nations
Was Wilson's baby
This is what your stake in his whole press
The belief was
It if Wilson lost the president
Republicans knew you was sick
It would kill him to lose
The League of Nations
And
And they sought
You know what he could recover
So they can
Conspiracy
Includes
Edith
Wilson secretary Justice multi-doctor Darko
A neurologist
Wilson
And Wilson's good friend and Crystal physician doctor Grayson
Right but he starts putting out releases saying
The president is suffering from nervous
He's in his bag
Until they started to paint
This
Idea
The presidency
Yes he's
Lll
But his mind is
Clear and he's running the country
Write an end where is our vice president now this didn't he want to become president
Vice president
So
Marshall bikes going on
Speaking towards you like getting money at what he's really not interested in being president
So when this happen
Didn't even tell him
Exact date and time for two weeks later finally finally some people
Prodim
And say you should go up and demand to see the
So it goes to the White House
Edith Wilson meet him at the door and
I'm here to see the president
Anita says
Will let you know if we need you
That was a
He said okay turned around and left
Yes I can you just like
He was not in some kind of House of Cards way you know conspiring to like take over the phone
The opposite of Frank underwear he did not want
The presidency at all
So it is Wilson is running the White House
Okay so let's start with
What happens when she assumes
The presidency
Do you set up a desk outside the presidential bedroom
And she wouldn't eat cabinet members and everybody else there
And as people approached with papers to be sign appointments to be approved
And Welfare and get his take on a if he could talk
Otherwise she would just write on there the president can't deal with this
In day-to-day running Wilson cannot participate so Edith
What a lot of times
Cover the appointments of people in the cabinet
How she would take
Young people who had to be ambassador
In fact she would get laundry list
Of thing she had to do
You know this sort of a running checklist
Edison bulbs
State
Foreign policy
Cabinet appointments at Railroad Strike that she had to handle there was this big wheat sale to Russia
And of course
The League of Nations
Solar power is a river with flow up
The door and then eastwood-directed white Sochi governed by
She governed by deciding what was imported
Now question is who's signing bills and everything else
Well
Uber
His personal valet said that he has would take his hand that would be Woodrose hand and move it on document
To emulate his
His signature
At a point she just artscience
Edith Wilson
Had very childlike
I can write
Wilson
Had this very ornate
Princeton
Signature
And so what started coming back to people was his sort of childlike scroll with you
Little circle
Exactly
And he says people started to get suspicious
And so what about like Congress and and everything that is on call for any hearings or investigations or anything like
White people in Congress new
In fact the guy named Turner Falls
Stood up
Senate chamber in and said
President Wilson is not running the White House
We have a president resign
Mrs. Wilson is running the White House
People knew this but
They didn't have a Smoking Gun and also every time
This would come out
Dr. Grayson wood counter
What's another press release saying things like
Wilson's doing great
Your President Wilson is so fat I wish I was as fit as President Wilson any but he did point out that
A lot of reporters were actually pretty close to the truth
The New York Times and other newspapers would occasionally come out and say
We think Wilson had a stroke
We sink
Is muffin is running the White House
And so it is with
We have to get them out
And so what she did what she had a special ramp built in the back of the White House
Had the big Pierce-Arrow portable she looks like an atom
And they put Wilson they forgot a Coney Island wheelchair modified it put Wilson
Push them back there
Then they lifted and put a suit on and put his hat on him lift him into the car put his right side out that
You know was I paralyzed
And then they drove around washing
With Wilson saying up as a sort of macabro you're waiting
Action figure
But people and even New York Times reported
That they saw the president's the present was out for a drive
She was manipulating
The image and the price
In-N-Out it was very good at that
Wonder
Is the president or a cuz I mean sometimes you let you know like I understand you know she's she's she's governing by access
Any issue really the president or is he just more like a
The staff is she more like a president is not
A reactive
Proactive
Position and Wilson could not be proactive
Anything
The real Smoking Gun and all this
It's in the papers wardrobe
Up to 1990
Everything was
Dear mr. president
After 19:9
Everything became dear mrs.
Wilson
Remember all things were carried on by quora
Facts
Email obviously
So these letter show that the power shifted from him
To her
Greaser Tracy hunt
From Radiolab with outline of the 25th Amendment
William hazelgrove book is called Madam president.
Presidency of Edith Wilson
Play my Talisman that story and then life
Seems like maybe we should
To have a play
Land for all that
Present has a stroke and there's no plan
For what to do
Will turns out it would take
48 more years
For us to figure this out
JFK's assassination in 92
63 push
Congress
To really make things a fish
Show land on February 10th 90
25th Amendment ratified
Basically setting in stone
The official
Succession plan
And a fraud purposes for the album
The most perfect album
Devendra Banhart
Wrote a song for us where he Bass
Basically lays it out
In song
I love it
1600 Washington DC
Even though I'm at the bottom of the list
Allura and never wanted
Saloon
Please pay attention
That's been in place since
1700 Steel
Today
When the president
Completely rearranged
And even worse than an endocrine moral compass in a developing code of ethics
Ensalada what house they win the next game the vice president
How much drywall after seeing Lincoln's ghost Oso Berry in the Sun
Down the hall
Who presented newspaper
Facebook
Glendale
And so the president
Gluten
Shota
But soon discovered said no Riku left the White House
Secretary of the Treasury
Did Swifty Colin Quinn
10 minutes
This'll be the Secretary of Defense
It was a miracle that they survived after ingesting gentian weed with a Havasu by
Calendar of the month of June
Attorney General
Inside the Secretary of interior the feeling morally Superior
Look up that night on the dock website
Jerry veracocha became depressed but a heart attack at me
Enceladus secretary
The debut on Pennsylvania Avenue but after sniffing too much glue. One more day could they get through
When they suggested again
Sensor the Secretary of Health and Human Services we chose but their willingness to expose
The truth about UFOs
And so the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development they did but they read the
And so the Secretary of Transportation welcome to
Subway stop that way and services yet to be restored
Living skin
Celebrity found dead
Prayer
Ensuing game the Secretary of Education
But they should have with the letter of resignation and so the Secretary of Veterans Affairs
What's the results in HIV and not even tmsod mdrc
He couldn't leave that have a sensitivity and Son naturally dance
To go into recovery
N17 secretary
Trying to explain that the matriarchy simply means equality
Too scary
Free vegan recipes
People mowing swallowed by the sea
Play the song the 25th Amendment
We have a great animated music
Six video for that
Watch it
Weed
Funny short essays about all the Amendments listen to all of the other songs on the album
The most perfect
Album.
I'm jad abumrad this is more perfect
Will continue in the MoMA
I'm Jad abumrad this is more perfect we are Marching through the Amendments just did 25 liner notes
Tracy hunt song Fire by Devendra Banhart
Moving right along
26th Amendment
Right to vote at age 18
The right of citizens of the United States who are eighteen years of age or older to vote
Shall not be denied or abridged
Bobby Knight
It states or by any state
On account of a
26th Amendment
Is all about giving young people
The right to vote
It basically
Represents this moment in our history
Moments
Floral
Where we as a country started to really ask her
At what age
Do people
Should people
Have the right
To have a voice in our democracy
Prehistoric ari-tex from here
It all starts around World War II
In September 1940 The Selective Service Act was passed and for the first time
In history American boys were being drafted
And the love of your life
During World War II you had all of these young men who are about to be sent overseas many of whom were
18 but still don't have the right to vote because in a lot of States at that time the voting age was stilled
21 and 21 have been
Bike for a minute into a lot of people that didn't seem fair
Put the moment where people really really start to get mad about this
Is Vietnam
They came up with this phrase
Old enough to fight old enough
Devote
Fight at 18 died
Old enough to vote at 18
And so with that
The 26th amendment is ratified in just a hundred days faster than any other amendment in the Constitution
And actually it's interesting to think about this amendment now because
People
Recently have started to feel like
18 isn't good enough
Next to the youth vote
It's a little bit younger a group of teenage
Actress has won the campaign called 16 in USA
They want to lower the voting age to 16
In cities across the country
Hi
Hi Alec is that you
Yes me
I'm good
This is Alec Shriners
And I'm
From washing
I'm 60
What kinds of things do you do like besides political
Work at a kombucha
That's that my local Farm
Yeah but I'm also a
Another neighbor
Alex has been in the news
But recently
Is too low
To 6
He's an activist with this organization called vote 16 DC which has gotten behind this bill in
In his hometown of Washington DC
To lower the voting age
After the Parkland Florida shooting
DC would be the first
To allow minors to vote
An interesting Lee Alec told me that that
Same argument from the Vietnam era
To vote
It's come back around
But in a new form
No not again
Another High School
All of the school shootings that have happened at least shooting at a high school in
Kentucky in Rockford Southern California
Littleton Colorado
They've created that same sense
But if people are dying in elementary school
They deserve to have their voices heard
I just
I think it's really frustrating for me personally
That it's
Taking aspirin
Shot in schools
For people to be like
You know what I'll give you the right
Right to vote
Alex actually says that he should have that right for more basic reason
Just think that
You know every two weeks I get a paycheck and I get tax
Take it out and you know where those tax dollars go that go into the council members paychecks
And the council members get to vote on budget setting
Conclude my hard-earned money
And they get to decide where that
It's not only that he says that young people are already behind the wheel we're going 60 miles an hour
Our but you don't want us to walk into a voting booth and Nino
Couple of boxes and make a
Important decision
We drive a car
When we go in to apply for a license we can choose whether or not we want to be an organ donor or not
To the basic point is
If you
Process to pay taxes you trust us to drive
You trust us to be part of the decision to donate an organ
Then you should trust us to vote
But here's the thing right
When I went out
On Election Day
To ask people do you think 16 year olds should be able to vote if they thought this was a good idea
Most of them were like
Now
No I don't think so I don't think so
Absolutely not that's around the time I get in the marijuana their judgment is off now
Is that a thing that people are talking
I even had a 16 year old tell me that 16 year olds shouldn't vote
And ask her why most people that I talk to you like that guy
They just had this gut feeling that
16 is
Really different from 18
Is 16 is not a certain things that are wrong with that age might not be informed about these issues
I mean I'm thinking of my kids when they were 16
People
Constantly are coming up to me after event
They look at me and they say I like like I trust you more devoted
You know I
Trust you to make out more info
Decision
I trust myself
But
What about the other
What about the others
Yeah just looking at social media for have some gives you
Previous answer that kind of 16 year olds
Now to be fair just wondering if I could ask you a quick question
Somebody did think differently do you think 16 year olds should be able to vote
No thought into
Weirdly enough that's
Seth Meyers of late night talk show hosts
He was Voting right where I happened to be gathering tape
What's the weather like got reaction reaction is you could let 16 year olds vote
And we wouldn't be any worse off
You know you're like the only person who said that
Yeah I believe
I don't know. Now I'm starting to doubt my answer
Stand by you
And as the day wore on I actually did encounter more people who felt like maybe it's different now
All the musicians are listening to you are also talking about politics
MTV Has Fallen
So maybe there more were maybe 16 today is
Different from 16 back in the day
Strong opinion but you know what gun violence going on they probably do
Yeah today's most 16 year olds are mature enough
Understand what's going on at the light
Now from a psychological perspective the time people are sick
16 their abilities to make
Thoughtful deliberate decisions to consult with x
Experts when they wanted advice that those
Those abilities by the time people are sick
15 or no
Worse than the abilities of adults
That's Laurence Steinberg professor of psychology at Temple University
He says that
The research out there seems to suggest that
Cognitively
The average 16 year old Isn't that different from the average 18 year old
They're both equally likely to make bad decision
It almost sounds like
It's not that
Adult
Are smarter than two
16 year olds
It's that
16 year olds are just as stupid as
I guess you could look at it that way or let's just say
That the proportion of 16 year olds
Who are stupid
Is no greater than the proportion of adults
If that's the case and
It really is true that the average 16 year old today is more politically aware than
16 year olds in the past then
It really is hard to think of a reason
Why
They shouldn't have the ability to vote
You know right now 16 17 year olds and up me personally I have nothing that a politician
Once
You lower the voting age to
Teen they actually come to us
And they're going to ask
They start to care about
When I spoke to Alex
The vote in the DC Council
What's a couple months away
He was super optimistic
That the bill had the votes that are needed in order to pass
And that it would become the law of our nation's capital
If the stars pass
You'll see 1617 old voting in 2020
I will be 18
At that time
But I know where you live
Wake up early that morning and I'm going to take my
Neighbors going to be 16 at the
The time to go vote
Realized you to be the first
6 year old
The history of this country to vote for president
Phil 22 - 778 youth
Vote Amendment
Customer Allen
Thank you very much mr.
Chairman
Finally last week the DC Council met to decide the fate of the bill earlier this spring
We watch
Incredible voices
Take the helm
Seletar country
We saw incredible voices
Talk about
Gun violence
Voices talk about action
Incredible voices
Lead a national conversation
That the adults
What we saw Were Young by
People stepping up
Young people
Were any cases 6
That was councilmember Charles Allen who opened with that statement in support of the
After him another council members vote
Jack Evans
German again
What is significant unreadiness
On behalf of
Privy council members
Majority
So I'm going to
Make a motion to table this
Still at this time
He proposed a motion to basically kill the bill
There's a motion before us
Table the bill
Emotions
Cable is not
Debatable
The 13 council members been voted on whether or not to table the bill
And yes
Yes
Evansville Kia
Gray
Conor McGregor
Snow
Snow to make a long story short
Guilin Hills
Other measures
Disabled
So for the moment
16 year olds are not going to be voting in Washington DC in 2020
But that's just for the moment
Producer sarkari without liner Note 4
26th Amendment
The song that came attached to it on the album is from a Philadelphia band
West Suburban living
Okay more perfect
What is produced by me Jad abumrad Susie lechtenberg Julia Longoria Kelly Prime sarkari and Alex overington
With help from Elie mystal Michelle Harris David Gable
Cats Laszlo and moesta BMO
Text Nora Keller for her help making a record 27 the most perfect album and are Jeeps thanks.
The Jeffrey Wright for reading the Amendments for us
You can listen to all the songs and read short funny episodes about all the Amendments and watch that video
Devendra Banhart singing
A song for the 25th
The most perfect album
Thanks for listening