Listener-supported WNYC
Be Studios
But I think we should start the story on June 25th 1969
But first you should say Who You Are
I'm jazz
Ride this is more perfect okay so why
Why 220 when was it
June 25th nineteen
Supreme Court chief justice Earl Warren is retiring or a Warren of
The Warren Court
Isn't that a big word
Yeah that's what I think of you think of legendary
Supreme Court Justices he's probably in
He was one of the mount Olympians he's a big deal
Rights that he's retiring he's been on the court for 16 years
And he's in an interview and he's asked
How would you list Mister Chief Justice of the Supreme Court's most important decision you're 16 years here
He's kind of astounding
Before you hear the answer
Think that you need to know that he could have said all kinds of cases
Is he was the chief justice
During
Miranda
Earl Gideon petitioner Gideon versus Wainwright
Duty
Athens Big Bore
Brown versus Board of Education okay
Sad when I know that one
He doesn't say any of those
Was he say
He says this little case called
The Baker vs. Carr case
Baker vs. Carr
The back case
Is perhaps the most important case that believe that
Since I've been on the court
He thought that case whatever it is is more important than the case that desegregated schools
You did
So what the hell is it
Exactly
No really what is it
It's this case that was so dramatic and
So traumatic
It apparently broke to Justice
There was an instance
In which my
Brother found my father going upstairs
To get a shot
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
United States and this honorable Court
Is this more perfect miniseries about the Supreme Court just a frame the story we're about to hear for
Second
As we were putting the show together
We hosted a panel discussion
Best one stage and a woman in the audience asked the following question
Yes could you
Address what I see is the
Increasing politicization
Of the Court the apotheosis of which I guess was
You know voting
Electing Bush to be a hour
President
Difficult always been this way is this just my perception that it's becoming more popular size
See this turns out to be really interesting question turns out
I didn't know this until City started looking into it that there was a moment
When the Pandora's Box
Just got ripped open
So I think they understand that moment and this story you have to get to know 3 characters
These aren't necessarily the three most important justices of all time because at that time you had chief justice Earl
Warren and William Brennan on the court and he's our kind of giants
But for this story
These three guys are
One of them is on the right one of them is on the left
And one of them is
Stuck right in the middle
Tragically in the middle
Air on the conservative side
What difference does it make when it's in the Constitution
Any other expression or action by the state
You had a guy named Felix Frankfurter
Did Justice Frankfurter was one of the most
Latest really it name is really Frankfurter
One of the most
Influential Justice
Of all time I bet taragrove she teaches constitutional law at William and Mary Law School
I'm here
A very influential scholar at Harvard Law School before
He became address
With a close adviser to Franklin Delano Roosevelt he was extremely smart
Towering figure
But as a person
Justice
Justice Frankfurter
He wasn't necessarily
The nicest person
I heard that from everyone
I always call him a Bantam rooster
He was a difficult Krusty figure who is short
A little bit of a pouch
Was one of the most
What Justice is
He was a tough customer when a clerk would come to the US
Supreme Court Chambers to deliver a message in the person of the door
Tried to hand Justice Frankfurter the paper
Frankfurter would inevitably Let It Drop to the ground
So the person had to bend down and pick it up
Two handed to him again
Dude that's a
And by the way the voices you heard besides Tara Grover professors Mike seidman Georgetown University
Microphone won't School Craig Smith California University of Pennsylvania Supreme Court Clerk
Alan Cohen Long John
Okay so Frankfurter is on one side of the aisle and his Nemesis is a gentleman on the other side of the aisle
Illiberal named William O Douglas
He was Justice Douglas now in the Supreme Court Chambers recording from the 1950s
7 interview with Justice Douglas
Looks very well as faces 10 rugged his eyes sparkle
Mountain climbing environmentalist
Big on civil liberties
Music by generation was like Justice Frankfurter
Douglas was a prick
But everybody around him everybody hated him
All those same adjective
Applied
Here's how the New York Times
Scriptum Douglas was married four times
This is footage from his last marriage to his wife Kathleen
He was 67
She was 23
So
Yes yes that it that is William Douglas
They have these two guys Frankfurter the Bantam rooster Douglas
The prick and as you can imagine big hater
Charter
Despise
So Frankfurter had this habit of monologuing and while he would go on and on Douglas with just pull out a book right in front of them
Start reading you know he was just opening his the same for Frankfurter I actually found a series of interviews that word
Donald Douglas in the early sixties where he basically calls Frankfurter names
Wow
Why they hate each other so much
According to Mike seidman some of that comes from
Maybe there
Difference in background
Frankfurter was
A Jewish
Immigrant from Austria
A Douglas was a Westerner
But according to him
Or of their hatred
Actually was ideological reflected
I really important split
Over how powerful the court should be
Doctor Frankfurter
Quartz just want not to intervene and he believed that many matter should be left up to the political process
And the court should stay out of those issues
Court want to intervene to protect for example of minority groups Free Speech rights things of that sort
Do you have this personal Feud going you had this
Ideological war that was brewing in the court
And into the middle of all of this
Walks Charles Whitaker
You might call him the Swing Vote
Okay this is Alan Cohen Supreme Court Clerk
Or Justice Whitaker
From 19
Whitaker grew up in a small town in Kansas called Troy
Antithesis of flashy this is his granddaughter
It's kind of a one-room schoolhouse overview Little Red Schoolhouse work on the farm
But he
He he determined that was not the life for him
Kate says when he was around sixteen he became obsessed with the idea of becoming a lawyer and she says he would actually practice law
To the animals
Can you imagine you know pushing
The plow along in the fields and them lecturing and arguing cases to the cows or to the horses or whatever
Earlier that he was lecturing to yes
Oh and on the side he was he would hunt he would hunt the squirrels opossum raccoon
I need sell the pelts for a few dollars
Any amassed I think $700 would that money put himself through Law School
My understanding is that he simultaneously went to law school and high school
What which is just mind-boggling but yeah apparently he went to the head of the law school in Kansas City and he's like
I don't know high school diploma but
You need to let me in
Vadim just saw how ambitious he was and he was impressed me is like Alright you're in
I love this guy
He's like Mr bootstrap
Totally any how to make a long story short the top lawyer and Alan Cohen says that's because he would
Do better than all of his opponents he would outwork them out prepare the great attention to detail
Great
Presents before a jury
And then he becomes a judge for a federal district judge and then an appeals court judge
Then in February of 1957
He gets the call
As I recall it was in the evening and asked if he could be in Washington
Nginx
Warning this is Kent Whitaker
Charles Whitaker
He should certainly but my best blue shoe deals at the cleaners tonight
What did he wear
As a matter of fact
My mother or someone else got the cleaners open up at night
In the first allegation
Tending to show that the corporation's right of exercise of free will happen
This is one of the first time that Whitaker spoke on the bench
Energex with a question for the attorney and he is Midwestern bullet
Minion Rush
But I have a question or two
The thing is crazy to me is it
He walked into the highest court in the land in
He didn't even go to college important
Understand that he had no formal education
Another word she never took history
Political science or social science
But do you love the law my father was not an idea log
He expected
The court to be
An arena in which there were Lively arguments on legal issues
That's what
He enjoyed
What are what's really good at what you love
Has Kent Whitaker puts it
His dad was kind of the walking embodiment of that thing that
Chief Justice John Roberts said back in 2005 during his confirmation hearings chairman. Come before the committee with no agenda
He was sort of a blank slate
My job to call balls and Strikes
And not the pitch
Or bat
My father was not interested in advancing a
Pause or a
Siri but frankly that's adjusted
Should be that you are approaching it without a political agenda and you're deciding it I think
Exactly right
But
In practice
Show many of their cases
There is no law
To turn to to decide those cases
Ken says that his dad quickly discovered the law by the Supreme Court is never clean cut
Cases make it there precisely because the law isn't clear
Without pressure
And it's in those cases
You have must have your ideology
As a
As a starting
And the fact that he didn't have an ideology
That was vulnerable he was definitely getting lobbied
From both sides
Sprinkler on one side
Douglas on the other the new kid on the Block and was being pulled by
Each one like
The way the judges bowling for votes within his first three months he found himself in the middle of a death penalty
Polycave she was found
Your bedroom by fireman taken outside
Turn that after 4 now
A guy I've been tried for arson and murder and Douglas and liberals wanted to intervene to help them
They feel like you've been treated unfairly by the lower courts
But Frankford when the conservatives thought that the Supreme Court should be
Just a should honor Preston
According to Justice
Does Douglas
Justice Whittaker was undecided all the time
Douglas would tell him one thing
Writing and Justice Frankfurter would say something else
I think there was some thought that you
He might
Side with
The guy who talked with him laugh
You know
He ends up being so undecided on this death penalty case that he forces the court to delay the vote until the next
In the world series of cases like this
Read aloud be fuzzy ideologies would Harden and Whitaker he would be right in the middle
Physical
Depictions of him in that first year from people who saw him
Describe somebody who was
Restless
Terribly unhappy
I had lost a lot of weight nervous
Was agitated most of the
The time
It was a lot of stress
This was just for the normal course on the California procedures and butt over the next week
Bounces back you find his feet
His production increase
Eventually
In his third year his fourth year and part of his V
He wrote as many opinions that is any other judge
He wrote as many dissenting opinions as any other
He was one of the nine it was fully employed
And he wrote some very important opinions
During that period of time
And Along came a bigger versus
Does car
And it broken
Avis more perfect I'm Jenn I'm writing a story from Suzie lechtenberg
About the case that broke two justices
Number
123 Charles W Baker at Alcatel appellant versus Josie car
Okay so it's April 19th 1961
The Supreme Court is hearing Baker vs. Carr
This is an individual
Voting rights
11 qualified voters in the state of Tennessee
Not on the surface Baker vs. Carr was about districts and how people are counted in this country and this is
Is one of the most basic ways that political power gets assigned in America
That growth should be reflected in the number of Congress people that are representing them but at that time
Tennessee Hennessy hadn't changed its legislative district
Since 1901 which was 60 years earlier will this create a big problem
Sims 4 urban areas like Memphis because in those 60 years people have moved to the cities in
Gross and rural areas were getting smaller
But the Tennessee State Legislature had refused to update account and it was still giving more representation to those real
Rural areas
In Tennessee
The figure was
23 to 1
NYU Law Professor Sam is that girl that for people that don't understand how does it actually dilute
Your vote
This is very
You have one District that has
One person in it and you have another District
It has 20
T3 people
The district that has one person gives all the
The power to that
The district
It has 23 people
Spread it out over Altamont
What I think of it this way
At that time a person in the city in Tennessee
Had one 23rd as much of a voice in the legislature as a person living in the countryside and
Cheers
Sword of the Insidious underbelly of that
It just so happened that the people living in the countryside
Are mostly White
And a large percentage of the people living in the city were black
Underline all of the reapportionment litigation leasing South was
White supremacy
That's Doug Smith historian and the author of on the market
Your doorstep this is deeply tied to white supremacy in the maintenance of Jim Crow was a method of making sure that rural
A white legislators continue to control the power structure
So you had the situation he says we're a small minority was choking the majority
Suburban areas from any sort of any sorts of funds cities couldn't get the money they needed for Rhodes education social services so
So the question at the Supreme Court was
And it actually tackle this in two separate things
What should I do about this
And here's where you get to the ideological Smackdown liberals on the court like Douglas basically agreed with the plaintiff when they are
Liberal
Yeah this is clearly an injustice people in the cities are getting screwed
Their voting rights have been diluted in the basement
Yes
People are getting hurt but we're not going to do any
We can't Frankfurter
Zipper sleeve said we cannot get involved that as bad as it says it was not an issue that the court should get involved in right now
Well
How to wear the salute during the fact that this is a unique situation
Tennessee situation if we end up doing this in Tennessee pretty soon we'll be intervening in California South Carolina
Jason will be rewriting the entire us legislative map
Tennessee
This is the United States not Tennessee
Yes so basically he felt like this would force the courts to get involved in politics
And he really believe that the court should never ever get involved in politics
This is a
This is an idea that goes way back to something called
Political question.
The political question Doctrine says
No federal court can decide this issue at all
E-courts simply had no business
Getting into it work
Consider to be fundamentally political questions and what could be more fun in my life political than the makeup of the legislature
It's a philosophy rooted in the notion that unelected lifetime judges should not
Happy substituting their will
For the will of the people's elected representatives
Frankfurter feel like even if you have a terrible political situation if the justices stepped in and overruled the legislature
That would be worse than doing nothing at all
Because it would be fundamentally undemocratic
I'm he viewed
Give you the political question Doctrine
Is a crucial limitation on the Federal Judicial power
And he wasn't alone the courts at follow this guideline for about a hundred and fifty years
And even with the current case in Tennessee federal court that first heard the case
Recognized
The situation actually referred to it as in evil
Play info
But this is that this is a political question
Malapportionment
The political question and only the political branches can handle this
Protecting and enforcing
Voting rights
So
Ventana school when the lawyer for Tennessee got up there
Didn't try to defend her Tennessee was counting or not counting its people he basically said yeah what we're doing is bad
But it's nobody's job but hours to fix
Is it worth
The legislature of Tennessee
Not
Terraria potions
Warriors
Federal District
Violate
Angel.
Separation
He basically said if you step in you're going to screw up the balance of power in America
Power America comes from We the People
Not the courts so this matter should be left up to the people of Tennessee and their elected representatives
If the whole problem is that you don't have a voice in the ledge
Glacier then how can you suddenly
To have a voice
In legislature
I mean either way to change it would be SC legislature itself where to give up power and why would they do that
Can of course
Once elected officials are in power they have a vested interest
And keeping their districts exactly as they are because
Those are the districts that elected them
And fundamentally
Electoral Representatives knew that if they redrew the lines and they would be
Voting themselves out of a little
Copower
ASCII Charles Professor Duke Law School
Not to do anything
So for the Liberals on the court they felt like this was a fundamental flaw in our democracy that needed to be fixed
And nobody was going to fix it if they didn't
Frankfurter he's like if you think of this one you can have to fix that one and that one and that one and that one and where is it going to stop
If you do this
There is no way out the Court's going to get stuck and what he called political Thicket
The political Thicket Court must not enter the political Thicket
Frank farina's Rittenhouse Square
The imagery of the
Ticket is that
You know the deer very proudly with
Corn
Goes into
To the thicket
Gets entangled
Can never get out
Frankfurters Plainwell
Once the courts are in there will be nothing
Beyond it and someday
The courts will be forced to declare winners and losers a very high-profile election
Okay so after the oral arguments are over in Baker versus car
Are the justices head into conference that's a meeting with just the nine
Right down the middle and Charles Whitaker
He was a potential Swing Vote was deeply torn
Keepin leaning frankfurters way
A clear conscience
Right
Finish the Spurs at first argument he asked a number of questions that suggested a great deal of sympathy with the plaintiff
Power
In the course
Constitutional right there's a lot of thought that he might actually come down on the side of of the plaintiffs in the case knives were Frankfurter really
Really baginda
Rip into a Justice Frankfurter
Right after the first real argument
Event during the conference
Even 90 minutes
Speech
Photographer
90 + straight minutes
Darting around the room pulling books off the shelves
Pulling books off the shelf
Reading from prior cases gesticulating wildly
To make its point
And the whole time looking directly at Whitaker
There was one account that I heard where Frankfurter went on for 4 hours
4 hours really lecturing Whitaker really really belittling him
Yes it was it was horribly intimidate
At one point
One of the justices on the liberal side
Justice Hugo Black
He took Whittaker side was trying to make him feel better
And black said to Charles Whitaker just remember we're all boys grown tall
We're not the gods who sit on high and dispense Justice
But it's very difficult not to see yourself in that role
Particularly if your vote might be the vote that decides everything
This started a weigh heavily on Whitaker's mind
He was disturbed by the by having the weight of Spring Court on his shoulders
According to his family Kate and Kent my mother tells me that he
At that time
Was under a lot of stress
And spoke as though he were dictating spoke his punctuation
Hello Judas, it's very nice to meet you could clearly thinking about everything that he
Might say being recorded I remember his
Stating that he felt like
All the words that he ordered were being chiseled in stone as a result of Leaky Shed
You don't talk much
So after they heard the case the first time wudaokou couldn't make up his mind
And actually incidentally there is another Justice Justice Stewart
Who was the other Swing Vote in the case also couldn't make up his mind
The court decided to hear the case again in the fall
Just cuz they needed more time
And over the summer remain deeply divided that he actually
Written memos on both sides of the issue
Doug Smith says Whitaker wrote both and opinion for intervening in Baker vs. Carr
And a dissent against intervening in Baker versus car
At the same time as he circulates
60 page memo explaining how this was a political question that should not be decided by the chords
Please God
You know a fire in his belly
He's not going to let
This one go
Number 6
Charles W Baker at Alice Cullen
Monday October 9th 1961
It's 10 a.m. and the court is back in session
Lawyer arguing the case against the Tennessee legislature begin to talk
Federal courts
Action
Frankfurter sit quietly for about
5 minutes listening
Without the light
And then
You don't need them
I know right
Frankfurter hammers the attorneys with questions
During the course of oral arguments
He speaks approximately 170 * 170 + 70
Charles Whitaker
Have some
For the allocation
Amish legislatures to dispatch
17 *
Well
After nearly four hours of oral arguments
The justice is recess and going to conference
Frankfurter needed
Desperate
He had a good war
And he would tip
After him
Like a
Dog after a bone
Trying to persuade
And that
Harassing
Me. I have to make a point here
It was a nightmare
And I saw the night
How so describe it to me
Well
He was
A nervous wreck
And like a Cat on a Hot Tin Roof
I found out I don't know if he told me or his wife told me
He was on tranquilizer
Overcome
What he thought
Was just work related
Stress will clearly
Something
Was taking hold of him
Who had trouble concentrating
Highly fraught I would characterize
He is eventual breakdown
It's something of a slow descent
By the early spring
After the cord has return from its winter
Recess
Whitaker was absent from
Court
You mean like he just didn't either getting show for work one day
Apparently so
Clerks didn't know where he
He was
The other justices
Didn't know his whereabouts
He just disappeared
Really in the
Little
Of what's going to become one of the
Monumental decisions of the 20th century
He disappears
She had to
Escape
Where'd you go
Well
He went to really what would be a cabin in the woods
In the middle of Wisconsin
He called up one of his former Los Associates in Kansas City.
Come up and join him
And according to Craig Smith
He in the sky whose name was Sam Milby
They would just
Set there
On the bank of the lake
In silence
They would sit for hours on end not talking to each other
Just waiting for the Justice to speak
We have no way of knowing what he was thinking at that moment but
I imagine he was just
Sitting there and he was thinking about these two realities that could unfold like
On the one hand if the court stepped into politics
They can protect people
But on the other hand
President with the set
Would it make the court too powerful
How much case
Do it protect the people
Has received
Images mine went back and forth and back and forth
Kurt decided he really had to get back to work than this
Protege would say to him
No just relax
Did you just take it easy and
Get yourself
Together before you decide to go back
After three weeks Justice Whitaker returns to DC
Back to Washington
For a few days
But can't again his son
We found my father to be
Really in extremis
Debate and end I think I'm borderline suicidal
When you said that he was suicidal what do you mean
There was an instance in which my
Brother found my father going upstairs to get a shot
A few days later
Charles Whitaker check himself into a hospital
There is
Some evidence that it was really Justice Douglas Who convinced Whitaker
Go to the hospital
That's Justice William Douglas again
A few weeks later March 29th 1962
The presidential press conference from the new state department Auditorium
Washington DC
Several announcements to make
It is with extreme regret
That I announce the
Retirement of associate Justice of the Supreme
Supreme Court
Charles Evans Whittaker
Effective April
April 1st
Justice Whittaker
Remember the Supreme Court for nearly five years
Have the federal judiciary
Beignets
Is retiring at the direction of his position
Reasons of disability
I know that the bench in the Box
Of the entire nation
Join me in commending this to just
Aquatica
First devoted service to his country
During a critical period and its history
Text I want to take this opportunity to
Distress again the in Fort
The tax bill now before the house representative
Wow
Whatever happened with the case with Bakery card
Whitaker didn't vote on Baker vs. Carr
So you could say that this case that
Essentially broken
His vote didn't count
Around the time that he was in the hospital there was sort of this liberal coup at the court where Frankfurter lost a couple of other vote
So in the end the decision actually wasn't very close at all
What was it it was 6 to
And Brennan wrote the majority opinion and he says that this whole
Kind of cluster that we've been fighting over
Apostates in Tennessee counter voters
But this is something the court can and should look at
So another words I decided to
Blow their horns and go into the thicket
Oh yeah they did
And just one or two final questions of what happened to Justice Frankfurter
The thing that I find
Crabs most extraordinary
Is it less than 2 weeks
After decision in Baker versus car came down
Felix Frankfurter was working at his desk at the Supreme
Concord and
Frankfurter secretary found him
Sprawled on the floor of his office
From a stroke
He suffered a massive stroke
And the never return to service
And while he was in the hospital solicitor-general Archer
Ballcock
Visit a Frankfurter
And Frankfurter
She was in a wheelchair
Could barely speak
But he
Apparently conveyed Archibald
That the decision maker versus
Skarhead essentially
Caused his
He felt
So passionately
That the court should stay out of
The case
That Keef
Physically
Physically deteriorated
After the court had gone the other way
After Baker vs. Carr President Kennedy essentially had to Supreme Court vacancies to fill
Now Whitaker seat he filled with a guy who turned out to be a moderate
Frankfurters vacancy that second vacancy
That vacant
Can see
That will lead to the appointment of a man named Arthur Goldberg
That is the fifth vote
That
The four liberals
What are regarded as the four liberals that becomes the fifth vote that they need
Really to create what has
Come to be regarded as the Warren Court Revolution
This is when the Supreme Court basically became an agent for social change
With the 1962 term
That's the revolution that is going to change
Are political boundaries prosecutor confession
Criminal justice the way we treat 1st Amendment
Religious and obscenity issues that's the Warren court that people remain
Remember
And that's the court that came into existence when Felix Frankfurter left
I'm so just thinking about that question that that woman asked all the way at the beginning of the story
Could you address what I see is the
Increasing politicization
Of the Court the apotheosis of which I guess was
Yoona voting
OLX in Bush
To be a hour
President you can
Kind of draw a line from this moment in Baker versus car
All the way to December 9th 2000
Holes in six new states have just closed and the lead story at this hour is
The state
Florida
Is 2
Close
I think Felix Frankfurter would have said
See
That's what I told you that's what would happen
Is that eventually you will you will be deciding a partisan
Which
Presidential candidate
Essentially received the most votes
For those who help themselves on the losing side of bush V Gore
This was
Justice Frankfurter
This was the moment
Bad
Baker V Carr
And
When I teach this to
Students
Particularly in the decade
After Bush V Gore
Sent sent
Sentiments about the
This was still quite Raw
I would say to them well
Is this
Was Frankfurter right
And I remember a student in the mid
Mm
Who said
In class I never thought I would
Say this
But
I hated the outcome of bush
Precor I was so angry
Proceeded
But if
Bush V Gore is the price we have to
To pay for
The courts making the overall
System
Work
Somewhat more Tyler
Broccoli
Surprise him with
If we totally sign off what happened
The Douglas Weiser lost track I am so after Baker vs. Carr was decided he went on to be a Supreme Court Justice for three
13 more years and to this day he actually holds the record for being the longest-serving justice of all time 36
Frankfurter Baker vs. Carr was the last case that he ever heard
And he died a few years afterwards recover
After Whitaker retired from the court he moved back to Kansas City with his family and his son said that it took them about
2 years to get better from his nervous breakdown but he did get better and eventually he got a job as counsel.
The General Motors but
He never returned the benching never with a judge again
Okay more perfect is produced by me Chatham rod
With Suzie lechtenberg
Tell Kelsey with Soren wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington Karen Duffin Shawn Roberts
Katherine Wells Barry Finkel Andy Mills and Michelle Harris
Special thanks to Ian Riley
Archival interviews with Justice William O Douglas come for the Department of rare books and special collections at Princeton University Library
Supreme Court audio is from
Free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
More perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation The Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
And the Joyce Foundation