Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
Leadership support for more perfect
/ the joist found
Cake on jeroboam Rod this is more perfect
United States we gave the Supreme Court the power to find Justice for people
Wii Sports people who've been abused and manipulated
I mean baby knock on the door that power extends Beyond state borders both ends
Sometimes even be on national board with Swiss
Question is how far we want to go
Should our Supreme Court
Did the Supreme Court of the world
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
Okay so I grew up at a time
When a lot of people genuinely saw America differently than they do now
This is the 70s and 80s Carter Reagan years
There's a sense
If you are new arrivals
America was special
Exceptional
We held the world to a higher standard
Certainly brought my family to America
Okay so it's not that way anymore so much and it seems like everyday at least in my lifetime we're asking the question
How should we feel
About that
What was that is that higher calling that's somehow For Better or Worse embedded in the idea of being American is
That stupidly wrongheaded and arrogant or is there something in that that we still
Still should embrace
That argument is happening has been happening and
Totally fascinating way at the Supreme Court
Centered around this
Teeny peeny Wallie
It seems to have some pretty big question
About Who We Are
We want to be
Story comes from
2K peas Kelsey Padgett
And I
Kp-1
I believe you are now kp-1 okay I am now
If you want to stop it
Del Sol
The Story begins appropriately enough not in America but it starts in 1976 with
This woman I have to
Get used to
Yeah
Okay so I guess the first thing if you could just introduce yourself why
My name is Dolly filartiga
I am from Hawaii
Paraguay it's a small country right on top of Argentina
Andales family the Florida coast
Pretty big deal over there
You my family was that my grandfather was
Very
Fridge
The Florida keys made their money exporting tobacco to Europe for big cigarette companies like
Datong
Lost a family that owns it
Beautiful flower in the countryside
Lots of land
Do airplanes
Now this could have been dollies
But you will say I'm going to win
And it wasn't
Because of her father
Your father what's his name
I want coin coin and what what did your dad do for a living
Her dad very famously turned his back on his fancy upbringing
The entire family to the countryside
And there he set up a clinic to give Medical Care to the poor indigenous
Farmers in that area 47000 people
He was the only doctor in a lot of cities that became kind of like a patron saint of the countryside
Not only would give the medical treatment but when they came in he would tell them go vote rise above your station
And as you can imagine as word got out
This really pissed off
Paraguay's ruler at the time
A guy named alfredo stroessner
He was called the pulpo the octopus because it said he had arms and tentacles that reach into everybody's
Live there in the country
Hatsune Horst American history here at Appalachian State University
Wadali was growing up Renee live
Next door in Formosa Argentina
Paraguay
What part of this like big network of dictators
All across Latin America and it was called Operation Condor
Operation Condor
Was a network that link together military dictatorships of Latin America so
Brazil Argentina Chile
Bolivia Uruguay Paraguay
Renee said the Operation Condor was a lot like a spider web
With Pinochet at the master Weavers
Spider
The Communist Revolution in Cuba had just happened and so these six
Super militaristic dictatorships
They banded together to pretty much trap communism in Cuba out of South America
Remember this is a cold war in America really wanted to keep communism out of the continent to
So it's really likely that the
The CIA was involved
The result was a network of state-sponsored Terror
In the Darkness
Part of the night they will come to your apartment and
Dragon stuff you in the trunk of a Ford Falcon car
And you disappear forever
My father used to tell depressed
Vote for the strut nut
Contacts behind Dr filart against Rebellion
Kelly said he travel all over the world giving talks trying to show everything what is drawing a rose
Doing in the car
Who tells patients when the government comes to buy your crops
14 day weather on sale
Don't give him a thing
Sally tried her best to ignore all this
We didn't get that long with my father I have to say that
So
When I get older she moved away from the country
I came to the city
To live
What city was
Asuncion
She worked to put herself through school
And then what are Ethan and Alex
Follow me
And then Dolly says she work to put her two siblings do school
Her sister Anna Lee at the time was 14 and her brother julito was 17
Dockweiler
He was her favorite
Polito look like my mother
Green eyes
Daniel hair like her I know that he had
A lot of girls that
Crust on him
This is Dolly's daughter Paloma
Very handsome
Yes but he wasn't a player
And what was what was hoagitos personality like
Was he loud
Was he quiet
You see those people that
See things and you left because you
So funny all the time
Just people that a joke comedian comedian with always so that he would
Become a comedian he was very funny
Types of YouTube
Redis
That's the backdrop 1976
Sally's in the city with her two siblings
Why Dad's on the country drumming up opposition to the regime
At that time
Accordingly.
She said many friends that he feel like he was being followed
He didn't want to tell ask because
We are we still teaching to be careful
Even my father who are you to tell him be careful because you are
Why my son is
And at that time in Paraguay it was well known that there was spies
Everywhere
They put away
Without what
Send expression in one tiny person with hairy feet
Scolipede eyewear
It's a nickname for informers of the regime
So things are already tense
And then
On March 29th 1976
Dolly and her siblings are turning in for the night
Around 11
Telangana Libra sleep in one bed
Incognito has kids room
And so he went to rescue Steve and then when I go 9
And what happened was that
We wish her and the middle of the night movie
3:00
Define Bean in desert Baptist and she wakes up like
She throws onycho over her nightgown to cover myself and she goes to the door where she finds a cop
He say you'll have to come with me there is a little problem with your brother has been house
At Pena's house remember that name aspecto Canada America benyo
She didn't know him too well but he was a policeman and she always had suspicions about him so.
Only steps out and it's a chilly night in her nightgown
What
Four policemen card officer who's at the door walked over to paint
His house into the house down a long hallway that she says was lying with even more policemen
35 + 35
She says she walked down the hall the policeman sort of parted for her
And guided her to a room in the back of the house
A winning to that room open that door
Insolito Spa
He was lying on his back
Anna mattress
And this
Human being my brother was so
Beautiful
His body is
Converting gas as you can see where
Recent stabbing
Over and over again and
Maybe tied up
Burnham they cut him I found
Fitbit densities
This
There was an electrical wire attached to his genitals
Boss trucks
Juju chiusano how to spray how how other human being can do that to another one
Monica never done anything to YouTube.
I don't know
Dolly said she bolted out of the room and immediately ran into Inspector General Pena
He was standing in the doorway
ISO Pena in my way
Autonomy
You better shut up
The thing that uses
Surf
And you better keep quiet because next time we'll be you something
He told you next time it would be you
And your family
You better shut up
I say I am. You feel ad
You don't know who I am.
Don't make me shut up today but tomorrow in Valley with no
My duty to my brother
Over the next three years the family tried to get Justice
They suit Pena in the paraguayan courts
But the lawyers were threatened when was disbarred
When Dolly and her mom testified against Pena the same as twitches
So we went to jail
When Dolly and her mom got out of jail they race Wilson
Showing what they did to my brother taken dance reporter through newspaper articles
The coffin investigation
Before anything could happen
Pena
She disappeared
Havana
The country altogether
The question is
If you're Dolly what are you do
Your brother has just been brutally murdered
You know who did it
But you know you can't get Justice in Paraguay because the whole court systems in with the regime
And you can't go to the international criminal court
Because it doesn't exist yet
And even if it did exist
Your case is way too small
So what do you do
When I said we have to decide
Fast forward to 1979
I moved
The Washington Dallas living in DC jeannene cooking any houses working part time at a law firm
All this time she's had feelers out with her dad's connections ngos
Just trying to find out at least we're paying is living in there
Finally
One day that's bring
She got a phone call from one of those connections
Babe
Found pinyin
They told me that opinion
What's leaving kid in Brooklyn
She's been working at a furniture store in Brooklyn when a fellow paraguayan had recognized him
Outed him
I didn't know what I was going to do but I want to chastise
Deep ditches in this case I was desperately
Got a pair of gland responsible for the death of another paraguayan in Paraguay
What's happening firewise like even if he did something wrong and I Y
Which it seems like he did
There's no pictures of nothing to do with America
When I said we have to decide
So
I was looking for help
Daily contacts a lawyer who gets her in touch with this guy
Peter Weiss Center for constitutional rights
Peter says even before dali showed up
We were trying to figure out how to sue people committing crimes against humanity and war crimes
For example 504 unarmed Vietnamese women children and old men were massacred overall
4 Hour. By US troops this was around the time of the me Lai massacre in central Vietnam
When that happened my colleagues at the center and I was there a way for them
U.s. military on behalf of one of the victims crime was committed
Abroad
So I came and met Peter
And password head so I called an emergency meeting of the Santa stuff
Is there a way we can help is there some like wormhole in American law that would let us bring non
Can Americans and non American crimes into American courts
And one of us at the Sony was obviously a good researcher
And I said hey you know there's a super old super obscure law
Something called the alien tort statute
Alien tort statute
4th Ave case
I don't know how many
Hours and hours and hours and hours
Trying to find
Damn phone
These law
That they used to use against hepatitis
Debbie. The Pirates
Spider
Thank you
Pirates
Mia
What do pirates have to do with anything
Who yet what are you want to go to Kelly to handoff
To choose someone answer my question
Sure who are you by the way
I'm Kelsey Padgett reporter okay yes
This story has to do with pirates definitely will get there
Before that
This is even
Freeze your back
2K
You got to you got to buy it and got to go with me on this
Journey because
It's it's
Is this a lot
Story
Reagan's Journey
We're going to
We from DHR la.
Old way back in 1784
Granola
Anna Banana this is William Casto he's a professor at Texas Tech told me the story
And it's really a story of like bites of a piece
Yeah
Here's the situation
It 1784
You got this guy yesterday Longchamp
Charles Julian DeLong.
And he's a french guy
Chinese living in Philly
He would apparently was an officer in the French Cavalry Regiment
And a nobleman by birth
By the way some people didn't like it
Thomas Jefferson said
He's enough
Quote abs
Skewer and worthless character
Okay
Why
Why you say that
Doesn't matter what's important is that he is here
America has a bad reputation and
End up meeting this
Girl
A nice young Quaker girl
A quote
Eros
To a competent Fortune
Yeah
And
Her friends disapprove
Very much so
And so it started circulating rumors around town around Philadelphia
That long time
Was a liar
That he was not of noble birth and wasn't even enough
Probably gold digger
You know since she had
This money chops is really mad about this he wasn't snacks
And he put on his uniform and he
Stormed over to the
French Embassy
Freaky ghost
Embassy
And there he spoke with Francois
Barb marwat
Who was the embassy
Here's an aside
Marwat later was Napoleon's Menace
Picture of banana
Oh and he negotiated the Louisiana Purchase
Well that's just an aside
When is barbed wire is like
Important dude
But you know the other friends
The long-term stuff
Maybe Skylander guy walks in
I guess he doesn't show a lot of respect he's like you know any drop everything and help me out with the situation cuz people are spreading rumors
You're saying I'm not a nobleman or whatever I need you to stand up for me
And marbois refused
We don't know why
At any rate in response
Longchamp shouted at marbois
Google Translate
I will dishonor you
And then he called him
And this is a transgression
A laughable scam
Which is kind of
Can you imagine people calling someone that laughable scam today
It seems tame honestly very day
But those words
Would create a
National
Crisis everything were talking about today
Goes back to this
Little confrontation
How what do you mean by Connor was as big deal.
Hamilton dies right something like always gonna laughable Scamp food cause
You don't even like that's the kind of thing you do a duel over it was an indignity
Where boil was so pissed at the moment and he did the right thing in that time. Which is
Still have a duel with the man contacted his bosses he wrote a letter across the seas to France and instead
Y'all
Will you do about this now the French
Don't like what's going on the French
Want us to
To put him on a ship back to
France
And have France
Punish the long time
And the
Pennsylvania executive Council
Agreed
But the judges refused
That's ridiculous
All that
Causes France to say
You know what
Be sure that America's
Take care of this they're going to punish this guy
Maybe we can't take this brand new country seriously
Give me some land of no law
Huge thing and you got to keep in mind at that time United States was a third world nation
We were weak France had been our buddy during the revolution
And the feeling was
We desperately needed the help of other countries
Because it reduces baby little country by the way the Dutch Ambassador was Furious to because he said
If you don't
Punished long jobs
I'm leaving the state
He actually threatened to leave
State
It really created
Problems
So we had to do some
But the question was
What the national government
Had no Authority whatsoever
To deal with or punish
A person like lingerie
Because it wasn't a crime to just say I will dishonor you
And even if it were
The incident happened at what was essentially the French Embassy
Samovar you
That that made it
This is a situation outside of the United
States so I step in there and I'm also the only under the rules
Yeah that's the argue
YouTube did we have jurisdiction over that space
My point is that the new US Government they were just powerless
I didn't know what to do
What happened
Well the case goes to court
And the judge in that case
Figure out what to do
Really badly
Got to punch this guy and he's looking at this book
No law is that no laws
Skype
You don't
There are some
Start explicitly written down but that all people across the world
Agree
Homemade
The Greeks that this is bad
Entente
The classic
Pirates
The Pirates are out there on the open
Pillaging
Plundering
Killing
And they are not really subject to anyone nation's laws they're not doing this in a nation
No one had specific jurisdiction over
Doing all the way back to Roman times
Pirates were designated as universal enemy
The hostess houmani
Generous
That's a male mowing history professor at Yale University
The phrase in Latin
Hostess houmani
The enemy of
And it means that
That may be there
Things that are
Zohan
You don't have to
Ocelot
And you don't have
Howard
Stop
The perpetrator
They're just so bad and
Piracy
Okay
So what the judge do
Decides
This french guy in Philadelphia
Insults the fancy French guy in
The way that
We're going to solve this is
By saying that
The insulter
He's a little bit like a pirate
Now you just need to turn Pirates but it's the same concept
He said that that guy the long jump
Has broken international law
He is guilty of
An atrocious violation of
The law of nature
He not only France The Sovereign he represents
Also hurts
The common safety welding 1/8
He is guilty of a crime against
Whole world that's a quote from the ruler
They then
Finding
100 French
Crowns
And two years
2 years
For sale
I will dishonor you
Wow
This move by the judge basically works
Marble in France field good
There on Earth
Protected the Dutch Ambassador doesn't leave he stays but more importantly
Our story
In 79 Congress passed some of their very first laws
There's like this one big Bill about
Courts and in there
Is this thing called the alien tort
Statute
The only force that shoot
You know it was written into law to deal with this kind of situation
You are a diplomat
Insulted
But more generally it was meant to connect us law
To internet
Simplifying with a bunch but it basically says like
Somebody violates International norms
You know like a
Crime against the whole world
They can be sued in US Civil Court
But you're saying there's a law
From the beginning that allows and non us
Sue each other for non us crime
In US courts
Yeah
So weird
But like the thing is this is this is Kelli again when it comes to this law
Forever no one actually used it
It was barely mentioned for 200 years
Why
Why wouldn't it come up
If you think about it kind of makes sense it wasn't used
Because
It was a super specific LOL this is a weird circumstance in which we really needed to bring international law
And use it inside our borders
But that kind of thing like
Diplomatic
Bite that didn't happen very often
And more generally
The prevailing idea at the time was that
Internationally we should
Kind of Stan are laying like if you're going to come into our country
And that's what are citizens of gal we're going to do something about that but
If you want to do something to your own citizens
That's not my business
There's an old idea that in every country The Government Can
Due to its people whatever it wants and a nobody in any foreign country no foreign government has any biz
Business telling them what to do
This is Eric Posner the University of
The reason that the alien tort statute was
Pretty much ignored is because of this idea
That we're not going to tell you what to do in your borders so don't you come into our country and tell us what to do
Don't know this but there was actually a humanitarian basis for this
Harsh sounding princip
Came about in the 17th century
The problem back in the 17th century were religious wars
Protestants and Catholics Catholics and the Protestants endless strife and so the idea was
Let's simplify things
And just understand that in foreign countries people have different values and ideas and it just not
Decorah good in the long run if
If we try to
Tell people in foreign countries how they should behave
And this was the dominant
View
Hundreds of years
Until World War II really
But the Hulk has changed everything
At one of the defenses that Nazis
Gave to the specific charge of massacring Jews is that they're protected by the principal siren
That was you know considered unacceptable argument and countries around the world basically agreed
That limits had to be put on sovereignty
And those limits would be known as human rights
And a few years later in 1948 Universal Declaration of Human Rights
On which they are organized in suddenly
All eyes turn to human rights
Professor Samuel mine again
He says if you fast-forward to the 70s
Americans having fought Vietnam
Having solid themselves and doing so
Want to bring human rights to the world now
And the human rights movement was very exciting you know there were rock concerts in
You know it's Joan Baez and a lot
You know rock stars on
Pop culture icons get involved the Peace Prize
Price for 1977
As long
Is I am present
Jimmy Carter's inviting the government of the United States dissidents from Eastern Europe to visit the White House
Continue throughout the world to enhance human rights
It's it's a little new car that's very exciting to a lot of people and and rightly
Queso
It would be great if America could make the world a better place
So this brings us back to dali
I commandment
Peter and Peter Weiss
Trying to figure out how to bring dollies case to us courts that's the contacts
America is having this moment with human rights
Wanna bring it to the rest of the world
Someone someone in Peter's office to just using this old little law to get Justice for Dolly it seems obvious like
Course so I called an emergency meeting of the Santa stuff
Basically the idea was that
Some crimes
Like piracy
Was so bad that
Pet boarders didn't matter
Like anyone should be able to prosecute them and the US should be able to bring these people to court on behalf of the world
But I have to tell you that the majority of
Calling Samsung
We were slightly insane did your boss say like
It's all about Paraguay
Eventually just case gets in front of the federal circuit court
Does the federal court eastern district Brooklyn
And the day of the trial you stop hanging in the elevator at corn
Yes
I met him in the elevator
And I asked him
Why you do that to my brother
Why did you do that to him
Why
Equivalent answer sheet what shape
Anyway
Lemon decor
Keisha butter Waianae answering so what
Anacortes admitted autopsy reports
We went in there photography
Photography pictures
We've bring picture of him with the mattress
Alita was in the mattress time defeat in the hands ladies
Computer says that after he made his argument an interesting thing happened
The judge
Started to go back to his Chambers and
Before he got
Out of the country turn around
Interesting
Pancakes
So what happened
Well
The judge ruled against them
But they appeal to the second circuit
And ultimately
A judge orders Kenya to pay 10 million dollars to Dolly and her family
What they want
Yeah what happened was like a miracle
I was able to get Justice in United States
In the Florida case
They convinced the second circuit that the alien tort statute
Quest for human rights
They say look I'm torture is now like piracy
That's all an explosion of cases that mean in 1984
Granby Libyan Arab Republic and peace out
There was a case from Argentina called for TV Suarez Mason 1991
Guatemala 1993 Ecuador and Peru and 295 former Yugoslavia in 1999
Basically what you saw in the eighties and nineties and into the early 2000s is the cases from
All over the world started just like
Flooding into American Court
The reason this statute is so important is it at its American law
It gives American lawyers who want to use their legal training
Something to do with part of this
Lawyers can save the world
Wow
Practicing law looking at the role of the 80s
It's hard to underestimate just how much impacted
This is Katherine Gallagher also from the center for constitutional rights
35 years has become the source
Almost all significant human rights litigation
In the United States and indeed in the world
And that's John Bellinger
Legal advisor for the
Department of State
From 2005
Before Florida cuz there
Was very little that
Victims of human rights violations
Could do
There were a lot of folks
Especially in the American legal system who felt like America had never been a greater force for good in the
World
But
The rest of the world
Wasn't so sure
That's coming up
More perfect will continue in a moment
This is more perfect I'm Jedi home run
Back to the 2K peas Kelsey Padgett and Kelly Prime
Here's Kelly
Where we left it a lot of good just happened we have an explosion of cases
American human rights lawyers are feeling really good about themselves
But
Diplomacy
Is a delicate thing many foreign government
Including many Western democracy
John Dellinger again Great Britain Australia Germany
Switzerland
Would regularly complain
Tumi
As the legal advice with the state department that
They thought that the alien tort statute
Was in fact itself
A violation of international law
Because
It allowed
Us judges
To have jurisdiction over
Directions to Tad's
Absolutely nothing to do
With United
Instead of dialing it back
Human rights lawyers decided
Why not push it
Even further
Surrounding 25
Give me the big leap they decided that instead of just going after
Individuals with foreign government officials
They were going to use this law to go after foreign corporations
When the first alien tort statute cases were filed against corporations
These cases were really seeing as
Is slightly crazy
How can you do this these are corporations these are not government
These are not dictators
How can you see them under this law
Human rights lawyer said was
It always keeps showed us that this law is about modern-day Pirates
What better example of pirates do we have nowadays
The multinational corporation
If you want to go all the way you could say
Babies big
Massive entities that just can reach out the chemicals into any countries between jurisdiction move from one
The next to the next and brutal crimes like sometimes they Empower dictators
Sacramento crime
When you try and pin them down like when you want to hold them accountable
Banish
So yeah
All that sounds
Really
Abstract
For me it didn't really register like
Why you would go after a corporation
Until I heard this story
The story of cancer wewa
That even I grew up in a place with household in that my father was was a national figure because he was a right to know
Commentation newspapers
Just like Dolly can head this
Famously outspoken.
Social critic
Use a famous thorn in the side of the
The reason in this case
Military dictatorship
In Nigeria
New Year's Eve the military deposed the civilian democratically elected president
An 80s 90s Nigeria went through a
Series of military coups
And Kim's dad actually wrote this account that was like Fairy famous millions of people run
Country watched it
He would write articles about the
Andantino the subject of his birth is Collins and his television program
The inequalities of Nigeria political system
Situation of time Nigeria
Tons of oil under the grey
Estimated 30 billion dollars worth
Boil and in order for the military regime to get that
Out
They partnered with a division of shell companies in Nigeria as applying domestic gas
Generating electricity from was
The people who lived on the land where the oil was
They're really poor
Given
Barely any of this money against insult to injury
Uncheck
Oil production is creating an environmental disaster in our community
New Zealand
Is Loft
For the next Thousand Years father showing reporter ruin farmland
Q70
Oil still seeps to the surface
Nothing is going to grow here
You know that's it successful and has been devastated by all production in some places surface water contains
900 *
Accepted level of benzene
2 Kings dad you know he was writing articles about this he was speaking out about it
But eventually he decided
That was enough
And I need decided I think in the late 80s that he was going to take to the streets
Who lost the 1993 organized dogani day
For three hundred thousand people came out to protest
We are going to demand that right
Non violently
Over the next month
The protest keep going the escalated as tension increased I know it was badly beaten and then she'll
Too loud resulting in the closure of oil operations in the area
And they took millions of dollars with them
And the government depended almost solely on the revenues from
That's the one economic activity
And so
How long after the protest
Kim's dad was
Thrown into jail
And
Can junior he babykins frantically traveling the world trying to raise awareness of
Bad situation
Publicly put pressure on
On General abacha Nigeria head of state
November 10th 1995
2 years after his dad's been arrested
Annie's at the
International Conference New Zealand
Trying to
Wabi world leaders
And he says that after he just got this
Funny feeling
Walking across
One of the streets and I just saw the sun set
That evening
Beautiful sunset I see
Big Red
Sun
Just sinking into the bay
I'm dumb
Felt something go in my chest
And
I think I knew
I knew that something had happened
Cancel we were right in human Rights activist campaigner on behalf of his fellow tribesmen
Time this morning in the Nigerian prison
It says that world leaders spoke out
Prime Minister of England even Nelson Mandela
Unfortunate result to no avail
Nothing happened
Difficult to know what to do with all of that
How do you how do you get Justice full at what what happened to your father
You could argue
And
This is what lawyers later did ARG
But the only way to get Justice was not to go after the regime
What to do after
Show
And it's parent company Royal Dutch petroleum
In going after shell they claim that
Baby helps the Nigerian government do some
Horrendous things they claim that show aided and abetted the
Nigerian government
Kidnapping in
Torture and rely directly to the stuff or or jaded embedded so the claim is that they
Guns
Directions to buy guns
Well actually the allegation the claim is that
But still that's it that's not a
Rats that Cinderella things to like they claim that she'll wood
Call Lynn
Special Forces Unit of the Nigerian government that
Colloquy everybody was calling the kill and go mom go there claiming she was calling and hits yeah basically but she'll was like
Hand in hand with the governor
Of course she'll denies all this
And in 2002
People
I can
Put Moss Brothers
Lost family
You know and also surviving victims of all the Twilight State they banded together with some American lawyers
And brought a case under the island
They allege that she'll
Was essentially a hostess houmani generes
The enemy of
Of the human
Kind of race
And therefore
Could be tried in American courts
Yeah
And as you can imagine they got pushed back
In this case.
Challenged
All the way up to the Supreme Court
Ruger argument first this morning in case 10 1491 kiobel vs Royal Dutch petroleum
This case was actually argued twice but we're combining them here for Simplicity
So the basic issue in this case seems really simple at first
Can you use this law against Corporation
Like if you read the full article decisions
Like the pirate and slave trader before him
An enemy of all mankind
This is Justice Kagan actually reading from the Florida decision and saying you know we
The Court decide this is okay
The word today's Pirates
So the question was are corporations in that category
Baby considered today's Pirates
The principal issue before this court
Is whether a corporation can ever be held liable
For violating fundamental human rights Norms under the alien tort statute
Nigerians bringing the case
And it won't let me start by saying that
International human rights Norms that are at the basis that all the terrible crimes
All art agreed are crimes against humanity
My actions
They're not defined by whether the perpetrator is a human being or Corporation
Says that torture their today's Pirates
What about a group of torturous what about
Pirates Incorporated
What events led operation to buy
That's Justice Breyer basically agreeing that in this case to differentiate between like
A corporation doing bad things and a person doing bad things it's kind of silly
Air power play
The question is who are today's Pirates
He says Adolf Hitler was like a pirate
Who is there The Dread Pirates of our time
Billions for specialty Appliance of human rights cases from Florida on
Is part of a trend in the world today the trend in the world today is poured universe
Crystal Justice for people that nnn corporations that violate these kinds of
That's the trend in the United States has been the leader in our government is proclaimed our leadership position
We thought the argument went extremely well and we really did not see how
We should lose
But then
It was shells turn trouble is that
The choice to pursue corporations
Santiam on again the goose that laid the golden egg
Because on the one hand
It makes sense to shift
Two corporations they have the money
On the other hand corporations
Wolf use their money
To hire the best lawyers they can buy
Where is like
Kathleen Sullivan mr. chief justice and may it please the court
Kathleen Sullivan got up there she and the defense team basically
Sidestep the whole issue of whether corporations
Should or should not be considered Pirates whether this law should or should not be applied to corporations
They actually went
Bigger
They started talking about all the reasons why I actually use in the 80s for non-american crimes
I feel really bad idea
For anyone
I came down to three main points
Reciprocity
Battle United States Court
Anywhere in the world regardless of the place of the conduct
The other nations of the world 19
To do the same to us basically if we can take people from other countries and try them in our courts
What's stopping them from doing that to us
To the principal against International friction is at its highest
Nightmare you're basically saying other countries that you didn't elect win like them either frankly I didn't vote for them
You didn't vote for them they were appointed
And now
They're going to be patrolling international law are we really comfortable with that and I want to stress that
The point is that the u.s. is projecting here
Our law on to foreign countries
And finally
On the most
Basic level
What distance does the kids like that have in the course of the United States
How is any of our business
To the United States what's the weather at the point that really jive with Justice Alito
The United States has nothing to do
In a way
In that moment
He's captured how
America hits
Shifted
We didn't want to pretend to be that shining City on the hill anymore
That was over
For the court in case number 10 1491
Kiobel and others vs Royal Dutch petroleum company and others
Indian the court decided to rule in favor of shell and Royal Dutch petroleum
Wrote the decision in 1822
But no nation has ever yet pretended to be the Customs moron of the whole world the guardian of morals
The whole world
It's just a matter of common sense that when Congress passes a law it is passing a law that applies in the United States
You're not some other country
Unless
The law tells us otherwise
Regulating conduct abroad
Serious foreign-policy consequences
And courts are and should be reluctant to invite such consequences
Unless that is was Congress clearly intended
The wasting no reason is that the extraterritorial conduct conduct that's outside the United States
Isn't going to count
It had there has to be some relationship
To the United States
Basically they took the 80s and they clipped its wings
Do you feel like Z
I'll tell you the read that they start bringing my mind and I'm wondering if you would agree or you
Stupid
The sense that I have with the ATS is that
It came about in the moment great idealism and Hope
And now after the fog has cleared so to speak
It seems to represent not
Hope it knife day
The fact that we think
We can change the world
It's that easy
The 80s and that it's falling out of favor somehow represents in a way that way in which we fall
And had a kind of sober Awakening
I wonder do you feel like human rights
In the way we understood it is dead
Now it's
I think it's transformed our idealism
But maybe
The disaster in kiobel was a moment of kind of stepping back
To think a bit more broadly
Play about how we can make the world a better
And Samuel moyn says we do need to rethink some things
Maybe frankly it's a little dishonest to judge
Pretend the America brings Justice to the world
America was founded on the idea of
Human right now which was the first nation in the hist
For the world to be found it explicitly on such an idea which is
It's not really true nns Dave presented their cases
The human rights movement leaves out how much
The United States has often been involved in the evil they're portraying in court
So at the very least he says that what this decision shows us is that
Before we run around judging other countries
To take a hard look at ourselves
More importantly and we can avoid the question what's the best bang for our buck
It's just not
Proven yet that 80s is it
He said all you really had was
A few individuals who won cases and by the way most of them never got any money
Really
Yeah
Dali didn't get paid
You know after she won
Kenya flag
Again
And so in a way that the alien tort statute didn't have far to fall to begin with
Symbolic victory
You could definitely see it that way
Do you feel like you got Justice
Did what did you get here today
Badali Florida good
Doesn't
You didn't get
Any money back correct
Yeah but it never was for important for the money
Indecent the money won't pay
Don't blame me rafelito
A fine
Jacalito
Not normal you live album
I know how to say that they need some time but
There was a tree song
Yes
I lost a brother
Baidu
When we won that case he knew you're in United States I get so many other brothers NC
Easter through all over the world
Nothing fine
Jacalito
Deviant
Diet
Pollito Leaf forever
Greasers Kelsey
Padgett and Kelly Prime
So the debate about the 80s and America's role in the world continues the court just heard our
Arguments in another 80s case this term
Call Jester Viera Bank
It's a suit brought by nearly six
Thousand plaintiffs against a Jordan based Bank
Accused of financing terrorism
That the court will use the case to further limit the 80s but
Dermals piercing
Okay more perfect is produced by me Chatham rod with Suzie lechtenberg Julia Longoria
Alex overington and Sarah Carey
This episode was produced with Kelsey Padgett
Insignificant editing Juju from Jenny Lawton take a Jenny we also had help from Elie mystal Christian Fair
Linda hirshman David Gable and Michelle Harris
Supreme Court audio is from Oye
A free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Leadership support for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
Additional music for this episode with by Nicholas Carter
Turn on a sad note, Sarah we were Junior who appears in this episode
Passed away in October 20th