WNYC Studios
The Honorable
Supreme
This is more perfect
I'm Jad abumrad
Today a little bit of a departure
Maybe it's more of an addendum
So we just released an episode about citizens united
Which is one of the most
Argued about cases
History in this this was a case
We lie about
1st Amendment
Whether we should limit the First Amendment
No in that case
He had this tension
Adjust
Is Kennedy who saying don't touch it don't touch it.
Touch it
I don't care if all this money comes into our political system
Don't touch the first two men
BHS
Desoutter
Sing
I don't know maybe we should touch it because sometimes
Your freedom
Impinges on my equality
And should those two things be in balance
It's a
Fascinating and
Important,
Station
And it was one that we were having internally
At the team while we were making that up
There's a certain point we decided
What sucks you take that conversation in
Make a live event
Something that we
We did a few times in the runner-ups
Season 2
We would have the public debates
Indy WNYC greenspace
I want to play you
Some excerpts from that debate
That we had about free speech
And we did it Sir Classic debate format one person took one side 1/4
Another
In a questions were
Should the government do more in this day in age to limit Free Speech should
Twitter
Dumor should face
Dumor should all of us collectively
Be doing more to stop
Dangerous hateful
Full speech or is this precisely the mum we have to stand up louder and prouder
Protect that
Speech even if we hate it
Two before we got into it
I took a poll the audience
Everybody thinks that you're right to free speech
Especially online okay people
Say some bad things
But you're right
To free speech
Should remain pretty much Unlimited
Those of you who feel that way
Make some noise
All right you guys are you guys are Thunders over here
Is it more accurate
Those of you who don't think should be limited go
Okay
Now those of you on the flip side those of you think there should be some clear
Hard
Limits
Easy easy
Don't you think there should be some clear limits
On what you can
Say online Make some noise
All right
Okay thank you
Good sense of where we're starting
All right let me introduce her to bitters for round one the question is should the government limit online free speech taking one side of that
Question is
Mr. Elie mystal
Are legal editor at more perfect also
And editor above the law
A site for legal newsies on one side
Of the stage
End of the question
On the other
Mr. Ken White
A First Amendment litigator criminal defense attorney at brown white and Osborn in Los Angeles
He has joined us here
From the Left Coast
He's a former Federal prosecutor he runs the free speech and criminal justice blog Pope at.com
All right
Let us begin
What's up with you Ellie is there something wrong with the First Amendment would you say
I don't have a problem with the First Amendment it was a beautiful thing written for white people who want to overthrow the government site
I have a problem with absolutist
Who want to elevate threats harassment
Impulse for genocide
The level of a secret right
I do not think that the First Amendment prohibits us from preventing a Nazi
I'm getting a permit to Rally
Any more than I would think
Did the Second Amendment prevents us
From having a sociopath not get a gun permit
Okay
Absolutism is
Absolutely wrong
Honda Civic
Okay element style strong beginning
What do you think
Why don't know what absolute is Ellie is talking about the last one I know is Hugo Black and he died nineteen
Anyone we have well-established
Narrow
Exceptions
For the first time
And they are narrow for a reason
We got them they rode On The Backs
The powerless
Being suppressed by the powerful
All of the types
The restrictions that Ellie would like
Are ones that have historically been used
Against communist against labor protesters
Against War protesters against minorities
And everyone else
The Nazis aren't the ones in danger
From the tight
Restrictions la
Is suggesting
Okay there are the two basic positions
Let's get the debate started
Alright Ellie start start a sock
Explain why you think that
Hateful speech fake news
Shouldn't be protected by the first
Can just admit it just agreed
That we already regulates
Speech at some love
So really all were debating about tonight the only thing that's even Up For Debate is where we want to draw that wine
Henwood draw that line so it protects
Nazis
I would draw that line so it protects
Us
From the knot
Let's start with a pretty simple example
Fire
Just kidding
I'm sure you've all heard that the thing that you can say
Is that you can't shout fire on the crowded theater
But actually Under Armour
Current laws
Probably can because our current standard is that what is unprotected or things that lead to direct inside
Excitement
Eminem
Lawless Acts
That's a very high bar
So I can probably say fire when I probably can't say is
Fire
Kill who you must to survive
That would probably get me in
But the fire analogy comes from an older standard older than the one that I just quoted
It comes from Oliver Wendell Holmes
Some of you might
And his standard when he use the you can't falsely shout fire in a crowded theater
Analogy
His standard was false
And dangerous
Speech that is
False and dangerous
Is not protected by the Constitution
I think that's where the Winans I think that's an eminently reasonable line I think that we had a hundred fifty years of a free republic with that line
So I want the line
Where
Dangerous lies
Or not
Protected by the
I don't want the government deciding what's a line of what
Trip may I remind you we are currently led by a President
Who thinks global warming is a Chinese hoax to Corner the tungsten
And that's why I don't want the government deciding
What to suppress based on its
Decision about what is true or not
Ellie refers
To the fire in a crowded theater Justice Holmes famous quote
Let's remember what he was talking about he was using that quote
You can't shout fire in a crowded
To justify jailing a man who is protesting World War II by handing out flyers suggesting that people
Just the draft
That was a clear danger that the government saw
If you don't think
That is plausible
That the government would be suppressing the same type of speech now if you gave it
The power if you handed it to them
Out of fear of not
Then just look at what happened after the protest
Just last year
The alt right
Annunaki
Rose there were massive protests
Response
In our largely republican-dominated State legislatures leaped into action
And it's 17 places
They proposed
Heavily
Punitive anti-protest Bells
Including porch Army examples
Making it easier for you to get off if you run over a protester
That's what the government does
With the power to suppress
Speech when you let the government decide what
Trip I think you just proved
That our current first amendment standard doesn't do
Bull
To actually protect protest
All it does is protect Nazis
You want to talk about the Oliver Wendell Holmes case
What's talked about where our current standard come from
It's relatively recent 1969
Brandenburg V Ohio
Now what was that case I said 1969 you probably thought it was
We're making it know it was for Clans
Brandenburg was a klansman
He was all
Making plans Satanist
Somebody arrested his ass for being a klansman he got convicted for inciting violence
Anacortes
He's just a klansman
We really need a new standard that protects the right of plans men to threaten black people
In 1969
But you see
L you know that's not
How to write case
That's the one that's best
Your
The right cases
Is 12
The right case
What is 12 years earlier
Yates vs
People convicted
For becoming members of the Communist Party
Under the Siri
Some ideas can be punished
As clear and present danger
Even when there is no imminent advocacy
Wrongdoing Yates
Built the wall that eventually Brandenburg
Completed
Brandenburg V outlier
The one that shows how the power is consistently used by the government can you explain to me a sinner that allows me to stop playing
Cuz that's what I want
Like me
How I can make plans but not sitting in a field then I think we can agree more than we disagree
The first amendment is
Here to protect minorities are you kidding me
The Constitution even think about black people, 13th Amendment I think as we all know so okay you're saying that
You would like to change the standard so that
Will it help me understand okay
How would you have it what would the standard be
I can give you an example
The president is a canyon
That's balls but it's not particularly dangerous and so we can let that
Kind of slide right
Hillary Clinton is running a pedophile ring out of a pizza shop
Do not pass go do not collect 200
The monster
Okay babe
Bethesda to very clear examples
The idea of falseness and danger
Can get pretty squishy
I mean
Can I call up an example
If you get if you guys don't mind so
The daily Stormer
Which is a very
Popular Neo-Nazi site
There was a situation where they basically took a Jewish woman
A real estate agent
That's the thing right there you can see on the screens and they superimpose it on image of Auschwitz
They published her name they publish her kids
They said hateful things like we will drive you to Suicide they called Fraser at Roloff
On her
Does that qualify for you and doesn't qualify for you
Can
Would you limit that kind of
I think a lot of the
Comments
Sent her we're true threat
That is a reasonable person would see them as statements
Actually 10
To do her harm
I think some of the speech about her
Miche incitement Stan
That is intended to
And likely cause imminent Lawless action
Against
But ideas
However he
Can't be true or false
And it's not for
For the government to regulate
Weather ideas
Opinions
Are true or false
Real true idea
Climate change not real
This idea we can make these decisions I don't think that we need to
Your standard requires and I and I have unfortunately because I am black on the internet
I haven't fortunately had to deal
With some
True threats are not true threats some
Trying to wrestle with this issue when I go to the cops to try to ask
Production
Wrestle with this issue of what actually protected speech and what's actually not protect
Am I popping with the current standards
Is that basically wait until they start shooting at me before they stop them
I want to stop them before they start shooting I want to stop them before they start driving their cars into crowd of protesters
Because by then it's too late
I want them to stop to but
Here's the problem
With a history of America being
What it is
With a power having been used in the past being
What is what possesses you to think that if you give this broader power to attached
The government it's going to be used the way you wanted to be
I'd rather have this debate in 2020
Okay
Is today all right now you've heard Ellie and Ken's points the question is
Did you change your mind
Who thinks
The government should limit what we say online with your Samoyed
Let me get those of you who actually lean farther in that direction over the course of this argument
Let me hear from you guys
Stop lab you got a few views
Those of you who do not think there should be limits placed from the government by Us online buzzer
I think
We may have a winner
For the first round
I'm going to declare that you can white are the winner
First-round give it up for Ken white First Amendment attorney former Federal prosecutor and founder of Towpath.
Thank you for doing this gif
Pizza coming up we're going to ship
The question little bit
Set of asking
What should the government do about
Abbreviation of limited
Now we're going to ask what your Twitter
Did what your Facebook
You know
With all the fake news that's happening all the hate speech is collecting online
Should they limit
Free speech
More than
That is coming up after the break
More perfect
It's more perfect time Chatham rod
Let's get back
Back to our debate
A free speech debate
WNYC greenspace
Okay so round
We're going to take that same basic question that we asked around 1 but now we're going to transpose it
Whatever we think
About the First Amendment
It does Place limits on
The government
But not so much on Twitter
Are Facebook so the question is
Should Twitter and Facebook or other social media companies
Severely limit online
Or should they
I want to pull you guys for it's just against we have a baseline to start from
Those of you people watching on Facebook
Do you think the sight of which you are on right now should aggressively
Limit
The speech that you might type
Take take the online poll
Desert in the audience same question should Facebook and Twitter be allowed to severely limit
Online speech to find it as you will
Okay doesn't you think he'll know
All right
That's I guess
I got a kind of acid are mixed
Santa where we're at in the audience okay so here to debate this topic with Ellie is Karin mcsherry
Legal director of the Electronic Frontier Foundation which is committed to defending civil liberties in a digital world give it up for her
Alright so
Corrine look start with you why what do you think about the prospect
Twitter or Facebook stepping into
The takedown Liza
Takedown hates
I think it's a very dangerous path
Fortunately we're already well along
I think in moments of Crisis and I think we're in a moment of Crisis right now we look to Simple Solutions for very complex
6 problems
And we are often
Sorry
And I think that is where we are right now the internet
Grew up
The way it did for mostly good
I would argue
Because
The platforms and the intermediaries mostly stayed
Neutral
If we have a world in which
Facebook Twitter Google Instagram put themselves in the position of a quart
Decide what speed should be up
What speed shouldn't
We're going to walk down a dangerous path because
Those decisions those tactics
Wood evitable
Be used
Against speech that we would support
For one thing
They will be inevitably
Used eventually by governments private censorship does not stay private
If it comes
Public censorship
Almost inevitably
And the third reason is really practical
They're already doing it and they're doing it
Badly
All kinds of Louisville speech is being taken down everyday Google and Facebook can't save us from the Nazis
We have to do it
Okay thank you Korean Ellie what do you think
The First Amendment does not apply to Twitter or Facebook
Anybody who tells you that they have a constitutional right
To say what they want on Twitter is an idiot
Which waterfalls Waze
They don't just want
Free speech
They want
Consequence
Free speech
They want to be able to say their vile trash
And still keep their jobs and still keep their homes and still get the girl
These people
All right
We should have Twitter at least at the level of a Jets game
Those are the basic sides
Start
The debate
Hiker and take us off
The problems here are legion and almost start with the ones that I that I just
Touch on briefly before
The reality is
That we can all target people that we hate right
Right now but if we think that the rules that Twitter and Facebook and all those guys are going to come up with are going to be used
I guess the beach that we support
We are foolish it's already happening Community standards complaints are used against valuable speed all the time I know
No because I hear about it everyday in my
Job
Then the related problem to that is when you get your lawful speech taken down you don't have any options you don't know how to get your stuff
Put back up do we have courts
We don't have a right of appeal
We don't have any challenge
These performers have the right to host any speech they want they actually have the First Amendment right
The host any speech they want
But
I think his users we want him to use that right wisely that's not happening right now
User I want them to stop Nazis
That's really all I can learn about the and stop them from
Mercante
They can't that's foolish
Sorry
Lyndhurst
Here's why you know what I know they can't because they're trying and they're failing over and over they cannot tell
The difference between hate speech and Reporting on high-speed get taken down and suspended
When they're doing perfectly
Waffle
I think one of the reasons why this is so important that we demand better from Facebook from Twitter from Reddit
Is that the reason why we're seeing so many more Nazis now
Is because of these platforms have allowed them to organize
There was a reason why
The clan was on the decline
20 years ago
Because you because wearing a hood and going out to meet your friends the middle
Feel by Brandenburg did
Wasn't really how the modern society was going
Expedition Twitter and Facebook and the site and read it came along
And now they have a way to talk
Talk to each other and realize that no I actually hate black people too though so do I let's hang out
No screw these people there's no there's no cost
Too Short reason why Twitter should allow them to exist or Facebook or whatever there is no business reason why Twitter or face
Whatever she allowed
Get them the F out
You know what I think I think about it
One of these we heard in the wake of Charlottesville with a lot of
Please folks got radicalized online
So why would the prospect of them getting radicalized online what would bounce set out in terms of the
Failure
That these sites are doing
I'm curious if you talk more about
Okay so a couple things I just want to respond to
My view is if white supremacist and clansmen and Nazis are organizing I weigh before they were doing it out in
Public where I can see them and I can challenge them and I can respond to them and law enforcement will say the exact
Same
Think people who fight terrorism say it's much better for the for the you know the
People to speaking publicly for the radical to be radicalizing where you can see them
They're going to organize anyway
Okay
So would you rather do with a student secret on the open I prefer.
Going finally make their own Nazi website
Wright's make your own Nazi thing right so that when
Whenever I get tense agree with me
Whatever the government is ready to stop these people still of all pre-registered they would have all said
Indeed.com
So we can continue The Silo conversation that we're having right now which is a big part of where I want to see you try
I think that's
That sounds very nice and it's a good talking point but in reality I think that's very very dangerous for our society we need
People to be talking to each other when they only talk to people who agree with them they never change their mind
Proven time and time again I feel like that is such
A happy
Slappy white version of this story of if we just talked to these people we can convince them that maybe black people
Shouldn't be sent off to prison camp
Once or twice and the rest of the time they're running cars in the people it doesn't happen nearly not long enough
We have gay marriage equality now
Because people talk
But it helps what I want to answer Jazz question cuz I think what you're asking is for an
Example of why I'm worried about how I wanted you are worried against Elie's work
So the weather works
Mountain and the way that is likely to continue to work as this other social media companies employ a combination of humans and
Mostly algorithms to try to figure out what's bad speech and what's good
And they
Message
So they end up taking down this statement all white people are racist
As an example of hate speech but they won't take down
Puma show the previous ones this from a congressman
Who said not a single radicalized Islamic suspect should be granted enter measure of quarter
Etcetera etcetera nasty stuff right they can't tell the difference
And that's what happens in there is an app tips Republic I hope you guys are all propublica supporters and fans cuz they're great
They did a detailed study to look at Facebook
Whose policies
And they found out that among other things their training their moderators
2 in some instances protect white men
Over black children
Yes where we are right now that's what we want to endorse that's we want to encourage I don't
I will stipulate that there are many examples of them
Getting it wrong they get it wrong or not great at this
Job yet
But we live in a real world where the actual not talk about Twitter
We live in the world
Were the actual cops
Get it wrong every freaking day and in my most radical statement
I'm not saying let's get rid of the cops
Cuz they don't know what they're doing
No I'm saying let's get better cops and for Twitter I'm saying let's get better Twitter
So they don't get it wrong some
Do you want to talk about letting the perfect be the enemy of the good
Just because Twitter and Facebook have not gotten to the level
Yet whether able to effectively police seized
Doesn't mean they should just stop trying
What we have where we are right now is
Thousands of accounts
Are being suspended
Everyday
Let's just say a relatively small percentage of those are for perfectly lawful
That's a lot of waffles Peach
That's a lot that we have authorized
Twitter and Facebook and everyone else to take them and encourage them to and keep in mind I want to say one more thing that I said before but I'm
Want to emphasize it
Once we start down this path
You think that this is going to stay within the decision-makers at Silicon Valley you are dreaming I mean that's bad enough I'm not actually sure why
Why we all want
Silicon Valley to make decisions about what's pee
Peaches okay for
All the rest of us
What even got to start it's not going to stop there
Governments are going to come in when they see
That Google Facebook Twitter can easily take down
Accounts they're going to say okay
Could you do that for us
This doesn't
Somebody needs to stop these people and I refuse to believe that we live in a country where
Take question here in the back
If Facebook emailed you and said you can be in charge of what
Considered you know
A speech that is either less
Afdah poorest
Taken down you could build
You know whatever team of people
Would you accept
That would you think that
But that could
Create something that
You would be satisfied with or not
Ofo
I was Queen of the world
Hard to turn that down
I think even I would have trouble in all instances being perfect about what was
Loss of speech and what wasn't sweet but that actually isn't my main concern is that even I could then potentially be required by a
The government
2 then use that algorithm
For other purposes and I'll be really dangerous but here's the one thing that I would say in this is where I think we agree
Is that if I was Queen of the world
And I was
Running any of these companies one of the things I would absolutely do
Is putting much better
Processes for
Appeal for people to challenge when things are taking down rocks
This isn't just a
Speech issue
It's a due process issue because
Let's face it
Of course these aren't you know official government forms we all understand that but nonetheless this is how we talk to each other
These are our public spaces
And in this public spaces it's really important when your account get suspended when you get taken offline
To be able to
Get back up what you're doing is perfectly legal
And right now the reality is and I know this cuz I hear from him
All the time
It's very confusing you don't know who to appeal to you don't know who you don't know why you're taking down half the time
And you don't know what
What to do on the far right
Hi I just wanted to get your opinions on
Money
Because I hear a lot of talk about the
Does being
A speech issue or not but I think we're platforms the social media platforms I think it's
Really all about money
And it's about
Followers
And young kids are getting rape threats and
Threats and that they eventually
End in suicide I think that this has to do
With money I think there's
A bigger issue
And I just don't
Hear anyone talking about it and I just wanted to know
Thought about that
I think that that's that's really a real pressure point cuz I think
Elijah Cummings
Genuinely so
Do you want comfortable making money from
From hate
But unfortunately we still have a problem and I'm going to give you a sample from an article I just read yes
Conversation Piece about Google and how it runs advertising and search and so on
From talking points memo
Talking points memo mentioned that you know one of the problems that they have because these processes are so a pig
They survived because of Google advert
Them to write their legitimate site trying to do good for the world they survive because of Google app
Advertising they keep getting penalized
For hate speech because they're reporting
On hate speech
Specifically Dillon
Dylann roof
Situation
So y'all read the robot.
But no it is because we agree to the robots are bad but I think that we can all agree that talking points memo
Is a decent site
Infowars on Heather had if Google and Facebook and whatever slam them
Why would that why would that be so hard
If you really don't think
That we yet have the technology and the resources necessary
In order to
Police
These sites better
How about we go the other direction how about we just out
People
How about you just if you can if you're going to view Twitter going to tell me you can't tell who's threatening to kill me
Just tell me where it is
Just tell me who it is and I will handle it myself
What's wrong with that
See now he's just trying to piss me off
So we're talking about is now a step further its
Social media companies and intermediaries by the way all the
People that you interact with
They take it upon themselves
Two out yet
Write to pierce your anonymity
That is profoundly profoundly dangerous
Anonymity Anonymous speech is the most probably the most important form of political speech that we have
The ability
To speak
Especially online
Without fear retaliation means that you have the ability to speak your truth
If we out people if we
Except
That social media companies should be judge and jury over that should just
Expose people to the world without any choice without any recourse because once your outage
Sting to have a society
Protect ourselves
From these people
It's called Shame
We could
Shame them into being part of the her
If I didn't want to be part of the hurt we could know who they are and say hey guess what you're no longer part of the hurt
Shame is a powerful weapon that we used to have a Twitter is taken away from us
And that is why these
These people are allowed
2 *
That weapon was also used to persecute minorities all over there and everything was always you
Minorities at some point
We used to stop naughty that's just a
Walkthrough used to persecute minorities when they were paid by the hour or I'll call you from a good thing
The one thing we have always understood in this country and this is before the 1st Amendment
Is the importance
I'm anonymousspeech
All right let me just jump in for so I can leave out weave a question here on the right
I just want to say that like
Is there a moral reason
Twitter
The government
Lean towards
And I personally am someone who
Do you still have
Abhorrent
And I was raised
Is fundamental Trish
And My Views about gay people
Had I spoken them on
Probably would have
Put off some
And it was
Not Shane
The change my mind
Encountered
People who are engaging
Who treated me like a
Even though
Had back
Open Twitter
And it changed my mind
And I don't know if you guys familiar with the Westboro
Interstate Fateh
Casein one
They have really the worst views
Any group
Considers himself
And there
Person who ran their Twitter is a friend of mine
Megan Phelps
Roper
She has a great story
About how using Twitter
Essentially like
Spread terrible hate
Saying things like fake
God for aids for killing date
But it was through Twitter and through the argument
When she got in the through the relation
She got in
That she found a way out of that bubble she lived
And now is
Out in the world doing amazing work
If what you want Ellie happen
That's rule that you want to shut up that klansman do you want to get rid of
He doesn't go away
The mold grows in the shadow
And it's
Only in the Sun
You know it's only
It's only when you get it out in the open and we have this
Conversation
As a former believer and some of the stuff
I don't lose heart like we can have our minds J
We can we can
Be convinced
Of the truth
I respect her story and I'm very glad that some that you were able to
To to to get to where you are
However
Turns out that I believe what you want me to believe
For good so I don't know 2829 yours
Of my life
I am a 40 year old black man I am sick
Of being the educational PBS after school special
The racist white people
Gay people are sick of being the ABC Afterschool special for white people
Women are sick of being the after school special training teach the white man why they also should have rights
It is simply no longer acceptable
For you to expect other people just trying to go about
Posting their dinner
Recipes on Facebook
It's ridiculous for you to think that we should still have
The burden of educating you
You should go get educated somewhere
That can't be on us all the time
And I'm willing to do it I'm willing to do it here
I'm a hater I'm willing to do it in in in public I'm actually I'm leaving to go to a bar
And have a drink with
People that I can't stand
But at some point when I just want to like get on Facebook and see the Mets score
I shouldn't have to hear your b*******
Okay
I think that was what
He was saying
At all
Microphone
I think he was just saying silos bad
We should all be together and then
No I think that
No I think we don't talk to each other
Nobody's mind Everett
Changes
Imma jump in now I think I think Aaron Curran have done all day
Wait you guys
Who thinks that
Twitter and Facebook and said should take a strong hand in severely limiting online
He says that you think so clock
Those of you who disagree with the a****** clapping to your left
Make some noise
I believe that mean
Means that you are the victor
Thank you to all
Elie mystal more perfect
Legal editor and
Executive editor
Text Erin mcsherry from the Electronic Frontier Foundation and Ken white popehat. Com
This episode was produced with Elaine Chan and a very excellent Folks at WNYC greenspace
Mixing help this week from Louis Mitchell
Supreme Court audio is from Oye free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute of Cornell
Leadership support more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial
Next week