Listener-supported WNYC
Be Studios
Leadership support for more perfect
Is provided by the Joyce Foundation
This is more perfect I'm jad abumrad this week
Conversation about a mystery
Chemistry actual is connected to one of my favorite stories we've done so far
The political Thicket the political Thicket Court must not enter the political Thicket in the imagery
Be at the thicket is that you know the deer very proudly with his new horns
Goes into the thicket
Gets entangled
Can never get out
Frankfurters claim was
Once the courts are in there will be nothing Beyond it and someday
The courts will be forced to declare winners and losers a very high-profile action
If you haven't heard the story definitely hit pause right now go back in the feed find the story called political Thicket
Listen to is
Definitely one of my favorites
Essentially the story of a case that many people
Point to as being the first time that the Supreme Court got into politics
Text with soiled themselves with politics
Switch
Make a beeline from that moment to Bush V Gore
That case
So dramatic
For a court that too
Literally broke
To Justice
The shattered
2 human being
And one of those two justices
Justice Felix Frankfurter
Is at the center of the mystery we're about to tell you about
Just to give you a sense of who he was
Play you a little clip from that earlier story
He was extremely smart towering figure but as a person
Justice
Justice Frankfurter
He wasn't necessarily
The nicest
Person I heard that from everyone I talk
I always call him a Bantam rooster
He was a difficult Krusty figure
A little bit of a pouch
Was one of the most
Condescending egotistical of just
It says
So Justice Felix Frankfurter not the nicest guy but
Important
Presided over a ton of really important cases like for example
Brown V Board of Education
Big one
Being the slow March towards desegregating our school system
Any of the mystery today deals with his papers
These are the notes that you took while he was on the bench you know
Drafts of decisions that he wrote the Scentsy Road a memos back and forth with the other justices
Maybe the notes you took when they were all in that secret conference room that they go to when they're arguing
Got stuff to like people like us are like a man we got to get those paper
But in this case
There are no paper
Which brings us to
The story of one of the biggest
Heists
In Supreme Court history
The Vanishing
Of Justice Felix Frankfurter papers
From the Library of Congress
One day they were there
And then poof
Never seen people have been like Where What Where What Where are they what happened who took them
Harvard historian in New Yorker staff writer to Lepore
We may remember I was a big part of our guns episode we just released
She
Recently tried to get to the bottom of this paper caper
And more perfect
Producer Sean rameswaram
Talk to her about it
In such an ecosystem where
It's so hard to gain access
To these papers to these documents
At some point someone might try
To gain access to them
Unlawfully
Which
You once wrote a wonderful story about that I was hoping you could maybe
Retail and I I was thinking here we are telling stories
Maybe
Just imagine we're sitting by the fire
He can hear it
Crackle in the evenings crickets
Westfield
There it is there it is
So the largest heist in the history of the Library of Congress
I
Guarantee
You would not have guessed
If I do not have gas
That it was a papers of Felix Frankfurter
More than a thousand pages
A Frank for his papers were stolen from the Library of Congress
An early 1970s they have never been recovered.
Single page of them
It was a
Kind of extraordinary Heist
It was investigated by the FBI they had a prime suspect they can be know how there was a grand jury called
Extensive investigation involved the nation's leading journalist
Involve other members of the Court the nation's leading legal Scholars
We're questioned and were part of the investigation
The whole thing unravels
Days
Hours
Before the Saturday night Massacre and the
Explosion of Watergate
And was quickly forgotten
Does all of this this immense personality this historic figure
Did this plan to why it was his papers that were stolen or were they just the ones that were in the library the right time for
Someone to steal yeah I don't think we know that unless the
Mystery really solved
And I feel like I got so
Close
What did you mean what what didn't you have to put it all together
Can you reveal that
I guess
We think about it
We're trying to solve a staff
You need to know the motive of the thief
And to know the mode of the thief you need to know what was stolen
But in frankfurters
Case
His papers and only really just got to the Library of Congress
So when the papers disappeared for a long time nobody even notices
I'm really proud of the nation probably have been letting people look at them because it's then you can start to reconstruct with Missy
What's clear from what was missing of these more than a thousand pages
Is that it was the best stuff
And so one theory that the FBI had early on was
I was trying to make money cuz you could like
All of it frankfurters corresponds with Lyndon Johnson
Princeton
Was missing as presidential signature
You could sell that I mean where you going to sell these things another question but like maybe that that's the case
The next theory that the library working with the FBI
So
It's a scholar
And a scholar who just
Cool
Mike wants to have this stuff
And doesn't want anybody else to
Like a fanatic like a collector
Lego yeah Lego just
You know sometimes when you
Will you work an iPod just for like a journalist you don't want to be scooped
Scholarship the same thing as an incredibly juicy
Imagine
Reading frankfurters diary
And finds out
Okay
Frankfurter
God I slept with William Douglas his wife or something I don't know
Forever
You don't like something to treat me like I'm going to write a biography of Frankfort and this is how I'm going to sell it
The last thing you would want would be for another scholar
I have finding the archives all the time like
Shoot
They put it back in the box and you give back to the library and you know it someone else is going to call you
I'm never going to get
And you just got to forget about it cuz you
Imagines to call someone else
Maybe something like that like that you could imagine
A journalist if we can imagine
Are you just can't resist and it was new security
The library
I thought I interviewed everybody was investigated by the FBI
I need these Larry stars that like yeah
I have photo copy Xerox machine
Early xerox machine
And you'd like put a nickel in it but they would just let you take
Folders download
Down the hall and episode of stairs and through double doors and go to the bathroom at the back door of the bathroom and there was this one xerox machine
You can put a nickel in
And you just walked out the door with your folders
You can't do that. Anywhere
And it was this case it actually led to a cracked
So
The FBI quickly came to the
Conclusion that
Whoever
Had bothered to do the incredible labor of stealing all those paper
There's a lot of smoke
Women someone who both really wanted to write about Frankfurter
Had found something incredibly juicy
But had been forwarded
Bye
The kind of
Cabal of Frankfurter
These people are called the hot dogs
They really are sitting by the campfire now it's on the hot dogs go on the
We've been
Sharpening of wooden stick
Star green wooden sticks
Now you put on the hot dogs and roast them
The hot dogs are the former Clerks of Frankfort
They are known as hot dogs and they loved him
Because like many an ornery person you know apparently was
Very stand-up person to work with
And they were so kind of protecting his legacy
Anyway so that the case is kind of just gets steamrolled by Watergate
But
This is kind of like the Alex Jones theory of the Felix rings
Diligent legal Scholars
Is this the story together
And I
It's a little conspiracy theory minded but it's not Beyond The Pale
So one of the pieces of paper that
Appears to have been missing from
Frankfurters
Is really interesting
And was potentially quite damaging
To William
Brink
Who had been nominated to serve on the
And who's
Confirmation
Proceedings were happening right at the time
The frankfurters papers
Rancho
What was controversial
Rehnquist
Was
The issue that had forwarded Nixon's earlier
Judicial appointments
Which was his relationship
Desegregation
Nixon who will recall
Pursuing the southern strategy trying to woo
White Southern Democrats
I nominated some potential justices who were segregation especially had been segregationist earlier
Frank was not but rank was served as a clerk for Robert Jackson in 1950s
And asked by Jackson to prepare a memo about Brown V board
Rent Pacific Mo on Richey Road
I realize it is an unpopular
A nun humanitarian position
For which I have been excoriated by liberal colleagues
But I think Plessy V Ferguson was right
I should be reaffirmed Plessy V Ferguson 1896
Decision legal principle of separate but equal
This is not Jim Crow legalize this is mentioned
And so it's probably
You know in Newsweek and didn't read the comics
Blue Savannah real big problem for wrinkles during his confirmation
Drink with work very hard
Too quiet that's
He said
I wasn't expressing my own views
I was asked to write a memo about
Justice Jackson's
Ann Jackson
Sakroots former secretary Elsie Douglas
She told reporters
That's just a lie
Mike Jenkins and ask his clerks to write
Down memos about what Jackson should think Jackson Hewitt he thought he has his Clerks
To tell him what they thought
So he could
Alli Breen if you could come to liberate on the most
Positions that they would present him with
So when was the send a letter to the Senate Judiciary Committee tried to
Explain all of this
Senate Judiciary Committee threatens to hold
Hearings over the holiday or after Christmas is December of 1971
Nixon start putting pressure on senators
And you can imagine
Somebody at this point might have thought
I wonder
Was anything in frankfurters papers Witcher huge winter just been given to the recently given to the Library of Congress
The wood cast light on a ringquist nominee
And one of the things that is no longer in frankfurters papers but appears to have been before the law
What does theft
Is a letter that rank was wrote to Frankfurter in 1955
On the question of
Segregation in the memo to Jackson Western 1952
And there's two legal Scholars Brad Schneider and John Barrett who argue that
Bring Chris would have Revisited the arguments
They made and I can
52 in that letter to Frankfurter and it
Someone from the FBI or from the Nixon white house or on the White House plumbers
Could have been told by Nixon by hausermann by United is Jokers
Can you set up the gear I don't live in Congress and pull anything from ringquist from frankfurters papers but the Hydra tracks
Take a bunch of that crap out
We want to make it look like someone actually stole frankfurters papers like as if anybody can't you donate
My daddy was the whole thing was yet another Watergate cover-up he know we had another dirty trick
It's kind of a cool Siri isn't it
He did great that's great
Is that conspiracy theory also
To in your eyes those credible or do you do have an alternate theory of who may have taken them
Do you think it could have been just some nebbish
Academic core or biography
I do have a Siri
Termite evidence for that theory
I can't tell you that theory
And
In a theory we are disappointed to learn
That it is very unlikely that the paper still
The FBI had a prime suspect
Yahoo denied any involvement and
Did not accept an offer for kind of animosity in exchange for turning the papers
So although you know
They tended to believe that
That person probably had the papers
The FBI never made it
BFDI apps
We never made an arrest
An 8-day talk to a lot of people
They did they did take the investigation really Siri
But on the other hand
If the FBI had
Conducted the highest in the first place wouldn't their investigation have been just designed to cover up that they were the
Culprit would have to be thorough yeah right I mean you're not going to be like the Library of Congress calls in Frankfurt his papers and missing be like they were too busy
Because
That that would look very suspicious if they taking them
I love that. Anything fun Theory
Explains a lot
It's just very little evidence I'm just going to be completely clear
Evidence for what's a sheet of the timeline works out just a little bit like
You know the New York Times published a timeline of the kind of
Well this is the day that Donald Trump jr. net worth
Natalya and then this is the day that Wikileaks published the timeline lines of beautiful
But that is not enough
Coming up
Step back and ask how the world did this
How could this happen
Who gets to decide what happens to these court papers this
Betta fish
That's coming up
It's more perfect time Jedi will ride back to our conversation
With
Imperfect producer Sean rameswaram and Harvard historian and New Yorker staff writer Jill Lepore
So so what's the Supreme Court's official policy and all the papers that go to the Supreme Court what do they do with all that stuff
The Supreme Court's official policy is it is none of your business
It's very surprised myself was frankly surprised to discover this
That the national records act presidential records act legislation that
Protects
Other
Papers
Of the federal government
Specifically excludes the Supreme Court
So what happens is completely up to the justices including most importantly
The discussions that the judges
Have
Conference
And their notes from those discussions and the
Papers at their clerks a symbol for them
I'm preparing how to
Consider a case or
Preparing
For a case that they decide
Not to consider
It's completely the discretion of the just
Sweater to preserve that for the future for historians
For the public for that matter after journalists
They could destroy the land they often do
And how far back does the state he goes back to John Marshall he was one of the most important chief justice
This is
Marshall was an incredibly effective leader of the cord
But under his
Can you record gained an enormous amount of
But she really believed that
The justices
To be able to confer
With full candor
Their deliberations needed to be
Secret
In perpetuity
A lot of people that I'm opposed to Jefferson in particular that was completely inexcusable
Really important value in a republic is transparency
And Marshall was essentially mean
I mean that he loved the idea of the Mist
Courtney in the Mystique of the Core Music reserve of power
So
The tradition dates for Marshall and India are very strong arguments to be made in favor of the deliberations
Being kept secret I think
Certainly for
Period of time
But that we should never know
What was behind these decisions
Who's I think
From the Vantage of a historian
Athletic tape
Book from the political principle that they're strong and it's on the other side
The strong argument to be made that this is indefensible
First of all
They can decide to save nothing
They can burn that paper
New small number of them have indeed
Second they can
Decide they're going to
Give the papers to an R
Then they can give a tenant to a really inconvenient archive
What's 8 as a rule in this nine justices you want to meet you there
Conference notes
I see the paper folders that they assemble the papers about the
The case
You could very well have to go to mini farfan places which
Doesn't seem maybe that inconvenient
Maybe to your listeners but
Is it hard work being trained and getting enough money to even get to these places are
But these are the people who's in
Career has been spent
Pay by taxpayer
Funds
To do the work
Of the federal government
Indeed
Portion of their papers that concerns the work they did for the federal government
A lot of people might say
Belongs to the public
My own view is it is indefensible that the court has no power
I'll see with her guard
2 Court related papers of its justices
Their rules people
These people can't set a rule for themselves, but I understand they don't want
Congress sitting rule about it that for them that falls under the separation of powers issue
But they should have the rule on the rule just shouldn't be
You can have your kids
Decide to burn off
What do you think it would take
For such a rule at this point to be passed
I would have thought
Honestly
They did might have come in the ass for math of the
Bush V Gore decision in two
When people might have said you know what
Supreme Court really powerful
In an era of judicial Supremacy
We actually need the Supreme Court to be saving
Papers because future Generations need to understand
By what means did those nine people
Come to that
If you could steal
The papers of any Supreme Court Justice living or dead
Or Justino
Borrow for a weekend to pour over whose would you steal
I'm I'm going to just go for the gold here
John Marshall
Classic
Yeah just be kind of original guy
He was Jefferson's cousin
He served on the bench with
Bushrod Washington George Washington's cousin
These guys were making momentous decisions early on
Madison V Marbury what did he ranked people into that who cares about me
I don't really want to really like when he's sleeping with the boarding house owner
Choice choice
I'm prepared to defend its second choice
Pills
More perfect Sean rameswaram speaking with historian Jill Lepore
Do you want to learn more about this definitely check out an article that she wrote in the New Yorker called the Great paper
By the way bushrod Washington was George Washington's nephew not Cousin but whatever
Supreme Court audio in the show is from Oye a free law project in collaboration with Legal Information Institute Cornell
Leadership support for more perfect provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
I'm Jad abumrad