Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
It's me chat album ride here with more perfect season 3 than most perfect album we are Marching through all the 27 amendments to the
Constitution
Playing songs
From the album we put together along with audio liner notes that
Digging a little to what each of these men's meet with now
Today we have three three songs we put these three together
Because
They represent
Times in history when
Collectively we decided to
Make
Would seem like
Small tweaks
To our democracy
The small tweaks ended up having
Arguably
Mass Effect
Fundamentally Shifting the way that we do things here in America
For Better or Worse
Is that generally or up to
We got three Amendments of that sort three songs to go along with it
From the most perfect album
Most perfect album. Org
We're going to start with number 12
Probably not the man that you've ever thought about but
Producer Rachel Cusick has
And she brings you this
Lighter now
Imagine a world where
Ladies and gentlemen the Republican nominee for president people
Donald J Trump
And the Democratic nominee for president Hillary Clinton Donald Trump and Hillary Clinton
Both run for president of the United State
Trump wins Hillary loses
But instead of bowing out
Hillary Clinton becomes Trump's Vice
Let me respond to that because that's
Horrifying
Different kinds of campaigns there and it's a crazy thought
Donald Trump's ideas
Aren't just different
They are dangerously incoherent
She has no natural talents people attacked each other's character do we want his finger
You're anywhere near the button
She's one of the worst secretaries of State in the history of their mental stability
The psychiatrist
Explain his affection for tyrants
But you were
Totally out of control
I said there's a person
With a temperament that's got a problem
Their voters
Half of trump supporters into what I call the basket of deplorables
They're not deplorable
The racist sexist homophobic xenophobic
Islamophobic you-name-it lock her up is right
How do you lie to the FBI
And now you're running for president
How does that happen
I'm in no world would you pair these two people up and then expect them to coleta Country
But
For the first few years of our country
That's how elections worked a bunch of people ran for office person with the most votes became president and the person with you roast beef
Vice president
Very quickly things went South
1800 Thomas Jefferson squares off against John Adams Jefferson side basically called Adams a hideous for Mac
Adam Sandler's back saying that Jefferson was the son of a half-breed Indian Squaw
And everybody jumps to the conclusion that there is no way that you guys can serve together
That our country needs a better way of doing us
And that way was
At 12.
Election of President and Vice Pres
The electors shall meet in their respective States
And vote by ballot for President and Vice President
One of them
At least
Shall not be an inhabitant of the same state with themselves
They shall name in their ballots
The person voted for as president
And in distinct ballots
The person voted for as Vice Pres
From then on one person from each party would run with a chosen psychic and as long as they weren't from the same state elections
Could carry on as normal without any Force Partnerships
I can't help but Wonder though if
Maybe
In some small way this amendment fueled some of the hostility from the 2016 election
Take away the pressure to be civilized
Rachel Cusick
That lineup for the 12th Amendment another band that tackled the 12th
On was buried album
Happens to be one of my favorite bands
I've been listening this guy for like 10 years from the band octopus project
Guichos
The 12th Amendment for a track
Without knowing too much about the amendment itself
Unlike the more famous amendments like the first of the second
The 12th is
Is pretty dry and mostly deals with
Procedural details rather than describing
Specific individual rights
So we weren't
Completely sure how to approach it
When researching the amendment a little more
Especially in the NSA we found called who's afraid of the 12th Amendment
It became clear that
The dryness and procedural language was
The point
That the Federalists
Believe that an intricate structure of
Checks and balances was a more effective deterrent
To a tyrannical government
Van enumeration of specific rights
Or parts
Barriers as they called that approach
Can I say something
Really interesting to us about the concept
The series of
Dispassionate systems and mechanisms being as much a defender of Liberty as some of the more
Dramatic
Flaming sword amendments in the Bill of Rights
The looping mechanical clacking sound in the track
Connects with that image for us
And I really like how the interlocking rhythms of
The drums and the clacking sound provide the basis for the more dramatic
Sense and Thurman's to enter on top of to continue the musical metaphor
Four of the different approaches in the different amendments
I hope you and racetrack
Text
You can hear that full-song from the ox
This project or any of these songs on the most perfect album
At the most perfect album. Org
That's okay so we're going to skip right ahead from 12 to 20
Because they both came about around the same time they both deal with the
The oddness
Of Elections this particular one
Number 20
Triciclos a
Devilish little window of time that
Occurred
After an election
Before a person
Took office
Sometimes called the lame duck period Which makes it sound gentle and harmless
But
The Julia Longoria looks plain
It's not
It's a small Niche but I'm certainly a 20th Amendment person in there not too many other people trying to fill that void
So I talked to this professor Ed Larson
Who considers himself a 20th Amendment man absolutely correct and it's like kind of hard to get people up in the morning
For like structure
Changes I guess
The Bill of Rights might be a little bit more sexy for lack of a better word but
Well it got me up this morning it can get people up but it takes more explained
As unsexy as the 20th Amendment might seem
It was past
Thanks in large part
To a very sexy
President hotel room with his mistress when he got word that he just getting the nomination
Dark Horse candidate
Warren Gamaliel Harding
Warren G Harding 29th president of the United States has become fat
Famous for his
Femi infidelity
And his failures as a present
Hi there very few supporters
General consensus among historians and political sciences to both parties
Is
Harding
Define
The bottom
Pardon himself famously said
I am not fit for this office
And should never have been here
A modest man who had a lot of reason to be modest
He wasn't exactly an ideas guy
The Republican Party chose him as a compromise
He would be a tool of the special interest in it to all of the members of Congress to to love the people picking him
It turns out generally kind of a tool
And this one episode in President Harding's presidency was unpopular enough
Reddit Inspire the country to change something pretty fundamental about the way things ran
The old system was set up
Almost
By accident
It was an accident
Timing
Since the founding of the nation
Our government ran on a very strange
Elections would happen in November
Like they do now
But new readers wouldn't take office until way later
Presidents
Started their terms
5 whole month
After they were like
And Congress
The new Congress didn't first meet for a year
Is created a strange phenomenon
Where anytime of Congress is elected
The old Congress
Lame duck congress
They call it
That had been potentially voted out by
Those guys got to meet
Bro whole session
A whole session where they didn't have to answer to the p
You ask why why would such an
Obvious
Anomaly not be correct
The reason is it's why other a logical
Constitution Amendments don't get past
The lame-duck
The lane.
Game from the
The lame Ducks game because they basically had an entire session of Congress
Where they were free to do what they wanted
And because
Every member of Congress views themselves
What is a potential lame duck
They all are going to retire or lose some time
You could never get enough of them
To vote for the amendment
That is until
This one
Shameful
Episode
Under Warren G Harding
Bucs backup
President Harding ran on
2 catchphrase
I invented a new word
Normal
Return to normalcy
Whatever normalcy is we're going to return to it
And right after World War II
That was a popular idea
.
Vision
When America was
Was great
He wanted to
Bring that
The other was
America first
Stabilize America
Prosper America
Bank of America
He called for
Isolationism breaking relations with our traditional allies in Europe
Getting rid of immigrants
I know you're thinking
The push to immigration
Legislation that became law that for the first time
Excluded
People from America based on the
Source of where they came from
Southern Europe in Eastern Europe totally barring people from Asia
Of course barring people from places like Africa
And the
Pills for a return to normalcy
Play Ed America first
Had tremendous residence
In 1920
By 1922
His second year in office
Wasn't quite so
Sure because you had a back way
And the midterm elections of 1922
Where a landslide against
Harding and the
Looking party the Democrats
Gained
84 seats
It's a huge wave election
It was one of the biggest losses for a sitting president's party that the House of Representatives had ever seen
Just for contrast
The latest midterm swing in the house
Was roughly the
20th largest in his
This one was the
Fourth largest
Boston history
And yet
At the time when you did have a wave election
When one party
What's power the other party hung around
In control of Congress
Passing all sorts of bills that were against the will of the people
I understand that like 4-year for like the first hundred fifty years of the democracy
Half the time Congress had the potential to be completely undemocratic right is that
Fair assessment I guess people wouldn't have called it a democracy back then I was some sort of republic
But the audacity of Warren Harding's next me
The corrupt bill that he tried to get past
During the lame duck
Session of 1922 most notorious one was his
Ship's Bell
Built to build ships
For the Merchant Marine that would
Prophet
Republican donors and his friends
Mightily
It woke a lot of people up
Both Republicans and Democrats
Do the problems with lame duck
Also there were widespread rumors
That he was promising jobs
Two lame duck members of Congress
Who Woulda
Vote his way
President Harding
Didn't end up getting his way
One of the most famous filibusters in history
Stop the show
Ship's Bell
And
The widespread outcry against the corruption
Launch the campaign
That would end
With the following Amendment to the US Constitution
Read for us now
Buy actor Jeffrey Wright
20th Amendment
Presidential tournaments
Succession
Assembly of Congress
The terms of the president and the vice
Didn't show end at noon on the twentieth day of January
And the terms of senators and representatives at noon on the 3rd day of January
The years in which such terms would have ended if this article and not been writing
And the terms of theirs
Successors shall then begin
Baby.
Did that fix it
Well
What did the 20th Amendment solve
Lame duck problems
So we still have a legacy
Not completely in the short lame duck. It's no longer a lame duck session
It's shorter now but we do have a period when the old office holders can't
Continue to hold power
And that gets criticized because that old Congress if it loses power will suddenly confirm about
Bunch of Judges or pass a bunch of laws or the president will issue a bunch of Pardons or or dual hose
Fluid last minute regulations
That's still a legacy
That wasn't changed by the 20th Amendment because the 20th Amendment itself like everything else in the mirror
American in the constitution is a compromise
Julia Longoria with that liner note for the 20th Amendment
The artist
That tackled the 20th on the most perfect album
Is Virginia rapper R&B singer Huey Supreme Samantha's going in on his project was
I thought it was a
Cuz
It's vital
That people have to
Black people importantly but everybody really
Need to know their constitutional rights especially in today's climate on my thoughts going into the song as I had the 20th Amendment
And on this a bunch of different sections to this amendment
Interesting to see how would I type
And
The way I posted is I I posted from
From the perspective of
The actual person as if I was in Congress myself
But I can't stop yet
Men In Black II
What I like what the song is it Huey spring rights in perspective somebody who's lost
Maybe an election who knows
There in that lined up. But they that they they decide
Not to be opportunistic about it
Because the work
He's way more important than they are
And so they just want to do good
Switzer flips it
Tell me more about like somebody who's
Faithful Inn
Selfless
I pray that I don't
Get here the whole song at the most perfect album. Org
Anjana barad we will continue in a moment
I'm Jedi boom Rod this is the most perfect album we've done 20 we've done 12
One more to go 17th Amendment
Popular election of senators
This song
I mean it is about the 17th Amendment
The one and only amendment that creep
Senators being
Voted in
So on chill while recording the song I wrote most of the lyrics during a cartoon that will pop up if you Google
17th Amendment
Okay so a little background that is
Indie rocker singer-songwriter person
Stef chura
Chose to write a song about the 17th Amendment
That is an amendment
And she write about
Lyrics
That
Melissa Lee tries to
Stamp Out undue influence
From
Special interest
Appraise Yukons
Your politicians say drain the swamp
Special interest
No more special interest
Well
I didn't know this
The back in the day
We the citizens of America
Did not choose our Senators directly
State Legislature
Would choose them
For us
That open the door
For those special interest
To walk in and essentially by power
You had a big
Oil companies big coal companies all kinds of become
Making these backroom deals with
Legislators to get whoever they wanted elected and the 17th Amendment
Made the electing of senators way more Democrat
Stop this song goes out to my senators
And the choice that we get in
Yeah so thank you
This was a pleasure
You can hear Steph Curry entire song at the most perfect album. Org
The Senate of the United States shall be composed
The two senators from each state
Elected by the people thereof
For 6 years
Producer Julia Longoria hit it so
Crazy story
For the first hundred fifty years of our democracy
The people
Did not vote for
Our senator
Nope that's so yeah the 17th Amendment change that it made things more democratic
And frankly
This seems like a very boring Amendment and I feel like we should move right along because there's really nothing to see here you're right
Most people don't go around thinking about the 17th Amendment and kind of like
You know
Burning with the desire to have their state legislatures appoint senators
Yeah but
That desire did burn in the heart of
This man
Yes
My name is John Daniel Davidson I'm a senior correspondent at the Federalist
The Federalist is a conservative online magazine
I'm John DD has written in it
About the needs
Rethink the 17
And maybe go back to the way things were
Where state legislators would choose our Senators for
It's an idea.
Firstcut flame in his heart
On a long drive
What he says
He saw democracy at work
So I went to Alabama and I drove around the state
Going to a lot of different small towns
And talking with
Baptist Churches white working-class people
The state was in the middle of a special election to replace their senator
As I spoke to these people the number one thing that came through
Was that they felt
As though
Federal government
Did not represent them
And did not represent their values and that they had no voice
They felt like American democracy was being rigged
Bye
Wait for it
Special interest
At the time there was one candidate who spoke directly to that feeling
His big message
I do care about you I am like you I will represent you and not the special interests
That control Washington when he put it like that it sounds
Kind of
Romantic though I mean so you like a psycho I'm going to absolutely it sounds romantic
And until you end up with candidates like Roy Moore
Let's break it down a total of 9 women has now come forward with allegations of overtures by Roy Moore
Is a 14 year old
Girl
Moore is a pedophile
Right and that's when the reality kind of comes crashing in
That
You do need to temper the will of the people
How to direct it in positive drug
Letter words maybe the people
Don't always know best
Maybe
And this is something here a lot these days
Maybe democracy
Is not all it's cracked up to
We do not have a democracy
Established by the
That's Todd's a Wiki one of the first people who called for the repeal of the 17th Amendment would you say that you worried like the fan
Founder of this movement refers to a bit of an overstatement called a movement
This is fun
He has no fantasies about
Xvii actually being repealed
But he thinks it's a worthy thought
Experiment is it fair to say that
You kind of want to send it to look a little bit more like this
Supreme Court
Well I think that's what the framers had in mind
That people who served in the Senate
It would be
People who weren't really going to
Stupid
Scrabble
Provokes the way that
Back the house of
To do it
Tod's argument sort of mirrors with a lot of the founders
Way back in the beginning
We're scared of
Hamilton Madison Adams
When they're big fears was that the people don't always know best
That democracy is good but it's not everything
Cuz what ends up working with
People is sometimes rhetoric
Stooping it
Scrabbling and telling people what they want to hear
Path argument is that we need a vetted group of people
To take the Senate
I don't mean senators are smarter
More independent
More thoughtful
I wanted to ask you these people that you talk to
Did they convince you any
Give me more reason to pause than I thought they would actually historian Nancy Unger
Team demak
Can you give me like the
Hatchiyack
Radio jingle version of the argument for the 17th Amendment
And like why we shouldn't curtail the people's right to basically shoot ourselves in the foot
I would probably have to give you Robert LaFollette quote
The Supreme issue involved in all the others
Is the encroachment of the powerful few upon the rights of the many
Doesn't exactly roll off the tongue
But we'll take it
Nancy argue
You kind of got to pick your poison
Like on the one hand world without the 17th Amendment
We kind of already know what that looks like
Anybody can do a Google search
And look at some of the cartoons from the Gilded Age and Progressive Era those are the periods right before
For the 17th with
And there's a very famous one of all the senators in the Senate
But behind them are the real bosses of the Senate
And huge money bags
You know senators were essentially being
Bought and sold now money-in-politics obviously
Still an issue
It's not uncheck
The way that it really was I believe prior to the Seventeenth Amendment
So that's one reality
Balanced against that you have
The current
Where you get
The Roy Moore's of the world
And it seems like we the people have this tendency sometimes to take out the proverbial gun
Polish it
When it right down at our foot
I think that is a problem but for me it's the lesser of two evils
Nancy thinks back to those Progressive lawmaker
Curse who
First made the 17th Amendment happen
Bear moment
Was this
Real belief
In the power of the people
It's progressives you don't love these people were being with live during the Civil War they remembered Abraham Lincoln they really
Believe
That you could trust
The people in power them and they would use that power
For good
That says a lot about their moment and I think the idea of repealing it now says a certain
Amount about our moment
There are risks
In democracy
I just don't think that we have the right to expect that everything is going to be simple or it's going to be perfect
The deeply
Frustrating thing about democracy
But also the deeply beautiful thing about it
Is a every decision is only here for
Every bad decision
And also every good decision you know you're never done
You're always working you're always
Developing you have to fight for democracy every generation has to fight for it in a new way
Next week will have the final episode of
This season final two amendments look out for that
Prostitute Leah Longoria
And also to Donnie dinero who sang a song about the 17th Amendment but you heard in that story
More perfect produced by me jeroboam Rod Susie lechtenberg Julia Longoria Kelly Prime sarkari and Alex overington
With help from Elie mystal Michelle Harrison Dave Gable
Thank you to actor Jeffrey Wright
For being the voice of the Amendments and to the National Constitution Center for collaborating with us
On the website
Nora Keller is the reason
Are album 27 the most perfect album exist
Listen to it
At the most perfect album. Org
Thanks for listening