WNYC Studios
This is more perfect season 3 that right
Are we hearing are the kominas
A South Asian American punk band that chose the 9th Amendment
Give me the whole song at the most perfect album. Org
We have released an album as I have mentioned in the past two episodes were really excited we made this album called 27 the most
Perfect album
We asked a bunch of musicians
Write a song that interpret
One of the amendments to the US Constitution
Bunch of different artists
Participated again canoe the whole thing at the most perfect album. Org
We're on iTunes Spotify all the stuff
On the podcast
We are
Releasing what I like to think of it
Is audio liner notes
Tucson
The short little stories that illuminate some aspect of the amendment
Now the first 8 amendments
We're very clear
Right to free speech
Right to bear arms
3rd Amendment
Whatever
But then you know you get to the amendments
Talk about the rights you have when you are arrested by the police
Superman effect concrete
But then
Things get Spacey
Unhinged
Untethered
Especially when you get to the next three 9th Amendment
10th Amendment
11th dimension
This tremendous
A little bit trippy
Not to say they're not important some people would argue they're the most important amendments but it's just that they're very hard to understand by Joe
Reading the text
Can I have to talk about them by talking about something else
That makes me sad
So that's what we're going to do
Play the songs
Second for the moment
The liner notes we're trying use metaphor
To bring these
Spacey amendments
Back down to earth
Starting with
9th Amendment
The Knights Inn on enumerated rights retained by P
The enumeration in the Constitution
Of certain rights
Shall not be construed to deny or disparage others retained by the people
Yeah
Listen to one more option in the constitution of certain rights
Shall not be construed to deny or disparage others retained by the people
So I've been reading about the 9th Amendment
More perfect producer and learning the basically
The reason it's around is because the framers wanted to cover their asses
Basically the 9th looks back at the previous eight amendments and it says
Deserve rights but they are only rights
You got way more rights than that
Pictures aren't written down
Which I guess makes sense but
Does it
I mean
We can pretty much choose to do anything that isn't illegal
But there are lots of things aren't
Constitutional guarantees
I mean
Mckown
If we have boundless 9th Amendment rights why don't we have a guaranteed right to marijuana
Are free refills window seats
The right the complimentary dinner mints the right to tasting tiny pieces of candy out of those bulk container right.
Ice cream for breakfast
Everyday it's just like it's super vague and I
Wanted to know how to understand it better so I started Googling whatever I could
And I came across a professor
This is Judith bear from Texas A&M University political science
And I specialize in public law and you just told me about a case
Call Griswold versus Connecticut
The story of Griswold vs Connecticut begins in 1961
Okay Estelle Griswold was the executive director
Planned Parenthood League of Connecticut
Still got together with a Yale med school gynecologist named Sealy Buxton
Started a clinic in New Haven
Popular in the community they had lots of clients
And within ten days the police shut them down
Because keep in mind this was before Roe v Wade and in Connecticut in the mid-60s
The use of any
Contraception
It was illegal to even use birth control so it was super illegal to start a clinic where you coach women
In married couples about it
But it's all Griswold was doing it anyway I think it's very evident unenforceable
I think if you had a policeman under every bed
In the state of Connecticut they still could not prove anything this is tape of Estelle Griswold from that time
Continuing
Baby illegally
But we are continuing our program
So in the late fall of 1961
We issue two warrants
One against Estelle Griswold and the other against dr. Seely Buxton
Buxton are arrested
In violation of the contraceptive statue
What happens next
Is the clinic at shuttered
They go to court
The case makes it all the way up to the Supreme Court
And eventually they win in a way
The field was very obvious
An incredibly odd
Also like
Somewhat metaphysical in the opinion
William O Douglas the Justice who wrote for the court
Wrote the various guarantees create zones of privacy
Amendments here the first
3rd the 4th and 9th V
Saying they all guarantee privacy and if a woman wants use birth control in her own home
Are privacy there should be protected
Privacy is important
Got it
But
Things get weird when you realize the word privacy
And is privacy mentioned anywhere in the Constitution. Absolutely not
Is nowhere to be found
The actual word privacy is written exactly zero times in the US Constitution
We all believe that we do in fact have that right
What to make of this
Well
In the Griswold case Douglas offers the following explanation Douglas
That certain constitutional guarantees have the numbers
Formed by emanations
From these right
Snake gives them light and substance
Numbers combinations light
Substance
It's so it almost sounds like
I'm just so captivated because it just
It sounds so physical it doesn't sound that high-level law it's like
Penumbra
Comes from two Latin words
Meaning gear
Shadow
So you're using a metaphor from the natural world
To describe an idea
Justice William O Douglas said the all our constitutional rights have penumbra's of emanation stretching out into space
Imagine
An exploding star
A supernova this glowing white ball with light radiating out in every direction into the Vas
Space
So according to him while the law doesn't say anything about privacy explicitly
Pepsi is kind of
Contained in the space that
The law emanates
Into
Something
Hello
Hello the soccer cup
It is and I'm going to take you off on speakerphone
I think I'm going to take you off this
Speakerphone
Why did they go
Where is it
Idea that we can understand the 9th Amendment through
Cosmic metaphor
Now that's so beautiful weird
Headset no so vague like everytime I really try and wrap my head around it it's just
No I think you're still in doubt
And so
I thought maybe I just need to understand what a penumbra actually
Is
So I called the guy who knows
Hello yes I'm on speakers no longer we do not understand how that happened it is strictly magical
Probably in a
Black hole vortex
This is dr. Ed cropp director of Griffith Observatory in Los Angeles
Doctor cup is an astronomer knows a lot about the numbers so I asked him for a definition Umbra
Is a Zone
Eyeshadow out
Side of the main Central shadow
That is cast by
A Celestial light like the
The Sun
Think about a solar eclipse where the Moon is casting a shadow on the Earth
The deep dark center part of that
Shadow is called
The Umbra and the penumbra is the less dark outer fuzzy edge of that shadow where
What is deep
So kind of like the furry shadow on the edge of a dark shadow
A little
My suspicion is that you've probably not seen a total solar eclipse that correct
Last year doesn't count feels like it counts
The the fact okay whatever
I asked him based on his understanding of the numbers and astronomy
What do you think Douglass meant when he said certain constitutional guarantees have
Penumbra's formed by emanations
From these right
Give them light and substance like does that make sense to him as an astronomer
No no no no no
Night I certainly understand how you're saying about the love but that's a different thing than the actual
Experience of the penumbra
So sure if you want to think about it if it's the law if it's a light source it would emanate
Light
Which
Could create a shadow but the shadow doesn't
Give the light
It's light in substance
It already
How's the light
Inside of it
And
You know it's it's
Difficult
For me to
Endorse
That that that analogy
Douglas
What did you mean
Does it surprise you that
His metaphor doesn't hold up
No not at all
This is David J Garrow
Missy in the making of Roe v Wade
And he's written a lot about Justice Douglas Juvenile Justice Douglas reputation
Pulling these Concepts
Out of the air almost literally out of
The astronaut
Glare
Unfortunately that was par for the course
With Justice.
Yeah. You Tatian for being a brilliant legal mind but
Also kind of a jerk
Not to mention a womanizer and
Kind of lazy
His former clerk said his opinions were quote
Drafted in 20 minutes
Easy to ignore
Is another quote here that they were superficial or just plain sloppy like that
Strong is almost unprecedented
For a justices
Former Clerk
Speak
Critically
Highly critical
Of the just
Subsequent
Public
Thanks
Seriously Justice Douglas you can't
Put in a little effort here
I guess another question attached that buddy
Do you kind of
Yelled at like does it feel short
For example it's been reported
The Justice Clarence Thomas
I had a
Sign in
Is Chambers at the Supreme Court saying
Please don't emanate in the penumbra
All that sad when I when I hold all of this in my hands the unenumerated rights
Penumbra the moon all of it
I feel like maybe Douglas
Was destined to fail
Tonight's amendment is different
I'm like the first eight amendments to outline and incredible detail what Americans should ask
Of their new government
The 9th Amendment comes floating and without astronomical Vibes gesturing dreamily all the uncontainable
Indomitable rights
To which Americans can lay claim without ever being able to point them in text
The founders of this country one of the things
They had in mind
What's the law wasn't just a set of words or a set of rules
The law had a spirit
Ever the spirit of the law
And that there was something behind those words
That you couldn't
Put your finger on
Couldn't exactly name
Maybe Douglas failed because he was lazy
Maybe he failed because he had to
Maybe it's failure
Is the whole point
Kelly Prime did that audio liner note for the night
Bennett
Ride Along
10th Amendment
The powers not delegated to the United States by the Constitution
Nor prohibited by it to the states
Are reserved to the states respectively
What do the people
This is often called the states rights
I'm in it
And the history behind it
In Tuscaloosa
Very hot
Nearly 100
It's pretty dark
70 years ago states rights
Swerve
Repeatedly invoked
To say
Segregation tomorrow segregation forever
Cannot mandate
Quality because we have a right to regulate
Play in this area
That's the ugliest
According to Heather Gerken
Dean of Yale law school but
She says it's not the present
Do you want to see where has most of the workmen going on
1 State however has Doug and it's healed
Mental reform where has the most work been going on
Moving forward lgbtq issues
That's what happened at the state and local level and that definitely predates the Trump Administration
Two states rights
This Tenth Amendment idea
Cuts both ways
And maybe the deeper point is that
Yeah this push and pull between the federal government and the states
It's fundamental
To the way the country was built
Heart of the app
Fundamental architecture
Sir like if you go to DC and
Is Capitol Building look up at the curve Dome
In a basic Dome what you have is the wait
Of the Dome itself
Immense radial Force
Pushing out away from the center
Down against the stone walls
The stonewalls resistant push back up
And the only reason the thing doesn't fall on your head
It's because of those inner forces pushing against each other
To go slightly farther feel there's a concept in architecture called 10 Segway
With the Integrity of the structure is the tension itself that's what holds it up
10th Amendment
Is evidence that the founders
This country had
Something like that in mind I mean these guys were builders
Washington
Jefferson they were on and on about designing their own homes
And the Republic
Did they design for us
Is built
On forces
Colliding
Forces
Any kind of balanced tension
That's
Kind of what the tenth amendment is all about
Okay
I think we should all be here
Cool
Everybody
Emily Rick
Big to meet you guys thank you so much for that song it's so amazing I guess first would you mind
Introducing yourself this is Rick Alverson
Pennsylvania
Bentley near Chest 10th Amendment
Facebook Kelly Prime in studio
We are an excerpt
Can you tell me a little bit about the process
The writing the song like if you were to paint a picture of look what idea came to you first
We live in Virginia
In Richmond Virginia and the
The idea of states rights is very volatile
Idea here
I think we were thinking of the idea of the individual versus the collective and
Eternal struggle in the American
Brand of democracy
I think it was
Envisioning
Legal historical struggle might look like in the context of a relationship
What an individual bring to a relationship and how an individual
How they identify as a couple
What year we put it into me
I vs. we dynamic
You can be a beneficial friction or it can be a problematic volatile sort of thing you know
I think that we are
I mean just so increasingly divided and polarized
All of the new on
Out of a conversation
In a way that
This doesn't really allow us to hold a space for being individuals and being a collective at the same time
In a way that doesn't feel
That was a song by the band linear
Love that song written
10th Amendment
Farrar album
Call 27 the most perfect album
You can listen to the full song
All the songs in their entirety at
At the most perfect album.
I'm Chad album Rod this is more perfect
I'll be back in a moment
Caged add more perfect we're marching through the Amendments listing two excerpts
Songs inspired by these amendments
27 most
Perfect album and we're telling stories about the Amendments we've done 9
Buju Banton
Now
11th Amendment
Suits against States
The judicial power of the United States shall not be construed to extend to any suit in law or equity
Commenced or prosecuted against one of the United States by citizens of another state
For by citizens or subjects of any foreign state
Okay so this is another amendment
That's
Little hard to park
I mean technically says he listened to it
Did you get your power
Or the United States something
About how a person who lives in one state
One of the United
By Steelix a Georgia I don't know
Natsu
Barnes day
A difference day
To someone who lives in Georgia
Can't sue the state
Florida
That's
Basically what
I mean it gets more complicated way more complicated but at its base
It's this wonky little Rule and it says the 11th Amendment
I've got the Bill of Rights which is one through 10 and
Spilled with these Blockbuster
The right to free speech
The right to bear arms
The right
2A
Trial by jury of your peers and then you get this
Why
Can't answer
At least come up with a satisfying
It helps
To Free Your Mind
The literal
Here's Julia Longoria
It seems
To me that the 11th Amendment is hugely
Complicated and difficult to teach even in law schools
Yes I spend several weeks on it in a minute Advanced upper-class course
But Susanna Sharia professor at Vanderbilt law so we have the unenviable challenge
Trying to package this in like a 3 to 5 minutes
Little tap dancing so general public so
The metaphor that I
You could have tried
Is it
Seems maybe like it
The appendix
Of the gothic Constitution where body is the appendix not too bad
I woke up one morning feeling just a little bit queasy and nauseous. Maybe I had eaten something
Dr. Heather Smith
Is an anatomy professor
And she was first introduced to her appendix
When she was 12 years old
When it hurts
Like the discomfort became more and more localized into the lower part of my right abdomen
And by the end of the day that day I was in the emergency room having my appendix removed
This is how a lot of us encounter the append
On its way out
And if you look at a picture of the appendix it looks like this
Weird
Long wart
Coming out of our large
Darwin when he look today
Call the vestigial organ evolutionary remnant
Say something that
Was useful in the past that is no longer useful
Darwin's hypothesis was that
Nr8 ancestors
They were much more folivora
Brass meaning that they ate a lot more
Grasses leaves and silver climbing up trees and eating leaves and branches then you just special
Enzymes and their body to digest that stuff those enzymes were stored in the appendix area
At least that's what the
But then over time
Are diet
So his hypothesis was
That are large intestines essentially shrunk in size
And that when they Shrunk the appendix trunk along with them
So the theory is that now it's just this
Depleted useless organ past its prime that does nothing but
Cod problem
And for some people it's tempting to see the 11th Amendment in kind of the same way
Where was once the super crucial thing
And now
It causes pain
Are you saying it was crucial one point
Yeah actually went why
Well
You have to remember this amendment was drafted
Originally in 1793
Bats Bradford Clark a law professor from George Washington University
So only
4 years after the
Tution was adopted and only 2 years after
The Bill of Rights
Keep in mind the country is a baby at this point like it's a newborn
And so most of the people who wrote the founding document had actually recently
Ben British ends in Britain
There was this idea that you can't sue The King The King has a dignity
That would be affronted if he were
Dragged into court by a comment
And the founders of the United States
They took that same idea and put it into the US
Most people took for granted
But the federal government would be immune from suit
But it didn't seem like the states
We're going to get that seem immunity
And seats were like
We're not signing on to the concert
Institution if we don't get that immunity
B2 maybe it's hard for us in this modern
World
To put ourselves back
Into the mindset of the people
At the time but I think the states
Burberry
Proud
Of winning their independence
So in the Declaration of Independence
They declared themselves
To be
Free and independent
States
We don't think of this today but the word state
What's the word that was used in international law
To describe
A Sovereign Nation
And it's still used that way in other countries
And one of the prerogatives of sovereign states
What's not to be sued
In its own courts or in the courts of another sovereign
Without its
Consent
And so that was the basic idea
Dates were never going to give up immunity
They would never sign on to the Constitution without it
So in some ways the 11th Amendment kind of Saved our concert
Esthetician
The states wouldn't be forced to
The payback.
I thought they were not people
And because of that
The country could continue to exist until that was very important back then
I don't think we worry about that
Very much
Now
These days according to Suzanna Sherry I think the 11th Amendment is mostly used
States from their own illegal act
I don't think that's a good thing
The 11th Amendment today causes all kinds of
The pain if you happen to have a run-in with
State the tribe says the lake is part of a watershed sacred to the Coeur d'Alene Indian
But since the Supreme Court
The state
Can't be sued you mean to tell me even if he's Medicaid recipients are right but neener neener neener
I can't sue you and hold you accountable and you're free to violate the law
Florida refuse to negotiate with the Seminole tribe
And so the Seminole tribe trade
Sue them in federal court
Springport said nope
I feel that the people that will hurt from
Smoking cigarettes should be compensated for it will be difficult
Because the 11th Amendment
Protect States from federal lawsuits for monetary damage
This is why the 11th Amendment is soaked
Let me see think like should we just get rid of the 11th Amendment like should we be going full appendectomy
Well
I think
I think that might be a pretty good metaphor
Stop it. There is a
Butte it's as if they're word
Dispute among
Doctors
About whether the appendix was actually a useful or
Yes there is there absolutely is. Oh I didn't know that they've just come out with a study that says
Actually
The appendix
Might be useful
So like when there's a time of turmoil in the stomach as they caught like a diarrheal episode
What to use that on the podcast
Watch me
So I just want to kind of like walk
2 Step by Step
A diarrheal episode
Heather Smith again is one of the people who discovered this so let's say for instance you had a tourist who went to
Another country and got some kind of serious
Gastrointestinal
Issue and they had
Episodes of diarrhea when your body
Flushing everything out
The appendix actually has this kind of
What a
Beautiful function
The appendix may serve as a safe house
Bund of a reservoir for beneficial gut bacteria
So maybe the appendix
Isn't vestigial like Darwin
The term that we use in an evolutionary biology is called an ex app
Patient
Though it's where
A structure
Serves an Adaptive function but it's not its original
Function in the same way the 11th amendments day looks very different than it did in 1790
That's because the Supreme Court
Bandit
Is that the 11th means a lot more than it says
It protects
Against
All kinds of suits
Of course there are exceptions
But it means a lot of times a Floridian can't sue Florida for damages
It also might mean you can't sue a state that's
Choosing to be a sanctuary for immigrants
Depending on who you are
You might need that
Or you might see it as a good thing
A reservoir
First state power
A critical piece that finishes the federalism puzzle
The top of the Tenth Amendment Dome the penumbra
Of the 11th Amendment
Julia Longoria with that liner notes for the 11th Amendment
Here's the song
Come to my guy named Kevin
Patrick Sullivan who goes by the name field medic
Bernhard MCC
Field medic with a song for the 11th Amendment you can check out that song and
9th Amendment song from the caminas 10th Amendment song from linear
And all the other artists
Did have written songs for this album 27 the most perfect album
About the amendments
The Constitution you can check them all out at
The most perfect album. Org listen to the mall
More perfect
Reduce by me cherubim Rod Susie lechtenberg Julia Longoria Kelly Prime sarakari and Alex overington
With help from Elie mystal Michelle Harris David Gable and Nora Keller
The voice that you heard reading the Amendments for us that is actor Jeffrey Wright huge thanks to him
Thanks you for listening
Okay we'll see you next time