Hey its Chad
This upcoming season of more perfect
Might be the most perfect
Yet
No
I don't know First Amendment
Is the life cycle of a democratic idea 2nd Amendment in schools
People to be like
You know what I'll give you the right to vote 13th Amendment
In 1865 when we passed the 13th Amendment
Have been fighting for the legal right to vote since the 1840s where did I pick that up
Are you picking up from history how many amendments are there to the US Constitution
27th Amendment
Four Seasons
More perfect we're going to do an experiment
We're going to release
An album an actual album
Has music inspired by the amendments to the United States Constitution
People feature original music from musicians that include Dolly Parton
Kash Doll Caroline Shaw Devendra Banhart many others
27 the most perfect album
Coming soon
All of the songs
Will be released with audio liner notes
Little
Funny
Found
Sad
Hilarious
Short stories that accompany each of the amendments
Along with the songs it all goes into the podcast
Starting
September 18th