Hey it's Chad before we start this episode of the most perfect album
Let me say the words which I know you know
You know that I know you know
Which is it more perfect needs
The only reason we were able to do this season at all
Did you step forward and helped us pay for it
Supreme Court and wanted to know how did we get here
Question how many of us are asking
Right now
This is we want to take it any different direction we brought you 27 the most
Perfect album
Kind of an omage to Schoolhouse Rock
So I learn about the government and the idea was like in this Civics challenge moment they're all living through let's get musicians to
Together to help us
Bring the Amendments the Constitution to life
Now in the podcast
We're telling stories about the amendments
Convening a conversation about this on
Going struggle for the soul of America that is a grand story tell I believe we're just getting
Started
But we can't do any of it
Without your support more perfect
We hope you agree is a one-of-a-kind thing but it does not exist without you so as our way of saying thank you
And encouraging you to continue to support the show
We will give you
Because we are public radio to our core it is in our DNA we will give you a tote bag
For a $10 a month contribution which helps us make
More perfect
We will give you the more perfect tote
What you might call the most perfect
Tote
Vista Real Talk is actually quite beautiful
Nice visual design
And as it does it will carry our hearts
For $10 a month
We will send you
Lemoore perfect toe
More perfect
Click the Donate button or even easier just text the word more perfect
270 101
Then it just takes a few seconds on your phone that's radiolab.org more perfect if the Donate button or text the word
More perfect
70101 and thank you
From all of us
Okay so what if we start by playing people the voice memo
To bring a little bit of joy in the world this week
Yes
Yes guy liked
We should say
Jad abumrad
Lechtenberg
Exactly
These are more perfect so I guess what people should know is that you went to Nash
Nashville which is your hometown
To try and convince
This artist
To be
Are album
And you know that I'm a superfan +
You're nice enough to do this
Okay. Just say hi to her
Hi Susie this is Dolly Parton how are you I understand you're a fan of mine and I appreciate that
Maybe I'll get to meet you sometime when I come to New York
Absolutely I think she'd like that
I'm here with your friend
Seriously just make my heart explode every single time
Dolly Parton did do the album we're going to play who the son she made in
A bit
About the 19th Amendment women getting right
Devote
Play that Amendment this week
So we can play Dolly Parton
Feels like it's needed past couple of weeks doesn't matter which side you're on
Ben hard
I have to go to jail because I'm holding up a poster now
The last second I will go to jail this is ridiculous
It's been a tough stretch and now things are shifting of course 2
The next big milestone
And a lot of the Focus right now is
On when women are ready to vote Democratic Senator Elizabeth Warren
Power America
On November 6th
With this in mind
Bring it back to dali
If you've been listening to our series you know that we made an album about the amendments
Students called
27 the most perfect
Album
And Dolly Parton
Chose to write a song about
V90
Amendment women's right to vote
The right of citizens of the United States to vote
Shall not be denied or Abridged by the United States or by any state
On account of sex
Play the song
What's a tire
August 18th
Women's suffrage amendment
Spotify
Women have been fighting for the legal right to vote
Since the 1840s
In 1890
National American women's suffrage association nawsa
Was established with Susan B Anthony is leaving for
But
Women have been fighting for their rights
Since the very beginning of time
Birthday cake we couldn't we couldn't drink
They said we couldn't even speak
2 wheeler smoking
The truth that's when he's got smart enough
Adam don't like rude but that okay
We have to fight for women's rights
Which every time because the time marked up and down the street we have to talk
When women finally got the right to vote
What state is Washington having babies
But we knew we couldn't quit
We protested came about
Rebuild the truth
With every birthday
On August 18 1920 women's suffrage amendment was ratified
Dolly Parton
The song for the 19th Amendment
I think what is implicit in
Lyrics
Such good word play
In that in there
Umbrella Corps has implicit in in what she's writing about there
It's just what
A struggle
It was
Not just to get
To the point
Having a 9
19th Amendment what to get the amendment itself rata
You will talk about history being searched hinged on the
He's very tenuous moment
Could have gone another direction will this is one of those mon
It all came down
To the wire
Summer night in Tennessee I'm going to turn
Properties liner notes to my Radiolab family producer
What if Nasser
Content of course
Compadre comrade-in-arms
Are here
With the story now y'all in New York
I'm going to put on my most southern accent now
Yes, most southern accent this is Carol Busey
Girls we can handle anything
Carol is a professor of history at the volunteer state Community College in Tennessee near Nashville
You all do understand that Nashville is now the
It
City
Seems to be
But for our story
There was a moment in Nationals history there was not just
The it City it was the
Laugh
Stand it along and
Vicious struggle for women to get the right to vote
It was the summer of 1920
That's an oral history recording of 101 year old woman
And Abby Crawford Milton
Who in that very hot summer of 1920
Descended upon Nashville with hundred
In hundreds
Other suffragists like herself
Anti suffragists
Lawyers politicians
Business people
They all came to Nashville for this
Pierce
Legislative battle
Okay
Now let me stop here and take us one step back
And we're also going to bring an historian Jill Lepore at Harvard
She told us that at the end of the Civil War ran 1865 s Congress was considering this new Amendment which would give
Former slaves the right to vote
Goddess small band of women
Who work wishing
Hoping fighting to be included in this new Amendment women expect that the 14th Amendment is going to live
Any discrimination within the constitution on the basis of
Race
Color or sex
They had been the stalwart allies of abolitionists
And women are really important of the founding of the Republican party and so when they say they know y'all can you guys going to do the cement obviously
You're not going to forget us right like we're going to write this political Ramos do it like let's just do it let's get this
Done this proposed amendment is being talked about in Congress to beam
Perfected as being tweaked and it's about to come to a vote when almost at the last minute
The word mail is put in there
Amending the amendment so that only men can
It's the first introduction of the word male into the Constitution
So not only
Does the 14th Amendment
Bale
To guarantee women their citizenship and the rights of command
Privileges that come with citizenship
It specifically excludes
Betrayal we're starting back at
Square one so
Stop point someone that are like God damn it like all right we're just going to go vote and show for instant
Actually tries to vote they won't let her go to the Supreme Court I guess you won't be surprised to hear are you on edge of seas what is it
What are we going to do I can't wait to hear is it going to rain
Is it raining
Ladies it's so cute that you thought you were included in the Cubs
No no no no no
We love you but now
And then in 1878 Susan B Anthony proposed another amend
Address for the right to vote people laughed about it and then put it aside for the next 40 years
Was no movement at all on this amendment until
June 4th 1919
Just after World War 1
After centuries of
Suffering suffer
Both houses of Congress finally passed the 19th amendment to give women the right to
Devote
Amendment came after months of women protesting outside the White House
And years of working jobs that before the war it only ever belong to men
But force it also came with a constitutional
Catch it had to go to the states
To be ratified
Was just means that each state had to vote to approve it
This is something
I just break and it's sometimes a bit hard to
Congress can write an amendment to the Constitution but it doesn't actually go into
The fact
Until 3
Quarters
The states
Decide to go along with
Three-fourths of the state legislatures have to ratify the amendment that be
Well 36 in this particular
Instance had to vote for it
Now and then
Then we got to 35
States
And
Stop
It just got
Stuck at 35
Knowing that the suffragists were only one vote shy
The anti-suffragist
Beefed up their camp
At which made it
Harder and harder to get that final
Allstate it was looking grim
Until
There was a Wednesday
Just one state that seemed
Like it might be.
Teetering
August 1920 Nashville Tennessee
See legislators from all over the state start arriving at Union Station
They're just immediately greeted by
Ro and
Anti-Theft
Kind of pain either a yellow or red rose on their lapel
Tell everybody
Across town would know which side they stood on that was Tom vikstrom he's The Unofficial historian of the very place
These legislators were headed the most fashionable place in town
The Hermitage Hotel
Pictures of Lobby during the month of August
Swarming with people both Pro and anti suffrage women cooling themselves
Palm leaf fans and of course no air conditioning man smoking cigar smoking politicians
Second floor mezzanine you have the headquarters of the anti suffragists
Exactly worth noting that a lot of the anti suffragists were women campaigning actively against
The right to vote they think it's going to reduce
In some ways their moral Authority within the household
Women belong only in private life not in public life
Public life is
The meaning and its
Besmirch
So on the second floor you had to add Ties on the 3rd floor Suite 309 you have carrots
Chapman Catt leader of the pro suffer
She had no children and her husband had died she had devoted all of her energy
Towards this
One goal of getting women the right to vote
So she's up she's the big Washington to Bigfoot from Washington is really much like a general
Both groups are there because this hotel is just a few blocks away from the State House
And they are trying to convince as many Tennessee legislators as they
Possibly can
Take them over to their side it was all kind of high Jinks and you name it eavesdropping
Telegram
Or fake phone call messages
So the suffragists are running around trying to stop these legislators from leaving town while there's a room back at the hotel
Helicopter Jack Daniel's room where there was some Jack Daniels being dispensed
By the anti-suffrage people
And supposedly prosalvage legislators
Could be heard through the hotel walls singing anti-suffrage song
Tennessee is supposed to be dry
And yet
The ant has r
Flagrantly violating prohibition
By having these events
In which the liquor flows quite well
Closer and closer they got to the final day of voting it became apparent that people who had come to town
Saying they were in favor of ratifying this amendment wearing yellow roses
Started wearing red
Roses
Red roses if you remember worn by the side that didn't want women to get the right
The anti
Yellow roses were worn by the side the dip
On the morning of the final vote
There so many
Red roses too yellow roses to yellow roses to red roses flip-flopping floppity flipping around that buy
This point no one had any idea what was going to happen
That's exactly right when does stop you here for a second is it now clear to everybody
Buddy that if the legislature of Tennessee passes
They will become part of the US Constitution
Oh absolutely absolutely
You know you didn't have any cushion states that you could go to
You know Nevada neck
There were no Kush
It's now or it's going to be a long time
And finally it's going to happen one way or another
On August 8th
Tank so the morning of the vote
The hotel starts emptying out everyone heads over to the state capitol
But misses cat because she was going to be looked at as an outside agitator
She decided to stay behind
In the state capitol in the house chamber
It's hot and humid in the room is
Hack the 96 legislators are settling at their death
And above them
In the gallery around the top of the house chamber Bend
Fire there along with the anti suffragists
And you can be assured that both sides have their little pads
Enter counting the votes
And islay look at the Roses
There are 48
Yellow roses in 48
Red roses
And all these roses reliable I mean supposedly
If you're wearing a red rose you're going to vote against it before the voting even begins
They can see that we've lost
Cuz you have to have a few have to have a majority
And the Speaker of the House
He had initially
Supported suffrage but he's really on the side of the ant Eyes by this time
And before they really start the vote he actually steps down on the floor
To give a speech
Against ratification of the amendment
So you know there's another letdown you know is lost we've lost we've lost
And two blocks away
Suite 309 of the Hermitage Hotel
Tits Carrie Chapman Catt
She was very nervous about what was going to happen
So what you going to do she said there is only one thing left to do
We can
Pray
So they start
The Roll Call
And as
These names are called
One by one
These men stand up
And voice their vote
If they are wearing a yellow rose
He say I
For women's suffrage
They're wearing a red rose they say nay
And among these legislators
A young man Harry T burn a republican legislator
From Niota Tennessee a 24 years old he's the youngest legislator
In the house
Small man little glasses with serious face
The air is tense and still
Until
Keurig tea
The young man
Stems from his desk
A red rose in his lapel
But in his pocket
He had a letter from his mother over there in Niota
Dear son
We've had nothing but rain since you left
Her name was
Stubborn
Uncle Bill and mr. Bushnell came over this p.m. State about an hour
They were in the Ford we haven't had that car outside
She left
And if this rainy weather doesn't let up I fear we'll all have to stay at home the rest of them really is justice
Ordinary letters Tower of what I'm writing
From a mom to her son he was real sick yesterday but was better this morning
She's been complaining all summer tucked into all of those mundane details about life in Niota
There was this little motherly
Dig
A product I've been watching to see how you stood but haven't seen anything yet
You know son I've been reading about the suffrage fight in the papers and I really hadn't seen your name anywhere
And then she says don't forget to be a good boy and help Miss Thomas cap
Vote for suffrage and don't keep them in doubt
With lots of love Mama
Harry T burn is wearing a red
Rose
And his vote
He
Votes
For women to have the right to vote
So there in the balcony there's just a moment of silence what's going on here what's going on
You can imagine this you can imagine this
And then it don't sanya
Hey Harry's changed his phone
It's not going to be 48 to 48 it's going to be 49 247
The suffragist you can imagine our
Crying the anti Tsar Furious
You can imagine the total chaos here in this situation but there must be an awful lot of attention
Made the Harry Wright like what the legend is that the aunt has
Start chasing Harry
Through the house chamber
Harry is completely undone oh my gosh what have I just done so he jumps out of window not nash
Not jumping out of 5 story window
But he gets
Out of the building and shimmies down the ledge to the State Library which is in the same building
He gets in the window there and mrs. Moore the librarian Mary Daniel Moore
Hi Tim in the stacks
Until the storm blows over
Now that's the legend Harry really climb out of that window and he said
Jimmy Yang happen we don't know
How exaggerated that part of the story
The shelves from the hill carried all the way back to the Hermitage Hotel
Mrs. cat
Could hear them from her window she knew
They'd won
It was in fact
Pass
The certificate of ratification
Was sent to Washington DC
And received
By the Secretary of
The final tally was actually 5240
After Harry changed his vote
When other legislators switch sides but
It was clearly because Harriet Janet first
That's right see that vote was the wreath at vote
Became the 19th Amendment to the United States Constitution
Yes in the in a manner of speaking yes
After the vote
Mrs. Katz and fat burn
Italic
You are blessed
With a brave and honest
Sun
Whatever the enemies of justice and decency made do now to show their vengeance upon him
He's bound to have a great day
You will ever be proud of him
Carrie Chapman Catt
Well is political career ended rather short
But you know
He took his mother's advice
And
He did get his name in the paper did me
Just a wonderful
Pale
And I always would in the story by saying
Not just think about this folks
In the middle of nowhere
Petty Texas
My grandmother went to the Methodist Church
In November of 1920
With her four-year-old daughter at her side
And voted because of something that took place
Right here in Nashville Tennessee
Little Nashville Pride
Their Arts
I was radiolab's a lot of Nasser with Tracy hunting Robert krulwich
Just answer to sour the mood for a second and obviously a massive milestone for women in the United
It states but it was pretty well understood
By the legislators in that room
In fact that many of the women who was lead to suffer
Purchase movement
This wasn't a victory for all
This is a victory for white
Historians will tell you that this was
You know the 19th was great for a middle-class white women
Didn't do a whole lot
App for black women in the sea
I've worked for decades
Women and men of color who tried to vote
To deal with
Literacy test
White only primaries straight up
Violence and intimidation
And I think one of the grand stories of the amendments
To the Constitution if you read them chronologically what you see is this the story of a country
Striving for these ideals
Not quite getting
And then trying over and over to
With each fix getting maybe a little bit closer hopefully fingers crossed
Is the story of a country growing up
Maybe that's
Too generous a reading but that's honestly how I see it
So after a v
16th and 19th amendments
Switch should have solved voting
Question with didn't
Jump forward you get to the 24th Amendment 24th
Abolition of poll tax
Which try to address one of the main ways votes have been
Expressed throughout American history
The right of citizens of the United States to vote in any primary or other election
Shall not be denied or abridged
By the United States
Or any state
By reason of failure to
People.
Or other two
January 23rd nineteen
64 we ratify the 24th Amendment eliminated poll taxes in federal elections and Farrar album
Musician Caroline Shaw created a really really beautiful
Song for us
Every time every day
Franchise
What are the most precious
Voicemail
Make laws
Other rights
Eleuthera
Anarchist
Toledo room for classroom
Wait and see one at the Sara Lee Bridge there right
Voting is the
Highest form of political expression
Where is little use in Piccadilly if you can vote
That was Caroline Shaw with
The song about the 24th Amendment
Kevin morby also did a song for us
24th
You can listen to his song all the songs
At the most perfect
Album. Org I'm Jedi boom rod
Perfect
Continue in a moment
I'm chat album ride this more perfect
District and Caroline Shaw
Before her Dolly Parton
And the story that is behind the story that is
The center of her song
About the 90
Amendment
Women getting the right to vote
Vapormax story
Marching right along with the most perfect album our next ban
Has an extremely
Personal relationship
Skip to the amend
Perhaps closer than any other band on this album
Sell clothes
So person
They've actually Pro
Performed on the steps of the
Supreme Court
Chicago
While being sued by the federal government
Beaches to put that in context
So why don't we start why don't you tell me
Your name and the bandier
My name is Simon Tam I'm from the slant so I've been a part of the band from the very beginning
I guess goes back to bed
About mm
Xiamen
Spoke to Suzie lechtenberg
Producer in the studio the Slants
Are swerving all Asian synth-pop band to Slants how their music Chinatown dance
Iraq
That's a one-way they've been to
Described on the TV
Wanted to start a
The Simon told Suzy that he formed the band
Because he was tired of there being no Asians
In rock music
He chose the name
Very explicitly
Because of the
Stereotype piano slanted
Isis
Physical trait that I was ashamed of
This is growing up he was
Bully
How we looked and made fun of
But then when it came time to rock
Decided to take the term
Why not make it something that
We can be proud of
Set and flip it
Something that could be cool like an
Endemic
Reclaiming of a stereotype
And so
The idea for the science was born
And did you ever get pushed
Back from anyone about the name the Asian American Community love what we're doing
The first time I kind of Mew
Or was made aware that there was any kind of problem
Was with my attorney called
Me after we had worked on
The application to register
R trademark
Calls me up and it says
Hey Simon we got a problem
Seven-figure so I must
Dundee trademark
You know that paper works very confusing
But the attorney said no it's
It's not that
He says
The problem is that they say your name is disparaging
Two persons of Asian descent
Their name
Is considered derogatory to Asians
We are releasing racist to Asian people
Keep receipts
Stu read me section 2A of the land
Something
You know written in the 1940s
Basically says you can't register trademark
That the government considers to be scandalous
Immoral or disparaging
What was confusing to Simon
And to his attorney
And they looked into
Is that they weren't the only
Slants out there
The Trademark Office had given something like that term
The trademark for that term do you actually gave it out to hundreds
Of other people
We asked them why
Why this case
Like why did you denied for the band
The trademark office is responsible space
Sickly hey if you go to the slant
Dot-com
You'll see photos of Asian
All over the website
Was true
I was literally my face
Today him it seemed like wait
The essence of this rule is that anyone can register the slant
As long as they're not
Asian
Which seems kind of odd
Not to mention
Potentially
A violation of his
14th Amendment
We haven't talked about the 14th Amendment yet
We will
That's the one that says
Everybody gets
Protection under the law
Here he seem to not beginning
Protection
On account
Of this rule that was
Try to prevent discrimination against Asians
Hangout the band starts at
Campaign tries to get a bunch of
Organizations to write it letters for them to get every single Asian-American
Newspaper in the country to write on her back
Half
And the trademark office
Still said
No that's not good enough
And so they appeal they say you're violating her
14th Amendment rights
Our first amendment rights
The trademark office
Countersuit
And to make a long story short
The case ends up at the
Supreme Court
I cannot imagine being taken
Supreme Court so what is your
Your feeling when you find that
Well
Always wanted to go
Was hoping it was under different circumstances
But at this point this is a lot bigger
Like
Knowing how long
Music groups last
This
Case could very well just
Continue to exist whether I had a band or not
So in January of 2017
Lee vs. Tam
Supremes heard the case
Thank you Mr chief justice
And Simon and his bandmates were right in front
What were the oral argument
Well that were arguments
Extremely surreal
Words that have other meanings in common discourse
Consumer
The intended purpose of the trademark Quattro
It was a room full of non-asian
People arguing about what was the fence
Station
People these words
To cause controversy
Absurd
Wasn't it about
Halfway Inn
Happy sweaters
When Justice Ginsburg
While she was questioning the government's attorney
When she says hey
Everyone
Nose
Ticket Clinic
United Way
But describe
Sting out of the word
Of course my heart swells and I'm like hell I think I'm in love with a Supreme Court Justice
Sport gern Simon goes back home doesn't really hear anything for months
Until
June 19th
Mm
I woke up and there were like 760 notifications on my phone
Indie rock band
The Slants
Will be allowed to trademark their name
A long time to trademark
And we found out that it was
Unanimous in our favor
And so
That is how the slant ended up doing an impromptu unplugged
Set on the steps of the
Supreme Court
Interestingly some people in the wake of that
Decision speculated that the Washington Redskins
Of all people would benefit from this landscape
Teams trademark had been denied
Because many Native American
Felt it was derogatory
In a couple weeks after this last victory
The denial of their trademark was avoided
It's so like everything
Supreme Court
But for our purpose
Out of the laundry list of American bands that have
Spoken out
Against the Federal
The Slants are the only ones
To our knowledge
To go to the
Supreme Court
And when
Any unanimous
Decision
Obviously
When we decided we were doing this amendments album
The Slants were one of the first bands that we reached out to
Yasso
View original approach
To do the
The album and I think
Requested to write a song about
The First Amendment because
Yeah we we had such a direct experience with that
But I thought it was a little
Obvious
Is pressed juicery
And then I started thinking about the different amendments and how I always wanted
To do something around
The 18th and 21st Amendment
Which is of course prohibition 18th Amendment
Prohibition of liquor
And then what eventually revoked is
21st Amendment
Repeal of prohibition
Because I always just found it really fascinating
The history of round
I mean
The reason why prohibition didn't really work us because
And all of the people didn't accept it so kind of shows
That when you kind of stomp out certain rights
Some people feel our
Parent they kind of find ways around it anyway
And then
Hi
Thought of this idea which I shared my
Guitar player I said what if we use 18 and 21 with a metaphor
44 age
Because
When we turn 18 we assume that we
Have all these rights
Like you have the right to
Vote
You can buy cigarettes or other things we can't drink
So you actually don't have your full set of like
Adult rights until you turn 21 and so I shared that with him and my guitarist Joe
Started writing
The song
Code 1821
Which is basically
Kind of about that about growing up in and the disillusionment the loss of Innocence that's what I think
Oh man the Slants killed it I love that song it's such an Anthem
You can hear the whole thing
All the songs at the most perfect album. Org
More perfect is created by me
Jad abumrad Susie lechtenberg Julia Longoria Kelly Prime sorry khary and Alla
Lights overington
With help from Michelle Harris Elie mystal David Gable and Nora Kettler
Thanks Jeffrey Wright
Burying amendments for us
This episode was produced a lot of Nasser Tracy hunt Matt kielty and McEwen Robert krulwich storm wheeler Dylan Keith and Rachel Cusick
From the lab
Blue dachshund with stories and songs
Not the 13th 14th
+ 50