WNYC Studios
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this more perfect
Today to stories from reporter Catherine Wells
First
Has some adult content in it so be warned feels new with kids
Might want to skip
Yours Catherine
So maybe we can start with the
The night
Started start with a start the who what when where
The best way to describe piano
You have a front row seat
The Greatest Show on Earth
September 17th
On the outskirts of Houston
There's
Deputy sheriff named Joseph Quinn and he hears this
Call go out on the radio
Somebody's called in and said there's a man going crazy with a gun in an apartment
She happens to be driving right by
Apartment complex
Pretty familiar with the complex
I knew where the building was so he's like hey I got this I'm right here
I could listen and see if I hear any kind of sound to disturb
Walked into the breezeway
On high alert senses heightened adrenaline pumping
In-N-Out in the middle Courtyard
It was a gentleman standing out there
Tootsie
Xiaomi he started yelling over here over here I could tell him I was
Upset
He's up there he's up there I should have wear any points up to this apartment on the second floor
Is that where you're saying that apartment right there he said yeah
So a couple other officers arrived and they get information
You know there's a blood pressure down to where you don't get tunnel vision
Went up the stairs
Wireless
When I get up to the top of the stairs
Got to the apartment door and their door was
A jar was open
I listen for a second
I could detect anything in the apartment
So we got ready and I
Push the door open all the way open
Announced our presence Sheriff's Department
Anyone in the apartment come out where we can see you keep your hands in plain sight
I did just two or three times
Very loudly
Still no response
There's a bedroom in the back of the apartment
To a back bedroom
It was closed and
These
Two officers start walking towards it
Is it open
As soon as he did
People arched back
Startled
So go to the bedroom
You've got to be kidding me
Really
What was it
It was
Two guys have
Something I'll never forget I mean it's like
Okay so here's the story the two guys that were in the apartment where John Laurens
And Tyron Garner
John was an older white guy he was in his fifties and Tyrone was a younger black guy in his 30s
Come to find out basically these gentleman downstairs
Former lover on again off again lover one and he was upset that the other that the day
They were engaged in some kind of
Pics of the guy in the parking lot was the boyfriend of Tyrone and we don't really know why he
Call 911
But the thought is that maybe he was jealous of whatever was going on in the apartment and he decided he wanted to get the
So you know the cops come in and Johnny Tyrone have no idea what's going on they didn't know that
The boyfriend had gone and
Call nine-one-one so they're shocked
Quinn says they start yelling at him
Just I mean combative
Belligerent
Refusing to comply with anything
80 gauge we were homophobic we were jackbooted not
Starting point
Besides
We're leaving here in the way you're acting and they're intoxicated we're going to have further calls here
Yeah it's not again
I'm here
Recite Surah Reston
Really what what
On what charge I mean they're just in their house
So that's
Question
Coleman for 15 years and
Blessed with the ability to have someone of what you would call a photographic memory
Meaning Hindu the penal code really well
He starts
Thinking he starts going through all the possible laws
Could apply to this
Statue 2106
It says that members of the same sex can engage
It's
Aloha Banning sodomy
You get sexual intercourse
Or not
Even treated like civilized
This is John Laurens from an interview he did with Lambda legal in 2008
It's one of the few bits of tape that we have
This is all of a sudden we're taking you downtown
I wasn't allowed to put clothes on
I was handcuffed and dragged downstairs
Officer Joe Quinn has a different version of that story
They refuse so
We forced them to put
Some underwear on you know we actually got him down and put underwear on them and escorted them out of the apartment like that
Which temperature second whatever happened in that room which cats will go in
Second
This moment
Two guys supposedly having sex and being charged with sod
It was like a strike of lightning
It would begin the process of a profoundly
Reshape America
What's interesting
This is one of the first things that you bumped into if you are an idiot
About to walk with Giants
And then you try to make a podcast about the law
Is it
There's often disconnect like laws are these things that float above us all these beautiful abstractions
And yet if you want to challenge LOL you got to find a person
Down here in the mud
Pictures perfectly Sumo captures what you feel is wrong with the law you got to find a perfect plaintiff
How do you find that person and what happens if they're not so perfect
These two stories are going to hear about a particular tactic that sometimes called test case litigation
And I wasn't too aware of before catheter
The Second Story actually touches on a recurrent case
We just decided a few days ago
Affirmative action will meet the guy
Who brought that case
The critics say is basically.
Throwing some of the most iconic civil rights law from the 60s
First
We get back to Katherine Wells with the story of a case called Lawrence V Texas
Oak
Come on Inn
I brought out my alarms
Vs Texas box of
Stop
So went to Houston and I visited a guy named Mitchell katine he's a lawyer there
And
He showed me the arrest papers he had the arrest paper
CJ Lawrence Criminal
Officers observed
The defendant engaged
In deviant sexual
Conduct
Charged with homosexual conduct
Right there and writing I mean it's
It really is strange to see those words on a piece of paper it seems like such an anachronism but it was not
Has dated
September 17th 1998
Snow in 1998
Texas wasn't the only state that had this kind of law on the books
At least 13 other states also had an anti-sodomy law and it's important to note that you know this law wasn't used very
Very much people were not arrested for this law because when would police be present in your home to observe you have
This is Dale Carpenter
No law
SMU Law School
I mean sodomy laws weren't really about stopping any
Body from having sex
They were really about ensuring
That we could label
People Criminal
It was
A label that people could
2.2
So the people who disapproved of homosexuality could say
Look defining app
Of homosexuality
A crime
Crime
Can you commit the crime
Well you're a criminal it's a criminal statute people can say your criminal
Which then give the state
Illegal basis to justify all sorts of housing discrimination employment discrimination
Military in every context
Statin effect
How many people argue that these laws
They also sent
Strong cultural message
The most recent example here in Houston is better described as a vicious
Killing in this was at a time when hate crimes in Houston word
Surprisingly, 27 years old died after being beat with a nail-studded two-by-four
2nd senseless killing in the Montrose area in less than three months is a lot of blood and was real parents
They've been shot
To make a long story short was very eager to repeal that sodomy law
Okay so John and Tyrone were arrested on a Thursday night
The next day it's so happen
That
Because of the location of John Lawrence as a partner
The case landed in a Justice of the
Peace Court meaning after Quinn made the arrest
The report was sent to that court for processing
Now this court is
Mostly deals with traffic
It's mostly a traffic court
But there happens to be this clerk in the court
Who was
Gay and it couldn't believe that there that somebody had actually been arrested for homosexual conduct in their home
Is Clerk and his partner go to a bar start talking to the bartender
I believe it was a Friday night
This is William Lewis he was the bartender what I was doing
Tender 90
Who is two guys come in and they tell Lane
You're not going to believe what happened
It's a couple of guys were arrested
And charged with the sodomy
And Linwood Lake
He just can't believe that such a thing happened it's such an unusual occurrence
And
Linford send me the report Monday morning Brighton early
I can hear my fax machine go off
I pulled it off
Officers observed
The defendant
Engage in deviance
And
And that's when it hit me
Oh
I mean it was so clear night and day to me
Immediately knew what I had in
What why does he care so much about
Well so when he wasn't
Being a bartender Lane was a community organizer
Tickly around LGBT issues I was present of the game has been political
Dukakis that's one of the oldest LGBT civil rights groups in the south
He been waiting for this moment how long have you been looking for a case
7/8 years
7 light years
Cuz just too
Later explicitly what why did you need I needed a test case
You can't change a law like that
If you don't have
A case
People in the Texas legislature have been trying to remove this law from the book
Books for years according to Dale Carpenter every time someone would introduce a proposal to repeal the law it would
Snickers and catcalls in the state legislature
It just wasn't really going anywhere
So activist who decided the only way to get this done is to bypass the legislature and go straight to the Core
So I need a case I had to have a someone guilty
Celine start trying to track them down at this point that you guys have been released from jail
Conversation basically went like this
Hi my name is Lane Lewis I'm a gay activist here in town you don't know me
Oh that's not important but I understand you've been arrested
I'm begging you not to plead out
Meeting don't just say you did it and pay the fine I knew I couldn't have them played out I will find you
Do lawyers
Raise the money I will pay for everything
Just
Don't do anything
Until you and I have an opportunity to me
She looks later they all meet at Mitchell katine xoffice
And it immediately becomes clear that these guys are sort of an Odd Couple John Lawrence at that time was
About he was 55 years old
Lab technician for a hospital with a young skinny black guy 24 years younger than John
I was study job from place to place and job to job no idea
What their connection was they weren't lovers
About heavy drinkers
Very heavy
Both have criminal records
Yes Tyrone has been convicted of assault and drug possession and John have been convicted in the sixties of Murder By
Automobile yeah they were not the perfect Planet they were not the poster boy these or not
Pretty tween
And they weren't political no not at all
Not at all
Weanling told John Lawrence
I'm a gay activist here in town John Lawrence didn't even know what that was I don't know what a gay activist is
Basically neither of them had any interest like no interest
And being a public figure
I gave him the whole
What your country can do for you ask not what you can do for your country speech I mean literally
I reminded them of who Harry hay was
Arguably the founder of the original LGBT movement
Ulysses may not remember but at one time it was illegal for
Certain number of a male
And the LGBT community
To get together in one location is illegal
Can do it the idea that they would be Networks
Of sanctuaries in places where we could come and out of which we would be able to move and organize and change things across
The country
So I told him a little bit about that history in
How far we've come and how far we had to go
And that
Bad enough
How to change that
So I told him
I said
I'll be able to protect you
For maybe the first year or two
But there's going to come a time when
I will no longer be about you
It'll be about some
Much much bigger
So
They agreed
Tyrone's attitude was okay
What do you need me to do
John was much more indignant
They took the wrong person
Golden song
It was a ridiculous law
But
Texas loves to keep Samantha
Quiet things around
He was mad
He was angry
Here's where the story gets
Complicated
Because
At one point according to Lane Lewis
They were having this conversation and John was ranting you know about how he been treated and
He said you know what the worst part is we won't even
He wanted. He said
That they were not having sex
Wait what that they were not having sex that they were
Sitting in their underwear on the couch
Watching the late-night news
They say they were sitting there doing nothing and the cops just burst in and started pushing them around and
That they were never even having sex
Wave it is in this whole case about them having sex
Sir sing the thing that this case is supposed to be about
Might not be true
Right so I interviewed
Three of the four police officers
Joe Carpenter says when he talked to the police officer
He did find that their stories were sort of all over the
The place one guy said it was anal sex seesaw
One day later said he thought it might have been oral
The other two officers said they never saw anything
Fidel says he believes John story
There probably was actually no sex
You think what might have happened is that the cops walked in and saw some gaytard on the wall and some gay magazines lying around
Feeling that really set off the office
And they said well we know they're homosexuals they probably engaged in homosexual conduct at some point and that's illegal in Texas
There was no no no doubt about it I mean I have no
No reason to live Quinn to this day
Still insist that he walked in on them
Copulating he says he saw what he saw and he just did his job
That's fine I don't agree with your lifestyle but that's
My opinion that's what it is
So there's no way to know what actually happened obviously but
In a way it doesn't matter
Because when John said that Tulane that they weren't even having sex
Message on don't ever say that again
Don't ever say that to anybody
Again
Because we could have people know that
We couldn't have people find that out
Is it going to go forward to this we were scared that
Another case would get screwed up at that point
And potentially
The da dropping the charges
You had to preserve the LIE
Correct correct
Dumb question
You can just do that you can just preserve a lie to keep a case going
Is that that's okay keep in mind it wasn't our job
Prove or disprove the LIE
The thing that mattered was not what did or didn't happen that night the thing that mattered
Was what the arrest report
Set but if what the arrest reports said
Potentially didn't happen
Should that matter
Well
No no one
Our legal system is not designed to bring out the truth this is a misc
Conception does not bring out the
Ezio Carpenter against people who play their roles
And pursuing
Whatever they think their best interests are
That's exactly what happened
So
For the first few years my job was to keep the boys out of the out of the news
And why was that
Well they had a tendency to drink
And get rowdy
And fight
And they like to go to CD hotels and rent rooms and get really really
Hi drunk whatever
And inevitably they would start fighting with each other
And so
What I did what I would do without wood
I knew the difference
Places they stay busy would go to the city hotels and talk to the clerk's give him a business card tell him
If these boys come and check in they cause problems
Call me first
Fan on more than one occasion that happened I'd get a call at 2 in the morning
Your guys are here they're causing trouble I'm going to have to call the cops how would jump out of bed put on my clothes cuz we couldn't have them
You know they're already on the front page of the used
The chronicle we could not have our defendants
Doing a perp walk for drugs and alcohol
So I would drive down there and I would figure out
Which one was causing the most problems
Put them in my car
And I would drive them somewhere else I would separate them out
That happened more than once
More than once
Celine city of the spear that
John and Tyrone wood would start talking to the media and let something slip
About
Their version of the story
So get them these little cards small little sentence basically said
Thank you for contacting me
Please refer to line Lewis and had my phone number in my ear
And I said so anytime the media contacts you
Don't think about what you say
Right that's what you get screwed up when you start
Thinking about what you want to say to the media pull this out of your wallet
Read it
Even though there were these close calls
As a case wound its way through the court system
Mitchell katine told me about this
One time there was this
Press conference
And we came outside to the normal media
Group that was out there wanting
Quotes and talk to us and they didn't want to hear from the lawyers they wanted to hear from the clients
He was like all right
Just this once
Tyrone get up to the mic and I think a reporter asked him
You know how do you feel about this
And he said
We didn't do anything wrong
He just kind of yelled at out and
Angry way we didn't do anything wrong
Metropolitan back and was like that's enough
That's enough next day
We didn't do anything wrong
That was the quote on the headlines of the mornings
Paper the next day and certainly I knew what you meant
But they weren't having sex what you know
Could also be interpreted as
Homosexual conduct
Nothing wrong
He says luckily
That's how people took it
Fracking
Couple years
You're kind of how it went down
They started at this
Justice of the Peace Court they were sentenced to a fine of 125 bucks so it peels
Send the case gets kicked up one level to the Harris County Criminal Court their find again they appeal it again
Level to the 14th court of appeals onemorelevel ultimately the Texas Criminal
Court of appeals which has the highest
Court of Texas
For Criminal Appeals refused even to hear the case
So the only next step is
Will hear argument next door number 02102 John Geddes Lawrence and
Tyrone
March 26th
Almost five years after the arrest
The case length of the Supreme Court
And by the time he gets up there
Mister chief justice inmates
The court the story is not dwelled upon at all
They didn't say
These guys weren't in a relationship
If these guys were having sex
One of them was cheating on his partner
Seems like they might have not been having sex anyway
Didn't say any of those things I said
Family relationships are established that there are hundreds of thousands of people that this is about
Families and relationships
How people in loving relationships
Have the right to express themselves and whatever they want it's none of the state's business
In the privacy of their own home
Performs much the same function as it doesn't show contacts
You know basically people in relationships have the right to have sex with each other regardless of their gender
Protected forever
The distance from
A fundamental matter
American values
Wow
It's like watching something float up from the sort of monkey like Realm of of human real life and then it just
It's kind of pretty rats
Netflix app
Yeah
It was such a pretty story that people words
Suspicious
My people were asking
How did this arrest even happen this was a setup you all set this up
That was their big Battle Cry
Show me Tokyo teen says he heard this over and over again
But I always want to say so so what if it was does that make it any less
Have a case
Who cares has further questions
Thank you very much
The Honorable court is now adjourned until Monday next
3 months later
Record number 02102 Lawrence against Texas
Justice Kennedy begins reading a summary of His
The question before the court has the validity
Have a Texas statute
For two persons of the same sex
Intimate sex
Wakanda
Everybody's waiting for the out
Houston Texas
Super contacts it wasn't totally clear how this case was going
Come out because 17 years earlier there's been a case called
Bowers vs
Does Hardwick
And then they had ruled that sodomy laws were fine
And I would suggest to the court that there is no constitutional
Conclusion
But there should be a fundamental right to engage
Homosexual sodomy
The Supreme Court almost never will sings order that recent
So Justice Kennedy starts talking about all the similarities between the cases
Dispatched
The tension starts building
And then finally he got
To the moment where he said
And it's not correct today
And at the point Justice Kennedy said that there were
People sobbing
Rallies Across the Nation gay rights Advocates celebrated their legal Victory a ruling so brought it surprised even many of
Court rules in favor of two Texas man who challenged a state law that made homosexual
The ruling overturned a Texas law that allowed police to arrest gays for having sex
12 other states have similar laws
Including a good morning John Lawrence was at home in his apartment in Houston
Watching the tanks
And all of a sudden it says has rule the law in concert
I came out of bed quite happy
Obviously not everybody
What's happy about it I have nothing against homosexuals
Promoting their agenda
Justice Scalia said basically
If you want this to happen that's fine but you're going about it the wrong way the court is not the place where this decision
Should be made you need to go talk to your fellow citizens
And convince them that this
La needs to check
Coming to us and asking us to bypass
What your fellow citizens seem to want that is
It's not how
What persuaded citizens
And imposing one's views in absence of democratic
Is something else
He sees this as a
Small minority imposing their views
On everybody
Ebony
Said he was worried about something else
Today's opinion
Dismantle
The structure of constitutional law
That has permitted a distinction to be made
Between heterosexual
And homosexuality
But this decision would open the floodgates
And that it would only be a matter of time
Before the court was being asked
To decide on gay marriage
And he was right when Kennedy read the marriage decision in 2015
The courthouse
Private
Yet it does not follow the freedom
Outlaw to outcast
Maybe a step forward
So what happened to
Garner and Lawrence
Well
John Lawrence and Tyron Garner didn't live to see this
Tyrone died in 2000
N64 meningitis
Had no money
He was 39 and his family was very poor
And they didn't have the money to bury
They didn't even have the money to reclaim his body from
County morgue
As for John Lawrence he died in 2011 at 68
From heart problems we didn't even find out about it
Until a month after he
It was dead
This hero of the gay-rights move
Was unknown and on
I just passed
What is a fair about
Sort of boat
Practice of bringing things to the Supreme Court
The two people whose story this case revolves around
Concerta Fade Into the background afterwards
Well one is tempted I think to be very cynical in some ways because it means that
These people were useful as long as they were useful and after that they could be forgotten
Galaxy had that reaction a little bit I mean this is
Story of social progress but there's something a little funny at the center of it for me
We're playing this for our legal editor Italian style
In a lot of ways are our legal system
Duval's in to an end
Justifies the means
Kind of Justice
We we care we we we care about the process so much
And unlock the processes
Extremely important Ellie isn't this just weird to you like this is a dumb law like a dumb dumb dumb dumb law
Why not to
Should there be an Avenue to say this is a dumb law was taken away why do you have to find some people
Didn't
Have
Sex they say
10 that they have
Sex then marched them up all the way through the court system and then forget about the time you just seems weird to me
Seems like a
Empty theater
Why do we have to do it that way
Because if you wanted to put a ballot initiative up in 2003 in Texas saying
Is gay sex okay
It would fail
It would fail in 2003 in
You probably fail in 2016 in Texas
To probably fail
In 2032
In Texas
That's why
The majority isn't always right
So you you you you
Take you basically take the Democratic at
And this isn't this is a this goes back right to the founding of our country
Like when are you going to let popular will
Run wild and when are you going to
Constraineth
Not just restrain a constipated
You know when you going to stop it
Nn
Warranty Texas is a is an example of a
We just going to stop
And it was the right call
So after this Supreme Court decision did Texas immediately go and repeal the law
No actually the laws still on the books in Texas
Know the Texas legislature
Like other legislators around the country refuses to repeal the law it stays there a sort of
Remnant of a
Kind of a dark
Almost forgotten past
Keep in mind they can't enforce the law now that is unconstitutional
But they refuse to take it off
Coming up the very deep dive into the guy behind one of the most
Controversial cases this term in case that just got decided late last week
Score perfect
United States
This is more perfect I'm chat album Rod if Supreme Court cases can sometimes feel like play
Where the activist and lawyers are sort of like the directors pulling the strings in the people in the center of the case
The plaintiffs are just like he's in perfect actors
Who been cast
And the scripts are written for them
Well that dynamic
With definitely an effect this term
Text just last week we have had a decision just handed down
In what was billed as the landmark affirmative action case of this term
Impact College admissions Nationwide
The case Fisher vs University of Texas centered around the following question
Use racial preferences in college admissions
Now the University of Texas has a policy where the top 10% of every High School class automatically get in but for everybody else
They will consider factors like race in the question was
Is that okay
Couple days ago the court decided
Barely
But yes it is okay the Supreme Court has upheld the affirmative action program at the University of Texas
Affirmative action and higher education is constitutional
Now the case was brought by a young white woman named Abigail Fisher
Erase me if hurt her chances to attend the University of Texas
Activities I was in who were being accepted into UT and the only other difference between us well
She was arguing that affirmative action discriminates
Against her as wipers
Now
What you saw in the wake of that decision and even before
Eonline
Warrant
Hate
Directed
Square liter
Cancel did Khalid black people have it better
If you don't take your little ass on somewhere maybe if your grace didn't suck your dumbass
Maybe you would have gotten into a good college Becky with the bad grades
Really happy you and your racist lawyer got shot down
Because this case may have very little to do that be Fisher I mean if you look at the press conference
Treated differently based on their race is the one of the podium but behind her
Are in the background
You'll see the sky
He's there in every single press conference quarterback
At the edge of the frame not too many people know about him his name is Edward Blum
And he's the one who actually brought the case
When it comes to this case and so many others
He is the architect
He's brought dozens of lawsuits not just this one
And he seems to be a maestro of getting cases to the
Supreme Court that challenged civil rights law
Critics or paint messes like one-man Wrecking Crew
For civil rights
He's almost single-handedly rolling back Decades of civil rights
And when it comes to affirmative action he says he's not done just make a long story short we wanted to meet him
Figure out how he does
Went to Tallahassee
Border Katherine Wells takes from here
That's where you live
He Winters
In Tallahassee
You walk in what initially struck
Golden Retriever
Is what initially
Struct me
Literally V
Of course
And
I don't know what I was expecting but when you hear about these cases you know I mean critics are really
People are mad about the
It is deeply disturbing truly outrageous
So I go to meet him and
Your flight
From Austin
The Dallas
To Tallahassee uneventful and
On time and
Good looks like a totally nice guy
A regular guy
Like a dad there's something in me that just loves tradition
And custom you love
Listening to the Great American Songbook
Beautiful
Frank Sinatra
And
Ella Fitzgerald
I love
Art and Museum
Independent films
Golfer what's his what's the story with his backstory
Well he's 64 I was born in a small town
In
Michigan
My dad
On the shoe store there my mom
Work with him in the shoe store
What happen your kind of political leaning
Up to this point
I'm
The first Republican my mother ever met
How to use the word typical but it it really
Was a typical liberal Jewish household
My mother and father
Where Franklin Roosevelt
Harry Truman Democrat
Always
He said he was
That way to all the way through college
The University of
Grad school University of New York
Where I spent a year
Studying of all things
African literature
But he says somewhere along the way his political leanings
Started started to shift I spend
A summer in Israel
Call Mom
Living Mana
Auntie says he came out of that experience a little less liberal than he was before
And you got married and then in the early 80s he's living in Houston working as a stockbroker
And
We met
Aren't our neighbors
This particular couple they were New Yorkers who would move to Houston both grew up as
Liberals and a guy he sort of opened my eyes
To the world of
The Neo cons
The guy introduced him to these magazines weekly
Standard National Review commentary magazine conservative
And this was around the time that the neocon movement was really hitting its stride
Garibaldi's New York liberals
Defecting
Is what he says
Thousand
Individuals
To grew up in the
Question
The wisdom
Obvious liberal
Policies
And he says
Slowly slowly
Overtime very
Gradually
He became one of those
Fast forward a little bit he's living in Houston garden-variety existence
And something happens that sends him on this entirely new
Basically he and his wife moved to a new neighborhood
They move from the suburbs into the downtown area
Urban and
In 1990
We went to vote
For the first time in our new neighborhood
I realized
That the Republican Party had not fielded
Candidate
To oppose the Democratic incumbent
Running for congress
This is a district
It has almost 600 thousand people
You don't have a choice you've only got one person running
Decided to run
Himself a lost item
No great surprise to anyone
He actually lost by 32
But
Along the way
What is something really unusual happy
During my campaign he and his wife Lark piano they decided they were going to go meet voters and their disc
They got a giant print out of all the addresses in the 18th congressional district
Call daywalking list and they just started going door-to-door meeting people
Handing out literature
Take
The even side of
Oak Street
And my wife would take the odd-numbered side of Oak
Street
And we would start to walk
And
Reese's
Very quickly they realized that
The district
Shape
Was funny
Some houses on one side of the street would be in the district in the house is on the other side
Sometimes the district would
McDonough Highway caption apartment
Text comeback it just
Didn't make sense
This is like Bloom wife of Edward Bloom peculiar because we had Maps we had to
Follow
And it was
Very odd the Wade some streets were
In the districts in somewhere
Took a while for it all to really sinking as to how this
Could happen I guess about a week of this
We realized that neighbors had been separate
Almost house by house because of their race
He comes to believe that the reason this was done was
For the explicit purpose to create a majority after
American desk
This is an untrue
Clothes from a clear and simple wrong part of the reason this was done was the Voting Rights Act of 1960
Of Americans are denied
The right to vote because of their color
Giant
Step forward in civil rights
One of the primary things that day it is eliminate barriers to voting like poll taxes and literacy tests
Strategies that have been used to keep minorities
And then this other thing it did
Sort of in a roundabout way through a series of interpretations is
It encouraged the creation of districts where the majority of Voters
Were minorities and that's because
You know one of the strategies that have been used
Use previously to
Dilute the minority was to take minority communities and
They called it cracking they
They said it split them apart and too many
So that they were never
In the majority enough to elect a representative
Voting Rights Act tried to
You correct that
18th congressional district
Was one of these majority-minority just
The district
Drawn by the text
But you have a slight
African American majority
I think about 51%
But this was the problem according to bloom
The way they got to that
African American majority was bite creating this District that's zigzagged all over the city and cut through neighborhood
I could not understand
People live close to
Together they sent their kids to the neighborhood schools they shopped in the neighborhood shopping centers they were worried about
Neighborhood issues
Brixies neighborhoods
Depart by race
Seemed
So wrong
In his mind
This law was actually
Not limiting discrimination but actually perpetuating
I don't know what the average person upon realizing this would have done but
I decided
File a lawsuit
Decided to sue the state of Texas
Called a few friends
Who lived in the 18th District
And a few other districts in Texas African American Hispanic
Looking and looking and looking until I found a lawyer that I can afford $7,000 a month
Filed lawsuit challenging the constitutionality Texas's
Rediske
Play the recent charged with yes the Voting Rights Act was good in its day
But now it was being used as this excuse to segregate people into racially polarized District
Worked its way through the lower courts and
Am I
Shock
And surprise
In 1995
Number 94805 George W bush vs Alvera of the Supreme Court
You went to the oral argument
Our opponents
Step to the left turning
Pele
The constitutionality of three congressional districts
They make
Their arguments
Y'all we have to put
People together by race
The Texas legislature has the obligation
To satisfy Federal requirements in a federal requirement
Like remember the Voting Rights Act we're trying to make sure that there are enough minorities in this
District
So that they have a chance to elect a representative
Then our advocate
Made his arguments
That was just being made
Basically said
But look at the map
The map is
Bizarre
And the only reason
It could have gotten this way as
Because you're only thinking about race
Only race
Think about it that seems messed up isn't that messed up it doesn't matter what your ultimate goal is
You cannot use
Forbidden tools rate is forbidden by the 14th Amendment to be used as a tool
A very tense situation
Let me explain
So in the end
Supreme Court
Hair-splitting decision
But I think it's at this deeper question that
In our society
Discourse we just haven't figured out how to talk about anyway
You don't look if you're defining race
Just the color of someone's skin
The government cannot use that in any way that's against the constitution on the other hand if you take
Take this wider View and you look at race in the context of History social context
How can the government address discrimination without taking race into account do they have to
So it's just typical balance
You can't look at race
But you have to look
Grace
And
The Supreme Court says to Texas look
All you're doing in this case is sorting People based on how they're labeled on a saint
You're not looking at that wider context you're not looking at if these communities with next to each other
Fisher common interest
You're just sorting them based on
Race alone and that's not good enough
You can't do that
When the
Opinion came down
The Supreme Court ruled in our favor
For 5 to 4
That was
Quite
A day
The day that we won that lawsuit
I was
String
Hooked
Forever
Edward Bloom decided that this would be his face became the court to try to strike down
Every race-based policy he could legal team was taken on the road I recruit
Plaintiffs in New York
Virginia South Carolina to challenge congressional district plans and we won
In each of those States
He helps to school districts in Florida and Texas and the use of racial quotas in case through 12
Magnet schools even after affirmative action in Houston city Contracting
Affirmative action
Six of which
Made it to the Supreme Court
Including
In 2013 in a five to four vote
Ford very divided Florida Supreme Court today
The Voting Rights Act of 1965 Supreme Court struck down a very important part of the Voting Rights
Becky 1965 Landmark lock is considered one of the most important pieces of civil rights
Legislation ever passed Shelby County vs holder this decision
Gutted the Voting Rights Act
Specifically there was as part of it that said
States and counties with a history of discrimination
How to check with the federal government first
Before they go about changing their voting laws basically the federal government was saying look
You've been up to all this stuff work
Now we're watching
Supreme Court said
You know
Time for change
That list was made a long time ago and
It's outdated
This decision
Restores an important constitutional order to our system of government
This was blooms
Fidget spinner
When Shelby County k
I think a lot of people burst into tears when I came down
Yeah
I understand it is deeply disturbing
Deeply disappointed
With a court
Decision in this matter
Change during the Civil Rights Movement
People died for the precious right to vote
This is congresswoman Sheila Jackson Lee of Houston tech
I would like to have the Supreme Court Justices go back in time
Second time and March with those who marched after Bloody Sunday
From Selma to Montgomery
A balloon has a right to his opinion
It doesn't mean that it has to be the opinion of the United States
I understand that
People were in
Gravely upset
I also know that there were people who were greatly relieved
And Gravely
Ratify
Yeah but I think what gets a lot of
People
Is it
You look at the Civil Rights videos you see tens
40 thousand people in the streets March
And you hold that and if you make a split screen in your mind you hold that thousand ten thousand people in one side
On the other side
You one guy
It does make you ask basic questions about tomorrow
That's a false
It's
That maybe your split screen but that's
Really not
Good luck in nineteen
America
Was
Held hostage
Bye
The legacies of slavery
And
The chokehold
Jim
Crow
Fast
Forward
The reauthorization
Of
The voting right
The chokehold
Gone
Away
African Americans
In the Deep South
Registered to vote
In numbers
Often exceeded
Participated in elections
In numbers that
Exceeded why
In terms of
Electoral opportunities
We have
Come
180 degrees
From
1960s degrees because of the law which you helped overturn an instant we don't know
YouTube what degree that is the psychology of America changing or the fact that we had a law that
Cat people online
And now that love has gone
And now we see voter ID laws coming back into play which I think any like sane person would admit is it is it is
Is it is an attempt a blatant attempt to disenfranchise
Just people so it feels a little bit strange that two I mean I completely agree with your things have gotten better
Same time I think
Well that was because of the law that's now gone
Look laws
Change laws
Evolve
+ and at some point
They need to come to an end
Okay
So just to jump back in
Something we haven't actually talked about yet is
Original question how how does this actually happened how does it work
How is one person
Able to be so effective to do this work if you need a computer a printer
A cell phone
Really about it
Play who pays for the lawyer fees
Who do you go to individuals that know of my work
There are foundations
Okay so he's a 501 c 3 like the NAACP and Lambda legal that funded
Lawrenceville
The Texas case
And if you're a 501 c 3 public charity as he has you don't have to reveal your donors to the
We do know a couple of his donors though and they're
Wealthy very conservative
So in the end what he does
Is 2
Just sort of a
More
Maybe a more strategic or sophisticated version of what Lane Lewis did in the first story
Like
In this case that he just lost last week
He wanted to challenge affirmative action so
The first thing you did was sort of do a casting
He said to find the perfect White
Set up a website called UT not fair. Org
Race as a factor in the admissions policy pretty budget it's just him looking at the camera
In front of a poster that says UT not fair
All high school students have been rejected from UT
To visit
At
UT not fair. Org
Tell us your story
And then he started talking to the people who responded
I think I ended up
5 responses
Of those about a hundred were
Viable
With a 75 you throughout just fly
Oakland teacher didn't think they would be
Sympathetic
Whittled the hundred down to seven that he thought would be sympathetic 7 or 2
Did not
Really want to go forward like I don't want that
Attention they were fearful
The backlash
Anyway
To make a long story short he ended up finding Abby Fisher because a friend of his called and said
Hey my daughter just got
Rejected from UT
I heard you were look
I think I'm a very
Like a very like introverted person so I feel
Like sometimes is a lot of pressure
I think it's in the end it's totally worth it and and to be able to tap a voice
In this into know that my voice is making a difference is really rewarding
She seemed like the perfect planet
Strawberry blonde hair
She's kind of shy in front of the camera in a good way
But last week
They lost
Sweet talk to him before all this happened so we weren't able to get a reaction from him but he did tell an Austin news
Paper that
The night after the decision came down
He had three glasses of wine
He took an Ambien
Any thought about these particular lyrics
In a Billy Joel song
The song called Keeping the Faith
I'm a long day
Runner
If there's something just emblematic about my personality
I run
Long distance
He says he's definitely
Not done
He's actually already has
Two more cases against
Affirmative action in the works
I have retained counsel to litigate
Harvard admissions
Policies in
University of North Carolina
Admission
I'm am sorry to just doesn't strike anyone I mean forget the politics whether you're on
On Lux aeterna.
The tactic doesn't strike anyone is like
Fishy
I resist giving Ed Bloom that much credit
Ethel MS Dollar General
Gladiator
I would say
What the fundamentally he's just implementing
A strategy that was perfected
By the people he now ironically seeks to disenfranchise
I'm this is civil rights movement 101
He's got laws if he doesn't like
That he knows he
You can't overturn
Through an election
What was the failed Congressional
He had that Lust For for political power
Couldn't get it through the electoral system but he found this other way
I'm to do it this is exactly what this
Okay so me and this is one of the most
Fascinating
Things about the
Story
If we go back to remember this case there's a famous case called Plessy versus Ferguson
Sir no not really a good example
This is Susan Carr law professor at American University Washington
10 College of Law
Plessy versus Ferguson 1892 that was a case
Where are the state of Louisiana
La witch
Said that people of color
And white people could not ride in the same train cars
If you heard the story
This is how it goes
Somebody named Homer Plessy black man sits down in a white car he is arrested and decides to sue
Annie's case goes all the way to the surf
The thing about that case
Is that it was a total setup
Flaming
So we go back when Louisiana passed that law requiring separate cars early civil rights groups were obvious
Horrified by this but
The railroad tie
Companies were actually
Mad about this too because they thought it would be much more expensive to run the trains
If they had to have add additional training so they have white cars in Cars of color
And so rights activist
Companies
They recruited somebody named Homer Plessy
Who was
7/8
White 1/8 Africa
And they sent him to go sit in a white car
On a train that he got into a
First class
People's car
And they sent somebody to go arrest him
Got a off duty police officers
You could do that at the time that you can hire a private detective to make
Pinterest
And today they hired that person to
So
Plus he gets onto the train
The conductor comes by and plessis Lake
Just thought I should let you know I'm actually in a black
And the conductor says well in that case you're going to need to be on the other
Car in the strain the Homer Plessy says
I'm good actually I I'm going to be staying right here
And the conductor says that you have to move and Homer Plessy you says no really not going to
Things get heated and eventually this detective that they've hired comes in and wrestling
And they brought a lawsuit
That's amazing the whole thing is cooked starting with
The arrest challenge the separate cars law and they were able to get it up to the US Supreme Court
And they were hoping
That they would be able to establish that
The idea of separating the races with uncut
Sensational
But unfortunately they miss
Calculated in the Court ruled that the law
Was Kant
And what they got instead was
Separate but equal
Totally backfired
But
It was this early example of this other way
You know if you can
Find a plaintiff for create a plaintiff
You might be able to bypass the legislature and go to the Supreme Court instead
The n-double-acp later picked up on this
Today weather true
Geniuses
They perfected it and they perfected it under circumstances where victories were highly unlikely
Play example in the early 1900s they do things like send a black guy and a white guy all over New York City
Segregated theaters
And see if one of them was prevented from being seated
And if they were
They would sue those theaters
And when victories that way then there was this other law in Louisville Kentucky that said nobody
I could buy a house
Or live on a block in with white people lives if they were African American
So they recruited a white guy to sell a house to a black guy and then they had the black guy refused to take the house so the white guy could say
You said you would buy the house but
I'm not buying the house because I can't live there white guys who's the black guy that was a manufactured case
It was one of the NAACP
First victory
And that's the case we're just as Homestead and it said that he ended up not publishing
Hey wait a minute this isn't even a real case
What's the time
Anything that involves manufacturing a case or fomenting litigation
All of those things were
Illegal
It's not just unethical but actually illegal
Yes
Criminally illegal
Sienna's
Something like that we see ambulance-chasing today the lawyers for the n-double-acp were very aware of AC
And this came to a head in the 19th
Britton The Voice EP
Wanted to get the court to end segregated
Basically they wanted to overturn
Plessy versus Ferguson
And the way they were doing this
You know they needed the plaintiff so the way they were looking for plaintiffs is going to
Meetings with parents and sort of
Quietly you know subtly trying to ask
Parents if they wanted to
To be the face
SOB's cases Virginia knew that they were doing this
And they tightened up these regulation
Since it said you know you can't
Drum up litigation
To try to stop them from doing this
So the n-double-acp sued
And they took this issue all the way to the Supreme
Test litigation
Is essential because
No matter how it legal it is public officials
Annette case the Supreme Court said
Actually
Manufacturing litigation is
Is a form of political
Expression
Really
And it is totally okay like free speech basically
It's a way of expressing your political view
And test case litigation exploded after
Play the 60s and 70s a lot of other movie
The women's movement Poor People's movement
Saw the success of civil rights movement was having with the strategy
And now I guess I'd include that blue
The founding
Principles
Of the Civil Rights Movement
Have been embraced
By the vast majority of
Those founding principle
Guide
These losses
That
Basic
Fundamental
Guiding principle
The Civil Rights
And how it needs to be applied to
Today I am.
I can't say what I think of that on family time Family Radio
That that is that is not that is an actor
Epsom is not
Carrying the standard
Forward for civil rights in America
Bailey says he is actually doing something good
Deeply important to our political system a lot of people who
Who agree with
Adblue
There they agreed with him in a way that couldn't be expressed in the polls
They're out there
I'm this is one way for that and that happens I think again that's at the another call back to the Silver Rights with
When you have a minority
The leaves in summer
They just get trampled
In popular election
Okay
But do they still have a voice should they still have
Should people have a way
I'm to not change on their behalf
/ the will of the majority
Seems to me
Textbook what courts are supposed to be able to do
To look out the rights of minorities political
I'm more than head of Africa racial religious
And see that they are not being trampled by a majoritarian attorney
A bloom is helping a minority of people who believe what he believed
Yeah I'm so not prepared for you saying any of this
This is really surprising to me
Thank you to Katherine Wells sincere thanks to her for reporting these two segments and Elie mystal are legal editor more perfect
What do spiny Chatham rod with Tobin low Kelsey Padgett and Susie lechtenberg who will take it from here
With Soren wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington Karen Duffin Sean rameswaram
Katherine Wells Barry Finkel any Mills Dylan Keith and Michelle Harris special thanks to deal Carpenter his book
Flagrant conduct is all about Lawrence versus Texas thanks also to Lambda legal Lisa Hardaway JD Doyle Arbor
German Amy Howe and gay Charles Supreme Court audio is from Oye a free law project in collaboration with
The Legal Information Institute at Cornell more perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation
The Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
And the Joyce Foundation