WNYC Studios
Can you hear me
I can hear you
Do you want
Who's your team
I root for Michigan
Because
Harvard in the sports bar without getting beat up
Killers different tears right
KU and Duke and bright
This is my private game chat voices are Susie lechtenberg more
Sexy producer
Uninstall
Legal editor
Okay so we made an album this season
West Branch musicians to interpret the
27 amendments to the US Constitution
On the podcast
We're telling stories about those amendments stories about why they matter
Aquila audio liner notes
To the song
Now the 13th Amendment 13th Amendment
Abolition of slavery
Is one of our most
Important
Please put in right after the Civil War 2
Put it into this National
Trauma
Of slavery
That right did its job back
65 and now it's kind of dormant
Right
Not exact
There is this little matter of the NCAA
Should we tell people what NCAA stands for
Susie Nelly take it from here
The NCAA is the National Collegiate
National Collegiate athletic
It is the governing body
For college
All of them is the Men's Track and Field Championship day 1 It's the final day of a division 1
Men's swimming and Diving championships
Wrestling Championships women's fencing championships in volleyball championship
From soccer to rowing to water polo to gymnastics
The revenue-generating one
AR
College football
Time to settle
The madness
And Men called.
How much money did they bring in
1.1 billion
And how much the players make
The players make $0
And zero cents
Volleyball
You may have heard of all this
It's been covered quite a bit
It really left into a lot of people's Consciousness back in 2014 when this guy Shabazz Napier
Who was the star player for the University of Connecticut said
During an interview
I go to bed and I'm starving
He didn't have enough money to eat
And this was just a few days before
Keeping score 22 points and Lead UConn to win the national championship
Neuropathy feel like
You want something in return
For all of this
Is Eric
There are not what some people arguing
Because the ideal of the traditional ideal
Or that people play for the love of the sport
And not for financial
And this was somehow spoil that somehow
Paying them enough to eat
Would spoil
Now interestingly if you survey people on this issue which we did
Hand washing posters alphabet I think that they should get paid
How much do you get paid
I definitely feel like you should get paid job and you're a student you have to be full-time as well so that's
Bessie two full-time jobs
They still profit margin on them is way too high
What you'll find is that
A majority of black people who are surveyed
On the other hand you think I should get paid no absolutely not how come
Because they're college students will find that most white people about
6 out of 10
Jose
No
I kind of believe they are getting paid by Guinea scholarship
I think if they're on a full scholarship that's
A lot more pay then
Any other
College
Kid Whatever Gets you
I really really don't think so
Ellie again
All of what my head always goes back to is
There's a lot of this conversation that should have been settled
And it should have been settled
In 1865
When we pass the 13th amend
13th Amendment
Abolition of slavery
Neither slavery
Nor involuntary servitude
Except as a punishment for Crime whereof the party shall have been duly convicted
Shall exist
Within the United States
Any place subject to their jurisdiction
Okay so what does NCAA basketball have to do with the 13th Amendment
Well the 13th amendment was ratified after the end of the Civil War it abolished
Slavery involuntary servitude
But there's
Sort of disastrous
That says
Except as a punishment for Crime whereof the party shall have been duly convicted
Involuntary servitude is okay if you are in prison
This is why states can use prisoners to build roads and fight fires and do all kinds of things
And not have to come
And believe it or not this is what the NCAA indirectly cited as a way to defend their practice
Back in 2016
2 Penn State runners
Sue the NCAA saying they should get paid
The 7th Circuit Court of Appeals came back with a verdict saying no
They don't have to pay you
In the reasoning the judge appointed to a case about prisoners not getting paid
Because of the 13th amend
Understandably
This comparison between NCAA athlete
In prisoners
Made a lot of people
Bentley has a racial overtone
Because we're not talking about this in hockey
And baseball nowicki
Conveniently having this conversation
About the two sports in particular
Basketball and football
That are predominantly black
Including former NCAA players
Who have gone pro
And how the contracts are
Basically struct
You know they were indentured servants contract isn't totalscan the fact it is
The fact that their nonprofit organization
Business model based on the plantation business model
My grandfather
Grew up on a plantation
So if I'm not
People know what that is
But the promise of the plantation was that next year will get better
Will never let you see the book
Will never let you
See how much cotton you pick
This is just how much it worth
Speaking to the great Bill Russell
We had a conversation in
Beijing music college and slavery
I just really dislike this
Which I understand
What people
Echo Janka law professor at Cardozo
Michigan fan first thing my children more when they were
Michigan one
Can all sing the fight song
Echo says
Look it up
So the connection
Ford labor law
This analogy that college athletes are two colleges as prisoners are
Prisons is
Unfortunately
Unfortunately then
But all that's really being said is that these students are not employees
No one was calling athletes
Indentured servants or
Play in the NCAA
Deeply broke
There's a casual cheap
Nest to the way in which people toss around
This is like slavery that is like slavery
In ways I thought
Think Ashley devalues Yagami
Alside
Did you just makes my skin crawl
I'm with
They're not
Chattel slavery
Was a horrible thing Ellie again
Having two
Play for Nick Saban is not the same
I get it
One of the things
That bothers me
About
13th Amendment conversate
Is that
There is a
There is a desire
Certain people
Look at the 13th Amendment
Hang up
Mission accomplished Banner
And and then consignment
Hope slavery was bad
Fix that
And we're done
No
That's not what the 13
18th amendment was about that's not what it was ever intended
The very first cases
About the
Talk not just about
Abolishing slavery
But about abolishing the
Incidence
Badges
On the 13th Amendment
Was a powerful
Legal docs
That should have allowed
Congress to go in
Andrew Tout
Not just slavery but discrimination
And when I look at
The NCAA
What I see are the incidents
And badges
These players are in debt
Play
They must play
For free
Where they're told
They must play when they're told to play
On the backs of oh but you sign but you signed up for the scholarship
If they play poorly
I think this is important but
When I think about the badges
Slavery
I think about
Parker prison
I think about that
Huge numbers of 1/2
Into our
Proportionately
Prison
Arrested
I think about
The fact that people lack the right to vote those to me are the
Badge isn't it
Echo says he agrees with the overall Spirit of what Ellie and some of these athletes are saying
He just thinks we're looking in the wrong place if we focus on that
But it strikes me that what is really happening here
Isn't about the athlete
It's about a settler harder
What is our relationship to our past
Like the history that the 13th amendment was designed to solve
Is that history still with us
How much
Where is it right to point something and say we are the way we are because of that
Because of how we were
Where is it a bridge too far
That conversation is going to be with us for a long time
Because
You know
At the very least it
Comes around every March
Are you ready for some more
My perfect executor Suzie lechtenberg
With liner notes for the 13th Amendment
Thanks also to Elie mystal
Attributing legal Editor to a show and Echo Janka law professor Cardozo
Okay on the album side of things we had
Two different artists
Who submitted songs for the 13th Amendment the 1st
Comes from brooklyn-based soul singer
Bette Smith
Course on the song it's just
That's an excerpt from Bette Smith song about the
13th Amendment in your the whole thing at the most perfect album. Org
Bill's got a second song and we're going to go out on this one
Cumsum rapper Kash Doll
2 minutes
Thanks to the 13th Amendment we thought this was
The one that would end it but we still her ass still mass incarceration so much for the emancipate
Patient Proclamation
Slavery is legal if you're convicted of a crime
Gwinnett crime that you committed probably don't fix the time
Have you build a ship for that sit and they pay you with dime a conspiracy they try to censor you when you speak
They can't hide behind the sheets on. They do you like me me while you take your chances out here trying to survive
Not a lot of pain since 1865 but still they try to teach you that everybody
Until you up for the same job as white people just don't want to be walking to the gate
Staying here United ready to fight for our freedom
That was Kash Doll with
13th Amendment
Genji noodle thing at the most
Perfect album. Org
I'm Jedi boom Rod will continue in a moment
This is my perfect time chat album ride this season we asked a bunch of different positions to
Interpret
The 27 Amendments
The US Constitution which resulted
In an album
And a one of the great joys of that was watching all of these
These people
Take the stage e words
And
Make
Personal
It's hell with that in mind
We did the lineup for the for the 13th Amendment here's his next one producer Julia Longoria
Tell me
The origin story of
Of your tweets
I feel like you are going to stay like why this girls of her like what Adam nausea
Just friend Julia why are you her friend
So
Recently my roommate and best friend
My name is Aaliyah Marie Alameda
Was on a quest
Troll me I left who annoy you
And ask if nauseous
Not only in private
Butt in public
And privately I had asked you earlier
If you were stranded on an island with
3 Amendment
What three amendments would you
And he rolled your eyes and walked away for me
Cement thinner
And see what ends up happening and I love this because
This project is created a lot of
Add conversations for all of us in our in our daily lives
But
Aaliyah ended up
Tweeting
The question that the entire show
Like all my co-workers
They said
Julia
If you were to go on a date with an amendment
Which amendment would it be
Who's the lucky who's lucky Amendment
This is
This is classically aware she's just like talking
Stupid but she manages to hit the nail on the head
Prairie like
What the whole season's about like we're taking you out on dates
With the amendment
You listen to the SEC
Sexy song you hear stories about them spend some
Time estimate question
Get to know them a little no pressure we're not making our long episodes about these things they're short
First Dates
Lithium
Okay so in your head like when you're writing this do you have an amendment in mind for you
I think I would do not
Yeah I'm probably more okay so 9 I'm going to pull up my phone really quickly
Distant like remember this
It says the enumeration in the Constitution
Petition of certain rights shall not be construed
To deny or disparage others retained by
People the ninth amendment is about the rights that we have that
Aren't necessarily listed in the Constitution
Esthetician
They call these
Number alright
And looked at one way
This amendment is about
Possibilities
Sota music The Nines is kind of like love at first sight or something or is it already like
Evit like
The weird corners of
Of you that like you don't
No
Yeah you know Alexa
The tall dark
Serious
Guy that like Ivan
I so high
That's not like she's got like
I don't want to get gender to the amendments
But that's another can of worms
But I think this is where we differ on the 9th because I feel like it would be good for like a couple dates
I think when you get down to it it's like okay
Okay bro but like really what are you actually about me like you know they just like
Casino
Number
Uni like okay I'm done with the stargazing like I'm ready to move on
But your thing you want I like
Mary number 9 is everything I'm saying I want to date like
Do you have to you know we don't
I don't know what I want in my life like I don't know if I would marry 9
I don't know I know my dad would want me would have be like
With the Second Amendment that's the right to bear arms
Would you date 19
Today date
Minion
19 of course is women's right to vote
Yeah I guess everything
I don't know
I feel like
That's another settling Amendment you know like all great like you treat women with her snack
It's like just the vote like
What amendment would you end up marrying you
The one the one right
The 14th Amendment
Citizenship rights
Equal protection
Apportionment
Civil War.
All persons born or naturalized in the United States
And subject to the jurisdiction thereof
Are citizens of the United States
And of the state wherein they reside
The amendment that grants citizenship and equality equal protection of the law
Is all of the all the
The stuff you know like it it checks all the boxes but it just like
If it would just live up to its goddamn potential then maybe maybe we could do this cuz I mean you look at look at
The history of the 14th Amendment like
Japanese internment dude like
These people were born in the US are citizens why can't we seem to live by the the beautiful things in
In written right there in the Constitution 14th Amendment date
For a couple of months and then they
Cellulite
Haley
Maybe you want to get
I don't think 14 but I would
I mean look at whatever. But equal protection of the laws
That's like
God damn like
I would marry that yeah if it would live up to its potential
Ina
Does any Amendment
I got my moments
Israel
They're so tight back
They don't solve all your problems they talk a big game
When push comes to shove do they show up looking for amendments
Still like tacos in at night that's not what they're going to do
There's not
I mean
A lot of
Are you still holding out hope for the night
It's really love it it's so good
I want to be like
60 years old
On a rocking chair in a Florida room
I'm sitting with a Madman
And being like
Hey did I ever tell you
When I was
Little
And I want a minute to
Return to Sender
What
You've never told me that
Story this is
To see
More perfect Julia Longoria
With her pal Aaliyah Almeida
And before I go I just want to say that
This is really an introduction to the poem The One and Only poem on the album
From Sarah Kay
My name is Sarah Kay
And this poem
It was inspired by the Fourteenth Amendment and
Tell the story of her grandmother
Who was
Interned
During
World War II in Japanese
Internment camps
Even though she was
An American citizen
I think
I've been a lot of time now
Wondering what it means to pledge allegiance to a country
But does not pledge allegiance
To you
And that's what I what I think about when I think about
The 14th amend
You can listen to Sarah's poem at the most perfect album. Org
And that's it I'm out
The 14th Amendment change the way our constitution works
Took some time
But it overturned
The infamous Dred Scott decision and it was supposed to make black p
Full citizens of the United States
Over the years lawyers like
Thurgood Marshall
Who would become a Justice
Just and Ruth Bader Ginsburg
To become a Justice
They used it to fight for racial equality in gender equality and today that Fight Continues
With lgbtq people immigrants.
Disabled
Countless others that
14th Amendment
Has become pivotal to those battles
But there was Battle
Obviously as we seen the news this week in fact
Continue
So I guess you could say a 450 years after it was ratified the 14th is still a work in progress
Steve
Free guns
Directions
Play
Silverman
Create
Where's marshmallow
Nnamdi ogbonnaya
Wrote a song for us about the 15th Amendment
Kind of speaks for itself
Circuit play golfing
Baby stuff
A baby steps
Problems
That's Nnamdi ogbonnaya
With a song for the 15th Amendment
Musically the harmonies on that song with just bananas
And I'm amazed it how
Deeply research that song is
And actually that is kind of the kid the case for the second song that was
Met for a sabbatical
Right after I read the credits
More perfect is produced by me
Jad abumrad Suzie lechtenberg Julia Longoria Kelly Prime
Sarkari and Alex overington withheld from Elie mystal Michelle Harris and David Gable
Thank you
Big thank you to Nora Keller for help making a record 27 the most perfect album
Text to Jeffrey Wright
Reading amendments for us you can listen to all the songs and read
Short funny essays about all the amendments
At the most perfect album
Dad work
Thanks for listening
Hi my name is Aisha Burns and I wrote a song about the Fifteenth Amendment
Mission for the general tone and feel of the song
The complexity of the amendment and the context under which it was passed
Black Americans the right to vote
Super Violet really changes things and the first black man vote the day after the amendment is passed
Over 600 black men
Enjoying local state and federal legislative bodies
And there's a real sense of
Agency within the black community in this year's however by the end of the decade State start passing
Their own laws that
Practically nullify the 15th Amendment things like poll taxes and grandfather clause
The main challenge that I faced well
Well arranging the song was deciding how do I tell the story of
What at first maybe seems like this big moment of Triumph and Power
So this kind of eerie feeling
That lingers through the song that the same time
The vocals especially can you give this sense of having overcome something which I and I think both of those things are true
As a black American it felt really important to me too
To tell that story and it's full complexity