Listener-supported WNYC
Be Studios
A more perfect people
I know you haven't heard from us in a while
A new season is on its way it's going to be a very interesting special different
Kind of situation for us than the first two seasons
Will dropping by today because
Supreme Court is made of hard came up with a really big controversial
Decision
Court upheld President Trump's travel ban
It was a split decision 5 to 4
Like so many decisions these days
But both sides
Name dropped this one particular Supreme Court case from back in 1944 at the korematsu
Decision
The majority
Said korematsu's got nothing to do with the travel ban The Descent
Sad
Yeah it does
This decision is just like korematsu the court now is using the same dangerous logic that use back then
If you
Haven't already
You can meet korematsu for yourself
We actually started off season 2 with this story from producer Julie Longoria that takes a look the korematsu
To decision
The guy behind it
In light of today's decision
It
My penis sting listen
Producer Julia Longoria start this off
The year is 1967 and the place
Is San Lorenzo High School in East Bay of California
And we're in a US History classroom
I was actually a junior in high school this is Karen korematsu I'm the executive
Director and founder of the Fred T korematsu Institute in San Francisco so on this particular day
Karen is sitting at the back of the classroom and our teacher had assigned each of
My classmates a little paperback book to read you know books about American history government in the US
Assignment was to
I get up in front of the class and give an oral book report that mean this is a long time ago so that's the way they used to do things
I don't even remember what my my book was are my subject but Karen said she was just sitting there and class list
Listening as one by one classmate Scott up
Talk about George Washington or Abraham Lincoln or whatever and then my friend
Maya who is Japanese-American 3rd Generation like myself got up in front of the class
And her book was called concentration camps USA
About the Japanese-American internment
And I thought
No that's interesting I hadn't heard about that before
What's that about
Am I his book report went something like this
In 1941 the United States of America was attacked
The president's president
Roosevelt had to respond
Broadband
So in terms of Defense
One of the big questions for Roosevelt was what happens if the Japanese invade the continental US
America's founding
They probably come in on the West Coast
And you had more than a hundred thousand Japanese-Americans living on the West Coast
Like what they turn against the United States
They didn't know
And so her friend my explained to the class on February 19th 1942
President Roosevelt issued executive order 90066
That gave the military the authority
To forcibly remove anyone of Japanese ancestry from the West Coast
She goes on to explain these the horrific circumstances and
How
120000 people of Japanese ancestry had been real forcibly removed from their home
She explained they were put into these
Detention camps really without any due process of law but then she went on to say but there was this one
Batman
Who refused to go to the camps
And he was arrested and he sue the government and took his case all the way to the Supreme Court
And then you became a landmarks
Supreme Court case
And that man's name
Is Fred korematsu
Oh
I said to myself
That's my name
She says the class got really quiet
And I had
35 pairs of eyes
Turn around looking at me
Okay yes
She. My last name is korematsu my dad's name is Fred but no way
There's no way it's my dad someone would have told me
So
Corson I go running home and
Confronting my mother and asking her
What she say
Well I got the standard to answer wait till your father gets home and you can ask him
That voice you heard by the way was Elie mystal our legal editor and by the time he
I got home it was 8 in the evening and so that's a long time after you know 3:30 in the afternoon
And I come down a little bit and I asked him in and he said
It happened a long time ago
And what he did he thought was right
And the government was wrong
And it was at clear and simple
I could just see
This hurt going over his face and I just couldn't ask him
Any more questions
Karen says it wasn't until years later that she learned what really happened
And why her dad never wanted to talk about it
Well
I was 21 then
This is fred korematsu at stapleton from the densho archives
And I was up on the hill
Sunday morning
My girlfriend on Fred story starts
Out on a date when you're that age you know you have a girlfriend just like anybody else
And she was more important to me than anything
Fred and his girlfriend Ida are driving in the Hills above San Francisco looking down on the city the Golden Gate Bridge
Bridge you've been dating this girl for a while now
Italian-American
Most of his friends were Caucasian we were in a car
And we were deciding what to do with such a nice day
If It Go picnicking or something like that
And then all sudden I heard
Pokemon are
Radio
Japanese Embassy
And I was quite shocked we both were
Fred knew there was a war on and that the US was likely to get involved
Even try to enlist in the US military but was denied because he was Japanese-American
This is sitting there one of his first thoughts was
Why does it have to be to pan some country was going to attack Pearl Harbor
I wish it was Russia
You know I just thought about that you know
I was bitter with the pan-fried having this happen
So I took her home
And then I went home
So
He gets home
Paintball shot
They're all sitting around the living room
The house is
Just in the spare his mom is in tears they were proud of being Japanese you know
They obey the law
They did everything that supposed to mean
To have this happen
I put them in chain
It was even hard to talk to them after that
Fred had a traditional immigrant Japanese-American families
His parents were born in Japan and then all his brothers were born here in the US born in Oakland California
He was the third out of four brothers and being the Third
At the 2nd to the 1st
That mattered absolutely
Fred wasn't unique position as the third son he could resist
We asked Lorraine Vani I teach at Seattle University School of Law for some contacts
Kiawah professor and a friend of Fred's family the cultural tradition is that the first son is the favorite son
The oldest was going to inherit the family garden and Nursery business II would help out with that business
Dad as a third son was very low on the totem pole
His parents didn't have the same expectations of him relatively speaking he was kind of the hook
Unlike his older brothers he didn't speak much Japanese and he felt more American than anything else
When I was in school we start each day for the Pledge of Allegiance I studied American history
I always been a good American citizen
So when he came home that Sunday when Pearl Harbor was attacked
Is family responsible whole thing was
Unsettling
I am
I didn't know what to do
And Fred says
Pretty soon after
Things got very weird
Within a few days I put spotlights on the whole Nursery at night
And they had a gun standing right now
Our home there around the fence there watching us cuz I went out one night to have a cigarette and I was saying on the
Parts of a cigarette
And God Yolanda if I was singling somebody
Ridiculous
Then came Roosevelt executive order
That big order 906 6
Authorized the military to make a series of smaller ones
The first set of orders was a curfew order
Saying that
Japanese Italians and Germans were subject to a curfew
Second order was a freeze order directed just at the Japanese on the West Coast
They weren't allowed to leave the area and then the third order wasn't ordered that they could not
We met
On the West Coast
Except for in the custody of an approved location by the army
They're about 15 of these assembly centers
Japanese-Americans were told to report to one of these centers by a certain date
Fred's family began to scramble to worry about what they were going to take
What was going to happen to the nursery and still expecting my mother you know the attention and
Worries so in the days before his family left
Fred made a decision
I am I had my own worries and I had mom girlfriend my own problems he decided not to go with his fam
I am
Doctor then bedtime
That I can want to
I won't leave with you
You didn't want to leave item behind
We thought maybe the two of them could make a break for it later on
Leave the state
Before the evacuation deadline
And
They said fine if you can do it
Go ahead
He was the third son
So he knew that his older brothers would be able to take care of the family and they said he was
Was a grown-up and he should make his own decisions
And so he did he went off and got his own apartment and his own job as a welder
I'm kind of lived under the radar
News brothers will be there to take care of his parents if you're with the family
Like my family or any Japanese family
You feel the pressure in the
Sadness
But on the outside is different just like a normal
What if you know
Just like we've been living all the time
I felt right at home
You know I'm an American citizen to you know
I didn't feel guilty
Cuz I don't think I did anything wrong. He was politically
Aware at this point
If you're asking me about whether he
Refuse to go as an act of political resistance
I don't think initially
Unconsciously he probably
Knew that what was happening to Japanese-Americans was wrong
But I don't think he had the words for that we might have today
Is on his way home from work one day that he reads in the newspaper
Paper about his parents and all the other Japanese-Americans in the area being taken away to camp
Baby's sick to my stomach and on that I can see my parents going in you.
My brother's going to camp and I'm not there you know
But that was only time that I felt kind of
Lonely you know like what what am I going to do now you know
It begins to slowly down on him what he's done
By staying in the Bay Area he is officially breaking the law
And he and Ida aren't sure what that means like will they be thrown in jail or worse
He talks in the archives about how he's worried
And I was worried to
Because now he could get arrested
So they start to think about their options
Fred decides to get an ID with a Spanish sounding last name on it so we won't be recognized as Japanese
And then
Ida says essentially
That might not be enough
She pulled out an article regarding plastic surgery
And
What do you think of this
I looked it over
And well
I didn't
I think it was a good idea but she said hey why don't you think about
That's this might be a good thing that will allow you to stay here
So the idea would be that he
You don't have his eyes doubled or something like that
A plastic surgery procedure where you put a fold in the eyelid
So you look more white less Japanese-American
Did you think I work
And that's I don't know
Well
She said she'll be looking to it
And
Why is it that I'm going to lose so we decide to try it
So Fred gets into his car and he drives into the city into San Francisco and he
Just stops in front of the doctor's office
Amsart spacing
Walking up the steps of this Victorian and then
Walking down the steps to leave and he was a really crummy idea and then
Walking back up the steps
Thinking well yeah maybe I just right it's a good idea and the down the steps
This is a ridiculous idea
Giving some doctor your hard-earned money to
Change your face
So it goes up
And down
And I
Turn down a notch
I'm down until
He decided to just
Going
Have a procedure done
He really did it as a way to
Protect them as they try to leave the state
The doctor said he was going to work on his eyes and then also fix a broken nose I had a broken nose
I'm playing football and I never had it fixed
And
So you could do a pretty good work on me
But it turned out he didn't do everything he said he would
Regis
Took my money that's what it was I join
There wasn't anything change except
I didn't have a broken nose anymore
So he drives back to the East Bay with a new nose but the same eyes
And shortly after that day at the doctor's office he's out buying cigarettes at a convenience store
Leclerc
Recognized him and reported him
And one day walking down the street he was stopped
And arrested
And
Spent his Memorial Day and 1942 in the San Leandro jail
When we got caught
They called her into
Yeah
And
I see the police chief
Talking to her for quite a while
I imagine it's a small jail and he's just been admitted so he's sitting in the lobby and he sees I to come into the front.
He's just out of earshot he can't make out exactly what they're saying but at a certain point
A stop talking
And she just walks out
So
That was the end of it
I never did see her again
They never saw each other
So you sitting there alone in the sea
San Leandro jail and they end up transferring him to Oakland jail for some reason and then he ends up at
The federal prison in San Francisco because resisting the order with a federal offense
Anyway
One day I got a call from the guard
And told me I had a visitor and I didn't know it was you know
I knew all my friends were in can't or they were in the military but Fred Goes Down to the visiting room anyway
And there's assman there
Well I believe in civil liberties
Right of people is being denied
This is something that I'm concerned about the man says his name is Ernest besic and then it was over
Easier to talk to me
He asked if I need some cigarettes or something like that you know
Just to break the ice by the way I asked him
Who do you represent
And Earnest response well
ACLU or something like that
We have no way of knowing what exactly was said between Fred and Ernest besig
Both men have passed away
But it seems like something important must have happened in this conversation because
If I was Lori Benitez I don't think he had the words
Or that we might have today Fred
Didn't have
Language of resistance before this moment
Something in that conversation must have given it to him
Because when Earnest Pathak asked him
Do you want me to represent you in a court of law
Fred says yes
What do you imagine the words were that
Might have turned him in that moment
Imagine
That
Method must have said to fraud
We think that what's happened to Japanese Americans
Is unconstitutional
We'd like to bring a lawsuit
To say the Japanese Americans
Are being sent away
Only because of their race
And in that
J-fred language
For what I think Fred knew was wrong
Basic try to get Fred out of jail but the military stepped in and said he had
How to join his family and camp
They were at a place called Tanforan race tracks
It was a temporary holding spot
So that meant that the first place that Fred went after jail was
A converted horse stall
The wind just blew in there no that's blue in there and everything
This was a small horse stall because Fred had asked for his own
Wanted to sit and think about what to say to his family to were also at Tanforan
Sat and looked at the single lone bear light bulb above and the smell of manure
Hey I mean it's ready for horses not for human beings
And then all sudden I hear a knock on the door
And I'll open it with my brother is hey you can't stay here
You got coming
Cedar Park
We walk spread over to the Star Wars families been living
And I was surprised the way they fixed up their stalls
They
Solar Paula cracks
And they put newspaper for the walls in the paper that all up
This was a common thing for these families
Thousands of them were transferred to more permanent camps and many stay there for up to 3 years
Overtime
The community
Kind of tried to build lives for themselves
You hear stories
MC pictures
People building small Japanese gardens
What they found in the area
She saw newsreels about the people who made the Desert Bloom
Eventually saw people
Farming you know baseball teams
My brother he was involved in various Japanese activities
And
He thought it might be a good idea for me to
Get some suggestions and opinions regarding to
If I should fight the case or not
So Phresh brother calls a meeting
You got about 30 young people together
Imagine it was f****** a mess hall or something like that
They discussed Frets case
They were
Discussion is to themselves or in little groups
And I stood around and waited for someone to speak
But no one actually came out to speak to me
I can see Fred kind of standing in a corner as people are gathered in small groups
Whispering to each other
Stealing glances at him
But no one says
The word to him
Finally one dead and you said Fred were undecided on
If I should find
Acacia not because
They don't want to
Make any more disturbance
Anything to upset
The parents right at the time because they were
To upset already and think just being in Camp
I told them their parents have been through enough
Leaving their lives behind
Basically they said
We can't help you
But there was one Japanese American group that did decide to say something about Fred's case
What's the name of the group
Jas
CL
Ernest message had a nickname for this group
The Japanese-American Citizens League
The jackals
I meant
With a leadership of that group
Several of them
I purged them
To oppose
The explosion
But they didn't seem to be particularly interested
The JCL condemned Frets case
And anyone else who fought against the government orders
Said it would not support any of these individuals were fighting the orders
And called them
Self-styled martyrs
Wow that use that phrase
Yes
They would basically get everyone else into trouble
To do this by myself
I just wonder if I was doing wrong or
I'll maybe putting them in Shame by
I'm bringing the issue up again
Because of Japanese people lay their peaceful people when they they like to leave things alone if they can
Because they were in enough trouble as it is because of this Pearl Harbor attack
And the country blame them
So they have the sort of a guilty complex
Even though
They have nothing to do with it
Majority I'm just avoided me so therefore I assume that
That
I got myself in this problem
And
That was my problem in the end not theirs
Fred continue to fight his case he argued that basically rounding up
Thousands of Japanese-Americans American citizens without a trial without due process
Basically amounted to racial discrimination
Is case made its way up and down the courts and eventually two and a half years
After he met unexpected in that jail cell
The case arrives
At the Supreme Court
Yo he thought that by the time his case got to the Supreme Court
That's Fred's daughter Karen again he would
Be able to vindicate his family and everyone that had been incarcerated
And that's how much he believed in the Supreme Court
And so when that didn't happen he felt like
If he felt like it was his fault
It's a big bird to carry around
What ends up happening is
On December 18th 1944
The Supreme Court
Rules against Fred
It's kind of a
Complicated decision
The Supreme Court said
Racial distinctions
When the government is making racial
Addiction is serious
We need to look at this very very carefully
And that was a big president
Sun a lot of ways
It's
Kind of
Victory for people fighting racial discrimination
But then the court turned around and said
Even though racial distinctions are serious
This one
Is not
Strictly racial
We are at war with the Japanese empire there for
Rounding up Japanese-American Citizens
Is a way to
Defend the nation
Kind of your friend at this point
Like it sounds like it sounds like lonely and then I can almost imagine because you're
Your
By yourself
Pretty-much on all fronts
The country that you feel so a part of that you want to actually enlist in the military to fight for
Doesn't seem to want you at that moment
Your own Community doesn't seem to want you
Your family
It's a Shame by you
Your girlfriend
Is gone
I can't imagine being more alone at this point
Any never shared that with my brother I
He shared it with my mother
But but we didn't that wasn't part of our Peg dinner conversation
We did it during World War II
You know
What is speed
This is the crazy thing about the korematsu decision
It is
Still on the books
That guy Carl Higbie got on Megyn Kelly and
Said this
Stuff about korematsu in the very next day he got on and apologize for saying that
But he's right
Korematsu is technically still good law
Justice Antonin Scalia
One said
That sherp korematsu was wrongly decided
But if you think that it's not going to happen again
You're kidding yourself
The car isn't going to get across the president
An international America
Would you like us to
I think so
You would you like it
No
That's not injured in school yet it's a judge named Richard Posner
Not the time that we talked to him he was on the 7th Circuit Court of Appeals
He was widely considered by
People on both the left and the right to be one of the most influential judges in the country
He sometimes called the 10th Supreme Court Justice
And he's a big defender of the korematsu decision
What do you say then to Fred korematsu what do you say then to to a Japanese-American about
Kind of the law and the courts
Well they were given compensation
Right I mean Thursday
There is no pain suffering there is there there's an anguish right that we can
Exactly commodify
Yeah but
At the time it all happened
Shortly after Pearl Harbor
It seemed like the right thing to do and probably was the right thing to
And I imagine that
The officials and
Federal government in
They probably didn't know anything about Japanese-Americans on the West Coast
Roosevelt ever compared to Japanese-American doubt it
Like I just
Thanks
The fact that he had never met anybody
I might have been a reason for him to be more restrained in his executive orders right now
No because all he cares about is the defense of the United States
If there's any possibility of Japanese-Americans somehow cooperating with a Japanese invade
Asian forced
That he has to
Move the Japanese-Americans
What's this I'm sure that's all he would have thought
I mean I think it's all he did think
But what else could you have thought of
That's the only thing
He is going to focus
And if he doesn't he could be impeached
Or he could also
Worried about citizens right I think one of the look you're not you
You're missing the priorities
Is the priority is defense
That's the priority that's what these people are thinking about
You think they have time to be thinking about any
Any kind of nice ideas for protecting people
Any more than
Lincoln did
What he's referring to there is a moment in 1861 when Abraham Lincoln basically tossed this alleged Confederate
In jail without due process
Man Justified it by saying he had to save the Union
Nikes
Supreme Court Justice Roger Taney ruled against him
Cheerleaders at all well Tony he's the Chief Justice and he said this
Jerk should be released
I guess I have to do that he's the Chief Justice
No you do that enough time
As the president you're out
It seems to me that
That's why we have courts
We have all, that is not why we have
We do not have cords
So that presidents can be checked
Institchu ations of a national emergency
That was my cords were set up
Then what I mean
I'm flailing now but
Then what stops then what
If Congress can't stop them and if the courts can't stop them
Like what can stop a president in a time of War
There's nobody that nobody can check that that's the president's responsibility
Obviously I'd like a do-over because it somehow In the Heat of the Moment
I forgot
That I'm talking about defending the rights of actual American citizens
And Posner is talking about
People who are Rebel
Tube country
There's probably a way where I could have said
Pointed that out to him
Friends of the Court stepping in
I mean it happens it happens to Truman
But you know judge Posner is right
But it doesn't happen
A lot
Which is why he gets to be judge Posner and I'm the guy that had to check with a p
And by the way do you think these Supreme Court Justices
Are great big brains
Pink Stars
Who are selected because of the best lawyers in the United States
And their decisions are
Are usually great
You think you all that
I don't I don't have a high respect for the Supreme Court at all
You look at them
How they are appointed who appoints
This is so why do you think the Supreme Court has such a great balance to the
President
This is what gets me up at
Get me going because
I still think it can be used as a present
So your ears you're still worried that it can be used
And that it
Do you think it will be like you don't like
You know I think we cannot take this for granted
Fred korematsu couldn't get Justice inside Supreme Court question is
Can you find it on the outside
More perfect will continue in a second
This is more perfect mchat I can ride here with Julie Longoria
All right so getting back to the story of Fred
Picking up from the decision what happened after that
So the
Internment camp where Fred was staying closed in 1945
And Fred have gotten permission by that point to work at a steel mill in Detroit
So he was living in Detroit
He fell in love with a woman named Katherine
They got married moved back to the Bay Area and had two kids
And Karen his daughter says that they were kind of ostracized from the Japanese American Community they grew up
Outside of the Japanese Community he was involved in Boy Scouts
Girl Scouts so I was a girl scout so we have the camps when we had to open the camp he would work on that
The Presbyterian Church in Oakland and then he became an elder
Even join the Lions Club and he was President twice
And Karen says throughout
The 40s
The 50s the 60s
She never heard him talk about his case no never
No never
Hit he just
Never
He never seen ever
Told the story
Even after she confronted him about it in high school yeah it's
That's it
But she says
In like 1969 ish
68 or 6
69 when the world was in a very different place
They got a phone call back in those days you know you my parents
Phone number was in the phone book
Of all things
Tell me my father we get phone calls from
Boston when it interview on but she really didn't want to talk about his case much he just
It was just too painful but this time there was a professor on the line
From the University of California Berkeley
It was a Japanese guy actually and he told Fred
I really really want you to come into my class
There was a ethnic studies
Class that was actually off-campus ethnic studies was not even recognize that
So he he talked
Yet at this ethnic studies class and these kids were brutal
Met UC Berkeley at that time had this in a notorious reputation of being very radical
People were asking questions during the whole hour this is Jean Quan former mayor of Oakland she was in the class that day
It was important times as you did as a different country like you have to learn up
Stand up to Authority and certainly these students were like DLC astounding saying well
Why didn't you why didn't you protest why didn't you do this why didn't you do that why didn't you fight harder
And we're almost
You're angry that we he wasn't angry I think
You got to remember that a lot of these students even know anything about the count
Many many kids had not had Frank discussions with their own Tara and so was korematsu me was probably a
Surrogate for light
Your parents
How could they have gone to that and never told me they had no right not
To tell me
And so they're really angry at their parents
Surrogate or not
Red felt like he was being indicted all over again it it was such a painful experience for my father he never
I want to speak to anyone again
Redwood ultimately challenge his conviction in a lower court
And you would win
The Supreme Court decision still stands
He was able to clear his own personal name
In around 1990
Again the world in a very different place
He finds himself again on a college campus
This time the University of Michigan
My father mother will Walking with some other students
Across campus to see the newly renovated library and
Beyond my father loved architecture was very old Gothic
Library so they're walking through the sort of open cloth
Looking at the architecture
And then they come upon this group of students
A group of
Arab
American students
The students start walking toward in
They
All of a sudden kind of surrounding my father and they had this
Certificate
To give to my father
To thank him for speaking up
So that was meaningful to him
Why why did that make you emotional
Why that story
Because it meant so much to my father
That this group really honored him
That also had been racially profiled
Y'all to think that he would be able to
Touch their lives it it kind of reinforced what
What he was doing
Do you have the same faith in the Constitution that your dad did that.
Have
Great faith in our constitution
It is a great document
It
It so happens though that it's the way that certain people interpreted
That gets us into trouble
Producer Julia Longoria
With a big assist from our legal editor Elie mystal
Water is clear 3.0 coming here tonight the Trump Administration unveiling news
New travel restrictions on certain foreign Nationals from eight countries
Everything with the feeling with a thinking they going to start a new line in United States
This is what we want we want
He wanted to Liberty V1 the people we are the people we the people
There are many many lawyers here they're all working pro bono today they're from different organization
What resistance looks like sends a message that they cannot do it
The way with constitutional protections without people standing up for the Constitution so
I think this is inspirational I think it's wonderful and I think we need to be vigilant and keep fighting
Here's something we should definitely know in today's travel ban
Decision the majority on the court did
Port to overturn korematsu
Which is a big deal
They said it was wrong the day was decided
And that it has been overruled
In the court of History
The Descent
Said that
The travel Ban case
Quote merely replaces one Gravely wrong decision with a nut
UK
You'll hear from us again very soon with information on the next season
In the meantime
Thanks for listening
Okay more perfect is produced by me Jad appenrod Susie elect
Edinburg Jenny Lawton Julie Longoria
Alex overington and Sarah Carey
Kyocera
Which elements Cristian farias Linda hirshman David Gable and Michelle Harris special
Thanks to the archives for the tape of Fred korematsu and Ernest bussick Supreme Court audio is from oil
A free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell leadership support for more
Perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial
Foundation