Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
The Honorable United States
Autumn United States
United States
J&J Adam Rossmore perfect
A miniseries about the Supreme Court
Begin
By the way album
I Love This Bar
We live in a democracy with three branches and it you got the executive branch
The legislative branch in the judicial branch that third branch
Judicial courts
Consists of about 100 ish
Federal courts on top of those courts is
Decor
This Temple
Of 9 now 8
Unelected lifetime appointees who seem to have this tremendous power almost tyrannical power they are wicked
Important and we reminded of this
Huge
Every time we turn on the TV
From losing our fundamental rights in this country
Cuz you we aren't election in the phrase that you hear a lot
Is it one of the most important things in ex-presidents going to do very well.
4 Supreme Court Justices
Never mind that most Americans have no idea
Cesare 2/3 can't even name a single just can't even name the one that just died
Judge Judy
Doesn't matter
We all know that whoever they are they're incredibly powerful people
Did they can instantly strike down a law that took years to pass Primm Court reversed
A Century of law
That I believe will open the floodgates
They can undo executive orders they can even change
Angel definition tok what makes a person what makes a marriage
They can even deciding election Justice Scalia usual responses get over
Ghettos of the possible corrupt
Washing of the
American Pie
Presidential City
Now with all the background chatter in the election it's so interesting to think about
The fact that
When it comes to the court in their power it didn't have to be this way
Have to be this way
And it wasn't
For a long time and it wasn't for a long time
Yeah Boy Kelsea Padgett will take it from here
I mean if you go back in time so you like early 1800
Court had so little power
They were meeting in the basement of Congress
That's a Linda monk constitutional scholar one
Newspaper refers to it later as a dark dank potato hole
A potato look like a swamp
Imagine there were spiders in there and they said there were windows
Maybe it wasn't that bad but still we think of three separate branches it's kind of hard to think of yourself as a separate Branch when your me
Reading in the basement of Congo
Not only that would Congress actually sets up
First Supreme Court
They created originally a supreme court of
Sex
Justices
That's your law professor akhil Reed Amar even number
How
Odd
Dates for freaked out over the court
Divided for for what's going to happen oh my God
Into function with an even number of just
You know where we're at
Originally the first Congress they created
Sixth member cuz they're not imagining
The court as deciding everything
You know the court split
Who cares
Because at the time they weren't deciding big
Case if they were deciding like affirmative action Roe v Wade nothing like that
They're really like he's a little tiny rinky-dink cases
And most of their time was spent literally riding in carriages from town to town
Trying cases around
The country and that's a big hassle they don't even get to sleep
In their own bed why are they riding around with so
Actually
Chatous
Separate geographical Zone
But they're in charge of that's actually still true today but I'm like today wouldn't went where people you don't come to the Supreme Court
Back then people were coming
That's a lie I'll install are legal
Why what
Seek out these guys someplace else
To hear my local issue
In South Carolina if they have something to say about it they can come South Carolina
Sit on my farm
And talk to me
Got to think about the country
In 1818 or 4
This is a state
Wright State
Eccentric
Which is to say that being a supreme court justices
The time is not a great gig
It's rough
Consequently the people who chose to do this
Well
Academy
Oh yeah I totally meant and who are like really smart but like a Motley Crew that isn't
Organize
Is a lawyer constitutional history enthusiasts pieces at the time on the court you had this one guy
Nicknamed old bacon face who has
Is like a maniac
He's like the kind of like Charlie Sheen Wild Thing in Major League type character very hot-tempered
Foul mouth
There's another one who
You know is like 4:55 and like really silent
The Supreme Court looks like a pretty rag-tag bunch
All of this happens and I think it's important
4 people understand all of this happens in part because
The Constitution is
Embarrassingly
Silent
On what the Supreme Court is
What should you do
How it should be constituted
Article 3 says article 3 of our
There shall be a Supreme Court
Thanks guys
Like if you read the Constitution which spends a lot of time to talk about the House of Representatives how are you going to count slaves
Its and it's going to be by population
Census every 10 years
Cuz the house is important
When it comes to the Supreme Court
All you get is like a
Couple of sentences almost nothing
At all
That's kind of the puzzle of this like how did they get so powerful
I mean it started out as it's like
Nobody's
In a basement
And now they're these
All powerful
Priest
The Supreme Court
Of the United States
9 men
And women
Heian government
Who sit in judgment on many of the Great question
Before our nation
So how did that happen especially when there's like argue
Nothing in the Constitution that said that that should happen
You can trace so much of this
Back to one movie
By one man
John Marshall John Marshall
The new
Chief
Justice
He writes to the court
1801 Marshall glycolysis first meeting of the cord
And one person shows up
What do you mean the other
Actually it was three
Play before we go too deep it can you just like what do you look like
They all look
He didn't mean that he was tall
His square jaw
Piercing eyes Marshalls
It was a smart cookie
Any would need to be
Because he ends up getting in this
Very famous by
Which is very famous second cousin
That would change the course of the American history like forever
Well
Just a little man named
Thomas J
TJ now John Marshall and Thomas Jefferson
We don't like each other
You think Hamilton and Jefferson
Actually it was Marshall and Jefferson
Who really despised each other
And yet they both come from Virginia they both come from the backcountry
Why all the hate
Family beef at one point John Marshall's wife's mother rejected Thomas Jefferson
What
Yeah with his wife's mother Gaston his mother-in-law
Yeah to the great Thomas yeah I know but that doesn't seem like enough for a reason
The non gossip
Cuz they were in opposite political party
I think an important thing to understand about Marshall is that he's a party man
Okay party man likes to party
Committed to his team
His team is
Are the federal
They love big
What time is National Bank
Rev up National Power the Republicans Thomas Jefferson's people
He likes
Small tiny government let the states have the
Or maybe even a favor The View that states can veto a federal law if they don't like it at least two guys please
Two cousins
Both National figures
Totally different philosophies
Even before Marshall hits the court
They're going
Baby Fenty Beauty and the Beast actually a slugfest to paraphrase
Marshall you're dishonest
Jefferson you're a hack Marshall you and your friends are poisoning America dislike
That is a food fight it's very difficult to stop the tendency to view the people that you disagree with as
As Eve
You're really hard we do that today all the time right
They even as much if not more than today
They thought that the other side was trying to destroy
The Americas they just create
Anyway
Drive to 1790 the Federalist or empower the Federalist holes all the dino branches
John Adams
President mostly love poison party
Hated by Thomas Jefferson
They literally call him like his rotundity very offencive
So out of the power and ultimately our guy John Marshall Marshall as Secretary of State when the highest officials in the oven
Station you know Hardiman
And for a while things are going well for his
Party
But then
Thomas Jefferson
Republican sweep in
Crush
Absolutely Crush
The Federalist
Like Landslide Crush
Yeah
Fleetwood Mac
The Republicans ran the table in 1800 they're going to take over the house
What do I do
We need to save the Republic
The Federalist have basically been swept out
But in his dire moment he has to say
Idealista
How old is the White House
The Supreme Court
Supreme Court normally nobody cares about the Supreme Court but like in this moment you thinking oh my gosh this is my last hope
As luck would have it a vacancy pops
Avakin Chief just
Position
So just as
Majestically has recently died and there's a vacancy well
Sitting chief justice Oliver Ellsworth steps down and Adams picks his secretary of state
John Marshall
To be the new
Chief
Justice
That's how we got John Marshall
And John Adams is one other thing
In the waning seconds of espresso
Adams and Eves repudiated Federalist jam through a whole bunch of federal judgeship
They create scores and new judges and they throw Federalist into almost all of this position
E-40 appointment he just throws in 40 judges right at the last minute to recreate sporty judges at the last minute and
Then he appoints Jefferson I would be
Ask Jordan is pissed a second
But in the meantime Adams have just a few days left in
His presidency so he's like frantically trying to get all these judges
Nominated people off confirm then once you confirm someone you have to let give them their Commission
You can just go around claiming you're a judge or claiming your paperwork
Formal seal
Signature of the president
End
As story goes as the clock is striking midnight on John Adams
Last day Adams is teen there in his office then try and get these papers out the door there
Frantically signing them stamping them
It's imagine like youngboy sprinting to the dead of night over their head
Like I think totally apocryphal story is that Jefferson's attorney-general like
Dorit midnight Netflix
Put down your pen
But apparently some of the commission's don't deliver
They just are left
Sitting on the dash
Because it wasn't like an oversight or something it's not even like
I thought like if a couple or left on the desk it's no big deal
It's a sign commission from the president it's like still a binding talking the fact that it wasn't formally delivered you know
You still get your
So
Kind of terrible situation for Jefferson he shows up the next day
To take power and the Judiciary is
Filled with ghosts of presidential appointees pass
Just a Bastion of
Partisan judge
So
As you can imagine
Jefferson and his friends think that this
This is not fair
Jefferson
Cease Marshall
And all of the other judges that Adams appointed
Adams is spies
On his
Administration
So Jefferson he decides to immediately retaliate
Cuz you know he won the presidency he won by a lot
He's like you're shoving all these judges down my throat and on top of that
We got your name to be the head of the judges the head of the Supreme Court is my evil second cousin War what is this
Joe Jefferson is running the country
Republican Congress to
Among other things
Cancel the Supreme Court term for 1802
Go home
Yeah they were like there's no more Supreme Court sorry
What happen today
What Obama's plan for immigration gets knocked out imagine him like instead of having like that peaceful press conference where he likes
Choses disappointment imagine instead he was like
Supreme Court
No good punks
That's right
Anyhow
Marshalls in a way for over a year there's no. Rancourt meeting
And when he comes back
Pretty clear to him.
Supreme Court
It's on life support
At the Republicans
Pull the plug any minute Marshall knows already that there are there rumblin
That one of his colleagues a man named Chase
Old bacon
You know
Backup should be impeached
So we see this Motley Crue in a dark tank potato
He's like
I got to do some
We're fighting for our life here
I was thinking about this on the way over
And it kind of reminds me of
You know there's a summer camp movies where there's a baseball team and they're like super ragtag and I can't get together
Like at the end they have to like play the really good team with the like the nice professional uniforms that's kind of like
The judges on the Supreme Court and Marshall
What is kind of like the counselor the camper you know with the new kid on the Block who who comes to the team is like
We can do this
You can do it
Q 80s movie training montage
He knows that the US is even going to have a court system
Supreme court Chief Keef this team up for the first thing that Marshal does is just
Professionalize
Did you ditch
He starts the tradition of wearing black robes
The part that judges appeared in their robes of just
She figured that the black robes would make them look
Westlake partisan hacks
And more like
There
Floating above the
The Fray
Beyond politics
Next moves all the justices into this one dorm the same rooming house
No wife no family all business trying to create that more perfect union
In the Judiciary
And just
To grease the wheels little bit
How to Madeira my dear
Is that someone yes but it's a fortified wine
Justice Marshall would order it in Great quantity
That many scholars think was part of John Marsh
Okay so he's professionalizing teams get them together
And then they get put to
It's a cousin on cousin smack
That's coming up
We continue
More perfect
JM Chatham Rod this is more perfect
Back to our story from Kelsey Padgett and we arrive at the
Pivotal moment
Cousin on cousin SmackDown.
Change America
Okay so remember I already told us that some of those
Commissions didn't get delivered
5 and that they were just
Like sitting on a desk somewhere and how they thought it wasn't a big deal
Because
It's still a binding document
When Jefferson comes to
Power
Apparently he
Find
A person is like oh
Look at this
Deliver these commissions
Guess you can't get those positions
Sorry what are the people that
Lost out because their commission did not get delivered was 1mr William Marbury
This businessman
Ears
Age to be Justice of the Peace
It's a pretty low ranking position
So he's sitting there he's waiting for his commercial show up like of course it never does and it
Finally Dawns on him like
Oh
The Jefferson Administration has it
I'm going to go get it
So and what he does actually end up being really important
But he files a lawsuit directly in the Supreme
But you can do that you can just go right to this report
My first time at this time
Congress has just passed a law that said the
Why can certain
Restring circumstances you can just go directly
He goes directly to Supreme Court and he says I have a
I have a legal right
I want
US Supreme Court
Order Thomas Jefferson give me that darn piece of paper that says I'm really a judge
The case gets name Barbara B Mann
Because James Madison is Jefferson Secretary of State
Forcing Marshall in the courts to
Have this confrontation with Jefferson
So now it's The Showdown it's between Marshalls ragtag team and Jeff
So basically what happened is
Deborah has a trial
Marines lawyers to get up there and they're like what happened did you have
Damn what you do with it
Twitch marbury's lawyers are like seriously these are all important official document signed by the president like
No one knows what happened
To their credit like no one like a sponge
Doubt
Official eBay
Stop arguing about whether or not the papers
Exist and they're like this is the more important question
Does the Jefferson Administration have to honor those papers do they have to give the commission to Marburg are they required
Is there a legal requirement that they give it to him
Any Marshalls had it several sounding hell yeah he should have gotten that Commission
Cuz the law is the law
You decide you're not going to follow logic
Cuz you don't like the guy who made the law
Fair
I mean that we talked a lot in this country
We Pat ourselves on the back of the sky
About our peaceful transfer of power
Elie mystal again how we seamlessly can go from one party to the other party
Without Bloodshed in the streets and whatever
Good for us
How do we actually get to that point
And this is a key reason why we
Because the decisions of the past administration
Still hold value even when that Administration
Is kicked out of office
Overthrown
By popular vote
Their decision
Still have still have sway still have a legal Force
Jefferson was
White
Obviously
Negating that
Marshall wants to say that a person you know
Suck it up cousin
Give this guy his papers official
Do your job
But he thinks twice
She understands how weak
1480 alkmaar
Marshall's afraid that if he orders Jefferson to give over those papers
Jefferson is going to straight up laughing his face and say you and what army I'm not going to do it
Literally they just got back from a
Congressionally mandated you can't come to work time Jefferson nose
Bulwell
But he has no intention of granting that
He will never
Give that
Jefferson nose
Marshall Motors
Marshall knows if he tell Jefferson
To give him the commission Jefferson is going to ignore him and in the power of the Supreme Court
Basically evaporate
Ellie says like if you think about it
If executive branch is going to say kind of right at the jump it if you make a decision that I don't like I'm just going to ignore that
Then every executive branch
Going on from Jefferson
Throughout the rest of our history is going to just ignore this
Supreme Court when the Supreme Court.
That the executive.
So basically Marshall
Pasta
If you rules for Jefferson he's selling out the lot he's going to make
The court look weak
Heroes against Jefferson
Jefferson can ignore the court
And
They're going to look weak
Either way Jefferson
And by the way
Supreme Court
Maybe disappears forever
Marshall needed to find a way
I'm to get through that he needed to
Find some way to kick this case
To be clear John Marshall
Running away from a fight with Thomas Jefferson
He says all true thing
He knows the times Jeff
Since you know straight up has more power
And so he's retreating
Wow it's like suddenly feels like apocalyptical moment
What does he do well so the thing that he does
It's like
The most
Jedi Master s thing ever
How did something page decision in in the beginning
It's a lot of pages
How is wrong
How he can't do what he did
How he is ruining America
A lot of that in the Marshall decision
But then when he gets to the matter at hand
He doesn't little
Ship
She says okay hold up yes
Barbary is right you should have gotten that Commission
And yes mr. Jefferson should not be doing this
We the Supreme Court jurist
To hear that
Court needs to have the power to hear a case
If a court doesn't have the power to hear a case
Even if you were completely right
Even if your position is
You can't get relief
Wait why would he say that they don't have jurisdiction
This is like where he uses the force
You know earlier I mentioned that Marbury brought this case under a law Congress has passed
It's at Marbury to come straight to the
Work like for this kind of situation
Well
John Marshall he goes back to the
Figure out like what he can do here
He finds his little sentence with article 3 section
Two in the Constitution that says like basically you're not supposed to go to the
Supreme Court first you're supposed to go to a different
And then
Of course it's an appeals court exactly but but he basically tells Marbury the point
You came in and you came to the Supreme Court first
And
You did that because Congress passed a law that said that you could come to the Supreme Court first
But
The Constitution says
That you can't come to
Supreme Court first
So I can't help you
Is that your fault mr. Marbury but that law was unconstitutional
And we're not going to follow that.
Digital director
Si see what you did there
Maybe I see I don't know in Star Wars
The first one where Obi-Wan Kenobi is fighting with Darth Vader
He says
This like that
But real
Marshall is agreeing to lose
He's like found this way to lose
Like let Darth Vader strike them down to make it more powerful he's basically saying to his cousin
Okay you don't have to give her a breeze
Commission
And the reason you don't have to give Barbara his commission is his cuz that law doesn't work
Because we
The court
We get to decide
When something agrees with or doesn't agree with console
So like to grass
You win
Cousin by the way
We the court have the power to declare things unconstitutional that was the sort of Jedi Master
For laying down to the right
He establishes a new rule of the game unconstitutional
Inside this morning
Highly technical highly political
Drama between these two cousins
John Marshall
Sneaks in
An atomic bomb
This incredible power
In Marshall's decision he wrote is synthetically the dude in province of the judicial Department to say what
The law is say what the law is say what the law is and with those words he made the court would have
What is today
US Supreme Court ruled Monday along that would Americans born in Jerusalem Israel
The place of birth is unconstitutional is unconstitutional
Constitutional fun Constitution
And no one has ever done that before well I mean like people talked about it
Theories about it
The first time
The Supreme Court.
In the face of the president
Ernesto a Miranda petitioner vs Arizona against the United
And that's how it is on this path
New York Times company petitioner vs lb
Today
What is so much more powerful it's grown into the 800-pound gorilla when it
Simon Says jump
Other branches
Tend to say
How high
Take you for granted
Three words Bush V Gore they decide the presidential election and and no one blinks
Mr. Bento
Yeah yeah yeah I know you could be excited for me clothes you could reasonably argue that Marbury versus Madison was
Not the big moment
When the court got its power because
It really depends on what you mean when you say power
I guess we were talking with our legal editor Elena Stalin
Constitutional scholar
They both said like look what happens after this case
30 years down the road is
John Marshall
Still the Chief Justice he gets into a dust-up with Andrew Jackson
Message Jackson were talking about so generally it was
I would like to do horrible things Native Americans
You probably shouldn't do horrible things the Native Americans
I don't remember asking you a god
Damn thing
Essentially had a situation where Marshall makes ruling saying we have to respect Native American sovereignty and Jackson family
Supposedly
That we don't know if
True I think it's more fun to believe that
Did say that
It works better than me
Now let them enforce it
John Marshall has made his decision now let him enforce it
To make a long sad story short you get the Trail of Tears thousands of Native Americans were marched off their land
There's evidence that they were purposefully move during the winter so that more people would die along the way so well
The court maybe had constant
2-channel Authority it didn't have a key
Actual power
Until or just got here on this and that the students are in the 1950s
Court orders school to desegregate they don't
And the president sends in the troops
National Guardsmen
Playing boots on the ground
Force
Still so often comes down
And exactly
Willing to putt
Boots on the ground
In order to enforce
That's on the power becomes real
Although maybe not
I don't know what time
Before I went to college
And eventually after hours
Austin College where things were not
Separate
At one point is we're working on the story Elie talked to his mom and she told him that
When she was growing up in the mid-sixties
Years after
More than a decade
Best brownie
You would still never know what happened no one would know it.
Clarksdale MS
Mississippi
There was a public library but I was not allowed to go to that Library
My father
Who was China
Could going
Into the library
So many times I sit in the car
What that one
The library to get a book that I want it
And this is this is after the passage of the Civil Rights Act
Yes
Shanghai
School I graduated
Just
Yesterday as a recording this
Icourt had to issue
How to issue another ruling ordering a town in Mississippi
Desegregate its schools
Yeah that didn't happen
5 years ago
Yesterday man
Yesterday
The courts
Can make these laws
But if the people
Aren't willing to go along with
With and what do these laws mean
I think ultimately I agree with learning Han
He was a judge in New York in the early nineteen hundreds
Too much upon laws and courts in concert
Tatoosh ins that these are
False hopes
Liberty lies in the hearts of men and women and when it dies there no law no court no cost
Teaching and save it
Indian For Better or Worse
We the people still have the power
Okay so why do we call this podcast we called it
As it turns out
The top
Vast majority of Americans like 60
He 6%
Cannot name a single Supreme God
For justice
We also found them when we went out and a lot of people had no idea how many justices
There are
Do not know how many Supreme Court justices
17 Supreme Court judges
12/9
9 yes
We think we should know about these people
We should at least
Know their names
So the title of this podcast
Is a mnemonic device
To help you remember the names
Names of the justice
This is so their last names are
Kagan Kennedy Thomas
Ginsburg Briars
Breyer no s there
Roberts
Alito and Sotomayor and Merrick Garland get Sandoval's
Garland
Cake and Kennedy Thomas Ginsburg Breyer Roberts Toledo Sotomayor maybe Garland
So first letter last name cake 80GB Ras maybe cheap what if they turn them to song
Help you remember
Kittens kick the giggly blue robot
All summer
Baby
God damn
Kittens kick the giggly blue robot
All summer
Baby God damn
Maybe
God damn
Can you get the Game of Thrones robot
Maybe
God damn
Ready
Kitten pictures
Baby
You can find that song on a website radiolab.org more perfect
And now you make one
Send it to us
Seriously
More perfect by me jeroboam Rod Suzie lechtenberg
Tobin locale
Padgett and Sean Robinson
What's on Wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington Karen Duffin Katherine Wells Barry Finkel Andy Mills
Dylan Keith and Eva.
Special things to Judith Resnik Paul Bogle early and told Jessica Miller anemic you and Matthew Matt kielty aletheia
John Mead Bernard Nadia Sirota and John Hanrahan
Supreme Court audio is a free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation to Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation