WNYC Studios
This is my perfect I'm Jack I'm rod
J a story
From our producer
Julie Longoria
So I've been working on an episode about sex discrimination for like
Months now
We're supposed to release it
Sexual harassment scandals have been golf Harvey Weinstein Senator Al Franken
This week
Actor Kevin Spacey today Troy more today the story we're going to tell is not about sexual harassment
Quick I can't
Thanks tree with all the stuff that's happening look at what's happening with you
Thousands posted the claims online using the simple phrase me too
Talking about it and I can't help but think that we seen this before
Outcry for public change
A backlash
Women out there
Seriously
Like we're in our respective quarters and men to help us letting out a big screen
How do people not know but
When things quiet down
Will there be a change
And what kind of change is the kind that will stick
Today story
It's about a time in the not-so-distant past when there was a similarly loud rock is division in our country
Over sexual equality
Wonder Woman
Quiet
Strategically
Laid the foundation
A real change
Supreme Court of the United States
God save the United States and this honorable Court
Here we are
I'm going to ask an orderly false question which is where would you like to start as if we haven't been doing this
You're so damn long
Okay
So let me outline
The
Basic dilemma that's at the heart of the story
I'm going to put it to you as a question
If you were to
Do a Ctrl F in the Constitution like how many times do you think the words
How
Sex
Is one one time
In the Nineteenth Amendment which
Grants people the right to vote
Based on
Really
Yes that's the only time
The only time which is crazy cuz we are looking at is there a sex where that's not sex like gender or some
Is there like ladies in the condition of women no women have a
Problem
Which is that basically we're not in the car
Accept it like in this one little spot
So when it comes to discriminating against women
Some people have argued that
You
There's nothing in the Constitution
That says you can't do it certainly the Constitution does not require sexual
Discrimination on the basis of sex
Constitution doesn't require it it simply doesn't forbid it
Fatboy Justice Antonin Scalia
It doesn't mean nobody ever voted
For that
Where do you get it from
There was nothing it said that I mean not not those words explicitly but there is nothing that says you can't discriminate
Not on the basis of sex
That's legal editor Cristian farias
We had a 40
18th Amendment
I told people that we are
Equal under the law that everyone is equal protection of the laws
It does not say Miss, I never applied the 14th Amendment
Identify the 15th that's Martha Griffiths congresswoman when you think about the history of the Fourteenth Amendment
As legal editorial Linda Hershman says the Fourteenth Amendment was
Passed in the aftermath of the Civil War along with the 13th and 5th
13th Amendment abolishing slavery and 16th Amendment giving black people a black men the right
Boat if you understand that
14th Amendment to be
A part of that Trio of amendments okay it was meant to bring equality to black people
When the Fifteenth Amendment have been written which that every citizen could vote
In The Name Of Heaven so I couldn't women vote
Why don't you why don't you have to have the 19th Amendment
Of course the answer why is he didn't consider women people
There was this basic assumption in the lot
Equality for black people is one thing but men and women
They're different it was the case that the Supreme Court had never once
Met a distinction between men and women it didn't like Wendy Williams law professor emeritus at Georgetown
What are some greatest hits of ridiculous distinction
What's the case called Bradwell and it was 1873 or 4
In that case
A woman
Wanted to become
A lawyer
Illinois Bar said and the justices said that that that was a perfectly good rule
Because
The justice system
Could be seen as not appropriate for women
Now
Let's jump clear into the next Century here
Okay it was called gessert versus Cleary that went
The Supreme Court
And the issue was
Whether women could be bartenders
The court
Thought that was
Pretty humorous
That it made sense that women could not be bartenders
Unless their husbands or fathers
Were in charge of the bar
You know women are not
Supposed to be at the bar at either bar those two cases represent attitudes
Almost 80 years apart
Women belonged in the private
Sphere
That was not only the place it was built into their
Bodies
And that was the assumption
Bro bong
Long time
But just about
This country who feel like they're being pushed around things had started to
Come to a boil
Sex and race
Because they are easy visible differences have been the primary ways of organizing human beings into Superior
An inferior group
So in the late sixties and early seventies people like Gloria Steinem
Other than those chosen audre Lorde
Stop sexism to get some traction saying okay it's time to put it in the car
Constitution
Hurry up and historians say it's a constitutional convention for women
Resolution APUSH
For something called the Equal Rights Amendment
What are your hopes for do you think it will be ratified the stratified early next year
In 1975 it will be ratified
But it didn't get the boats in 1975
1976 will be the year
Or in 1976
4 in 1977
And the movement is stalled
Why what
What's dalda
Well
A lot
But much of the credit goes to this woman
A woman named Phyllis
Sloppily my husband Fred for letting me come today
I love to say that because it irritates the women's libbers more than anything that I said
She was a lawyer and a
Self-described housewife
Who started the movement
Call stop Yaris
Beneficiary
Give me a great opportunity to get out from under their obligation
Her position was that the Equal Rights Amendment would actually strip women
Of the special privilege that they have that comes from being a woman
We not I think though the laws of our country have given a very wonderful status to the married woman and the wife has a great deal
Mini rice
For example she has the legal right to be supported by her
And she said
If this amendment passes
It will be certain unintended
Consequences
Amendment says you cannot discriminate on account of fact and if you wanted to know
Marriage license to a man and a man or deny homosexual the right to teach in the schools
And that would be unconstitutional under era
And that argument
Caught on
They are things that could happen from the passage of an era
None of us
Would like to see happen with generation after generation deteriorate
I think that there would be homosexual to expect preferential treatment
To hear what I have to say cuz you know what's going to happen if I passed the ER there will be $100
Bathroom swimming using all our stall County Waste in the paper towels in the yard and all
Drive to
I don't know what we're going to do
Had the Equal Rights Amendment passed
Legal editor Lynn Hershman against it would have looked a lot like the racial Civil Rights Movement
Did
But the Equal Rights Amendment did not pass
It fell
States
Short
To get a constitutional amendment passed without you need 3/4 of state legislatures to say they want it
That is
38 out of 50
They only ever got 35
Dude
So the question is
If you want to get equal rights
For women
Written into the law
What do you do
There's no era
The women's lib movement Spark
Backlash
What
Do you do
Well
Enter stage left
Notorious RBG
Ruth Bader Ginsburg RBG can do 20 push-ups and not the so-called girl kind
For she was a Supreme Court Justice or a workout sensation before all that
Ruth Ginsburg she was at the ACLU
This was in the 70s
And one of the characteristics of Ruth Ginsburg which exists to this day
You can hear this
It's the first time she argued in front of the Supreme Court in 1973
When you ask her question
There would be
Silence
Enough silence
To make a person nervous and start trying to help her answer the question
Kuwait
But
We can imagine
It was in one of those long pauses
At Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Rescued from the key principles behind the era
Repackage them and March them in through a side door
Sex like race is a visible characteristics
Bearing no necessary relationship to ability
Has been the major bases for unjustified for at least
Where to buy cannabis like what it what exactly did RBG do so let me walk you through it.
It's beautiful
But you're a fight is underway
And RBG and her colleagues are watching this
Right and they're getting worried
What if the area doesn't pass
What are we going to do if that's the case
How are we going to get equal rights for women
So they decided
Okay as an alternate approach
Let's go back to the fourteenth
The 14th amendments immediate objective
What's the provide National Protection
For the newly freed slaves
You know which
As we said was designed from the beginning to be only about race
Suggest broader object
The states were prevented from depriving any person
Equal protection
Have the balls
Well it says the word person
So that
Should include women
If they could just get the courts to see it that way then
By default almost we would have
I sort of era
And accordingly
The task was
Showing that the racially inflected
14th Amendment apply
Sex the what about the law is she trying to
To change what
What does she want the court to say
She wants the court to say that sex would be treated just like race
And here's why that's so important
When the court sees racial discrimination
Under the Fourteenth Amendment it takes a really hard line
Looks at it really really closely
Or at least it's supposed
Whereas other kinds of discrimination
Not so much
It is actually some discrimination is necessary
Discriminate
It has to
It discriminates between 18 year old and 17 year olds
Between criminal and non-criminal that would be otherwise right
But the courts decided that race
Is going to be a big red flag
They're going to ask government's legislators presidents to have a compelling reason a compelling State interest
Do race discrimination
Otherwise
It's going to be on Cox
You with me so far
Yes to discriminate based on race you need to pass a really super hard test
By the way the legal name for this test
Strict
Scrutiny
Animation
Call the lake
We mean business or something like that
But anyway the point was that like they took it seriously
Which you know back in the day they weren't doing with sex discrimination at all
Because when legislators would come up with these Lots like this women can't be bartender sloth
The Supreme Court would be like
You know
You guys probably have a good reason for that
Listen to review reason it can just be a reason does not to be very good this up to be good
Victor even maybe even make it up on the fly it just has to be a reason
For upholding this law like in the case of the bartenders law
Bars are dangerous
Women need more protection be like okay
So RBG needed a way to convince the court
To be as intense about sex determination
As they were about Reese's
Discrimination
But how do you convince an audience
Of men
Were used to discriminate on the basis
Who been doing it for years
How do you convince them that discrimination is a bad thing
I think of people who want to keep women down would like nothing better than to women go off in the corner at
I speak only to win
Nothing would happen
This is her giving a recent talk about her 1970s strategy
You need to persuade
Men
If this is right for society
Part one of her strategy
Choose your words carefully
The head of Secretariat Columbia
Who said I'm typing these things for you
And jumping out all over the
Pages Texas
Don't you know that
The audience you are address
The first
Association
Of those men
What the word sex
He's not what you're talking about
Why don't you use a grammar book
Charm use gender
But you know the word sex has a charge to it
Gender
Cooler
In part two of her strategy
Choose your cases carefully
This is all happening in the 70s
Eastwind RBG is the head of ACLU women's rights project
So she's deciding which kinds of cases the ACLU is going to support
As they make their way to an all-male Supreme Court
Strategy was
If we live in a man's world right now
We need to find cases
But nine men at this moment
Can handle so for example early on her tenure at the women's rights project
The other Lefty lawyers
Are suggesting that the women's movement needs
To take up the cause of us being right
And she says
Not
Yes
And I think
Go slow
Is the right approach
She said first
We need to go after that
Small
Insidious idea
At the Supreme Court had been keeping alive for years
The laws of our country have given a very wonderful status to the married woman
That Phyllis Schlafly idea that discrimination is actually good
For women gender classes
Applications
Will always rationalize
As favors
The women
And so
RPG decided not just to bring cases where women were the victims of
Discrimination
Okay
My name is Curtis Craig
She brought cases
Where men are the victim
Who were you as an 18 year old
Now that's a great question
That was like any 18
You're old
Young man
Invincible thought I was quite the ladies man you name it I mean
He made it into Lambda Chi Alpha at Oklahoma State
He was living at frat house
Arab attorney was primarily made up of wrestlers so was when you went down the hall
You're about to be taken down at any moment you be thrown into the wall
You leave a body print
What do you mean like an indentation literally in the wall or like
It was
There's amazing
There was a lot of partying going on
Lot of beer yard would be filled with beer cans
And here's the key if they wanted to get all that beer
They had to enlist the help
Of the lady you know the sorority sisters yes you would have a female buy you a beer and
Can go out and
Party they need women to buy beer
Why because in Oklahoma
State at the time, had a very silly
Girls could buy beer at age 18 but
Boys had
Wait until
21 was something about
The level of maturity I guess for women versus men at that time the basic principle was that
Boy got into more car accidents so
They should be trusted with
Blessed beer
Did that make you angry
Well I was extremely unfair I would say
It made I think most men angry at the time
And a Supreme Court case
Was born
So the thirsty
Cboys
I brought this
To the RBG RBG gets involved in this
Beer case
Yes but this is this is a this is a situation where women have rights men don't
Why would she want
Argue this case
Matcha tea want the opposite
This is
Where
Chris strategy is
Kind of like
A trojan horse
You look at this case right on the outside
It looks like
A case about men being discriminated
But
If you think about it
Beneath that discrimination is actually this
Unspoken idea
About women
So go with me on this rated men
Are irresponsible they can't handle beer then women girls are more responsible and well
I'll behave
More delicate they could be trusted with something like beer cuz they won't abuse
You know so
With that line of thinking
It's not long before you're
Women
Them from
You know scary places like
Bars or courtroom score
Political office
Using this case
RBG is able to walk into the court this discrimination about men but also the discrimination against women that's
Attached to it
In or inside of it
That's clever
We're just getting started
More perfect continues intimate
This is my perfect I'm Jedi boom Rod here with Julia Longoria
Who's telling us the story of
A case involving boys and beer that became a kind of Trojan Horse
In the battle for women's rights
Know the story of the Trojan Horse maybe you know this it's you know ancient Greece
You got Sparta fighting Troy the Spartans want to get into the city of Troy
Giant wall City
Too big they can't get in
And so Odysseus comes up with his clever plan
Give the Trojans this giant wooden horse
They'll bring it to the city
Don't think it's a gift that we're retreating
What they thought
And then at night
Are soldiers were hidden inside the horse will come out
And they will take the city
In our case
Odysseus is is RBG
She said she's trying to get into is the Old Mills
Court
What
In order for this
Very
Admittedly imperfect
We need someone in the horse to come out the warrior in the horse the woman warrior
And
In our case
That woman warrior
She didn't even know she was going to go into battle
Julia you take from here so
I got in the car
And I drove
A long-time tiny little gravel
Road
Waiting up to
Narrow Street
Houses
Sparta North Carolina
Scott Sparta thousand horses and Trump sign
Tractor up
And so I walk up to this house it's this beautiful cream colored Cottage perched on top of amount
And I come here
Whitney Houston Saving All My Love For You blasting
I know I didn't
You Caroline
Very nice to meet you and I meet
What up what
Carolyn whitener
Simbi 77
She
Immediately offers me a course
Will you have a beer with me
No I can't I'm a diabetic
I can drink a little but not much
What does she look like describe her reddish blonde hair green eyes
Wrinkled and hoops
She has like this
This air about her that she could have been a beauty queen you know
But she also could have been a car mechanic
So we get to talkin I thought a little bit about who I am about the story
She actually told me like a French Lick
I'm proud of the young women I have a granddaughter that I'm so proud of you
Your generation they're finishing the fight I started and I was essentially like
No no no no
Stop like your story has like a huge impact on like
Women like me you know
Henry imagine
Embassy my name was never tied in with it
Was always Craig's name
So
You know it wasn't that big a deal
She told me she grew up bouncing around different oil field
How tall is Arnold field trash
That's what we were called oilfield trash
Battement Carolina and her brother and sister split the school year between two or three schools a year removed
Jesus school didn't come easily to her but my dad he taught all three of us had a whale he was a welder how to work
Work on a car is there a dependent when she was about 13 they moved to Chickasha Oklahoma
Indianola
Is where she met
Dwayne that was the first boy I went with they met in high school
And they were roughly the same age but he was
3 years ahead of her at school
And know what attracted you to him
His mind
He had an excellent mind
And he was just a farm boy
With no education he never went to college
He could have been about
Anything you don't want to do it then what do you think attracted
Him to you like what do you think he saw in you
I was somebody new in town
Talking to Carolina I got to send
She did not have any shortage of
Suitors betta when turned 18
Turn that off
And when I married
My husband
I was equal to him except the money and he didn't think anybody could handle that but him
He acted like he was Raising me and he probably was
She says she was really comfortable with him he was a quiet man with the
Brilliant mind
But
He just what he was pure German girl
Have you ever met a German man
Okay they are in total control
And how does Carolyn connect to the case with the Frat Boys in RBG
Okay so here's what happened
It's 1962
Carolyn and Duane are about 20 years old at this point
They moved to a town called Stillwater Oklahoma
Open a business
Stillwater
Is a college town
Black college Towngate got Oklahoma State University right there tons of fraternities including Lambda
Method wrestlers
Huge homecoming drawing over 40000 alumni we didn't know what homecoming was
Had no idea what homecoming was but shortly after moving to Stillwater
They open the doors
To the honk and holler and where we went in
Was just about
Three blocks poor blocks from the college
And we went into business there
A drive-through convenience store is like the real old gas station with oil.
In the floor here that would work
Customers pull up
To the side of the convenience store and the drive-thru
Honk their horn
Holler their order and you'd have to go out
And why don't them come back in and get what they wanted and take it back out
Soda in and out and in and out
All night long
You wear tennis shoes out real fast
It was all
Cheer Energy and guts
Homecoming night we were supposed to close at 11 the store is flooded with
Customers
Tell
I think
Two or three in the morning they're like thrilled because they've never run a business by themselves before
And all these college kids are coming in and buying Coors beer
Including of course
A steady stream of girls buying beer
Presumably for their boyfriend
And it Al I never did get to see homecoming
I saw was cars coming in and out
Fast forward a few years
Back at the University at all
Had long blonde hair Curtis Craig's buddy named Mark Walker
The time is it a political science class and the professor starts talking about the whole fight for the era
Which is happening right at that moment
And at this point Oklahoma hasn't ratified the era
Somehow the conversation turns to
Gearlock
MRSA
Talk about discrimination this beer law
Is discrimination against.
And the professor challenged him about doing something about the beer laws if he was going to complain about
The one day I was behind the counter
People coming in and out Mark Walker walks into the honk and holler so young man
Came in to talk to me
She doesn't really have time to talk
She's running in and out but
They stood there waiting patiently I bet he was in there for hours and it was looking at the beer license
You looked at the license
A nurse is that Caroline's name
Is the one on it
Because actually my husband lost his license after he sold beer to a young man
So
He put them in my name
Anyway
At a certain point
In between all the hunks and hollers he asked me
What I thought about the beer laws
And I told him
I was very vocal about it
I always had been she says it doesn't make any sense we send these young men off to war we're being drafted at 18
We don't let them drink beer when they come back
Was that just
At The Mention the liability issues you have these 18 year old girls coming in buying beer slipping into their boyfriends
How am I supposed to stop at
Your you can't
True
Who buys what
So eventually when Mark Walker ask for her help he
Said he was
Going to do a term paper be like
Sure why not I was always willing to help them
Because they had helped us
Get started
And I still thought it was a term paper
So was he
Not being completely honest with you then
Well I didn't hear half of what he said
I was busy every time he came in
So you know
It wasn't that important at the time
So I didn't think any more about it
He left
My husband was gone
He was out of state working
And I knew I didn't even say anything to him about it it wasn't important
You know I just thought it was a conversation
But it wasn't just a Converse
Because before that meeting mark
Had gone out
Looking for a lawyer
That's correct
And Curtis and Mark and the other frat brothers
I tried to reach the money that was flawed in a campus town
Her body
Use their last dollar for that last beer
But they managed to find this lawyer who would do it on the cheap
Alright well I'm just bread yogurt Attorney-at-Law no big signal no big deal
Remember I'm always wearing his military boots actually I believe you warm even to the Supreme Court
Fred had worked on another male discrimination case
In the past
This case was pretty straightforward
Most irresponsible and drunken woman in the state could buy it and unlimited
Quantities that 18
Well that was discrimination
What kind of Mora male rights case
What was
And do you remember corresponding with Ruth
Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Ruth Bader Ginsburg before she was on the court
Somehow
Ruth Bader Ginsburg noticed
And she watched
As Fred made his way up the courts
Losing at every level
And by this point Ruth Bader Ginsburg was head of the women's rights project at the ACLU
She already argued a few cases
Is before The Supreme Court
Which had changed the court
Slowly
For the idea that sex
Was like race
And she thought that this case
With interest
She gave her to call a problem
Interpersonal relationship
There's no question
I was something of an unreconstructed male chauvinist
So she was not
Fred did not see this as a women's rights
We're just kind of an unnecessary insult the man for no reason at all
Looking at this case.
No Fred
It's more than that
It didn't matter to her
If the plaintiff was a man or a woman
Because in most of those cases
The discrimination against the man was derivative of a prior and worst discrimination against the woman
Here's to the ladies
The bear and the week
How do they do it
Where do I find all that energy
That's seemingly inexhaustible store of pets
Ginger
Again
Bruce was after the stereotype about women that was nestled inside the fear loss
That women are more responsible
And well-behaved
But in order for her to make that connection she needed Fred to write his brief
In a way that would be useful to her
So prefer not just to male discrimination
But discrimination based on gender
Well
I supported her
I just never was
Shall we say a militant feminist
Ruth had her work cut out for her
She was getting used to dealing with these roaches from the sticks
So with other local lawyers that she'd worked with in the past Ruth have been more forceful
Insisting that she make the argument
But that had backfired
So she likes like okay you argue it right
She wrote The Fred telling him that
She didn't need to be the one to present oral argument before the court
She was fine if he do it
But she very gently very persistently
Was able to convince him to let her help him with his legal brief
Betta
I think it was a
Couple months later cuz my husband was out-of-state every month meanwhile back at the honk and holler Carolyn has no eyes
Idea what's going on
No no ID
And I got a phone call
My husband was on the phone
Well I have salesman in and I had people coming in and out
And
He was
I right
Furious
I couldn't figure out what was going on
Choose like
Case reading about well he had picked up a newspaper
In North Carolina in a bank
And it was on the front page of the newspaper
With my name and
About us soon
It look like we sued everybody in the state of Oklahoma that was an office all way down to the
Garbage man he's like what did you do how are you we don't want to get mixed up in this we don't want her name on this one.
I want to make a fuss like this could hurt business like how dare you you know I didn't know what happened I really didn't
No eventually she figured out it must have been that kid came in
And now it's like at the Supreme Court
What I was back and forth on that phone with him trying to wait on customers and I bet that
Took about 3 hours and he would not let up on me and he kept calling back and call him back he called Allah
Lawyer he was mad
And then the last phone call he said I am flying back in and he said you pick me up
Couple nights later
Drove to the airport
Picked him up
Anna
He was still mad
That was the longest
Car ride
As they grow back
She says he just
Lectured her
The whole ride I just listened to him
What did he say
I don't know what he said word to word
Yeah I just know he was strong with what he said
With my husband it was best to just be silent
I was never afraid of him
But
I knew how far to push it
Tommy got from the airport to the other side it was about an hour and 20 minutes
That's a long an hour and 20 minutes in the car
Where you can't get out
And over the course of that hour and 20 minutes
She said something in her
Kind of shifted
And at a certain point she
Basically turned to him and was like
No
Like I know you want me to drop this case
But I'm going to fight this out he threatened me Every Witch Way
I didn't budge
And probably
The reason why I didn't budge
Because he fought me so hard on it
You know I believed in it
That I had never stepped out like that that's the first time I really
Put my foot down and didn't budge
I gave so much to him
I mean
I didn't get a salary for 25 years
I didn't ask
I figured we were equal
I figured I work the same hours he did
And I figured I stood
Deciding not behind him and not in front of him
October 5th 1976
Day of oral arguments
The lawyer Fred Gilbert across very many people that I didn't care for him I didn't care for
He was so
Pushy
Insist
That Carolyn needs to come to these
I didn't have the money to go and I didn't want to go
I never traveled anywhere by myself what I recall that day Curtis crack came to
I was dressed up
Student I had borrowed address
Plastic look like leather walking up those stairs high heels I remember that distinctly
So big beautiful building felt like I was walking forever up those stairs
I was burning up I was sweating
Will hear arguments next to the 75628 Craig against foreign
Whenever you're ready
Fred Gilbert starts things off
Keep box up to the podium in his combat boots
Ron Darling
Even though
Most alcoholic most immature
Mosto
I purchase 3.2% beer at age 18
Absolutely unlimit
The law doesn't say it
But those words
And by all accounts
Didn't exactly kill it
The worst justices just kept hammering
Movies age backing track
Hammering
What is before the courts
Before the court
What's before the cord is your complaint Curtis was sitting beside me and I kept punching what does that mean
What are they talking about what does that mean he kept
Be quiet
Overall tell you
I didn't understand what they were doing
Challenge today was originally enacted
19 night but she says what caught her ear was a moment when Justice rehnquist when he called me
When you say we
You're referring to your client who is the tavern keeper
Saloonkeeper
Can you call me that in the Supreme Court I came so near standing up and corrected him and I've always will
Going to do this time I didn't
Technically
As arguments went on Fred did at least
Try to do the thing that Ruth wanted
Anything to be if you could pass a law saying
No negro will
Compare sex discrimination to race discrimination
The thing is you can't discriminate even for something like public safety
On the basis of certain criteria what is the court ever held the Discrimination of this sort is of the same class
Commission the basis of race
Got to this court has come very very I ask you a question has it ever held
No one has never held that it is
To be treated the same as race
To make a long story short
By the end of oral argument
Things are looking great
4 fret
1.2 even interrupt
A Supreme Court Justice
You don't do that
Supporting the denial of
Beer too young
It just
Yeah
Wasn't happening
I don't have time for parting thought I thank you for your time
Well you win some you lose some
Right
Ladies
What no no no
Here comes the craziest part of the story
Double trojan horse horse within a horse because
After the Fred Gilbert debacle
There was another case
At the Supreme Court that afternoon and it just so happened
35699 last night it was a case being argued
By none other than Ruth Bader
The plushie organize I've not forgotten how
To get that argued the same day that was on purpose yeah oh yeah
Cheney
She somehow managed to get herself in the port on another case on the same day so I couldn't confirm
That for sure
I don't even know how you would do that
But what I can tell you is that
She arranged
Picosecond
Because she knew there was probably a good chance that
Fred be completely incompetent lawyer
Was going to be
You know less than amazing
The court was asking him questions and he was completely incapable of answering so finally the court just went all nevermind and then one roof
Dornoch to argue her case they asked her about Gregory bar
Concrete involving
A law that would not permit males to make certain purchases of females
Discrimination
Yes mam
My question is whether we should examine
Discrimination against
In part because such a loss
Insidious impact
And then she told Justice Stevens
Even in this case
It seems like men are the ones who are being
Discriminated against
Beneath that discrimination is a more Insidious 1
Compliance safety
Discrimination against female
Is it your view that there is no discrimination
I think there is
Discrimination
That almost every discrimination that operate against males operate
Against females as well
Is that a yes or a no
I just don't understand you and I are you trying to avoid the question
I'm trying to
Clarify the position
But I don't know of any line that doesn't
It doesn't work as a
They go back and forth a bit
Justice Stevens is basically like
Why do you keep insisting on this
Why do you keep
Saying that discrimination
Against men contains within it discrimination against women
Are different
Would you like no they're not there
Is it discrimination against
My case depends on your recognition
That
Using gender
Resorting to. Classify
Scotty questionable
And should be
Closely
Reviews
Makes this point again and again
All discrimination based on gender is bad
Must be checked with something at least approaching that hard core standard
At the court uses for race
That was really something
Seeing this little woman
Get up
Purely a Gmail discrimination
I'll never forget that because she was small
Yes she's so small in person
The chi
Had a lot of force
About
2 months later
December 20th 1976
Craig
Against
Justice William Brennan announces that the court
Is breaking down the beer law
We hold that Oklahoma's gender-based
Differential
Doves Cry
An invidious violation
Best silly beer case
Was basically the first time the court clearly said
That when you discriminate based on gender
You need to pass
Harder test
It wasn't as rigorous as race it wasn't
Strict
Scrutiny
They settled on a standard that we now call
Intermediate scrutiny
And it was pretty damn close
RBG would go on to strengthen the standard overtime
But this was the case
That first got us
Kind of Equal Rights Amendment
Suicide door
We wish that the
Arrest protocol
Make that announcement
But of course we
Very pleased that
After that
The day the decision was announced
I had just came in from work I was at home
By myself here in Stillwater she's by herself
In the kitchen
In the phone rings
Can you call
Call
National news
Call to tell me that
We had one
I didn't ask
What we had one
I didn't ask anything
I just said okay
She hung up dude there for a little bit and then Craig called and he wanted me to come down and celebrate with the guys they are his
Fraternity
Eternity
She told them
No thanks
And then she hangs up the phone
Did you get the one more phone call and it was my husband he was in
North
Caroline again
And he heard
He heard something about the case but he didn't hear it all
And he said what's going on now and I said
We won
And he says
Is it over I said is over
It's totally over with
He said good
And he hung up
I fix me a very
Good
Drink vodka and Coke
Sit down the middle of the floor and that's the way I celebrated
I drank that drank all by myself and it was over with
It was over with
Caroline says that
Decades
After this case
She didn't understand what it meant
She didn't understand
Is it legal principle or that it ushered in this new era for women in this country
But even so
In
Her own life
This case
Was it beginning
Play a couple of years after we won that case
I went into China
Right after it opened up
She saved up money and went with her sister-in-law
Dwayne didn't want to come
I did I would ever so curious
And we never went like the tourist went
We get on a train and if we saw something we wanted to stop and see
We would stop
We never had a schedule
And I never did really go to shop I was just curious about the people
And how they lived
That's so so much
And I talked to so many people while I was gone
That
It was like a hunger
And you grow from it
And I just wanted to see things
And that was just open it just open the doors for me
What happened to Caroline in the
Xi'an Duane divorce in mm
And and when you and when you said she didn't know
Defector KSAT
For decades like when did she figure it out or what
What what how
So
In 1996 this professor guy named Bob Darcy called her up and invite her to speak at
A class
And
She is kind of learning from the students than from the
The professor
Like what the key sack
Actually stood for
And then eventually the professor puts her
In touch with Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Again
In person
And
Sort of starts to. On her
One of the letters
I don't know if that's the one
When were sitting in her bedroom
She was looking through some old letters
Then pulled out one with the Supreme Court
Still on it
Can you read it
No I don't have my glasses you'll have to read the cashier caroling as I told you in 1996 and we celebrated the 20th anniversary
Craigslist
Is born
You are the true heroine of that case
Although no financial gain was at stake for you you realize the potential the case had in Paving the way
For the Court's recognition of equal citizenship stature of men and women
A constitutional principle
How about I was going to get that
Framed
I haven't done it yet
Find Ruth Bader Ginsburg I need to get it laminated for Heather
Refined
Producer Julia Longoria I'm Jedi
Sing and here is more perfect and Radiolab David Gable to read the credits
Supreme Court audio is from Oye a free law project in collaboration with the legal information
Ocean Institute at Cornell leadership support for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
That's it more more perfect
Produced by me Jed abendroth Susie lechtenberg Jenny Lawton
Julia Longoria Kelly Prime Sean rameswaram
Sorrow
Sorry I didn't get to say it
Anytime I love doing this
I used to do it I did voice overs when I lived in Japan cuz I was a native
I used to sing at Tokyo Disneyland in my side gig
On my days off was recording voice-overs
Add a little Japanese Studio
I did a lot of language lessons for kids
Listen
And repeat