Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
Before we get going just a quick warning this podcast contains some descriptions of graphic violence and also some strong language
To be warned
Nice to see you again Chad
Why did you say that weaken Venom was that all about you been away for awhile
The only way I can see you is when I come visit you
If you have other family
Okay so this is Radiolab producer Matt kielty
Yeah I'm talking about
We're talking about a Supreme Court case from 1989
Today man has a story that he's been reporting for about 2 years
That we are going to play
Both here on more perfect
And also here on Radiolab
So buckle up where's where should we start I think we might as well just
Start
Should I try to sound Southern with a guy named Woody connect from a lawyer with us
Essex Richards law firm in Charlotte North Carolina
Pick it up in 1985 1995 I was a very young lawyer I was 32 years old
I just started mine law firm and I was taking about anything that came through the door
And 1 days is 40
This guy walked in late 30s fairly thin 5.95 attend bonecrusher
Nez black
PS
Or was he passed away Mr Graham
The man seems to Thornton Graham and what he says
Well
Like what what happened to your leg
What's with the crutches
And the thorn lays everything out for him.
So
He was pulled over on West Boulevard in Charlotte which is the four-lane road
Somebody he work for the city of Charlotte in the department of
Patient on road crews doing Road repairs
It was Monday afternoon and on that day wanted to join his friend to co-workers stop by his place
Is an
After talking for a bit Mr Graham asked to be taken to
Nearby convenience store it was only two or three blocks from his house he needed some orange juice
Because he was
Suffering the onset of a diabetic insulin reaction
Soda Thorn Hopkins from car
They drove over to the convenience store to store and got out of bottle of orange juice
Got to the checkout counter but
There's a line there
So it puts the bottle down and hurries out get back in
Find car by takeoff
Now
This is where the problems
Started
10. At the same time all that's happening there's actually an officer who was African-American
Sitting in his squad car and what that officer observed was a man hurrying out of the store jump
Tapping into a waiting car and quickly driving off
So you started to hail
The Thorn is friend but after a couple of blocks
Hold him over just to determine what was going on there
So he goes up to the driver side presumably gets to Thorns buddies driver's
Goes back to his squad car
Start radioing to get ahold of the convenience store to see if anything that happened
And it's right around that moment that the soreness in the passenger seat of the car suddenly opened his
Store got out of the car
Circle the car watch
Twice
Lake Sardis stumbled around it when they sat down on the car
He started going
In shock
That was like a seizure he would have a really yeah and it was terrifying
This is the thorn Graham Junior
He was a type 1 diabetic what is type 1 diabetes been with one and two from what I understand the type 1 diabetes
Is when your body just doesn't produce enough
Insulin
Any movie that seizure look like
Well one incident in particular
Art remembers being in church and he got like
Is Blank Stare on his
Json
You see the beads of sweat come on his forehead
His body was siege up and he was shaking
He would bite his tongue up and
So I can remember my mother trying to let you know for sure spoon into his mouth to keep him from
Biting his tongue up and
The main thing was try to get some orange juice and that way it would raise his
Blood sugar in
And what you got the orange juice in the heat sleep for a couple hours and then he wakes up and
He be exhausted
But he be alive
Alright so
Charlotte City street at this point four other officers arrived Its Thorn had actually passed out
On the kirb one of the officers
Rome Instagram over on the sidewalk
And cuffed his hands behind his back
At what point of what are you up to
Raps
The Thorn by the handcuffs and picks him up off the
Herb from from behind
Oh wow
The Thorn was sort of in and out at this point I guess he tries to tell the officers but it was a diabetic but he had a medical card
Ask the officer to pull the wallet out of his back pocket
And
One of the officers
Sad
Ain't nothing wrong with the motherfuker Buddies drop
At some point around here the details are a little unclear
Pretty nasty
A scuffle ensued
According to what is known as kasodus at the storm was resisting the officers and apparently officers slammed his head into his room
Car
He suffered head and shoulder injuries he also ended up with a broken foot cut his wrist
And eventually
The officers pick him up one on each arm one on each leg and just
Throw him into
The back of a squad car
While this was going on a few people gathered around and how long after that the officers learned
That nothing at all had happened at
The convenience store there was no crime there was no robbery there was no shoplifting
So he drove them back to his house still in handcuffs
Hold amount of
EPPICard
Offended someone has gotten some OJ and
The office
Thesaurus
Lay them out in his
Front yard took the handcuffs off and then just drive away
Was there an apology
Oh no
Now what came out of that day in Charlotte
Would end up becoming one of the most important
Supreme Court cases
History when it comes to policing
And what you mean about this case is have something like you needed some orange juice
That
Something so seemingly small
Would eventually become tied to this end
All the shootings we've seen in past years mostly of young black men every time we hear one of these shootings ever
Every time there is an outcry every time the cop gets off this incident is looming in the shadows
Shaping the outcome
Many ways it is quietly Define the air that we're living in
And I wanted to know how
How did it happen
Rihanna
Supreme Court of the United
States
At 21.2 clock little bit I will say this about my dad now he wasn't someone that would
Would just lay down and roll over
Talking to storing Junior I asked him a little bit about his dad and he told me that the thorn senior grew up in the Southeastern North Carroll
Alana on a tobacco farm
He was a hard worker get student is sisters told me that
He was the first
Blacks or African-American accepted to Duke University
My grandmother
She wouldn't let him go because of you know doing this are right there that she didn't want him to have to
Experience
All that all that mess
This is a CBS News special report civil rights
Movement was
A lot of things otherwise this
Big part of it that was about
Police brutality
Los Angeles
Also what was the long hot summer of 1967
150 race riots across the country
Police station keeping teeth in
I will not accept
Charges against policeman I will not accept charges against policeman
This is a job not some wild-eyed cracker that made the statement although there might not be any difference
Not be any difference if you can think on that
You understand that
If we cannot bring charges against the policeman who have murdered us and destroyed our homes and businesses where were we
We go where will we go
She didn't want him to have to experience
All that
All that matters
So ended up I think he ended up going to Fayetteville State
Black college in North Carolina
Amanda Sorensen graduated one of the first jobs
They had he work for an employer call Dell Precision Springs
It was a steel company that specialize in making Springs but at a certain point you actually suing the company discriminate
Nation based on how they were treating
You know people of color so after that day with the officers and Charlotte one thing I do remember Dad saying was that
It wasn't right
Difference going to fight
Right and that is how he ends up walking into Woody's office on crutches in 1985
He tells what he I wanna sue the Charlotte Police Department so we went ahead and just filed a lawsuit in federal court
Woody takes it to trial and basically is ours going to the police but
Excessive force
That was totally unnecessary under the circumstances
Like they wrapped up a diabetic who is telling them that he was a diabetic
Eventually the judge
Ruled that
No
These officers did not use excessive force and if you were going to claim that they did what he had to show
Police officers had acted maliciously for the purpose of causing harm
Hot today they had to prove that the officers X cement
Darden
Yeah that
Woody and the thorn had to prove that the officers
Had it out for the thorn and we simply couldn't do that
If it seems like a really hard thing to prove
It's an almost impossible standard to me
I think it's important to zoom in on this
Stop. For a second because it's really kind of like the
Crux of the story
If the question is what should the standard be for holding a cop
Accountable
Portuguese
Force 10
In the mid-eighties
Malicious intent was sort of the prevailing standard
If you're going to claim that a police officer use excessive force against you and the standard was that you had to prove
But the officer did so
With malice
In their heart
Why was that the standard
This is kind of hard to explain. I don't have the 14th amendment in front of me but it essentially
All you really need to know is that it was connected the Fourteenth Amendment to a particular clause
In the Fourteenth Amendment and this is why would he in the thorn lost that case
Okay alright so loses a federal court lose it Federal makes its way up to before it starts
Court of Appeals
That went nowhere the court of appeals ruled against us
Same thing same thing
Then nothing after that ruling what are you get the phone call and you hear me
From Jerry Beaver unknown civil rights lawyer
In the area in Fayetteville North Carolina Gerald was older and wiser than me that's your wording not mine
Mary had caught wind of the circuit decision you should not have to require that the police
Softer
Got it in for you
I just wanted to beat the crap out of you just cuz it made him feel better
So I called Woody and said are you guys planning on taking this case
To the Supreme Court
McClain can't really afford that I said tell him he doesn't have to worry about that we will be glad to take it on pro bono
Oh and see if we can get this ruling overturned
Wechat drawer
Let's go
So Jane we get together and they start looking around like like what's out there what cases can we draw and argue that there should be
Different standard well of Glee season 4 cases
Pulling up in the court that you had lawyers trying out all these different ideas now most of the courts were using the fort
Malicious intent standard that appearing would have been like then there was also in the number of cases
What's the eighth unusual punishment punishment
From their totally explain what is cruel what is unusual it take the word cruel cruel
Play that you're trying to hurt somebody inside somebody's head right
The wonders of the amendment that some of the courts were you seen that
Woody and Jerry look to as they're sort of like
Redeemer
The 4th amendment
4th amendment
The Fourth Amendment which is which is the government cannot subject citizens to unreasonable search and seizure
I have it on my legal pad
The fourth amendment is the right of the people to be
Secure in their persons houses papers and effects
Against
Unreasonable searches and seizures
Shall not be violated
It is seizure just another word for force
Like I have the right not to eat
Eating your shot by my government yeah it's it's not just that but yes it it also includes that
Entering so much about the fourth amendment is that in there
Is this one
Important word
Unreasonable reasonable reasonable
The concept of reasonable
What is reasonable and what is not reasonable
In-law reasonable is it supposed to be
Objective
You look at the case from the facts of the case
Not the wire
Correct then you ask was this person's Behavior reasonable
Or not they have to act with objective reasonableness
Wait a second reasonableness is a slippery thing
What you find reasonable would I find reasonable
Today will be different be completely different yes or no
It can feel slippery but legally the whole concept of reasonableness have hundreds of years of
Precedent
I mean I I find this very fascinating and I don't know if you want me to give you like a little bit of
Backstory
Do you want
To give me a little bit of black stuff in it if it's interesting how it came to be and how popular it is
Take me to take me on the ride okay alright so we go back to the 1830s Andrew Jackson
No no actually we're over in Europe lower where is Belgium this is going to be like a little windy but I think it kind of makes sense
In 1830
This guy I don't care I don't care delay is a mathematician he's an astronomer
If you want to picture something he had Hollow cheeks he's big sideburns
A little bit like
David
Straight iron
Did the guy from
The Edward Murrow movie
Jason Bourne movies
Music that helps you at all
Observatory but astronomers
Habits issue
They had trouble pinpointing the location of stars because
Telescopes
So bad
But Kelly was one of these astronomers who knew you could use
Asset statistics difficulty settings
You could take an average of all the different measurements and average of the meteorological data and I can help you pinpoint
We're stars were actually going to be in the sky so that they can make predictions
Whoever seems like revolutionising astronomy
Italy became
Fascinated by this idea of averages and what humidity
He kind of took that idea
I took it down from the heavens from the sky and
Started applying it to humans
So you can call me through data in medical journals trying to determine the average height of a person the average weight
The circumference of somebody's chest with each other like come up with these or proto-man Tennessee
Totally Arabic huge impact on public health
But he ends up actually going Beyond this and it's beyond just like physical traits and he starts to like push into
Man's morality and he's looking at crime rates
Suicide rates
Marriage rate
And in the 1830s he starts laying out this concept
What is in French
Loam when which translates into the average
Man
The average man so so this is like big data 1830 Style
Yeah and Indus idea Lomo and the average man
He became a very useful in law
English law
Really
How exactly
Money sign
In Victorian England there was Much Ado About people who wanted to sue for damages
Arlette the bandages
There is a need for constant average
Way take measuring stock to see if a person at Straight From the Block
This really seemed like the best way to determine if the accused
Had to pay
Here's how we will fill this need put a man on the stand
Adam raised
His right hand
Let's say he stacks of hay in a terribly negligent way much more like a funeral pyre caught his neighbor's home totally at 5
But he says that he did nothing wrong so Jerry I ask of you what is it that we shall do
How about think of ordinary folk if your average typical reason blog
Avenger
Take a look
Epic use that hand
And ask yourself
This one question
Did he behave
Like you're ordinary
Average
Reasonable man
Wow
I didn't even know you had
If it's okay
So you're saying that
Judges and juries begin to use these averages as a way to sort of like
Figure out like if you're suing somebody else
If it's somebody else did they act out of the ordinary where they
Yeah it was just curious after 10 delay in this whole average man thing that English law
Started developing this idea this standard don't initially as
The reasonable man
Standard
Eventually switches a person to be a little bit more gender-inclusive
This reasonable person
It's one of the longest established
Fictional characters that exist in what is known as like the legal village where you have these other little characters like it starts with the reasonable person
And then you start you get like a slew of these other
These other characters that come out of that which is I have a little list there's
The ordinary prudent man of business
The officious
Bystander there is the fair-minded and informed Observer
There's the reason Bulger there's the reasonable parent there's a reasonable landlord there's a reasonable neurosurgeon reasonable civil engineer there's only one
Reasonable
Hairdresser
Really
Trade or craft
Where there's this is being done or you have the ability within your craft harm somebody
Legally it became very useful to have an average
Archetypal person
Doing that crap
So that the jury or the judge
Would have something to use as a measurement when rendering
It's interesting so like in the hairdresser example
Whatever it was that led to that
Ray's probably was a Cadillac
Survey
And imagine one of hairdresser Behavior
Yeah lake lake maybe you went in to get a haircut and you walked out and
Half years gone right and you're just like we're to have my year ago and then it's just you go to Courtney like any reasonable hair dress
I would not have made that cut
Right
Switch success starts with a C
Stronger and ends up with this
Village of reasonableness the funny thing about the village
Please this is pretty sure Kelly Prime in English law
Like Matt said there's like this Village of people but in England at the time they had this idea that it wasn't like
A village it was people on a bus
Call the man on the Clapham omnibus
Switches are roughly I looked up London bus route 88
I don't know they just ride the all day those people just waiting for the case to come up and do a hair dresser
In the next. Concept moved in like Australia
I was like okay we should use that until one part called that the man on the Bondi tram and another Park called at the man on the Burke Street tram
Hong Kong got it
And they said it's a man on the
Shang-chi one tram
It went to the bus
Convenient vessel to hold all these reasonable people
England said all these people are on a bus
Because
You didn't want someone who's like
So slowly
That they are like they're not riding the bus really cold up in a cave somewhere or someone that is like
IHOP on their Castle it's like the Common Man exactly so it said it was described as reasonably educated intelligent but
Nondescript
I think like what what Woody
And Jerry
Bring it all the way back
We're simply trying to do is to say we need to use the Fourth Amendment and his idea of unreasonable search and seizure
To create a reasonable officer
So we need to add a reasonable officer to the Village
Where the bus
So
Riley the cases submitted
In 1989 almost five years after everything happened to the store and Graham that one day in Charlotte
Give an extra number 87 6571
His case went before The Supreme Court
Dethorne Graham vs enes Kanter
Now it's almost there for the argument was there as a spectator
Watch
Jay was actually in the case
To get butterflies of course
You may proceed whenever you're ready
The Chief Justice
Replace a corn
I'm pretty quickly these arguments you don't know what
Turn into like this word soup
Object
Standard free. Jerry
The lawyer for the officers
The justices
Getting super meta about what constitutes objectivity objectively unreasonable
What's objectivity
Predictive factor analysis testing standards
Anthony objective analysis bad Intent no intent
I think we're playing with words
Until
One Justice Thurgood Marshall the lone African-American the Quarry
Clumsy Ninja sass
What reason was there for handcuffing a diabetic
At the time the officers didn't know that he was
Diabetic
You had to be there
Yes to go back one step even before the officer Connor
Solo practitioner
Acting very suspicious
Unusual man
Hurry into a convenience store
What did he do that was violent
Mr Perry's
Testimony of petitioners on Witness.
Petition was throwing his hands around
The Buried and ask for officer
I'm talking about this.
What was he doing before they tried to put
He was acting in a very bizarre manner
He ran out of the car
Circled around it twice
And then sat down
District Court
The officer didn't have to wait until he is
Did he strike anybody don't believe the record indicates
He was acting Indiana drug predictable and potentially dangerous man
Can you answer to
He did not overly threatened
Tri-County
Did he have a weapon of any kind
The record doesn't
Directions
The record shows that he was properly stop
Has a suspect
Criminal investigation
He was acting suspiciously that he was acting in a bizarre
Manor
Did even after he was handcuffed in the office if it wanted to
To put them in the car the Undisputed record shows that he was vigorously fighting and Kicking
Abject
To being arrested
Rather than Giving Tree
He was never real
He was handcuffed because the officers were concerned that he was a criminal suspect
He was acting a very unusual and erratic way
He was
Throwing his hands around Indy The District Court stated from the record that he was handcuffed
Arthur protects himself
As well as the author
That's the VA District Court summarize the record
They are different
The difference illusion
When Justice Marshall
Said that
Suddenly
I heard
Adjudge
Who understood our point of view
Somebody gets it
And all of a sudden
I felt like I was not an idiot after all
Then she put that their opinion is written by a chief justice William rehnquist
And
Inner pinion rehnquist says
Skip it down a little bit
Claims that law enforcement officials have used excessive force
In the course of an arrest investigatory stop or other quote-unquote seizure other free citizen are most properly character
Rise is invoking the protections of the Fourth Amendment
Which guarantees citizens the right to be secure in their persons
Against unreasonable teachers
And must be judged
By reference to the Fourth Amendment reasonableness standard
So they get their reasonable officer standard they get it
And it get it unanimously nothing opinion
Wow
It was a breakthrough
Stretch to say at the time to a lot of people were concerned about
Audi
PCS Forest
It felt like this was speaking
The new era that favored Plato's Enclave us
Is now if you were a victim of police violence
Justice you have this new Universal standard objective standard we no longer has a show that
The officers active
Maliciously
Sadistically
And you say what a reasonable officer do the same thing
Or not
Established like what a reason Lobster is what they would do by calling experts looking at dad about age and rank and
Stranger things
What's up with that this would be
For the first time in hundreds of years maybe they would have
An objective
The standard
That was a breakthrough
After winning did the case get kick back down to the Circuit like what happens to the thorn
Everyone in the Supreme Court
The case went back to
The trial court level for another trial
Alaska facts
And sorry Mr Graham had another day in court
Another trial we picked another jewelry
Apache presented diabetic insulin reaction bottle of orange juice pulled him over unconscious and cough
Physical education broken foot lacerations wrist bruised forehead quad car
Front yard
The guy who did nothing wrong
I was beaten up
The case was given to the jury
Entry was told
Okay
Knowing what you now know
Take the standards reasonable standard and ask yourself
Is what happened to the store on Graham
Reasonable
Liberated came back out and I decided in favor of the police officers
Mr Graham law
Now what do you think the jury really focused in on the police officers perspecta
And from the office
Detective all they saw was a black man running in and out of convenience store
They thought you might be stealing something they had no idea he was a diabetic
I'm up he was a little bit out of control car creating trouble
Diabetic but he's a drunk
Mike dangerous
Reasonable officer would subdue that person
Excuse I'm so sorry
There goes the dog in yard
So when he was actually moving from his home in St Louis
Back to where I still had a lot of family in Charlotte okay mom back
Hopefully I ain't going okay now
I was just wondering did your dad talked about the
About what happened that day or do you talk about the court case at all
He didn't
It wasn't something that he talked about
Different Junior says that this tablet
I'm trying to get on with his life he started making
Can Furniture in his spare time
Going to church a lot
But he had his he had his trouble
He had a p ends up having sex
A substance abuse issues
So
And which
Fortunately you you was able to overcome that and
That was after the Supreme Court case after that's correct that's correct
So I mean I don't know if
His his
We're trying to deal with that was
Do substance abuse I don't know
When you were dehumanized like that
When when another individual
Where do they
It's you know it's it's it's kind of hard to explain Matt but
When on someone
Who has
Authority
Chess
It's like
It stays like they take something away from you
When someone does something like that to you
It strikes at your core
It strikes at your very being
And I think you lose a part of yourself
That you can't get back
Franklin senior died in the year 2000 he was
54 years old
But after his death
Is named lived on in this
Ace
Naseberry
Weird
Way
So 2014 tonight after an unarmed African-American teenager was shot and killed
Ferguson Missouri
Not far from where does Warren G live
A white officer Darren Wilson
Shot and killed
I'd like teenager my
Michael Brown a reporter from CNN contacting me
And up
He talked about how
They were going to use my dad's case doing that trial as a defense
For the officer
The CNN report in pharmacy
No I had no idea the grand jury deliberated over two days
Making their final decision
Equation for surgery was
Did Officer Darren Wilson act recently
When he shot Michael Brown the determined that no probable cause exists
To file any charges against officer Wilson
You returned a no true bill on each of the five indictment
That was reasonable
They killed her baby man
Luigi
Play Bob Jack.
Same here shot and killed by two officers while holding a pellet gun
To ask what
Original police officer
Would do in this particular situation
Detroit found that the officer who shot and killed the 12 year old boy Tamir rice
Recently
Ben
Eric Garner grand jury in New York City has refused to indict yet another white police officer
Send John Crawford on 18 year old black man killed last month
Reasonable
Samuel Dubose police officer who killed an unarmed black man
Alton Sterling
Reasonable reasonable
Oklahoma Charlotte Police Jamar Clark
Philando Castile
Reasonable are you kidding me right now
Evolve
Where did Bobby
Going back down to 1969
And in almost every one of those cases
Graham vs Connor Supreme Court decision
How many people felt was
Post to establish a new Universal standard that would deliver Justice
Victims of police violence
It ended up doing
Feed sack
Prevented the victims from getting relief
Instead
Protected the cops
One person my colleague who covers cops describes it as like cops
Kopsia dislike their first amendment
Texas break glass
How did that happen
Can watch it app
More perfect will continue in a moment
Radiolab
This is more perfect I'm Jad abumrad
Me to say a few words for contact police officers have dangerous
I think we can all agree and on occasion they do have to use Force
And we should say that the majority of the people who are killed by police every year
Are white
But if you look at the number of black people were killed and you balance that against
Fact that black people only make up about
12% of the overall population
What you end up with
Is
That an unarmed black man is
Roughly about seven times more likely to
To be
Killed by police in an unarmed white man
Taqueria wants.
Add these numbers
Are very
Disputed and argued about but what is clear
Is most police officers who use deadly force whenever charged
Even smaller
Percentage serve jail time
So mad
You actually let me just ask you
All the cases we heard about
Before the break that Litany of cases
In the past few years in every single one of those
The jury was asked did this officer behave like a reasonable offer
It should
And every single one the jury said yes
Yeah yeah
Why
Well that's it because
The reasonable officer standard
Like from from the moment that it was created
I was actually kind of it was constrained
If you very important ways
Pure the
The jury instruction
From the 9th circuit
And this is what dreams members are
I told to think about when they have to assess this kind of use of force
Geraci told this is your job
The Back Eddy Primetime kilogram
Yeah
It says under the Fourth Amendment a police officer may use only such Force as objectively reasonable
You must judge the reasonableness of a particular use of force from
The perspective of a reasonable officer on the scene
And not with 20/20 vision of hindsight
Those those are
A couple really crucial
Phrases with
Perspective
Of
An officer on the scene so you have to look at it through the eyes of the officer on the scene and then
You can't look at it through the 20/20 vision of hindsight difficult yourself
Officer in the moment and look at the world through their eyes and and that's how you have to understand these things
Where did that where does where did that idea come from to that
Thumbs
From Graham the guy comes from the Chief Justice
William rehnquist
Pinyin
Which
Tiebreaker
The reason why this particular use of force must be judged
From the perspective of a reasonable officer on the scene
Rather than with the
20/20 vision of hindsight
And if calculus must embody an allowance for the fact
And this is extremely important
The police officers are often forced to make
Split-second decisions
About the amount of force necessary in a particular situation
It so if you can see this this idea of reasonableness
Is
Circumscribe
Fairy type
By time
It's not asking like what a regional officer would do
Herein in general
During a moment where
Where do you have to use Force
Instead
What is asking is what would a reasonable officer do in this split
Second
In this little tiny sliver of time where the force
Actually occurred
In fact that moment legally has come to be known
As a superseding event
Meaning what
What is the meaning of This Is Us
Meaning of depth in that moment
That superseding event it is essentially it breaks
The
Chain of causation
So if you think of time is Justice like Continuous Flow this is like no
You break that
You stop that and you take this one little moment you pluck it out
And you like this moment
This is the one moment that you look at
That's all they can think of
And it turns out if you ask a jury
The question
About use of force
That way
About this one little moment
The Graham standard that many people saw it
I'm in Hope wood would help victims
The police violence
Does the exact
1% Mike McCauley who covers cops describes it as like cops
Kopsia dislike their first amendment they just think of it like as a shield
Okay so this is NPR reporter Kelly mcevers
Staff embedded
Podcast and
All Things Considered
So please actually as she's coming police shooting to the Past
Like year for NPR and we sort of been comparing notes with her as we've been producing our story
LOL back
Has she sent us an email
AC say something
That most people don't
Etsy
See how cops are actually
Trained
Understand
Do you want in
Timberlake
Yep
Okay so I went to sleep
Are you hungover
For this two-day
Training course called
Street survival
Isn't a hotel Ballroom one of those hotel conference and how many people do you remember
We're just under 200
Cops
Lots of really jacked dudes with cats
Mostly white sergeants and lieutenants rookies right out of the academy submit to your guys from Oliver
Ohio Pennsylvania neighbor. Super happy about
Angry stares in the beginning there's just like a lot of side eye
Good morning Cleveland
How's everybody doing
How many of you have been to a caliber press
What's the weather report please your hands
That's why you never been here before
ProPress class
Oh wow
Toasted whole thing is put on by this company called Calibre press
Actually been around for a really long time and they teach classes
Classes are in the police departments are they all from all across the country in this particular one
I want to talk a lot about stress
Survival in
The general idea is
How to survive and blank make it to retirement
I mentioned heart attacks
Emotional health
Suicide
You know how to basically do this job and
7 survival
And live
Living
And Lasting
2530 York
They talk a lot about self-care
About sleep and exercise
Making sure that your spouse and your family like understand the stress of your job and they talked about going to therapy I mean it's like
Wow there's times when it's this really touchy-feely kind of thing
Overwhelmed
Happening
There's Diva moments she says when a lobster got up
Talk about contemplating suicide
Starving
I started alienating myself
F****** hating everybody
Everyone was like
Crying so I mean it's a really intense
Couple of days
But for our purposes the reason we were there other reason we're excited for Kelly be there
Is it a big chunk of the class
Let's talk about that
Is devoted Graham
Ugly uses
How to understand Grand and and how it impacts their life
By the way this is the instructor that like Granite structure his name is Jim Glennon he himself was a cop for years and years and years
Start using Force for 18 years
What's the lake China outside of Chicago
Force policy
On a regular basis
4 *
Red
What I would do is show a video and then let's talk about Ranbir Scarface on this video
So
Find a projector
It is really interesting to see these videos from their perspective
Video of a
September 2015 a guy named Freddy centeno
Freddy centeno has gone to a woman's house
Like to woman's front door
And threatened her and says he has a gun and the cops
Pull up the other car there's like 20 feet away from centeno who's walking towards them on the sidewalk
10 shots 7mm hits
Frank long
I translate the white one
Jim's claim that happens in 1.566 second
Jim shows the lawyer for Freddie Santana's family
Is basically just like
It's it's an atrocity like this was an atrocity nothing about that use of force should be considered reasonable
Because the cops missed
Situation near Old write-up on Freddy centeno didn't create any space didn't get Freddy centeno anytime
Get on the ground
You have a chance to get on the phone
In the video shows the officers did not get a chance to
Respond to their commands
Search employees all these reaction clips and then
Play the original body cam video again
Hey Chris you see Freddy centeno they come to get on the ground he doesn't
Engine slows the video down
As you can see Santa's right hand reaches into his pocket
Gym passes
Things like take a look at this
Right here
Jim has his Frozen moment where you can see it at Freddy's and his hand as started to move
The movement of a hand a couple of inches
Just
Starting to come up out of his pocket that's moment from the pocket to the out of the pocket this to Jim was the moment
Seems like this is the only moment that matters like forget what happened before forget that the officers rolled right up on centeno forget that they weren't giving too much timer
Space
This moment
Right here
Start pulling his hand out of his pocket this is the moment where you ask a question
What would a reasonable officer do
Right now
Bach I can't tell what it is you probably can't even without outside information
Turns out he had a a nozzle
From a garden hose
What was the call
However you see this
Start moving up or down
He doesn't go to the ground
Pull something out
And so
Is this work under gram
What
I believe
For him he's just like over and over and over stresses
What would a reasonable police officer do
In that moment
What did you know what was
Text but rehnquist in the decision is like what rank was said is
Circumstances
Certain rapidly Hobby Lobby
Mastering
This is fast it's Dynamic it's nothing like television there's no five cameras on it there's no change in the music
Upswell in the music
It's fast and the court recognizes that
Jim plays another example of this one of the guy
Like I can police officer shot because they thought he had a gun got a knife but the cops got the call that he had a gun and
In the split second he raised his arm like he was raising a gun up
Another one
Viega to call 2 a.m. domestic
Chanel video of a police officer shooting an unarmed white man in head and again walkthrough beat by beat
City girl look at just a moment forget everything else
And what you realize if you do that
Did you force someone to the jury to look at
Just that one moment forgetting everything else to look at this one slice of the eyes of an officer
The whole concept of what is reasonable
Ships
The only real question you can ask when the moment is so confined is
Did the officer feels threatened
Lake was the fear that that officer had a reasonable fear in that moment
That is a very different standard than what
Woody and Jerry in the thorn Graham that intended
Yeah so
Kexp playlist
Story that you report for podcast embedded
It actually gets at some of the stuff
In this particular case who who was John Farrell in what
Tell him Ferrell
The football player from Florida the big dude
Yes he looks like a football player so this was September of 2013 John the federal is living in Charlotte
North Carolina black man 24 years old and
One night it was a Friday night
He goes out
Some friends cuz that to a bar
Has a couple drinks makes his way home exactly know what happened
But well John the bear was making his way back home at some point his car was he lost control of
Fry's car crash in the woods office Road and Suburban
Charlotte didn't have his phone but he's in like this little Suburban neighborhood so he gets out of his car goes up to the house of this woman
Is knocking on her door warm inside she's a white woman new mom she comes to the door thinking it's her husband who works tonight
So she's come to the door and she's like about to let him and then she's like well wait a second who's the person Penny she opens the doors he chosen Federal
Did she calls 911
She doesn't know who the guy is
Alarm systems going off
And you can hear screaming turn off the alarm turn off the alarm in the background and you can hear him
911 tape you can like hear and banging on the door
You have your baby with you
I don't know what to do okay I'm right here
Pressure on our way okay
Now we don't know why John Farrell was banging on the door but
Very possible
They likely
It was just because he wrecked his car and need some help
So they called him thinking that they are going to the scene of a breaking and entering
There's a dash cam video from the squad car when the officers description it's an African American man with green shirt and light pink
Today's top stories driving down this road driving driving driving until finally you see
Kim McManus green shirt and white pants
Walking on side the road
Walking towards
Squad cars you see the red light of a taser on
Cast
And then
Take off one of the officers is yelling at me get on the ground zero keeps running runs off camera
Keep your appetite
What are you up to spiders 12 shots
Adams Rite John Farrell
Foster crown
Full movie
Bumbu
Any dyes
Are that here's a guy who was unarmed who did nothing wrong
And he was killed
Plain and simple
Well if you you asked was that reasonable on some basic level
No
It was not reasonable this man
Should not have died
What in the trial this case did go to a trial jury trial
The jury was instructed forget everything
But that moment of force
It's like no 20-20 hindsight look at just a superseding moment
And then ask the question again
Why is it reasonable for the officer to pull the trigger
Ie
Was it reasonable
Prevent officer
To be afraid
And the officer who shot and killed Jonathan Ferrell
Who's facing charges his name is Randall Kerrick
You've been tried for voluntary manslaughter the suspect
Began aggressively coming towards me
And during the course of this trial officer
The character cast and could you tell the jury about
What pace he was coming at you
At first it was a pretty rapid pace
Moreland morva a fast walk
I gave loud verbal commands for him to stop and get on the ground
How loud are your verbal commands
Very loud
Tell me how loud you were yelling to the suspect and what you were yelling to the suspect
So he says he was running at him
This is a huge question
Was he running Adam
Really running away from
I try to run past them by him yeah
Like if you sort of diagram the whole thing out the way the cop cars were parked awake Eric was standing
It is possible
The Jonathan fair was trying to start a run between the mall at the prosecution was saying defense was like no no no
Running at the cop
Didn't suspect saying
No sir
Why did you interpret his
Body language to me
He's going to attack me
He's going to take my gun from me
Did you have time to holster your weapon
No sir
And here I was
Suspect
Match the description
He just ran through a taser
Which at the time I thought was had that work
I thought the taser had struck him
Make contact
I had absolutely no idea if he had a weapon on him or not
And was he at first it was the suspect ever still
No sir
Did he continue to advance on you
Juicer
No matter what I did he wouldn't stop
I wasn't sure how many rounds I had fired none of them affected him
And anyway anyway I didn't think my gun was working
Thought I was going to die
There's nothing I would do to stop it
What was the reason that you continue to fire your weapon
Because he wouldn't stop
People trying to get to my gun
Toilet down the question was
Was it reasonable for officer character
I feel afraid
And after 11 days a testimony the question was put to the jury
There were six opinions one way there were six another
On the 1st going to the Jury Room it was six
Sex
On one side a white guy named Bruce rap
We were sitting in that courtroom
And we were sitting in that dreary
Deliberation room has no bigger than this living room
Okay
And
It's hot
We're arguing where it's
It's it's going nowhere
And so the more it went on this went on for days
And he started the leading the charge on that we have to
Quick Care
Pretty much adopted foster care can it be right to be afraid
He told Kelly that Jonathan Ferrell the guy who cared shot so what Bruce Rafi sing to me like you know he was a young man
Disheveled confused
Angry if you will be made a very aggressive move towards these police officer
After disobeying commands
Choices in this video
Cliff the very first time love you.
Stop sit down
Put your hands up
Do any of those
Other than what you chose to do which was to charge
Opticare
And told that there's no other way around what I saw
And then I kept coming back to that
And this is exactly how the defense painted
Write this case is not about race
This case is
Is about choice
And that's stuck in grease trap he's mine so that when he was asked was it reasonable for character shoot him
Cycle yeah cuz Johnsonville made all these bad choice
This is an old trick
From
From my defense attorneys spoke to an African American man
Wasn't supposed to be
He might have had a few drinks where he was
The police responded to what he calls
This was early in the morning
This was far from where he lived
This was this
This was that
Which caused me
At the end
To write on the board
Just what did he do
To deserve to be shot so many times
Mystery Room in the Jury Room
I wrote this on the board
What did he
Do
What's the what happens with the jury
Splits
Bunch of Italians eat to quit Ford konvictt painters most of them Wayside with
Quitting Cara
And for jurors most of them people of color
Side with convicting care
Breaking news
In the trial of Officer Randall Kerrick the judge
Has just declared a mistrial
2015 Espy Charlotte settle the lawsuit which on the Pharaohs family
2.25 million dollars
That same here optic Eric resign from the Charlotte
Department
The city paid out $179,989.59
The money was for back pay Carrick Social Security and retirement
An attorney representing them in a separate civil suit
There's something interesting about
Listening to Moses talk
Guess what did he do
To deserve to be shot so many times it feels like
This time
Fourth Amendment reasonableness standard is reasonable officer
Standard like what
Understand is that it was an attempt to really
Look at these situations these shootings
Uses of force cases
Through this sort of objective lens
Swear you're just looking at all the fat on the ground
And yet he says don't seem to be tied that like any sort of objectivity
Yeah hearing Moses where you're like oh that's actually like
That feels like a
Pure sort of objectivity
Like what what
What has this guy done yet
Actually done anything
He ran it a buddy
Maybe
But that was
It
And
Like if you're white
Are you more likely to say yes that was reasonable because he's white and he was afraid of a black man
Like that is the question
Given the history of our country I'd say many cases that's not even
Thanks Christian I'm actually left with is
If this is where the reasonableness standard has lettuce
Is there another standard
I think that's right
This is what he can at again he represented the phonogram in that original case
When you say it applied you wonder
Whether or not this is the best standard or there might be something better
I just don't have an answer to that
I would I would suggest the whole more erratic
Is Elie mystal more proof
Next legal editor we ended up talking with him about this
Shortly after the philando Castile verdict came out so he was
Well that was a tough pill for him and many people
Swallow I would suggest that they have to be
The cops have to be right in fact
Which is something we usually do not apply for what does that mean like it from in the scenario of a police person woohoo
Is that mean like I need to be right that you don't have a toy gun that that's
So if you shoot me because you think I have a gun I had best Havoc
And if I don't have a gun your ass is going to jail
Cuz you were wrong
I don't care if you lie thoughts
If I was telling you I had a gun
If you are not right in fact than you
Have to go to jail
I think that is that would be a standard
Several hours to prosecute
Beast Boy socks
Cinepolis person's going to just going to argue that like you don't understand the pressures that are under its
The split-second decision
Monday Morning Quarterback
If you do what you just said we're not going to do our jobs
I would say screw you
You have had your chance
You had your chance
To police my community
Without murdering us
And you have failed for 300 years
Enough
More people might get hurt if I wasn't
I'm willing to risk that
I'm willing to try it that way
I'd rather I'd rather
Illegal shoplifting people
Go free
Then one
Illegal shoplifting person gets shot in the street like an animal
Gotcha if you want to talk about changing the standards that is a standard changed
Now that is a zelle said
Radical
Probably not real
Given that most Americans according to polls respectively
Confidence mclees Percy please to be the enforcers
HIPAA law
But there are other ideas
Out there there's
Starting
Bubble up
And what's constraining us if what's keeping us
Stuck where we are are the words of Graham
Then what offers does a way out
Could actually
Also be hiding in there
What do you mean
Okay so you know how
Chief justice rehnquist when he wrote the decision in 89
He put in all these phrases that took the idea of a regional officer and unconstrained it bro
These were like it's been trained only
To this little moment in time it's been trained to the perspective of the officers or constrained that there's no 20-20 hindsight
All that
What in the decision he also you slipped in this other phrase
He was actually calling back to an earlier today
And what he wrote was
The question is whether the totality of circumstances justifies a particular sort of seizure
Tality of circumcised
Totality of circumstances
It seems to be at odds with
All of the other stuff
Right which is all about like little slivers and moment
Detecting that this is like this is the whole thing
Both both ideas and their wants right now you see the lower courts are arguing
About what displays actually means until half of the circuits are saying kind of like everything that we've already talked about
Which is that all the totality circumstances means is that
You look at everything to answer the question was the officer's scared you look at everything that the officer would have known
Turn everything the officer would have seen received and then you ask okay knowing all that was it reasonable for the awesome music
The other half of the circuit say
Natalia circumstances
Isn't just about what the officer knew what the officer saw and how it answers the moment
Fatality means like totality
Like what did the officer
Do
Leading up to the mall
Did the officer
Try to get a search warrant to the officer try to deescalate the situation before
Are using force to be officer try to subdue the person before using deadly force
Assembly all those things that usually kept out of the frame
Maybe
Can be let back in
Supreme Court so far has shown no interest in ruling on this in trying to sort this out
But they might
Because the argument is happening in the lower courts
So in a way we're kind of looking at a time very much like 1984 when does Lauren Graham got pulled over at
Outside a convenience store in Charlotte
Waiting to see whether it matters that the thorn Graham
Wasn't trying to steal anything
Maybe just a diabetic
Try to get some orange juice
Did what happen your dad affect how you
Thought of
Police how you thought police
Bean bean black man
Well
You'll believe it or not
It didn't
What's up
I like the base my
Opinion
It's based on my own
Experiences
My dad and I can say this Kelly
I can remember my dad telling me stories of
Where he grew up in eastern North Carolina
On a tobacco farm
In that small town
I can remember him telling me a story of
A black man
Who have been accused
Being inappropriate with a white woman
And how the white
Got them in broad daylight
Castrated him in broad daylight
And I say that
In saying that
Although he experienced all that stuff growing up
And the racism that he experienced growing up
He didn't teach that
You didn't teach that does he told us
To love people
So
Even now myself
I base my experience over
Four-person
I base my experience of the police
Based on
My dealings with
In and not that I want
But I have yet
To encounter
A police officer who's been mean to me who's been rude to me
Who's mistreated me
And that's the God's honest truth
Without
Button and being completely honest
When I see you on the news
Like a kid in the 12 year old in
It had to be begun
All right yeah
Examples like this
That
That that does affect mean that does
Make me does that make you think of your own children have you talked to your answers
He's got BB guns that look just like real guns
And you know what he he knows that
Hey
They don't leave the house
What's it what's your twelve-year-old name
My son's name is Tanner
Tanner
I'm here when you talk
Detainer about
The fact that like the BB gun doesn't leave the house I mean what is that conversation
Michael did Tamir rice when he was shot and killed when the new story came on
A+
Cuz you need to do with live TV now
Hey, why don't you watch this
Right now tan is 12 years old he's cute he's this is that
But the fact of the matter is
Infusion
Few short years
He would be considered a black man
Unfortunately
He's going to have
A Target on him
Himself so
St. Louis BB guns you got
See this is why you can't take these
Out of the house I don't want you to take these out of the house
Even if you're outside in the yard playing
In a police should happen to come down the road hey
Drop it
Drop it immediately
History was produced
Reported by Matt kielty
The Pegasus from
Kelly Prime
Weather objectives Chinese movie havior
Definitely check out the other more perfect episodes that are many more at radiolab.org
Perfect or search for more perfect wherever you get your podcast
Deadly check it out spread the word
More perfect is produced by me Jad appenrod Susie lechtenberg Jenny Lawton Julia Longoria and Kelly Prime
What's overington in sarkari
Battalion install Cristian farias Linda hirshman David Gable
Michelle Harris
Production support this week from Derek Don and Dylan
Thanks to Kelly mcevers and Tom Dreisbach from NPR's embedded
Eddie montgomery at the Tampa Bay Times
Frank Aycock
Leonard Feldman
Cynthia Lee and Joshua rosenkranz
Supreme Court audio is from oil
A free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute
Cornell leadership support from our perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
Reasonable search and seizure
Do you think that would be