Listener-supported WNYC
Be Studios
Leadership support for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
True symbol of the United States is not the bald eagle
It is the pendulum
And when the pendulum
Swings too far in One Direction
It will go bad
Back
Backpack
It will come back is more perfect
A series about
The cases that land in front of the Supreme Court and in this episode
Which we might as well call pendulum part 2
Take a deep dive into what might be V
Most horrible Supreme Court decision ever
In an attempt
160 years after the fact in a Hilton hotel Ballroom
To finally say it right
Can you tell me about the Constitution
This is a case that split the United States into
Civil case in question is the Dred Scott case
Which if you ask people I was wondering if you've ever heard of the Dred Scott court case
Scott sounds familiar doesn't go well
Teacher would be really mad at me right now
Civil rights thing
Earworm I'm more like the name has some familiarity yes yes
What is that mean
So what happens a lot of times that people don't actually understand why they're free so Dred Scott
That is one of those fundamental decisions that is that lays the groundwork for the reasons why
We can live in a Multicultural Society
This is Elie mystal
More perfect legal editor really understand the case
You've got to go to a place called Fort Snelling
It's a small army base about 15 minutes north of the Minneapolis Airport
Go freshly laid on the ground and our producer Julie Longoria took over here
Number to Josie manager program here at the Minnesota Historical Society gave her tour
DC right now is the space that we think you know it's probably weird
Dred and Harriet Scott you know where they live
Before we go into distress set up when in time are we what's happening the 1830s worth
30 years out from the Civil War about half the states in the union have slavery about half dome
So it's this question that's kind of still unanswered like should we be a free Nation or should we be a slave Nation
Real tension here and there is a real understanding here that
This might not work and just as we're about to reach this Breaking Point Army doctor named John
John Emerson slave owner
Steps into free territory
And arrived here
Do this
Army base
On a hill
And he brings with him his one slave
Dred Scott and now we're actually inside the Fortress if you will and
You know all of the stone all the weld windows
It's
I don't like
Whenever I come here I have this kind of cold feeling
Even if it's hot outside
He walks up to the back of this one squat building on the far end of the base
Can you describe the through I think we're probably looking at a
Epsom and 1/2 foot ceiling
Wood grain floor wood clapboard floor
Stone walls
The tiny room little bigger than a king bed
Is a fireplace little tables and Redwood cabinets
Is the home kitchen is a laundry places
You know you're One Stop Shop
And the reason this room is so important is because Dred Scott
Living in this room
For the first time in his life he got a taste
At what it might be like
To be free I mean obviously he was still a slave but
Dr. Emerson would leave the fort for months at a time and have him work for other people
Autonomy and Harriet and red met here
When he was here he met a girl 36-7 they met here he likes to stay
Stand here and imagine just how that money went down I can imagine
You know Harriet you know haven't been here
And and red being over by the store
And I'm having a conversation with someone of the other black guy that was here
And I imagine him saying
Here she comes walking by
Jim who is that
I'm going to make her mine
I can imagine
Him saying that
Over the next few years Dred and Harriet had
Two kids
Both of them girls
And I personally I think that that what happened was
Children seeing change everything
So what ends up happening is that
Dr. Emerson
Moves Dred Scott and his family
Back to
Missouri
They're back in the slave state
And dr. Emerson ends up passing away
And it seems like his wife is going to maybe sell Dred Scott's daughters
So what Dred and Harriet Scott end up
Deciding to do the whole reason we know Dred Scott's name
Is that they
Decide to sue for their own freedom
That's a lawsuit that Dred Scott had every right to believe that he would win
A Doctrine called once free always free
That the minute your foot landed in the snow of the north the minute to you and your owner walked
Mean to free territory you were free and you could not be returned
2 estate of bond
This was a well-known
Legal argument and impact Dred Scott one at a lower court so it goes all the way up to the Supreme Court
And the Supreme Court says
You're still property
And the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court Roger Taney
The black man
Has no rights that the white man is bound to respect Tawny
Amazingly broad decision
Not only slammed the door on Dred Scott
He slams the door
On the potential
For any African-American
Free or not free
To ever have
Full citizenship
In this country
And at that point at I'm at the highest court of the land to make that decision
That was putting a. On sort of this overarching
Battle between the North and the South before slavery and abolition is and so
When this happens
Now you start seeing Civil War popping off
Now as far as Dred Scott the case
Is concerned speaking legally
The thirteenth and fourteenth amendments to come along and overturn it but like that lie like the black man has no rights
That a white man is bound to respect like you can't overturn that line and these days
As the pendulum swings and we see a rise in blatant
Overt
White nationalism and violence over statues
That line still hovers above at all
What's a pose
You're a direct descendant of that case of that history supposed to name is Scott who last name is
Tahani
What do you do with that
Tickling now like what do you do with that history do you ignore it is it not your problem or do you have
Address it if you do how
Coming up next after the break we walk into a hotel lobby in St Louis
And get an answer we just did not expect
More perfect will continue in a moment
This is more perfect I'm chat album Rod okay now we come to the reunions
As she was supporting the story producer Julia Longoria
A little Googling located a couple of Scot Tani descendants and then found out that they were actually planning
To meet up
To have this kind of historic Summit
Which was like we thought was bananas
So she went
It was bananas and as soon as she came back she sat down in the studio
And told Elie mystal and I all about it
So where to start
Viking stoves
I walked into this
Hilton Frontenac hotel in St Louis classic
Hotel Atrium with like a fairy
Weird
Carpet pattern
And I walk in and it's like hello it's almost like a conference
Greeted by
The great great
Granddaughter Dred Scott
Literally this is our inaugural Sons and Daughters of reference
Association is the name Flynn Jackson
She's the main organizer this is always a dream that I had about 12 years ago
Then she immediately tells me I'm a network or I'm going to connect you with everyone
But I like doing invisible family right here and immediately she introduces me to these three people
Mimi Le Bourgeois John le Bourgeois family
The first family who owned
Her great-great-grandfather
She also introduced me to the
Great great great
Grandson of Thomas Jefferson I meant Davis
A descendant of Jefferson Davis
You know the guy who led the Confederacy against the Union in the Civil War and everybody's hugging it
Laughing it was wild
Meaning of the utopian society
Exactly
And the whole idea everyone kind of wanted reconciliation reconciliation I was like
Reconciliation reconciliation
And so I'm wandering around and going up shaking hands with random people and then I meet the
This one guy
Yes
Dread Madison I am the great great grandson of Dred and Harriet Scott
And
I look in his eyes
And I was like
Holyshit
Those are Dred Scott size
I mean there's really only one picture of Dred Scott that exist
And
From around 1857 he's wearing a suit
Staring straight at the camera
And is either like almost glassy
Pupils are really big and it's
Striking
I felt like I was looking right into those same eyes
Have you always known that you're related to Dred Scott and magic and what it wants to relationships about his
History what are you when you think about it
What are you
Where you feel
I have mixed feelings
Based on what
He tested Tony said and the decision I made. You are subhuman species with no rights a white man is bound to respect
No rights that white men are bound to respect
What really hit me the hardest knife it is hard for me to even think about this cuz it did just bothers me
Who was the Trayvon Martin
Just keep walking home from my store what's my name wasn't breaking any laws someone decided to follow
Pull up on him
Any luck murderer
Big guy parked his car got out of his car invaded it show me a space
And murdered him and used the stand-your-ground law
Your ground is yours until I decide it's not
I mean just as he's about to shake hands for the first time with the family who owned his family
Arrogant
Did that all go through here but you know you have to approach people
The approach people for who they are you got that open mind
One of the most striking things I learned from Dred Scott Jr Jr Jr
And also from his sister Barbara I'm Barber mcgregory I'm Dred Scott's great-great-granddaughter
Is that the Dred Scott history was actually something that was kind of
From them it was
Oshkosh weather
Because
The Dred Scott decision I don't know if you were understanding what that was
That that was the last straw that sparked the Civil War my dad
When they were growing up they had deaths
They couldn't tell anybody who they were
Related to
Your dad. Generation this was like a hundred years after the decision that generation a secret
That's his great-grandfather
His grandmother was Dred Scott's daughter
Dread junior junior told me that
His dad
Was actually partially raised by Dred Scott's daughters
Whose name was Lucy
Try to hide the fact in fact who told me she was
She might have been kind of mad when
Maya
Grandfather grandmother name my father Dred Scott because she was in hiding
You got to remember when she was
6 years old they would have hiding for 5 year
During the trial
Gardner sister
Is the whole basis a trial was
He didn't want his family split up
So when you lost the second appeal he sent the girls in the hiding
Because Steven want them towed away
So
Lizzy stayed pretty much Undercover
She lived in off a little
The room but she always had that the shades closed
So Jordan Barbara told me their parents never talked about Dred Scott I never had a picture up in the house
Never even knew what he looked like
In fact
As we were standing there in the lobby of the Hilton
Dread pulled out his phone
Photos of Dred Scott
Pictures of Dred Scott and he brings up
The photo on Google
Things like this
Dark eyes
He's wearing a suit
Like he was impressed I think like you wouldn't expect to
Slave to be dressed so nice. The first time you seen the picture Dred Scott
But it seemed like he was noticing things in it for the first time looks really dignified and stirred in that
A picture
But he looks looks like a man who's going through it is ready to go to some more
Okay so at the end of the night I end up at the hotel bar with another sentence
No I thought what her is about
No I think you should answer that so the Dred Scott case is a famous
Supreme Court case
And the Chief Justice who
Real demon cases Roger Brooke Pine
So I'm at Sonic
Charlie tawney is the great great grand nephew of Rodger Brooke Taney who is the chief
Injustice 2 basically denied Dred Scott his freedom
Kind of a tall guy white hair glasses on tip of his nose
At 11 bath original copy that decision and he was actually sitting there
Next 2-3 descendants from the family who originally owned Red Sky
They're like come join us and so to my left is
The descendants of
The people who own Dred Scott into my right are the people who kept Dred Scott enslaved
Are you not going to eat one of those
And they're all just having gin and tonics and crab cakes
Past is never dead it's not even past
Can you describe the first images you saw of Tony eventually I steer the conversation
Back to Charlie Tanya's ancestor Roger Taney the Supreme Court Justice
We have pictures of him hanging on our house when I grew up in the house
It was up on the wall and it had that I remember it had this so late over it
Unlike the Dred Scott family Charlie Tony and his daughter Kate Kate taney Billingsley
Grep knowing exactly what Roger looks like his skin
Flopped over and he had these
Long jowls but he was also a thin man
He looks like
Shriveled up little old man who lives up in the house on the hill that hardly ever comes out of his house and all the kids are scared of
You grab them
When's the first time you study of the Civil War probably like fifth grade
Sixth grade
And you're like sliding down in your seat when I get to the Dred Scott decision because you know this is really terrible and that's
My family
Did that
So that you're very aware of it
And we're also I mean and we're also in a while while you're
Well that's a black mark on our family the also ran one of the most productive
The courts
During a time of explosive growth in the cut
She was very proud of his role
Helping form America
What is known for is the single worst decision ever made by the Supreme Court
If your family member it's it's
A little a little difficult to have that be the only focus
Sitting there it was pretty clear that Charlie Tawny was
Kind of like Dred Scott Madison he also had some mixed feelings still having red having red
Numbers as letters I think I think he was
I think he I think he really loved
Guaifenesin
Family and that he was a very loving father and he was against slavery
It's pretty clear he thought it was a blot on the national character
He thought slavery was wrong
Are we
He thought it was wrong and should have been chili be done away with
He told me that in one of his legal arguments Tani
Totally rails against slave drivers
These people are reptiles
Who deal in the traffic in a few minutes
Sitting there Charlie tells me that
Roger Taney was
Trying to save the Union
That somehow if
He ruled that America was
Luvocracy
Once and for all
That might somehow
Delay the Civil War was trying to solve
The issue of slavery in America that might be true but
You put you can't overlook this
Will you read that language
That he was
A stone racist
I just was
And
And I asked them
Like when you met the Scott
Like what did you feel like what did you
Did you feel like you wanted to communicate something to them and
The blow descendants
Family who originally owned Dred Scott
Sad
Yeah like we're sorry
Have you ever I turned it on Ian's it like have you ever actually apologized
He's like I don't know I don't know if I ever use those words
I don't recall ever using those words
How's the weather next day
Pikachu at The Forum about hundred people crammed into the Grand Ballroom of the Hilton
The preacher
Serta forget to begin today in our proceedings I'd like to ask you to stand with me
I go to the Lord in prayer to bless these proceedings today
Led the group in prayer
Heavenly Father we come to you this day seeing your blessings in this room only asked Lord that this reconciliation
Begin today in a profound way in each of our hearts we learn from our past move to our future
Bless us this day and Lord we give you praise in Jesus name we pray and all of God's people said
Hey man you make me sick
And then time we would like for all of the
Distended if you will please
Just stand
Descendants get up on stage
Can you get like a little spiel about
Who they are what reconciliation means to them
Wife Martha
Is a half-sister of Sally hemings you might not know about their answer
They had the same father
And then after about 5 people have spoken
Please welcome to the stage
Charlie Tony Bennett
Morning
So the first thing I like to do is
Toyota
Your honor
Let me start with Rodger pisani what it was like to grow
The grub is autonomy in terms of how we feel about him as a real it's a mixed bag
Because on the one hand
Azan you're proud
He was
Are the longest serving Chief justices
The Bible he swore Lincoln in with
President Obama
However
That's not what he's known for
What is known for its one thing
He's done for the Dred Scott decision
And just so we all
Want to get a handle on
Let me read your sentence
Shiro
Which is a painting at the time of the Constitution
That African-Americans here's the quote
For more than a century have been regarded as being
Open exterior order
Associate
So far.
They had no rights
Which white man was bound
Respect
You make me proud of him
You can talk that
So
I looked up reconciliation
The process of reconciliation
And their three stash
The first step is apology
The second step is forgiveness
And the third step is
A new crop
But some someone has Kate about this issue apology
Atonic bringing an apology
Scott
It's like bringing a Band-Aid to an amputation
It just is not enough
But he was like
You got to start somewhere
So let's let's make a little history
You have our apology
I spoke to Scott descendants afterwards
What was that what did you think of it very much more emotional than I thought
Great great granddaughter Barbara macgregory no one's ever apologize Clinton made an apology
Some years ago but coming from him
Didn't mean much but
When
Connie
Emotional when he was reading that letter that was more heartfelt to me then
Anything else
Whose apology was okay but but his emotion really touched me
Barbara the Dred Scott defendant was like when he choked up reading that
I could feel that
But that felt
Like healing
But you doing
Hello then I qualified her brother and I ask you what you're thinking about how did you respond to all that
Dred Scott Madison
The one with the eyes
Everything was fine it's just odd to be honest the last part hot Cheeto worth
I like it I don't think somebody should have to apologize for something I didn't do justice to answer
Chester. I just I was very uncomfortable with that that's the fact that they
They're here is apology enough apologizing for something your ancestor did your part of a gene pool
You judged by your works not someone else's
Show me that you care don't tell me that you're sorry
Show me that
You going to do better
That's the only comment I have on it
Couple final notes when we talk to Dred Scott Madison later
He was pretty clear that look Charlie Tawny
Is already doing a lot of good he's helping the Dred Scott Foundation to raise money
That's why he felt the Charlie didn't need to apologize also when we started the story they were statue
Pictures of Rodger Brooke Taney in Annapolis and in Baltimore both in front of courthouses
Actually how the Scots
One of the first ways they come together they had decided collectively
On a plan to amend those two statues rather than take them down they have decided to put a drill
Scott statue next to them and they've been working on it
Politicians that met with the mayor of Baltimore
Finishing up the story Charlottesville happened
In the wake of Charlottesville
Standing outside the Maryland State House in Annapolis
In Charlottesville Virginia Ghost Town
In the same way
And it was a golf clap when tati came off the pedestal here and was
Remove but other than that everybody was quiet nobody had an opinion on this to themselves
145 year history gone here tonight and I'll get out of the way this is all that's left this is the pedestal that is
More perfect is produced by me Jetta
Susie lechtenberg Jenny Lawton Julia Longoria Kelly Prime sarkari Sean ROMs for
Alex overington telescope with Elie mystal
Cristian farias Linda Hershman David Gable and Michelle Harris Billingsley
Play a man of his time helped Inspire this episode Supreme Court audio is from Oye a free
Project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell leadership support for more perfect is provided by
Choice Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation