Listener-supported WNYC
Be Studios
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is more perfect
Right now
Capacitor is working madly on a story about a Supreme Court case that will be decided any minute
Most important
Supreme Court cases this term
Maybe in my lifetime
But in the meantime I wanted to share something with you guys
As you may know that this podcast new podcast for listening to more perfect is radiolab's first ever
Spin-off
The episode for me
The Radiolab episode for me that inspired
Me to try out this whole series it actually goes back to 2012 it was our first time ever reporting about
Greencore
I asked the entire team at Radiolab to look at the docket for that year pick a case make a few calls with sword
Experiment
Twitter Tim Howard
Came back with the following
About a little girl
Becomes
The center of a very big
This is the story that got us hooked
I'm thinking about this
And in many ways
It inspired us to
Make more perfect
Houston so I first
I first heard about this story I saw it listed on the
Supreme Court DACA
Different cases
Is that they were going to be hearing
This spring
Well the name of the cases baby girl versus adoptive couple
Actually in strict legal parlance
Is called adoptive couple V baby girl
That's not a particularly catchy name
Associate professor of law at the University of South Carolina
Stood out to me because
At first that this would even be a Supreme Court case
It seemed more like a straightforward custody case
Right
But
When you dig in
There's a lot going on here text messages
And it is not straightforward
At all fairly not
So let me walk you through it the way that I learned about
The Story begins with a couple
Matt and Melanie capobianco
They are a couple who live down here in South Carolina he's a technician at Boeing she's a developmental psychology
Just nice middle-class
Why couple they're in their late 30s
You really wanted to have a kid they had gone through
Infertility problems it wasn't working out
So
Eventually they decide to adopt
Enter a woman named Christy Maldonado
She lives about a thousand miles away
I believe she's in Oklahoma she's in her twenties already has a couple kids
She's pregnant
And decides that she wants to give
The baby up for adoption
And
Apex the capobiancos
Everyone seems happier capobiancos get the baby and the name are Veronica
Almost that time of our family called it at
Boss ladies is everybody around
This is Matt and Melanie capobianco
But you were happy to do whatever she told you
Poster child for a proud father you know
It's just gone
That's wrong as it could have possibly gone
This basic layout on folded on TV news
Young child ripped from the arms of the only parents she's ever known and turned over to the Native Americans
Logical father she is never met a man Veronica had never even met what happens when Veronica was too
Biological dad turned up seemingly out of nowhere and according to these clips had been around for two years had abandoned
Child and now he's asking for custody
In a court is making them stand by and just let it happen
Well it's mainly because of this walk in child welfare at the 1978 Indian Child Welfare Act
Dustin the dad
He's Cherokee you support the Cherokee Nation that makes his daughter Veronica eligible to be Cherokee
In the laws designed to keep Indian families together preference to Indian kids staying with Indian parents
So even though he actually sign papers
Green to the adoption
He was able to invoke this lot
And get custody of Veronica
Side is Cassidy way
Ben
Uses cherry kienast
Reverse
The rights he signed away to hang on is all going to make sense
Okay but you text Elliott
Yeah
New Year's Eve 2011
With cameras rolling
Dustin Brown drives his pickup truck
Charleston
Matt and Melanie capobianco flush to two-year-old Veronica could possibly be the last time
Hyundai hold their baby as her mom and dad and that evening Veronica is transferred to Dustin
And she like we had enough time for her to be Not Afraid when she
Assassin gets into the truck
Holding his two-year-old daughter for the first time
The reporter asks him
Do you think this is in her best interest
And this is all you hear from
I think so we need to give her a call
Have you ever seen the child support
They declined any further comment on camera
He gets into the truck with Veronica
And they drive away
Back to Oklahoma
Can I do can I ask you what was it when was the last time that you spoke with Veronica
The day after
Yeah
Spoke to her for about two men
Totally love Darren
I love you Mommy and I love
Love you Daddy
Just few minutes
Able
InTouch
And that was 16 months
How long was Veronica with him again before this have
About two years
Oh man that's
It's hard
And you know when I first heard about this case
That's basically the
The only way I thought of it you know it's just
That's a crazy Injustice
That's basically all I
Saw
And for someone with no background in this
Then you see a case like the baby Veronica case
Where's this coming from how can this possibly be okay
Does Marshalls drug again in her article for slate kind of caught me off guard because the title was
Doing what's best for the tribe
2 year old Veronica was ripped from the only home she's ever known
The court made the right decision
Yeah
So I called up Tasker like what do you mean by that
But I think important to realize is that
The problems
But
Equi was intended to address didn't stop happening
Long ago and in this is where the story
Turn into the
Biggest rabbit hole I've ever falling and didn't tell you
The only way you can begin to wrap your mind around
What's right and what's wrong in this story is
Go back to the six
How you doing how are you
Turkish
Lawyer who lives in Long Island now which is where I visited him
But in 1967 the fall of 67
I was on the staff of the association on American Indian Affairs
Sort of a legal advocacy group for American Indians
Any traveled all over working with different tribes
And
One day
Where he gets a phone call from this guy Lewis good house
The tribal chair the Devil's Lake Sioux Tribe in North Dakota and a guy says
I really need your help
He said there's a child
Devil's Lake kid one of ours
It was just abruptly taken away by social workers the Benson County North Dakota Social Services age
Agency came in
And they took
Little Ivan Brown
Away from
His a grandmother he was sick
Order stated reason for taking driving away
Neglect because what because grandma wasn't
Wasn't around no actually bird says that the social workers were looking for that classic nuclear family allowed
Magical mother
Biological father children
So when they saw him with an older relative but no Mom or Dad they thought
And they took him away the tribal council was
Really
Upset by
They wanted to
Fight a battle
Took the case but in court in that case by the way this is Alex Forney she got Ivan back
After
Somewhat protracted battle
But
He began to wonder how widespread is this
2.67 to the end of 68 into 69
The tribe after tribe
Doing interview
And he says that everywhere he went
He would hear these stories
I remember it vividly
This is Deb Wells
She's a member of the Rosebud Sioux Tribe
When she was 10 years old A car pulled into her driveway
Social workers
And I got out of car
I told my brothers and sisters I said go high
And
They had to drag this out from underneath the bed got around and got in the house
Then I caucus to Scottsbluff
And Patricia foster home
It looks horrible
This was
Just part of
Every native families history
She grew up on the Pine Ridge reservation in South
Dakota I remember when I was young we go to one of the Border towns
And my grandma
Would say
Stay in the car
Lock yourself in
Don't get out of the car I'm going into the Trading Post
Cuz they're going to steal you
Really yeah
What we found
Is that not every reservation
Photos of Standing Rock reservation
You couldn't not find the family
That didn't know of a child in placement
Social Services
And told my
Mother and dad that they were taking a bridge for physical check-up
And Alice pack
Michael says that his dad spent the next
30 years looking for
People that he was interviewing
What reason did the social workers give you for taking the child
An answer that he got ran the gamut
Conditions of poverty
Alcohol
Overcrowding maybe they don't have adequate
Ventilation in the house no indoor plumbing but in most cases he says the reasons would have stood up in court
They would put papers in front of them and they would sign
It was signing some families
If they could they tried to fight it but they usually couldn't afford to
Book the tribal people of poor
So we began to do with
Statistical collection
Of data
State-by-state
Asking how many Indian kids are in foster care
Respite care adoptive placement and institutional place
Juvenile facilities money arrived at the end of that analysis
Is a pretty shocking number
About one-third
Of Indian children wear in out-of-home placements in non-indian setting
1/3
25 to 35% of Indian children Nationwide
Where in out-of-home placement
That's a real number that is a real number that's the number you see sighted again and again
Nobody connected the dots
Everybody thought
That it was their own
Personal
Tragedy
Nobody realized
That this was a pattern and a
That was decimating these cry
How would this happen on this scale
I mean like with the supposition a bunch of social workers making the same decision in the
Dependently
Where is Italy
Policy well at this is basically the social workers
Very much acting in the spirit of the day
Because you have to keep in mind that in the fifties and sixties
You have all these government policies that are put in place
Who's
Entire purpose is basically two
Tried it once and for all solve this
Indian problem that's going on and on
You got this guy 1953 is a senator from Utah starts basically trying to terminate the tribe
You mean like take away their sovereignty
Yeah he goes tribe to tribe trying to convince them or force them
Tell them they have no there's no way out of it
He argues
That this will be best for all of them
To integrate them
Yeah the whole
They will melt into the wider culture that's what we'll save them
Part of this was
Part of the social workers that were working that.
They were working under the auspice
Pictures of a thing called the Indian adoption
Which
Was very much about
That ideas
You take these kids from their poor condition
And you connect them directly
Two white families that are looking
How to adopt
So far this is definitely top down very much
In any case
The end result of this is that a third of these kids are being taken away
There were literally communities where there were no children
That's Terry cross
He's executive director of the national Indian Child Welfare Association
In Minnesota there were community
It's where there were no children
In flask
There were communities where there were no children
I mean what is
What is a culture except
Healthy ideas and
Traditions that you pass on to your kids
That's Marsha's ugh again if you are hemorrhaging your children
Then you're going to disappear
So what would you do
Well it's to mass of a problem if you trying to fight
All these removals of kids on a case-by-case basis fugetaboutit
A national laws needed so Bert spent years Walking The Halls of Congress literally
Endless lobbying Congressional hearings until finally
So it does a lot but basically when it comes to adoptions
They will have placement preferen
So the first preference would be
With the immediate
So you removed from Mom your
Place with Dad
Maybe with Grandmother they say no second preference would be
Someone else in the tribe
+ 1/3
Is any other American Indian
Any other and then after that
Other than the child could be placed with
Another family
Well so if you're white
And you're trying to adopt Indian
Yeah yeah a lot of rope
Yes
But
By and large
Most of us think that echoes
Probably
The
Best Federal Indian law ever
Did the most to
Help Indian tribes
Respect tribal sovereignty
And really fulfill the United
This is trust relationship
With America
But now because of this case
That law may be in jeopardy
Will continue in a moment
Tom Chatham Rod this is more perfect run the middle of a story that was
Our first attempt at
Supreme Court Reporting
And
Reporter Tim Howard
So in April I went to this conference in Tulsa
Big room there are 700 people there
Muslim work in child welfare organizations in Indian communities around the country
There was some traditional Cherokee drumming their films Workshop
All anybody could talk about but this case there is no issue
How the baby Veronica case may
Fact the Indian child welfare act so please please do keep
Baby Veronica and her family in your prayers
Everybody was on it really worried
In this situation this is Terry cross again he's one of the organizers and
He told me that
Look
The capobiancos
I feel for them
But in what world is it okay for one family
Who feels they were damaged by a law to put thousands of other children at Jeopardy
For their own hurt I can't imagine a world where that's okay
Well I mean it's hard
For us to say that because
You know that's not what motivated us
Our daughters what's motivating us
Well how we feel we just feel that in
And this case is it was a
Beautiful law that was put into place to prevent the breakup of families
Indian families
I just think it wasn't
Really supposed to be applied to situation like ours
They say but we get it there's a huge
Storical wrong here
What does that have to do with us
Reminds me of arguments it happened over affirmative action
Ridley definitely but hear the details are
Are are so different you know they say
This is a law that was
Created to protect Indian families right
You got a white couple and then you got it Dad was out of the picture so
You're not actually protecting Indian family you are forcibly creating a new one
Absolutely I mean the process you're breaking up a loving home and I don't think that was the Ben 10 of the law ever
I asked my personal opinion is that
Aqua has outlived its usefulness
What causes more problems then
That's awesome
This is Mark Fiddler
I want to see Chinese for Matt and Melanie capobianco he also happens to be Native American himself
Enrolled member of the turtle Mountain band of Chippewa Indians that's a reservation up in North Dakota right on the boardwalk
And I was right kind of fell off foot into culture so to speak I go back to the Rasmus summer and Mark actually used to argue the other
Other side
The most important thing was to
Keep Indian families together
Annette Indian kids score place
And on Indian homes
Experience emotional
Psychological harm by
Being raised outside of the culture
But then I got a case in
Bus 94
Which gave him pause
Boy
That's a good word
With a K sandwiches Young American Indian girl at Sierra wanted to be adopted by this white couple
And Mark
Opposed it in my heart of hearts I knew it was
Probably
Not the right thing for the child
He won the case
She was removed from the couple's home
Sierra would tell you herself she had the
She had a pretty rough life
She bounced in and out of more than 20 foster homes
Runaway many many times
And got into serious trouble with the law
It always nag me
Mark says even though the tribes
Suffered
That doesn't change the fact that if you
Take a kid out of a loving home
You're going to cause her real
Harm
And he says that's why he took
Because the capobiancos know they are
Among the most loving people I know
He said they did everything you could ask her just amazing people
Emmett the birth mother Christine Maldonado when she was pregnant
They got to know her she
Tell the connection to them
That's Lori Miguel's she's represented Christy since last year
And they were also willing to have an open adoption
Yeah we still have a relationship with Kris TV
We love her to death and Crissy give birth to Veronica they were there
With her in the delivery room
The day she was born a cut the cord
Matt
Capobianco cut the
Umbilical cord so that's such a degree of intimacy that I
I know I mean having given birth twice myself
Did anyone other than my husband would be
In the rooms
It's kind of scary but that it gives you some idea of how she felt about the
Capobianco
Now as for Dustin Brown Veronica's biological dad
A couple months before she was born Christy the birth mom
Send him a text message asking him
Pay child support or
He wants to waive his rights
And he replied
I waive my right
Rather than pay
A dime in child support
Well there's a contrast
So the beginning it sounds like he did not want to be a dad a few months later
Key
Things to make it even more official by signing a form agreeing to the adopt
And then he changes his mind yeah you know
Obviously I was wondering what was he thinking
Cuz you can't avoid the fact that how you feel about this guy
Is going to influence how you feel about this law and so I was trying to get in touch with him I was
Pestering his lawyers will he do an interview this one on for weeks and and they were basically like
He doesn't want to do interviews
He doesn't want to talk
Yeah yeah he said he didn't get him
Shortly before we're going to wrap this story
I got an email saying come to Oklahoma
He lives in this one story house on this tree line block
In a small town north of Tulsa
Hey how's it going
What it look like is it a very
Normal looking guy
A little bit of an army haircut
He had a stash
That night when you got Veronica
But he's clean-shaven now smile
So anyway we go inside and the first thing he tells me
Is that Veronica's not there
She was out with his wife Robin
Because I with my wife
Turns out he's remarried
In any case testis alright we sat down at the kitchen table and started talking
Something tell me like where we are
Dustin Brown for Nowata Oklahoma this is my house
I'm part of the wolf Clan
Oakland is 107 Cherokee
Wiki Clans and my name Dustin
Meads
Brave Warrior
And I
Turkey
Next you know join the Army up and
Dover Dirac I'm like wow
I'm here for the Cherokees
I'm brave Warrior outing
Desert
He's been registered member since he was a little kid
His parents were members and their parents and he said he's proud to be Cherokee
Basically because it means that
He's from where he lives
What's the big deal to me
So anyway we
Sorry talking about the case and it gets complicated there's a lot of detail not going to go into all of it
Basically he and Christy Maldonado the birth mom we've known each other since we were 16
We've dated off and on
2008 he joins the Army basic training he lives on a base it's far as away
Panda Christmas time that year
He basically says
Let's Get Serious
Got down on one knee and proposed to her said hey
I want to bring into my life
She said okay that's just great
And
Almost a month later
She send me a message saying that she was pregnant and
I was excited
I mean
I have children with her was
Was one of the things I wanted at that time
Told her I can move you and your kids up to the base
Housing was going to be free on base
There was schools for her kids she could
Get a job right there on base you know
Everything was taken care of me and everything was going great now
And then
Pretty quickly the whole thing just sour
It's impossible to know exactly what happened but Christie says that Dustin
Just simply didn't offer any
Support
He says that he
Did Harry tried to at least
But shortly after she got pregnant she basically just shut them out
Stop taking his calls
I didn't get no phone calls no text message nothing from Riley blue and on the cycle what's going on he says that he tried to get in touch with
Trying to call her
Still no answer
A couple times that I've went back to the bars and went to her house though there's 4 hours from the base
Knocked on her door I can hear
You know voices in the house
I sound like her and the kids they wouldn't answer the door for me
Then one day he says
She sent me a
Message saying
I don't want to be with you no more
+ 3 weeks after that she's like
I want you to sign your rights over
His parental rights
Would you sign your rights over
You guys are texting this we talkin
Show the whole time we're text messaging this
Because she wouldn't talk to me what did you think it meant
To me I just
Does she wanted me to sign my rights over to her
And I'm like
This summer I really don't want to do
He says
She kept texting him that question
And looming in his mind was
The fact that he just learned so we're going to be going to Iraq to
The radar Mission so he starts to wonder what's the right thing to do here
There was one of chances I was going to come back I want to make the right choice and
But the mother
BSO parent he says
That he's holding out hope that if he does make it back will get back together and she'll just change your mind
Finally told her I was like alright I'm signing rights over
Months go by
Christy has a baby peace as he doesn't know exactly when because they weren't speaking
But then six days before
I had to go to the port of Iraq
I get a phone call from
Some guy in Washington County the process server
Said hey
We need you to sign some papers so you sign your
Restaurants over by directed him to an office right near the base
Went there
Sign the paper and what did you think that man
The whole time I thought I was just
You know the paperwork for me sign customized to her
But
When I got done sign the guy said
You just sign your rights away instead of the biological mother
There's been up for adoption and she's been living in South Carolina
4 months
Dustin says this is the first moment that he realized what was actually happening
That the baby was up for adoption
And he says that he had no idea he had just legally can send it to it
I should have had a lawyer there with me
At that point I might grab the paper and the guy looked at me and said if you going to rip that up he said
It's not good to do that
That he could be arrested and also what do I got to do
He said you get a lawyer which he immediately did
That's why the courts have ruled in his favor because they say that from that moment
He's clearly demonstrated that he wants to be her dad I mean I never
Never once
They don't want to give up on my daughter never once that I want to give her up
I mean everybody says that I gave her up
Never wanted to
Mark and Lori say that
If this were any other guy
Any other man of any other race whose story would be over right about it
It's too late
He wouldn't have any rights at all under every State's laws
Too late under the Federal Constitution too late
He rejected
That opportunity to become a father
He has one thing in his favor
Teslore
He happens to be Cherokee
And because of that fact not only can distort of man
But he gets an automatic transfer of custody to him
Mark and Lori see that as basically the worst kind of preferential
Treatment and that is unbelievable
This is John John Nichols this is Shannon Shannon Jen's Dustin's lawyers
And John says okay there's preferential treatment
But think about why all the protections of iqua are there he's Roblox what they are for a reason we went over this earlier but
You know basically people are being manipulated out of their kids
Emoji might like to think that that's ancient history now fast forward to 2010
The same thing is happening in this
We have a registered member
Of the Cherokee Nation
We have his child
Being given up for adoption without his knowledge
And without his consent
And they kept this adoption from him for months
And then spring it on him six
Days before he leaves the country
It looks to us like it was engineered to make sure he got served but not enough time to where he could put
Put up a fight I believe it was absolutely intentional
Enchanted suggest
That they knew about Equity new would apply
And they were trying to sidestep
Are so many errors
There's one important form where Shannon says
That they went out of their way
To make it look like Veronica is not Native American
That's just dumb
It's a Preposterous argument another for Mark and Lori say the reason that nobody puts Cherokee
And big bright flaming letters
Simple
Chrissy herself is predominantly Hispanic
Dustin is predominantly
Caucasian and is approximately 2% Cherokee
What
Did you say 2%
Yai Veronica herself a b a little bit over one person
Wait this whole thing is happening because he's only 2%
Well you look at changes things come out
Well yeah but you have to keep in mind that
Cherokee Nation
Doesn't care about the percentage of Cherokee in your blood that's not how they determine their members
Being a member of the Cherokee Nation
Is like being a member of the United States you are a
Citizen of the nation
You know if
If your parents are US citizen
You're automatically a citizen Assistant Attorney General for Cherokee Nation
If your parents are Cherokee citizen you're automatically a citizen but you can automatically apply
So it's based on Direct lineage
But still
You're right because this is the argument that is most troubling
To the tribe
Both Chrissi Nimmo and marshes ugh told me that
If the Supreme Court
Ends up deciding
Equi is unconstitutional because it really is race-based unconstitutional cuz it's race-based preference
It calls into question every single federal Indian law
There goes Indian law
This is a case that they could use to do that
If iqua falls because it's unconstitutional
You could have a crazy domino effect
Every single
Federal Indian law
Is premise
On
Giving some sort of special treatment Indian
What would that mean concretely if
Indian Longwood to go away it means that their policing the court system education anything to do as a
The Sovereign Nation all of that just evaporates
A tribe would just become another group of people
On
Summerland
That said
This is not
The likely outcome
No
The Supreme Court will probably rule as narrowly as they possibly can
And as far as the tribes are concerned
They can do a lot of damage to the law without calling it unconstitutional
You know they could allow for
This
Certain kind of exception to iqua
Which would make it a lot easier for people like the capobianco is to adopt
So they can roll any number of
Yeah
And the thing is that
It's all
Strangely connected
To this
I figured maybe three year old girl
No signs of this I'm thinking I'm just going to
Suncoast
So when when she finally showed up
Halfway through my interview with Dustin
Hello
Hi
It was kind of surreal
Date my daughter Veronica though Daddy
Hey Veronica on Tim
She's got dark curly hair she's a ball of energy
This definitely bullheaded
Within a minute
She's giving me a tour of
Every single object in her room
And this
I mean everything
Gummy bear
Army bear
Marijuana daddy dog tags on it
She was a very very proud
Cool host
Few minutes later if she wanted to show me her
I don't think I've seen geese in a long time
Desert desert real
Yeah she feed them out of her hand
Liberty
Thomas the Train so
Happened to her but if the Supreme Court said
Dustin Brown shouldn't have qualified
As father
What they do is they would send it back down to a South Carolina
And then they would have this new best interest evaluation
Basically like what's the best thing for her at this point
She's been with him now for
About a year-and-a-half
Cancel that actually
Might really change the calculation
10 mm
Honestly
Hanging out with
Her and Dustin
In the backyard
Is really easy to forget
All these people whose lives are just
Completely Tangled Up In This scene
Christy Maldonado the birth mom
She intended to give Veronica life has been going on for
We've kind of been in a holding pattern for like well forever is waiting and waiting waiting
Of course that the hundreds of tribes are just worried about their own kids
Pretty cool are you a good swimmer
Bad summer
Summer you not cutest member
Anima vestra marry you just Miller
Yeah
So the Supreme Court came to a decision on this ruling about a month after we first air this podcast
And hit here
What they say
Okay so the Supreme Court ruled
Five four
In favor of the adoptive couple
Which is to say against the birth
To Dustin Brown the dab
It was like a 60-page
Ruling and
Not being
Totally confident with all the ramifications were
I just made some calls
Hi how are you
I'm doing great how are
For example I Skype
With Marcia Zug
Who you remember from the pieces
She's a law professor at the University of South Carolina
Can you walk me through what this opinion means
Well in terms of
Veronica's placement
How to come out the other way
Then it would be over she would stay with Dustin Brown her biological father
End of story
What we have now
Is the court of holding
The termination of his parental rights
So basically the Supreme Court ruled that Dustin Brown shouldn't have been allowed to invoke the Indian Child Welfare Act
Because he didn't have what's called continuing custody of Veronica
Continuing custody
Right there argue that this other about preventing the breakup of Indian families and there was no Indian fam
Only here because they didn't live together dad and a daughter to write
So they don't scrap the Indian Child Welfare Act
They just say that it shouldn't applied in case like this
So basically according to Tim it was
Is pretty narrow ruling
What then
Is it the Supreme Court kick the case down to a lower court
South Carolina and that lower court ultimately
Awarded custody of Veronica to the Kappa Beyond
Dustin Brown try to fight it
There are lots of lawsuits
It's flying back and forth in both directions
But in the end
Veronica
Did end up
Going to the
Send two and a half weeks since our daughter Veronica
Peppermint Malachi Bianca
And on October 10th 2013 Dustin Brown called The Press
It was a love for my daughter that kept
Me going all this time
That is it was also
The love for my daughter
Dude that finally gave me the strength
Things that are Beyond My Control
The time has come
For me to let Veronica live a normal childhood
Never so desperately needed
And deserve
Dustin Brown then announced that he would be stopping his
Forget
Santa Veronica
One day you will read
About this
Xiamen airlines
Never ever
For one second
Never ever for one second
How much
I love you
I thought for you
My home will always be your home
Always welcome
I miss you more than
My little girl
My princess
I will always love you until the day I die
One more thing
In our story we talked
A lot about
The possibilities are the larger possibility
Effective this case could be
Used as a
First step
To basically declare
Indian Liza
The race-based situation
Could then be negated
That didn't happen it is
But
There is a sense that they they kind of
Planted a seed
For example
Justice Alito who wrote the ruling
He started off with mention of Veronica being
1.2
Cherokee
Which
Is interesting cuz it sounds like he's about to make an argument for why this is a race-based preference and whites of
Violation of equal protection
But then he doesn't make that are gay
He pulls back
So the question is
Why did he start the ruling that way
She trying to send a message of some kind
I asked
Marsha
What you thought about
Why you think they started it off that way
I've been thinking about
It clearly
Sat wrong with at least some members of the court I mean when listening to the oral arguments you could tell that
And Robert's parked on it as well
I think it's an indication that at least some members
Court
Have serious
Reservations about Indian law
Because they just don't see Veronica is an Indian Child
To them
Indian is a race
She doesn't have enough blood to be of that race
Hey there's a possible
Indication of
Where future Indian law cases are going to go
Since then the Supreme Court has seen a handful of Indian law cases in the biggest development so far
Is it the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the federal government
Change
The rules surrounding the Indian Child Welfare act were there about you the new rule changes are going to go into effect December twenty
What you mean is that when a child like Veronica is put up for adoption
The state would have to ask whether or not she was an Indian Child the father would have to have been asked whether or not
She's an Indian Child in the state would not be able to consider
What percentage Indian blood she has in determining if she is an Indian
How to say the hope is that
Future veronika's will not have to go through
What does fraud
CC
Cute snakes to Tim Howard
Who now produces the amazing podcast reply-all
They just put out a four-part series on the criminal justice system
It's cold on the inside
Definitely check it out
At the time we made this episode Radiolab is produced by myself Jennifer Rod our staff includes
The amazing Robert krulwich ellenhorn Soren wheeler Tim Howard Brenna Ferrell Molly Webster Melissa O'Donnell Dylan Keith Levy and
Immaculate
We had help from Megan tan at Kelsey Padgett
Answer TP to Melanie and Derek Klena