WNYC Studios
Perfect the most perfect album final episode
For those of you who maybe you're just too I don't know why you would
We just be doing it on this one
Let's say you are what we are up to
Who is we are taking
The 27 amendments to the US Constitution
Stodgy words that are
Are so important
Define our rights as American
But they're so large
They are
We didn't
Even us who have been reporting on court cases
3 years
I had never read
Amendment 23 I just hadn't I hate I couldn't have told you what it is
So make a long story short we decided to put together an album
To reanimate
These
Crucially important words through the power of music and in the podcast
Raw from the liner notes
List of the songs were telling stories about these amendments about
Where they came from
What they mean to us now and we have
2 amendments left
Two songs
To go with each of those two amendments
And we will begin this final episode
With one I just mentioned
23rd Amendment
Presidential vote for DC
The district constituting the seat of government of the United States
Shall appoint in such manner is Congress made a wreck
The number of electors of President and Vice President
Equal to the whole number of Senators and representatives in Congress to which the district would be entitled if it were state
If it were state
David worst day
Okay we arrive at Amendment 23 all those words
Just a second ago with the amount due is simply this
23rd Amendment
Gives the citizens of
The District of Columbia the citizens of DC the right
To vote
For president
Which for me
Begs the question
DC didn't have the right to vote for president what
The White House is in DC for god sakes
How to take a 23 amendments to give the citizens of DC the right to vote for
Why Julie Longoria why and why don't they have that right in the first place
It was kind of an act
Didn't
Reason why this ended up happening is
The founders
Wanted to
Put the White House
In a neutral place
They wanted it to be outside of State politics
So you wouldn't run into a situation where like
The Civil War breaks out in the White House is in Alabama like what
What would Abraham Lincoln have done in that situation
We wanted to make sure
The capital would operate from a peaceful place of neutrality
So the founders took corners of Maryland and Virginia and created a city that would be controls
Buy conch
I don't think anyone meant to disenfranchise
All of the nearly
700000 citizens that live in DC
But that's what ended up happening
Because DC is not a state
The Constitution didn't really address it
Princeton
It didn't have electors in the Electoral College
Alexander Hamilton. Eventually we fix the representation problem in DC but that didn't come until
Which amendment number 23
Crazy to that long
I did actually fix the problem in the end no actually all the 23rd Amendment did
Is give the citizens of DC the right to vote for
President
Which you know
Is no small thing but
It left many things on answer
It didn't really clarify what DC is
Constitutionally like is it a city is it a state
The way our system of government work
You got to be part of a state to have senators
You got to be part of the state to have a vote in the house
DC is simultaneously
Not a state
Eat and not
Part of a bigger state
So it's
Definitely a thing
But it's like not enough of a thing to get it full representation in Congress
You don't have
A full democracy unless you treated equally
And a district is not treated equally because
We're the only jurisdiction
The pay federal taxes
I know whose member cannot vote
And whose member has no senator
And that's that's you you can't vote right
That's me
This is congresswoman Eleanor Holmes Norton and I represent the District of Columbia Nations Cafe
She kind of sits at the center of the blind spot of
The 23rd Amendment
She's
The non-voting delegate
From Washington DC I'm called a delegate I'm
Just like my
Pearson called delegates so sorry at what what is a non-voting delegate what is that
Kind of what it sounds like like it
A congress person who represents their constituents in Congress
They have an office in Congress does all the things that normal Congress people do
But when it comes time for the final vote on the floor
They don't have it
They don't have a vote
Why isn't the whole reason you elected Congress person so they can go to DC and vote on bills
Yeah
Over the years there have been
Over 150 proposals to change this ideally Eleanor wants
To solve it by making DC the 51st state of the United
But it's become like this
Political thing where like
DC is
Berry Blue as a city
It's also 47% African-American what's happened over the years is that some Republicans have found ways to block
Eleanor Holmes Norton zafords
To get representation
Some people say
It would be unconstitutional
A huge disappointment to me but very frankly I'm used to uphill battle so you can get yourself together
Everything to know about Eleanor Holmes Norton
Is that
Long before she was
The congresswoman from DC
She was a civil rights activist
Give me organizer with the Mississippi Freedom Summer in the 1960s equality
Is not
Brain part of this
I'm almost any other diverse Style
Amazon made a show about the lawsuit she won for young women researchers at Newsweek the idea of women's
Yesterday
When she was a lawyer at the ACLU she won a historic
First Amendment case
Where she represented
White Nash
Sometime
I got the same people
Who
Would not defend me
The woman is fascinating she was the first woman to head the EOC the equal employment opportunity commission
I'm wrote the first federal guidelines that helps make sexual harassment
Illegal
Under federal law
And Eleanor Holmes Norton
Leather push that Anita Hill could even be her
She was one of the people who demanded that Anita Hill be able to testify before the Senate like
She is a revolutionary
Invite
Congresswoman Norton
Thank you so much
Which is why I found it
Dreams
Two-seater in this position thank you very very much
Why would she choose this job I christened
This ship
Potomac
Water
Taxi
B2
Soon I hope to have a real name
The day we visited her she was speaking at an event
At the Wharf
Our neighborhood on the water that she helped develop
To Christen
A new water taxi
Macy brands
Fair
When
And I know politicians have to do that sort of thing that's rain
But the juxtaposition of the Revolutionary I read about and go
Fortune
And this woman
Who sale
Her
Boise smacking a staff against the yellow Water Taxi
It was
Confusing
You've been doing this
For a long time right
Since 91 and I'm curious
You had a really varied career you know you've
I watch the Amazon special that's mostly based on your life and and you were the first woman
I wonder why you made the turn
To be in this position where your hands are tied
Ironically my hands are tied in the least
Can't
Do
The final vote but by the time the final vote comes in the house it's a done deal so I have to
I have to do the work
Ahead of time which is what every member
Even those we have the vote
I have to do it made things even more confusing
Is that she insisted that even though she
He cannot vote
Her job is no different than any of her colleagues
I go to the house floor
Like everybody else I work in committee where most of the work is being done
I go and
Talk to two members of the Senate and and it kept coming up
She kept harping on that point my job is no different than I do what everybody else says if you want to get a bill passed
At one point
She got really upset with us
Because we made the mistake of comparing the situation of DC to the territory
Which also don't have voting representation in Congress
Places like Puerto Rico and Guam are completely different places
It seems almost like an insult to her to ask questions about
This thing which seems so obviously true
The every single respect
Accept not having the final vote on the house floor
We are a state
Wheezing
The irony of this comes out almost cartoonishly when depressed person
That we talked to was in the room band yet told us that there was this buzzer that goes off in the office when there's a vote on the house floor
Ben was telling me about a sound that happens when there's a voter's me like that with
So what is that I don't know what that is
What is what
Now there's a boat
When you hear the Bell you know there's about in this
Born shoes that you have 15 minutes
To go to the floor
Ornette signal
Whether to vote on the rule on something else
So that is supposed to Signal like that your butt over there kind of thing
It does mean that
If you have a boat you should be preparing to go
About
And for you to
What is that what does that
Signal to your house that beat make you feel
What that may mean I've been on the floor ready to discuss the bill
I can discuss any Bill including pills I can vote on which is which is the most bills
Withdrawal bill
Going to the floor
Speak on the bill I'll be going to the floor to speak on the FAA
I didn't know how to make sense of this irony
This woman
Who's been
Representing disempowered people
All her life
She's almost
Choosing to be in a role with virtually no power
And then insisting in these moments
That she's not disempowered at all
If I were going to demand change it seems like
I would shout from the rooftops
I don't have a vote
That my job is completely different that I'm completely disempowered
In these moments
Eleanor Holmes Norton had almost
Is willful denial of the miserable situation that DC finds
It's open
I only had about 15 minutes
Congresswoman Norton
And I went home from DC totally baffled
By the interaction
So I started
Looking back at her speeches and her writings
Deep
Cuts on C-Span
And I found this one panel from 1987 at the Sag Harbor initiative
What was called
The Retreat from equality
And it clarified things for me
I do want to say something about the Constitution
Southern Marshall
Did a great service to the country
Remind
Thurgood Marshall
Reminding it that
Of our own Constitution
But it is very important.
Powerful myth
One of the only remaining powerful meth
Is the myth of the concert
The Mist
Whatever our religious or ethnic
Powerful men
Has not always been
Is true
For those who believe in God
Even when there is war and famine and pestilence
They can indeed live
Of the concert
Is in a very real sense
When there was nothing but racism
They believe those words
Call Babe
They ultimately made the black people there for
How to be
At the Forefront of those who celebrate
The
Not because it is perfect
Because they have made it more perfect
One of the worst things we could do in a Time
When so little
Brings us together
Try to debunk or destroy
Powerful myth
Anime
Of the Great American Constitution
Which has been copied all over the world
And which continues to drive up to a more perfect Society
In some ways I think
Eleanor Holmes Norton
China stands in 4D
DC
She lives in a
State
A suspended denial
In order to keep fighting
If she were
Black people or women or any of the people were not in the original We the People
If we ever succumb to our powerlessness gave up
It would all be over
But if Eleanor Holmes Norton keeps believing in the Constitution
Believing in the myth that it tells us the myth of her own power despite the odds
Despite even the reality of her situation
Maybe
She can make her reality
Match the myth
I mean hey we got the 23rd Amendment didn't we
Has Julia Longoria with
That liner notes for the 23rd Amendment
As for the album
We asked
Students at Duke Ellington School of the Arts
The song for us
23rd Amendment
The song is written and arranged by their teacher in the classroom
Performance is great at the most perfect album. Org
Jordis
Duke Ellington School of the Arts
That was sort of an edited version of a song they put together for us for the 23rd Amendment
You can hear the entire thing and see the entire thing is well at the most perfect album. Org
I'm Jedi Cam'ron We will return in a minute
This is more perfect time chat at home run
Okay so here we are
At the Finish Line the very last of the amendments to the US Constitution 27
When we started this project
Most of us hear more perfect
Didn't know
How many amendments
Exactly
What each of the men
Now we do
More importantly
We picked the name
2017 clue the number in the name
27 most perfect album
Because while we were making it we realized this project
Is a kind of time
Right now there are 27 Amendments
One day
They'll be 28
Because clearly we have not yet gotten to that more perfect union and each one of these amendments represents a Time
We try to fix something in ourselves
This project is a testament
A love letter really
To that willingness
To change your thinking of
This album is serving emotional musical snapshot of who we are as a nation right now
Who is your trying to become
So it's fitting that I last line or notice
Short it's really about that
Kevin Devine the artist who wrote about the 27th Amendment for us
Tells the story of one guy
Spent 10 years
Trying to get two-thirds of both houses 3/4 of the states
To ratify an amendment
It had been written almost 200 years earlier
So I got the 27th Amendment
For this project 27th Amendment
Congressional compensation
No law varying the compensation for the services of the senators and representatives shall take effect
Until an election of Representatives shall have intervened
Just basically says the Congress can't give itself a raise in the end it's sitting term
GZA sound sensible thing
Apparently brought forth in the 1789 and then not ratified until 1992 which is by
190 years or something the longest margin
And the story the people I was interested in where this college kid in the early 80s you write some papers
Saying that
She believes that they could still be ratified
And his teacher gives him a seat
Intazza Mike there's no way that could be true
And then the sky kind of makes it like his bow know we kind of like
Thanks drum about it for 10 years
Mission
It gets
Resurrected and eventually
38th state to vote to ratify was Michigan in his speech the
Guy who sang the gavel and made it so
Said that
Something's take a year round here but others take a little more like 200
Minecraft pasteurize that for the first one of the songs I thought it was a really good entry point
And I've got a kick out of it a lifelong
Northeasterner family here in Jersey
Jersey was in line to be the ratifying votes
Michigan took it out of their hands
So one more bridesmaid moment for my people in New Jersey
Why
So that's it
7 past midnight
Kevin Devine with the 27th
Closing out
The most perfect album
Okay before we go
If 27 is just a moment
Anime
It's not the most exciting
King of the amendment
Silly there are more to come there must be more to come we need more
Just wanted for second as we go out
What will be 28
We all know we need a 28th Amendment
I'm not proposing a 28th amendment that 28th Amendment
Members of Congress Constitutional Amendment
Reasonable limits on Election spending around
Whatever ends up
Add song to the album if you make a whole new album until then more perfect is produced by me
Julie Longoria Kelly Prime sarkari and Alex overington withheld from Elie mystal Michelle
David Gable all truly amazing people I could not be more grateful to them all including NorCal
For her help making our record 27 the most perfect album
For reading the Amendments for 7 of course
To all the musicians at apart
I have no words
You guys made this thing a reality
Thank you
All of us here
You can listen to all of the songs as well as read funny short essays
And also see some crazy music videos that we made
At the most perfect album. Org
Thank you all for listening
Riding on this journey with us