WNYC Studios
And when I first heard about this project I was hanging out with my mom and Seattle and I
Started talking to her about how I would approach
The idea of writing a song about a constitutional amendment
We started talking about some different amendments and then
Started focusing on the 4th amendment
I thought of doing some research and I ended up finding
A legal term associated with the Fourth Amendment
Poem fruit of the poisonous tree
I named my son after
It means that evidence found by being searched illegally is being tainted evidence
Cannot be used against someone in court
I had a realization that the fourth amendment is basically about having consent in the way
Play retreated by the government and so my song references that by way of romantic consent
At the parallel
The first lyrics I wrote for the song where when you take
Take what you took for me
That was Briana marela with her song fruit of the poisonous tree
Inspired by the Fourth Amendment
Got to say it's one of my favorites
Jad abumrad this is more perfect
Season 3 this season
We decided
And I just make some podcast
Decide to put together an album
Songs
Inspired by the amendments
US Consul
There are 27
Is amendments
Outline our rights
As Americans
Issue a country that is
Constantly evolving and changing
We reached out to a bunch
Musician
Ask them to create a song inspired by one of these mm
35 different positions
Responded
Kissimmee
And we have created
The most perfect album
Entire thing at the most
Perfect album
. org
Most perfect album. Org the entire thing
Is on that website
Along with all kinds of information and some
Design
Albums also on iTunes Spotify all the places
Kieron the podcast
The more perfect team
Are telling stories
About the amendments
Sort of audio liner notes
Company
Songs
For this line
Sarkari
Did some bundle
Set the fourth fifth
6th Symphony
Stuck together when you read the 4th through 8th Amendments
Of the Constitution
What you're really looking at
According to
Professor Burt neuborne who we heard an episode 1
Is a story
You have an absolutely
Perfect
Chronological history
For Chronological picture
Open Bowling for Soup
It's a story about how the Constitution is supposed to fit
People when they come face-to-face with
The police
4th amendment deals with investigation the right of the people to
Secure in their persons houses papers and effects
Against unreasonable searches and seizures shall not be violated the Fifth Amendment
Deals with
Shall be compelled in any criminal case
Be a witness against himself
The sixth amendment all criminal prosecutions and 7th Amendment suits at common law
Accused shall enjoy the right to
To a speedy and public trial
An impartial jury and to have the assistance of cow
So for his defense
And the Eighth Amendment deals
Excessive bail shall not be
Required
Nor excessive fines imposed
No cruel and unusual punishment
It's a seamless
Story
Humble law enforcement
And the creation of
Protection
Edith
Stage in the process
So you can investigate without a probable cause in a warrant
You can interrogate by making somebody's incriminate themselves
You can't eat judicate without giving somebody
Due process and a lawyer
I know you can't punish
Anyway that's cruel and unusual
No other
Bill of Rights
Anywhere
How's this
Kind of
Organized and thoughtfully
Developed
Set of protection
But
We know that
So often
These amendments
Work the way that they
They're supposed to
Could you just tell me your name and how old you are
Christopher Scott
47 years of age
How many years ago now was it
That you got a rest
Dua 23 years ago
It was April 17th
97 Christopher is 26 years old
He lives in Dallas he has a girlfriend and two kids and he works in the produce department
Apartment at the local grocery store just leaving the everyday life of
Every person wanted list
Hammond employment
Being independent and being able to support your family
One night he's at his friend claude's house
Okay
McLeod SIMs card
Claude was struggling with a drug addiction and he didn't want to be alone so he called up Krista
Christopher came over and got out on a drive around the block
Lakme collage
Make about three or four blocks
Around the corner just talk
And while they're doing that I see cops
Everywhere
Play like circling a blocks and speed now than just you know Disney it's like that
Looking for people
He says that because he and Claude are both black driving around late at night
Seeing all of these police officers around
It made him nervous
I told god I think I'm in apartment coin your driveway
Who won the house in town for a minute
When they leave
Imma go home so they go back to claude's house get inside and sit on the couch and watching TV
Next thing you know
The phone ring
Is Dallas Police
Department
The cops say to him
We're outside your house
Same old tattoo guys
Did they start getting out of the car
They come outside
I was like me what
Why they want us
They hesitated after
But Christopher says that
They've actually got up to open the door for
Before we even had a chance to go out
The police officers
Got to look up I got about 7 and 8 9 MMS guns pointed at me
4th amendment
Search and seizure 4th is designed to protect your privacy
The right of the people to be sick
Secure in their persons houses papers and effects when you first come into contact
Against unreasonable searches and seizures shall not be violated m4a props with me
All about 20-25 minutes just laying there
No warrants shall issue but upon probable cause
Supported by oath and affirmation
Particularly describing the place to be searched and the persons or things to be seized
Search the car
And they couldn't find anything
What are they doing
At this point he said he had no idea what was going on
And then they scored me to a police car
And meet me put me in handcuffs once I got in the police car
They say we take you downtown to the Cape is building crimes against person
At the police station
Christopher is taken in for questioning
They take me to the interrogation room and I'm still not being told when I'm being charged
Weed what I'm being questioned about a nothing
Grand jury
Double Jeopardy self-incrimination due process taking
V is designed to protect you when the cop has you in custody and is asking you a question
V is the one that gives you
Did they like read you your rights and whatever that you have the right to remain silent and all that
I didn't get my Miranda rights read to me until I left
Interrogation
At some point that evening when they're at the station
Decapitated me see a lady is going to come identify
Christopher is
Take into this room and handcuffed to a bench next to this big window
In a while
The lady straight up to the window
And pointed at me and me and the lady Casita
In an police officer say this is the guy that killed your husband
Mia I could
.
But I read her lips
She said yeah
Bitched him
And I'm like now I know
She didn't just say what I thought you say
And I go back in there
I'm not looking
Whatever y'all saying I did I didn't do
And they say we are you know what Miss Scott
Retired me a sandwich
You're going to be charged with capital murder
Acetabulum murder
I say survey I ain't killed nobody
So I go in the restroom
I can't cry because I'm so scared tears won't even come out my eyes I'd literally
Pace myself is probably hard as I ever could
And it heard it
So right then I said is real
6th
The sixth seventh amendment in the seventh are designed to protect you
When they decided to charge you it all criminal prosecution
The accused shall enjoy the right
Speedy and public trial
Define impartial jury and to have the assistance of counsel for his
Defense sixth amendment is for criminal cases
7th is for civil
But they both say that you get the right to a jury and a lawyer
I don't even know what capital murder meant what does that mean where your lawyer tell you
Christopher is appointed a lawyer
And that same day in his cell
I can tell by his body language that he feel like
I was actually guilty
He say but periodically I'm going to come and talk to you about the Reno the process in
Disney another
None of that never happened
Nunda never had
Christopher says he talked to the guy for maybe five
I didn't see him anymore
Until my travel
Enter from
Starting from that first conversation that you have with him
To all the way to the trial
How long were you in jail
Maybe
A couple of months
First day of the trial during jury
I'm sitting in there I'm dressed in my suit
You know I'm trying to look respectable and in trying to keep a you know a good face for my girlfriend cuz she's
Is there
Trying to show that I'm still strong even though I'm weak at this time
The 6th Amendment
Guarantees you a trial by a jury of your peers
And what that means legally is
Always a
But
The spirit of it
The spirit of that word
Pierce
Basically means that
The jury should represent
The group the people that
Live around you
Some point Christopher looks over to the jury box and he realizes that
Every black member
Of the jury pool has been
I had a
All white G repair
And I saw this
I see it now
How did this happen
And I looked at my attorney
I see how
Did this happen
In the most technical sense
The 6th Amendment
He's present
But somehow
It still doesn't protect him in the back
4 hours
Call about 4 hours Captain America
He's bored
My deliberation nasty football
A 30-minute
That's it
So they come back in a judge as a juror parent panel
Have you came up with your decision
In a jury Foreman say yes
Your honor and indecision is guilty
Christmas card you are guilty of capital murder
Just like that
Years later
Christopher Scott
Would be
Cleared of all of these
Discharges
Unequivocally
So in that moment
These amendments
The fourth fifth
6 they let him down
But there is this
One moment
The trial where
You could argue that that
1 Amendment
Ever so faintly
Rings
8th Amendment
The eighth says once they convicted you and I want to punish
How can I do it
Can they be cruel and unusual
And the Eighth Amendment bars cruel and unusual
The only thing that I appreciated the most
That my judge did for me
She asked me
Why should not seek the death penalty
In my own and words was I could you kill an innocent man
In this moment it almost feels like
The spirit of the eighth amendment is
What changes Krista
She said mister Scott
You just saved your own life today
We're not going to kill you but we're going to give you a capital life sentence
And I almost think
Because
Although he was about to go to prison for a crime that he didn't commit
He says that
This sentence
It feels like Mercy
Because I'm like
Where you not going to kill me that mean I can fight for my freedom again
Christopher Scott spent 12 years in prison
For being exonerated in 2009
After someone else
Confessed to the crime
He sent founded an organization called House of renewed hope
Which tries to help exonerate others you've been wrongfully convicted
In the story of the events of that night there are some places where Christopher Scott's account in the Dallas
Police Department
Differ
What was presented here is largely based on Christopher's
Experiences he tells it
When we reached out to the Dallas PD for comment
They did not offer a spa
Will be back in a minute
It is more perfect
We put together
The album songs
For the season based on the 27 amendments to the US Constitution
Constitution
Sarkari
Just brought you some liner notes
From a memo
4 to 8
And we started off the Epic
Wisdom
4th amendment
Next song
From Briana marela
But that leaves songs five through eight we haven't talked about this yet
We haven't heard from someone
I heard that one
Starting with this woman I'm McKenzie
And I play music
Under the name Torres
Oh and what amendment
Did you choose to write about I wrote about V
5th Amendment
Grand jury double jeopardy
Self-incrimination due process
Peking so the Fifth Amendment as I understand it that's the one that protects
The person from
From no person shall be subject for the same offense
Be twice put in Jeopardy of life or limb and from self-incrimination
But the last part nor shall private property be taken for public use
Love just come
Is this the one that I have chose to focus on for the song
Peking
That last part of the Fifth Amendment is
Often referred to by just that were taking
It's what you always hear being debated
When the government
Decides
Seize private property for public good
Park
War
More controversially for a highway
Mackenzie chose to write about
This part
Connecting it to the story of Dred Scott
Call
That was Torres with the song about the Fifth Amendment
Monday the 6th
Which comes from a band headed by a guy
You may recognize
New movies this is Ezra Miller from Sons of an illustrious father
Picture of the sixth amendment Sixth Amendment
Right to speedy trial by jury
Witnesses
Cancel
Because I think reading through them we recognize both its importance and
How rarely in our times it was observed or adhered to
We use various examples in the song
From current events
To illustrate and demonstrate
That this
Like many of the other amendments
Has lost its meaning and application must come
In Chicago
Square
That's an excerpt from the 6th amendment song from Ezra Miller and Sons of an illustrious
Father Brown
Trio
Onto the 7th
Hello
This is Steve Hilton from Nana grizol
I was excited to write a song about the 7th Amendment 7th Amendment
Jury trial in civil lawsuit
Because even though it's a part of the Bill of Rights very few people know what it does
I can see this time using an analytical frame known as racial capitalism
Atlanta, Georgia
What are rights
Amendment song from Nana grizol
Band based in Athens Georgia
That included a couple members of
Great experimental Rock
Band
From my area
Neutral Milk Hotel
Eminem
For the Eighth Amendment we got a song from the local NYC surf rock band name
Wasted
Who were once apparently named the best party Band by GQ Magazine a here is frontwoman
Jessica Lewis died I set it up to write a song about the 8th Amendment
Because
I thought it's just so obviously already sounded like song lyrics
Excessive bail shall not require words that define disposed
Nor cruel and unusual punishments
High-waisted steak on the 8th
Rings out of the two most debated words
Usual is worth
Contain a lot
Stop the idea of Mercy tucked in there the idea of what is just
Punishment
Something there
We the people are supposed to be protected from punishment
That are cruel and unusual but those words
What is cool
What is a usual
What if a punishment is cruel but not unusual
Are we protected from that
These are the kind of questions people ask
About The Jacka
Which is what
Jessica says the band was
Thinking about when they wrote the song over 17000
People have an X
Cuted
Bolin death row
And 32 states still have the death penalty
Which is why I am just
My mind is boggled with the idea that these inmates
The last bit of freedom
Is the freedom to choose how they're going to die
And I
Can't imagine being the captain of your own soul and being forced to decide
Tire going to travel into the next world
I wanted the song to have
Eerie haunting creepy
Stick with you by like a siren song luring you into the field Melody
And then building to this redoubt the realization that
Did this amendment is so important hitting and involves so many people that have two
Weight and burden of death
I think that's why I was most drawn to the 8th Amendment and why this song
Kind of a little bit different sound for me and for my band high waisted
Usually tend to write in the normal pop and this
Song lured me into writing this sort of
Text Jim
High-waisted with a song about
The 8th Amendment
And we only played excerpts of the songs here in the podcast you can hear the whole thing's all the songs in their entirety
At the most perfect
Pic album. Org
The most perfect album. Org
She go there there is a whole site
Would you work really hard on
Which tells you not only know about these bands
But all about the amendments
What the words
I mean how they've been used throughout history or helping it's going to be really really useful to people
So check out the most perfect album. Org helping spread the word you can find the album itself 20
Seven the most perfect album on iTunes
Spotify anywhere you can download music more perfect is created by me Chatham Rod Susie lechtenberg Julie Longoria
Kelly Prime sarkari and Alex
Overington weed help for Michelle Harris David Gable and Nora Keller
Thanks to Jeffrey Wright amazing Jeffrey Wright for reading the Amendments for us
Thank you guys for listening
Rod signing off on our next episode will be exploring the 9th
10th
Xi an