WNYC Studios
When was Teletubbies first second
Auto Bethalto
Hey I'm genogram ride this is more perfect
A miniseries
We're just getting going up
Some of the ideas in the cases
Flow through
The Supreme Court
We're going to start the series off with a
With a story that isn't so much a courtroom drama this one is about an issue that
I think everybody agrees is about to land at
The Supreme Court
Again in a bit
Story comes from reporter Karen Duffin
And it begins with the Mist
Alright so we're starting with
My rights Maya Maya
I am the dark
How to tame a tree
Okay so my afoa lives in London and when she was about 25 she had
Graduated from college she was doing some theater things but she was
Like having this quarter life crisis and didn't know what to do with her life was called blue but I Central crisis
Organizations in Santa Ana please can I be useful to you
Plantation that did death penalty cases like a bunch of lawyers or what are they doing
They've been working on the death penalty for like years at that point to try to abolish it
I view the death penalty and I
Beautiful
What time is it at the shop end
A series of
Societal injustices
So anyway she's at reprieve one night this is 2010 I was sat in the office and
She's sitting there one night and Clive Stafford Smith who's the president of reprieve or the head of reprieve
Calls and says
Execution tonight
The execution in Arizona tonight
For killing Chester dryer
Lander
And stabbing the man
In 1989
There's an execution tonight and we just found out that the lethal injection drugs that they're going to use
It came from a
Pharmacy in England
But we don't know which pharmacy because Arizona refuses to release
Is the name does anyone in the office have some time alone to have some time to figure out whether stocks could have come
She raises her hand and she's like I have 30 minutes you know
I didn't know
What I was talking when I stopped
I want to find this
Supplier like why does it help them
What the drugs did they want to use an Arizona hat
To be updated
So they can find who made these drugs and prove that they are not FDA-approved and they can
Probably stop the X
Do they have any reason to think the drugs were it FDA approved
Is kind of a Hail Mary
Also
I started the half-hour research tasks that is taking me now five and a half years
I was trying to figure out with
Limited information where sodium thiopental could have come from in the UK to get
U.s. sodium thiopental is an anesthetic and for a long time it was one of the most common anesthetics used
In surgeries but it's also one of the drugs used in lethal injection
I was so
I didn't think I knew
The puppets full reset that I didn't but I was doing it very quickly
Because of course they have
Houston at night
Is running out of time
And option
I was in the UK so it's the evening morning Arizona time.
Number of algal species
Frantically searching
Medical regulations
And you know she can't figure out exactly what the name of the company is there's no way to know at that point
But ultimately she does figure out that there are no
UK companies
Authorized to ship this drug to the US
That was no
Effectively no FDA approved supplier of the star
Suit whatever this mystery Pharmacy was it probably wasn't FDA-approved
And I remember
And I emailed that over I think we had the time to intern affidavit from meal from fly
They write up a quick affidavit they send it back to the states and
The execution that night was
Stayed
Like halted
When I went to sleep and having stayed and I just thought I'd
You got a bit of time
Next morning
Workout
Did someone say
And I turned on World Service Center
Burnouts that Jeffrey landrigan
Was executed at 22
26 hours
Yeah
His final meal
Was
A piece of steak
His last words were
Well
I'd like to say thank you to my family
And Boomer Sooner
It turned out well Maya was asleep
The state of
All the way to
Supreme Court
The justices by 524 votes lifted
The stay of execution
Allowing landrigan
I could be put to death last night
Was put in place due to concerns over lethal injection drugs one of those drugs obtained from Britain
Was not FDA-approved but the US Supreme Court did rule
That there was no reason
Not talk about a rude awakening
Electro sac
Is that rude awakening with
Send my on a journey around the world it would get her called out by the United States Supreme Court it would Spark
A global conversation about the American death
Modell's little words cruel and unusual
Are embedded in our Eighth Amendment
United States
Supreme Court of the United States
Dairy bacteria
So we were in London with Maya who just learned that Jeffrey landrigan had been executed but to understand which she
Does next let me just give you a little bit of
In the fall of 2010 when Jeffrey landrigan was executed
The drugs that they use
The lethal drug sodium thiopental is suddenly in really short supply
Is the only us company that still made that drug with housing
Leica manufacturing problem so they have stopped manufacturing
Producing the strad so you actually see these emails between states like do do you have any sodium thiopental
California got help
From right next door
Arizona agreed to lend California a cup of death
And there's actually someone great email exchange between like the California Department of Corrections they send eras
Thank you email and I quote
You guys in Arizona are Lifesavers
Will buy you a beer next time I see you
You're a Life Saver Come on
So
When Jeffrey landrigan is said to be
Executed Arizona is out of that
And this is how they end up at
This mystery Drug Company in London
So after the execution my is doing all this research she's calling Pharma company on to these documents and
Very quickly she learns that the same company that is sending drugs to Arizona at 10 drugs till I can buy lots of different states
South Carolina Kentucky and dryers at the places
They actually become one of the primary suppliers that we've won Jackson Drugs to the United States
Why was it so hard to find out information about this company
So what happens is that anybody involved with an execution your name is kept confidential
And states have started keeping
Companies names confidential to
IC
So the next few starts calling suppliers and Distributors kind of trying to trace
Like how did this drug get to that company thinking that maybe that'll lead her to it
We had figured out
It had
Come originally
From
I was active ingredients made in
Some of those with
Sent over to Germany
The package put into files those were sent over to the UK that was one company that had got the Moxie with vibration
Sold their soul to another one that company chasing men
They were sent to
Best company in England
What she still can't figure out the identity of
But then the real breakthrough came just
Couple months after Jeffrey landrigan was
I think it was a lot of material coming out of that time I'm going to California and the ACLU got a bunch of documents and in one
One of these batches of documents
She finds an invoice
And this invoice
I just
I just remember getting the court documents and I was
I was walking with the Spotify slow internet connect
She was actually in Malawi at the time just
Constantly
Are willing the computers down at the document so I could stop even looking
In treatment figuring out
And those were the documents that
Hot
Name
Off
The middleman
What was it
Dream farmer
Dreamfarm A-frame fireman
Okay
So she's in Malawi Sochi
Yeah Rings up her
Calling and says can you go just look at this place in West London
And it's this
Residential area but also like
What sort of warehouses kind of middle-class you have
A couple of petrol stations a couple of cafes
Xiamen
This Pharmacy
Except that it doesn't look like a pharmacy
Because it's got a big sign on the front that says
Algon Driving Academy
I am not
On the door
El Cajon
Driving Academy
This is Nina. She's a freelance producer in London
It doesn't matter
Tiny little storefront
Don't see any evidences
And if you walk in
Hello
You walk in and the furniture
Is this reception area
But in the back
Hi
I'm underneath
Dream Pharma
Is that you high
I'm clothing
There's a guy sitting at a desk
His name is mehdi alavi he's in his 50s
Gray feathered hair going to play
Like square glasses with little bit like William Hurt he is dream Pharma
In other words
The company that is helping prop up the death penalty
System in America
It's a one-man operation operating out of the back of a driving school
One guy
Can I thought
Speaking to you about the
Injections
That you supply
How to get gorgeous
Oh, that I
I still have no
Oh
Aspen
What was it like for you
Are you still
Supplying
All right did you get where you are
It wasn't illegal at that point
Alright let it be
Fatigue
You would you like me to
Can't get involved in that
Fontaine
They found me
I found you
What how
We surprised when they
Fry's
I guess it unravels
Very much
Felicia
Enjoyed walking around
So what do you want
So now
Irrelevant
Amscot interest
You're not in the business of
Irrelevant
Well thank you very much
Glacier
You know my name
If not find
Coalition
The once Maya and reprieve found that guy mehdi alavi and his pharmaceutical broom closet of death The Next Step
Was pretty simple went to the UK government and they told them because in the UK it's
Illegal to be part of capital punishment in any way
We have a little bit that Sports
A product
For the facilitation of capital punishment
Patience with this text
Unique in the world continuous compound look a message to The Fight Against torture and the death penalty
When they realized
That the sole purpose of the exports of this drug
Waze
Prosecution
Stay put an Xbox controller
And just like that the supply of this drug is turned off
To the states or just out of luck
Well I mean 60% of Americans support the death penalty so that they're not going to give this up
Without a fight
And so
Over the next few years you have like this arms race Missouri says we're going to find the drug in Germany so
My address to Germany
And then she hears that a company called hospira is about to make the drug
In
Italy
Italian government
Really didn't want drugs made in the seat of the Pope to be
Execution
Paris pics passing said we cannot take the risk that we will be held liable by the Italian authorities if it's
Contact is diverted for use in capital punishment
And then
Denmark
Bunch of stage of Florida Ohio Alabama 11 other states they all decide they're going to get their drug from this company called
My account
I remember my first Cool Whip
She's like I'm did you know that your drugs being used in executions and they were like what
It certainly came shoot surprise for US vice president for communications at
We have
In the farm industry for a little more than hundred years
And we are here to
Safe
People's lives
This was the complete opposite
It Off
The intention of
Offer this product
Amaya says that she heard the same thing
All over the world
Even when States like Nebraska and South Dakota go to
India today
Get their drugs
And it's interesting in India because
India have capital punishment
So this isn't an objection
Capital punishment
This is
From every company has spoken to in India
They say but
Why
Why would they use medicine
Like if you're going to kill someone just kill them
Why are you using something that saves lives to do it
And actually there's a really interesting story about why we do it that way
That's coming up
I'm more perfect
Amgen aboumrad this is more perfect
A miniseries about some of the ideas and cases that
Flowing through the Supreme Court
Back to restore from reporter Karen.
So we left off with Maya in India and their wondering Baidu
Do you guys use drugs to kill people
Why would they use medicine
So what is the answer to life
Why do we dancers that goes back to this guy named Bill Wiseman
It's a terrible thing
To have one's
Reputation B&B based on on
Coming up with a new
Way to kill people
Bill Wiseman was a rising star
He loved
Wiseman died in a plane crash in 2007 this is him in an interview with reporter named Scott Thompson
Nkotb in Tulsa back in 2005
What is what
Spell story
So he grew up his dad's a minister is Grandpa's a minister and he's like I don't want the family business and he want
For years he he buy his account wanders through like 2 and 1/2 literature degrees he becomes a poet
He drinks a lot of corn liquor and you know he finally ends up in construction where he starts working with politicians and he's like oh
This is my calling I want to be a politician so he gets elected to the Oklahoma State Legislature in 19
74 +
Opposed to the death penalty and luckily for him this would just happen
Supreme Court declared the death penalty unconstitutional today
Miles across the country in 1972 the Supreme Court actually abolished the death penalty
Cuz they said it was being applied unfairly or
Haphazard
In a way that could only be called
Cricket
So Bill Wiseman is in the Oklahoma Legislature and he's like
Great this is not a problem we'll ever have to worry about
Thomas the public is furious about this decision
Support goes from 50 to 63% in just two years
Absolutely I
Very much in favor and favor of it we get some Law & Order into this country.
I don't think you should have taken away in the first place in almost immediately 35 States
Rewrite their death penalty laws essentially saying like no no we can do this right
And in 1976
Supreme Court says
All right
If you can administer the death penalty fairly and humanely
You can have it back
So 9072a death penalty abolished 1976 it's reinstated
Bill Wiseman get selected smack-dab in the middle of this
You know 1976
Suddenly
There's a bill in Oklahoma State Legislature about whether to reinstate the death penalty and bilhah
The vote on that
I know
The capital punishment
Interested it doesn't work doesn't
And I couldn't see any way to justify
I also knew
Then if I'd voted against it from my district
I would
Run a high chance
Getting whooped
Cuz 80% of his constituents were in favor of the death penalty
After all that wondering
Honey, this job that you love
Having the best time and I didn't want to get whooped so I was
In a real dilemma
What you do
The wrong thing
Devoted to reinstate the death penalty
For whatever reason
Of ego or vanity or need or the motivation to get reelected whatever the reasons
I knowingly made it
A decision
When I know is wrong
Susan the legislature and he's feeling like he just sold his soul
And as they're debating various amendments to this law someone brings up something sort of vaguely about a more humane
Mean way to execute people and he's like that yes.
And he becomes obsessed with this idea I was like a way to assuage his guilt
Yeah so he brings up some anesthesiologist and doctors and says I want to find a better way to do this and they say we can't help you cuz
The credit goes to no harm.
Did a little bit of arms 3 goes to the State medical examiner a guy named Jay Chapman
And Jay just sort of like freestyles has one line that that bill
Literally just sits with a yellow legal pad and rights word for word
I'm an intravenous saline drip should be established
High-end which be introduced
Hey
Ultra short acting barbiturate
In combination
Michael paralytic
The idea is that these three drugs would allow them to execute people but but painlessly
And right there in that office with just like
Yellow legal pad
They invent lethal injection in America
It would be
Hard to overstate just how important this
Moment in this offices because
The supreme court of justice
Given the country back the death penalty on the
Ground and the idea that we could we could do this right
And what bill has just handed America
Is is it a way to have the death penalty but but had to be humane
The ideal death battle
Yeah
Oklahoma adopted and then the very next date
Texas does and then dozens of states and
Since that moment
88% of all executions
Injection
I don't hear the word lethal injection or execution or anything else without
Feeling a tug
It's it's tied to me
I mean I'll always be
Which he live to regret he thinks that he actually extended the life of the death penalty and he actually eventually quit
This job becomes a pastor and becomes a very
A strong anti-death penalty
Advocate
How does a man
Who came up with the recipe
For lethal injection
What does he do on judging
The same thing everyone else does
So ourselves on the mercy of God
Say that way
Have done wrong
Nothing that I find really interesting is that if you look at the Modern lethal injection cocktail
Three drugs
FasTrak special needs Society II drug paralyzes you
And the Third Reich is the answer that stops
Tartan Kilt
In this drug cocktail you kind of see everything that we want and need from the death penalty just kind of all mix
Together
The third drug the drug that stops your heart that's kind of our sense of justice
The first drug the anesthetic
Kind of our sense of humanity or kindness
That second drug
The one that paralyzes their muscle
Fold the second draw
Is purely cosmetic
It sucks
No medical purpose
The reason it was put into the lethal injection cocktail in the first place was
So that
FasTrak doesn't work effectively
The second drug will mask any signs of
Visible suffering and it would be extremely significant
Because potassium chloride
Potent acid that people have described as
Being like fire going through your veins and being burnt alive from the inside
She said just imagine that that's happening to you
But something goes wrong with the anesthetic and you become conscious
You have this
Burning acid going through your body
And you're paralyzed all your voluntary muscles
Paralyzed
So you can't say
I'm awake I can feel everything this is agony
She says that it's that second drug that is both the thing that could make the execution most torturous
And the thing that meant that
Tweed Witnesses the views
Public
Wouldn't know that it was torture
Because we weren't supposed to know that
2 does she end up going after that second drug
The paralytic no actually seek she goes after the first ride the anesthetic and it's a total coincidence this is just
The one that had manufacturing problems that started the arms race
But it turns out that
This drug
Sodium fire
The anesthetic is the one that's
The most constitutionally important drug
Because in 2008 when the Supreme Court ruled on lethal injection they said
The first drug is necessary to prevent the prisoner
From experiencing severe pain
So there's no anesthetic
There's pain
Which would be too severe and then be there for what an Eighth Amendment violation
Cruel unusual punishment
So that drug the anesthetic is the key drug
But over the past five and a half years is Maya has like Wacom old her way across these different companies
She just made it harder and harder to get
There now 20 + companies
Who have they said we disapprove of the misuse of medicine executions than we going to take steps to prevent
And that has States scrambling the drugs used in a 32 death penalty States
Or now running out run out of drugs and is it resolved but you seems that things have gotten very DIY
Weather changing and trying new procedures never used before in the history of execution
Prison officials are in a difficult position
Human have the da start rating prison
Their Central using illegal drugs at this point until reporters are just starting to pay more attention and
In the middle of all that he began kicking his feet lifting his head in his chest off the gurney grimacing
How do you also get
Seems like this
High Country season in and a couple moments he actually mumbled
You would open his mouth and you'd see his chest move and we'll go all the way down to stomach so so clear gas
April 29th 2014 in Oklahoma a man in Clayton Lockett was being executed for murder rape and
Kidnapping Lockett execution used and new drug combination whose source is unknown he was sedated and declared unconstitutional
Conscious but
Started thrashing
Clenching his teeth and start moving the arm
43 minutes to die
Grizzly horrific spectacle
Happening after an hour and 57 minutes
Your situations like this in Arizona Ohio this drug formula is unconstitutional because
Started filing a bunch of lawsuits and one of these eventually got to
Supreme Court
1470 955
An interesting lie when it got to the Supreme Court
Things got very thin
This is Justice Alito
Is saying essentially
Actually a problem you made it a problem
Executions to be carried out
Ashley there many jurisdictions
Their jurisdictions in this country their jurisdiction
Two different drugs
By the abolitionists
And this is Justice Scalia
States cannot obtain
And now you want to come before the court and say well visits third drug
It's not 100% sure
Is it appropriate for the Judiciary
To countenance what amounts
To a guerrilla War
Against
What you think it means by Guerilla War
I think he's
Trying to say there are ways to 2 if you want to make the death penalty illegal you have ways to do it
You can call your legislator you can pressure them big
That's a lot but you're trying to like hide in the trees and like pulled
Drugs off
And
Make themselves scarce
That you're forcing
Illegal problem that doesn't exist
It's about you answer to the question
You've been interrupted
Does justice has called you guys out kind of
It's
Look into this a lot of narrative around this being
Activate
But this is nothing to do
With me or anyone else
It's that the companies
Don't want that medicines uses
Options that manufactures the Distributors the pharmacist anesthesiologist
Whoever else it might be the Indian industry
None of them has to be positive
Ohio capital punishment machine
Is there an argument to be made here I mean I get what you're saying that like all these different people in different countries have been like unknowingly
Grafted onto Ohio sex
Execution team which doesn't seem fair but isn't there an argument to be made that like
Even so
The effect is that she has taken a death penalty that is
Kind of Humane Maybe
And made it more cruel
Because that's kind of the accusation in the air
It's
I'm going to say two things one of them
She didn't cause it she's
The states are chasing the companies and she's chasing the states rights so like you can't say that she caused it but what you more important
But you also can't say is that it is actually more cruel
Because
There's no evidence
That there's been an in
Increase in Boston
Executions
What I think is happening is just that we're paying
More attention to lethal injection
Tonight we're just
Looking at it more
Bosch excuse has been happening forever and we're just now noticed
Yeah
None the less people do accuse her of making this more cruel and nausea
The drugs
Because
States in their sort of desperation to still be able to do this are looking for other ways
To do it
And some of those ways
Might seem like we're going
The lady that was
Spearheaded the getting rid of the injections all she did is basically force people to be shot
This Paul Wray state representative house district 13 Utah
He says one day he was sitting in his office
That was actually listening to the local NPR station in federal judge in Oklahoma
And they're talking about
European pharmaceutical companies
Used to provide this country
Bristol drug but now refuse to sell it to
European drug companies no longer selling the drug cocktail
So I called our department of corrections and says hey do we have access to the drug and they said no we don't
How you know we have a set amount and then we're out
Because he hung up the phone.
Thinking a little bit of research
Kind of deep into the history and
Eventually came to the conclusion well let's revert back the firing squad
Play me like firing squad John Wayne firing squad like line up against the wall
No it's like they have a chair and they bring the person into the room and they strap
Them to the chair they put a hood over their head position will look at the heart and I'll pin a Target where the heart is and then there's five men with r
Rifles and one of them has a blank but none of them know which one it is
And then on the 20 orders given they all shoot the individual
In the heart
Lawmakers in Utah voted to bring back executions by firing squad
What is Lethal Injections are not readily available already says he was just trying to solve a problem
Completely taken off guard by the media frenzy that
Have the cruel relic of Old West Justice Henry lenet International condemnation
Stopping it now is an embarrassment that barbaric
We should be shooting our people this is ridiculous this is not the time
Bob Moses
Why is it sad
Do you think the firing squad itself
Created this
Well it it's it's brutal
You know it's it's certainly not the easy give him a couple of injections in
They quietly
Go down
You know this is calling it for what it is
In fact
I would argue you want to look at
At something that's more Humane and you definitely the fiery sky
What caught my attention was it was so sudden so quick
Boom boom just like that
These are reporters talking about witnessing at firing squad X
Houston and Utah
It was over
Pretty quickly it was cleaner than I expected
And it was fast
With the firing squad
Yeah your ear dead Within
Your seconds of the pulling the trigger
Bible is directly to the heart
It's over
Not the paralytic that hides its is done
Buddy buddy moved
He moved a little bit
To some degree that bothers me
And that seemed to carry on
Alaska
222nd
This is how you tie his chosen to solve the Wacom old problem has already been upheld by the Supreme Court
Approved
Electrocution
We have approved death by firing squad
That's Justice Scalia in 2008 the Supreme Court actually approve the firing squad in 1879
And the people who are part of the firing squad are actually volunteers
Do you have a lack of volunteers or in abundance of volunteers
They had hundreds
I'm nobody's forced to do it is
Another there are people that are willing that big Tennessee is their civic duty
You know the help carry these out
I'm always down there I actually asked Paul
I really wanted
If you put me in touch with somebody who's actually been involved with the firing squad
I'll call somebody
Okay
Better wait till this thing
16th and Hill Air Force Base
All right I like it the sound of
This is Kenny we agreed not to use his last name and Ken's Dad ran the firing squad for a couple of decades
So as you see there's two cottonwood trees over here those old cottonwood trees
They'd set up an
And that's what they would drill the firing squad
These men were selected because for one there
Absolute monarchs
Tuesday just had moral clarity
They
Many of them did not want to be on there but once they were called
They felt obligated
To see it through
And told me that on execution days his dad and the other Shooters they would sit down together at the
Kitchen table and you know it's just like a little family family breakfast
This mom should make coffee and
She would do scones or biscuits and gravy and she wanted those men to know
That it wasn't easy and that she appreciated
I know there was a lot of prayerful times around the house and nose
Mentor over getting ready and I know that
I am
It is pretty solemn moment I prayer
Is it for the person being executed the victim with
The prayer
I think you have to pray for strength to follow through on what you have
I think that
You know you might need a little guidance and you might need a little understanding and
And something bigger than yous out there
I think that
If we're going to have the death penalty people just have to understand that there's some savagery involved in it
And nah
It's unfortunate that it is but
If we have it to do list
Let's do it let's do it humanely
One of the things that I found kind of striking is that
My afoa is against the death penalty and you have to focus in Utah that are for it
But everyone seems to agree that
We shouldn't fool ourselves
I favor the death penalty
But one thing I've never favored in some common ground between me and the abolitionists
Is that lethal injection
Is a terrible method of
Execution
That's Robert blecker at a New York law school professors
Sounding a little bit like Maya
But he says he objects to lethal injection not because it's
Cruel not because it might cause
Pain
But because it certainly causes confusion
I attended
An execution in Florida
Bennie Demps
And I also was with my father-in-law when he was in a hospice dying for
From an incurable and very painful cancer
And the death scene
In both
Situations
This was bizarrely similar
In both cases the
The person dying was
Lying on a gurney with an IV coming out of his arm
Wrapped in white sheets
Medical technicians at his side surrounded by loved ones
And it struck me as bizarre
That we are killing Those whom we love
In a fashion
That's so nearly resembles
How we are killing those we rightfully
Detest
There should be no resemblance this isn't medicine this is
Punishment
The firing squad
Is honest and acknowledges itself for what it is I have one objection to the traditional firing squad
Glad that you tie uses
He says he doesn't like the fact that one person get the blank and that nobody knows who that person is
That to me is symptomatic
Of our failure once again to take responsibility for what we do
Nobody should have a black
If we cannot face what we're doing
And acknowledge it
Then we shouldn't do it
And we may be coming to a moment where we are about to do that to look at this and acknowledge it
Because
In 2014 in a case that was really just about lethal injection just as viruses look like
Stop
Just talking about the details like questions about which medicine that we use
For the court to consider a basic question
Weather
Institution
In other words what he's saying is
It's time to talk about not just like the mechanics of what we're doing
But whether we should even do it at all
Reporter Karen Duffin
Now when Breyer said that in 2014 he was into the scent lost the case but
A lot of people saw that statement as this invitation like Breyers saying to the lawyers of America send us case
In fact some of those cases have just started to arrive 2 days ago a case
Made it in front of the court almost made the US Supreme Court on Tuesday refused to hear in a few
Asserting that the death penalty violate the US Constitution's ban on cruel and unusual punishment
Ruth Bader Ginsburg
They're on the way you're something else it happened while we were reporting this
Destroy this one for about 2 weeks ago
The pharmaceutical giant Pfizer has announced
But it will no longer allow its drugs to be used in Lethal Injections
Market source of drugs used in execution
This basically
Cake white sage
Spells the end of lethal injection in the United States but it's closed
Because now any states that want to keep doing it
They essentially have to go underground
To get those drugs
More perfect
Star first Radiolab spin-off sideband whatever you want to call it please play me Chad Ivan rod with Susie lechtenberg
Kelsey Padgett
And Tobin low
You told me you want to do the rest sharp with Soren wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington
Karen Duffin Sean rameswaram Katherine Wells Barry Finkel Andy Mills and Daniel moattar
Special thanks to Ben Cohen Mona Lynch Austin search Chris Zimmerman Julie toll and the death penalty
The information center
Supreme Court audio is turmoil a free law project in collaboration with the legal
Information Institute at Cornell
What perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation The Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
Can and the Joyce Foundation
Coming up next week on more perfect
The most important Supreme Court case
20th century
Probably never heard of it
Charles W Baker an hour
Case was so dramatic
So traumatic there was an instance in which my
Brother found my father going upstairs to get a shot
But it actually ended up breaking to just
That is next week
Subscribe wherever you get your podcasts
I'm Jad abumrad thanks for listening