WNYC Studios
Hey I'm Jared I'm around this is more perfect
Final episode of season 2 long-overdue
Today I'm going to fulfill a promise that I made to myself
At the very beginning
Of more perfect
Several years ago
I started to show it was out of a very
Basic
Desire to understand some things that I knew nothing about people talk about something I knew nothing about
In one of the very first questions it I bumped into
As a supreme court idiot
Was it why does everybody keep talking about this thing called Commerce Clause
What was the Commerce Clause what the hell is it
Section 8 Clause 3 of The Constitution 16 words
Two commas Congress shall have the power to regulate
Commerce with foreign Nations
And among the several States and with the Indian tribes power to regulate commerce
The four nations and among the several States and with the Indian tribes there are no more sexier words in the English language
Better words for when we're never written
That's Jamie Floyd Norris viski will meet them properly and second okay so
Pictures of the definition isn't that hard it's written right there in the Constitution those 16 words
Have something to do with Commerce going across state lines fine but
When you start to stare at those were
Really track how they've been read across time
You realize that within that she'll of boring
Is a cosmic power
Like for me
The experience I had learning by the Commerce Clause was a little bit like watching the X-Men movies
Initially it was like my name is Magneto why is Magneto the head of the bad guys
Was why are they follow him he has the most boring power can control metal
You can shift into any shape she wants storm can control lightning
Initially has power seem like you have the worst one
But then
You see these seats were he's like being attacked by a thousand policemen and he just kind of
Mixed are bullets freeze in midair for a pics of a whole Bridge with lights
Pointing at it and then hit you up
He has the best power
Because the whole world is made of metal she can control the world
If we build the world a different way baby not but
This world is just say I'm Frankenstein's monster
Today
I tell you the story of that monster
Story
That contains everything we fight about is Americans
States rights civil rights equal rights race big government small government all of it
Wrapped up in those 16 words
Two commas
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
All right
Do you even explain why
Something like the Commerce Clause exists
Split a dollar bill issued by
A central bank
Are you looking at dollar bill right now
Federal Reserve Note United States of America
That is James Chen professor of law at Michigan State University now the
Sing about a dollar bill the awesome obvious thing is that you can
Take that dollar bill and buy
Some Sour Patch Kids or whatever dollar buys these days
Anywhere in America
But in the late 18th century backed all the way through to the 20th century
Wasn't like that no no no no no all the states have their own Banks
And their own bills different sizes colors example there's a moment when South Carolina has is pretty little green South
South Carolina Bill same time Rhode Island
SF Giants
Pink
Square thing and if you are a South Carolinian in Rhode Island trying to buy some
Carrots and potatoes let's say you hand them your South Carolina bill
Well the Rhode Islanders would look at that and say why don't know what this is
Who's the trust this bank right and so they would discount
No
Based on the distance from their own home they would discount the note based on
How it looks how professionally drawn up it was
They might look at that $10 and say
That's only worth 8 to me
Felidae
Horrible way to do business
Socks for the person holding the note right
So what the government decided to do is to say 8 words can use one bill
Swindell
To be so much easier
This is one of the ways God was going to pull all these
Different states
Together they're going to regulate the currency
And not just the currency itself they were going to regulate
The flow
Of that kind
And this is where the Commerce Clause comes in
This is Jamie Floyd
Journalist
Host of all things considered here I come
It's early in the Republican Howard 1820s
Now just to hit pause for 1 second to the Commerce Clause with
The pre-existing thing in the US Constitution
Thought about her or where where is it in the minds of people a day to nowhere
No we're not other people
She says 1824 to Steamboat operators get into a thing it's a business going back and forth
Newark New Jersey the East think they should be the only one allowed to do that and it makes its way as we say
All the way to the US Supreme Court
And who's sitting up there with a big bad dude named John Marshall
Marshall is the sort of Rambo
Of the course
He look at those 16 word Congress shall have the power to regulate
Commerce with foreign Nations and among the several states he looks at those 16 words and a couple of, xandy.
Pretty much for the first time
Did those words give Congress the power
To regulate
Commerce
Between and among states
This boat is going from one state to the other
The only way to resolve that
Is for the federal government to come in
And controller
Again the idea is it this is the only way for the country
To function as a unified thing
John Marshall's decision he says
You look we have United States of America
We don't have a divided States of America or independent States of America or New Jersey in
New York existing
Separately we decided to organize
As a United States
And so what
John Marshall says it's because of that
There has to be a power to regulate trade between those days in amongst those days when there are dispute
Otherwise it's all going to fall apart
He was at that point that the Commerce Clause
Gant glow
Womb very faintly
For the next hundred years the government experiment with the Commerce Clause in cases involving
Trade with Native American tribes or navigation but if you want to talk about power
The real power
Of the Commerce Clause got Unleashed
In a wheat field
My father was a farmer I'd like to say all of his life
Pride in the fact that he never he never work for another man he would tell me that yourself
Well my name is the same as my father at
Roscoe Curtis filbrun
I'm a junior Roscoe film
Bird the time he was a fifth generation farmer in Montgomery Ohio
Our farm was just right next to Dayton Ohio Roscoe
Is about 40 year old man
At this point we're talking about 1941-42 good looking
Sturdy
Fiercely independent I never worked for another man in my life
Apparently that was his motto he would tell me that many times over the years if you had to put like Captain
In America with a pitchfork
This is
So Roscoe's got this far more than a hundred cows on it he would male cows until both of these are
Farms went practically no catch chickens 2000s
And a we had a very big Garden he would plant things you know light string beans lima beans
Sweet corn potato carrots radishes different kinds of apples
Trees are strawberries and raspberries
And of course
Sweet sweet
Okay set up out of the way here's what happened
It's 1941
Roscoe
Senior my dad was out in the field I think on his tractor
That day he was plowing the weed or something and
Apparently must have been some guy
From the
Department of Agriculture Local 8
I guess going around to various farmers in our community
Wanting the farmers to answer several pages I think of questions
And this particular date this government gentleman came out into the field
He looked around
And he said Roscoe
Oceans you got 22 Acres of wheat
Lesoir
You're over
Your quota
He was 11.1 Acres over what was permitted
And so the guy tells him he have to pay a fine
A really big fine
My dad looked over and he was just as sober as a judge in a courtroom on a murder case
And what happened next would change the country forever
In ways that we are still literally living with
But Mitch's Surf fill in the gaps here
Tell you what you need to know about why they're they were even having this conversation
And to help me with that my name is Ari savitski and I'm an attorney friend of the show man of law
An important thing to understand is that you know when our story starts with Roscoe filburn agriculture
Pictures of huge Returns the economy the Great Depression is happening abundant
And the Dust Bowl 1930s
And so you have a lot of people who rely on selling crops and buying crops and so wheat prices to matter of life
Millions of Americans asking for action
Ionic from now till 1938 Congress enact
What's called the agricultural adjustment act to reboot the economy so the 1938
Cultural adjustment act got the federal government into the business
Regulating
Busy with the government did was they said to the farmers America we are going to give you essentially alone we're going to
Guarantee you a certain minimum price
We're going to give you X number of dollars per bushel or whatever it is
That will help lift you out of poverty
In exchange for that
You have to
Promises
To only grow a certain amount
It's in the big fear was that they grew too much
There be the
Flood of Supply on the wheat market prices would crash
And that would be bad for everyone you know we is sort of a collective action problem right everyone's going to sell as much weed as they can
But that means prices go down and everyone makes less
So with the government
Decide to do in addition to giving out loans is that they placed a cap on how much wheat a person could grow
So quote a straight-up quota
That way you ensure the supply of wheat is steady and you ensured that that the prices don't cry
And whole reason the government could do this regulate the entire wheat Market
What's by hendricken on the Commerce Clause has 16 words
Basically said
That when something like wheat is bought and sold and moved from one place to another one state to another cross state lines
Well that's Interstate Commerce and that's something that Congress can regulate
So my father having the back to Roscoe filburn without inspector
On his farm
Spectra says
Look Roscoe you've grown too much weed my dad looked over and he was just as sober as a judge in a courtroom
Romano murder case
And what do you think he says back he says wait a minute I'm going to show you exactly how I feel about that
No
That's how I feel know you government might have been a family guy she says I don't get it
I'm not I'm not have nothing to do with interstate commerce
And
This is the key
Explain to the inspector that yes
According to the government quota I'm only supposed to grow about 11 acres a week and I am growing 23
But then extra 12
I'm not selling it to anybody
He doesn't sell the Wii
He doesn't trade the way
What's he doing with this week he uses all the wheat to feed his animals
Feeding it to the farm animals the weight
He said the sum of the week to the stairs I
I was just keeping it on the farm well yeah so it's in a completely internal Operation Ivy
I mean I feel like the poor guy gets kind of dragged into a national case
Who was interstate commerce to feed my cows I'm on my phone I'm doing my business
Big Brother leave me alone but
Big brother does not leave me alone
The inspector
Says we're the government that's the law
Please uphold it
Pay
The fine
50 Cent
For every
Access bushel I think it is
Are 239 excess bushels of wheat for which she was unifying about 117 bucks
In today's dollars
It's about two grand
2 Grand
My my father
Apparently he wasn't real crazy about that and I guess he didn't like that too much
If I have been 20 or 25 years old
I would have probably advised my father not to do what he did but I guess they sue the federal government
Huh
His army was like look I'm just trying to feed my cows come on I guess it went to
Are Court in Dayton Ohio
That was the first stop and I believe
That he was rambling to Roscoe the Ohio court agreed there's no
Commerce of any kind going on your unlike the original case with the boat price I believe I even remember
My sister telling me that the he came home and he was just
Delighted that he did win
But then
Governor pills the case and
The poorest when it got to the Supreme Court of the United States
He he he lost
Key lost
In a decision that I think it's fair to say
Still
Drives conservatives and Libertarians bonkers
And I'm neither one of those things but I get it
What does Supreme Court set
Is it Roscoe filburn growing that extra weed and not selling it still
Counts as interstate commerce
Could have that extra week causes him to not
Buy it
On the market
He needs less wheat from the market in all the farmers of America did that
And that be really bad for the market the idea is that if you need more wheat than the quota you go on
On the market and buy it
Even though you can grow it yourself
Got to buy it because if everyone can produce their quota and then whatever extra they need
And pretty soon the regulation breaks
Which means that the government intervention in the wheat Market will have failed
You will have to feed it or attempt to regulate this Market therefore we have to regulate even things you don't do
That is so weird it's such a mine frankly it's like
He's not doing anything we can Hartwell on Behavior this is this is Obamacare
Like the health care
Getting heated over Health Care the individual mandate
Just explain that's a reference to Barack Obama's healthcare plan hotly-debated couple years ago
Still hotly debated
What are the key ideas without plan is it in order for health care to be affordable for everyone
Everyone should have to buy it
So we're going to require people
To buy insurance
What else you pay a penalty
Which made a lot of people mad cuz they're like hey the government's force me to buy something I don't want my decision not to get Healthcare
Is not
Participation in interstate commerce
It's not even economic activity
I'm sitting here on my couch not buying
You sitting here
From the individual perspective that makes perfect sense but if you can out
And Justice Kagan said this in court
It's not so simple as uninsured people
Are increasing
Normal family premium Congress
Sitar
The price that everybody
Obamacare makes sense to me so it's a way of getting back to Roscoe
Things you're not
Because you know farmers and Island this is the case
In which
Congress receives a tremendous amount of power from the US Supreme Court
Essentially this case
It says that Congress can regulate
Almost anything
And that is
The single most significant precedent
In the area of the Commerce Clause the Big Bang
Did anyone try to raise their hand in them
Will this be like whoa if you can regulate the non behavior of this American Farmer
Then that's not even a slippery slope that's like a cliff that goes right down like there's no say hello to that
Editorial from November 13 1942
Set if the farmer who grows feed for consumption on his own Farm competes with Commerce
Would not the housewife who makes herself address do so equally the net of the ruling in short seems to be
Did Congress can regulate every form of economic activity if it's soda size
Would not the housewife who makes herself address
You so eager like said yeah it's like yeah
If you make something with shoot I've my wife and I with our kids made these little like a miniature stuffed animals for them to play with the other day
Are we then in violation of some
Oh my God
After the Roscoe filburn case those 16 words in the whole definition
Commerce
Expand because now Commerce wasn't just the buying and selling of things it was the knot
Buying and selling apps
And that expansion
That would go Way Beyond we it would go into Realms much much deeper
Much deeper in US
That's after the break
I'm Jared I'm Rod this is my perfect will continue in a moment
Is more perfect time Chatham rod
So we had the big bang of the Commerce Clause in that Wheatfield
Where Commerce
Scats
We find not just what you're buying and selling but also what you're not
Buying selling your negative Commerce
But at this point
Sum 41 we're still talking about
Markets were still talking about Commodities there comes a point when the use of the Commerce Clause goes woo
Beyond that
Where it gets into matters of the heart
You might say this is the moment
When the Commerce Clause gets
Weaponized
Hello hey can you hear me
Yes this is Jad from Radiolab more perfect in New York
Jack
Jad Jad
Jad jad okais
Will Andrew is here and he's worth
Really understand what I mean
Yes meet this guy
Can you do it yourself tell me who you are
Your name
Ollie McClung jr.
And how old are you
And where are you speaking to us from right now
Time in Birmingham Alabama
You were born Birmingham
Yes
Aside from some time at college in Florida and a stint in the Coast Guard
Ali jr.
Has lived in Birmingham in his entire life
And the reason we call them up is that for 75 years his family ran
A Famous BBQ joint
Name dali this is your dad's business
From what I understand right yes my grandfather founded it
1926 to this was passed to your dad who passed it to you yes
Okay we were in business together till he died
Holley's BBQ was located on Birmingham Southside the building we were in its time you're talkin about 1914
Natural 68 it was concrete
Block
Big sign outside said world's best barbecue predicted for today
Barely during lunch
Align with stretch out the door
Ollie's was famous for its slow cooked
Pork and chicken and Fritz spicy vinegar BBQ sauce biking
Chocolate pies broasted a lot of pies
But all these was also famous or would become famous
For something else entirely
McAllister the times
The way things were
That time chords
Throughout South Birmingham
We had
Carryout business as well as sit down business
And
Those
Bye-bye Black customers came in and
I ordered
Carry out counter
Put their food out
And
Truth fact history
Take it on
With them to eat as opposed to sitting down and
What he saying is it all these barbecue was segregated if you were white you can eat inside if you are black
You couldn't remain
Dwight work
So what is the temperature of the Commerce Clause okay so the Federal Gov
At the time this will be the Kennedy administration and LBJ
They want to come down and places like Ollie's barbecue but their hands were sort of tied
We have this thing called the Fourteenth Amendment says no State shall deprive any person
Of life liberty or property without due process of law nor shall any state the night equal protection of the laws
Any person died right after the Civil War
Basically outlaw
Things like segregation
Corseted work we have another 80 plus years of Jim Crow and the reason for that is it the Supreme
In court shortly after the 14th amendment was passed
Kind of neutered it not kind of they did
1 ways they did was by insisting that we read the 14th Amendment as being targeted
Only at States if you look at that sentence the second since the Fourteenth Amendment says no State no State shall
Deprive any person of life liberty or property without depressive problem is is when
A restaurant owner like Ali McClung the nice service to Black patrons it's not
Alabama doing the damage to the private business of Alabama ordered McClung family
To discriminate against black patrons they just did it so the 14th amendment can only get two states
Hear it has no reach because there's no State action there is nothing to regulate at the state level
So
The best decided to do
In a fascinating
Legal gymnastics is they decided to use
Commerce Clause Congress passes the most sweeping civil rights
Male ever to be written into the law has the right to be open to the public
July 2nd 1964 Congress passes a sweeping Civil Rights bill that was hinged on those six
16 words and I will
Explain to you how
It's kind of fascinating
It's just a second the first
Just to get us to that point
So 1964 Civil Rights
Active
Did you desegregate right away
No
We were we were not happy with it obviously
I want to read you something that you said in 1960
Before I believe these are
Serve your account of something that happened in
Indian restaurant
Day after the Civil Rights Act was passed
A black man comes into the restaurant asking to be served
And and you turn him away
Forty-five minutes later comes back with a young girl for all the black
People they sit down at the counter they want to know
Why you why all these wouldn't serve them
And they were taking notes
And your CO2 the same may seem like agitators
Yeah in fact they were they
They were folks and came
And when around several places
Justin
Test the law basically yeah
And you are a and you return those books away
Yes
Get timeout
Why
I was just because that's way
Had always done this way
Until the law
Got to judicate it
We weren't going to
Unilaterally
Change my thank-you note from their perspectives are there because the laws been changed
Yeah
Yes
Ali says right after the Civil Rights Act was passed
Serve an emergency meeting was called of the Birmingham Restaurant Association Unidad 1
I discussed with the
What's a mammoth executive of it
This was going to be such a
Potentially
Harmful
Restaurant businesses make you would miss all your way customers is that what you worried about
I mean that was a possibility
And
Somebody ought to do something
So we
Coming up being
Once
Do something
I fall asleep
Today filed the suit
Basically saying to the federal government you have no right to barge into our
Small
Independent
Local business
Start was
They can't really
Tell us what to do because we're not an interstate business and that's all that the federal government regulates and
Up until that point that was all they had regulator
The case went to the US District Court for the Northern District
Of Alabama at the lower court level 3 Jersey special
Panel
We had a unanimous
Decision
Our favor
The Alabama Court agreed
There was no interstate commerce happening year
And that
Ollie's did not have to
Desegregate they could sell their ribs to whoever they want
And we were
Optimistic about that
Government in appeals
And the case
They say it goes all the way to the Supreme Court
Right let me know explain to you how the government made this argument cuz they made it in court
October 5th 1964 General Archibald Cox
Why the government should be allowed to use the Commerce Clause of all things to desegregate
Ablaze operate a restaurant in Birmingham Alabama specializing in
Barbecued Meats this is a business that sells and buys a lot of meat
July 1 1964
$69,683 to be exact and
Birmingham Alabama to plant
Song that that plan came from other states so they've moved in
In other words you think you're a local business but you're not meat is sourced from places other than Alabama
What about ketchup ecstatically
Not minding Alabama soul
You know we bought it from a local vendor that local vendor probably bought it from somebody who bought it from somebody that got it from out of state
Reaching beyond what it ever been done before basically was basically telling them the same thing they told
Roscoe filburn
You are not an island
And that was only the government's first argument they had another art
That is a second then still more directly it was even more
Radical
Swaying racial discrimination in restaurant
Interstate
Which is caused by the artificial narrowing
Supermarket
Resulting from the eggs
So here's the argument
If you deny black people access to restaurants and hotels
You are effectively shutting down interstate travel by them
Imports of the country where this practice is commonplace
Entire
Deep South you're limiting their ability to cross state lines and
The central argument
Suggestion is that
When you discriminate against someone
You create
Downstream
Negative
Commercial effects
Like you create a chilling effect
Because
The person you're discriminating against is then less likely to travel across state lines
Send money
So in effect you are
Depressing their future interstate commerce
If you ask
Black people
With this experience
From this time.
They were universally say
We never left home unless
Every Tire
Was triple-check
Every belt was triple checked in the car
Because we did not want
To have a car breakdown in a hostile southern town
And get lunch.
Right right
It is
An entire system
Of travel and commerce that's at stake here
Essentially the argument was discrimination is bad for business
Expensive
And
Ultimately in a unanimous decision
The Supreme Court
Same court that 100 years earlier had basically gutted the 14th Amendment this
Supreme Court
Agreed
That discrimination in restaurants pose significant burdens on the quote
Interstate flow of food and upon the movement of products generally
Remember that decision coming down
I'm certainly
Where were you
Pause at work
Can you tell me a little bit about how
You and your dad
Process that decision
Simply
Certain one who came in after that
And they were
The very next day
There was a group of local law civil rights leaders
Who came in tonight launch
I knew some of them by
Haven't seen him in the news that sort of thing
They were not regular customers
Orlando after frankly but
Lay
Celebrated our what even want to say
Tested I don't know what the motive was I came in late lunch
They got served it's like anybody else
They came in and it was fine
The law
What's inside at Seoul
That was it
With a tents
No
Ellen the waitress who was why you no one was
She was a little
Answer about it and was it this way just to see a black woman yes
It was now but she was
Like most my employees been there a very long time
Panda
Have never
Served other black folks
In a sit-down situation and
And
Of course
It was
Little bit
Upsetting but
Different cute little hesitant at first I
Answers to right hand side women
She didn't we didn't
That was not a problem
After the ruling it's not as if a lot of Black customers 70/30 coming into Ali's Barber
Q they didn't
Chris how a guy named Nathan Turner Jr.
2014 he was interviewed
Turn into herpes
He grew up nearby Ali
Just the fact that I've always pushed it that far
To take it to the Supreme Court
It left a bad taste
Pun intended
In the miles of a lot of black
People in Birmingham
In-N-Out 53 years later
How do you think about that Supreme Court decision
Well
You're at if you're asking about segregation that's one thing we ask about Spring Court and
Seasoning on the Commerce Clause I still disagree with the
Let me put it real
Real succinctly
I think
What you had
And that
Decision
Was it rather than
Civicsource
Correct but I don't know
It rather than three-quarters of the Congress
And 3/5 of the states I believe it is having two
Or maybe 2/3 Carlos whichever it is
Having two
Vote to
Repeal an amendment
The Constitution
You had basically 9 appointees who
Repeal the 10th
Amendment to the Constitution
10th Amendment basically says that the powers not given to the feds
Are reserved for
For the states
For the people
That's about as succinct as I can say it
But you understand how this is going to sound to a lot of our listeners
I mean that you are making a
States rights argument
As a not-so-veiled way to continue to discriminate
They're really in the end this is not about stay
States rights I think that's going to I was going to sound to a lot of pee
Well it may very well but it's not the case
Was there segregation
Yes
Where we going to voluntarily
And that
Probably not
Would we go back and reinstate if we could no absolutely not
But the
Issue that you're talkin about with
Commerce Clause in the
Constitutional
Issue
You're still just what I said
So you still believe 53 years later that the Supreme Court got it wrong that they should have never
Use the Commerce Clause to make you desegregate Ollie's
Yep that is correct
But
Don't hear me say that I don't want to go back to have segregation
That's a separate issue but is it separate I guess is my question you know
My God grant you
If you think of it in the abstract
Federal government being able to regulate
Commerce across
All
Boundaries
Is an enormous power
And he could be a scary power so I grant you that at the same time
You have a Civil Rights Act
That
It speaks to a different amendment in the Constitution
Ryan that you and your father will not willing to follow so how is the government going to get you to
To pay attention
And to get in line
They've got to use the Commerce Clause
So on some level isn't it
Isn't the power
Present
Because the other principles
They would otherwise regulate your Behaviour
Just aren't working
What that's that's the point
Choose which
Which is the priority
Basically
I understand you were which is the priority
I will
Which is the priority of
Those amendments
Answer for you the 10th Amendment that grants states rights
For everything. Enumerated
Outweighs
The Dignity of black
No
Will put so say to me differently
Well
The 10th Amendment
Left that to the state
The Fourth Amendment yes
An agreement to the 14th Amendment
Gifts
People rights
Everyone writes
But here's the thing about rights
It's kind of like the first law of thermodynamics
There's only
And people don't realize this a lot of time
That's the only so many rights
Only a finite number rights
If you take some
Give something to someone
They come from someone else or somewhere else
Now
It's very well to say that
The end of segregation
Was a higher right
Memo important
Ban
They misuse of the Commerce Clause
What are we
Say
But you're still a balance and just
Which one you
Think is most important
Today's products recalled zero-sum
Bali's basic point
We talked about this for another hour
Was it in achieving desegregation that way
By the way
Civil Rights Act
Dramatically altered
Desegregated
Huge parts
By doing it that way
He says with the Commerce Clause
Something was sacrificed
He calls it a zero
I wouldn't call it that
I don't think most
We call it that
Treating people with dignity and equality is a net win
.
But
It is legitimately strange
Did the government had to take such a roundabout
Ass backward way
To fix this
To fix this grave Injustice what you would think would be the obvious
That you would go right to those civil rights
Parts of the Constitution
It was like, that's what's weird is it we have the 14th Amendment and yet we go to
The Commerce Clause or something
That is
So clearly stated in one of the Amendments lawyers are very tricky
Search Jamie Floyd Again by the way
The lawyers in those cases
Is that what they wanted to win
They wanted to win more than they wanted to make a social statement about
Equal justice equal rights the 14th Amendment I mean those things mattered
Most of all they wanted to win
They wanted to shut down discrimination
At those lunch counters
And if Congress could shut them down or require them to open their doors to all Americans using
Those 16 words
I'm okay with that
Yeah
No I mean obviously the if the ends do justify the means in that case
But it does make you if you were to put that case and the weak case in your mind as a kind of split screen you
It's
It's a little strange because I do think
Okay we have
I didn't mean to I said hopefully we're Americans with principles that matter
You know that we believe in equality believe in racial Justice
But really we just believe in money
And we can do all the other stuff by bootstrapping it
E-commerce
But somehow as as pure principles
Play what don't have teeth while it's deeply troubling that we have to use Commerce to achieve our higher
Are values
That is weird to me that is
Fundamentally weird to me
It's kind of cynical
I mean
I
You are right we are
At least in large part about
Commerce Center
But if that's who we are
Then we should embrace it and use it to our advantage
And if we can use it to our advantage perhaps it does take us to our higher principle
How to understand why it's not all bad
One of Jamie's .22 hadn't actually thought it was that
Legislating morality
Fletchling what is good and what is bad
Doesn't always go well
Cuz we very often don't agree
Galaxy there been times where people kept slaves and thought that was just fine
That was right
400 years you had the 14th amendment in place but it couldn't solve all these Barbie
And here was a way
For the government without going at the moral questions head-on
Government budget and all the way into the barbecue joints in the hotels in the restaurants and the houses and now the cake shops of Amer
Erica and all the way down into the local
And it was because of this increasingly expansive idea of Commerce
That was now no longer the buying and selling of things or the knot
Buying and selling of things it was now
Any Behavior
They could create a kind of butterfly fish
That might one
Day many steps Downstream
Have a future effect
On the buying selling things
Was right his case that was a massive shift
It shifted totally the federal government's role Beyond business even if you
I think it's good then that's fine
And it's for the better but
Just asked me realize that it was a
MasterChef from
The way
The country of Benin
Up before that time
Ft McClellan case James Chen says
Service government
Use
Of the Commerce Clause
Pretty much went wild yeah there was just no real limit
Begin wave those 16 word sort of like a magic want to pass laws on everything from Fair labor standards
2 marijuana is a schedule 1 drugs
Spell justice for victims of trafficking
Species 1992 professional and amateur sports sports protection act which forbids States
Authorized Sports gambling
To make the argument itself
What's the government even has to defend itself
James Chen says there were times when the government would pass a law it get taken to court and the government would basically
We not show up
And he would still with the governor even has to argue
So you can see the McClung case as sort of a second big bang but then
You get to the mid-90s
At this point 1994 U of a democratic President Bill Clinton Democratic majorities in both houses of Congress
And
Together they pass
The violence against women act
Today is the first day of spring
And I think it's appropriate that we begin a new season of Hope
In the fight against domestic violence
Thank you all for being here
This is an important day
The Act was sort of a sweeping rethink of the federal government's role in
Trying to prevent violence against women it beefed-up investigations
Prosecution
It allowed women to sue their alleged attackers in federal court
Responsibility domestic violence is now the number one health risk for women between the ages of 15 and 44
Or Nah country
And the law was hinged on the Commerce Clause same essential argument is in the Barbie
That same fault my name is Christy Brown Colour to my life
A woman named Christy brzonkala starts her freshman year at Virginia Tech
And just weeks in September 1994 I was raped by two football players in my own dorm
I'd met them for the first time just 15 minutes before they assaulted me
These two football player she alleged had raped her repeatedly on a single night in 1994 I was raped three times
She went to the local campus authorities
She told her story
Call children hearings didn't go to the police
What is suspended one of the two students he appealed
And when you returned
Christy brzonkala dropped out of school
Christy brzonkala
Ultimately decides to sue her alleged attackers and the school
Under this new law the violence against women act
And the case
Ultimately makes it to the Supreme Court
Will your argument now number 99 5 Christy brzonkala vs Antonio Morrison
When Christie's case got to Supreme Court her lawyer made the same argument
About women that the government is made in the Ollie's Barbeque case about black people
That discrimination
Or in this case outright violence
Has a huge Downstream effect on the economy has concluded the gender-based violence
It's actually affect the national economy
Gender-based violence and the fear of that discriminatory violence
Two truths women's travel interstate
Restricts women's choice of jobs and ability to perform those jobs
Reduces National productivity and increases medical and other costs
And again the court was given tons of evidence about the economic effects
Congress heard from women
Who's batter is kept their partners for morphine every year this cost the country bill
Billions of dollars and that economic Downstream effect was not hard to prove in this case
She dropped out if you ever get it right it's not just her it's everyone else who similarly situated
But in this case
Yarygin what's happening in a very different time in the country very different mood
In front of an increasingly conservative Supreme core
It just wasn't buying it anymore and Arbors on Carla's complaint alleges that she was the victim of a
Songs of Chief Justice rehnquist reading the majority opinion
Justice could failed to provide her a remedy for Morrison's conduct but gender motivated crimes
The phrase economic activity
Another word for very sorry for what may have happened to Christine bronkala but this is not Commerce
This is why eyelids suggestion was at least in the Ali's case there was something
Here they felt like the link to Commerce was too thin
Arguments in Congress May regulate non-economic violence coming all time.
Based solely on that conducts remote effect on interstate commerce
Chief justice rehnquist got his majority
2 * 2
Chipaway
At the commerce power
YouTube Tiny teeny teeny weeny little bit
Jamie Floyd says that
Tempt
To roll it back
Continue Suites rolling back
It is rolling back
Still pretty powerful don't get us wrong but where were left
At the end of the day
Is it a really confusing place
Ali
McClung excluding black people from his dining room
Yeah for commercial act we can sit reprehensible but I
I would like to think that raping Christine
Would be at least as bad
Totally what
This kind of
Absurd abstraction gets us to
And in
A coherent Ideal World
Can't be right
Maybe that's just the inevitable thing that happens when you try and make
Make it all about money
This episode was produced by
My sarkari more perfect is produced by me Jenn I'm a run and an amazing team Susie lechtenberg Jenny
Gallatin Julia Longoria Kelly Prime Alex overington and sarkari with Elie mystal Christian
Darius Lynn Hershman did Gable and Michelle Harris we have production help from Derek John and Lois Mitchell
Record audio is from Oye free law project collaboration with Legal Information Institute at Cornell
What more perfect / the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
On behalf of the entire more perfect team thank you guys
Glistening spreading the word
You'll hear from us again