Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
United States
Supreme Court of the United States
Where is do it
Hey I'm Jared I'm Rod this is more perfect
Mini series about
And today story from a reporter Sean up your last name can you say it rhombus firm rhombus
Confirm
Cinemark place
Who set the table for you we live in a representative democracy
In what does that actually mean practically speaking when do we come in contact
Check that democracy two places seems to me manga
One when we vote
Right yeah you asking me
I was deep in thought
If you vote if you've always true I know like
College-educated super Progressive human beings were like why would I ever voted to the exact
Just don't even care about the world makes my point like voting is the first weigh-in
Sur La Table
Entirely optional the second way is not you will be fine if you don't do it
And I mean
Serving on a jury
This is where I like We the People decide
Who goes to jail who gets free who lives who dies which is where we actually do
Democracy
Today we start with the story of a guy who
Who is Supreme Court famous
Would you say yeah he's in the books he's like a chapter one the most important names you've never heard up because he's at the center of this ongoing
Battle about
Who gets to serve on juries
And his name
Depending on who you are either symbolizes the best parts of American democracy
Receipt
Or the most cynical
Just his name
Yeah go for
James Batts
James Kirkland Batson
Hello
James
I went to his house in Louisville
Tell me your full name and tell me where you're from
About that James Batson Louisville Kentucky
James Batson his name just kept coming up over and over again what I was looking for the history of jury selection America so I called them up
And I was like hey
Israel airport in New York City and I'm really interested in your case
Because there's this other case
Can I come talk to you
Okay make sure my full name and
City
He's tall
He's built like a fridge
He's a black man Bernal drove Truck local in Cross County
Orthopedics 15 hours one way
Florida
As a kid he was
Is a students graduated from Aaron
Technical High School
Q's and I'd like a vocational school specializing in life
Engineering industrial electricity
You seem pretty
Popular 18
But shortly after that
Seem like
The bottom fell out
13 Batson grew up in the West End of Louisville in the 1970s and the West End was super rough
The people selling dope
Prostitution
Does everything have to do with fast money
Young age
Fast money was like
The American dream
I mean it's pretty hard when a lot of people around you got a nice things and they got them because they're doing
Doing something illegal
You keep coming up rabbit ears
You shaking your head like you know what rabbit ears are what
Pupil mobile pockets
Can I let him neither one of them
He said also when he was 10 he wanted pair of shoes he couldn't afford them trailer
Well when they first came out if you didn't have a pair of those you had on with the
Call Buddy
Everybody
Cheap tennis shoes
Tim's brother asked his mom
Romani and they she gave them some money but not enough
How to make up the difference they went out and they
Stole people's empty soda bottle
And turn them in for like
The deposit
Resent all nickel apiece
Throwing up pop bottles
That was my first
Experience with
Illegal money
Doing pop bottle
Show everything else bands from there
Fast forward a couple years James has more ground he starts doing some petty crime and he starts breaking into house
They think they actually gave me a name call me to pants pocket burglar
When the crime would happen burglar would take only
Japanese pocket
Big purses and jewelry no merchandise didn't fit in his pocket he wouldn't take it
That was you
I'm not admitting that was me
Possible deniability
Children's tumor names
Vibram acne
Gothic V
James start stealing bigger things and he starts getting arrested
Tattooing in and out of Courts
And then one of those small in that cases
Became I think American legal
They got me out of car
92 cops pulling over
Pull me out the car they say you have the right to remain silent anything and went to that little
Protocol whatever
They tell him some burglaries that happened in that area
And I think they said I did them
Will you move
David
The time I've been doing some margaritas or whatever but anyway
James said he didn't do this one
And if they didn't have the proof
He was driving around in his car
When they pick them up
When they arrested me I'm thinking
They didn't really have a case against me they didn't catch me breaking into a house
You got me out of car
An old fingerprints nowhere
He thinks he can win
Okay so I'm not going to jury trial
And
The mere fact that you and I are talking about
James Batson
Case 30 plus years later
Is amazing
That's a prosecutor my name is Joe Gutman I'm from Louisville Kentucky
Griffin little raised in Louisville
Want to be a lawyer since he was a kid my parents would through a divorce when I was very young and I wanted to go to law school to help.
Kids and divorce has the bats in case he's 26 years old and had just be
Become a lawyer change this case was in the first six months that I was in the prosecutor's office
Pretty impressive first year
Starting out
I lost my first date trial
Really
Batson's case you know this low-level burglary of breaking of a house in a purse being stolen he was a go
Maybe this will be my twin be evidence
Disappeared that he was guilty of the crime
James was
Accused identified as the one is having done it
Two eyewitnesses they're saying James these Witnesses photos of him before
Because
Do you need naps
So
To come to the case
It goes to trial
And had a hung jury
They end up being a hung jury
Hip hip hooray
It means they can come to unanimous to
James gets off
Why was it a hung jury in Kentucky you have to have a unanimous vote
So the defense is looking for that one juror
The keeps from convicting there is apparently one juror
Who just didn't buy it then by the evidence and thought James was legit
It was a black
One black lady came to visit me
After Drew's over
She said I really really don't think you're guilty the rest of
The jury
Was trying to make me say that you
Guilty or not guilty
So end up being a hung jury I was disappointed
At that point I was
Having second thoughts about
Is this the right career for me
SoJO gottman
He says imma try this case one more time it was pretty close to guilty
I have this one juror who hung it up
Tell me two or more time and it does something this time
A little differently
Just a setup as you know when you get a jury summons you go in you're on a jury pool
At the beginning of a trial
Jury selection
Eddie asked you touching you're outside the prosecution the defense sometimes the judge they give jurors into a room and they start
Lots of question is there anyone here who has been the victim of a crime
Victims of crime
To figure out which stores do we want
Member of a church do we want to get rid of
And that's the more important part of this process which jurors do we want to toss office jury pool
So what are the rules to get rid of jurors
There's two ways to get rid of jurors to get down to that group of 12 in this
And the first way is called striking
Cause this type of me to excuse him for causing this time
Tracking for cause is like when they ask you can you be fair in this case if you say you know Noah
I really can't I really strong feelings about the people or the subject matter
That's a strike for cause or it's like hey that lady who's sitting in the chair of the defendant
That's some
That's my cousin
We grew up together
Roll a complex Venture Lane kombucha that's my boss
We go out every Saturday for brunch whatever it is
You're too close to this
You can't be fair got it so that one's cause
That's pretty much common sense it makes sense to everyone but the second way is
The heart of this whole matter this whole story
It's called a peremptory challenge
Preempt reroute
Peremptory
That's a word depending on how you punch it into Google
It'll be like that's a type of a son what does it mean what is peremptory meet Brenda challenge means you get a certain number of straw
Just to get rid of people you think might not be
Fair to you
But you can really use them anyway you want and but these
Strikes
You want to give any reason
How many days do you get
So it varies from state-to-state in some states
20 in other states
It's for
In Kentucky then and now each side gets
88 juror
Did they just get to put the Exxon and say you're not going to sit on this trial hooker truck
They don't explain anything and this isn't just some
Weird legal rules we made up
Like 20 years ago this is something
Has been around
It's older than America
Goes back to England in the 11th century
And before that some say he goes back to like
104 BC Roman times really really
And the idea is I feel like the visualization is like
Seesaw
Like okay
We need to get to this perfect group of 12 people and
You know there's going to be people who are biased either side so each side gets the eliminate people you get three you get
You get for you get for and then we'll
Come to this balance in the jury
A group of people
Port going to be fair
Tilted their way from other side
The thinking is Atlanta balance yet and also the thinking was that this would give outside more faith in the process and
At the same time
Protect both sides
From
Tyranny of a trial judge
How to hack
Power cannot you're okay
What happens in this case is the second trial begins
Take me to the
Mama Theresa
Imagine early
Yeah that's that's the first thing that
Well
The only people that were in the courtroom
Were some family members of mr. Batson his attorney a detective
And me
And the jury
So the reason we're talking about this case and Joe gottman and James Batson
Is because the next thing that happens is Joe Gutman gets up there
He scans the jury pool and at this point he says there are 13 people left
For that were black
9 that were white and he uses his peremptory challenges
The strike off 1
Blacture
They're all gone
Leaving all white
Do you remember
Striking
For minority
Do I specifically remember
The reason for each
No I don't
I asked Joe was the reason because they were
In fact
Black no
I can see that they were not stricken
Because of rice
And I remember
Specifically did one of the jurors lived in the neighborhood
Yes exactly remember what his reasons were for all four black jurors but
What's important for our story is to know that James Batson is sitting there in the room
As all of this is happening
Just completely strikeout
Damn right I told my lawyer
Projector that you know
Voices by rev jet
James said because
Not fair
He should know it's a long-standing rule he's allowed to do that
Sprite what we want
He was white
Inside nose for people that have just been struck off the jury they're burning the courtroom was white
So again
Jo Malone YouTube Jack and again
What you mean you can't you work for me you do what I say you just check anyway
I don't care as long standing rule
And he did
And it all came behind that one objection
Yeah
What happened
Is after the jury was select
Dugdale
James Attorney
Said
Judge how I want to make an objection
We went up to the bench
He said
Your honor you can see there's an all-white jury I would like for him to explain his strikes
But before I could get another word out of my mouth
Judge Ryan said Mr gottman
Does not have to explain his rights
It's not the law
Let's move on
Move on
So they moved on with an all-white jury
I got found guilty
I got 20 years
Yes
Sebastian goes to prison
Danville KY
His first move when he got there
Appeal immediately
And ultimately his appeal ends up in the hands of the sky David niehaus
Jefferson County public defenders
Office
Anyhow decide to do something
Ambitious
What we did is
We call it taking
A tour of the jurisdiction
Washington
Khalid
Electrical Eagle Road Trip
Sammy house and his team start looking at other states
Looking at other regions to find out what this is
Problem
Elsewhere is this just something
Limited to the South or is it
Something else
Give me like are people in other places doing what Joe got midday
And when he found is that this was happening pretty much everywhere
So
They filed an appeal
Which worked its way up to the courts
And
In December 1985
Thank you gentlemen vacation submitted to hear arguments next year in Kentucky
Case arrives at the
The Supreme Court of the United States
I get a call one day
From the Associated Press at checkup
How do you feel about the
Supreme Court accepting
Case of James Kirkland Batson and I was almost speechless and
I did
Go just to observe and learn
Mister chief justice and may please the court
So here's out ultimately went down
Bat inside my house
He argues that these strikes were being used take black people off
Jerry's and this is happening everywhere able to list some 25
Jurisdictions and
Practice pilot of the 14th Amendment equal protection
And the 6th Amendment
What does the right to a jury of your peers representative of the community as possible
So if Lewisville is like 17% black
The jury's probably be about
17% black
And the prosecutor shouldn't be allowed to
Askew that without having to give a reason
Most of all
Kentucky's response to requests
We Believe
The historical nature and function of the device itself to Kentucky saying
We shouldn't have to justify these strikes the court has told us that again and again
Is always been unsettled enough controlled by the court
Unexplained and his practice
Centuries and
Yes and maybe some of uses but this is a tool that lawyers need
Thank you gentleman McKay's this semester
4 months later the court delivers it
Its verdict
And in a seven to two decision
Batten wood
The court found that the prosecutor's actions for sure violated the 14th Amendment
They said racial discrimination of any kind in jury selection
Is not allowed
Que Dan Rather
The high court ruling today it is illegal
Illegal even on a Grand Prix challenge it is illegal
For a lawyer to reject a juror on the basis of race
James Batson sentence with immediately vacate
How's that feel
Can you send describe them
If you imprison and you know your sentence is being taken away
Talk to break every now and then and then
It's coefficient come up
Be hanging out playing chess
I got a loan and logbooks Batson rule
And that was the biggest eel
Of all this
The headline
This new
Rett syndrome named after him
Justices put new limits
What it's called free MP3 challenge the bathroom the bathroom is an echo of what
You see people minorities getting booted off of a jury you can say your honor I think that's a violation
In the other side B of the Defence of the prosecution
Pasta provide non
Racial reasons
For why they eliminated that chair
And for a lot of people this is a break
This is like finally we figured out how to do this right
There was a system in place to protect everyone and that system was even extended to civil cases and eventually the women is
It was a big deal when the case was decided and the initial elation
Was quickly
Tempered
With a strong dose of reality
This is Jeff Robinson he's a director of the ACLU Center for chest
Because what bats and prevents is
Deliberate
Racial
Discrimination
And I almost immediately
All over the country
Prosecutor started training each other teaching
Each other on how to get around Batson Equal justice initiative
In Montgomery Alabama
Train is all across the country
Some of these are on video
And I found one
Made it on YouTube when you're picking up jewelry you got to stay these basic rule this is one of those videos this one
In the Philadelphia prosecutor named Jack man lecturing to a room full of young prosecutors on how to pick a jury
Selecting black
You don't want the real educated ones and my screen is black
Women young black women are very bad there's an antagonism I guess maybe cuz they're downtrodden
So there are downtrodden to areas and they somehow want to take it out on somebody and you don't want it to be you
The crazy thing about this video is that it was film just a few months after the Baton decision
Batson vs Kentucky I'm sure you've all become aware of that
Casey Jackson man basically tells his prosecutors look we got this new rule
Here's how you break it you strike the black person off the jury but just say it's for another reason
Because that's what Batson required
This is a racially neutral reason
When you do have a black shirt you question them at like and
Honest Little Chute that you have Mark something down that you can articulate later time if something happened
Las Vegas strike three blacks
Start with first three people write it down right then and there I'd rather ride in my little box there you know the woman had a kid
About the same age as defendant and I thought you be sympathetic to amore
She's unemployed and I just don't like unemployed people because I find enough today before this is almost this training to create
Catalog of reasons
Put on the face where race-neutral
Just say you're excluding them because they're too tall
Are there 200 that person was wearing a black sweater things like well he lives in a bad neighborhood
The person would maintain eye contact body language or they belong to a church
Tattoos
What are a nurse
Any of those reasons have a markdown
As long as a prosecutor doesn't say I excused that person because they're black
That's some says it's completely okay
I was actually working on a case
This is lawyer Bryan Stevenson
My office said the time was called the southern Christmas depends who it is who's and I was in Atlanta Georgia
Butterfly Boucher
Alabama and when was this
This is 1986
And we were defending someone down in Swainsboro Georgia
Guy by the name of Gamble
And the bathroom decision came down
I and objections were made with the prosecutor used his peremptory strikes exclude all of the African-American
And we said wait a minute you're on if there's a new decision Batson vs Kentucky
Which means that the prosecutor can't do this
And the courts at while I read baton. What this means is the price going to have to give race-neutral reason
The prosecution I've got my race-neutral Visa
Is Weis truck this woman
Because she looks just like the defendant there was an African American man to wait a minute what is that
No she doesn't
He said it's not judge that I see that you did
What struck this man because he lives in South Waynesboro
And that's where the defendant
And we record the sale of all the black people live in South Waynesboro
All the way to
That's not a reason to reason. You know that is erased
He said I stop one person
Because this man was in the military and he was discharged
After 5 years in the military
And in my experience or honor
You only get discharged honorably after an even number of years
What a juror was put back on the stand was so where were you discharged from the military honorably yes I was
I was actually decorated
I got this metal I got this award I got these things
Well I still accept the Prosecco
Kids reading for excluding that
A person my favorite was
The prosecution gets better
This man because he testified
That he was a mason
Any said you're on I just don't want anybody who's a member of a masonic lodge
All my jewelry they have their own code their own rituals are all culture
I don't want that
The jury was put back on the stand we asked her are you a member of the Masonic Lodge
I've never said no I'm not he said I'm a brick mason
And the judge says I still know what you mean I'll let you exclude that person right
And so almost from the very beginning there was this
Cynicism this gameplay I used to tell people
Bath is not going to eliminate racial bias in jury selection
But it will make the jury selection process a lot more entertaining
Y'all should come to court and just watch the show
So you not only did Batson
Not change anything but that's in made things worse
Steven breit put to me is basically
Set of procedures
Two sortilege enemies and cover up the race discrimination that's going on
You had this
Smelly putrid problem of racial discrimination in jury selection
And instead of
Tossing it out
We just
Sprayed Febreeze
It's kind of perfume
Vaguely cheap cologne it's still there
Begley hidden
And now with the Batson rule
If you think the prosecution or the
Defense is striking people off because of race
You have to call them out and then you have to
Somehow
Try and prove that the reason they're providing is a lie
And that's
Really really Tiff
Since
1986 Ford xample in the state of Washington
There been
Probably 4748 challenges on baton issues where people have been convicted make said waiting
The prosecutors were excusing
People of color from the jury
Because they were people of color
Out of those 46 250 challenges there's been one
River
The state of Tennessee has not reversed a single case
Under Batson
And the 30 years for it's inside the Baton decision came out
As a result he says there still many counties in America where the diversity of the jury is not increase
Very much at all
So for example in one Louisiana Parish they looked a felony cases
Is over an eight-year period
And found it nearly half the black jurors
Horse track
Houston County Alabama
Over a five-year period
The date established at 80% of the African Americans qualify for jury service
80% 80% and that's in death penalty cases so
I mean if you think about that like a big percent of time Deezer
Lawyers who are
Going around the bathroom rule going on the Block
Going on the Constitution to get these all-white juries
Who are then oftentimes pudding
Black
Mint
To death
And
That reminds you some pretty dark
Super Bass
I mean
That video
Training video
The assumption that video is it
Having black
People on the tree
Would hurt that guy
Would hurt the
Yeah
Show me Justice
Assume that orbit is there any
Any data that would say that's even remotely
Be true the hardest thing about looking at this stuff
Analytically
The juries are like
Black Box
They don't let
Journalist
Academics in
Often
Study
What's going on
Two trees kind of sacred that
Yeah but
The few times we've gotten data like to do
This group called the capital jury brought
That looks it
Data speed
SafeLink application
Because that's where the stuff ends up being like
Life or death
So they looked at data in
Like 350 cases in 14 States
Over a number of years and they found that
White man
Are more likely to go for the death penalty than black men when you get to sentencing that number that the difference between
White and black is really exaggerated
White men are
Are seven times more likely to want the death penalty
Is in a black person
There's another study that was done in Florida
Amazon look at felony cases over like 10 years and
They found that
All-white jury pools
In Florida convicted black defendants
Percent
More often
Okay but was really interesting is that Gap was practically eliminated when at least one member of the jury pool
Black Interstate but one black person
And that difference
Yeah and catastrophes
Why I mean
Types of criminal cases
Usually involve cops and the reason is often cited is
That nope black
Jurors are less likely
To believe
Cops
Bikers are more likely to
Insert some sense of
Suspicion
Into
The states are the Commonwealth or whatever is tested
And almost everyone talked to
Gave me a version of this
That that you know we have black going to jury to deliberate more
And that black people are less likely to trust law enforcement especially
Jack McMahon
Who was the guy we heard from in that video
Antivirus
Personage
Could ever imagine
Stone Cold liberal
To the nth degree but I was talking about practicality
Jewelry backpack
I still stand by that
The man asked you this
And you're trying to drug test
And the defendant is going to claim that the
Cops online
Okay
You're the
What
Demographic group
It had more
Bossier
The police live
Then
Minority
They have seen
Police
Lionville belief police
Live more than
Some white guy lives in a rich area believes that police officer every everything he says
I'm so is the prosecutor you're trying to win the case
And that persons not going
The person is going to be
Questioning
Witnesses
And you're given the Opera
Opportunity
True peremptory challenges to strike them why wouldn't you
Give me a full mattress
Well I guess
I see the argument that you know use your friend challenges
To get the best you can to win but doesn't eliminating a black
Jerry because you believe they might have certain biases against app
Police officer versus a white juror
In some way violate
The equal protection Clause of the
The 14th
I don't think so
Not at all because
It's not because of
The color of their skin
Cause of there
Demographic
And where
Sidle demographic
The fact of life
I think those Facts of Life in those societal
Demographical Concepts
All stem from the color of
Their skin
Maybe a deeper issue that we can't deal with
Jury selection
But you're right
But the reality is
The reality is that that that that's what this
Situation is so
So you're saying that if you're the prosecutor you
You should stay out for this guy will probably be worse.
For me he probably
Believe those cops online but I'm going to take him because I want to uphold the
There is no prosecutor in the country
I want to I want to show my altruism
And I'm going to keep this guy on my
Jewelry who made this
Believe my
Accentuate
Because I want to be altruistic
How to solve a problem like Batson
More perfect will continue
This is more perfect miniseries about
Supreme Court on Jad abumrad explain how we got into this hole
Brass about
Racial bias in Jerusalem
I think we should
It's because of a case it was in front of the Supreme Court this term in case 1483
Foster versus Chapman
So basic facts
This is a murder case in Georgia
A younger black man kills an elderly white woman the prosecutors dismiss a bunch of black Jersey
Is and the defense having this new Batson rule says hold up
Can't do that
And prosecutors give
These race-neutral reasons and the judge says
That looks good to me
Years later something sort of incredible happens through like one of those Freedom of Information Act
Type things
The defense actually gets
See the notes
Prosecution
Should had
During the
Trial the notes they kept her in
Jury selection this is one of those rare times when we pull back the curtain and we find out what the prosecutors were doing
This is lawyer Steven breit he actually argued Foster case in front of Supreme Court late last year
And he says what you saw these notes was that the prosecution
They literally wrote a little B next to the name
Each and every black juror B1 B2 B3
Highlighting all the black sand in in green on the list of all the people summoned for jury
Racial discrimination is really hard to prove
This is actual physical proof
In a file in the state like this is the Smoking Gun we've been waiting for so what are the what are the prosecutor
How did the prosecution argue in front of
Prosecution was like you know what actually wants an ultrasound they said
We were just riding those bees because we wanted to make sure we notice
The black jurors you want to keep track of them
4 months
Project trial defense counsel
That's lawyer representing Georgia Beth Burton
And she saying of course we're going to notice race this is the post Batson world end
We're going to no trace and we're going to write it down
I would be more surprised quite frankly if there wasn't some sort of highlighting or
Is that the reason he highlighted
Actors in green
He being the original prosecutor
What about the black jurors and did all these different things
Was because he was preparing defense in case
Correct. Justice Breyer asking
Well why didn't you make that
Argument
Like
When the case was actually happening the years and years ago
What isn't a little surprising
But he never thought of it
Didn't tell anybody
I would say that's on
The good news is that
In a 7 to 1 decision this
Supreme Court agreed
That
Is prosecutors reasons War
Utterly ridiculous
I'm just going to ask you
Violation
That's Justice Kagan
I don't think it is
Is that
This case was in front of supreme court at all
Good at to get appealed up to the highest court in the land
Before someone said
Oh yeah that's about annihilation
That's how hard it is
And the Supreme Court though it made a forceful
Decision 7 out of 8
Didn't make a new rule
This is not works offer up
Datsun 2.0 or didn't double down or throw it out or
You send me Ruel
No they said this is really wrong but
Didn't go as far to say
Because it doesn't work
So we still got bats
So okay if we want to diverse juries and
We know that Batson
Work
What do we do
So I asked
Everyone I talked to
That question
Got a lot of different answers
But this was the obvious
Amanda Nance
Margaret was a professor of law
IIT
Chicago Kent
College of Law
What I'd like to
The court to do
Is eliminate
Peremptory challenges who is a no-brainer
Again steambrite is a lawyer we have to
Supreme Court gives you these rules
Appropriate challenges
And then says
Well wait a minute don't just break people you know you were going to look into all the ways that you strike the people wouldn't give him at all that for crying out loud
Simple even Jack man the guy from that training video he was open to
We've had 30 years of experiment with Batson and it's not working
We now have to go the route that Justice Marshall suggested back in Batson
So in the bathroom decision you got Thurgood Marshall
Marshall like the most important attorney in the Civil Rights Movement turn the first black Supreme Court Justice
Key in the same paragraph
Call the Baton decision
Historic
And then said this isn't going to work this decision isn't going to do anything
He was basically a fortune teller he said both those things in the same breath
In one paragraph he starts about going this decision today
Historic
By the end of the paragraph
You're never going to fix this until you get rid of print through town
Set an alarm for 9 breakfast just do away with broom tri-strike
Constitution
1st Ave
Art denied
Peremptory challenge
Peremptory challenges
You will have discrimination but what surprised me most and Reporting this story is that like I talk to people
On the left side of the criminal justice system on the right side of Criminal Justice is ACLU types
Law professors academics
Conservative prosecutors
Guys we got to get rid of printer challenges right almost every single one
Will say no
No
Crucially important to organisms it's an easy solution just get rid of
Peremptory Sahel
Italian style are legal editor law professor sunwolf from Santa Clara University and lawyer David niehaus again
And here's one of the arguments
If you take these things away all the decisions about striking jurors would be made by the judge
On the question whether Jerry could be fair and impartial and for that to work you have to have a fair job
And
There are an awful lot of judges
Who aren't there
Here's another argument I heard from Jeffrey Robbins
Jason from the ACLU
And this is based on my experience
34 years in the criminal justice
Jeff Robinson says if you can find some way to take race out of the equation
Parentheses
Super useful
Call Annie told me about this one
Case very high-profile homicide
Lakes in the state of Washington
This case
Was incredibly complicated and also
Potentially involved
A coerced confession
Buy some undercover cop
Sand
There's a police officer on the jury pay
He says
I can be fair
I know the police officers that investigated this
I've worked with him before
I think they're really good people but don't worry
I can be fair
Everything about his back
Was saying
I do not want this man to serve on this
But he was saying
I can be fair
I could not exclude him
Moana challenge
Call
Why not
Because he said he could be fair the fact that he's a police officer doesn't mean he can't be fair but isn't saying I'm
I know some of these people involved in this case enough to get him dismissed for cause it's enough to get more questioning but how well
How do you know I'm not very well
So you saying that case if you said okay. Like to dismiss jurors 17-4
For cause the judge would say there's not a record
I don't think any judge in this country
What dismiss that juror for cause
And so a peremptory challenge is important
So
I've watched
More jury selection videos on YouTube than any person
Evershed and
It's this amazing thing where you see these people
But not necessarily used to being in a courtroom
There's certainly not used to be grilled in public by a bunch of people in suits
Take it up there to the jury panel
And they got to ask these questions in the trial
Over and over again
Can you be carrying a partial
Nobody says no
Everyone feels like
Yes I can be fair
I'm thinking I could I can be totally unbiased
I think some of them believe that they can actually do this nearly impossible task
And others they know they can't but they might say yes anyway
Believe me
Knows the bias Jersey
Comment they don't reveal things they lie about things for people that when you're questioned them in a jury that you know they're lying to you
Trying to get onto jewelry or trying to get off the jury bias people are being allowed to serve
So any tools that can help reduce the number of biased years on Jerry
Is essential to just
So yeah if you got a really
Crappie outlook on chores and humans then maybe you need more front through challenges but the way Jackie Robinson put it to me was that if you're using parentheses
Challenges the right way
It forces you to be like
Equal opportunity
Suspicious
Suspicious of
Everyone
And that's
The only way to be fair
My parents
We're both
Active in the civil rights movement in Memphis Tennessee
Is activist to people you could ever want to meet
Both black
I would never let my mother
Sit on a criminal defense jury
Because my mother is being about black defendants was
You're the reason I have to lock the door in my neighborhood
You're the reason that I get disrespected when I go out into the
Community
And I'm going to take it out on you
My father's position
Would be
I wouldn't believe a police officer if he told me it was raining and the water was coming down on my head
And so what this is about
Is
Actually
Putting into effect what the rules
Say
Talk to jurors and find out what they think
But what about Thurgood Marshall the idea that
You know
If you have renter challenges if you give people a way to discriminate they will discriminate well
I was born in 1956
It's on 1954 Thurgood Marshall argued Brown versus the Board of Education
Which
Had a significant impact on my life
Thurgood Marshall with someone that I have respected and someone I have admired virtually my entire life
But I can't agree with him that I want all peremptory challenges eliminated
And why do you think Thurgood Marshall Justice Marshall
Went straight to no print Justice Marshall concluded that
He did not have faith in America
To be able to make these kind of
And
I understand why you concluded that
And you do you have that face
I still do
And how long that will last I don't know
But I still do right now
Robinson says that
To give up on these parentheses is like giving up on who we might be one day
Because of
Who we are right now
That's
Conceding
That we are so divided by race that we will never be able
To try and fix it
And I'm not prepared to concede that
Okay one last thing for my trip to Louisville
What's up Shane
All right
Thunder blew me away
But I'm Joe Gutman I'm a teacher at Central High School
Also an attorney at law
I'm James Batson truck driver and
Construction worker amongst other things
I probably should add that on the
Former prosecutor
Best suitcases
Joe gottman and James Batson those two people whose conflict in a courtroom back in 1983 gave us the bathroom
They are now in 2016
Prince
I'll talk to him about time you have to
Yep we're friends now how often is it that a prosecutor becomes friends with someone
He helped convince
Not not often I mean retired from a
Prosecuting Austin 2001
Ed Cena
Too many awful things
To make a long story short it was time for me to do something else
And starts teaching at a high school in Louisville
80% black
Where do we wear
Posing drug testing covered on Asuna side
Jackson
Well drug testing in schools
Seems like a good idea but in actuality
So the day I visited Joe gottman's classroom which is like a full-on Mach
Courtroom in a classroom
He's doing his mock trials with
Not be allowed in school
School says no funding for what it's all said and done
I would prefer to be known
More 4
The accomplishments in this
Classroom
Jennifer Batson
As for James a baton case
Eventually died from illegal
Activities
Andy Roebuck
War on jail
Concept
Me trying to get people
Stop doing crime
And the books actually how they
To sort of met up again one day a few years ago
James came to Jose school to give him a copy
He gave me a copy of his book and asked me if I'd look over it I wanted his opinion on it I read the book that night actually
And he got
50 books
Into the school system here in Jeff
County now
What happened in the past is in the past
30 years ago he did what he did I did what I did
Let It Go
As far as a legacy the Batson challenge goes it's really interesting to hear them talk about it
Especially because
In the eyes of a lot of people who know these issues
Joe was a villain that was always the painful part about
Decision advances
Is the label of being erased
Prosecutor
What does that mean
Well that was a horrible label
Yeah I mean so horrible
Butt bouncing
Started
Anita discussion and Anita change
On jury selection in America
Can maybe I was just
They're Weatherby fate or whatever
But this was the start
Change
Suning
Take it for what it's worth
But
Maybe if Robinson's right we can look at all this
And
Have a little
Tiny Buddha
I think
Baby.
Shawn Robinson
More perfect xidan Shawn Kemp more perfect
Tobin low
Kelsey Padgett
Kennedy Mills
With
Soren wheeler Elie mystal David Herman Alex overington Karen Duffin Sean rameswaram Katherine Wells Barry Fink
Michael and Michelle Harris
Special thanks to
Hila Klein
Julie Cole
The Charles
And Sarah
Supreme Court audio is from
Free law project
Collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell more perfect is funded in part by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation The Charles
Evans Hughes Memorial foundation and
Ridgeway sound