Play this is jazz
So more perfect season 2 is
Nearing to a close
You got this episode you're going to hear
One big one app
Holidays and then we're basically done
Start to think about season 3
Can actually want to ask for your help as we look forward
Baidu
More perfect
Is an
Nitro's organically out of Radiolab we were doing these stories about
Law
You know like 60 words
We're like to do more of that
So we did
Ultimately we created the space where
The idea was could we take these
Massive topics like guns
Gerrymander
Affirmative action just to name a few from the season
Recover them in a way that was still kind of
Human
Surprising
Cinematic
We had this amazing team
Borders
Fact checkers
Researchers
Mosers
To make this series and here we are thinking about season 3
I need to ask for your help
In order for there to be a season 3 and Beyond
We need some folks to step forward right now and help us pay for the cost
Of making another season of more perfect
Radiolab do this but if you are new to this it's really no mystery it cost money to make this
Series
Taipei the incredible team that we've hired
To get them on planes
Make sure they have equipment
Payroll Studio cost the band with all of it cost money
This
Is a deeply reported highly produced
Situation
It's not just two dudes in a studio
So here's the simple pitch 75 bucks
Can you do it
75 bucks
Text adopted
To help us pay for another
Season of more perfect
Go to radiolab.org more perfect click on the Donate button
That's radiolab.org more perfect the Donate button or
Here's an easier way
Text the word perfect the number 70101
That's the work perfect and number 70101 ticks just a few seconds
If you dig the series
We got to hear from you
Thank you very very much
Here we go
Rihanna
Set up the Supreme Court of the United
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
Okay ready this is more perfect ride here with Julia Longoria
Hello hello Julia
Hi so we've been getting this question
From listeners and it's something I've always wondered
To listening to the
To the song we just heard the Oye Oye
Who is that man
Who's singing so like soulfully and rhythmically
And
We
We look
I understand that in your retirement you might be doing some
Dancing
I dance now
Least
Once a week
Fussbot 3 hours
Alfred Wong Marshall the Supreme Court from 1976
Before
He's a New Yorker son of Chinese immigrants
He earned a bronze star medal in World War II
And worked in the White House
And
Beloved
To dance what style
Where are you
Watch other people dancing
Steal some of their steps
I understand. Even given a lesson or two at the court
Apparently he thought some Supreme Court staff how to ballroom dance
What does bidding
Because as the Marshal of the Supreme Court
Part of his job
If you keep time on the time keeper
Oral argument at the Supreme Court is a bit like a dance
Each side generally gets
1/2 hour
When lawyer starts It Off
As soon as he starts to argue or she
It's a countdown clock
That first lawyer presents to the 9s
And the justices
Kind of lead
They interrupt
Acting Quest
When it gets down to about 5 minutes
Atraso squid
A white light appears on Electra
When the first floor finishes
The other lawyer gets
Return same thing
Represent justices ask questions
Batiste lawyer only gets
30 minutes
Now
That is the
Nightmare former
For many many attorneys login
When they run out of time
Put the red light
No excuses
You have to stop
Okay well that's a mystery solved
So the thing I want to talk about today is
The dance that Alfred Wang presided over
Sometimes
It gets
A little
Dicey
Okay so I
Was working on her episode about Ruth Bader Ginsburg
By the way is called sex it feels too few EPS back definitely take a listen
And I was listening to an oral argument after oral argument
After oral argument and I noticed something
I kind of sent me down this rabbit hole
Okay so I'm going to present you what I have as a mini
Episode
Till I get to 11345 West
Picture against the University of Texas
Assisted Austin and the story starts
With this
Yes I am I'm sitting in my living room
On my couch
Members of course I'm listening on my computer to the oral argument
Central issue here
Is weather the University
His name is Dylan schweers
The lawyer now but at the time he was a second-year lost
A JD candidate
At Northwestern pritzker School of Law
And the case itself doesn't really matter for our purposes
What matters is the rhythm of the conversation
Neptune
To test
Strict scrutiny
You have the lawyer but Ryan making his case
The traffic and then you
Because the clutch is supposed to raise it on its own in this case Ruth Bader Ginsburg
I'm sitting there listening
Dylan doesn't think much of this particular moment because he knows from his Professor I'm Tanya Jacoby I am a professor of
Buffalo at Northwestern
Pritzker school of law that interruptions are just
Part of the deal the justices do interrupt The Advocate
Constantly the.
Suffix
The rule is that the justice
This is our loud
To interrupt
The blow lead lawyer
But not the other way around there is this rule that says
Directly if a Justice begins talking you as The Advocate
Cease talking immediately lawyers are not allowed
To interrupt
Which is why
I was listening
This other moment really cut his ear
It's a moment where the lawyer Burt Ryan is talking
Am I your steps in
Mary Hughes
Skirt back down
In Greece
Sufficient
But then
You still haven't
Get away from them
Give me another
Well I say
Start to kind of bicker
And Justice Sotomayor are essentially having an argument amongst
Styles going back and forth back and forth
Virtually
Rex.
So much so
Vet
Justice Sotomayor said let me finish my point
Say let me finish my point
That is a
That to me was very striking
He's right
For their edges
Chelsea's a subordinate walking into their house
He's like that's against the rules
It keeps listening
They start to notice that this moment
Kind of keeps happening
Does a critical mass
Again and again the female justices just keep getting interrupted
And I just
I could not believe the amount of times it happened I'm I remember I opened up a word doc and I wrote
And said term paper idea
Men interrupting women on the Supreme Court
At this point my ladies in the house might be thinking
Okay Dillon
Gambling is going on in here
Real shocker my fiance about this I think she would describe the whole thing as ironic
So I'll let you know I mean the skull is from linguist
Two psychologists of showing that women get interrupted
In pretty much every forum
What's so striking about a DS
Is that
Health information
Oh I'm sorry that I
Yeah so men interrupting women not exactly front-page news but
No one had ever done a systematic quantifying of this phenomenon on the Supreme Court
So what you decided to do was
A call the audio from Supreme Court years 2004 to 2015
Into the computer
This is hundreds of thousands words
Into the computer word transcripts not actual audio but whatever and they did hand code a few additional years including one
Sandra Day O'Connor was on the court
But to identify the actual Interruption points
How to computer look for dashes
Every time anyone gets interrupted on the Supreme Court
Two little dashes pop-up in the transcript
So Tanya and Dylan create an algorithm
That would be able to count
The dashes that were interruption
Let me guess let me guess meme
The female justices were interrupted the the most number
Well technically no
Really the most
Number of interruptions actually happened between two men
Scalia and
Did not get along
General bases
Except
Houston
The state
Justice League
Portuguese
Justice Scalia who died last year than conservative brierley liberal
He spent about 21 years on the court together
During that time they were constantly up in each other's
And
Justice Scalia interrupted Justice Breyer four times more often than any other individual Justice
Except for Justice Breyer who was interrupting Justice Scalia has twice as much
Rosso ideology transgender that's kind of don't know
Hopeful no no no
Because that's fat between Breyer and Scalia
It's really an operation even though these two men were
We interrupt each other
Inovalon
We still managed to find a very large Ginger fact
So when they compiled all of the interruptions together
+ reaching back
Toq years when Sandra Day O'Connor was on the court
They looked at how many interruptions were happening to the female dresses
It's versus the men the women are Interrupted about
3 times as much as the average man
Three times as much
1%
Tus temperature
I simply waited with an expectation that we would see that patent
But I think that what's really surprising is that our impression that the
The Advocate
We interrupting the just
And that that was gendered
Meaning the male lawyers the lowly lawyers
Even they felt they could interrupt the female dress
But that was shown to be
Systemic
Was really shocking because
Speech patterns
Like interruptions are a product of dominance
And so men interrupt a lot
Because they have
Traditionally been dominant within Society
But that means that if a woman is an imposition of
Clearly demarcated higher power than the man then the man should not be interrupting the woman
And in terms of the justices interrupting each other was there one master interrupter
Yes in fact absolutely
See if you can guess who that is
Interrupting RBG
He is the Swing Vote
Considered by some to be the most powerful man in America
Justice Kennedy
Hands down
He interrupted the female justices the most
Which
If the number of interruptions is any indication
You might be under the impression that his opinion is more important than everybody else's
On the court
Which is
Rude but maybe not wrong he was number one and then he was followed by Justice Scalia and
Chief justice rehnquist
We have some great examples
One of my favorites is he in trouble
Timer three unrelated
Justice Ginsburg
Suppose there were three unrelated case and then Advocate stops responding to him and then about
30 seconds 45 seconds later he says
Interrupted Justice Ginsburg I inadvertently interrupted just
And then went on to ask another
There is another
Great example
When
I was with Justice O'Connor
Dresses
Scalise's question and I think
Rochester Turner's asking to
Justice Kennedy chimes in and says
I think this gets to what Justice
Sister Connor was that
Is your answer
The last time
But then went on with his question so even if it wasn't really what you was trying to get it he had a good idea what just
What's Ohio's saying
What is Justice O'Connor doing message
So
Don Antonio actually found in this linguistic analysis
That woman's
Faced with this
Garage
Interruption
They've actually
Found ways
Whether consciously or not
To adapt
And almost
Fight back
But how about we talk about that after the break
I'll remind you again for your turn back
Julia story that
We here at more perfect restore appointing are bow at
Season 3
Lama temple season 2
But we need your help
We need help
Paying for some of the cost of producing another season
Of more perfect
If you have done anything in the last 11 and 1/2 episodes please stand up show your support go to radiolab.org
Slash more perfect
Or
You can text the word perfect to the number 701 or one that's
The word perfect
The number 70101 Texas
It's a few seconds
Super appreciate it
We can't do this without you
All right
Back to the store
This is more perfect MCAT up and brought here with Julia Longoria
We're talking about interruptions on the Supreme Court so if you are one of these female justices
Who and you're incessantly getting interrupted by the man
I'm curious like how how did the female justices adapt
SoDo Netanya noticed
That
When women first
Get on the court
They do this
Thing in there
They caught the lights
They ask if they can ask a question
May I apologize for asking questions
But may I ask you a question
And during that time
The man who jumped
Justice Kagan
Let me just finish this gets interrupted again and again and again
Can I ask and then
I don't know not really you can't
But over time
Tanya and Owen find that eventually
The female justices
Find a way to adapt
Situation
What we didn't notice overtime is that
Their use of that language
Definitely.
All four of the women
Sure
Significant reductions in the use of that flight language
Some of the justice
Was never quite get down to the level
Mail
Speech most of the men into the court not using that language much at all
Ruth Bader Ginsburg
Having been on the court the longest out of all the women
Seems to be
Very good at
What was the first reason for
Nothing more direct
So instead of saying
May I ask
You're jumping it
Understand can you point to the statute
Where's that
Or where should we disagree with the lower pinyin
Have we ever
Analyzed
Question a Justice will
The temperature dropped and the woman will just continue talkin
And often when the floor
Why do women start to behave like men exact
Which
Tends to fend off interruptions
2 points
Take the case of Sonia Sotomayor
Coward
And targeting
She is a woman Supreme Court Justice
Latina
End
In a lot of ways she should actually be
Owning the anti interruptions game of all the female Justice
She's the one that adapted most
Quickly to the less polite
Dial instead of speaking like a man most quickly and I think as a result is seen as aggressive
A terror on the bench nasty
Overly aggressive
A bit of a boy blunt
Even pulling
Will her Infamous have her that some of talked about who practice before her flare up at all today
Sonia Sotomayor
Roseanne Barr
And so I've had a lot of people
Odessa
Sotomayor she's very aggressive
She told sloth
And the numbers that released
She talks about as much as the average man
Sotomayor is also the woman who gets interrupted
The most
So you're still have your damned either way right
Now
Maybe the most
Surprising
Think that they found in this study
Is that as more and more women join the court
First you just had Sandra Day O'Connor
Nrpg joined
Today you have Sonia Sotomayor and Elena Kagan
You think
The men might get used to it
Am I cool it on the interruptions
And
No
It was
The opposite
Number of interruptions
Has
Increase
It's certainly as they're Movin On the cord
We can't say for sure that that's
The cause or effect
At the same time
But given that there is so much interrupt
Turn off women disc
Proportionately and the rate at which
Women are being entrapped
Just seems to be increasing
Play Lost Boy years since they've been three women on the car
It does seem to be
In line with other research in areas such
Congress and the boardroom
It show that as more than
Into the traditionally male domain the men become a
Actually more aggressive
They're probably getting used to the idea
Refute I could women
They can live with that but as the numbers increased who you know
Significance to reality
In the men's.
In a really
Talking to women
Life
It could be that there's a soda pump that eventually get over
Maybe if we have half a
The courting women
Eventually the men would settle down and get used to the idea
Maybe
RBG get this question all the time
At the most senior woman on the court
When do you think
It will be enough
Will there be enough women on the court
And my answer is
When there are nine
Thank you Julia
You are welcome
Thanks also to Tanya Jacoby and Dylan schweers we've got their study at radiolab.org
Flash more perfect
Supreme Court audio is from Oye a free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Leadership support for more perfect provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation
You'll have one more more perfect
In season 2 that will come to you after the holidays
While you're in the holiday mood
We are trying to raise money to
Make another season of more perfect
Please if you have enjoyed this episode or any of the episodes the American pendulum 122
The giant one we did about the Second Amendment
Citizens united enemy of mankind any of the episodes we put out
If you enjoy those episodes
They spoke to you in any way if
They taught you something about how this crazy-ass
Fitworks
Step Up
Help with paying for the next season
Radiolab.org more perfect click the Donate button
Or
Text the word perfect to a number 70101
That is the work perfect
The number 701
And on behalf of everybody here more perfect
Thank you
Riding with us on this