Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
Our story today starts couple years back
On February 26th
Washington DC
You know we we got up very early that morning
This is February I believe so it's pretty cold
And I tell you we were sitting there
Announcer the cavernous
You know empty Metro station rehearsing
Guy says he has been Ryan Clayton went through what they're about to do over
And over and over
It was very helpful to serve go through go through and go through it
Two incomes to help on a train ticket a couple stops
Get out walk
Blocks
Crosby Street and then walk
Up the marble steps
Supreme Court and then we have to wait in line
Get through security
And you're trying you know you're trying to just be
Be cool once they're inside they pretend not to know each other and then you know you get brought into the chamber
My first time ever being inside
They take their seats in The Spectator section
Look around
And it's such a grand
Kind of intimidating
Space
There are these red velvet curtains
The back
If you look up marble
Carvings
On the
The walls and the ceiling
And on the North and South walls there are these huge portraits
Great lawmakers through history
Moses
Hammurabi
John Marshall Muhammad
So I was just taking all of that in
Feeling feeling the butterflies
And I had to send
That it was very much doable
Avengers just waiting
Eventually the court-martial comes out says a few words
About how it works
When you're in there and not
Speaking so on and then finally
The nine justices enter the room
Almost like priest on a cloud
The robes
Whispering around them at that point tried to meditate son just
Be smart and stay cool and then Chief Justice John Roberts speaks
1211 84 octane Fitness vs icon Health & Fitness Incorporated
In case case self is not important
A florist make their arguments or no further questions your honor side Orchard to a pharmacy
Thank you, so that's all Ryan make his motion and I was just
That point just sort of thing
Like the practice in the sense of Readiness in
You know a little bit of sort of rock and roll Han Solo spirit
You know just say like
It's game time but you got to do this thing
And I stood and said
I rise on behalf of the vast majority of the American people who believe that money is not speech
And that our democracy should not be for sale
I saw the security coming towards me from the left and like people getting up and I'm so depressed
Dashing through the chairs protected me from behind a Medicare hug me and then pulled me back
To those people
Kai Newkirk was arrested he spent the night in jail
Later pled guilty to three misdemeanor charges
But no one had noticed Ryan
No one had noticed they were together that Ryan had secretly videotape the entire episode
So when D-Day session was over and Ryan went home
And posted the video on YouTube
The story
Just went crazy
To the role of money in politics
Because almost no Outsider had ever gotten a camera into the court supposed to happen
Antonio cameras are banned from the court
Highest court in second Bill Gaul
The gall
Of someone to walk into that esteemed chamber and do that to those esteemed justices
And by the way
Just once
Still hear arguments first this morning in case 1313 to know the Supreme Court action that we didn't February 2014 was the
First but not the last
Thank you Miss
Chief justice
There's a fifth anniversary of citizens united there were seven people who did as destruction
This is from January
21st 2015
Security again rounds of protesters
Chief justice Roberts tries to laugh it off please
The same gun you can sort of hear Justice Ginsburg
Trying to figure out like how many how many protesters are in the room
Over the next
You're so
We did
More actions next one
April 1st 2015
See if there's another
Justices Scalia and Thomas murmuring to each other
Please
Can you adjust the time I say I think that's the same dude is the last time
Kind of hard to hear over the yelling at you can sort of hear Justice Scalia lean over to Thomas and say we should throw these people in jail face
Anyone else interested in talking will be admonished that it's within the authority of this court to punish such disturbances by
My criminal contempt
Optari
You do it
So here's why we started the story this way over and over again the protesters call out one case
20 most controversial cases in American history
It was decided on January 21st
To a good chunk of America that was the day that corporations
To control of American democracy
It is the Dark Ages
It is our Dred Scott I would suggest a
Revolution
But a revolution against the corporation the corporations that make all the guns and the bullets
Get rid of citizens united and its pernicious effect on our electoral system
One of the worst
Supreme Court decisions ever
Position of the United States Supreme Court in the 21st century
So this season of more perfect
We're rethinking a lot of the most hated Supreme Court decisions in this one citizens united is definitely that
It is widely Lowe's across the political Spectrum
We got curious
Why why is it hated so much what exactly is
Why was it decided the way it was decided that turns out that last question
Gives you a unique window
Did not just how the Supreme Court works but Inside the Mind
Of arguably the most powerful man in America
Rihanna
Set up the Supreme Court of the United
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
Okay so the story of citizens
United
Begins with a landmark film from the corridor
A small town America
And I have mores some people call you in a week
I call you my base
It is summer 2004 commercials for Fahrenheit 911 are all over the place
The true story
And if you've seen documentary you know it's very critical of then-president
George W bush
For leading America into war based on
False intelligence
In the commercials when you looked at them they they came across this highway
Political and in highly effective
This is Michael Bowes he's one of the 3 B's
Important to the story
Know at the time that he was seeing these ads to his eye they came across as a
Especially political because at the time
As president I'll said if you clear a national priority
Is for America
Over the past 3 years
American two-faced miniseries challenges
That summer
George W Bush was in a tight race with the Democratic nominee John Kerry which direction would John Kerry lead
Your actual political ads
George Bush's mistress
We're running wall-to-wall
John Kerry has
Weapons
Nearest country to ask for Fahrenheit 911 to do everything they can
Music did
Kind of
It kind of Blended right in
Fahrenheit 911
Late July
This is David bossie
Be number two in an interview that he gave to C-SPAN
I decided over the couple of weeks that Fahrenheit was out there that it just was having a lot bigger impact than
Even I wanted to admit
To this day Fahrenheit 911 is the top grossing documentary of all time
Inn at Summer of 2004 when the film was out bows and bossy were like a George Bush's down in the polls
This film has something to do with it
Italy decided to produce a documentary film
Bad
Essentially counters
Fahrenheit 911
The weed that he's talking about is the conservative nonprofit the embassy run
Called surprise surprise
Citizens united
David bossie B2 is the chairman and president of citizens united
Michael Busby one vice president and the general
And just for contacts
The guy started
Citizens united
Is behind one of the most devastating political ads
Of all time
Bush supports the death penalty for first-degree murder
Dukakis not only opposes the death penalty be allowed first-degree murderers to have weekend passes from prison
The Willie Horton ad in 1988
Prettymuch tank Michael Dukakis presidential campaign
Daniel
After Bo's embossing saw how successful Fahrenheit 9/11 was and more importantly
How much precious airtime the movie Zathura
They thought
Let's do this we went out and we found
The best filmmakers in Hollywood they could do this let's make a movie
Who produced it
It was called Celsius 4111
The temperature at which the brain begins to die
You know liberal rain seduced by
Michael Moore's movie and then we wanted to run
Television ads
Promote that
But
We run into that problem
A big fat
Problem
The f
E
The Federal Election Commission which by the way was created in 9
1974 after
Shearwater Bay
We're basically
You had campaign money
Funding
A crime
Okay to the FEC came about post-watergate to basically regulate money and election
Money from corrupting policy
And he was like
Look your ads
Do not qualify
Can't do it
Cuz even though you are a non-profit you cannot use your corporate piggy bank IE your Treasury
To put ads on the air cuz remember that law do we have John McCain won his battle for campaign Finance
Form the 2002 bipartisan campaign Reform Act
Also known as mccain-feingold
Restrict
The use of corporate money directly
Before our guests Kennedy
Medela Avicii said if you ran ads you would be violating that law
Which boss eb-2 was like
Hey wait a minute
This guy is running TV commercials
Which in my opinion were a lot better than John Kerry's commercial
Trying to make George Bush look bad
Why the F does he get to run ads we don't
The fcc's responses like
He's
Media
You can run ads on TV because he gets a media exemption you
You're not media
U-Haul corporate
So at that point in time
We decided
That we would get in the documentary filmmaking business
So citizens united producers broken promises the United Nations at 60
It's very difficult for Outsiders to understand about the UN has how ill-prepared and untrained most of
Sapphire
Border War the battle over illegal immigration
That same year
Basic children
Mapreduce ACLU
At war with America
Goodbye 2008
We had a substantial history
Of making documentary films that we had made
Over that period of time
Several have won awards
Any of that's word to January 2008 United States is heading into another presidential
Election in the two candidates on the Democratic side
Barack Obama
Of course Hillary Clinton and Barack Obama
Citizens united Productions that's their nonprofit movie production wing
Made a new phone
Vindictive
Avenal
Ideological
Intolerant
Super subtle it's called Hillary
The movie she is
Steeped in Comfort
Mercy steep
Insley
Guess what we faced the same obstacle that we faced in 2004
Bows and bossy you can make the movie
You just can't let anyone know it exist
I was forbidden to advertise
Again this was because of mccain-feingold advertisements paid for with
Corporate money couldn't go on TV or on the radio 30 to 60 days
Before an election or Primary School don't understand
Mccain-feingold
Criminalizing political speech
My lawyer told me I would be
Indicted
And put in prison for five years
/
Count
Meaning every time they found a violation I could be put in for
It's so so
We decided to not let the FEC the Federal Election Commission
Come for us
We actually sued that
Razoo
Where are we Sue
This is Jim Bob
B3
He is in Indiana bass campaign Finance
Thank you mister chief justice and may it please the court case to Federal Court
We lost
They lost
They appeal
Direct me to the Supreme Court
And Wallah will hear arguments today in case you're awake 205 Citizens United versus the federal election
Commission
Right so we're in the courtroom now
Bright
Participation in the political process
Eastbay
Unsurprising argument
This is journalist and author Marcia Coyle she says you had the lawyer for the bees
Taking a very strong position by not allowing us to run our ads for Hillary the movie
It's wrong and you're violating our first amendment rights
In the case that you consider today
It is a felony
For a small nonprofit corporation
To offer interested viewers
In 90 minutes
90 minutes documentary
90 minute documentary 90-minute documentary
A 90-minute documentary documentary
90 minutes
90 minute documentary
90 minute documentary documentary
90 minutes documentary
90 minute documentary when you hear a certain word over and over and over it just turns into mush
90 minute documentary documentary it happens all the time when you listen to Supreme Court or are
Argument documentary
It is opening statement Ted Olson
Said that word
Documentary anytime
It just started to sound so weird but the point he was trying to make by saying it again and again and again
Is it citizens united
Was making a documentary
Things that are important to the public they were not
Quote
Oceaneering electioneering
It's another hour to hear over and over again music
But what it means is like camping advocacy and there are certain words
Eight of them actually words and phrases like vote
Elect
Support
Cast your ballot for vote against
Defeat
Reject
Those words are the functional equivalent of those words according to the court
Suddenly make something advocacy electioneering and therefore
Regulated
But citizens united said look this is a movie about Hillary Clinton in a we don't say Vote or don't vote
Sold on DVDs
We're trying to
Disseminate the movie to an independent fire who will then offer it
They threw HBO movie
Definition of robust
Uninhibited debate
About a subject of intense political interest
Set the First Amendment
Is there
To guarantee
Is there elephants the film
Pretend liberal justices like David souter were like
Come on really a government's brief over open up ages 18 and 19
What's a quotation
Do anything
Qualifications not qualified as Commanders
A long discussion
Of the record
Qualification
History and conduct of someone who was in the political Arena so they go back and forth for a while
Was citizens united just making an elaborate campaign ad
The distinction between the 10-second
Commercial
And say the 90 minutes
Infomercial
Like how can you tell is it about length is about who's doing the speaking blah blah blah
As Marshall said this part of the argument
Unsurprising
Thank you counsel
Then
The government
I got time to do justice
And made it please the court and this is where things really start
My turn
So the government lawyer Malcolm Stewart gets up there and he says these ads for this movie and this movie
Are clearly
Come on
The court should find an ad is the functional equivalent of Express advocacy
Only if the baddest acceptable of no reasonable interpretation
Appeal to vote for or against
Pacific candidate that's a very complicated way of saying if you watch the damn movie it you just can tell it looks like an addict
It smells like an added to that in the past the candidates would have
Are frenchtons 3 minutes
Infamous
So that's all fine and good but then
Walmart heirs and advertising
If it says we have
Candidate action figures for sale come by them
That counts as an electioneering communication place at the right time that would be covered
Chief justice Roberts
Required
Congress to draw the line work
Lessor testing malkin-stuart probing
How far the government can go
Like if the government is allowed to say like that thing you're doing is an ad therefore it should be taken off the air at certain times
Where's the limit to that
Like what if the add as the government defines it is in
DVD or a buck canadain just yank those away to the Constitution permit
The Restriction of all of those as well
Apply the electioneering communication restrictions
And it's here where like you almost here the conservative justices be like
A book was published
Campaign biography that was
The functional equivalent of
Express advocacy
All that could be ban
I'm not so you could be bad I'm saying that Congress could prohibit
The use of corporate treasury bonds and could require a corporate
Name
One use of the candidates name
It would be covered
Correct
500 page book
Vote for
The government could ban there
Look at search for exit would be Express advocacy
And it would be covered by the federal election campaign act at this point
Out of this trap Springs
First Amendment protections
Question is obviously
Not presented here
The back down your position is the time of the Constitution
The advertising for this book
The book contains the functional equivalent of Express advocacy
What happens is
They eventually get him to say
And at the end it says
Vote for
X
Yes or position would be that the corporation could be required to use pack funds rather than General Treasury
If it didn't we could prohibit the publication of the book you mean the government
Kanban books
Being ate out in the courtroom and hearing that answer well it was stunned silence
Best kimbap b3v idea
That
Anything the government could do
Could amount to Banning a book
You know sent a shockwave through the courtroom and that's Jeffrey toobin from The New Yorker
He was also in the audience that day deep dark
Kind of
Secret
It was now exposed to the
To the light a day to the public
Did they really were in the book Banning
Book burning
Business
The question of the book
Underlines
How difficult it is when the government gets into regulating
A political speech
Jim
Malcolm Stewart kept protesting like no no no no no you're not understanding
Could prohibit
Did use of corporate treasury bond is not about banning political speech it's about regulating the money
Used to make that speech cuz if we don't sometimes do that some voices will be way too loud but okay that's
You know that's a find
Fiction
In the minds of the average
Person
And it's a distinction she says it just got lost that day
The precedent that you yourself say
What extender Banning the book
Assuming a particular person pays for
I think the court is already held in
Boston and Kim McConnell vote Congress
Coming up
We go behind the scenes into the mines actually of the justices
As they deliberate backstage about what to do next
And things get kind of weird
In the Supreme Court today a debate about the movie
Sort of
Producers of a
Withering 90-minute movie
Hillary Clinton
Argued that part of the
Mccain-feingold campaign-finance
Is unkind
Alright so after oral arguments wrapped up the justices retreated
To what is perhaps the most
Secretive
Place
In the known universe
In the most private and perhaps important place inside the
Supreme Court
For lease inside the court.
And only then
Meet together around a table in the Justice
Is conference room
They discuss the cases
Heard an oral argument
And begin the process
Of reaching a decision of the Court
This is a place where cameras will never go
No one can enter the room
Except for some reason C-SPAN
UC spans feature documentary
The Supreme Court
What's 1 * C-SPAN those bastards were able to get into this room and film
The table
In the chair
I'm actually quite jealous cuz they didn't let us do that they didn't let us see
Special room or speak to the justices so she's been yeah
They have some kind of deal with the devil anyhow
When is we don't know
What happened in that room on that day but
We can piece together a couple of things
Imagine the rest of me we know that they went in
Clarence Thomas put on some tunes
RBG was like wow that book thing I need a drink
Actually don't know that either those two things happen but it makes sense to me the Clarence Thomas
Would like to do bees
I just feels
Right
But what we do know is that the Justice sat down in the usual order they said
The conference table in the same places every day
Chief justice Roberts gets things going with some discussion
Discussion
Pornography case
Save this cases
About this
The arguments are
7 spelling
I think we should reverse
So there's some conversation and then
Because again this is standard the Chief Justice called for a vote
This is the part we care about he
Presumably as his colleagues okay who here thinks it's citizens united has a case
Now we know that the four liberal justices
Steven Spencer Briar Suter
We're like no
They do not have a case
All that citizens united is doing is making a campaign ad this is electioneering
They're pretending it's a dark but really it's not they should be right here
On the other side
We know that the for conservatives
Scalia thomas alito Roberts
We're like yeah they got a case
Citizens United First Amendment rights are being pinched
Until you had a split
Like you often do on the score for liberals or conservatives but there are nine justices so as always
All attention turned
To the man in the middle
30 years
Is often the Swing Vote making his opinion critica
He is considered
The courts pivotal Swing Vote has basically split down the middle for 4
One ring to rule them all
All right let's just talk about Justice Kennedy for second he has been
The Swing Vote on this court
So many times that is often called the most powerful person in America
Because very often his boat
Is the only one that matters
You could argue that this one dude as determine more about your life
As an American
Can almost any other single guy
But
From the outside
People who don't really know much about the court II
Me you
Not maybe not you but me
It can be really hard to predict what he is going to do on any given case which way is going to swing
For example
Arabic voting rights case he sides with the conservative
The Marshall Plan was very good to the Morrill Act of Northwest Ordinance
It does
100%
Goes to the developer in
Now on gun rights the Heller case if you talk about
Aswan conservative
I view it as a general right to bear arms quite without reference to the militia either way but Environmental Protection
Is liberal greater than harm the greater the risk
Class action goes conservative
What is the unlawful
Gay marriage is liberal
Exercise the fundamental right
Sumerian Allstate
No longer may this Liberty be denied to them
I want to be
So
When the Chief Justice went around the room and got to Kennedy was like alright Kennedy what's a Gummy this time
From the outside
It was anyone's guess
But as I mentioned one of the Serta cool things about the citizens united
Case
Is it gives you a little window into the mind of this
Very powerful very mysterious man
So before you answers
I was wanting
Romania Bucharest Romania
In the days of communism
You may wonder why is there an Eastern European man in the brain of Justice Anthony Kennedy that'll make sense to men
For now all you know is that this is Alex Kozinski he's an influential judge
Is it in the 9th circuit in California
It was actually a party member it was a member of the party before the war
Truly believe in communism if I was a great system and
How to remember the moment
When he was at his dad's office because I was about 7 years old or 7 or 8 or something and my father wasn't there
But a couple of other companies officials were and as her standing there Alex picks up a newspaper starts reading it was a newspaper
Called free Romania
And so I
Read free Romania
And then I ain't so sure I've sent to be funny I guess I said well I don't know why they called kilmainham because there's so many people in prison
You just thought he was making a joke my father into very serious trouble
The officials essentially threatened his dad
Because of this job question was whether the they were teaching me
Disloyal things at home
Eventually they clear them but it was it was touch-and-go
So after that my father had this signal he says if you're ever in public with me and
You say something and you hear me
Pinching my nose and sniffing
You just stop talking whatever it is you're saying you
Are you going to give an explanation you don't continue just
Stop docker
Years later
Alex Kozinski would leave Romania leave communism behind come to California
Become a lawyer
Then a clerk clerk in Sacramento for Anthony Kennedy
Who was the new judge on the ninth circuit
He says he told Anthony Kennedy the story oh yes
And they talked a lot about what it's like to live in a place where you can't speak your mind of course I know who knows
What exact effect has had on Anthony Kennedy's mine but we know
That story is in there my honor
I will do my best
Mixed in with all the cub scout oath service reviews
Sights and smells of Sacramento California where I grew up
Of course mixed in with all the Catholic church services
Stuff from me know summer spent in Austria teaching
So we know that story was in there was a we also know
Did a certain point growing up Anthony Kennedy read a book
The really large this hat 1984
One of those important
Works ever written 1984 of course of dystopian novel
By George Orwell
Kennedy talks about it all the time and speeches 1984
The dictatorship is always surveilling you
Trying to control your thoughts
You are so friendly
A1984 has one of the most brilliant themes in literature
The protagonist is being tortured
Chewing the writing you know.
Freedom is the freedom to say two plus two equals four
I probably can't stand the pressure anymore
Okay to intuos5
But the torture continues is it why you continually
The torture continued
Not until you just say it but until you believe it
Wichita
Already
This is
Powerful reminder
The government want to plan your destiny they want to plan what you think
Never happen
So clearly
Inside
Anthony Kennedy's mind
Maybe this is as close to an ideology as he has he's often talked about as having
Very little discernible ideology will maybe this is it inside his mind
There is a fear
A timer
Beer
Of the government getting too close of it reaching its authoritarian tentacles into our
Alives
Carmine's
In our bodies
Framers
An idea which is
Central
To Western thought
This is how we put it at his Supreme Court confirmation Hearing in 1987
And that is
There
Is a zone of Liberty
Arizona protection
A line that is drawn
Where the individual can tell the government be on this line you may not go
Incel
To go back to the secret room
When chief justice Roberts asked Justice Kennedy
Alright Kennedy which way you going to swing
I imagine what he said
Accessing the word imagine is alright Mister chief
I know you think I'm a swinger
I know everybody else thinks I'm a swinger
But on this issue
I do not swing not only do I think the citizens united has a case
But I think that campaign Finance law that would limit their speech
Shut down government
Who did parkour and said that it was lawful to ban of book
We know that two things happened after Kennedy so they gave his answer to Let's Go Big Lots tear it down
We know that the conservatives on the court were like
I like where you're going with this and they started to gravitate to his side we also know the David souter
He was the justice
In court she lie about anything she's deceit
She's ruthless cunning
Sounds to me like campaign
Who is basically accusing citizens united
Trying to pretend they were playing politics really they were
We know that Justice souter
Got really pissed
Because if we go into David suitors mind his room within a room
The view is very different
David souter is a New Englander
Quiet
Focus
Spend long afternoons reading
Walking through the silent Hemlock Forest
This is story that suitors home in New Hampshire was stacked with so many books that his house actually needed a new Foundation
Which is to say his reaction here was
Very out of character
By all accounts he was not
Happy because Kennedy's whole thing that Liberty is the law nothing should compromise that that for Suitor
Set up alarm Bells because
My exercise My Liberty to the
Greatest possible extent
I can suppress
The rights of a lot of people
That is souter a giving you talk in 2012 and what he means is that Liberty and equality
Have to be valid they both can't win all the way all
Corporate money just started pouring into elections
That's basically handing a mega
To the richest people in society
Does got2b
The possibility of
A limitation
Incorporation
So that they do not drown out
No we don't really know what David souter was thinking in this moment but I imagine I'm thinking forward
To everything that was about to happen explosion and political campaign donations
These two brothers are trying to buy America
Donald Trump essentially super Pacs are allowed to give unlimited fun
Billionaire hedge-fund Tycoon gets credited by many was playing an instrumental role in Donald Trump select
Action
Whatever he was actually thinking that moment
We know that
After Kennedy made his stance at let's go big
Justice souter justice souter
Wrote a very very
Strong draft
Descent a real Bridge burning
It's explosive I should coil Jeff toobin Jeffrey Rosen of the national Constitution say
He said that Kennedy's opinion is really an illegitimate use of the Court
Power the way the court was
Proceeding
Rick Braun suder accuses the court
Of the judicial activism
I'm taking
A narrow case
Pineal case but one teeny little film and then using it illegitimate
Lee as a hobby
To really rewrite the laws
Campaign Finance
He argued that this kind of move
Essentially makes
Them the court look like a bunch
Political hacks
Questioning the Integrity of the cord itself
Unfortunately we can't read that dissent that Sooner Road because his papers won't be public
Until 50 years after his death
All we know is that he most certainly sent a draft around to the other eight just
And then whatever
Didn't hold
Justice souter went to
That Bass
Keno
If we do this
Now
We will look bad your court
The Roberts Court
Real look bad
Someone described
His argument as
There are few institutional hot-button
That you press
In the courts.
And thanks
And justice
Suter was pressing one of those
Hot buttons
Apparently sing to a chief justice that your court is going to look bad is like
The Supreme Court equivalent of going nuclear
In the meantime we'll all this is happening you've got the 3 B's Bose bossy Bop
Baba baba baba baba
Does dying for an outcome in apparently every day we would go down to the court to see if they were going to
Issue decision in our case that
And of course each day
No decision
Yeah and it's now the end
Did June now we're down to the last
Day of the Court
10 a.m. June 29th
We're back in the car
Before
The justice
This is come on then
The clerk of the court
Walked into the courtroom and
Harrelson
He is if you were call the lawyer for the bees
And says I'm going to have to
Talk to you something
Later something unusual is going to happen
And pitocin that he told me later his first thought was uh oh
Did I do something wrong
The Marshall calls order
Honorable the Chief Justice
And the associate justices
Supreme Court of the United States
Oh yeah
Oyez oyez
The chief opens the session
And then in 1964 Congress enact
Kennedy recent opinion
In a different
And then RBG reads a dissent
But they had no vested right to promotion in a different
Get up there
What is fight does not
With an opinion in a different case
This is a strange resolved
But finally
Chief justice Roberts
Comes back in
And so the very last
Fasting
The teacher
Says before he
No ends
Term
Case number 08205 Citizens United versus the
The federal election
Is there will be reargument
Citizens united
Is set for reargument later this term
Bum
Chief justice Roberts Paisley says
We're not going to make up our mind today
The comeback
And talk about this again
And we're going to debated on Kennedy's term
Campaign Finance law mccain-feingold
Infringement of free speech
He says that
This is what happens next
Now we know it was sad
But this is the last session in which our friend and colleague
Justice David souter
Will be on the bench with us
Suitor
Is out
We wish him the best in his well-deserved retirement
On this occasion we have sent Justice souter a letter
That I will not read
Made it today
Dear David
We have all felt a profound sense of loss since the announcement of your decision to retire eventually he quote
What's the New England poet Robert Frost
Trade White marble for White Mountains
And return to your land
Easy wind and Downy
Oh you will not be among us
After he finishes
Justice souter Stern
Dear colleagues
You a generous letter is touched me more than I can
Say and I will only try to leave you with some sense of what are common Services meant tonight
He also quotes Robert Frost
You quoted poet
And I will too in words
Set out the ideal of the life engaged
We love
I need a one
Enterprise accounts for the finest moments of my life on this court as we have agreed or contended with each other over the
Those things that matter
Decent people in a civil suit
Society
419 fareham drive without life with you
All of us sharing our own desk to use with one another
Working side-by-side as fellow servants
Just friends
I will not sit with you at our bench again after the court Rises to the some of this time
But neither will I retire from our friendship
Which is held us together despite the
Full of the most passionate to send
Is made the work light us through all my tenure here
And for as long as I live
I will be thankful for it
And be under a very grateful obligation to each one of you
Alright let's be real I mean we cannot say for certain why Justice souter retired at that moment
Just a cigarette
For a long time that he didn't like
DC that he wanted to have
Time to hike while he was still vigorous enough to do it we also will probably never know exactly why Roberts
Held the case over for reargument what we do know
Is in holding the case over that meant suitors in
Flammatory Bridge burning descent
Would never be popped
The Roberts Court
Got to save face
And not have
This kind of in
Internal fight
Dirty laundry
Avoided the
Embarrassment
Would have come from
Application of this
Play fast forward a couple months
The court reconvenes one more time to hear the case the room is packed
Standing room only three arguments 08 2:05 Citizens United vs
Federal election committee
Commission
And here's the thing
Everybody knew what was going to happen
Against
And there's no flight plan on going to go with more dangerous than in the elections
The government
Silence
Corporate objectives
And those corporations may have the most knowledge
Issues and in your stomach during the election
He'll probably come as no surprise that
Kennedy is it a whole lot of talking all that carrying on and when the court finally decided the case
Landmark decision five
The four
K08 205 Citizens United vs the FEC
Is the first amendment has any for
It prohibits Congress from finding or jailing citizens or associations
Simply engaged
Political speech is indispensable to decision-making in a democracy
Because the speech comes from a corporation rather than an individual
The government seeks to use its full power
Including equipment
The command where a person to get his or her information
Or what disgusting stores here she may not here
This is unlawful
No obviously
La people are not happy about this decision the American people
Save the world sneaking and cameras and of the Court you had President Obama at the State of the Union
Free of law
But I believe will open the floodgates
Professional
Including foreign corporation
Basically calling out the justices who were right there in the audience
And they're sitting right in front of from there
At one point the camera Zooms in on Justice Alito
At least friends
Samuel Alito grimacing and mouthing the words
Not true
Speaking of true here's what's true
The upshot of this decision I think most people would agree is a Suitor was right Obama was right
70-year ton more money in politics
Citizens united has made it
Hospital
The exact amount of new money that flooded in is a little bit hard to measure
But what's pretty clear is that all those super back
Superpass that you hear about
Foxboro Mass
He does things where I like an individual can give an unlimited amount of money to get someone elected or not
Rogue billionaires
Putting money into secret group 6 of the citizens united decision basically threw gasoline on that fire
But before we get ahead of ourselves
Everybody hates this
Not everybody hate people who object to it I'm going off the deep end
I think I've lost my mind
I think they're not truly liberals
This is 9th Circuit Judge Alex Kozinski again he was the guy in Kennedy's head the case stands for the symbol
Position graph
When you band together with other people
You don't lose your freedom of speech
What other bi Union or
Association
Corporation you know a lot of
A lot of organizations to
Take the corporate form this is Michael Dorn
He's a professor of law at Cornell a former Kennedy Clerk
Even though he is critical of the decision he says you do need to keep in mind
Any opinion itself
Essex County points out that under the law as it was written
The ACLU would be forbidden from putting on its website
An essay
Promoting
The candidacy of a Pro free
Which candidate
The n-double-acp
He couldn't promote a pro civil rights case
Twitchy might argue with those groups are not
For-profit there should be a difference between not-for-profit and for-profit Slot The Washington Post
Is this a for-profit
CNN for profit
These are
Core
Tatoosh ins
Of our
Christy they're protected by freedom of speech by freedom of the press
So you say well okay so we're going to make it
Exception
Media corporate
What's a media corporate
Media corporations are often just
Divisions of other gigantic Corporation
For a while
Inbc was a
Division of General Electric
Does that mean that you're going to
Carve up
Which parts of their funds can go to the
Speech rather than to other parts
And do we really want to trust the government
To draw the line
Another it stings can get really complicated fast
Which is why Alex Kozinski
Funeral speeches funeral speech
Let's don't touch it keeps government away from it
And he says when the citizens united decision came out in perfectly right to me
Still seems absolutely correct
And I think I everybody who are all the people who object to it then
Being foolish
Now Justice Kennedy for his part 2 years ago
He was at Harvard Law School
School
And having what they call these public conversations with
The dean
What is students
I got up and asked him
Do you regret your
Vision
5 years later
Curious if you can stand by some of the assumptions that underlie your opinion there when you see all the money that has
Chord
To our elections
And he said
No
I don't regret
The decision
Certainly in my own View
What happens with money in
And in politics
That's not good
But it does
Sing to me
One thing has been
Disclosure people don't really have to worry because we have
Disclosure laws
And when these
Corporate contributions are being made
They have to reveal
Who they are
The funding source
This is something he actually talked about explicitly in his citizens united decision
Extensive
Disclosure
He told the students that transparency will protect you
It'll protect us
Did you live in this cyber age
You don't need to wait for 3 months after the election for a reporter
You can be done in 24 hours
The voters don't like the people are funny
Don't vote for
His point is it if you have the information you need to make a good decision
Nobody's Free Speech should be limited at all
And this is
Frankly
Perfect example of the kind of high-minded principal
That works
In reality
Not at all
No
I mean he's right
There are disclosure laws but they are really
Really easy to get around
For example right now I could write
3 million-dollar check to a 501 C 4 like
Citizens united
Or the NAACP for that matter and they would never have to tell anyone
That money came for me
I could just hide in the shadows
That's why this kind of donations are often called
Now there are people who could change this who can make
Disclosure and actual meaningful
Think
For example
The FEC is one of those places
V FEC
Could
Choose to fix all the loopholes
Require that all the money that's coming to politics in the wake of citizens united
The very least be identified
Is it the FEC is required by law
To have no more than three Commissioners be a member of
Party
Essentially want there to be balance between Democrats
And in this day and age what that means
Is gridlock
So with the idea of strengthening disclosure laws comes up
Stalled comes up
Install comes up
Installed comes up get stalled
Go years ago
Here's a little fun going to tape
Couple years ago two of the democratic members on the commission Gus
So frustrated
At the non action of this Commission
That they petitioned their own commission
To allow for public debate
About things like
Strengthening disclosure this is a recording of the open meeting of the Federal Election Commission held on June 18th
Today this is commissioner and Ravel to allow people to comment
Directly to the commission
About issues that are of great importance
To everyone
In this country
Unravel is a Democrat she and her colleague Ellen Weintraub
And as soon as I finish making their opening statements set device chair thank you
Thank you madam chair
One of the Republican members of the commission and got by the name of Matthew Peterson
Sad
Okay so you want to bring a petition but you don't look I'm looking in the rules here that says that only
Quote person
Can bring a petition
Definition of person
Excludes Taurus that does not include
The federal government or any authority of the federal government
That would seem to indicate that a commissioner acting in his or her official capacity
Does not qualify as
Is a person under a p
DesiRulez
I mean first of all let me say I
How not to leave
I thought you were actually going to take the position that I am not a person
I just said that a corporation is a person but I'm not a person
Around 11
CFR and I will
Stipulate that we're not in the room,
I'm sorry that I'm not a person
Another Deputy Commissioner Caroline Hunter falcon
Bathtub that has gotten my colleagues will not admit that I'm a person that
Really sweating because I'm a member of this commission I am not a person
Is just kind of dumping I didn't mean literally you're not a person course your first
Sing I think you're not an alien at least not today but
But
I asked the vice-chairman yesterday I said are you guys going to have a problem with this
Is it good I just finished my I didn't say that I was just going like this
If you don't put my head down I'll call on you now
Thank you I really do find it comical that you're going to
You are so opposed to having
Dim the public has opportunity to weigh in on these issues that you're willing to take the legal position that we're not person
I find it comical that
We got an email.
Getaway
It's ironic
Tyranny on the agenda thing but as I said I'm happy to consider the new proposals but I just don't like to do it on the net
Like this
This meeting is
Adjourn
Unravel one of the two Democrats you just heard you brought the petition
Resign from the FEC in 2017 she left out of
Frustration
And if the FEC is kind of useless when it comes to
Fixing is home money in politics
Sting
And if the courts of seventh chords of sad will where do we look for help
The IRS
Congress
Be more functional right
Right
Documentary documentary
Justice Kennedy documentary
Justice Kennedy
More perfect is produced by me
Alex overington Julia Longoria and sarkari
Shawn Hugo Elie mystal Cristian farias Linda hirshman David Gable and Michelle
Paris Supreme Court audio is from
Free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
It support for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes
Heroes Memorial Foundation
Thanks
Papa
Peppa Pig