Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
Leadership support for more perfect
Is provided by the Joyce Foundation
This is more perfect time Chad album Rod
So one of the big conversation sets
Just come out of
The Vegas mass shooting comes out of
Every
Unfortunately we are at
One a day here
It's like what is it
About America and guns
What is it that makes it so unique
When it comes to guns
Complicated question
Different answers I'm sure
Part of it
The obvious
Is it we have these words baked
Into our founding
Today we're going to tell you
Really surprised
Story of how those work
But how we came to read them the weight
Do we do now
Producer
Shaun Robbins firm takes from here
I think we should start with one of the most
Confusing sentences in the constitution in the Bill of Rights not We the People
Not that one I got a different one
A well regulated militia
,
Being necessary to the security
Of a free state
,
The right of the people
Keep and bear arms
,
Shall not being
Say one more time and do it do it with the comments
Sure a well regulated militia
, being necessary to the security
Of a free state
Oh, the right of the people to keep and bear arms
Totally unnecessary,
Shall not be in
Is that the one that's about guns
Adam Winkler who wrote the book
On the 2nd Amendment end of book is called gunfight he's a journal
He's a professor of law at UCLA
He said it's almost as a James Madison the author of the amendment I just discovered this wonderful new thing the, and why
Wanted to put it in there as many times
Which is like
Nrt professorial joke
But like seriously what is it in like
It has to be this one couldn't have been the amendment about like quartering soldiers in your house that was really confusing
They made like Jess
Indecipherable
And ever since
Generations of Americans have been confused
By the language of the Second Amendment
So when the singers written we had just fought this war with the British
This Revolutionary War
And they try to win it right from the get-go
Coming for our guns
So these new states are looking at this new federal government they're going
We don't know we want to trust you quite yet
So does the Second Amendment says
You guys can fight back
Like the feds aren't going to disarm you you can your malicious can keep you
Stats
I think we agree on
But then after that you just look at the sentence
That is not just a commas that are confusing
If you look at the sentence as a whole
Pieces don't seem to
Get together
There's some noun
I mean
It's obvious that the sentence is about someone's right to bear arms but who
Who get that right
At the beginning of the sentence
You got a well regulated
Militia
Demolition
States have a right to form militias
What's to assemble
Groups of people and those people got to have their guns
That's easy enough
But then later in the sentence
There's, the right of the people to
To keep and bear arms
, shall not be infringed
The people
Which people
Those people over there in the militia
All people
If you mean all people
Why'd you say militia
It's like
The first quasi
The point of some sort of collective right to bear arms
And the second clause
Seems to point to some individual right to bear arms supposed to be a popularly ratified document
It's actually not that easy to read
And it's not it wasn't that easy to read then
This is Jill Lepore staff writer at the New Yorker magazine
She's also a professor of American history
I studied 18th century
I'm really trying to the 17th and 18th century American political story
And Jill says
From the beginning when people thought about the Second Amendment they tended to just focus
On the first part that the primary motivation for the amendment is
About militia well-regulated
Militia
But this confusing sentence was
Widely read as the
This Collective
Militia right not an individual one truth that the Second Amendment fact guarantees the right of a
An individual to bear arms and that the government federal government
In any fashion
Juices that just didn't exist
I disagree with the way you characterize that
Although what you said is stated in the media frequently the Stephen halbrook he's represented the NRA in several
Okay so I've written several books on Second Amendment issues
He actually thinks
Hey the sentence is just
Fine as is I don't think it's complicated at all
The framers were thinking about an individual right to bear arms 2nd Amendment refers to the right of the people to
First Amendment refers to the right of the people peaceably to assemble
I mean who is that it it's individuals are not some kind of collective that doesn't exist in reality
So which
Which was it
That that's a really good question to add I mean
If it's complicated 1/2 what I can tell you is that
No people I spoke to for the story said
At least in the
20th century when the when the second amendment was
Taught in law schools
It was taught this
It was taught as a sort of
Antiquated
Outdated
Thing that has to do with malicious not so much
Individual rights
But
Tulip or Stephen halbrook and their respective side something they can both agree on
Is that this
Super sacred Second Amendment the third rail
Of our American politics today
That just was not
I think
It was not like that it was utterly ignored ignored
This amendment When I Was An undergraduate
Undergrad at Florida State University
When did the Florida Supreme Court and start looking up law review articles on constitutional law issues and I found that
There was hardly anything written about the Second Amendment
Except for the third amendment the zoo there was no amendment that was less written about less
Legislated less
Activated
Lessa subject of Supreme Court conversation
And the Second Amendment this is not to say people didn't think about guns
People had guns States regulated guns but for most of our history the Second Amendment
It was like
Heavenly sword of the runt of the Bill of Rights literally like no one argued about it it's a striking thing to think about
There was no fight no fight how surprising that is
Is giving its centrality to our
Political compass
What is
Extraordinary transfer
Because there was this
Window of time where
All of this
Changes that the script
Just flip
There's two hundred years
Of everything being chill
And then suddenly
You got
This
I want say those fighting words
From my cold
So basically in
The Flash the Second Amendment goes from being
Ignored to being you
Supposed to be Radioactive
And in the process we start to read the thing totally differently all of a sudden this is hot
Leave the beta thing that's got nothing to do with that first part and everything
To do
What II
Nothing you can do folks
And me
What are the Second Amendment people maybe there is I don't know
And what I want to know is how did that happen
How do we start reading the Second Amendment the way we do now
And and what I found out is that
In the modern history of the gun rights movement
And how we read the second amendment can be boiled down to these
Totally
Unrelated disjointed seeming
Revolutionary event
Am I underweight and invasion in Sacramento
Damn let me know what in the hell to a Revolt in Cincinnati Prudential do you have
Tell me I'm wrong and finally
Number three
A reckoning
At the Supreme Court of the United
Unbelievable
What is that
Cat sound
Can you imagine that
So you can tell me the story 3
Rihanna
Supreme Court of the United States
United States
Chapter one
The Invasion
I'm a carpenter I'm a builder I'm a stand-up comedian
Yes drama structure repairman high performance aircraft
Ideal electromagnetic field backlight non-destructive testing to the Gemini mission program
And I'm an expert shot
Guns
I was an expert shot with guns or novice
12 years old I was raised a hunter and a fisherman
Besides being a carpenter and a builder
When I'm 12 years old my father buys me a high-powered rifle
How to memo
I can knock a elephant down with that
You said I'm getting at
Can I get you to tell me it's so we had to start at some point I have you tell me just
Your name and who are we are and who who who you are
My name is Bobby seale I created the Black Panther Party on the founding chairman and National organizer the black
Standing right now
Where Oakland California
The Black Panther
So this transition from the militia to the individual my right to bear arms
You could argue that
That whole individual gun rights movement started
In the 1960
Cities with the Black Panthers
In Oakland
It's an unlikely and got a surprise in origin for what's known as individual rights interpretation of the
Second Amendment
Wewood different breed
I mean wheezing well-read guys we do I s*** we know I history just get some contacts as 1966
It's been
An exceptionally bad time for race relations all over the country
11 1500 people were in the
Attack dogs and hoses
And in particular major tension between
Black community and the police
The late 60s there were several high-profile incidents of Officer shooting unarmed black man
This is what was happening
You know and
What we did is that yet we took a position
October 1966
Barcelona spain Huey P Newton they start this organization called the Black Panther
Black Panther Party for self
Defense
Fue Bobby's co-founder if he was 2 years in law school
You was going to the University of San Francisco School of Law
And
One day he's sitting there as as you do law school thinking about the law
Think about Malcolm X
Thinking about what you can do in Oakland
And it hits
The Second Amendment of the Constitution guarantees
The citizen's right to bear arms on public property
But they can argue
That the Second Amendment gave them a right
Have a gun
He said pass a constitutional Democratic civil human right
In those who
Claim that the second amendment protects an individual right
Right to bear arms says people who argued that were in the minority
They want taken too seriously
Play this is one of the first times that the individual rights reading was forced
Into the mainstream because
We have a right to bear arms we individuals then
We control the police observe the police
Tell him that we I see you talk about controlling police
What do eagles do you in law school so what legal status do we have
Second half of the Second Amendment right of the people to bear arms
Possessing bear arms okay he also pointed to a California state law
It said you could carry a gun as long as it wasn't concealed
If the gun is not concealed is not illegal
So the Black Panthers started policing the police
We did
It would go out an armed patrols and follow police cars on 7th Street
West Oakland California a nightlife District a police officer
Sing from down the street
And the Crowds Are
The Gathering holding a gun
Can you see when it happened
What's a high standard going to cost 89 or $79 I bought the damn gun Isis here Huey
You got your shotgun now
White cop on one side of street arresting somebody
And the other side of the street you got a dozen black guys holding shock
Strictly for observation
Was standing in a line I had everybody standing in line
He told me
The moment the cop notice
Immediately stopped what he was doing with
The guy you pulled over
And walked over to them and said you have no right to observe me
And who is his no California state Supreme Court ruling states that every citizen has the right to stand and observe a police officer
Carry out the duties as long as it's not a reasonable distance away
A reason
Costumes 8 to 10 ft
What's an approximate 20 ft from you
Observe you whether you like it or not
He said man what kind of negroes are these
Let me see that gun no
You cannot touch my weapon
The cop says
Are you a Marxist and USA are you a fascist
Are you a Martian
Are you a fascist
Then the cops I asked you first
And you saying I asked you second
OU
I mean
It's like a standoff
And this is where the dominoes start to fall
Senate results
Diesel about the cops in Oakland are not happy and they
Family start
Running without the chain next thing we know
Got to protect
Society from nuts with guns
And I think we should act when we intend to act Mumford State Assembly representative Oakland
Just trying to put a bill in
Stuffed Black Panthers
Places
What does Bill the Mulford Act is up for debate at the California state capitol in Sacramento
And Bobby seale decides the Panthers
Be there for the debate and that they should take their gun
I took a delegation and armed delegation to the California state legislature May 2nd 1967
I have six women
N24 mail
How many guns
3 guns
And where they loaded
Yes
So they roll up the assembly in Sacramento
And guess who happens to be waiting for them right there on the front lawn of December
When we talkin what what year were talking to
I don't know who it was
Guy by the name of win one for the Gipper
I went up there
When we got there Ronald Reagan happened to be on the front lawn
Regan Regan
I did not know he was going to be there on the front line
He was on the front lawn
Future Leaders of America
Kids
So you got Ronald Reagan 50-60 feet from us
And a bunch of white kids 1112 hanging out on the front lawn of the of the State Building in Sacramento
And he said some of the kids come running Gun Club
Andalou press
Follow
What's going on what's going on
And Bobby seale cuz I'm going to read a statement the Black Panther Party for self-defense called upon the American people in general
And that's what I read the statement had a black people in particular
Take careful note
Are there races California legislature
Which is now considering legislation
And I keeping the black people just arms and Powerless at the very same time
Racist police agencies throughout the country
Intensifying the terror
Brutality murder and repression of black people
Etcetera
While he was reading that uniform Capital guards come running out grab Ronald Reagan
Took him in the opposite direction from us away from the kids
Okay
That's what we decided to go inside
Because the assembly was in session at the time
Next thing I know
We all loading
13 elevator
Used shotgun rifles pointing up
Camera NX
Crowded
Body touching body crowded
When they got off the elevator he asked him
Which way do The Spectator section
So the Panthers could
Watch the legislature debate the bill somebody says this way to the right
And so I walk into this door and as I walk into the door
The president pro temp in the State Assembly where on the actual floor of The Simpsons is not the guy
Goddamn spectator sex
I said come on get the hell out of here men win the wrong goddamn play sweetie walking to the state capital with Rashad Evans
Am I under arrest and then all hell breaks loose
Am I underweight
Am I
I turn around and I see
State Assembly NY State Assembly ducking down behind their deaths
Does government work
Exercises
Is constitutional rights
I can point to this
Forgotten
Unknown moment
Here in the State Building in Sacramento
I've liked
The game changer
For the conversation
About guns
In America
Because suddenly
Overnight we were on the front pages of newspapers around the world who are
Ragtag organization with this International notoriety
Deuce to the world
You had a lot of people going
Wait what like there's a bunch of black man rolling around with guns
Walking into the Capitol Building when there's
Kids around what came of that that provide
The law said no one
Could carry a loaded weapon
Inside city limits
Within a hundred fifty feet of public property this was directed at the Black Panthers we know it was
The people have all kinds of opinions about the Black Panthers and what they did
Particularly after Huey Newton shooting happened at 5 a.m.
Later that same year was arrested for shooting and killing a cop marks the spot
Parole officer John Frey
Was found fatally wound
The case was eventually dismissed
But
What seems clear is that the Black Panthers decision to use the Second Amendment
On themselves
To show up armed
At the state capitol in California inspired
Vigorous backlash
FBI director J Edgar Hoover today asserted that the Black Panthers represent the greatest internal threat to the nation
Perkins thought a Revolution was about to Breakout
Right here at home
This led to a whole new wave of gun control laws in California but also
Federal gun-control nanny of witches
Seemed
To be targeted towards African-Americans rather than just reducing gun violence
We've got to get guns off the street
But the irony was
Even though those laws were designed
Disarm
Left-leaning black radicals
Many white rural conservatives
Thought that they were next
But government was going to take their guns next
Every action
Create a react
At the same time
Panthers thing is
Hitting front pages of newspapers around the world
You got assassinations you got race riots you got Vietnam protests
All of a sudden everyone's clamoring for gun control
Democrats
And Republican
In fact
No reason why out on the street
Civilian
Should be carrying a loaded weapon
Reagan that was the exact
Same day
At the Black Panthers showed up at state capitol in Sacramento
With a shotgun
Reagan
Gun control
What's Happening Here
Is the Black Panther show up in the capital
Sacramento
And Ronald Reagan react
They create some gun control
Then there's even more gun control even federal gun control
And a lot of people are sitting home watching this
And they start to get very
Upset
Which brings is to chapter 2
The revolt
You know we can't allow this to happen
I can buy the damn pistol that I wanted
These two guys John aquilino live in Rockport Texas
Joseph turow Buffalo New York
They get us there
And they've both been in the guns pretty much their entire life
My father was
Veteran
World War 1
Did some Recreation
Shooting with
My mother used to love to go to the amusement park
And spend all day shooting 22
Little things that moved in the shooting gallery but neither one of them
Totally hardcore about their gum police until around the time
The Black Panthers
The fact that here bunch of people who were
Slightly darker
Complected then New England
Ivy league grads running around with firearms
Did that scare people
Hell yes
Did it scare you didn't scare me I didn't
John told me Joe is well that it wasn't the Panthers themselves that was a problem I don't like anybody to tell
Tells me I can't do something it's all the gun control laws that came
In the wake
When the gun control Act
First pass
Today we begin to disarm the criminal
Caroline
And then say
A lot of things just appeared that I had been used
Joe said he starts the gun shops in his neighborhood close
Like the furniture store in Buffalo that used to have shotguns
$5 think they stop selling them
And he says that is really bothered him because
The reason you have a gun is for protection
It's like another form of insurance
Which wasn't an abstract idea for him buffalo in the 60s and 70s
Not the safest place in the world
His house
Was even broken into
I could only
Describe
Home invasion
These guys actually
Better
Their way
2 Doors
Joseph seen his wife and his dog huddled in one room with a gun
Wally's two guys storm through his house
Andrada
I didn't take care of my wife
Purse
Some other money
And they are
I mean by the time the police got there
Devon
Joe's whole relationship with Firearms is there a predicated upon that this idea that is for self-defense and
Hear he's got
People breaking into his house
He's got
The cops not being there for him he's got the government trying to take his gun away so what do you do
You join
The end
Ra
Fight this gun control
But
This came at a moment where the NRA was at this
Crossroads unlike
Any edit seen before
Orson
Back when Joe joined in the early 70s the NRA
Was not the die-hard supporter of gun rights
Let me know today
Because according to Adam Winkler
It was never meant to be the idea behind the NRA
Continue
Fundamental right down to
Today was to increase Civilian Marksmanship training so that the next time there's a war Americans would be
Capable of fighting
You know you don't hear much about the NRA's founders
But the NRA was formed in the 1870s right after the Civil War by a reporter for the New York Times
Who thought that the Union Soldiers had been so ineffective in the Civil War because they were not familiar with
With firearms
Really yeah
But a hundred years their main focus was
Like teaching Boy Scouts how to shoot straight not
Second Amendment
And apparently if you go back through issues of American Rifleman
In the forties
50s
The Vietnamese version of Playboy guns inside a girl
You'll be amazed
That you can't find a single mention of the Second Amendment
Anywhere in those magazine
The NRA at that point was
Sort of like a gun trade group they work
Not super political and
And the people who ran it they were Hunters
Joan Hunter
They were just like these wealthy businessmen who like to hunt
According to John Rich guys who
They were hobbyist
But you had all these people coming in
Like Joe and like John who were convinced that guns weren't about
Shooting ducks they were about self-defense
Protecting yourself against criminals
In a time of starkly Rising crime rates this would lead to this straight up
Head on collision
At the NRA
Now
Joe and John join the NRA
The organization had just for the first time
Sort of set-up this lobbying
Yeah it was the brand new Institute for legislative action
John actually got hired to work there in 1976
And this true for legislative action
Supposed to fight for gun rights
Capitol Hill that's what they both wanted it
Today
Let's put it this way
We were the
If you would the bastard stepchildren of
The National Rifle Association
Really yeah
When the institute for legislative action
Was formed in 1975
The NRA
Refuse The Institute any Office Space
In the building
In the mid-seventies the part of the NRA that Lobby politicians
Had to rent office space from the hotel neck
Next door to the NRA is crazy
And then
Right after he was hired 78 people
Fire
Very interesting leaves big
Firing
And then there was word
Did the NRA wanted to move
Weave washing
Selva headquarters there and moved Colorado Springs
What's in Colorado Springs
Olympic camp
They were going to move to headquarters and put it in here this
The Olympics
Sports training group so that they could then start writing all the magazines about all the Olympic sports
They really didn't know
They wanted to turn the NRA from organization of firearms owners
A Publishing Company
They wanted to get out of
The policy
The older Garden seem to have the stomach for whatever
Gunfight some members wanted to hat they were very moderate
They thought like maybe we should try and kind of get out of this hole gun business thing
Getting out
John says there's even a moment when a report surface that suggested we should change the name of the
Association
Really yeah they were going to take rifle out
Tell me more tell me everything I say
Do you remember what any of those proposed names or no but they were considering at least taken rifle out
Oh yeah
Huh
And it is Bridal
I mean Iowa
So pissed off
And that's
When
The seeds of Revolt were planted
A few months later
Call to order
The hundred
Members
This is from one of those meaning
Cincinnati Ohio
77 the annual
NRA meeting of members
If it was me but I'm not sure why 22nd
They had a big Auditorium a Cincinnati Convention Center
1000 people showed up
Tumblr Cina thousand
Putting John Malone
Now
Pride of this big meeting
Secret meeting
Joe and a few other guys from Illinois Texas
Arizona going back and forth
By mail at a motel in
Florence Kentucky
And they decided the form of small
Pierce faction Lin the NRA
Do you have a name to call
Google call the Federation for the NRA
Call ourselves.
Federation for a nurse
And this tiny group
Planned
Akoo
Honorary life with hot steaming night
Denali
The Federation members were all wearing button that said National Rifle Association with the word rifle
Underline we wore orange hat
Walkie talkies
To connect with each other how many people were there somewhere between
1015 of us spread out through the meeting start to remember well basically
Please remove
They did all the niceties
I pledge allegiance
Pledge of Allegiance
Would you value
Opening prayer
Lord
You are awesome
Blah blah blah blah blah
And then
Little business
There are four
Microphone
Now is the time
When it came time for the members part of the meeting where members submit proposals which
It happened like this
Super parliamentary sorta way
This guy Neil Knox
He was part of their group
Any kind of bullrush the microphone
And he said
The Gather members have a list of bylaws
That they would like to have voted
Translation
Bugattis 15 demand
Restricting demands
Not sure if it's more or less than Martin Luther number one we demand that the NRA
Not moved its headquarters cancel that we demand The Institute for legislative action which
You want to kill
Should have more power through hell yes
Hell yeah
And we demand that the current NRA leadership
Be replaced
We wanted to take over
So the Federation guys making all these demands was crazy
Was that the
The leadership of the NRA
That was one of the meetings they just sat there
They they were like
Dumbfounded
But every time the Federation guy would make a motion judge border would say
Do I have a second
Okay the motion has been made
We start to speak for and against
Intermittent
The Federation members will use their walkie-talkies to coordinate who spoke at what microphone
How many votes did you need that day
I think this lease
600 volts
And how many votes did you think you had if you needed 600 so how many do you think if we hadn't the slightest I do
Going in
We
Debated
50/50 support
So as each of the 15 amendments are being debated the insurrectionists are running around in their orange caps with their walkie-talkies trying
That discussion debate
Lasted 8 hours
It went from 7 p.m.
Spotify
4 a.m.
And nobody love
They were all there
I mean we really didn't know whether to pull this off
But Joe says one of the big turning points
Is when a guy named Bob Kukla gets up to the mic
He was at the time the head
Of the institute for legislative action
To get into the mic and
He played it take
Remember to that takes right this was one that Bob
Cooper secretly recorded I don't know how he did it but what you hear on this tape is Bob Kukla
Talking to his bosses at the NRA and the yelling at him berating him
Or going to orbit
Time somebody talks
They're basically like
Bob
Shut up
They have the tape there any plated over the
And
Of course that electrified the audience
Do you could actually hear
People gas
The rank-and-file was
Audibly
This was this was evident
That the other side was going to deep six
Gun
Metro fights
People on the tape their own the room
Oh yeah there's still sitting next to him
The table
Over the course of this one 9-hour meeting
On a hot
Stinky night in Cincinnati every single one of those 50 proposals
Was Pat
We stopped the building in Colorado
Ensure the error I wouldn't change its name
Justify the leadership know just like the political savant
That figure that Hillary is going to get the presidency
They just
Absolutely took it in their shorts
And maybe the biggest change the most important change
Was that
The Institute for legislative action this
Political lobbying arm of the NRA
It was given the keys
To the car
They were not
The bastard
Stepchild anymore they
War
The NRA
You know what
We won and essentially
Staged
What are they called 1776
It's the same thing when the sun rose the very next day
DNR a whole new board
Committed to a new
No compromises view of the sea
Second Amendment
Individuals have a right not only to have a gun but to have almost any gun that they want and have as many of them
As they want
I can take those guns almost any place they want
American Gun politics
Literally change
Change overnight
I just shortly after this coup
The NRA
Both
This Abridged version of the Second Amendment
Right on the wall front center and its headquarter
The right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed
Nice clean
Totally uncomplicated sentence
Conveniently left out was the part that talked about a well regulated militia
Be necessary for the
Security of a free
Restay
I asked John like
What about the militia part of the
Why doesn't the NRA ever talk about that okay babe now you get me back to asking you if
John I love you dearly
Trust me
But
It's only been in less what 30 years
That if you'll pardon the expression
The b******* media has turned the militia into a four-letter word
The militia is you and me Sean
Post-coup
The NRA took a very hard line on gun control
And became an irrepressible political force in America
Scare congressman
Lies in its ability to mobilize its members in any congressional district
At the touch of a computer button
They start pouring millions of dollars into lobbying and just
A few years after that Cincinnati revolt
The NRA endorses its first
Presidential candidate
The Constitution does not say
The government shall decree
The right to keep and bear arms
Reagan Reagan the Constitution says the right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be
Be in French
At this point everyone and their Uncle leaves out the militia part of the Second Amendment
Which is why Americans eventually starts
Don't forget that
The militia clause or whatever you want to call it even exist
I wish I could save that instead of the last
Winter things that most surprised me when I was doing some research
This is Jill Lepore
By the 1990s the new interpretation of the Second Amendment
Had so penetrated
Popular opinion
That people were more familiar with the Second Amendment then with the first
The First Amendment
That Eclipse really
Kind of shocks
But even if you did the Panthers and the president in the American people are all down to sort of forget about this militia
Clause of the 2nd Amendment
It didn't mean a lot without the
The courts
And of course
Particular
Supreme Court
Woodbine
Chief Justice of the US Supreme Court from 19
69 to 1986 lawrenceburger
I think you saw me giving a television interview and he says that this new interpretation is it
Second amendment was
The greatest pieces of
One of the greatest pieces of fraud I repeat the word fraud
On the American public
Do I have ever seen in my lifetime
And this was a republican appointed by Richard Nixon now
Yeah
Yeah so the Supreme Court obviously not dying to have this conversation at the moment
But it's not just the Supreme Court if you look at the federal courts the entire
Federal court
System in America
There is not one
In our history at this point
Over 200 years
Been a single instance
Of some gun law some State local gun law
Getting up to a court and the court going you know what you can't do this
It violates the second amendment that does not even happen
Really it would not even there wasn't I like an amendment Smackdown anywhere in federal court
This isn't this isn't a thing
Why didn't Supreme Court to weigh in on it
That doesn't even look like it could be a thing it doesn't even look like much more than a fantasy
Until
For gun owners there are few names.
To become synonymous
Getting our rights
Ladies and Gentlemen please welcome a true patriot
Dick Heller
Dick Heller showed up
Freedom
Twitter and changed everything
Well hello Freedom lovers everywhere out
Play R Kelly.
More perfect will continue in the MoMA
Heller in 2008 revise the Second Amendment or you could even say
Reeves life in the Second Amendment because the second
Had never been taken truly seriously by federal courts
Until 2008
Destiny Levinson professor at the University of Texas law school
This is my perfect time Chatham Rod here with
Sean rameswaram
Price of Sean
Chad it's so I guess now it's time for chapter 3 to kill a right
You're going to get the dick
First
Here's what's going on in America
Amendment have become
One of those issues that can get you elected
Academics have begun to have a vigorous debate about its meaning
But the Supreme Court is still staying out of it
They're leaving this up to the states
Which already have all sorts of gun laws of their own to deal with
But then December 12
Mm
Republican George W Bush become president elect
After divided US Supreme Court has effectively halted
Florida's Contessa
Presidential vote tally
The NRA likes George W bush National Rifle
And he likes that
Protecting the Second Amendment
To the United States
Constitution
And in 2001 the Bush Administration declared that the Second Amendment protected an individual right to own
Guns UCLA law professor Adam Winkler again
Right that was not limited as most courts have held
The service in the militia
It almost right after he gets into office Bush's Attorney General John Ashcroft
Put out a letter this public letter to the NRA announcing that the Department of Justice
Adopted a new interpretation of the Second Amendment
And then right around the same time as the Bush Administration memo came out
Court in
Texas
Rule.
The Second Amendment did protect an individual right
Bear arms
And that was a
The big deal before this all the decisions and kind of
Beard in the other direction and because of that Court ruling and John Ashcroft letter
List three libertarian lawyers
Alan gura
Constitutional attorney Bob Levy a chair the board at the Cato Institute
Clark neily thought the timing was right we thought it was a good time for some litigation
And one thing you need to know about these guys is that they weren't necessarily doing it
The guns they had no association with the NRA or the gun rights movement
Then it was
More about getting the government to back off in our country when the government wants to restrict our Liberty
It isn't coming on the government to make the case for it as income in the government to say here's why you shouldn't be permitted
To exercise that right so that was their rank
I've always wondered why the gun rights movement has
Becomes a proxy war for like anti-government
Is Mmm Yeah well I mean if you think about it
The something professor
Sandy Levinson told me
Is that
Embedded in this amendment
Is the very idea that you can take up arms
Against the government
To protect yourself
And your fellow man from tyranny on the far right
Or occasionally on the far left
You find people who are willing
Say this that this is really what
Terrific
The Second Amendment
But mainstream conservatives in mainstream liberals
Arnott
Very happy with those arguments they are embarrassed by them
And so mainstream conservatives
Want to talk
About self defense against
Burglars
And mainstream liberals
Want to talk
About
How
The second amendment protects State organized militias
And almost nothing else
Hey we're getting back to the story these three libertarian lawyers they decide
Put together case
And their idea was to Target this
Really restrictive gun law
NDC
All handguns were banned you could own a shotgun or rifle but the law specifically made it illegal to ever put a round in the chamber
Even in self-defense or there was
There's really funky we described it as a
Ban on all functional firearms
But in order to challenge that law they needed to find a plaintiff
Interesting how do you
Find a plane
You look for somebody who
Got robbed what do you do
Well we can actually instigate
Litigation and we can take out a
Full page ad in the New York Times saying you want to vindicate your second amendment rights give us a ring Bridge of central got the word out talk to
I would say between
2 and 3 dozen
People they all had really interesting stories they found a guy who was
Gay gentleman named Tom Palmer previously been assaulted when he lived in California because he
He was gay was almost murdered by a skinhead mahbuba phobic
Subs and he wanted to go
To protect himself. Our lead plaintiff was an African American women named Shelly Parker
She was trying to protect yourself against
Local drug dealers and the cops actually told her she should get a gun
Which was a legal
Weird so they have this whole group so we ended up with three men and three women the 20s
2D early 60s formal way to America America
And the problem they ran into
Was that all these super sympathetic plaintiff
Didn't have the Sperrys
Special thing they needed
To bring a case
Standing
Standing with your sister legal term meaning they didn't have a sufficient grievance to be in court like if you can bring a case you have to show that you
Cuban actually harmed
Bye
Not being able to get a gun you have to show some physical concrete proof
The harm has been done
But you've been
Denied a gun
And none of the plaintiffs had the
Except for one.
Dick
That's me
Good to meet you and you
Dick help
John this is my favorite hat
Make America
Free again actually gets paid by the Frida
With a big
Western handgun in the center
It looks like you drew a trigger out there that what you did
Well it was missing a trigger so
We had to update it
Who's we
Okay
Where's the Supreme Court
The building where he became famous he's
Swim seventy five year old white guy
Sports classes that look straight out of the 70s
You got a situation here you want to cross
Sure what's the situation
The anti Trump protesters are here actually happened to meet him in DC today after Trump won
The election apparently
President-elect is visiting the White House there were protesters everywhere
Notmypresident there anti Trump protesters
Don't you like freedom
What about freedom
Most of the protesters are passing us wear white but
Chest
A few young black men pacify
He says
See you on the plantation
Freedom
Yeah
I just say that
We in Washington we call it the government Plantation
You didn't mean
You kids are about to be slaves or something cuz that's how I interpreted it
The more power government has the less Freedom you have the closer you get the ball and chain
Other Plantation
This pretty good place to eat right there
If you here for a couple of days if you've been in there
I have not
Yeah pretty good
Okay Hyatt Regency this is good for you we can do this to
We need to talk about Hyatt which is just down the street from Supreme Court and
And explain to me that his journey with guns
Like John and Joe
Began pretty casually
Flight 1976
Is living in DC
And one day he's sitting at home
I was watching
My hero Matt Dillon
Gunsmoke
Different Matt Dillon
And he had this long-barreled handgun
I was about 30 years old
And I figured ghali
I should own my first gun so when I went and bought
My what I call my Matt Dillon special
Hi standard 22 revolver Matt Dillon Buntline
And it was just
I live in America
We're Cowboys Society
I should have a cowboy gun and weave
Nothing no really deep thought to it
But then just a few months after he got that gun in Ark
October 1976
A trend that started with the Mulford Act
And the Black Panthers back in Sacramento
Hits Washington DC DC gun control regulations outlawed
Firearms ownership get that gun law which outlawed all hang out so I had some choices
I could
Turn it into the government
Not going to happen
I can throw it in the Dipsy dumpster
Or
There was another option I could go to jail
Not going to happen eventually he decides on option D
Give the gun to his brother my brother lived in Maryland so that made it very convenient
Did you just go visit your gun in Maryland what are you
I yes I would go visit
And caress and use my gun
What did you use it for
Target practice of course
Take me to
Gun visitation situation sound functional but
I think like any long-distance relationship they mostly sucked because more and more he didn't feel safe where he lived
About 10 blocks from the Capitol building right across the street from
The number one most infamous
Drug dealer Den in the city
Cold Kentucky courts
Every night at 2 a.m.
The chief drug dealer would fire a 9 mm
Into the air empty the clip
And that was the signal
Every night at 2
Drug dealing was over
For the day
It's clear that living through the crack epidemic in DC really
Shaped a lot of dicks views on guns
So
In the years after the handgun ban
Dick starts the very long process of finding a way to get his gun back to DC and he eventually even quits his desk job
To pursue getting his gun back full time
I'm all over Capitol Hill
And I see
Security guards have guns
Well
Going
Why can't I be a security guard
Golly
Maybe that would help me
Have a gun
But I can't have on my own
Let's see how easy or not easy this is
Dali
One step
Leads to another
Just like that
Dick was able to have a gun in DC but only during the day
And only while he was working
Like Barney Fife
At the end of my shift I have to turn in my gun and my bullets
And they kept it there
And they kept it on site in the sea
You finally starts looking for some help
Illegal
I knew Washington cuz I lived here and I'd gone to something tank
Cato and Heritage
Some others I knew they existed out there looking for some help
Turns out these lawyers are out there looking for some dick
No no
Wasn't there ideal sympathetic guy
I was told repeatedly and it was in print
But I was the worst
Choice less-than-optimal
Because of that Plantation thing you said or
He was always talk smack about
Federal government and interviews
One day Clark neily put a note in my hand and said dick Heller this is what you say
I just wanted a gun
To protect my house
Shut up
Play it wasn't their favorite plaintiff
But the one thing that no one else has done
Which is besides just wanting
An illegal handgun in DC he actually fill out an apple
Occasion
To register a gun that you already possess a gun in Virginia
And had that application denied and he had this denial slip or whatever it's called
You like literally had this physical proof
All of his grievance
And simple technical arbitrary little stupid piece of paper gave him
What's known as standing to bring the case stick Heller ended up being kind of Last Man Standing that was nothing to do with that was not our
Choice regardless
Became their guy and these three lawyers they take the case of the DC Court
And the judge
After
Inspecting it said the case can go forward
Magic Moment
The Supreme Court is entering the debate over the Second Amendment right to bear arms
Today's cases roster huge interest among citizens and politicians alike and it is divided even the president
And vice president
Chapter 3
The Reckoning March 18th
The day the Heller case was argued
Supreme Court everyone under
Do it how high the stakes were
Outside in front of the Supreme Court protesters by the hundreds were marching and
Panting
Favor of gun rights
And in favor of gun control
Journalists from all over the world to send it upon the supreme court that day
An inside the Supreme Court House
Not a creature was stirring not even a mouse
You could have heard a mouse I say
And
Everybody is just
Quiet
And you can hear your heart beating
And suddenly
Bam
And then Oye Oye Oye
The clerk yelled at the top of his lungs
And then there's a strange sound
What can that be
It was the swishing
Of the Robes of the justices as they ascended the steps
To the bench
Unbelievable
We will hear argument today in case General 7 290 District of Columbia vs. Heller
History of the Supreme Court with directly try to figure out what the Second Amendment mean
Dellinger
Immediately
Good morning mister chief justice to me please the court
DC lawyer Walter Dellinger github
And jumps right into it
Essential question
What was James Madison thinking when he wrote the super confusing sentence like 200 years ago was he
Thinking about the individual people and the right to own a gun or was he thinking about the collective right
Of the militia
The first text to consider
Is the phrase protecting a right to
Keep and bear
If you look at the phrase the phrase keep and bear arms how it was used at the time
Bear arms
Used to refer to the use of arms
In connection with militia service
Madison's rough drafts of the Second Amendment it's pretty clear that
When he says
People have a right to bear arms
All he really means is
Report for Duty
The language
Keeping and bearing arms when was first called confirmed
That's a right
It's a mystery
Why would they say the right of the people
To keep arms just the people in the state militias
Why wouldn't they stay state militias have the right
Dickey Farms
Listen to Justice I believe that the phrase
The people and the phrase the militia
We're really in sync with each other
The Federalist farmer uses
The phrase the people are the militia
Includes all the people
Yes I do believe it includes
At this point everyone jumps in a bunch of just start interrupting each other
Metallica scrum and they're all trying to figure out okay so when Madison was afraid
Not being friends
Who were the people he was talking about
What those words meant was the people just the militia or everyone all the people what is the
Relationship between the second part of the sentence the people part and the first part of the sentence
The militia part Verdugo rokita
Highlander Scottish Highlanders for some reason
They even tore the starter diagram Madison sentence
In the net result
According to Adam Winkler
Was
For liberals
Steven souter retire Ginsburg
Seem to want to emphasize the militia part of the sentence
Avenue had the four conservative justices Scalia Thomas Alito Roberts who seem to want to emphasize the people party
I don't see how there's any any
Any
Contradiction
Auntie people's team captain the quarterback
The first chair that day was
Without a doubt
Justice Antonin
Scalia why isn't it
Perfectly
Plausible
Indeed
To assume that since the framers knew that the
Justice Scalia
Of course was
Very conservative Justice grew up in Queens long time reporter covering the Supreme Court
She's also written a biography of Justice Scalia he was an avid Hunter and he grew up at a time when
Young men were trained in firearms in high school auction
Even from the time he was a kid at school and queens he said he used to
Carrie is gone
For rifle practice at school
On the Subways of New York
Can you imagine doing that today in New York City
You're being unrealistic
Chicken thinking that II
Santa Claus is not broader than the
The principal purpose here is the militia
The second clause
To keep and bear arms
It's going to be throughout the arguments is that Scalia is very very
Forward Lee pressing the sort of individual rights
Argan speaks of the right of the people and just like David souter
Are arguing back sing
What are the collected the militia
This goes on for well over an hour the justices for grilling lawyers
Arguing amongst themselves everybody trying to figure out
What was in James Madison's head
Until finally
Justice Breyer
One of the Liberals
She's on the phone
Myquest forget what Madison intended
There is no way for us to know
Let's talk about now
Let's talk about gun violence
Descendants was most
Definitely written about muskets
What about handguns
An assault rifles
What is reasonable
Now
80 to a hundred thousand
Some people every year
In the United States
Or either killed
In
Gun-related
Homicide
Or
Crimes
Active
Or suicide
Suicide
That's why I say 8100
Now in light of that
Why isn't
A ban on handgun
Reasonable
Or a proportion
Respond
On behalf
Alpha District
Because you are for the same reason I was offered by
Numerous military office
At the highest level
Of the US military all branches of service
Writing to
They agree with us at the handgun ban
Search the week in America's military preparedness
Alegria basically argues
When you take away people's guns
They're going to be less prepared
If and when they enlist in the army
To which Justice Breyer's like
They cancel practice shooting rifles banned in DC
They can go to gun ranges I guess the neighbors
What does that make it unreason
People first
With a very high crime rate
Assuming
If the objective is what the military people say
To keep us ready for the draft
If necessary
Is it on
Simple Forest City
Without height
Just say no
Handguns
Here
Well you want to say yes that is correct but I want to hear
What
What is a big crime problem I'm simply getting you to focus
Stop by the way it was Justice Scalia telling Alan gura
How to answer just a
Does Breyers question
The answer is yes Justice
And actually feels any standard of review that might be offered under Section
Instructions
The oral arguments last 90s
7 minutes
Far longer than most other cases
And going into the arguments
Many Supreme Court Watchers
Figured the case would be a close
5-4 decision
And it could go either way
And as with
All of these clothes cases
Question was what would Anthony Kennedy
The swing Justice
Do
As in so many issues in America
Comes down to what does Anthony Kennedy believe
So at the oral argument and I had the Good Fortune to be at the oral argument in the Heller case
Everyone was looking
To hear what would he say about the Second Amendment
His was really the vote that counted in the very first comment he made
Remote set learn to defend
Himself and his family against hostile Indian tribes
Outlaws
Wolves and bears and grizzly something like that
One of the first things he said was
About bears
Bear arms but
Grizzly bears
The Pointe candy was trying to make with clear
Don't you think the framers had other reasons that they wanted people to have guns
Other than just being a militia
What about
People being in their homes
And is meeting to defend
And that's when I silently
Scream at the top of my lungs so nobody could hear me yes we win
...
Something
Will you turn out to be historic Supreme Court decision handed down this morning
07 to 90 District of Columbia vs. Heller
We hold that the second amendment guarantees an individual right to have
And that the district's handgun ban as well as its requirement to firearms in the home
Be rendered inoperative
Violate
It was
A groundbreaking reading of the Second Amendment
Scalia minimize that Clause referring to
A well regulated militia and put the stress on the second Clause that refer to the right of the people
The people will not be deprived of
The right to keep and bear arms
This was Edgar zakat for him
On the bench
I think so
Rip the militia Clause December 15th 1791
The June 26 2008
A pretty good run if I'm being honest
For the first time in the history of these United States
The courts definitively declared
That the Second Amendment
Give every American
The right to a gun for self-defense it was it was a great day for freedom in America was a great day for the Constitution
Great day for citizens
It's a great day for gun owners it was great day for fearful people
Of course
Not everyone agreed
I mean to me that's a travesty
This is Jack Rico
Professor of history and political science at Stanford University
He filed a brief for the court and
He said scalia's reading of the history is just
Wrong
The Second Amendment is not about individual right that we shouldn't even be talking
About history
Because the nature of firearms has changed so radically for the 18th century to our own time and that ultimately
And here you go just as Stevens in his descent the court has decided to end
Political Thicket
Southern-style politics
To be honest
Let Me Ride That really believe in constitutional law anymore
I think I social laws of fiction
Pedro has become so highly politicized
In so many areas
I think I socialize
Is bunk
Wow I just destroyed I'm not a lawyer so that I don't have any professional steak
Interfering the Judiciary
But
There's a very big
But he did have a major caveat section of our opinion points out that like most rights
What's the Second Amendment right
Unlimited
He said like all right
It's not absolutely the right to keep and carry any weapon whatsoever in any manner whatsoever
And for whatever purpose
Which is very important to keep in mind
Long-standing
Possession of firearm
Mentally ill
Or laws forbidding the carrying of firearms
Sesame Place
This is another thing that we tend to forget
The decision says
Every individual has the right to bear arms
The most interesting lie like the decision also says
Of course we need gun control
The word Heller
Come to represent
Like
2nd Amendment rights
Are you against Heller even though being for Heller
Is being for gun control
Fusing yeah it is
I mean after all this time it's still just
Totally confused
You have a right to a gun
But the government has a right to regulate it
Decal gets his gun back in DC
But PC still also has all sorts of gun regulation
You see the same pattern all over the country some states are lenient
Summer super strict
And both approaches seem to comply with Heller
In a way the Heller Decision
Is just like all those commas and Clauses that we started with and James Madison sentence
It's the
Confusing declaration
That leaves the door wide open for interpretation
Which
Obviously sucks
We could use a little more
Clarity on
How to live with this
Second Amendment right to bear arms
Open it gives us an opportunity I think
Opportunity to get it right to fix it
But now be pretty good time
What story was produced by Sean ROMs firm
Adam Winkler Facebook
Which a lot of our research
Drawn from
Ice cold gun fight
More perfect is pretty spy me Jad appenrod
Jenny Lawton Julia Longoria
Kelly Prime
Sean Rams forum
Alex overington
Sarkari
And Suzie lechtenberg
With Elie mystal Cristian farias Linda Hershman David Gable and Michelle Harris
Supreme Court audio is from Oye
A free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Leadership support for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation