WNYC Studios
Is more perfect time Chatham rod cell
Last season we profiled a guy named Edward bloom
This is a guy who
According to his critics
Had almost single-handedly roll back Decades of civil rights law
Wasn't a lawyer wasn't politician but somehow he sort of found this way
To play the courts
Hook up just the right case find just the right plaintiff
Target voting rights affirmative action all kinds of different laws that take race into account
Same to us the time that he was sort of the Hidden architect not too much was known about him
In fact at the time that we did the story
There is a big case of his targeting affirmative action that was coming before The Supreme Court
And there was he this moment or his plaintiff
Play two feet found
Young white woman Abby Fisher was on the steps
Supreme Court
Giving an interview and
He would literally be behind her in the shadows
Almost at the edge of the frame
Which ones to know like
Who is this guy
What's the story
So we produce a profile
And what I'd like to do
This podcast is update that broke
Because
Recently I talked to Ed bloom again about what he's up to now
And it's really
Pinterest
Maybe traveling depending on where you stand
So
Going to play
A chunk of the original
Justice recepta contacts and then follow up with a new interview in or if you'd rather not hear the original
Skip 2 minutes
Otherwise
Producer Katherine will start this off again we wanted to know like who is this guy
Since you paid him a visit
Yeah so I
Went to Tallahassee
That's where you live
He Winters in Tallahassee
You walking what initially struck you
Golden Retriever
Is what initially
Hysterectomy
Literally physically laugh
And
I don't know what I was expecting but when you hear about these cases you know
Critics are really
People are mad about
It is deeply disturbing truly outrageous to betray the American people
So I go to meet him and your flight
From Austin
The Dallas
To Tallahassee uneventful and
On time and good looks like a totally nice guy
A regular guy
Was it look like
Like a dad there's something in me that just loves
Tradition and Custom
Listening to the Great American Songbook
Beautiful
Frank Sinatra
As long as I hope
And Ella Fitzgerald
I love
Art and Museum Independent films golf
What's the skies backstory
Well he's 64 I was born in a small town
In Michigan
My dad owned a shoe store their my mom worked with him in the shoe store
Cleaning up
The first Republican my mother ever met
How to use the word typical but it it really was a typical liberal Jewish
Household
My mother and father
Where Franklin Roosevelt
Harry Truman Democrat
Always
Democrat when he said he was
That way to all the way through college
The University of Texas
Grad school University of New York where I am
Spent a year studying of all things
African literature
But he says somewhere along the way his political leanings
Started started to shift
I spent
A summer in Israel
Living Mana
And he says he came out of that experience
A little less liberal than he was before
And you got married and then in the early 80s he's living in Houston working as a stockbroker
And
We met
Aren't our neighbors
This particular couple they were New Yorkers who would move to Houston both grew up as
Liberals and the guy she sort of opened my eyes to the world
World of the Neo cons
Show review commentary magazine conservative magazines and this was around the time that the neocon movement was really hitting it
Stride you got all these
New York liberals
Defecting
Is what he says
Thousand
Individuals who grew up in the night
1960s
It started to question
The Wiz
Obviously
Liberal policies
And he says slowly
Overtime
Very
Gradual
He became one of those people
In any case
Fast forward a little bit he's living in Houston Garden variety
Existence
And
Something happens that sends him on this entirely New Path
Basically he and his wife moved to a new neighborhood
They move from the suburbs into the downtown area
Urban and
In 1990
We went to vote
For the first time in our new neighborhood
I realized that the Republican Party had not
Fielded a candidate
To oppose the Democrat
Incumbent
Running for congress this is a
District that has
Almost 600 thousand people
You don't have a choice you've only got one person running
Bloom decided to run himself
I lost item
No great surprise to anyone
He actually lost by 32 point
But along the way something really unusual happen
During that campaign he and his wife Lark you know they decided they were going to go meet voters in there.
They got a giant print out
Of all the addresses in the 18th congressional district
Started going door-to-door meeting people handing out literature
And I'd walk down say Oak Street take
The even side of Oak Street
And my wife would take the odd-numbered side of Oak Street
And we would start to walk and very quickly they realized that
The district shape
Was funny
Some houses on one side of the street would be in the district in the house is on the other side wouldn't
Sometimes the district would
McDonough Highway caption apartment complex
Come back at it just
Didn't make sense of this is large bloom wife of Edward Bloom this peculiar because we had
Maps we had to follow
And it was very odd the way some streets were
And the districts in somewhere
Took a while for it all to really sinking as to how this could happen I guess a better week of this
We realized that
Neighbors
Had been separated
Almost house by house because of their race
You come to believe that the reason this was done
Was
For the explicit purpose to create a majority
African American
This is an untrue
Clothes from a clear and simple wrong part of the reason this was done was the Voting Rights Act of nineteen
Of Americans are denied
The right to vote because of their color
This act was a giant step forward in civil rights one of the primary
Eliminate barriers to voting like poll taxes and literacy tests
Strategies that have been used to keep minorities
Facebook voting
And the other thing it did
Sort of in a roundabout way through a series of interpretations is
Encourage the creation of districts where the majority of Voters
Were minorities and that's because
One of the strategies that have been used previously to
Dilute the minority was to take minority communities and
They call it cracking later
They split them apart into many different discs
So that they were never
In the majority enough
Electorate
So the Voting Rights Act tried to correct that
The 18th congressional district was one of these majority-minority District
The district
Ron by the Texas
I do have a slight
African American majority
I think about 51% African American
But this was the problem according to bloom the way they got to that
African American majority was by
Creating this District that zigzagged all over the city and cut through neighbor
I could not understand
People live close together they could send their kids to the neighborhood schools they shopped in the neighborhood
Shopping centers they were worried about
Neighborhood issue
Brixies neighborhoods
Heart by race
Seemed so wrong to me
In his mind this law was actually
Not limiting discrimination but actually perpetuating
I don't know what a
The average person upon realizing this would have done
I decided
To file a lawsuit
Decided to sue the state of Texas called a few friends who lived in the 18th District
Racially diverse group of people African-American Hispanic
No I found a lawyer that I can afford $7,000 a month we filed a lawsuit challenging the con
Constitutionality Texas's redistricting plan
But now it was being used as an excuse to segregate people into racially polarized District
It worked its way through the lower courts and
Tonight
Shocked and surprised
In 1995
Number 94805 George W bush vs Alvera of the Supreme Court
Look it up
AR
Components step to the lectern and
Is the constitutionality of three congressional districts they make their arguments
Texas basically said all we have to put people together by race
Legislature has the obligation
To satisfy Federal requirements requirements
Like remember the Voting Rights Act we're trying to make sure that there are enough minorities in this District
So that they have a chance to elect a representative or advocate
May I please the court his arguments
But look at the map
The map is
Bizarre
And the only reason
It could have gotten this way as
Because you're only thinking about race
Only race
Think about it that seems messed up isn't that messed up it doesn't matter what your ultimate goal is
You cannot use
Forbidden tools rate is forbidden by the 14th Amendment to be used as a tool
A very tense situation
So in the end
Supreme Court
Hair-splitting decision
But I think it's at this deeper question that
In our society
Discourse we just haven't figured out how to talk about in a way
You don't look if you're defining race just as the color of someone's skin
The government cannot use that in any way that's against the constitution on the other hand if you take the
This wider View and you look at race in the context of History social context then
How can the government address discrimination without taking race into account that they have to
So it's difficult balance
You can't look at race
But you have to
And
The Supreme Court says to Texas look
All you're doing in this case is sorting People based on how they're labeled on us
You're not looking at that wider context you're not looking at if he's communities with next to each other
Common interest
You're just sorting them based on
Race alone and that's not good enough
You can't do that when the
Pinyin came down
The Supreme Court ruled in our favor 5 to 4
That was quite
A day
The day that we won that lawsuit
I was going to stream
Hooked
Forever after that Edward Bloom decided that this would be his bank became
Must you use the court to try to strike down every race-based policy he could
Name was taken on the road I recruited plaintiffs in New York Virginia South Carolina
Try not to challenge congressional district
Plans and we won in each of those states he helped Sue school districts in Florida and Texas
To end the use of racial quotas in K through 12 magnet schools
Houston city Contracting to kill affirmative action
Fails but I've been the architect of over two dozen lawsuits
Six of which
Sex
Made it to the Supreme Court
Including
In 2013 in a 5-2 for vote very divided Florida Supreme Court today struck down
He parts
The Voting Rights Act of 1965 Supreme Court struck down a very important part of the Voting Rights Act
Tri 1965 Landmark lock is considered one of the most important pieces of civil rights legislation
They Shoulda never pass Shelby County vs holder this decision
Gutted the Voting Rights Act
Specifically there was just part of it that said
States and counties with a history of discrimination
How to check with the federal government first
Before they go about changing their voting laws basically the federal government was saying look
You've been up to all this stuff we're now we're watching
Supreme Court said
You know
Time for change
That list was made a long time ago and
It's update
This decision
Restores an important constitutional order to our system of government
This was Bloom's biggest victory
When Shelby County
I think a lot of people burst into tears when I came down and I understand it
Disturbing
Deeply disappointed
With the Court's decision in this matter
Change during the Civil Rights Movement people died
For the precious right to vote
This is congresswoman Sheila Jackson Lee of Houston to
I would like to have the Supreme Court Justices go back in time go back in
Sometime and March with those who March after Bloody Sunday
I from Selma to Montgomery
A balloon has a right to his opinion
It doesn't mean that it has to be the opinion of the United States
I understand that
People were in a
Gravely upset
I also know that they were
People who were Gravely relieved
And Gravely
Ratify
Yeah but I think what gets a lot of people
Is it
You look at the Civil Rights
Videos you see tens
Thousands 40,000 people in the streets marching and
You hold that if you make a split screen in your mind
Hold that thousand ten thousand people in one side
On the other side
You one guy
It does make you ask basic questions about tomorrow
That's a false paradigm
It's
That maybe your split screen but that's
Really not
Good luck in 1964 19-6
America was held hostage
Bye
The legacies of slavery
And the
Choke hold
Jim Crow
Fast
Forward
To 2006
The reauthorization
Of
The Voting Rights
The chokehold
Had gone
Away
African Americans in the Deep South registered to vote
In numbers
Often exceeded
Participated in elections
In numbers that
Exceeded
In terms of
Electoral opportunity
We have
Come
180 degrees
From
1960s degrees because of the law which you helped overturn an indent and we don't know
To what degree that is the psychology of America changing or the fact that we had a lot
Cat people online
And now that love has gone and now we see voter ID laws coming back into play which I think any like saying purse
Admit is it is it is it is an attempt a blatant attempt
Disenfranchised
People do it feels a little bit strange that two I mean I completely agree with your things have gotten better
Same time I think
Well that was because of the wall That's now gone
Look laws change laws
Evolve
+ and at some point
They need to come to an end
So after winning the Shelby County case
Ed Blum turned his attention to
Affirmative action good universities be able to
Racial preferences in college admissions you found a young white woman named Abigail Fisher
Race may have hurt her chances to attend the University of Texas
There were people in my class with lower grades to Warren and all the activities I was in who were being accepted into UT and
The only other difference between us what color are skin
Case goes to the Supreme Court
And in that case
The Supreme Court has upheld the affirmative action program at the University of Texas
Who is constitutional
Ed Bloom law
But
At the end of that original piece he made it clear to us he wasn't giving up I'm a long distance Runner
If there's something just emblematic about my personality
Run
Long distance
And even as the court was coming down with his decision against him
He was planning his next move
That's coming up next
This is my perfect MCAT I will bring the action up to the present
After Ed Bloom lost that Supreme Court case against University of Texas last year
He kept the case going on the state level
And he took aim at two more schools
I have
Retain counsel to litigate
Harvard's admission policies in
University of North Carolina admissions
He formed an organization called students for fair Admissions and this time
The target was perceived discrimination against
Asian-American
Case against Harvard is in the early stages but I recently called them up
You just kind of get an update
On this
Crusade
The ultimate goal is to have the Supreme Court revisit it
We can come fortunate opinion in Fisher
And in the use of race and ethnic
Once and for all
That's the goal of this organization in this organization
Mistake
Active until that
Is this a situation where lie quiz
Utu
Italy recruited plaintiffs
Yes
It is it is
So I did
With
Students
For fair admissions
What
I did with
The University of Texas
And that is
Working with
Friends
And allies
Tofu
Yearn for the day that race and ethnicity is not a part of the University admissions
Set up three new website
Harvardnotfair.org
UNC not fair
. org
And UW
Not fair
. org W being
Wisconsin
So it was
Our Hope
Define students who had been rejected from those three schools willing to join students for fair admissions
And let us proceed
Into Federal
And that's that's
What we did
Ed told me he got hundreds of responses to these websites
From students who felt like they've been discriminated against
He went out of town to just students he felt had the most Merit I talked to the kids
I talked to their parents
Each of those kids and their parents who agreed
To join
And
Participate
As
What about participating member in a lawsuit
I got on a plane and went to
This is weather
Learn about their background let them ask me questions and who are they
What can you tell me about the for the Harvard case they are all Asian
Many of them are
Children of immigrant
Chinese
Children of
First generation Korean and Vietnamese
And they have
Superlative academic records
Startlingly
So
Perfect GPA
Perfect SATs in a CTS
Activities
Sports
Lots of volunteer effort
And how many how many of them are directly associated with the case
That is something that the judge in the Harvard case has placed
Undersill
Wisely
What I think
Well
We remember what happened with the
The harassment
Of Abigail Fisher
If you don't take your little ass on somewhere different Grace didn't suck your dumbass
Maybe you would have gotten into a good college Becky with the bad grades
Really happy you and your racist lawyer got shot down
Abby was
Hounded
Abby
Was
Threatened
We learned an important lesson
And that is
Although there may be students
Who are
Brave enough to put their name on a lawsuit
The consequences
Canby
Dangerous
And frightening
So all of the students involved in those
Three cases
Harvard
UNC
And the University of Texas
Have
Standing
As members of the organization
And their names
Their addresses
Their email will never be made to the public
It's a funny thing though because
I mean the idea of a
Plaintiff
Even if it is
Often
Pecan extract
Strange to have plaintiff's that you can't examine and that you can't say OK Google who are they
Exactly what others
And you're right Abigail Fisher
I think was
Is the subject of some very high
Kind of harass
The same time who she was was a helpful starting point for
For the conversation about whether this should
Exist
Informative action or whatever you would call this doesn't happen in the corded happens in the world that have
Society in this is something that is
Affects all of us
Well this is
Very common
And Federal
The ACLU
Which is a membership
Often
Suzhou
In the name of the organization
Disclosing only to the courts
Their members who have been Direct
Actually harmed by the
So what we're doing is Not Unusual
Yatchan
Okay so you said in interviews
On this lawsuit.
Asian American students are being penalized for being a
High-achieving minor
How do you argue
That they're being Penal
Well in litigation like this
We know that the court
Allows the use of race and ethnicity in admissions
What we also know
Is that
You cannot
As a university
Have
Heavy of a hand
Using race and ethnicity
And
Furthermore
Numerica
Quotas
Are completely forbidden
And how we show that Asians are being
Target in the harbor
Is to look at the number of Asians
Applied to Harvard
What percentage
Year after year after year
Has Harvard admitted
And what we have found is it from 1992
True 2013
The
Percentage of Asians at Harvard admit
Has been remarkably
Flat
In fact in 1990 to 19%
Harvard's freshman class
Was Asian
Wow in 2013
18%
Oration
Now that doesn't mean much
Until you realize
That the number of Asians
Applying to Harvard
During this period of time
Better than doubled
Just a quick note here Harvard hasn't actually released data on ethnicity and admissions for
The years he was talking about so we can't confirm the numbers
Fuse we know that
Ed Loomis
Drawing
In part from the
National Center for
Education City
To the government
And by the way when he says 19% of the Freshman Class
Turns out the number
Using reverse
2 more than just for
If those kinds of data point
We're presented in court
In an employment
Lawsuit
Dude against a major corporation like
Walmart
Walmart would lose
Any judge would look at that and say you've got to
Quota
Walmart
Your
Employment Practices
Fall afoul of
Title 7
Let me just push back against f
You know immediately that idea lyrics
Expressing
And the and the start of the fight
The spirit of the lawsuit is premise on this idea
If you take away race
Filtering in admissions that what we would have is a more meritocratic
Australian grades
But I mean
Hasn't the meritocracy
Isn't that true
Just a myth I mean especially in a place like
Like Harvard I mean if you look at the data at Harvard you see that
People whose parents went to Harvard we have family members who went to Harvard
They get preference
Treatment in the admissions process
If you take that out just
It's a few wrongs okay people who have
Families
It can afford to send them to Kaplan prep courses
Is for the standardized test
They get a better like up and isn't that just kind of affirmative action for white people so that there's two ways I want to answer
The first is that
It is
Not up to me
It is not up to this organization
To dictate how Harvard or
Texas or
University of North Carolina fashion their admissions policy
The only thing legally
That we are advocating for
Is
The end of racial distinctions in the admissions
Process
Number two
I agree
Glad
Colleges and universities
Cannot
Use just
Strictly
Grades and SAT scores
As an admissions correct
I believe of Legacy preferences
Should have been ended at Harvard
And throughout the country
Decades
Citgo
I think people who write big checks
Do universities
Whose children then get a leg up in the admissions process
I think that audit
I think the colleges and universities
Have an obligation
Reach Out
Kids from disadvantaged background
Kids whose
Family income is too small and blowout
Whose parents didn't go to college
Who maybe grew up in a tough neighborhood
Colleges should use that
And not race
If they're going to give
A leg up
Yan
Helping kids from
These disadvantaged background
That means
That there will be lots of African-American kids lots of Hispanics
Lots of Asians
And lots of white kids
You know a helping hand from Harvard and Princeton and Yale and stand
There is no reason why an Asian applicants to Harvard
Who's
Parents are laborers
Mom works as a maid at a hotel in New York
And dad works
As I'm kitchen worker at a Chinese restaurant
There is no reason why that kid should be penalized
And white kids
African American kids and Hispanic kids who come from professional backgrounds
To be elevate
Ending racial classifications and preferences
And instead substituting
Socio-economic preferences
Is something that both the left
And the right can agree
But it's interesting to think about what might happen in the transitional
Space
Between say and Ed Bloom victory
And that remedied
Ignition switch
Cuz I was just thinking I might okay so take
Sexy men like
Abigail Fisher in with holder in the rights
Left side remind
Let's say you get
The harbor case to scotus
And you win
And
The court agrees that there is some kind of quota and place
Any longer support that
There should not be any kind of limit on high how many high-achieving Asian-American students get into Harvard
Or any University
It's interesting to think of the effect that might have on white applicants
Like
Abigail Fisher we make this
Argument
In our lawsuit
The argument is that
African Americans
Hispanic
And white
Are getting a preference
Over
Better qualified
Asian app
So it is very likely
And white
Seaweed you asserted that in our lawsuit
This is not an attempt
Reinvigorate
White applicants
All of the ivy league
Schools like Duke
Stanford
The number of whites as likely to go down
The number of Agents
Likely to go up
ATS
That's why we don't have any whites as plaintiff's in our Harvard lawsuit
That's why none of the kids
Join students for fair admissions
How to challenge Harbor
We're white is because
They're benefiting
From the Discrimination that Asians are suffering there
Best ever bloom
Harvard sent us a statement which didn't directly respond to Ed Blum specific allegations but they did
Save the date
Do make an effort to create diversity in the student body
Because when a student encounters different types of people with the experiences that student grows
And you can read their full statement on our website
But also have some additional information about the lawsuit we talked about
Scanner in the early stages that's a radiolab.org more perfect
More perfect
Lechtenberg Jenny Lawton Julia Longoria Kelly Prime Alex overington and sarkari
Is Elie mystal Cristian farias Linda Hershman David Gable and Michelle Harris
Special thanks to Katherine Wells who produced the episode called the imperfect plaintiffs
Go back and listen to the whole thing if you haven't pretty good dream Court audio is from Olla a free law project in collaboration with legal
Formation Institute at Cornell leadership support for more perfect provided by the Joyce Foundation additional funding is forever
Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation