WNYC Studios
Isabel perfect Amgen iPhone ride
This season we are bringing u27
The most perfect album
Together a series of songs
Buy a whole bunch of different musicians inspired by the amendments to the US Constitution
Thus far we have done one two three four five six seven eight nine 10 11 13 14 15
Today we're going to keep going nonlinear we're going to LeapFrog ahead but also double back
When your liner notes first than the songs
These two amendments
Alright enough
Are of a very particular breed
You know in the taxonomy of the 27 amendments there are the ones that are the sort of the big ones
Soaring
Principled
Freedom of speech
You know those kind of minutes and then
You have the one key
The procedure ones that are almost like
Engineering drawings
Like okay we've got this house it needs a structural fix so here's how you do it
But this thing against this thing you bought this
Do that
Maybe it'll work
They're very kind of practical
Actually find those kind of measurements to be the most inter
Today we have two of those starting with
16th Amendment
Income tax
The sixteenth amendment is
Probably not
One of the ones that
Do you know off the top of your head
More perfect producer sarkari
But
If you live in the United States and you're bringing home a paycheck
It's definitely a part of your life
Congress shall have the power to lay and collect taxes on incomes
From whatever Source derived
Without apportionment among the several States
Without regard to any census or enumeration
You probably also know that
I don't like the IRS
What what don't you like
They take our money
Is basically American tradition to complain about paying taxes
We spend at least six
Billion man hour
Dealing with taxes in the United States Senate 2016 polls showed that
Vladimir Putin and OJ Simpson
Are more popular than the IRS
Rooms at Chipotle
So we left
Complain about taxes
Jet
And here's the puzzle
If you look at the rate at which
Which we pay them
The United States has a really high rate of compliance compared to other countries
Somewhere between 80 and 85% of all taxes at the IRS estimate should have been paid
Are actually paid by individuals and corporations
That's James armchair the department of Economics Tulane University
And before him Jim Hines
Professor of economics and professor of law at the University of Michigan
What they're both talking about is sometimes called
The compliance rate
How good
Are we at paying the taxes that were supposed to pay
End America
Scores
Unusually well or good about five out of every $6 of taxes at the IRS believes
Should be paid in taxes are actually paid and tax
And both of them told me that
This crazy high number has puzzled Economist for a really long time
It just shouldn't be as high as it is
Just to put this in perspective
In recent years the United States has ranked
7th in the world when it comes to literacy rates
21st
When it comes to the strength of our democracy
And 31st
When it comes to life
Pregnancy
But somehow the most International surveys the United States is among the top three countries in the world
Compliance rate with
Access
An economist
Don't know how to
Explain this
They literally call it attacks
Compliance puzzle
Anna puzzle gifts
Even deeper if you look at the number of people that the IRS
Actually goes after
Stair every year
What percentage of people do you think
The IRS audits
60%
About 60% maybe maybe 70%
Sun
Hook weather alert
That's awesome
Buy likes
69.5%
What if I told you that that number is actually
Half of a percent
Damn
Wow
I mean
I just thought it would be
Be a lot higher
For the last several decades
The IRS is auditing
Has been steadily going down the overall audit rate was
More than 5%
Pirs blades big cut since 2010 the agency's budget has
Shrunk by a billion dollars it also has
17000 fewer employees
So really all signs are pointing towards rationally speaking know what your panties are
Your chance of getting caught
So
You should
You should pay zero
That's Vanessa Williamson fellow in governance studies at the Brookings Institution
That's not what
People do
And the question is
Why
Why do people pee
No it's going to side
For a second the fact that a lot of taxes get taken out by employers
There's still a lot of cases where people have to voluntarily to
Declare their income and they do it and why
Why do they do it when the chances of getting
Caught ziehm solo
One answered
Could be that
They don't know that
The chances are so low and they're scared
Because the IRS works
It's really hard to make them sick
They use
The media
Frankly is
Part of their device for effective
Tax enforcement
Their message that they want to transmit to people is if you don't comply properly
We're going to make you real sorry about it
They try to get that message across in a lot of different ways there are high-profile prosecution's
Sanford was found guilty and
Will report to federal prison in Connecticut on Monday Wesley Snipes
Passenger 57
But I'm sure it was not lost on the IRS that if you have a famous actor go to prison that will help
You know I get people's attention
Leona Helmsley
The self-appointed hotel Queen Somebody from irr you know very wealthy
Call socialite in New York married to Harry Helmsley who owned a lot of fancy hotels
She was known in the Press has the Queen of Mean
I mean it was
The perfect villainess
For the IRS
The helmsley's were indicted for not paying their taxes
Mo Harry did not have to face charges because of his health
Leona did
I am not going to
DJ alive done nothing wrong they had her arrested on
April 14th
In an era when
Half the country did their taxes on the evening of April 14th oh my God
So
So fear like
Carefully cultivated fear might be one piece of the answer here
It doesn't seem to me
To be the whole story
You waiting for somebody to play chess with
Because when I went out to talk to
Two people I heard a few but he man stories for sure
But mainly what I heard was that people felt like the taxes that they were paying
We're going towards
Something
Everybody had that one thing in their mind that they were thinking of
I mean
Federal welfare programs like food stamps
Housing programs and excetera
Starzer everything another part of tax compliance is what called tax morale
And that's wrapped up in our sense our Civic sense that paying taxes is the right thing to do every year the IRA
IRS commissions a study essentially asking people why why do they pay
And last year 95% of those people said it's every American civic duty
Bipartisan view paying taxes is the cost of citizenship
As well as American democracy itself
They talk to you about politics right they talk to you about contributing to the people they see is us
Taxes is only right
What's this really not very fair to anybody else who is
Part of the community and therefore deserve to be represented doesn't work if you know
Put a little something and it's got a little something out pay your taxes
And the ex post you know hundred years later on the 16th Amendment has got to be pretty favorable
I mean
Try to imagine our world
Without income
The kind of government that you would have is not the kind of government you have right now
Sarkari with a lighter note for the 16th Amendment
The song on the album
Comes from a Chicago Illinois band called post animal.
If you want to hear the rest of this song the rest of any of the songs on the album go to
The most
Perfect album. Org thank you
YouTube post animal
And all the bands contributed
Gain the most perfect album. Org
I'm Jenna from Rob this more perfect season 3
Continue with one more men after
Is more perfect
Most perfect album season 3 on Jad appenrod we just heard a song from post animal before that liner notes for these
16th Amendment going to jump
Forward now six spots
Two number 22
Another seemingly wonky one but actually kind of cool Kelly Prime
Brings us the liner notes for this one
The 22nd Amendment
Isn't a big one
Honestly
Not even a medium one
After we got our right to speech our right to bear arms
Actually abolish slavery to find citizenship and made sure men women and people of color all got there
Right to vote
Kind of feels like a loan Falls over the Constitution
Right
Ron
In 2018 suddenly this unassuming little amendment number 22
Just getting really
Interesting
The most dramatic political change in China in decade and it all started back in February
With news from China
China's ruling Communist Party proposed Sunday to remove term limits on the office of President giving prices
The right to remain in office indefinitely in office indefinitely
3000 delegates
Being told the Amendments when needed
Because the challenges China faces
Require a strong leader
And the United party
So China has had a two-term limit on the office of president for over three decades
And this year under President Xi Jinping
Describe
Not long after
Trump responded
Kitchen is grey
Gentleman
He's now president for life
He suggested it was something we should consider
This is Gillian Metzger professor of law
Columbia Law School
I remember people freaked out like it was one of those I mean for a day they are too but you know there was another remember the 22nd
XXII
Two term limit on president
No person shall be elected to the Office of the President more than twice
And no person who
And then they remember the 22nd
Yeah well I think what WhatsApp
22nd Amendment says no
No president for life
2 *
8 years
Max I wonder if you can tell me
How long have we had the 20s
What words have the 22nd amendment send
So that means that the two term limit is actually younger than Donald Trump
I think that's right
We didn't have any term limits on the presidency for 163 years
For most of us history we didn't eat it
The right now a wind is blowing in America
McKinley win
I'm coming in on that wind are a lot of basic questions about
What kind of country we want to have
Let me tell you about two other times
When that same wind has blown
Let's go back
The beginning
Was it a time when America was choosing its very first president
George motherfuckin Washington
10 president
Was arguably the most famous person in the western world
This is denver brunsman
Peking university
We do have to keep in mind that the motto of the executive
What's the time
Was
The monarchy
This was right after the revolution we had just won a war against Britain for Independence
But
Is clear the weather we didn't want it was
Pretty unclear what exactly are presidency should look like
Up to that point I mean going all the way back to ancient times
Young people like Caesar
Oliver Cromwell
Oh there was a pattern of
Strongman Leading Armies
Victory
And then staying
Hang on
So that was a basic Playbook
In walks
BDubs
He was about six two and a half
Tall athletic
In his younger years he was handsome
High cheekbones auburn hair
That today we might almost call
Aloof
People admired
Bing someone above
Others
In other words this guy walked
Tok and glowed
Like a king and Americans kind of default started treating him like one
Are the guys at the Constitutional Convention they gave him the power of the veto the power to declare war the power to pardon
Intermittent
No way if anything I think there was
Is more of a saint
As Hamilton
Target at the
Convention
That that should be
A lifetime
Office
Soap George Washington get elected
Keyspan
1 year 2 years
4 years suddenly 8 years in office
A lot of people thought that he would just keep serving till he died
Play George Washington kind of struggled with that question
Click on the one hand America is a democracy and in a democracy we go with what we the people want
Seemingly what we the people wanted was
For him to stay on
On the other hand he's just one guy
What's laws
Yasso Washington
Resisted
The office the king in different ways and
Wrote a great letter
To an English historian
A woman named
Catherine Macaulay Graham
And Washington remark to her that I walk on untrodden ground
Basically that everything I do
Is oppressive
Should I stay
Pusha T go
Garrison said however he answered that question it was going to reverberate forward in time
And so in the wee hours of the morn
September 19th 1796 George Washington
Pushes his Farewell Address newspaper any road back to Mount Vernon
Back to Virginia to Mount Vernon and and saying
People picking up the newspaper that day and appears to me proper especially as it make induced two or more distinct expression
Of the public voice that I should now appraise you of the resolution I have formed to decline being considered among the number
Of those out of whom a choice is to be made
Going just one newspaper had the Farewell Address is called the American Daily Advertiser but very soon I got reprinted
And many other newspapers is hard to overstate how surprising this would be because
All of Western history it almost never happened before that someone willingly gave up their power
Washington medaille 3 years later
Answer the message I think would have been clear that this was potentially in office for life
The way I like to imagine it is it by stepping down George Washington
Just barely avoids getting swept away in this
Kaley wind that have been blowing through the country
And with that one action he forced all the Fate
The state suspended above us 436 years
Until
Was there a president like
President in particular that change.
It's 1932 nation is in Desperate economic shape
Black Tuesday
Market crash
It's the Great Depression
Jobs savings
Thousands and thousands of banks started failing Farmers went bankrupt Americans were literally starving
But then
Franklin Delano Roosevelt rolled in
And he instantly
Takes charge
He had an incredible command over the media
Fireside Chats
Ladies and gentlemen
The president of the United States
We didn't have television
My friend
I want to talk
For a few minutes
When the people of the United States about blank
But he had this incredible ability to communicate directly with the American people through the radio
I want to tell you what has been done in the last few days
And why it was done
And what the next
SEPTA going to be
By speaking directly to the nation during its darkest time
We were strong enough to get out of the
Depression
He calmed our fears
Exchange
Congress the American people
Give him unprecedented power
He transformed the federal government took control of the economy
Establish huge new social welfare programs
And Americans elected FDR for four consecutive terms as president
And then
In 1945 in the middle of his fourth term
He dies
And you could say at this point
The country wakes up from
A collective dream
The depression is largely past
We've weathered Pearl Harbor most of World War II
And suddenly we're at war with ourselves
Fighting about
How much power a president should have
Wartime is one thing but
Forgodsake
Let's return to the
Conventional
Let's make it a constitutional
22nd
No person shall be elected to the Office of the President more than twice
And no person who has held the office
The president or acted as president
For more than two years of a term to which some other person was elected president
Shall be elected to the office of President more than once
That means two terms
You're out right right exactly on one hand it does seem kind of
Undemocratic to me in some ways that the American people
Continue to say
Yes we want that person
And there's an election every four years we respect the result of
It seems a little bit undemocratic to me that we
Would be limited as
As American people
I think you're right
Text Julie Metzger again
Present only stays on repeatedly depression is Real ACT
So
I think there is a strong Democratic argument of
Presidents whose able to get reelected in able to
Generate popular support
The Democratic answer would be to let the people elect the president
On the other hand Gillian says the presence of these days is soap
Powerful that once the president gets an office
They can bully at the competition they have access to all these resources a giant megaphone I think we have to
Acknowledge that there are a lot of factors that those limit
The extent to which
The result of our presidential elections are reflections
Of popular will
Pure and simple the 22nd Amendment
Might be undemocratic it does Tire hands
At the same time
Maybe that's a good thing
I mean take
As an analogy the story of
Ulysses
Inewstore Ulysses and his men have to sail past the sirens in
Byron Stingily beautiful songs that lure Sailors to their death
So Ulysses knows he's not going to be able to resist the song so he tells of men
I'm not going to be able to resist just tie me up
And then we'll go past the sign cuz I can't trust myself in the moment to make the right decision
Perhaps the 22nd Amendment
Is a little like that rope
The Ulysses uses to bind his hands so he doesn't waver
If it's a profit locked
There will be times when it will cost us
A good present we might want to keep
But it's a prophylactic measure to not let ourselves really entertaining those thoughts
I'm go down that road
It's one small way we've chosen to protect ourselves from that Sirens song Those kingly win
President
But sometimes blow
That was pretty sirkeli Prime
With liner notes
For the 22nd Amendment
And on the album covering the 22nd is in a Brooklyn band called
Pavo Pavo
They wrote a sort of
Crooning Indie pop ballad
From the perspective of a departing president
Here's an excerpt
More perfect is produced by meet you at album Rod Susie lechtenberg Julia Longoria Kelly Prime song
Sarkari and Alex overington
With help from Elie mystal Michelle Harrison Dave Gable
Thanks to Nora Keller for her help making a record 27 the most perfect album
And thank you to Jeffrey Wright for reading the amendments
You can listen to all the songs and read short and funny essays about the amendments
At the most perfect album. Org
I'm Chad I've been robbed
Thanks for listening