WNYC Studios
This is more perfect I'm jad abumrad
Season 3 of more perfect
We're releasing an album
Service song cycle of the amendments
United States,
Institution
And we're telling stories about each of those men
Some of you might recall
The last season
We did a deep dive
On the 2nd
We're going to rebroadcast
For you now it
Comes from Shaun Robbins firm
He hosts an amazing show called today explained
Really did a stint with us hear it more perfect
Second chance
I think we should start with one of the most confusing sentences in the constitution in the Bill of Rights not We the People
Not that one I got
A well regulated militia
,
Being necessary
To the security
Of a free state
,
The right of the people to
Keep and bear arms
,
Shall not be infringed
Salem
And do it do it with the commas
Sure a well regulated militia
, being necessary to the security
Of a free state
Oh, the right of the people to keep and bear arms
Totally unnecessary,
Shall not be infringed
Is that the one that's about guns
Adam Winkler who wrote the book on on the 2nd Amendment end of book is called gunfight he's a journalist
He's a professor of law at UCLA
He said it's almost as if James Madison the author of the amendment I just
Discovered this wonderful new thing the,
And wanted to put it in there as many times
Which is like
A nerdy professorial joke
But like seriously what is it in like
It had to be this one come to the Bendy Amendment about like quartering soldiers in your house that was really confusing
Guns that they made like chest
Indecipherable and ever since
Generations of Americans have been confused
By the language of the Second Amendment
So when the song was written we had just fought this war with the British
Is Revolutionary War
And they try to win it right from the get-go
Bike coming for our guns
So these new states are looking at this new federal government they're going
We don't know we want to trust you quite yet so there's the second amendment that says
You guys can fight back
Like the feds are going to disarm you you can your malicious
That's
I think what we agree on
But then after that you just look at the sentence
That is not just a
Comments that are confusing
If you look at the sentence
As a whole
Pieces don't seem to
Get together
There's some noun confusion
I mean
It's obvious that the sentence is about someone's right to bear arms but who
Who get that right
At the beginning of the sentence
You got a well regulated militia
Demolition
States have a right to form militias
Jets to assemble
Groups of people and those people got to have their guns
That's easy enough
But then later the sentence there's
Oh, the right of the people
To keep and bear arms
,
Shall not be infringed
The people
Which people
Those people over there in the militia
All people
If you mean all people
Why'd you say militia
It's like
The first Clause seems to point to some sort of collective right to bear arms
And the second clause
Seems to point to some individual right to bear arms
Life is supposed to be a popularly ratified document
It's actually not that easy to read
But it's not it wasn't that easy to read then
This is Jill Lepore
Staff writer at the New Yorker magazine
She's also a professor of American
I studied 18th century
I'm really trying in the seventeenth and eighteenth century American political
And Jill says
From the beginning when people thought about the Second Amendment they tend to
To just focus
On the first part
That the primary motivation for the amendment is
About militia well-regulated militia
But this confusing sentence was widely read as
This Collective
Melissa Wright
Not an individual one truth
Did the Second Amendment facts
Guarantees the right of an individual to
To bear arms in that the government federal government
In any fashion
Juices
I just didn't exist
I disagree with the way you characterize
That although what you said is
Stated in the media frequently Stephen halbrook he's represented the NRA in several
I've written several books on Second Amendment issues
He actually thinks a
The sentence is just
Is fine as is I don't think it's complicated at all the framers were thinking about an individual right
The Second Amendment refers to the right of the people to
First Amendment refers to the right of the people peaceably to assemble
I mean who is that it did this individuals or not some kind of collected that doesn't exist in reality
So which was it
That that's a really good question to add I mean
It's complicated 1/2 what I can tell you is that
No people I spoke to for the
The story said
At least in the 20th century when the when the second amendment was taught in law schools
It was taught this
It was taught as a sort of antiquated
Outdated
Thing that have to do with malicious
It's not so much individual rights
But
Stephen halbrook and their respective side something they can both agree on
Is that this
Super sacred Second Amendment the third rail
Of our American pilot
6 day. Just was not a thing
It was not like that it was utterly ignored ignored
This amendment
When I Was An undergraduate
Undergrad at Florida State University went to the forest
Supreme Court and start looking up law review articles on constitutional law issues and I found that
There was hardly anything written about the Second Amendment amendment that was less
Written about less
Legislated less activated
Lessa subject of Supreme Court conversation and the Second Amendment
Didn't think about guns
People had guns States regulated guns but for most of our history the Second Amendment
It was like
Luxardo runt of the Bill of Rights glitter like no one argued about it it's a striking thing to eat to think about
There was no fight
No fight how surprising that
It is given its centrality to our
Political car
Versation today
What is
Extraordinary
Because there was this window
Time work
All of this
Changes that the script
Just flips
There's two hundred years
Everything being chill
And then suddenly
You got
This
I want say those fighting words
From my cold dead hands
Gabriel So basically in
The Flash
The Second Amendment goes from being
Ignored
To be
Supposed to be Radioactive
And in the process
We start to read the thing totally differently all of a sudden this is hotly debated thing that's got nothing to do with
That first part
And everything
To do
What II
Her judges
Nothing you can do folks
And me
What are the Second Amendment people maybe there is that
But what I want to know is how did that happen
How do we start reading the Second Amendment the way we do now
And and what I found out is that
In the modern history of the gun rights movement and
And how we read the second amendment can be boiled down to these
Totally
Unrelated disjointed seeming
Revolutionary events in Sacramento
I'll be damned let me know what in the hell to a Revolt in Cincinnati in Prudential do you have to tell me
Show me I'm wrong
And finally
Number three
A reckoning
At the Supreme Court of the United
Unbelievable
Whois
Cat sound
Can you imagine that
So you can tell me the story in 3 chapter
Yeah
Rihanna
Supreme Court of the United States
Chapter one
The Invasion
I'm a carpenter I'm a builder I'm a stand-up comedian
Jazz drama
Structure repairman high performance aircraft
I need electromagnetic field backlight non-destructive testing for the Gemini Mister program
And I'm an expert shot with guns
I was extra shower guns when I was 12 years old I was raised a hunter and a fisherman
Besides being a carpenter and a builder
When I'm 12 years old my father buys me a high-powered rifle
Palliative ammo
I can't knock the elephant done with that s*** you said I'm getting at
Can I get you to tell me
We have to start at some point I have you tell me just
Your name and who are we are and who who who you are
My name is Bobby seale I created the Black Panther Party on the phone
Ending chairman of national organizer the Black Panther Party
Where in Oakland California
The Black Panther
Yeah so this transition from the militia to the individual my right to bear arms
You could argue that
That whole individual gun rights movements
Started
In the
With the Black Panthers
In Oakland it's an unlikely and kind of surprising origin for what's known as the individual rights interpretation of the Second Amendment
We would different breathe well read guys we do you know I history
Context is 1966
It's been
An exceptionally bad time for race relations all over the country
More than 1500 people were in the
Attack dogs and hoses
And in particular the tension between
Black community and police
60s high profile incidents
Of Officer shooting unarmed black man this is what was happening
You know and
What we did
Is that yet we took a position
October 1966
Bicillin is friend Huey P Newton they start this organization called the black panthers black panther party for self-defense
Defense
Fue Bobby's co-founder was 2 years in law school
You was going to the University of San Francisco School of Law
And one day he's sitting there as as you do law school thinking about the law
Think about Malcolm X thinking about what he can do in Oakland
And it hits
The Second Amendment of the Constitution guarantees
The citizen's right to bear arms
On public property
But they can argue that the Second Amendment gave them a right
Have a gun he said that's a constitutional Democratic civil human right
There's always been those who claim that
Second Amendment
Protecting an individual right to bear arms who argued that were in the minority
They want taken
Too seriously this was one of the first times that the individual rights reading was
Forced into
The mainstream because
We have a right to bear arms
We individuals
Then
We can control the police
Observe the police
Tell him that we control the police
What do eagles do you in law school so what legal status do we have
That second half of the Second Amendment right to bear arms
Possessing bear arms okay he also pointed to a California state law
It said you could carry a gun as long as it wasn't concealed the gun is not concealed is not illegal
So the Black Panthers started policing the police
We did
It would go out in arms patrols and follow police car on 7th Street
West Oakland California nightlife District police officer pulled over
Watching from down the
Street
And the crowds are together
And if you holding a gun yes he's holding a shotgun shotgun that I bought him
What's a high standard going to cost 89 or $79 I bought the damn gun Isis here Huey
You got your shotgun now
Is white cop on one-sided
Street arresting somebody
And the other side of the street you got a dozen black guys
Holding shotgun strictly for observation
Was standing in a line I had everybody standing in line
He told me the moment
The cop note
Stimuli stop what he was doing with the guy
Pulled over
And walked over to them and said
You have no right to observe me
And who is his no California state Supreme Court ruling states that every citizen has the right to
Standard Observer police officer
Check out the duty as long as it's not a reasonable distance away or reasonable
How to use a 10ft naproxen 20ft from You observe you whether you like it or not
He said man what kind of negroes are these
Let me see that gun no
You cannot touch my weapon the cop says
Are you a Marxist and USA are you a fascist
Are you a Marxist
Are you a fascist
Then the cops I asked you first
Are you saying I asked you second
Oh you up at
I mean
It's like a standoff
In this
Is where the dominoes start to fall
The Senate results until peacefully about the cops in Oakland are not happy and they
Family start
Running without the chain next thing we know
Society from nuts
Swiss gun
And I think we should act win10 Dua Mumford State Assembly Mumford who represented Oakland
Just trying to put a bill in the stuff Black Panthers
Shotguns
Guns in public places
What does Bill the Mulford Act
What is up for debate at the California state capitol in Sacramento
And Bobby seale decides the Panthers
Should be there for the debate and that they should take their guns
I took a delegation in arm delegation to the California state legislature May 2nd 1967
I have six women
N24 mail
How many guns
3 guns
And where they loaded
Yes
So they roll up the assembly in Sacramento and guess who happens to be waiting for them right there on the front lawn of the Sun
Are we talkin what what year were talking to
I don't know who it is
Guy by the name of win one for the Gipper I went up there
When we got there Ronald Reagan happened to be on the front lawn
Reagan
I did not know he was going to be there on the front line
He was on the front lawn Future Leaders of America
Kids
So you got Ronald Reagan 50-60 feet from us
And a bunch of white kids 1112
Hanging out on the front lawn of the of the State Building in Sacramento
Come running over where we are they thought we were done Club
And in the Press
Bollard
What's going on what's going on
And Bobby seale cuz I want to read a statement
The Black Panther Party for self-defense calls upon the American people in general
And that's what I read the statement had a black people in particular
Take careful note
Are there races California legislature which is now considering legislation
Aimed at keeping the black people disarm
Impalas at the very same time
Racist police agencies throughout the country are intensifying the terror
Brutality
Murder and repression of black people
Etcetera
While he was reading that uniform Capital guards come running out grab Ronald Reagan
Took him in the opposite direction from us away from the kids
Okay
Is it we decided to go inside
Because
December
Was in session at the time
Next thing I know
We all loading
Laundry elevator
He is shotgun rifles pointing up cameras in there
Crowded
Body touching body Crowder
When they got off the elevator he asked him which way to the spectator section
So the Panthers could watch the legislature debate the bill somebody says this way to the right
And so I walk into this door
And as I walk into the door
The president pro temp in the State Assembly win the actual
Close the Sims this is not the goddamn spectator section
I said come on get the hell out of here man win the wrong goddamn place
Walking to the state capitol
Rashad Evans
And then all hell breaks
Am I underweight
Take your hands off me
I turn around and I see
State Assembly NY State Assembly ducking down behind their deaths
Is this the way the racist government work don't let a man exercises
Is constitutional rights
I can point to this
Forgotten unknown moment here in the State Building in Sacramento
I've liked the game changer
For the conversation about guns in America
Because suddenly
Overnight we will on the front pages of newspapers around the world who are
Ragtag organization with this International notoriety in being introduced
Most of the world
You had a lot of people going
Wait what
Like there's a bunch of black man rolling around with guns
Walking into the Capitol Building when there's kids around what came of that that provided
The law said no one
Could carry a loaded weapon
Inside city limits
Within a hundred fifty feet of public property
This was directed at the Black Panthers we know it was
The people have all kinds of opinions about the Black Panthers and what they did
Particularly after Huey Newton shooting happened at 5 a.m. later that same year was arrested for shooting
And killing a cop approved blood marks the spot where twenty-three-year-old officer John Frey
Was found fatally wound
The case was eventually dismissed but
What seems clear is that the Black Panthers decision
To use the Second Amendment
To arm themselves to show up armed
At the state capitol in California inspired
A big risk backlash
FBI director J Edgar Hoover today asserted that the Black Panthers represent the greatest internal threat to the nation
Birkenstock
A Revolution was about to break out right here at home
This led to a whole new wave of gun control laws in California but also Federal gun-control nanny of
Seemed
To be targeted towards African-Americans
Rather than just reducing gun violence
America was like
We've got to get guns off the streets
But the irony was even though those laws were designed to
Disarm
Left-leaning black radicals
Many white rural conservatives
Thought that they were next
The government was going to take their guns next
Every action
Create a reaction
And at the same time that the Panthers thing is
Hitting front pages of newspapers
Around the world
You got a assassinations you got race riots you got Vietnam protest
All of a sudden everyone's clamoring for gun control
Democrats
And Republicans
In fact
Why out on the street
Fideo
Civilian should be
Carrying a loaded weapon
That was the exact same day
At the Black Panthers showed up at state capitol in Sacramento with their shotgun
Reagan Reagan was into gun control Reagan's got his fingerprints all over this
What's Happening Here
Is the Black Panther show up in the Capitol Sacramento and Ron Reagan react
They create some gun control
Then there's even more gun control even federal gun control
And a lot of people are sitting home watching this
And they start to get very
Upset
Which brings us
2 chapter 2
The revolt
You know we can't allow this to happen
I can buy the damn pistol that I want to buy
These two guys John aquilino live in Rockport Texas
Joseph turow Buffalo New York
They get us there and they've both been in the guns pretty much their entire lives
Fatherless
Veteran
World War 1
Did some recreational shooting with
My mother and I used to love to go to the amusement park
And spend all day shooting with 22
Little things that moved in the shooting gallery but neither one of them
Particularly hardcore about their dumb beliefs
Until around the time
The Black Panther
Give me the fact that here bunch of people who were
Slightly darker complected than New England
Ivy league grads
Running around with Firearms at the did that scare people
Hell yes
Did it scare you
I didn't scare me I did
John told me
Joe is well that
It wasn't the Panthers themselves that were the problem I don't like anybody
That tells me I can't do something is all the gun control laws that came
In the wake
When the gun control Act
Repasts
Today we begin to disarm the criminal
Carolyn
And then say
A lot of things just appeared that I had been used to Joe said he starts the gun shops in his neighborhood
Close
Like the furniture store in Buffalo that used to have shotgun
$5 think they stop selling them
And he says that is really bothered him because
The reason you have a gun
Is for protection another form of insurance
Which wasn't an abstract idea for him buffalo in the 60s and 70s
Not the thief
Best place in the world
His house
Was even broken into
I can only describe as
Wangjing beijing
He's got extra
Better
Their way
2 Doors
Joseph seen his wife and his dog huddled in one room with a gun
Wally's two guys storm through his house
And Rod
I think they grade my wife
Purse
Some other money
And they are
I mean by the time the police got there
David Bond
Jose whole relationship with Firearms disorder predicated upon that
This idea that it's
For self-defense
And here he's got
People breaking into his house
He's got
The cops not being there for him
He's got the government trying to take his gun away so
What do you do
You join the n
AR
Hey then I join
Flight discounts
But
This came at a moment where the NRA was at this
Crossroads online
Any edit seen before
Orson
Back when Joe joined in the early 70s the NRA
Was not the diehards
Supporter of gun rights
Let me know today
Because according to Adam Winkler
It was never meant to be the idea behind the NRA
To be fundamental right down
Today was to increase Civilian Marksmanship training
So that the next time there's a war Americans would be
Capable of fighting it
You know you don't hear much about the NRA's founders
But the NRA was formed in the 1870s right after the Civil War by a reporter for the New York Times
Who thought that the Union Soldiers had been so ineffective
In the Civil War because they were not familiar with firearms
Really yeah
But a hundred years their main focus was
Like teaching Boy Scouts how to shoot straight not the Second Amendment
And apparently if you go back through issues of American Rifleman
40s
50s
Are the enemies version of Playboy guns instead of
Girls you'll be amazed that you can't find a single mention of the Second Amendment anywhere in those magazine
The NRA at that point was
Sort of like a gun trade group they work
Not super political and and the people who ran it
They were Hunters
John Hunt
They were just like these wealthy businessmen who like to hunt according to Joe guys who
Yeah they were hobbyist
You had all these people coming in like Joe and like John who were convinced
The guns weren't about
Shooting ducks they were about Schultz
Protecting yourself against criminals
In a time of starkly Rising crime rate
And this would lead to this straight up
Head on collision
At the NRA
Now
Joe and John join the NRA
The organization address
For the first
Time
So to set up this lobbying are
Yeah it was the brand new Institute for legislative action
John actually got hired to work there in 1976
And this true for legislative action
Supposed to fight for gun rights
Stop Chapel Hill that's what they both wanted to do but
Let's put it this way
We were the
If you would the bastards
Step-children
What's the National Rifle Association
Really
Yeah when the institute for legislative action
Was formed in 1975
The NRA
Refuse the insta
Attitude NE
Office Space
In the building
In the mid-seventies the part of the NRA that Lobby politicians
Had to rent office space from the hotel next door to the NRA
Is crazy
And then
Right after he was hired 78 people
Fire
Very interesting lady big firing
And then there was word
Did the NRA want
Wave Wash
Selva headquarters there and moved Colorado Springs
What's in Colorado Springs
Camp they were going to move to headquarters and put it in there this
Olympic sports training group
So that they could then start writing all the magazines about all the Olympics
Sports
They really didn't know what the hell they were doing they wanted to
Turn the NRA from
Organization of firearms owners
A Publishing Company
They wanted to get I was just
Politics
The older guard didn't seem to have the stomach for whatever done fight
Some members wanted to hat they were very moderate they thought like
Maybe we should try and kind of
Get out of this hole gun business plan
Not just kind of getting out
John says there's even a moment when
A report surface that suggested we should change the name of the association
Really
Yeah they were going to take rifle out
Tell me more tell me everything
Do you remember what any of those proposed names or no
But they were considering at least taking rifle out
Oh yeah
Huh
And it
It is Bridal
I mean I was
So pissed off
And that's
When
The seeds of revolt
We're playing it
A few months later
I'd like to call them
Annual member
This is from one of those meetings
Cincinnati Ohio
77 the annual
NRA meeting of members
If it was me but I'm not sure hey 22nd
They had a big Auditorium a Cincinnati Convention
The thousand people
Shut up Tumblr
Trina
Jena Malone
Now
Pride of this big meeting
Brandon little league
Secret meeting
Joe and a few other guys smell on my taxes
Arizona been going back and forth
Phone by mail
Florence Kentucky
And they decided to form a small
Pierce faction Lin the NRA
And your secret that you have a name to call someone
Google call the Federation for the NRA
Call ourselves
Federation
Foreigner
And this tiny group
Planned
Akoo
Honorary light red hot
Jamie Knight
Cincinnati
The Federation members were all wearing buttons
National Rifle Association with the word rifle underlined or orange hats
Red walkie talkies
Connect with each other how many people were there somewhere between
Denovellis spread out through the meeting start to remember
Well basically
Please remind me today did all the niceties
I pledge allegiance
Allegiance
Would you buy
Opening prayer
Lord
You are awesome
Blah blah blah blah blah
And then
There are four
When it came time for the members part of the meeting where
Members submit proposals which happens in like this
Super parliamentary sorta way
This guy Neil Knox
He was part of their group kind of bullrush the mic
And he said
The Gather members have a list of bylaws
Did they would like to have voted on
Translation
Bugattis 15 demand
15 demands
Not sure if it's more or less than Martin Luther
Basically number one we demand that the NRA not move
Cancel that the institute for legislative action which
You want to kill
Should have more power through hell yes
Hell yeah
And we demand that the current NRA leadership
Beer place
We wanted to take over
So the Federation guys making all these demands
What was
Crazy
Was that the leadership of the NRA
That was one of the meetings they just sat
They they were like
Dumbfounded
But every time the Federation guy would make a motion judge Porter would say no do I have a say
Second
Okay the most
Has been a debate would be
Would start to speak for and against each men
The Federation members will use their walkie-talkies
Coordinate who spoke at what microphone
How many votes did you need that day
I think this leash.
And how many votes did you think you had if you needed 600 so how many did you think it we hadn't the slightest idea
Going in we anticipated
50/50
Lisa pork
So as each of the 15 amendments are being debated the insurrectionists are running around in their orange caps with their walkie-talkies
Discussion debate
Blessed eight
Hours from 7 p.m.
For 5 in the morning 4 a.m.
And nobody love
They were all there
There were
I mean we really didn't know whether to pull this off
But Joe says one of the big turning points
Is when a guy named Bob Kukla gets up to the mic he was at the time the head
Of the institute for legislative action
You get into the mic
And
He
Play the tape cassette tapes right this was one that Bob Kukla secretly recorded I don't know how he did it.
You here on this tape is Bob Kukla talking to his bosses at the NRA and they're yelling at him berating him
Or going to war
Every time somebody
He talks about guns
The reason we like Bob
Shut up
He had to take there and
You played it over the
And of course that electric
Defied the odds
Do you could actually hear people
Gasping
The rank-and-file
Audibly
This was this was evident
The other side
Is going to deep six
The gunman
Metro fights
People
On the tape they're all in the room
Oh yeah
There's sister sitting next to him
The table
Over the course of this one nine our meeting
On a hot steamy night in Cincinnati
Every single one of those 50 proposals
Was passed
We stopped the building in Colorado
Ensure the answer I wouldn't change its name
Expired the leadership just like the political savant
That figure that Hillary is going to get the presidency
They just
Absolutely took it in their shorts
And maybe the biggest change the most important change
Was that
The Institute for legislative action this
Political lobbying arm of the NRA
It was given the keys
To the car
They were not
The bass
Bastard stepchild anymore they were
The NRA
You know what
We won and essentially
Staged
What are they called 1776
It's the same thing
When the sun rose the very next day
The NRA have
Whole new board
Committed
To a new
No compromises
Does view of the sacrament
Individuals have a right not only to have a gun but to have
Almost any gun that they want and have as many of them
I can take those guns
Almost anyplace they want
American Gun Parts
Literally changed overnight
And just shortly after this coup
The NRA
Both
This Abridged version of the Second Amendment right on the wall front center and its head coach
The Rite of
People to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed
Nice clean
Totally uncomplicated
Conveniently left out was the
The part that talked about a well regulated militia
Be necessary for
Security of a
Free state
I asked John like what about the militia part of the set
Why doesn't the NRA ever talk about that now you get me back to asking you if
John I love you dearly trust me
But
It's only been in less what 30 years
That if you'll pardon the expression
The b******* media has turned the militia into a four-letter word
The militia is you and me Sean
Post-coup
The NRA took a very hard line on gun control
And became an irrepressible political force in America
Grandinfo agree the NRA's power to scare congressman
Lies and its ability to mobilize its members in any congressional district
The touch of a computer button
They start pouring millions of dollars into lobbying NJ
A few years after that Cincinnati revolt
The NRA endorses its first presidential candidate
The Constitution does not say
The government shall decree
The right to keep and bear arms
Reagan
Reagan the Constitution says the right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be
French
At this point everyone and their Uncle leaves out the militia Park
Of the Second Amendment
Which is why Americans eventually start to forget that
The militia clause or whatever you want to call it even exist
I wish I could save that instead of the last
One of these at most surprised me when I was doing some research this is julep
By the 1990s
The new interpretation of the Second Amendment had so penetrated
Popular opinion
That people were more familiar with the Second Amendment then with the
Best Buy 1990s
The First Amendment
That Eclipse really
Kind of shock
But even if you did the Panthers and the president in the American people are all down to sort of forget about this militia
Clause of the 2nd Amendment
It didn't mean a lot without the courts
And of course
Particularly the Supreme Court
Woodbine
The US Supreme Court from 1969 to 1986
Warren Burger
Song giving a television interview and he says that this new interpretation is it
Second amendment was
What are the greatest pieces of fraud I repeat the word fraud
On the American public
That I have ever seen in my life
And this was a republican appointed by
Richard Nixon now
Yeah
Yeah so the Supreme Court obviously not
Dying to have this conversation at the moment
But it's not just the Supreme Court if you look at the federal courts the entire
Federal court system in America
That there's not once in our history at this point over 200 years
Been a single instance
Of some gun law some State local gun law
Getting up to a court and the court going you know what you can't do this
It violates the second amendment that does not even happen
Really
Not even the weather like in Mammoth Smackdown anywhere in federal court this isn't this isn't a thing
Current Supreme Court to weigh in on it
That doesn't even look like it could be a thing it doesn't even look like much more than a fantasy
Until
For gun owners there
Q names
Become synonymous
Protecting our rights
Ladies and Gentlemen please welcome
A true patriot
Dick Heller
Dick Heller showed up
Freedom
Twitter
And changed everything everywhere out there
More perfect will continue in a moment
Heller in 2008 revives the Second Amendment or you could even say
Breathes life into the Second Amendment because the Second Amendment
Had never been taken truly seriously by
My federal courts
Until 2008
That Cindy levenson professor at the University of Texas law school
This is my perfect I'm Chatham Rod here with Sean Roberts firm
Price of Sean
Chad
It's I guess now it's time for chapter 3 to kill a right they were going to get to dick
But first
Here's what's going on in America
2nd Amendment has become
One of those issues that can get you elected
Academic
Have begun to have a vigorous debate about its meaning
But the Supreme Court
Is still staying out of it
They're leaving this up to the states
Which already have all sorts of gun laws of their own to deal
But then December 12th
2000 Republican George W Bush become president elect
After divided US Supreme Court has effectively halts recount in Florida contested presidential vote tally
George W bush is elected
The NRA likes George W bush
National Rifle Association
And he likes
The proud history
I protecting
II am in
To the United States cost
Petition and in 2001 the Bush Administration declared that the Second Amendment protected an individual
Right to own guns
UCLA law professor Adam Winkler
Again right that was not limited
Is most courts have held
The service in the militia
And almost right after he gets into office Bush's Attorney General John Ashcroft
Put out a letter
This public letter to the NRA announcing that the Department of Justice
Adopted a new interpretation of the Second Amendment
And then right around the same time as the Bush Administration memo came out
Texas
Ruled that the Second Amendment did protect an individual right to bear arms
And that was a first
The big deal
Before this
All the decisions of kind of
Beard in the other direction
And because of that Court ruling
And John Ashcroft letter
List three libertarian lawyers
Alan gura
Constitutional attorney
Bob Levy
A chair the board at the Cato
Toot and Clark neily thought the timing was right we thought it was a good time for some litigation
I want thing you need to know about these guys is that they weren't
Family doing it for the guns they had no association with the NRA or the gun rights movement for them it was
More about getting the government to back off in our country when the government wants to restrict our Liberty
It isn't coming on the government to make the case for it isn't coming on the government to say here's why you shouldn't be permitted
To exercise that right
So that was their angle
Always wondered why the gun rights movement has become such a proxy war for like anti-government
Mint
Is Mmm Yeah well I mean if you think about this something professor
Sandy Levinson told me
Is that sort of embedded in this amendment
That is
The very idea that you can take up arms against the governor
Protect yourself
And your fellow man from tyranny
On the far right
Or occasionally on the far left
You find people who are willing
Say this that this is really what
Terrific about
The Second Amendment
But mainstream conservatives in mainstream liberals
Arnott
Very happy with those arguments they are embarrassed by them
And so mainstream conservatives
Want to talk about self defense against
Burglars
And mainstream liberals
Want to talk
About
How
The second amendment protects State organized militias
And
Almost nothing else
Anyway getting back to the story
These three libertarian lawyers they decide
Put together case and their idea was to
The target this really restrictive gun law
In DC
All handguns were banned you can own a shotgun or a rifle but the law specifically made it illegal to ever put a round in the chamber
Even in self-defense or there is
There's really Funk we we we described it as a ban on all functional Firearms but in order to challenge that law
They needed to find a plaintiff
Interesting how do you find a
Plaintiff
You look for somebody who
Got robbed what do you do
Well we can actually instigate
Litigation
We can take out a
Full page ad in the New York Times saying you want them indicate your second amendment rights give us a ring essentially got the word out talk to
I would say between
2 + 3000
People they all had
Really interesting stories they found a guy who was gay gentleman named Tom Palmer could previously been
Assaulted when he lived in California
Because he was gay
Was almost murdered by a skinhead mahbuba phobic
Subs and he wanted a gun
To protect himself
Are lead plaintiff was an African-American woman named Shelly Parker
She was trying to protect yourself against
Local drug dealers and the cops actually told her she should get a gun
Which was illegal
Weird so they have this whole group so we ended up with three men and three women mid twenties to early 60s
Former y2am rapper
American and the problem they ran into
Was that all these super sympathetic plaintiff
Didn't have this very special thing they needed
To bring a case
Standing standing with a legal term meaning they didn't have a sufficient grievance to be in court like if you can bring a case
Have to show that you've been actually harmed by
Not being able to get a gun you have to show some physical concrete proof
The harm has been done that you've been
Denied a gun
And none of the plaintiff had that
Except for one
Dick
That's me
Good to meet you and you
DeKalb
What does your dad say
Sean this is my favorite hat
Make America
Free again
Actually gets paid by The Fray
With a big Western handgun in the center
It looks like you drew a trigger out there that what you did well it was missing the trigger so
We had to update it
Who's we
Okay
Where's the Supreme Court
Building where he became famous he's
Swim seventy five year old white guy
Sports classes that look straight out of the 70s
Got a situation here you want to cross
Sure what's the situation
The anti Trump protesters are here actually happened to meet him in DC today after Trump
Trump won the election the hate Freedom apparently
President-elect is visiting the White House
There were protesters everywhere
Cornet
Notmypresident there anti Trump protesters
Don't you like Freedom what about 3
Freedom
What about freedom
Most of the protesters that were passing us wear white but
Just as a few young black men pacify
He says
See you on the plantation
Freedom
Yeah
I just say that
We in Washington we call it the government Plantation
You didn't mean
You kids are about to be slaves or something cuz that's how I interpreted it
The more power government has the less Freedom you have the closer you get the ball and chain
Other Plantation
This pretty good place to eat right there
If you here for a couple of days if you been in there
I have not been a pretty good
Okay Hyatt Regency this is good for you we can do this
We need to talk about Hyatt which is just down the street from Supreme Court and
And explain to me that his journey with guns like John and Joe
Began pretty casually
Like 1976
Is living in DC
And
One day he's sitting at home
I was watching
My hero Matt Dillon Gunsmoke
Different Matt Dillon
And he had this long-barreled handgun
I was about 30 years old
And I figured ghali
I should own my first gun
So when I went and bought
My when I call my Matt Dillon special
Hi standard 22 revolver Matt Dillon Buntline
And it was just
I live in America
We're Cowboys Society
I should have a cowboy gun and was just
Nothing no really deep thought to it
But then just a few months after he got that gun in October 1976
Started with the Mulford Act
And the Black Panthers back in Sacramento
Hits Washington DC DC gun control regulations outlawed
Firearms ownership get that gun law which outlawed all hang out so I had some choices
I could
Turn it into the government
Not going to happen
I can throw it in the Dipsy dumpster
Or there was no other option I could go to jail
Not going to happen eventually he decides on option D
Give the gun to his brother my brother lived in Maryland
So that made it very convenient
Did you just go visit your gun in Maryland what did you do
I yes I would go visit
And caress and use my gun
What did you use it
Target practice
Of course
Take me to
Gun visitation situation sound functional but
I think like any long-distance relationship they mostly sucked because
More and more he didn't feel safe where he lifts I lived about 10 blocks from the Capitol building right across the street
From
The number one most infamous
Drug
Dealer Den
In the city called Kentucky courts
Every night at 2 a.m.
The chief drug dealer would fire a 9 mm
Into the air empty the clip
And that was the signal
Every night at 2
Drug dealing was over
For the day
It's clear that living through the crack epidemic in DC really
Shaped a lot of dicks views on gun
So
In the years after the handgun ban
Dick starts the very long process of finding a way to get his gun back to DC and he eventually then quits his desk job
To pursue getting his gun back
Full-time I'm all over Capitol Hill
And I see
Security guards
Have guns
Well
Going
Why can't I be a security guard
Golly
Maybe that would help me
Have a gun
But I can't have on my own
Let's see how easy or not easy this is
Dali
One Step leads to another
Just like that
Dick was able to have a gun in DC but only during the day
And only while he was working
Like Barney Fife
At the end of my shift I have to turn in my gun and my bullets
And they kept it there
And they kept it on sidon
He finally starts looking for some help
Some legal help
I knew Washington cuz I lived here and I've gone to something tanks
Cato in Heritage and some others I knew they existed and right around the time out there looking for some help
Turns out these lawyers are out there looking for some dick
No
Wasn't there ideal sympathetic guy I was told repeatedly and it was in print that I was the worst
Choice less-than-optimal
You know because of that Plantation thing you said or
He was always talk smack about the federal government and interviews
One day
Clark neily
Put a note in my hand and said dick Heller
This is what you say
I just wanted a gun
Protect my house
Shut up
Play it wasn't their favorite princess
But the one thing that no one else has done
Which is besides just wanting
An illegal handgun in DC he actually fill out an application
To register a gun that he already possessed again in Virginia
And had that application denied and he had this denial slip or whatever
Call me like literally had this physical proof
All of his grievance
And simple technical arbitrary little stupid piece of paper gave him
What's known as standing to bring the case
Dick Heller ended up being on the last man standing there was nothing to do but that was not our choice regardless
And I became their guy and these three lawyers
They take the case of the DC court and the judge after
Inspecting it said
The case can go forward
Magic Moment
This Magic Moment
The Supreme Court is entering the debate over the Second Amendment right to bear arms
Today's cases roster huge interest among citizens and politicians alike and it is divided even the president
And vice president
Chapter 3
The record
March 18th
The day the Heller case was argue that the
In court everyone understood how high the stakes were
Outside in front of the Supreme Court protesters by the hundreds were marching and
Panting
Favor of gun rights and in favor of gun control
Journalist
From all over the world to send it upon the supreme court that day
An inside the Supreme Court House
Not a creature was stirring not even a mouse
You could have heard a mouse I say
And
Everybody is just quiet
And you can hear your heart beating
And suddenly
Bam
And then Oye Oye Oye
The clerk yelled at the top of his lungs
And then there's a strange sound
What can that be
It was the swishing
Of the Robes of the justices as they ascended the steps
To the bench
Unbelievable
We will hear argument today in case 07 to 90 District of Columbia vs. Heller
This is the first time in our history the Supreme Court with directly try to figure out what the Second Amendment mean
Richard ehlinger
Good morning mr. chief justice and may please
Walter Dellinger gets up
And jumps right into it
Essential question like
What was James Madison thinking when he wrote the super confusing sentence
Was he
Thinking about the individual people and their right to own a gun or was he thinking about the collective right
Of the militia to own a gun
In the first text to consider
Is the phrase protecting a right to
Keep and bear arms
If you look at the phrase the phrase keep and bear arms
Hot was used at the time
Every person to use the phrase bear arms
Used to refer to the use of arms
In connection
Whitman service
When he says people have a right to bear arms
All he really means is
Report for Duty
Keeping and bearing arms when do you list the Amendments first Clause confirmed
That's a right
Keep arms just the people in the state militias why wouldn't they say
State militias have the right to keep arms
Listen to Justice I believe that the phrase
The people
And the phrase the militia
We're really in sync with each other
The Federalist farmer uses
The phrase
The people are the militia
Cut against you if the militia included all the people
Includes all the people
Yes I do believe in include
At this point everyone start interrupting each other
Metallica scrum and they're all trying to figure out
Okay so when Madison what the phrase
Thinking of the people
What those words meant with the people just the militia or everyone all the people
What is the relationship between the second part of the sentence the people part and the first part of the sentence
The militia part Verdugo rokita
Common-law Highlander Scottish Highlanders for some reason
Farms in both Clauses diagram
Cycling cases
Discord
Internet results
According to Adam Winkler
Was
For liberals
Stevens
Souter retire Ginsburg
Seem to want to emphasize the militia part of the sentence
Avenue had the 4 conservative justices Scalia
Thomas Alito Roberts 15 to 1 emphasize the people part of the sentence
The second part I don't see how there's any any any
Contradiction team captain quarterback
The first chair that day was
Without a doubt Justice Antonin
Scalia why isn't
Perfectly
Plausible
Indeed
To assume that since the framers knew that the
Destroyed by tyrants
Justice Scalia
Of course was
Very conservative Justice grew up in Queens
This is Joan biskupic longtime reporter covering the Supreme Court has also written a biography of Justice Scalia
Avid Hunter and he grew up in a time when
Young men were trained in firearms in high school auction
Even from the time he was a kid at school and queens he said he used to carry his gun
For rifle practice
School
On the Subways of New York
Can you imagine doing that today in New York City
You're being unrealistic
The second clause is not broader than the
The principal purpose
Second floor
Just the right of the people
To keep and bear arms
It's going to be
What year throughout the arguments is that Scalia is very very forward Lee pressing
This word of individual rights
Argan speaks
And just like David souter
Are arguing back saying
What are the collected the militia
This goes on for well over an hour the justices grilling lawyers arguing amongst themselves
Everybody trying to figure out what was in James Madison's head
Until finally
Justice Breyer
One of the liberal just waited like you're saying
Is unreasonable the phone
Forget what Madison intended
There is no way for us to know
Let's talk about now
Talk about gun violence
This sentence was most
Definitely written about muskets
What about handguns and assault rifles
What is reasonable
Now 82 a hundred thousand people
Every year
Where in the United
State
Or either killed
In
Gun-related
Homicide
Crimes
4 Act
Or suicide suicide
That's why I say 81
Now in light of that
Why
Isn't a ban on handguns
Reasonable
Or April
Fortunate
On behalf
Because you are
The same reason I was offered by
Numerous Military Officers
At the highest levels
Of the US military all branches
Service
Writing to briefs
They they agree with us at the handgun ban
Search the week in America's military
Preparedness because basically argues
When you take away people's guns
They're going to be less prepared
If and when they enlist in the army
To which Jessie
Spires like
They can still practice shooting
Rifles banned in DC
They can go to gun ranges I guess in neighboring
What does that make it unreasonable for a city
With a very high crime rate
Assuming
Objective is what the military people say to keep us ready for the draft
If necessary
Is it unreasonable
People first city without high crime rate
Just say no
Handgun
Here
Well you want to say yes that is correct but I want to hear what
Because it is a big crime problem I'm simply getting you to focus
Stop by the way it was Justice Scalia telling Alan gura
How to answer just as Breyers
Question
Is Justice Scalia
And actually feels any standard of review that might be offered under Section
Construction
The oral arguments last 97 minutes
Far longer than most other cases and going into the arguments many
Supreme Court Watchers
Figured the case would be a close 5-4 decision
And it could go either way
And as with
All of these clothes cases
Question was what would Anthony Kennedy the swing just
Do
As in so many issues in America
Comes down to what does Anthony Kennedy believe
So at the oral argument and I had the Good Fortune to be at the oral argument in the Heller case
Everyone was looking
Here what would he say about the Second Amendment
His was really devoted
Accountant and the very first comment he made
They are concerned
Himself and his family against hostile Indian tribes
Wolves bears and grizzly something like that
One of the first things he said was about bears
Like not bear arms but
Grizzly bear
The point County was trying to make with clear
Don't you think the framers had other reasons that they wanted people to have guns
Other than just being in a militia
What about people being in their homes
And is meeting to defend themselves
And that's when I silently screamed at the top of my lungs so nobody could hear me yes
Sweet
...
Something
We were turned out to be historic
Supreme Court decision handed down this morning
Columbia versus Heller
We hold that the second amendment guarantees an individual rights
And that the district's handgun ban as well as its requirement that firearms in the home
Be rendered inoperative
Violate
It was
A groundbreaking reading of the Second Amendment
Scalia minimize
Steck was referring to a well regulated militia and put the stress on the second Clause that refer to the right
Right of the people the people will not be deprived of the right
Keep and bear arms
This was as good as it got for him on the bed
I think so
Rip the militia clause
December 15 1791
The June 26 2008
A pretty good run if I'm being honest
For the first time in the history of these United States
The courts definitively declared that the second amendment gives
Every American
The right to a gun for self-defense
It was a it was a great day for freedom in America was a great day for the Constitution great day for citizens
The great day for gun owners it was great day for
Fearful people
Of course
Not everyone agreed I mean to me that's a travesty
This is Jack Rico
Professor of history and political science at Stanford University for the court and
The history is just
Wrong
The Second Amendment is not about individual right argue that we shouldn't even be talking
About his
Because Rachel Firearms has changed so radically for the 18th century to our own time
And ultimately
And hear your Echo Justice Stevens in his descent
And what political Thicket
To be honest I mean
I don't really believe in constitutional law anymore
I think I socialize affection
Pianos become so highly politicized
In so many areas
I think I socialize
Is bunk
Wow I just destroyed I'm not a lawyer so that I don't have any professional steak and defending the Judiciary
What
There's a very
Big
But he did have a major caveat the next section of our opinion points out that like most rights
The Second Amendment right is
He said like all right
It's not absolutely it is not a right to keep and carry any weapon whatsoever in any manner whatsoever
And for whatever
Which is very important
To keep in mind
Cast doubt
Possession of firearm
You
Or lost
Forbidding the carrying of
The firearms
Sensitive places touch
This is another thing that we tend to forget
The decision says every individual has the right to bear arms
The most interesting lie like the decision also says
Of course
We need gun control
Edward Heller
Come to represent
Like
2nd Amendment rights
Are you for or against Hillary
Even though
Being for Heller
Is being for Duncan
Fusing yeah it is
After all this time
Still just
Totally confusing
You have a right to a gun
But the government has a right to regulate
Decal gets his gun back in DC
But DC still also has all sorts of gun regulations
You see the same pattern all over the country some states are lenient
Summer super strict
And both approaches seem to comply with Heller
In a way the Heller Decision
Is just like all those
Commas and Clauses that we started with in James Madison sentence
It's this
Confusing declaration
That leaves the door wide open for interpretation
Which
Obviously sucks
We could use
A little more
Clarity on
How to live with this
Second Amendment right to bear arms
Open
It gives us an opportunity I think
Opportunity to get it right to fix it
Nothing but now be pretty good time
What story was produced by Sean ROMs firm
Adam Winkler Facebook
Which a lot of our research
Which is drawn from skulls gunfight
More perfect
Express by me jeroboam rod
Jenny Lawton
Julia Longoria
Kelly Prime Sean ROMs firm
Alex overington
Sarkari
Suzie lechtenberg
With Elie mystal Cristian farias Linda Hershman David Gable and Michelle Harris
Supreme Court audio is from Oye
A free law project in collaboration with the Legal Information Institute at Cornell
Leadership support for more perfect is provided by the Joyce Foundation
Additional funding is provided by the Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation