Listener-supported
WNYC Studio
Small perfect on jad aboumrad season 3
Season 3
This season we're going to do something a little different than what was done in the past
Can you tell me how many amendments
No ma'am not gay
Coffee and I don't know I have no idea I'm guessing somewhere around 10
I would guess somewhere around
20 21 or 23 24 25
There are 27 Amendments
Did the United States Consul
This season we're going to focus
On those words
Explain why
First of all the name Moore
The name of this podcast
Comes of course
From the preamble to the Constitution
In the reason we chose that name
A couple reasons me first of all it's a weird phrase
Can't really have something be more
Perfect
Because Perfect Isn't absolute
But beyond that
The phrase sort of gesture that this idea that America is
Constantly evolving
It's never done
They were always in the process of trying to drag ourselves out of the mud
And get to those higher ideals
Make ourselves
Moorpark
Be more perfect
Very often we don't make
Marriott
We're always
Trying and that is embodied in our founding
I mean we wrote this thing called the Constitution
And then we kept changing
Mending it adding a new rights filling in Holes
Where we fail so that we don't fail again
So far we've done that 27 times
The season were going to look at all 27 what do they mean why are they important
How do they hold us together
In these turbulent
* but the thing is when you read these amendments
The words themselves can feel very abstract very musty very far away
So
We decided to make an album
Actual album
In the spirit of Schoolhouse Rock
We reached out some the best
Best artist musicians around the world we asked them to make a song
About an amendment
Did the United States Constitution
No idea this was going to work
But we put out some calls
And we got all of these amazing artists
Participate in this compilation
Kashdoll abuses her Dolly Parton the Dolly Parton wrote a song for us
What's the 19th Amendment
Devendra Banhart
Where the song about the 25th Amendment
Richmond
For two years of continuously working on this weird
Super proud to announce
The most perfect album
Which is now on iTunes
Spotify
All the places
And you can listen to it online right now in its entirety and it's amazing
At the most perfect
Fixed album
. org
Now in the podcast season which begins now
What we're going to do is tell stories about these men
Soar like a little audio liner notes
To accompany the song
Suzuki funny
Sometimes
Hilarious sometimes pointed sometimes
Poetic little stories
About the Amendments that hopefully explain what they are
And
Why they matter too
So
Get started first amendment
Freedom of religion speech press assembly and
Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion
We're getting the free exercise thereof or abridging the freedom of speech or of the press
The right of the people peaceably to assemble and to petition the government for a redress of grievances
Wind speed
Metro Baptist Church
Rihanna Love the Chief Justice and Associate justices
United States
That was one of these submissions that we got for the First Amendment from the band
Cherry glazerr you can hear that song and everything in its entirety at the most perfect album. Org
Got to submissions for the first amendment in a play another one in a second first
The liner notes
What's the First Amendment
Which come from
Producer sarkari
Sorry ready
Okay
Here goes
This is a this is a funny story this is it this is a story about my about my technological incompetence
This is Burton Uber
Norman dorsen
Professor and civil liberties
At New York University law school is like casually a big deal
I was the national legal director of the ACLU under Ronald Reagan and
Ibanez Ibanez constitutional comp
I mean I someone who
Tries to enforce the Constitution for more than 50 years remember you saying that you've argued cases
Front of the Supreme Court right
Yeah and argue
Number of cases myself in a court and if it in the breach
Copper 200
So I spent a fair amount of my time
Waiting on the Supreme Court steps
Okay so
One Summer
When he was just starting out as a professor
V 1996
I had a wonderful asset
Who work for me
And she been with me for
4 years
I am one day she sent me a personal point I'm so tired
I was taking your handwritten draft
Typing them up
And then having you giving you the typewritten version then you change it then I have to
Retype it
Have you ever heard of this thing called a laptop
Cornell computer she basically says to him
You know crazy idea why don't you just learn how to type
We could make the changes much
After I wouldn't have to retype
What time and you find it much easier to work
I should know tools
I don't know
I never never learn to talk
Why can't I just can't do it let's just keep going I like writing by hand makes me think
She said well I'm going to do you a great favor
Said I'm not going to type your stuff anymore
You don't understand how it works I'm the boss you're the employee
I tell you what to do you like this if I tell you and she said no no no you don't understand I Know Who You Are
Learn how to use the computer it's the best present I can give you
So what do I do I do if my laptop
And I decided I would learn how to read how to use WordPress
Twista
Program everybody
So what do I do I type out the Bill of Rights
That's the text I know best
To the Bill of Rights
Starts with this
Text
That basically says
We the states
We think that this constitution need some more
It doesn't do enough
To give the people rights
To protect them from
All of his power that the government has
So what we're going to do is
Midget throwing
Extra rights
Is Extra Protection
That
We think really
Every American should have one of the things I wanted to do was figure out how to move
Who's text you know you highlight the text and then you can move it from one place to another
First practice
How to learn how to highlight text
And so I typed the Bill of Rights out all all 10 amendments
I'm in the next door
Practicing by highlighting
Portions of the text Congress shall make no law respecting the First Amendment to the right of trial
Aruba jewelry shopping
Voluntary service
Copy paste cecibel search and seizure
I'm moving stuff around
Unusual punishment
Every single time I move it around
Is something that tells me that it's
It's no it's it's there's something fundamentally
Florida
I thought well it's because you so used to
The old way
The new way is more than you know is it's something that you really can't process
But I realized I don't really look at it very much as a whole anyway
Ghetto been hard-pressed to tell you
Exactly what words came where I began to realize
That there is
Text that we have
The 10 amendments that we have
ADP
Structure
The same kind of deep structure that you would find in a poem
Take for example the First Amendment
1st Amendment
Freedom of religion
Beach Press
Assembly
Petition it consists of six idea
Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion
Or prohibiting the free x
Exercise Theory
2 or abridging the freedom of speech or of the press
Or the right of the people peaceably
Way to assemble
And to petition the government
For redress of
Could have been written on the back of an envelope
These days the first amendment is
Wrapped up in all kinds of
Thorny stuff like
Kneeling at football games and
Hate speech and money in politics
But if
You
Just step back
From all of that
And you read the text of the First Amendment
And you really try to think about
What the words are trying to say
You find that the logic behind it is
Kind of beautiful
The order of the words in the First Amendment
Is the life cycle of a democratic
Trinity means
So those first two clauses
Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion
Or prohibiting the free exercise thereof
Create a free space
Inside your mind
Believe as you wish
That's the founder saying
That space inside your head where you think your thoughts
That's sacred
The government can't touch that there can be no government so that's the first idea
The freedom of your thoughts once you believed
Don't want to say it which brings us to the next
Or abridging the freedom of speech Clause says if you got an idea
Why won't you go ahead and share it see you the freedom to
I think about the freedom to speak that thought
If you really want to make a real dent in
Do you need some way to be able to speak
Speak in a very loud voice which brings you to the 4th Place
The Press
Which is speech amplify
Once you gotten your message out to a large number of people when people would listen to these ideas and move
It's natural for those people
I want to do something about it
To move together
I'm too organized for the right of the people peaceably to assemble
So you can think of that even speak that.
You can create a movement but that's not why
Which is the six
Idea a petition process
Web search
Twitter search you have a right to take your argument to the government and to petition the government
For a redress of grievances
Enforce the government
And either accepting or rejecting
And then that government if it says no
Is subject to being voted out of office
I'm Suited
This is Madison
Giving us
Blueprint
For tomorrow
The Big Bang
When democracy begins
The way I'm hearing it is like
Like cocentrix circles like starting and inside the mind of one person and then like reverberating
A series of concentric circles
Beginning within your mind
And then moving
To your closer
Acquaintances
Then to the
Society at Large
Yeah and then finally
To the entire policy
To the entire people
By the way is the only time in human history
But those six ideas
Never been United
And I single
Text
Only time
I went back and looked at every single rice bearing document in our tradition
All the way from the Magna Carta
Through the English Bill of Rights through the colonial Charter through the state
Patricians poem through the French Declaration of the
It's never been done before
To put the 6 building
Democracy
Together
In a single coherent
Text
The first amendment is the ideal city on the hill
It is the ideal community
Got the founders were trying to establish and remember establish for the first time
That was NYU
Professor Burt neuborne and more perfect sarkari
With liner notes
1st Amendment
As I mentioned we got to songs about
Cuz we left it open
Choose whichever Amendment
By the most
And the other song about the first minute
It's from an artist named Joey Styles
He's a First Nations
Canadian rapper and hip-hop artist
He
Night to talk that idea of the
Gleaming City on the hill
And looked at its underbelly
It all the people
2 throughout history haven't been allowed in that
How much rat Ghost Dance Part 2 I was dealing with the freedom of religion
Adam I specifically the Ghost Dance as a teen
150 to 300 mostly women and children Massacre for Ghost Dance
It's me that shows they were
Scared
They're scared of us having our culture and ceremonies because they Empower us
I truly hope the warrior Spirit Shines on this track and our natural side of being Wild and Free set stone
Oh
Every move I make
Turf products
Best bras
Psalm 40
Student choice
Stardust
Tales of Phoenix
I can feel the spirit
Attorney
Feel-Rite
Any home is gone on me I was going to take a shower
Go to seed Florida
The power
Where is matter Brothers Furniture
Is Joey Styles
With the song about the First Amendment
The Second Amendment is up next
This is more perfect
Most perfect album of Jad appenrod
Be back in a minute
This is more perfect
I'm Jedi
Second Amendment
Right to bear arms
Okay so this amendment
Kind of hard to summarize
Usual do last season
More perfect today
Very deep dive into the
Truly surprising history of the Second Amendment
How these 27 words and three commas
Became America's favorite
Bite
About 5 seconds are in a put that back into the feed
If you're interested give it a listen
Do you want Cliff Notes version
Here it is
The text itself Second Amendment
Right to bear arms
Houston tax a well regulated militia
Being necessary to the
The security of a free state
The right of the people to keep and bear arms
Shall not be infringed
The first thing you notice about the
The text is it
It's a weird sentence
Grammatically it's very strange a well regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state,
The right of the people to keep and bear arms
, shall not be infringed
Is that
Scan
Totally I'm not sure I mean obviously this amendment is about the right to bear arms
Inspector who
For whom who has the right
If you diagram the sentence it seems to
Offer to potential answers
To that question
In the first part of the sentence you get a well regulated militia
What answer which is that the militia
Has the right
To bear arms
The case then maybe only the people in the militia
Have the right to bear arms
So okay people in the Army can have a gun but the rest of us
Don't necessarily have that right
If you just look up
The first Clause you might come to that conclusion
But then later
You got the second clause
The right of the people to keep and bear arms
Shall not be infringed
So here you have the people
Straight
To keep and bear arms shall not being
French eraser first you got the militia then you have
The people
Are the people
The people in the militia
Or are the people a larger category
Then
The militia
People here
If that's what they meant
Why would you start the sentence with the militia which
I don't know it's weird
Doesn't make a whole lot of
Tumi Italy
Now one of the things that
Many historians will say about the Second Amendment
Poseidon facts
It's confusing
Is that for many many years
It was just assumed that the
The first part of the sentence
A well regulated militia
That was the important part and they will tell you that for a long time
No one cared about II Men
Except for the third amendment the zoo there was no amendment that was less written about less
Legislated bless debated
Then the Second Amendment
According to historian Jill Lepore
People don't think about it
Argue about it
But then
You get this
Crazy
Chain of events
Honorary life with hot steaming night in Cincinnati
Is that yet we took a position across the Federation for the NRA
I mean we really didn't pull this off
I can buy the damn pistol that I want to buy everybody is just quiet
When you can hear your heart beating
And suddenly
You know what we want American Gun politics
Literally changed overnight
We hold at the second amendment guarantees an individual right to having use arms for self-defense in the home
Now we read the Second Amendment very different
We take the first part well regulated militia
Equibase
Sickly forget it
We just focus on the second part of right of the people to keep and bear arms
Shall not be infringed
Disarm Americans
This is a sacred right
A symbol of freedom from an oppressive government
Two other Americans
It's an offense
And so that
Grammatical confusion that
Once
Was there but ignored
Now has been
Clarified but replaced by an even larger compared
Gut-wrenching confusion
Herbal coffee with us for a long long time
Listen to the
Okay so
4r album about the Amendments we got three submissions
Songs about the Second Amendment
Listen to all of them
At the most perfect album. Org by a group called setting
Another by musician called Michael Richard clicks
And another by an all-female mariachi band
Called flor de toloache
All three of the songs are pretty badass
Play a bit of
Of this one who's flor de toloache
The bearing
And keep your arm is you right here in this country you got in their mind
I can do you harm
Cuidado
Lalalala lalalala
You may want
You may want to
OK Google
FML
That was flor de toloache with their song inspired by the
Second Amendment
Okay moving right along with them the first
Going to second
Sort of
Now third of it
Quartering soldiers
No Soldier
Chilling time of peace
Be quartered in any house
Without the consent of the owner
Nor in time of War
But in a manner to be prescribed by law
Does anybody know what the third amendment is
The third amendment is part of the Forgotten amendment that I bet most
Lawyers probably couldn't even tell you what it says
That's my third Amendment right
Gears producer Julia Longoria
With liner notes
For the 3rd
So I've talked to two several
People about
The third amendment and they all point me to you you are the third amendment man so how did this happen
What else wanted the job but they missed out
Professor Tom Bell is kind of a hipster of constitutional law
And that he is a sucker for a
Scared I would pass the first and second figuring other smarter more knowledgeable
People to cover those I got to the third though and I realized after
Research
Said much about a three-minute blessed
Neglect
Did heart
Sergio likes to barge in for a second
Icefield appropriate actually
Evinrude bike
OnPoint on topics so just to sort of explain the 3rd Amendment
All of the 3rd Amendment really says is that
Soldiers are not allowed
To barge into your house the way I just didn't your story you're not allowed to do it
It's your house
They're not allowed to
Coming to your house and then stay in your hair
Right which might sound to a snail like yeah why would we need a rule saying that
But people who wrote the third amendment were worried about this
Because it happened
During the Revolutionary War
British soldiers have basically treated the people like a Boston like Hotel owners accept without paying they barged
Listen to their homes they stayed in their homes
While they fought the War the people of Boston were not happy
And so the founders wrote
The 3rd Amendment no Soldier shall in time of peace be quartered in any house
Without the consent of the owner
Which
Thankfully sounds kind of musty
Tea to us right now
That kind of thing doesn't happen anymore
Well not so fast
You're right that there's never been a third amendment case
That's made it all the way 2
Spring Court
Never
And that's why
This recent relatively obscure case
In the state of Nevada
Caught
Tom Bells I
Yes yes they didn't have to Grapple much with
What is courting but they did ask
Is this a soldier
And it starts with a phone call
To a man named Anthony Mitchell
From local police local police officials
In the morning if they wanted to use his house as
Kind of look out
To spy on his neighbor
Watch him for a little while Mr Mitchell said I really don't want to get involved
Documents after breaking down Anthony's door the cops
Stop yelling profanity is inspired multiple pepperball rounds is dog and Anthony only latest fetal position
One understands his claim is premised on the police qualifying as soldiers because they have
Military apparatus
Unfortunately
Anthony Mitchell wasn't able to go on the record about this
But
According to court documents
Anthony claimed that
The police quarter themselves when they stayed in his house
About nine hours
Not only did they stay there and apparently shoot pepperball rounds at his dog butt
The eight
His food
Like they say they went into the fridge
He thought he had a
Quartering
Claim
I'm sympathetic
To the complaint
If you look at our police
Not Andy Griffith
Mayberry RFD anymore
Guys in
Face masks and helmets with heavy armor riot gear truncheon
And teargas M16 rifle
Armored vehicles so big you need a crowbar to open the door in what look like
Text are armored troop carriers any out on our domestic
Streets
Is very upsetting
The founders
Probably something seriously about noon or should this apply to police
Because they didn't I didn't think about please
Militarized police that we have soap
That's another reason to be sympathetic to this
I mean
I did I never had much hope
In that
That
Complaint
It's just you can't put that heavy burden on the slim shoulders
The 3rd Amendment
Just not with that
The judge in Nevada agreed
Anthony's 3rd Amendment claim was shot down
Courtside basically when it comes to the third amendment
The police
Don't count
Because you're not so
They're not
Has anyone ever gotten any farther that argument
No because really there
Haven't been
Very many third amendment cases at all
What you think about all the First Amendment cases and second amendment cases that have been brought forward
I didn't go anywhere
There just aren't
Many third amendment cases
Even in the lower court
Is it possible I had to do some further research I discovered holy macro
The third amendment has been violated
Time and again medicine fee and US history
And most of the time no one
Barely even noticed
First violation that I can find was the War of 1812 that's us fighting Britain
Camping around the East Coast
US troops take over a bunch of farms
Burn down the house
That's quarter thing happened in the Civil War
This is what I discovered most recent this really breaks my heart
1941 us declares war on Japan they sent troops to the Aleutian Islands
This chain of islands
Not the kind of chilling novel asked if you had a map has a longer beard out in the ocean pollution Island
And pretty quickly the federal troops
Puritan Aleutian isle
Feelings and said to the Islanders you're in the way
They were there we have their testimony
Get a bunch of boys Long Way from Home lightly supervised that are the places of aternum down and steal things as ordering
You really think we could ask where they were wearing red coat and in tricorn hats you know how much were obviously you need to have this
Ordering no
Body said a thing
Unifylink
Frankly a little ashamed for the legal system
How did all these victims
Socrates violation
And no lawyer could pick up a constitution
And notice that it's shameful
Comedic
The third man was like a canary in the coal mine
It tells us how our rights doing our are really plainly spelled out constitute the right
Third Amendment right that's like bronze in the Olympics
Which is right up there at the top
I'm doing on that
Terribly
Violated
Many times
It mocked
It's really cool when it is violated Court say I you know who knew about that well that's not a serious
I really hope for more from my Bill of Rights in my
Okay Julie Longoria
Dumbbell with liner notes for the 3rd Amendment
Here's the song
Comes from the band palehound
This is Ellen from palehound for my song I chose the 3rd Amendment
Which states that you are not required to house soldiers in peacetime
That doesn't really apply to Modern Life at all so I kind of chose to Road Ephrata song about keeping Vine
I want people out of your life
Who plays today
Gets palehound
With a song inspired by the third amendment
I love the lyrics
You shoot your guns in my backyard you crushed my flowers and
Garden lawn with laws on my side
I'm not letting you in tonight
Both palehound and They Might Be Giants
Wrote original songs for us about this amendment to listen to both
Go to
The most perfect album. Org
Our website is super cool by the way
Amazing artwork
Might make you laugh out loud
Some of it there all by artist Louis Missouri
Also we collaborate with the national Constitution Center to write about each of the amendments in a way that is super easy to understand
Go to the most perfect album. Org to check it all out more perfect is produced by me Jedi from Rod Susie lechtenberg
Julia Longoria Kelly Prime sarakari and Alex overington with help from Elie mystal Michelle Harrison
David Gable
Nora Keller is the reason our album 27 the most perfect album exist
Thank you Nora
And thank you to actor Jeffrey Wright for
Spending an afternoon with us donating his time
To read all of the event
We're super grateful to him
To all the musicians who donated their time and energies and talents to the
This project
And we're grateful to you for listening
I'm Chatham Rod will be back
Very soon
More episodes