Stealth technology the Internet GPS in the palm of your hand, autonomous operation
Technology is a driver of our times since its founding in 1958 in the midst of the cold war DARPA, the defense Advanced Research projects agency has been a driver of technology
Welcome to voices from DARPA a window unto DARPA's core of program managers their job to redefine what is possible
My name is Ivan Amato, and I'm your DARPA host. For this episode
The last one I will host, I decided to collect observations that program managers have shared with me and you listeners, since as they reflected on their time at the agency
So many of them told me that the job was the best, most fun, most rewarding, most impacted job they had ever had
Even though they knew from the start that they would only have the job for a few years, that's how DARPA rolls, you can get the dream job and bring your new blood to, but then you need to hand that dream job off to yet some newer blood
Let me start with the words of Peter Hynum
The agency's deputy director, who in a previous Santa DARPA from 1999 to 2003
Served as a program manager overseeing programs in electronic wrong fare and electronic communications
I love the way he described the program manager's job to me back in June of 2020
I don't have a program manager quite literally invents tomorrow
The upward program managers have the leeway the authority to find the the best teams in the world to work on a particular problem, and then they have the authority and capabilities to drive to achieve the results that are of to them
DARPA is a place where the program managers are the ones who really drive the ship, the office directors and the the front office
Our job is to make it possible for them to do that to give them the tools and to help them achieve their goals
A DARPA program manager blames a research problem with a plausibility story with a deep awareness and knowledge of the state of the art, and that problem idea
A very careful idea with use cases and such as to why that problem is of great importance to national defence and to our military
And then how it can be executed as a research program and then how progress will be measured and assessed, and then who will be who will benefit from the results
How will those results transition into practice and again and again and again for 60 years now, DARPA program managers have set up programs, have run them
And quite literally, that rigour, that passion that a program manager brings to the job will be saving lives 5 10 15 years from now
I am particularly grateful to Tyler McQuade
Who was a big ideas program manager in the agency's defense sciences office in September 2016, when he sat down with me in a studio on the 13th floor of DARPA headquarters in Arlington for my very first podcast recording, I wanted to start with Tyler because my aim was for the podcast to be accessible to a wide audience
And I knew he would say things like this
a coconut
It smells the way it does because a chemistry
But he also revealed that tantalized, what if mentality that I would encounter over and over again throughout my podcast recordings with program managers or PMs, as they also are known, DARPA, is that one
Place where
We are thinking about
Innovation unconstrained like, where can we go
Yeah, that where can we go?
That could be a tagline for DARPA, dev Palmer was another podcast guest earlier in the series at the time in late 2016, he was a program manager in the agency's Microsystems Technology Office or MTO
He would leave DARPA the next year
But in 2020 he came back as PM's also sometimes do to become MTO's current deputy director. Back in our podcast discussion
He heaped a whole lot of love about working at DARPA
Coming to DARPA is like grabbing the nose cone of a rocket and holding on for dear life
It's a fast moving place that has a significant impact on the trajectory of technology for the nation
And being part of that is an incredible thrill, the idea that you can come up with a technical idea that's interesting to you
And create a community to pursue that ideas
is an experience you won't get anywhere else
You can take flyer bets on crazy things like integrating magnetics with semiconductors,
and people will actually soldier up and tell you how they're gonna do it.
Blake beckstein has followed a similar path to deaf Palmer's he too started out as a program manager in his case in in the biological technologies office, and later took on some management responsibilities
I recorded him when he was still a newbie
Blake has one of those gleams in his eye that makes anyone think this guy is going to do something amazing
after all
One of his ambitions has been to protect nothing less than food supply from both natural and engineered threats
Which is another way of saying biological warefare,
well, I came to DARPA because I saw a fantastic opportunity
For my research community, the DARPA mission is unlike things that I've done in the past
Because the dark emission is to look at high risk, high reward
projects that could benefit humanity in a sort of that 20 to 50 year time frame,
and it also gives an opportunity to derest
ah, some programs and some projects
So that they can actually come to light and and see youth
So when the opportunity to come to DARPA presented itself,
I thought it was just this awesome chance to do some really great science,
and I was encouraged because I was asked to think about things that traditionally weren't funded very well
You know, the positive that can come out of this and the world changing abilities that we're gonna gain is incredible
Beckstein came into DARPA with an uncommon specialty and interest in agricultural biotechnology and food security for eber furu
Who was a DARPA program manager from 2014 through 2018 in the agency's Defense Sciences Office, also brought in a unique mindset, and she was nervous about it
She was skeptical about how a mathematician like herself would fit in in my podcast featuring Furu, which aired in March of 2017, I asked her what she thought she might be able to do at DARPA that she could not do elsewhere
I say DARPA is probably the best place to be
If you are an applied mathematician, in fact, I just say for if you're a mathematician
and I'd like to solve problems because one of the greatest thing about DARPA is that,
there is this wealth of information, wealth of problems that are important,
and I have to say they're very, very cool
The coolness factor for problems to solve for a mathematician here is enormous
because you feel that not only you're solving a problem that has importance,
they're certainly broader impact
As far as you know, you're solving important problems in national security,
but you also feel like the problems are so rich that in some ways,
there is so much to contribute the richness of the problem is maybe the the biggest driver,
a motivating factor for anybody, certainly for a mathematician.
And I just want to add, and I've been saying that to my friends to my colleagues, anybody who would listen
that why mathematics is actually very important to to DARPA and encourage them to become future program managers
Is that when you're encountered by important problems and you see that your your ideas
The role you have as a mathematician that not only you try to look at these particular problems,
but you try to abstract out and coming with different representation that would yield better solution for these problems, so you basically see that your ideas are at work
I mean, what better satisfaction are there
Hear that mathematicians out there
Don't forget about DARPA could be just the place for you wage shen, who's nearly five year stint as a program manager or APM for short ended in 2019, he reveled in the way DARPA embraces the most fundamental kind of scientific in an R&D continuum that can lead to the highest technologies of all, obviously
Even within the US government, there are a number of organizations of fund basic research
The fund applied research that fund various projects along that continuum
And I think DARPA has a very unique role
It's it's a role that spans the gap between basic research and applied science
Oftentimes, we're looking for the applications that seem impossible, whether it's, you know, launching ah drones off of flying aircraft or you know
Detecting human trafficking online, all of these things are things that you know we're emerging capabilities 3 or 4 years ago, but now have proven to be possible
And so DARPA's, in a very unique place that
Allows us to push the technology beyond the theoretical stages to the point where we can actually see where the where the applications are going to be,
so we're not builders of the ultimate technology
Right, and at the end of the day, we fund the research, and that research eventually becomes product types in other forms,
but if you look at the you know progression of robotics and self driving cars, all of those AI technologies were curated out of DARPA programs early on
and have subsequently you know a ten year horizon after that become productizeable
The industry has been able to take it up, so we serve a very crucial role
And the reason that we can serve that role is
The program managers themselves, these folks come with the ideas
And they can see the horizon
Jonathan fouth, who from 2015 to 2019 brought interests in the social sciences and social psychology to DARPA as a program manager in the information innovation office expressed to me in the middle of his PM stint,
a multifaceted enthusiasm for his temp job at the agency
DARPA is such an amazing place that
It's hard when you're in
field doing research and development and leading other people and doing it
to not know about DARPA to not know about the amazing things that DARPA has done
So for me, it was it was very natural to say, boy
I could imagine at some point
Appropriately, in my career, I would love to serve at DARPA and spend those four
or five years in my life here helping
Arriving at DARPA
There's a sense of incredible empowerment that with the
wherewithal(为做某事而需要的钱) that you get to
really make some extraordinary things happen, not just
oh, I'm going to run a program
But no, I'm going to, you know
write a seminal book with
the best people in the world I'm going to
change a whole discipline
It's an amazing feeling.
and when you do all of that and you tie it back to national security and feeling
like you're serving your country, it's a great feeling.
As you already have heard a PM job at DARPA is temporary three or 4 years
Maybe 5 is typically what you get
That's not job security, but it has been a catalyst for both individual and institutional achievement
I wholeheartedly agree
That one of the things that makes a successful organization, this idea of bringing pro managers in for a short amount of time get
The work done that they envision getting done and then leave in order for new blood to come into the culture and into the organization
It's important
That's Scott Wierzbanowski of the Tactical Technology Office I recorded a podcast episode with him this past April
Just a month before he finished his four year PM gig
By understanding that you have a very limited time in a very special place like DARPA, it becomes your priority
You focus all of your time and attention, day, night weekends on whatever these projects happens to be, it becomes a passion
It becomes your life and you can do so for a 2 to 4 five year period, where this is everything that you're focused on,
but eventually human nature takes over, and eventually people either get burnt out or they no longer have newer ideas that needs to be brought to bear
And that motivation isn't necessarily gone, but it is time for other people to come in with their new ideas
And there's another new ones that happens too
you have a program and you work this program for a couple of years,
and you're focused on making it successful,
but sometimes a program manager can get biased(有偏见),
and by bringing in new blood or a new program manager into a particular case
They may see in a different light and maybe able to make changes that the other program manager didn't wasn't aware of
or maybe just decided that it'd be better to go down a different path
It's a double edge sword, but I think in general doing so,
we're bringing in new program managers into take care of programs that are ongoing as well as bringing their own in is really what makes us such a
A great place to work
Peter Hynum when he was serving as acting director of DARPA during part of 2020,
outlined what he thought were some of the most important institutional traits that made DARPA so successful
One of them was that temporary nature of the program manager role, but there were others
A DARPA or originally when it was upper back in 1958, somehow the framers the people who put this machine together
Quite a few things, really, absolutely right
And it's those my view, those those few things, but of an enabled DARPA to succeed over 60 years now
and delivering and and continuing to deliver and invent tomorrow for the department
So the first of these three things is that to everybody who works on the technical side of DARPA
program managers, office directors
front office folk.
We are all temporary by design, we we come
We send we spent four years or so here and then we leave
We come from industry
We come from universities we come from elsewhere in the government
We come from the the military services
We do our job, we push hard and then we leave this one thing
DARPA also is a project agency, so there are no standing activities
DARPA is not always going to do X or Y
It's continuously changing
I'd like to say that in some ways, DARPA is framed to catch the night guys or to be in it and to
drive to the next level, so it's in the zeitgeist(时代浪潮), and in some ways, it is that it captures it exactly, and that's what these two things enable us to do
People, ephemeral people will temporarily and project based,
and then the third pieces, DARPA has no assets of its own
We have no laboratories
We have no test facilities, we have no factories,
so we don't have a standing army of anything,
so and it's perfectly framed as an institution to continuously track and drive and push
the frontiers of knowledge applied to problems at real interest and importance to the military
For major Christopher Orlowski, who was a program manager in the Tactical Technology Office when I spoke with him in the fall of 2017,
it was access to the collaborations it takes to move audacious ideas toward real technology that was special about the PM job
the biggest thing I've learned since being a program manager is that
the innovation and collaboration is a team effort
I don't do it by myself
There's no way I could begin the fathom to manage all these programs
and all these efforts that are under by myself,
so I have a great team, a great support team that helps our technical experts in the field
in their fields
And that ultimately, even us is not the ones that do it
It's the engineers and scientists at companies and universities and defense contractors that we fund
that are the ones that ultimately are gonna bend metal and write code, and they deliver these capabilities to war fighters,
but I can't forget the war fighters either, because their invaluable advice recommendations are also part of a loop
So it's a collaborative ecosystem that results in the innovation that provides these new capabilities
It is those war fighters that were foremost in the mind of Rosa Alejandra Lukaszew
when she joined the defense sciences office in 2017 DSL program managers conceive of an overseas, some of the agency's most fundamental science projects
In her case in the way collections of electrons behave in materials, among
other really fundamental stuff, I spoke with her when she was about halfway through her
three and a half year run as a PM
As an American
Not by birth
but by choice, you know, I have a deep love for this country
The admiration for this country and a sense of duty regarding you know, trying to help this country to continue
Be what it is right now, and the best way, in my opinion, is to try to see, okay
What are the needs of the people that are the forefront of defending the country that would be the defense
the arm forces in general, right
And so what is that is going to make that difference in terms of you know
Advances in technology, advances in research that can help this dismission,
and clearly DARPA is at the forefront of all of these funding agencies on that particular direction,
so I was very, very intrigued and curious and interested in being part of this particular
organization for that reason,
before colonel Matthew Hepburn came to DARPA's Biological Technologies Office to work on the challenge of responding far more rapidly than ever before to threats from both known and new infectious diseases,
he had been pushing that goal in policy jobs in circles
That's when he got a call from the then DSO director Jeff ling, who asked Matt if he wanted to come to DARPA
Where he could try and turn policy into action, in his case, into the technologies it will take to prevent pandemics
One of our mantras at DARPA is this idea
Inspiring, inspiring creativity and new solutions to problems
And oftentimes, we say by sort of recruiting and people who have not traditionally thought about our problems
to help us with those solutions, and so you know, I would love for the listeners of this podcast to
be more inspired to address the problems and infectious diseases.
And and what I mean by that is, I always say, people like me
We've invested our entire careers and our life work into this
And we have deep knowledge of the subject, but I love the thought of people that have expertise in computer science
in mathematics in what we would say, well
Maybe those fields aren't necessarily obviously related
That's who I think that's how we're going to solve the infectious diseases problems of the 21st century, and so when I speak on this, it's almost part
It's one part recruiting, and it's especially recruiting that may not have all of the biases
of the traditional experts in infection disease to come up with a creative solution to solve it
Matt must have really liked his DARPA job because he left in 2019 after six years, a long timer in DARPA terms
for about half of the time that Hepburn was working in the biological technologies office
Brad ring hysen had been working first as the office's deputy director, then is the director
I met ring Hyson in March 2020, just as the World Health Organization declared that the spread of SARS CoV-2 infections had grown into a global pandemic into covid-19,
partly because of the programs Hepburn had worked on
ring hyacinth and his team of PMs were in a position to deploy the DARPA model of research and development to this new multifaceted crisis
DARPA plays a really important role for the the entire government, quite honestly
But specifically for the department of and that in its ability to predict what is emerging uh as threats to both
our war fighters and our DoD personnel
But also to the country as a whole
And that has been something that's been persistent through the entire lifetime of DARPA,
but specific to infectious disease and emergent disease, this is something over the last
two decades DARPA has been there.
We've learned what is needed and what is required to be able to fight the types of outbreaks
and pandemic that we're seeing right now. With some amazing program manager's amazing forethought that's happened back 5, 10, even 15 years ago
Program managers started thinking about an ideal world
where we can have a rapid response platform where we could instead of having to develop vaccines over the course of years
Maybe even decades at at in time
Wouldn't it be great if we had a world where we could reduce that
research and development process down to a matter of potentially weeks or months
rather than having to wait on that tremendously long time frame, which we know
living through what we're living through right now
It's just too long.
even though the job of DARPA program manager is by definition temporary
Some PMs like the job so much they come back dev Palmer, who we heard from earlier, had done that,
so did David gunning, whose fingerprints are all over the ascent of Siri and the entire category of digital assistance
I've been here three times
Because to me
It's one of the most fascinating jobs you
Can have you're the pinnacle of new technology development
You have such a broad view of what's going on, and DARPA gives you this incredible freedom to pursue
what you see is, you know, a vision on where where
things should go.
and Fisher a PM in the Defense Sciences Office, is another several timer at DARPA
She got her start as a so called SETA, a contractor working for none other than Tyler McQuade, he was the PM I featured in the very first episode of this podcast,
SETA, stands for Science Engineering and Technical Assistant
SETAs, who often bring in PhD, postdoc and top tier professional experience to the job
work closely on the programs with the program managers.
They are essential parts of the team.
When I asked Fisher during a podcast conversation in 2018, if there was something I had failed to ask her
This is how our conversation went
well, you didn't ask me how fun this was.
Well, tell me how fun it is.
Well, this being the podcast, but also life in general at DARPA,
and I say that because we get to interact with amazing top notch scientists on a daily basis multiple times times a day
Um, and that's really exciting, and it's really fun, and it's amazing opportunity,
and those are the folks that are doing the the hard work to implement all of the ideas that we might generate here
I'm really put them to practice and and again from you know,
the perspective of coming to work every day and being humbled by that and being so excited and energized by what they have to bring
in terms of their ideas and their talents.
Some program managers get the DARPA bug earlier than others
Few have gotten that bug earlier than current BTO program manager Eric Van Gieson,
whose portfolio of programs are anchored in the molecular biology of disease and health
He told me an hour podcast conversation in 2020 that DARPA had been on his mind since the 1980s
when I was in middle school, I would ride my bike over to the library in falls Church across from Marshall high school in northern Virginia
And I would go in there, and I'd read popular mechanics
And I'd read car magazines
And I started reading stories about DARPA that
was when we were starting to hear about some of the the computing technologies and the networking technologies that were coming out of DARPA
As part of ah the unveiling of the internet and so
that got me interested
in 2020
I spoke with current DSO program manager Mark Wrobel,
who hadn't had DARPA on his mind since he was a teenager, the way Van Gieson did,
but he had long known about the agency when he started his PM stint in March 2019
one year later
When it became clear that SARS CoV-2 had spread into a pandemic,
Wrobel began pivoting a program under his wing known as sigma plus, to see if the threat detection technology that was its focus could be adapted for early detection of viruses.
DARPA does amazing things, and as a federal employee for how going on 12 years, I think now and as an
active duty service member for 22 years, you know very few places in government
do you have the real capacity to make change to innovate
to discover and to do amazing things, and DARPA is one of those places
It's literally a dream come true to be a program manager here,
never in my wildest dreams, did I think this was actually going to come to be, and now I'm here, and
it's been an awesome year
It was an awesome year when I detailed, and I'm hoping for another few years of awesomeness
Before I wrap up my tenure here.
Like Wrobel, John-Francis Mergan
A current program manager in the Information Innovation Office had a long career before coming to DARPA
He had long thought about a stint at the agency,
and when the time was right for him,
he finally found himself in a technology playground that was as fun as he
had hoped it would be
coming to DARPA was something I'd always wanted to do
But I needed to wait for the right time in my career.
I wanted to be sure my son had graduated from college.
I wanted to achieve certain milestones and also get some people in place at my old employer to make sure that the research could carry on,
and I also wanted to have the right set of ideas for programs I didn't want to show up and wander around for a year
trying to come up with an idea for a program, so I had my little basket of program ideas,
and I came in the door, I was all excited.
I started up and part of the reason for coming to DARPA is there's several neat things that DARPA program managers get to do
One
They get to talk with other people who are who are in the organization
and get their ideas and get them completely unfiltered.
But the other one is you can tap into researchers all across the globe
You call up and say, hi, I'm from DARPA, and I was wondering what you were thinking about something
And usually the conversation will run far longer than you ever anticipated or you ever even planned,
but you're sorry, when it's over.
I've been able to talk with researchers at Caltech at MIT
And they'll call back with another idea afterwards
that is unbelievably exciting, and for someone like me,
having that kind of access is the greatest entertainment I could ever hope for
the other big piece about this is you get to go see their labs
And you got to go see stuff happening,
and as you can guess from being a pilot and from being a ham radio operator, I'd love to touch the technology
I love to play with it
I love to do things with it
Over and over again, I heard from program managers a sense of responsibility to war fighters, to the nation
To the taxpayers a sense of privilege and of gratitude the fae of all people got to do this job
The PM job
Here's how Tristan mcclair Begley, whose current portfolio of programs in BTO are all about helping word fighters remain healthy and heal from mental and physical injuries expressed to me this past July
Program managers exist in a privileged space
We are given a lot of freedom with which to make decisions with which to resource efforts in order to produce research projects that are very near and dear to us
There is a lot of I would dare to say that you know, program managers are
very personally invested in the the programs that they're responsible for, and so you know
We have a tendency to take things personally because there is that degree of relationship that exists between the ideas, the problems we're trying to solve
The reasons why we're trying to solve those problems and ultimately how the research is done, and I would
say that despite that emphasis on the program manager, as this sort monolithic entity responsible for
all of this fantastic research and pushing at you know the boundaries of what is you know currently possible
I would also say that it has been part of my experience that this is a profoundly collaborative agency
that I spend a substantial amount of time in very productive discussions with my colleagues
here at the agency, getting very different perspectives on a number of fundamental issues and questions
As well as the collaborations that I have both with the other government mental agencies
The end users who is ultimately going to take the thing that I tried to invent
and turn it into some real enabling capability for national security,
for rehabilitation(修复) for treatment for restoration in our veteran population in the you know, broader civilian population,
and then also with the with the researchers themselves
that part of the job of a DARPA program manager is not just coming up with clever ideas and setting things in motion
But also continuing to work and pay attention to what the research is producing
What does it tell you about your initial hypothesis and any assumptions that you made
and which of those things are ultimately going to be rejected, we don't
learn as much from success as we do from failure, and so
sometimes you just have to be mindful that and do your best to establish the
appropriate balance between things that are practically impossible for a reason versus things that are practically impossible just due to a
lack of innovation
talk to just about any program manager, and they will tell you that DARPA, as an institution,
has enough of a track record to claim it has a special sauce, a special institutional culture
that makes it about as impactful as any player can get in the innovation ecosystem
Here's how Tim Chung, a PM with the tactical technology office, puts it
I definitely believe DARPA has a secret sauce that has continued to
been able to generate both the ideas, but also create and execute and realize those ideas
I think on the one hand, certainly from the Tactical Technology Office from which I have,
we really love seeing technologies demonstrated, so systems being brought together
and realized in some sort of field tester demonstration, and I think that's one end
on the other hands we're interested in creating whole new, you know, foundations
whole new areas of research that hadn't really been thought about.
And I think that being able to expand that spectrum and do it in the context of, you know
100 or so program managers across 300 programs is is pretty phenomenal.
During a podcast recording in the spring of 2020, Chung floated a neologism that captures some of the institutional audacity DARPA is known for
It also relates to part of the draw for scientists and engineers like Chung, who have been the masterminds behind challenge based programs
Including most recently for Chung, the subterranean challenge known for short as Sub-T, that challenge was all about seating,
a research community that will be able to develop autonomous and robotic systems that work in
natural and human made underground settings for national defense missions and for humanitarian tasks such as
such as disaster response.
I'd say one of the ways I describe DARPA
This was one of my colleagues had previously described the research this way
is there a lot of folks out there that might say some research is impossible
or some vision is impossible, and my colleague at the time said, actually, no
It's not impossible
It's rather it's unpossible, it's just that it hasn't been done yet
It's not that it can't be done
It just hasn't been done yet,
And I'd like to embrace that philosophy and everything that that I'd try to touch in the sense because it hadn't been done before is not proof that it can't be done
In fact, it's a challenge to say that maybe I'm the one who can who, who can do it
And DARPA really gives us both the tools and the inspiration and the kind of community
I'd say that both the support, but also my you know, program manager colleagues, when I see all the amazing things there
making possible, it makes me think that the things that once might have been considered impossible or are simply just opportunities
for Bruce draper, a program manager in the Information Innovation Office, one of the most exciting ways these provisional unpossibility Chung referred to unfolds
is the way a DARPA project can spawn entirely new and lasting fields of research and development
In a place like DARPA, you can create programs that help define the field and and create intellectual communities of people that are trying to tackle brand new problems, and that's an opportunity
It's something you can do it in DARPA
You just can't do anywhere else
That community building opportunity resonates with Sergey Bratus, an I2O program manager colleague of Drapers who came to the agency from academia and has been intent on recruiting performers from that sector into his cyber security programs
It has been behind several DARPA successes that I've experienced personally to define a new direction
define a new trend, and put some grand funding behind that trend in order to
get academia to listen to well, this is the need you might be missing
This is the a cool thing that might
with time create its own first tier publication of venue of journals and conferences, and there, I believe DARPA has been greatly successful
And talk about things that have never been done before from 2016 to 2020, Mike Fiddy was a program manager in the Defense Sciences Office
Where he took on programs with goals as mind soaring
as extracting propulsive energy from quantum mechanical fluctuations inherent in space itself
in a discussion soon before he left the agency in June 2020,
Fiddy pointed out to me that the researchers, that is, the performers in DARPA speak
that program managers contract with to work on projects
tend to feel that they are part of a team with crucial goals to achieve
And so they become motivated to perform not just for themselves
But really for the country
I think there's something special about DARPA in the eyes of our performers as well as those of us fortunate enough to work for the agency, I think that rapid turnover
that sense of urgency that very well organized structure DARPA has make
performers feel that they engaged in something special when they get funded, and they want to give their best,
and I do see a lot of performers who put in um
really a lot of extra effort to make those deadlines, keep us informed,
stay on track, they understand that we're usually in an arrangement with them
where there's program managers were in regular contact and
wearing involved month by month, quarter by quarter with with what they're doing, and they don't want to disappoint
And they understand that the program has a goal and the goal was approved
for good reason because it's addressing
some need that the DoD has.
Air force lieutenant colonel c David Lewis is an African American program manager to get where he is
He had to overcome systemic racism and to seize those opportunities that did arise whenever and wherever they did
Because there's a phrase that we use in the air force all the time, and that is a bloom where you're planted, um
You know, of course, being in the military, we don't get to choose where we live all the time
We don't necessarily get to choose what assignment
we get assigned to, and so the phrase is to say that no matter where you are,
do the best that you can do because it's going to help out the country,
and you always have to be prepared for when opportunity knocks because you know opportunity
And my opinion shows up at everyone's door
The question is, what have you been doing to prepare for that opportunity, when it comes,
it took a lot of preparation pretty much, I think over my entire air force career up until that point
to be ready for this opportunity, and it's worked out thus far
Part of the opportunity, lieutenant colonel Lewis alludes(提及) to here has to do with the
privilege that program managers enjoy to devote taxpayer money,
a precious resource to tough and risky problems that are worth investing in
because of how much could be gained for the nation by the solutions to those problems
in late 2020 I spoke with program manager John Waterston
A former nuclear submarine crew member and now captain in the US Navy reserves,
he thinks of DARPA as something like a venture capital fund with a mission to further the cause of national security
I feel what we do at DARPA is being a venture capital fund, right?
We are a place where you can bring ideas and mature them so that they have the most impact going forward, so
at DARPA, we don't have excessive bureaucracy
We're able to move fast
We got this advantage, that everyone's motivated to succeed and good ideas that have the most impact,
and that that's what makes me excited every day that I come to work
It makes every day different, and those two things kind of keep me pushing you know
now for almost four years.
make that five years now in our podcast conversation
Waterstone pointed to yet another crucial ingredient of DARPA's unique success at conceiving of new technologies and capabilities and ushering them toward realization
That ingredient is an embrace of the valuable lessons that come from failure
I'm not judged on success of my progress, so I'm very comfortable operating with a lot of risk
I've had a lot of failures along the way as a PM at DARPA, forgotten rid of programs, things didn't succeed
They didn't fire me
What they did to say, what did we learn from it
And how do we make the next iteration of what we do better, it's often said to fail fast
And we take those losses, and we turn into something valuable and that, that what makes DARPA a very special place
that celebration of risk taking and positive valuation of failure are also part of what BTO program manager Seth Cohen identifies as one of DARPA's most empowering traits
and in a podcast episode we posted in February of last year, he noted with interest how other government agencies sometimes try to emulate the DARPA model
And so DARPA plays this very special role because it is known for being a cutting edge agency
It's known for pushing the boundaries, and and though our performers are highly qualified and highly skilled individuals, they don't
teams of individuals, rather, they don't necessarily have to have shown
that they can do this yet it's the latest and greatest in many ways can be the most riskiest research, and that's an important role
I think that DARPA fulfills is pushing that very cutting edge
allowing people to take chances to try crazy ideas that are still grounded in good science and good concepts
but that might be outside the comfort zone of a lot of other parts of the federal government to fund,
and I think that's why you see, and this has been spoken about for many administrations now
other federal agencies trying to emulate DARPA.
Cohen told me he could not be more grateful for the opportunity to be part of an organization that others aim to emulate
I have to really say that DARPA has been, as many people told me, it would be one of the best places I could ever imagine working
It is a fascinating agency filled with incredibly, smart, motivated people who create an incredibly supportive work environment
So I'm very pleased to an honor to have been part of DARPA and to continue to be part of DARPA
Even though program managers at short timers have that hair on fire, urgency about doing their work, they also are working on hard problems with long time horizons
It's a disconnect that many of them, including Whitney Mason,
who was a program manager in the Microsystems Technology Office
actually fond to be tantalizing, something about contributing now to a return on investment
that will take decades to unfold
the thing that I think is the most amazing and the most impactful part about DARPA is
that I get to throw the dart(飞镖) really hard
I get to say I've done some research
I've talked to people, I think it's gonna work, but it might not, right?
Failing fast is an option if you learn something, and so you really get to explore the space of what might be impactful ten years from now
20 years from now, 30 years from now, as opposed to having to make sure that it works, which is
also a valuable job, but my technology doesn't have to work in two years,
it doesn't have to go on a tank in two years.
It can be way out there and far reaching, and I think changed the world
I often heard from program managers during my podcast discussions that they
viewed DARPA as an ideal of technology innovation, yet it was an ideal that was real and operational
One of them is Gordon Keeler, a program manager since 2017 in MTO, where he
and colleagues are doing their darndest to keep the 70 year sprint of the microelectronics
microsystems technology revolutions going far into the future
This is what he told me.
I had no doubt really in my mind
DARPA was clearly the pinnacle of doing innovative scientific research and development
and leading the community to go do new things.
New things, indeed
That's DARPA's thing
And Keeler speaks for everyone else at the agency when he invites innovators out there to think about collaborating with DARPA
Good ideas come from everywhere, and you mentioned the limited tenure that we have at DARPA
We're always looking for new people, and so if you've got ideas,
I care a lot about Optical Microsystem, so for sure, come see me
If you've got ideas in this area
But you know, ah, get involved, DARPA is not one person or one place
It's a collection of people that are excited about moving technology forward,
and so you know, maybe you want to be a program manager, maybe you want to work as a SETA
and maybe you want to be a performer and keep doing research search, but
reach out and get involved with DARPA
You might say that DARPA director Stephanie Tompkins has gotten involved with the agency
She runs the place now, but her current position is just one of the four jobs she has had at DARPA
And she says the program manager position is one of the best
I've been extraordinarily lucky
To have so many different jobs at DARPA, i've been a program manager
I've had leadership roles in technology offices
I even served a year as the acting deputy director, and then I left DARPA
forever a few years ago or so, I thought, don't get me wrong
Getting a chance to come back and serve this organization as its director is a tremendous privilege
But the program manager is the center of DARPA, the PMs each and every one of them have a chance to change the world
And I can't think of any simpler way to put it
They come in with ideas that they think will make the nation more secure
They put together their plans and very quickly get an army of brilliant people working on these ideas
The rest of us at DARPA, our job
is just to support the program managers so they can get on with their jobs
of changing the world, it's just such an amazing place
I can't think of anywhere else I have ever been or ever heard of that works quite like this one
on with as much freedom
It's just extraordinary.
Thanks, listeners, for sharing this time with me and with
some of the program managers who have joined me over the past five years to capture
some of the psychological, sociological and cultural foundations, and that
underlie DARPA's exceptional place in the innovation ecosystem,
I look forward to handing the voices of DARPA podcast off to my
colleagues in public affairs and hearing the innovative new ways
they are likely to take
so listeners goodbye for now,
for more information about DARPA's entire portfolio of technology development programs
and the program managers that oversee them,
visit DARPA.mil
and for links that enable you to download all episodes of the voices from DARPA podcast
go to the voices from darpa page on dapra's website.