Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
We ended up going from 0 to 800 homes in a matter of 4 weeks
And I have to tell you I thought that this was it like this was our rocket ship to the Moon
You thought we made it we're here we got it right this is you build it they will come and look what's happening and so we go
Get introduced to 20 vest Silicon Valley and of them reply to her email five of them
10 minutes for coffee zero invested in US
From NPR
How I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements
They built on Today Show
Story of how a side hustle to pay rent
Biggest hotel chain in the world
Pictures ago you been 5 years ago most of us would have thought the idea of
Renting out a room in our home to a complete
Stranger
A little creepy even spending the night in someone else's home you never met with
Probably seen weird
Especially on vacation or business trip
But now it's not just normal it's actually the preferred way to overnight from millions of people or
Around the world celebrities do it
A company that made all of this normal of course
Is Airbnb
Guys who started it
Add no background in travel or Hospitality or even technology
Joe gebbia graduated from art school at the Rhode Island School of Design
Franceschi is co-founder was Jose College buddy they
Play pickup basketball together
And actually graduated in 2005 both
Joe and Brian moved out west
Brian went to LA
Going to San Francisco
And in the first year Joe who was designing book covers at a Publishing House
Worked
Really hard to convince Brian to move up to San Francisco to start a business
Is Joe tells a story after some prodding
Brian agreed
Both of us simultaneously quit our jobs he left his I was at Chronicle Books full-time at that point
And I left
To dream of something with him
You guys were like in your
20s need a whole lot of money presumably
I get this point now we're just a couple of college grads you know eating Ramen
Yeah
What is everybody Ramen Everybody Eats Ramen so cheap Ramen Ramen Ramen
Give rice rice cereal to Mexico
You're eating Ramen
And what you're just like spitballing ideas
We spitballing ideas that first week was so exciting the first week
He comes you're you're like my God yes I mean the first week felt like RISD again
Place is full of ideas
And then
Something ominous
A letter came in the mail
I open it up it's just me
Pulled out and its former landlord
To politely
States that are rent
Is now 25% higher than it was the month before weight in one month
By 25%
25%
And that's legal
It was not under my control
Wake me up with Intuit
And so we would like
Freaking out
Of course I went random eye
My online banking and it was like oh my God oh my God can I make rent next month and Bryant the same thing we realize that we we almost
We aren't getting paychecks at this point yeah
So
This is the moment where
Your back's against the wall
And I feel like
Call the creative training at we'd received
Start a payoff if you start to think about okay well how come
Designer way out of this
And that was when I
Reflected on
Previous experience I had
Back in Providence
The day before that I laughed I drove cross-country I sold off all my stuff
And when I was having that yard sale
This guy pulls up in a red Mazda Miata
I start looking my stuff
And I'm getting pretty annoyed cuz I'm ready to go home
Bonanza buying a piece of art that I was selling so we got to talkin
And he tells me all about
How is about to go into the Peace Corps and driving cross-country
He doesn't know a soul in Providence so I can buy them out for a drink that night
And I make the mistake of asking him
So are you staying the night
And he makes it worse by saying
Actually I don't have a place man
Like we've all been there right like my house this guy
So before I know what I'm saying I'm like
You can stay in an air bed in my living room
Goodnight is set him up in the living room
And I I go to bed I try to fall asleep
I'm staring at the ceiling thinking
Oh my God
What have I done there's a complete stranger in my living room
What did he say
So I get up I tiptoed my door
And I go lock my bedroom door
The next morning we wake up
We get breakfast together turned out he was not psychotic
10 piece of artery but hangs in
Classroom
He's a teacher now and he still
Saint Joseph
Don't touch
So this is a dude that entire would eventually become Airbnb so how did you
So you're in your apartment your rents going up 25%
And what do you
Used Lexus rent a room
Well I'm looking at my laptop
And there's a design conferences coming to San Francisco
Industrial designers
Conference
On the Converse website in Big Red Letters it said hotels
Sold out
And
Man what a bummer
Designs want to come last minute and I can have a place to stay
And in that instant I woke up and I'm looking around the living room
Can't wait
With so much extra space here
And I have earbuds in the closet and the idea of Hosting people on air beds
I'd rather we become natural to me
And
The thinking is
It'll be more than just
The place to sleep we can cook breakfast in the morning will pick him up in the
Airport
I will give them a neighbor who died and a map to San Francisco
So did how did you get the word out that it has these designers noted
This is available
Well we can know we didn't want to use any the classified websites cuz there's going to be people in her home
So we made our own
Raining in Adrian
What we did on your website
Perhaps you design your own website
Stead said what
Well it said
Who we were it said about that this concept of
Stay with us mobile provide these things for you
This website was just for the design
That's it
Recipe for 1 week at the website
It was a little recalled air bed and breakfast. Calm and
Start get emails from around the world designers who needed a place to stay
From London from Brazil from Japan people actually started sending us their resumes
LinkedIn profiles to 2/4 one of these B's limited 3 air bed
For $80 a night you could stay in San Francisco with Brian and I
Square
Yeah so is more Catherine and Michael were the first three guests and
You know
What happened next I don't think we could have predicted
They stayed with us and we got to show them
San Francisco they got to
Get the feel like they
They belong there in the sense that they don't feel like Outsiders
You know what I mean like yeah
And you'll never forget
Saying goodbye in and watching the door
Door click closed
And thinking with Brian
What if we made it possible for other people
Thought I'd share their experience in and
Gas in their home and show off their City
Yeah
At what point did you and Brian look at each other and go
Okay man
I think this
Start business
Was it like right after that door closed
I wish I wish it was but I can say that that was the case
Send that December we both went home
For holiday
End
A respected New Year's Eve parties everyone who asks so what are you doing in San Francisco
Say what were entrepreneurs
What do you want for neutering
And we just really have very much
Other than to say well let me tell me this time we hosted these three guests on air beds in her apartment
And one of two things happen
People do said
Oh my God that's the coolest thing in the world
Where can I do that
Or they said that is the most bizarre creepiest thing I've ever heard
And they left the conversation
And I think one of the things that I've learned is that great ideas
I think they usually start out
As polarizing are not kind of like it's kind of okay
They either really talk on somebody's emotions are an elite and desire that they have that's never been answered
Before
Were they really
Heard them in some way
As long as there's people who really gravitate towards IDM
To me that's a signal that them you might be on Sunday
So
What you do but how would you guys do next
Well
We knew that we needed a great technical expertise
And
Funny thing
The roommate who moved out that Brian can move in
Was a guy named Nate with Charizard
Meet with an engineer
Who found me on Craigslist
And as we lift together
There were some similarities in
How many tonight
Worked
Which is that we come home from her day job
And in the evening
We would both
Work maniacally on her own projects
And I look over my shoulder
I remember thinking to myself
This guy has to work ethic just like I do
If I ever need an engineer
I think I'm going to
Call Nate
So here we are
January
So I meet Nate for a drink I die
Tell me about this this
Weekend experiment with these three guests
And
I need love the idea
He's like
We can use the internet tax you get people off the internet how cool is that
And he have these like this coating
Experience
Scyther yuan
No Brian
Use a computer science degree from Harvard yeah it sure did
So I guess at this point you have your
Your team assembled
Idea
If your website so when do you
What you really decide to launch it
We all agreed that we would watch the next version of her sight air bed and breakfast
At the next big
Tech conference because
Actually we thought the original opportunity was
Housing for conferences
It's right so the next week when I was coming up
What's South by Southwest
And every year the same thing happens Hotel sell out months in advance people Scramble for housing
And it's also the the the place where
Some of the attack grated launch
West Twitter launch their Foursquare and others
Recycle this is perfect
We're just going to follow the rocket ship that the all that didn't
So at this point we have about three weeks to build before South by Southwest
I'm doing design its encoding
We're just on a piece together
Point of no money at all
Just doing this
So
We get it out just in time shipping
When you say your ship it what do you mean
We release the next version of a site
And we think this is this is the next greatest thing at this point there's not a single listing on right
But yet
We actually had six people
Put up listings in Austin and we had
Two people
What does sweating
One of them
Luke Bryan
So it was not a smashing success at all this is where you guys like
Sad are you laughing about it or
Now this is completely demoralized
Yeah it was this idea that we were so excited about
And nobody
Took us up on the idea
So we learned two things from Austin
The first was that
Exchanging money in person
It's really awkward
Especially inside of a home
So we thought we'll
Why do we pass exchange cash in person
What if we just bring the transaction online what if we allowed people
To see monthly pay with a credit card same me you would for traditional combinations on the internet
But instead you get somebody tell me
Right
And suddenly
We realize we had a business model
We said well maybe we'll just take a transaction fee
As we
Flow the funds from guests
The Host
The second thing we learned is that there were people who did want to travel
Where they weren't after taking place their emailing us including our first three guess, Michael we must hate
I'm going to Vancouver next week
How do I stay in somebody's home I had such a good experience he got some like whoa
Is there a conference going on
YouTube
Why does it need to be Converse maybe this is just
Trapezoid
So we went back to me and said
What's the what's the ad payments
Let's make this a travel site
And they start to warm up the idea
But had some real
Questions about how to get to Marketplace like that started
So he started to build something
Even more ambitious
Well actually he moved back to Boston
To be with his girlfriend
Kind of the Bands falling apart a little bit
And that's only had an idea
Which was
What if we re watch this new version of our service
And we do it
The crest
Of a tidal wave
Press
Which in summer 2008
Was Barack Obama
It specifically
Obama speaking at the Democratic National Convention
Denver Colorado
Where
There was a housing crisis
Because
100000 people are anticipated to see Obama speak
Andover
Less than 30000 hotel rooms most of which were picked up by delegates
So this is a real problem in fact the mayor of Denver at one point thought about open up the city parks so people can camp out
What if we time the relaunch of a service to be the third launch
During the DNC we can ride the coattails of all the Obama press to bring what awareness to the
Marketplace that's exactly what we did we hustled Seafood in Denver we met people on the ground we got local
Press was turned into Regional press with turn the national press and eventually International press
Wow and so this is still weeks before the convention this is like July 2008
What happened
Well
We did a live interview with CNN
Formal living room
And we have about a hundred people
Actually book and pay with a credit card at your service
Which this was like the first
Sign of overworking viable Marketplace
Even to the point where we were getting customer service calls
For the first time
And that just like was your cell phone
Yeah
How did it go
Wait we ended up going from 0 to 800 home
It's a matter
4 weeks
So 800 homes
Are on this site called
Airbnb
That's right and I have to tell you
I thought that this was it like this was
Our
Rocketship to the Moon
You thought we made it we're here we got it right this if you build it they will come and look what happening and they came yeah
And then the convention ended
And
All those numbers came crashing right back down
So here we headed to Lana because at this point we'd also started talking to invest
With all this is a great time to talk to investors or numbers are up yet
Working with stories that we can share with that press
We get
Introduced to 20% Silicon Valley
None of them reply to her email
Five of them units
Coffee
Invested
In US
Wow
It was completely demoralizing
Like 2008 was the worst year of my life
Really oh my gosh yes because you put so much into this thing
Write like
I don't have nothing else going on in my life except this
And to put it in front of very credible investors the guys are to pick the Googles and PayPal and YouTube's of the world
And since the focus Square in the eyes ago
It wasn't weird
I'm not invested in this
What do they say what what why
Well they didn't say this but here's the underlying reason
It's because we've all been taught since we were kids
That strangers evil Danger
No one in their right mind
Investment service that was
Based upon
This pitch that
What we want to build a website
People publicly post images of their most intimate spaces their bedrooms there bathrooms
The kinds of rooms that usually closed when people come over
And then
Over the internet
You can invite complete strangers to sleep in their homes
It's going to be huge
So so this is like back to the conventions you're thinking
We got it we're going to get all this make all this money and I'll raise all this money in and all of a sudden you get back to Sanford
Just go and nobody wants to give you any money
Exactly
Nobody
How are you keeping up the business
Going if you didn't have any
Any cash we did raise around financing we call it
The Visa round
Which missions are you
If you max out your credit card
You know those binders reheat baseball cards
Yeah I had one of those except the one baseball cards and credit cards
We would go through Visa
After Visa
Two MasterCards on final two Amex
Just maxing out
Credit cards
That's how we funded herself
I can tell you like there's not no worse feeling than getting a credit card statement that's only going up
With no hope of ever painted town named for this by the way
In the startup world
There's a name for this phase of a company where you have a product in the market but they don't fit yet
It's almost like two gears that don't touch this mysterious gap between these metal gears
That you can't figure out
How to close the gap
And because the trough of Sorrow
It's a long
Period of time
You don't have product Market fit in
In the data and analytics it looks like the Midwest of analytics because it's perfectly flat
There's zero growth
And this is when people tend to quit this is when people tend to quit
Emily come back how to give you in as partners eventually climb their way out
House of sorrow and gyros near listening to how I built this NPR
Thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible first to Prezi
Business the better way to present
If you're tired of selling to your customers using the same old deck slides
Try Prezi business
There's engaging interactive presentation platform that features built-in analytics cloud-based collaboration
Tools and the unique ability to adapt with the flow of conversation
Perhaps it's time to update your marketing and your professional reputation with presentations customers
Will actually enjoy and remember schedule your free demo and prezi.com built
Thanks also to stamps.com with stamps.com you can buy and print official US postage
Search for any letter or package on demand 24/7 right from your computer
No more trips to the post office and no need to lease an expensive postage meter
Sign up for stamps.com today to get this special offer
A 4 week trial plus Postage and a digital scale
Go to stamps.com click on the microphone and enter
Built
Just one more thing before we get back to the show
We've been
Incredibly inspired by the hundreds of stories
You sent us about the companies you are building I'm just read a few examples here we heard from Seth
He'll he's got a company that
Taking pre-orders for a product that grew out of a
Camping trip extra pieces
We grabbed are nylon hammocks strung them up on a little island in the middle of a lake
It's froze our butts up so he's now got a prototype for a product
It's an insulated hammock that he says solves cold butt syndrome which is a real thing look it up
We also heard from Leah fazzini she started semolina artisanal pasta 2 years ago in Los Angeles
Business before and she's had some
Real hurdles like she says she engaged in some hand-to-hand combat with her pasta extruder and she lied
Bella is doing okay for organic pasta is already for sale online and in Holt
Food stores in Southern California we also heard from Larry Moss of Rochester New York you rights built my business
Out of thin air based on a product that typically lasts a week
Hillary is talking about balloons like the kind you make balloon animals out of except his balloon sculptures
You can check out his story in the amazing pictures
Facebook page and fire there we love it
You like us and if you want to send us your story about what your building go to build. NP
Dr. O r g that's billed with a d. Npr.org
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Its 2008
Jonas Partners have no investors
And a lot of credit card debt
And I'm trying to figure out
How to raise
It was at this point that Brian and I are in the kitchen late one night like 2 in the morning
And we're just trying to keep each other's spirits up
And
During the peak of Obama vs McCain
Is like September
And we're working on this idea of being are bed and breakfast in providing maybe we give our hosts breakfast cereal to give their guests
Would it be funny if it was politically themed
Oh yeah we call it like a Obama O's the breakfast of change
Or maybe at McCain's Maverick in every bite
And we actually ended up making breakfast cereal
Wait
You made breakfast cereal
Like actual cereal to eat
That's a good question
Which is how do you make breakfast cereal and how do you do it with not zero budget but a negative urine a deficit by the way
So you know I pick up the phone I called Kellogg General Mills
And
Check onto the pitch and I got hello
Hello
It hung up on me
And then it dawned on me will maybe we don't have to make cereal
Maybe we can just
Go to the grocery store
Buy some cereal off the shelf
Designer unboxing
Put the bag of cereal in her inbox you would up and and sell it that way
Just sell it on the street well maybe it'll make website
Instead of Airbnb or in addition do not assure
Then the question was
How do you make the boxes
So I found an illustrator
Did Art Direction put all the pieces together
I found a RISD alumni
In the East Bay here in San Francisco that
Winning
And
You know I like I poured it all out to this guy sitting
Here's the idea of the concept of really excited. Here's the mock-ups and sketches
Alright here's what I'll do
I'll make 500 of each box
You guys don't have to pay me up front but pay me commission-based underwear sale
And it dawned on us that
With 500 of each box will that was a limited edition
That was a collector's item
We could number them
On the top of the box at 500 and suddenly
We decided we could sell a box of Obama bows and Cat McCain
$40 a box
She's just a crazy story I don't even I don't even have forgotten about Airbnb where where we going
What's going on with his interview
Look it's an entrepreneur Bender
So we make Obama's. Com
We get the boxes Sarah put a hundred boxes together we mail them out to all the press that we
The Weeknd
Melty way
Every morning show had a box of these
So we didn't get featured on all of these different shows CNN did a live interview with us about breakfast cereal
And we were the number-one politically themed video
Altenen.com for the entire day
And after that CNN interview
We ended up selling out of Obama bows
Which is incredible like where did you think you were going to go from there like almost didn't matter because
$40 box * 500 boxes
Yeah $20,000 in breakfast cereal
Yeah which was breakfast cereal. We just enough to pay off her credit cards
All right so you pay off your credit card bills
And then what you go back to air bed and breakfast well we got to this list for the Fateful dinner one night
With one of our mentors
It was Michael Seibel and Justin Kahn
And so I brought the dinner with them and
They've been helping us the last couple months and what kind of like
At the end of the rope and they can tell and they're like
You guys need some help
You should
Participate
In this incubator program called y combinator
Threat dinner we woke up on our phones and the deadline was the night before
Like come on
The end up
Emailing the guy who runs in a guy named Paul Graham
They knew and they say you know a Paul there's these guys if you got this concept and and
It really benefit from being in your program
Tickle to the application
Send it to you and Paul right back into the give it to me by midnight tonight
Sabrina race helmets
We start to fill out the applications pretty intense yeah
Aspen X2
We get this callback
Better application got accepted
So we got to the next round which is an interview
Puritan advance
Do the grill each other with all these retail questions
Cheap and expand internationally
You know what's the next big future going to build
Excetera excetera
And so we going to the interview it's in the small tiny room
At the Y combinator office
And as for partners around the table
Sit down
Very first thing
A toboggan is mouth is
You mean people actually use this
Miguel
Yeah that's weird
That's not a good start of any kind
It kind of went downhill from there
What another room
Nothing like this is our last chance effort and it didn't go so well
And that's when I remembered that I had brought a box of Obama's
To give to him as a gift
Psycho Ronnie back in the room
I whip out the box I handsome guy Paul we got this for you
Because
Oh where'd you buy this
I go well we made it
Because what do you mean you made it
And I told my story in 60 seconds to go wait so you guys funded your company based on selling breakfast cereal
Immediately turned around and put the box of cereal on the shelf behind the desk
On the ride home
We get a phone call
Paul Graham
To inform us that he'd like to offer us
A spot
In the Y combinator program
And
I'll be waiter found out
That the reason we got in wasn't because of her idea
It was because
Through the breakfast cereal we can prove to him that we had hustle we had Grit
If we can figure out Hussle breakfast over for $40 a box
We can figure out how to make a website work so you get into y combinator
And
What what is a
Like what does it do for you guys what what happened there
Y combinator was a game-changer for us
And I'll never forget the first office hours
That we had with Paul Graham
Sit down with us
And he goes
Where's your Market
And
We all get each other and were like
We don't really have a market
No one's really using the website
But we go you know
New York is showing some promise we have 30 hosts in New York
You're renting it there extra rooms out in their homes in
Migas
Your customers are in New York City
But you're here in Mountain View
And yeah we're here for your program
Everything goes
What are you still doing here
Go to New York City and points his finger at you he's got this thing where he looks at you
Pointer finger
And it was in this moment
Sitting in this room this tiny room
Wear something profound change for us
Because up until this point
We had subscribed to the ethology of Silicon Valley
Which is that you have to solve things in a scalable way
Because what happens when one day
The rocket ship takes off
You already left behind because your code held you back
And so
We could try to solve her problems by a coating her way through it
End
If you remember that didn't get us anywhere cuz we are in the Midwest of Analytics
And so here comes Paul Graham
Gave us permission
To do things that don't scale
Such as
Fly across the country and meet the early doctors of your service
Yeah and it was in that moment that we felt so much more free
To think
Even more creatively about how we could get our service off
The ground if you could do things that don't have
Have to scale
What else can we do
And
As we start going through the search
Results and looking at the house
Identify the pattern
And the pattern was this
People just generally didn't know how to take a good photo of your home
So the phone is really bad
Sentence of the photos that you had on
Decided that timer
Crappy photos
Well you know people using their camera phones at the time was like flipped
Cameras on switch
They're taking pictures at night it just wasn't
Different merchandising their home and away.
You would want to stay there so therefore no one was looking them
And we thought you know
Mozart School took some photography classes in photography my whole life in fact
The Hobby
I'm going to bed if we just flew out there for a weekend
We could probably take some ice for photos
And we won't charge you for it will do for free
So that weekend we bought plane tickets Brian and I flew to New York
We've emailed her hosts all three of them
We rented a really nice camera
And went door-to-door throughout Manhattan Brooklyn and then other parts of New York
And it's funny cuz he had knocked on the door and then they open the door and introduce myself
As I am Joe I emailed you from Airbnb
An account like looking over my shoulder so yeah where's the professional
Photography promise I go that's me to my mom's going to take the photos for you yet
So you're the guy taking the photos
So yeah I'm taking photos and in what school is at
The photos are looking pretty good and getting the lighting right
Composition in I'm kind of
I'm staging to place a little bit of skin fluffing the pillows and then make sure that the place doesn't look cluttered
And
I show the photos in the back
The camera said hey what do you think you know do you like these
And
These houses were like
Oh my God my apartment looks amazing I can't believe it
Do you want to stay for some tea or coffee
And so I'd end up spending a few hours sometimes in their in their homes
Just talking with them
And this is where
Instinctively we went into design research mode
Which is
Going out and talking to the people you're designing for
Such that you can understand
The world from their point of view
To inform your point of view
Yeah and so I called this
Enlightened empathy
Which is seen the world so closely in the shoes of the person that you're creating for
That you can see
The world that way they see it
I I bring those inside back and you combine it with your own
Design point of view
To create something new
So here we are in the living room
Could you show me how how you check your calendar
Show me how you message with guest
And
In those moments
We saw how are perfectly designed interface
Completely and utterly failed
Well with what we thought took two or three clicks to get done
People were taking
1012 Quicks they were stumbling around getting the Lost
Within our own website and you guys did not know that up until that point
We had no idea
And so it wasn't until we actually sat down next to her early adopters some of her most passionate
Early customers
And they reveal to us
The mysterious Gap
Cleaner product
In our Market
Was the inefficiencies
R user interface
What's interesting about this is that
You don't strike me as like an egomaniac or somebody who doesn't like that you sent me somebody really wants it and it's
Surprising that it took you guys so long to discover this
I know right
I know
But once we did it was
It was like
Is like a jackpot yeah
So we came back with Oliver our discoveries
Something interesting
Are numbers
That second week
Went from
$200 a week
And fees
Which is what we're making for 6 months
Right which is not sustainable 3guys cannot leave out that zeref yes go
Are numbers jump to $400
In one weekend we just from pictures and making a couple of
Simple well
I worked at Nasa is there a bug in the system because that's just that's just crazy
How do we double in a week
And sure enough we're done more
Reservations with the house that we had met
Which was very interesting guy is that
We didn't notice at the time but because New York
It's such an international destination
We have guests coming from Berlin we guess coming from London from Sydney from Vancouver
Kuba coming as guests
Experiencing this new service of staying in somebody's home
They go back to where they came from
And it's had this Epiphany moment Saha they go
Wait I have an extra room
Why don't I rent that on the site and they would sign up
And they would sign up
At what point did you were you able to
Actually
Attract money from investor
Was it around that time
It's precisely around this time
So
What I've learned is that when the gears start to click
Investors can hear that
And they actually this time they came to us
And get offers coming in from
A variety of different groups
And the one that shocked us the most was Sequoia capital
Which was a print it is a preeminent
Venture Capital firm
In Silicon Valley
That we thought well maybe one day
A year from now we'll go talk to them it's actually they were not going to her.
Yardworks talk to us
Closing a deal with them. We got our first round of financing which
It's a huge relief
We can paint runs comfortably and we can hire start tired team
Cornett at what point do you remember
Sitting with
What's the name Brian
I think this is going to be really big
Well one night
This isn't
It was probably like 11:30 at night is really tired
Mathia this point we have an office
And I used to look at every listing that got added to Airbnb I
I would go straight at night and just click through
Each of them
And I come across this one that says
Fiji Islands
And I'm like
What's that
I click on it
And sure enough
Somebody out in the South Pacific
Listed
A 5-acre private island
Our site
Complete with personal chef
Complete with
Water sports
And I'm looking to the photos of thing going
Holy cow this is me
Rentable
And it was in that moment realize that the power the spot forum
Is that we put it out there and
The creativity of the people who have
This could be the back to it
Has gone beyond
Any of our expectations
So you guys have obviously grown much much bigger since then
A bigger than than most
Are all hotel chains
And you have some similar challenges to two companies like uber
I'm with some City saying hey you know you guys should be regulated like hotels
So how do you
How do you respond to that
I think about that question
In the context of Innovations over the last hundred years
End
There are three examples that come to mind of new ideas the edge of the world
That had
Pretty rough start
Butter now so commonplace in everyday that you'd laugh
You thought like
Allow like people are against that at one point
So ATM machines
At one point in
I think it's the 1970s
Wer
Had a lot of criticism
I think they're actually laws
Being written against them
In certain States. The US
Cuz it's new and different way
Baking are you have to go inside and then and talk with her
Person behind the desk of you. Maybe up sell you one of the services you just went to
A computer in a wall in in
Retrieved money for course
Can I retrieve it at ATM machines
No
The VCR thing is another great example is first patented in
Mid-twentieth century
But in order to become a product until
These babies early 80s
Because it was met with such resistance from incumbent industries that didn't want people to
Watch movies at home
The car is another example where
When the Model T came out in 1908
Representative new way to travel
But anyway to
The new form of transportation
And there are certain cities that were against the car
And they're actually
Laws drafted to
Outlaw cars
But you know after a year of trying a new more efficient way of transportation
Are the people demanded that they didn't go back to horse and buggy
And so the policymakers you know
How to
Modify
The lost it to what people want
Cancel
I think the world is ready for our invention
Given that has been over a hundred million people that have stayed in homes all over the world
End
The good news is that a city's come
To learn about what we do and what we offer
But they tend to want to work with us
Because they see that there's an economic economic impact then
Allows
People in their cities
Different neighborhoods
To benefit
When you
I think last year Airbnb was
Value of
20 billion.
Kelly Moore
Today
Is that
Crazy to does that shock you when you think that
You just started this thing and it is an idea that really went nowhere for the first
Couple years
In your apartment in San Francisco
And it's not worth
Billions
B
Does it mean anything to you or to you is it just a number on a piece of pie
I don't think about it too much
I mean yeah
The things can change if you look at the first.com
You know what I was
Griffin Georgia
I was so enthralled by
Every day there was a new story of a new company that started in Silicon Valley or San Francisco
I planted a very deep sea
With me that one day I want
To be a part of that
So I also remember in
The first.com of companies that were
Here today gone tomorrow
Yeah there's there's a list of 10 of the hottest companies from the 1990s
One of which you would still remember
It's because technology moves so quickly that if you're not thinking about what's next
The world around you can change faster than you do
Joe gebbia Budweiser company that he first tried to
Bill before Airbnb was called bonds which are basically I am not making this up
Butt cushions for art students the company kind of hormones after Airbnb success but
There still a website for it and every now and then in order still comes in and I still run down to the garage
Do you have in your garage
Instill in your garage
It's a funny thing cuz it reminds me of like where I started and it is very grounded website
Is it cripons. Com
Only 600 left
Listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episodes in good how I built this.
Npr.org and if you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other people know about it
Because of us directly at hidta at npr.org
The show's producer Suite by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music is also to novigrad
Ensenada Mexican food at Jeff Rogers I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
I want you to come see how I built this
Live on stage
Now hear this podcast Festival
On Friday October 28th in beautiful Anaheim California
Now hear this is a 3-day Festival of your favorite podcasts
October 28th through the 30th
With shows like NPR pop culture happy hour dinner party download and WTF with Marc Maron
We will be doing a live episode of How I built this on Friday October 28th
So if you can only make it for one day make sure it's Friday or you'll miss out on a show
To get tickets and information about the
Full lineup go to now hear this Fest
Dot-com
Hope to see you there
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support
7 days a week