This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this hiscox hiscox the business insurance
Experts who Taylor intelligent Insurance Solutions to fit each businesses very specific needs get a quote
At hiscox. Com
Hiscox business insurance experts
I left that morning for the office knowing that's the day and I was
Sitting in the office waiting and my partner was on the phone talking to the lawyers you know. Ended on the eyes
Is the cross the t's on the contract is that day you're you're you're about to go and sign your name on the car
Contract that very day
It was indeed like within an hour We're we were ready to get in the car and go over
And I
Should I got to take a walk around the block and so I did
Went out to the parking lot and I just started weeping
You couldn't even want to do it
Do you want to do it
From NPR how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
I got on the show today
That's first name to create Clif Bar what are the most popular energy bars in the country
Back in the 1980s energy bar was shut down your throat before
Running a marathon or going skiing and that was a whole aisle of Lara and Luna and chia bar
Bars in the supermarket
And they weren't in the bottom of our backpacks are in the glove compartment of our cars
In the late 1980s
Gary Erickson was living in the Bay Area he was one of those guys who would inhale energy bars right before
Signing or racing his bike
And also that he was working at a bicycle seat back during which was going to was fine
For a little while I think all along I even through high school I think I always wanted to have my own business
And even though managing
A manufacturing facility making bicycle seats
Felt close to have my own business it wasn't my own business
And then
Crazy thing happen
I was saying my mom's
Kitchen table and she was serving me this
My mom is Greek and my grandmother's Cregan
They taught me how to bake a young age in my my
Mom is serving me something was like a calzone and we called a Greek calzone
And I looked at that and I said
You know I bet I could sell these
And so here I am of God
I'm working for the bicycle company and racing bicycles now I'm going to start a business
So we made a few in her kitchen I went out to some delis around Berkeley and San Francisco and are they
They were hit people pick them up but what's inside of them
I'm so we had different feelings the typical Greek filling the spanakopita which is a spinach and feta cheese
They were really delicious
This wonderful brioche
Kind of dough
But
When I started this business I needed to
To keep working so
Cuz I
Didn't have enough money size funding the business
With the bicycle company
2 fun
The small bakery that
I started called
Cali Sweets and savouries witch
I was named after my grandmother
So at night you would like
The baking like all through the night and then get up in the morning and then like go work in the factory likes
Exactly exactly
And then one day
In 1990
I was out on a
A ride with
A really good friend and we did this one long day trip in the Bay Area
Is 175 mile one day ride we thought it was going to a hundred
25 miles
And we took along with us
6 energy bars are on the market at the time the only energy bar really
That was on the market at that time that
So many cycles for eating does power bar
And they were also from
Coincidentally
And so
We're each packed six of them probably put a banana in there too and we
Did this ride where there was very few stores and
When were at the top of
Mount Hamilton I didn't five of those
Bars NEARBY
And I looked at the six month I just said no way I can
I can't do one more
I would rather starve than eat another 1
Why
Latest dare
Hard
They were they never really did taste good but we always as bike racers we always thought of them as the bitter pill that they do the
Job but it's not about taste
And here I have a bakery and everything we do.
Taste great
We're riding down the hill were coasting down into San Jose to get to a 7-Eleven
And I turned my friend Janice said you know what I can make a better energy
That was it
That wasn't
Literally the next day
I called my mom
And she had help me with all these rest
Mom I'm coming over and we're going to make
An energy bar
She's like what's an energy bar
Try to explain it to her and I said it's kind of like that great
Oatmeal chocolate chip raisin cookie that you make but we can't use butter we can't use sugar and we can't use oil
Chisel that's impossible
I said let's just try so for the next 6 months
I brought over
Bags of
Ingredients that I have been researching on
And we're not talking about
Exotic ingredients were talking about hole in Greek
Scuzz PowerBar was
Made with
Stuff that
Was more kind of Highly produced and highly refined
And I wanted to be more like my mom's cookie
What kind of ingredients are you using
We were using whole oats
I'm real fruit
And a sweetener we didn't use oil
Or better but we use a sweetener that was made from rice
In a rectangular so they were like a bar and wasn't going to be a cookie and had to be like a bar
And
We had many failures
And at times you tried to talk ourselves into that this is great and it then I would bring it out to my friends in
Plastic bags that I was racing with and training with night to hear try this but keep it a secret
And they be like we'll just
Terrible
Okay go back to the kitchen
At what point did you
Do you say okay I've got this thing we got it
So it was after about six months
I was
Trampoline
Continue to sound like but we just knew my mom and I just knew like
Okay this is what we were looking for
And then you take a risk
You're not sure
And then you put a package around it
And that stories
Let you know what another real good friend that I was working with name Doug Gilmour you know I helped him out with some of the advertising
For the bicycle company and I knew that he was very very creative
Person
I said you need to design the pack
And
He came up with the climbing image
Which is now
University icon
And has a very deep meaning of
You know what the introspection of climbing and
Especially on an overhang the way it is yeah
And we needed a name for
And they're all kinds of names were
Where
We are considering
He wanted it to be Gary bar I didn't
And one day I was
Crossing the Bay Bridge coming over to work on it with him and
My dad's name popped into my head
I'm taking
That makes sense I name the bakery after my grandmother
I can name this after my dad he's the one that influenced me
With the Great Outdoors this is about the outdoors this is about this is a connection with Adventure it's
You know taking it on the go
When you are Outdoors you and your adventures
Any perfect sense
And so we need to Clif Bar after my dad my dad's name is Clifford Erickson
Once you have the bar down the recipe down
How do you even have the money the resources to
Turn this into a business in a product that you were going to like put your whole life behind
I never ever would have thought it's
Turn into a house but all I was thinking was
I've got this Bakery
I can figure out how to make this if I can just take a small market share from power bar then I can continue my life
My style and have the freedom of my own business
And do something that I love to do which is both run a business and make a great product
And that's that was easier said than done
Why is that
So
We
Try to make it in our Bakery we just didn't have the equipment
To do it
So I found a bakery down the street
Dad agreed to help me
Produce it like a like a mom
Like a cookie Baker
And we
Leverage
The packaging companies and said
Will pay you
Will make a small run will give you what we can and
When we sell the first
Amount will pay you
I mean back then I didn't really even know what I was doing I wasn't
I didn't learn this in college and maybe it's a good thing I didn't learn this in college cuz I would have done it this way but
I just started thinking out loud like how am I going to do this I have no money
So basically
You went to these
To the bakery you said I'm not going to be able to pay you right away but then you would turn Rancid
Distributors you would say look
Can you pay me on delivery
And then use that money to pay the
How did you once you start to manufacture
Clif bars like how did you even get
Anyone interested in the mood while what did you do did you like walk around I just shops
Some stores and not say I did a couple things one is I
We go to bike races
Or
I went to running events
I just started passing out the bar
We did one ad
One advertisement
In bicycle magazine and a few other magazines that was pretty hard-hitting
I guess power bar
I was like okay there's a new kid on the Block kind of thing
The title or the headline was it's your body you decide
So did you want you want refined ingredients or do you want holinger
Pictures of both ingredients
That cause us to be sued immediately
Oh wow
Are Insurance picked up the
The tap and we ended up settling with tar bar
But it created this buzz in the bicycle industry where people said have you heard of Clif Bar
I don't think I don't know if you could pull that off now
And we were the
You know now there's
Hundreds of bars out there
TurboTax
Us and Them
Did you have to
Like to go out and raise money that you have to ask people to invest in the company or were you able to
Tentative
Somehow do it with very little money
You know I never thought
Of
Either looking for outside money or wanting outside money
And maybe that was
A good thing of my knee naivete because
What you do that you know you lose control of your destiny
I tried to get a bank on my
I did get a $20,000
My father gave me
Office credit card $20,000
But most of it
Man I look back and I kind of think how did I pull this off
Because
And it wasn't big
Yeah this was just
A few bike shops in a few notches
Food stores
And
Yeah I remember being at a show like the marathon the LA Marathon setting up a little table
Standing out there in the Isle
With a tray of cut up bars and and if people like by say try to try this new energy bar and they were like
Energy bar
Alkmaar
And they try and then they would
Walk along and he wouldn't want to look back and
Mike Cleary. You know
Did my embarrassment and then
32in and turn around and come right back door what is that
And I knew you knew you had it then when
You saw that kind of response
And so the
It was Word of Mouth
And the word spread throughout the country so what happened in that first year after you
Like like
I mean when you were still
Working at the bicycle company
Yeah I was working the bus company for 2 more years still in it and I was using that money to as living hand-to-mouth in
I was sleeping in the garage and
I was just using that money
To also fun
You know some of the extra bills
And then there was a Tipping Point
By the end of 1992
We sold $700,000
Wow so you were making money within a year
Bobby year-and-a-half
2 we really started
We started making
And
From there on it was
It was like a wild tools like a getting on a wild horse and hanging on Wii
Almost doubled sales for the next 8 years in a row
You basically were the artist company right like did you
Did you make any mistakes by that point arida sailing on was it like Smooth Sailing
No
One of the larger mistakes was
You know I caught a handshake deal with the time I
Didn't
Use corporate counsel very
Effectively
Fact that you know
Where's were too expensive
Sidon
I normally use a lawyer so I did a handshake deal with a distributor
In the early 90s
Where it ended up biting me
Because
They weren't performing and so I
Cancelled
Quote contract
And they came back and sue me for ownership
Too long of a story but it but it ended up we went to court we settled
And it cost
A lot of money
The salad I made a big mistake I never should have done a handshake deal on a distribution International distribution deal like that
Cheats you almost lost the company
It yashow it was
It was a knockout dragout
Fight and
I
That was the most sick to the stomach
I had felt up to that point
About business
One day when I we went to we went to mediation and I fell
At the end of mediation outside
Oh my God I could lose this whole thing
So we fight we fight we negotiated it ended up being just
Pam off
Cost a lot had to go get a bank loan
I went and visited like five or six Banks finally found one at a party
This guy talk to me and said
I'm uninterested when we went to visit with him and
They gave us the loan
And we paid it off in a few years
And then we're free
Added you like Copa that emotionally mentally like you had to run your company and you are fighting off
This other company that was trying to take you over
I
I think I've learned a ton
With other things I've chosen to do in my life like rock climbing
My friend uses the term sharp end of the row
Which means when your rock climbing
You're either leading or following
And when you're leading
You're on the sharp end of the Rope
You could take a pretty big thought I had done a lot of leading in my life on
In rock climbing
And I wouldn't you I was used to being enough
Position of
Facing danger but being able to stay composed
The weird thing is actually clean better when I'm on leave then I'm falling
And I still try to figure out that
How that metaphor works but it
Cuz you are you're in more danger if you're leading but I think I'm more Focus
When I'm leaving
And so
I was on this big lead now I've got this
Lawsuit
I got the company growing about all the manufacturing issues and
Collections Bubba
But I think
Because that
I was so focused
Nothing was going to stop me except something did Olmos
Stop and offer Gary Erickson and almost couldn't refuse it with this guy Roz
Listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible first to Hyatt
I believe the modern business traveler is changing the face of business
Please business Travelers don't settle they're refusing mediocrity they're Reinventing their careers bending titles
Breaking new ground
And because they changed
Business travel is changing to
And that's why there's a place and a house were good enough
Hyatt Place and Hyatt House hotels
You've come too far to settle now
So book your stay today
Hyatt.com why settle
Thanks also to Prezi business
Better way to present
If you're tired of selling your customers using the same old deck slides
Try Prezi business
Barely engaging interactive presentation platform that features built-in analytics cloud-based collaboration
Tools and the unique ability to adapt
With the flow of conversation
Perhaps it's time to update your marketing
And your professional reputation with presentations customers will actually enjoy and remember
Schedule your free demo
Prezi.com
Slash built
It's how I built this from NPR
Garage
Okay let's fast forward a bit
This is now
Year 2000
What about 8 years after a Clif Bar has lunch then
It's doing it
Credibly well it's got a growing
Staff almost
40 million dollars
In sales
And I should mention Gary Erickson has a partner in this venture
Bleach have 50% ownership in the company
And something else is going on at the same time
Big food corporations start to get into the game
And they start buying up.
Competitors
Empire Barbers already already sold and balance are sold so it's just
It was kind of
1/3 as a third
So we got approached
Bye
Travel Company
And
In a very uncharacteristic I got a untied from the Rope of being on lead
Eden said
All right
I guess this is what you do
I'll put it in what happened
We
Tired and investment banker I mean long story short but hard investment banker to put the company up for sale
Instead of us talking to companies which hire somebody to talk
Companies in
It was an odd moment I can remember the exact moment that I
Got a call if my partner said
She said I want to sell the company
All right
So
There we were we
But the company up for sale
And started traveling all over the
All over the country
Visiting these large companies that wanted
Us to be part of their portfolio
And we got an amazing deals from one of the large companies are we got to do we got an offer for a
$129 on $49
Quaker Oats
Oh I guess you heard
So you guys are sitting at the
The table
Quaker Oats
120 million box
Listen 2000
If that meant you would have gotten 60 million your partner gotten 60 million
And you could walk away
And like
Did you seriously I mean you were seriously thinking about doing this
More than serious
We
Had
The deal
Essentially done
On April
I know the date April 17th 2000
We were going to meet our investment banker
The people from
Quaker and as well as all the lawyers
To sign the deal
And I would have been up
And we have told the company what we were doing till all the employees and they trusted us
It was a naive
Nice thing to say the things wouldn't change
But I still set it
And it was not true and I knew it wasn't true that
Of course
Just going to change
It could be better could be worse but
You can't say it's not
Change
Yeah
And so I left that morning for the office knowing that's the day and I was
Sitting in the office
Waiting
My partner was on the phone talking to lawyers yunnan
Don the I's and cross the t's
Summit Contracting
She was she was ready to sell
Oh absolutely was it was done deal and her in her eyes
And you couldn't wait because she was
Very fearful of the future
And understand that to some degree but
Why would people walk away from buying our product
If we didn't
Sell the company
I never said I was for the three months that we were selling the company I was just living in the dark
I was not sleeping well I was not riding my bike I was
Probably not very fun to be around
And I said I just
I was fighting it
You're internally but not really
Pictures of a counselor and talked about it
Probably would have gotten to that point
But there was and I started
I started to
Have that amazing moment of just shaking I'm shaking right now is thinking of it
Were you in that day you're you're you're about to go and sign your name on the contract
That's very good we were ready to get in the car and go over
And
I said I got to take a walk around the block and so I did
I went out to the parking lot and
I just started weeping
You couldn't even want to do it
They want to do it
I guess it's like
Noah
Walking off the field
I mean this was everything that you built right
Yeah this was
This was I put everything that this is my this is my life and this our employees and this is my family is named after my dad
So what did you
What did you do what did you tell your partner
So halfway around the block I decide not to self company and then I felt completely free
It was like oh my God I'm free again
Now I have to go back around the rest of the block and forgot what I was
My partner
And I told her
Need to put phone down
Tuna sandwich
Wow
And she knew immediately when I said that
That I was
And so she was on the phone with the lawyer she said
We're not selling
So I can imagine she's in the room with all these
People
30th floor of the Comerica building.
Deals off
So
Now I'm in a new situation where
I got it now go back and convince our people that we're not selling the company and that it's going to be okay
We told him he couldn't do without
Sewing and now we're going to know I'm saying we can
Secondly
My partner wanted out so I had to negotiate a deal
And so that was 7 months of negotiation and
And third was I had to go out
Our attorney says Dialing for Dollars
I had to go find $69
You have to find 60 million dollars
Basically by your partner
Because that's what you were offered to her argument was look that's what it's worth
Eggs
So
I mean just think that you don't want to have to deal with as you're growing your business cuz
We were growing like crazy yeah
Sonoco share this deal
And
Decided that I would
Try to meet with the entire company every week
And hold a meeting
Two so that I could be in front of them
So they could see me every week saying
We are not selling the company cuz they were convinced this is going to be a short-term deal and then I would go back
Yeah and sell the company and
I got calls from like
Private Equity groups that they heard what happened there like you are out of your mind you're never going to make it
Never going to make it if you didn't have the debt and I have $69 a day and did you send.
Take me to write maybe I'm not going to make it maybe I'm crazy like what am I doing
I must have been serving some good Kool-Aid at the at the office could people
Started believing that we have to do it
And it took us nine years to pay off that thing and we did it
Play me a time Gary light
You could have taken the money and then like how this Charmed Life
Fan bike
10 fish stand
Start a foundation in NJ
It's kind of like to go to conferences and just given toxin
But there was something like what
What was the thing that prevented you from doing that from because that would that would have been an easier
Route you would have done the quality of your life
Like the things you can buy and own in the way you could live would not have been substantially differ
What the way you live today
True true it would probably the same
Well obviously wasn't about money
There is
There is something deep about
You know wanting to
Grow this business
And I mean I think my wife has it
Very well you know what
It's the power of yeah the power of a lot of money could be good you could
Don't need a lot of money to start a foundation
But the power of
A business
Done the right way
Is way more powerful than
To rich people
I don't want over say that because
You know
Rich people that are doing some great things but yeah
As the company has grown pekin
60 to 400 ploys now you know our community service program Malone
Contribute over 10,000 hours of community service last year we could we can't do that as two individuals but we can is a
Company
Carrie Europe
Your dad
Cliff
Passed away
Yeah, cool like his
His legacy like your connection damn lives on in this snippet
Best this brand this thing that we all buy and eat
Clif bars helmets
That's really cool it
For 1
He was able to
Experience
Both
That bar
Named after him and and the growth of the company
Yeah I'm just so happy that he did get to experience it
For a very long time he was from Door County Wisconsin he would go to Wisconsin on vacations and bring Clif bars
He walking the bike shops
Hey Daddy what you think it was caused by
We love quiz
I'm Cliff
What
Your cliff
Oh my God
Making noises celebrity
Either
This narrative or I wouldn't say I'm ethology about entrepreneurs that they are
Successful entrepreneurs are like single-mindedly Focus
On the go
Akane no an invalid in themselves
And have very little or no self
Is that does that characterize you did you ever have
Any self-doubt did you ever did you ever have sleepless nights about what you were saying what am I doing I doing the right thing
Or would you just like totally focused and and just
Confident in what you were doing
Orange.
The ladder
I can't remember a day where I didn't believe
And we would get through anything
I don't know where that all come
Comes from
I don't
No that's
That unique but
And I do think
Back to Summer
The
Adventures that I
Chosen to do
You know I'm not I'm not a super high risk
Person I don't
Leaving I believe in climbing with a rope
But I do think it teaches you a lot
Because I remember
Years ago I climb the face of Half Dome and
I never once thought I was going to make it
App that face
It was just
I was tapping her I called happy nervous
I was nervous and I was happy
At the same time
There was no doubt we're going to
Make it enough for a second did I say
That anything would stop us from doing that message
One of many
Climbs I've done and and or sportbike Adventures
That's the same way I feel. Clif Bar
Years ago Gary Erickson
Step down as CEO at Cliff are you still super involved with the company and in 2010 he and his wife
Kit handed over 20% of the company to their employees
Listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episode
How I built this. Npr.org and if you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes
Let other people know about it you can also write us directly at HIV tea at npr.org
How I built this shows produced this week but runty Nara blue E2 also composed the music
It's also to neva grandson has meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers on Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey one more thing before we let you go if you get a chance check out my other podcast
It's called the TED Radio Hour
And it's a show about Big Ideas
Feature some of the most
Incredible Minds
On the planet this week's episode is all about the anthropocene this
Strange. Of time in which were living where humans have a bigger impact on our planet
Any other Force
You can find the TED Radio Hour on iTunes or by visiting npr.org podcast
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
Templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com