Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Hey just a heads up to let you know that there's a little bit of strong language in about the first minute and a half
Are the show soap
If you got the kids register
Cover their ears for men men and a half in the
Can you get to go
So you called your dad like that guess what I'm drawing the family business
How to make beer whiskey I was worse I went home and and was he excited
Really but I told him I was kind of hoping that he put his arm around me and
Cuz this 150 year old family tradition was going to be carried on no heel
Look at my gym you've done some really stupid things in your life this is this
Stupidest from NPR is how I
Built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movements they built
Today Show
Jim Cook started Brewing an old family beer recipe called at Samuel Adams bottle it up
And then helped kick-start the craft beer movement
In America
It's a boy last year the number of breweries in America past the 4000 mark
Most of us breweries make
Craft beer seems like ipas Porter Stout sloggers you name it
Beer that wins Awards all over the world
And a lot of it even gets exported to places like Germany in Holland and Belgium
Beer brewing is practically a religion
But if somehow
He went back in time to like 1980
And someone handed you a cold bottle of American Beer
You might not recognize it because
A mighty python fans might remember this
American Beer used to be a joke
So that was what it was like when Jim Cook was a young man but he knew a lot about beer because he
She happened to come from a family of beer makers my dad was a broom
And
It's like being a chef
In the kitchen
He was responsible
The recipe and
The quality
Of
The berry wasn't the only
So
He got out of brewmaster School in 19
There were a thousand breweries all over the US
36 years later when I started Sam Adams that thousand had dwindled down to
And my dad
Bad
To move from Brewery to brewery as
The breweries closed
Did you have any
Intention like as a kid or as a
Teen of
I like doing this doing the same thing your dad did
No
My dad
Told me that it was a miserable way to make a living
And he eventually left
The Brewing industry
Entirely
The last thing that he wanted for me to do
Was to go
Back into Brewing
Crazy cuz if they were like it wasn't
His dad
Every oldest son for six Generations
Has been
Brewer
I believe I'm the only
6th generation
Brewer in the United
Is States
What did you do
Actually I really didn't know
You know I had this wonderful Edge
Educational
Opportunity
That nobody in my family
Had ever had
I after I graduated from
College
Started a JD MBA program
And I could just feel this
Pressure behind me pushing me
Towards
Some career decision
So
I dropped out
So what would you do that
Well
At the time I was involved in a
Lot of outdoor activities
Rock climbing kayaking backpacking
Things like that
And my climbing partner
He got me involved
In
Outward Bound
I was able to do that
During the summer
Bars and then
Hyatt
I learned that
You don't need
That much to live on
If you're really enjoying what you're doing
And so how many years did you take
Did you do that for
I did it on and off for three and a half years
At the end of that three and a half years I thought okay
I think I'm ready to go back
And got my
MBA in
My JD
And
Dave started
Working as a Management Consultant
A company called Boston Consulting Group
And you
We flew first class you know you
You consulted
CEOs and retreated
Really well
It was great job
For a while
Yeah that's pretty good
Why did you leave
Redis
Epiphany
I guess after 6 years it
Bcgi
Ask myself
I want to do this the rest
My life
And the answer came back
No
The next
So the corollary to that was look I don't do it for the rest of my life
Probably don't want to do it
Tomorrow
So how did that like
That decision
Lead to hit you think you have beer
That's a good question and
I knew I didn't want to work in the corporate
So I thought I'm going to start my own business
I don't know what it's going to be
My dad had given me
Actually copy of Inc magazine
And there was an article in there
About Anchor Steam
Is this
Small Brewery in California it was owned by
Great guy named Fritz Maytag
And
Fritz
Had a viable
Small
Brewery
It was an outlier
When I was
Consulting
What always fascinated me
With the outlier
Because that's where the real learning was
There was obviously the potential to find a market
For a really high-quality beer
And I started to think
About it and
I
Developed a different
Business model
For what is now called
Craft brewing
So this is in the mid-80s right
Yeah 1984
So you
You called your dad like that guess what I'm joining the family business I'm going to make beer whiskey I was worse I went home
And was he excited
Not really
When I told him
I was kind of hoping that he
Put his arm around me and
Cuz this
150 year old family tradition was going to be
Carried on to yet another generation know he looked at me sit gym you've done
Some really stupid things in your life this is the stupidest
My scrub
Pause for second Askew kids
You have this great
Job
And you just left
Yes and I left it
Because
Staying there was very
Risky
Leaving it was not risk
And it's the difference in life
Between things that are scary
And things that are dangerous
And there are plenty of things that are
Scary but aren't
Dangerous
And there are
Things that are
Dangerous
But not
Scary
Yeah and
Those are the things that get you
That can give you a climbing an alloy
From Outward Bound
1 things we
Tough people do was
Rappel off
Cliff and they're really it's a very scary
Thanks
To do but you're also held
Buy a belay rope
And that rope
Ahold
Har
So walking up the
The cliff backwards is scary but not Danger
Yeah okay
Walking across
You know what
Degree angles
Snowfield on a
Beautiful
You know later
Mets
Afternoon
Bright blue
Sky
It's not
Scary at all but it's
Very dangerous
Because
The snow is melting
Eventually it's going to find a layer of ice
The water will lubricate that and you have an avalanche
That is dangerous but not scary
In my situation
Staying at BCG
Was dangerous but not scary in the
The danger there the risk
Was
Continuing to do something
It didn't make me happy
And getting
You know 65 and looking back and go oh my God I wait
Wasted my life that is risk that is danger
Citadel was that what you said your dad did you convince him that this was
Worth trying
He eventually
Did
Come around
You know I sat down with him
The thing that
Convinced him I think
All the American breweries
Basically making the same kind of beer yeah you know very light
Very easy to drink
And
I'm not going to compete
With bud
And Miller and Coors
Everybody in the US who wants
Good beer is drinking the import
So is that that time it was like
Heineken bags St Paulie girl
Those were considered
The great beers of the world
And what I did know from my Brewing background is
They are not the Great
Beers
The world
The Dare
Was
The possibility
Making
Beer with a lot of flavor
The balance
And there's a
Particular flavor structure of good beer
When you taste it
You will get that structure
And
I could give it to people
Fresh because beer is parachute
Beer has about a four to five months shelf life
Any imported beers
We're almost always stale
They were typically in green and
Beer bottles
And
Visible light
Isomerize is a compound in Hobbs
That's why you get skunky beer
What you come up with
With a recipe that
N0 you thought okay this is going to re-educate American Beer
Why drink this beer
Instead of what are you say
That was easy
After about an hour and a half when I dad was beginning to get it
Oh and you know you're right
Nobody's making great beer
Maybe somebody should do that then you took me up into the attic and there was a
Trunk and
There were family recipes
Any took out one of the recipes
And said this is the rest
It was from my great-great-grandfather's Brewery
My dad
Handmade
A version of this beer
At wooden shoe Brewery in Minster Ohio where he was brewmaster
Because the brewery was kind of going down the tubes
Any thought maybe we can turn the brewery around by making big
American
Lager
And the owner
Tasted it
Told my days at Charlie
Nobody is going to drink huh
People want
Water with
Beaumont
So make water with foam on
So you just took this recipe in and start to experiment with us
Yams at the recipe I started making it in my kitchen
Adam is
Extremely difficult beer to make
You can't really do this as a home
Yeah it requires
Much more precise
Control
A Brutus
And I could
Tell this is going to be a good beer if I can make this right
This would be a really good beer
Okay so you make a beer but how did you
Because you didn't know how to add a begin
Start a beer company
Well the first thing
I realized I had to find the best brewmaster
In America
To help me
I'm he was a man named dr. Joseph away.
And he was
The first
American Brewmaster
Combine
High level
Scientific understanding cuz he was a PhD
Microbiology
With
Decades of practice
Gold experience how did you even convince him to get involved in your life
Fly-by-night startup
He turned me down at first
Here. This is
Really crazy
And
You don't have enough money to pay me
Yeah which was true
And I took
Dr. Wade East
I'm not some
You know idiot kid
Just making beer in their kitchen
My dad
Was a brewmaster my grandfather and
He remembered my dad
A little bit
I said well
I'll tell you what
I'll give you 2% of the
And that
Piqued his interest
He signed on
And he helped me adapt a $0.19
Entry recipe
20th century
Brewery
So did you have to go out
Raise money to
Build a brewery
Well
I realized
There are breweries out there
And my dad was the one who gave me this insight
What we did
Is
We rented space
Dr. Wade Easton I showed up
Brewed beer
And
Then
They packaged it
And I
Didn't have to have my own Brewery for several years
When we started
We didn't have
Things that you think you need for business
We don't have an office
We didn't have a telephone
Yeah I just
Ask myself
Am I spending money
On things
That are going to make the beer batter
Or am I spending money on things just because that's what you're supposed to spend it on
Come up with a name
Santa Ana
Well
It came from my
History teacher when I was a junior in high school. The revolution
She highlighted the role
Of Samuel Adams
Depending on what books you read he was a brewer
You know
I wanted a name that was
Assertively American that reflected
America's
History and tradition etcetera etcetera
So on the label
There it is Brewer Patriots and
I wanted to do what Sam Adams it done
Only my little way I wanted to create
Beer Revolution
And declare their independence
For the United States
You just met will be back with him cook and he'll explain how he actually convinced people
To like his beard
Play with this guy Roz and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey one just quit thanks
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First to wix.com
They believe every great business needs a stunning website
Wix.com
Easier than ever to create yours
All the things you need to look amazing online images videos and professional text
And the best part is
You can do it all on your own
Go to wix.com and create your stunning website
Today
Exosuit to stamps
Starcom
With stamps.com you can buy and print official US postage for any letter or package
On demand 24/7
Right from your computer
No more trips to the post office and no need to lease an expensive postage meter
Sign up for stamps.com today to get this special offer
A 4 week trial plus Postage and a
A digital scale
Stamps.com click on the microphone and enter built
Just a quick reminder that
If you want to tell us about the company or the products that you are building
Go to build. Npr.org that's
Build with a
That NPR. Org we've already heard from hundreds
Listeners and incredible stories
Soap at the end of the show today when I share one of the stories in
Amazing one
Do they sell Instagram
Okay back to the show
It's how I built this from NPR
And I Rise
Experimenting for a few months with a family recipe
Jim Cook finally got it down to exactly the way he wanted
At this point
He had to figure out
Has salad
So
My dad told me you know you can start a business
It's lonely
It's going to have its ups and downs
See if you can find a partner
So I looked around
BCG was full of like the best and the brightest from
The top
Business Schools
Somehow
I couldn't see
Them be my partner cuz they are all the same skills I had
Yeah
Realize wait a minute there is a person who
Is
Energetic talented
Resourceful
Great people person
Has
All the skills that I don't really have
She was my secretary
So it was just me
And Rhonda
She was
23 years old
No College
Degree
Bartended at night
We were the perfect complement
That attitude
You guys convinced
Bars in
Chop stew
To take your beer
Well I was hoping
Did I would get a distributor well there were five beer distributors in Boston
I went to each one of them they all turned me down
Because because
To them it looks like a stupid idea this was a beer
That had a lot of color had a lot of flavor and had a lot of taste
This was in the Heyday of Light beer and you know they'd ask me okay so what's your marketing plan
Marketing plan what's your advertising budget
I don't have any money for advertising
Will tell me about the company
It's me
And my 23 year-old ex-secretary so wasn't very
Confidence as a business
And the only way that I could
Get my beer
Out there
Was
I would put
Cold beer in
My briefcase every morning I could fit seven beers
And I had these two blue cool pack
Sleeve of cups
And
I went
From bar to bar cold calling just going walking in the managers and yeah trying to do
Get to him
I never sold anything in my life
Was that hard for you
Yes
I was sure I remember to this day doing my first sales
And
Hit the streets in Boston I remember I was
Okay
I'm just going to call in the first bar
That I come to you
And I came to
A bar
I didn't know what I was doing and I have my
Consultant Sudan
So I started talking to the guy behind the bar and he was nodding and I thought that's a good sign
But he wasn't saying anything
Luckily
In the back was the manager
Cuz the guy I was talking
Into which What's called the Barbie
The barback is the guy who likes stocks the glasses and
That this guy didn't speak English
So he was just nodding away managing his back think
Oh my gosh there's a guy in a suit here he's talking to my barback
He's either IRS or he's Immigration and Naturalization Services
It neither one of those
Seattle we rushed up
And yeah I kind of had my 32nd drill
Hi I'm Jim Cook
I'm starting a small Brewery
Here in Boston
To make
A new beer
I'm going to call it it's called Sam Adams
And
My real
Point was
To get them to try the
So
You know I build up to this in
Sitting would you like to
Try it out he said sure leave me a bottle I said oh it's cold
I have some cups here
Let me pour you
Before he could say no and of course
In the bar business
If you pour beer
You can't just throw it out
Yeah
So
We tried it together
He said kid
You know I didn't think the beer was going to be this good
I'll take
And I was so excited
And of course I went back and
Actually Rhonda was
Taking some time off before we start I called I was so excited
Rhonda you know
We got our first customer
Industry practice
How many cases did he order
I forgot
So I had to go back the next day and apologized and I was scared again that he would have liked changes my
Reminder anyting but he gave me a 10 case order
Services like 1985
And you launch and
You got to get some attention and your 6 weeks after Sam Adams came out yeah
It got picked as the best beer in America how did that happen
It happened out in Denver Colorado
It was at the
Great American Beer Fest
Pretty much beers from every Brewer
And
Babe
Went around over tonight
Taste of the beers everybody got to vote for the best beer
And they did this countdown
You have 10 9 a.m. I thought we'd finish in the top 10
But they
You know they kept getting lower and lower
Announce
You know
Anna's
Number to the second best beer in America is this and
Psyquel
Yeah maybe next year and then
And the best beer in America is Samuel Adams Boston Lager
And the whole company was to
Pikachu and Rhonda
Yeah
Do that mean you were profitable from
From the start
Yes we were profitable from the first
Full month
Because
Convectors talking about earlier
You know
It was the ultimate
Lean
Start up
Like I said we had
No office
We didn't even have
A telephone we did all our business from
Payphones I knew where all the good payphones with embossed
We're the ones that were warm in the winter
The ones where you actually had a little
Shelf or you could put stuff on
So
That was very
Clear when I started
It's just very clear to me that way
Only two things that we needed
To do
Really well
We needed
To make
Great beer
Consist
And we needed to work our butts off to
To sell it at the beginning this was like a a regional thing like Justin
In Boston in
Yeah
So how did you get it to
Spread across the country
It happened very slowly
You know it
Basically
Started in Boston
I sort of
Grew a little bit out of Boston and
Went to Worcester I was doing a lot of the selling myself
So
One bar
At a time
And a lot of work a lot of shoe leather
A lot of Motel sixes
So I think
The first city out of
Add a New England was Washington so I would go down to Washington
Down here I'm going to
I still know
A lot of the bar owners here I sit at bar
Before I came over here the Irish Times yeah famous Barnard one of my first
Account
And
Was talking to Brandon the current owner
But his dad
Put Sam Adams
In there
Almost 30 years ago
So
You know was very hard in the beginning getting places
Just to carry it and probably got
You're 95%
Rejection so I make 20 calls to get
One account
And
Then we got picked as the best beer in the mirror
Yeah we got a bunch of publicity around
That people
People magazine to the story
Which was good and bad
Cuz
All that publicity boost
Did the salesman we ran out of beer you could not make it fast will it take 6 weeks
To make Sam Adams and we weren't expecting it
So we're out of beer for 3 weeks
We lost a bunch of
Piss people off
But it was clear there was
This idea was a bigger idea than I had
Did this wasn't going to
Go Take 5 years to get to $1000000
That way
A million bucks it'll be great
I'll be happy life
Yes exactly
And by the way
5 months
I remember
Sitting at a bar with Rhonda
And running we had business plan
But
Something's telling me this is bigger than we thought
Going to be
That
We are climbing a mountain
Here
And
Nobody climbs a mountain to get to the middle
We're going to climb this mountain to get to the top
And
It may take 30 years may take 50 years and
Our mountain is
I want
Sam Adams to be
The largest and most respected of the high-end beers
In the United States
That's our Mountain
Remember
Part of your strategy at scenes
Was like attacking it
Those imported beers that are member
Hearing a radio ads
Can you do
In the 90s were you taking
Declare your independence from foreign beer
The radio spot came about because there was radio station in Boston
Then they want a beer for a party
And so we traded him beer
Prayer time
Now they gave us air time at 2 in the morning
Thinking
Who would want that to me
I thought that was great because
That's when
The servers
In the bartenders
Get off the shed that's when they're so they gave me all this airtime
And
At first was going to like get radio tallinn
Tell record it and then I found out well
You can hire that but
Yeah there's all these Union rules and you have to pay residuals you got to track it
I can't do that
I'll do the spots
Myself
So my spot was
When America asked
For your abs
Tired in pool
We didn't mean there beer
But the beer they send us
This is hardly their best
They send us Heineken outlawed in Germany
Because of Germany strict
Beer Purity law
Edit
The backstage send us isn't the same backs they have in Germany
They had forbidden adjuncts
To it
That
Was Beth
The company threatened with the litigation oh yes
But I knew I was right
They're having a brewing background they knew it and
You could also tell it on analysis
My feelings always been
If you're right about something important
Push it
Tok so after I guess
Like about a decade
After you launch you decide to go public
What happened watch it YG
You decide to do that
Welp
I thought it was time
To do something to
Reward my investors because at that time I think
A dollar
Invested
Was probably worth $400
So I went to a couple investment Banks they described the IPO process
But when they describe it to you
You realize
That there's nothing public
At all about it's all for their buddy it is all for their buddies at
The big institutions
To buy the shares
And make a bunch of money in
That bothered me and I thought
I got to find a way around that
So I started thinking about it
And I came up with
Idea
So we put coupons on the six pack
That allowed you
To buy 33 shares
Boston Beer Company
At $15 a share so was born at $95
What you said to send in a check
And
The investment Banks freaked out about it
They told me you can't do it it'll never work they give me all these reasons not to but
I stood my ground
I was insistent and I knew
The investment Banks
Make money on this
So they will let me do it
If I refused
Compromise
So I refuse to compromise
Eventually they all came around
And
We got a hundred and thirty some thousand people
Offset
NHL
We got
65 million dollars
That was the first time
Something like that
Had been done and other people
Have
Continue to do it followed up on it
So earlier you said that you want
Salmon recipes
Largest and most respected
Of the cortical high-end beers in the US
Do you think you would
This may sound
Surprising but
I still don't feel like we're there and
Yeah but I got to give you some perspective of what do you think our Market
Sharon United
Pain 13%
Yeah that's what everybody thinks
A little over 1%
So the big Brewers
Fillmore beer
Then I make all year long
Yeah 90% of the US Beer Market is in the hands of
Big
Global
Brewing conglomerate
You're not like a small company
How many points do you guys have now
I'm weak. A little over 1400
People that's
To me also
Really
Gratifying because
The average
W2 compensation
$70,000
So there
You know they are good jobs
Atterbury those are Manufacturing
Good-paying manufacturing jobs
In communities
All across the United
States
When you think about
How you built the company and and
And Sam Adams and
And how much of it do you think was
You're skilled in your intelligence
And talent and how much of it was
Guy
I'll take the lock
So
It all humility a lot of it was like I look back and things could have gone wrong you know that
Brew Kettle code of ethics
Exploded
Or
Yeah that first guy could have told me
Is a really stupid idea go back to your
Job
You know a lot of things
Didn't go wrong that they could have
Did you
Could you have ever imagined that
Craft beer in America
Would become what it
What if
I never
Imagine
The
Success
Step weave
Unable to have
And I never
Imagine that there would be
Other
Craft Brewers
You know many of them enjoying
Their own
Success
Today
American Beer
Has gone from the laughing stock that it was
When I started
The best place
In the world to be a Beer Drinker
And when the rest of the world
They're looking at the US
I wish we could do in our country
What Americans have done with beer I wish we had the beer culture
That America has
You know
Which makes me feel good
Every time I have a beer
That's Jim Cook he has a new Memoir out called quench your own thirst
Business Lessons Learned over a beer or two
Cheers by the way it says he personally taste every batch of Sam Adams that they brew es mates
What's 24000 beers of the past 30 years that he was required to drink
It's part of the job which sounds like that's bad job
Listen to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episode you could how I built this NPR.
Or you can also subscribe to our show on iTunes and please do us a favor and write a review let us know what you think
Casa right to us at HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this car show is produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by Rammstein
Thanks also to leave a grandson has Mexican food and Jeff Rogers and Gyros and you're listening to how I feel
Built this NPR
Hey thanks for staying with us because
This is the part of the show where
You could tell us about the stuff your building I'm the CEO and founder of fiendish
British is an app that charger designed for people who want to make new friends but don't necessarily want to hook up
Tinder
I want to you know hang out you know sometimes you meet somebody and it's a little bit awkward because you're kind of like
So do you like steak know you're asking is kind of weird questions so I just thought there had to be a
A better way to really connect with people in find friends based on shared interests so with this app you don't swipe
Left right on someone's picture you swipe on things that you're interested in everything from Sushi to
Donald Trump to tennis shoes you know whatever it is that the moment there are users that have things in common with you
You'll get a notification that you have friends waiting for their shoes already up on the App Store
Still in beta mode so it's got a few bucks they're working on them
Chandra and her partner are trying to get funding for the app by the way they're doing all of this
In Orlando Florida
So I know that's not a place most people think I would Tech hub
But on there is actually a texting here and it's growing, and it's really important for us to kind of put ourselves on the map in the south
Southeast that there is Tech interest and great ideas and Innovation if you want to tell us what you're building
Go to build. Npr.org that's build with a D
Got npr.org
And thanks
Before we go just a quick
Tip to let you know about another NPR Podcast
You should check out is called Bullseye with Jesse thorn
It's your guide to what's good in pop culture
Every week Jesse interviews people like hammerness
Zito Rashida Jones
C Hoffman and many others
At work in their lives
You can find your favorite new TV shows books
Movies and music
And a new insights
Love
5000 l
NPR one app
Npr.org
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week