Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
We spent the whole $14,000 we have zero in the back we create
It is beautiful email address send and we're praying please please and suddenly
450 instructors joint and so that's when we said this is this is
Is going to be our life and and let's make it work
From NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
Immigrants from Colombia turned a scrappy aerobics class into one of them
Biggest Fitness brands in the world
Okay so it's the new year and you know we're all thinking about
Getting back
Jim it's just for like a week or two
But during those glorious two weeks
You might stumble into a class in which everyone
Seems to be really really happy unless there is a good chance
The class you're taking
Is Zumba
Yes this is Simba it is a kind of mash-up of
Aerobics and Latin dance and Hip-Hop and
I'll begin with the guy named Alberto Perez he goes for the name
Metro is a Dancer by training
And back in the 90s
He was living in Cali Colombia
Aerobics during the day to make EX
The money and the
At night he would
Dancing
Company
He was heading to his Robux
That's when he realized
But he left his regular music
At home
And the only music that I have with me and this moment it was
Wait Latin
Music
Landmark Cumbia
Moringa
Salsa
Different kind of music
Start the class I didn't say to my students
I make a mistake
Hiatal and listen to class today
I want to do some
Differently say you okay
Home Depot lumber
And I start my class and everybody loved it and this moment I discovered
But I saved myself
I need to do this for my life I love it
It's so cool
Basically started this new kind of fusion aerobics class in Cali for a long time and it
Became really really popular
So he decided to try his luck in America
And he told all the stuff he bought a ticket to Miami
Annie
Started knock on doors
I went to the games I'm finally in the body
Bad things shipped to me I didn't speak English I can explain what I do
And I come back
Save money and I come back again
Miami
Went to the different games
4 *
Finally the third time
One America
Woman in the north Miami Williams Island
Gnocchi
I want to do a body shot with
How do you say perfect
I went with my friend chickens lay everyday
Did you say Beto
You okay do division
I like Tarzan what is the people
No
She want only you and her
My cat
Lucky
Party
Taiwan tea with one person your ass like a
Restrain
But okay I went to the gym a WhatsApp
Friday like at 3:30 in the afternoon this time all the genes in the
The planets empty
Allied
Let me see what
What's on ai weiwei
Can I play
Audio, watitoh point you know
IG wow it's my life I messed up to take my first steps by first aid
And In This Moment other people come to the gym
To go to the training maybe they lift weights or something and they come in
And they are always wrong because they think it's a class they don't know some people who are true
The gym working out saw you
Auditioning for the
A manager and they started to like come in and check it out
Exactly
Are they coming into people 4 5 6
And one morning I like it 20
85 people
I'm people
Clap every song
I know dictionary
15 minutes
I dance for 1 hour
And this moment a woman tell me okay you know
I want to do a chance for you
Come here in one month
Antechamber
Only for tomorrow
And this moment my my friend translate all his new as a Whopper for this is the only thing they need
And I come back to my city
A nice soul
My car is on
Get off
Sore everything
I paid my
My bills
And I come back
The first thing that you buy yourself a Pontiac
85 North condition
The car
Airport $400
I know you rent a little
Apartment
100 dollars to
Dalila Bela
I my first baby was Eric Smith
Waiting
2 blanket
I like teach my first class
And I came late because I lost in this moment that doesn't 6 the GPS
I like him lately
Jimenez Lai Tai Chi
Believe it
But anyway
I come to the room
There was room
People was quiet I didn't say sorry excuse me because I didn't speak English
I like play the music and I say please God help me
And I started partying
People smiling
The Red Sea story
Pause the story for Sight because I want to I want to bring in another guy who comes into the picture at this point
Hello
Your helps
Zumba become
Arepas
Avocado and that forever be listening
This is also
Alberto called me Alberto call him Beto
So Alberto's
Beto Perez Zumba
Columbia burns up
Domane
Alberto is a guy who was going to help him make it into this
Huge thing
But before that happen
Alberto Perlman was living in Miami
Surround 1999 with all the guys my age were starting internet companies and I said why not
So he launches in Latin America
Seem to be going fine for a short period of time until
The Dot com bubble burst
Alberto's company
Collapses
Yuck so I personally was
Out of a job and I had
No money in the bank
I didn't know what I was going to do and I was having dinner at my parents house
And
My mom
Kept talking about Beto's clocks in at that point fair to hear Miami he called his classroom besides
Because Rumba in Spanish means to party
And then she turned to me and said
What do you meet with bettas
Maybe
If you're looking for something right now maybe you and him can start a gym together or some
And I said I don't know if I'm going to start a gym
But I'll meet with him
Sketches that means your background was in
Technology in in like
Direct Market yourself
Seems so weird
Like I said I really my thing
What the thing that pops into my brain at that time was
Could this be an infomercial
Could this be
Something that we could
Basically sell some videotapes of this
Splicing
Do something with it but I wasn't sure
I wasn't sure
So the next day
I was meeting with Beto at a Starbucks
This isn't like what
2000-2001
And she told me his life story
Which is on believe
The Columbia also so I knew
What was happening in the country
But he was in Cali
And Kylie was
The epicenter of violence
And
Xerosis
15 year old kid
Dancing on the streets and that's in clubs and dancing in James and
And so it was like juxtaposition right with all the violence happening
This kid make
Everybody happy and
It's downright
That's what he told his life story
Class cuz a Zumba class into something what a Zumba class is that
Destructor
Is always telling
Story
The music selection
How they teach the class
So I went to see the class
And the one thing
That I noticed
Was that every single person
Class was smiling
And I had
Ben
A gym member
Before and I knew that normally a smile is not the
Typical face
People are doing
When they're exercising really heavily in the gym right is
People are suffering
Forcing themselves
It's it's kind of like
The drill sergeant mentality
But then there was this
Plus
Which is like an oasis inside the gym where every single person
Was smiling but they were drenched in sweat at the same time
And I'm like this
Sky
Doesn't know it but he has
Discovered
Like a magic pill he has discovered the exercise that people want to do in
Instead of the exercise that people have to do
So you said to him would you say to him do you say hey let's start a business
Yeah you told me about the what do you want to do
Nana said I Know a Man
Let's do it
Conquer the world
And the funny way you know
Did you take him seriously
And I know he say okay let's do it
You want to be my business partners yes
Perfect that was it
Create some videos of your class
And
Basically
Create a collection
DVD said it was VHS of it.
I'm actually a VHS set
And sell it
On TV
So we can explain where it comes from and why and what the results are in
And so that was the
Original idea
The idea was
Go to like
He was just a boy cat video like Jazzercise
Just going to sell
An infomercial on that was hopefully going to be your business
Yeah like are are the most fresh in our memories of that time was typo
Remember taobao martial arts
So we was like that was the theory cuz Beto told me
When people come to my class
They don't
Leave
And it's because
The class is fun we say fun equals lasting behavioral change
I get I get that but I'm trying to scare what was the thing that made Roomba size
Different from other Fitness class
More fun
I think we
We do the same thing that Jane Fonda do in the beginning
Everything
It's easy
Second the music music only I do weighted different kind of music
Indian Bhangra Panther
Anybody can do it always I will always thinking they my mom
Do my class and
It went to things that Beto did that was very smart of the beginning is he said I want a microphone
Because if I have a microphone
I will interrupt
The music and people need to be able to hear the music
And so he doesn't scream at people in the class or
If there's no
Talking it's only visual cueing soap
With hand signals would we tell people what to do
And
The magic is letting
The music
Lead the choreography lead the class
And there's a moment
In the class
That we call fetch
Ffej
Bring electrifying Joy
I said that moment
Is 20 minutes into the class
And a person suddenly feels completely liberated
They're having fun they're not thinking about what you need to cook that night or their job
Or their kids or
Everything that is in their life they're completely disappears and it's a stem and the music
Did you have to go out and raise money to
So we was July of 2001
And we went to some of our investors that had invested in spiderlabs
Which was that the incubator
And we told him about this and they said we loved it we're and we had raised about half-a-million dollars
But we haven't gotten the wire transfers yet
And then September 11th happen
And everybody backed out
Everyone
We don't know what we're
We're going to do when we didn't know when I mean
For the next two months were all come
Confused what's going to happen with
What's the world and you remember that
It was very tough
And
Then around November of that year
Beto told me
My boss at
Crunch
Let's introduce you to the CEO of crunch
Set time in crunches
Is a gym chain I don't know if you
Are you part of it yeah and so I
Met with her her name is Donna Cyrus and Donna told me
Hey go me with
Doug Levine the original founder of crunch
So
Lunar New York
Met with dog
And he told me listen I've seen better teach
And I love what you guys are doing
And I said would you like to invest
And he said I can't advise because
Right now I'm
I'm selling my company and
But I can introduce you to some interesting guys in Ohio
Cool
Do infomercials for a living
And they might be able to not only invest but also help you
So the next day I'm on a plane to Ohio
It to meet with a company called fit
Quest
And I'm in a room full of total Gypsy remember a total gym
Chuck Norris machine
I'm in a warehouse for a total gyms
And this lady
It is looking at a tape that we created of his Cloud we just filled this class with a Handycam
I showed it to her
She said this is what I want to call my boss
And
Finally the CEO comes down
And says this is Banton I like it
But the special speak English
And Scotty need to film an infomercial with him talking Hank
And I'm like well you know what I've never spoken to him in English let me call him
So I called him up
And I'm like paper they're asking
If you
Hey speak English
And he said
Tell them yes
Go in Spanish
So they loved it and they said okay we will test the same commercial license to Brand what's this class called
Who had just
That was last week discuss changing the name
What was wrong with Roomba size
The word Roomba
In Spanish
Means to party
But it's also means
The type of dance there's a ballroom dance called Rumba
So it was a very difficult word to
Trademark
So we sat
In a restaurant
And we basically went through the alphabet
Anything that rhymes with Roomba so boom boom boom
Goomba sounded like
Pregnancy workout dinga Congo bunga
Sangha
Mango
Manga
Zumba hey
Zumba
Yeah with z and bettas like I love the letter c and we said yeah this is called Zumba
And that was it when we come back in
Moment how Beto and Alberto hustle their way to a contract and eventually set their sights on something
Much much bigger guy riding you're listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First to freshbooks the cloud accounting software used by over 10 million entrepreneurs
Thunder Mike McDermott started the company in his basement and spent over a decade building freshbooks
Now with their all new version you say even more time processing paperwork and get paid faster
Send invoices in under 30 seconds accept online payments in two clicks
And see what a client is looked at your invoice
Are your free 30-day trial quora freshbooks.com built
Adventure how I built this
In the how did You Hear About Us section
Thanks also to Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms fisheries and ranchers to bring you all the ingredients you need
Create incredible home cook meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered right to your door weekly in a refrigerated box
ReDiscover how fun cooking can be
While enjoying specialty ingredients and exploring new flavors and cuisine
Get your first three Blue Apron meals for free
Plus free shipping by visiting blueapron.com built
Just one more thing before we get back to the show
If you like this program you will love another show I host it's called the TED Radio Hour as in TED Talks
Any sweet potato
5 amazing talks and we interview the people who've given those talk
The show is
Based around 1
Big idea that's designed to inspire and move you and give you a sense of the possibilities at
The world to take a listen
You can find it at npr.org
Podcast
Or iTunes or on the NPR one app
It's how I built this from NPR
Garage so it's early two thousands Alberto and Beto have a business model for Zumba which is basic
Mickey's Dance videos for people to play at home
First they need an infomercial in before they can make that they have to make sure that Beto who is the dance
Teacher can speak English which he can't and also at this point a new business partner
Enters the picture whose name and I'm not making this up
He's also helped her to Alberto Aggie on and in case you lost count Zumba is having run by
3 Alberto's and so
My flight back to Miami and Alberto
Artyon and I are teaching better English for the next two months because the people who were going to be in summer
Commercial
They won't make it unless better speaks English coming down to Miami to meet
In 2 months
When they coming to Miami before I say to a better better don't worry because my daughter was worried
Because he say he say yeah he's speaking
Aladdin
And I say do you know any how you say
Which it was stupid automating okay
And I do say nice to meet you sorry I need to go
But that was on Bae like
50 because we were 60 days trying
It is like this is not going to work now
When there's people coming
Coming in the end of the class I wanted to lose you on
When I say. Hi how are you nice to meet you so ready to go
Nice to meet you strain to go and Escape
How do I escape ladder to say sorry he need to go back
Sobc sofa
You know
You know we need to put in a show
And I went to my car waiting in the parking garage with my Pontiac 85 North Edition
The conversation continued order to come in again
Hey where are you I'm here in the parking lot
What happened
Yes they do it they want to do it they wanted to do it so I'd better talk to you in and I had to write
The whole infomercial
A script
In Spanish phonetics
Welcome to Advanced Zumba
Launch that and we talked well
This is it
It's like having a party who are you working out
Wheely Zumba now we're going to get a royalty ass and maybe we should find some other products
Salvia television we don't know we don't know what we're going to do until the deal was that you would get a royalty
But they owned the
Rights to a weed license
Will I see like that
Because we don't have money to do it ourselves right and we don't know how to do it frankly Maddie know how to do it yeah
When you guys want you to commercial were you making money
A little bit
It was good it was good at me they sold
I remember what the number was
It was enough to
Keep the lights on in
And keep going but it wasn't enough to till like
Ghetto fund your life and light pay your rent and everything or to just another job really not really been through
Stoat still taught his classes
Do you have other jobs I had a morning job
What was it
I was selling food to Latin America
I was hoping
American brands sell food
Latin
Wow so you guys are all basically
This is you your this is really what you want to do but this
This is kind of like your side project
Cuz you really had other real job to pay the bills
Yes that was tough it was tough times it was very long hours
We I mean I worked in the mornings and then
And the afternoon I went over to
Alberto Young's house and
Stay there till midnight
Packing DVDs or whatever we were doing like we're doing every single thing
We're doing all the jobs which is great because
When you do every single job
Then
As a company grows you know
What to hire
Was the business healthy and they were you guys
Did it seem like you were going to
Drive or did you ever get to a point where you almost no
We're almost collapse
I remember
Alberto xi'an walking over to me saying
Listen this is
This is not going to work you know it's great while working hard but
We can sustain that we can't pay the bills
And we we have one employee
And we're all doing everything else and
And it's hard it was just hard to
Keep lights on
How much money did you have in the bay
We had about
Maybe that was it
LG
Yes we were close to Broken we have a conversation
With the okay guys
I think this is it
One day Kellogg's
Call Oz
The cereal company or the food
They want to send something
DVD Insider day
Cereal box cereal box Zumba for
For the Latin Market
And we say okay good do it
When we went to the set to film the video
They
They have 120 a tiger remember Tony a tiger tattoo for one guy
Put the costume on
Yo movie needed movements like nothing special I say Alberto. You know what
Let me know what up with the cost of a tummy attire
Because I'm here to say it
Elektra superhero dynamic
Stupid
You know Tony do step by step side to side
They hired somebody else to like Tony the Tiger but you were not happy with how he was dancing so you put on the costume
Did it instead yes
Barracuda Tony Tiger Rising I was
We were so lucky because In This Moment
The CEO of Kellogg's
Come to the set
We didn't know
And I was inside the custom dancing like
Crazy
Sweating inside
It's like
You don't think who is this oxygen in between songs
It was
Crazy and this moment like a couple years
I got 50
$1000 for
Guy that helped
That help but it was not enough
What would it what did you guys do that
So
Then people started calling
Their call center
Because I'm a Kellogg
Saying
Hey we want to take
Zumba classes
Is in our area or some people started calling saying we want to become Zumba instructors how can we become Zumba instructor
And they were like well will give you the corporate number
The corporate number
Was a MetroPCS cell phone
Next to Alberto Jones bed
And
At 2 a.m. it would ring when The infomercials were airing
And people would say I want to become an instructor the first three times he hung up
Unsync the fourth time he's like
Something Happening Here
And he called me Anna and Beto and told us
You know we been getting all these calls from a struct
That they want music
They want
A choreography
A newsletters they want
Community that they want event they want all these things
Maybe we can
We can put it all together and
Create
Something service for them
To give them everything that they need
Like a subscription service
Yes
And so
Wait we caught up in Deland
We started brainstorm
And we said well what do we need to do
Said the first thing is we have to make sure that we deliver
10 *
More value then what
It costs
Suicide what do they need
Madewell Laney Korea
They need music many students how do we get them students are we get the more participants in their class
Show marketing support let's create their career in a box basic
So we came up with a name
We called it the Zumba instructor Network
And we launched it in 2006 in January of 2006 and we spent the whole 14
0 in the bank
We created is beautiful email
It went out
And Alberto xi'an told me okay if 200 of them join
We will continue with this business
Press send and we're praying please please
And suddenly
Instead of getting
Email responses we got phone call
And these structures were saying
Were you loving that your launch this and we know you guys are trying to make this work
Can we pay the year in advance
Everybody says how much and wish I was $35 a month at that point was 30
And they said that's it
That's it for my entire career that's all I have to pay and we said yes we have to pay in date
They said we love it
And 450
Instructors joint
And so that's when we said this is this is going to be our life
And let's make it work
At this point you guys are still entirely self-funded
Yeah
It was just from
That that royalties we got and then
Kellogg's and then.
The fees from
The trainings and that it was all like
Inch by inch very slow growth
And
Thank God we were always able to meet payroll of art to employees
Sometimes we do things to like pay the bills so
What's a beta why don't we do a special Master Class
A because we were running
$1,000 shorts
And so we would
Email everybody we knew is a special master
Classen
So we would all chip in and all help each other and
And find ways to do it
Since you guys are training all these instructors teach
I need a place to teach the classes so
So where the gym is interested in this
No they would laugh at us
So I remember that 24 Hour Fitness had a class called Salsa moves at that time
And
LA Fitness add a class called
Latin impact
And they will tell us like why we have our own brand why do we need your breath
But then you when you went to one of those classes they had
Five people four people three people those glasses were empty
And we said no we have a formula
We have a formula that works our class
Attracts
People and people love it
Different
And they would understand of the beginning
And finally
Hey there first
Really big chain to bring it in was
24-Hour Fitness
And it exploded
And they had to hire multiple instructors
Per location
Then all the big
Gym chains followed Equinox and crunch
A crush always had it because of our initial relationship with them so they were really the first one
You guys were doing all this
How are you getting the word out about Zumba music
Word of mouth or where you advertise
So one of things we were able to do in 2007/2008
We had bought the rights back to
Do the infomercial
Fitness questions
Ford 2500 stop airing
As we did our own
Infomercial
And we started airing.
And that was helping at the word out and there was word-of-mouth and there were more people coming to class
And
When something is good
People Finder
And two other people were saying well
This
Structure must be doing pretty well maybe I should become an instructor to
So what was like the Tipping Point when did this model really start
So in 2008
The network was growing
But
We started seeing what was happening in the economy
And we got very nervous
And I remember that we sat
In our conference room and we said
This is going to be a very tough year
And look at everybody's
Losing their jobs
People cannot pay their mortgage
But for the next few months
We started seeing
That are
Instructor trainings
We're getting
Pact
And that there were more and more people who wanted to become instructor
And we also saw that the instructors were reporting to us
That's our classes were packed
Calling us telling us
We don't know what's happening but we've doubled from
25 people now that I have 50 people in my class what's happening
So we started asking people
And there were two things that were driving it one
Was
Some people were out of a job people were sad
They turn to Zumba
And they said
For 1 hour and when I forget everything that is happening
And I'm just going to be happy
And
A people who need an extra income
Said well now I'm going to get paid to workout
And someone to become an instructor
And I'm going to make this part of my
Income
What does the financial crisis actually help your business
We weren't we were a solution that people turn to
Hey during those hard times
What happened around
Around this time which
I was reading that
Approached by
By Pitbull like by the the artist pitbull who was like new
Founder of Zumba
Can we work together with
What's the story there
How so you know what happened
In 2009
In 2010 in NBA 2K
Telling me
When they trust me the artist Will Come Just As We it was a tough thing to
Able to license the music and it was always hard and he said trust me one day they're going to come
And in 2010
Hey
Pitbull came to us
And sad
What are you guys doing
And we're like
What do you mean
And he said
This song Calle Ocho you remember that song I Know You Want Me
She said
People are stopping me in airports
Wearing shirts that say Zumba
Saying that is stirred your favorite song
What are you guys doing for Lakewood
Instructors are just playing it in their class
And he said well you guys are like a radio station
You guys
Have all these DJs
Playing in gyms around the world
And you guys I think you guys can break records
And we still
Are you serious
And he said yeah
And I'm going to give you my songs as soon as they launch
Put him in the Zumba classes
And you guys are breaking wreck
So people was the first guy to discover
That zumba was a way of promoting music
And then we work with
With Wyclef we work with Daddy Yankee
Rustlers with Shaggy most recently moved
Wood Timberland soap
Both the hottest Latin artists in some of the top
At us artists
Have all been noticing
That zumba is
A great way to reach 15
Million people we reach 15
Million people taking Zumba classes every single week
And I think that Lori artist and Eric
Music
Companies
I know
Did somebody say perfect way to
Promote your music
Because when we send
Every month
The music
We select 13
Songs
And we send every month to the instructors
That's mean pissed 13 songs going through
Arundel Wharf
Arundel water and in one month we have people
Dancing to Daddy Yankee's music
In China
I'd we have people dancing pitbulls
Music in Japan we lunch the choreography for Shakira
And Carlos Vives they have a new song called la bicicleta
And in aggregate the choreographies were shared 50 million times
On Facebook
You guys know how many
Instructors you have now
We don't disclose that but we basically
A focus more on the number of people that are taking classes
We have 15 million people taking classes
And where in 200000 gems
We have more locations teaching Zumba
Then there are McDonald's in the world
So what like what do you think explains that
At Music and Dance
Are a universal language
We have classes in
In
Luxury neighborhoods we have classes in
The in the inner cities
What are the classes free
And we have classes in schools we have classes
Churches with
Classism
Basements we have glasses on.
Dance studios
Yeah we have classes in
In Russia with ukrainians and Russians
I mean the governments are fighting each other in their
Together we have classes in Israel
I wish I ribs and Jews taking classes
This Together dance brings people together
Like when you think about
How you were teaching this class
Cycle room Versailles in
Cali Colombia like 25 years ago
That that are 25 years later we would be talking about something that
Has really become one of the biggest
Fitness stories
In the last decade
Imagine that
Yeah it's it's
Somebody tell me when they do know
And United States
Eschar
Make money
But super hard
To be somebody
But you are somebody in this country Judy.
I did not understand
Now I understand
Zumba
And me and my business partner we are somebody
Because I know that people have
Morning you know it's one more for the medium
Is here
When people recognize you for your labor for you
Work on that
When they open the Hartford
Something you do it
It's amazing
Best Beto Perez co-founder
Alberto Perlman
Zumba
And by the way
Lots of Zumba instructors teach full-time in Santa Barbara who pulls in
Six figures
Just teaching Zumba classes
And her monthly subscription fee to zumba just 35 bucks
Heading to listen to show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes
He good how I built this NPR. Org
You can also subscribe to our show on iTunes and please do us a favor and write a review let us know what you think
Casa write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet it's at
How I built this
Shows produced this week by run abdel-fattah with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to leave a grandson
Anna's Mexican food and Jeff Rogers
Gyros and you listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks for sticking around we're now at the
The end of the show
And it's time to hear how you built that
My name is Nicholas Gilson and I am one of the original founders of Gilson snowboards
Nick and his business partners fell into the snowboard business they were Middle School teachers in Nashville in
Project with a challenge their students to build a better snowboard I brought in the original prototype
For an idea I had when I was my students age when I was in Middle School
Was basically to design a board which instead of being flat at the bottom
Was curved and they hope that it would make for a faster ride and even though their first design total
Early failed
Betadine chili came up with one they love
With this board you can actually ride close to flat
And engages really surfy drifty Maneuvers that allow you to get through the trees way easier with way more
Morcerf emotion until with barely any money
Nick and his partner quit their teaching jobs and set up a snowboard shop inside a stable in Pennsylvania
Who's inactive stable it was an active do they were donkeys and horses next time machine
Mike says they were able to make their boards even better then started to travel the country starting to come
I'm pretty much the way our grandparents would have we need to tangibly and physically share something with people and so we were
When on The Marcels in the community travel 17000 miles from coast to coast
And I started getting these people on the boards since they started the company three years ago it's been growing
Pretty fast they've sold thousands of board they don't have 16 employees and they have a small Factory
In Pennsylvania
Just down the road from the donkey stable
There is a week-long. And November where we put in more orders than we did in our first several years,
Combined and we were looking at each other like alright I guess we'll take a nap next week you know this is not
10 of Gilson snowboards
If you want to tell us about the company or idea your building go to build. Npr.org
Build with a d that NPR
. org
And thanks
And just one last thing one day is NPR's new Daily Show inspired by the First Amendment
What day is the new show with those who makes the news
Greg s
Can topical debates all friend and ways to make you think
An Engaged
Each day one day Will Champion your right to speak freely
Checkout 1A with Joshua Johnson
WAMU NPR
You can find it on the NPR one app or visit npr.org podcast
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week