Support for how I built
Best and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation
Seewhy michigan
Is attracting top talent and top businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
I remember walking down the street completely freaked out
With a friend of mine who also went to meetings and I was scared
And because I didn't know what I was doing and he said
What have you got to lose
He said maybe it'll be like one magazine that you make and you can go around and say hey I made this mag
Magazine and then you can apply for a job and get a job somewhere or maybe it'll be huge
From NPR is how I built this
Shobha innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movement built
Salvia take a small alternative magazine in Montreal and built it into Vice media
Witches
Totally mind-blowing
Now valued at over 4
Billion dollars
I'm sitting here in the studio
And I'm looking at the website
For Vice
And I'm clicking through you know it's
Typical mashup
Hard-hitting news and then
Oddball
Feature
I like this one that says that the story is a psychologist analyzes the fights couples have
And Ikea
Identify with
And then you just
Scroll down a little bit
There's just one
How majority-muslim countries are handling
HIV infections
And of course you can you know you can click on Plenty of
Slick videos that take you all over the world like
This one
Cockfighting in the
Canary Islands
Ana Belen Dominguez acerra activist
An organization who fights for animal rights in the Canary Islands
I'm meeting her because she has arranged to meet Jose Luis Martinez president of the Canary Islands cock fighting Federation
Play we know that flashing news websites
And I almost as fast as they launched but for some reason
Vice
I stuck around
Its YouTube channel has over a
Billion views and
A couple of Peabody
Prestigious
But the thing is
Vice co-founder suroosh Alvi
Keep didn't set out to create any of this in fact
He barely made it out of this
Money is alive
I was born in Toronto and my parents emigrated
From Pakistan
A couple years
They are retired academics
My mom taught at
Miguel
And my father at University of Toronto although my mom also. Athena
University of Minnesota
For a while
And so I ended up going to high school in the states
So I heard a lot of you have to work
Twice as hard as white people to get anywhere in this world grown up
Is it that turned out to be true
Yeah
What what did they want you to be
Well
Feels that are most respected
And in Pakistan at least
When I was growing up with medicine or engineering
So I think that
You know in an Ideal World
I would have been a doctor
With that with a ba I'm
The black sheep
Of the family everyone has multiple degrees to seem intelligent in Montreal right
Yes or you could send
I was not a good student I originally went into psychology I got kicked out of that program ended
Getting a degree in philosophy
It was a
Tough
Slot guide
Come from you know small
Private school in
Minneapolis Road high school and
Going to go was just a different badges lot of distractions in Montreal and that's a
Place where you can buy
You can hit a low point right
Yeah
That's where I
Bottomed out
When I
You know finished Miguel it was
Also with a
Full-blown heroin habit
And so
I spent a couple years afterwards kind of looking for a geographic
Bouncing around jumping
From City to City
Bumps that with me it's here in the city this environment it's
Just to decadence
Blah blah blah
So I ran around
And
No matter where I went
I kind of took it with me
End up in Eastern Europe and even there in a remote part of Slovakia
Was able to
Stay strong out for upwards of five years and
Ended up back in grad school Toronto
Studying psychology
And I dropped out
And that's when I really was like
You know descending in the talespin
Heading bottom and when I end up back in Montreal it was
To go to rehab
How do you know it's time to go read
I couldn't
I couldn't sustain it anymore
Keep the
The Web of Lies
Going
Yeah there was this got a double life
I've been waiting
No no one really knew
That I was
Heroin addict
Your friends and family
I got my parents are
Conservative Muslim
Immigrants
But Progressive
As well as far as Pakistani immigrants go
But they thought I had the occasional
They didn't know the
Send a ball
What's going on with me and when they found out
My mom went to bed
Russian my brother wanted to kill me my dad
Had a heart attack
I don't know if that the heart attack was directly related but I don't think it helped
It was bad it was a really bad time and so my mental state at
At the time was
Was not good
I did go into a bit of a
Depression at that point I went I had to go to rehab twice
The first time it didn't stick and
Yeah like they found out that I was using again
And
It's the only time in my life that my mom's ever hit me
And at that point I remember that
Was my bottom
So it's like early 94
On the waiting list to get into a treatment center
No friends no
I wasn't speaking much I was kind of you know kicking dope in my parents house on a waiting list to get a new treatment center like
Life is not great at that point
How long does it take you before you
You started to assertive
Feel like you
Or regaining control over your life
Black I came out of the treatment center and I was so scared that I was
The relapse and it was just like I was going to meetings this going to
NA meetings at the time
Yeah they say you should go to 90 meetings in 90 days when
Stop drinking or doing drugs and and I was going like two meetings a day
I got my own little apartment in Montreal and was on welfare and I just
What are my bike from meeting to meeting all day everyday and it was during
That time that I actually started thinking
About
What I wanted to do with the rest of my life and
I had this idea that I wanted to work for a magazine
And you wanted to write about like what I like
Like music
Pop culture are like
Like what will
I didn't get that far
Something I felt like
Talk about those things yes music culture
I felt like there was just
A lot happening that wasn't being talked about when I picked up magazine
Depraved underground culture that that I was obsessed with was not being covered properly in the alt-weekly
What's it like a realistic possibility could you just go in and work for a magazine or or news
No I don't think so I had no experience doing with my only
Writing that I've ever done was
Academic
You're writing in University and when I was going to these meetings in Montreal
Someone came up to me
An out-of-the-blue they started a conversation with me
And they said you have a sponsor I said no
And they said well I'll be your sponsor and I met some random dude who is a random dude
Walked up to me yesterday Narcotics Anonymous
He was in the meeting with me the meeting ended and he came up to me
He said what are you what are you doing like are you working I said no I'm not working I can't even get a job volunteering anywhere ID
Tried to volunteer at this place and they
She wouldn't let me
Tend
Out of the blue he said have you ever thought about writing he didn't know me
I was like actually yeah and he's like well I know a place I'll take you there tomorrow
So he took me to this place these Haitians in Montreal who
Had a a bilingual magazine going
Call damaj Intercultural that it was becoming French only and they want to start an English magazine
And he vouched on my behalf
This is the guy you want he's really good
He worked there before but he was like this
This is heaven-sent Angel who just was like
Put in my path and it opens up a whole conversation of
Do I believe in God do I believe in a higher power. I believe in Allah all this kind of stuff and
For me that whole story is like the proof of existence moment for me in my life
Something greater than me put me
There in this place where this guy just
Walked up to me and shows me to talk to me
And happened to know a place that was looking for a guy to start an english-language magazine in Montreal
Exactly
So what was the magazine called
So I went in for this meeting and he vouched for me and said that he don't be long time that I was going to work really hard I did
Didn't have a lot of experience but that
He thought I could do this thing and day
They said okay and they gave me a desk a fax machine a phone and a computer
I started this process of
You know making a magazine
Diamond
Alright voice of Montreal
Is the name that I came up with at the time
And I had no idea what I was doing I just
But I knew it's a few people around town and
Started this kind of recruitment process of finding writers to write in the magazine and
And I remember walking down the street
Completely freaked out with a friend of mine and I was scared and because I didn't know what I was doing and he said
What have you got to lose
He said maybe it'll be
You know like one magazine that you make
Can you can go around and say hey I made this magazine and then you can apply for a job and get a job somewhere
Or maybe it'll be huge
And like that conversation
On the street
That was
A huge mode for me because that gave me the kind of strength
To continue on when I was
Like overwhelmed could barely tie my shoes straight coming out of a treatment center like
It was a mess
And I owe him a lot because he
Realize what he was doing at the time but he gave me this kind of
Strength to
Keep marching forward
So you get to the magazine what like what kind of
Publication was it
It was a 16-page newsprint magazine
But you were like that that kind of a really like the
Torpor stepchild
The two big all week
Like you guys were totally
A joke compared
We were the laughing stock
Because it was a shrinking English Market okay
So it's you
Mitchell bilingual City
So there were four
All weeklies already to French ones into English ones
And then we came on the scene in the English Market is actually shrinking
There wasn't enough
The advertising to sustain those to let alone the third one
It didn't make any
Economic sense
Yeah but I really believe that there was an audience there for what we were talking about
So you guys were recovering like what like
Episode of the alcoholic alternative scene in Montreal like skaters and
Punk shows in hip hop
Is music like Underground Music
And I wrote this
Terrible editorial about
The search for authenticity and then heat for like quitting real content but
I stand by that editorial like
I hope you got nobody ever finds out and publishes again because it
It was awful but it is the spirit
Of what we do today is
Was was there so you are like you are basically the editor-in-chief of this
Magazine in your early 20s voice Montreal
And like who did you hear some the people you brought in to help you start it and create it
You're one of my
Friends from college he connected me to a bunch of different artists and also two different writers in one of these writers
It was a guy named Gavin McInnes and he
It was funny and had a comic book called pervert
That's why I asked him to become my assistant editor
And I think is going to be my, excited or whatever that means
Micardis around town and put together a Comics page
Count the public face of
Advice I guess
How did he how did he get involved
So Shane and Gavin
Grew up together in Ottawa
And
The first night we met he was just like he said literally said you're my new best friend what happened
On acid as well I should know I should qualify this right
He was in a bar called a bifteck
Gavin I had been driving around the city all day Distributing the magazine it'll just come out
And we finished our rounds and went to the bar to meet Shane and he was in there he's been waiting for a couple hours for us and
By himself somehow managed
Epicurus psychedelics and was drunken
Novice
Of course you don't
Sober
Tired and I walk him this a drunk man on psychedelics
Who is I call you from Pakistan you must love cricket and then was like
Pretending to like bowl like balls at me
But he's worked for for Greenpeace before and he could actually sell
You know
With greenpeace usa
Erase a lot of money for them and
Eastern Europe he was involved with some activities
Where he was making lots of money so he knew how to make money activities
Basin activities I'm going to leave it up. He was good at making money and you could
Yo self
Rattlesnake boots to Rattlesnake
And so then it was me Gavin and Shane working
Amiss
Office with the Haitians
We were there for like 3-4 months and
But it wasn't working out
Because we weren't getting paid
Commissions on the ads that we were selling it at all
But we're on welfare
And so we talked about the vacations and said
You know it's it's time for us to delete even if we came up with this thing where
We said the Village Voice has a trademark on the word boys
And there are suing us and forcing us to change our name piss you guys were the voice of Montreal we told the world
That we were being sued by The Village Voice and that's why we had to change the name device
Basically made this thing up about the Village Voice to generate publicity
Yeah
And it was a complete lie
That's why we dropped the O and then how we started Vice City basic created a new mag
We we created a new man
To find a new office or did you start working at your apartment or that's a good question we we got a new Loft
And like not too far from the original office
I brought five grand for my parents Davenport five grand from his parents and Shane got $5,000 worth of computer
From his dad is that working
No idea or something and
So it was with that
Dollars
Canadian
That we started Vice
Okay so this is now like
Like I guess the mid-90s
And you guys
Become vise
What was the magazine like at that point like at what did you cover
We really wanted to
Again
Such an over
Use word guy but it's
It's a good one authenticity like how do you create
Real content
And we're going to journalism School
So the way to do that is to get as close to the source as possible
And if we were going to write an article about
The prostitution
Community in Montreal let's
Get the prostitutes to write that story
Then let's go out with pimps as they drive around and interview them and so we created this
Really raw
Magazine
There are a lot of typos but it was alive like I think the worst kind of jumped out
The pages and it was kind of shocking stuff and yeah
And we were so
Without freedom of
Depress
With such a big deal like we're so anti-censorship that even
If you
I'll be towards advertising if you buy that page of advertising you on that page you can do whatever you want with it
So we had these
Skateboard companies from Southern California that had like
Are pornstars in their ads
Nude pornstars in the ad so the magazine all the sudden has
He's crazy articles with
Lots of nudity advertising
Skateboard companies called serial killer skateboards or whatever it was
This whole weird little
Take on
American culture that was coming from Montreal so we were
Science magazine to San Francisco Chicago La New York and
Americans reading it up
So you guys making money you like
Pretty soon after
Not sure where you pistol
Bootstrapping it in
Barely
We were bootstrapping it because we couldn't
Afford to have that we didn't we couldn't get a loan
So we just printed copies based on how much we were
Selling and advertising and
It's what we call this kind of
Punk rock capitalism just be really aggressive you really ambitious and you can't have that
Those are the rules that we live by until we
Tok our investment for the first time and that was when
That was an
When we sell 25% of the company took onion Richard sowinski he was like
Some rich guy who
Just why to invest in magazine cuz it seems like kind of a crazy investor
So Shannon I'd realized at that point that we needed some help
If we want to grow the magazine
I'm like who Investments like maybe Larry Flynt wood and
There was a guy in Montreal named Richard sowinski who
Had a software company called discrete logic that he'd sold to Autodesk for several hundred billion dollars and
He was starting to buy a media properties
And we had been
Interviewed by
The French daily and Montreal called The Press
And so we said
In that interview in the press that he was interested in buying us
And he done Reddit
And then it had his office contact us a few days later and said
He wants to meet you guys who are you guys
He has no idea who you are but apparently he's interested in buying a so we met him
And individual very quickly to sell 25% of the company to him
Crazy amount of money for you guys at the time
Raise ya
This could have happened in Montreal there was no due diligence I took place it was literally one meeting with him
At a restaurant that he
He loved and so he bought it and moved it into the basement of his office
And he
Brought a bottle of Jack Daniels and kind of for Shane to drink a bunch of it
And that the end of the meeting said I want to
To buy piece of your magazine come back to me in a week and tell me how much
And and don't try and gouge me
And so we we left his office and spend a week going like how much
Do we value our company for like it
I was kind of arbitrary pulled it from the air
Yeah we pulled it from the air and came up with this number somehow justify that it was a million bucks
And he read it
What is all in one piece paper to
The price of ice
She right at me said
That's a lot of money and then he signed it
And a Whiskas upstairs and they wrote us checks
And I think his
Advisors like this is such a bad idea
This shouldn't be happening but again no due diligence no like accounting nothing
And his office was actually walking distance from our office and we went out it was
Springtime in Montreal we literally did somersaults in the grass when we left 50,000
So with that money we were able to
Scale magazine
We're able to move to New York
Play comeback the story of Isis move to New York and it's almost complete collapse
It's how I built this from NPR guy Raz stay with us
Hey Belinda thanks to two of our sponsors
Help keep this podcast going first to
Casper
Online mattress retailers
Casper mattress
Design
Developed in the USA
Engineer
They use to Technologies latex foam and memory foam
To give just the right amount of
Bounce
And if a risk-free trial try out your Casper mattress for 100 nights
With the free delivery and returns along with a special offer
Listeners to this show
Casper.com
Gilt
And use the promo code built
Iridium $50 tour dates
Air mattress
Terms and conditions apply
Exosuit the Hyatt
I believe the modern business traveler is
Changing the face of business
Please business Travelers don't settle
Refusing mediocrity there Reinventing their careers bending titles and breaking new ground
And because they chain
Business travel is
U2
And that's why there's a
Play sand
Play housework good enough
Isn't
Hyatt Place
Hyatt House hotels
You've come too far to settle now so book your stay today
Hyatt.com
Why settle
Really quickly before we get back to the show I want to invite you to come
See how
I built this live on stage
Now hear this
Parcast festive
On Friday
October 28th
And beautiful Anaheim
Time California
Now hear this is a 3-day Festival of your
Your favorite podcasts
October 28th
Through the 30th
What shows like NPR
Happy hour dinner
Party download and w
Utf8
Marc Maron
We will be doing a live episode of How I built this
Friday October
So if you can only make it for one day make
Sure it's Friday or you
Miss out our show
To get tickets
And information about
But the full lineup
Go to now hear this
Best
Hope to see you there
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's 1999
Gavin shane and suroosh chevy 250
$1,000 check
And a dream to become much
Speaker
We always had aspirations to
Talk about the world and other things
As well and we
It started building up a stable of writers that was International
But we had a ceiling
Becoming National in Canada
Wasn't good enough for us
We aspired for more
And we thought okay we have to go don't know if we want to become
Bigger
We need to go to
Either New York or London or LA
Want you to say
To do with the money
He had this vision
So we had
Vice and then he had a magazine called shift which was like a spin meets wired kind of
Magazine for slightly older crowd and then he had another company called Halo 46 which was
Travel luxury goods high-end brand
And he wanted all three of these brands
To diversify and become multichannel brands
That was going to be tied into a big e-commerce platform
And he's going to take it all public
And so that's what we did with the money we
We build a fashion division the film division the TV division of Music division
You should have a brick-and-mortar
Presents for your
Fashion Division and huge fish and that you guys weren't even
Thinking about like you were you were thinking we're just two
He's kind of ahead of the Curve
It's kind of like an Amazon kind of thing and like we came in and we actually
Executed his business plan and like you actually started a fashion label
Yeah and we
We had four four clothing store like you got designers to make like Vice
Fashion
Yeah but we also sold a lot of thought we were advertising the magazine we sold their clothes
That we we realized by doing it that we don't want to sell pants for a living that we're better at making content
That's really what we want to do but it's service
Its purpose at the time
Seems like really
Like trying to move no
Very quickly
So when's he kind of
Run out of money in
Retreated to Nantucket
And this is when the butler.com Bible verse
So what were they leave you guys
It left us
You know
Kind ride bike stores in New York
You in office space
In Manhattan
End
You had employees
And you
I'd no money
It was bad
Is it was bad time
So what happened to sew ins
We found out that Richard was in Nantucket at his house and so we rented a car and drove up there
We took the ferry over and
Calling from a payphone
Can you pick this up
And was very surprised that we were there we had met any contact with him for like a month or something like that was coming
Russia running out of money
Yeah
So we went to his house or like what's going on you said
It's over the money's gone
I'm done
I can't put any more money into this
So
What are we doing so
Then we came back and that's when we move to Brooklyn
He left his office I unscrewed the mirrors out of the bathroom and took
The plants in the desks and filing cabinets that we still have
I'm still using the same filing cabinet that I stole from that office on 27th Street
It all happened so quickly we
And we sold more equity
Saul Alinsky so you ended up taking over
Control of the whole company at that point before the company basically fell apart
He
He bought the entire company from you
Stock trading
Our shares for his company which was called normal net
And the like you're worth 44 million dollars now so we went from being on welfare to theoretically being
Worth 40 million bucks
In a very short amount of time
It just all collapsing and being broke again and all the sudden we have these doors and we have Dad
For the first time
Is olinsky still own completely owns the brand of that point
Yeah and then we bought it back from him
How did you do that
Verb
Pennies on the dollar exchange at a deal and
You know he
Was
Nice to us in a way like
Even though
He put us out of business but he was
He he agreed to sell
The company back to us we did a deal with him I can't remember exactly how much but for
4 and we got a deal to buy the
Pax weed
Dollar Equity Bank
How how are you able to raise the money to buy them out
I borrowed money from my brother
Well we'll have to borrow the money
So you guys buy the buy back to company
It's yours again
Essential you got to completely rebuild it
So what did you do did you like
You got these the shops you got
The film division in this division
E-commerce
What do you do
We went back to doing things how
We had originally done.
Which is weekend
And we owed all this money to these
Italian like fashion companies who are manufacturing our clothes and Shane went into
Took meetings with all of them
And figured out how to
Reduce the debt
So he's like what I know you want 200000
I've got 20
Take it or leave it sue me or take the 20 grand
And that's how we worked our way out of gas at that time and we just
Went back to eating beans and rebuilding
And doing things
How we'd always done them before we
Tok investment
And so that was
You know like
I really valuable lesson and
Being able to buy the company back
And
Have a second chance
Was
Was huge
Aren't you in the in the midst of all this year you were still putting out
The magazine
Yeah the magazine was hot
They were still doing well like from a
Cultural level
Maybe not making a lot of money it was
Profitable because
It had to be
We weren't paying people much money and
We
Weren't Distributing millions and millions of copies but it was getting out there and it was make
Making an impact
And getting some recognition and you're still mainly covering like Counter Culture
Yeah
But when occasionally we would have photojournalists
That would come in who had been in Afghanistan
Or
Jamaica and done something with like
You know
Gangsters in Jamaica and we would
Run their photos like we tried but we didn't have the resources
We didn't have
Annette worth we weren't
Doing reporting
In the traditional sense
At all
It was a Culture magazine that occasionally
Did some kind of
Music photojournalism
If it was gritty and raw
But in 2006
That was when everything
Changed for us when we picked up cameras
Video camera
Yeah
We took a meeting with MTV and they said if we gave you money to make a DVD what would you do
And we said it would be
Play jackass meet 60-minute
And that work we were speaking their language you know and
So they gave us money to make a DVD so we said okay let's go make the travel
The vice guide to travel DVD
I said where did you go
I went to Pakistan
We found in this area 3 years ago
We wanted is the massive illegal arms Market
Believed to be a source of weapons with Delavan
We just got to recreated what we done in the magazine
Is this loaded
But it was
First time we were
Telling stories in a different medium
And it was like a eight-minute segment
We started on this DVD
That
Segment eventually ended up on the homepage of
See you then
And
They treated as news
The co-founder of Vice
Took a trip to the country's most volatile City
Karachi
It's crazy it to think about it
Right because
If you if you go back to the early 2000s
There were a lot of really cool magazines and there are a lot of really cool
Like seeing people doing cool stuff
And
But for some reason you guys
Made it act like why do you think
That is how was it that Vice
Became vice and those other Maga
We refused to die
Again we're survivors right and we always
Find a way
Do a deal even when
Times where it where dark and it was hard
And we found a way
And we Diversified
The right time so we would have
Some other deal
That would
Keep the lights on
While
The magazine is going through a downturn and we're having a hard time selling ads
Don't do a big deal with with Viacom that will
Keep us going for another eight months
You know and then
Do a deal with
No private Equity Firm and get some money from there
And it's all about it is crazy that all those magazines are gone
For the most part and they were also
Big
And we were like the stepchildren
And they disappeared
How do you feel when people say that biases
Is
Like self-indulgent you know and it's all about the
Reporter
And it's not really news
Because I can give you a her that right and you you hear that from mainstream news organization
Sure so how do you feel that I need to you to
Defensive juice ignore it or
Maybe they're right
And we ignore it for the most part
I think.
Often wrong or their they're basing it on one thing that we did way back in the day whatever
But I do believe
Strongly and how we create our content
And the importance of
Having a point of view and and subjectivity
Yes we didn't go to journalism School
But I think that there is
A place for
The type of content that we're making
We're winning
Peabody awards
You know for all the people that are taking shots of the real something
Those accusations are coming from a place
People feeling threatened
As well
You know
Wild Al Jazeera America shutting down and in that kind of thing
Horseweed we have me Compton that isn't
Great that isn't perfect there are mistakes for learning we're going to school in public
You know in an in
And when I do think there's a lot that
They teach in journalism school that we've tried to incorporate into the content we make
Be accountable
Yeah
Have there ever been stories that you guys have done that
But you will
Yeah
Can you talk about them without fear of being sued or
No I mean like that there's there's the one that the McAfee
Story I don't know if you remember that one the guy who did the
On the run from the police couple years ago exactly where we kind of embedded with him and and
Released a photo where we didn't
Scrub the
Geotag from it so people
We basically exposed exactly where
He was when he was on the run which we obviously weren't trying to do and everybody celebrated that mistake
Everybody been all of the competition in in the other
Your news organizations
The
Novi Southern China
Do this reporting in and they're making rookie mistakes
So that was you know learning a lesson and in public the hard way
But for the most part
You know I don't have a lot of
Regrets about
Did the content that we
Make and have made visits got us to this point
Today over time you guys have attracted a lot of investment
And today
Spices value it over for
Billion
Dollars
You started this like
English language version of a Haitian Fresh Magazine in 1994
Like how crazy is that
I mean it takes me back to that time on the street where my buddy said to me he said
Maybe you'll make one copy of the magazine or maybe it'll be huge
One day and in my gut at that time
I felt like a
Maybe this could be huge
I couldn't
Define and I didn't know that this is how it was going to manifest itself in that
We would employ
New two thousand people in
And be valued it over
4 billion dollars but yeah
Pretty amazing David lives
In New York you no longer edits or manages anyone at the magazine
Infected a
Suroosh basically
Two stories in
Travels around the world
You get a new series
Call Tara
Metro drops October 11th
Vicenews.com
Listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this NPR.
And if you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other people know about it
You can also write us directly at HIV tea at npr.org
How I built this
Shows produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis
Lhasa compose the music
It's also to neva grandson has meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Are you the only one of us without sleeve tattoos
I'm a minority
If you're still up
One more thing
This month
There are
Two more presidential debate
October 9th
Cheats
And after that
NPR politics podcast
Is inviting you to
To skip the cable news hangover
And get caught up with them
They'll have new podcast episodes The Morning After
Turbos debate
So you'll know what happened
What it means
What time you get to work
Class whatever your morning routine
NPR politics podcast
Apartment the morning after the presidential debates
Subscriber list
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week