Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days away
Campaign monitor.
It was nothing more exhilarating than seeing all those people streaming and nothing more crushing than then seeing
Are people posting on Twitter on their blogs and say like another startup it doesn't know how to scale like like so clown
You're both like running on zero sleep
For two days devastated and I was like this is it we've built this great thing and we totally messed it up
From NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements
On the beach spark that idea that turned all of us it's a good photographers and made Instagram one of the fast
Fastest growing apps of all time
Okay it's
And Kevin Systrom
Just a few years out of
Stanford and doing the Silicon Valley thing
Travel startup
My day
And teaching himself
Kodak
At night
Different from college Mike Krieger
Is also in the area pretty much doing the same thing
And after a few months of experimenting
Cabin build an app
He calls it bourbon in
The check it out where you can tell your friends your
Coffee shop
Le bar or whatever
Kevin thinks this app has
You know
Some potential
I mean at that time there were so many checking apps there was four square there was gwalla and there were a bunch of others trying to make it
I'm in of course following
You know kind of
The trend I was like there's something here about
The device is Neverland
Pockets being available to share new types of information
And I was like location is is the type of
Information people are going to want to share
I think the inside Mike and I had along the way was that actually there were more types of
Information the fact that like these devices had
My camera
That would lead to a visual
Communication Revolution we're like all of a sudden
People aren't just come
Getting texts and voice
But they had the chance to
You communicate with
An image
But initially art that was on location
Frank Liotta
Very happy that we
Discovered the image thing for him away so people were using this app
Yeah
You know it was just compelling enough to get like a handful of beta users but I would you know basically come home
Night and just Tinker with this idea
And
You know how long the way I prototype it enough that I was willing to give it to a handful
What friends and those friends give it to a handful of friends
And before you knew it we had I don't know maybe 80 90 people using it and only at that moment
Did I decide that like hey maybe this thing could be a company
If we actually tried
Then like
At what point did you say we we should try to like racing money for that
I went to a bar
We're a bunch of investors were getting together
And
I like I kind of mingled around the room and
Yeah people are kind of showing their prototypes on their phones to different investors
And I showed it to this one investor is named Steve Anderson
Just one of our first
Investors
And he was like this pretty cool let's set up coffee
You know we can meet up and you can tell me more about the app and
That was like the biggest accomplishment today and I was like oh my God there's investors willing to talk to us again
So I went and I had that coffee and I sat down and as as as we were talking actually
I have an alert that would alert on my phone every time someone signed up
Because I was really excited when
From 80
85 years
90 users
And I'm as I'm sitting there with him like a bunch of people are signing up and I wasn't entirely sure why but he looked at me and was like
Did you plan this like
That you have a bunch of
People sign up while you were done waiting to be nicer
So now I honestly don't know who
These people are
He looks at me is like alright Count Me In
But he actually said one thing to Migos
Before I do this
You have to find a co-founder
It's willing to do this with
And at that moment I was like all right
Got to find someone awesome
Two kind of partner with
Make this all happen
To Mike how did you guys like
I mean how did it happen like
You can't be Kevin you're like I liked
It's cool I want to work with you I mean
Did you lose arm or
Formal
I think
Word came from was we had a kind of shared kindred spirit of tinkering so on the weekends a lot of times I would be at coffee bar
A great coffee shop here in San Francisco and I'd be working on iPhone apps just
For fun and bourbon
That the checking itself I didn't find as compelling but
Having a sort of visual status was really compelling
So I got excited enough that I think I've come up with Kevin was like look if you ever do this
Real like what's up
Crustacean and I think that first meeting we had about it actually I was like Count Me In
She said like I'm I'm excited enough
To do it end
Not like the the cliche of your life flashing before your eyes like my future flash before my eyes were talking to Kevin right then
I just imagined myself
Working one-on-one with him on something that I was really excited about in San Francisco
Just trying to make something of it and I was like
Like Ike there was something in me that just stared at that time
I just got my first
When you met at investor
He just he was just like
Here's a bunch of money
Well
He was like okay
I'm willing to give you $50,000 to do this and that's more money than I had ever heard of in my entire life
For a business cutting at the time
But the second someone shows any interest in Yuan Silicon Valley
All of a sudden you have a bunch of other people that really want to invest as well. No one wants to miss the next
Google the next whatever and that
Initial check went from 50000 to 200
And then there was another investor in Andreessen Horowitz who came in
And put 200
$50,000
So you're two guys with like basically a prototype
And a couple computers no office
Who raised a half million dollars and we're looking at each other like we think we can make
This last I mean we were we were living on peanut butter and jelly sandwich
So how did you guys
How did you turn bourbon into
Became Instagram what was
Who's the Genesis
I think the
The best thing for a neon
NRS failure and
For us
Where was the lack of momentum
We I mentioned we got to
We got about a hundred users using
100 no no no no a hundred like you can fit them in a room
And Eric races this guy in Silicon Valley likes to
You know talk about
The Lean Startup methodology
One of his
One of his lines is like don't ask why keep
Don't use your startup
Ask why the p
People who continue to use your startup
Keep using it
And when we looked at our our user base our whole hundred people
Each of them loved the photo aspect
So that's why we ended up
But they were already a bunch of photo websites
Open photo apps
So how are you able to
To come up with an idea that
That would make
Your thing different
So we're both kind of burned out
We had decided the bourbon was going to do any
Everything we had
$495,000 left in the bank
Because $5,000 to buy a couple of
Computers right
And
And we're like alright it's okay if this idea doesn't work out we can really string this
Half a million dollars out for a long time so
We're going to come up with a new idea
So we started focusing on photos and we were both burned out I was like right Mike I got to take
I got to take a break so my now wife and I
Nicole went to Mexico
And we were working on this idea photos of Mike was like alright I'm going to prototype this thing while you're on break
You come back and then we'll like reconvene so Mike started prototyping this app and as I'm away on
Walking down the beach with Nicole in Mexico we were in this little surfing town called Todo Santos
And I'm like you know Nicole I think we're going to focus on photos and she goes oh yeah that sounds like
Like a great idea I love all the food
Photo of house on Behrman
But she goes I don't think I'm going to post that much and I got to go why not and she goes well my photos aren't that good
I said well
They're great and she goes
Well they're not as good as your friend Greg
And I was like well Greg uses a bunch of filter apps to like make them look nice
You should probably add filters
That's it like we we just need to be able to make people feel
Their photos are worthy of sharing
And I remember going back right from the beach I sat in the room with the little dial-up connection that's the little Hacienda
And I I literally just like
Research how to make the first filter
Which ended up being called X pro2 and if you scroll all the way back on my account
The very first photo
There's a Nicole's foot and a little stray dog in Mexico and that's because that day I made expert 2 and I went out to a taco stand
For lunch to test it
And I took that picture and posted it on the Prototype that Mike had given me
So
That was kind of that the intersection
Of the ideas
Photos
And filters and it all came through consumer insight
There's just like
What problem are we solving
Share something that people love
And make sure that they feel great sharing
Tosa Hollander
Take from the time you do
Decided to
Move away from Bourbon and then
Lunch in
It was only eight weeks from the time we had basically sketched it out to when we
You put it into the Apple Store
We press launch on
October 10th
5 mm
And it was like about midnight
And I
People just started streaming in
It was crazy
It was like like how fast
The first 24 hours with 25000
People sign up around the world
Which sounded big to us at the time
Yeah that's incredible what were you expecting that
No I mean
Couple things that show.
How naive we were at
Number one
Midnight in San Francisco it's 9 a.m. somewhere
And we didn't quite realize how Global harvests could be
So turns out everyone who's signing up at the beginning actually lived overseas so when we looked into the database more
Who are they
People they all had
Email addresses
Germany
Kong
And various places around the world
And before you knew it we actually had overloaded our system and it was a very small naive system it was a single
Computer in it
Colocation space somewhere in LA
Yeah it was it was nothing more exhilarating than seeing all those people screaming and nothing more crushing than then see
Are people posting on Twitter on their blocks and sailing
How to scale like like so Clowney
We are both I mean at that point like running on zero sleep for 2 days devastated and I was like this is it we've built this
This great thing and we
Totally messed it up
And to be clear there's no reason we should
Succeeded
Like I mean the server was just like him
He was down every other hour and like
People just kind of forgave us and they would come back and they would share their photos and
At the time mobile networks weren't that great either
So people would actually blame their connection and not us which is great
But
Those initial weeks I mean
It was just like
Trial by fire and we had to learn everything on the job and we had so many chances to fail but we just
Kept at it
And and kept work
I pulled a bunch of all-nighters
The amount we learn that first year was crazy
It was like 5 years of college all in one
And yes pretty exciting
And tiring
How do people even find out about it
How do they know
Did they should download this
This app
So we had this intuition that if you're going to throw a party which
Just kind of what an app launch really is
People screaming to the door
You want the next sort of know
How they should act and who else is there so one of the things we did was
We have
You have a hundred
Invite that
You can have before you launch your app
To the Apple store where you can invite people to
What to try it out and what are we going to use this
Find people
And we used them a combination of some journalists that we got
You know of her
Know the last couple of
5 years
In
Just got in the valley
We also went on the site called dribbble.com which is sort of like
A place where designers Go and show off their best work
And we figured
Photographers might not instantly take to Instagram because like
They want like super high-resolution or if they have other
Are constraints
But designers love photography but it's not their main
Job
So we pick basically but
The 10 top designers and dribble and we emailed them and some ignored us
Finding some Rebecca
I'll try rap
And it has great cuz
Coming in day 1 people who
What explore things get a popular page at the time that show the most popular
Photos across the whole community
Wow you can take that on a phone like we take this for granted a little bit now and have cameras have improved every year
But I think part of what we showed two people back in 2010 was that there was something really amazing you could do with
Just the phone in your pocket
Welcome back our President Obama Snoop Dogg and about
500 million other people started to use Instagram
And what happened after Facebook bought it for a billion dollars
Garage listening to how I built this from NPR
Support also comes from choiceology
An original podcast from Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of toy salad
You'll hear a classic psychology experiments retold
William is an opera fan who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation
And is an average chest
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find out
Schwab.com podcast
Or wherever you listen
Support also comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to study group
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities
These can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed return
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct
Low-fee motto
Learn more at game Bridge. Live / NPR
Game Bridge is not available in all states
It's how I built this from NPR
Garage
It's been a year after Instagram
Launch
And it's grown to
Million user
And Mike Krieger and Ken
Kevin Systrom
Ariix
Expanding their staff
Very very quickly
CenterPoint
Investors
Thing under door
We have said investors Choice office
We be like trying to keep the servers up and we have someone would like cap on her
Hi I'm so-and-so from
Someone to invest
And partners and I like to take you out for lunch and we're trying to keep this side up
But we met you know a bunch of people along the way and
The ones we did make time for we're the ones who are most
Black full of that time
I knew what we were going through anchor
Help
Very shortly after you launch this thing
What is valued at in
More than 20 million dollars
Yeah
Was I think our first round was like
I don't remember it was like weed
You took $89
Financing online
20 president
Roughly a 30 million dollar valuation
There's something
And I mean again
Attestation lifecycle
Never heard of it
Okay it's worth it
This is crazy
I didn't really think much of it I just wanted to get back
Twerking I think Mike felt the same way we were just look so focused on building
What we're building
It just like
It kept growing and
The question was
I got in Mike and I are
Every single day worth
How what scale can a
Just got to and
I think it really started to hit us
When we would be out
And see people using it
In the real world
It was kind of cereal over time
I mean I mean that they deserve that like from the outside the store just seems like
Clear
Linear like
Jumping for
From success to
Success like it
EZPawn
Put it up there in
All this money in the
Stratosphere
But what are moments in the beginning even even after that initial
Fire.
And Beyond where you thought
I mean all the time
Like 3 weeks in
Kevin turned to me and he said Mike I don't know how big is it going to be by think we're on
Something else I will see and every morning I would wake up
Expecting that that was the morning that
Bratz doll
And that was it
And if I knew what I know now about metrics and how to measure the weather people are coming back over one day 7 days
30 day.
I would actually been I think a lot calmer because I think it would have shown as
Babe that shows now that
People who join Instagram tend to stick around and become more active and that's really exciting that the time I didn't know that other guy that signing up are they
Can I come back tomorrow like is it all going to change
And that was sort of an internal worry and externally
You're as we launched and grew
Became a very competitive space end
We would see in a company's got announced
But had
Tens of millions of dollars in Investments even before launching Andre like man like this
These guys have so much money
They're going to come in and you know at hakkasan
Going to be really hard and
That's the other lesson learned which is
You know your valuation and the amount you raise it can be helpful in building your product but it does absolutely nothing
Make people your end users don't care at all how much money you've raised they care if you're providing some cut
Car value
I'm in the product
Lesson learned over time that you know you have to earn it everyday
I'm curious to get your
Your take on
Why it
Continue to grow
There are a lot of
Cool apps
That you and I both know that launched
Amazing
People used
Gone and
There are lots of people who work really hard or really creative a really smart of Amazing Ideas
And put out a really cool products
So why
Why do you think Instagram
Survive and thrive
I think there was this opportunity that we spoke of that
Back in the day that
People had
Cameras
In our pockets
The first time
And digital photography was clearly going to be a thing
But the second that camera got added
The phone
And then you had it with you at all
All times
And that doesn't mean that you're going to take
Take photos on it obviously the quality has to be high enough
But we started the company right at the moment we're like
The quality of those cameras
Just kind of met up
Point-and-shoots
And because of that
Everyone starts
Taking photos on the
The phone
But they had no place to play
Or if they did it
Card I mean they would look at Facebook
Maybe like well you know like have to upload them like on a desktop or
I on Twitter like doesn't really showing the timeline
I'm so they had this problem like there's no place to easily share all these
All the time
And we just happened to be the right
Tool for that job
At the right moment
And
We created
I believe the thing that kept growing was
We couldn't open now
We sat down
Very early on
Product design
Oyster sauce okay
Do we want to be a place where you
Send a friend request
Have to accept it in order
To see
Those photos or do we want to be open where anyone
Unfollow anyone
I'm so glad we ended up
Choosing the open model
Because now
You can follow someone
From Japan
You can follow
You know a chef from New York City
You can file your favorite celebrity or you can call your friends
And not like hadn't really been done before in
In photos if you look at
Every photo service
Before then
It was basically a closed only
Friend's only Network
And we were the first ones
Really open that
The other was a moment
In my other radio show the TED Radio Hour
Where
PPL be like
Just how big
The show
Became when when pink
The pop singer
He's about to shut we like wholly
She looks like
She was in the shower
Did you guys have a moment we were like
Jesus like
They're using this thing that we built in like our basement
I think for me
The biggest one was the White House or obamacare's Obama join first
Legos part of
Champagne
That he was running and
I remember like
Instagram isn't enough how to use it and I remember
You know every
You know every time somebody is using our appetite either see or hear about a mic
Hope it doesn't crash I hope it works perfectly
I hope they like don't have any question
Keep them from using at so that was I think it a big infection moment and I think the other one was
I noticed that the New York Times when they would cover his head stop saying Instagram,
The photo-sharing app and then it was just
Instagram Aiko we are we have now reached the point where they they can assume that most of their readers
Know what we are
I am
I am old enough to remember when in PRC
Would say
Google
For me is I feel embarrassed because you had a really good example about like the president using
For me it was like our first celebrity of Snoop
Do you remember Snoop Dogg signing up
I meant we were like
Is this actually Snoop Dogg and then I got an email that was like Snoop Dogg's people want to meet you guys and everything
Oh my gosh
I don't even know what does it mean people like
Snoop Dogg has people
And I remember Justin Bieber signing up and
And the world going kind of
Bonkers
For that is why my world I mean
Teenage girls and
They basically started using the app incessant
Took off with like
A bunch of really young people as well
You obviously everybody knows
Eventually you sold
Instagram to Facebook
Billion dollar
I mean
Incredible that
2 years
Greatest thing
That happen
You couldn't have planned for that you couldn't have
Even have been in that mission
Yeah I mean the first day
That we went home
After pulling that all nighter to launch Instagram
There's a guy sitting on the muni here in San
Subway system
And
He was using Instagram
Oh my God like we did it like someone in the world is using this thing out in the wild
That feeling and that moment is the currency that you maximize
When you're not
It's like seeing someone using your product
And loving it is like way more rewarding
The Nanny amount of money
In the world
You guys now or within the Facebook
Family right
An independent
Company that you are part of Facebook
How to change the way
You are obviously a lot bigger yeah
Initially that was actually
Pretty awesome because
We had all these problems killing our services in like
The Facebook infrastructure
Come over and we seen that before here this is what you do
So I made our lives actually a lot better
And we were able to hire some of the best
On the world end
And share Talon I like the colors of the older brother or the other sibling where were the we were the first company that Facebook
Fire dancer
Kept running and then since then you've seen Oculus
Send WhatsApp
And
I think a lot of things that we figured out early on and turn
Terms of the relationship
The office space
Hiring
And I think we
Off
From both sides of the
Of the table I purchased it from
A spirit of hate how can we make Instagram better through these Integrations rather than
How can you make Instagram more like Facebook in or try to
Adapted to be exactly
There was this
This controversy that happened
With Instagram where
You change the terms of service and people aren't
The impression that their photos were
Your property in
A lot of people like
Black Instagram
Moment
Presently that I mean that's
That was a
Learning lesson for Feud for you guys
Huge lesson
Number one
People read the docs that
You know
You put out an
You should care about them as a
The founder so your terms of service basically what happened we had these terms of service that we had
I think effectively copied from some other site way back in the day and just find and replace their name with
Instagram because we're a startup we didn't know what we were doing
But we eventually got to a place
Where when we join Facebook Facebook is like hey you actually need a real one that like fits with the way you guys work and we're going to make all these
Make changes and we went through it
And I was like a great this makes sense and I didn't really read it all that carefully
And one of the sections
Reading it again today if I look at it
Can be interpreted that we were going to take
User photos in somehow use them in advertising
That was definitely not our intention and like no one in the company of evil
And thought of that idea
It just if you read the sentence that way you could see that maybe it would worry people
So immediately
Yeah we had this
Big protest in
And people were
You know
Leaving the service I mean if we have a graph of account deletions at that
That was skyrocketing
And Mike and I sat down / like what do we do
And
And we felt helpless and it was like all over that was that first day all over again
It's like we've screwed this up how do we make sure people know
I went back to my house like
Why we just apologize and say we're wrong
And I posted this Punk post on our block you can probably still find it online
And I was like we're sorry like
We didn't mean this
That's absolutely not what we're trying to do
We tweeted about it and actually the graph of
Deletions at that moment
Drops to zero
And sometimes you just have to say sorry
Sometimes you just have to say you were wrong
And reassert what you're actually trying to do
I'm at interaction with the
The community still sex
And my mind is something
That we try to do every
Every single day which is
Be really transparent
People put our community
81st because like at the end of the day
Without them where a photo-sharing
How much of what happened
To you guys
Instagram
And this whole story how much of it
I'd say 50%
Actually I have this thesis that
The world runs unlock
The question is what you do with
Everyone gets lucky for some amount in their life
No question is are you
Are you alert enough
To know you're being lucky right or you're
You're becoming lucky
Are you talented enough to take
Take that advantage and run with it
And
Do you have enough
Grits do you have enough like
Resilience to stay with it when it gets hard because everyone gets lucky
In minimum wage every week
Can you find a Dollar on the ground or you know you got a break at work to work on
Project are you meet someone really interesting
The difference between people I think
If you succeed in the long run and the Pea
People don't is frankly that often isn't that like
You got lucky and now it's yours too
Yours to make awesome
And that first day I think we got lucky by having the right ideas the right time
The right place we we were lucky to have met each other I mean
There are a lot of co-founding Paris
Intact who have not worked out and Mike and I are like great friends
Least I think so right Mike
And
The question is
Can you take that lock and capitalize on it
Instagram co-founders Kevin Systrom and Mike Krieger by the way
After the sale of Instagram to Facebook for a billion dollars those two became very very rich
But today Instagram according to Forbes is worth more than 50 billion
Which makes Instagram bigger in dollar terms than places like Alaska
Maine Rhode Island Mafia
Listen to the show this week if you want
More or less than two previous episodes of Good how I built this. Npr.org and if you have a chance please subscribe to
Who are show through iTunes and let other people know about it you can also write us directly yet HIV tea at NPR
Yard. O RG
Shows produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis
Los ocampos the music they also to neva grandson has meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Verizon you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey thanks again for listening to how I built this
Here in the US Monday September 26th is the very first
Presidential debate in the next
Morning
The NPR politics podcast is inviting you to
To skip the cable news hangover
And get caught up
With them
Still have new podcast episodes
The morning after
Every debate
So you'll know what happened and what it means by the time
Time you get to work
Class or
Finish walking the dog
So whatever your morning routine
The NPR politics podcast
Part of it
The morning
After every debate
Subscriber listen
NPR one app
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week