Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Hey everyone it's got here just a quick note to tell you that this episode is about Angie's List they are a financial supporter
Of NPR
But we thought the story of how the company came to be was so interesting that
We wanted to tell it to you
Soap Puritas
People started calling you and you are the only person Manning the phones
I literally in like a hundred square foot Office Space
And so when we needed a second line we got a second phone so that I do remember times I feel like sitting on the floor in the off
Office literally like toggling between two physical phones with no home button
From NPR how I built this show up
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movements they built
Angie Hicks and Astoria building in Columbus
Tow company that brings in 350 million
Here
Show in summer of 1995
Angie Hicks at just graduated from college in Indiana with
Is where she's from
And like a lot of college graduates she was looking for a job
The previous Summer She interned at a small Venture Capital firm in Indianapolis
Airbus there was a man named Bill OST
Bill Withers
Just a few years older than Andy but
He already had a lot of business expo
So they kept in touch
And with Angie job-hunting
Collegeville was giving her advice about
Where to apply
Hiring that kind of thing
I was back in the day where you would literally send your resume and cover letter by mail so I sent out
Numerous letters and resumes
And then calls me up one day and says
Hey Angie I have an idea
At that point he had moved to do Columbus Ohio
Is it like why don't you move to Columbus and we can start a business all raise a little bit of money
Money from your friends and enough to to get you through the first year
I want you to commit for a year
So what so what you think
It was a little out of the blue and I would never have defied myself
As an entrepreneur
A lot of times when I thought of classical entrepreneurs I would like a they're risk-takers their big idea thinkers
That
So
Ring my hands about that decision and
Talk to my parents about it and
Well you know you don't feel well you know he's not going to lead you astray
And then I talked to my grandfather and he was incredibly conservative I lived through the depression
I'm just me.
Like to pay cash for everything
Yeah he looked at me without even hesitating and was like
Will you you should do it in G
I mean what's the difference between being
22 and looking for a job and being 23 and looking for a job
I was like
So
Literally like
Loaded up all of my worldly possessions in my 40s
Escort in office
So at that point did Bill actually have
A business in mind or was he just like hey come to Columbus and then we'll figure it out
We have a couple ideas
But then
Landed on what became Angie's List when
Bill was trying to renovate his house in Colombo
It was a second house you don't
This house in Indianapolis is also a fixer-upper but in Indianapolis he was introduced to a little business called
Unified Neighbors
Cars that have been around since
Since the early 70s
Which was basically a list of who was good and he wasn't in the city
For Home Improvement
So what do you move to Columbus he just kind of assumed there was something like that in every city
And so
He's like we're going to try to start our own okay so this is like like 95
That's right
So you get to Columbus what did you do there like how did you
You start
We started just talking to people that we knew so you're the first stop on my light or was two bills next
Door neighbor
Patty did you say it was your pet
We're starting this business
People find the best contractors in town
And Patty had lived in her house lived in her neighborhood for entire life
You know someone did not need what we were selling it was probably Patty
But Patty love the entrepreneurial Spirit of it so she looked at me and she was like this is great
I'm going to take two member
One for me
And one for my son
Give me a list of every service provider should ever used
And she also gave me
Her church Direct
She told me that I had to call everybody at her church directory and tell them that
She said they should buy it
And how much was a membership at that time
$19 for the year
We are magazine in a concert
So during the day when you could ask me for the name of a plumber and electrician and then the
In the evening I would go out door-to-door
And also ask
4 reviews
So you did everything you you wrote I wrote the magazine
Like magazine is a very
Generous
Term for brochure issue
So how did you
How did you get more subscribers
I literally for the first three or four months I've been
Basically went door-to-door every
What was that like
Remember I'm an introvert
It was probably one of the most miserable experiences you miserable because
You just weren't getting a traction like Hugo
Door-to-door people would just say
Play buzz off for tonight in the mid-90s
I got now I like to look back on it
Experiencing
Yeah it was hard
There was a moment in the
The fall and he has like you think about like I was 22 and I kind of realize that this is my life
This is my career really didn't need to go to college to do what I was doing
Did you know anybody in Columbus
Bill and his wife
So you were just like
On your own in Mississippi
Just working all the time
Going door-to-door
As an introvert
You are totally miserable
Ava love one day
And I appreciate the fact that he realized
But I was upset
Siri suggest that we meet like it's a little Bakery down
Until we get there
Soon as I sit down I just start crying
He just starts talking
Annie's just like
Selling me on why we were it was going to be great and you know he talked for probably another 30 minutes
And everyone in the fake real looking at us like what is wrong
And I'm in he likes to tell the story that like at the end
All I could muster to say was that I was not going to quit
Soap so what happened after that conversation is did you just go back out on the streets and start
Selling door-to-door
Success by
One or two membership
If I sold two memberships a day it was
Fast forward a little bit in real life k
This is probably not the marketing plan
And it's going to work so then we're going to have to raise
Insane amounts of money was like $50,000
And so you know where can we Market that we can do it in an economical way that we won't burn through $50,000 real
So we
We lucked out in Columbus Ohio has at that time had these little Weekly News
And so
So we put an ad in the back of the weekly newspaper and it was
Listen your neighborhood by neighborhood
And
It was this little too by 3 ad that said tired of lousy service
So are we
So we decided to do something
And people started calling you
And you are the only person Manning the phones
I literally in like a hundred square foot office space that the people in the other
Offices around me thought my parents rented
For me to do my homework
Working at a card table
Turn off phone system we had a phone
And so when we needed the second line we got a second phone
I do remember times I be like sitting on the floor in the office literally like
Toggling between two physical phones with no hold
And what people like your subscribers are just call up during the day and then say hey I need a plumber or like a roofer and you would say yeah yeah yeah
Yeah it's like or if I didn't have an answer given the list was then I would go for
Figure it out I remember one time
This woman called
She was new in town and wanted
To sign her daughter up for ballet
I'm so
So it's like hang on
Luckily I remembered cuz I signed up all the members that I had a member who was apart of the Columbus ballet
So I call her up
Ballet lessons
So yeah we're I would just
It's kind of try to make
You were you are like a human however I cut you were a human Google
Yes you were the like the person like when you type it into Google you were the person the other side
Answering that question
And what was the company
Call by the way
Oh sure it was called Columbus neighbor
So you don't got to decide
A simple knock off of the unified Neighbors
Yeah we debated names
One of the guys that was involved with puppies on them
The board he was like what's called the list
And you know like it's pretty good name by the way
Let's forget.
Yeah maybe heart attack
And then Bill throws any like what we could just name it
Angie's List
Since
Angie's who you talk to and
It does make a good story and
No matter what happens
I can always relate back to you know Angie was the first one that answered the phone
So you know
Probably not knowing what I was getting into
That was a decision we made
So when you ran these ads
And you started to see more subscribers
How long does it take before you start thinking
Is actually working with sexy generating some cash for the
We ended up signing of a thousand members in the first year
Azurite
This could be with this could be a go at it so then we started thinking like maybe we should go and see if we can acquire unified name
Savers in
Right right
So
We ended up accomplishing it about a year after we started income
So then yeah I kind of wake up one day in July
36 +
I've got
Two offices so I had to
Start advertising to hire some
Some help
I'm 22 I don't know how to hire anyone
So I placed a little ad in our newsletter
Hire people
And I have this one woman that came in her name
And I haven't interviewed anyone before so I like asking questions
Finish up the interview and I'll get back to you in a few days and I just remember she looks
BVI
If you're going to hire me
You need my phone now
Like I was just like
That's exactly right so the next day I hired Mac
You know Maggie is now this year celebrating
XX
Anniversary
So in those
Early years
He must have just been working like a
Because you had to deal with billing
Magazine getting new subscribers
Expand Indianapolis
Selling advertising like did you did you move to Indianapolis when you when you guys acquired unified Neighbors
No I didn't know actually I just drove back at
Cricbuzz would have my week in Columbus
How how long is a drive by the way
3 hours
Like what you sleeping like 4 hours a night
It was it was it was a lot I mean you can find yourself you can just work work work
There's a lot of time in the day and you can work a lot of hours
That guy couldn't have picked
A better time in my life
Have to do something
No family in your life or your kind of
Geared to do that
It's funny though because
You are so different from almost
Every entrepreneur that was interviewed in that
You are not
Incredibly optimistic about the
Success
Tumblr Leone
You are
Kind of thinking about maybe
Packing it in you were not
Natural Hustler
But you were doing all of these things
I think Avenue in retrospect music
Think about what makes an object
An entrepreneur
Honestly I think a lot of time
It comes down to per
Yeah
And I think a lot of times people can have the big idea
And they can have
You know kind of that initial kind of fall in love
With their idea for
Starting some
But
They don't write it through the heart
And I give it up
Yeah
So while I might not have had the big idea and while I might not have been the big risk
I have perseverance
I think that
That is my aunt
Angie Hicks almost got downsized
Horizon you listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped keep this podcast going first to stamps.com
Stamps.com wants you to know that with the holidays fast approaching the post office is getting busier by the men
Avoid the hassle and use stamps.com instead
Westaff.com you can buy imprint official US postage for all of your letters and packages using just your
Computer and printer
Right now sign up for stamps.com and get this
Special offer
4 week trial plus Postage and a digital scale
Go to stamps.com click on the microphone and type in built
Thanks also to SimpliSafe the award-winning home security system that never locks you into a long-term contract
SimpliSafe uses an arsenal of Wireless sensors and has 24/7 professional monitoring
All for a fraction what other companies charge
There are no installation cost or hidden fees
So you can protect your home and family the smart way
Right now listeners podcast
$200 off a special SimpliSafe security system
Only if you go to simply safe.com
Flash NPR
Just one more thing before I get back to the show
As you probably know by now
The end of every episode were telling your stories about the companies or products that
You are building so please do stick around after the credits to hear it
But for now
Show
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So about three years in Angie's List have expanded form
Two markets
4 Market
And so they decided to build a bigger manager
Bill oesterle came to work it
Full-time CEO
She says
The crazy hours and hard work of the early years had really started to take a toll
I was super burnt
And so it was like a Jeep I know you
Periodically about business school why don't why do you think more seriously about
Not prepared to do that had to take the GMAT hadn't done anything but he basically decided in September that I would
Apply that
Wait so you your plan for business school in the fall of 98
Like 3 years after you launch this company which is now really gaining Traction in and looks like it's going to
Become something
Like I guess you could argue that those three years were kind of like your business school right like why did you
Feel like
You wanted to go to business
You know for me if I hadn't
Taking that time I probably would
I kind of need
Perspective
How do I learn to be a manager because I was forced to be a manager
Like I got through an acquisition I'd raise capital
But did I really understand everything that I
I was going through
And so it was a great time for me to step away and
I'm kind of gain for spect
Applying to to school
Kellogg
Harvard
I ended up not getting it
How I got into Harvard
What was that like was it was
We are going there
You know I was
I've lived in Indiana or Ohio my entire life
It was one of those things where I was like I was
So flattered
To actually have just gotten
Individual
A girl
Middle class kid
First in our immediate family to go to call
So for me it was kind of like loud
What is kind of Adidas
Experience I'm going to
Take it for what it's worth
But maybe I had a differ
Perspective
When you are at business school and you would like to run these models of
How business is ran or how to be a leader
Will you like where the time for you that's not how it works in the real world cuz I've been there
Yeah
It was fascinating to watch you you'd have these conversations of companies
The cut 20% from its
From its bottom line New Jersey alternative people
People like what we should just cut 20% of staff
What kind of like
Have you fired someone before
Have you ever actually done that because
That's really hard to do
And yeah sometimes you have to do it and sometimes that's the right decision but
Let's make sure we really understand the
Wow you were there
Will you
Involved with Angie's List
Well I was actually I was still keeping
Was it your intention to go back
Civility
How does the arrangement that like hay
You should go in
Explore what there is.
Are you not like we're here but you should go see what
Weather is
Interview
I realize that sometimes you don't realize what you have until you
Yeah
So I decided I was going to go back
By that point Bill had hired a chief operating officer
Who had conservatively model the business
In such a way that after I agreed to come
Comeback Bill had to call me and say
We may not be able to afford
Wait what
But why was that because you wouldn't NBA that point
No he was just like he was literally like we we now have too much overhead and I was like are you just being you
You are is this
Send anywhere just like going to be like
This is what this is what the model says and I'm like you know what
I'm coming back
Screw you
I co-founded this company bill
Exactly needless to say the guy that ran the model was incredibly conservative on it
So we were all fine but it was is a funny moment
So when you got back what was your what was
How do I gave you
So the chief operating officer position was filled so I just decided to get a check mark
If this is going to be hard question for you to answer but it's just my observation that you must be
A person with almost
No
Yo
I am I right I mean that's exactly right I joke around
I don't worry about titles I worry about getting
There's too much
Stuff to worry about
To worry about
And maybe that's see I often
Remind myself yeah cuz people ask me is
They come into the business
Like what's it like to work at like I like the last person to ask
I got tell people at orientation like I am really shy if you see me in the diner you need to come talk to me
Okay okay so you come back to the company after business school this is the early 2000s right
Yeah so we
So that's what we started opening markets
Anamorphic
Places where opening one or two year
The invite
When did you go from being a
A newsletter
Book a physical newsletter to being
An online company
So we put our first website up
Play early
Mauser 99
And basically literally we hired two college kids
Seville archives
Which is a basic like you know marketing informational website
I had email
You couldn't check the list
I was just for Market
So how's that website working one day
We realize it's like you know half of our sign
We're coming in over the
I guess I should actually build a web
So you know
I was like yeah
It's probably more in
Interesting to read the reviews then to have Angie read the reviews to you either getting the mailing
Well they were just calling at the number
Taking this online is it
Like a business model is based on
Basically building a community of
Trust
End
You have did this before the airbnb's and the
The Ubers and that you know these are there that the sharing economy kind of
Right so
At the beginning or people
Skeptical of others
Yeah I think it was actually even an article written
She's probably
10 or 12 years ago about the fact that
There was a Fascination as to why consumers were willing to share their opinions with
They're like you for information that they are giving you
Get right yeah
The article and it was a
There was something
Special about the service at first I thought it was like oh it's Columbus because I know all the members are
What's Indianapolis but
There's almost there's there is a sense of belonging and obligation
It's became a culture of the service in it replicated itself in city after
After City
I mean what are the values we
We had it was the fact that we started when we
We started pre-internet days
In many ways we looked at who we were going to mimic
For our business model
We looked at journalist
Every story has a sore
Yeah even occur to us
That we should allow people to review anonymous
Isn't that proved incredibly powerful
Why do you think people were willing to write these
Refuse that
They're paying for
Because if they didn't
The next first
And if you think about the kind of decisions are making around your home I mean these
Hi I called you like the high cost of failure decision
It's right I mean it's the time when
You probably know the least about what you're buying
You spending a lot of money
And if it goes wrong it could potentially ruin your largest
Yeah
Are there bad information and I mean cuz a lot of these companies are small company so how do I find out where
XYZ Plumbing is any good
There's lots of places to get information
But people are willing to pay for Quality Inn
As you get started to expanded you
Did you go out and raise money
We did you know that you know that was one of the things
Bill having a venture-capital back
Was incredibly valuable for us
Cuz usually nrr raising money came around you no wanting to
Grow the market
Okay so what you're saying is you didn't need money to manufacture a product
You were primarily spending money on marketing
We're requiring members were to stick around for a long
Upfront the marketing to acquire
Once we were able to scale to National Market
Erased opening
So in about 18 months we opened 100 mark
What were some of the mistakes that you made
Why you were in that in that sir
Carol expansion
So you know
We waited a number of years before we opened
Chicago
Cuz we were really uneasy about the
The cost of
Expanding into a city that big
You know what we realized we open there was
You know it just took off like
Like crazy why did most companies start on the coast
Because there's
For the population of
Absolute office
And clearly that strategy
How many members by the way do you have today
Over 3 million babe
Whatever you ever just about everything
DUI
Like when you see a
Incredibly positive review
And also incredibly negative
If you like but how do you know which one to believe
What I often find when I look at reviews
You know one it's really important to actually read
I learned this early
No matter how great you are as a cup
Company you're going to get
Honestly believe you learn more when you can
Can see a company that has
A couple of complaints here and there
Then you do about a company that has all glowing
You know what I'm part of that is like hey Ya
They might make a mistake
Can you really want to know how they're going to handle it when the
What's going to happen if that
You know what the countertop was wrong length
And now they have to redo it
Because that's what you was a consumer fear right I fear when the job doesn't go well
And you don't on the flipside no years ago I mean cash early on in the business we allowed companies
Start responding to reviews
Cuz they were like hey it's not mean I actually understand that
The consumer gets to give their opinion
A chance to say our side of the
Historic and so we introduced that witch
Purple incredibly valuable
The consumer
Because you do want to know how they're going to rain
Right but I do spend a lot of time talking to service companies and kind of
Encouraging them not to
Respond on
Cuz usually that's when they're angry no one likes negative feedback hours to Jessica to get a cup of coffee comebacks
Think about it before they
Because
What they say can be more powerful than 10 reviews
Might ever
To do like when you have to get something fixed in your house
Do the contractor to show up
Are they freaking out like as a super nervous they're like oh my God Angie is going to like ruin me if you can
Ruin me
I'm okay my reviews
Start with the same as everyone
But yes
You a lot of times my husband
Is the one that
At home when
And we have worked on
Pics is not my married name so so that helps until they kind of
Look around the room and start seeing you
Pictures
And they were like oh wait
They're like holy crap it's Angie
It's Angie Hicks of Angie's List she still the chief marketing officer at the company Chicot
I found it and despite her best efforts to avoid the spotlight she says she can't go to grocery stores or flea
Anywhere without someone asking her for advice on finding a contractor
I'm getting some bathroom tiling done this is true story in Washington DC just have the top of your head
Good bastard Tyler
Listen to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous
DS episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us at Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet gets at how I built this
Our show is produced as Weak by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to neva grants
Sanaz meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
A guy rides and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks for sticking around because we are now at
The part of the show where we get to tell your stories about the things that
You're telling this one came about when Brett Johnson noticed
2011 and 2012 I think it was there was a big cayenne pepper crazy kind of swept across the country
Maybe it wasn't the craze but apparently a lot of people were touting the health benefits of cayenne pepper
I had this idea what if we could integrate cayenne pepper into a throat loss
Cayenne pepper into a throat lozenge something they called
Fire truck
Put it in your mouth and it takes about 15 to 20 seconds for the actual
Giant really hit you
You can feel it in the back of your throat you feel this kind of soothing effect
Of the spice of the cayenne pepper I know this may not sound very soothing
But Brett says that the heat from the pepper actually feels really great on your throat
A lot of customers who are singers and actors they really like the fire drop because they feel as soon as their vocal
Chords and helps them kind of feel after night of performance
Bracelet that for now most of the people who are buying fire drops have
Cold or sore throat
And I mean is it for years in
Company still has a small problem
We're seasonal business in summer time is a slow time for colds and sore throats and so it becomes
Challenge to figure out how to manage cash flow properly
Despite that challenge Brad says the company is just
Starting to break even full-time jobs in addition to this because it's kind of a
Growing operation right now the goal is to August take a full-time someday but
But the growing operation for now tell us the story of the company or the movement that
You are building
Go to build. Npr.org
Build
With a d. Npr.org
And thanks
Before we go just a quick
Tip to let you know but another NPR Podcast
2checkout
Bullseye with Jesse thorn
It's your guide to what's good in pop culture
Every week Jesse interviews people like Cameron s
Zia Rashid
Jonesville
Hoffman and many others
At work in their lives you can find your favorite new TV shows book
Movies and music
And gain new insights
Love
Pencil sign out
NPR one app
Npr.org
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week