Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Probably would have been better if I just kept my own company and not
I'm going to work for anyone because all of a sudden I had a lot of money and not a lot of friends and I was in
Immediately attacked by the media and the industry and I felt the cold shoulder from ever
Everyone and I said oh my god I've made a massive mistake here
Ron NPR how I built this
Show innovators entrepreneurs idealists the stories behind the movements they built
LA Reid followed his Instinct for
Spotting Talent went on to create some of the biggest hit makers in pop music
So you
ShopRite
Services of course
Pink and that she singing about La tell me you'll be a popstar she's not saying about Los Angeles cheap
News about a guy named L A Reid
Who's won the most
Powerful executive
In music
Built his own record label
And then he went on to manage several others but
What is really known for is
Finding amazing
Talent
Discovered pink in fact
And Toni Braxton and Rihanna and Justin Bieber TLC Usher outcast in men
Any others
Everything about him is
He just seems to have this sense of what pop music fans want to hear
In that sense it really began when La was
Did the kid growing up in Cincinnati in the 1960
Listening to a lot of music
Just hearing music on the radio
Buying 45
Buying James Brown's records
Old Motown records to buy old soul records
And bringing them home
And just drumming on the table along with the songs
By the way I thought I was going to be the next James Brown
Didn't work out
So the truth is that I failed miserably like a
Oh yeah all the time fake Mike's of the broom you make the mirrors
You know we did everything you know we had a great time growing up and music was everywhere
So how did you get into into play NAB and how did that happen
Funny Story I played at home by myself forever
And never play with the band
And then one day I'm in my
Basement and
I look out the window while I'm in the basement playing by myself
And there's a guy staring at
And it startled me
So I stopped and I went outside and I said hi and he had friendly eyes so you know the fear kind of went away
And he said
You play pretty good there's a band around the corner that needs a drummer
You know his name was Vince and Vince took me around the corner to meet
A couple of other musicians of bass player and guitar player
And you know I joined their van it was really that simple
And one band Led to another and
I think things started
How to get pretty serious by the time I was in high school
So I read that this is around a time or where you met somebody who would become this
Transformational figure in your life
His name is Kenny Babyface Edmonds
One night Kenny came to watch my band play
And
About six months later I got a call from him asking me could he join my band
Acid
And I don't think you fit
And then I met him a little while later in the studio
Man in the session
Kenny Edmonds was writing a song and performing it
And I walked in while he was
Recording
And when it came out of the booth
I was like oh my God that's Skaneateles
What's the guy that called me and said he wanted to join my band and ice
I said no
How stupid am I
Because he's pretty incredible
So what you doing
I instantly befriended him
You did join our band we started to write songs together
And I made our demos that eventually got us
Recording
And the name of the band was
The
Deal deal
And you guys like
Started to
Yeah we we had
Some notoriety for sure
Our first record
Was a song that I co-wrote called body talk and
It became a top-5 song
On R&B radio
That was good enough to get us on tour with
The great Luther Vandross who allowed us to open for him
So pretty much
Overnight life change and all of a sudden we are
On a massive stage in an arena with 15 20000 people for night
But the most fascinating thing was
The talent that was around
Watching Luther Vandross every night
And watching the musicians in the background singers
And the entire Productions that went into the shows
And I think I became more
Fascinated by the talent that we were around
Then I was about actually being
A performer on stage
I think those probably the beginning
Miso adrift
Into
A talent finder in a talent nurturer
More so than I
Performer
So how does you
And Babyface
Disco from
Being a band
To say hey you know what let's get out of this business
We were signed to a label in
Los Angeles called solar records
And
The label was
Like Junior Motown
The head of the company dick Griffey
Call
After hearing some demo that Kenny and I did and asked us to
Come out and produce other artists on the label
Before long we started getting calls from all the record labels in town
And back then you have to write the song ever
So we did it all
How many how many number one hits
Did you guys write
We had probably
What
How did you guys know what
What it was
Hey
It just takes great talent and Kenny Edmonds my partner is one of the most prolific songwriter
Ever
But he had this great talent and I had the greatest job in the world I would hear the songs first
And decide which ones were
The good one
See what you would you say oh that's going to be
Perfect for Whitney Houston exactly
This song is great but
The bridge not quite sure or that lyric I'm not sure if that lyric is it
Or
It sounds great doesn't as a slow song
Let's make it faster see how it sounds
Maybe you should take it from that artist
Give it to another artist
That was my thing was
To try to find the absolute perfect
Pairing
I-40
Material
UCCU in Babyface are
Training at these hits
And at some point
What happened
What does he say to you or do you said in hey you know we
We should stop working for other people we should like
Bill orender white why are we allowing
Our music to be picked over
Or people to make decisions about which songs will be singles
You know we actually know we're very close to it
We should do it ourselves
We lived in Los Angeles by then we loaded about trucks when we move to Atlanta Georgia why why Atlanta
We didn't have a reason
We really didn't
We decided Atlanta
By looking at a map
Insane
How about Atlanta
And we did it move to Atlanta put a flag in the ground we open
Turn it up a little office and called it laface records and we held auditions we would go on the radio and
Say Okay auditions are being held at the club Roxy yard or the Atlanta Knights or any of the night clubs and we will
Just hold auditions looking for talent
And before long the talent just came running
Because we were the only shop in town and it's nobody's you wonder why
People think of things like that and I did it and I did
Wildly successfully and I still don't know why we did it
How are you funding the business
We will work for hire so we will get paid
And we use that money to build a recording studio in Atlanta
As a record label we were funded by Eros the records
Which way is
The great Clive Davis
So they had look up with joint ownership
Yes we had a joint venture we brought the talent they brought the money
We made creative
Decisions in
We would bring it to them
For marketing and promotion
So
How did you learn how to run a company
Up until that point you were
Jamie was a two of you and you weren't here
You said you were a writer but like at this point you are
Your CEO
Yeah
It is I didn't know how to run a company but what I did know
What's how to manage
How did how did you know that
Because I was a band leader for so many years
Yeah and you know there's not very much difference
Between being a bandleader and being a
CEO of
Because it's managing tala
I won't say that I mastered it but I certainly do something about it
When I started
The company
And I figure the rest out
People who are summer
The biggest pains
In the world
Riley China goes there weren't bigger pains in the ass than the kids I went to high school
I mean
Imagine this I was at a very young age trying to manage people that were
Drug addicts
Are people who weren't particularly motivated
But maybe they had great talent
Or people who
Wer
Just difficult for the sake of difficult
And I did manage to get these people out of their houses
And onto a stage
So for me was always people management
It was never completely company manager
Tomatoes always people man
And I take it one meeting at a time
And one person at a time
How did st stephen the First
Like at the beginning
The first two years
That we had to label
Sharp learning curve
Who started the label in 1989
Our first signing
Was a band called Damian Dame
And we gave them our best material
And it didn't work
Like it's just nobody was stitches fell flat black people weren't buying the records we just thought you know we thought hours to record to fail this
Because we we thought we were perfect like
You know we could all these hits we have
So can't be the music it must be the production or the promotion I'm sorry
And Clive Davis said to me
Or maybe it's the talent
Yes they were
Berrytown
The people but they would not
World class super
Start
Level Talent
They weren't
Lake Whitney
So we learned pretty quickly that we needed
YouTube time better Talent
Did you feel like a failure after I mean cuz
You can put all of your
Effort into this
This is your first
Big test and you guys are sort of this
You know the successful Duo and then
Best thing to spike falls apart pretty quickly after you
Silent mode will you feeling like maybe this is not going to work
Maybe we're going to go out that it would work but I did
Have to think about a different strategy
So my strategy was
Wait a minute this isn't working let me think
What are we doing wrong
I said I know what
We should get a soundtrack
To a big movie
And we should put all of our artists
On it and we should put all of the talent
That we have relationships within the industry
We should ask them to be a part of it
I will use this as a launching pad for our label
And our new artists
So I dreamed up this idea Dennison. Now how do I put
Give me the movie
Need a movie
In a minute we're going to find out how La found that movie
I'm guy Raz you're listening to how I built this from NPR today with us
Hey bro I just quit thanks to two of our sponsors who helped
Keep this podcast going first
To Casper
Online mattress retailer the Casper mattress is designed and developed in the USA and engineered for
They use to Technologies latex foam and memory foam
To give just the right amount of sing
Bounce
A neighbor risk-free trial try out your Casper mattress for 100 nights
Free delivery and returns along with a special offer for listeners to this show
Go to casper.com
Gilt
And use the promo code built
To redeem $50 toward a Casper mattress
Terms and conditions apply
Exosuit to stamps.com
With stamps.com you can buy and print official US postage for any letter or package on demand
24/7
Right from your computer
No more trips to the post office and no need to lease an expensive postage meter
Sign up for stamps.com today to get this special offer
A 4 week trial plus Postage and a digital scale
Stamps.com click on the microphone and enter built
And one more thing before we get back to the show
We've been asking you for your stories about the
The things that
You are building soap
Please do stick around to the end of this episode to here
One of those stories
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros so it's 1991 and laface Records just had a major failure with one of its first bath
But Ellerbe thinks they can recover they can pull out of this
If they do this
One thing is a produce a soundtrack for a major Hollywood film
But of course
To find that film
So
He picks up the phone
So-called friend of mine her name is Cassandra Mills
Ship recently had a soundtrack
For a movie called New Jack City
I said Cassandra how do you find that movie how do you find the soundtrack
Tell me walk me through it how does that work
And she told me she said okay you have to go to the movie producers and have to go to the studios and just see what they say
Bellator releases look like
And try to attach yourself to one
I said okay that sounds like a lot of work and I know no one so this
Not going to go out really didn't have those relationships right living in Atlanta
And living in La working in recording studio at no salt
Yeah
So Cassandra callback
Eddie Murphy has a movie called boomerang
It's in production
Perfect for your labor
You should go and meet Eddie
They should meet the producers in the director Reginald hudlin and Warrington hudlin
And convince them
I said you know
Perfect
How did you get a meeting with him
I just called about the numbers I called their office and
I said hi this is LA
From LA and Babyface and we have a new record label called laface records and I'm sure you know as we produced
Don't Be Cruel by Bobby Brown and we produced this and that and
Yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
We can meet they were particularly excited
So happy I'm calling you
That was my
And I also learned that didn't work
So they gave you meeting and end you flew up to New York to go to New York and I met them
Were you nervous
No I wasn't nervous
I'm so goal-oriented
I'm going to get the
I have to get
What was your pitch that was your pictures
My pitbull is basically that your movie is a reflection of who we are as music people
We are all cut from the same cloth
We write the songs
That your audience wants to hear
You know I don't remember exactly what I said but Boyle I must have been good that day
Anyway so they said okay great
Now who was host
Who's Distributing your life
Innocent Clive Davis from Alistair Begg
They said okay well if you can get Clyde to come in
Will do it
So I call Clive and ask him when you come to a meeting with the headlands
Clive agree to do it
Came to a meeting with us Clive Eustis
His magic Charmin
We had a deal
And that was it
And how many artists of that point had you signed under under
Not many we probably had we just signed Toni Braxton with just signed TLC
And that was it and so you needed
Did to have enough artist to sing those songs but we had great relationship
Types of talent
And we went to Boyz II Men and we asked Boys to Men to be involved in
We asked Johnny Gill to be involved we have
Cuz you've been writing songs for these guys
It's already yes
And we put it all together
It became Boomerang was sold 3 million copies of the album
And
We launched
Toni Braxton
TLC
Offset album and we won Grammys with Boyz II Men Four end of the road
So that album was the launch pad for our Label laface records
Wow so you can
Really busy at this
Yeah now I'm managing
You know Kenny and I'm managing
The artist on the label and
The songwriters and the rappers and a managing the relations
Arister
And I'm also putting together a little staff and figuring that out and figuring out how to
Keep those doors open and keep the bills paid and
I learned
So what were some of the mistakes that you made
In a while your run
Was there any
You did
Take a look back on
I think that was just
Is really dumb or something to learn from that I'm glad it happened
Because I learn from it
I think I really ran into my difficulties
When Kenny and I decided to seller come
Eres Tu record
What did you decide to do that
I'd watch
Berry Gordy built Motown
And sell it
I'd watch this as a business practice
I watched David Geffen build record companies and sell them
So a part of my goal
From the very beginning was
The building asset
That we could sell
The idea was that we could make a lot of money by selling this company
So you know we got our Stewart agree to buy the company from us
And there was one stipulation
This was like the
Most difficult thing in life
Probably my entire career
The owners of our stuff they said we'll buy your label but you'll have to agree
To a move to New York
You'll have to replace Clive Davidson takeover hours to record
As its president
The sky was your mentor
And also
Arguably the most famous
Record Executives in the world
In the World Records who was it was that tents
Between you and him at all
We went through a very tough. We went to a very very tough.
And Clyde felt I betrayed him
NFL he'd ignored me
And ignored my opportunity
Cash in on
The work that we do
Done
So we both had
Issues were
Put each other before that it happened
Aren't you able to just have no it listen
Going to cash out and move on
Yeah
But that really wasn't
How it works
Because it wasn't an option for you I didn't want to move I mean I wanted to work
Yeah but I mean you could have cashed out and then gone
Started your own thing
Sort of but
The way it really works is
I'm the manager of the
The talent
And
What you're buying
Is really me
You're not just buying
Those records that have already been massive
Successful your buying
What do you hope to
The future will be
So
That's kind of how it work
How do the people that are so reactive
The people and arastoo
Clive loyalist
Didn't react favorite
Night of the any of the other record
Executives at the other labels or the media
All the artist community no
Active favorably
And being all of a sudden being in charge of Carlos Santana and Whitney
Career
Along with all of my laface artists
It was bittersweet
Because
3 years after I took over hours to record
We were
Wild
More so than we were at
My face what was that word that success comfort
What light from which artists
An example was
We had pink
Food sold 10 million albums
How did you discover
Pink was a great one
Sharon Daley was an assistant at our office I walked past her office
She's listening to a demo
I said hey what's that you're playing
She said I was just girls
Philadelphia
Turn it up
She turned it up
What's the weather look like she pulled out a picture and these three white girls
I thought they were black
Oh my God this is really mad
One of them Alecia Moore
With the outspoken lead singer
Who's about 16
But maybe 17 years old
And we signed the group
Based on hearing that demo
Walking down hall
And then once we sign them
I encouraged her to leave
The group and become a solo
And she left the group
Change the name to Pink
Become a world-class *
How did you like how did you identify her as the one
The band
That was going to be
That's just one of those things you know if I get if I have a gift that is my gift
I love Talon
By the way I'm not any difference in the public the public knows also man of a great artist comes on television or on the radio
Republic always knows Lady Gaga that's great right
So I think of myself as a super consumer I don't think of myself as a professional
I think of myself as a
Fan
And anyway something became a fix
Assassin
We had Usher who had a big
Assassin Outkast
Had the Monumental success they won album of the year
They sold over 12 million copies of their album
But at the height of it all
I got fired
Wait
But why
I'm doing many things
We were we were really successful
So it wasn't Talent are you hard you think your hard work
I don't know that I'm
Particularly deaf
I do believe that I'm very
Other people who have my
Job similar
Play cat Hustle
Look
If I'm in the room
With the other record exec
Pretty difficult did not notice me
20 years I've been the only black hat
So I definitely stand out in that respect you. That can be good and bad you know that's the reality of the world you know
And I am not
Playing any kind of a race car door complaining at all because I have a wonderful
Career and I've been supported
Both by Executives and by the talent so I don't say that as an excuse for
Getting fired
Maybe I just pissed somebody off
And the takeaway was
If I
Not sold my company
Then I wouldn't have gotten fired three years later because
I was the owner
How do you feel when when you lost a job like where you
I didn't get a chance to get upset was the weirdest thing I think in that moment
That I got fired
I felt like someone
Iceman
Ear
And I was
I saw Stars
4 sec
And as I'm writing down the elevator
You know from the skyscraper in New York City
And thinking about what just
To place again in my car
I call my lawyer
And I said you know I just got let go
He says yeah I know
Call you right back
You literally called me right back within like
A minute or two
He says okay Doug Morris wants to see you
He's the head of Universal Music
He wants you to come to his office right now
So I drove directly to Doug's office
That day you were fired
Call DET hour
And 40 minutes later I was shaking hands with Doug Morris and I become the vice chairman of the Universal Music
Within within minutes
Wow
And Ducks as you know I'm the luckiest guy in the world
They just let go of a great talent
And I'm so happy to have you
And Doug and I are still together today
So when you were fired from that was a
Period when you then
Went to Universal and indigestion
Stuffed animals where you
Usurp oversight
Zio versus Island Def Jam
Yes
Is that where you sign Rihanna
Yes Rihanna came to my attention through
I heard now manager Jay Brown who was an A&R guy at the label
He brought a demo to my office one night I usually work really late at night
And he played me to Delmar said that sounds really good get her here
He brought it to New York City auditions for me and for Jay-Z
Kjzi hired as
The president of Def Jam
We signed her on the spot
On the spot yeah it's always on the spot yet
Yeah I don't let people leave if I think you're going to be a big star I don't let you leave you know
Sometimes people insist they can I think about this then the answer is usually no
You can't you need to do it right now because the minute you walk out my door
And other record Executives know that you're talking to me and I'm going to sign you
You have 10 offers at your daughter next
So I can't risk
Yeah
Do you see you've you have
Foremost your career you
I've worked
With other beer companies
Store for bigger companies
Do you still work for a bigger so
The parent company now or right
But you still see yourself as an entrepreneur
Oh I think so
Yeah because I still do
Music publishing you know as an.
Napa Norfolk
But I'm also an entrepreneur for the
Major corporation
So you know the truth is
Maybe it's a little bit of my calling
To be a little bit
Both
Because
And I jumped at the Opera
Opportunity right or wrong
You know or whether I handled it well or not
Whether it was difficult or not I jumped at the opportunity
Become to work at Aeropostale
So I think there's something I liked
About the major corporation
It's something that they like about me being enough
Give a miss
Timbermist like sitting in a room and and writing songs for other artists or do you
Or do you like
Now just love the deal-making in the
You know the signing in the
Creating the artist and all that
I love it all I love
Theater of
Yeah I love it
Thousand moving parts
I'm keeping all the balls in the air
That's what I love I love music first of
Of course but I think I get
Great
From juggling
Like many many things
And making sure that they all
Land properly
You know that's what I like
Air traffic
How how much
Have your
Success in your journey from
Cincinnati in
Sick on the floor 2
Gun Indianapolis IN
Just hustling in in
And working
You know whatever money
I need to make to
The success you've achieved
How much of that is
Your skill and
Your intelligence
How much of it is
They say it's better to be lucky than to be
You know
I would have to say that
There were times that I was
Really luck
And then there were times that
I had
2B Talent
Right
So
I'm going to say 55
Ellie Reed he's have a seat
CEO of Epic Records in for 30 years in the industry he's still discovering new Talent
In 2014 against the instincts of most other record executives
La signed Megan
Trainer within a year
She brought Epic Records three top 10 singles
Places to show this week if you want to find out more or listen to pre
Previous episode
How I built this NPR. Org
Subscribe to our show on iTunes and please do us a favor and write a review let us know what you think
You can also write us directly at hidta at npr.org
Otis
Shows produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis
He also composed the music
It's also Geneva grandson has meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Because you know I'm all
Hey thanks for staying with us
Here's the part of the show where we share your stories about the things that you
You are building in this week
We are from a listener in Bend Oregon on 10th Sheridan
Owner of Wawa
While I tech company that makes very delicious coffee can says
Even though that coffee is instant and it comes in a little packet you don't always have the time
Time to grind your own coffee being able to just
Add Water wherever you are is
Pretty special in my opinion without compromising
The quality for
Even the highest coffee snob
It says that he's actually going for a flavor that tastes as good as a
$4
Pour over coffee that have a caramel sweetness nutty like hazelnut leather wet
Hyacinth pine needles go tropical fruit
Use coffee beans from specialty Roasters all across the u.s. and he wants to sell his coffee online but he's obviously not the
First person to try and make a really good
High-end instant coffee rhalic Starbucks
So there is competition out there
Another problem
Now that he's trying to scale-up he still has to work out his
Freeze drying technique when you pump it up in size and you have all of these variables with
Temperature and pressure
And when everything's in a vacuum is not so clear-cut
Can Sheridan hopes to have Wawa coffee ready to go by December
Audios is Kickstarter backers
1339 cups of coffee
Like you can and if you want to tell us about the company or idea that you're building
Go to build. NPR. O RG that's build with a d. NPR
. org
And thanks
Kiss another NPR Podcast
You will definitely enjoy cut all songs
What's considered as NPR's music
Discussion ended
Discovery podcast
Each week
Bob boilen and Robin Hilton share the best of the best new and upcoming music
You can download artist interviews live concerts in lots
And lots of songs you'll fall in love with
Buy new all songs episodes every Tuesday
Npr.org podcast
And on the NPR one app
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week