Support for NPR in the following message come from Pushkin and Des
Presenting the podcast against the rules
Michael Lewis explores the corrosion of fairness in America
And what it has done to our society mostly without our noticing
Listen to against the rules wherever you get your pot
Hey it's guy here just before we get to our next episode a quick request
Please do subscribe
To how I built this however you get your podcast with her iTunes
Google play or
Stitcher wherever
Please click subscribe and then every Monday
Go get the new episode right
Do your smartphone
Thanks
Have to be so very careful about who you discussion hard times with
Because those who love you and care for you the most like your mother like your best friend
Don't give you the worst damn advice in the world you need to get a job
The Florida sleeping bag
From NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
I'm Gyros and white Cathy Hughes refuses to take no for an answer
And how that helped build one of the biggest African American-owned businesses in the country
So you might have never heard of Kathy
He is but
The company she started
Radio one
It's the largest African-American owned broadcaster in the US and it now has
More than 50 radio stations and media Outlets
All across the US
Kathy didn't
Exactly stumble into this line of work
Screw up in 1950s
Omaha Nebraska
And even when she was little
She couldn't stop talking about
What it was
But you wanted to do
I wanted to be the first African-American
To have a syndicated radio show
I've had that desire since
I was 8 9 10 years ago out
But that's what you want to do for me
Childhood
It's so interesting
When I go back to the high school that I graduated from that every single solitary weeks in a note home to me
My mother saying she talks
Too much
Like I'm practicing for my future career
Eye of
Grew up in a household where there were six
One back
And I did my radio show every morning
In the mirror with a tooth
And no matter how many blows my brothers and sister with get old Heap upon my head when I finally opened the bathroom
So they can get ready for school
I never
Came out of that bathroom every morning
Until I finish my radio show
Everyone thought at that time there was something wrong with me
I mean
There are no black people in radio particular no black women cuz it getting remember we're isolated in the middle of the United
The 1950s
If it 1950s exactly
And so they thought I had a pipe dream by nuns at my school described it as delusions
Is a branch of
Tell my mother that she perhaps you see
Counseling for me because I had this vision
I being on the radio and people hearing me from coast to coast
OKC have a stream and a lot of people think you're crazy but you
I want to pursue it
But then
As a teenager I guess your
18 to get
First sexually
Experience
I'm in the doctor's office he tells me I'm pregnant as I couldn't be able to have sex one time
He's a hate to surprise you Kathy but it only takes one time.
Arranged it that way
Arrested Development
No question about it I went into a sadist a State of shock but I realized
That I had
Mission I had an obligation to someone greater than myself
And I was determined that he wouldn't be a black suit
Statistic
I was determined that he and I would not grow up in the public housing
That I have grown up in
I was determined
That he was going to have an opportunity which meant that I had to be very serious
Purpose
Why was still
Young teenager a child myself
Stop
Ricardo Medina
Support yourself and your inner child
Yes but I'm third-generation entrepreneur
So I grew up having to work in a family business
110 years ago my grandfather started
School after being the first black
To get his EDD
Comparable to a PhD
And my father was the first
African American to graduate from Creighton University with a degree in accounting
He opened up a tax service
And I was in charge of the Prentice Hall Ledger switch were all the tax regulations that changed every week
I
Typing
10 years old I was taking shorthand by the time I was
12 and having to be proficient at it because
I was a staff person
My family kept imposing upon me to come to work okay so even though you know pregnant
16 a mother at 17
Sounds like how did you do it financially while I was already working
And I was very blessed
I know I say this too young but there's this easy to be a teenage mama when the baby still in
Infancy
Because
All they do is
Go to the bathroom and sleep that's all they doing cry little in between
And so I could take him to class with me
You when you enrolled you enroll the University
Jay and I took him a lot of University of Nebraska at Omaha
I have put him right he be riding a carriage on the floor
Add but it became a problem once he got up and start walking
An Institute you work at like the College radio
Yes I volunteer to that radio
Station it provided a voice for us in Omaha
In the city that was
Severely sick
Datatel
I read that
The why you were there you met
Someone who
University basic
Change the course of your life
Yes Tony Brown
An African-American host
Tony Brown's Journal
Comes To Town
And you're wasting your talents in Omaha Nebraska
You need to be
Where you can really have an opportunity
Need to do
What you want to do what you do with radio
10 years later
He was offered the opportunity to establish the Howard University School of communication
He became the first Dean
And
He asked me if I was interested in coming to Washington DC
So you move halfway across the country we enter by guess for 5 year old son
At a point and
Find apartment and you start working to see that you did not know you had you got lost
I can't tell you how many times I would go out New York Avenue
And get lost or I'd go out at a street that it's name change Virginia some more
Try to get to Washington
Do you like this
Do you mean you come from Omaha Nebraska which one to tell you about a letter I wrote my mother
Yeah animated I told her that my eyes actually work
Retired at the end of the day
Staring at the greatness
The black people
I had never seen
So many wonderful people of
Color
Doing so many wonderful thing
I'd actually put in a letter to my mother that my eyes were tired at the end of the day of just staring
It was Elvis in all still am to be very honest with
I mean
There's no City like
Washington DC in the whole wide world come to the city
In the seventies for
The only whites
Buy thank you. People in charge
Academy told it and wait
During my whole generation in the nation's capital is Ali gotten better
I've gone from watching
Black Mirror get elected to watching a black president get the left
I guess you get to
Howard and
Decision
Radio station
Goes the sales manager
Play music at that time
Play jazz
One night
They did an 18 minute long
Piece of Pharoah Sanders
And I think he held the note the entire time
Okay
18 minute jazz song all you heard was this one
And I was like
I can't sell this
So your job was to find advertisers to f
Ties on house but also to help
Define
How the radio
Relationship Bistro
Annexation
Oh my God
Was it sounds like the kind of place
Because it was a mess
A young person like you an opportunity in your 20s
Could take it over absolutely and the fact
That then Dean
With a big fan
Of my work ethic
He said you need to see can you teach these kids how to work like you folks or Nebraska work
I always believed that rising at 4 a.m.
And then getting dressed and leaving
By 5:15 5:30 for the office that was just my lifestyle
And Stingley
I've have been reared
To believe the witch again so critical for entrepreneurs
That you don't stop
Based on what the clock says
You stopped based on the accomplishment of the task
Yuan
Cheer in DC with your son by the way how are you doing all this is a single mom
We have
Often times people ask me do I get if I had anything to do over what would it be it would be to have more children
It was easy with him remember I told you start off taking him to college with me
So
He had his first little tuxedo before he was at a great school cuz he was my date I took him everywhere
I had a sleeping bag in my office
We have dinner together we would do his homework
Then I put him in the sleeping bag until it was time for me to take him home
I didn't know anybody I didn't have anyone to leave him with
So what were you able to do at the station
At that time you get there as early 70s the first thing was to create straw
Guy realize that the first thing they needed was an understanding of the eye
Epidural
Community giving them
So how are you
The Quiet Storm
Tell me about The Quiet Storm
It was simply
Recognition of the fact
The city had a sizable population of single
Unattached
Human beings who
Still wanted to feel good about a Friday night or Saturday night
All they were missing
Was the entertainment so I structured
My format called
Quiet Storm
Sticks and stones
The basically was a 5-hour
Presentation
Of entertaining you at home by yourself and Company
With the selection of music
Before Hip Hop
If you were going to be successful in the world of black music you had to tell a story with your music
And so all I did was weave
Ghost stories to get
Oh
Sam Cooke
Carmen McRae the ballot
Basically
How did that show takeoff how did it become popular
Well I hit the right target demo
And I guess we should mention that
The audience's pradamalia
African American
Interesting Lee enough my first
Audience with
Escape predominantly gay
I put the first openly gay are personality on the are at Howard and almost lost the top of my head because
So the gay community
Absolutely love the quiet storm and then the black community migrated
Yes absolutely it was strictly Word of Mouth
And it went from like number 36 in the ratings to like top 5 and it when I left we were
Number three so you have this incredibly successful career at WHUR
You know I
I think I can do this on my own like no no not at all not at all
There was a group of investors called the Washington broadcaster
And it's 32 board members and investors they included some of the most distinguished
Black and white Washingtonian
They had tried for
Well over a decade
To get a
Signal that was dark back on the air
They've gone through millions of dollars and they could not get the signal
Only are they wanted to revive a radio station yes they wanted this dark signal they had lka Tabitha hits
They spent their money in all the wrong places
They approached me
And offered me
Double quit Howard University was paying me but more importantly they offered me the opportunity to
A station from the ground up
So these owners they bought the station and they hired you to run it
Yes
They hired me to get it on the air
Then they hired me to run it
Then they ran out of money today so they told me to shop a package for finance
And I said to them that that's not the responsibility of a general manager
Did I will do that
If you give me an equity position
In your company
And one of the members said to me
If you think that your
Smart enough to own a radio station you should do it for yourself we're not giving you any equity in our station
He was being facetious but I took it verbatim seriously
I was like oh my God
He was right I should do it for myself. I'm not exaggerate
It was like a charge went through me oh my goodness this person who's a multi-millionaire who I
I've been mired who's now probably in their 70s is saying to me here I'm Juno
Billy 30
That I'm smart enough to do this with them
And he's challenging me if I think I should own part of their station do it for myself
Thank you Lord I hear you I hear you I literally
Literally
Put all my papers in my case
If
Not walking
Skip down the hallway from the board meeting
I mean like what just happened
Did she have a nervous breakdown or something
I knew what I was destined to do
Cathy Hughes founder of radio one coming up the story of how she did end up buying a first radio station
The first of dozens and how is really days that she live literally lived at station
Listen to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible first to Hyatt
I believe the modern business traveler is changing the
The face of business
Please business Travelers don't settle
Refusing mediocrity there Reinventing their careers bending titles and breaking new ground
And because they change
Business travel is changing to
And that's why there's a place and a house
Good enough
Hyatt Place and Hyatt House hotel
You've come too far to settle now so book your stay today
Hyatt.com
Why settle
Thanks also to Prezi business
The better way to present
If you're tired of selling your customers using the same old exercise by Prezi business
Are the engaging interactive presentation platform that features built-in analytics cloud-based
Collaboration tools
And the unique ability to adapt
The flow of conversation
Perhaps it's time to update your marketing
Your professional reputation
With presentations customers will actually enjoy and remember
Schedule your free demo
At prezi.com
Slash built
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's late 1970s and caffe uses
Just walked away from her
Her job managing a radio station
How to restart a router
And she's looking for stations that are
App for sale
And she happens to find one up a black AM station in Washington DC
It has fallen on Hard Times
So
She decides to buy it
What were they asking for
$1000000
Wow this is like 1980 know this is 1978 we didn't get it till Taxi naso 19:7
Navigate to buy the license
The station
You have to come up with a million dollars how much money did you have in your bank account
1000 + 10
So that's what you had. That's what I had was anyone else
There was everyone at that time Senator Edward Brooke had just left the United States ended the first time since
Encino reconstruction date
He was a bitter Muhammad Ali was bidding for and everybody wanted to do our nation's where you were busy
The station again
The former Senator and Muhammad Ali
Yes
So how did you get it
I had
An angel
Dewey Hughes and I were married at that time and he at worked at the station
So when do we
Went to the owner and said
My wife and I would like to buy the station
He's at where the world are you going to get the money
Yashow
Where did you get them
Did you get a bankson
Yes 32 of them
32 Bunnell
30/30 lending Institution
And all of them said no
We're not going to give you a million dollars and you should because none of them have them
Exactly how you were
And all of them said no
We're not going to give you a million dollars
They asked me questions like that I plan to have any more children
They asked
Me if
Did not think that I was
It's too young to be doing just taking on that level of responsibility
They asked me questions
It had nothing to do more often than not
How did you go to
32 Banks
Rejected
Rejection
Show me the number I told you that my father was a CPA
I knew the
I knew that if I kept ass
I just had to
So how did you get the
Oh
Female Banker
Week on the job Lydia
Cologne
Chemical Bank of New
Said that she thought that her first loan her first week with
Puerto Rican and she probably guessed that it would be a male cuz she was for the
She said yes and I just kept by now
My
Presentation
Should have been taught
Oncologist
Kathy was flawless I mean after 32 times are perfect. Okay
I should have gotten an Academy Award I was so good at it I can't
Condensing
And she said something to me that I teach you all myself
Deeper she said
Please don't sell pass
Close
And I never forgot that cuz that was another one of those slap-in-the-face is I was like wow she's absolutely correct she said
I couldn't believe she is
What she said yes
I kept trying to convince
Can you get the money
Can you buy this
The station
Where was it
1680 Wisconsin Avenue part of Georgetown in the highest rent district of the sea
So that's why I moved into it
Wheatley sorry sir I lived in the radio station
I live there
You because I had to pay rent in Georgetown
And 1680 Wisconsin was then and still is a beautiful
Valuable diagonally set on the corner piece of property made it real convenient to go to work in the morning at waughtown
So you moved in there with your son and husband
I know I moved in there with my
Send by then my husband was like
Enough
I don't want to do this as your marriage
Fell apart absolutely the station brokers
The debt
Was just
Overwhelming for him kid never been an entrepreneur never having been in business before even
So it's just me and the kid
How many years did you guys
Junior Summer
Almost three
No
Number one that can remember the part of the story I told you that I was just in awe of Washington
See I'm in Georgetown I've been able to move back there yet okay during my struggling days
I had
A prime Corners you would see the president having dinner at one of the restaurants and you must have been under a lot of fun
Ankle pressure right
So how did you deal with it
When you have overwhelming Financial
Applications
The first natural
Human impulse
Sister hides to recoil not return the call
What would I have been trained to do
Is play offense
Not defeat
So I would call
And I would say
Play I know I owe you ten
All I have is
Is $1,250
I'm sending it to you
The token of good faith
That I will repay you every cent that I owe you but right now this is
Is all I have
And most of them
Said that
They had never ever interacted with anyone who let them know upfront
That they could not make payment
I think that is the reason I've never been foreclosed on I've never had to file for bankruptcy and thank God
God I have never had a paycheck bounced I've never had a business check
Nor personal check balance
Because I tried to stay ahead
Of the issue of not being able to pay the debt
Are you at people
Like we're depending on you
4 salary
I was running a 24-hour seven-day-a-week broadcasting for
Facility with
Full and part-time employees
14 of us
And you were one of the people who went on the only thing I don't know how to do a spider up the transmitter who had to go on the air
Because you didn't happen
And what did you do just opened up the mics
Start talking
Well it started off because
We did for they call
Formats
And we found out that what was missing in Washington DC
Was Newstalk
From a black perspective
Put that research did not tell
As you well know here hippie
PRS the most expensive format that you can do
All right music is one person
Play the music read the news to every
It's a one-person
Austin show
Music
When you talk about news
And our talk and information
Research is critical
There's always some
When your listening audio
And who knows more than you and just
Waiting in the cut
Oh no that's not good
Correct okay
You can't do it by yourself in this
Text format how are you able to
To run the station
Administer the state
Deal with the
Stress of all that debt
And raise a kid and
A show how many hours to show by the way
4 hours 4 hours ago everyday and 6 at 10 a.m. how are you able to do
Do all of that
Because it was exciting
But that's
When you said the stress
So the debt it wasn't
I had no.
Pay them
I used to brag
I used to brag to my lead investor syndicated communication
I will be the most profitable
Company in your portfolio one day and they were like yeah
Okay good
Great keep that dream alive Kathy
I used to tell them
You will make more money off me and Mike
When you've made off
Anyone now this is what I'm also telling them that I can't make my payment this month
If you think oh it's overwhelming
I've got all this
Sell anything I'm working 18 20 hours a day
Then it's too hard
You can't do it
But when you know
The day is going to arrive
When you're going to have enough money to pay everyone
That's what you have to
See in your mind's eye that's what you have to believe
Yeah I knew it I could feel it
And that's when I was in the sleeping bag cooking on a hot plate and washing up in the public bathroom in the radio
Rio station at 1680 Wisconsin
I don't it I knew it
I just knew I had to hold on
And when
You're starting off in business
Have to be so very cure
About who
You discuss your hard times
Because those who love you and care for
Are you the most like your mother
Like your best friend don't give you the worst damn advice in the world
You need to get a job
You shouldn't be sleeping on the floor in a sleeping bag
What type of environment is that for a child
Kathy was
The station
Profitable
Quickly
7 years
So what was it that made you
You guys profitable how did you get
Keep sweeping the
Floor ever
Date
To the best of your
TM 1 day
The world is going to
Say nobody Sleeps
The floor better than her
So it is that when you started
To to expand
Yes I realize that
I could not
Survive we just a little thousand watt 8
Did I had to grow I either had to grow or I have to go
In Richmond
Yes because
Our specialty is where turnaround artist
What they all have in common
Station Garden
We took the stress properties and turn them around
Because we could afford them
Did you get the money to buy them
Again if your lenders know that their money is good with you they give you more
All right
Lenders don't invest
And ideas everybody's got ideas
The invest in you
People loan money to the person not to the
The Disney hot to the idea
They have to feel good about you
How many stations
Did you eventually
Bye
Fake that we were up to think 35
So
What
Was the
Point where you sad
Let's go public
Let's make this and that you've 38.5 I did my son went to Wharton and got his MBA
And walking across the
The campus
Of UPenn
My son says to me
Do you still believe that we have to
Negro Largo
List of course I believe we got a girl Grace
He said we have to go potty
Because we've got a
Add
With the deregulation
11% of all radio stations in the United States of America are owned by one company
It's kind of hard to compete with your over here with two or three I mean they would come into a market they have five
5 Powerhouse radio stations with one format
Eliminated all the competition
So we knew we would that we had to grow into
We had to get much larger
So you had the answer yes we had to go public we had no choice
A lot of people to list it they didn't think that they would be a wise decision
For us I tried to discourage us we had a couple fall starts
But
It was the best thing that could have happened ad
The other thing that we have done
In our company as we stay in our Lane
We're not trying to open a restaurant
You're not trying to go into concert promotion we stay
In
The Telecommunications Indus
Soup at the height of a radio one how many how many stations did you guys actually have
75 stations which was the height when we bought
A package of stations from Clear Channel
75 that had never been done and urban broadcasting before were you able to retain a significant
Share of the ownership
Yes
Not just own but also the voting
Which owl has again been a blessing
The same syndicated Communications
37 years ago who sit down and showed me how to write my first business
They're still in business
With me
You haven't really talked about
Is is discrimination because
You must have
A lot of it
Not only is woman but
Is an African American woman
Yes one of the the issues that has always face
Entrepreneurs
Is
The
Lack of available
Capital
Them to go into business
Start to maintain their business
I remember
It was a bank
NDC rigs
And I had a big contract
But the payment
Who's coming in
And
It was so interesting because a black Banker
Of that bank said to me you would loan her $15,000
Where to buy a car
But you won't loan her $10,000 to make her payroll
And yet she has
The contracts showing that the money will be coming in
So often has been easier for entrepreneur to buy
A new flashy car and it's been
For them to meet payroll which is a tragedy of us not having as many lending institutions in our
BTS we need and want
It looks like I still
Which is
You faced all these challenges
And you kept
Going
What was it that kept you going
A belief in God
Because when you really believe in God
You can believe in yourself
As I said
Becky I quit my job
Not knowing where the next
Piece of money was going to come from where the next check was going to come from I knew that I would be sitting here today talking to
I believed it because I believe in the power
The Creator
And
I used to never ever
Give a speech or accept an award writing first
Thank God
And I still do but back then when I first started
They said to me that nobody's interested in all that religious I said that's not religion
That spirituality there's a big difference in my book
Between being loyal and understanding yourself in relationship to Creation
I have one last question
This energy this
Glow the
Destroy this
Passionate
Intensity that you
And in this unshakable
Belief
It will work out
Is it something that
You have
That is
Specific to you or do you think it's something
Definitely an acquired skill
If you
Allow yourself
To be bogged down and lose your enthusiasm
Then you're dead in the water
But if you remain optimistic
Cheerful and committed
To your goal
There's nothing that can stop you
Cathy Hughes the founder and chairman of the board of Radio One the company now has more than 50 radio station
Oceans across the country and Kathy son Alfred that little kid is a baby tuxedo who went to Wharton
He's now the CEO
Listen to the show this week if you want more or less than two previous episodes you can go to hell
Npr.org please subscribe to our show through iTunes
About it you can also write us directly at HIV T at
Npr.org
I'm sure this week is co-produced by run abdel-fattah and run scene Arab Louis also composed music
It's also Geneva Grant
Sounds Mexican poor and Jeff Rodger
I've got rice and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Here one it's sky here we have an app
At NPR that we really like it's really great and we'd love for you to
Try it it's called NPR one
And you can use it to listen to NPR news shows
And podcast and as you do it actually listens to you and figures out what you like best and then gives you more of that
So you can download NPR one now try it out
Find it on your app store right now
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week