Basically what happened is when we called the store
You know hey let's can I send you some more nope can't it's not selling and we would
Always say but you're not selling it to take note it's not selling and this happened
Time and time again and then after about 2 months it was like this stuff is taking up too much space I want it out of my sight
Ramen
The ark is how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they built
The story of how Melissa & Doug
Bernstein Delta multimillion-dollar toy company without ever selling a single screen
Video game or app
Okay so
If you have a small child in your life may be a niece or nephew or a grandchild
Maybe your own child
At some point in the next few days this time of year you
You will find yourself
In a toy store and you will be frantic
Looking for a new Transformer or
Shopkins
Angry Birds video games
Why you're doing that
You might stumble on
Toys made by Melissa & Doug Burns things are toys
They do not have to be plugged in or
Charged
Upgraded with the latest
Software
They're just simple old-fashioned toys affect things like
Wooden blocks
He said
Puzzles
Easels
And the company which is
Actually called Melissa & Doug
Was created
Melissa & Doug Bernstein
We're still dating back
In 1988
And the way they met
They were actually introduced by their parents
What's it like love at first sight
Instant connection
I think from Alyssa with love at first sight would be my guess
Ino it was very interesting because we are both very
Strong people
So I would say it was
Interesting yet contentious
Social what were you guys
Doing
Time in your life
You know I've always been a
Wild
Creative but never believed that
Could turn into a vocation
So of course
Instead of pursuing creative
Things I ended up as an investment banker at Morgan
What is a creative job in the world by the way did not like numbers because her
What were you doing
I
Was I right out of
School I was planning on going into education and I
Wanted to you
Work at a university
And
Right when I was getting ready to do that
And head off into it
Career in High Ridge
Educational
Got a call from a person I work Summers Ford
Jim McManus
One of the
Greatest mentors greatest marketing people in the world and
Mr McManus said nope you're not doing that you're going to come work for me and be my
My assistant be my right-hand and so I went there right after
School work for mister
McManus for a couple of years and had
Incredible
Experience
But it wasn't what you want
It wasn't something that I wouldn't want to do I'm like Melissa at her invest
Banking experience
But no but there was something inside me that tugged and wanted to
Things one wanted
To do something
4 children frankly wanted to
Do something of my own
Creation also
Wright suits
What did you do
Well we
Booked ourselves into a little
Bed and breakfast in Lenox Massachusetts I think was called the cliftwood
And we walked ourselves in the room
And
Did what everyone would do if locked in a room in Lenox Massachusetts and brainstorm business ideas
We literally said let's close this door and we are not leaving this place until we know what our path is
What we're going to do what was the idea you came up with in that hotel room in Lenox message
I think we walked out of there knowing that we wanted to start by doing some
Interactive
Products for children things that they could really
Interact with rather than be
Passive recipients
So okay so you get back to West
Report Connecticut and like what did you do
Within a week's
Quit your jobs
We did
We determined that this is what we were doing we literally took our
Savings account
Put them in one joint account which was nothing but meager
At best
And we
Decided we were going to use those funds to
Create our first product at this point
Melissa
Are your parents regretting that they introduced
That's funny that you
You say that
And I would have to say
My parents
We're scared to death
I bet I remember when we were in Melissa's kitchen and we were right
Talking about doing this I remember them being
Concerned
Say because
She had the greatest thing going
And
She was leaving it to do well we weren't
Two serpents jacket we were going to do
No problem
You know they work as as
Depression-era
People they were just very fearful
Worried
About Sakura
Whereas
We couldn't have been less work
We felt like it
Warrant living out
Your passion and
Wanting to go to work at
Everyday running to work everyday
Then it didn't matter how
Zoe
She was got this like
Small amount of money in
And
What's the product
So what we decided to do first
It was
We both had
A little bit of it
Experience with
With
Television
Programming
And we decided that we wanted to make
The program
For children
That would be groundbreaking in that children wouldn't
Sit there and
And watch it
They would actually participate
The program
And so we literally
Rote
Scripted
Produced
Directed
Cast
Wrote music Melissa song
Sweetest Thing lyrics
Like a VHS
Video
Ultimately
Three of them do what you were
You like eating
You were on camera
So we wrote a script for this
And
We literally went around to stores and
Parks and we cast real children
We didn't want the
To be
Contrived or fake
We didn't go to
Casting age
We literally would
Would sit in
Grocery stores and look for animated children
An approach language
Probably
Today
We literally in parking lots would watch
Apps for children that are interacting well with their parents and we had eight children that were in this V
Video and then we shot it it some
Friends houses
Westport Connecticut
From schools
Kids singing was it dancing yes and yes it was singing it was dancing
And it was
Encouraging children
Who are watching this
Participate along
Was literally teaching them some of the songs
Teaching them
What were dance
Dancing to talking directly one of the things that was so unique about it is
The boy who led the
Programs
Talk directly to the kids at home and
Truly
Befriended them in a very
Honest and
Insincere way
Do you remember if you remember any of the songs
My kind of girl
Go ahead most thing it
Ready
Special friends special friends we will be special friends
That was like the the emotional one at the end
But the others were very
Dooby dooby all sorts of making sounds with your body make
Sounds with your lips
How much money did you guys
Sink into
Because at that time it was not
Cheat to make films
What's a lot
Probably
I think all told the first one we probably spent about
30 or $40,000
To produce
Well it did it took all of our savings and then
Finish this we said wow this
This is awesome
And then we looked at
Each other
We'll wait what do we do with it
We had put
No thought at all
Into what do we do with this product
We now have to figure out well how
How are we going to be no pay for the next
Lunch and and what are we going to do to get the
This product out there
So
Do you make
But thousands of copies
To start the salad
So we did and we got our first little lessons in business
Because right
You want to make some copies and
Can you find out
Well we won't make
Four copies we
U5000 copy
And we said what in the world are we going to do with 5000 coffee
Please we made list
Silver relatives and that didn't get us fully to 5000
And so we literally bought a little
Combination television VCR player
Put it in the back of my father's station wagon and we started driving around
Knocking on doors of retailers
And the funny thing was this was right around the holiday
Play time when we
We finish this product
And so all the little
Mom pop toy shops throughout the New England this was there
Busiest time of year and we would walk in there and apologetically carry in our
Tape player in our TV and put it on their counter and beg them please can we just show this to you please
And I think after enough begging the
Figured out the only way to get us out of their store was to
Take a few of these and present them to their customers so we would leave
Very happy that they decided to take a few of these
Tapes and try to sell them by the way this was another thing that was completely against
What was happening in the end
Because
As a manufacturer you never went directly in
You actually
We had middle
Call call Daniel
Raps
Who represented your product
But we
Realized that if we used one of those
I mean they would never do R1
Tiny little product Justice
Hundreds and thousands
The products
And that if we
Wanted to get our product
Truly distributed
That we were going to have to do it or
So our sales
At the beginning
People were not buying these
He's from the stores
So they were baiting in the stores and they were remaining on the shells which is not good for long term
Business proposition so we learned
Yet another few business lessons
One was
What we learned
Are packaging was interesting because
You looked at it and you had no idea
Idea what the
This product was
I called the mysteries in a box
When you have something that is in a box
And you have no idea what it is and you're not
Promoting it on TV or advertising it
It's very hard
And the second thing we learned was that for something new like this you need to help
Seed some knowledge
Support about it
It's so Melissa and I then started
All of are we
Weekend driving back around
Restores all throughout the
Connecticut New York
New Jersey map
Chusetts
And we would have play dates in their stores
And we would sit down in a carpeted area
The store
Songs with children weeaboo
Hope and pray that they would be one child their two children they are in
Maybe they would tell a couple of friends
But it sounds like
I mean not to be like
Cruel or crude but like
Become a failure
I would say it depends on how you do
Define the word failure
Because it probably was a failure in terms of
Having a product
The instantly salt
And instantly with
Successful
Yet it was the biggest
Success we ever had in that what we learned from that and all the learns came from that are
Precisely every single thing that are busy
Toothpaste on today
Tumblr
What's the point you know
The idea of having direct relationship
With all these customers
Doing anything that they want it I mean they would call us in the middle of the night
Problem with one of your tapes
The phone was on her bed we would answer
In the middle of the night
Everything we do today we learned I would say in that first
First couple of years and frankly
Maybe most importantly
Just the fact that
Not everything is going to work perfect
So at this point where you guys called Melissa & Doug
Your company
We actually
Weren't
Our first
Company name
We called ourselves
Lights
Camera interaction
And the reason
The companies called Melissa
It's funny
Because
Weed from day one every
A single product we made we were signing our name
And we were riding on the back
Activate if you have any comments for us
Please call us at
Melissa & Doug
And so as we started to get more more products out there people would call our company
We would answer
The phone or someone would answer
The phone and say
Lights camera traction
I'm sorry I have the wrong number I was
Melissa & Doug
And so one day we said well wait let's just answer the phone say home listen dog
And that's how we became listen
4 alarm
One or two years in we are three years into it at this point so focusing in Thailand video
The first one
Basically it was a video year we produced a video year 4
3 years we got 3 videos out there in relationships now with I'd say probably
I'm going to guess a couple thousand
Retailers
So how did you like move from
Videos to
Toys
Have you like start to think
Start making
Well honestly like most things it was another Brain Stew
We were talking
In the car about
Some of our favorite child
Toys and
We're talking about on Pat the cat
Pat the bunny yeah right oh yeah
Of course books that had
The Tactical
I'm pieces on them to touch women
Pat the bunny
Thinking about exactly
And we said
I don't know
What made us a at but we said well wouldn't that be
Great in a puzzle
Could do
A tactile puzzle
And
We brainstormed
Not having a puzzle that had animals
And that the
Height of each animal was
A piece of plush that had the
That animal in the look
And came up with this idea for what we caught a fuzzy puzzle
And
Uno
How to design a puzzle in where to get a manufactured and
Produced in
Where where did you going to begin
I would say for most of the things that have happened along the way we had no idea
And we learned as we went and we would
Almost the way you were asking the question now we would ask ourselves the question then so
So wait a second
We need animals
Artist
How do we do that so we went to the library
Are we looking at
A lot of children's books
Look for illustrators that we liked and we would
Contact illustrators NYC who might want to help illustrate this
I'm in
Each step of the way was
You know a new
New face of learning but at no point was there ever
A a magic answer or an easy answer with lot of
Making mistakes and falling down and
Some
Some horrible learning experiences along the way
How did you guys
Find your
How are you able to like
You know pay for the manufacturer
Puzzles
Take loan to
Cosecant investors
You know this is why we grew rather slowly
We wanted to be
Be self-funded
And we lived incredibly
Frugally
For at least 3 years
We ate
Ramen noodles which were $84 and
Turkey hot dogs
On a hot plate
About 50 cents a meal
And we live
With our parents for a few years
Until we
You know
You literally get one room in someone's home above their garage
And helping with errands for
You know what
Decrease in rent
And we've been Outfield every cent
That we made back
Into image what I would say we we literally were not we did not take
Take money out of
Career that
Like the fuzzy puzzle
Were you able to sell it
Oh gosh I wish it were that easy
Not quite not quite like that so now so so once we had the design for
The puzzle I mean everything again was
Trial and error but I could tell you one of the things that happened early on was the very first time we went to a very large
Toys
Show
Where you would exhibit
Two retailers and show them your products
And the agent who we hire to help us make our puzzles had a
Display setup just down the hall for
With our exact puzzle when he was selling who's basically
Selling your puzzles as
His own
Yes he was
And this is someone that we had a
Entrusted and he told us the reason was because
We wanted to
Grow slowly and bro with r are independent neighborhood stores
And he wanted us to immediately take them and put them in the mass-market and
And because we didn't want to do that he figured he would just do that on his own with our Prada
So that was his good reason
For doing
So
I'm just curious like
Your reaction at that moment was
To go to say what are you doing
What's going on
Did you confront him
No we weren't confrontational about it we ready
Huge show thousands of customers
And when they came to us
And they started to tell us at
This is what this person was
Was doing
And they assume that we were part of it or that we knew was going on when they found out the
The truth of what was going on
It was amazing how many customers
Just came up to us
And literally
In front of us
Ripped up orders that they had
Had placed with this
Person who was our aging
Since I hear you
You can show this to him
Now that we understand what's going on we will absolutely never in our life
Time Warner anything for
Fat person
I think that gave
A little glimmer of hope
Blessed myself
While on one hand we had a little bit of an exposure to the
The darker side of the business world
I would say simultaneously we had a really nice exposure
To that there are a lot of
People out there who
Will appreciate
The Loyalty that you have to them
And everything that we
We've done to them and
The first couple of years
And are now saying to us
We don't care even if he wants to
To sell it to us for
Less money than you are anything
I think it doesn't matter we are loyal to you for everything
I'm guessing you guys were able to
To recover from
Like move on with puzzles
I guess
We we started to see our way you know it's always about right finding the path through the forest and it was like
This was the category that
Sort of was our path we said oh my gosh I think we're onto some
When we come back in a moment
The story of how Melissa & Doug Ruby on puzzles
And then made the biggest investment of their lives
It's not a toy that became a million-dollar
Mistake
And I was listening to how I built this
VR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible first to Google and Squarespace
For making your business official
When you create a custom domain in a beautiful Business website with
Squarespace
You'll receive a free year of business email and professional tools from Google
It's the simplest way to look professional online
Is it squarespace.com Google
Start your free trial
Use avocado
Build it
For 10% off your first purchase
Google and Squarespace
Make it professional
Beautiful
Thanks also to Goldman Sachs
Insights from some of the world's leading thinkers on markets Industries and the global economy
Affirm podcast
Exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Does your discussions
Topics with far-reaching implications
Climate change
Autonomous driving
And the future of China's economic growth + much more
Best exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on iTunes Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
At a gs.com
Slash pocket
Paint one more quick thing before we get back to the show
If you're feeling a little anxious about these
Times we're living in
Spell do I have a podcast for you
It's another show I host it's called the TED Radio Hour
This week our show is all about
Reconciliation
Ideas about
How we might be able to come together even when it's
Feels impossible
So if you're interested check out the TED Radio Hour by visiting NPR. Org
/ podcasts
ITunes or however you get your podcast
It's how I built this from man
NPR
Gyros seoul
This point it's
The mid-1990s
Toy company Melissa and Doug
Is literally
Just Melissa & Doug
Two-person operation
Melissa designs all the
Puzzles Doug
Try to get them into
Stores
But then they decide to start making
Other toys
You know all these made up until that point
Apostle
And we look backward at what was
Wonderful
And incredible from the past and we saw wooden toys that category and we said
Okay here's another category wooden toys
Wow really expensive
Completely inaccessible
2 average
People
The aesthetic
Very
Unapproachable
Two kids not very playful
And here's a category that we can go in and we can
Really really
So at this point like
Kids are playing with plastic
Play toys and battery operated toys and envy you guys thinking we're going to be the anti
Battery Toys
We're not going to do that
So we thought it was so
Interesting that every toys
Was chasing
Running forward right chasing the hottest fads in
Trends and hot license
Was like
Get out probably Cabbage Patch dolls and TV advertise toys and a lot of sort of hot toys
And that was
Kind of the market
And we
Saw in this
Experiment with puzzles that ended up working we saw
Oh my goodness
People actually still want
Things that are nostalgic
Make them remember their past but they don't want them Dusty
And like they found them in some old attic
They want them
You know injected with Pizzazz and brought to
So what did you say to me
What are first line was about
A dozen basic
Basics reinvent
Pounding and sorting and stacking
Manipulating
Alright land blocks yeah yeah
And doing them at
Incredibly low price points
And
Packaging them in a way that I've never been package with a package or designing all of this
Samosa
Yes
It's all made out of like
Plastic
Or would
I mean
50% of what we make is still wood
And then
Other materials we use a lot of metal
Use canvas
But mostly not
So at this point are you guys
Do you have an office
Do you have a place for
We working at up or are you sick
This is still just a
Truview orders now do not have some employees
Heights at this point we probably had a couple of part-time people that were helping us we have
So we have a person who's coming up on his 20 years this year
His first job with us was
A mix between helping us
Change our baby Brandon's diapers
Helping us weed the driveway
And also when trucks would come
Deliver products to our house he would help us unload the truck and load the products in in
Help us pack up
Products and ship them
So when you really like transitions from puzzles to wooden toys
You're still just selling them mainly in like
Small
Start independent stores in New England
Yes
What is time we ate expanded Beyond New England but definitely the small
In stores we were
Firmly convinced that that
Was the only way we could really get our products out there
So I mean sound like
You guys are not pretty steady path
And did you make any
We have actually never made a mistake it's the
Craziest we have had so many failures that's why we love that word because
Failure is a word you have to get comfortable with and you can't
Fear the failure
So tell me about some of what were some of them
So behind my desk
I have
About I can't even fit them anymore maybe 500 toys that were all my very favorite
Toys that failed in a big way
Some of them entire categories because
Everyday I want to remind myself when I
Come to work and come to my desk that the line between success
Send failure is as fine as a spider web and you really never know what were some of the
That didn't work
Oh my gosh so many but one of the lines that we were most excited about and I think was a
Huge investment with a line called puzzle world
And it was an entire world
Made out of puzzle pieces
Not only horizontally they connected to form a base but you could build up vertically and don't skyscrapers
It was the most amazing
Line ever but also our most elaborate undertaking and above more to Lenny Moore Machining it was
Far our largest Endeavor ever hear of development play tables and it was very expensive
And costly to buy inventory because unlike other products the retails were about 30 to $100
Forceps they were sold in sets
It was not
And we had all our prototypes
Which took us over a year
To create and only brought it to Troy fair and had our play table out and the reaction
Was actually incredible the best ever of we have I believe we have
Had a thousand assortment
And we literally by the third day of toys are we sold out
But we made it clear to our retailers
That this was going to be a big undertaking for that because
This was not an item that was TV advertised
It was expensive part understand
And it was going to take a lot of education on their part educating their cuss
About the merits of this but we told them
If they do this it will be an annuity
They walk
Have you know years and years
Of the selling and generations by more sets and will create more
Jessica each set connect
Get to the other side it was all interconnected and it even connected to the popular Railway sets at the time the Thomas and the bre
Rio so it connected into
Any existing
That you had as well
And they agreed and we
Turn it out
Do you want to
Oh Sherrie she
But not tonight she tells all the exciting gray part it all came back to us
Warehouse receiving it all back that was my role in what happened people just didn't buy it
Basically what happened
Is when we called the stores two weeks later you know hey let's can I send you some more
Nope can't
It's not selling
And we would always say
But you're not selling it
Delete a note it's not selling
And this happened time and time again
And then after about 2 months it was like
This stuff is taking up too much space
Case I wanted out of
At my store but it just didn't it just it never took off
The stores never got behind
I mean I think it had the
The potential to
But it's hard you know it's
It's hard to run a store and you have thousands of products
And you have lots of
Competing interests and here we are thinking
Well you'll just focus on our product
It reminded us that there's a higher burden on us
Because we take our products
Really person
When we think that everyone in every day is going to
Take all the time too
Explain everything about it the way that
We the inventor's what
And that's not always the case that can't be done
So we realize it
Our job
It's our job
To design it in a way that
Today's forecast
And that's really what
We started to do a
Do you know when they like how do you know when a toy is going to work
It's amazing you know really
I mean we don't have nowhere nada
I hit driven company
We joke that we have a lot of singles and doubles
Guido
Really want home runs because we don't want it here today gone tomorrow we're in Evergreen company we want our
Forever
Even when she's working at a product in the new Star owned
Test laboratory with our six children at home is always
Using rrr products with their own children
I would say the initial ideation I mean you're obviously feeling a good God that you're you have an idea that's going
Going to work and then throughout the process we do a huge
Amount of
We call it Mom test
Mom is synonymous with
Caregiver dad
You know anyone who's
Playing teacher
I am we get
A good
Sense as we're going through
The process but the truth is that's the
Joy of it you never know
For sure at all and there's surprises everything
Single day
Because
You start this company in 1988
10 years really
Before
The internet starts at
Take off and there was no reason
Why would a
Products and analog toys
So unlikely in fact every reason why they wouldn't
See you then and I think that's been a part of you note
Except we have a
Model
I think that's been a part of it all long is
To not go with the tide not go the direction not look at things
That's what everyone is doing that's what we should do because our feeling is always
If we copy
Every good model out there
At very best what does that mean
We're going to be mediocre
By definition
Because we are simply following and copying whatever one
Elsa's doing
Was there ever a point though so when I don't know like investors or somebody
Since you guys like you got to do something with batteries we've got to do something that
You know
Electronics or something
They say to us every single tag
That that's
And you know that is
One of the things I think that has kept us successful is we stayed true to Mission you know
Ever since we started with our very first puzzle
Did this on your own for pretty much until it
You are
A successful company
But I guess
Just a few years ago you decided to to
To see outside
Investors correct significant ownership and we brought in
Some investors who now will
Will sit on our board and
Participate very
Actively with us also
Helpful because the truth is for the first 20 years
We really did this without mentorship
You know it was literally was finding her own way in a very dark room
What did the entire investment allow you to
To do as a company
Well I think
Two things one is they have
Rolodexes that are much larger than ours and in
Introduce us to Folks at
Can help with things and then financially also
Frankly Freedom 2
Grow and expand more exponentially if we want to
Expand our footprint internationally and so
Open up those doors to
I'm curious how
Did you guys I mean obviously if you got I mean
Oceans obviously
But it seems
Like you have a great relationship
And
Your great business partners but also a great
Kapolei parents if you got kids as well as he can
What's 6 kids that right
Yep
You were just trying to just trying to figure out how many kids she was going to stay with her first
Oh I was going to say
If you considered a child
Six children and then.
Stupid like honestly
Is it all I can Blissful and joyful and laughing ORD were there moments of tension between the two of you
You mean this morning or in general
It's a combination
The good news is that we
We absolutely do have things that we disagree on which is good and which is healthy
But I would have to
To say that I think we have
Our respect and admiration that that keeps it working
Quickly
You know both from a business and a person
I mean in terms of
The business we never would have been able to make it without it
I mean this is
Absolutely
A partnership and a partnership is necessary to go through everything we've gone through I mean this
Although it seems Blissful and easy
Are the 28 years has not been easy and we have faced every challenge imaginable and it goes on and
John everyday Melissa & Doug Bernstein run the toy company
Melissa & Doug the company has grown from just the two of them to almost a thousand employees
With revenue of more than 350 million dollars a year and they still make
Lots and lots of puzzles remember the letter puzzle you take the letter out and see
Says that the Puget Sound of the letter and
For some reason one or two letters weren't in the Right Slots
I fall asleep in my kids room with him
And I know and I just heard
Jay
Where's that coming from Over the sensor
Is that what this is all about you want to reply to do you want a replacement for that
You need to sleep tonight
Listen to show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous
Episode
You good how I built this
. npr.org
You can also
Subscribe to our show on iTunes and please do us a favor and write a review let us know what you think
Castle right to us at Hib tea at NPR. Org
And if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
Shows produced this week by run abdel-fattah with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to leave a grant
Sanaz meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Gyros and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey thanks for sticking around we are at the very end of the show which means it
It's time for you to tell us about the company's
Is your building
What's 1 kilos from Paul kaster he's from Kansas City Kansas
And his company is called
Crooked Branch
Studio
We specialize in handcrafted wooden bow ties
Handcrafted wooden bow ties are actually
The wooden bow tie is just like a pre-tied fabric bow tie except for
This all started for Paul about a year ago when a friend gave him a wooden bow tie is gapped gift if your
Woodworker and you're a preppy guy in high school
But as a woodworker I kind of saw all the flaws in the design
So Paul decided I can make a better wooden bow tie one that actually looks
Less flat and more like real fabric
Soapy set up a shop in his basement at home
And he started selling the ties on Etsy the greatest compliment that I ever get is
I didn't know that was a wooden bow tie
And I got that one couldn't even tell
Call has an entire line of bowties now and he figured out how to get wood from all over the world
Maple
Sherry by the way
Tall is
17 years old he's a senior in high school
There are
Some days where it's
Just really crazy
Inside what I do is I come home at 3 from
High School
And then I work till 8 or 9 and then I study from 9 to midnight
And then
Do it again the next day
Paul says his company has made about
$18,000
And profit
He's even hired two friends
And
Is Mom she works part-time for him making the neck straps for the ties
Okay my mother yes
About 15 to $20 an hour
This is a real family business now
Call plans to go to college next year and he says he's going to run his business from his dorm room but he says
He's already learning
It's been
The greatest learning experience
I can almost say that I've learned more from this than I have for my school in the past year that's podcaster from Kansas City Kansas is company
Please called Crooked Branch Studio
And if you want to tell us about the company or idea you are building
Go to build. Npr.org that's
Build
Npr.org
And thanks
As the end of the year approaches a lot of you've been asking about the best way to support how I built this
So for 12 thank you for asking
And it is pretty easy to do
You go to stations
Npr.org
Find your local station and you make a year-end contribution or even better
You've become a regular monthly donor and when you do please tell them that how I built this
Sent you
Find a local station at stations. Npr.org
It takes like 2 minutes it's
Totally tax-deductible
And I please you tell them
How I built this NPR
Again that stations that npr.org
Thanks
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com