Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
My favorite quotes is if you want to understand and study the juvenile delinquent
Cuz it's cuz they're saying you know this sucks I'm going to do it my own way and that's what they all say
They just say this is wrong I'm going to do it this other way and that's the fun part of business actually
I love breaking the rules
Ramen PR
How I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists the stories behind the movements
Lego
How far from pounding hot metal in a converted Chicken Coop to sounding the outdoor
He says he does not want
Got your money
If it isn't that kind of entrepreneur who's going to wow you with a PowerPoint presentation or a
Snappy elevator pitch
He's basically a surfer a kayaker in a mountain climber who sort of stumbled into the role of businessman
So pretty
How can I say this
Eccentric
In the best possible way
If I never had any interest
Becoming rich
Actively work to slow down patagonia's growth in
Profit margin
Despite his best efforts to keep it small
This little clothing company he started 50 years ago
Has turned into a huge business
Well I never intended this
It's just
I just have this
Snack that every time I look at
Product guide
I look at it nice
You know I can
It could be better
So every time we went climbing
We come back with ideas on how to improve the climbing gear which is very crude enough
And so
You know I became a blacksmith
I've taught myself blacksmithing so that I could make
Some of the
Climbing Hardware that I thought would be better than what's available you're literally like pounding
Hot pictures of metal into shape
That's exactly right you don't do nothing
Parents backyard then my father
Help me convert a chicken coop into it
Hello shop
Well as making the anal pitons metal spikes that you pound in the cracks and I was making the Caribbean
Snap blankson
Target
Yeah cuz I mean at that time mountain climbing was still
It wasn't a huge commercial Enterprise
No they were probably
The climbers in the country cow
Yeah
And all the gear came from Europe in and it was pretty poor quality
Like the pitons were made to be used once
Because Europeans looks at
Climbing
Conquering mountains
And you just leave all the gear in place to make it easier for the next group
And we were brought up
Another philosophy of John Muir and
And also throwing
We felt like nature should be left alone and
You should do a climate but leave nothing behind
And so I made pitons out of better materials
Put in and take it out
And used over already
It was a lesson in
And quality I think because
Dear P&P towns were selling for
$0.15
What's a piece
And mine word dollar and a half
And I guess you just for like 10 or 10 or so years
Yeah
Were you doing well
Well yeah we had 80
Percent of the market
And anyway I guess you had no intention of ever making it that right
No not at all right I didn't respect businessman I had no interest
Business whatsoever I was a Craftsman
But you know we were making
Are they any money
We're making about 1%
Prophet the end of the year we're basically paying ourselves
By the hour so how did you guys Branch out from
From climbing gear to clothing
Well I was on a climbing trip to Scotland in the winter
I was walking by some shop and I saw a rugby shirt in the window
Watch pretty cool so you know as real colorful head
Blue and red and yellow
Made really tough
So I thought this make a really great shirt
Climbing
You know the caller
Can I keep the gear slings from cutting your neck and you know at that time
Active Sportswear for men
Was basically Gray
Sweatshirts and sweatpants
That was it. Men did not wear either
Colorful
And so I started wearing this
Climbing and everybody was going wow
Where'd you get that
So it's kind of Lights came on I thought well maybe out of
Import a few these from England
And see if she'll sell and sure enough they sold
And then I started making some climbing shorts
Pantsing
One thing led to another and I realized
More profitable than making
Pitons
How did you come up with the name Patagonia
Well in 68 I did
6 month long trip
From California down to
South America
We drove
What time does surf don't let me down
Jocose
Downtown Lima and then sold a surfboards and then climb volcanoes down at southern Chile and
Skeet off of Ammon
I kind of fell in love with that area
Patagonia
You know on those days nobody even knew what
Patagonia watch
Kauai
Timbuktu
You know how many people know where
And so I decided to call it Patagonia because
I wanted to make clothing for those kind of conditions
Cape Horn
Like super high winds cold
Crazy temperatures change in weather exactly
Is it is it like
You did not know anything about clothing
Here right I didn't know anything about closing I learned everything by
If I get an idea immediately take a step 4
And see how that feels if it feels good I take another step
I feel bad I step
You know it's different than people with a scientific view or they
Take everything out to the Instagram before they make a move
So I I learn by just doing
Either one of the first products we made it was a pair of climbing shorts and
I made the pattern for it
I knew nothing about powder make I just took a pair of
Shorts apart and I kind of looked at it and I
And I wanted you to make a really tough pair of shorts so I use
Canvas from
Outdoor furniture
Palace Korean woman
Working for me and she had to show it on a walking foot machine which is the kind of sewing machine.
Used for
Sewing leather cuz
Fabric was so II
And when she was done with him she stood him up he stood straight up
So we need them stand up shorts and you know it took about 50 Washington to break him in but
We still make those shorts but
Of course not is the heaviest
They were
It seems like
Your
Main motivation was to just make stuff that you would want to wear and use yourself but love
Nobody's making stuff good enough
And you were just sort of like I guess I have to break it
Yeah you know I I I used to do every
Conceivable sport
And then the people that work for me where all sports
Also we knew
What we wanted
You know what I heard somebody say that
You wait for the customer to tell you what to do you're too late
So we were our own cuss
And I think that was a secret
Coming out with products
A lot of products people didn't even know they
They want it or need it
When you start to do this
And you have to hire employees and you have to form a company and you had to
Deal with payroll like the back start to scare you
Oh yeah
Yeah that was pretty scary and we made a lot of mistakes
And in fact we were so successful in the
Ladies
We were growing too fast we're going to 50
80% of here
And now you can't do that for very long before you
Run out of money basically
On retainer nanjing
And so we were also
Ramped up to Griffith
80% and we only grew
25 hours
Which doesn't sound bad but when you build all the inventory for
Her that
You don't make it
It's pretty rough and then there was a recession down and and the banks wouldn't give us any more money in fact
I had to lay people off with
Was really hard because we're
Family
Style business
I knew everybody working there
That was really tough
DJ moments
During those periods
The ups and downs where you thought
Patagonia might fail
Oh absolutely
We didn't know where they were going to make it or not we couldn't get any loans from anybody
My accountant
Introduce me to some Mafia guys who understand me
Some money at 18%
Interest
Which I turned down but
What day does this is we got some personal loans from
Some friends and pretty much
Fired some management that got us into this problem and turn things around
Why do you think it happened was it just bad luck was it
The economy or was it
Wizz Air
A strategy that didn't align with
We were just going for girls
You know not saying no
It's just
Broski
Creep up on you I mean we were just opening more more dealers or Opening Our Own retail stores
You know nothing goes forever
And the fact that's why the faster a business grows the faster it dies
And so once we got out of this we decided to
Put ourselves on a
Growth
Program so that
We would be in business a hundred years
So all decisions
Then on were made as if we're going to be here a hundred years
So what
Slowing down the girl saying no
A lot of opportunities
And just
Being more responsive
Like like how
It just
I don't prime the pump I don't we don't advertise it
Vanity Fair to get new Custer
Affect our advertising budget
1/2 of 1%
Auto Sales
And so
I wait for the customer to tell us
How much to make
When year will grow 3%
Another year will grow 20%
It's not this
Smooth curve like public companies who have to grow 15% exactly every single year or else their stock
And all those two kinds of growth one
Where you grow stronger and when you grow fat
Anna
You got to look out for that growing fat thing
Imagine art when we come back how he slow growth by telling his employees
Go surfing
How I built this on NPR
Thanks to our sponsors who helped keep this podcast going for a to stamps.com
When you're running a small business constant trips to the post office can waste time and energy
Especially when it's packed during the busy holiday season
So sign up for stamps.com so you can start buying and printing official US postage for all your letters and
Packages
Right from your desk using your own computer and printer
Right now stamps.com has this special offer for our listeners when you sign up
It's a 4 week trial plus Postage and a digital scale
Soap for the stamps.com click on the microphone and type in
Built
Thanks also to Audible
Audible has an unmatched selection of audiobooks from leaving audiobook Publishers and business information provide
Riders including the personal MBA
Master the art of Business by Josh Kaufman
Audible is offering how I built this listeners a free 30-day trial membership
And a free audiobook
To get started
Go to audible.com built
Start listening anytime
Any place
Oh and just one more thing if
You like this program you may like another show I host it's called the TED Radio Hour Ted isn't TED Talks
Where we take a journey through a big idea anyway this week's show is all about the science of compassion
With some pretty incredible thinkers
So you can find the TED Radio Hour on iTunes or by going to npr.org
Podcasts to look for
TED Radio Hour
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Took that tough. In the early 1990s
Avon and his team started to focus Less on growing and more
Lasting is
The company
And it's hard to do things like
Use more environmentally friendly material
And they also started to do something
Weird for
A business
Instead of telling customers to
To buy their stuff
Patagonia kind of told them
Not to
Yeah
Believe
This company is the resource
That I have
And that I should use that resource
To show a different way of doing business
In fact we now have the largest
Garmin repair center in North America
Well Repair every single piece of Patagonia matter how old it is
Then definitely in fact we've got a truck.
It's going around the country
Repairing people's clothes no matter whether they're Patagonia or not
And then we're trying to teach people that
You don't throw things away you you repair them
And then we weave
Committed ourselves to owning
The product forever
So when we sell you a jacket
We still on it
If you get overweight already
Tired of the color whatever you want to get rid of it will help you
Sell it to somebody else
If breaks down will fix it
The f is finally you know completely shot
You give it back to us and we'll recycle it into
Morgan
So it forces us to use
Fibers that can be recycled
It forces us to
Design
See a jacket that you can replace a zipper cuz it's very easy to
Design one where you can't replace a zipper
Is change the whole way we do business
Yeah so like what about you how many how many Patagonia
He be surprised at all my stuff is
Years and years old I'm sitting here talking to you my pants
Probably seven or eight years old my shirt design
Probably the same
But you know it's it's kind of interesting
Friend of mine went to
Garage sales Jackson Hole recent
And there was a jacket that we made about 10 years ago and it was purple man
Great shape
The woman wanted
$3
So you offer 15 sheet
Any win on eBay
Anna guy from Japan said hey
I like to buy that jacket how much you want for it all
You don't make me an offer
Tulalip how about 750
So actually
Distance keep their value
Which is pretty amazing and I mean this thing is like a new Patagonia jacket is not exactly
Cheap stuff
Well yeah I mean we have a
Lifetime guarantee and we can't make things cheaply
I'm for trying to make
The very very highest quality weed
We can end it
You know it's like organic food is cost more than regular food
As a truth
And it causes you no less harm the environment and so
Black people pay for that and I'm not interested in
And coming out with a line of
Inexpensive clothes
You know it's kind of like eating meat
I eat meat but I eat
Tiny little bit at a time I don't either
16 oz porterhouse
And I think
Was clothing we're telling people looks think twice
If you're going to buy a jack at the skin by one that you can also wear over your
Sukkot in New York City in a rainstorm
So that doesn't sit in the closet 9 months a year and and so on own few or things but really good
What is
Is a party still conflicted over this idea that even with all the
Responsible things you do
Uart
Still part of
Consumer world
Yeah
We certainly are ya
And that's why we try to
Kind of put a spin on it by
Don't tell me our customers
Twice
Before they buy
Anything
Not just our product but anything
You have
No
College degree your meat of a business degree you're not
Like you are not a businessman
But you are you became one
A never bread that you can call yourself a reluctant businessman
But do you feel uncomfortable with that title
No not at all because I think
What I did
Is once I decided that was it
Decided to really study up on it
I studied every book I could on
Japanese
Management styles
Scandinavian
Businesses
Cuz I thought there had to be a different way of doing business
And
I still wanted only work
For part of the Year myself
You know what I take off from
June until November
I'm gone I got a place in Jackson Hole when I go fishing every day and
I calling maybe three times
In the five months
Lambcon
People know that if the warehouse burns down
Don't call me
What can I do you know what to do
How are you going to do that
Well you know I heard a great thing on NPR X
Swimming at Stanford
Studies ants
She said
You know ant colonies don't have
They don't have bosses
And everyone knows what their job is and they get their job done and
Compare that with dictatorship
It's a lot of companies are top-down management and it takes a
Tremendous amount of effort to run those
So what we decided to do is just higher
Motivated young independent people
And leave me alone
Nme night I wrote a book called
Let my people go surfing and it's all about we have a policy that when the surf comes up
Drop or can you go surfing
I don't care when you work
As long as the job gets done
And now you know I've had other companies
Come to me and say oh I love that idea are they going to do tonight
Comprehensive
Forget it you'll fail
Because you have to start with a very first person you hire
And I've had
Psychologist
Studier
Her employees and they said I got to tell you
Your employees are the most independent ever seen any company in fact they're so independent unemployable anywhere
About the company
In the seventies you guys were doing
Maternal and paternal leave
People taking their infant to daycare for the staff and will flexible work schedule of the things that we
Even to this day today are still
Not that common in in all companies
YouTube
40 years ago
Oh yeah I mean
We wanted ever kids with us at work
Do you know who put them in a cardboard box on your desk in
And that work for a while but then
Got some Screamers
And so my wife and I started
And we didn't want to just
Somebody just babysitting these kids
You know we recognize it
025 is the most important
Learning time of
Person's life
And so it's
Not a babysitting service
The kids are come out of our company or the best product
It comes out
Not once been in prison yet
Always things
Costco
The company
Money
Well if we're going to be here a hundred years so you know it's
We're not going to sell out we're not going to go public and so
It's good business
I mean I have
Probably 70% women work
For me I have women and all upper management
And I don't want to lose him
Where did you
I mean a lot of the people that we talked to on the show are motivated by
In a wine to change an industry
Or change the way business is done
Or to change the world or two
Make money
Nevermind I think everybody would agree that they wanted to make money
Isn't you where did you and where do you find the motivation to
This company
Ryman Frey
Well you know where my favorite quotes is
If you want to understand that entrepreneurial studies of juvenile
Cuz they're saying you know this sucks I'm going to do it my own way
I
Have a background
As always the shortest guy around I could play
Sports pretty well you know team sports but
When it came time for a
Actual game mode fumble the ball
I realize that
The best thing to do is invent your own sports then you can always be a winner and so
That's what the entrepreneur. They just say this is wrong I'm going to do it this other way
If you want to be successful in business
You don't go up against Coca-Cola
These big companies are they'll kill you
You just do it differently
You figure out something that no one else has thought about
And you do it at totally different way and so
Breaking the rules
You have to be creative
And that's the fun part of this
I love breaking the rules
You still must live by it by certain rules
I cannot guide you
Well I've been a student at kind of sand Buddhism
What's my life
I believe in you.
The more you know the less you need
I've been fishing
Fly fishing with one fly
The one taipei
Butterfly in different sizes
It has limited myself to that
For a whole year
And I caught more fish than I've ever caught in my
I realize that all of these
Hundreds of thousands of different fly patterns
Colors
Shapes and everything
You can replace all of that
With
Knowledge
And
Technique
And it's a good lesson for me
Detroit historic saying the world it's a simplify your life
Cuz everything pulls you to be more and more comfy
And so
I think what I learned from
Fly fishing
Is that if we have to
Either we're forced or we decide to go to a more Simple Life
It's not going to be an impoverished
It's going to be really rich
Bundchen are under of Patagonia
He never took a penny of investment by the way salons 100% of the company
And because of that the company doesn't make the numbers public soap
Despite the fact that endless growth may not be Yvonne chenard sing
Patagonia reportedly dated
Three-quarters of a billion dollars in sales last year
Their best year ever
Listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episodes
How I built this. Npr.org
And if you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other people know about it
You can also write us directly at HIV tea at npr.org
Shows produced this week around 10 Arab Louis also composed the music
It's also to neva grandson has meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
And Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Did you ever consider becoming a priest
Priests for Life moving to a monastery
Not at all
Hey thanks for sticking around because we are now at the part of the show where are we
Hear about your stories the things that you are building
This week we have a story from
Stateline
Nevada
Hi my name is Cassie Burnside and I'm the owner and founder of fatco yep
Costco
Why would anybody want to put the word fat into the name of their startup
Will you still back a bit because about 4 years ago
Cassie started to notice something that
Can a bugger I would go shopping and I would look at labels and look at ingredient panels
And not be able to read or pronounce anything
I had no idea what these ingredients were and she was bothered by products that go directly onto your
Skin like deodorant lotions and creams but then she thought
Maybe I can make some of those things myself and use you know
Old fashioned ingredients
Ingredients that we used a long time ago
In soap making and candle making and I started wondering like why don't we use them anymore why
Those things go away
And here is where
Fat comes in
Because Cassie realize that
Animal fat is used to be a main ingredient in things like soap and lotions
And so she decided
Why not make skin products with
Beef tallow
The fat from a cow
Chop it up and you cook it low and slow
And rendered Tallow is the liquid fat that drips off of the card fat during that rendering process
Just to be clear Cassie does not do this at home she gets her towel from a company in Colorado that special
Socializes in rendered fat
And then she mixes the fat with other oils and fragrances to make things like body butter and lotion
They're nursing their nutrient dense
They're very concentrated and a little goes a long way cuz he actually took a big risk but two years ago when she
Twitter engineering job to start backhoe
The last year she made close to $700,000 selling her products online
And she says all the friends and family who told her this would never work this is crazy and weird
They're not saying that anymore
I can't lie even my mom told me I was a little crazy
And now she's you know she's our biggest fan she will go to her grave saying she was customer one for fatco
We absolutely love hearing the stories from you so please
Tell us about yours
Could a build. Npr.org that's a build with a D
That npr.org let us know what your building
And thanks
As the end of the year approaches a lot of you been asking about the best way to support
How I built this so first of all thank you for asking
And it is
Pretty easy to do you go to stations
. npr.org
Find your local station and you make a year-end contribution or even better
You've become a regular monthly donor
And when you do please tell them that how I built this sent you
Find a local station at stations. Npr.org
It takes like 2 minutes it's
Totally tax-deductible
And I please do tell them how I built this sent you
The Gannett stations. Npr.org
Thanks
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com