Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
33 to 1 of the TED Radio Hour on NPR
In the past few months I've been working on a new project where I've been meeting some of the most
Amazing entrepreneurs the founder and owner of
Thanks
As in Spain
The other guy
My product was all about the rear end
And so the word spanks was
Kind of naughty and kind of funny and a little bit risky but back in the 1990's
When Sara Blakely came up with the idea
She was not joking around
I was basically coming in and disrupting an entire industry than looking at something in one way
They were making Hosiery to be seen on the leg
And I knocked on their door and set guys
It's actually going to be hidden under clothes it's a new type of undergarment
And that
Very moment
Seeing an opportunity and
Being on someone's door
That's the starting point
Going for all the stories in
Michelle
It's called how I built this
And it's about how some of the most I can
Tonic companies and Brands were built
Usually with lots of struggling
Failure before
Finally making
Will hear from the innovators and entrepreneurs be
Instagram
Vice Patagonia Clif Bar Sam Adams beer
And of course thanks
And many many
Anymore and by the way
Most of these people
Head pretty humble beginnings
Isotox
Machines door-to-door for about
7 years
And I know it sounds crazy but I kept feeling like I'm in the wrong movie
Where's the director where's the producer of this is not my movie
Will hear the apps
The downs
And
The drama
I put everything into this
This my life and it's our employees missing
My family is named after
My dad
And I'm shaking right now is thinking of it
Stories about perseverance
Are used to measure C
Success by
One or two memberships
If I sold two memberships a day it was a banner day
Stories about bootstrapping
We did all our business
You know I knew where all the good Payphone
We're the ones that were warm in the winter
The ones where
He actually had a little shelf or you could put stuff
And financial melt
So we went to his house
Like what's going on you said
It's over the money's gone
I'm done
Put on this new show probably the one thing you'll hear more than anything else
I knew it I could
Unshakable optimism
In the sheer Joy
Creating something
My God like we did it
Someone in the world is using this thing out in the wild
That feeling
Is like way more rewarding
Then any amount of money
So if
You've ever built something from nothing something big or small or something you really care about
Just dream about doing it
Chicken RT Podcast
How I built this
From NPR
The first episode comes out
Number 12 and you can subscribe
Right now
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week