Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email templates
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com
You were basically introducing is really low fares were these Airlines trying to match your prices
Yes in some cases they were and we told the Republic of Texas that
You could fly at the lower fare but if you paid the higher Fair we would give you a free bottle of whiskey
And so for a couple months we became the largest liquor distributor in the state of Texas
From NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
I'm guy Roz and Ali show how an eccentric Texas lawyer
A crazy idea in the Southwest Airlines now one of the biggest airlines in the world
Could you could you to start by introducing yourself Mitchell killer
Make it herb if you would herbplease
Can you just say your full name
This is Herb
Kelleher
And your best known as the
Founder of Southwest Airlines
How how old are you
Okay great
We are very excited to talk to you about
Going to jump in here for like two I mention that before we really started our interview
I can get some time to just chat with her and I learned some interesting things about him like
What do you eat for breakfast
Normally for breakfast I have cheese crackers
And he likes to drink
Wild Turkey Bourbon
And that he's been a smoker for
Pretty much his entire life
I just enjoyed the magical
Mystical Aroma On Site
Osmo
So how soon after you wake up do you have a
Well it's
That was a quick okay with your cheese crackers
Didn't before my cheese crackers story of how herb launched
Southwest Airlines 50 years 1966 to be exact
Herb was a young lawyer
He's living in San Antonio Texas
He had started his own Law Firm helping clients to start company
And one day one of her clients got and Rollin King
Cosmo
Pacific Southwest
And it flies only in California
And I have an idea it looks
Let's meet for a drink
And Rollin
Came to me with the idea of setting up a similar operation in Texas
And and how soon after he sort of floated this idea
To you saying yep
Let's do it let's start a company
It was a very short period of time maybe you know
Like a minute
No it was longer than that I was just joking
But was that a very short days
Case within days
Within days
What first I was very skeptical
But then I did some research and discovered that PSA was very successful in California
The Texas
Supplied all the requisites for an intrastate Airline
Because it was a big state that had large metropolitan areas
Far enough apart to justify flying
And so well Houston Dallas and San Antonio weather
Obvious first Target
Because they were the
Three largest cities in Texas
What did you
Know about Airlines
Well I knew nothing about Airlines which I think made me eminently qualified to start one
That because
What we tried to do at Southwest bus
Get away from the traditional way that Airlines had done business
So I started with the tabula rasa blank
Slate
And I think that was very helpful
So at this point in the how old are you by the way at that point in your life
I was 35 35 okay
So you have in your family or just right for children
Four children and you got the successful Law Firm by life was eat with your history
Profitable at that time
No it was not notably
Profitable
As a matter of fact
Warren Buffett reportedly joked about it at one time
NSAID
If a capitalist had shot down the Wright brothers
At Kitty Hawk in 1903
The economy would probably be better off
And so it didn't have very great
Returns
It was constantly
Difficulty why did you
You can think that this was a plausible
Idea
I think it was for your lure
Of doing something
Different
Doing something that was exciting
I really always have
Had a great deal of curiosity
And then I thought to myself well you know
Mostly adults
The United States of America
Haven't been able to fly because of the cost barrier
Is too expensive
It's too expensive for you they just thought it was business people on
Expense account
And so what I'm saying is that
In terms of
Market analysis
There was a huge
Untapped market for flying out there okcu
You decide with Rollin to start a company was that right Incorporated
But of course I was just a piece of paper
And we start to receive money
To the extent of about $500,000
That's a bit was quite a lot of money to raise I guess
Is it that time it certainly was
Listen.
We were set to go
I am Warrior Competition like at the time of their other airlines
That we're doing these Texas life-like flight between Houston and Dallas and end each other places
Oh yeah they proved to be our biggest adversaries because they were not exactly
Warm
Welcoming and hospitable
Yeah we didn't get kisses on both cheeks when we announced that we intended to
Create an intrastate carrier soberanes continental and transtex
Slater text
International
Really took out after us
And I get this involved in
Political fights and fights
The courts and they just thought that they would
Apply their incumbency
And their financial strength
To bleed Southwest Airlines
The dance before I could ever fly
They were
Suing Southwest Airlines
Correct why were they saying you shouldn't operate
Well joke
The arguments that they made in
In court or actually all kind of
Specious
And this is
One illustration of where
People attempt to use
To manipulate the government
To prevent competition
That's what they were up
So how long does it take you to fight these
These legal challenges
Well between the time when I start working
On forming Southwest and the time we flew our first flight
It was four and a half years
Wow it took a little pertinacity
Yeah
During that time the company ran out of money
And a 19-6
T9 the board of director
Had a meeting and talked about shutting
They are lying down
Shutting a company down
And I said well how about
If
I lugait for nothing and pay all the court costs out of my own pocket
Would you be willing to continue under those circumstances and they said
Osher
What was it motivated you to fight
For 4 years
To lunch this Airline
But first of all I was idealistic
Because I figured if they can prevent Southwest Airline
From introducing
What Southwest Airlines proposes
To provide physical
Consumer
Then that is
Assign
That the free enterprise system is failing
And one of the things that motivated me was to
Is that
Validate
The free enterprise system
And another one was of course
It was very hot competition and
I like to win
But what's up
Like what I don't get is it was such a huge gamble anyway because you you could have spent those four and a half years
Fighting
And then winning
And then Southwest Airlines might have fizzled out anyway
I'll tell you what guy you put your finger on something
Because
If you had taken a poll in the state of Texas
The statue of Father application
I can show you
The 99
What 9%
Of the population of
State of Texas to take this single never come to anything
I'm very serious about that several people told me that they said
They were glad to see
How how much the flight energize met in that I was enjoying it
But herb don't get yourself it'll never make a dime
Did you ever get sad or depressed me how did you keep your spirits up
Wild Turkey Hill.
Haggai it may provide a little boost
But frankly my spirits
Just don't get down
I don't stress very easily
I'll give you an example.
They have stress glasses
Southwest Airlines years ago many years ago
And up
They invited me to come over and speak
You know the fella that was running the classes
He said to the class you said we know
Herb undergoes
A lot of stress all the time
Hotel the class how do you handle it and I said
I don't have that I liked it
That was the last time I was asked back to the collapse
So
So you I mean what you were going in and out of courtroom
For 4 years
How are you making a living at that
Well I'm still practicing law
I mean I was doing a lot of other things during that time which led to very long week
Walmart occasion I was in the law office for two full days
And at the end of those two full days I've went home shaved and 1/2 a fundraising dinner for Southwest Air
But that's kind of the
The perseverance
That it's Amanda
To help get Southwest Airline started while still practicing law
I'm doing many other things
So what happened to the court
What's up with the Southwest
It was
Through the United States
Supreme Court
And through the text
Supreme Court twice
Before we could fly
And the Texas Supreme Court handed down
An order
19 hours prior to our first flight
When was that
Well that was a 19th June of 1971
We start flying on June 18th 1971 what was the flight where they go
The first flight
Went from Dallas to San Antonio
But the one that received all the publicity went from Dallas
Houston
We were the underdog
Okay what sort of David vs the Goliath
Seattle not just one but three of them
So there was a lot of news coverage about it and that's the reason people pay a lot of attention
2 is finally getting underway
Were you on that first flight by the way
No I was I was busy working to make sure there was a second flight
Do you remember that day that the first like to Goffin
Remember why you feel that you feel like finally this is done
Oh it was wonderful. I'll tell you the experience I had
When the first airplane came in
It was over a in Fort Worth American Tanger
So I went over there and there's this
After four and a half years
I'm stuck my head
In the back of one of the engine
And mechanic gravity
Hold me back and you said you realize that thrust reverser goes off
It will decapitate you
And I said at this moment I don't give a damn
So at this point Southwest Airlines and what it starts advertising it starts
Flying many Ripple with it was a flying more than one route was it flying multiple routes
Well it was Dallas Houston Houston San Antonio and San Antonio Dallas
Do one of those legs well on some flights we had the fares as low as $10
Those we had theirs as low as 15 or $20
We were about
45% lower
Then the other carriers
So how are you able to do that how are you able to charge
So much
Such a lower fare than the other
At through enormous productivity
But but how I mean I'm assuming you said a few planes
Will we start out with three
And then we got a fourth
We had to get rid of one airplane in order to meet our payroll
Right after Southwest start flying and so
We decided
That we would fly a for airplane schedule with three airplane
Ten-minute turns at the gate
We bring that airplane in
+ 10 minutes after
Stopped at the gate
Ditto
It would be pushing back again
And we had airplanes that unibrow operating
12 hours a day sometimes so each one of those additional flights
Representative Revenue generation opportunity that the other characters didn't have
Okay but even so I mean
Those other carriers
Like braniff and Texas International right
They were charging
Much much higher fares and it couldn't just been that you turn to plans around faster
Knows the whole country thing you're right about that
I was just giving you an example
Out with the ten-minute turn because it's a vivid one
Addition to that
They were by definition a monopolist
They had been under 40 Years of federal government supervision through the c a b
That the Civil Aeronautics board yes right
And during that time
If they had a little thing Angel problem
Of the cab with just give them a fair increase
I hope so
That's how their fares got so high
As compared to what we were doing
Since we were regulated by the
Ucab
Okay so you weren't regulated in the same way but
Are you doing other things like
Lake peigneur employees less
Well it dependent initially we were paying them less
As the years went on we were paying them or their total compensation
I was superior to the other carriers and in addition
When we turned our first very slim profit in 1973
We set up the first
Profit sharing plan
In the American airline industry
And I think we made a profit of I don't know a hundred thousand dollars that year or something like that
But that would alter course to pour billions
Enter employees pockets
And your employees were
Were you nice as well
Yeah we were the most heavily unionized carrier in the United States
Arlo cost were not due to being a non-union carrier
Since we were
More unionized than our competitors were
So you were basically introducing these really low fares
Woody's Airlines trying to match your prices
Yes in some cases they were
There's no question
What about those mattafact braniff at one point
Put in a lower fare
The Narrows
What's it called an introductory Thayer cuz they've been serving Texas you know for 40 years by that time but it any of
One of the things that came out of that was
We maintained our full fares
And we told the Republic of Texas
If you paid the higher fare
We would give you a free bottle of whiskey
And so for a couple of months we became the largest liquor distributor in the state of Texas
Flying at that time with
Give like a madman and you know
Tumblers with
Stop action
Glamorous experience with Southwest was competing on
Christman you will not
You were not doing in fly cocktails
Like what do people think of your service forces
Competition
God I got a story to tell you on that
It was Thanksgiving of 1971 remember we've been in business since June
Yep
And my sister-in-law
The life of lady called me
Myra law office
And she said her about
She said I just flew from Houston to San Antonio on Southwest Airlines
I've traveled most of the world's Airlines which was true
You know she was a world Traveler
And she said I know you're going to be a big success
You got the best in-flight service
That I have ever experienced on any Airline
And I said
Am I glad to hear that how many passengers were on the airplane
She said just me
In just a minute
Southwest goes National and Herb convinces Travelers that Airlines do not have to serve in-flight meal
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey everyone gif
Thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First to audible who has more than 250 thousand audio programs from leading audiobook publishers
In business
Information providers
Including presence
Bringing your boldest self to your biggest challenges
By Amy Cuddy
Audible is offering Highway Builders listeners a free 30-day trial membership and a free audiobook to get started
Go to audible.com built
And start listening
Anytime Anyplace
Thanks also to Amazon LaunchPad
Program dedicated to supporting new products from today's brightest startups
Stop everything from newtech to Beauty
Explore the stories of the inventors and entrepreneurs that brought their Innovations to life
Discover interesting items every single week while buying with all the confidence you expect from Amazon
Support startup by visiting amazon.com LaunchPad
And one more thing before we get back to the show please do stick around till the very end after the credits because that's where
Where we've been playing your stories about the companies
Yodeling including
The one today how to maybe make millions from vegetable scraps so please do stick around and now
It's how I built this from NPR
And I Rise
1970s Southwest Airlines only fly within the state of Texas
In 1978
Something really important happen
Congress decides to completely deregulate the airline industry
And for Southwest Airlines
That means
They can now start flying to new cities
Outside of Texas
At this point you Southwest is expanding and your competitors are no longer just taxes are lies your computer
He was like American and
And an N Pan Am and TWA right National major International carriers
Were people skeptical that Southwest would be able to compete in
Oh yes
We were described as
The Texas Airline that could only be
Successful in
The state of Texas
Okay
And then we were described as a
Sunbelt Airline
They could not be successful outside
The Sunbelt
There was a
Press conference for winning the Baltimore
Where was the reporters there said that
Waiting on mr. Larry said I know you've been very successful out west but
Now you're coming to the east
The most competitive
Part of the country as far as Airline Services concerned
And I said yeah
It's so competitive that when we start out here
We're reducing your existing fares by 60%
How competitive does that sound at that time
Were you guys already serve No Frills
What we were no frills we're in the sense that we were short all
And I got a restriction
What you can do you have relatively short flight till like peanuts
Two drinks
That sort of thing but you know
When we start flying long-haul lights
From San Antonio to Los Angeles
Where to press conference
You know to announce a new service
And
One of the
Reporters there said
What are you going to serve
Meals on those flights and I said no we're not
We're going to charge you $400 less
Bertram
Right
And I understand you can get a pretty good sandwich at Jason's for $400
So when I would Point did you give up your life right
Actually that was at the request the board of directors in 1981
Can you were still you still had your own law practice that you were doing other work for
Throughout the entire 1970s
Oh yes yeah
And I'll tell you the truth you know I didn't really hang her
Doobie Park corporate life
Because
Lawyers have a lot more freedom to do their own thing when and where they want to
But we hired a very excellent fellow named Lamar Muse who was a real battler
To get the company off the ground in operation
He had substantial Airline experience
Bad. He did a wonderful job
And so you don't find me a 1981 we lost
Successor to Lamar
And the board director said to me you've got to do it and it did you want to do it I felt I had to do it
And I'll tell you why because the start of the 1980
You had unemployment of 10.8%
You had a double-dip recession
You had the air traffic controllers strike
Then Lamar Muse
The guy we had to get the cut me off the ground he launched a competitor against just gold Muse hair
You left Southwest and then lodged a competitor
Yep that's 3 years after he left gold Muse are you feel like that well I thought it was somewhat in modest on his paw
But because he called muser after himself but where you at
What are you doing we work together all these years and now you're done
We bought them later you buy some later
When they're on the verge of bankruptcy
We bought news there
But it was there
In 1981
So I figured I'd better do what the board asked me to do
And come to Southwest Airlines
Full-time
Was making money at the time
Yes
We've been profitable every single year
For 43 years I guess now
You must be the other airlines crazy because they were
A lot of them
Have had good years and bad ear
But it seems like Southwest is just
Has never had a
Bad here
What we've had years when
You know earnings were down
But we've never had a loss for a full year since 1900
B2
And we've never throw those an employee at Southwest Airlines when the rest of the industry during that. Up until
Has probably furloughed I don't know
A million-and-a-half employees
Throughout the world
Basically
We
Look at history and said this is a very dicey business
Serbia
Delta Airline business
Yeah
So we may be flamboyant from the marketing standpoint but we're going to be very conservative from the Fisk
Google stand for
And
Established
A rule of thumb
That we're going to pay 80% of the cost
List of all brand new airplanes from internally generated funds
And actually wound up paying 100%
For most of our airplanes so we had
The largest
Percentage in our Fleet of owned airplane
Of any carrier of any size
So so
What does that mean
Well I mean
You're not taking on that
Right when you do that
So when you get in the bad times you're not threatened by the deck payments
Which is put cameras into bankruptcy and out of bankruptcy and back into bankruptcy you know for
35 years
You heard from from the outside from listen to stories
The airline industry
Seems so
Brutalight is it do you think it's more Savage than other Industries
I think
That it's more competitive than other engine
Mysteries
And one of the reasons for that is
That our principal Capital asset
The airplanes
Moovit 540 miles an hour
Yeah
And you know if you have a shoe factory
The fails in Seattle as an example
You can't
Within hours transport that chew Factory 2
Chattanooga Tennessee to compete there
But if
Your Seattle Air Service fails you can have your airplanes
In San Antonio or Chattanooga
Within a matter of hours so
The very mobility of your Capital assets
Breeds a lot of competition
Did you like that competition. Did you like being an airline CEO now
Imagine all that stuff
Was it fun for you
Well I have to adapt myself
Yeah I love being with the people at Southwest Airlines
That was like a fountain of youth
For me
They were so wonderful and entertaining and
Ghetto
Great to be with
That part of it but
When your pricing lawyer pretty much
Do Your Own Thing
And
It's a swift Pace wealth
Things to move as swiftly at first
What I came to Southwest Airlines full-time and
We're moving swiftly compared to the rest of the
Airline industry
But not compared to my experience
Were you pushing for expansion and growth and all those things
During your tenure
Oh yes I mean Southwest Airlines
Expanded enormously
You know from a very small base
But I soon realized
It was a speech
That I want to hear
We're of a guru said if you can improve a corporation five four
Percent in a year that's a mirror
Oh okay I was trying to do 25%
Maybe that's why I feel a little frustrated
So it really brought my thinking you know more in line
Even if it might have seemed like it
Play slow process for you
The fact that Southwest was growing and
That prevailed in this industry is is pretty remarkable is pretty unbelievable
Given that you know so many of those early competitors don't even exist anymore and some of the great iconic Airlines
TWA Pan Am
Exactly many of them
There are very few left
What mistakes did they make that you seen that you have made
Well
We just did things
Differently
Black Market
Bashar
Who is Shiva
Supposed
I told anybody say
Mansion Market
Chair I punch him in the nose
Because here all these big companies fighting over their market share and losing money and following employee yeah
Let's focus on profitability
And if we have 4% of the market were profitable that's better than having 90% of the market
And being unprofitable
What's the value of Southwest
Overall
Oh
Probably
20 billion dollar something like that
One of the biggest
Airlines in the United
At in the world
In terms of passengers
Sunbelievable
Yeah
It really is
It's like I've had too much Wild Turkey
Fantasizing
Weather when you start of the company
How much how much did you invest
Personally
I invested $10,000
Which must be worth
Quite a bit today
Imagine if well it's going up some
Since then
But
That's a company
That's what I thought was
Requirement
Of good leadership
I was turned down pay increases
Bonus increase
To set a good example
I thought for all of our people
Corsa stock that I got
Rose enormously in value but that was in lieu of cash compensation
SeaWorld
Mainly paid with Woodstock
Yeah basically was stock at like at the biggest kick out just to give an Exemplar
When I did a stock option deal
In lieu of pay raises was a pilot so they could Southwest Airlines
Stock options
In lieu of a pay increase
I took no pay increase
Along with them
I'm not trying to single anybody out but
There was a
The head of an airline that was smaller than Southwest Airlines and on the verge
Going out of business
Do salary and bonus for three times what mine were at Southwest Airlines and that's the way I wanted it
Are you from worried that somebody know some young you know
Herb Keller type
Characters going to come around and put up some upstart Airline and knock Southwest office
Chris Brown
I'm concerned about it all the time
I got a letter to her employees
And
It was about my 10 for most concerns for the next decade of Southwest Airlines okay yeah
Number one
Was us
That we ignore competition
That we get complaints
That way
Get cocky
And I used to line think small and ask volume will get bigger
Think they can act big and will get smaller
So could happen one day
So it's possible
You know,
History buff
And if you look at the largest companies
And United States
As the 19th century turned into the 20th
Most of them are gone
The central leather company
+ 1900 + 1901
Was the 17th largest
This company in the United States
But it didn't anticipate
What the Advent of the Ford automobile
Was going to me
You know what it did
It made buggy whips and saddle
And never stop doing it until it was gone
And if you look at countries
Boys look at companies
They perish
If you have any sense of History
You realize that and you don't try to avoid it
And hearing the story of how you made this happen and all the work you put into it
I wonder if you think your
Chicken wire differ
To be able to
Put up with all that stuff for so many years
Well I said I probably am wired a little bit
Currently some for many people and they're probably very happy about that difference themselves
One of the things is that
I never look back
You know I don't spend a lot of time regretting things
It went wrong
And furthermore
I think
I've always had a great deal of fun
Out of what I was doing
And you know
People would say to me why don't you why don't you burned-out yeah
You know I was working 200 hours a week
Loveland server simplywell
It's easy
When you have a passionate joy and what you're doing you don't burn out
Herb Kelleher co-founded Southwest Airlines 50 years ago
And he served as CEO and then I'm bored
Before retiring in 2008
We wait her tell her once resolved a trademark dispute with a rival airline are both using the slogan
Planesmart
He was all this not in court
But the challenging the other CEO to a public arm wrestling match
Which herb Kelleher law
You can see that entire arm wrestling match
Just go to Google and type in the malice in Dallas
Halex listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to
To how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us at h i b t a
Npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet gets
That's how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to leave a grandson has
Best Mexican food
Jeff Rogers
Gyros and you listening to how I built this
From NPR
Gloucester weather
Because
What are listeners has an amazing story about the company she is building and
My name is Caitlin watch until I'm in Los Angeles California
Actually Caitlin grew up in Chicago but when she went to college in La she noticed a juice bars ever
Pettit juicer at home
Siri put this carrot in the juicer and outcomes
Tiny tiny amount of liquid and I see these nouns of
Vibrantcare Pepino and it smells so good it's so fresh and she just looks at me and she goes I usually throw away the pole
I've no idea what to do with it in that
Is how Caitlin came up with an idea for a business
The next day I was like wow like what if this
Juice pulp could be used to create healthy snacks at a more affordable price point until I called above
Bunch of juiceries right then and there
And I asked him what are you doing with your juice pulp
So she found some juice bars that's agreed to give her their fruit and veggie pulp a small commercial kitchen
Turn that poop into snacks next like
Granola have five different flavors so apple pie peanut butter and carrots
Red velvet red velvet
Rayshun just a few hundred bags of snacks a week
Only selling it health food stores in La and online
And she spending the business with money from an incubator and some from her saving soap she's still in the red
Working pretty crazy hours
COC and he's been the pope and being so happy just to see it process until like a better product invented
Sold on the shelves I just think that's the craziest thing so I love it yeah
If you are tell us the story of the company or the movement that you are building go to build. NPR.
Iorg that's
Build
With a D
NPR
Dato RG
And thanks
One more thing before you go there's a new show at NPR ATS called the radio ambulante
In fact it's our first ever podcast in Spanish
The show takes a look at Latin America and the US Latino communities bring you stories that you might not otherwise here
Stories about punk rock
Cuba stolen books
Columbia or junk Bonds in Puerto Rico
Radio ambulante tells Latin
American stories from the inside
Check it out
NPR what happened
Npr.org podcast
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week