Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Every business I started I would count the months
Play my profitable do I have enough to pay the bills
I mean I've been been in the situation enough times when it will start up
Where the bill collectors were calling on a continuous basis
He throwing it back then you had answering machines and it was like you didn't want to hit the button on the answer machine cuz
Hello
Mr. Mark Cuban I've left 17 messages
Running PR gets how I built this a show about
Gators entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Raz and Mark Cuban
Was going to transform the economy in millions and then billions
The dollars
So if you know who Mark Cuban is
Probably seen him on Shark Tank
Millionaire and billionaire investor and if
You don't know the show basically there's a panel of investors who are the sharks
And they hear a bunch of pictures from people who are trying to start a business
So do you like the idea
And would you want to see a net increase
Appthority to 50% your company
Again what was my question to you
And I wouldn't Mark Cuban is doing the judging
Course I like the deal which is why I offered you a chance to close it
You should just shut up and take the deal
Hallelujah
Instead of keep on selling
And you kept on trying to sell
Okay so this is the Mark Cuban that many of us are familiar with
Self-made billionaire at 8
40 owner of
The Dallas Mavericks
But how he got to this point
Here's the story
True like what
What was Mark Cuban like that day
Graduate from college
Paint that picture
Yeah I was a hustler I was an entrepreneur
I didn't know I remember I remember making a list
Potential Industries I wanted to go into
I wrote them down
Cable industry
Technology
All these things that I thought would be up-and-coming Industries in
I was just going to start applying for jobs until I get home
And my first job out of college
Was
At Mellon Bank in Pittsburgh
Which I kind of backed into because they thought I had my MBA
But I didn't
I just taking all my MBA classes starting my freshman
And Indiana
Then they were kind of disappointed I didn't quite have the chops that they expected cash
So Batman
Thanks for just going
Through the process of
Converting from paper systems to
Digital system
My job was to do systems integration we were system conversion
It's a nearly 80
Yes
And so that's where I got my introduction to
Computers in really where I found that I really like computers I had really taken it at Indiana
Yeah and then I quit
And when
Why would I quit
Just because I had no future there
It just wasn't for me I just was not a good employee but I tried to take initiative
I'm ever taking myself I'm going to have an impact and I'm going to try to do things differently to stand out
And I started writing a little newsletter
You don't think I'm lying you were on my
Why was there right now just like this in my mind that I'm going to have an impact I'm going to do what I think we're newsletter for like
Other employees
Yeah other employees at the bank then
If it plays out the banking of the bank we're doing the conversion for
And I had
Lots of humor in it
And it was hysterical I if I have to say something
Pad
Then all of a sudden they got back to my direct boss who basically had
Just dismiss me once I find I did have an MBA
And he just tore me a new one you just rip me
Just like anime
Okay I don't belong here
Cuz he thought you were like this annoying
AppStar kid who was just yes kind of going over his head
Yeah basically it's like who the hell you think you are
The only use that nice the language in
Oh yeah
Ruskin
So how did you end up in Dallas when your kid from Pittsburgh went to school in Indiana
I had a bunch of buddies from IU who went down there and they said the weather is amazing the girls are hot and the economy is getting better
Could you got to remember when I graduate graduate from Indiana
I mean it was not a good time you know there's a recession and this
Free PC
And a bunch of my buddies had
Went down to Dallas and said you got to come check
So what did you think you were going to do down there
I know idea
I had no idea
I figured worst case I have fun
Started to borrow my senior year in college so I knew how to bartend
I understood the bar business
Worst case I get a job working as a bartender
And then see what came along in
And that's exactly what I did I got to
A job at a place called a Lawns working as a bartender
And in the meantime
I would go through the help wanted ads
There is an ad in the local paper that
Said come to
This agency
And will help you place and I might look him up
Paying a fee
Look like now the employer pays don't worry so
I got sent to a company called your business software and they started quiz me
And actually smart questions but it was
You know
What do you know about PCS and this was 1982 at this point
I might he sees we're not as saying no
People did not have their own computer no no no nobody
Right it was brand new
And I was like I don't know a lot
But what I do know
Is
How to open up a manual
And read and teach myself and gave him the examples of what I taught myself at Mellon Bank yeah I got a job for a teen
10 grand a year +
Your business software
And so what did you have to do for the company like who is your ex
Cool job my job was it was a retail store
And my job was to get there
And open the store by 9:30
Have all the PCS dusted the windows
Cleaned
I'm set up the software and then
Learn all the software that we were selling so that when people came in I could answer the
So you just anchor and
Read the manual Natalie
I figured that's how I taught myself everything yeah cuz I actually tried to buy a TRS-80 from RadioShack
And I didn't get approved for
Accredited
Already had my Sears credit card in my
Discover Card taken in
And cut up
It's okay
Since I can't afford to buy my own PC
I would stay there late or I would take one of them home and just
Crunch the hours and teach myself
Were you a good salesman I needed you like are you kidding me I would
The best
I crushed it
How are you the best
One of my strengths is always been being able to put myself in the shoes of
Any type of business
You got shoe store okay
I understand how that works you got a bank understand how that works
You got you know an oil refinery I'll figure out how that works
And so if I'm able to figure out how the business works and what makes a profitable
Then I'm able to
You don't figure out how to apply the soft words
To solve a problem in
The thing about the industry back then was it was brand new to everybody that's what I would tell people
It was so new to everybody that if I put in the time to learn it
I can stay ahead of everybody in new stuff was coming out everyday I'm but you know not as much as you see the day with apps and everything
What new stuff was coming out everyday
It wasn't that hard if I put in the time to keep up with
Was that your plan like
Just keep working for the
This company or whatever comes
We came along
No might my plan with I knew I was not going to be an employee long-term
New York
Do Your Own Thing
I just just who I am
You know who I was
My entire life
I mean I read that you
If you wanted to be rich from Herman
So what
What what did you do
I just tried
You know from
Packaging baseball cards when I was 9 or 10 years old and taking him down to the park and reselling them
Mark and I'm up you know buying and selling stamps and garbage bags door to door
Getting together a crew of kids in
Selling candy door-to-door
I mean I remember thinking when I was 11 years old
I'm literally looking out the window in our house
If I hustled I can I can move out of this house and take care of myself
Pay my own bills
Wow
What's a realistic
Good salad and once I learned that
Selling was about helping people
Then it it almost became
Easy
And then it was just a question of effort
How did you
How did you start your first company
And how old are you
First I got fired from your business software because I went
And
I sold a deal that was going to make me a $1,500 Commission
The customer wanted me to
You'll come pick up the check in the morning so that they could get started as quickly as possible
And so I said yes
And then I told my boss look
Additional disk I want Kevin
Kevin wants me to come
Pick up the check
Now cuz I want to get started like know you've got to open up
Store
I'm I got Barbara doing that
I know you got to open
The store
And so I made the executive decision to go pick up the check thinking
But I handed them to check
I would be okay if you fired me
Soaps what would you do
You know I took my commission
Because I was fired I went and
Took some other customers I was working with
And started a company called micro Solutions
Describe what Microsoft
What does it actually do
We're sitting generator
So what's that worth
What that means is we would take software
And we would modify it to your particular business need
Install it and stay with it till it works
So you were just doing this on your own with just you
I had a partner that
Help do some software development Martin Woodall
And he basically did our Counting
But more importantly he was organized
Izzy know he was anal as they come
His organizational skills is really wet
It really helped us because I didn't have to worry about the accounting getting done
Checks getting ready
And all that kind of stuff
How did you get people to hire you how did you and would you go door-to-door would you call Kyle I would network-1 successful at
To another
And so
I went to a company
Call architectural lighting who I'd be
Been talking to
I said look your software cost you five hundred bucks
I don't have the money to to buy from the wholesaler
If you guys would Advance me the money
I won't charge you anything to install it
And I promise you that I'll make it working
If for some reason it doesn't
Then I will read
You work for you or figure out a way to give you the money back
And they did and it worked
And then I went to the next one in the next one the next one and you got to realize that you know
My personality is such
That
I would start
Learning software working on an application that I was riding
And I start working on it
And I look up and it be 36 hours later
Use the workaholic
Not even a workaholic it's just went when
I didn't look at it so, try to work 24 36 hours or whatever
I looked at it's a saying okay this is
This is fascinating this is intellectually challenging I want to solve this problem
And if I don't do it I'm not going to get paid and I'm going to lose all this time
So solve the problem in and that's what I would do and
You know the thing about programming
Yo you concentrate so so so so hard
That time flies
So as as the company grew and end
Became more successful
When did you think okay
Pizzetta I've made it
I remember being
And being at a bar with my buddy
Leaning back and going
I have $100,000 in the bank
Never my wildest dreams did I think I would have
$100,000
But then it got no business kept on growing and things got to get better
And then I remember having $800,000 in
This is the 80s
And getting an offer to sell the comfy
Yes
And who was it
If you member company CompuServe by chance of course and they were part of H&R Block and so we sold it to copy
You serve and named it The Copy Service
Systems integration group
Sold it for 6 million dollars
Gave a chocolate to my employees
Ended up with two million
And Martin it up
2 million
And boom
Sea salt company for 6 million
You walk away with
2 million and then you got
Local taxes
Course
So you're like in your early 30s
No that just turned 30
And I remembered
Bunny the stockbroker Raleigh Ross
And telling them I want to invest like a 60 year old man
Because why
And what I taught my
I read this book how to retire at the age of 35
That was like a book I kept on my desk
That was my mission
You're an in this book how to retire at the age of 35 the whole theme was
If you look like a student you know
Yell and Save
A million-and-a-half dollars
Who are you living like a student
You can live a long time just like this and
And really enjoy your life and and that's what that was my mission
What happened along the way was
Raleigh was at Goldman Sachs
And
Because I knew the technology business and low query networking business
I started getting questions from all there
Analyst
Like like what kind of questions
Yeah you just installed this synoptics router
Tell me about it what do you think about it what works and I knew the intricate details of Aldi's
All this hardware and software
And so
You know I'm like
Wait a minute these guys are using my information to make decisions on the quality of these companies and stock
Well maybe I should start doing that too
And and so I started buying these stocks
And and selling stocks just based off of my knowledge of the companies and knowledge of the products
And I was
Feeling it
I mean literally you know over the next
For years I made 20 some million dollar
Chess pie
Buying selling sex with a $2000000 yes
Like I'm assuming at this point you have nothing to worry about
Yeah I just said
I'd worry about not screwing it up
What you were still at worried about screwing up at that point
Trust me I had a healthy.
Dosa fear
You know every business I started I would count the months
Play my profitable you know what do I have enough to pay the bills
I mean I've been been in the situation enough times
With startups
On my own
Where the bill collectors are calling on a
Continuous basis
Keep going
And back then you had answering machines in
It was like you didn't want to hit the button on the answer machine cuz
Hello
Mr. Mark Cuban I've left 17 messages
Coming up in just a minute
Mark Cuban figured out that audio on the internet was going to become a huge thing and how that turned them
From a millionaire to a billionaire
Gyros and you're listening to how I built this from NPR
Haverhill
Thanks to two of our sponsors who help with
Does podcast going first to Casper
Online mattress retailer the Casper mattress
Designed and developed in the USA
Engineer
They use to Technologies latex foam and memory foam
To give just the right amount of sink
Bounce
A neighbor risk-free trial try out your Casper mattress for 100 nights with
Free delivery and returns along with a special offer
Listeners to this show
Go to casper.com built
And use the promo code built
Iridium $50 toward a Casper mattress
Terms and conditions
Supply
Thanks also to stamps.com
When you're running a small business constant trips to the post office can waste time and energy
Especially was packed during the busy holiday season
So sign up for stamps.com so you can start buying and printing official US postage for all your letters and
Packages
Right from your desk using your own computer and printer
Right now stamps.com has this special offer for our listeners when you sign up
It's a 4 week trial Plus
Postage and a digital scale
Soap for the stamps.com click on the microphone and
And type in built
And one more thing before I get back to show
Please do stick around till the very end
Because that is where we feature your stories about the the ideas in the companies that
You are building
She comes right after the credits so please do stick around and now
It's how I built this
Stream NPR
Kyroz
Mark Cuban
Himself
Computer program
Started a software consulting company
For a few million
And was
Officially retired
At the age of 35
But that retirement
Did not last long because in the mid-1990s
Mark Cuban wound up starting
Another business
So what was
So my college buddy Todd Wagner came and we should get together all the time
Eyebrows retired so I was the guy
Let's go to lunch and have a drink
Yeah
So we we get together is like look
He's got to this other guy he knows who's
Doing this thing with pagers to try to get Sports
Audio transmitted to pagers and I'm like
Now that's crazy
I'm like what
Indiana Bass
Right now we try to listen to Indiana basketball
We would have to have somebody in Bloomington Indiana
Hold
I found a phone yeah with to the radio right and then we will listen to it on the other side here in Dallas
Crazy
There's got to be a way this new internet and I've been playing with the internet
I might just got to be
A way that I can figure out how to
No transmit audio
And eventually video over the internet
So that we can solve that
Right now that
Totally obvious right but at that time like in the mid-nineties
Did people think this way
Was a good idea
No hell no people were laughing
Fire by them radio
What was the technology was a technology even there
No it wasn't at that point but I figured I could
Can figure it out and we were
I was playing with NFS files all this other stuff on here you know I went and bought
Appelt Backpacker belt
Computer for 3 Grand
Set up an ISDN line of my house
And
Just started playing and playing and playing and try and if
Thanks and there were ways using wav files
Stop that you could transmit audio that been done for a long time
But actually streaming it
And over the internet
In a more efficient manner that hadn't
So I set up a website
And
Ricotta Daddy net and then we went to the local a local radio station here in Dallas klif
I went to a Master Lock
You know how cable TV is just blown up
And now you can get any Network anywhere
Do you have a TV
I think this internet thing is going to do the same thing for audio in the bed
Anjali video
That you're going to be able to stream
Things digitally
All around the world and we're going to really make the world a much smaller place
And you can make your signal
How much more Global does
And
We here's what we need
To do I want to bring an eight-hour VCR
And we're going to record your Norm hitzges show and
All this stuff all your sports shows
And then I'm going to coat it
And put it on Audiomack
Soap soap
What did were people to people start listening
Oh yeah oh yeah oh yeah
And people started coming
And we started getting emails
All around the world
Oh my God
You just cured my homesickness I'm leave it living in
Korea
Yeah I'm living in Oklahoma or California and I miss Dallas
Or I'm stuck in my office and now I can finally get
A b and c
More like
Damn we got something
And you know we just started taking out from there
Bliss Carnival
You are a multi-millionaire at this point like you are sitting like burning the midnight oil like sitting
In front of a glowing screen night after night after night
Why were you doing that
That's who I am cuz I wanted to win
Right away what's that mean
Against what against to against
You will a new a new streaming was the future
Who is no doubt in my mind
And
Beyond that that's who I was I mean I like the idea
Of your Peewee said I could see around corners what's next what's new
What's next
And there was no doubt in my mind that streaming was neck
And I are members telling our employees
We're either going to be a multibillion-dollar company or we're just going to be friends and was going to be a big flame
But streaming is going to be
In Norman and we have a
How are you
Making a profit
We wanted to say I failed on my teeth every bimonthly
Profitability goals
But it was it was really obvious to me that
This is going to be huge
Enormous
If only just to reach
Offices because
There was no other way to get media at your desktop
Yeah you could have a TV there
And most people can have radios there
And so we were the media device and people were putting media
PCS on every desktop
And yeah you had the the Broadband width of Corporation
It was a perfect storm for us we just had to have the Conch
And so we just kept on
Growing and growing and growing
And so I went out racing money from
Friends
It was like what are we going to Value this company at
Blackwell
The last company
I sold
After 7 years for 6 million
Let's just cut that in half
3000000 that'll be a valuation
That's all we sold
Yo 1% chunks for $30,000 to
Four friends
When we sold the company
Those $30,000 chunks for Worth 22 million-dollar
You sold the company to Yahoo for how much 5.7 billion is
Got your key so what's up what percent of the company did you order that
When you sold at 33%
In 1999
Yes actually close in mm
Okurrr
Billionaire
And you're thinking okay now and retire
Yeah kind of
Pretty much did you start to think about
Finally
The Dallas Mavericks
I didn't I didn't know how that came about was
It was
October
We're early November of 1999
And I've been Dallas Mavericks season ticket holder for
A few years
And I'm ever going to the game started the 99
2000 season
And
It wasn't a sellout
And I was excited
But nobody else was
And I'm never looking around thinking
I can do a better job
Nas with my girlfriend
My wife
And I'm never telling her
Do a better job then
Yo ding ding ding the light bulb went off on
I can put my money where my mouth is
And so that's exactly what I did I talk to my cells rap and put me Tech meghani Mark McGwire
Who was the former player working
Champiro ice Pro Junior the owner
Connected with Ross
Didn't even negotiate I just said you know what whatever
And pay them
285 which
Probably a hundred million
But yeah it wasn't like it was preordained
Plan that was my all-time goal
It was I was I've always been a basketball Junkie of always love the game
Play pickup I still play pickup
It's in my blood in
It always just
Seem like why not
So what you say you paid a hundred million too much
What about the Mavs everybody like are you an idiot it was the highest price ever paid for a sports team
285 million dollars that everybody thought I was a moron
I need some so crazy now because of NBA teams are words like
Amazon billion
Dollars
I asked you about the NBA because
You get in a lot of trouble
Like you have been fined
A lot of money for
For like yelling at the ref so do you
Did you cause trouble for fun or do you
You stupid cuz you like
The fight
Just depends on the circumstance
If I'm playing pickup or if I'm playing in the in a league
I'm never arguing over calls or whatever and never have
Family Guy and there's a bad call okay
That's the way it goes
Yo in the NBA it's a lot differently when I first got
There when I first got to the NBA
Rep really work at managing the game
Rather than calling the game by the rules
And
I remember early on
Reading something from the director of officiating back then who said
We don't call the game
The same in the last minute
As we do in the first
Winchester
Infuriated me to no end
And then from there it was just like okay
I'm on a mission to
To make this Fair
And
Set me off
With a lot of those guys
And probably cost me a championship in 2006
But
It was come a long way since and I think
You know I'm there for the NBA's better
Did you kiss sometimes you yell at that
Rhapsody
That that's my spot you know whether to be honest
If you just see me
Outside of game
Imus Mellows you
You can be glad you're not like an angry guy
No don't have many reasons
No. I have no reason to
Majority game
That's where I let out my
It's like when I played
Let's play rugby
Like Joyner rugby game I'm going to try to beat the hell out of you and then we'll drink afterwards for that was where I let out my
And doing a math game you'll see me yell and scream
You know that's my
My stress
It is at the same thing on Shark Tank because you can
You catching because I'm me and
Essence
Yeah right what why is that
If there's an entrepreneur who's got their life tied up in something I'm not
But I'm going to be so
Supportive and I'll come up
What suggestions even if I'm not in
Are you trying to scare me
If you're trying to pull a quickie
Or your products
The scam
I'm going to nail you
Because I don't
I know that people see these products and no go to buy them
Yeah we had one on the end of the season where is Kyle pavlakis
Where
They had a
Fitbit looking device
That shot
And the whole idea was
Aversion therapy
So that if you don't want to smoke you shock yourself when you're getting ready to shut the
Set the smoke
Shock yourself when you getting ready to eat
Yeah whatever it is that you're trying to avert
And it would train your brain
And when they tried to show the science
Leave all the signs for aversion therapy in general
But nothing specific
Picture their product and I called him out on it
And I was like
Okay why you just use a rubber band
You know it snap yourself
When you
You're going to smoke
And so
Those situations Almanac
If your hearts in it when your heart's in the right place and your efforts there
I'm going to support
You've invested
Like almost $29 I guess
Skin
Company made money yet off of any of those
If I got 20 million dollars back
Have I gotten
You know if I was going to Value it when I have more than 20 million of value absolutely
Do out of the seventy give or take companies that I've invested in
I'd say
Tore out of business
Tore out of business and just aren't smart enough to know it
And then the next
You know the top
That are making 500000 or more in profit
Per year
And have paid me back a lot of money or
It reinvesting
A lot of that money into growth
Then there's others in the middle that are just growing in
And running their businesses the way they should in
You know we'll see if they click and take off or not
Yashow market
Amazing because
Unlike other people who been on the show
It doesn't seem like
Becoming a billionaire was
Weird to you
And like all of a sudden you're weird trust me was it
It is so much money to this day wears
Yeah it is crazy I mean I knew I'd be wealthy you knew that you just knew it
Yeah
Look I mean from the time I was
25 on
I was making money and saving money I'm in
Increasing my net worth
You know on a monthly basis
But to this day
I meant I mean yesterday I remember being in my backyard and
My kids were there
And just thinking
You know I never would have imagined
Never in a million years would I have imagined
I said that I'd be in this
Position
You know I'm just trying to appreciate it is crazy
If you woke up tomorrow
I found out that
Everything was gone
Are you money
Welfare
House like
What you had to start over what would you
At what you do
I get a job as a bartender at night and a sales job during the day
It's not working
And probably
Yeah because I be a billionaire that built up to be a billionaire you got to get a life
Right I started my company
Yo at a time when the stock market was going
And that that was my luck
And I was smart enough to do it smart enough to run it
Smart enough to execute on its smart enough to head yet
But no question there was luck involved
Oven so how could I become a multi-millionaire
Millionaire again
I have no doubt
On cuz I work hard enough
And I
Look and I don't mean that to sound disrespectful there's a lot of people who work
Really hard
But in sales
Annoying
What my sales skills are in
The products that I'm able to
The cell
I think I could find a job selling a product that had enough
Commissions are rewards for me
And then leverage that out to start a company somewhere somehow
And then
Build some wealth
Now maybe not the same
But enough
Peterbilt
Mark Cuban is the owner of the Dallas Mavericks
Many years he really wanted to learn how to dunk a basketball like Michael Jordan any tried and train the tribe
And at the age of 37 after years of training
He finally did he finally got the ball
Listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episodes of How I built this NPR.
And if you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other people know about it
You can also write us directly at Hib tea at npr.org
Shows produced by Rammstein Arab Louis to also composed the music it's also to Nev a gram
Sanaz meshkinpour at Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey thanks for sticking around to the very end of the show because this is the part of the show
Where we've been hearing from you guys
It's about the company
And ideas
Your building
Thousands
Love you literally thousands
Brittany
And if you haven't
Please do tell us your story
Rebuild. Npr.org
RG that
Build with
Sadie
Where are you
Volume
You need to do
Out of the way
Here's this week
Big story
So my name is Marty Peters and I live in Gastonia North Carolina
Charlotte
Where Marnie works as a massage therapist
Money is a flight from North Carolina to Maryland and she was with her two little kids
And where kids
Was her baby son was swaddle to her chest
And rather kids are 18 month old daughter was strapped into the seat beside her and she was demanding to play with her
Toys and each toy gave her she drop on the ground
And because I had my son wrapped around me I couldn't bend down and get them
The toys keeps slipping up the tray table in rolling down the aisle or crayons and stuffed animals and figure
All over the plane and so as I was sitting there closing my eyes going okay what
It would help me in the situation
I started to make this product in my head and what came to mind is the least
Was an inflatable lap tray
For kids
But the more that we travel the more I realize that they need a place to put their things that they need a pillow that they
They have to be able to carry it themselves a bag a pillow a tray table
All-in-one took money started to sketch out some ideas
She went to friends and family she raised about
$20,000
And then
She went looking for a manufacturer and there was really only one company that was willing to work with me as a small
Inventor
And
They were marvellous for 18 months we went back and forth with samples and prototypes
And finally came to an agreement this pass
Spring
And
Was able to
Actually get the first shipments at the end of August
And marnie's invention she calls it pet pack that's p e t e p a k
It is a stuffed animal that you unzip the belly and it's a lap tray and you can zip the
The back of its neck and it has a little pack that you can put your books in your Trinkets and toys
And then you can turn it over and it becomes a little pillow Transformer
Right now there are four designs is an elephant's a panda a lion and a pig it's a pharmacy says
50 of them mainly Amazon everyone really wants to see me succeed and because
Surrounded myself with these pretty amazing people my friends my family they keeps me going even when you have those
Is entrepreneurial slumps where you just go okay I don't know if I can do this anymore and every time I feel like
That I have somebody behind me going yes you can you've made it this far as you can keep going nowadays whenever Marty travels with her kids
Playing all their stuff stays together in one place on that tray if you want to check out pet packs you it looks like
Mike Marney is currently selling them on Amazon you can find them by going there typing in pet PA
In search box and if you want to tell us about the company or idea your building go to build
NPR. Org that's filled with a d. Npr.org and thanks
As the end of the year approaches a lot of you've been asking about the best way to support
How I built this so first of all thank you for asking
And it is
Pretty easy to do
You go to stations
. npr.org
Find your local station and you make a year and contribution or even better
You've become a regular monthly donor
And when you do please tell them that
How I built this
Sent you
Soap find a local station
At stations. Npr.org
It takes like 2 minutes it's
Totally tax-deductible
And I please do tell them how I built this sent you
The Gannett stations that npr.org
Thanks
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com