We went to a contract manufacturing loss
Latrice Rafael on Assad
And told him I'll dream cave in the pitch
And said we need you to do like a test run for us
He's absolutely no reason
To do that
Because
99% of everyone that sits opposite me telling me this story does not
Succeed but for some crazy reason
I think you've got something interesting and I want to be in for the ride
Running PR is how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Heelys
Stories behind the movements
For women that have beauty parlor to building one of the leading skin care companies
The world
Dermalogica
Tell the story about Jane wurwand
Really begins
About a month before
She turned three
Is that month
Her father passed
Gene
Barely remember
What she does remember is
All of a sudden
Her mom had to get a job
There were four girls in the family.
Feed-in
She now had to do it all on her own
This was Scotland in the 1950
James Bond happens to have a skillet
She was a qualified nurse
So even though she had
Worked for many many years
She was able to fight
Find a job
And also
Pass along a name
Important lesson
The five words that changed my life
When my mom sang to me
It's just in my phone
Learn how to do
Learn how to do something
She was absolutely adamant that we each of us have to get a skill set training
That no matter what happen if we were somewhere anywhere in the world
We would have a skill to an all-hands
We could
Go to work
Immediately and earn money and keep food on the table
So when she was old enough
Jane wurwand decided on her skill
She become what was called at
The time
A beautician
And right after she got her qualifications
At age 19
Cheap started looking for work
I decided
Clown as it sounds so flipping out
It was freezing cold it was the winter of 1970
7 is one of the coldest on record
Animating the Sunday paper and I want to see way so hot
Display Sonos
Because I have to feel better about this
Freezing cold
Platinum living
So I look at the weather in the Sunday paper that said Johannesburg South Africa
7 degrees
Oh my God I wish I was in Johannesburg South Africa
If I turn the page it's like the universe sending me a sign
Does 1/4 page advertisement from the South African government
Saying
If you meet our
Prerequisite
Conoco station
We will pay in assisted passage for you to emigrate
South Africa as long as you agree to live there
Two years my soul
Good grief
I could be in Johannesburg in a month
And they had a list of
10 careers
That they wanted to recruit
Kanye West Old vocational training
The number one is Bush's number two is
Rotisseries
Third was a hairstylist in the fools who is a beauty therapist
I am six weeks later I was on the flight to Johannesburg
Until when you got there where were you actually able to find a job
Yeah
When I go to Cape Town I sat in this
Immigration hotel and I
Picked up Yellow Pages literally started calling salons in the Yellow Pages
To see if they would hire me
I'm by 5:30 that evening I had a job
Was it was it weird
Deliver at the time what was it like
To be there
It was
Completely
Different to anything I've ever
Experience
Yeah I remember my first day going to work I was taking a bath
But just kept coming I kept putting up my arm and they wouldn't stop and I couldn't figure out what was going on because of the front of the bus it said
The point and that's why I was going to work
Woman at the bus stop finally said to meet you and then I'm going to stop you because on the bus at the
Front sedney Blanc
Garnet means non-white
Launch is it we have to wait for a bus
Hawaii
Anyway you said that was so what am I supposed introductions I ain't never seen it obviously I know it's you.
Ya must have been
I must been strange
When you were there in South Africa where you more less doing the same thing that you've been doing in London
Scancam manicures pedicures everything that I've been doing
I'm trying to do I'm in love with the industry and I'm feeling so happy that I had this training because literally
As old as it sounds I know I could walk have a
Michael Castillo today I'll have a job by tomorrow because
There was a such a demand for the work we do and if you skill.
You got any love it you're going to get work
So how how long did you end up living there
I lived in South Africa for 4 years
And is that where you where you met your husband
Yeah I met him in South Africa he's from Cape Town
And he was already in process
For green card for the United States
I'm all we would dating his green card came through
And I can't even explain how exciting it is it is like
Getting the golden ticket
In a Willy Wonka chocolate bar it's
It's so hard
Emigrate
Legally and do it properly and he did and it went off he went and I was so excited for her
And
At the same time I had a job with an American company
And they were based in Los Angeles and
Within a few months that she got offered a training trip to Los Angeles
Until I met him when I came on that business trip
Together we just said
We've gotta do something here this is such an amazing Country Inns
Such an amazing opportunity
I went back age of my notice
Unhide an immigration attorney in LA and
4 months later I was on a flight
To Los Angeles
Secret telling this is like
Early 80s
Yeah it was January 1983
I was 24 and never been so excited in my life
Londi's in Los Angeles with a suitcase in one hand
And my beauty school diploma rolled up in tucked inside
Honda
Had no idea that it was an unemployment rate of 10.4
Time in California at that point it was good not to know these things right
My boyfriend be looking for a job for 6 months couldn't find anything
Living in a one-bedroom apartment in Marina del Rey ready to take any
And I'm a Londoner sdorica
I'm going to get job in Asylum
So I'm going to start cooling my
Trustee
And the first thing that struck me was so hardly any adverts
Skin care
They were mostly just like
Paris
How weird
Anyways and I quickly realized the ones I could find it was initially a handful
Roland Beverly Hills
I'm a very sordid from
Elitist expensive
Sword of offering
So I went and interviewed at water-cooled go to job interview went to in
I want to go there
The people at the front desk clerk
And yet
The people I was seeing in the white uniform to wear off in skin care treatments while we're paying like
So when I have my interview
There's Johnny questions message I do a question why I just noticed all the people are American on the front desk and
The people in the treatment rooms or european
And the woman who owns a who's French
Said to me was really simple The Americans
Have horrible training they don't know how to
In treatment
And the Europeans Council
So high in carbohydrates
I want away from the interviews and can't repeating what she just said to me in my head in my throat
I think we've just spotted the greatest opportunity
In this industry
Anna is
Train Americans
How to do better skin treatments
Ines
Combining with that
Retailing and selling
I'm surprised it's like skincare wasn't a big thing in in the us at the time
Skin care regimen
Very limited because it was old
Big head big shoulder pads
Dallas it was all makeup
I mean you can pick up magazines than Vogue Harper's Bazaar fashion magazine
Always articles on makeup that was nothing
The dermatologist
What will saying oh you can use anything you need soap for multi
Remind you that not only
Did
The correct product
What can you go to result in the skin
Mournful
When you receive a treatment in a salon it's about human Connection in human time
And there's something much bigger happening in every salon
Then just the service receiving soap
I was absolutely convinced
There was a waiting audience
For the next
Sierra in skincare
So at that point
Like what did you do
I went back set with Raymond my partner
And he was hurt
No we weren't married then we was
We would just dating living.
So he was having the same experience
Because oddly enough
The only job Piedmont
Secure was
Selling skin care equipment
4 Japanese
Company
Commission only
And we both come from the industry by spinning
So
He can sell one piece of
Does Japanese equipment which was amazing uses
Sophisticated equipment
To do what
To do skiing
To do steaming a foliation and it was brand new cutting-edge and he wasn't selling a piece
Honestly I'm trying to sell it
So we were having this Epiphany desota together because he was at how come they don't understand what I'm
Suning
Absolutely sounded in Europe and the rest of the world and we sat down
And said
The opportunity is
Huge
We can teach
How to do correct skin care treatments
And we can sell this equipment to the people that were teaching
So right then and there you decided to start building a plan to
Create a business
Yeah we actually cooked at up together on a drive back from San Diego to cos to nakul 2 hours
Nanette driveway completely to through a business plan
Wake up back on the kitchen table
On5
Pages of yellow legal pad
And the plan was
To train the
Professional
Skin therapist
Then cold
An esthetician
Are we going to take everyone who has lice
We were going to Bridget to the two-year training that we felt would bring them up to 11
Efficiency where they could be success
To the goal was really simple we're going to make
Skin therapist
Successful
Unable to run their own business
And be financially independent
Social Security was that you guys would open up a school and yeah
Ravens going to still sell equipment he was going to stay on the road I was going to teach
I was going to use the equipment he was selling in the closet I was teaching
Sell the equipment off to the claws
Are we cold at the international dermal Institute
Had you even have
Cash to start at the open up at
Yeah it was a helluva difficult together leaves
Cuz remember we were immigrants with no credit right
We had no Bank references with nothing
So the only space we could find was an empty space that been empty for years
Next to the Social Security Office in Marina del Rey
And they found it very difficult to lease
This is like long lines of people waiting for the checks every day exactly
Sitting you know people waiting to receive
So we rented it
And then we got the equipment from the Japanese money for
TripAdvisor
10 and We're Off to the Races and now the challenge walls
Who are we going to train because we didn't know anybody
Glove Butler
People have to know what
We were well so we knew that I'll Target malk it would license
Esthetician so in other words they had to order to be licensed
To work in the industry
So I called the State Board of Cosmetology in Sacramento Calif
On a cool demand I said do you have a list
Of everyone license
In the state of California
Epiphone skin care
It was very short list was at 2300 names and they said yes we do
Am I said
Is that list
Available is it public record
And they said yes
And I said can you send me the list
And they said yes we can salute the last
$25
I would you like us to print on Avery labels
Please
Something did
Wow and so we caught in the mail like the label of every person
Yes
So that was it and we sat in the library we go to phone book now
Cruise for the phone book
Are we plotted the zip codes within a 50-mile radius of Marina del Rey
Are we peeled off all the labels that fit those zip codes and we sent her a postcard
Saying this is who I am this is my qualification
I'm teaching a free one-day class
We mailed out we were hoping we got him
Like a dozen response
We had 70 responses
Within 24 hours free one-day class
Bring people in to get them so people would know what you're doing
So
We took 70 people rented Chaz took 70 people
Turn off to a couple of weeks of doing the free calls we charge $10 a person
So now we had $700
In that one day
Which is here and you were like teaching what
Cleansing double cleansing
Steaming
Exfoliation massage
And then I'm turning the moisturizer with very simple
I'm so by December of 1980
Trey
I was offering
8 different coffees you were teaching all of us last everything yeah to every class did all the loans
Laundry home at night to a one-bedroom apartment
Fight in the garage laundromat
And I never slept
Never slept
Twerks
Animo 16 hours a day
7 days a week
Fiji is
Fiat didn't take a salary because I mean by teaching classes
Gonna know we were actually earning enough
To pay the rent for the school
Uncover $300 a month for May
I was taking $300 a month half the business
To just sit with my underwear and panty has kept his job as a sales rep
And he was making enough money to pay our rent on our apartment
And a big night out was a burger on a Friday night
That was huge and we we
Saved every day
I'm for 3 years it was
Just us
A guy who immigrated she was a friend of ours
Who joined us in flat turn off floor in a futon
And he was out pushing the cloth he's he was out soon as a sales rep
Come and take free one first and then we'll
That's what they did
And Willy full class
Yeah I'd full Clauses with waitlist
Yeah what people were flying from San Francisco they were flying for
Phoenix still coming from Nevada
They will meet each other they were rooming together they will
They were forming friendships
The cost was finished at 5
Enduido de Pino pizza and boxed wine by 7:30
Eating burgers and
Lemon water
That we would know
Eating you no Twix and
Kit Kat
So short that time like
You know 8310ss Earth
The first years that I mean did you see yourself as an entrepreneur did you
Divisions maintenance
Huge thing or was it just something that you love doing that you were
It wasn't well Festival I didn't use the word on
I'm not sure I didn't knew that
Maybe I did
It was the hot sexy would like it is now
I just saw I'm going to leave the tribe we're going to change this industry
I'm so for three years the international Donuts she was already busy
Very quickly I realized and Raven and I both together said
What happened today using when they go back
And when I would often this they would say
They will European price
French German and Italian
Why you don't use an American Prada
Invasive
Which one
And I realized it would know American made
Products in the salon industry. What time is it in the department store in in the drugstore there's nothing
A light bulb went off the both Raymond and myself we both said
Okay
The big opportunity
Is product
Unwasted to me
If you had to write down
The kind of products you want to use
Do you believe you could write down the briefs for line unless it
Absolutely
You should write down the bridge
Unless said about making a product
When we come back in the moment
Will hear how Jane and Raymond invented that new line of skin products
And how they almost lost it before it even got off the ground
I got rice and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Everyone just a quick things
Two of our sponsors who helped keep this
Podcast golang
First to stamps.com
With stamps.com you can buy and print
Official US postage for
Any letter or package on demand
24/7
From your computer
No more trips to the post office and no need to lease and expensive postage
Sign up for stamps.com today to get this
Special offer
4 week trial plus Postage and a digital scale
Stamps.com click on the microphone
And enter built
Exosuit to Hyatt
I believe the modern business traveler is changing the face
A business
Please business Travelers don't settle there
Refusing mediocrity there Reinventing their careers bending titles and breaking new ground
And because
Beijing
Business travel
And that's why there's a place and a
House were good enough
Isn't
Hyatt Place in
Hyatt House hotels
You've come too far to settle now
So book your stay today
Hyatt.com
My saddle
Please stick around to the very end of the
The show today were saving that spot for your stories about the
Products and companies
You've been going
We've been getting
Hundreds of these
Story Circle
Credible
We've actually love reading them
To share something with you so stay with us till the end the end
Will tell you about
Okay
It's how I built this from NPR
And Gyros
And Jane and Ray have
Set it to create a whole new line of
Skin care products
They wanted to be
Different than anything else in the market
I wanted cleanses
It would completely went off with water
I wanted to develop
An exfoliant that would be really really
Efficient and not cause irritation to the skin
I have an allergy to lanolin
I didn't want any lanolin in the product I want to know mineral oil no fragrance
No drawing out
Alcohol no artificial
Ocala
Re-named the line Dermalogica
We had the international dermal
Attitudes that was kind of fitting with that
And we wanted to know which line it with a bridge
Between a pharmaceutical product
Anna skincare
Prada cosmetic
Cat sounds like
Amazing a lab to the
Yeah
We start food with no drawers
Only bottles into
And we didn't have soda
Pink Jordans with gold
Thompson
Pink boxes we had gray and white pack
A packaging look
Pharmaceutic
Many times people criticized in the early days it was on play
And we felt it was utilitarian and that was the image we want a
That was who we were
Even working with you
Price for
Permission Cricket when you were still really young your and you're
Your early twenties and late twenties
How did you know how to make the
I've no idea
So
Icosapent took him is doing you and he said
Look at you looking for chemist
I can make the product
You want to use a lot of Botanica
Speak to the rule material for
Supplies for the plumbtech
And ask them
Who in Los Angeles
Formulating product if anyone
Using a lot of plants
That's cuz you need to work
Someone that knows he's material
And that was what we did we contacted the raw materials
Supplier New Jersey often do you have any come smell like that using you materials
And they gave us a list
And we started cooling relay
Honda Odyssey
1793 hive
5 would take a call
And of the five there was one that number one was willing to work with us the number to we felt could do it
Boot camps in LA
Yeah he was in LA he's since passed away but he was in Los Angeles and
We couldn't pay him that was this
So we figured out Raymond figured out this amazing kind of
Way of paying him based on
The first two years
Manufactured
Products
Percentage of
The product that we manufacture not a percentage of sales because
We wanted to make sure he was tied into the fact that if we wouldn't actually able to ever make
He wasn't going to get
Paid
And he agreed
And and what did you decide
Jamaica was a one product
Two products of 27 products
Because we needed to go in with a.
If we went in with one or two products
We couldn't
Capture
Skin therapist
Attention and say you need to use this
Exclusively in your room and you need to file this
It would have been enough to like creams
23 cleanses to moisturizer
Three boosters
Two masks
Annoying makeup remover
And then we had eight or nine products
That were professional only peels
Unprofessional moth
Some things that would only be used in the treatment room
He was making
All these price
Yeah he was like Rumpelstiltskin is formulating them all you were going and testing them out a little bit earlier
I briefed him
He came back 2 days later with a little cardboard boxes samples I could we possibly have made these
Any copyright I mean that's going to save on them both elephant
But they were both great
I mean an end
In 9 months
We had developed 27 formula
And we named them in one afternoon
How are you like even
Funding that
Is easy weather today like
Hundreds of thousands of dollars
Test it and just to look into the tubes that I probably should
How did he how did you how were you able to do it
We were buying tubes that nobody wanted we were buying 500 at a time that they were setting to us Vino
Feeling them yourself
No but we went to a contract manufacturing Los Angeles they actually saw the Felon also.
And told him I'll dream cave in the pitch
And said we need you to do like a test run for us
We can pay you like
$500
And his minimum ones with Bowser
Without him we really would never come because he looked to us
After we've been sort of like pitching
Breezily for an hour
He's absolutely no reason
To do that because
99% of everyone that sits opposite me telling me this
Story does not
Succeed but for some crazy reason
I think you've got some
Something interesting and I want to be in for the ride
How are you able to test them
The product I tested everything approved ever
On yourself
You are like your own
Guinea pigs with my own guinea pig and then
I took it to Claus
I like week the students like to Austin with a soul
I love that
And they were using it in the classroom
Just out of curiosity does that have to go through like
Any kind of regulatory
Mission writing
We would
What's the movie that we were very young
New company in
A lot of the rules I suppose we weren't even aware of
Probably
But Tom
At the time and still we weren't using any ingredients
Controversy
We would eliminate
Titulos de Z
Irritating
Ingredients
I'm so in the nine months that we would
Testing the product
We would develop
That we had
Had any incident
Reactions or allergies
He said I was at that you just like
You just launched
Yeah
We launched in January of 1986
And the crazy thing was the chemist
To develop these formulas who we were
Going to pay off over to you.
Came to us in December
Of 585 four months before we were due to Launch
And said that he did not believe
In the product he didn't believe we could be success
For any new venture
What why did he say that
Because he just seen so many stars
Cops fail this is the visitor chemist
This is the guy that you like this is Rumpelstiltskin
And he just said I don't think it's going to work
Yeah I don't think it's kind of what I'd like you to pay me out for
For the formulas
Now
And we didn't have any money to buy the 4th I mean that he wanted something extraordinary and we whistle them down
Came down to
United soda $14,000
Hollywood
Lot of money for yuan
Why did the chemist not think
It would work
How to get to believe enough
How do you do using the formula
I think he's at least with two immigrants
These crazy immigrants how well do they know about starting a company
What do they know about funding a company contest
Doll skin care
Were you freaking out
Yes we were freaking out but we had to figure this out scramble
Put it together so
We
Borrowed money for family we put together everything we could from the
School we put it together when you pay them aren't you so nervous like if this is the guy sing to you this is not going to work
And you're like we better come up with a 14000 but we're going to be kind of screwed because this guy saying it's not going to work
We were worried that formulas he was giving us
Literally be younick I exchanged on the table of a Coco's Diner
Que pasa manila envelope of formulas however we passed the money at
Honda
We were worried that the phone is he giving us for not formulas that we approve but we actually had
The guy who was going to manufacture the product
Look at
Formulas for us and he's another
This isn't that right
This the real deal
Just thinking about that that moment where a guy was a total expert
Sing to you
Who's never manufactured
Skin care products that
Listen to work
And yet you have to come up
$14,000
Hey him
Did you have any doubt
No
You didn't think you didn't maybe is right
No he couldn't be right wasn't possible because if he was right
We are about to launch into the biggest disaster of all life that may have been
But we turned each other one with self repeated enthusiasm
Yuan Ray
Like you were a world like this is going to work it's going to work
Isn't it I need one of us is having a modicum of doubt
Guarantee the other woman having a good day so on the days when I might be saying
We not crazy right
Rabies
It's going to be great and on the days when he was saying
I think it's a house of cards maybe it'll going to collapse
I'd be saying
Nana we just have to
Plato's Closet was so fantastic everybody's excited
This is going to work
You know what
If it doesn't work
It's not the greatest disaster in the world we have nothing to lose by
Alex
What if it works
And we did the classic immigrant tsinghua
Look at the population only takes 1% of the population to buy one product
Enormous
Bigger than it could ever be in the UK
So
Let's go
Okay so you had no investors and
And you basically figured
Will sell the product that will fund
The manufacturer of more of the product
Yeah exactly
Most of your customers were who
My students
The first account we opened was in Bakersfield Calif
20 hour
And I was one of your students who had a salon there or
Becky Sinclair
What's the name
She won't talk with the check and I said Becky I haven't even shown you the product and she said Jane if you and Raymond are in
I'm into
And I said you are first account in the world
And that was at my student came out they came up and said we want and we want to be positive that
This was a California made skin care product
We were going to Take On The World
And you are not selling this in storage right
The only
Do you have to have a skin Center hydrotherapy
And why was that why wouldn't you just like sell it in Walgreens
I don't know because
Because I'm asking therapist we knew that this was an educated
It so it had to be people understand
The skin
I don't sell these for the people that brought us
The party
I my mom another piece of advice she gave me was you leave
The party with the person you went with
We whittwood committee
Justin Theroux
Headed Dermalogica do
In that first year
Did $1000000 no face
That's insane
It was
So
Insane you must have at that point
Like I had all these buyers who wanted
To buy you out
Via
And those people want you to lend us money
And you didn't take any of it
No we wouldn't even sales
Funding the business
Yeah it was so
What's great I mean
That first year we were planning everything back into the business to know more stuff we hide our itself. We want to
People walking in that with dumb logic
I thought we were putting everything back into building the business
But how are you like
Teaching classes and
Hiring staff and like
Building
We were working all tell the story a day
I didn't hire another teacher until 1980
Salvage rights in the closet teach McCarthy's
I'm still doing the laundry
And Raymond
And
A couple of other people
What handling the product
When the class is finished at 5
The clock we would do the UPS oldest
I was packing the boxes still in the box is right in the label they were five of us in the company we did
Everything
We finished it
10 at 9:11 at night
Everyone came back to my house
Fall flat for spaghetti
And then we were back at work
The next morning
When did yuan Andrei
Searcy back and say I might actually get really rich from doing this thing that we never
New we can get rich
Lost you
Lowry
No I mean
We knew we had a
The tiger by the toe
Tile.
And we
New
That we had to
Spread of thousand snatched movie needed eggs in Old basket so that
Is there was a recession in one place it wasn't going to take a business
And international terminal
Who is now the number one provider
Advanced education in the industry worldwide we train a hundred thousand skin therapist every single year
And lost you
A wholesale turnover was a little north of 250 million dollars
Take you guys were
You basically ran the company
Promise 30 years
Yeah
And
Decided to sell it
Last year sold to Unilever
Why did you decide to do that
You know we from the company as what I supposed to say was you never beneficial
Dictatorship
We've always had a great
Team
We still have a great
Team but the decisions ultimately
He came down to Raymond to myself
Product approval Advertiser everything the brand ID
And you know we realized
Much that we hate Susan
Think about it the death rate is holding steady at 100%
Pho
Ultimately
We're going to have to make a plan
Of what we wanted to do with
The company we have to dilute has the 17 + 2
And neither of them wanted
To come into the business and we didn't want until we tell them
Kind of before they were born we decided we have five children and not coming into Dermalogica
It's our dream and we believe
It's a burden
Two kind of shoulder your children with that
Responsibility
And so we
Decided will hire a CEO
Are we going through a couple of CEOs
In the eight years before we decided
We eat apples at work
Can we realized
The problem probably wasn't the CEOs a problem was fully off
Because
We are the founders you don't we have this flu
Passion about the ownership
It is very hard to run a company when the founders Room Place
Kind of want to have the last word
And so we decided we should at least it's
Explore the idea of an ox
We've never taken a phone call from anyone that was interested in buying never even taking a
Cool cuz we said we don't even have a car
It's a despot
Until we we could have lined up
Who we thought would be the right partner
For us
And then we we set about
Deciding which ones we wanted to court
And Unilever
With very aligned with us
On that sustainable living plan
The very long with us on the volume
And so we decided to go forward
And I have to say we have one year in and it's been a fence
So much so that Raymond and I kept
Absentia.
The company was still involved
It and that chemists the one who like bailed a month before Dermalogica
Lochte he ever come back to you guys
And apologize
No NFL
He never did know he was like Rumpelstiltskin that flew out the window and never came back
It means amazing like looking back at your story
Because your mom was a widow with
For girls
And the cheetah racing around and she must been a little worried when you laugh
England for South Africa and
Us
Very little
What did she make of your
Of your success
I know I know that she was really proud she felt validated in the direction that she pushed us in
She passed away in 2001
But she's so awesome
Success
The Lofts of months of my mom's life shed Alzheimer's
I'm not sure if she remembered
Anything about gemologica
She remembered me and I sat on her bed when she was in the hospital in
I was giving her money
Carol I was right back to filing her nails and
Painting lemon
She was watching me
And she
I looked across at the woman who was in the chair next to her
And she said to her with a huge liquor price she said to
My daughter is a qualified manicurist you know
And am I smile just always doing it because I felt the
If she doesn't remember anything about
What's accessory side she's really proud
But I got that training and I'm going to be out
Okay
And I was
Jane wurwand founder of Dermalogica
Now spends most of her time on helping women around the world become entrepreneurs through her foundation
And of course we couldn't let Jane go without asking for her number one skincare tip
Soap Puritas
Single best thing you can do for your skin is keep it out of the Sun
So you wear sunblock you where you hunt I stop lying out in the sun
Get busy start your business
Got change the world
Listen to the show this week
If you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you could how I built this NPR. Org you can also
Describe two are showing iTunes and please do us a favor and write a review let us know what you think
Kelso right to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet gets at
How I built this
Shows produced this week by Runabout Fateh with music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis thanks also to the immigrants
Santa's Mexican food and Jeff Rogers
Gyros and you listening to how I built this
Hey thanks for sticking around because
Right now
Pressure washer
Hundreds of stories that
You guys have been sending us these are stories about
The things that
You are building
Like many new Ventures this one though
To talk about
Start with the problem
We could actually refer to it as trash juice
Fresh juice
Juice
Which is the runoff from dumpsters and garbage truck
If you're in urban dweller you walk by and you smell it and you do not want to go anywhere near that
Okay so Michael vanity and its Partners came up with a device to put a stop
To trust you
Before it even starts
Think of it as a utility cart
There is a hundred foot hose on it
And when you pull the trigger at the end of the toes
Phone comes out
Think of it
Scrubbing Bubbles x 1000
In these Scrubbing Bubbles are, like the secret magical ingredient here
Michael says they're full of bacteria that eat up all the
Junk in dumpsters and in trash chutes
And then the phone kind of evaporate so you don't even need water
To clean it up and
No water
Old tractors
We test out the product
We got incredible feedback
And
The maintenance guys
Cut my cleaning time in half
Michael's company is called TP foam it's about a year old and so far they sell sweat 60 of cleaning cards
Two buildings from Maine to Florida
What orders are coming in and Michael says so far they're doing pretty well
If you want to tell us about the company or idea that you're a building
Go to build
Npr.org that's build
Got npr.org
Thanks
One more thing before we let you go if you ever wonder
What podcast should I listen to
The big listen is
To help
On NPR news podcast host Lauren Ober in
Is YouTube podcasts you might never have heard of
And gives you the inside scoop
Pancho's you already love
The one you listening to right now
When you want something new find the big listen
NPR one app
Npr.org
Flash
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cust
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com