Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource
Tools tips and information
In about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
We haven't told anyone that the site was lie if you just want to drive any traffic to it because we were
I get an order and then 10 minutes later we get another order
And then another order and then another order and kind of go from there
This feeling of elatement a crap
From NPR it's how I built this
Nashoba innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movement since they built
Gyros and
Founders of Warby Parker tell the story of how they burst and idea and idea
Disrupted the entire eyeglass industry in America
I grew into a billion dollar Temple
So back in 2008 and Eagle Blumenthal and Dave gilboa first arrived on the campus
The Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania they were there to start business school and they met each other and
Two other students Andy Hunt and Jeff Raider the for them would go on to co-found Warby Parker butt into
2008 that time they didn't know that yet but they did know something that they all had in common was they were really
Frustrated with how eyeglasses worked its stem from this thing that will most people
Probably experienced at some point they kept losing their glasses and Dave and backed right before
Start a business school at accidentally left his glasses
An airplane and it cost me $700
And I just couldn't justify the full-time student paying that much for a new pair of glasses
Yeah the new iPhone 3-g had come out that way didn't lie at the Apple Store paid $200 for and it did
All these magical things
And meanwhile the technology behind a pair of glasses is 800 years old in
It just didn't make sense but you're like okay I've got this amazing iPhone this magical
Portal 2 all of you knowledge eyeglasses made out of
Plastic
Are like
Super expensive
Yes it was complaining to anyone that would listen about why glasses were so expensive and then Andy kept losing
His glasses
And you was buying everything online but couldn't figure out why you can buy new glasses online
Effectively sunglasses on my right because this like 2008 and I mean by that point
He likes selling things online with his brand new idea
We kind of started this conversation where we are
Kind of frustrated by different
Pieces of the eyewear industry
And we knew that Neil had spent a number of years
I'm working for an hour non profit and
And probably knew a lot more about this than we did and so
We're on the computer lab one day
And that we started asking me a bunch of questions and
No pun intended but any color eyes are open that there was a massive opportunity
What do you remember about that
Being in the computer lab me I would like over there
It was
So like why are glasses so expensive then
When I was working at nonprofit visionspring I've actually designed eyewear and I would go to the factory
Mapreduce
Glasses in
So I knew a little bit about the optical in
Australian
And it's dominated by a few very large companies one of which is
Luxottica
Exotic as a marker
The cap about 30 billion dollars
They
Jamon Oakley Ray-Ban Oliver Peoples persol and Arnett
They license almost every major fashion brand Under the song like Ralph Lauren and Shannon Allen
Prada Dolce & Gabbana
They also own a lot of the major retail chains like
LensCrafters and Pearle Vision and Sunglass Hut
Company owns
All those things have crazy Sears Optical Target Optical
The store and all those brands
Persol Rayban
All owned by the same company owned by the same company end
They on the second largest vision insurance plan in the country eyemed
So
You walk into a LensCrafters you don't realize that
Mustache election
Car frame
Games that they've made
And the vision shirt
So you knew that
Exactly
So we just thought like a
Well now
It's a lot clearer why
Glasses are so expensive
So we thought
Why not
Glasses
The light bulbs went off
Turn all of our minds
And then later that night
Let you know when you have a feeling at or just an idea you're so excited about you actually have trouble sleeping
Exactly
It was that
Feeling
It was like 2 in the morning
Shut off an email
And then I'd like to a one-day responded and 202 Jefferson an 80 responded in like we were all
Up thinking about
Next day
We decide hey
After class let's all get together and when she sat down at a bar right on
23rd and Walnut
Andover beer
We're discussing this more
Hand
Should we do this
Should we really go after this and we also said yeah
How do you say you guys are
Business school and you're thinking okay let's do this
Play quite a business plan that you start looking for money I think all of us we talked about how it's
Decided we were about this idea and he said while we're at business school to learn how to write a business what better way than to actually build on
On ourselves so
We all decide to take the same class in entrepreneurship class
Without thought of that class is edible business plan and we spent the next several weeks
Really researching every element of
Or idea getting a bunch of great insights from professors
Running a bunch of surveys standing for hours in
Different optical shops in
And then that culminated in Playa 40 page business plan
We entered the Wharton business plan competition and we got eliminate
In the semifinal round
They just kind of put a chip on her shoulder
Where we sat okay well now we got something to prove
And
At that point we felt really passionate that
This is going to work that point you're still working out
Taper Avenue
You still did not have
Any money I'm assuming
I even have a product
You didn't have a manufacturer so
Why were you guys for concert
How are you even able
The test the idea
Yeah we talked to everyone that
I will get us 5 minutes
Just about the idea initially we got a bunch of push back but said
Well gaddiya buying glasses online is
Kind of strange to me
Kahoot
Basically all our friends
Classmates
And a lot of people told us that
Creating a brand is hard enough
So is creating an
E-commerce site
You should pick one of those but for us the magic
And creating a bird
Greater brand
I'm so behind in on this issue that we had to figure out a way
People can try on glass
People are saying
Nobody's going to buy glasses online because you
You got a touch of your
Feel them
Exactly
Surreal moment of self-doubt
Journeys are always these moments where
You feel like a complete
Play the idiot
I this was like
One of those challenges.
Really made us question
Should we continue to spend time on this versus
The million other things that week
Can be doing at school
So how did you
Thank you to get over
People
You know thinking they needed to touch
Going to try them on
So we just thought a lot about how do we
Remove every Ops
The call to purchasing
And the thought was well if we offer
Free shipping that will encourage people to buy food
Free returns
That will also
Make it less risky for our customers and that's
Should have led us to this other idea to do a home try-on program
So you guys decide
Let's send these people let them try them
And they like them
They just send them back and we'll put the lenses in and that's it
Did you guys have any other problems that you
Anticipated
As you wish
True
This idea
Yeah I think the other element was that
We were trying to sell a product normally cost several hundred dollars
And
We were telling
For less than
$100 into
There was inherent skepticism about the
The quality
Right inside WeChat log
How do we
Just get as many of our glasses on
This is possible
Yeah man
That's when
This light bulb went off
Program what's really no
No company
I was offering
Until that time and
Beside we just want to get
Are products on
People's faces in
Can people by afterwards
So so so you guys wanted your glasses
Obviously be much
Even less than a hundred bucks
How
How did you do
Decide on the exact
Price
Our initial thought was
What's the sell glasses for $45
We remember going into the head of the marketing Department's office at Wharton
And we sit next to him Slide the deck on his desk and say hey
Where can I transform the odds
Pickle industry
We're going to charge $45 for a $500 pair of glasses
Have any kind just laughed at us and said no I won't work
Like you didn't even like retard act like every graph goes up and to the right
And he said
I'm sorry guys I
First of all
Prices
Is the biggest in the
Decatur air quality
And it's just outside of the realm of believability that you can sell a product
Let's price
So we walked out of this meeting pretty deflated
But it led us
To investigate pricing a little further
It showed us
That yes prices
Time indicator quality there's a psychological barrier around $100
So one thought what should we charge $99 and
We thought that was too discounting and cheap and we were
Building an aspirational brand
So we actually settled on $95
Using just our instinct
Thinking that this stuff
It sounds cheap and that it looks deliberate and
Officially love
What's decent
How did you guys come up with
Because it sounds like like a an aristocrat from like
Northumberland
In England or something like
Warby Parker
The hardest thing that we did in those early days was
Set 11 a.m. that all four of us liked
Still have our spreadsheet. Over 2000
Names that we tested
On our very patient friends
Yeah
Too early Jack Kerouac characters
That Dave actually discovered
When he went to the New York Public Library exhibit on Cadillac
And to the characters were Warby pepper
And Zack Parker
And that's it
Everybody that
I joints Warby Parker
On their first day on their deaths together
Copy of Dharma bums
Alarm 50 weather goodies
Bestial Blumenthal of Warby Parker after the break Neil and co-founder Dave gilboa
Removing that well-thought-out business plan
Paper and into the real world and Gyros and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Market
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic out
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast
Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts
And features including e-commerce functionality
The end mobile app
Squarespace also offer
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR on gaara's and Taylor show we've got Neil Blumenthal and Dave gilboa two of the founders of Warby
Parker
Come up with this idea and they
Thought it through and
Now
The only thing left
What's the exit
How much money do
Did you guys raise initially
And how did you do it
So the next thing about business school was that most people work
For a few years before going back to school and so
Collectively the four of us 2
The car life savings from
When we were working before school and invested into the business
We invested $120,000 between the four of us
To get the business
Stop the ground
Yeah we work for year-and-a-half
I pay myself a salary we didn't have an office
We did win a couple of Grants from Morton to that that helped as well.
We were very Scrappy and
Famous bootstrap
Quite a while and we ended up
Launching a business and then when
Another 15 months
Before we
Raise our first round of funding
The Hedgehog
Ashley find the manufacturer to make the glass
I mean did you kneel to have contacts from
When you work at that
Nonprofit
Yeah
We leverage allowed the relationships that I had then
To visit
Is the factories
And we actually
Prepared
A PowerPoint
Because even though
This was going to be a vendor that we are
Buying from
We have to sell them on our vision and that we weren't
Did Sirius and
How far
To pay them
Forsyth Tech
Monthly payment upfront
Okay so you pay for these frames
The manufacturer makes
And what did you even
2 with all those glasses
To remember
Getting boxes and boxes of these frames
Ship to
Are apartment admin I fit with the doorman building the doorman had
No idea what to do it literally took us
A couple hours to load
Do all these runs
In the elevator
Into our apartment
Then stack all these
And then unpack them and we
Ourselves
Inspected
Every single frame
And this was all the while
We were
Working two
Figure out
How are we going to watch it
We basically
Need to start the business only ambassador
Free things
Our initial inventory
Our website
And some PR
Knowing that you'll
One shot
Sort of launch
A brand
Even before you
You launch the company
You had a publicist going out trying to
To drum up publicity for
Had meetings with
Almost 50 PR
Part of it was us evaluating them but
I'm at the same time we had to sell ourselves to the
PR firm
Nothing less sexy in the fashion world than for mbas for Morton
We knew we were going to launch
Sometime in the spring
And we really wanted
How to be in
Premiere magazine doesn't
Approval
Sowa
What we were targeting
And so
We had some production samples
We didn't have a website up
But we were really pitching
Harvey's bags
Asean zaz
Exclusive Lounge partners
We were
Thrilled to hear that she
GQ envogue we're going to run stories we have no idea
The stories were to look like with the content was going to look like
I mean
Why would these huge magazine
Lake Trust
A bunch of
Business school students
Didn't even have a company like if you went to the website at that point there was nothing up there like
Crazy to think that they would have done that right
I can do a few things at work in our favor right one was
Identifying
The right
PR
Person to help rapper
Persona 5 we often say that
Tiaras
Like 30% the messenger 70%
The message
Address the message
This is a
Pretty novel at the time right there was
Nobody selling glasses online so the idea of selling glasses
Online was novel
That $95 price point for $500 glasses
Funny novel
The home try-on program was novel so in fact
GQ actually called us in that play
But I wear in the article that they put
So I think they were
Like these hooks that writers and editors could get excited about
So how much of an impact did that
Did that have on
Yeah we we were
Just blown away by that
Impact that it hadn't
The traffic in sales so
We got a call from
Are publicist
The day before
He was going to hit newsstands and we still had a landing page up
He went to warbyparker.com it said coming soon
Please enter your email address
GQ sitting tomorrow
And our website
Still had a bunch of bugs in it we are working
With one developer
And we were on the phone with him kind of frantically
Working out some of the most critical
Bugs
On the site
And we finally at 4 a.m. Saturday
God's verses
Stable enough
We all need a couple hours of sleep before
For we have class tomorrow
And
We were sitting in class the next day
We haven't told anyone that the site was live our
Parents didn't know the site was live our best friend's didn't know the site was live
But we didn't want to drive any traffic to it because we weren't sure it would wear
Had my phone set up to
Be notified anytime we got an order
And those around 10 a.m.
And so I get an order and
A 10 minutes later we get another order and then another order and then another order and kind of
Go from this feeling of elatement
Oh crap we have to have business inventory
And we hadn't contemplated building in any sold-out functionality or weightless functionality of the site
So you are literally selling out of glasses but people still ordering them because it's the website
Didn't know when you would run out of there we had no inventory tracking it all because we knew we were assuming one to two orders a day
And got a job that have nothing else my mom would buy a hundred pairs of glasses from us
But we are we really have tempered expectations because we also recognize that what we were trying to do was
Hildebrand
And that takes a really long time
So we called an emergency meeting after that first hour-and-a-half class and we were debating
Okay what do we do here or do we just keep taking orders and then figure out what to tell
Bellator do we take down website
And while we're having this 2 minutes
Discussion and I'm looking at my phone and we have
10 more orders am I get to delete we got to do something here
And tell
We place an emergency call to our developer
And miraculously was able
How to build in
Is weightless functionality on the Fly
And
Within
4 week. Weed sold out of
Our best-selling
Mixtiles we had to wait list
20000 customers
Did you guys sell
Yeah 10000
What's up
And you just did not I you would not ordered enough glasses from the manufacturer
You literally
Couldn't and they couldn't make them fast enough for you
You know it I think
We were ambitious in terms of the number of frames that we purchased but also
Not overly
Risk tolerance
And I think we've
Approach this business in
In a way that yeah that's not bankrupt ourselves on inventory we hadn't raised any money
Investors
Yeah it was our our life savings that we important so there was
Really a
A limited number of frame that we have the ability to
I mean
Like a good problem to have
That you you have a waitlist
Volume
Out of the gate
Killing it
Is that am I right or was it actually
IPad Pro
I think we've learned a lot of important lessons in
30 days weather
We were terrified that
May we had all these early adopters
Excited to
Place an order from us and we didn't have anything
Need to sell them
And for a lot of customers that took us
Numbers of 9 months
To get through the waitlist
So we were terrified who are these people are going to
Meet with a bad taste in their mouth
A lot of companies
Yeah and I think it did have some positive effects that it created this aura that
Wow this
Andrea Lee Height
Nothing creates cool like scarcity but I think we also learned
At 11
In terms of
Being empathetic to customers
Founders we reached out to everyone on that
Waitlist
Time for
People that were
Bad experiences were really good
Disappointed meme
Glasses
People discounts
You know what I think
From the gecko we wanted to create
Have a positive impact on the world and part of that
Is treating
Customers Fair Lady
Treat them fairly when I come
Price
Treating them
Fairly
When they call up and
I'm playing
Bantu apologize and ask
Explain when
Make mistakes and then have something that
We did from the very beginning
Premier League
And we're still trying to figure out
How to run this business
Apartments
Time students
Spark customer service line
With a Google Voice number that we set up when someone
Call
It would simultaneously ring all four Founders cell phone
Customer service
And so we looked at our class schedules and their 12 hours
4 week when all four of us
Class at the same time
And
We said it while we should hire someone who can answer the phone when none of us are available
And so
Will be hired
The name Rin
I said you're going to be working 12 hours a week and
Transfer
We're doing and
I make that first weeks ended up working
100 hours
And now she's running
Our customer experience team what's it about Hunter
50 people
Antennas as I kind of Off to the Races from day one
So did you guys I mean how quickly
Did you guys come
Get together to say
Holy hell
This is real
Can I make it
We were too busy staying up all night responding to customer emails and
I remember when the first couple days like we actually decided to go to one of the classes that we were all in
And
We were all typing
Previously on Arkham
Computers cuz we weren't really paying attention and we were just responding to
The customer email
How to process orders
I'm and everything in the classroom got really quiet
Evan the four of us are no luck.
Everybody was staring at us including the professor and here we were typing away when clearly they were done.
Let's to be happy
With obvious you are not you are not listed as a we just stopped going to that class
I mean I remember waking up
Every morning with the laptop on my chest
Because I honestly
Persona cast
There's an overwhelming amount of work in those early days and so
We didn't have
Even a minute to breathe in and take a step back
And think about what would happen
So after this line
And after the company obviously
Start to gain traction
When did you guys decide
You know like we better
Checkered racing money
And we went
And try to get Dad
Cuz we figured I'd fly give up equity
If we could just get some loans to help us
Find the cemetery that we needed
We went to 18 different banks
And only one
Would talk to us
And again this was
2010 so soon after
The financial crisis
And what all these going officer said is
Hey we've never seen such a beautiful business plan we've never seen a company
That has such great early results
But
We can't give you a loan because you don't have two years of tax return
What did you guys do
We ended up getting
Any $200,000 SBA loan
We had to sign
Pride 400 document
Including one that said we weren't going to use the money to open a zoo
And we really try to think of other creative forums
Financing a business
And so we working
With a third party will just
Company that managed
Summer inventory
And
Loved our brand our business in
He was asking what can he do to help Drive growth in our business so that they can have more business
I really constrained by
Our ability to purchase inventory at the
Pyside Wild
You guys seem like you're really good at
PR
Our company need some help
Lotr what if
You do some PR Consulting for us
And
We'll pay you a few hundred thousand dollars
So I guess you launched in 2010
Today you have closed
800 employees
You sold
I'm sure millions of pairs of glasses
How much do you think you are successful
Was because of
You know you guys are
Smartass
Really hard workers or
Or how much of it was it was like
To say that there's a lot of it
Deliberate serendipity
For example we were really lucky
To be exposed
H2r marketing
Professor that helped us think through
Pricing
We had created Goodwill by
Being friendly and doing well in his class and he was willing to dedicate time to us
So I think there's a million examples of that or
Eyemart
Friends
Calling in favors on our behalf
Want to think that we were just straight-up lucky on his timing
Right timing is everything
Paint coming off
The financial crisis
The public was
Looking for ways to save money and I think a brand like ours
Even resonated
Even more
Last year I read that
That you guys raised like
A hundred million dollars
Soap
What's what's a company valued at
At our last valuation was over billion dollars
When you when you hear that a billion dollars
That's crazy
It's pretty crazy
Yeah you know
It's exciting but not nearly
As exciting as
Psych coming to work
Everyday and
Being in an office
They said we'd actually designed ourselves
Seeing people in the subway wearing our glasses like that one
Never get old can you recognize your glasses
Oh yeah
A10 fact
The first time
We saw the glasses in in the wild
I remember
Seamless prostatic what are my odds on the subway
Fireman
Union Square
And I just are following the person
Handy David
If someone's following you on the platform like
You've got a dirty look but I just big like ear-to-ear smile
That's Neil Blumenthal Warby Parker
Neil and Dave gilboa co-founded Warby Parker with two other friends for business school generator and Andy
Company actually partnered with the nonprofit where Neil used to work fish in Spring
Bring eyeglasses to people around
The world don't have access to them
Hey text listen to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes
She can go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And it's at how I built this
Our show is produced as Weak by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to leave a grandson has
Mexican port at Jeff Rogers
Gyros and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey thanks for sticking around
Because we are now the very end of the show the part of the show where we
We hear about the things
You are building
This week the story of Two Sisters who are trying to
Change the way people
Sac hi my name is Melissa Lee I'm from Somerville Massachusetts and my sister Linda
Co-founders of Cruz facts
Melissa and Linda are in
2 things you wouldn't necessarily think need to be fixed
Skiing
And
Trail mix
Both seem like they're kind of
Great except when you put them together because then
Then you have a problem
It's this trade-off of I'm really hungry
But I have to figure out how to get the
The snack
And not have my fingers go numb so you have to
Yo take one glove off user
TV stand
Given that right fumbling to grab a glove full of
Pretzels with M&Ms
In the pocket of your
Winter coat
It doesn't work
So to solve this problem Melissa and her sister came up with 8
Trail mix that comes
In a tube with a hinged
Lid attached to
We wanted it to be able to be open with one hand to be able to be open with a glove on
And
Sort of to be able to fit in your pocket
No matter how bulky your gloves
Just a flick of your thumb
Open the tube YouTube
Tip it back
Chugs and dried fruits and nuts
Send
You hit the slopes
So I think spreading the idea that is
It's drinkable or that you would
Use it like you would use a water bottle
That's what I like people really start to understand the concept of wow this is like something different than just
My regular trail mix in a ziplock bag
It actually took
Melissa and Linda
Several months to find the right
Kind of tube
Science labs
And eventually they landed on what they thought was the
Perfect fit
Incubation tube for testing those on people they were like they was kind of like urine samples and I was like
I don't want a package it in something that reminds people of your and that's the last thing I want
So the two sisters
Cat searching
Found the right match
Which course
Crew socks are not being sold at a few ski resorts in New Hampshire and Vermont
Company is only 6 months old and it's not yet profitable
So for now
Melissa and Linda are
Keeping their part-time jobs as
Guristas
Somerville
But the best part for Melissa
She gets to work with her sister
I wouldn't be able to do this if I had to do it alone there's just so much
Doubt that goes into the process
And I think it was
Really really helpful to have someone by your side
And someone going through all the
The same ups and downs
Text Melissa Lee She co-founded
Crew
Snacks that
Pron
If you want to tell us about the company or idea you are building
Go to build
Npr.org
Build with a
Add
Npr.org
Thanks
As the end of the year approaches a lot of you've been asking about
The best way to support how I built this
So first of all thank you for asking
And it is pretty easy to do
You go to stations
. npr.org
Find your local station and you make a year and contribution or even better
You've become a regular monthly donor
And when you do please tell them that how I built this
Sent you
So find a local station
At stations. Npr.org
It takes like 2 minutes
It's totally tax-deductible
And I please you tell them
How I built this NPR
Beginning stations that npr.org
Thanks
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cust
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com