Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
In the middle of my meeting with her I could tell I was losing her and I just knew it was my one
I'm shot so I said you know what Diane will you come with me to the bathroom she goes excuse me I go I know
I know it's a little bit will you just please come with me to the bathroom I want to show you my own product before and after
And she she said okay
From NPR
How I built this
A show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
And the stories behind the movements they go
The story of house
Sara Blakely you designed a new kind of underwear called its tanks and eventually became the youngest
Female billionaire
In America
Blakely was growing up
Florida
Exactly
Dream of
Designing ladies
Is undergarments
Chicks you want to be a lawyer but would you take LSAT
She failed
Twice
After college she got a job at Disney World
As a ride breeder in the early nineties
She got another job
Who is selling facts
Door to door
Feeling
More life
With all the rejection and
Daddy here where you at
It was like water outfits
Duckback
Oh my gosh no I
Would feel very defeated and many times I would
Get in my car and drive around the block multiple times you know just trying to convince myself
To walk through the door
And sometimes I'd walk through the door and they were small offices were the whole office would turn and look at me at the
Same time it helps
I'm something to completely lose my nerve and just say oh sorry I'm I'm in the wrong place and turn around and walk out so
I stumbled my way through it believe me
And I know it sounds crazy but what I was selling fax machines door-to-door I
Kept feeling like I'm in the wrong movie you know where's the director where's the where's the producer of this is not my
My movie and I was really
Determined to create a better life
So how did working there
Like help you discover
What it was you worship
That that was
When I first started wearing Hosiery daily and I realized him figured out what the control top
Top portion of the Hosiery was doing for me in my
I closed it was really making my clothes
It's so much better
But I had spent money on a pair of cream pants
Spent $98 on them which for me was a lot of money
And they just hung in my closet on Warren because every time I would go to wear them you could see the undergarment
Regular underwear left
The panty line
The song wasn't a great solution it also left marks that you could see and then
That shapewear was
So it was like the girls were so sick and overdone
And I saw an opportunity for something right in the middle that was just
Create the perfect canvas undergarment
For women
And I guess I should say for people who've never worn
It's like this is an
Undergarment made out of
An elastic material
Basically
Titans and
Snooze everything around you
Your butt and thighs
Yes
And so when I cut the feet out of my own control top pantyhose so I can wear those cream pants the light bulb went off
And then I started pursuing the idea
Like how to use an
Started
Build a business
Did you have any money to do
At the Capitol
You have wealthy friends are for
Family
I had set aside $5,000 in savings from selling fax machine Store to Door and that's what I saw
Started Spanx with
And so the first thing I did was
Started to
Research if the idea exists
Dead and I went to the Georgia Tech Library in Atlanta every night after work for
A week and a half
Researching every pantyhose patent that ever exist
And then probably on the 7th or 10th day of me being in there some guy came up to me cuz you know there's a way
Website called USPTO. Govt and I said no what is that I scribbled out of my notebook he's like
You can search your put in a patent and it'll search for you so
That website became one of my best friends and once I determined that there wasn't anything
That existed
In a patent form
And then wanted to see if there was any Market appetite for it Beyond Myself
I literally went and asked one person I went to the Neiman Marcus down the street from my apartment
Went in and asked the sales associate if
She thought anybody would ever want something like a footless pantyhose to wear Underpants
And her face lit up and she goes yes in fact I have lots of customers who've been making their own homemade version of that
Because there's no right under garment to wear under a lot of their clothes
And that was my whole focus group guy
That's it okay there's a market to me
Had you ever
Sone NE
Were you to do a back
Cannon design
Manufacturer
Sure Staff
No
What did you do how did
You can start of things
Figure out what material you needed to use I've never sewn I have never taken a business class in my life I didn't
And have anybody in the industry or even know anybody that it worked in fashion or retail
And so what happened when I
Came up with the idea is I just started
Taking other
Pantyhose
And then I went to Hancock Fabrics down the street and all these
Different arts and crafts
Stores and started trying to
Paper clip
Different pieces of elastic to the bottom and different pieces of lace
And you know obviously didn't get very far and my idea actually needed to be made on him
Machine and that's why I really needed a manufacturer to give me the time of day
To see if I could even make the
And in the meantime
You are
You still selling
Yeah because I needed the money
Coming in and
The health insurance in all all that comes with that so I was working on my idea at night and on the weekends
And when I kept calling all the manufacturers that I found that were mostly ignored
North Carolina on the phone and not getting anywhere
I mean no one would tell
My call or they didn't
You know I just learned from my cold calling days you got to be there in person
I took a week off of work
And drove snort
North Carolina
And just started cold
Calling Manufacturing
Showed up and said
Yes
So I walked in the door just cold and just said hi I'm here to meet
CDL owner in their life
And you are
They always ask you the same three questions it's 8 and you are and I say is terribly
Faye and
You're with
Headspace
Sara Blakely
And you're financially backed by Sara Blakely
I'm thinking imagine how that meeting Matt and I must have been more like have a nice day it's great to meet you you know
Were they just not
Interested in the idea at all
We have the manufacturing plants didn't get it at all and I found it very interesting that all I was meeting with for men and then it kind
And it became clear to be why they probably been so uncomfortable for so
Because the people that were making them more
Spending all day in them
You know and so it if they were they were not admitting it
So I had a hard time explaining why this product
So important and
They couldn't wrap their minds around I was
Basically coming in and disrupting an entire industry been looking at something in one way and they want to decline year after
To hear they were making Hosiery to be seen on the leg
And I knocked on their door and said guys
I just want your hosiery material
And I don't need it to be seen anywhere
Actually going to be hidden under clothes it's a new type of undergarments
So how did you convince
Manufactured
To take you on to make
Well it took a few visits
To North Carolina and a lot of
Really persistent
They all sent me away at first
And a couple weeks after I left one manufacturer Highland Mills in Charlotte North Carolina the owner called me
Eddie said Sarah is Sam
I've decided to help make your crazy idea
And I just pause that I was about to jump out of my chair and I said really why why the change of Hearts them and all he said is
I have three daughters
And so later I found out when I got the chance to do it that he had run the idea by his
Three daughters over dinner and they said Dad this is actually a really good idea we think you should
Give this girl a shot
And he still didn't understand it or think it was a good idea but he said that my enthusiasm in Like Mike
Confidence and how good this idea was going to be
Stuck with him
Do you know about what you were doing
No sew
When I came up with the idea
I kept it a secret for one year
I did share my idea with people like manufacturers or lawyers are people that I thought
Help me bring my product
To life
But I was very careful right away was just a gut feeling I had
To keep it to myself
Because I believe that ideas are the most vulnerable in their infancy
And
It's interesting to turn to your right or left in that moment until a friend or tell your husband
And you know when you do that instantly egos invited into the mick
And then you end up spending all your time defending it
Explaining it
I'm not pursuing it so
I needed to be at the place where I knew I wouldn't turn back no matter what I heard
I had invested enough of my time and
I had enough Sweat Equity into the idea
That I'd I told people and the things I heard where you know a honey if it's such a good idea why isn't somebody else
Already done it
And we'll leave if it is a good idea Sarah you know you're going to spend your savings on this and then sick
Six months the big guys will just knock you out of the water and
That was all coming from a place of love but I feel like if I had heard that
The night that I cut the feet out of my panties I probably still be selling stocks
Machine
So once
You started
Amethyst
Felt was really
Special like
Did you
Did you begin the process of
Getting it patented
I did so I went to
The three different law firms
I couldn't find a single female patent attorney in the state of Georgia and I even called the Georgia
Chamber of Commerce and they said there isn't Fun
So I said okay I'm going to do my best to explain his two to three men let's see what happens and
You know they were very nice they were
Not super impressed probably with the idea and they they all quoted me between 3 and $5,000
Catnip
So I decided to write it myself
And I went to Barnes & Noble on Peachtree in Atlanta and bought a book called patents and trademarks
And I wrote the patent
And then my mom's an artist and so I asked her if she would
Catch me in the Prototype
It for the patent and that is the picture of the US patent and trademark office
But I went back to the one lawyer who gave me a little bit more of time of day than the other ones
And I said listen Dan
I have written my own patent
I have done all of the work except for the claim
That is the part that I am not trained for I don't understand how to do that
Please I need your ex
Proteases are any chance you would do it for a discounted price
And he was blown away go to Britain basically the entire patent yes
For $750 I'll do it over a weekend and I'll write the claims
Portion of your pad
So you
So then you got
Yes but you know there was a moment in this journey that was
Quite funny I
When we're in the final stages of the claims
The lawyer said Sarah there is I need to know it's technically in the Garment from a
Fiber and yarn level
Okay
Only one person to call on that nut
Ted and Ted would have become my friend in the back of the manufacturing plant North Carolina and Ted had
The most
Thick southern accent you've ever heard in your life
I mean it was intense and so
I called Ted on the phone I said Ted my lawyers on the phone and we're trying to finalize
Cotton can you tell me exactly what's in the Garmin
He's like yeah
They're 70% nylon and 30% lacquer
Okay great and so my lawyer and I are riding and I could thanks Ted and I'm up all night guy the night before I submit my patent to the
US patent and trademark office and I'm thinking
How is there lacquer in this
This product like
How is that possible
So I called Ted the next morning and I said Ted is Sarah we weave
Spell
Lacquer for me
Yeah Lycra
Okay okay okay thanks
Call my lawyer on my do an oil change on lacquer it's Lycra
And he laughed so hard because you know fast you would have got no patents are on trying to make pantyhose out of paint thinner and like
Coming up
How Sarah got spanked
Into the department stores
The closets
Many women
You may know
I'm guy Raz how I built this
Ramen PR
Support also comes from choiceology
An original podcast from
Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of voice allergy
You'll hear a classic psychology experiment retold
William is an opera fan
Who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation
Mission and is an avid chess play
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist
In a major Symphony org
Restaurant or a farmer
Listen to find out
Schwab.com podcast
Or wherever you listen
Support also
Comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers licensed professional counselors who specialize in issues such as depression stress and
Anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment
At your convenience
Get help at your own time and your own pace
Schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built
To learn more and get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
By offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Hey it's how I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
Took this point in our story
Sara Blakely has
Designed a new kind of
Shapewear
And then
Want to take get it out into the market
The first
Come up with a name
The name was a journey that since the time I cut the feet out of my pantyhose. Tell the time I launched it in stores with
2 years
And I've been writing names on scrap pieces of paper everywhere I was
Casino in most of the names were on the back of rental car agreement
Because I had great thinking and in cars
And I wasn't getting anywhere with that I didn't like any of the names and I knew it wasn't right
And then I sort of narrow down my thinking at one point in time and thought Kodak and Coca-Cola are the two most recognized
Names in the world what do they have in common
They both had a strong case down to them
And I had
Friends that were stand-up comedians and I knew that the k sound makes your audience laugh
So I just called it together
I know I don't know but it said it's a known Trade Secret of Mana
Comedian
And so I thought you know what I need to have my invention have the k sound in it for good luck
And almost as soon as I neared my thinking down that way the words
Spanx came to me while I was in my car
I saw the word across
Like in my mind across the dashboard of my car and I pulled off the side of the road and I thought
That's it
And I went home that night I didn't tell anybody
And I wrote down spa and chaos
And I went on USPTO. Govt at I sit in and I sat there and stared at it for a while and at the last minute I
Backspace
And deleted the K in the ass
And put in an app
I dread that made up words to better for products than real words do and they're easier to trademark
And even though it did actually have the cake and it had still the case down and so I felt great about it and the name is just right it's
My product was all about the rear end
And it's about making the rear end look better and no panty lines and so the word spanks was kind of naughty and kind of
Funny and a little bit risky and it just all work tonight and I hit send and
150 dollars
Took my credit card and then a couple months later I got back an official certificate from the government thing that I was the proud owner of
The word space
Okay so you've got a manufacturer
Patents
Anime
How did you
My very first account that I called on was Neiman Marcus
Even
Get in there
I called them
Guy I just called them
I went in the Yellow Pages and I looked up the Neiman Marcus number in Atlanta and I said hi I'm Sarah and visitor Prada
How can I come and show it to you in the lady laughs and goes up man we have a buying office and it's in Dallas
I said oh well what's their number
So she gave me their number and I started calling them
And I just kept calling and trying to get
To the Hosiery buyer and I called for days at different times and she answered the phone and I took my shot and I said hey
Hi I'm Sara Blakely and I invented a product that is going to change the way your customers were closed
And if you give me a few minutes of your time I'll fly to Dallas
And show you
What you say
She said
Well if you're willing to fly here I'll give you 10 minutes of my time
And I said great
And I jumped on a plane and I flew to Dallas
And I was in the meeting with her and she was this beautiful woman impeccably-dressed I'm at the Neiman Marcus headquarters I have a z
Ziploc bag for my kitchen with a prototype in it
A color copy of the packaging that I've created on my friends computer
And
My lucky red backpack from college that all of my friends begged me not to
You cannot go to the Neiman Marcus headquarters with that red
Eastpak old
Dingy backpack I said yes it's my good luck charm I have to admit they were
Really pleading with me
So what happened in the middle of my meeting with her I could tell I was losing her and I just knew it was my one shot so
Did you know what Diane
Will you come with me to the bath
And she just paused because excuse me I go I know I know it's a little bit we just please come with me to the bathroom I want to show
Show you
My own products
Before and after
And she she said okay if you walk down the hall with me and I went in the stall and I had on my cream pants that were the reason I
I invented this
Without Spanx on and then I went in the stall and put Spanx on underneath and came out and she looked him and she goes
Wow I get it
Brilliant
And she said I'm going to place an order and I'm going to put it in 7 stores and see how it goes
I couldn't believe it I got in the car and I was shaking
And I called Sam from the manufacturing plant Lego Sam Sam is Sarah I need more I just landed Neiman
Markesan
He posited there's nothing on the other end of the phone for assume like a minute
Sam are you there
Is Tara
Don't take this the wrong way but I thought you were to give these away as Christmas gifts or something for the next like
5 years what do you mean Neiman Marcus just took it on my Neiman Marcus just took it in ID more
Okay so you are in
Neiman Marcus
Are you thinking
Oh my gosh that is the biggest mistake that entrepreneurs make
That is when the work begins
Personally I paid people basically friends to go buy the product and create a buzz about it because I was like you know a
I got to have these things move off
The shell for the
Buyers not going to give me any any more chance
Sweet you
Paid people to buy them
Yes
I called every friend I had in all the Seven Cities that Neiman's
Sent
The Spanks to
And called friends that I hadn't even spoken to since fourth grade and you know kind of like hide Sarah remember me from 4th grade
Do you mind going to the store and buying thanks and I'll send you a check
And
It was really tough because I was one item
In a bin a department
And a new brand and I didn't even get a whole row in the Hosiery Department I got a pocket
So
I needed to do whatever I could to maximize this chance
And I went
To the stores and I
Would explain what the product was I would demo it I shut the before-and-after picture that my friend took
And then I would stand in the store from 9 when they opened until about 5 or 6
Everyday
Basically doing
Everything
Yeah and
I realized that one of the biggest challenges I had
Was that where my product was being sold in the store
Was an issue is being sold in the Hosiery department and my customer was in the shoe department
And she was in the ready-to-wear department
And so I started
Realizing I got I have a challenge I've got to get my product out of the department it's supposed to be sold in
Tohatchi how'd you do that well I went to Target and I bought
Stan's
You know free envelopes
And I ran around the store and put them at every
Cash register
And everybody thought somebody else approved it so they kept them there for a while
Neiman Marcus
Moving your life
How to spank
To the cash register and they just assumed that that was like
Some high ropes
Said yeah do that
Other than that how are you
People know about it
It was a lot of a lot of hard work for me to get the word out I mean I've never advertised
Spanx is 15 years old and we've never done any formal ad
Campaign or anything is so it's a very Word of Mouth brand
No money
You had to get the word out
And you
You did things like
I ready
The Oprah yeah I did I sent it to Oprah with a note and
Turns out she ended up picking it is her favorite product of the year how did she even
Find it in the
Isles of males
Well I found out that Andre
Her hairdresser.
And
Put them in her dress
And she tried him and
Put them on and
Has basically warned him everyday since
Also went
She liked
Pick up on them.
Order Starbucks
Cover shipping pantyhose the women are the Spanx all across the world basically from my apart
So that's an enormous opportunity and then another thing I made a decision that was really
You know unconventional at the time
I decided to go on QVC
The TV channel.
The Shopping Channel
Yeah and
Had a lot of people say Sarah your brand is at Bergdorf Goodman to Neiman Marcus you can't also sell on QVC Live killing
Your brand and I just
I just had guys
I'm going to be the one on QVC and
I'm going to control the message and it's going to give me an opportunity
Explain what this is and you know I felt confident in that
And they gave me five minutes of airtime
And
I sold 8000 pairs of Spanx
In 5 minutes
And that was after
You know a year of standing in department stores across the
The Country Inn on a really good day I'd sell between you know 35 270 parrot
In a day
And in sales muscle
Muscle ache keep going up
Cuz I read that
By the end of your second hear you
Like 10 million dollars
So did that feel
It was great
I never was doing it for the money you know so I wasn't really that ever that focused on it I mean I can even remember after a cup
Couple years of
Thanks I'm still in my apartment and my accountant kept trying to convince me to buy a house and I was like I'm not interested
My little brother was always calling and telling me different ways to
And I just it was really just for the art of it like I loved I loved being able
Pay my own rent
It's tantamount
2 feet of the woman that was a really important thing for myself
But it was really just I love making the product
Did you have
Early on.
Listen you got to
Descale a bass
I need money
I mean best
Company
Help you
Yeah I did I had all kinds of
Things coming at me in the beginning and still do you know if
15 years later but
I remember one of the most
Interesting was within the first 6 months I started having several
People come up to me and say what's your ex
And I had no idea what they were talking about cuz I've never taken a business class
And it dawned on me that people actually start things just
The seldom
Still on
Yes
Did you ever think
No
I was always nervous but I was always so connect
The product when I was so
I was so creating this
Before it happened
107 facts
Fax machine Store to Door
I was
I was thinking about it I was writing about it at
I was visualizing it I was
Preparing for it
I thought you know I don't have the most money I don't have a business
The grey I have no idea what I'm doing
Amelia factoring a retailer any of this
But I do care the most so let's see what happens
When you
CVS
These things when you see things
Sara Blakely
Self-made billionaire
Weird wigs
See that
You see that number that word
Yes it's very weird it reminds me of in middle school there
Used to be these things in the malls where you could go in and picks up magazine cover you wanted to
I'll go in the booth and we'd smile and then we'd be on the cover of Vogue or whatever
I just did it feels very surreal
Sara Blakely founder of Spanx
15 years on the company has
Continue to grow and
And as yet
To go public
Amex listening to the show this week this
By the way is our very
The first episode of How I built this
If you liked it
Do us a favor
Subscribe
ITunes
And do as an even bigger favor and register review on iTunes
Get the word out
You can also write us
Directly at 8
ADT A10
Npr.org
Are cheetahs
How I built this
Shows produced this week by run ml fata
Was Frenchy in Arab Louis
Also
Compose the music
Thanks also to neva grants
Santa's Mexican Flores
Rogers
Vice president
For programming at
NPR
Gremlin
And Gyros
And you're listening to
How I built this
From NPR
Hey thanks so much for listening to
The first episode of How I built
If you ever find yourself
Conversation
Danity wig
Spell NPR's code switch
Hosted by
Gene Demby and
Shereen Marisol meraji
And Coach which is a podcast
Helps us understand how race
And identity
Crash in
Everything else
Charlotte
You can find code switch
NPR one app
Npr.org
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week