Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
What did you think of New York was it overwhelming to you did you would you stick it when you got there like very strange place
These New York that you see in movies like voice Gotham where this smoke is coming in
All night from every street so I had like 50 bucks in in my pocket
I was going to 50th Street between Lexington and 3rd
The driver
Drop me in 193
Between 8th and 9th
They were very upset with me
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they go
Show how Jose Andres one from tending the fire at his father's cookouts to building a restaurant Empire
Eventually changing the way Americans eat out
So a past 10 or 15 years
You might have noticed a trend
At restaurants all across the u.s.
Where you get there the waiter says okay here's how it works everybody orders
One or two or three plates and you all shared family style
And you know of some octopus or some shrimp floating olive oil and Sublime whatever
The person who
Most responsible for that trend is the Spanish celebrity chef
Jose Andres he basically started the small plates movement in the US
And his company thinkfoodgroup now has
25 restaurant
Cross the country in place
La Miami Vegas and here in Washington DC
Jose grew up in Barcelona when he was a kid
He was fascinated with food
My father probably
Is the one that helped me to understand the meaning of being a cook
My father would always cook on Sundays for families from Friends
He would make a big paella.
Traditional Spanish
Rice
He will never let me cook
She would always put me in charge of making the fire
He will send me through the forest
To pick up the wood
One day you got upset when it cool, he said
No I need you in charge of the fire der important
Echoswap said we came you send me away
When the buyer was finished and he fed everybody
She's going in the sides and told me
My son I thought that you understood
I gave you the most important task
Cooking
It's out it's easy
If somebody is controlling the fire
You want to be a great cook
Be in charge of the fire
Then you will be able to cook whatever you want
That was a big lesson
So your kid and you decide this is what I'm going to do I'm going to become a chef I was not very good at school
Very difficult time concentrating
And I went to cooking school I never graduated they gave me the diploma last year
Almost 30 years later
I know how you felt cooking English
Unaccounted cooking English Anaconda
That was amazing
And then I will always be working
Formulas not working
For me I was like a little kid
In the kitchen for me was like
If I was a little Wizard and I was
You know in this Castle in this Tower were
The Witch of the the master wizard was there trying to teach me I was that kind of a guy
I will spend every minute I could and I had three
In any kitchen that they are
Boys
In need of help in Barcelona Barcelona
And so wherever there's a kitchen you would go I will be there so
I was working in very high end restaurants for lunch
I was doing catering for thousands of people at dinner
But always doing something during summer
I was very lucky
Because I feel I always had somebody
Looking at
Thinking about what I should do next
Or taking care of me
I'm trying to yeah
To learn
So was this man call
Jose boots
For some reason I became like you
Child he was out chef
He was an amazing chef
One of the
The bishop Cena Spanky run the restaurant car rental
Date did the restaurant of the
Aristocrats of Barcelona
He was the one always guiding me where to be
But then
One Summer
He sent me through the rushes
A tiny
Delish
A fisherman
2 hours north of Barcelona very near
France
And I went to work
With a man called Ramon closes
A crazy man crazy Chavez
He will give you guidance
Bye
Throwing you a hot pan towards your hat
That was the way of learning and their way of teaching
But I'm telling you that this town was very important for me because there is what I meant
Ferran adriá ferran adria was the lives of legendary chef at elbow
Should I get the place that
Introduced molecular again
Astronomy
Yes
Did you just like walk into the India Restaurant yeah
He said that the bar
He order
Gambas Al ajillo
And he was already famous I know it was a 23 year old kids
I was a kid but you was a kid throw
But already he had an aura
Around him of the guy that was
Pushing the envelope
The guy that
Leave
In this kind of Little House
Alpena Mountainburg
The restroom walls
I'm bored
Sometimes
Nobody show up
No one guessed
No One customer
But he had an aura around him
And right there right then
Is the mom and dad kind of ICU in the deal
I'm going
Thalia restaurant next year
To the restaurant that's on how
Almost over the last
Eddie is
Hiset
The bar
What's the future of astronomy this encounter a chance encounter with
Sarah Nigeria and you basically
Figure out a way to work with a guy
And that just happened
The restaurant that becomes the most
Important restaurant in the world
Yes
Wow that's that is
Tesla
The way I think I think only happens when you are
Actively moving and searching
4 yd snacks
I think what you are at home saying
Man things are not happening to me
Shore
What are you doing at home
Go on walk
I don't care where it start moving
Look for the horizon
I was looking for my Horizon
So what was it like to work at
Attaboy
I ended restaurant we began kind of rebelling to anything was come
Congrats
Not in a bad way
Was only like Saran
I was very clear like we we cannot keep looking for inspiration
Going to France
We need to start looking inspiration
I feel I was
In the beginning of the explosion
I was
In the moment that something amazing was created a new universe
Was being created
I was there right when the explosion happen
Is something you don't realize
Until few years later
What was it like to be in that kitchen in those early days was it just crazy was Theron
Nice kind was he tough was it
What was the
Atmosphere there
Cerramos all of the above
Cause things were happening
Inbred quick moments woman
I remember I had the gelatin
Almond milk
Everybody knows that
A gelatin is good when it's called if he's hot
Mounts
I got the part
Of hot oil
Tehran
King
Doors
The yellow Tina fountain
He began looking at the oil
I could see that he was thinking about dropping
Almond milk
The cooks in the kitchen we were five of the time we were quickly looking at each other
He's going to do it he's going to do it
Why he's going to do it
This is going to be bought everybody knows if you put that all gelatin in hot oil is going to melt
Annie's going to explode
Well
In that moment the Alamo
Going into the hot oil
12 years later
He created
The liquid
Trokita
The jewel put in your mouth will be like a traditional croqueta
The flavor of chicken
I'm will explode in your mouth
But that was a message
Of who Ferran Adria was the message was
Don't be afraid of trying
And don't take things for granted
You have two Spirits undiscovered things in your own
If you follow the teachings
For you
You are only following what somebody else has done before you
You need
No only to read
Honda Fury
You need to discover on your own
That's a Moment of Truth learning
So you're at
Lb Yorkie
Into the early 90s and you
You move to the US how did that happen how did you end up coming to
To the US
Well in between working out there but I was in the military service
I had to do the military service in Spain right
You have to know no but in the old days
Yes well
Happens that died
I got my military service they send me to
Hobbies
In the south of Spain
I had
Great
Service in the Navy I had my
Apartment cooking for the Admiral
Dancing Flamingo and drinking Sherry and living the life of a young sailor
I finished my military service and I was like
Because I am without the job
I have no place to go back to
Then I call I make one phone call one of my teachers
He tells me
Is a restaurant opening in New York City
I need somebody in 3 days
Wow I'm like
Okay
3 days all right
I'm ready
What did you think of New York was it overwhelming
Well that rival was very amazing because it look like very strange place
These New York that you see in
Movies like voice Gotham
Where this smoke is coming in ahead
Every street
So
I had like 50 bucks in my pocket I was going to 50th Street
Between Lexington and 3rd
The driver drop me
1893 between 8th and 9th
Qunar
2 hours to make it there how is the restaurant
The restroom was called Paris Barcelona that was a chain
This was right before the Olympic Games
Barcelona
On every Spanish company and especially Catalan company
They all wanted to be
America
They wanted to be in New York
So you're working in this restaurant and
And I mean did you like it was
Interesting
No sew so I arrive there
Very quickly I realized that
Not the place
I was aiming for
Coming from a boogie
So I told him I was leaving
I get a phone call from Chicago
The Great Richard Melman
One of the legendary restaurateurs of America
Week hundreds of restaurants
I met him
And he tells me Jose I don't know what you will do in life
But whatever you do
Throw the anchor
I'm belong
Learn
To belong
In that moment I received this phone call from Washington DC
I have these opportunities
I come to Washington DC I met my partner
This is your new partners
Yes
What are they want you to do
They were dreaming
Open a Spanish restaurant on London
We the aim of hoping in the hollow
Around January 1993
Okay now Jose we should pause here and Mensch cuz we're in DC
And I have been here long time
This is like 1993-94 like at that time
People did not really know what Spanish food was there wasn't common food in America so how did you
How did you know that you could actually
Create a market for that
Toposar
Our way of life
More than a type of
Foot
Tapas in Spain in Seville you go with your friends in a bar
You don't see it
You are always standing up and you have one beer one to his next and you move to the next one
Obviously I cannot come
Turmerican try to impose our way of life
What holiday did the Gooseberry befriend
The Spanish cooking that was happening before
Or
Specialty restaurants in Florida New York
Biggest bias populations
What we did was that we had to bury long menu
I'm where we were
Really telling people
The sharing was that way for war
When we come back in just a moment
Jose Andres with some advice about sharing plates sharing a business and sharing the title of
Horizon you listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to
Two of our sponsors
Help make this podcast
Possible first to hello fresh
Did a meal kit delivery service that makes
Cooking fun easy
CM convenience
Hellofresh sources the freshest
Ingredients measure
To be exact
Quantities needed
Along with step by step recipe
Cheats for delicious meals
Designed to take 30 minutes
To make all approved
Buy registered ice
Everything is delivered in a special insulated box
Free shipping
How I built this listeners
Get $35 off
First week
Deliveries
Just visit hellofresh.com
Enter promo code built
Thanks also to stamps.com
Stamps.com wants you to know that with the holidays fast
Approaching
The post office is
Busier by the minute
Avoid the hassle and use stamps.com instead
Westaff.com you can buy in
Print official US postage
For all of your letters and packages
Using just
Computer and printer
Right now sign up for stamps.com
And get this
Special offer
Or we trial plus Postage and the
Digital scale
Go to stamps.com click on the microphone and type in
Oh and just
One more thing before you go
Back to the show
Please do stick around 2
To the very end
Because we're going to hear about your stories and the products and companies
You are gold
We've been getting
Literally hundreds of these stories are really love reading them and
And sharing them with you
Please do stay with us to the very end
And now
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So it's the early 1990s
San Jose Andres
Has opened a new Tapas restaurant
Washington D
DC his very first and
Well
Except some of his diners
Don't really want to share their food
And I always
Gave this answer which is very truth is like
I do believe that for tonight work invented and created no for eating or they were invented
To protect
Hiplet
Trump anybody take away your plates from you as we became more civilized
We began using forks and knives really tweet
You said to put that thing
Our territory
But I always tell people that
Tapas versus not opposites only
20 inches
Yeah you want to go Tapas you put the plate in the middle of the table
Can people know that that's the signal to share
If you don't want to do Tapas people
Multiply 20 in
Shoe
Ratio for Chrysler knife
And everybody would know that you were the one to share
That was my simple solution
To make sure that even those people not
I like him the sharing
I will be comfortable in a place like heaven
At this point you are still I guess in your in your early twenties so how did you
How did you handle being the head chef
When I open a learn
On that day was ill-prepared to be that
Singapore
I'm barely I'm 23
I've working very high end restaurants
It's where we don't do necessarily volume
And we aim for
Prestige
Another 7 I'm coming to Oakland
These Tapas Spanish restaurant
When I really never managed a very big kitchen
Again
Their young
We have a lot of followers of experiencing
Different environments
Different restaurants
Different people
All those things kind of without me realizing
All my time in New York
Prepare me
For pretty much believe in that anything
Everything can be possible
It's amazing because that restaurant
Elio is so associated with you
Right in the sight of this concept of like small plates
Who have the vision of creating it and and now you have
25 restaurants in somehow
You guys are all still together right
Job well everything has it been
Enchant a lot over the years
We used to wear the same people you didn't like fall apart and like happy device and like kill each other.
We had fights
We had
Exchange abuse
Exchange of opinions
I'm in for them I was a very young kids when I can
I'm not sure what I have
Iona to them and this is the message I sent to many
Knowledge chefs and restaurant people that they need
Business people it is good that you are able to
Two very early on in July
Surround yourself
With people
You want to be with
For many years I had
Only for family
Only for friendship
But also for business
And if you can make the three it's even more wonderful
This is a very powerful
Tool
That's why I always tell people. Dumb saying that the lawn
You can do more
Yeah together you can conquer the world
I mean given that you're right
Major company now
Hundreds of employees
Do you
Did you get to log as many hours are spent as much time in in the kitchen or in the creative side of
Really
Building up
Interesting menus are you kind of have to give let go a little bit and let other people come up
Is pain
A lot of
Of my
But I would call Brain time
Thinking
Creating
I cook at all hours
In my free time I need mine on free time
Cooking is why I really enjoy
I see myself
Very much like car Orchestra
She doesn't play
Any instrument
But he's able to produce beautiful music
But you know one thing
I'm very lucky that they have
Chaps who shops yams
My name is Emily
The many of them
Astounded
No more Talent
I'm what I have that the always War Ready Wellies
And in my favorite group we have
What we called
Thankful tank
That's my creative
Arm
For me creating that arm
Off
8 9 10 11 12 in the Beatles
That the only thing they do is thinking
Creating
I'm maintaining quality
ASAP Bari
Powerful research and development tool
I know you said the Lord
My team travels with me a lot
We always go to Faraway countries
We're always getting inspire
Because if you want to get in
Inspire you have to be on the move
When you put together this very big menu at Jaleo
And you created a sort of small plate
System there
Was there also any consideration of how how the economic so that would work because presumably
You'll be selling more
More
Play the food right so presumably you could help it would
Did it help me to help the restaurant
Needed bottom line
And Beyond
It's a business like any other
I can't tell you you were harder
When you have to put the house
3000 is more plates
Dongguan service
Then 1000 big play
It's more work
So sometimes believe me I'm like I'm tired of his my plates
I'm going to be sending them super
Steak and potatoes
Even nice people
That will tell me
Jose I don't want is more plates but then they go to sushi
What is a sushi restaurant
When is MOD Pizza the time
Ice people that complain about this more place and they go to great restaurants and what they give you
Is malt balls have
Homewood city of Meriden
At the end
He's very funny dad today
When we have people complaining about certain things
They're doing those things
They need to be thinking
What's on the plate
Because today the weight we eat
Is an amazing form of democracy
Because by what you eat
You are boating
How about the things you
Think should be the only on your plate
But in the place of many others
So we all need to start singing
The jewel Cambodia
Would you play
A plate is an amazing form of democracy
If you are a young sat for young
Business man or woman
Try to get in
To the food industry
Date today
What if I switch
To give to a Ito a twenty-two-year-old Jose Andres today
Well
The big is a diocese
I wish
Iei finish High School I wish I finished University
I have a 17
Carol daughter Carlota
I'm going to go in through the process
Kind of
Seems she she's a green we're going into
She's going to do business
Because you can be anything you want
You will always work for yourself
I don't care if you want to be
Painting in the middle of the streets of Washington DC
Singing with a rose in 5th Avenue
I don't care
What's the crazy business you want to be part of
Make sure that you have the business background
Businesses on the I wish I learned
When I was
I had 30 years
Off the School of Life
Now I think I'm going to be putting these next head of yours
Input interpretation
Everything I learned
Over the last day
You have like
25 restaurants
Even on TV Guide cookbooks menu for your major celebrity chef
Yeah
But when you were a teenager in
And Spain just
Cycle learning to cook
Did you imagine you could ever get to this point
I don't think I ever
A train more than
Making sure that the next plates
Put forward in front of somebody
Is the best you can be
Quite frankly I always say I don't open restaurants
I tell a story
Sometimes I wish
That I only had one restaurant
I'd only one
And I will be there every day
On every hour
But I know that that will be so bored
So I created a company around me that will
Fulfil my personal needs
But to this day I still
Consider myself that
I am only
As good as the last play ticer
Even if you do radio
Show do the radio show on Jehovah's good
You fix it but the radio show is going to be there forever
I never for anybody to listen to
But foot
Is Berea funeral disappears
So this is how hard
My profession is
You only have one chance to make it
The address is a chef and the co-founder of thinkfoodgroup
By the way you should try his gazpacho it's a pretty easy to make just get some fresh tomatoes cucumber
Green pepper a little Sherry vinegar olive oil and garlic throw it all into a blender that's it delicious
Listen to the show this week
If you want any more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org and if you have a chance please
You subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other people know about it you can also write us directly and HIV
80s npr.org how I built this
Shows produced asleep around teen Arab Louie
Also composed the music it's also to neva grandson has meshkinpour at Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
You still with us
Okay great because we are now at the part of the show where we talk about
Your stories in this one came to us from Dennis Darnell come in the house
And there'd be that one fly flying around you have no idea how it got in there but it's flying around at the buccaneer
I think we can all relate to that problems one that summer day in San Diego where Dennis live
Joyland we're sitting in the kitchen and they were watching him
Fly Buzz all around
We sat there and watched it
Trying to get into the garbage can
And what was said
Why do I drill a hole in the lid
And let it in
But put a trap
On the underside of the lid
And that is how the garbage can
Fly trap
Usborne flies
Of course love
Garbage
Dennis designs trap where
You drill a hole in the lid of your garbage can and then you pop in this little plastic doorway for the fly
But there's also a second part which is the cartridge
Which is lined with flypaper
And so why the fly thinks it's going down into the garbage can
It actually walks into the Disposable cartridge
And becomes
Stuck in what's a cartridge gets
Full with like a hundred flies
You don't have to look at that more sticky or gross
Stand just push the button
On the lid
And the cartridge falls into the garbage can
Tennis Australian have filed
Three patents for this flytrap and they sold them on their website and at Ace Hardware stores in San Diego
And just last week we reach out to Ace Hardware headquarters
As well as Home Depot
But now that they're keeping their day jobs and enjoying the fact that their kitchen
Is pretty much fly free
Hey if you want tell us about the company or idea that
You are building go to build. Npr.org that's build that npr.org
And thanks
Hey thanks for listening to the show this week if you're still looking for another great NPR Podcast
Please check out pop culture happy hour
Are there is
So much out there to watch and listen and read
Wisconsin become so overwhelming
But this show how culture happy hour helps you sort it out and figure out what's worth binge-watching downloading
Reading
Pop culture happy hour calls out the best most
Creative and most
Fun things
Out there
You can find something to make you happy every week
On pop culture happy hour from NPR
Find the show
Npr.org podcast
And on the 8th
NPR one app
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week