Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Hey everyone just before we begin the show when I let you know about the live shows
We're doing this summer we recorded our first one to three weeks ago in New York
With Jonah Peretti of BuzzFeed
Superfund
The crowd loved him we loved it was great
Now if you couldn't be there in person
Don't worry you'll be able to
Hear it this week this Thursday in fact so be on the lookout for it
And since we have been doing some of these live shows
Today's episode is a repeat but it's
One of my favorites and just a heads up to let you know that there's a little bit of strong language
In about the first minute and a half of the show so
If you got the kids register
Cover their ears for Amendment and 1/2 in the
Can you get to go
So you called your dad like that guess what I'm drawing the family business
Make beer with Sky was worse I went home
Really when I told him I was kind of hoping that he put his arm around me and
Cuz this 150 year old family tradition was going to be carried on no
You looked at me sit gym you've done some really stupid things in your life this is this
Stupidest from NPR
I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movements they go
Today Show
Jim Cook started Brewing an old family beer recipe called at Samuel Adams bottle it up
And then helped kick-start the
Craft beer movement
In America
At some point last year the number of breweries America
Cast the 5000 mark
Most of us breweries make
Craft beer
Ipas
Porter Stout sloggers
This is
Beer that wins Awards all over the world
And a lot of it even gets exported
Places like Germany in Holland
Belgium
Beer brewing is practically a religion
But if somehow you win
Back in time to like 1980
And someone handed you a cold bottle of American Beer
You might not recognize it
Because
Monty Python fans might remember this
American Beer used to be a joke
It's it's
So that was what it was like when Jim Cook was a young man but he knew a lot about beer because he had
Happened to come from a family of beer makers
My dad was a broom
Master and
It's like being a chef
In the kitchen he was responsible for
The recipe and the quality
Of
The berry wasn't the owner
So
He got out of brewmaster
School in 9th
There were a thousand breweries all over the US
36 years later when I started Sam Adams 1000
Add window down to 50
And my dad
Bad
To move
Brewery to brewery as
Vista breweries close
Did you have any
Intention like as a kid or as a
Latino
I like doing this doing the same thing your dad did
No my dad
Told me that it was a miserable way to make a living
And he eventually left
The brewing in Des
Entirely
The last thing that he wanted for me to do
Who was to go
Back
Indie Brewing
Little bit
Crazy cuz if they were like it wasn't your dad was a brewer like
His dad was a pervert
Every oldest son for 6th generation
Has been
A brewer
I believe I'm the only
6th generation
Brewer in the United States
So what did you want to
Actually I really didn't know
You know I had this wonderful education
Oportun
That nobody in my family
Had ever had
Maybe after I graduated
From
College I started a JD MBA
And I could just feel this
Pressure behind me pushing me
Towards
Some career decision
So I dropped out
So what would you do that well
At the time I was involved in a
Lot of outdoor activities
Rock climbing kayaking
Backpack
Things like that
My climbing
Partner
He got me involved
In
Outward Bound
I was able to do that
During the summer
And then
Hyatt
I learned
That
You don't need
That much to live on
If you're really enjoying what you're doing
End
So how many years did
Did you do that for
I did it on and off for three and a half
At the end of that three and a half years I thought
Okay
I think I'm ready to go back
And got my
MBA in my JD
And
Dave started a
Working as management
Consultant for
A company called Boston
Consulting Group
And we flew first class you know you
Consulted with CEOs and May
They treated you really well
It was great job
For a while
Gas sounds pretty good so why did you leave that
Had this
Epiphany I guess
After 6 years
Bcgi
Ask myself
Do I want to do this.
And the answer came back
No
The next to the corollary to that was with
I don't do it for the rest of my life
I probably don't want to do it
Tomorrow
So how did that
Like that decision
Lead to Haiti youth
Think you have beer
That's a good question then
I knew I didn't want to work in the corporate
So I thought I'm going to start my own business I don't know what it's going to be
I'm fat
My dad had given me
Actually copy of Inc magazine
And there was an article in there
About Anchorage
Is this
Small Brewing California it was owned by
Great guy named Fritz Maytag
And
Fritz
Had a viable
Small
Brewery
It was an outlier
When I was
A consultant
What always fascinated me for the outliers
Because that's where the real learning was
There was obviously the pit
Potential to find a market
For a really high-quality beer
I started this
Think about it and
I
Developed a different
Business model
For what is now called
Craft brewing
So this is in the mid-eighties
So you
You called your dad like that guess what I'm joining the family business I'm going to make beer with Sky was worse I went home
And and was he excited
Not really
When I told him
I was kind of hoping that he
Put his arm around me and
Cuz this
150 year old family tradition was going to be
Carried on to yet another generation know he looked at me sit
Jim you've done some really stupid things in your life this is the stupidest
Pause for second and ask you cuz I can tell
You have this great job
And you just left
Yes
And I left it
Because
Staying there was very
Risky
Leaving it was not
And it's the difference in life
Between things that are
Scary
And things that are danger
And there are plenty of things that are scary but aren't Danger
And there are things that are dangerous
But not
Scary
Yeah and
Those are the things that get you
I can give you a climbing analogy
From Outward Bound like
1 things we
Top people do Wiz
Rappel off a cliff
And it really it's a very scary
Thanks
To do but
You're also
Held
Bye
A
Belay rope
And that rope will hold
Har
So walking off the cliff backwards
Scary
But not dangerous
Yeah okay
Walking
Across
You know what
Degree angle snowfield on a beautiful
You know late
Mets
Afternoon with us
Bright blue
Sky
Not scary at all but it's very Danger
Because
Snow is melting
Adventure is going to find a layer of ice
The water will lubricate that and you have an Avalon
That is dangerous but not scary
In my situation
Staying at BCG
Was
Dangerous but not scary in the
The danger there the risk
Of it was
Continuing to do something that didn't make me happy
And getting to
Yo 65 and looking back and go oh my God I wasted my life
That is risk that is danger
Sedative without you set your dad I mean did you convince him that this was
Worth trying
He eventually did
Come around
You know I sat down with him
The thing that
Convinced him
I think because
All the American Brewers were basically making the same kind of
Yeah you know very light
Very easy to drink
And
I'm not going to compete
With bud and Miller and Coors
Everybody in the US who wants
Good beer is drinking the Imports
So is that that time it was like
Heineken Heineken bag
St paulie girl
Those were considered
The great beers of the world
And what I did know from my Brewing background is
We're not the great beers
The world
The Dare
Was
Possibility
Love making
Beer with a lot of flavor
The balance
And there's a
Particular flavor structure of good beer
When you taste it
You will get that structure
And
I could give it to people fresh because beer is Parish
Beer has about a four to five months shelf life and the imported beers were almost always
Stale they were typically in green and
Beer bottles
And
Visible light
Isomerize is a compound in Hobbs
That's why you get skunky beer
You come up with
With the recipe
Be that in
You know you thought okay this is going to re-educate American Beer Drinker
Why drink this beer instead of what they're used to
That was easy
After about an hour and a half when I dad was beginning to get it
Oh and you know you're right
Nobody's making great beer
Yeah maybe somebody should do that
Then
You took me up into the attic and there was
Trunk and there were family recipe
Pieczenie took out one of the recipes
And said this is the recipe
It was for my great-great-grandfather's Brewery
My dad
Handmade
A version of this beer
At
Wooden shoe bar in Minster Ohio where he was brewmaster
Because the brewery was kind of going down the tubes
Any thought maybe we can turn the brewery around by making big
American lager
And the owner tasted it and
Pull my Daisy Charlie
Nobody is going to drink huh
People want water
With foam on it
So make
Water with foam on it
So you just took this recipe and and
Start to experiment with
Yams at the recipe I started making it in my kitchen
Adam is sick
Extremely difficult
Typical beer to make
You can't really do this
This has a Homebrew
Yeah it requires
Much more precise
Control
I rooted and I could
Patel
This is going to be a good beer if I can make this right
This would be
A really good beer
Okay so you make a beer but how did you
Blake has even know how to
How to begin to
Start a beer company
Well
The first thing
I realized I had to find the best brewmaster
In America
To help me
I'm he was a man named dr. Joseph A weighty
And he was
The first
American Brewmaster to combine
High level
Scientific understanding
Cuz he was a PhD
Microbiology
With Decades of practical
Experience how did you even convince him to get involved in your life
Fly by Night startup you turn me down at first
Here. This is
Really crazy
You don't have enough money to pay me
Yeah which was true
Flexible
Dr. Wade East
I'm not some
You know idiot kid
Just making beer in their kitchen
My dad
Was a brewmaster my grandfather and
He remembered my dad
A little bit I said well
I'll tell you what
I'll give you 2% of the company
And that
Piqued his interest
He signed on
And he helped me adapt a 19th century recipe
20th century
Brewery
So did you have to go out and raise money to
Build-A-Bear
Well
I realized
Denver breweries out there
And my dad
He was the one who gave me this insight
What we did
Is
We rented space
Dr. Wade Easton I showed up
Brewed beer
And
Then they packaged it
And I
Didn't have to have my own Brewery for several years how when we started
We didn't have
Things that you think you need for business
We didn't have an offer
We didn't have a telephone
Yeah I just asked myself
Am I spending money
On things
That are going to make
Beer batter or am I spending money on things just because that's what you
She supposed to spend it on
Did you come up with a name
A Santa Ana
Well
It came for my history teacher
When I was a junior in high school. The revolution
She highlighted the role
Of Samuel Adam
Depending on what books you read he was a brewer
You know
I wanted
A name that was
Assertively American
That reflected
America's
History and tradition etcetera etcetera
So on the label there it is
Brewer Patriot
And I wanted
To do what Sam Adams it done
Only my little way I wanted to create a beer Revolution
And declare their independence
For the United States
You just met will be back with Tim Cook and he'll explain how he actually convinced people
To like
His beard
Play with this guy Roz and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated placed
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from NPR sponsor gamebridge the Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities
Can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities and a Sleek digital experience that reply
Places fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions
Send a direct low-fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Game Bridge is not available in all states
It's how I built this from NPR
And I Rise
Experimenting for a few months with a family recipe
Jim Cook
Finally got it down to a
Exactly the way
She wanted it
At this point
He had to figure out
How to sell it
So
My dad told me you know you can start Abyss
It's lonely
It's going to have its ups and downs
See if you can find a partner
So I looked around
BCG was
Was folded like the best
In the brightest from the top business
Schools
Somehow
I couldn't
See
Them be my partner cuz they are all the same skills I had
Yeah but then I
Realize wait a minute there is a person
Who
Is
Energetic
Talented
Resourceful
Great people person
Has all the skills that I don't really
Have
She was
My second
So it was just
Me
And Rhonda
She was
23 years old
No college degree
Bartended at night
We were the perfect complement
That attitude you guys convince
Bars in
On shops
To take your beer
Well
I was hoping
Did I would get a distributor
Well they were five beer distributors in Boston and went to each one of them they all turned me down because
Because
To them it looks like a stupid idea this was a beer that had a lot of color had a lot of flavor and
Taste this was in the Heyday of Light beer and you know they'd ask me okay
So what's your marketing plan to have a marketing plan
What's your advertising budget
I don't have any money for advertise
Will tell me about the company
It's me and my 23 year-old ex-secretary
So wasn't very confident as a business
And the only way that I could
Get my beer
Out there was
I would put cold beer in
My briefcase every morning I could fit seven beers
Hannah Hindi
These two blue cool packs in a sleeve of cups
And
I went
From bar to bar cold calling just going walking in the managers and
Yeah trying to get to him
I never sold anything in mind
What was that hard for you
Yes
I was sure I remember to this
This day doing my first sale
And
Hit the streets in Boston I remember I was
Okay
I'm just going to call in the first bar
That I come to you
And I came to
A bar
I didn't know what I was doing and I had my
Consulting Sudan
So I started talking to the guy behind the bar and he was nodding
I thought that's a good sign
But he wasn't saying anything
Luckily
In the back was the manager cuz the guy I was talking to
Was what's called a barback the barback is the guy who likes
Stocks the glasses and
That this guy didn't speak English
So
He was just nodding away
Managing to the back thinking
Oh my gosh
Is the guy in a suit here he's talking to my barback
He's either IRS
Aries immigration and naturalization
Action services
Eat neither one of those so he rushed up
And yeah I kind of had my 32nd drill
Hi I'm Jim Cook
I'm starting a small Brewery
Here in Boston
To make a new beer
I'm going to call it.
It's called Sam Adams
And
My real
Yeah end
Point was to get them
To try the be
So
You know it
I build up to this
Setting would you like to
Try it out he said sure leave me a bottle
Oh it's cold
I have some cups here
Let me pour you one
Before he could say no and of course
In the bar business
If you pour beer I can't just throw it out
Yeah
So
We tried it together
He said
Kids
You know I didn't think the beer was going to be this good
I'll take it
And I was so excited and of course I went back and actually Rhonda was
Taking some time off before we start I called I was so excited Rhonda
We got our first customer
Asbury practice
How many cases did he order
I forgot
So I had to go back the next day and apologized and I was
Scared again
That he would have liked changed his mind or anyting but he gave me a 10 case order
Services
Like 1985 and you launch and
You got to get some attention and your 6 weeks after Sam Adams came out yeah
It got picked as the best beer in America how did that happen
It happened out in Denver Colorado
It was at the
Great American Beer Festival Wichita
Pretty much beers from every Brewer
And
Babe
Went around over two nights
Taste of the beers everybody got to vote for the best
And they did this countdown
You have 10 9 a.m. I thought we'd finish in the top 10
But they know they kept getting lower and lower
Announce
You know
Analyst
Number to the second best beer in America is
Is this and it's like well
Yeah maybe next year yeah
And then and the best beer in America is Samuel Adams Boston Lager
And the whole company was to
Pikachu and Rhonda
Trip to do that mean you were profitable from from the
From the start
Yes we were profitable from
The first
Full
Month
Because
Going back to us talking about earlier
It was the ultimate lean
Start up
Like I said
We had no office
We didn't even have
Telephone we did all our business from Payphone
Yeah I knew where all the good payphones in Boston
We're the ones that were warm in the winter the ones where
He actually had a little shelf or you can put stuff on
So
That was very
Clear when I started it
It's very clear to me that way
Only two things that we needed
To do
Really well
We needed
To make
Great beer
Consistent
And we need
Get to work our butts off
To sell it
And at the beginning this was like a a regional thing like
10 in Boston in
New England
So how did you get it to
Spartacus
It happened very slowly
You know it
Basically
Started in Boston
I sort of
Grew a little bit out of Boston and went to Worcester
I was doing a lot of the
Selling myself
So
One bar
At a time
And a lot of work a lot of shoe leather
A lot of
Motel 6
So I can
Bankatfirst
City out of
Add a New England was Washington so I would go down to Washington
Down here
I still know a lot of the bar owners
Here I sit at bar
Before I came over here
The Irish Times yeah famous part one of my first
Accounts
And
Was talking to Brandon the current owner
But his dad
Put Sam Adams
In there
Almost 30 years ago
So
You know it was very hard in the beginning getting
Places to carry a
Probably got
U95
Percent rejection
Can soy make 20 calls
To get one account
And
Then we got picked as the best beer in America
Yeah we got a bunch
Publicity around
That People magazine to the story
Which was good and bad
Cuz
All that publicity booster
Did the sales and we ran out of beer
You could not make it fast will it take 6 weeks to make Sam Adams and we weren't expecting it
So you're out of beer for 3 weeks
We lost a bunch of a cat
Piss people off
But it was clear there was
That this idea was a bigger idea than I
Lights at this wasn't going to
Now Take 5 years to get to $1000000
That was five years ago
A million bucks it'll be great I'll be happy life yes exact
Anime
5 month
I remember
Sitting at a bar with Rhonda
And running we had business plan
But something's telling me this is bigger than
We thought it was
Going to be
That
We are climbing a mountain
Here
And
Nobody climbs a mountain to get to the middle
We're going to climb this mountain to get to the top
And
It may take 30 years may take 50 years
Our mountain is
I want
Sam Adams to be
The largest and most respected of the high-end beers
In the United
That's our Mountain
Member
Part of your strategy a team
Was like attacking
Those imported beers and I remember hearing a radio as a
You do
In the 90s where you say
Declare your Independence
From foreign beer
The radio spot came about because
Sabres radio station in Boston that want a beer for a party
And so we traded him beer
Four air time
Now
They gave us air time at 2 in the morning
Thinking
Who would want that
Academy
I thought that was
Great because
That's when
The servers and the bartenders
Get off the ship so they gave me
All this air time
And
At first was going to like get radio Talent
Tell record it and then I found out well
You can hire that but
Yeah there's all these Union rules and you have to pay residuals you got to
Track it
I can't do that
I'll do the spots
Myself
So
My spot was
When America asked
For Europe's tired and
We didn't mean there beer but the beer they send us
Is hardly their best
They send us
Heineken
Outlawed in Germany
Because of Germany's strict
Beer Purity law
The backstage send us
Isn't the same backs they have in Germany
They had forbidden adyen
Thanks to it
That
Was about the company
Were you at threatened with the litigation oh yes
But I knew I was right
They're having a brewing background I knew it
You could also tell it on analysis so
My feelings always been
If you're right about something important
Push it
Tok so after I guess
About a decade
You launch you decide to go public
What happened
Why'd you decide to do that
Well
I thought it was time
To do something to
Reward mine vest
Just because at that time
I think a dollar
Invested
Was probably worth $400
So
I went to a couple in bed
Banksy describe the IPO process
But when they describe it to you
You realize
That there's nothing public at all about it's all for their buddy and his all for their buddies at the bay
Institution
To buy the shares
And make a bunch of money and
That
Bothered me and I
I thought I got to find a way around that
So I started thinking about it
And I came up
Idea
So we put coupons on the six
Pax
That allowed you
To buy
33 shares
Boston Beer Company
At $15 a share so was born at $95
You said to send in a check
And
The Investment Bank
Freaked out about it
They told me you can't do it it'll never work they give me all these reason
Not to but
I stood my ground
I was insistent and I knew that
The investment Banks Kitty make
So they will let me do it
If I refuse to compromise
My so I refuse to compromise
Eventually they all came around and
We got a hundred and thirty some thousand
People who sent in their shells
We got six
Define million dollar
That was the first time
Something like that
Had been done
And other people
Have
Continue to do it followed up on it
So earlier you said that you want
Salmon recipes
Largest and most
Affected
Of the cortical high-end beers in the US
Do you think you would cheat
This may sound
Surprising but
I still don't feel like we're there and
Yeah but I got to give you some perspective what do you think our market share in the United
Penn 15% yeah that's what everybody thinks
A little over 1%
So the big Brewers
Fillmore beer
Then I make all your right
Yeah 90% of the US Beer Market is in the hands of
Big
Global
Brewing conglomerate
Small company
How many points do you guys have now
I'm we've got a little over 1400 people
That's
To me also
Really
Gratifying because
The average
W2 compensation
$70,000
So there
You know they are good jobs
Atterbury those are Manufacturing
Good paying manufacturing jobs
In communities
All across the United States
When you stink
About
How you built the company
And Sam Adams
How much of a do you think was
You're skilled in your
Intelligence
And talent and how much of it was
Guy
I'll take the lock
So
In all humility a lot of it
Looks like I look back and think I could have gone wrong you know the
Brew Kettle could have exploded
Or
Yeah that first guy could have told me
Is a really stupid idea go back to your
Job
You know a lot of things
Didn't go wrong that they could have
Did you could you have ever imagined that
Craft beer in America
Would become what it was
I
Never
Imagine
The
Success
Able to have
And I never
Imagine that there would be
Other
Craft Brewery
You know many of them enjoying
Their own
Success
Today
American Beer
Has gone from the laughing stock that it was
When I started
The best place in the world
How to get Beer Drinker
And when the rest of the world
They're looking at the US
I wish we could do in our country what Americans have done with beer I wish we had the beer culture
That America has
Yunnan
Makes me feel good
Every time I have a beer
That's Jim Cook
Accomplished a memoir last year called quench your own thirst
Business Lessons Learned over a beer or two
Cheers by the way it says he personally taste every batch of Sam Adams that they brew es mates
What's 24000 beers of the past 30 years that he was required to drink
It's part of the job which sounds like that's a bad job
And please don't turn us off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are build
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
American
Express open
If you listen to how I built this you're probably curious about ideas
And you probably have some ideas of your own
American Express open can help you with money and know-how
So you can turn those ideas into action
Visit open.com to get
Business done
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
And the story we did back
And November
My name is Caitlin watch until I'm in Los Angeles California
Which went to college in La she didn't notice it there all these juice bars everywhere and whatever friends
Peta Juicery home
Siri put this carrot in the juicer
And outcomes bike
Tiny tiny amount of liquid and I see these nouns of vibrant carrot pulp you know what
Smells so good it's so fresh
And she just looked at me because I usually throw away the pulp I have no idea what to do with it
Is how Caitlin came up with an idea for a business
The next day I was like wow like what if this juice pulp could be used to create
Healthy snacks at a more affordable price point until I called him a bunch of juiceries right then and there
And I asked him what are you doing with your juice pulp so she's got to give her there
Fruit and veggie pulp
Into snacks next like
Granola have five different flavors so apple pie peanut butter and carrot
Red velvet red velvet
Hope pantry and it's still the small batch operation just a few hundred bags of snacks a week
Italy selling at health food stores in La and online obsession
Kind of pathetic
You know seeing these bins taupe and being so happy just to see it process until like a better product invented
ABC sold on the shelves I just think that's the craziest thing so I love it yeah
Back when we first talked with Caitlin in the fall she was applying to an incubator program run by Chobani
Yogurt
She made the first cut and in about a week
She'll find out whether she's in for real
And if she is she'll travel to New York
And then Idaho to learn how to Bonnie does business and maybe she'll get the answer to a question
She's still trying to figure out
How do we get
These products are usually premium price you know vegetable infused I'm healthy grain free
Max and
Make it actually really accessible for people through the use of neglected resources like juice pulp
So just that opportunity to be able to kind of work with a company that
In that same mindset is it would be amazing
Kaitlyn's business has also grown from just one person
25 part-time volunteers
Including a pastry chef and a strategy expert from Google all of a sudden all these people came into my life
And we're super passionate about it and excited and
Are just my go-to people for everything from the strategy to food safety plans and makes me so
Excited because I'm like okay we're ready to go you know it's keeping me going right now Kaelyn is making a profit just yet
A company's doing around $2,000 a month
In sales
She's also working on a new product of vegan cheese
And it's going to come in three flavors barbecue sour cream and ranch
And you can read more about pulp Pantry on our Facebook page to search how I built this on Facebook
And of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes
You can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Because it's h i b t at npr.org
And if you want to send us a tweet it's at
How I built this
Please also subscribe to the show if you get a chance you can do that through Apple podcasts or however you get your pot
Guest
Usher was produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by rum teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Diva Grant sanaz meshkinpour Claire Breen
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
NPR
Yo-yo everybody Stretch Armstrong
If you love this podcast you are listening to
Check out new show what's good with stretch and Bobby
This is not your average
We're going to be telling stories that you're not going anywhere else
How's the NPR one app
Vufine
Your pocket
It's
What's good
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing plan
Farm use by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email templates. Drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com