Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
And I was like literally on my kitchen floor
Stopping like I'm going to lose all of this and it made me have to make
Make a decision like in that moment I was either going to give up and just say I can't do this
Party's over or I was going to have to throw all my chips on the table and we were going to have to do something
Radical
NPR
How I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
They go
Kendra Scott
Turned her spare bedroom into a launching pad for a multi billion dollar jewelry company
When Kendra Scott was a little kid in Kenosha Wisconsin
Should I send get driven up to Milwaukee
Cheetah visit
Glamorous
Who worked as a Fashion Corner
Later at the Gimbels Department Store
Downtown
Are going into her closet
Was
You know magical and I could become
Anything I wanted to be you know I would play in her clothes and her jewelry in
I would sketch ideas of clothes and Handbags and shoes I would
Brake antique pieces of jewelry apart and try to put them back together again I would style my mom
IMac I don't can't say it was great looking but it was creative like I could say that I loved it
Lakendra really thought of fashion
Is a hobby she never imagined it is this
Things you would eventually
Do with her life
By the time she turns 16
Her parents marriage
Just falling apart
Kendra and her mom moved
Houston
Andover College
She decided on Texas A&M
But shortly after the start
Her freshman year
Her stepdad was diagnosed
Cancer
So Kendra
Dropped out
Just was like you know what
Right now this is the most important thing that I need to
To do and so dropped out of school
Move to Austin
And was spending you know an unbelievable amount of time
At MD Anderson in Houston
And
That's weird my first business actually started was
I went home and started designing headwear
For women undergoing chemotherapy
So you know there were times when
It would be in the hospital you know what he's in for treatment therapy
B7 hours in a procedure
Two sitting in a waiting room
Is really really
Hard to do for 7 hours so we would go out we would meet people would be in the cafeteria we meet women and Families
And I could just see one you know it's so devastating for
Anyone who's going
Through cancer
To treatment
For a woman you know.
To lose your hair as well it's a
The part of your identity and
Either weren't great options
For these women
And I just started hearing the struggle
And I loved hats and I love fashion and I thought you know I could take some hats and if I could
And put in some cotton linings
Comfortable headbands things that would make them more comfortable to wear because a wolf
You know hat
Is not comfortable when
When you've lost your hair
Right
So this could be great you started to 2
Yeah so initially I wasn't making the app
Size buying hats
And then I custard thinking about it I'm like you know
Don't know if I could try to buy hats and I couldn't find them anywhere
I'm like no one is selling hats
Where are all the hats
And so my first business was creating a hat store
With the intention that I could also have a
Space in a place
People undergoing chemotherapy
To come that was
Private
They could have a private area
To try hats on
I had to speak Spanish see that it was going to be like 1930 again
Everyone was going to wear hats and there was going to be this big
Movement of people wearing hats again
What is you
At that point meaning
Your stepfather was
He was battling cancer
AM 710 at the same time you launch
This company's Fitness
Yeah so you know it was a really crazy saying I remember talking to my father and my mother
And my stepfather and saying you guys I want to
I want to do this
And you know my unbelievably and I look back now like that my parents were like
Okay do that I mean I think my mom was
Going through a lot so maybe she wasn't in the right state of mind but she's like
Do it honey and my dad was the same way and he said look you're not you spending the money I'd save for college
You know it wasn't much remember it being like $20,000
I bought my first inventory and sign the lease and all that kind of stuff what would you call the store
The hat box
We can't stop you for sec
You were like
That's amazing so how did you even have
Why this
You know
I think
Are you kind of go in things without necessarily
Understanding like all the risk
Let's do this
And you know it was amazing and I had to sell every hat so like
I clearly to make money I mean if you needed a top hat I had it
A joker hat
I had it
You know whatever a fedora a church hat
Derby hat
I was your person
You open up and then what happen
People start to come in from day one
I'm not really
Slow-twitch of color slow build
There wasn't the demand for hats that I really had dreamt
That there would be
We tried a lot of really Creative out-of-the-box Marketing tactics
But at the end of the day
We would sell some hats but it was it was tough
I mean I remember a lot of days
Call my dad just
Crying and being like
Like that I sold one hat
You know and I've been there
Like 12 hours
And I sold a hat
I was so determined
To make the Hat business work
Which
I did it I mean five years after eating Top Ramen
Like struggling and working 7 days a week and open to close and I couldn't really afford to have anybody
I had to shut it down and I mean I failed
Youjizz
We're losing money all the time hemorrhaging money
Yes
You know I remember when I close the hat box
You know saying I would never go into retail again
It was just too hard
You know hear my store closed
My stepfather now passed away
From cancer
You know it was just a very dark
Working sad time and I fail
I completely failed it
It's something that he was one so proud of
So I really felt like I had let down him and so many ways
But
I think at that time I was like okay
Go get a job
And so
Yeah wet and I was able to
To get a job at a local travel company that had a magazine associate
And I was able to do some really creative things
Building this magazine for them and
Respond by
I wanted to do my own thing again
Yeah
And what about your own life
Anyway you
We married at that
Got married in 2000 so about the time that was all going
Bad I did have that one you know bright light of
Getting married and
And then in 2001
Having our first son
So
That was really a
Catalyst for me because
The job that I was doing what you know at the magazine
Required me to travel
A lot
So I really knew
At that point that I needed
To figure out something else
And
I realize that you know what I loved was
I love fashion I love to sign
And with the hatbox I saw what a difference
What I love could do to help other people with you know the hats for women undergoing chemotherapy and I thought that if I create a company
I could also do something really
Good
But that would be success for me
And that literally was the foundation of Kendra Scott
How did you land on
On jewelry design
You know I could make it with my own two hands
I can't spell to save my life
So you know I loved
All that facets of
Fashion and design
But jewelry was always like the icing
It was that extra Sparkle
It always Fit 2
So when your pregnant
Believe me jewelry is very important because you're wearing potato sacks so if you can put on a great statement necklace y'all
All sudden feel glamorous
So I think being pregnant
I was looking for beautiful
Gemstone jewelry
That I could afford
And it wasn't out there
It was either inexpensive
Plastic glass
The fall apart after one time wearing it
Or semi-precious jewelry that way
With so far
Out of my reach was unattainable for me
And I just felt like there was this
White space
And the jewelry industry
That
For women like me who wanted beautiful
Quality product
But needed it in the more tangible
Point and that's really going to kind of what I set out to
Do when I created my first line
How did you even know how to
So I took some very simple jewelry making classes here in off
Send
There's a local feed shop that had some classes that I took on wire wrapping and
And then I would look at things and I literally would break them apart to try to figure out
How they were made
And I set up shop in the extra bedroom of our house
I had some fold-out tables that my mom gave me a beadboard pliers and some wire
And I'm and that's what the first collection was made out of you just literally started making jewelry
I literally started just making jewelry
When I was finished I remember looking at it going you know what this isn't half
Bad
You know I think people would like this
What it look like
It was Color Film was I love colors
So
I was trying to mix
Color in a unique way
ISO putting
Stones together that might not typically be
Put together and create really pretty colorways
And it was
Hand-beading hand-knotted
Wire wrap Silhouettes with some chain and they were like
Bracelets
Pendants and what were they necklaces beaded bracelets we did
Necklaces
But I was known for my earrings on my chandelier earrings and really pretty drippy Stone
You know earrings and
Long
Shoulder dusters and so yeah I I I put those little pieces that I made and I I literally
Took $500
I'm to get all the supplies I need it to
To create this
Collection
Which was a big deal for us
You know our
Mortgage I I remembered at the time being around
$1,500
So
$500 is a lot
And we are going out we have a newborn baby and you know it was
Like
Here's Kendra one of her crazy ideas you know the hatbox had failed my husband's probably like what is she doing
I promise I'm going to bring home $1,000
So how
Did you think you were going to do that
I went out and I put this jewelry
In a tea box
A wooden tea box
I'm actually we've gotten for as a wedding gift
Took my little son Cade in a BabyBjorn and we went store to store in Austin
Asking people if they be in
Exactly was any part of you nervous about doing
Oh my gosh yes I remember sitting in my car
Outside of the first store for probably 20 minutes
Just
Figuring out like what I was going to say and if they were going to kick me out like if you know they called
Security or something but I thought I did have the baby so I felt like I was in better better shape but
I was so passionate about it and I think when I walk
True that passion shine
Andrew
Soap so what was your pet
So I had a very basic line sheet
And an order form that I printed off of word
And went in and I said hey I'm Kendra
Scott and I've got a jewelry collection and I always joke that
You know I don't know if they love the jewelry or they just felt really sorry for me or the baby yarn bright
Baby I take a look
You got to pull out all the stuff I like whatever it takes
And I know that they bought it and so are they wrote orders and I ain't no literally the last store I went
To that day
I had to sell my entire sample set
So that I would have enough money
To buy the materials I needed to
Is the orders I want that day
And I came home with a check
$1,200
Ana member walking in and you know tell my husband I'm like
We got a business
So that
After that day of
Play hockey at door-to-door
Store to store
You had two basic
Just go back into
Get to work you to start making lists
Stop completely and I remember like I put a bulletin board up on the wall
And I have like my four orders
Pens like
It was so big time like what was in production
And you know I ended up getting one of my friends to come over and taught her how to wire wrap and she like help
Make a new sample set and then also
Produce these orders
And delivered him and I remember
The day after I delivered one of the store she called she's like I'm out
100 need more and I was like
What how quick can I get more and I'm like
And it was just kind of like oh my gosh and it was exciting it was really exciting because
People loved it
And it was fun because he here I'm an awesome just telling these stores and
Then another store in Lake Dallas what hear about it and I
For them
And all the sudden I got a call one day
Jay from this
Showroom
Dallas and she's like
Elisa Kendra Scott
Who are you
And I said
Kendra Scott it she said
Well I know so am I stores in Austin they're not buying my line they're they're talking about this
Local girl from Austin
I want to see what you've got
And so I went up to Dallas and she said well you know what I might as well be selling it and so she really helped me kind of
Start to build the brand and get further exposure you know in the south
To wholesale account
And and that was a great that was a great break
We profitable right away
Well yeah we were running a pretty
Tight ship out of my extra bedroom you know and I got this great new rap
I don't know if you remember
Harold's stores but
They were a company that had a great catalog business and stores a good retail chain
But they were my first big order
And they came to Market
I remember the rapping like oh don't sample for them like they never really buy anything and they stamp all the time I'm like a wolf
I don't have anything to lose
I'm so I made samples up
Per their request and like wrapped up in tissue with
Like ribbon I don't know I might even put perfume in the Box I was like butterfly release do you know
And like if I'm going to do it I'm going to
Try to do it and sure enough I got a call and it was a $75,000 order
How many pieces was that
It was I think I want to say it was
Play 2200 or I mean it was like in the thousand
Sky
How did how did you even manage to start making
You fake it till you make
Cuz they had no idea I was in my
Extra bedroom and that was when I was like oh my God I have doubts
Production
Clearly can't make all these
Please and they wanted it delivered in
In like 8 weeks
And I said yes to everything cuz
I was like okay I will do that
And a member of the buyer you know when she gave me the order
Started crying on the phone to her and I just said
You just made somebody
These businesslike happen
And it we're still friends and she says like she still remembers that moment because I was so emotional
But we did it so we actually called a friend to
I had worked as a
CEO of a very large retail chain
He had some production a resources overseas
They have the stone capability there to which we
It's great so it was all natural stones I remember it
Key as a friend
I called and said can you help my friend out and literally thanks to him that first order was produced on time
And we shipped it out
Ticketed and carted on my dining room table and UPS up picked it up on my front doorstep
You know it's
Biggest lesson
I can ever give any entrepreneur
Don't be afraid to ask for help
It is not a sign of weakness it is the greatest sign of
Strength
When we come back in the moment
How the 2008 recession almost killed Kendra's business
I saved it
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this mess
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and opened up free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to study
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed return
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital Xperia
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions
Send a direct low-fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Lives NPR
Game Bridge is not available
What all states
Hey welcome back to how I built this
This from NPR
Gyros
So it's the early 2000s
And Kendra Scott
Just landed her first big order
But if she wanted to make it national
She'd have to give her jewelry
Into the famous
Fashion showroom
New York
And I started calling them and sending them samples and you know
Nobody would call me back
I would send cupcakes I don't know it's a southern thing here we need a lot of cupcakes
Anything I could get to try to get a response out of the showroom is it in the
Just weren't interested
No and not be told I get 20 calls a day like
What's going to make you special
Do you have any jewelry designers are out there or wannabe jewelry designers
I can't tell you like how many times I got told no and and
Basically kind of laughed at and told oh you're from Austin Texas what are you selling Southwest jewelry
I'm like no hello I'm selling baseball
They want to put you in a box right and
It was really good flading but you just have to like have it like I'm not going to let this fail
And I remember one showroom out of like the
20 or 15 and I was
According
Finally called me back and he's like will you just like stop
Calling me like
You like I will talk to you
But you have 20 minutes and you need to come to New York
And I'm like okay
I meant I'm coming
And like this Saruman in York like sell jewelry from
Different designers
So this is a wholesale showroom
So they'll carry multi-lines
Some carry
Multiple lines of jewelry some would carry handbags jewelry other accessories
But wear whatever and this is where buyers so the buyers
Department stores buyers of Boutique
This isn't
Direct-to-consumer this is not a store this is a actual
Showroom for Jose
Right
And so this was a really great one
And again not too big so I will
If I get lost in
He was a tough New York guy and he wasn't kidding about the 20 minutes and I went in and
Show to my collection and tried to
Explain to him what my goal invasion was
Weather Brandon
He said you know if I'll look it over I'll talk to the rest of the folks at work with me and we'll get back to you kind of thing
And you know 22 minutes later I walk down
Kind of deflated thinking
You know
I don't think he's going to
Like I don't think that one is great as I wanted it to
And it was about
3 days later and I was driving on
Loop 1 in Austin Texas and
You know my cell phone ringing
Lisa Kendra
We want to carry your line and I had to pull over
High on the highway
Did not say
But yeah it was something that we know we got a New York showroom and that we really we sold into Nordstrom the next Market
What what is it what is it mean
Was the design
Like markedly different from any
Out there
Or was it just a disk I happen to like
Your stuff
I think that
That you know like he wouldn't have carried it if the design wasn't good
You know he sees a lot of things so I thinking of the design was good I think he was excited about the price point
I think he saw that there was value and there was
That would be exciting for customers to be able to have that and it was something that
That she didn't have to show
And again like we were filling a void
And that was the reason that we got his attention
How did you even know for example like
Adam
Ice things
How did how to do all that
I did it guy every time I kind of learned as I went along then we went overseas we
We're able to buy better you know
2 volume we're going to rock to Stone manufacturers verse
Going through importers and exporters and in all these other moments
So it worked out that we were able to actually
Play really price
Is smartly and for me
The more directi
Could go
I could pass that value on door
Customer and she could get the most
Beautiful
Stone quality
Handcrafted jewelry but under $100 for a pair of earrings
And it really was about
Like getting out there and trying to source
You know
Manufacturers in the stomach
To do it okay so go back to the the New York showroom
And then that the Nordstrom's order what did you
Look how were you able
To fulfill that
Yeah so we were able to
Start working with a sourcing
Company who started helping us
Diversify our manufacturing and give us more resources
And so when we were you know got the first Nordstrom order at this point I was still
I'm in the extra bedroom so we actually did ship Nordstrom out of the dining room again
And then we shortly moved to our first
A corporate
Headquarters
Which was an ad
It was in Attica where was that
It was an Austin it was little Victorian house that had
Subway office Beloit Subway shop office below it and
It was an attic space I'm ever going in his like will we have the attic available in like how much is it he told me I'm like okay I think we can
Swing the Attic
Alvin and then we moved into an addict so
It was a big upgrade
From my extra bedroom light
Let me tell you
You and
If we had about ex employees
Wow yeah we were
We're on fire guy
So I had a lot of production
Assistance at that point
Literally helping make all the samples create all the samples and house
I had a graphics
Designer I really believed early I like I wanted to control the brand and I think you know working in the magazine for a while
Just saw the power of
Of having an authentic
Tech brand that
You know we really
Controlled
She was
Was basically designing
Jewelry and you were over saying
The design of each
No I was designing they were they were producing
In the early days I was designing every single
Now I still lead the design
For the entire collection
We have six employees
By this point where you already
Were you making a lot of money
Yourself
What are you still
No not at all
I got it all there I mean there were lots of times
Since when I didn't
I didn't pay my
Yeah I had to pay everybody else I'm at remember telling my landlord on several
Vacations
Address
First of the month
So Nordstrom's
Check is running a little late
Could I have like two more days
And he just smile at me and be like no problem he was not for newer he was
So wonderful and so thankfully I had a cool landlord in
If we were floating
Constantly I had it I think I had about a $10,000 float
That I was always in my mind
I have like when things are coming in and when I could pay thing
I was going to pay rent
Pay payroll and
You know pushing people off to figure out who I should
Yeah and I bootstrapped adeyemi at this point I didn't I didn't bring any invest
Capital N so I had a line
Netcredit
With the bank
Against my inventory and my
Purchase orders
How big was Goliath
Well
The very first line of credit I got I think
Quiz about 25000
Then and then I got it moved up to 50
And I had a $50,000 line of credit
For a while
And then I remember
It went to 75 now
The big miles
Like then I didn't know how you go out and raise money or bring an equity or
I don't know how you do that I was just worried about
Filling the orders that I had to fulfill
Yeah
What did you quit
Decide to
To open a brick-and-mortar shop
So do you remember I said I would never
Going to retail again with a hat box
Those are like famous last words
Spot
I didn't for a long time I was honestly really scared
Really really
And I thought this is much better I can
Can design
Make Me Over manufacturing and I'm selling
To these Hotel Partners they have the product and they have to sell it right like it was safe
We were growing but we weren't growing dramatically
It was like
We were at about a million million 5 year
You know at this point now I was a single mom
So you know I
I was able to pay our rent and do the things I need to do first marriage
It ended
Yep HobbyKids
Two little boys
Until you are doing this
Smallest drone
And running a bit
Yes
Yeah Becca my little one he was
And the other one was
So they were little little little
So they wouldn't you know they come to the attic with
And I had a pack and play and
Toys in
To me those are
Magical day is quite honestly it was very special time for me and the boys it was hard
But it was like there there is that determination like
I couldn't
Fail that
Had to make this
What's work did you have help from your mom
Albert child-rearing
She's unbelievable she is just
Yes and my sister actually moved in with me for part of that time
Travel and try to sell your line
Yeah and I brought Kate my oldest I would bring his 75,000 freak
Flyer miles and he was three and a half
Irene
You should act for kid
I think back now I don't even know who this person is and how I did it cuz I don't think I could do it now but
Again asking for help I mean I had some friends in New York
Who would help with
My son when I was there doing the shows
I mean I surrounded myself with these amazing wonderful p
People who
Had big heart
Who believed in me
And you know I'm so thankful
Because I couldn't have done this without
The people around me to support me during this time
So you decide to
To open a brick-and-mortar store
Austin
So here we are we're going along I'm just telling my little orders to all these Hotel counts in this amazing
Wonderful thing happen
Dance called the
Recession
Which
Turns out to be the greatest gift
Kendra Scott
Company ever received
Which sounds really crazy but it really was the greatest gift because
I was sitting at
Safe
I was so scared to go outside of my comfort zone
You know seeing what happened with
My first business
But then the recession hit
And everyday I'd walk in and stores I've been working with
What 4 years were shuttering
One after another buyers that I had been working with and built these great relationships with
We're getting laid off from their job
I mean the whole world
Changed
And
My line of credit gets called by the bank
Because I'm a high-risk
Pink fashion and Jewelry
And all these things were happening and I was like
In a literally on my kitchen floor
Stopping like I'm going to lose all of this
You no answer
I got these boys
I have to race
That was like a very scary time and it made me
Have to
Make a decision like in that mower
I was either going to give up
And just say I can't do this
And it's over party's over
Or I was going to have to throw all my chips on the table
And we are going to have to do something like
Radical
And that's what we decide
Headed to do
What you do radical meaning retail
So your answer was
We we got to go out there
And open up shop
Well what my answer was is that for all these years I've been worrying about what buyers
The buyers
I wasn't thinking too much about the customer
And I realized I had to refocus
That all of my attention had to go on the customer
I had to know what she wanted more of I had to engage with her
Personally
And so our complete Focus went from business-to-business to business-to-consumer
And that man an amazing wealth experience
And it meant being Innovative and creative with creating a customization opportunity for
Our customers
And
Store
Really was meant to be our labret
So we moved our
Our office
Above store in
In South Congress in Austin Texas
To all of us would have to walk through the retail store every day
Before we can get to our offices
That we were four
I really have to
To see what was going on and look at the product in a fresh
Perspective
How did you finance
I mean the recession-hit
You are
You know kind of
Profitable but you're not really
Crazy
So how are you able to
Put the money into getting a retail space
Then going that route
So a great thing happened I was with it when I was with this bigger Bank
We're not going to name any names but when they work about
Caller line we had a local
Texas Bank
Loved me loved our brand and took our line of credit on gave us an extension
In addition to the line of credit
They took on which one
Was phenomenal
And really helped us
Fortunately because of the recession
All these stores were shuttering so I was going to South Congress which is now the hottest hippest place in Austin
In 2008
It was
Almost a ghost town and so negotiating a great lease and getting space
Was actually
Pretty easy right
But I thought you know if we're going to do it I want to do it totally different than ever
I don't want to just open a jewelry store
I don't know if you've been into a jewelry store but it's kind of scary
Play sometimes there's a
Like cases
You have to ask
People do strange things it's scary
Sometimes
Burly guards at the
The Gate of the door it's
It's not exactly a warm and fuzzy feeling when you walk in and so
We want to take all the scary out of
Out of it and so the cases were open
Jewelry with
Fraley displays
Canino tables
Then you could touch and feel it and we had signs that said have fun try on
You know we had the color bar where
You can sit at the bar and customize your own pee
Piece of jewelry in pic
Stones that would go in the setting and then our girls right in front of you
Woodstock the stones while you're drinking a glass of champagne
It was fun
It was fun and it was fresh and it was
The jewelry with a
Hannibal
And I think in the recession it was
Refreshing for p
Cuz it was something that
Afford to do and it made them feel
We had lines
Around the block
I couldn't believe it
How did you
How are you
The scale app
At one store
Did you
Have to eventually
Get outside investment
So
Not with the second
Pet store
Or the third store so we didn't bring in
Investment Capital until 2
Very small amount
I mean I was running a business everyday that way
Was bigger than it was the night before
I didn't know what
Doing and I knew I needed to bring in
I'm more qualified team so Union 2010 we still only had seven people
You know we are
Walgreen right we were young we were hard-working we definitely
We're in a passionate and excited but I needed to get some gray hair
In the building
So to speak
And
In order to do that we know we needed also have money to do
Intuit we brought in
Cool who is
Fantastic and with me to this day
And you know I stop paying myself actually when I hired him
Because I knew we had to have him
I knew I needed that you know expertise and I remember going to our controller who's now my VP of HR
And and saying Christine like we got to hire this guy and she's like country we can
Can't afford him
And it's like we can't not afford him
I said stop paying me
We're hiring him
And I'm and they did and then finally you know our Smyth EOL on who is Whitney still he laughed when they he real
Realize that I wasn't getting paid
Cuz I was like she wasn't that long but she's like
I think we needed thank you
Maybe get paid I'm like okay that'd be great
What's up with you as an investment you were able to
Scale-up
The point where you not have
Volume 50 stores
54 right now and will have a
And you still sell in big retail
Blake Nordstrom
And in other places
Yeah Nordstrom Neiman Marcus Bloomingdales
You know I think
If you would have asked me next
Two bedroom if I would have ever thought the
This business would be as big as a
Stay I would have
No way could I have dreamt
But now
I see it
Early days
When you are
Kidding
Grounding
Sleepless nights are having like
Your stomach
I'm I still have
Of course I mean he running a business has an easy
It was everybody would do it right you're always worrying about things me now I have
5 mm
Work for us
There was Phantom responsible for their family
Keep you up at night there's always something right that key
Keeps you up at night but
In the early days it was also there's a
Exciting
2 because
He got this idea and you have the singing you just I would wake up more just
Anxious because I just wanted to get up and I wanted the sun to rise so I
Don't do it
And I still in that way I mean I wake up at 3
Three 4 in the morning and I have ideas and I have asked
Sketch pad next to me and I'm writing things down and
Tearing things out of magazines I still have that
Giddy excitement
Everyday
And that's what
Keeps you going
You feel like
Love it
Love it love it like your children love it
It's amazing to me that
You
Didn't finish college
Are you barely did a year
I wouldn't even say I really
Eat you never
You never studied business
You didn't study facts
Dopest
Credible
Business
You failed a lot
You had a lot of
Bring out all my positive attributes
How much
How much of this do you think was
Your
Helen
How much of it was
How much it was
I don't know block me I don't I don't really believe in lots
This is been very hard you know there were a lot of days I didn't
Think that I would
This business
I think
Part of it is
Is drive right
And I saw where we needed to go
Giving up with not enough
I was going to figure
Hear this out
And I think I've learned so much from the hatbox
That was my Edge
Education me I learned
Business from A to Z from open to close
Literally close
You can't teach that in a book
You can't learn that in a class
What do you think would here like watching
Airport or
And some City
Can you
See somebody wearing
Oh my God I get so excited I still get excited I see people all the time and I used
Sty
Carry my business cards around I use
Is to get like
See somebody and I'd rights
15% off 1
Dad sign my name I be like going to the store
Somogyi I love you, you know you're wearing like you're wearing your Kendra you look so beautiful
And so now we have caught you in your Kendra cards are like
Gold ticket
Any given to all of our employees and it's so if you are wearing Kendra
Just got in one of our country
Employeescu they like literally will run up to be like we call you and your Kendra you look so great and we give you this golden ticket
And that came from my business card but
I love it I always go up to people and like you look so great thank you so much for wearing our jewelry
It never ever ever gets old
Ever Kendra Scott founder of Kendra Scott
Design
Original $500 investment
Paid off pretty big
Last December
Berkshire Partners made a large investment in
Company
It's closed but according to a report in Reuters
Berkshires investment raised the value of the company
Billion dollars
Please don't turn it off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you guys are built
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors Cleveland Clinic
Cleveland Clinic is ranked number one in the nation in Heart Care
22 years in a row according to US News & World Report
For more information or to get a second opinion
Is it clevelandclinic.org
Heart Care
Hey thanks
Sticking around because it
It's time now for how you built that and we got this story from Joshua esnard who grew up
In Ithaca New York we were immigrants from St Lucia in the Caribbean and my dad being an old school car
Caribbean guy
Everyone knows about the old school parents they cut their children's hair they did but his dad
Kids version of a haircut
Was not exactly Joshua's idea of a haircut and I wanted to edge up my hair and have a cooler hair
Hairstyle so I realized that I need to find a way to give myself
The styles that all the cool kids at
Joshua didn't have the money to pay a barber
And we tried giving himself a cut with his dad's Clippers
Well I ended up with bald spots and
Let's just say that I spent
A lot of time in middle school with hats on my head
Joshua is 13 at the time
And the kind of kid who loved
To draw and Design
Diana I realized that if I can cut some pieces of plastic and cardboard
And mess them together for certain designs and stencils
I may be able to use that as a guide
To help me cut my hair
Basically he head stencil
He present
Against his head
And then head shave around it and the first haircut was
Perfect
Like the crisp
Curves on my sideburns
We're just amazing to the point that people were like man you went to the barber
Who's your Barber
Me I'm the barber he would say
And Joshua kept using his stencil through middle school and then high school and in his mid-20s
Has he decided to patent his invention
Within a few months
The cut buddy
Was born so I actually took the product
And I shot a video of me cutting my own hair
With the cut buddy
He put it on YouTube and got some sales but also maybe this is because Joshua doesn't have the
Best hair for this sort of thing
Some people started to
Troll him oh my goodness he has a receding hairline his product
Sucks but
What they didn't realize was that
The main issue was obviously me as the model
So Joshua
Cast out
4 guys with the
The perfect hair 2
Demo his product on YouTube
And those videos they actually started to work
He started selling like
You doesn't cut Buddies
Day
And then
What a popular DIY site posted
In one of the videos
It went viral
I'll never forget it I'm putting on my clothes
And my phone just starts going
Ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding
Notification read the orders started coming through the website
And it turns out the cut buddy works on all different types of hair
Appeals to a lot
A different kind
It would be the college student
Who's cutting their own hair under a dorm
It would be the single mother or father who has to cut
To children's hair
In this trying to save some money
It would be the barber that's in training
That's who's lyrics
One video went viral Joshua quit his day job and he started selling the cut buddy
Full-time
He's now hire two people
Since early last year he says he's sold
Thousand
Hi buddies I'm mind boggled big time everyday I wake up
I'm like
Damn I can make my own hours and I love what I do
Yes I'm I'm totally mind-boggling
Joshua esnard is the founder of cut buddy
He lives in Fort Lauderdale Florida
To find out more about Joshua in
And kabaddi head to our Facebook page
Just search how I built this
On Facebook
And as always we love to hear and share your stories of please keep sending them to build. NPR
R. O RG that's build with a D
Npr.org
Thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I feel
Built this. Npr.org
Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and newspaper writers review while you're there
You can also write directly to us at hi BTW at NPR. O RG
And if you want to send a tweet
Ask how I built this
I sure was produced this week by run. Dale fata
Music composed By REM teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva grandson of meshkinpour
And Jeff Rogers
Are interned is Claire Breen on Gyros
Any been listening to how I built this from NPR
We are trying something this month we're asking all of our listeners to tell a friend or a loved one or a
Pandora
Uncle rape anybody really
About a podcast
That
They love or one that they think that that person might love
And tell him about it in real life go
Explain
The podcast how it works maybe even show them how to download a podcast
And do us a favor tell us what you are recommending the other people by using the hashtag
Tripod so that
Try
Tod
And thanks
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email
Lakeside drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week