Support for how I built
Send the following message
Come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn
Why by searching Michigan pure Roberts
So they showed it to us
I'm like wow look for me as coming from a design background like this is sick this is as good as it gets
And I'm and they're basically okay here's the building what would you do with it
Sobieski I go home
And
Start thinking of
Concept
Of a name
I buy the domains I build a website
I designed some
Floor plans really simple you like a quick like business model I stayed up all night
You did this in one night
Yeah basically because
We have been challenged was like what are you going to do and we have no credibility right so my thought was
If I do all this stuff and come back tomorrow it'll seem like we were planning it for a weeks in advance right
From NPR how I built this entrepreneurs idealist and the story
Behind the movement
How to friends hustle their way into Manhattan real estate
17 billion dollar office sharing company called wework
What's a back in 1985
Someone picked you on an idea to build a chain of stores that
Just sold copy
Or saying 2008
My friend asked you for some seed money to create a service that allows you to rent out a room in your home
2/8 total stranger
Orcas in 2010
Someone told you hey you know I want to open up a salon that only blow dries hair no cuts no color
I would totally jump aboard
But the reality is in the early days
Almost no one at Starbucks
Airbnb or dry bar
Because who would need that one service right
Last Adam Neumann and Miguel McKelvey
A decade ago
When they started to pitch a landlord
On the concept of leasing out unused
Parts of their buildings for shared workspaces
But not just any work
A membership include good coffee
Foosball table
Wave lighting
Decor
Comfy chairs
And looks
Most importantly
A built-in community
And today that idea they had
Is called we work
It has buildings across
The US and in more than a dozen countries around the world
Purple long before that happen
Long before the vision of a
Communal workspace
Even on Miguel McKelvey radar
He was actually living in communal life
Miguel was raised in an all-women
Collective
And Eugene Oregon
There were five women who are all really good friends you know best
For a long time.
Pretty much decided to have children without the father's
Picture I'm just
Because it was a time when they wanted to break
Free from normal sort of
Arrangements and configurations
And they all depended on each other for everything sort of like they were we were a family
The five women and their children some meatballs
Bus for girls
And then 10 years later
The basically those five women
Word connect
Go to the parents of any of them could
Be in charge
Exactly and we all had
You know all the holidays together from things
Thanksgiving to you start
Merry Christmas like that was our family like
Everyone was
Was pretty disconnected
Did from you know their other
Biolage
That was you know that's what I grew up with and I consider them like
My mom's my
My aunt you know whatever you want to call it in my brother
Adjective
Feel different when you were a kid or was
Is it just like that's Eugene Oregon
It's kind of
5 hearing
I mean there was a hippie Vibe amongst the
Smaller Community there and there was no kids with funny names you know like I remember a kid named wind
Do you know in another
Morning Star and evening star in
I'm so that made you feel not
2 weird
I think not until I was older and I realized
Kind of had money
That it became an issue like
Things that I
Didn't have any
After we always had
Crappy cars that were always break
Breaking down in light
Billowing big
How to smoke
How to use more like the sort of
Being poorer than the lake
Being
Weird from a family
You know sort of
But at the same time
I
I wouldn't say I wanted to get out
But I did from a very young age have
A dream of
So
For some reason from the time I was a kid when it would be like saying really
Boring summer day
I would be like
You know your what do you want to do
What do you want to do I don't know what that I want to go to New York
And for some reason I started saying that when I was a kid and I think it like
Became more and more of a
The thing the more I said it in the morning
Became real and wasn't from like a I hate this place
I've got to get out of town was more just
For something big
Wow
So you grew up in this environment
You are one boy among
Lots of women
Yeah he's always
All women pretty much basically
Four Sisters Inn
And 5 mom
Yeah
And I mean looking back on it was weird in the sense that like I didn't have
Like I look at it now in terms of like say
My own Simon
The role that I
I play in his life
And I realized
At all
You know my mom
Did develops A Love For Sports overtime but when I was younger she had known
Knowledge Ranch
And you love sports
Yeah I mean from a young age
I did but I didn't have my
Guidance
I'm in Wichita
Why play basketball
But never I didn't play it seriously until I was really in
So you know I was like a kid
Hanging out
With a ball but not like I didn't
Scales and tails
And keep an eye exclamation
You are seeing Hawks mean
Ciur
6 ft
Yeah I know
I can still dunk I'm proud of that I try to
Couple of days ago that's a good
Costco.
He wasn't just any basketball player he was actually really good
Making the team at the University of Oregon
So he was good
He wasn't
Diego
So he focused on his studies
I got a degree in
Hunter College Miguel spent a few years trying to build
Startup in Japan
It was a company that helped connect
In the back of his mind
You still have the
Dream to live in New York
Maybe even work as an architect there
Shogun 2004
He started applying for jobs
So first of all no one does something for everyone to learn
In my experience is that a New York no one's going to reply to you if your
Address on your resume is not a New York who cares like who wants a Deal With It Tina
So I learned at a friend who my friend's brother was living there and he was like you can use my address
Change my address to his
Address in Queens
Immediately I got
Want to suggest that one switch
Slime
But I got to
I think three interviews
So I'ma
My flew out
And
I think it was a
A Wednesday
And
Timeout with one firm
They were all
Super like
Shikari
Xen like
They're all black
Cool glasses
Superslick office and all that noise like
Dino ID
Fit in there like
Not for me
I mean the other one I went to was in dumbo in Brooklyn and it was
Just two guys in
Tiny little off
And they were in jeans and t-shirts and you know they had like
Relaxed vibe
And you know I talked to him and basically this guy Jordan parnass who
Was the owner of the farm he was like
Okay great we like you we need you were really busy can you start tomorrow
And I'm like
Cuz I said I lived in New York right now
So literally I've nothing with me I'm like
Well
Can I have a week you know cuz I was trying to make up a lie on the Spotify why can't I start tomorrow and
Renegotiating basically let me start Monday instead of
Thursday until I Beast I went back
Portland I literally packed up my entire apartment I called my mom and like Mom
Take all my stuff
She packed it up and put it in her back
And I moved to New York with a duffel bag on Sunday night I remember I landed and
And
Never look back
And you are young but you weren't like
Another word for like
Somebody starting out from
Scratch
And the job was $10 an hour
So I mean I was in was like I'd Money in the Bank
Certified for
Professional architect
Well I wasn't a certified professional architect right I was a junior level draftsman
Like I was the lowest on the totem pole that's what they wanted they wanted a person they could pay little
Who do odds and ends jobs
Taking that risk it all
No because I think one it was
I get to move to New York
Which was the big
Your goal in that was
Do you know getting my
The door but two
Balada Luz
You know I mean I didn't
It's like I didn't have anything to my name
I didn't have any money I was
There's nowhere I could there's no way I was going down
The worst case scenario move back to my mom's house
Eugene for a while
And what was a job like
So what happened there which was really cool is that
The Jordan parnassa grown up
Help with dog training in Montreal
So Dove is American Apparel
Founder
So originally when I first went there the project that they had was an American Apparel Store
And it was in lower Manhattan there was one that already done and then they're working on the set
You need to design a torta like
Yeah design it and managed the construction end and build-out
Yeah it was but also American Apparel this was their first retail right so they were a wholesale company and they were just
Exploring could they do retail
And so it was great timing because one
Getting there at that time when American Apparel was just starting out was great but to my background being in business
Actually was applicable to this new idea
Retail rollout
And so what ended up happening was over the course of you starting out in more of project management role of
Okay
Now we have two American Apparel
American Apparel stores now we have three now we have four now we have five
It turned from that which was actually managing
A project
2 now we've got in the office we have 10
Now we're doing
20 now we have 40 concurrent project how that was how fast
Explosive there growth what is firm in 2004 and like
Just a few years
She's like 30 40 50
200 after 4 years or so
So mean
You got to this firm at just the right time
Flight landed this really
DeLand
Clearly that
Change your life
Yeah
I definitely had the attitude that
This feeling that
Every potential thing that's going to come up is something I'm going to use
And so
American Apparel
Projects were tough under like really tight time
Timeframes and Doug was like
Really
Intense
And you know there was times I remember a day
Black Friday is on
Obviously the
Friday after Thanksgiving and I remember him calling me and saying like
We have to have the store open there's a problem in Denver we're not open I'm going
Kill you
Something to that effect on you was like this is the most important this is the most important moment of your life right now
You have to get on a plane
Right now to Denver and make sure the store opens
But it was like once you've been through that it's sort of like well what's going to come up that will be
He works what's more intense and
Person scream at you at the top of their lungs in until
Respond to it in like a positive way and say I'm going to take this
Experience and know that I
Can learn from it
Do something
So when you are
Injectafer
Did you
Start my own firm
Business cycle
Keep doing this for a long time
So there was definitely an expiration for me in terms of
I think really
The learning curve when the learning curve expires
That's when I start looking
King brother think so
I think once we've done a whole bunch of American Apparel Project tonight
Before I started thinking what what else am I going to do
And this is
Kind of starts the wework story is that
Why was working for the firm at a co-worker
Israeli guy named Gil
And I became friendly with Eminem
You know where
Yeah I Was An Architect working on American Apparel projects in
We became friendly and I remember you know he invited me over to his
Apartment one weekend and
I went over there
And
As we're walking into the building
I think in walks this other
Dude and
We get introduced and
It's Adam
It's a hot summer day in the oven
We work
Adam Newman and he's got his
Shirt off I think which
Just to walk into a New York
You know Condo building rental building elevator with no shirt is one kind of statement
And then to
I remember ads were like
You know going up in the elevator
Starting conversations with people who are on the elevator and then he's like
Holding the door as the person get off and then continuing the
And I don't know Israelis at all so first of all I'm coming from Oregon I've never met an Israeli
Play before so I don't even know this sort of abrasiveness which I've come to love
But there's that and then there's Adam Hoosier
Just has like a really
You know
Exuberant sort of personality
So he was girl's room
So what I didn't know that at the time though because I mean
I didn't understand like it wasn't like I'd been pretty introduced or knew the situation or what I was coming into but sort of on that elevator ride it was
Explain to me along the way
So you and Adam
Yeah that sounds weird cuz it doesn't really make sense to me aside from the fact that we're both tall
We don't have that much in common I mean
Totally different people
For whatever reason we just connected we just
There was something between us that just sort of made sense
I'm so he had a couple of startups
One of them both of them I think we're baby clothing
Companies and
He had sort of an idea for
Innovating a baby clothing by putting on knee pads
In baby's pants
Saint to protect
I'm with their called crawlers would she have a baby at
No no baby
I don't understand where the whole baby thing come from we have to
Ask him to remember but
He was interested in succeeding in business
And he thought that was a good idea and until he was pursuing it
And that's actually
The way we became closer friends was he was looking for a new office for his baby clothing company
And he was looking at spaces in Manhattan and I was like look
You're going to get double the space
For half the price
In dumbo what you know in my building where I am
In Brooklyn so
I may convince them to him to move there
And so then he was just down the hall from me where I was working at that at the firm on the American Apparel
Did you find
Kind of charisma
An atom that you saw
Yeah I think so I mean it's more like
Yeah it's a Christmas a good word for it it's also more of
A brashness which I think is cool but which I don't have like I can't you don't like to be
Well I like to be next to the center of attention
That's the thing is that like I like the idea but I just don't want to be a cat
So I but I really enjoy the energy
Leave that sort of
Comes from
Like I like that
I like seeing you
So so
What happened to he one day come up to and say
I have an idea and I want to do with you is a
Seamless or is it a little more complicated
So it's hard to say exactly
That moment like it's hard to remember but but yeah something to the effect of we're talking about this building that were in
And we're looking at
The
Relationship between all of these tenants cool cup
And then the level of service that they're getting from the landlord
And he had
Scenes are the business model before of like coffee
Which I wasn't familiar with but he was like
I think if we make
You know these office suites we can we can make money we can make more money than the landlord is currently charging
Scream like a bunch of shared
Offices in cubicles invented
Exactly so I mean not nothing too complicated other than just like
Hey right now they lease you an empty space
With
You know 2000 square feet minimum
And you basically has a
The small business you have it in your own hands
To figure that out
Build it out you got to buy all your own Furniture you got to
Sublease space if you can't fill it all up like you're facing all those challenges
And you're paying a good price with the time was you have 20 bucks a square foot or whatever which he knows a good deal
But it was just a very low level
Service since I think
He
Brought to me that idea
And I was like
I'm sounds great
The challenge was that neither of us really had it
Experience in real estate or anything
And so
He would go to the owners of this building C
68j
And say
Hey
We see there
Floors that are available here will you least my dress
Well so they were like redeveloping the building over time they were kind of going floor-by-floor and trying to like
You know move people around 2 cuz they wanted to make my rent so they're kind of like improving cuz it was really crappy I mean I was like
Apache
So they were trying to say they had enough
Thought to say hey let's read about this weekend
Charge my money
And so I'm he started going to him saying Lisa Soho floor and at the time and I remember a floor plate there but it might have been you. 10,000
Repeat and they're just like who are you
You're like the baby clothing guy who
We can't even pay your rent on time
Yeah
Why would we rent to you it makes no sense like you don't know anything about it like we're the experts we owned 100 buildings
And they just kept saying No but
Credit to Adam in this is part of his
You know
Innate ability to like
Continue to press even when people say no he just kept going back and back and on those every week for probably
You sat down together to listen corporate you were just doing
You're saying he was trying to do this
Yeah we have no business plan we had nothing it was a very simple idea like
Hey could we break up
Space inside
No real
Plan it was just an
Simplify
The owner of the building
So he's saying no no no no for weeks on end and then one day apparently and I wasn't there at the time but he says
We are not going to give you a floor in
But I have this other building across
I've been clearing out
Come take a look
Hey let's go look at
This building
And it's
Beautiful
It's like perfect
Latino Brooklyn
Warehouse building
Exposed brick
Expose Timberglen
No beams and columns
Big Windows views of the water
You literally like
You know ideal
Building 4
The cool like you know startup Brook
SpongeBob and and they're basically okay here's the building what would you do with it
And
I'm like
What are we going to do
Adam's like I don't know I'm like okay I'll figure it out
Sobe Sky go home
And
Start thinking of
A concept
Of a name
Come up with green desk
Which is
Oahu
The space oriented towards people who are environmentally responsible
Possible
I buy the domain
You know I build a website
I design some floor plans really simple do you like
Quick like business model
Big Sky we remember when
Kinkos in had business cards made passing Little
Emotional fires
Please put I stayed up all night
You did this in one night
Yeah basically because
We have been challenged was like what you going to do and we have no credibility right so my thought was
If I do all this stuff and come back
Tomorrow it'll seem like we we we were planning it for a weeks in advance right
Only show up the next day with this
Whole thing and they're like
Kind of Blown Away like
Like whoa you actually
Have company
You actually have something real here and that was really you know
Of course Adam
Seoul
Presented this. But he's the one who
Mi Casa Fiesta
No money
We have not a moment to Adam and Miguel went from being
Guessing to building their first space
Literally by hand
Play with us
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this mess
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
Used to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account at gemini.com
Melt Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design and build their own website
Using customizable lights
And features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR I'm guy Roz so it's 2008
And I'm convinced of Brooklyn landlord to give them one floor in a building 2
Start a company
And the idea is to create this
Really cool looking
Space where people can rent out opposite
In the company of this point is called Green.
Even before they finished
Preparing the space
They started advertising
I remember the day when we first did it we put masking tape down on the floor to sort of show the layout of the works
And on we posted ads on Craigslist and people started calling
You know my cell phone and I will meet them into him to the building with just masking tape on the floor
And people started signing up from just the masking to Laughlin
That just showed how different it was one cuz it was cool and we had a list of all the things we're going to offer you never going to give you coffee working
Cool events this kind of stuff
And people needed it I do believe that you would get
Permanent workspace
Be yours or
Yeah so the the thing that was happening back then was there was
Their existing chart of corporate office
And then there was co-working
What's the time
Co-working is primarily tech-focused
It's a lot of like
You know engineers in a big open room
Headphones on a gherkin
And there was
Some of those wasn't like prevalent but you know there's some in Sanford
Cisco if you in New York
And they were primarily like oriented towards a group of people who kind of all knew each other and then they're going to come together
Weather and then they all went to work together in the same room in the invite some other
Adam and I didn't come from that all we were in this
Brooklyn environment we weren't from tattoo
And we were much more interested in this like diversity and all these
Cool different kinds of companies and what that energy is when they come together
That said
All those businesses are doing like
Real sales they're on the phone they're having meetings or talking to people
So this idea of like a big open room just didn't
Work for us it didn't make sense so I think when we first started it was more like
You're going to do small offices you could have like a small
Yeah 5 foot by 7 foot one person
A two-person for a person
Person a person office Inc
At the time maybe at 12 was
The largest Lee dead
And that was you know all glass partition so very open and Airy
And it was really like
You know hey
Join
A group of people working together but you're still in your own private school cost to join
I think at the time we were probably starting at like
$300 for like the lowest end and you know went up to
50000 for a 4-person office at ballpark
Was it expensive when you look at the overall net cost but also not cheap it wasn't like hey this is rock bottom prices
2008 like
Right before the financial
Yeah
You know that I think
Positive and negative in the sense that
One the world was changing very quickly and there was people who are thinking about things differently you know
Perhaps like working at Lehman Brothers or whatever is not
You know the
The best thing for your life where is
You could have been before
You either have some numbers like that or like how I used to be
For this company and now I want to do it on my own
So how many people did you sign up for that first base
So I mean I think
Each floor in that building was
A little under maybe I was 70 people are so
So I think that building was about 350 members
You know it filled up very fast and then we
Expanded Baptist
68j what's
Was the cool thing cuz we went back to the building they wouldn't let us have in the first place
And started building out more
You became the Arctic
Yet so Gill was also our partner at the time so there were three of us and we work together again you know
Worked on MM Architects help with that
And then I bet he was still working at American Apparel or with the firm that did that and then Adams still working for the baby clothing
Stylust beats to the operator so I did
All the stuff to get the business going
And I really was
Immunotherapy
Whatever 18 hours a day putting the whole thing together and
I really running it
You know
As a very small business
So did you guys start to make money at this like
Very quickly
Yeah so the challenge there was it was a good business definitely right off the bat and we were
Profitable
But the problem is is that
Its capital in
So we did the first building under R 50/50
The agreement
And we started thinking big we're like this is amazing everyone loves it where
Grow
And we started looking at Manhattan looking at 10
Cisco thinking of other locations
But they had a portfolio that they already own
The owners of the village
So is in their interest to use all the real estate in their own portfolio
So they're showing us our luck
Gyms in Brooklyn
We're thinking about building a big brand and thinking this is like a worldwide phenomenon like we're going to change the world or doing something really cool
And they're thinking
Let's fill up a large
Existing buildings that have big
Then so as soon as we started talking about like
Other bigger things
It just showed this is not a partnership
Going to work long-term
So you left
So we sold
So he sold to them
They got a great business was there
They're still operating and we got some money to start over again so they own green.
Leon green. Stay still operated and it's a nice little business what did you guys walk away
I wish I remember the details but I knew he must have gotten like
Somewhere between half a million a million dollars each
I mean it was a good amount of money and I think it also presented
A challenge
In that
We had to ask ourselves like
Do we
Take this money and put it in the bank
Or do we view no sort of
Go forward and invested in the next thing and I think
Bradamant II
Is clear like we're onto something big here and
But
Roll with it and
Keep going
Anything for Gilly was a little bit different like you saw this money and was like Hey I can move back to Israel and I
I've got a bunch of money in the bank and
Hey my life is good so no that was good for him in a good
Result for Adam and I was enough to say okay let's switch
Focus completely to this business
India to create a new name and a new brand in August
So I think one of things that we learned that green dust it was super important was when they when it was really working what was cool was the
The connection between people
And
The things that you would hear
People say to each other in support of each other even though they're in
Completely different Industries
Just eat a late at night there's
Across the hall people having these really cool conversations about life about business
And there's also happens of almost like accountability
Cuz one of the things about
Being a small business especially on your own or if your owner of a small company it's like
No one's watching you to see if you show up in the more I tried
But one of the coolest things that happens is like
Tell people become accountable to each other even though they're not working for the same company so if you don't show up for a couple days
Someone actually asked you like hey where you been
So that's one of the cool things that happened to sort of like
Okay we're all working together even though we're separate
You know
Okay so obviously this point
You could not be greenedesk
Marceau
How did you start to come up with a new name
So the problem that we had in trying to reinvent the business is like
What do you call that I know what is the name for
A community oriented business
You know without it sounding too like
Hippy dippy like how do you come up with something this
Suggest idea that we're all together in that we want to like
Be open and connected to each other but doesn't have these words in it that sort of sound
Like over the top in terms of you know
Let's all hold hands
So
We work
Yeah and I think it took a while to get there
What actually happened I think
Literally in the middle of the night Adams friend Andrew just
Literally came out with it and he said
It's wework
Kissui Levites we sleep it's
We eat at weed
Like this
Flowed with this hole
Fing
And was a dialogue that
Months old that just
Happened in a moment for him
In the middle of night and soon as we heard it
That's it
So where was your first stop where did you go to find it and your first
Place so we look
In Manhattan a lot
You did have a non-compete
With our green. Partner so we had a limited number of areas we could go so we're looking in San Francisco and also in
Manhattan and
It was tough and we had a lot of conversations with people who are like again who are you you have no background in real estate
And also people looking for a big credit tenants I mean specially in that environment of of the
Financial crisis a lot of landlords have been burned even by
Credit tenant too you know broke their lease
Went bankrupt or whatever
So very few people wanted to work with us
And we looked at it
I'm going to space is in
Everyone just said
Why you know who are you
And so really what happened to me
It was a friend of a friend of a friend
Knew somebody in and somehow
We connected
For this building I'm in SoHo
And
It was really a relationship sale
You know Adam again like
Redis persistence
And he was willing to go over and over and over to the owner and just
Convince him that
We were the right tenant for this building
And I'm in here
You know he he's good at making connections with people once that door is open like if he's a crack and he can get in there then he's never going to see
Stop until how did you put the money
Did you guys have the money you have so we had the money from the green.
Celso which was enough for the security deposit and you know it again
So it's not like this landlord has a
Carnival drops right here not like
Oh there's all kinds of companies clamoring to move in
Swing like a good place from a real estate
Perspective will take your whole building
And there's not that many other tenants
Look like was it ready to just
Rent out
The people or did you have to
Get it in
Like
Not at all ready
Full. It was actually
In terrible condition
So did it was it going to require to renovate that building
Probably in the order of a few million dollar
Because
You had a vision of what you wanted
To be right like
Imagining light
You know
Hardwood floors
Distressed wood floors and
Beautiful
Appliances and bright
Amelia so we were more conservative back then in terms of our investment you know
We did a lot of the work herself and mutilate the actual labor
Yeah there was a limit to how much they would build versus us until we had some responsibility one of our responsibilities was it
Wiring all the cabling
And so that we were out there getting bids for it wiring and remember we got
One for $100,000 and one for like eighty seven
I remember getting those last
I mean like
$100,000 is a pretty round number for
Wiring light
Shouldn't have like a more detailed calculation of how much that cost
So my little brother and I he's
The background in he was pretty mad and he's like kind of research
Search scientist W in his brain
And he had moved out to help us it was me
Tylenol
And I'm like hey why don't we look into how this actually works in the way his brain works has been to break it down into like the
The most micro Parts Peekskill
Every cable run how long is it
How many terminations you know how do you do termination
Then I mean I remember he asked me to
Going to cost us
$8,000 in materials and then you know whatever like 50 hours of Labor whatever the number was it was some
Crazy small number relative
That's where they
It's not rocket science so we can do that are
So we just did it ourselves
You wire
The building yourselves
Yeah you would like laying the wire dog
And all of it so we had to get like a hammer drill and like Drilling
To The Brick to hold
Like brackets to hold the wire we had to
I mean I was so much fun it was like
It was crazy but it was also like we're really
Fully engaged and we had to teach ourselves how to
That's an eye patch panels and program switches and
You know so you put in that whole infrastructure
I remember one of the things we had to do was actually
This thing called soda blasting which is
If you want that cool like exposed brick has been painted you have to blast the the Sandusky thing called so
Blasting where you use baking soda to do that
And we have to buy
Baking soda by like the 50 lb bag and you need bags and bags and bag of the sermon we would like rent Zipcars
Drive out to the place New Jersey load up the car would like to
A baking soda and we put so much in there that it would be like riding on the wheels on the tire so we be like driving back from New Jersey to the tunneling you because
As the tide like
Running on the back of the
The wheel well
But that was what we were doing was like every step was like we're going to and we rented the equipment that soda blasting equipment just to like do it
Air compressor
On the streets of Manhattan just sitting out there like
This is like the compressor is running out there in like
There's all this baking soda billowing out of the windows up
Upstairs it was awesome
You sign the lease to when you
Open the first floor how long was it
A few months or 3 months probably a maybe a little less with pretty quick
To take me into that first
Floor that you
You open.
Yeah so when you walk in you basically have you know an old wood floor which we refinished and had a lot of that cool character hundred
3 year old work wood floor you have
Exposed brick
Soda blasting
Disorder bring back to that
Rustic sort of vibe we had iron columns that were cool in High character
And then what we sort of inserted into that was sort of a Sharp
Modern Uno glass and aluminum cyst
So you have this
Play Between the old and the new
And another thing was like from the very beginning I didn't want to have an office Evite at all
Again this seems not like a big deal now but back then we did
Batman 2010
How quickly things change I mean back then we did all
Incandescent lighting
Workspace at the time it just didn't use that you had like a cool Brooklyn restaurant in Old auto garage
You had you know other people say doing boot
Boutique hotels with that buy but in workspace no one did that at all
So it's totally unique there was nothing like it
How many
People joined up
By the day you open
I think when we
First open the first
Floor we are probably in the 70 to 80% range
And then within the first couple of months the first two floors were were pretty much
So so once this building
Like most people started
To join up in this
Takeoff
Was Eydie immediately to go out
And get investors and
Like scale is
Huge
Okay so
Part of the story which we didn't talk about is
Before we even built the first.
Are we actually
Had an encounter with a potential investor who
In a room for one of these potential realest
CDL so we are pitching a building we really want to get this
Cool building downtown Canal Street
And the owner of it was like you know I'm not sure if I'll give you the building but I got this friend who might be interested
He's going to come over so this guy shows up to the meeting
Sit down doesn't really speak to us from shake hands with these are like an Orthodox Jewish guys
Knowing the black suit and stuff so to me still has an Oregonian a little bit
Like I don't really know the world
Too well but Adam felt really comfortable with it by then
But he ends up calling I think the
That later that day or the next day after the meeting and saying hate
I don't think we're going to get that building but I want to partner with you guys and we're like well we don't really need
Partner we got money we're building our own thing here
Is it yeah but I
What will it take whatever it takes I want to
How to be a partner
And so you know we were like
Why not let's throw out a number
And
We'll make it outrageous
Is no chance I'll say yes but if he does then he were fighting like we did pretty well and we had no building we had no
No signed lease
Even and we propose the 45 million dollar valuation
And
That's pretty high for
Sephora business that
Is unproven in
And until you said yes
I said Okay I want to be a third partner
Antelope
I'm coming to that
Which I think at the time was a little bit
Scary but at the same time it's like wow that's a real empowerment to say okay now we're going to have all this cash all this cash
Cute dress
So you didn't give us the cash but he committed to it he gave us some of the cash
A little bit to start and then a little bit more overtime and that's actually
A really great story in the sense that
He empowered us to think really big because we
We started out with this
About this
Valuation netsertive validated
Our picture of the future which was really big
So it was great and we're still good friends with him and everything is awesome but
That was the first step in the first money that we took his investment
And then of course overtime you got more more investment
Expanded you build more and more of these faces
Yeah and I think what we did
Was
We built fast
We built inexpensively
I mean turned around deals really quick
And we were successful
You know we built up credibility because each location that we did
Worked and we did what we said we're going to do
You know we weren't like saying
A tech startup where it's like oh there's some
You know hockey
Ustick
Growth and all the sudden we're going to have
Millions of users or whatever
But we were really clear that we're going to
You know continue to grow
And the vibe in the building's was unique and it was super cool and when people came in they could tell it was something different
Just on walking in the door would be like
Wow this is something I have
Seen before
And that validation of both
You know the business is successful it really work
Birthstone chart
Fundamentals of the business are really good
And then we're like
You know we're cool guys and we have a good story and we're here at the right time and you know those things all added up
Yeah you know me
I wonder
You must look at
Uber ride
Somebody's
Big Tech
Andy is coming that we think of it
Giants Ridge
And you don't we have people in the show people who started companies
Don't exist
White like her
And that was a fastest company in history to read
A billion dollars in Revenue
It doesn't exist
Right
Reminiscing about
Your company
Now
It's valued
Counting dollars
It seems like you could be there forever but
I mean do you ever think that
You know all this good
Collapse one day
You know it's a
Great question
One of things that we're holding onto
Bratayley
Is the feeling that we're still figuring it out
That nothing we've done so far is
The right answer
You still feel like a startup
100%
Value it said about the value is irrelevant right to the business Prof
Like who cares how much money are worth when you're facing a business problem that is always
News about being in that
Your primary interest is in
Solving it
In a better way so our primary
Reason for existing
Just trying to help other people
So our problem is like if they change WeChat
And it's sort of symbiotic in that
That way right and that's why I think we don't really have a Finish Line
It's not like Hey we're going to figure out some model
And then we roll it out across the globe it doesn't work that way for us at also
That challenge will never stop
Will have the learning curve forever which is what makes it awesome and Adam and I like we when we talked about this
Is 100 Year a challenge and it's not like he were building companies
We can sell it and move on
We're doing this cuz we think this is the most interesting and biggest challenge we can work on it until it's just
Keep on it forever
When you did your last round
Financing
The company was valued
Billion dollar company that you started
In mm
Which
Is
Do you ever did you ever give her stop and think
Not
That's a good question I don't
It's interesting to think about the times at which
I hate you
And
I would say I'll remember calling my friends when we were first reaching
A billion dollars
I can remember dinner with one of my best friend
When we were at 130
And he was like oh my God 130 like
Are you going to sell in retired and I was like
What like why would I do that like I'm just busy so much fun you know no chance
We got you a billion I remember feeling
Pretty bashful about even saying the words like I remember almost feeling like
Like wow I don't want to send this in a text message
This is going to sound so Preposterous like I want to call and only say it verbally
But then you know once
You cross that threshold it sort of like the other ones going from there and
First of all I wouldn't complain about the fact that
Get to live in Manhattan
I'm going to live in nice Apartments
And I'm living
You know I moved to an apartment with an awesome
View and not so
Childhood dream to Lexi the New York City skyline
I reach those threshold where I live agree
That's awesome
But beyond that I don't have like some big ambition for money
It's not really interesting to me it's more
Again like to be on a path where I feel like I get to
Continue to engage in
Something that's what
It's really you think about like
These
Huge boom
Gold
Or oil
Ortak
And the company's really
We're sustainable the company that made money
The most money off of these industries were they born to service them right like Levi's jeans
Surface the Gold Rush end
Is company to service the oil
Riggs or you know
The become visible the platform
You guys are kind of doing the same thing I mean there's Aztec boom
N&a
Boom of
Amazon
Supernatural spirit
And you
Kind of said what what services
Let's provide the service
Yeah that's a great way of looking at it I don't think I've heard it stated that way but I think it's really true and it's not
Just those things which any Tech boom is important but it's also a shift in what people are looking for in their life and what
Their expectations are from work because
There's a
Major shift happening in terms of young people thinking about going to work everyday
And what do they want back from that
People don't want to punch the clock anymore and then have their life start when they leave the office they want their life to be
Be integrated they want to feel like there
There's value in what they do everyday
And that's part of the environment that we create you know you can get that so you working a Google Facebook whatever super cool office you know me
Maybe you feel this by
But when you're a small company or so you're working for a bank or one of these places that isn't inherently as cool
You may not get that
Azizi and what we're offering is something we're
You're an independent worker or you're a small company of two people
Where you're like a division from a pharmaceutical company or a bank
We're giving you that name for a cool environment where like it doesn't feel like you're going to work everyday it feels like you're going to
You know a cool spot to like meet people and connect and collaborate right and that's I think the trend that we're working on
Lesser specifically attack or less so than any other business permits more like a mindset shift
Yeah
It is very interesting seeing you
Talk about this
With confidence in a
Barry
Shut up
Queer
Way and you
Animals to seeing you as this kid in this community
In Oregon
And I'm trying to square that Circle
It's it's just
It seems so important
Plausible
Sat
You know
Here you are, real estate deals are price
4 sqft and
All this
And I'm not that is a bad
Right it's just
Brightening do you ever
I think that's
Implausible
No
Primarily because
I've been doing all the hard work for the last
I mean literally
From 1990
Sex or whenever it was
95 when I started architecture
The score and I committed to the work
Like
I work non-stop since then and I don't mean like literally
I mean a lot of it was ours
But I mean it more like commitment
Like I've been committed to the work
An interested in engaged with the work since that Non-Stop
And I think that's part of the thing is that I found something that I love
To do and I
Felt what it feels like to love what you do
And I've never been willing to give that up
And I've been on that track ever since
Miguel McKelvey co-founder of we work by the way among the six kids who grew up with
Miguel and the Communists to are employed by wework and another Sadie Lincoln founded
Her own Empire a national chain of exercise Studios called barre3
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to find out
More about it the how I built this. Npr.org
Next week we're going to be back with our usual feature how you built that so if you want to submit a story about something
You're working on go to build. Npr.org you can also write to us and speech IBT at and
Grar.org or follow us on Twitter at how I built this and of course if you like us please
Describe podcast you can find it on iTunes or however you get your podcast or show was produced this week by Run
Teen Arab Louis also composed the music of Jeff Rogers Santa's meshkinpour and clear
Is Lawrence guy Roz and he been listening to how I built this NPR
Sam Sanders here these days I feel like I can't make sense of a News until I talk it out with my friend
I made a new show where we do that
Every week
It's called
It's been a minute
That's my way of saying let's catch up our first episode is out this Friday evening June 23rd
Check it out
It's been a minute
On the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast thanks
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor