Support for this podcast in the following message come from mizzenandmain
Creators of moisture wicking wrinkle-resistant dress shirt
Shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
Come and use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
Hey it's guy here so
We're still working hard prepping for a live episode coming up in
In a couple of weeks
We are looking forward to seeing some of you there in Seattle on September 14th
For my conversation with
Howard Schultz
Starbucks
But for now we got this one from our archives
One of our favorites
The story of Vice
Enjoy
I remember walking down the street
Completely freaked out with a friend of mine all who else went to meetings
And I was scared
And because I didn't know what I was doing and he said
What have you got to lose
He said maybe it'll be
Like one magazine that you make
And you can go around and say hey I made this magazine and then you can apply for a job and get a job somewhere
Or maybe it'll be huge
From NPR is how I built this
Shobha innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements built
Salvia take a small alternative magazine in Montreal and built it into Vice media
Witches
Totally mind-blowing
Now valued at over 4
Billion dollars
I'm sitting here in the studio
And I'm looking at that website
For Vice
And I'm clicking through you know it's
Typical mashup of
Hard-hitting news in the
Oddball feature
I like this one that says that the story is a psychologist analyzes the fights couples have
And Ikea
Identify with
And then you just
Scroll down a little bit
This is one
How majority-muslim countries are handling HIV infections
And of course you can you know you can click on Plenty of
Slick videos that take you all over the world like
This one
Cockfighting in the
Canary Islands
Ana Belen Dominguez acerra activist
An organization that fights for animal rights in the Canary Islands
I'm meeting her because she has arranged to meet Jose Luis Martinez president of the Canary Islands cockfighting fed
Play we know that fashion news websites
And I almost as fast as
Is a large butt
For some reason
Vice
I stuck around
Its YouTube channel has over a
Billion views and
A couple of
Peabody Award
Prestigious
But the thing is
Vice co-founder suroosh Alvi
Keep didn't set out to create any of this in fact
He barely made it out of this
Money is alive
I was
Born in Toronto and my parents emigrated
From Pakistan
A couple years
They are retired academics
My mom taught at
Miguel
And my father at the University of Toronto although my mom also
University of Minnesota
For a while
And so I ended up going to high school
Vim States
So
I heard a lot of you have to work
Twice as hard as white
Going to get anywhere in this world grown up
Is it that turn out to be
Yeah
What what did they want you to
Well the two
Feels that are most respected
Impacts on at least
When I was growing up was
Medicine or engineering
So I think that
You know in an Ideal World
I would have been a doctor
With that with a ba I'm
The black sheep
The family everyone has multiple
Ways to save on collagen in Montreal
Were you a good student
I was not a good student I originally went into psychology I got kicked out of that program ended
Getting a degree in philosophy
It was a
Tough
Slot guide
Come from no small
Private school in
Minneapolis Road high school and
Going to Galveston
Different distractions
In Montreal and that's a
Place where you can buy
You can hit a low point right
Yeah
That's where I
Bottomed out
When I
You know finished Miguel it was
Also with a
Full-blown heroin habit
And so
I spent a couple years afterwards kind of looking for a geographic
Bouncing around jumping
From City to City
From snout with me
It's here the city this environment its
Just to decadence
Blah blah blah
So I ran around
And
No matter where I went
I kind of took it with me
Thumbs up in Eastern Europe and even there in a remote part of Slovakia
Was able to
Stay strong out for upwards of five years and
Ended up back in grad school Toronto
Studying psychology
And I dropped out
And that's when I really was like
You know descending in the talespin
Heading bottom and when I end up back in Montreal it was
To go to rehab
How did you know it's
I need a rehab
I couldn't
I couldn't sustain it anymore
Keep the
The Web of Lies
Going
Yeah there was this got a double life
I've been waiting
No no one really knew
That I was
Heroin addict
Your friends
I got my parents are
Conservative Muslim
Immigrants
But Progressive
As well
As far as Pakistani immigrants go
But they thought I had the
They didn't know the
Tenth of what
What's going on
With me and when they found out
My mom went to bed
Depression my brother wanted to kill me my dad
Had a heart attack
I don't know if that the heart attack was directly related but I don't think it helped
It was bad it was a really bad time and
So my mental state
At the time was
Was not good at I did go into a bit of a
Depression at that point I went I had to go to rehab twice
The first time it didn't
Stick and
They found out that I was using again
And
It's the only time in my life that my mom never hit me
And at that point I remember that
It was my bottom
So it's like early 94
On the waiting list to get into a treatment center
No friends no
I wasn't speaking much I was
Kind of Dino kicking dope in my parents house on a waiting list to get a new treatment center like
Life is not great at that point
How long does it take you before you
You started to assert
Steel like you
Or regaining control over
Black I came out of
The treatment center and I was so scared that I was
Relapsing
Just like I was going to meetings this going to
NA meetings
The time
Yeah they say you should go to 90 meetings in 90 days when
Stop drinking or doing drugs and and I was going to like two meetings a day
I got my own little apartment in Montreal
Was on welfare and I just
What are my bike from meeting to meeting all day everyday and it was
During
That time that I actually started thinking
About
What I wanted to do with the rest of my life and
I had this idea that I wanted to work for a magazine
And you wanted to write about like what
Like music
A culture or lie
Like what will
I didn't get that far
Something I felt like
That I want to do
Talk about those things yes music culture
I felt like there was
A lot happening that wasn't being talked about when I picked up magazine
Depraved underground culture that that I was obsessed with was not being covered properly in the alt-weekly
What's it like a realistic possibility could you just go in and work for me
Magazine or orange
No I don't think so I had no experience doing it my only
Writing that I've ever done was
Academic
You're writing in University
And when I was going to these meetings in Montreal
Someone came up to me
An out-of-the-blue they started a conversation with me
And they said you have a sponsor I said no
And they said well I'll be your sponsor in a random dude
Walked up to me yesterday
He was in the meeting with me the meeting ended and he came up to me
He said what are you what are you doing like are you working I said no I'm not working I can't even get a job volunteering anywhere ID
I tried to volunteer at this
Wouldn't let me
And
Out of the blue he said have you ever thought about writing
He didn't know me
I was like actually yeah and he's like well I know a place I'll take you there tomorrow
So he took me to this place these Haitians in Montreal who
Had a a bilingual magazine going
Call damaj Intercultural it was becoming French only and they want to start an English magazine
And he vouched on my behalf
This is the guy you want he's really good
He worked there before but he was like this
This is heaven-sent Angel who just was like
Put in my path and it opens up a whole conversation about like
Do I believe in God do I believe in a higher power. I believe in Allah all this kind of stuff
For me that whole story is like the
Proof of existence
This moment for me in my life
Something greater than me to put me
There in this place where this guy just
Walked up to me and shows me to talk to me
And happened to know a place that was looking for a guy to start an english-language magazine in Montreal
Exactly
So what was the magazine called and how did it start
So so I went in for this meeting and he vouched for me and said that he don't be long time that I was going to work really hard I didn't have
A lot of experience but that
He thought I could do this thing and day
They said okay and they gave me a desk a fax machine a phone and a computer
I started this process of
You know
Making a magazine
Panda
Alright voice of Montreal
Is the name that I came up with at the time
And I had no idea what I was doing I just
But I knew a few people around town and
Started this kind of recruitment process of finding writers to write in the magazine and
And I remember walking down the street
Completely freaked out with a friend of mine and I was scared
And because I didn't know what I was doing and he said
What have you got to lose
He said maybe it'll be
You know like one magazine that you make
Can you can go around and say hey I made this magazine and then you can apply for a job and get a job somewhere
Or maybe it'll be huge
And like that
Conversation
On the street that was
A huge moment for me because I gave me the kind of strength
To continue on when I was
Like overwhelmed could barely tie my shoes thread coming out of the treatment center like
That was a mess
And I owe him a lot because he
Realize what he's doing
The time but he gave me this
Strength to
Keep marching forward
So you get to the magazine what like
What kind of
Publication was it
It was a 16-page newsprint bags
But you were like that the kind of really like the
Poor poor stepchild
The two big all week
Like you guys were
We were the laughing
Because it was a shrinking English Market
So it's you
Mitchell bilingual City
So there are four
All Weekly's already to French ones into English ones
And then we came on the scene in the English Market is actually shrinking
There wasn't enough
Advertising
To sustain those to let alone the third one
It didn't
Make any
Economic sense
Yeah but I really believe that there was an audience there for what we were talking about
So you guys were recovering like what like
The center of the Earth
Couch alternative scene in Montreal like skaters and
Punctual
Is music like Underground Music
And
Terrible editorial about
The search for authenticity and then heat for like quitting wheel contact but
I stand by that editorial like
I hope you got nobody ever finds out and publishes again because it
It was awful but it is the spirit
Of what we do today is
Was was there you are so like you are basically the editor-in-chief of this
Magazine in early 20s voice Montreal
And like who did you hear some the people you brought in to help you started in
Create it
You're one of my
Friends from college he connected me to a bunch of different artists and also two different writers in one of these writers
It was a guy named Gavin McInnes and he
It was funny and had a comic book called pervert
That's why I asked him to become my assistant editor
And I think I ask him to be my, excited or whatever that means
It was his job to find the different comic artists around town and put together a Comics page
Who's out, the public face of a vice I guess
How did he how did he get involved
So Shane and Gavin
Grew up together in Auto up
And
The first night we met he was just like he said literally said you're my new best friend
On acid as well I should know I should qualify this
Should I use in a bar called a bifteck
Gavin I had been
Drive around the city all day Distributing the magazine it'll just come out
And we finished all rounds and went to the bar to meet Shane and he was in there he's been waiting for a couple hours for us and
By himself somehow managed
Epicurus of psychedelics and was drunken
Novice
Of course you don't
Sober
Tires and I walk him this a drunk man on psychedelics
Who is I call you from Pakistan you must love cricket and then was like
Pretending to like bowl like balls at me and
But he worked for Greenpeace before and he could actually sell
With greenpeace usa
Erase a lot of money for them and
Eastern European
Involved with some activities
Where he was making lots of money
Basin activities I'm going to leave it up. He was good at making money and you could
Yo self
Rattlesnake boots to Rattlesnake
And so then it was
Me Gavin and Shane working
In this
Office with the Haitians
We were there for like 3-4 months and
But it wasn't working out
Because we weren't getting paid
Commissions on the ads that we were selling it
But we're on welfare
And so we talked about the vacations and said
You don't
It's time for us to believe in
We came up with this thing where
We said the Village Voice has a trademark on the word boys
And there are suing us and forcing us to change our name piss you guys were the voice of Montreal yes we told the world
That we were being sued by The Village Voice and that's why we had to change the name device
Basically made this thing up about the Village Voice did to generate publicity
Yeah
And it was a complete lie
I got out of that's why we dropped the O and then how we started Vice City basic Curry today
We we created a new message
Why did you like to go
To find a new office or did you start working at your apartment or that's a good question we we got it a new Loft
And like not too far from the original office
I brought five grand for my parents Davenport five grand from his
Parents and Shane got $5,000 worth of computers
From his dad is that working
No ID or something and
So it was with that
Dollars
Canadian
That we started Vice
Okay so this is now like
Like I guess the mid-90s
And you guys
Vice
What was the magazine like at that point
What did you cover
We
Really wanted to
Again
It's such an over
Use word guy but it's
It's a good one authenticity like how do you create
Real Kanto
And we're going to journalism School
So the way to do that is to get as close to the source
It's possible
And if we were going to write an article about
The prostitution
Community in Montreal let's
Get the process
Write that story
Then let's go out with pimps as they drive around and interview them and so we created this
Really raw
Magazine
There are a lot of typos but it was
Alive like I did the worst kind of jumped out
The pages and it was kind of shocking stuff and yeah
And we were so
Without freedom of
Depress
With such a big deal like we're so anti-censorship that even
If you
I'll be towards advertising if you
By that page of advertising you on that page you can do whatever you want with
So we have these
Skateboard companies from Southern California that had like
Your p*** stars in their ads
Nude pornstars in the ad so the magazine all the sudden has
He's crazy articles with
Lots of nudity advertising
Skateboard companies called serial killer skateboards or whatever it was
This whole weird little
Take on
American culture that was coming from Montreal so we were
Science magazine to San Francisco Chicago La New York in
Americans reading it up
So you guys making money like
Pretty soon after
Like bootstrapping it
Barely
We were bootstrapping it be
Cuz we couldn't
Afford to have that we didn't
We couldn't get a loan
So we
Just printed copies based on how much we were
Selling an advertising and
It's what we call this
It's kind of punk rock capitalism
Be really aggressive be really ambitious and you can't have that
Those are the rules that we live by until we
Tok our investment
The first time
That was an
Give me some 25% of the company to running rich
Jigsaw Winski
So he he was like
A rich guy who
Invest
It seems like kind of a
Crazy and that's
So Shannon I had realized at that point that we needed
Some help if we want to grow the mag
Magazine
Raku Investments like maybe Larry Flintwood and
There was a guy in Montreal
Richard sowinski who
Had a software company called discrete logic that he'd sold to Autodesk for several hundred billion dollars and
He was
Starting to buy a media properties
And we had been
Interviewed by the French daily and Montreal called The Press
And so we said
In that interview in the press that he was interested in buying us
And he done Reddit
And then it had his office contact us a few days later and said
He wants to meet you guys who are you guys
He has no idea who you are but apparently he's interested in buying a so we met him
An individual very quickly
To sell 25% of the company to him
Crazy amount of money for you guys at the time
Raise
Yeah
This could have happened in Montreal there was no due diligence that took place
It was literally one meeting with him
At a restaurant that he
He loved until he bought it and moved it into the basement of his office
And he
Brought a bottle of Jack Daniels
And kind of for Shane to drink a bunch of it
And that the end of the meeting said I want
To buy piece of your magazine come back to me in a week and tell me how much
And and don't try and gouge me
And so we we left his office and spend a week going like how much
Do we value our company for like it
I was kind of arbitrary pulled it from the air
Yeah we pulled it from the air and came up with this number somehow justify that it was
What is a million bucks
And he read it
What is all in one piece paper to
The price of ice
He right at the Sun
That's a lot of money and then he signed it
And they wished us upstairs and they wrote us checks
And I think his
Advisors like this is such a bad idea
This shouldn't be happening but again no due diligence no like accounting nothing
And his office was actually walking distance
More office in
We went out it was
Springtime in Montreal we literally did somersaults in the grass
When we left 50000
So what's up with that money
You were able to
Scale magazine
We're able to move to New York
Wake up back the story of Isis move to New York and it's almost complete collapse
It's how I built this from NPR
Garage stay with us
He thinks tour 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
A campaign monitor
They took email marketing and made it radically easy
So the big thinkers to focus on
What they do best
Developing Big Ideas
Choose from hundreds of
Specially crafted templates
Turn key design
Create campaigns
Get results
The best part
Drag-and-drop editor gets
The job done in
Record time
Try it for free
Campaignmonitor.com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and business
Unforgettable
Support also comes from luminary
The only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah has a new podcast
With his new show
The Daily Show hosts the challenges himself and his listeners
Explore unfamiliar angles and embraced differing viewpoints
Listen to Trevor Noah has a new podcast along with other original shows
Only on Luminaire
Visit luminary. Links built for your first two months of luminaries premium content for free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's 1999
Gavin Shane and suroosh alvi
$250,000 check
And a
Dream to become much
Speaker
We always had aspirations to talk about the world and other things as well and we
It started building up a stable of writers that was International
But we had a ceiling
Becoming National in Canada
Wasn't good enough for us we aspired for more and we thought okay we have to go.
If we want to become
Bigger
We need to go to either New York or London or LA
And so what is your investor Richard zielinski
Want you to say
To do with the money
He had this vision
So he had advice and then he had a magazine called shift
Which was like a spin meets wired kind of
Magazine for slightly older crowd and then he had another company called Halo 46
Which was
Kind of luxury goods high-end brand
And he wanted all three of these brands
To diversify and become multichannel brands
That was going to be tied into a big e-commerce platform
And he's going to take it all pop
And in so that's what we did with the money we
We built a fashion division the film division the TV division of Music division
And
Beside with brick and mortar
Presents for your
Fashion Division and education that you guys weren't even
Thinking about like you were you were thinking we're just two
Physique
He's kind of ahead of the Curve
This kind of like an Amazon kind of thing and
Like we came in and we actually
Executed his business plan and like you actually started a fashion label
And we had we had four
Tory clothing store like you got designers to make like Vice
Fashion advertising
Clothes
That we we realized by doing it that
We don't want to sell pants for a living that were better at making contest
That's really what we want to do but it served its purpose at the time
Seems like really
Like trying to move no
Very quickly
So when's he kind of
Run out of money in retreated to Nantucket
And this is when the butler.com bubble
Exactly
So what were they leave you guys
It left us
You know high and dry like stores in New York you an office space in Manhattan and
You had employees
And you are
I'd no money
90%
It was bad
It was bad time
So what happened to zielinski
We found out that Richard was in Nantucket at his house and so we rented a car and drove up there
We took the ferry over
And
Calling from a payphone
Can you pick this up
And was very surprised that we were there we had met any contact with him for in like a month or something like that was coming
Russia running out of money
Yeah
So we went to his house we're like what's going on you said it's over the money's gone
I'm done
I can't put any more money into this
So
What are we doing so
Then we came back and that's when we move to Brooklyn
We left his office I unscrewed the mirrors out of the bathroom and
Put the plants in the desks and filing cabinets that we still have
I'm still using the same filing cabinet that I stole from that office on 27th Street
It all happened so quickly we
And we sold more equity
Saul Alinsky so we ended up taking over
Control of the whole company at that point
Okay so wait
Before the company basically fell apart
He he bought the entire company from you
Yeah and then like we did a stock trade
Our shares for his company which was called normal net
And the like you're worth 44 million dollars now so we went for me on welfare to theoretically being
Worth 40 million bucks
In a very short amount of time
It just all collapsing and being broke again
And all the sudden we have these stores and we have death
For the first time
And so when's he still owned completely owns the brand of that point and then we bought it back from him
How did you do that
Verb
Pennies-on-the-dollar Shane data deal and
You know he was
Nice to us in a way like
Even though
He put us out of business but he was
He he agreed to sell
The company back to us when we did a deal with him
I can't remember exactly how much but for
4 and we got a deal to buy the cup
I'll be back sweetie
Dollar equity
How how are you able to raise the money to buy him out
I borrowed money from my brother
Well we'll have to borrow the money
So you guys buy the buy back to company
Play it's yours again
Essential you got to complete
Rebuild it
So what did you do did you like I mean you got the
Is the shop
She got the film Division and this division of the e-commerce like what are you do
We went back to
To doing things how
We had originally done them
Which is
We can't have
And we owed all this money to these Italian like fashion companies who manufacture their clothes and Shane went and
Took meetings with all of them
I figured out how to
Reduce the debt
So he's like what I know you want 200000
I've got 20
Take it or leave it
Show me or take the 20 grand
And that's how we worked our way out of gas at that time and we just went back to
Eating beans and rebuilding
And in doing things how we always done them before we
Tok investment
And so that was
You know
Like
I really valuable lesson and being able to buy the company back
And
Have a second chance
Was was huge
Cartoon in the midst of all this year you were still putting out the magazine
Yeah the magazine was hot
They were still doing well like from a
Cultural lag
Maybe not making a lot of money it was
Profitable because
It had to be
We weren't paying people much money
And
We weren't Distributing millions millions of copies but it was getting out there and it was
Who's making
An impact
I'm getting some recognition
And you're still mainly covering like
Counterculture
Yeah
But when occasionally we would have photojournalists that would come in who had been in Afghanistan
Or
Jamaica and done something with like
You know
Gangsters in Jamaica and we would
Run their photos like we tried but we didn't have the resources
We didn't have
A net worth we weren't doing reporting
In the traditional sense at all
It was a Culture magazine that occasionally
Did some kind of music photojournalism
If it was
Gritty and raw
But in 2006
That was when everything
Changed for us when we picked up cameras
Yeah
We took a meeting with MTV
And they said if we gave you money to make a DVD what would you do
And we said it would be
Play jackass meet 60 minutes
And that work we were speaking their language
MN
So they gave us money to make a DVD
So he's okay let's go make the travel
The vice guide to travel DVD
I said where did you go
I went to Pakistan
We travel to Syria 3 years ago
What is the mass of illegal arms Market
Believed to be a source of weapons with Delavan
We just got to recreated what we done in the magazine
Is this loaded but it was the first time we
We were telling stories in a different medium and it was like a
8 Minute segment
We started on this DVD
That
Segment eventually ended up on the homepage of
CNN
And and
They treated as news
The co-founder of Vice
Took a trip to the country's most volatile City Karachi
It's crazy it to think about it right because
If you if you go back to the early 2000s
Late 90s
There were a lot of really cool magazine
Show me there were a lot of really cool
Like seeing some people doing cool stuff and
But for some reason you guys
Made it at liquor why do you think
That is how was it that Vice
Became vice
And those other magazine
We refused to die
Again we're survivors
Right and we always
Find a way to do a deal even when
Times where it where dark and it was hard
And we found a way
And
We Diversified
The right time so we would have
Some
Other deal
That would keep the lights on
While the magazine is going through a downturn and we're having a hard time selling ads
Don't do a big deal with with Viacom that will
Keep us going for another eight months you know and then
Do a deal with
No private Equity Firm and get some money from there
And it's okay but it is crazy that all those magazines are gone
For the most part and they were also
Big
And we were like the stepchildren
And they disappeared
How do you feel when people say that basis is
Like self-indulgent
You know I'm it's all about the reporter
And it's not really news
Because I mean you you have heard that right and you you hear that from mainstream news organizations
Sure
So how do you feel about ending to you
Defensive guice ignore it or
Maybe they're right
And we ignore it for the most part I think they're
Often
Wrong or there they're basing it on
One thing that we did
Way back in the do whatever but I do believe
Strongly and how we
Creator content
And the importance of
Having a point of view
And and subjectivity
Yes we didn't go to journalism School
But I think that there is
A place for the type of content
That were making it
We're winning
Peabody Award
You know for all the people that are taking shots of this also think
Those
Accusations are coming from a place of
People feeling threatened as well
You know
Wild Al Jazeera America shutting down in that kind of thing
Of course we've we have me Compton that isn't
Great that isn't perfect there are mistakes for learning we're going to school in public
You know in an in
And when I do think there's a lot that
They teach in journalism school that we've tried to incorporate into the content we make
Be accountable
Yeah there ever been stories that you guys have done that you
Yeah
Can you talk about them without fear of being sued or
No I meant like that there's there's the one that the McAfee
Story I don't know if you remember that one
The guy who did the
Exactly where we kind of embedded with him and and
Released a photo where we didn't scrub the
Geotag from it so people
We basically exposed exactly where
She was when he was on the run which we
Obviously we're trying to do and everybody
We celebrated that mistake
Everybody being
All the competition in in the other
Unions are organizations that
Novi so they're trying to
Do this reporting in and they're making rookie mistakes so that was you know
Learning a lesson in in public the hard way
But for the most part
You know why I don't have a lot of
Regrets about
But the content that
We make and have made visits got us to this point today
Get me over time you guys have
Attracts a lot of investment
And today
Spices value it over for
Billion
Dollars
You started this like
English language version of a Haitian Fresh Magazine in 1994
Like how crazy is
I mean it takes me back to that time on the street where my buddy said to me he said
Maybe I'll make one copy of the magazine or maybe it'll be huge one day and in my gut
At that time
I felt like oh maybe this could be huge I couldn't Define it I didn't know that this is how it was going to manifest itself
We would employ
New 2000 people in
And be valued at over four billion dollars but yeah it's it's pretty amazing
Suroosh alvi co founder of Vice
By the way since this episode first Ram last year vices valuation has gone up to over 5
Billion dollars
That's for suroosh he's no longer editing BIOS on a daily basis these days
He spends most of his time traveling around the world and picking the stories
He wants to tell
Are you the only one of us without sleeve tattoos tattoos
I'm a minority
Instagram because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about
But the things you're building
Thanks to one of our sponsors
TD Ameritrade
TD Ameritrade is always ready to listen and
Conversation about your goals
Complimentary goal planning session to discuss your financial future
Visit tdameritrade.com
Podcast
Hey thanks for sticking around because
It's time now for how you build that
Ariel chicken with someone who he first interviewed back in the fall he's from Bend Oregon
I'm Sheridan owner of Wawa
Just coffee can says even though that coffee is instant and it comes in a little packet
So being able to just Add Water wherever you are is pretty special in my opinion without comp
Supervising the quality for even the highest coffee snob
Kisses that he's actually going for a flavor that tastes as good as a $4 pullover
Coffees that have a caramel sweetness nutty like hazelnut fake leather wet
Hyacinth
Pine needles blueberry mango tropical fruit notes
Watermelon is getting these coffee beans from specialty Roasters all across the u.s. and he wants
Starbucks Coffee online
But he's obviously not the first person to try to make a really good
High-end instant coffee
Starbucks
So there is competition out there
One other problem as soon as we try to ramp up
Everything went crazy it seems like you know when you
Pump It Up in size and you have all of these
Variables with
Temperature and pressure
It's not so clear-cut
Last November he had just finished a Kickstarter campaign
And he owed his backers
1339 cups of coffee
I mean I remember talking to you
Back in November and just being like I hope I hope this next batch is it
I was pretty determined
Find a way how to make it work
And give those people their coffee
And at the time Kent was
Kind of freaking out because the company in Missouri
It was helping him freeze-dry the coffee
Just kept sending in batches that taste
Burnt and metallic
And
That bass that we were waiting on it turn out completely ruined again
And we just decided
It's not going to work
Attend tennis partner would not
Give up
So instead
We just double down
And instead of sending or coffee out
Two contractors to try to process it for us
We just purchased our own freeze-drying equipment
And went back to doing it just ourselves
And
It just got so much better
Anime
Finally sent their first batch
Their Kickstarter followers
That was such a relief I mean we were just waiting for it to be exactly what we promised and nothing less
That's Ken Sheridan of Wawa coffee
Which plans to launch for real in October by the way
They just caught another really big break
A major investment of $200,000
From a former VP at Stumptown Coffee
It's of course been so many ups and downs
But through every down there's
Just this even greater upside
So that's that's kind of what I love about this
This whole thing
To find out more about Walla coffee check out our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listen
Think of a show this week if you want to find out more you can go to how I built this. Npr.org better yet some
Drive to us on Apple podcasts or however you get your podcasts you can also write to us
Our email address is HIV tea at npr.org
You can follow us on Twitter is at how I built this
It was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to Diva grandson of Michigan for Claire Breen
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Is Lawrence will
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey I'm sensanders here
Want to tell you about the
The only NPR show where you can hear about the latest White House drama
An
Turn TRL to MTV
Show is called it's been a minute
Every Friday
Catch up on the week of news and culture
Everything and every Tuesday I sit down for some long interview
With authors filmmakers directors
And more
You can find it's been a minute on the NPR one app or wherever
You get your vodka
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor