Support for this podcast in the following message come from mizzen & Main
Creators of moisture wicking wrinkle-resistant dress shirt
Shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
Come and use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
Patriots guy here with a quick note before we start the show
When you support public radio stations it help
Keep podcast like how I built this going and it helps NPR make new one
So if you want to keep this show and other NPR shows
Going
Please donate now to your local station
You can do that by visiting donate
NPR
. org
Slash
Built
And then when you do that you can shirt on social media by using the hashtag
Why Public Radio
And thanks so much
And just one more quick thing as you probably know we've been prepping for our final two live shows of
In the meantime
Check out this one is for my favorites from the year it's
The story of Zumba even if you're not interested in Zumba or any exercise for that matter
You will not want to miss this story
Enjoy
We spent the whole $14,000 with zero in the back
We created this beautiful email address send and we're praying please please and suddenly
450 instructors joint and so that's when we said this
Is going to be your life and and let's make it work
Ramen
The ark is how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind them
Movements
Immigrants from Colombia turned a scrappy aerobics class into one of the biggest Fitness brands
In the world
Okay so it's almost the new year
And you know World thinking about getting back to the gym or
Getting into shape even if it's just like for a week or two
During those glorious two weeks you might stumble into a class in which everyone just seems to be
Really really happy and
If you do
There is a good chance that that class they're taking
Is Zumba
Yes this is Simba it is a kind of mash-up of
Aerobics and Latin dance and Hip-Hop and
Begin with a guy named Alberto Perez he goes for the name Beto
Metro is a Dancer by training
And back in the 90s
He was living in Cali Colombia
Aerobics during the day to make EX
Extra money and at night he would
Dance in a company
Play one day he was heading to his Robux
That's when he realized
He left his regular music
At home
And the only music that I have with me in this moment it was
I said
Wait Latin
Music
Laura Cumbia
Moringa
Salsa
Different kind of music
Badaling
Start the class I didn't say to my students
I make a mistake
I ate Italian listen to class today
I want to do something
Apparently say you okay
Home Depot
And I start my class and everybody loved it
And this moment I discovered
And I saved myself
I need to do this for my life I love it
It's so cool
Basically started this new kind of
Fusion aerobics class in Cali for a long time and it
Became really really popular
So he decided to try his luck in America
And he told all the stuff he bought a ticket to Miami
Annie
Start to knock on doors
I went to the gym
I'm finally in the body
Bad things shipped to me I didn't speak English I can explain what I do
And I come back
Save money and I come back again
To Miami
Went to the different games
Forte
Finally the third time
One America
Woman in the north Miami Williams Island
Gnocchi
I want to do audition with
How do you say perfect
I went with my Frenchie translated
Do you say better
You okay you do division
On a Thursday
What is the people
No
She want only you and her
My God
Like if the party
Taiwan tea with one person you asked like a
Strain
But okay I went to the gym it was Friday like at 3:30 in the afternoon this time
All the teams in the
The planets empty
Let me see what
What's on Highway 20
I like to play
OG, watitoh point you know
Oye como va
Auntie wow it's my life I messed up to take my brother stabs like we said
And In This Moment a lot of people come to the gym
To go to the training maybe they lift weights or something and they come in
And they are always wrong because they think it's a class they don't know some people who are true
The gym working out saw you
Auditioning for the
Manager in
They started to like come in and check it out
Exactly
Are they coming in three people for 5
6 and one more going to have like at 25 people
I'm people
Laugh every song
I know Dish Anywhere
15 minutes
I dance for 1 hour
And this moment they woman tell me okay you know
I want to do a chance for you
Come here
In one month
I'm teaching myself
Only for tomorrow
And this moment my my friend translate all his new sa wow perfect this is the only thing that
And I come back to my city
A nice soul
My car is on
Get off
Sore everything
I pay my
My bills
And I come back
The first thing that you by yourself
A Pontiac
85 North condition
The car
Airport $400
I live here in Toledo
Apartment
400 dollars to
Dalila Bela
I my first baby was Eric Smith
Waiting
2 blanket
I like teach my first class
And I came late because I lost in this moment that doesn't six
The GPS
I like him late 50
Jimenez Lai Tai Chi
Believe it
But anyway
I come to the room
There was room
People was quiet I didn't say sorry excuse me because I didn't speak English
I like the music and I say please God help me
How do I start
The party and people smiling
Tainan
Hyundai
The rest is story
Pause the story for Sight because I want to I want to bring in another guy who comes into the picture at this point
Hello
Can you help
Zumba become
Avocado and that forever be listening
This is also
Alberto no call me Alberto call him Beto
So I've Been Told
Beto's
Beto Perez
Zumba in
Columbia brings it to Miami
Alberto is a guy who was going to help him make it into this
Huge thing
But before that happened Alberto Perlman was living in Miami
1999 with all the guys my age were starting internet companies and I
I said why not so he launches in Latin America
Seems to be going fine for a short. Of time until
The Dot com bubble burst
Alberto's company
Collapses
So I personally was
Out of a job and I had
No money in the bank
And I didn't know what I was going to do and I was having dinner at my parents house
And
My mom
Kept talking about bettas class in at that point fair to hear Miami he called his classroom besides
Because Rumba in Spanish means to party
And then she turned to me and said
Why you meet with Beto
Maybe
If you're looking for something right now maybe you and him can start a gym together or something
And I said I don't know if I'm going to start a gym
I don't meet with him
Sketches that means your background was in
Technology in in like
Direct Market yourself
Seems a weird like that's not really my thing
What's the thing that pops into my brain at that time was
Could this be an infomercial
Could this be
Something that we could
Basically sell some videotapes of this
Splicing
Do something with it but I wasn't sure
I wasn't sure
So the next day
I was meeting with Beto at a Starbucks isn't like what
2000-2001
And she told me his life story
Which is unbeliever
I grew up in
Columbia also so I knew
What's happening in the country
But he was in college
And Kylie was
The epicenter of
Violence
And
Xerosis
15 year old kid
Dancing
On the streets and that's in clubs and dancing in James and
And so it was like just
The position right with all the violence happening in
This kid make
Everybody happy
Discount right
That's what he told me his life story
Class cuz a Zumba class interesting what a Zumba class is that
The instructor is
Is always telling a story
The music selection
How they teach the class
So I went to see the
And the one thing
That I noticed
Was that every single person
Smiling
And I had
Been a gym member
Before and I can do that normally a smile is not the
To go Facebook
People are doing
When they're exercising really heavily
People are suffering
Forcing themselves
It's it's kind of like the drill sergeant mentality
But then there was this
Plus
Which is like an oasis inside the gym where every single person
Was smiling but they were drenched in sweat
At the same time
And I'm like this guy
Doesn't know it but he has
Discovered like a magic pill
He has discovered the exercise that people want to do instead of the exercise that people have to do
So you said to him would you say to him do you say hey let's start a business
Yeah you told me about the what do you want to do
Dinosaur dino Maine
Let's do it
Conquer the world
And the funny way you know
Did you take him seriously
End
And he say I know he say okay let's do it
Whatever you might be to Spanish yes
Perfect
That was a
Yeah we said we need to
Create some videos of your class
And
Basically
Create a collection
DVD said it was VHS
I'm actually a VHS set
And sell it
On TV
So we can explain where it comes from and why and what the results are in
And so that was the original idea
CIT it was
Would you like
He was just a boy cat video like Jazzercise
Just going to sell
An infomercial on that was hopefully going to be your business
Yeah like are are the most fresh in our memories at that time
Was typo
Remember typo
So we was like that was the theory cuz Beto told me
When people come to my class
They don't
Leave
And it's because
The class is fun we say fun equals lasting behavioral change
I get I get that but I'm trying to scare what was the thing that made Roomba size
Different from other Fitness class
More fun
I think we
We do the same thing that Jane Fonda do in the beginning
Everything
It's easy
Second the music
Norloti music only I do weighted different kind of Indian Bank
Panther
Anybody can do it always I will always thinking they my mom
Do my class and
It went to things that
Better than that was very smart of the beginning is he said I want a microphone
Because if I have a microphone
I will interrupt
The music
And people need to be able to hear the music
And so he doesn't scream at people in the class or
If there's no
Talking it's only visual cueing soap
With hand signals would we tell people what to do
And
The magic is letting
The music
Lead the choreography lead the class
And there's a moment
In the class
That we call fetch
F e j
Freeing electrifying Joy
I said that moment
Is 20 minutes into the class
And the person suddenly feels completely liberated
They're having fun they're not thinking about
What do you need to cook that night or their job
Or their kids or their everything that is in their life they're completely disappears and it's them
And the music
So did you have to go out and raise money to
So we was July of 2001
And we went to some of our investors that had invested in spiderlabs
Was it the incubator
And we told him about this and they said we loved it we're and we had raised about half-a-million dollars
But we haven't gotten the wire transfers yet
And then September 11th happen
And everybody backed out and
Yeah we don't know what we're
We're going to do when we didn't know when I mean
For the next two months were all confused what's going to happen with
The world and you remember
It was very tough
And
Then around November of that year
Beto told me
My boss at crunch
Once introduced you to the CEO of crunch
Set time in crunches at
Is a gym chain out of you
Are you part of it and so I
Met with her her name is Donna Cyrus and Donna told me
Hey go me with Doug Levine the original founder of crunch
So I flew to New York
Met with dog
And he told me listen I've seen better teach
And I love what you guys are doing
And I said would you like to invest
And he said I can't advise because
Right now I'm
I'm selling my company and
But I can introduce you to some interesting guys in Ohio
Cool
Do infomercials for a living
And they might be able to not only invest but also help you
So the next day I want a plane to Ohio
To meet with a company called fit
Quest
And I'm in a room full of total Gypsy remember a total gym
Chuck Norris machine Hospital total gyms
And this lady
And is looking at a tape that we created of his Cloud we just film this class with a Handycam
I showed it to her
She said this is hot and want to call my boss
And
Finally the CEO comes down
And says this is Banton I like it
But the special speak English
And
Cuz you need to film an infomercial with him talking height
And I'm like
Well you know what I've never spoken to him in English let me call him
So I call him up
And I'm like paper they're asking
If you
Hey speak English
And he said
Tell them yes
So they loved it and they said okay we will test the same commercial license to Brand what's this class called
We had just that last week discuss changing the name
What was wrong with Roomba size
The word Roomba
In Spanish
Means to party
But it's also means
The type of dance there's a ballroom dance called Rumba
So it was a very difficult word to trademark
So we sat
In a restaurant
And we basically went through the alphabet
Anything that rhymes with Roomba so boom boom boom
Goomba sounded like
Pregnancy workout dinga Congo bunga
Sunga
Timba
Mangle
Manga
Zumba
Hey
Yeah with the inventors like I love the letter c
And we said yeah it's it's called Zumba and that was it
When we come back to this moment how Beto and Alberto hustle their way to a car
Contract and eventually set their sights on something much much bigger
How I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
Play and it gs.com podcast
Thanks also to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Business insurance expert
To understand each business
Is as unique as a fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent in every business has very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance expert
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
It's how I built this from NPR kyroz so it's the early 2000s Alberto and Beto have a
Business model for Zumba which is basically to make these Dance videos for people to
Play at home
First they need an infomercial before they can make that they have to make sure that Beto who is the dance
Teacher can speak English which
Decant
And also at this point
A new business partner enters the picture whose name and I'm not making this up
Is also help her toe
Alberto Aguilar
And in case you lost count Zumba is having run by 3 Alberto's and so
I fly back to Miami and Alberto
Aigaion and I are teaching better English for the next two months because the people who were going to be in
Commercial
They won't make it unless better speak English
Yeah exactly at least we're coming down to Miami to meet him
In 2 months
When they coming to Miami before I say to a better better don't worry because my daughter was worried
Because he say he say yeah he speak English
And I say tiger do you know
Tell me how you say
Which it was stupid or anything okay
You say
Nice to meet you sorry I need to go
But that was on Bae like
Because we were 60 days trying
And it's like this is not going to work now
When there's people coming
Coming in the end of the class I wanted to lose you and I
Hi how are you
Nice to meet you so ready to go next
Train to go and Escape
How do I escape
And I'd like to say sorry he need to go
You know
You know we need to put in a show
And I went to my car waiting
Parking garage in my Pontiac 85 North Edition
The conversation continued order to come in
A game where are you I'm here in the parking lot
What happened
Yes they do it they want to do it
They wanted to do it so Albert arguing and I had to write
The whole infomercial
A script
In Spanish phonetics
Hola hola welcome to Advanced Zumba
Launch that and we talked well
This is like having a party
Why you walking out release Zumba
Yeah we're going to get a royalty ass and maybe we should find some other products
Salvia television we don't know we don't know what we're going to do
Enter the deal was that you would get a royalty but they owned
Rights to a weed license
Will I see lice
Because we don't have money to do it ourselves right and we didn't know how to do it frankly
You know how to do it
Yeah when you guys launches from Marshall were you making money
A little bit
It was good it was good at me they sold
I remember what the number was but
It was enough to
Keep the lights on in
Keep going but it wasn't enough to to like
Ghetto fund your life and light pay your rent and everything to get to another job really not really been through
Stoat still taught his classes
Do you have other jobs I had a morning job
What was it
I was selling food
To Latin America I was hoping
American brands sell foods to
Latin supermarket
Wow so you guys are all basically
This is you your this is really what you want to do but
Kind of like your side project
Cuz you really had other real job to pay the bills
Yes
Yeah it was tough it was tough times it was very long hours
Angry I mean I worked in the mornings and then
And the afternoon I went over to
Alberto Young's house and
Stay there till midnight
Packing DVDs or whatever we were doing like we're doing every single thing
We're doing all the jobs which is great because
When you do every single job
Then
As a company grows you know
What to hire for
Was the business healthy anywhere you guys
You did it seem like
You were going to
Thrive or did you ever get to point where you almost know
We're almost clap
I remember
I already told you I'm walking over to me sayings
Listen this is
This is not going to work you know it's great we're all working hard but
We can't sustain that we can't pay the bills
And we we have one employee
And we're all doing everything else and
And it's hard it was just hard to keep the lights on
How much money did
Did you have in the bank
We had about
Maybe that was it
Yes we were close to Broken we have a conversation
With okay guys
Set
One day Kellogg's
Call Ash
The cereal company or the food
They want to send something
DVD Insider day
Cereal box cereal box Zumba for
For the Latin Market
Are we say okay good do it
When we went to the set to film the video
They
They have 120 a tiger from a Britannia tiger tattoo
They pay you for one guy
Put the custom and
Gel moving in moving slow
Nothing special I say Alberto. You know what
Let me know what up with the customer Tony attire
Because Sonia tiger to say it
Elektra superhero
It's not
Stupid
You know Tony do step by step side to side
They hired somebody else but you were not happy with how he was dancing so you put on the costume in
It instead yes
Yes
Barracuda Tony tiger
And I think I was we were so lucky because In This Moment
The CEO
Ocala
Come to the set
We didn't know
And I was
Inside the custom dancing like crazy
Sweating inside
It's like you don't see who is this oxygen in between songs
It was crazy
And this moment kept us going for like a couple years that a contract
$1000 for
That helped
That help but it was not enough
What would you guys do that
So
Then
People started calling
Their call center
Pictures of a Kellogg's
Yeah
Saying
Hey we want to
Take Zumba classes
Is in our area or some people started calling saying we want to become Zumba instructors how can we become Zumba instructor
And they were like
Well will give you the corporate number
Corporate number
Was
MetroPCS cell phone
Next to Alberto Jones
Bet
And
At 2 a.m. it would ring when infomercials were airing
And people would say I want to become an instructor the first three times he hung up
I think the fourth time he's like
Something Happening Here
And he called me Anna and Beto and told us
You know we've been getting all these calls from instructors
That they want music
They want
A choreography
A newsletter
They want
Community that they want event
If you want all these things
Maybe we can
We can put it all together and create
Something service for them
To give them everything that they know
Lyca subscription
Yes and so
We would call the Pizza Land
We started brainstorming
And we said well what do we need to do
Said the first thing is we have to make sure that we deliver
10 times more value
Then what
It costs
Suicide what do they need willany choreography
They need music made students how do we get them students how do I get the more participants in their class
Show marketing support
Let's create their career in a box basic
Being so
We came up with a name
We called it a Zumba instructor Network
And we launched it in 2006 in January of 2006 so we spent the whole 14,000
0 in the back
We created is beautiful email
It went out and
Alberto Antonio if 200 of them join
We will continue with this business
Tencent
And we're praying please please
And suddenly
Instead of getting email responses we got phone
And these structures were saying
We loving that your lunch this and we know you guys are trying to make the
This work can we pay the year in advance
And everybody says how much and wish I was $35 a month at that point it was 30
And they said that's it
That's it for my entire career that's all I have to pay and we said yeah it's only a half
They said we love it
And 450
Instructors join
And so that's when we said this is this is going to be our life
And
And let's make it work
At this point you guys are still entirely self-funded
Yeah
It was just from
That that royalties we got and then
The Kellogg's and then.
Duffy's
From the trainings and that it was all like
Inch by inch very slow growth
And
Thank God we were always able to meet payroll of Arc
Two employees
Sometimes we do things
To like pay the bill so
What's a beta why don't we do a special Master glass
A because we were running
$1,000 short
And so we would
Email everybody we knew once a special master class in
So we would all chip in and all help each other and
And find ways to do it
Since you guys are training all these instructors teach
I need a place to
Teach the classes so
So where the gym is interested in this
No
They would laugh at
So I remember that 24 Hour Fitness had a class called Salsa moves at that time
And
LA Fitness add a class called
Latin impact
And they will tell us like why
We have our own brand why do we need your breath
But then you when you went to one of those classes they had five people for people three people those glasses were empty
And we said no we have a formula
We have a formula that works are
Class
Attracts
People and people love it
It's different
And they would understand of the beginning
And finally
Hey there first
Really big chain to bring it in was
24-Hour Fitness
And it'll
Loaded
And they had to hire multiple instructors per location
Then all the big
Gym chains followed Equinox in
Crunch
A crunch always hide it because of our initial relationship with them so they were really the first one
You guys were doing all this
How are you getting the word out about Zimbabwe was a
Word of mouth or where you advertising
So what I think we were able to do in 2007/2008
We had bought the rights back to
To the infomercial
From Fitness question 2004-2005 is that stopped airing
As we did our own
Infomercial
And we started airing.
And that was helping at the word out and there was word-of-mouth and there were more people coming to class
And
When something is good
People finding
And two other people were saying well
Structure must be doing pretty well maybe I should become an instructor
So what was like the Tipping Point
Model really start to take off
So in 2008
The network was growing
But we started seeing what was happening in the economy
And we got very nervous
And I remember that we sat
In our conference room and we said
This is going to be a very tough year
And look at everybody's
Losing their jobs
If people cannot pay their mortgage
But for the next few months
Started seeing
That are
Instructor training
We're getting pack
And that there were more and more people who wanted to become instructors
And we also saw that the instructors were reporting to us
That their classes were packed
Calling us telling us
We don't know what's happening but we've doubled from
25 people now that I have 50 people in my class what's happening
So we started asking people
And we're two things that were driving it one
Was some people were out of
The job people were sad
They turn to Zumba
And they said
For 1 hour and when I forget everything that is happening
And I'm just going to be happy
And
A people who needed extra income
Said well now I'm going to get paid to workout
And someone to become an instructor
And I'm going to
Baked this
Part of my
Income
Does the financial crisis actually help your business
Yeah we were we were a solution that people turn to
Hey during those hard times
It happened around
Around this time which
I was reading that
Approached by
But people like by the the artist pitbull who was like new
Work together with what
How so you know what happened
In 2009
And 2010 in NBA 2k telling me when they trust me the artist Will Come Just As We it was a tough thing to
Able 2 lights
Set the music and it was always hard and he said that trust me one day they're going to come
And in 2010
A pitbull came to us
And sad
What are you guys doing
And we're like
What do you mean
And he said
This song Calle Ocho you remember that song I Know You Want Me
She said
People are stopping me an airport wearing shirts that say Zumba
Say that it's their favorite song
What are you guys doing and pretty like we'll instructors are just playing it in their class
And he said well
Legend like radio station
You guys
Have all these DJs
Playing in gyms around the world
And you guys I think you guys can break records
And Whisper
Are you serious
And he said yeah
And I'm going to give you my songs as soon as they launch
Put him in the Zumba classes
And you guys are breaking records
So people was the first guy to discover
Zumba was a way of promoting music
And then we worked with
Wyclef we work with Daddy Yankee
Russell Shaggy most recently moved
Timberland soap
Both the hottest Latin artists and some of the top
Us artists
Have all been noticing
That zumba is
Great way to reach 15 million people we reach 15
Million people taking Zumba classes
Does every single week
And I think that Lori RT salary
Music
Companies
I know
Did somebody say perfect weight
How to promote your music
Because when we send
Every month the music
Whistle
Songs
That we send every month to the instructor
That's mean these through things aren't going through
Arundel Wharf
Arundel or an end one month we have people
Dancing to Daddy Yankee
Is music in China
Like we have people dancing pitbulls music in Japan we launched
Choreography for Shakira
And Carlos Vives they have a new song called la bicicleta
And in aggregate the choreographies was shared 50 million times
On Facebook
You guys know how many
Instructors you have now
We don't disclose that but we basically
A focus more on the number of people that are taking classes
We have 15 million people taking classes
And where in 200000 gems
We have more locations
Teaching Zumba
Then
There are McDonald's in the world
What liquor
What do you think explain
At Music and Dance
Are a universal language
We have classes in in
Luxury neighborhoods we have classes in
The in the inner cities
What are the classes
Free
And we're classes in schools we have classes
Churches we have classes in
Basements with glasses on.
Dance studios
Yeah we have classes in
In Russia with ukrainians and Russians that
I mean the governments are fighting each other and they're together we have classes in Israel
I wish Arabs and Jews taking classes together
Dance brings people together
Better Dig Two
Like when you think about
How you were teaching a class this
Like a Roomba size in
Cali Colombia
25 years ago
That that are 25 years later we would be talking about something that
Has really become one of the biggest
Fitness stories
In the last decade
Imagine that
Yeah it's it's
Somebody tell me when they do know
And United States is
Eschar
Make money
But super hard
To be somebody
But you are somebody in this country
Did you get it
I did not understand
Now on
Next time because
Zumba me and my business partner we are somebody
People have
Morning you know it's one more for the millionaire
Aaron's here
Baidu
When people recognize you for Jewel labor for you
Work
I know
When they open the Hartford
Something you do it
It's amazing
Espeto
Alberto Perlman of Zumba
By the way Zupas reach to Way Beyond gems and Community classes
Former First Lady Michelle Obama healthy Zumba class on the front lawn of the White House
And turns out
There was even a weekly Zumba class
In Antarctica
And stick around because it just a moment we're going to hear from you about the thing
Your Builder
The first
Thanks to one of our sponsors Squarespace
Create a beautiful website using Squarespace award-winning templates
Head to squarespace.com for a
Free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code
Build it
To save
10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that and today story starts off
With a poem call the roller of big cigars the muscular one
Bid him whip in kitchen
This is Alex Mackenzie and he is not a literature major he's actually building a business but he got the idea
Yeah for that business
From this verse by Poet Wallace Stevens
Be finale of seem
The only Emperor is the Emperor of Ice-Cream the Emperor of ice cream
That became the name of the business that Alex started a couple years ago
He always wanted to do something with
But when his wife showed him that
Poem something clicked and he decided to take a fresh look
At the ice cream business so my wife and I hit the road we toured the country we ate ice cream at Mom and Pop shops all over the place
Place we went to grocery stores to see what was in the aisle and I was just becoming sort of bored with what
The establish Market had to offer
Ice cream truck except instead of dishing out the usual soft serve or Bomb Pops
Heat up for a much more creative variety
It would be so great if a family could roll up and Mom could have vegan
Strawberry sorbet and Dad could have a high fat low are southern
Banana pudding ice-cream and the kids could have low sugar milkshake
And maybe
Gluten free ice cream sandwich Alex's vision of more upmarket ice cream
You still at College there was a business competition so he submitted this idea any actually
What which meant he got $50,000 to launch his
First ice cream truck
The only problem his wife had just gotten a job in a place where starting an ice cream business is not
A winning idea
Big Sky Montana we definitely had some reservations we realize we were
Going out on a whim you know moving to this very remote place but you know we came out here and we were shocked to see
How many people were actually in the Town Center every night there was no one here serving ice cream in there were all these
Families with money to spend Pura just looking for something fun to do so Alex and his wife Christina settled
YouTube Big Sky
And with his $50,000 he started experimenting with ice cream all of the flavors
I began developing at home with just a little Cuisinart unit that we bought on Amazon for like 50 bucks
Vanilla and chocolate Alex was going for much more exciting and exotic flavors like bourbon Peach
Pecan pie on the mountain huckleberry
And eventually he found a local Factory that couldn't make the ice cream for him
So he bought a bad and he started this dish it out we kill it in the summer
But that's too much summer here starts late and ends early so it's basically
Uline August and we've been able to gross about 50 Grand in just four months in a town of
2500 people
Buy more trucks but so far he hasn't had much traction we're not a tech company we're not a medical device company
We're not Airbnb you know so we're trying to sell these really sophisticated Silicon Valley.
Tights but I'm not getting as many bites as I'd like but over the past few months Alex has raised over thirty
$1,000 from his friends and family and he's hoping to get at least one more truck to make inroads in the south
West and then eventually if things go well to go National
Yeah in a perfect world I would love to have at least 600 truck so I could go head-to-head with Mister Softee
And we would love to ship our stuff on Amazon and we're talking to them now about that for the moment Alex still
Set 1 ice cream van in Big Sky Montana and he's not making a profit but
He absolutely loves what he's doing a lot of people ask me what's your exit strategy I don't have an exhaust wrap
I grew up poor
And I would be thrilled
Run my own ice cream company for the rest of my life.
That's my exit strategy to not exit
It's Alex Mackenzie of the Emperor of Ice-Cream to find out more about Alex's company
Head to our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build a PR.
Oreck we love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or here
Previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org please also subscribe to the show at Apple
Podcast or however you get your podcast you can also write us that's HIV tea at NPR.
Or you can tweet us at how I built this our show was produced this week by Run abdel-fattah
Music composed by routine Arab Louis thanks also to need a grant for Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our internet is Dianabol stack on Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
It's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week