This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Support for this podcast comes from American Express open
If you listen to how I built this York
Curious about
Ideas and you probably have some ideas
Of your own
American Express open can help you with money and know-how
You can turn those ideas
Into action
Is it open. Com
Get business done
So when I got the idea for bet I went out and talked to John and
And he asked me Bob how much is it to take you to lunch bet and I say
I said John about a half a million dollars and so am alone says to me said Bob here's what I'm going to do
I'm going to buy 20% of a company 480
And I'm going to loan you 321-8320 there's your $500,000 under that business plan
About you will be 80 and I'll be 20 is that a deal I said John
That's a deal what Malone didn't know at the time if you reverse the numbers and I'll be hating about you beat
I said John that's a deal
NPR how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
How Bob Johnson turned a small cable channel called bet
Into a media Empire and from it became the first African American billionaire
And US history
Washington DC
As a young man in the early 1970s plan to focus on public policy which is
What he did for most of his early years in 1970s
Bob stumbled into a job with an obscure trade association called the national cable television assoc
Very very early days of cable TV and very few people understand the
All of this new force in TV
Johnson
He was one of those very few people and it was while he was there when he started to dream about a black
Oriented cable channel
At the ripe old age of 33
Quit his job to pursue what was then a big gamble
A channel would call bet
And a channel that would have been
Make Bob one of the most successful media
Norse in America
Bad for a kid who grew up in a working-class home with nine brothers and sisters in Freeport Illinois
Bob Johnson sat down with me in front of a live audience
Lisner Auditorium right here and Washington DC
You know
You symbolize a lot of things
2 tip
Especially folks in the city
Because this is your city and what we'll get into that but I want to start with
Your child
Most of it spent in Freeport
Illinois
This was in the fifties and sixties what kind of place was it in v
Freeport is a
Small town about a hundred miles
Northwest stoves
Chicago Illinois
It's a rural farming
Community with a little bit of Light Industry
A town where people
Got along very well not a lot of integration
Neither one side of the town
Where are most of the African Americans
Live the other side of town what's the whites with
And they also came together when you got to the high school and Junior High
What what kind of parents were where your parents were they strict
Sure they kind of hands off
Uniqlo black pants
Straight if you
You got to have a good excuse not to go to church you had to
Dressed neatly
You know you couldn't
Drake lease around the house
So that was the weather
What kind of student were you at school
I was I was a
Turned out to be pretty smart and I was in
An advanced English class in never forget this Center said I could have been that has eleventh grade twelve grade
And I remember this particular pets I never get the guys name the guy was Professor answers
And one
Day in class yes
Everybody how many of your going to college
Well as I looked around the room
Everybody who is Ambrose in white raising hand so I said what the hell raise my hand too so I figured I could get
Pass that day
After doing that I said I really got to go out find out about college if I'm going to do this
So I went down and I found out about the an application to us
University Illinois State School
And I ended up going to the University Illinois
I was at a social studies teacher education was my major and with the idea
I was going to be a teacher but you know I graduated from honors
From University Illinois
And at that time the state department
Was looking to recruit
African Americans to go into the Diplomatic Corps
They would help pay your way to any School of International Affairs that would prep you for
Ida Pharmacy
And so I did that and then apply for number schools and got accepted at the Woodrow Wilson School Princeton
International Vegas
You
You first I just came down here to get into public policy around 1972
To a thing
What do you remember about
Washington DC at that
Well when I came down remember I came down out of Princeton so if you have a
Ivy league degree
There's a
A network
Ivy league graduate
And Washington
And I remember beating the lady who was the press secretary to Lady Bird Johnson and then forget it
He said who do you want to work for
I said I want to work for Kennedy
Yeah I Kennedy doesn't pay you nowhere
Kennedy
This was different Ted Kennedy
And then I said who else you like I said I like Walter Mondale
Is that LOL I can get you in to see my Dale so I go to see Mondale
He is off his doesn't have a job
And then he says
You know what I just know somebody who is at the
Corporation for Public Broadcasting
Would you be interested in that and I just
Yeah game down from Princess pitcher
So I go down and the guys looking for a public information officer to write
Information about the programming at the various PBS stations
Abby educational stations in. That was my first job as a
Public information officer Air Force
Corporation for Public Broadcasting
If any must have
Capture the attention of people
Pretty quickly because
Within a couple years you were working
For Walter fauntroy
Would go on to become the first
DC delegate to
Congress what happened
What happened was I didn't know anything about washing I just came down here off of
Princeton
And also not working and having a good time
There's an election
Didn't make a difference to me they both
Yeah I guess so I don't care about it and
So
So what I do is I found out what washing is like is when it changes
Streisand some people get fired
And and and I started saying well gee I guess I'll look around
And that's how somebody I know referred me to the Delegate for the District of Columbia Walter fauntroy who is this
Non-voting Congress
And
So I just did what you doing Washington
When Administration changes you change jobs
That's that's why I didn't that's why I ended up on that
Capitol Hill working as his press secretary
Attack point in your life
If you were not thinking about
Becoming a business if we went back to who you were when you were looking for Walter fauntroy
You would not have guessed I guess if it's points
That you would go into business with you
No the only business I ever had was a paper route not failed at that so I didn't
But what I did learn from that and another summer job I had I didn't like working for anybody else
So if I was going to be successful
I probably have to one day work for myself
So but now but when I was working as a press secretary you meet a lot of people
And I was at a party I live that time over in southwest DC
So I meet this lady at
This party Angie
We get to Talkin at
She said wow you make a good lobbyist for the cable ends
And I said I don't know anything about cable she said don't worry I don't know anything about it when I got it
So
I got in the cable industry
And that gave me the one stripe I was missing so I had to put it goes Drive ahead
Public affairs stipend cpb
It was the business Drive lobbying about for business
But deregulation
And out of that
Kmart
Andre to the Pioneers in the cable
So you just met this
This woman at a party
And she said hey you should get
Involved in the cable industry I work for this
Trade Association do you want to come
The people who work there
When I was talking to her she understood you know that
I had some potential
To be to be a lobbyist
What what
What is the cable in
Industry at that time I mean
With a lot of pee
People who understood that it was going
Disrupt Network TV or did most people kind of
Just think of it is at
A niche
Sector you know like a
Flash in the pan
The
Rule of thumb was from the broadcast
Cable would erode audience
And harm over-the-air free broadcasting what's really translated in harm their pocket
Then on top of that there was
Telephone companies to
Wanted to control cable lines getting on telephone
Because you can't get cable to home
Unless it's strung up on a telephone pole so the cable
Telephone companies in League with the broadcast
And a lot of members of Congress because
See if your a congressperson
Who do you turn to to get your story out your local broadcast
So they had a formidable group of opposition against cable deregulation
Chicken butt
No technology is a hard thing to
Keep tie down
Andaz
Satellite
Launch
And you can beam signals
Across the entire country
And aggregate huge audiences via cable
Overtime the argument for
More content free choice
More diversity of content particular
Who won the argument with a lookup a court case
And at the end result is you see what you have now is the zillion channels of cable and digital
Continent
And broadcasters
Healthy maybe not as healthy as they used to be but still love
A formidable content provider
So this was maybe an apocryphal story
But I have read that
In 1979
You met a guy from Florida who
Who is coming to DC
C2
To meet with Congress folks
About an idea he had you were a lobbyist
And you
Came to help him what
What's that story is it true
The sky he wanted to start
A channel for the elderly
Dan Silverman
So cancel
Said to me said I said I was your proposal he open it up and he had this they had this data
He said elderly people consume certain products
Elderly people have a certain income
Elderly people make up X percent of the population
I said what I said
Good data points in Georgia
Just kind of facility
Esl Channel off the ground I don't know why
But
I had his information so when I started bet I said
Black people have certain spending patterns
Black people have surgeon shopping pattern
I just where we had elderly I just filled in Black
And I just went in and took his model
And out of that game bet
Was that the the Genesis of the idea this guy have this idea for an elderly Channel and you're looking at in your sink
This applies to
Did African Americans as well
Now that was in the Genesis of it
That's that's too highbrow word for what I did
That was
That was pure theft
Genesis would be Genesis would be content
That was not technologically driven by satellite and cable it would be ebony
Ebony magazine
Elite assets and black Enterprise and even black radio
They told the story of black aspirations they gave us open to
Black content and information
Black radio stations play black music
So the concept
Are the Genesis if you will
Target program already exists
Life or look could have started Ebony magazine if they wanted to they didn't want to because it was segregated or Niche Conte
Fortune could have started Black Enterprise they didn't want to do it because it was Mitch Conte
What I did was to take advantage of the
Technological change that way
What brought about
By the launch of satellites
Do I allow signals to be beamed across the United
State
And instead of aggregated just black households in
Chicago
I get aggregate black cable households all across the
The continental United States
Cuz cuz you were looking at these media organization
Continued saying
We can do this on TV
They have the business model they sold advertising they had readers in this case or
Subscribers
And they made money so that model
Woodwork
If you could put together content
On television
But you had the aggregate
A large enough
Audience
Because
You couldn't compete with a local broadcast station
Trying to find a chest in one city you had to have the whole country
So you're there working for this cable trade Association this idea starting to
Kind of
Work its way through your head were there other people who were who were seeing the same Opera
Opportunity that you saw at the same time
Yeah I made it that the one that's Most Fascinating is
Is Ted Turner launching CNN
If you think about it
CBS with
Walter Cronkite
The brand
As a father of news
Could have launched on cable a CBS News Network
Instead of letting Ted do it
But they saw themselves
As a
30 minutes
6 p.m.
Period of news
They just didn't see news as a 24-hour
Audience product that would appeal to America
Classic country
Ted when he was starting in the same thing with the guys with ESPN
NBC could have started ESPN if they wanted to
And I was talking to Ted and he was pitching the idea
Two people about the
A 24-hour
News Network
It's a funny thing if you go back and read some of the clips
It's about what people saying when
When tattoos go to the 24-hour news
You find out people are laughing at me
So I so want a was talking about it and I say Ted
What happens
If there is a day where there's no news
Ann and Ted said Bob here so we got
We got a group of people we're going to go out start fires
And it will cover
Will cover the fires and it will have some news
So that's what happened is
People missed out
On the cable Revolution this is something a business to do is
Steak
And I see I was saying is that the reason
The railroad companies dinner on the airline
Is because the railroad companies they thought they were in the railroad business
As opposed to the passenger moving business
I mean everybody here in this room probably had one at a time
Yellow
Yeah analog
Sony Walkman
I bet you are in your closet someplace you haven't thrown them out
But they didn't go digit
And they lost out to
Apple and the rest is history
But yeah I want to come back to that in just a moment but I want to ask you
How you started this emanuar
I'm assuming you didn't have a whole lot of your own
Money to work with I had a paycheck but that was about it and I was working at the cable industry and so I had to
Believe the
My starter had to leave the cable
So
I borrowed some money from the bank
Start Gym number how much
It's probably $40,000
Senior bank loan
And
That's not enough to start
People television network so what did you do where did you go
I admit I was a lobbyist obviously and I met one of the board of directors of the trailer source
Json a gentleman by the name of the doctor
Did John Malone
And he and I became friends and one day said to me said Bob if you ever have an idea come talk to me
So when I got the idea for bet
I went out and talked to John and we're sitting in his office
And he asked me Bob how much does it take you to lunch
Bet
And I said John about a half a million dollars
And so Malone
Says to me say Bob here's what I'm going to do
I'm going to
Buy 20% of your company
And I'm going to loan you 320
18320 there's a $500,000
None of that business plan Bob
You will be 80 and I'll be 20
Is that a deal
I said John that's a deal
What Malone didn't know at the time if you reverse the numbers that I'll be 80 in Bob ub-20 I said John that's a deal
Now you got to keep in mind a half a million dollars
Tumi
Was equal to the
Total GDP of everybody black in Freeport
So
I got this
I am terrified
That's something bad to happen walk out of this building is amazing to Robbie this $500,000
Gave you $5,000
Like that with no due diligence no
Took 30 minutes for him to give me the check
Why why would he believe I mean
I told you I'm good I even have sex with you tonight
Man with no you haven't
Allen Express
I did I did a survey
I call I remember I got on the phone and call down to a place call Anniston Alabama
I call that barber shop in Anniston Alabama
The shop was owned by guy named
Pink junior Woods
So I called in and I said I'd like to speak the pink junior
I think Junior got on the phone I said pink
If I brought cable
Down to Anniston Alabama and play Grambling football Jackson State football
Would you guys cry
He said you can do that
I said yeah if you subscribe
Tomorrow is a guy on the phone said he program in football.
And they said yeah
So I took that back to Java latte Jana do the survey in the black community
And
People down in Anniston Alabama naisu mantises like other cities throughout this
They would subscribe
And so he said okay and he brought his lawyer yet took off 30 minutes
He wrote me this check
And so
Now John gives me the check
You know
I got a side job I got to ask you a question
But I waited till I had to check first
So anyway
I want to be stupid cuz with the check first
Do I say John
I never started a business before
What advice can you give me
And
And John bellone said Bob
Get your revenues up keep your costs down
That was my Harvard MBA and I was sick
And just moments how Bob Johnson took bet public
And then eventually
How it made him a very very rich man
Play with us you listening to a live recording of how I built this
From NPR
Support for this NPR Podcast comes from American Express open
Listeners to how I built this our curious curious about how good ideas become great businesses
And chances are you have some good ideas of your own but as you know
And business there can be a lot of roadblocks
American Express open knows how hard it can be to get things done and they want to help with money and
Know how
So you can turn those ideas into action
Is it open. Com to get business done
Play Welcome Back to the special live recording of how I built this
From NPR
Gyros
So it's 1980
Bob Johnson
Just taking that half a million dollars
John Malone
Duloxetine
But don't get the wrong idea
Actually a Channel with tons of content in fact
Blastoise
Barely longer than this podcast
It was on for 2 hours on a Friday and a Saturday night
That was it on the
Popular cable channels update USA Network
As we started programming more and more we started getting more hours
On the USA Network and eventually
We say we got to have our own satellite and so we
Had enough Capital to acquire satellite transponder
The beam around signal so we went from
8 hours to 16 hours at 24 hours in and what was the
That you were
And the content was
Syndicated programming that we could buy from the studio for cheap does content original
Inexpensive we didn't do anything original
We it had to be
We called it the three ends
Indican in the studios are in existence
That's all it is
So a Grambling football game they don't play any way we show up or not with camera
The way you do football games because there's an existing
That was in the can was yo
Yeah good times and Sanford and Son
And then in studio is
Youku
People like we are now
All we got to do is bring a camera you have a BT show
To offer content that wasn't going to be
Expensive
But that could build an.
Yeah if it would get your revenues up to the Goffstown
And then when vent when MTV refused to play
Or started out not playing black music videos
And the Black Talent wanted to have their videos down and I went to him and say
Hey if you keep making the videos
I'll keep putting them on
And as result of that we gained some sort of an early franchise position
Ensuring Urban R&B African American music video
And all of that was free
Electronic it was free
Totally free
Wow
I mean it's like it's like you think about a company today like a media company today and
You know investors want you know user-generated content
Making content is expensive which is why investors Love YouTube
Write or read it because
Nobody's paying to make that contact
If you if you
Want to look
At how I became
A business genius
Is not very hard all you got to do is come up with a business
Where you get free music videos
Cable operators pay and advertisers pay you
Do you get paid twice for nothing
That's a pretty good deal you got to be real
You got to be real dumb to mess up that model
So when you started to pitch bet
To advertise
In the first for five years
What were they you know
Comedy with open arms saying yes we will advertise on this
Not really early on a couple of big Brands said hey we we really reach black Auto
Chances we want to be in
Pepsi-Cola was an early advocate
What's that market stay with Anheuser-Busch
They got exclusive rights
But what you call the real Revenue generators that the package good guys
The Procter & Gamble
Colgate
In the light
They were slow to come on because they were reaching eyeballs
Amazon
May all the ascendicate it shows on network television and so you could you could accumulate a lot of black eyeballs and
Viewership
Without
Paying for something that was untested on Nielsen measure
Is cable
It was it was it was a tough
Argument to make
But
You make the case you say look
You got to
Reach This audience they consume your product
Stay work
Company
You do all of the Duggars social selling
You know it's just
You come
That's a within about two inches of threatening them
You know
And that if you're going to do is I'm going to tell Jesse Jackson that you had advertised and stuff like that
So
Overtime though is cable beginning rated penetration
More more programming came about
Advertisers began to see the value of getting in first
An advertising on BET or MTV
All right so you at you you are running this company
And
You got some momentum
You become profitable and in 1991 you take the company public
It becomes the first
Majority black owned
Company will be listed on the New York Stock
Right
No African-American had done it before on the stock
Exchange.
Who sings Been Around almost
Are going back to Bethel
Founding of the country little bit after the Revolutionary War
And nobody had done it
So and I had this notion that if you're going to be a visible
African American player in a pedometer
White culture business culture
You had to do something to get identified
And nothing could identify you more than playing at the game
You know
On a company go public
Be totally transparent in your ownership and everything about your company under rules
And that makes you part of the old boys club
Let me be the first one to do that
And and that's what I did and
Animated
Up one of the things that you know of when you've dealt with
During your time
You was
It came under
Criticism
I wasn't always a
Embraced with
And some some African Americans
Felt that
It wasn't
Good represent
Rotation of
African American culture you've heard those
I was in the past
Do you did you ever feel like they were
Fair criticism
I felt the criticisms were born out of what is
In the African-American Community if you think about
Historically the app
African American community
It is been
A collective
Has been a collective because they've been on set
By forces
Beyond their control
And they all as a result of that
They have to group together
And so when you start a business
It was the
Preconceived notion
That your business exists it
To further the collective the goal of African-American
And so if you were doing something
That they felt
Didn't do it say if you weren't doing black educational television
You were
Failing in your obligation
And so we got the Brunt
Of everybody who wanted us to be
Part of that
Collective
Because we were the only one
We just happened to Garner
Everybody's hopes dreams and aspirations
And then
The other part of it is in Black Culture
Because you have an obligation to be
I would say
More
Protective
Of our
You can't do anything to show our claws
So if you shows
Scantily clad women and videos and all kinds of gyrating dancing
And by the way I never made a video at all so don't blame me for
That was like that is not proper
Depiction of our people
On the other hand MTV
Could do anything they could do Pimp My Ride took my sister and pimp anything you want
We couldn't do that we done that we would have been banished in fact the other my successor
Debra Lee
She was picking it for a. Of almost 4 months outside of a house with people bullhorn
No taunting her because she was running BD that played music video
But Black America
Has always had to live
In a contradiction because
It is
Dominated by white culture
Did that criticism ever
Get you down with especially when you heard it for
From prominent app
African Americans did you ever feel
Chat about it
Were you saying what you're saying now
Do you think I would be here because it never got me down
Do you think
Do you think I'd be saying this in criticism ever got me down
No
Alright so you have this
Incredibly successful
Company now
A burgeoning medium
Empire in 1998
You decide to take it private this is a public companies traded on the stock exchange
How did that happen and why did you decide to
Buy it back
So do me the answer is as simple and I
Not sure why anybody would be
Baffled to ask me this question
Because I figured I can make more money
But you and me the stock price was like 31
You bought it back
Double that about
Now what happened was this.
Was
Trading at 31
We felt the stock was worth closer to 45 or 50
Because we're
Getting a discount on the value of ishares
Abacasa stock was family tree why was it under why was it being under belly
Because it was family traded I want a big chunk that I wouldn't have salad
John Malone on the beach
A lot of float in the marketplace to make the stop move up and down
So what we did was
We said
Les batiks
TalkBack
And take the company
Be private
And we offered 45 bucks a share which was a good premium to Stockton been trading consistently for 3 months at about 30
233 bucks a share
The next day the stock went to 6
Which proved that people said these guys are trying to steal the company we don't let him do it so
We ended up buying a company back at 62 bucks a share
And we kept it private
And then we sold it to buy a cam
For a hundred and
Swiss double
You made 3 billion dollars
That's right
In
In 2001
You sell the company to buy comp
3 billion dollars
Probably close to the p
BTS value
What was lucious thinking at the time did you think yourself
This thing is
Can I get anymore
We got it we we got to cash out the multiple of Mediacom
20 times ebitda
So naturally you're looking at it
Do you say how high can it go
Before you either one you get more competition which drives your value down
So you you look at and you say Zatanna cell plus
I had a partner John Malone had been in the company
20 years
His only exit
Was the sale of the Hellenic
Do I have that obligation to him
So
What did that $500,000 GetJar Malone
John's
180 cup at 3:20 and the other side got Payback
His 180 yield him
And 70 million dollars a Viacom stock
And you know and you know I did pretty good too
And the time it was obviously and pack a bowl because
You couldn't do that today
I know that BT's wear for 20 x multiple today now
At that point you become the first
African American
Billionaire
Overnight
In US history
Was that was an important milestone
For you
It wasn't a milestone in terms of me personally it was a milestone in terms of achieving some
Something that would
Get you
The recognition of visibility that
Would say
If African-Americans are given an opera
Opportunity
They can prove that they can generate wealth
For themselves
Their family
And it's country
That wasn't what I was trying to make
The goal was to say we can play at that level
Exactly like white Americans
If you want to change
Economic
Discrimination
An income inequality between African-Americans and
White America
Are minority Americans White America
You got to figure out a way
To provide a flow of Kappa
Into the hands
Of entrepreneurs and others who are
Fully committed
And fully capable
Of generating and maintaining wealth
Sony
Survive you are
How to say the least
Complex
You've got a lot of people in this
Crowd cheering for you
When you say that I paid for 50% of
But you have said I'm quoting you use this is something you've said in the
She said quote
I don't want to be seen as a hero to younger people or a role model
Books for African American youth
Do you still feel that way I mean
I said that ink and the context
Stove
Of this
A hero or role model for African American kids
A my opinion
Starts at home
The mother the father and the people who live in there
And then next door neighborhood
It
It makes no sense
Stupid jerk your hero
Because you see him on television
More often then you see
Your neighbor or your uncle
Who's going to work everyday
Struggling to survive
That's the real hero
Is the guys Justin Jackson just
So people take that early bus
That's the kind of hero that they autofocus
We just have a couple of minutes before
If we have to wrap up in a while I want to
These two very important questions
M2u
What what did your folks and your mother
At least your mother live to see
Your
Incredible success
You
Coming out of this work
Class home
9 brothers and sisters
Becoming one of the most successful entrepreneurs
In American history. And also among the richest
What would they have made of that
That they were very regular people they didn't you know
My mother used to say so people would come up and say I know you're proud of your son
Until you know the line she come back when I'm proud all my children and that was that was you know
That that's that's what she would say and if you know she would
Have a way of
Bringing you down I will put you in your place one final question for you Bible question that I
Listeners
Here in the folks that has holes will have
This made with the question I asked
Everyone who comes the show
How much of your success
Do you ascribe to
Your talent your
Intelligence and how much sugar
90%
Now that really is a thing
Every entrepreneur
Is lucky
You call it luck
I call it
Grace of God
That's what I call
There is no way
Path that I took
Could have happened without that
Kind of
Guy
And you know cuz
All along the way
If there were things Way Beyond My Control it just simple as this
I just happen to come of age when
RCA said
We're going to put a satellite in a geostationary orbit above the equator
And that satellite can being a signal to cable headends
All around the country
Did the guys at RCA then call me up and say Bobby ready we're going to launch it
You know it just happened I happened to be in the right place
At the right time
With the right people
And some Forest Beyond you
Put you there
Bob Johnson
Is my conversation with Bob Johnson live right here in Washington
DC at George Washington University
Lisner Auditorium
Stop blazing a trail after he sold bet he went on to buy the NBA's Charlotte
Bobcat and became the first African American owner of a major American sports franchise eventually Bob's
Sold the team to the second African-American owner in NBA history might have heard of him his name is Mike
Georgia
Pay thanks for listening to this special live
Episode of How I built this episode was produced by Rammstein Arab Louis also composed the music
Thanks also teneva grandparents Mexican for Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Dianabol stack
I'm guy Raz you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing plan
Form used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week