Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Support for this podcast comes from American Express open
If you listen to how I built this you're curious about ideas
And you probably have some ideas of your own
American Express open can help you with money
Know how
You can turn those ideas
Into action
Is it open. Com
Get business.
When I returned
I never had planned to come back I would say that they were people both on the board at the time and many people.
Starbucks in certainly hundreds of people of Wall Street that said you're bringing him back
Mean
NPR how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
Today I will pour kid from the projects in Brooklyn turn the small coffee company
Seattle the third largest restaurant chain in the world
Time in America when a typical coffee experience
Involved a styrofoam cup
Like a PTA meeting or a church social and it was usually served at of a giant aluminum
Warming up that coffee for hours and hours to be a cardboard box of happiness
Glazed donuts next to it
And if you have no idea what I'm talking about consider yourself lucky
Because you may not know how hard it was to find good coffee in America before Starbucks
I know I know some of you are hater some of you wouldn't be caught dead in a Starbucks
Corporate and that's okay that's totally fine but just consider for a moment
How much coffee culture in America owes to Starbucks
Am to Howard Schultz
Because if he hadn't stumbled into a little Coffee Bean & Spice Shop in Seattle called Starbucks
It may never have become what it is today
Not the time Starbucks was just a local chain in Seattle and it didn't sell brewed coffee just
But Howard was so blown away by the
Quality of the copy he tasted from those beans that he quit his job and beg the owners of Starbucks
The hire him then six years later when those same owners decided to sell
Howard raise the money to buy the company and just a few years after that
He took Starbucks National
That today there are 27,000 Starbucks location in roughly 70 countries around the world
Which isn't bad for a kid who grew up poor in Brooklyn a couple weeks ago in the Seattle
I sat down with Howard in front of a live audience to hear about how he took that Seattle Coffee Bean shop
And turned it into the Starbucks we know today
Thank you very much
They didn't think you would be here that's why they true soul I do whatever they could not believe you walked out
They were just amazed
How many cups of coffee do you drink everyday
Probably four or five a day
Four five
No caffeine after 5 p.m.
Turn up
And what what is your
Preferred copy drink
French Press of aged Sumatra would be my
Number one choice
Alright okay okay good
I still have Starbucks people here
A lot of people know that you were raised in a housing
Bayview in Brooklyn
Can you
Can you describe the apartment that you grew up in
Sure I grew up in Canarsie which is at the last stop
Of the L train in Brooklyn
In a housing project that had 34 building
Two bedroom apartment
For my mother and father
Sister and brother
I think the rent
In 1956 was $96 and
Well
Who did people live there
Who live there were people who are construction workers cab drivers plumbers
And it was a childhood that was
Based on
A real sense of community
And because they were
People with like-minded values
And it was a very diverse group of people
And I think it an early age I learned how to get along with a lot of different people because we were in one building with one elevator
And you had to go on
Yeah
Your dad
World War II that
Yes he was a
A driver
Mom
Receptionist
I guess I was certain point when you were a kid your dad got injured on the job
My dad had a
Series of
What I would Lucy describes
Really bad Blue Collar jobs
And he went from
One job to another
In the winter months
Of March of 1960 he was a
Delivery driver busy probably is one of his worst jobs
Picking up and delivering cloth diapers before the invention of Tampa
He fell on a sheet of ice and broke his hip in his leg
And I came home from school and he was kind of laid out on the couch
Eyewitness
What are Loosely described is the fracturing of
American Dream
And despair hopelessness
And what happened in 1960 if you were a blue collar
You know I uneducated worker
Despite the fact that you have served your country World War II
It was no workman's compensation there was no healthcare and you were dismissed
But what eyewitness scarred me
And that's what we
Kind of went through
Were you good students get
I was not a good student I don't think I applied myself very well
But an athlete you were I was in a
Yeah that was an athlete because in the projects
The entire day was spent in the schoolyard
I'm in a concrete schoolyard playing any sport that you could invent
Or organize
Do a dive on concrete
To win
Nn
It's what my competitiveness I think was born out of being that kid in that schoolyard
You know I became a very good high school football play
Which is so weird to think about cuz you're pretty trimmed I right I mean you're not like a
Big
Huge
You know how can't really guy right but it's like very good and you were recruited by a
But I was a fast white guy
Got it
So you so you are recruited by
Northern Michigan University to go
Play football there and and did you think that mean
Did you think there was any possibility you might go
To the no no no no
I never thought I was going to be good enough in a sack when I got the northern Michigan and I saw the size of these guys
And you know real Midwestern Grit
The toughness and the competitiveness of what I experienced in the schoolyard started drifting
Did you get any playing time I got hurt right away
I know it sounds funny but at the time you know i n n here's the thing a very famous guy
Was ahead of me in my position and that was Steve Mariucci
Great player became the coach of the San Francisco 49ers and he was much better
So football was not hard you are not going to play professional so you had to go out and get a job after you graduate what do you
What are you doing
I was very fortunate that when I finish school
I somehow convinced people
At Xerox to hire me
What do you need to come inside
I had no training I don't know I did not have a business degree at a communications degree from northern Michigan
But I I
Got a sales job at Xerox
This is 1976
And at Xerox
At first I sent you to a
Sales training school in Leesburg Virginia
And after that
For 6 months all you do is make 50 cold calls a day
But I'm not talking on the phone you used to go make a physical Coco
Into an office
Witnesses in New York or New York City 42nd to 48th from the
From 5th Avenue To The River To Go door-to-door office off everyday knock on the door and most of the
Purchasing no solicitor
You know if you got
A lead
You were not yet
Allowed
To sell the product you and I'll give it you an intern basic
You had to give it to the salesperson
Am I salary in 1976
I tell my kids to go that's not true
Was $1,000 a month
And I gave half of it to my mother
Does living at home
So are you good at I mean were you good at cold calling and I was really good
You would like you like you like getting lunch at the time so I didn't like cold calling but once I became
A salesperson at Xerox
It was clear to the
People of Xerox that I had some Talent
And I stayed there a number of years but I
All along I knew
That the
The discipline the regimentation the lack of
Kind of
Personal creativity
I was very restless and I was looking for a way out
So
It was enjoyable
I wasn't happy
It's interesting because a lot of people we've had on the show like Sara Blakely who started Spanx started out
You know selling the door to door
Do you think that was an important I do because I think the rejection
Of cold calling the humility that comes with the disappointment of not someone saying yes to you
I went through a steep learning curve and I started having a higher level of self-esteem
Xerox and IBM at that point in the mid-seventies were two kind of
Pedigree companies that you could call somebody working for Xerox
People felt
Kind of good about you until I told my mother I was leaving Xerox
And she started crying but I knew in my heart early on that I had an entrepreneurial
Ask for something
Different
And was looking for a different kind of offer
So would you be
So I left Xerox because
A friend of mine
Shared with me that there was a Swedish company
Opening an office in New York
And looking for gentleman
And I had no idea what the
The product really was
Met the person who was in charge
Of moving from Sweden to New York
And he and I
Mayday
Immediate connection and he became a life
Long friend
And mentor to me and higher
And his name was Kai alyacen
And and what were you saying
At first we were selling they were opening up a division for furniture
And I had to move to North Carolina for a year
Washer and I were dating a New York
You had met Sherry around this time your wife and I met in 1978 on July 4th
And this was 19
80 or so
North Carolina was not for me
And so I went to Kai and I said I want to come back to New York or I'm going to leave the company
And he said I kind of think about all this me figure out what to do and he
Gave me the general manager job
The consumer division in New York
And unbeknownst to me on a trip to San Francisco to see our largest customer which was
Macy's at the time
On the way back from California I stopped in Seattle because it was a small
Coffee company called Starbucks selling his product
And it was a non-electric kind of thermos coffee maker and I walked into the
The Pike Place store and I just said
I literally
Had the kind of epiphany that just spoke to me that this is such an extraordinary thing
About what they were doing and the coffee the romance the passionate people
Plaid and I I met the founders and over a course of a year I prefer
Sueded them
Fireman here's what I don't get what was it mean they were selling
Playing coffee beans which is it
But
I mean you have this really great job an apartment in New York and
What majors
Think I have got to drop everything and sell coffee bean roaster things going on I think she and I we had it under
Standing that we did not want to raise our
Orchids near
We wanted to get out
And I was in Seattle on this spectacular Majestic day like today
So
The combination of all of that
And the experience I had as a customer
And watching what was going on in that
First store
I just immediately was kind of Swept Away with this is the kind of
Environment
Product
And young company I like to be part of and I
Over course of a year
Just kept banging the door to say to the founders
If you expand the company
I think I can help you in and their dream and nothing against them their dream at the time was 2
Expand to Portland Oregon that was there
Big idea
And was that I mean part of your vision for the company that time do you think we can expand and continue to sell
Coffee Bean
You know I think
I had to learn the business
So I didn't know anything different at that time until I went to Italy
A year later in 1983
Drinker but I I did not know much about like Maxwell House and
Whatever
Sharp sorry
Come on
So you knew something about that I knew enough
That I had a
Great appreciation for the coffee I tasted for the first time
At the original Pike Place store and I was just blown away
We had four stores at the time and then the founder
Send me to Milan Italy
First trip for me to Italy to a trade show representing Starbucks and
That's when I was walking the streets of Milan and every 20-30 yards you are intercepted
Literally with a
Italian coffee
And I walked into all these places and kept seeing the theater the romance
And the
The nectar of the Gods which is espresso a big sort of copper espresso
The Elegant Style but what really struck me was the sense of community
And I started going to the stores
Almost the same time everyday and I would start seeing the same people are realizing that this
What is a third place between home and work but the beverage was a draw and so I
I realized while I was in Italy that
Starbucks
Was in the coffee business but perhaps the wrong part of the business and I raced back
With such
Enthusiasm in such passion that I overwhelmed them when I got back you said we've got
Got to do this we got to sell brewed coffee cuz it we're not selling book right now there was no service of
Any cup of coffee at any Starbucks was just pounds of coffee for homies and you come back into Seattle and you say
Guys we have got to do this it's going to be huge and they say
No
They viewed the beverage business in their parlance as being in the restaurant
And it didn't like
There is Messi
And that's not what they wanted to do
So
I literally
Pounded on the table for a year
And I think they just said okay
Get this kid out of her face
And we're opening a new store on the corner of
4th and spring in 1985
It was 1500 square feet
And they said will give you 500
Seed of the 1500 to open up an Italian coffee bar in the store
And
That was it I mean so we opened
The fortune Springs Starbucks store with their first coffee bar
Overnight
We had
Hundreds
Of customers everyday
And we introduced caffe latte the city of Seattle basically
Now here's the rub
It was
So successful that it completely dwarf
The other side of the bed
And
The two founders
At the time
Did not like
The disproportionate level
Obssales
And how the store was function
And they respectfully said to me
We don't want to repeat this
And I was crushed
I was thinking how could you possibly this is look what's going on here
Not to mention we're making more money
Yeah
I was devastated
Imeson believe it at first
If you really are you serious
And so
I think she knew I was
Depressed
And
I came home one night and said
I don't think I can work for anyone anymore
I'm leaving sermon
I'm going to start my own
So I told
The two Founders what I was doing
And then they surprised me and said
Well if you do that
We'd like to invest in
Which is pretty cool. But here's
Here's the rub
But of course you're going to use Starbucks coffee
They invested and kind of gave me legitimacy
To open up an Italian coffee bar in the Columbia Center Tower when the building open
I sign that lease with a
Developer in Seattle
Very famous guy here locally called Martin selig
700 Square ft
And he asked me for personal guarantee
I said sure I'm
I've no problem with that and by the way you are you're like 32 years old
And we had nothing so he wanted to personally guarantee I guarantee it
But knew there was nothing behind it and we open the store
Call Guild ranalli I went back to Italy I did a lot more research I spend more time there and I named the company after the attack
Italian newspaper in Milan
And we opened
Too stores in Seattle
And then it was a great location in Vancouver BC
And we sure that's open to Vancouver
So we open three stores
We're raising money to do that by the way how did you do that anywhere or people Cersei
Of course I wanted Howard Schultz on my gosh you know future genius CEO please take my money was it really
Easier to get that money the truth of the matter is that I spoke to 242
People
Try and raise
1700000 dollars
24 Mildred
And Starbucks was a seedinvest
Did not give me enough money to open up a store
And Starbucks put a little
Contract in which was
You have to raise
$600,000
To use r200
So I went out and try to raise money was having a very hard time you reminding me of
Cold calling
Lottery Jackson
Because
I remember people said
Let me
Try and understand this
The name of the company has a name no one can pronounce
You're going to sell coffee for two to three dollars a cup of coffee in a paper cup
With Italian names that no one's ever heard of
And you want to give Healthcare to your employer
And it was a tough sell
Now
Our first investor is in this audience
Her name is Carol Bobo
I don't know where she is
Well
Errol Carroll that was a good move
Em Carroll
Was Shari's dearest friend
And we went over to their house
I had all this business plan at the pitch and everything and
Carol and her husband said we don't need any
Pitch
Just going to trust
Already checked
But that night and gave me $100,000
And things started happening after that what was your ambition mean
Did you did you think this is going to be a national chain of coffee
Coffee bar
His interesting story
So the original business plan was 100
And we weren't raising any money
Because people didn't believe we could
Open 100
And I didn't even have enough
Funds resources
The kind of professionally reprint
The document
So I figured out a way to kind of white out
The hundred
And I wrote 75
So we opened our first store
Innate
And then a year after
Jury
The founder of Starbucks
Had acquired Peet's Coffee Company many people don't realize that pizza Starbucks were one company
Two years prior.
Injury K to me and Sheridan
Candyman Zedd
We run into some financial trouble
And we can have to split to company
And I decided I'm going to move to California and I want to keep Pete
The person who should buy Starbucks issue
And so
The prices
One-time sales
6 doors
3.8 million.
Which was
You know I was fantastic news
And
I'll give you a 90-day exclusive to try and
Come back to me
With 3.8 million.
So I was
Extraordinarily
Excited
But I didn't know where I was going to get the money
Yeah and so now we had to go back out and raise money
And it was very difficult
So how did you do it
We went back to the original destivelle giornali
Some of them were interested but a lot of them weren't
Because Elgin only had three stores we weren't we can prove anything
Show
You know Jerry kept checking in with me to see how are you doing on the fundraising and
Matt 60 days in
I said we're about halfway there
And I'm confident that we'll we'll get the 3.8 million.
And
He said I have to sit down and tell you something
We have a competitive
I said
Drake
You told me we had an exclusive what do you mean
And he said one of your investors
Rebuild your knowledge
Has
Showing up
And offered me $40 cash with no due diligence
And I was like
I'm I I just
I can remember that moment as if
My
The world just ended
Because I knew who it was
You told me
And
The person at the time
There were three business Titans
In Seattle
And he was one of them
And they had invested in elderly as a group
I didn't know what to do and Jerry said
I will hold for 90 days but
You have to know
On the 90th day I have to sell
Two or three days later
I'm playing basketball
And a friend of mine who is my Young attorney at the time
Scott Greenberg
I tell him the story that night after the game
And
Him trying to help me as a friend and as a lawyer says
You need to come to
The office tomorrow morning and meet her senior
And telling story
I didn't know who the senior partner was I know anything
So I go to the office following morning at 8 a.m.
And he takes me into the office to me
Bill Gates Senior
I walked in the office
With Scott and Bill Gates Senior said tell me the entire story
And I'm taking it to him chapter and verse like I am with you with more detail he's writing down writing down
And I finish any said Howard
We don't know each other just ask you this question one time
Is everything you told me true
And I said it's 100%
And he says to me when take a walk
And I said
Where we going
And
He says
We're going to see the man
My heart was racing
With such
Anxiety trepidation he's taking you to see
This guy I'm not saying the name but he keeps taking me to see
Be competitive buyer
So 10 minutes later we walk cross street
Got the office building
Can we walk into this man's office
Abdul cases 6
What's 7
And
Admit 80s he was in his prime
And he was a force
And we walked in at office
And
All I remember him saying is
You should be ashamed of yourself
Then you're going to steal this kid's dream
It's not going to happen
You and I both know this is not going to have
And
Within 10 minutes
He told them to stand down
We're walking out of this office
And this kid's buying discount
In just a moment
Howard Schultz explains how Starbucks spread from Seattle
East coast and then all around the world
I'm guy Raz new listening to how I built this recorded live in Seattle
Support for this NPR Podcast comes from American Express
Open
We know that listeners the how I built this are curious curious about how good ideas becomes weight
Businesses
And chances are you have some good ideas of your own but as you know in business there can be a lot of
Roadblocks American Express open knows how hard it can be to get things done and they want to help
Help with money and no house so you can turn those ideas into action visit open.com
Get business done
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
That guy rides
It's 1987 and Howard Schultz is just
Starbucks witch
6 doors at the time
And yet
Grand Vision of a
Spending all across
The country facts
Call Mike hobby shops Warren Oliver cities like they are today and the idea of hanging out in 1/4
Hours
Or working in one or catching up with friends
Passing the time
Until when Howard started sharing his vision of rolling out these copy stores
Coast to Coast
Lots of people were like
Crazy idea
A lot of people said that
We Believe early on that what we had seen in Italy
It was replicable in America
True in American lamps
It was thinking let's create a store that
Not only is a store for coffee but produces the sense of community
Between home and work
And
I think early on we realized that the brand we were about to build
Was going to be experiencing
I mean
How how did Starbucks do in in the first few years after you bought it because
You weren't
Comfortable
Right away right now we weren't profitable
But in order to grow the company
And Theresa money
We said kind of metaphorically we want to build a hundred stories
Skyscraper
Well we're going to have to invest to build a foundation so we started investing heavily
Like any other startup
In people and processes
And it infrastructure and so the company lost money
Almost from the day I bought it
Yeah
An investors I think
Understood early on
That we were going to lose money in order to build a much bigger company
What mean
As you begin to expand and grow Beyond
The Pacific Northwest and I think
Your first location was in Chicago
What was the secret I mean was it was was it building a narrative around Starbucks around the beans
Farmers around the
You know around the story of coffee
Is that how you were able to bring people into the
Into the stores
For something we did go to Chicago
Hazard first city outside in Northwest
And it did not work right away
So
I got fooled very easily because I selected that location in the summer
And then when the winter came
It did not have an interior entrance into the building
So the customers had a walk out of the building
In a cold winter Chicago to get started
You know what
Didn't do it
But we wouldn't have any any extra resources for traditional advertising or marketing we did none of that in even today
Starbucks
Is not a traditional marketing come
And it sounds
Really old-fashioned but we built the company
One customer at a time one cup of time
And I think we were we got a lot of positive
PR
About
The equity of the brand experience
And
People started
Anticipating that we would come to their City
He probably that the best example that is what happened when we open
Now I'm going to fast forward
In 1996 we opened in Tokyo Japan for the fur
What happened
So
No one at Starbucks had any International experience
No
And we told our board we're going to open up
We think of Japan
The first state the board
Said we should probably hire an outside resource to consult a word that really
It gives me hives
If you have a IRA
A consultant
It means that we don't really know our business
And
They went away and they produced is
Big report and before they presented to the board they gave me the bad news and said Japan will be a disaster
You can't go there Starbucks no smoking policy will not work
And no one no person in the entire country will ever eat or drink in the street because you will lose
Loose face
Any Yunnan economics of Real Estate
You can't sell enough coffee in Japan to pay the rent
And
I convinced the board that I believe
The Japan woodworker
Just based on what an instinct on I'm going to guess I just
I just knew
I mean I just I just felt we had to have the courage of our convictions
Going to be a national and a global company
We have to go somewhere in Japan had a direct flight from Seattle Department
Okay so
We make the mistake
Of opening up our first store in the middle of August
Westin Tokyo
So those are going to Japan in August
Humidity is 100%
95 degrees
You're in the street for 5 minutes and you need to shower
And we didn't have any cold coffee or frappuccino at that time nothing like
It was hot coffee
Show the night before
It's kind of a celebratory dinner with our Japanese partner
And is an interpreter
I'm thinking
Tomorrow is just not going to go well
I can feel it it sends me a problem
So I tell the partner for The Interpreter that I think you should expect since it's so warm
I can be a big open
Anticipate the fact that we have to build this business
And wait for the cold weather
Amyotrophy
Braids
Tell him what I said
Wow
I find out
10 minutes later
That The Interpreter said Mr Shield said it's going to be the biggest Starbucks opening up
Did you really do that
So I get to my hotel room and I get a call
From someone in Seattle who sings
Static
See
We got CNN to cover the opening live
Oh wow
And I'm dying
This is it
At 6 a.m. in the morning
We're driving up to the store
And
There's a lineup
Of hundreds of
Japanese people
On the street
And I turn to save interpreter
And I say
Did you hire extras
And of course no
And
We cut the ribbon
Gary Young
Japanese college student who slept overnight
Run to the front of the line and we following
Any says double tall latte
With Seoul
Crazy to me is that
Azure expanding
In the early 90s
None of these huge players and coffee like Nestle your
You know the other companies got into that game I mean they could have
Trust you if they wanted to
Do what you did why didn't they see that opportunity
And I've been asked that many times I think the large companies just never believed
That you could build a national company and brand
Around selling coffee
In the cup
I just think they were naive
Maybe arrogant
And they gave us a lot of Runway
You guys started to do all kinds of branding Partnerships
In the 90s
Ice cream makers with supermarkets bottled Frappuccino candy companies record companies
Were you ever worried that
You were diluting the brand
We were very disappointed a lot of things but we turn down
Hundreds
People wanted
To do with us
And I think we were trying to say was
Will our customers give us license
To sell
Coffee remember this was a huge incision back
Then
As to whether Starbucks should be in Costco
Discount the coffee
What's a great debate inside the company because
How could you sell at a Costco to Discount your stores
And it what happened was we introduced hundreds of thousands of people at Starbucks who never been in
Bottled frappuccino in a JV with Pepsi became a multibillion-dollar business
And we started believing that we could build a brand in our store
And then extend it
Into another form factor in the grocery store
And
We also learned that many people got introduced to Starbucks through bottle crap and get it
I guess around age 47 48 you
Step down
The first time
As a CEO the company at that point
Is doing 2 billion in Revenue
You're pushing more stores outside the US why did you step down
I felt like I was repeating myself
I felt I was
No longer engaged in the fun creative part of the businesses where I get the most Joy
What were you what were you doing when we fought
Mia between the lawyers
DHR shoes
You just what it was I was not having fun
I just decided that I needed a break from
The Madness of it and were you able to really step away away
Company
And ask him and I should have been paying kind of more more attention to the company but I
I started doing other things
One of which was the Seattle SuperSonics
Which weekend we can talk about or not I think we're going to leave that one
I'm not proud of that
Who wrote a famous memo to the bull
Gordon Diecast 2007
Were you expressed regret over the commoditization of the brand
What was going on
Was two things going on at that point first update the country was heading into a cataclysmic Financial
But I think
And I look back on those years I would describe it as the years of you
I got Starbucks was growing
At a pace in which growth and
Success
Began to cover up a lot of mistakes
And like what kind of steaks
TUMI stores cannibalizing other stores
Did not the financial controls and discipline that work
Warren place we're not being leveraged
And
I think the big mistake though
Was Wall Street in the stock price
Became an albatross on the company's neck
And so growth became
The strategy the company and growth is not a strategy
A10 Grossmont what
That customer service was wasn't as good that the
Product was not good that the experience of going to a Starbucks wasn't as good
Rothman too many stores too fast in areas that
Should not have had a Starbucks
And secondarily
The experience
We should Define the essence of the company
Was being compromised by efficiency
In the company in a management team at that time started measuring
Yield
Sales per hour
And doing things that
We're so diluted
To the essence of the foundation of the company and it really started
I think upsetting me
I began to go into the stores and not recognized
What we had built
What what did you see
Probably the signature thing that I saw
Was a new breakfast sound
That
Contaminated the odor of coffee
This is the grilled cheese
And not that it was
Wrong thing to do but it was executed so poor like the the Starbucks smell like
Yeah
Around 2008
Starbucks share price hits a record low
Some analysts are saying its days were numbered
Were they really
I'm at the time I didn't think so
But I knew we were
In a downward spiral and
The company needed to go through a major transfers
And when I returned a CEO which
I never had plan to come back
I would say that they were people both on the board at the time and many people at Starbucks
And certainly
Hundreds of people of Wall Street
It said you're bringing him back
Mean
He's the problem
Really
And the analysts in the media we're not very kind
But when I came back
I came back for two reasons and that is
What it means to love something in the responsibility that goes with it
When you told your wife Sherry
That you were going to do this
What was the response I mean
100% supported
I mean she went through the same pain I was going through and watching what we had built
Yeah
And knew I had to go back and you were gone from from running it for almost 8 years
Did you think you were just going to go in quickly stabilize it and then go back out
I don't think I knew what I know how long I would stay at that
But I think as we discussed earlier
The problems
We're so severe
And
Every rock that I turned over
Was worse than I had imagined
To the point where I had I made some very drastic
Decisions you at the shop
600 stores
We closed 900 stores and 90% of them had been open less than a year
The thing that I did that was probably most telling
Was when we decided to close the stores
For training
A12
Every Storm
Was closed
How much did it cost
I think we estimated
About 24 million dollars
Empress of lost sales
And labor so you're bored just love this
The shareholders love this things that I did that people said
He's really lost it
What's a training
Was so vitally important because Starbucks Coffee Company
Forgot
How to make
Quality
And
We had everybody in the company we train
Now
The thing that galvanizing Tire Company
Was something else
And that was we were in room one day and I said
I feel like I need to communicate
With every single store manager
In person
Dennis Wilson 2008
This is during the crisis with no company was traveling at 8
You can't get 10,000 people to do what you going to do and I said no
I want to go somewhere we can get 10000 store managers in a like a
We talkin about
By the way this event cost about 30 million dollars at a time and we didn't have the money
Why everybody there
Ya food
Everything
Until
I had to give a $39 fee
Yeah this is the of the ten thousand storm
And I'm
I'm running some notes and couple hours before from my colleagues at will
Sometime the truth
The realtor
Because at this point I knew
We were really in trouble
I knew that we had about seven months left if we continue down this track
Where we would be
Insult
And
I felt so strongly that I needed to trust our people
With the same information I had
And if and if I was going to ask them
To do the things that they needed to do
Which mint take
Every single customer interaction soap
As if this is your last
And make it so personal to understand if we don't
Correct the situation
You're not going to the Future Families
And you said that I said
Yeah
How long
How long does it take
To recover
Overnight we began to
Change the trajectory within 6 months
We were
Starting to climb back
And within a year
It was a memory
However
The real question was
What did we learn
We were so hungry and so driven
When we started the company
But when we were that successful
People got sloppy they got lazy
And this is so vitally important success in any business
No matter what it is
Is not an entitlement
It has to be earned we stop turning it and that's why we got in trouble
Building a company is a lonely place
Sometimes because you're imprinted especially as a man
Not demonstrating vulnerability
And I think one of the perhaps most undervalued characteristics of leadership
Is
Vulnerability and asking for help
And I've done that a number times so I think it's important I think When You're vulnerable
Ask for help people come towards you
And I think I've
I've tried to do that every step of the way and be honest and truthful about what I know what I don't
And most importantly what I believe
I want to ask you about
Your approach to
Your employees you calling partners
They're eligible for
Healthcare
Education benefits you can now earn a degree through Arizona State University
Would you work at Starbucks at least 20 hours a week
Free college tuition
I'm all of this is very expensive
But it does buy you a lot of Goodwill from from the from the Publican from your employees is that why Starbucks does
No
Health insurance
Equity in the form of stock up
Trying to prove something
To myself to my family
And many of us
Who were in the company
We're not born with a silver spoon
Many of us have come from similar
Backgrounds
And I think customers began to realize we're paying these kids
Give me an ownership they had health insurance
Any intimacy that was built between the Barista and our customers because of the frequency
Begin to build your list turnover
With much less turnover then and today than anyone in our industry
The my dad is in the audience tonight here you flew up from LA to be here
What are you my dad what are you
What do you think your dad would have
Made of your success and if he was sitting in this hiding tonight and use hearing your story
What are you
Think you would have
About his son who
Became one of the most successful entrepreneurs
In modern American history
My dad passed away in 87
At the age of 65
So he he didn't see any of the
A success that we have enjoyed
I think
It would be so shell-shocked
And and so proud
And I think he would it would go back to what he experienced
And I think
What he would be most proud of is how we have treated
Everyone in the company because he was that blue collar worker who is not respect
For lack of Education
And not being sophisticated
And unfortunately never really
Got the chance to
Be himself or be valued in a company
I hate he would Marvel at that
In many many ways and I've said this
Before
The values of culture and guiding principles of
Starbucks
Really are defined by me wanting to build the kind of company that my father never got a chance to work for
Howard thank you so much
Howard Schultz step down as CEO
Starbucks earlier this year he's now the executive chairman and you probably heard the rumor that he stepped
Down in part to explore a
Possible presidential run and I know I know you were probably dying for me to ask him all about this
And I did but just backstage before the show and his answer was pretty koi
Mostly says he's not really interested but when pressed on it he says Never Say Never
Hey thanks so much for listening to the show this week this effort
Has recorded in front of a live audience at Benaroya Hall in Seattle
It was co-produced by Claire Breen and runty mareblu who also composed the music
Thanks to Jeff Rogers sanaz meshkinpour Neva Grant and Lawrence Wu
Thanks also to Allie Prescott Jessica Goldstein and Andy huether
Our internet is Diana mu stock
I got rosney been listening to a special live episode
How I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com