Support for how I built this and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation
Seewhy michigan
Is attracting top talent and top businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
Yes they were somewhere I think
So the knock-off Market became looks alright three to four hundred of them
Everybody came in and said all we can do this
Coke Pepsi Red Bull monster when they all came in
Actually our market share dipped
From about 90
3% down to 67%
However the one thing they all forgot was
Yep have a great Prada
Robin PRP it's how I built this a show of activators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories
And the movements they built on Gyros
Today show how a former Hindu monk turned into a
Billion dollar business
Okay full disclosure
I have
On the rare occasion
Swallow the contents of a 5-hour Energy bottle to podcasts and sometimes
To get stuff done late at night
I bet a lot of you have bought a bottle of the stuff
The airport or pulled up to a gas station late at night and added it to your pile of Twix and Dorito
Frozen Diet Coke right
So how does it work
I don't exactly know I mean caffeine is Magic right
But I can tell you this little bottle
Made Manoj bhargava
Billionaire
When you turn 14 this is in the late 1960s Minaj's dad decided to come to the u.s.
India
Temperature degree
Tok the whole family
I moved to a tiny apartment in West Philadelphia and started life all over again and they didn't
I have a whole lot of money so every kid in the family had to work after school and when Munoz was old enough to get a dry
Driver's license
He scraped together enough money to buy a dump truck
It was the worst contract in the history of humans
Cost me $350
So it was pretty beat up
Italy to every fluid possible
Water
Oil gas
Transmission fluid in the evening and
Everything would leave the Ender
Good morning
So wait why did you buy the soundtrack
Wow I got a job
To clean
Houses in the ghetto in Philadelphia
These are either abandoned houses
Or houses that were being built
So I hired somebody some other kid
And we used to go
Clean the houses
Try everything on the truck
Go to the dump site
And try to dump this thing scores to dump the Newark burial U-verse
Jump up and down and try to
Shut it down
Tired after time I've ever had
How much money did you make doing this like was it really worth
The money
Well I made $500
For the summer
And I I sold the truck to somebody for 350 so I got all my money out of the truck
But you turned a profit
Well he thought there was a lot of
I don't know if it's a profit because if we worked 11 hours a day 5 days a week
All summer
Private laws
It was incredible amount of profit there
Kissing you do this I guess
You know as you are singing about college
And then in the duplicate you applied College
Well I apply to a few schools
And ended up at Princeton
That's pretty good
That's okay
Ain't nothing
My father was happier than I was
You weren't happy
Well I
I mean obviously honest
About it I feel like this is great but this isn't
And then you go to college for a really one purpose and I know
Fancy people have different reasons
Broaden your mind mostly everybody goes to college
Get a better job
That's why you really go
And so
I really wasn't interested in
The trappings of a
Better job
So
I don't need this
It doesn't make any sense
Site I got to find something better
And so after the finish the first year
And I left
You dropped out
Didn't your parents freak out
Pretty much
Imagine what did he say to you
You know they were not happy
For sure they were
What are you doing
I pretended I'm just taking a year off
So what did you
Like what you did you go back to Philadelphia
No actually
After the next
Several years I
For lack of a better word I'd say
I became a monk
Kind of a month
Like a monk in a monastery
Yes
I went
To a bunch of places all over there
Please put on the song a lot of places in India
And
Found something which was really valuable
I practice that
A lot of years
And that's
That's pretty much all I'm going to
Say about that
Yeah
I don't want to pry too much into the
Into the details of it I just want to
It sounds like that
Profound effect on who you became
History of Time
No doubt about it that was actually my true education
It was sort of an education on what is life how to live and how to live it so fundamental because it affects
How you do business how you do
Interaction are you
How you do everything
But also
How to look at some things in a very fundamental way
Most of us tend to just assume things yeah you know whatever our parents taught us whatever Society.
Well all of that was
Taken away
Start from scratch
That's a perspective that
That takes years
And then when you look at things different
Did you work hard during that time did you do labor oh yeah
Lot of work it was really tough discipline
I mean because you're never off
Ever
Day and night you're never off
Yeah how long were you away
For a lot of years
A lot time
Let's move on
Okay no worries
What did you do when you got back to
Why I guess my thought
Process at that time was that
You know I need to
Probably
Earn some money so I can support all the work
That
Is being done
Yunnan India
And then
I bought a business
That was going under
It was at what kind of business was it
Amazon Plastics business
Wow did you did you know anything about plastic
No but
Look business is really
Like Mustangs
Tell me about common sense
Yeah and we bought it for under liquidation value
So the bank finance the whole thing
And it was losing money and I looked at it and I said okay I can fix it
So what was the business called
And Indiana called at Prime PVC while their biggest product was chair straps you know the time that
Outdoor furniture
So then they invented the strap
Wow they made that and then they got competition
Got into trouble
How did you even begin to think that this
What you could do like cuz I'm
You had this incredible
Experience in India but I'm assuming you did not have any background in
Elasticsearch
No
You just look at it and say okay you know I don't know their stuff
I don't have to go and make the plastic
Stop
But I know
What it cost I can figure that out
He cut away that stuff which is losing its
I do it's not rocket science
But
If you use common sense you're in great shape if you use experts
You're in so much trouble
How long does it take
For you to turn that company around
Make it pop
Oh that that was 30 days
30 days
Just by cutting
Cutting costs and and cutting the production time and they're just a bunch of comments and stuff
You know you look at
All right where we spending money
And why are we spending that much money
I got it took common sense you say okay
I spent $10,000 on this
Sol Y
Is it making anything
No
So how long were you were you running this company
Well I was involved in it for about 7 years
And we grew at
From basically from 02 about
Hank
When I
Left it was 23 million in sale
Wow
So you sold that company
Yes I I kind of retired from it first
I said okay
In that you have done this already alright I got to go do something else
So I left town
Soaps I'm assuming that the one you sold this company you were
Like financially secure for the rest of your life pretty much
Okay so how do you go from
From semi-retirement
In the Plastics industry to
Okay so
After my retirement
I thought okay
What do I do now
And so I thought
The only way to have residual income in other words
Ongoing income
Is to have something that you own right you can you can either find
An invention or I can invent something
And otherwise you don't have a business
Adidas 2-way stood what is invented yourself
The second is to find it
So I started a company that looked for great Technologies worldwide
In the in a chemical area
And we got thousands of submissions
Pasties all over the
And then eventually what happened is
Founders
Technology
I found it in it natural products
Trade show
Where where was it
This wasn't
California
See you work so you went to the trade chart show thinking maybe I'll do something in the Natural Foods world
Well
Actually the other way around I want to try to go see if I can find something that I can buy or license right
So I went there and it
I turned out
I am meeting with you
These guys that
Addison
Sumproduct
So after the meeting a lot
And then it was like 2 in the afternoon I've had all my God I got meetings till 10 at night you know I'm not going to survive
Tyler Reddick
So then they had some energy something so I said
I went back to the ranch
You know you said that energy product can you
Can I get some
So they gave me a little bit
And my God it was
This is amazing with these are just people displaying a product at the trade show
Yes
And it was an energy drink
Yeah it was a big drink
Cuz I 16 hours
Yeah and it was amazing
For the next few hours and hours I was
Great
Syfy
Okay I could sell this
I went back to them
Undeserved
Neil Science Guy
And I'm just a lonely business guys
Basically cell get lost
What did you say you said to them hey I want to work with you guys I want to license this thing I want to buy this from you and they said no we're not
Cracked
So
I I kind of looked at it's okay I should be able to figure out very quickly
Yeah I looked at the later I said
Okay
There's a good starting what was it what was in the drink
I mean in in when they list ingredients I don't tell you how much it was
Right right
So you have to figure that out
You know how hard can it be
I'll figure it out
Sexy you go back to where you live and you started
Tinker with
A recipe to try and recreate a version of
This drink
Write my thought was
You know these guys come upstairs I can do better
What were you doing this in like a kitchen in your house
Well obviously I started a company and so we were
We had labs and so on
Until what I did wasn't really rocket science
People always ask you all the genocides background
Video background inefficient
Know that only got only message you up further it doesn't really help you at all
Okay because
Most inventions have been made by people who didn't have a background in whatever they were invented
If you look at throughout history the great stuff was made by people who didn't
Follow
The rules of the experts
Experts are great
Telling you what what you shouldn't do
And for that they're useful
Yeah but what you should do I don't have a clue
So what were some of the ingredients just that just I'm just curious at that they had that you were working
What is it called when you put in together
Basically they were vitamins
Amino acids
I mean in layman terms it would be vitamins for the brain and
So what we created with something that is really not much to do with energy
But it had everything to do with Focus
I mean the first thing I do is
99 fortunately everybody laughs at me in the company as well as I try everything on me
Cuz I'm not going to take it then I'm not going to
Anybody else
So I tried it on me
And
And see if
If it actually does
What it supposed to do in
It does give you
Better focus better
Clarity
Every product we make
Crime and get involved in
As if I can't use it if my family doesn't use it
I don't want to do it
Because then you're just a con man
You know you just
Selling people stop you don't use
I'm curious because at this around the time in the city early 2000
Do a lots of energy drink
Out there on the market right likes it she like how are you going to
Differentiate your product from from others
That were you out there
So
I thought about it and I said
Like if I if I make another drink
First of all I got to fight for space in
The cooler
And against Red Bull monster
I got also fight Coke Pepsi and Budweiser
So
You promised that if you want to try that
It's high tide poke and the second thing that came to my mind was
What if I'm tired
Why am I thirsty also
You know I mean it be like Tylenol selling 16 oz
Bottles of Tylenol I just want
To do a quick I want to drink this whole thing
And
2 oz it's really not a drink
It's a delivery system
So how did you take it from
This thing in the lab.
Bottling it up and then trying to sell it
Stores
How long did that process take
Think it took less than 6 months
You know we tried to product had it tested at a bunch of people take it
So then we find a toddler
Michelle K
You make these things
How to design by Design
Label and so on
And then off we went
We made the first batch
Actually it was great
But it tasted
Horrible what would it taste like
Why it tastes like cough syrup
Badcock
Not doing good cough syrup
It was really bad in just a moment, Noah's bark of a
Turn that cough syrup into liquid gold it's how I built this
ER
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First to godaddy.com
They give customers the tools insights they need to transform their ideas in personal initiatives into success
GoDaddy small business owners have everything they need to get their business online
Including 24/7 support
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology provider dedicated to small business
They're offering how I built this listeners
30% off all new products
Just going to godaddy.com
Podcast
And use code built
Thanks also to Green Mountain Coffee Green Mountain Coffee is passionate about making a smoother tasting cup
They're expert Roasters tasters sample Sip and carefully craft every blend until their shirt
Your cup is smooth and perfectly balanced
And now
Is a specialist nurse promotion get $4 off when you buy two boxes
Most Green Mountain Coffee
K-Cup pods
Keurig.com
Who sang all this month we are asking our listeners
To tell other people about podcast
Especially podcast that you love or podcast you think they might love
So if you know somebody who doesn't listen to
Listen to podcast but doesn't listen to the one you like
Tell them about it
Even better show them how to download a podcast
And then tell us what you've been recommending
Use the hashtag
Tripod that's try
Tod
And thanks
It's how I built this from NPR
And Gyros
Totally nuts at the guy who invented 5-hour Energy sounds like he has never had a v
Power energy drink
Shelta hats
Anyway at this point Munoz had a company and a product that
You still tweaking
And the only thing left
What's it come up with a name
You know I didn't pay attention to
The advertising guys who said oh no it's the branding
Imaging
You know you should name it slippers app
And you know
Is it on
Okay
To me I understand function
And that's what we're going to do
So we named it 5-hour Energy it's not a very
Clever name
Cuz my thought was that you have
Less than half a second
The consumer to either buy it or Not by
You have to communicate
During that half-second
What are you
You know what you want to do
What are you about
That's all we named it five hours
So how did you even begin to sell the product where did you go
Initially
Why we went to the largest vitamin store which is
Dancy
And so we went to them and they said okay sure the cubic the largest vitamin store in the country
You've no background of this industry
How did you even get into the door
I think one of the great Parts is not having a background in the
Because
Those who have great backgrounds in the industry always think to takes forever
That we slow things down
So it turns out GNC
Always looking for new products because
Once the product gets Mass
GNC
Sort of out of it
Cuz you know what Adam Walmart and everybody else
Nobody's going to buy it
Antsy see you pitch GNC you went to their headquarters and Pitch them on this
I gave him
Shots
Cracked so they put them
Bunch of their stores
Just like right at the cash register
Right at the cashier
And it just belong there you could
Tala just look that way
Should be there in a small around 2004-2005
This is for
Mm
And how did they do
Where do they sell right away
Not really I mean I didn't advertise at all
The first week it's sold only 200 bottles
It was horrible
Yeah
And this is a thousand stores
Are you sure you thinking maybe this is not going to work
No not at all.
Cuz first week I mean
Nothing sounds right now
Accurate
So six months later we just waited
Ensouled unco
And at the end of that six months
It was selling $10,000 a week
Just people tried it for 2 miles
A lot of exercise people that buy it
GNC in
Jesse's
Has very limited customer
It's over for them to be doing ten thousand a week
Astounding
I so then we went
To the drug
Companies
We went to
Rite Aid in
Walgreens
And then our
How long did it take for
5-hour Energy
To become
Prophet like
Profitable company was it in that first 6 months
No no no
And it took a few years it took to three years
Cuz of the first part
Is always the hardest
They're all kinds of interesting problems you know you have to advertise
And yet it's not everywhere so she advertises and nobody could find it
Hillary get the plane for like
Nowhere.
And then you go to you know that's how you put it in a drugstore
And you said okay you can find it at this trucks
And then the customer goes there and there's nobody there that knows where it is and can't find it
It's in there
So
There's so many
Different issues that happen in the beginning
That you have to have to start over
Just
Get through
Music business business is one of those things
You have to do everything right and then you have to get lucky
Yeah
When anybody says that
Good luck is not part of it
Is just arrogant
Why do you think it
Took off
Why do you think people bought it because
It's a weird little bottle I mean
I'm I'm used it I've used it before
And it is it does work
What is this weird bottle and you think
5 Hour Energy
Good for me like
We are definitely the media is
Has sort of looked at it and said oh God you know it's normal person looking at it would say
Different kinds of normal
If if you're working two jobs
If you're if you're driving truck
Configure
If your on Wall Street working 16-hour days if
If you're in the
Los Angeles
On a movie set
All of those guys work really long hours
At that point it's really not a choice it's like okay
I gotta survive somehow
There's a just a normal number of people that looked at it and didn't sort of believe the media hype
But you're right
The bottle
Makes it
And because it's out front
People look at it until why I don't know I don't I don't know if I should try next to the Slim Jims
Unlike the lighters
Yeah
But again we do Salah bunch.
If we sold it to everybody that needed
We would be 20 times outside
I'm curious about competitors
I mean
For people trying to try to copy the concept
Yes they were somewhere I think
Knock-off Market
Became likes alright three to four hundred of them
Wow everybody came in and said all we can do
Coke
Came in with a product
The shot Pepsi
Red Bull monster they all came in
With shots
Pinotage
Return to Oz
And
I am starting to have better distribution muscle than we have
More resources than we have
And so people try a name and came in at the Lesser price than us
When they all came in
Actually our market share dipped
From about 90
3%
Down to 67
And everybody everybody tried their product
Yeah however
The one thing they all forgot
Was you have a great product
So your market share dropped to 67% once all these competitors. Come in
Cracked
And now it's back up to 93
That's insane
I mean
There is nothing that has a 93% market share
Well whenever people ask me what product are you like I said
Where they wear WD-40
It's not a
Category
It's
We own that cat
Rihanna
Wentworth guys
But there's lots of really great products at yourself admit that when you tried that energy drink
It's a convention years earlier that was a good product but that
Never went anywhere
Presumably
Well there's also this other part
You still have to have some skill and
Some resources
You have to still get it in front of people
You got it
The start of a successful product is the product has to be
Okay that's just a start
Button that the second part II part is you got to understand
Digital Distribution Systems you have to understand
How to get it out there and have to work at it
Like I said you have to do everything else
At that point right
And if
Both the great product
And that
Comes along then you have a success
If you don't have a great product you can do everything right and still fail
What's soda
Your trait or personality
Trait that you do have
It is
Enables you to do this
To have the confidence to believe it I mean it I will you just
Incredibly optimistic that this thing was going to work
No not really I think one of the traits that you have to have
To be an entrepreneur
Is to be able to
And you know to take the Heat
A failing
Because
I mean there were so many projects I tried
Please ask me I said
How do you how do you get up
And do it again
Psychedelic I fall so many times
I've got pavement marks on my face
So what
Just got up again and do it again
And I went to probably 20 different products
Big failures
Little failures
And you if you
Can't do that
You know you should best just go work in a large company
You have signed the giving pledge which means you what you promised to give away to 99% of your wealth is that right
And so 1% will be laughed and
You have a child
Get me now you going to
You know make sure that your son is
A life of comfort or or are you basically saying note can I get anything
Basically there's an old saying
That
If you raise your child to be useless
Why giving money
And if you
If you raise your child to be useful why does he need money
Tok to you expect your child to do it all on his own
Absolutely everybody else does why you know
In order to make a a good worthwhile life
You have to have the confidence the only way you can have confidence to do it yourself
So
Temeku
Are children miserable is not I think the job of parents and actually I mean I was lucky cuz he said great I don't want
And so
He kind of grew up as a cheapskate
The cheapest guy I know
How has becoming a very wealthy person changed you
Double your lifestyle
Not a whole lot I mean
Basically you know I get up in the morning and
Pour myself some cereal
Go to work
That
I do have the most expensive Hobby in the world is to
It to work for that
People that don't have
How much
So now believe me that's a really expensive Hobby
Well I found out that
Bottom third of the world
Doesn't even have electricity you know I mean
You know what it would be like to just at the end of the day
1600 after 6 7 to just sit there in the dark
Adam billions more than billion people
So we I created this thing called The Invention shop
And we've created equipment
To go into these houses really cheap
That'll give them electricity
It's actually a hybrid bicycle you buy pedal for an hour and electricity for a day
To me with exciting is
To see
It all
For example you gave these bicycles out
As a test
And there was a widower with three little kids
And
I mean she was busy all day with the kids
So now with the lights in her house
She's able to sold till midnight
And I guess if I bucks a day
And with that she feeds our family
They even have money for school
That's a thrill
If somebody listen to this is prized thinking about starting a business but no money no connections just
Idea
What is it that they have
Do do what is
What is the the one thing that they
Have to
Have her Focus
Wild first
Use your common sense
Do not use MBA speaker
Second you have to be totally determined
I hate the word passionate
Because
You got hit in the face a few times passion seems to fade
Determination
Means basically you yet
Your face hits the floor
20 times you get up 21 times
You know you just get up every time no matter what happens you get up and do it again
If you have those two
And the third thing is a need is a sense of urgency
Do it now
Don't wait
Don't delay
If you have those three things those are all you need
Manoj bhargava is still the CEO
Innovation Ventures which makes 5-hour Energy
And despite his past life as a Hindu Monk and is General chilled-out Sensibility
Munoz does drink 5-hour Energy
He says about 5 bottles a week
I am assuming you do not drink it before bedtime that would be dumb
And please don't turn it off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors TIAA weather is investing advice banking
Or retirement
TIAA believe smart financial decisions should enable life not
Define it
Because real success isn't just measured in zeros
Is having a career that delivers meaning and purpose
It's connecting with family
Friend and it's giving back
TIAA calls this the new success story
And I want to help you achieve it everyday
Learn more
TIAA
Hey welcome back it's time now for how you built that
And you know we've been doing the teacher for a while and we've heard about all kinds of products or making snacks
Clothing bags bikes apps but somehow
We have overlooked this
Very vital and growing sector
Early in the morning and right now. I just fed him they're getting
Morning breakfast Dripping Springs Texas
Chickens in her very large backyard
Anyway she got her idea for a business about four years ago when she and her husband Monte were on a
Road trip and that time he was in the construction business
We were
Just kind of lamenting how not find the commercial construction industry was an
We were brainstorming different ideas and I said you should build chicken coops or we Seville chicken coops
Diane only had a couple of chickens in her one coop
Outback and she starts Almonte all the ways that that Coupe
Could be better and so I just said
Okay don't be a chicken coop it has to have
You know easy access doors has to be easy to clean and
I just said
Don't build something ugly
Went to work building a coup
That was not ugly and I said okay that's cute it was a coupe with a rounded roof not to buy
Foxy with clean simple lines
We could start selling these poop to other Chicken Keepers across the country
Because as the local food movement started to take hold all over the country
More and more people even in cities
Wanted
Chickens new people like the idea of fresh eggs even though it's just one item on your
Breakfast plate at least you know where it came from but of course if you are raising a chicken in a city
I could really bug your neighbors which says Diane is why you need a very classy look
So we use Cedarwood completely different wood than anybody
Selling at a big-box store or something like that when you look at one of our tubes here saying that the gray
Reign of the wood bridges very pretty
Their business
20 Cedarwood Loop start with
And they put them up for sale on Craigslist on a Monday and by Friday they were completely
Sold out literally
Friday night we're out there with our car headlights Shining
Into the shop with our kids helping us assemble all of these coops
So they had a business Diana Monte built-in 8
Thousand square foot shop in their backyard to make more coops
And during our busy season which is right now they have 10 people working for them in the last year
Diesel 1700 coupes
Which is enough to keep the family and the chickens going
The only problem the entire operation has become their obsession
Oh my gosh we cannot switch
I mean we do
Sometimes talk about other things but I would say that good percentage of our time is spent talking about Urban
New company
Bet Urban Coop company founded by Diane 20 of Dripping Springs Texas
Find out more Hitler Facebook page just search
How I built this on
Facebook
And as always we love to
Here at the share your stories
Especially when we can play animal sounds
So please keep them coming go to build. NTR
That work that's build with a D
Npr.org hey thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
RG
Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and favored Riders review while you're there
You can also write directly to us at Hib tea at NPR. O RG and if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this our show was produced this week by Trump teen Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to neva grandson of meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Are interned is Claire Breen on Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
I still think that's a pig
Hey everybody I'm Kelly mcevers host of NPR's embedded
On March 9th
We are back
With our new episodes
That police videos
What did he do
To deserve to be killed that night and shot so many times
People see what they want to see almost no one can see those videos from a neutral perspective
I was thinking see the gun see the game don't you tell him to you see the gun
Find embedded on the NPR one app or at npr.org
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com