Support for this podcast
In the following message come from mizzenandmain
Creators of moisture Wick
Wrinkle resistant dress shirt
Shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
And use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
I have to tell you that the biggest hits
I had in my life ending music and hunting television and heading business
I have been always as a result of significant projections
And repeated which actions so every time I have an idea that people tell me no don't do that
Oops
Brown NPR
How I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movements
Have a group of a spandex wearing play the superheroes called the Power Rangers help turn Haim Saban
Who won the richest man on earth
If you ask the Haim Saban what he does
I used to describe myself as a cartoon schleper
Cartoon slipper
Yep
What I did for years is I
Went and knocked on Doors
Try to sell
Cartoons all over the world
That's what I slept
And he slept
Some of the biggest cartoons of the 80s and 90s
Inspector Gadget X-Men and of course
His biggest hit
The Mighty Morphin Power Ranger
Just been revived is a blockbuster Hollywood feature
Me and four kids found a spaceship buried underground
I'm pretty sure I'm a superhero
But we're getting ahead of ourselves here because long before the Power Rangers lawn before
Haim Saban was flying around the world on his private jet or
Hangers Beverly Hills mansion with Bill Clinton
He was just a
Core Jewish kid living on a Dusty Street
In Alexandria Egypt
We lived in
Very narrow
Street
We were kind of
Lower class
Family my father was a Salesman in a toy store and my mother was a
We had family friends who were Egyptian Muslims Egyptian Christian
Greek
Italians it wasn't pretty Cosmopolitan city Alexandria
Shortly after the Suez War
Egyptian Jews were accused of being traitors so Hines family had to flee to Israel
I was twelve at the time and no one in his family spoke in Hebrew in fact they didn't know anyone in Israel
When they got there they were housed in a tiny apartment in a rough part of
Tel Aviv it was one rule in an apartment that had three rooms in the other two rooms
Who are occupied by another couple and buy a hooker
And her pimp and it was the five of us
My father base
How to draw
Selling pencils and erasers
Door to door
And some days you would sell three pencils and some days
She will tell
No pants
Toys R Us
To say the least a very hard life
IPS
And and do you remember
Going to school right away
Well I didn't want to go to school but my father thought I should be a lawyer
I mean I I wanted to make money
You know because
Living under these conditions
Does not
A very
Exciting prospects
We compromised that I would
Work during the day
Study
At night
So
I'd wake up
But sex I go to
Be a runner in
Travel agency
4:30 the afternoon
School until 9:30
Antonia come home I do my homework
In the staircase
Because obviously I could
In the room
The family was
And
Go to sleep and then
Everyday was the same routine
What were you a good student as
I was a pretty bad
Student and
The principal called my father and said
Your son most probably is going to make a lot of money one day but
A student
I ain't going to be any ain't gonna be no lawyer
So take him out of school so my father sat me down and said I need you
To finish
High School
Unfinished
What's high grade
And then you can do whatever you want
But you must finish
Which high school did you finish with high grades
Yes
Did you feel it anyway
Being a Jew
From an Arab
Country in Israel at the time
That I know you were you were
Christina server
Lower like a
Second class citizen by
I choose from
From European Time
Yes
I had a girlfriend
Louis parents were from Poland
And her mother said to her
If you bring
That's what's a fire that black
Animal
To the house
I'm going to jump
Off the balcony and kill myself
Bellflower
Yasso
We would make out in the garden
Then I owe you join the Army I was in the Infantry
And were you actually in combat or did you have a different kind of job
It was at the beginning in combat
Unit and
Then
They realize that they would be much more efficient at organising entertainment for the soldiers that
Well they put me to do so my job was to put together
Bands and go from one
Post
To the other for example I remember right after the
Six-Day War
We went down to the Sinai
And drove
From one position to the other
Weather
Entertainers
And entertain the soldiers
NH position
That's what we did
Obviously that foretold what you would do with your life you would become a person in the entertainment industry but
What was that your first exposure to
Tubing in
An entertainment
Environment it to actually organizing this
Yes
Well that's a job they gave me yeah you know I don't know why they gave me that job I have no
Background in it
Out of the fact that I
Play guitar.
Little bit
But that's a job
They assigned me to Uso
Why did the job I was assigned
When was that
What led you to kind of single maybe I
I should pursue this after at the Army
No
What let me to join a band
After I left the army
I was simply
The necessity to
Make some money
And get out of that
Ruhlman
Support my family
But my father didn't happen
To go door-to-door selling pencils
At the time there was no television in it
As well
That was radio
And I used to play
You know Beatles songs
And
An hour behind
The lead singer
Sounded exactly like McCarthy
So
We were pretty successful
Even though I was a pretty lousy bass player
I've read that you actually were so badly
That you would turn down the apps
I just at the beginning
Yeah so where did you eventually get good at it
No
I was never good enough
It was just why one day the two brothers that were kind of the basis of
The band the lead singer
Andy's by the way
Was the solo guitarist
Came up to me and
And said that
Why don't you be your manager
And
Cuz you're holding us back music
And I couldn't
Be happier
So one of the happiest days of my life was
The day I pulled on My Guitar
My last gig
And I became a manager and then
You manage one band and you manage
Steuben's and then
You build a business
At some point you laugh
Israel
It won't fit
I became a tour promoter in Israel and I bought
Many artists
Stories real from Ray Charles
Jose Feliciano
Blood Sweat and Tears
Many others how are you doing this is a 20-something year okd were just hustling you were just
Convincing people
Said you were the guy to make it happen
Mark Zuckerberg a24 has built Facebook
Before I was able to bring Jose Feliciano to Israel what the heck
You're supposed to be
Doing stuff
You know you're not supposed to be
Visiting Ghana
Counting on your parents
Okay so so at some point
You moved to I get to Paris
When did you decide to do that and why
Well I moved
Des Peres
Simply because
Israel was really
From a business standpoint
Kussmaul
And
Despite
My Success
Quote on quote
I was in
That
Of $600,000
Wait you were you at 6
$4,000 in
How old are you
By the time that happened I was 29
Did you accrue all that dead by the well
I had a big group of harpists from Japan
In October of 1973 ready to tour the country and the
Yom Kippur War to Castle by surprise so obviously there were no
Concerts at was no shows there was no way for them to even leave cuz the airport was closed
Most I had to return the money I had paid them in advance and I had a couple of
Other bumps in the road again that has nothing to do with me which is the devaluation of
Aldi's rallybound which meant that
We had big shows lined up where all of the expenses were in dollars and the revenue
What an Israeli pounds would this evaluation of the pounds we played to
Full houses on losing money every night so these two things compounded. Me too
$600,000 in debt
Freaking out I mean thinking how am I going to ever pay that back no I don't think I was freaking out that I wasn't supposed to stay
Data panic
Ghetto freaking out the shoes
You still have some control
But when you have a massive panic attack you have no clue
So what did you do
So I moved to France
And
Tyson this nine-year-old who sounded
Like an adult and he was a fantastic singer and nine year old singer in Israel
You said he was going to help you pay off
Well
I got very lucky I got very lucky
How did you get lice
What happened oh you know what
Being lucky means
It means having the scale
To grab the lock when it's presented to you who was the luck that was
Presented
Wildest first record that I produced
Went platinum
With his nine-year-old
Is what it is a 9 year old what was his horse's name
Noah
NOAA m
I have the song I Would You Remember
Deficient
Basically
Strike gold with this or platinum
Circus
Record and you've got a career I guess in France like it at this point to you
What did you do did you start a production company in in in France
And I started production company that I set up my own label
And I sold over a period of 8 years that I live there
On my own label more than 18 million records
Wow
How did you even know how to cut deals in Paris
I can meet you get there and Israeli
Obviously you spokes
Some friends from childhood
But how did you even know how to
Had a wheel and deal and go get a studio together and and
Define
Distributors
I have no idea
You just started knocking on doors
Oh yeah
Knocking on doors as what
Guido Wright comedian
Get ahold business people knock on doors
Old salesman knock on door
I learned it on the job I guess
You know I don't know I never produced the record in my life
When I produce that first record yeah
Why did you did you decide
To move to the US I guess
In the early 80s
Well
I bought a house here in 1978 and I moved here in 1980
Yeah and what did you intend to do in LA
Iowa
Planning to
Basically continue doing the same thing
Which is creating
Reproducing and distributing music and
Therefore I built the studio
In Studio City
And
We started
Creating music
Full cartoons
Why cartoon how did you even
Get into that that world at all
Well I
Studied
How music is
Paid for in America
Buy ASCAP
10 BMI
Isla publishing
The agency
These are the publishing
She's got like 8 or they are as Representatives
Collection agencies
Is what they
They pay royalties
And I pay royalties
So when I realized
Is pow
Much money there is
In this I thought
That would be a good idea
And was it because of her
Meet with music in cartoons or just
Any music
It's any music but music
Cartoons music
Can be very proud
The ball in his a reason why
If you look at the sitcom
There are musical stings
So they have cumulatively maybe 2 minutes of use
Maybe three
Banana cartoon you have wall-to-wall
And because these collection agencies pay
Based on the number of Munich minutes that are
You would make a lot more money
Drama music on
You know a little known cartoon
Then you would make
On the Mary Tyler Moore Show or The Cosby Show
A lot more money how the cartoon how did you figure that
I called ASCAP and I said can you explain to me please GIF of the pocket in pocket
And I called BMI can you please
Explain to me Mickey Booker T Bucket and then I sat down and I calculated and I concluded
That being a member of BMI is the right way to go
And I went for it
And how did you
Create cartoon music what did you do
Well I want on that knocked on door of different
Cartoon producers
And I made them an offer they couldn't refuse.
And I said to them
I'll give you the music
Chick-fil-A free
If you let me keep
Book The Publisher share
As well as
The composer
And people said well that's not a bad deal we don't really pay all these composer for that then you'll do it for free
I'll just keep the royalty
So what cartoons do you
Did you make music
Stop it.
Inspector Gadget
Yeah there you go
Amongst many others
We work for Hanna Barbera Ruby Spears
Indeed
Filmation He-Man
Just you know tons and tons of cartoons at one point
My music partner
And I
Where
The top writers at the dma
Do you remember the Heathcliff 1
Heathcliff
If you're the one no no no no cheese Cliff Heath
Cliff no one should
Terrorize the neighborhood
Are you
Are you a fan of my music
Huge fan
Okay
This is good
So I mean how are you getting all of this music composed
Well
At a given point we have so much work that was no way
That one or two composers can
Satisfy
Get all of the hundreds of epi
Like we were scoring
At one point had 12 Studios 12 Studios just making music for car
Cartoons plug Studios making music for cartoons when people ask me what are you doing side make music for cartoons
I could see the compassion in their eyes cuz they thought it was no room for compare
I was making money hand-over-fist
Of course turning point in your life I guess
Happens when you discover the
Japanese
Live action
Show
Why which of course became
The Mighty Morphin Power Ranger
Tell me how did you
Come across this
Boconcept
Well in 1984 I was in
Japan
Nail stretching on my bed
Turn the TV on there only
3 channels
Two of them showing game shows
Alarms
Some other reality base
That I do not
Understand a word
And the channel had these
Kitchen spandex
Kicking monsters butt
And I thought
Hey
This looks like
Like fun
All of a sudden dawned on me that once they turn into
Superheroes meaning into Power Rangers
And they have the master song and there
Kicking monsterbots
It could be
Anywhere
The order of the action scenes
Which is what cost the most money
What basic be accounted for
Choctaw qualify shooting American segment with American
Kids
Being an American environment and I tie this up
Into the action
Sequence icon
Create a show
Very little money because all the action scenes
I will purchase
And
That that sounded to me like a great idea never mind the fact that I truly
Enjoy the show
It's funny I remember cuz I was at when I was a child we lived in Japan
From 1979 to 1980
U2
And remember I saw Mighty Morphin Power Ranger
Bears on television America I recognized it immediately
He has a show that I watched
As a kid in Japan
What's the show called in in Japanese
Jewelry
Meaning 10 Ranger
Teach you bought this in August 1980
Asics around them
No I bought it
And I slept it
Remember cartoon Slappy slappy
And I slept at 480
What do you mean you would you try that you went around trying to pitch people on the show for 8 years
Yes
Well
I just loved it and I thought
Daddy Scott
So many alipay
That we do
At the time getting
See
On America
TV
And then
I said to myself
My goodness
Been on
For like 20 years
Something
In Japan with such a
Access
Why in the world
Wooden yporque here
I know
That some people look at it.
Tempe cheesy I don't know I heard all kinds of definition
To me it's a lot of fun
Show
And everytime I look at the pilot
Over and over again
I just
Couldn't figure out why
People don't see it and what do they say when you started today
They said
Why do you embarrass you
Haim Saban creator
Of the Mighty Morphin Power Rangers in Roman
Where to find out how he not only found a home for his show but figured out how to buy his
Very own
Kids TV channel
On someone else's dime I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey thanks tour 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign
The campaign monitor
They took email marketing and made it
G-Eazy
So the big thinkers to focus on what they do best
Developing
Big Ideas
Choose from hundreds of
Specially crafted templates
Turn key design
Create campaigns
Results
The best part
Drag-and-drop editor gets the
The job done in
Try for free
Campaign monitor
Take your emails and business
Unforgettable
Support also comes from Luminaire
The only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah has a new podcast
With his new show The Daily Show host
Challenges himself and his listener
To explore unfamiliar angle
And embrace differing viewpoints
Listen to Trevor Noah's new podcast
Cast along with other original shows
Only on luminary
Visit luminary. Links built for your first two months of luminaries premium content for free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Garage
It's 1992 and Haim Saban has been trying to sell his idea for the Mighty Morphin Power Rangers 2
Anyone who would listen
I'm pretty much no one is interested
Until he gets a meeting with an executive
Xbox named Barker leche
And I'm like everyone before her
Margaret
Actually likes it
She's the only person who said
There's something there
Something there
She orders the show to air in 1993
And
We go and produce
40 episodes
Ruby strep
On the fox kids network which at the time is the number one Outlet
For kids
I'm producing it meaning I'm just there
Whatever
Script every outline
Every frame
Every daily every sound effects every piece of music every casting I'm not
You know letting this thing go to anybody yeah
Basically
What's wheat producer
There's a mutiny at Fox
Books from Rupert Murdoch on down and the group of a failure to basically say
This is
Horrible when not going to air it
It is
This executive Margaret Leschi
But she goes to Patrick
So what she said she said look
I can fight
All my bosses
The Tetra I understand all of that
So I'm going to add
Early in the morning
In the summer
And I'm going to Eric for 8 weeks
Disassemble
Summer of 93
Correct
And I'm done I'm going to take it off and will College
I said you know what I'll take it. I'll take whatever you give me
And did you buy the way you owns the rights to the show
You was still you hundred percent
So you take this deal because you will have no other choice you had to take it that's right yeah and she
Leave the net
Well even told her that she's playing her career by putting this show on just scrap it
But you believed in it and she just put it on and within
Blessed and a weak beat every other show across the generator
The highest rating of any show on Fox kids beat at the time you had.
Looney Tunes or Tiny Toons you had Batman you had all these shows that wear their head up box kit
And he delivered double triple the ratings of all these shelves to a course that 8 weeks
Was renewed right right away what area is she moved it to the afternoon right away because
What's up your monster head for her yeah I know I asked you this but I'm still trying to figure it out like how did
You know this is going to be
Escorting you douchka meaning in my cut
God is many times more important
London brain
I have to tell you that the biggest hits
That I had
In my life
Any music
Hunting television
And hunting business
Have been
Always
As a result of significant which action
And repeatedly
So every time I have an idea
That people tell me no don't do that oops
And if you are mean
When that happened when that show was a hit
Did you go to other people to die
Told you this was going to work hard for you just so I didn't have time
Whatever I got my own
What do you want from me
Okay so Power Rangers
Is doing great
And
To this point you got the
The production companies
Savannah
Entertainment
And then about a year later
It wasn't that
Fox
To buy your product
Well I'm approached
By Rupert Murdoch
GameStop at the time
This is what brand 90
Before 95
And
He has all kinds of Concepts that
He's putting on the table
And I was holding firm
P****
Money exchange hands
We would put our content into
A joint venture
And he would put
The network
Into that joint
You were basically saying yes
I hear you I am not looking to sell my car
Create a joint
Venture with you
Cracked I realize that they
Sweetie
Great to have a great piece of content that is a game changer
Sephora Network about to own that Network
What's the weather like
Fox new kids coming to you insane
We want to buy your production company and all your cartoons and you're saying
I'm only going to let you have that.
If you give me half of
Fox kids is that right
Yes
I'm just trying to
Figure out why Rupert Murdoch would take that deal and he couldn't you just
Do all this without you
Was running Fox Gazette to duplicate Berkheimer
Including his International distribution and present
Worldwide
How long will it take
And she said
I can do it but it
Mike me five years plus
And he wanted to know work right away
He walked
Presence
And that
Categoria and by doing this joint venture with me
He was instantly
In the worldwide
Christmas lights
So he basically agreed to give you
Half of fox
Kids network in
Change 4
Your distribution Network and the cartoons that you had
Then at that point you owned
Half of the kid net worth
Yes
I mean a pretty incredible
Gamble Utah
Because you rejected his original offer
Yeah I mean I wasn't going to do anything
Bring in a partner
Making a company I own.
Yeah
What what are you guys doing
What's your next move
Wellington movies
Call. Chase Carrie and Margaret last one day
She was a trace Carrie was a chief Hopper
Officer
And I said look I got this
Decide yeah we
We should be
And the 24/7
And that is only one channel
That is
Not part of a Bitcoin
Conglomerate
And that has folded
Distribution
That we can buy
Ins
The family China
Owned by Pat Roberts
At the television
Correct basically you wanted Fox
To help you convince Pat Robertson to sell it
Right
And they said to me
Well
I knew he would never
Giselle
Icilome
Well how about we ask
How about that
So they meet with Pat Robertson Pat Robertson they call me afterwards
They say
Monticello
But Tracy's going to meet with his son Tim
Tim Roberts
Pat Robertson son
Correct and maybe the price
To find some kind of GoPro
Joni Mitchell
A few days later
And I say can I come and you said no no
I said okay fine they didn't want you there because they thought you were going to be
Pain in the neck
Because
Maybe they were concerned that I would be too pushy or I don't know I don't know the answer is I don't know
Care all I cared about
Was the result
So he goes to the meeting with him he comes back and he says
Nothing to do
I said okay you're done
You said you would. I said okay I want you to come
To a dinner with Tim and myself
Movies.
Should be you should have a dinner with
Tim
And you should let me have a shot of
Let me see if I can convince
Right and we said the three of us at dinner and I said what I said
We left the dinner with a deal in French
What did you say to him that made him I don't want to get into what I told him I want to get
Into I can tell you that chase told me at the end of the dinner you're crazy man
What are you doing
I just don't worry about it we'll figure it out
Houseman has a bit of an egg so it's not anymore
Not true
What's not natural you speak English better than I
I was hustling okay you were hustling
Andy Robertson then says okay we have a deal. We had some sort of a joint venture
Concept
That we agreed upon that through the negotiation evolves
Into basically
Buying the whole chat
Open Fox pay for the whole thing and what they pay
1.9 billion
Which
That sounds like a lot of money what was it a good deal
No it was not
It was a fantastic
Okay so you have the deal
And you bought this
What was a Christian
Cable channel
Transitioning into a kid show was that was it hard to do that
No look I mean we converted the channel from the channel That targeted people
80 +
80 years old plus size of a day was a disaster Zone
Yellow from the demographic standpoint so we struggled for a couple
And then as we were turning the corner
I realize
We had built the company
That was
Worth between 5 and 5 and 1/2 billion dollars
Competing with companies that will work
10 to 20 times that
The Disney's off this
Miss World
And so on so
I came to the conclusion
That it's time to sell
Social wait this is about
5 years in
Yes
And so you have this channel
Fox Family
And then
What you decide you want to sell it right I mean you own half of it but then Suboxone half
It's like how are you able to sell
Seoul
I had the right
Based on my contract
Red fox
To put my share to them
Which I did
And we said
Negotiate
They told me that they thought my share was worth half a billion I told them that my share is worth 2 billion
Let's sit down and talk
Yeah but half a billion dollars that's a lot of money mean wow
But you could have walked away at that point with half a billion dollars in
Would have been up I wasn't going to walk away with a half a billion dollars that was not a shot in hell I was
Want to do that okay
My stake in the company's what do Belgium that's what I thought
So what did you end up doing into a pissing match with my boss
Give me a property to sell it
If I can sell it for four and a half billion dollars would you sell it with me so you're sure they said yes
That I ended up selling it for 5.3
What the hell did you do that
Whatever two potential buyers
When was CBS and the other one was this
And Disney was
Really
Very interest
Stead ndic
And they ended up putting up
The right amount of money
Tortillas
I mean that that meant that you play walked away with
Easily with more than a billion dollar
1 + 1/2
She become a billionaire
Overnight
Yes
Why was it so important for you to get a billion and a half dollars rather than
Half a billion right I mean
Was it the money that was
That was important was it
The principal or was it
Something else
What about
Important to me it was more about what is fair
Time in Douglasville
The fair price
For the asset
Anyways money
Was getting becoming really rich
It does that motivate you
You know it's awesome
Only
Money but it was also
Money is a marker
To success
Yeah
We could we could continue this conversation and talk about
You bought Univision and 2000
Sex
And then you know you eat
Cricket in Bessemer
Find like that
Is it
Is it work is it
Getting to a higher number is it
Is a recognition what is it that motivates you
The joy of working like what is it that keeps you going
Everyday
Look I don't collect stamps
And I don't play golf
Yeah you know I don't have
Hobbies other than playing my guitar this is
My hobby
That you're getting
Deals done and
Making Investments and so on
And look it allows me to do things that I truly enjoy
Witches
Give a lot of money
Back
This incredible
Country that has given me so much about Unity the United States
And Israel which took me in when I was a refugee
So there's a lot of gratification in that
When you look in the mirror
In the morning
Do you see Haim Saban
If this is billionaire Mogul or do you see that
Kid
Who was
You know doing his homework in the stairwell
EBay
Modest
Department building in Tel Aviv
I see neither
I don't see myself as a mobile node do I see myself as a
Impoverished
Child
I just see a guy hurrying golf to use
The next phone call or next meeting
Today he runs an investment firm it's called the Saban Capital group but he hasn't stopped
Cartoon The Mighty Morphin Power Rangers movie is out in the theaters and his name
Is it right there in the title
I'm glad that you remember the theme song to Inspector Gadget
Gabba Gabba the Inspector Gadget
Right where the song
It is one of the best theme songs I think
Eva it really is
Yeah it's
Almost as good as Go Go Power Rangers
That's a that's a power pop
Yeah I know that's
That's life
Guy you know Moon River
Yes yes I thought that was calls you a woo
And please don't turn us off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you guys are build
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors Squarespace
Do you have an idea for your neck
Big Move
You can use Squarespace award-winning designer templates to create a beautiful website or online store
Equipped with everything you need to run your business
Is it squarespace.com to start your free trial and use offer code build it
10% off your first purchase
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for POW you built that and it comes from Paul
Call Tucker of Yorba Linda California consultant in the beverage industry for the past 20 years
And over that time he's also been brewing his own beverage
20 years and pretty quickly realized that the magic ingredient in craft beer is the Hops
Start a brew with Hobson
One day I had some left over and it just hit me that the Hop should be enjoyed on more occasions and how come
It's only in craft beer
No that's not necessarily a question everyone would ask bacon Maybe
But hops
Who knew it's a very subtle flavor you know it's something that is really pleasing and really pairs well
Well with food and
The more I looked at it the more I said wow this could be a whole new category but instead of coming up with
Another artisanal chocolate bar or a
Hops infused cheese Whataburger new drink
Maybe even a drink with no alcohol
As much as I love craft beer you can't drink it on All Occasions so yeah I started experimenting and
Probably about a year of research and many failures and trying different varieties
Came up with something that I thought was just phenomenal but parking up with has no barley no yeast
No fermentation no alcohol
And best of all
No calories Paul basically made up
Hops flavored sparkling water
They think of
Bitter but you know there are over a hundred varieties of hops
And lobster we use these Aroma Hops at
Citrus
Send Pine flavors grapefruit
It's really complex
And what I consider the spice or the magic ingredient
So Paul took his creation to a beer festival in San Francisco and
At first he was a little nervous about what beer drinkers would think
But when people came up and tasted it people were like
Wow you know this is
Legit the flavor is really interesting and refreshing and
That's what I knew that it's not just me
Think about this for a moment
Sparkling water is super hot right now
Just ask the company that makes Lacroix and
It's no secret that craft beers huge
Paul disfigured put them together
And he's managed to get his drink
Into a few small retailers in restaurants
That he's not making a profit yet but this year
He's expecting sales
Adult and if I can get it to the point where
A big company would like to pick this up and distributed worldwide then you know I would feel
Fantastic about that
That's protector his company
200 PS
Is based in Anaheim California
You want to find out more about it and visit our face
Facebook page and
Please please also tell us your story as you can do that by going to build that npr.org
Let's build with a DV love hearing from you thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to fight
Find out more about it go to how I built this. Npr.org you can also write to us at hi
IBT at npr.org or follow us on Twitter has asked how I built this please also help us
Stop by subscribing to our show on iTunes or however you get your podcast and leave us review while you're there
It was produced this week by run teen Arab Louis you also composed music makes also teneva Grant
Santa's meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers AR intern is calabrian and Gyros and you've been listening to how
How I built this from NPR
Ava still listening in a lot of people ask me what podcast should I listen to
And I listen to a lot in one of my
Favorites is NPR's Planet Money
It's full of
Super fun
Insightful stories that explain all kinds of things about the world
Don't even have to care about
Finance or economics to love it
It's a great show and you can find it right now
Npr.org
Podcast or
On the NPR one app
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week