Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here and happy New Year
To all of you just a quick heads up that
Our team is taking a bit of a break over the holidays so we're running a few of our very
Favorite episodes from
The archives like
This one
Really love this interview and we hope you will too so enjoy
I left that morning for the office knowing that's the day and I was
Sitting in the office waiting
Heard was on the phone talking to the lawyers you know. Ended on the eyes and crossed
Cities on the contractors that day you're you're you're about to go and sign your name on the contract
That very day
Like within an hour We're we were ready to get in the car and go over
And I said I got to take a walk around the block
And so I did I went out to the parking lot and
Just started weeping
You couldn't even want to do it
Ramen PRP is how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
I got a show today
Dad's first name to create Clif Bar what are the most popular energy bars in the country
Energy bar with something you shut down your throat before running
A marathoner going skiing a whole aisle of Laura Luna and chia bars
Supermarket
And they weren't in the bottom of our backpacks are in the glove compartment of our cars
In around that time the late 1980s
Gary Erickson was living in the Bay Area he was one of those guys who would inhale energy bars
Right before a climbing or racing his bike
And also the time he was working at a bicycle
Which was fine
For a little while I think
All along I even through high school I think I always wanted to have my own business and even though managing
A manufacturing facility make your bicycle seat supposed felt close to have my own business and it wasn't my own business
And then
Crazy thing happen
That was my mom's
Kitchen table and she was serving me this
My mom's Greek and my grandmother's Cragin
They taught me how to bake a young age in my my
Mom is serving me something was like a calzone and we called a Greek calzone
And I looked at that and I said
You know I bet I could sell these
And so here I am of God
I work for the bicycle company and racing by his clothes and now I'm going to start a business
So we made a few in her kitchen I went out to some delis around Berkeley and San Francisco and
People will pick them up but what's inside of them
So we had different feelings
The typical Greek filling the spanakopita which is a spinach and feta cheese
They were really delicious
This wonderful brioche
What kind of dough
But
When I started this business I needed
To keep working so cuz I
Didn't have enough money size funding the business
With the bicycle
Tow company
2 fun
The small bakery that
I started called Kellie Sweets & savories with
Which was named after my grandmother
So at night you would like
The baking like all through the night and then get up in the morning and then let go work in the factory likes
Exact exact
And then one day in 1990
I was out on a
A ride with
A really good friend
We did this one long day trip in the Bay Area
Is 175 mile one day ride we thought it was going to a hundred
25 MI
And we took along with us
6 energy bars are on the market at the time the only energy bar really
That was on the market at that time that
So many cycles for eating does power bar
And they were also
Coincidentally
And so
We reach pack 6 of them
Pythor banana near to Andre
Did this ride where there was very few stores and
When were at the top of
Mount Hamilton I didn't five of those
Bars NEARBY
And I looked at the six month I just said no way
I can't I can't do one more
I would rather starve than eat another one
Why
Latest dare hard
They were they never really did taste good but we always as bike races we always thought of them as the bitter pill
They do the job but
It's not about taste
And here I have a baker
Free and everything we do taste great
We're riding down the hill or coasting down into San Jose to go
Get to a 7-Eleven
And I turned my friend Janice said you know what I can make a better energy
That was it
That wasn't me that was it and how was it
Literally the next day
I call my mom
And she had help me with all these rats
It's for the bacon
Mom I'm coming over and we're going to make
And energy
She's like what's an energy bar
Try to explain it to her and I said it's kind of like that great oatmeal chocolate chip raisin cookie that you make but we can't use butter we can't
You sugar we can't use oil
Chisel that's him
I said well let's just try so for the next 6 months
I brought over
Bags of
Ingredients that I have been researching on
And we're not talking about
Exotic ingredients were talking about whole ingredients cuz PowerBar was
Made with
Stuff that
Was more kind of Highly produced and highly refined
And
I wanted to be more like my mom's cookie
What kind of ingredients are you using
We were using whole oats
Real fruit
And a sweetener
We didn't use oil
Or better but we use a sweetener that was made from rice
And we met I met him in a rectangular so they were like a bar and wasn't going to be a cookie and had to be like a bar
And
We've had many failures
And at times you tried to talk ourselves into that this is great and it then I would
Bring it out to my friends in
Plastic bags that I was racing with and training with
Nice to hear try this but keep it a secret
And they be like who this
Terrible
Okay
Go back to the kitchen
At what point did you
Do you say okay I've got this
Think we got it so it was after about six months
I was
Sampling
Continue to sample it but we just knew my mom and I just knew like
Okay this is what we were looking for
And then you take a risk
You're not sure
And then you put a package around it
And that stories
You know what another real good friend that I was working with name Doug Gilmour in a week
I help them out with somebody advertising for the bicycle company and I knew that you was
Very very creative
Person
I said you need to design the package
And
She came up with
The climbing image
Which is now
Nephrosis iconic
And has a very
Deep meaning of
You know what that the introspection of climbing and
Especially an overhang the wait is yeah
Then we needed a name for it
And they're all kinds of names were where
Where
Considering
He wanted it to be Gary bar I didn't
And one day I was
Crescent
Does the Bay Bridge coming over to work on it with him and
My dad's name popped into my head
I'm picking
That makes sense I name the bakery after my grandmother
I can name this after my dad he's the one that influenced me
With the Great Outdoors this is about the outdoors this is about this is a connection with adventurous
You know taking it on the go
When you are Outdoors you and your adventures
Any perfect sense
And so we made a Clif Bar after my dad my dad's name is Clifford Erickson
Once you have the bar down the recipe down
How do you even have the money the resources to
Turn this into a business
Product that you were going to like put your whole life
I never ever would have thought it's turned into it has but all I was thinking was
I've got this Bakery
I can figure out how to make this if I can just take a small market share from power bar then I can
Continue my lifestyle and have the freedom of my own business
And do something that I love to do which is both run a business and make a great product
And that's that was easier said than done
Why is that
So
We
Try to make it in our Bakery we just didn't have the equipment
To do it
So I found a bakery down the street
Dad agreed to help me
Produce it like a like a mom
Like a cookie bake
And we
Leverage
The packaging companies and said
Will pay you
Will make a small run will give you what we can
And
When we sell the first
Amount will pay you
I mean back then I didn't really you know whatever
I was doing I was
I didn't learn this in college
And maybe it's a good thing I didn't learn this in college cuz I wouldn't have done it this way but I just started thinking out loud like how am I going to do
I have no money
So basically
You went to these
To the bakery you said I'm not going to be able to pay you right away
But then you would turn Rancid
Distributors in USA look
Can you pay me on delivery
And then use that money to
Pay the
Once you start a manufacturer
Clif bars like how did you even get
Anyone interested in them
You do did you like walk around or just shops
Saint stores in a couple things one is
Would go to
Bike races
Or went to running events
I just started passing out the bar
We did one ad
One advertisement
In bicycle magazine and a few other maggie's
That was pretty hard-hitting
I guess power bar just like
Okay there's a new kid on the Block kind of thing
Now the title or the headline was
It's your body you decide
So did you want
You want refined ingredients or do you want whole ingredient
Pictures of both ingredients
That cause
Has to be sued immediately
Oh wow
Car insurance picked up the
The tab and we ended up settling with tar bar
But it created this buzz in the bicycle industry where people said have you heard of Clif Bar
I don't think I don't know if you could pull that off now
And we were the
You know now there's
Hundreds of bars out
Just us and Them
Did you have to
Like go out and raise money that you have to ask
People to invest
In the company or were you able to do
To do
Somehow do it with very little money
You know I never thought of
Either looking for outside money or wanting outside money and maybe that was
A good thing if my knee naivete because
What you do that you know you lose control of your destiny
I tried to get a bank on my
I did
Get a $20,000
My father gave me
Office credit card $20,000
But most of it
Man I look back and I kind of think how did I pull this off
Because
And it wasn't big
Yeah this was just
A few bike shops in a few natural food stores
And
Yeah I remember being at a show like that
Marathon LA Marathon setting up a little table
And standing out there in the aisle with a tray of cut up bars and
And if people walk by say try to try this new energy bar and they were like no no no I've had energy
I'll come on just try it
And they try and then they would walk along and they wouldn't want to look back
Lyrica. You know
Did my embarrassment and then
32 minutes
Turn around
Come right back. What is that
And I knew I knew you had it then when
You saw that kind of response
And so the
It was Word of Mouth
And the word spread throughout the country
So what happened in that first year after you
Like like
I mean we were still
Working at the bicycle company
Yeah I was working the bus company for 2 more years still in it and I was using that money to as living hand-to-mouth in
No sleeping in the garage
And I was just using that money
To also fun
You know some of the extra bills
And then there was a Tipping Point
By the end of 1992
We sold $700,000
So you were making money within a year
I'm probably year-and-a-half
2 we really started
We started making
Hand
From there on it was
It was like a wild toads like a
Getting on a wild horse and hanging on we almost double tails for the next eight years in a row
You basically were the owner of the company right like did you
Did you make any mistakes by that point where you just sailing on was it like Smooth Sailing
No
One of the larger mistakes was
You know I caught a handshake deal with the time I
Didn't use
Corporate counsel very very effectively
Back.
You know what is vertu expensive
So I didn't really use a lawyer so I did a handshake deal with it
Distributor
In the early 90s
Where it ended up biting me
Because
They weren't performing and so I cancelled
Quote contract
And they came back and sue me for under
Too long of a story but it but it ended up we went to court
We settled in
It cost
A lot of money
I made a big mistake I never should have done a handshake deal on a distribution
International distribution deal like that
You almost lost the company
It yashow it was
It was a knockout dragout
Fight in
I
That was the most sick to the stomach
I had felt up to that point about business
One day when I we went to we went to mediation and I
At the end of mediation.
Oh my God I could lose this whole thing
So we fought we fight we negotiated it ended up being just pay him off
Cost a lot had to go get a bank loan
I went and visited like five or six Banks finally found one at a party
This guy talked to me and said yeah
I'm on
Tristan we went to visit with him and
They gave us the loan
And we paid it off in a few years
And then we're free
How did you like Coke without emotionally mentally like you had to run your company and you are fighting off
This other company that was trying to take you over
I I think I've learned a ton
With other things I've chosen to do in my life like rock climbing
My friend uses the term sharp end of the row
Which means when your rock climbing
You're either leading or following
And when you're leading are on the sharp end of the road
You could take a pretty big fall and I had done a lot of leading in my life on
In rock climbing
And I wouldn't you I was used to being in that
Position of
Facing danger but being able to stay composed
The weird thing is actually climb better when I'm on leave then
Phone
And I'm still trying to figure out that
How that metaphor works but it
Cuz you are you're in more danger if you're leading but I think I'm more focused when I'm
And so
I was on this big lead now I've got this
Lawsuit
I got the company drawing of got all the manufacturing issues and
Collections Bubba
But I think
Because that I was so focused
Nothing was going to stop me except something did Alma
Stop it and offer Gary Erickson and almost couldn't refuse it with this guy Roz
Listening to how I built this NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy
To add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Market
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO Lance
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
It's how I built this from NPR
Garage
Okay let's fast-forward a bit this is now
The year 2000
What about 8 years after a Clif Bar has large Den
It's doing incredibly well it's got a growing staff
Almost 40 million dollars in sales
And I should mention Gary Erickson has a partner in this venture
Beach have 50% ownership in
Company
And something else is going on at the same time
Big food corporations start to get into the game
Competitors
Empire Barbers already
Already sold and balance bars sold so it's just
It was kind of just us
Is the third
As a third
So we got approached
Bye
Travel companies
And
In a very uncharacteristic I kind of
Untied from the Rope
Abby non-lead and said
All right
I guess this is what you do
What do you mean what happened
We
Tired investment banker I mean long story short with her investment banker to put the company up for sale
Instead of us talking to companies which hire somebody to talk to companies and
It was an odd moment I can remember the exact moment that I got a call from my partner
She said I want to sell the company
All right
So
There we were we
But the company up for sale
And started traveling all over the
All over the country
Visiting
These large companies that wanted us to be part of their portfolio
And we got an amazing deal from one of the large companies are we got to do we got an offer for
$129 on $49 in sales on Quaker Road
I guess you heard
So you guys are sitting at the table
Quaker Oats as
120 million baht
Foxes in mm
He that meant you would have gotten 60 million
60 million
And you could walk away
And like
Did you seriously I mean you are seriously thinking about doing this
More than serious
We
Had
The deal
Essentially done
On April I know the date April 17th 2000
We were going to meet our investment banker
The people from
Quaker and as well as all the lawyers to sign the deal
And I would have been at
And we have told the company what we're doing till all the employees and they trusted us
It was a naive
Nice thing to say that things wouldn't change
But I still said it
And it was not true and I knew it wasn't true
Corset
It's going to change
It could be better could be worse but
You can't say
Change it
Yeah
And so I left that morning for the office knowing that's the day and I was
Sitting in the office
Waiting
My partner was on the phone talking to the lawyers you know.
Donnie Isaac Ross
Maggie's on the Contracting
She was she was ready to sell
Absolute
It was done deal
And her in her eyes
Could weight be
Because she was very fearful of the future
And understand that to some degree but
Why would people walk away from buying our products
If
We didn't
Sell the company
I never said I was for the three months that we were selling the company I was just living in the dark
I was not sleeping well I was not riding my bike I was
Probably not very fun to be around
And I said I just
I was fighting it
You're internally but not really
Picture of a counselor and talked about it probably would have gotten to that point
But there was and I started I started to
Have that
An amazing moment of just shake
I'm shaking right now is thinking of
Will you add that day your your your about to go and sign your name on the contract that very
Like within an hour We're we were ready to get in the car and go over
And
I said I got to take a walk around the block and so I did I went out to the parking lot and
I just started weeping
You couldn't even want to do it
They want to do it
I guess it's like
Noah walking
Kilt
I mean this was everything that you built right
Yeah this was
This was I put everything that this is my this is my life and this our employees and this is my family is named after
My dad
So what did you
What did you do what did you tell your partner
So halfway around the Bloc
I decide not to self company and then I felt completely free
Is like
Oh my God I'm free again
Now I had to go back around the rest of the block and forgot what I was going
Inside my partner
And I told her she's on the phone I said you can you need to put phone down
Tuna sandwich
And she knew immediately when I said that
That I was serious
And so
She was on the phone with the lawyer she said
We're not selling it.
She's in the room with all these
People
On the 30th floor of the Comerica building.
Deals off
So
Now
I'm in a new situation where
I got it now go back and convince our people that we're not selling the company and that it's going to be okay
We told him he couldn't do without selling and now we're going to know I'm saying we can
Secondly
My partner wanted out so I had to negotiate a deal
Until that was 7 months of negotiation and
And third was added as
Our attorney says Dialing for Dollars
I had to go find
$69
Ua256 $2000000
Basically by your partner
Because that's what you were offered to her argument was look that's what it's worth
Exact
So
I mean just think that you don't want to have to deal with as you're growing your business cuz
We were growing like crazy yeah
Sonoco share this deal
And
Decided that I would
Try to meet with the entire company every week
And hold a meeting
Two so that I could be in front of them
So they could see me every week saying we are not selling the company cuz they were convinced this is going to be a short-term deal and then I would go back
And sell the company and
I got calls from like
Private Equity groups that they heard what happened there like you are out of your mind you're never going to make it
You're going to get your never going to make it if you didn't have the debt and I have $69 with Dad and did you do things.
Did you ever think like maybe they're right maybe I'm not going to make it maybe I'm crazy like what am I doing
I must have been serving some good Kool-Aid at the at the office could people
Started believing that we have to do it
And it took us nine years to pay off that thing and we did it
Play nighttime Gary like
You could have
Taking the money and then like how this Charmed Life
Fan bike
Fish Den
Start a foundation and just kind of like
Gitana conferences and just given toxin
But there was something like what
What was the thing that prevented you from doing that from because that would that would have been an easier
Route you would have in the quality of your life
Like the things you can buy and own and Waco to live would not have been so
Substantially different
The Way You Lie
Live today
True to it would probably the same
Well obviously wasn't about money
There is
There is something deep about
You know wanting to
Grow this business
And
I mean I think my wife has
Very well you know what
It's the popular the power of yeah the power of a lot of money could be good you could
Don't need a lot of money to start a foundation
But the power of
A business
Done the right way
Is way more powerful than
To rich people
I don't want over to say that because
You know there's people that are doing some great things but yeah
As the company has grown be gone from 60 to 400 employees now you know our community service program Malone
Contribute over 10,000 hours of community service last year we couldn't we can't do that as two individuals but we can is a
Carrie Europe
Your dad
Cliff
Passed away
Is that right
Yeah it's kind of cool like his
His legacy like your connection damn lives on in this necklace
Listen to this brand this thing that we all by and eat
Clif bars helmets
That's really cool that
For 1
He was able to experience
Both
That bar
Named after him and
And the growth of the company
Yeah I'm just so happy that he did get to experience it for a very long time he was from Door County Wisconsin he would go to
Wisconsin on vacations and bring
Clif bars
He walking the bike shops
Hey Daddy what do you think of us bust
No real of quest
I'm Cliff
Like what
Your cliff
Oh my God
Make some noise celebrity
You versus this is
Disnary
CMS ology about entrepreneur
Where's that they are
Successful entrepreneurs are like
Single-mindedly focused
On the goal
Stick on in a
Believe in themselves
And have very little or no self.
Is that does that characterize you did you ever have
Any self-doubt
Did you ever
Did you ever have sleepless nights about what would shiver think what am I doing
I doing the right thing
Or were you just like totally focused and and
Confident in what you were doing and
Orange dad hat
The ladder
I can't remember a day where I didn't believe
And we would get through anything
I don't know where that all
I'll come
Comes from
I don't
No that's
That unique but
And I do think
Back to Summer
The
Adventures that I
Chosen to do
You know I'm not I'm not a super high risk
Person I don't believe in
I believe in climbing with a rope
But I do think it teaches you a lot
Because I remember years ago I climb the face of Half Dome and
I never once thought I was going to make it up
That face
It was just I was tapping her I call Happy nervous
I was nervous and
I was happy at the same time
There is no doubt we're going to make
Enough for a second
That anything would stop
What's for doing that mess just one of many
Climbs I've done and
Or sportbike Adventure
That's the same way I feel. Clif Bar
Years ago Gary Erickson
In step down as CEO at Cliff are you still super involved with the company and in 2010
Play kit handed over 20% of the company to their employees
Please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the
Things your building
Clippers quick thanks to one of our sponsors TD Ameritrade
People who set Define financial goals
Are more likely to achieve them
And TD Ameritrade can help you craft a plan that's aligned with your specific objectives
Tell TD Ameritrade about your goals
And then you can start building towards something beautiful together
The schedule a complimentary goal planning session
Visit tdameritrade.com podcast
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I know for how you built that and today were upsetting story we first ran last February featuring
Alec avedissian who had the idea
While he was working at
Surfing in a fishing Village in El Salvador
And one of my friends that was living in the community actually showed me the roofing
I want to go home
It was colorful and bright
And so it made us just look at it again today I think that's a billboard and it was the roof was made from
Part of a billboard that
You'd see on the side of any road
Metallica members thinking how could that work on billboards
Paper right that that roof is going to fall apart in a day
But then he started to do a little research
And I was like why I had no I didn't know the Billboards were made of PVC so it's a heavy-duty vinyl material so
Directly UV protected waterproof
Southern Roofing and durable enough to last me to keep the water out then they could definitely
Turn into some sort of product Alex figured all of that bright heavy vinyl
To be made into a really strong duffle bags and backpacks and things like that
So after you left El Salvador and move to Southern California
He started to make a few calls
I don't know anything about billboard companies
But I just started calling and once I told him hey you know I think I can save you guys some money can I have a few of them
Basic yeah sure
Turn that the ad companies were happy because they didn't have to pay to dump
The vinyl in a landfill
Alec was happy because it didn't cost a lot to
Get the stuff
Pretty much the cost of shipping
And we had his very first sheet of vinyl to cut up
He designed something he actually knows something about
I carry bag for his surfboard I figured a surf bag is like a pancake there's only two sides to it so I did Easy A
Best thing to make let's start with that but
It took him a while to figure out how to actually get it made so my first bag I took to a car upholstery manufacturer
Try to know anybody that did sewing and that first bag actually looked good enough for Alex have want to make more
So fast forward a couple months and Alex start selling these surf bags in sport shops around La
They start to Branch out into other products like backpacks and phone covers
From one billboard we can get upwards of 150 backpacks and
Probably around a thousand phone covers at least almost every one of their products is unique different shapes
Different splash of color because
Each item is cut from a different part of a giant Highway advertisements Virgin Airlines
Alaskan Airlines
Gucci Pepsi Billboards washed and cut at a warehouse in LA County
Eventually found a factory in Mexico that does all the sewing turn it into product
That's Alec avedissian on the company rareform in Agoura Hills California
Since Alec was first on the show rare form has been on Shark Tank and the company started turning a
Profit and has grown a lot
It got a partnership with Coca-Cola
He started selling their bags
Disney parks
And REI
And all this growth means rareform is now repurposing over 1000 billboards
If you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up
And thanks for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes Good how I built this.
Npr.org please also subscribe to this podcast and apple podcast or however you get your
Lore podcast you can write us or email addresses HIV tea at npr.org are Twitter is at
How I built this was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music thanks also
Immigrants and Mexican poor and Jeff Rogers our intern is Diana I'm guy Roz and you've been list
Listen to how I built this from NPR
I'm Stacey Vanek
I'm cartafreccia and we are here with a new show
Jenna kator
Planet Money
On every show we take some number in the news
And we
Dive into it to find the big idea behind it
Get it on NPR one or wherever you get your podcasts
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor.