Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey everyone we've been really really busy this summer on the road with
Live shows
Just got one more happening in Seattle in mid-september and
Right now it is officially sold out
Please keep checking Twitter and NPR presents. Org
Because we may have a few more tickets for you by early September
Antique
Because we've been pretty busy with all this life stuff for got play a show from our archives
This week it's one of our favorites
Amazing story about how a single mom built
Nvidia Empire
So here it is
About who
You discuss your hard times with because those who love you and care for you the most like your mother
Like your best friend
Don't give you the worst damn advice in the world
You need to get a job you should be sleeping on the floor in a sleeping bag
From NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
I'm Gyros and white Cathy Hughes refuses to take no for an answer
How that helped build one of the biggest African American-owned businesses in the country
So it's possible you've never heard of Kathy
Hughes before
But the company she started radio one
It became the largest African-American owned broadcaster in the US
It's not called Urban one and it has more than
50 radio stations in media Outlets
All over the country
Exactly Stumble Inn
Grew up in the 1950
Omaha Nebraska
Even when she was little
She couldn't stop talking about
She wanted to do
I wanted to be the
First African American
To have a syndicated radio show
I've had that desire since I was
8 9 10 years ago out
So you want to do from childhood
It's so interesting
When I go back to the high school that I graduated from that every single solitary week send a note home to my
My mother seeing she talks too much
Like I'm practicing for my future career
Eye of
Grew up in a household where they were sick
One back
And I did my radio show every morning in the mirror with the two
Toothbrush
And no matter how many blows my brothers and sister with ghettout Heap upon my head when I finally opened the bathroom
Door so they can get ready for school now
I never
Came out of that bathroom every morning
Until I finish my radio show
Everyone thought at that time there was something wrong with me
I mean
There are no black people in radio Pachuca Lino black women could begin remember we're isolated in the middle of the United
In the 1950
Is it 1950s exactly
And so they thought I had a pipe dream by nuns at my school described it as delusions
The branch
Tell my mother that she perhaps you seek
Sling for Mac
Because I had this vision
I being on the radio and
People hearing me from coast to coast
I guess you have a stream and a lot of people think you're crazy but you
I want to pursue it
But then
As a teenager I guess
Steam to get
Get pregnant
First sexually
Variance
I'm in the doctor
What is all the tea tells me I'm pregnant I said I couldn't be able to have sex one time
Is I hate to surprise you Kathy but it only takes one time God
Arranged it that way you shocked when you found
Arrested Development
No question about it I went into a satyr
State of shock but
I realized
That I had
Mission I had an obligation
Did someone greater than myself
And I was determined that he wouldn't be a black scientist
I was determined that he and I would not grow up in the public housing
That I have grown up in
I was determined
That he was going to have an opportunity which meant that I had to be very serious
Purpose
Why was still
Young teenager a child myself
But still pretty hard you know.
Try to support yourself and your
Child
Yes but I'm third-generation entrepreneur
So I grew up having to work in a family business
110 years ago my grandfather started to school after being the first black
To get his EDD
Comparable to a PhD
And my father was
The first African American to graduate from Creighton University with a
Degree in accounting
He opened up a tax service
And I was in charge of the Prentice Hall Ledger switch where all the tax regulations that changed every week
I
Typing
10 years old I was taking shorthand by the time I was twelve and having to be proficient at it because
I was a staff person
My family kept imposing upon me to come to work okay
So even though you know pregnant is sick
16 a mother at 17
Sounds like how did you do it financially while I was already working
And I was very blessed
I say this too young but this is easy to be a teenage mama
When the baby still in
Infancy
Because
All they do is eat
Go to the bathroom and sleep
That's all they doing cry little MBA
Between
And so I could take him to class with me
When you enrolled you enrolled
University
Yeah and I took him a lot of University of Nebraska at Omaha
I have put him right he be riding a carriage on the floor
Add butt
It became a problem once he got up
Start walking
An Institute
Did you work at like the College radio station
Yes I volunteer to that radio
Stationary provided
A voice for us in Omaha
In the city that was
Severely sacred
I read that
The why you were there
You mad
Someone who
University
Change the course of your life
Yes Tony Brown an African-American host
Tony Brown's Journal
Comes To Town
And give me you're wasting your talents in Omaha Nebraska
You need to be
Where you can really have an opportunity
To do
What you want to do what you do with radio
10 years later
He was offered the opportunity to establish the Howard University School of communication
Has he became the first
And he asked me if I was interested in coming to Washington DC
So you move
Halfway across the country
For five year old son
At the point and
Find apartment and you start working to see that you did not know you had got lost
I can't tell you how many times I would go out New York Avenue
And get lost or I'd go out a street that hits name change Virginia some mornings
Washington
Do you like to
Do you mean you come from Omaha Nebraska
Which one to tell you about a letter I wrote my mother admitted
I told her that my eyes actually work
Tired at the end of the day staring at the greatness of
Black people
I had never seen so many wonderful people of color doing so many wonderful thing
I actually put in a letter to my mother that my eyes
Retired at the end of the day of just staring
It was a person. Still am to be very honest
I mean
There's no city like Washington DC in the whole wide world come to the city
The 70s from
Kelly Whiteside
Buy thank you black people in charge
Keto diet and weight
Doing my whole generation in the nation's capital is Ali gotten better
I've gone from watching a black mirror get elected to watching a black president get elected
Okay sweets
You get to
Howard and
DC and
I was the sales manager
Play music at that time
Play jazz
One night
They did an 18 minutes
Long
Piece of Pharoah Sanders
And I think he held the note the entire time
Okay
18 minute jazz song all you heard was this one
And I was like I can't
Celibate
So your job was to find advertisers to advertise
Is on the house but also to help
Define
How the radio
Just a mess oh my God
It was it sounds like the kind of place
Cuz it was a mess
A young person like
Opportunity in your 20s
Could take it over absolutely and the fact
That the den Dien
With a big fan
Of my work at
I think he said you need to see can you teach these kids how to work like you folks or Nebraska work
I always believe
Bad rising at 4 a.m.
And then getting dressed
I'm leaving
By 5:15 5:30 for the office
That was just my lifestyle
Amston Lake
I have been reared to believe which again so critical
Entrepreneur
Bet you don't stop based on what the clock says
You stopped based on the accomplishment of the task
July
You're in DC with your son by the way how are you doing all this is
Is a single mom
We Are One
Often times people ask me do I get if I had anything to do over what would it be it would be to have more chill
It was easy with him remember I told you start off taking him to college with me
So
He had his first little tuxedo before he was at a great school cuz he was my date I took him everywhere
I had a sleeping bag in my office
We have dinner together we would do his homework
Then I put him in the sleeping bag until it was time for me to take him home
I didn't know anybody I didn't have anyone to leave him with
So what were you able to do at the station at that time I mean you get there as early 70s
The first thing was to create struct
Do I realize that the first thing they needed
It was an understanding of the atom
Ignoring opportunity
Keep giving them
So how are you able to
The Quiet Storm
Tell me about The Quiet Storm
It was simply
Recognition of the fact that the city had a size of
Population of single
Unattached human beings who
Still wanted to
To feel good about a Friday night or Saturday night
All they were missing
Was the entertainment
So I structured
File format called The Quiet Storm
This is your picture.
The basically was a 5-hour
Presentation
Entertaining you at home by yourself and do you company do that
With the selection of music
Before Hip Hop
If you were going to be
Successful in the world of black music
You had to tell me
Story with your music
And so all I did was
To weave those
Stories together
What were you playing
Oh
Sam Cooke
Carmen McRae
Dybala tears basically
How did that show takeoff how to become popular
Well I hit the right
Target demo
And I guess we should mention that the audience was
Predominately African-American
Interesting Lee enough my first audience
Escape predominately gay
I put the first openly gay are personality on the are at Howard and almost lost the top of my head
Because of it
So the gay community absolutely love the quiet storm and then the black community Michael
Great it's absolutely Word of Mouth
And it went from like number 36 in the ratings
It's to like top 5 and it when I left we were number three so you have this incredibly successful
What career at whur-fm decide
You know I think I can do this on my own like no it not at all not at all
There was a group of investors called the Washington broadcast
And it's 32 board members and investors
Stay included some of the most distinguished black-and-white washingtonians
They had tried
Well over a decade
To get a
Signal that was dark back on the air
They've gone through millions of dollars and they could not get the signal
Only are they wanted to revive a radio
Yes they wanted this dark signal they had lkmm but they had spent all
They spent their money in all the wrong places
They approached me
And offered me
Double quit Howard University
He was paying me but more importantly they offered me the opportunity to build
Substation from the ground up
So these owners they they bought the station and they hired you to run
Yes
They hired me to get it on the air
Then they hired me to run it
Then they ran out of money so they told me to shop a package for financing
And I said to them that that's not the responsibility of a general manager
Did I will do that
If you give me an equity position in your company
And one of the members said to me
If you think that you're smart enough to own a radio station you should do it for yourself we're not giving you any equity in arts
Station
He was being facetious but
I took it verbatim
Seriously
I was like oh my
He was right I should do it for myself guy I'm not exaggerating
It was like a charge went through me I said oh my goodness
This person who's a multimillionaire who I have been admired who's now probably in their 70s
Is saying to me here I am to know
Billy 30
I'm smart enough to do this with them
Eddie's challenging me
If I think I should own part of their station do it for myself
Thank you Lord I hear you I hear you I literally
Literally
Put all my papers in my case
If not walk
Down the hallway from the board meeting
Alien life
What just happened
Did she have a nervous breakdown or something I knew what I was destined to do
Cathy Hughes founder of radio one coming up the story of how she did
End up buying a first radio station the first of dozens and how it goes really days and she live
Literally lived in that station you listen to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your
Long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini the regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So it's late 1970s
Is and Cathy Hughes
Just walked away from her job managing a radio station
Start around
And she's looking for stations that are
App for sale
If you happen to find one
A black AM station
In Washington
DC
It has fallen on Hard Times
So
She decides to buy it
What were they asking for
$1000000
Wow this is like 1980 know this is 1978 we didn't get it till tank teenager
78 to buy the lights
You want to come over
The million. How much money did you have in your bag
So that's what you had
Yeah that's what I had was anyone else waiting for the station
There was everyone at that time Senator Edward Brooke had just left the United States Senate
The first time since you know reconstruction date
All he was a bitter Muhammad Ali was bidding for everybody wanted to do our nation's
The station against a former Senator and Muhammad Ali yes
So how did you get it I had
An angel
Dewey Hughes and I were married at that time and he at worked at the station
So when do we went to the owner and said
My wife and I would like to buy the station
He's at where the world are you going to get the money
Where did you get the money
Did you get a bankson
If 32 of them
32 Bunnell
3030 Linden NC
Estheticians and all of them said no
We're not going to give you a million.
And you should because none of them had
And all of them said no
We're not going to give you a million.
They asked me questions like that I plan to have any more children
They asked me if
Did not think that I was
Too young to be doing this taking on that level of responsibility
They asked me questions
Since it had nothing to do more often than not
How did you go to
2:30
2 Banks
Get rejected
Affectionate
Show me the number I told you that my father was a CPA
I knew the law of
I knew that if I can
Kept asking
I guess hat
So how did you
Female Banker first
Week on the job Lydia Ko
Chemical Bank of
Said that she thought that her first loan her first
Puerto Rican and she probably guess that it would be a male
Cuz she was bored
She said yes and I just kept by now
My presentation
Should have been taught in
Oncologist
Was flawless I mean after 32 times of perfect okay
I should have gotten an Academy Award I was so good at it I can't
Condensing her
And she said something to me that I teach you all myself
She said
Please don't
Self pass
Close
And I never forgot that cuz that was another one of those slap-in-the-face as I was like wow she's absolutely correct she said
I couldn't believe she is
What you said yes you kept telling her on
I kept trying to convince
So you get the money and you buy this
Station
Where was it by the way
1680 Wisconsin Ave
And you walk in that part of Georgetown
In the highest tradition
Adversity
So that's why I moved into
Wheatley sorry start
You because I had to pay rent in Georgetown
And 1680 Wisconsin was then and still is a beautiful valuable diagonal
Please set on the corner piece of property made it real convenient to go to work in the morning I walk down the hall
Son and husband
I know I moved in there with my
Said by then my husband was like
Enough I don't want to do this is your marriage
Fell apart absolutely the station broker
The debt
Was just
Overwhelming for him getting ever been an entrepreneur
Never having been in business before Eva
So it's just me and the kid
How many years did you guys
Junior Summer
Almost three
No
Number one that can remember the part of the story I told you that I was just in awe of what
See I'm in Georgetown I've been able to move back there yet okay during my struggling days
I had
A prime Corners you would see the president having dinner at one of the restaurants
Under
A lot of financial
Pressure right
So how did you deal with that
When you have overwhelming Financial
Applications
The first natural
Human impulses to hijack to recoil not return the call
What would I have been trained to do
Display offense
Not defense
So I would call
My lenders
And I would say I know I owe you ten
All I have is $1,250
I'm sending it to you
As a token
Good faith that I will repay you every since
That I owe you but right now this is all I have
And most of them
Said that they had never ever interacted with anyone who let them know up front that they could not
I think that is the reason I've never been foreclosed on I've never had to file for bankruptcy and thing
Thank God I have never had a paycheck bounced I've never had a business check
Nor personal check balance
Because I tried to stay ahead
Of the issue of not being able to pee
The dead people
Like we're depending on you
Are salaries right
I was running a
24-hour seven-day-a-week broadcastify
Facility with 14
Full and part-time employees
Total
14 of us and you were one of the people who went on the only thing I don't know how to do a spider up the transmitter who had to go
On the air
Because you didn't have enough
And what did you do just opened up the mics
Start talking
Well it started off
Because
We did for the color format
And we found out it was missing in Washington DC
Was news
Talk from a black
Perspective
Put that research did not
As you well know here NPR is the most
Expensive format that you can do
Correct music is one person can
Play the music read the news do everything
It's a one-person
When you talk about
News
And our talk and information
Researches critic
Cuz there's always
Someone you're listening audience who knows more than you
And just
Waiting there in the cut
Oh no that's not correct okay
You can't do it by yourself
In this format
How are you able to run
The station administer the station
Deal with the stress of all that
I bet and raise it
The kid and have a show
How many hours to show by the way
4 hours
4 hours ago everyday indicted 10 a.m. how are you able to do all of that
Because it was exciting
But that's
When you said the stress of the debt it was
Don't stress I have no doubt that I was
Either you need to brag
I used to
To brag to my lead investor syndicated communication site
I will be the most
Comfortable
Company in your portfolio one day and they were like yucky
Okay good great keep that dream alive Kathy
I used to tell them
You will make more money off me and my cup
You've made off anyone in now this is what I'm also telling them that I can't make my payment this month
If you think
Oh it's overwhelming
I've got all this dick
I can't sell anything
I'm working 18 20 hours a day
Then it's too hard
You can't do it
But when you know
That the day is going to arrive
When you're going to have enough money to pay everyone that's what you have to see in your mind's eye that's what you have to boo-boo
And I saw her
Yeah I knew it I could feel it
And that's when I was in the sleeping bag
Cooking on a hot plate and washing up in the public bathroom in the radio station at 6
1680 Wisconsin
I felt it I knew it
I just knew I had to
The hold on
And when
You're starting off in business
Have to be so very cure
About who
You discuss your heart times
Because those who love you and care for you
The most like your mother
Like your best friend
Don't give you the worst damn advice in the world
You need to get a job
You shouldn't be sleeping on the floor in a sleeping bag
What type of environment is that for a child
Kathy was
The station
Profitable Pro
Pretty quickly
7 years
So what was it
That made you guys
How did you get to
How did you get Jaden Yuki profitability
Doctor Martin Luther
Sweeping the floor
Date
The best of Europe
In one day
The world is going to say nobody
Sweep the floor better than
So it is that when you started
Yes I realize
Stead
I could not
Survive we just a little thousand watt a.m. that I had to grow I either had to grow or I have to go
In Richmond
Stations yes
Because our specialty is weird turn around
What they all have in common
De-stress station got it
We took distressed properties and turn them around
Because we could afford them
Did you get the money to buy them
Again if your lenders know that their money is good with you they give you more
Alright lenders don't invest
And ideas everybody's got ideas
The invest in you
People loan money to the
Person not to the business
To the idea
They have to feel good about you
How many stations
Did you eventually
Bye
Fake that we were up to think 35
So
What
Was the point where you sad
Let's go public
Let's make this and that you've 38.5 I did my son went to Wharton and got his MBA
And walking across
Campus
Of UPN
My son says
Tumi
Do you still believe that we have to grow Argo
Nice of course I believe we got to go
He said that we have to
Because we started
And with the deregulation
11% of all radio stations in the United States of America home by one company
It's kind of hard to compete
Could you over here with two or three I mean they would come into a market they have five Power House Radio
Stations with one format
Eliminated all the competition
So we knew we would that we had to grow in
Scale we had to get much larger head so yes
We had to go public we had no choice
A lot of people told us that they didn't think that they would be a wise decision
For us I tried to discourage us we had a couple fall start
But it was the best thing they could have happened ad
The other thing that we have done
In our company as we stay in our Lane
We're not trying to open a restaurant
You're not trying to go into concert promotion
We stay in
The Telecommunications
Industry
At the height of already won how many
How many stations did you guys actually have
75 stations which was the height when we bought
A package of stations from Clear Channel
75 they had never been done and urban broadcasting before were you able to retain a significant
Share of the ownership after you went public
Yes
Not just own but also the voting stock
Which owl has again been a blessing
The same syndicated Communications
37 years ago who sit down and showed me how to write my first business plan
They're still in business
Sex with me
You haven't really talked about his
Discrimination
Because
You must have
A lot of it not only as woman but
Is an African American woman
Yes
One of the the issues that has always faced
Entrepreneurs of
Is
The
Lack of available
Capital
Put them to go into business or to maintain their business
I remember there was a bank
NDC rig
And I had a big contract
But the payment
Coming in slow
And
It was so interesting because a black Banker
Deutsche bank
Said to me you would loan her 50
$10,000 to buy a car
But you won't loan her 10000
Dollars to make her payroll
And yet she has the contracts showing that the money will be coming in
So often has been easier for entrepreneur to buy a new flashy car
And it's been for them to meet payroll which is the tragedy of us not having as many lending Institution
Actions in our community as we need and want
Just like I still
Which is
You face
All these challenges and you kept
Golang
What was it that kept you going
A belief in God
Because when you really believe in God you can believe in yourself
As I said
Betty I quit my job
Not knowing where the next
Piece of money was trying to come from where the next chapter
Who's going to come from I knew that I would be sitting here today talking to you
I believed it because
I believe in the power
The Creator
And I used to never ever
Give a speech for accepting award writing first
Thank God
And I still do but back then when I first started
They said to me they ain't nobody
Interesting all that religious I said that's not religious
That spirituality there's a big difference in my book
Between being loyal and understanding
Yourself in relationship to Creation
I have one last question
This energy this glow this
Choice
Passionate
Intensity that
And in this
Unshakable
Belief
Will work
Is it something that
You have that
That is
Specific to you or do you think it's something people
Can actually learn
Oh
Definitely an acquired skill
If you
Allow yourself
To be
Bog down and lose your enthusiasm
Then you're dead in the water
But if you remain optimistic
Cheerful and committed to your goals
There's nothing that can stop you
Cathy Hughes founder of radio one company is now called Urban one
By the way Kathy son Alfred that little kid in the baby tuxedo he is now the CEO of the
Company
And please stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the
Things your building
The first two quick things to one of our sponsors think about your eyes.com
So much of what kids learn
Come through their eyes
Take care of them by visiting an eye doctor yearly
5 1
Think about your eyes.com
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
And I'll tell you the story that we first ran in January
It's from Nashville Tennessee
My name is
Dr Mike Butera
I'm the founder and CEO of artifen makes musical instruments which
What's a natural mood for my
Because he plays like a few dozen instruments himself
Dinner party with a bunch of Musician's Friend
Then after dinner we wanted to play music together
But we didn't have any instruments
We just had
The phones in our pockets
So they hooked up their phones to computer speakers
Launch some music making apps
Start the jam
But we were just staring at our screens
We really wanted to interact with each other or
Get lost in the Music close our eyes like Mick Jagger Keith Richards
And then
Mike had an idea
I thought what is the speaker had a guitar
What is this speaker had
Keys on it what if it have a little drum pad
I just wanted the speaker to become
A musical instrument
So am I called up some of his
Engineer friends and ask them
Album billboard
This is what they made
My digital instrument that looks kind of like the neck of a guitar
Sounds like well
Like almost every instrument
You can imagine
It has a fingerboard and a row of buttons that can be streamed
What's happening
Can hold it like
Guitar
You can hold it upright like an upright Bass
But you can also set it down on the table or your lap and play it like that
Piano or drum pad
And when you put it on the violin setting you can actually hold your iPhone out
Move your iPhone around in the air
And that will act like a bow
Mike says it took them that 6 years to get the instrument
Just the way they wanted
Which isn't necessarily A
Silicon Valley style way to do it
It
What's more in arkaso a Nashville
Which is go into Studios with musicians and see what works and go back and refine it and and really
Look at the craft of building this
Since we last spoke with Mike
He's raised over $1000000 on Kickstarter and he's been selling his device
Just called instrument one
On Amazon and Urban Outfitters
And last month
Mike picked up some of the instruments
Took them to a big music retailers convention and well if they was kind of daunting
Against the big players in the industry
Fender and Gibson
Yamaha and Korg and Roland
Yeah and we're in this little booth
Next to the wall
But a lot of people stopped at the booth and tried out the instrument
We got best in show
Which was
Great especially because
We looked very different than most of the instruments
But because instrument one is so different
It's been kind of hard for Mike to attract investors
We talked with a lot of feces around the country
And they say
Hardware is not quite as hot as it used to be where more into software now
Figure that out
Get profitable as a hardware startup
Then we'd be interested in helping you scale as a software startup
So Mike is still trying to work out how to make
The instrument one profitable
Since he launched it two years ago he sold about 5000 of them
And now he even has a small team of people working with
We've had
A great time
Getting out there seeing the music people are making even just this morning someone posted
A brand new video of this one man band Jam next to a river
Just amazing stuff everyday
Tara of Nashville
His company is called artifen and his product
Is called the instrument one
And you can read more about artifen on her Facebook page to search how I built this on Facebook and of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build
NPR. Org we love hearing what you're up to
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or here previous episode
You can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Elsa rytas that's HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send us a tweet
It's at how I built this
Usher this week was produced by run. Abdel-fattah with original music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva grants a Mexican for Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
Gyros near listening to how I built this
NPR
Gregory Warner here to tell you about NPR new international podcast called rough translation
Each week where to take you to a different country to hear a story that reflects back on something that we are talking about here in the United States
Maybe get a perspective shift
Travel with us
Rough translation is on NPR one or wherever you get your pie
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week