This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who understands every small business is uni
Impaler's it's Palace
State your business is very specific
Get a quote or purchase a policy
At h i s c o x.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Before we start the show
I tell you that's really exciting news is that we're doing
Two more Live Events
Supported by American Express open
Before the end of this year
The first one will be right here in Washington DC on November 30th
My guess will be Robert Johnson who founded bet Black Entertainment Television
The second one is in Atlanta on December 6th
And I guess then we'll be Arthur Blank who co-founded Home Depot and who now owns the Atlanta Falcons
Tickets for both shows are going on sale soon so
Keep checking NPR presents. Org
I got more
Okay
I was so freaked out the first day
I literally couldn't speak I just stood there people would ask me questions like how much
What's the style number and I like Frozen
Help me out saying no
Headlight
Robin PR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
And the movements
Introverted interior designer got over her Eileen Fisher
A multi-million-dollar clothing company
For women
So if you know a little bit about that clothing in this
The Giants
Specially for women's apparel
I Brands like Chanel and
Versace and Prada and
Of course H&M and Zara
So given that Eileen Fisher does about 300 million dollars a year in Revenue
It's comparatively small
But in women's fashion
The brand is also incredibly influential
And not just for the designs but how Eileen Fisher started her company
To be precise
With just
$350
She never took a dime from outside investor
And she still owns about 60% of her company
Her employees
On the rats
Now you seen the clothes you'll know that they're pretty spare and minimalist
Loki butt
Also elegant
Which is
Describe Eileen Fisher
Funny because lately I've been kind of calling my selfish IX
I think I don't know that I'm wired so much that way I just think that's something
I was kind of shut down when I was young
I know
Classroom I remember they were like
Kids in my Catholic
School classroom and
Images always say for 2
To hide and to be small and
Not speak
Ellen grew up in a middle-class family in Des Plaines Illinois in the 1950s
60th Street
Five Sisters
And a brother
Her dad worked
Accountant for a local company in her mom's
Spent her days at home doing laundry
Cleaning and making dinner for all nine of them
I think but I mostly remember is my mother
You know they're kind of unhappiness I think I was hard
Beijing seven children then
I think she felt it was her job to do all the hard work
My dad felt
You know his jobs to go to work and make the money in
Come home and be taken care of after that so
She would
Pretty much
We we start ranting and raving all day
And then my dad would come home and just before my dad would come home she would
Get dressed
Academy already in
Sometimes you can put on lipstick
And
I just remember
I was about to say
Extend my mother had breakdown
And my father said that the
Next day
He was driving to work
Andy pettitte
Pull over on the side of the road and he broke down crying realizing that
He had thought only a few days before that these are the happiest
But they were happy
Let me know there were a lot of Happy
Moments
Yeah we played the kids play you know we had the neighborhood
Suburbs and bikes
Reply
Canik 9mm a good humor truck came down the stairs
We got ice cream things like that
So you know pretty much your tip
Suburban experience
Aileen wuornos
College at sea
University of Illinois in the late 1960s
Any real idea what
She wanted to do
Started out as a
The math major
But eventually
She decided on
Interior design
You know it
Just love fabric
Coloring
Playing with the shapes and
That's my mom for second I had sold with my mother when I was younger
So that was some of my
Happy memories with my mother
I used to have you
Picture in my mind
Clothes I want to wear
We would go shopping
I love being the Fabrics
My favorite place
In her early twenties Eileen moved to New York with a friend
But with no real plan
Skip this one 1972 when you
You could actually find an apartment in Manhattan for a hundred bucks a month
Search parent Eileen started doing some freelance graphic
Design gigs
Eventually
She got a job working with a Japanese graphic designer named sushi moora
I was an assistant so I started this
Doing whatever needed to be
And
We design logos
And we designed packages
Thanks for banks and
Then we did stuff for Japanese clients
Can be urine
Things like that
And
After a short while we were like working together and
You know we ended up getting into a relationship
She was like
Oh no
And were you
Traveling to Japan
Bright
Right so this is exactly where the clothing idea came from
Ice that we started traveling
We took two trips
Together two
Japan
I'm just trying to imagine like this is the
I guess the
Mid-to-late
70s
7 year flying from New York to
Japanimation pretty glamorous right and that was a big deal
Yeah I guess
So
It was also kind of stressful you know I felt
Pressure and
You know I couldn't speak the language so
Tried hard to learn it
There was glamour yes I guess
You know
But I'm not I don't I'm not so attractive
Glamour I am always more uncomfortable with glamour Sam this uncomfortable person that's why I had to make you comfort
Football gloves
What what struck you about
About design
So you came across in Japan
Hello
Simple and beautiful
Temple really
And fall I could
Really see like with kimono for example
1 shape
You know for thousands of years and
You know
They were just
Do you know use different Fabrics in different techniques
To make it
Different every time and
And it was beautiful
Beautiful and
That inspired me
How long did you did you work with is it was real
How long did you work
About
4 years
And
I mean that
Of course anytime there's a
Professional and personal relationship that this can also always often causes some complications
What was that
Does that sort of begin to unravel your personal relationship begin to unravel your professional relationship
God
Yes definitely it was all connected
We thought we could split up and work continue to work together but that became
Clear Within
You want that was just not going to work
But yeah so I ended up
Separating getting my own little Loft eventually after about a year of bouncing around and
Hiding a little space in a Lofton
Rebecca and you lived and worked
Where I lived and worked
And I was stumbling around doing
Still in office
I know some Japanese clients still and then some
Other
Work I was
Stumbling around and getting I don't even know how I feel
The pack
Cuz it was really
Day by day and it was it was
Freelance like
Design work
Apartments I did a few apartments
Small office
Dentist office tinkler whatever I
And trying to survive
Pay the rent and you know
Keep working as a designer and not go back to
Working as a waitress at my one commitment I was going to end up
Waitressing again I hadn't done that in many years and I can let go back to
And then I met him
People and that's when
I thought I had been kind of cooking on the side
Idea
Of the
And the clothing business and cooking on this idea
Already in the early 80s
Oh yeah
It was it was in my mind for probably five years before the first garments appeared to make your own clothes or two
Find clothes that was in your mind right to try and design idea come from
I don't know I think some of it was at when I was trying to get dressed
Let me know if the Japanese clients and you know the different I want it I need it
Look like a designer and what did that mean
What does it mean to look like a designer put together and no no
Clean and elegant and simple I wanted to reflect my own style of my own aesthetic
And I wore uniform when I was young
When I
Trying to get dressed as a designer
I kind of I never really liked the uniform but I
Like the concert
Just making
Getting dressed
Shut up and
Have enough to think about you enough to worry about
Get put the clothes on go now
I wanted to make a
Simple but I didn't want it to be so confined that it had to be exactly
Like you know the uniform
Or in a one only one
Particular
Chapin NY the same thing everyday and I just had this idea that I
Could make these simple clothes no one's really doing it
And
The images would come to me I would see this simple shapes
And the first one I remember was I called a box
Quite straight lines like a kimono sleeve and
It was about the whale
Drape when you had it on
But I was kind of the first pick
Picture that came to me and others were
You know the simple
Will Wiley pants and you know there was a vast and shovel and the first few pieces of the started come to me
I was talking to people cuz now I had artists
Friends in Tribeca and
Other people who were designing clothes and jewelry and things like that
Which often happens when people have an idea
You were saying how this idea
Design
Beautiful simple
Piece of clothing for women and and we're your friends think you should go for you
Definitely
Definitely and you would have these conversations for
You know
For a long time with many people like over a period of 5 years
People probably really obsessed
This is what I'm curious about
Because
This is the point at which
99.9
Percent of people
Do nothing
Did they have a great idea
And
They do nothing either because they decide not to do something or
Just because of
Bad luck
What was it
That
Switch that idea into something you actually tried
Okay that's good
So
I think
What happened is that I'm so I'm seeing
Pictures and I'm trying to imagine Where do I
And how would I make this
Happened
And I couldn't picture myself you know
Like what if I made these clothes how would I do that and went and then I couldn't picture myself how would I sell them
You know what I go to stores other people are telling me they were going to like
Henri Bendel in waiting in line for hours and bio go like nope
I don't like it
That was not you you were not a
You're not a hustler now
No I was a shy
Introvert at a time
But I knew I couldn't I was definitely on Hustler and I could not
The idea was mortifying to you to have
What what what do you think it was the would have been the hardest
Part of that
Rejection semi saying no or trying to articulate
What would it was it you
Both
I think
Probably it was still rejected
The time in oh
But art
Calculating
Was and still is
What kind of
Initial for me
Just thinking today about trying to tell story
Great encouragement
So you're thinking
Alright I
I don't want
Try this but I
I cannot even imagine what I would do after
I would have liked a sample of this
Until what ended up happening is that a friend who took me to the boutique show
And is like a famous show in like a trade show
It's at Rachel
Inn in York
Right
But it was a show Big Show that cater to the small boutiques around the country
And a lot of small designers and small companies would come there and show their thing
And so I remember going to the show
Out of curiosity Crainer
And, floating through and going like oh
I can do this
I see how to do this
I could just look at these different foods and saw how the designers were presenting their clothes
A little rack here a few things hanging
You know I know how to do a logo I could do they had I need a logo wouldn't I need a name you know
So I could picture
The whole story so it wasn't just like one garment
It was that I had to
People have to see a kind of ahold understand that it went together
And that it was a a little story somehow by going to the design
Show you thought well I don't have to be Carnival Barker I can just stand here and wait for people to come to me back when the people who
Like it
Will come in
Write orders or you know
Give me feedback and the people who don't like it'll just walked by
Committed to
Small section just like one
For 4
The same designer next show
For the next show
This is in like 1980
3 because I think for that I
Show that I first introduced
You said I'm going to go there and show my go to dinner and then I'm going to
Show my clothes right I have no clue
I know fabric you had designs
How much time do you have
3 weeks
You are the lyrics to come up with a
Clothing line of fashion line
No don't care do I know it wasn't really a special line to start out with for garments
But I had
So now you know as a kid so I knew
You know that it wasn't that comp
But I was lucky in that this is how is this is
Kind of weird how things
Happened but
You know again one of the friends I've been talking to said I have a friend
With a pattern maker she works in a
Clothing company
Maybe she can help you
So she came into work for me at night and on the weekends
The first three weeks this this woman
Volunteered
And she wouldn't will she said you can pay me I know you're getting a good for you can pay me
When you get paid
Did you drop a bunch of designs and give them to her
Tissot
Or did you sell them well
I pretty much talked my way through it I scribbled them you know my little sketches and she said well those are
They're pretty simple
What's special about the Miley and I was like well it's special that they're simple
But I'll help you
And so first I had to find fabric
I was kind of the
She helped me
No figure out where I could go to get Fab
What what kind of fabric was
It was a linen and cotton blend
Yeah so what did you what did you end up making
I made the Box
Top
The little crop
Pant
Kind of based on the flood pants from Japan
And I made a little
Shell invest the kind of went over
The
Top and then I made a little shelter
We're at the Shell with a simple pant oh my God you feel like the pieces on my line today it's so amazing
To see the pictures and the color colors were they
They were like a teal color and kind of
Burgundy
Black white burgundy salmon eat pinky right now
Ana ivory
So after 3 weeks you had
Piece of clothing
Samples
And that's what you were going to take
To this trade show
I will email them into three colors
So I had 12
And that's what I took
With my little logo
And I was I spent probably as much time obsessing about the
The graphics and the name because I didn't want to call it a new fish
Because I didn't see it as soap
Personal
I thought it was something that
You know
People would make their own
That it would
I hope that it wasn't so personally me it was
Change
What's up what did you end up calling it for the
Cuz I couldn't think of anything else and I was working as Eileen Fisher the designer
I already had my name registered as a business so I guess if I was going to take checks
Better having business name and so that's
Work for them
So like when they
When they make the Eileen Fisher Story movie
Like feature film one day and they have this scene in there
First trade show
Is this like this
Amazing moment where designers are like
Oh my gosh this is Life Church and I have never seen anything like it is that what was going on no no no no no
Absolutely not
I was so
Freaked out
First
I literally couldn't
I just
People would ask me questions like
How much does it cost
What's the style number
And I like
Brought with them
Other people in my booth would help me out saying no
I just want to give you a hug and say it's going to be
Bok
This is like
I was like
Headlights
She said did you eventually get over the stage fright in and
Start selling
I did I did I felt so to 8 stores
I felt about a hundred piece
So couple thousand bucks
Yep 3000
Boxer
Skipping home saying
I was thrilled
And it was the right amount because anymore I would have never been able to deliver
I wouldn't be able to get enough fabric I would have been able to figure it all out
Fast enough or get the money to make it happen
Yeah so that was a pretty that was pretty good you walk away $3,000 and these are boutiques around the country
Right
And presumably
Fill those orders
You made most of them
Yourself
Cut everyone myself on the floor in my loft in Tribeca
And then carry them in garbage bag
Down my stairs
Subway in
The queens and did you show your name Eileen Fisher in the
Act like a nut
Close the label I had an label Maids at the source
Tiny sewing company
Out in Queens
Sodam
So at this point this is like 1984
You got three thousand bucks
End
Are you like
Incorporated youku like do an LLC and all that
Stuff
I don't think I did that until
I got my next round
So how did that
Well I came up with 8
Style
And went back to the next one
And this time I had this
New fabric that I found it was a
Barry Tech
Extra French terry bearing
Lush fabric
Yeah
More like a
Elegant sweatshirt fabric
And
Came back with
Re
Different colors
Peach mint and white
Remember
And
This time
People stood in line
I was like oh my God I knew
Something was happy
When we come back, Eileen Fisher took her clothes from tradeshow floors to Department
Stores
Master country
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Sports
NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Honda state of Mark
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO Lance
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Next available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play and it gs.com podcast
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So at this point in the story
Eileen had just sold
$40,000 worth of orders in her second trade show
And things seem to be looking up
Only problem was
Now to figure out how to
Put together a real functioning business
But I was even for the back figuring out just how do I get the money
Buy the fabric
And
You know
You know how am I going to produce this you had
You have $40,000
What's $40,000 in cash budget
Maybe orders
You had to go and buy all of the material
And I'm assuming you
You didn't have $40,000
Right well I would have needed about 20 to do the production
And but I got some good advice sexy while I was at the
DHL that I deliver
Small order first
Why did White
Just for a lycan February delivery and then I did
The other colors for delivery couple months later so that let me spread out the delivery in
I could
Produce part of it while I was trying to turn the money
I did the orders on COD so then
When they delivered the
Boutiques with write a check and they had to pay right away to pay right away and
You know I have to show when they were standing line it was kind of easy to ask him to do Cod because I have
How to play with them I'm a small designer need
PCR DNA
Accommodated me but did you also try to get a loan at a bank
I tried and
You know I went to the bank I remember and I with my stack of orders and they were like well how long he been in business
They just looked at you and they're like
Do you have no track record you're not like how do you get it to how do you do that then
Right place at the first thing that person of the banks that which is greatest
How do you know the reason real order
If you check credit on the order
Okay now I'm done that
That's a good idea what it what does that mean how do I do that
Which stressed out about this or where you cuz you don't sound stressed out of
Your I think your demeanor your you just seem very
Come and know it was you were nervous
Yeah yeah
Well
Was I nervous even during the days
No no I wasn't nervous then I was nervous
Show
Present myself
But it was never nervous
You know trying to sell
Call my love.
How to get the money I'm going to do this
You know
Who's going to help me how am I going to ask what what do I need here
You know an idol shows my
On my Loft and I
Friendly borders
Another pay me up front deliver
Things like that anything you had to do
Little Tikes puzzle making kind of van
That was fun
And just taking it all out I like I like I guess I'm a math major somewhere in my soul in my like
Solving puzzles and problems and
No trying to make things right
To you would
Make some
Get the cash
And then
Use cash to buy more material and then just continue a kind of fund is that
Right right
Grambling day-by-day
You know how to make this working
You know it then go to the next show and sell $80,000 of the orders and then it's like oh my God
Can we go wow
You know
What
Did you
Did you actually
Say I'm this is real
I just going to trade shows
This is a company I need to hire some
Well
I hire my first
Official employee
Siggy who still works for the company today
And I don't remember thinking I'm a real business or anything
I just remember thinking I need help
I really need some
Stable
Help
And did you start to go to department stores and and do the thing that you were mortified
To do earlier in your
Design career no I never did that but eventually open the store on Madison Avenue and
Byers
From the department stores
Come so you open this
The store on Madison Avenue in
And a headed to do
Really well again similar experience to that booty
Teacher wear
You know people just
Ben leinbach clothing
PacSun closing
It was so delighted to finally
I remember that's when he was
Fire somebody from Bloomingdales came in because they've been looking at the line I'm curious
And they would say things like
You know it is a great close but you know they're just going to get lost at Bloomingdale's
And
Simple
Simple you know
But I knew that was the idea
Anyway so when they came into the
So are they new
They didn't understand it but they knew something was happening
And so they wanted to open the shop
Smoke shop
Yes I was a kind of a I think that
Catapult address to another phase
Who are your customers were they
What was a certain type of woman was it a certain age was it a certain profession
Yeah that really days I describe the most
Artist
Therapist and teacher
And it seemed like they were people who
You know
Say they
They help people find themselves
Something like that you know
That are that they could
Figure out how to
Make your own style with these
Is closed and they could
They operate in the you know not inside
The corporate world they didn't have to dress
Certain kind of way
Were you able to finance
The stores
And
The production just threw
Existing sales
Yes and know how we found we were able to get a line of credit
What fabric in bulk even though we were small
Because we
I was very dedicated to a certain fabric so
Built around 1 fabric
And then I
I had my brother-in-law can was helping me and he got me a small line of credit if
$50,000 line of credit
Then I got a new accountant to you no help me to happen to the
Thanks how you had to put business plans together and
It says combination of credit lines and loans and
UNICEF funding
It was growing and it was
Unprofitable
It was always profitable
From there were you
I mean what's the growth
Just
Off the charts with you
Who's that was happening
You know it was
Strong and steady and I know it was
Not exactly awesome
Charts
But it was exciting and sometimes it felt like you know like
Horses in a carrot like an out-of-control Hilton Hotel you know like it was pulling me somehow
No
Mosto
Wasn't
2 out of
Controls
You know it was mostly organic it was never like an attempt to make it ever bigger than it was
It was more like okay
It's working so that's open to more stores
Or it's working for more store
You know or now you know
No other department stores want to buy the line
Shaq
Nordstrom's
You know
That kind of thing
What was your Revenue with that
Oh
Different moments in time how much
I can't remember I remember my dad came to visit me one time in the early days and he
Set back in the chair he was in the county was going over some of my books I want to make sure I was
Campaign things are working out okay without
Adorable
And he sat back in the chair
Do you know
How much money you made
Here
And I said no I really don't think he said
Gross sales
Forcing her plenty of expensive but
You know was still
Pretty
Pretty shocking
How did you I mean as the company was growing
1990s
How did you
Deal with
Being a CEO did you
Did you like that
No no no no no
No I think it's CEO is
A word that I've always
I am always been sort of uncomfortable
Not actually held that title used to call myself Chief creative officer that was sort of the clothes
I could come but I did know that sort of the bucks stop with me
You know sometimes I had to make important decisions
Now which work would have been would be hard
But I always kind of help
Business leadership standpoint pretty
Pretty loosely
And so I like the designers
Being with it and making it snow
Their own and working together and you know
In the in a sort of collective way
And I feel that way about the leadership and even today were leadership
Team
Pretty complicated and we're really working to streamline it and we're getting better we're getting a lot better
Period of time when you really mean
Really just started
Exploding
Yeah
Did you find yourself in a position
That you were reluctant to be in
Yeah
I saw myself more as a designer artist
Rather than a business person
Even though I wasn't bad at it
In terms of
Maybe not so much the managing people
I guess I never like telling people what to do
I ate and I never liked working
For other people
Oh you know when they would try to tell you what to do it didn't
I didn't like being told I like give me the problem and let me do it my way
Nothing
Ellen DeGeneres
I mean I know that
In the 90s it was a
Incredibly
Active time for Eileen Fisher and
Continue and also personally knew you were
You been married
You had to
Children died in the
4 year period of time
Two young kids you are trying to run this company
And
Your marriage was
I'm falling apart
How did you
You manage the personal on the
I would say that wasn't the hardest
Hardest
Ever and if I look back
Man if I could do anything differently that be
I'm not not going into regret but
That was incredibly hard
God I think about all the women out there trying to start businesses and work in the business world and
So hard to do
Men's families
So I really had to rely on
People in company
I tried
Two again Minnesota lead Loosely into
But I
With being in two different places and wanting to be at work when I was at home or worrying about work
You know I'm reading reports and trying to understand is
It's working or not what's working and what's going wrong
And at the same time worrying about
The kids when I was at work and just
You know
I guess the
Nothing I say to myself now is that if I look back I would
I would have just worked harder and being where I was
Doing what I was
Doing in the moment
Stop tryna
B2 play
And stop taking the work home and do the best
Toucannon
You weren't trying to be the best mom you could be and
And also run the company
And
And you
I messed up
It's kind of sounds a bit like
What your mom went through
Overwhelmed right I mean she was
It was relentless everyday was his hamster wheel
Yeah
I did the best I could I I had to let go a lot of hair
How to trust a lot of pee
People
Which wich worked and didn't you know it worked in places
And then there were moments that I felt
You know sad about her let go too much over here on
I know
Going to a store and see pieces I didn't recognize or feel like the line didn't look where I adore
I couldn't find the clothes I wanted to wear or wasn't really the concept it was gone
Where was the soul of this company and you know what happened
Yeah
You know
Once I got divorced
My kids were four and eight
And I said I am
I'm going to stop working on Wednesday Thursday Friday
I worked in my home a lot and I would
I'll let the people keep working and I close the door and go out and be with my kids
And you know my husband will have the kids on Mondays and Tuesdays and
Share the weekends things like that
So it actually
Works better for me I don't think it worked
So well for them they didn't really like the going back and forth
Dolphin and I guess
Yeah
But I think that
I know overtime I sorted it out and
Things got better I got I got stronger I I started doing things like yoga and meditating I had some time to myself
My mother never had you know
I don't have to have a breakdown actually so
To get a hold of myself
SharePoint Eileen where you thought cuz your business was
I just bought are huge like you were
Successful
Beyond Your Wildest Dreams the late 90s is not even
Today and
Did you ever think maybe I should just
Passionate and sell his company to somebody in just
Wash my hands
Oh my God no I never never thought they had never filed
Never never cross your mind
That would be like selling my first born child really felt like that under so much stress and you had
You did have that security blanket
You could have done that
Alright was never about the money no
I mean
Probably in the very beginning when I didn't know how to price
Close wasn't about the money by
It was personal I guess I wanted it to be how I wanted it
To be and I think
Still true
And actually what I did do was sell part of the business of employees
So we are 40% and Esau
Employee-owned
And I always wanted that
Collective idea wanted
I wanted the people who are apart of it
Paid and feel like owners and be owners
Yeah
I think Eileen Fisher has
Like
55 + apartment you buy lean fish
Your company
Has like
About 60 stores around the world
Train rides
The right
Ashley s and
Thousands
Employees
1200 direct employ
But many
Probably ten thousand people work daily on are making our clothes
Presumably ask
Became bigger and bigger it became
More corporate
More corporate because
I just had more people you have
He was like a lot of Revenue or doing a
Plus million dollars a year
Lizard point
Mike Moore today but
Was that
Will weird for you maybe you're the you're the person who didn't want to work for other people
All of a sudden you are your name is a
Oh man
Is a weird
It is weird
Yeah it was weird
Still weird
Write a book called how I became Eileen Fisher
Schleich
It's just strange
Keep singing
If any of your dad
Coming to visit you
In New York
In the early days insane
Like looking through your books and saying
You guys made $200,000 last year just being so
Blown Away by that
Eileen Fisher.
Hundreds of millions of dollars in Revenue
A year
I mean
Is it strange
To you that you
Rich even though you never wanted to or tribe that wasn't your intention
Yeah
Oh yeah
I feel very uncomfortable
That's something that I am
I think my working therapy
Because you grew up with like
7 children your house of
Dis Metairie
Middle-class oh yeah I put myself through college
I don't need to go to school so you know
Temperature parents ever see
This level of 6
Yeah my mother did
My father was utterly totally impressed by
I $20,000
But my mother did I don't know that she understand
Did it quiet
You know my sister's will work in the store out in the Midwest and so she's going there
She's so adorable she would go in and even as the company got really big and cheese
Damages we have a section of Damages I did sell in the back
Duarte
And she'd go to the back
Storm picked out those dams
Maven take him home
Go to the first
Put on the main rack
But I think to her no
You know it could have been 200,000 would be this big nobody
Hitman
How much to her
It sounds like
You are
And in pretty good place in life
How you personally
Assertive
You don't have to do the
Logistical operational stuff of the company
Can I have like vision and
Big picture stuff and
You seem like
Sure really happy
Yeah well you know
Not everyday not all the time
But I I know how to work with him
Can I watch my mother she was
Depressed
And you know
I remember having this inside
And before I started the business
When I went through a kind of a dark moment in my late twenties
I remember going you know having this Revelation that
I can make a different choice
I don't have to be depressed
Because my mother was the
Might have to be overwhelmed because my mother was overwhelmed but it don't have to be depressed
I didn't I didn't understand the full impact
The different choices I had to make but I realized
That I could choose
And
Doesn't mean it doesn't get the better of me some days
I also know it doesn't laugh
I would say
Happy I'm happy I'm also really sad sometimes I'm also really
You know scared like before I came in here today I'm really anxious I'm really
Excited I'm really
More feeling full and probably ever in my life
I love that
You
Is everybody listening to this is going to say
Eileen Fisher
Future successful
Credence amazing company and brand
Has
You know made it beyond our wildest dreams and yet
She has bad days she gets out
Absolutely
Absolutely I think what's different
Is now I know that
And I can
I can look at it and I can just be with
So if I'm anxious I can just say I'm anxious
And it's okay
You know I don't have to try to
Pretend I'm not
I can just
Be who I am
That's okay
Eileen Fisher the founder of Eileen Fisher
By the way Eileen still oversees all of the designs
For the company and in recent years
She launched a program called Green Eileen
The goal is to eventually you reuse or recycle almost all of the clothing
Company sells
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things you are building
Thanks to one of our sponsors
Delta Airlines
Now you can enjoy free mobile messaging while flying on Delta
You can use iMessage WhatsApp and Facebook Messenger
Simply by logging into the in-flight Wi-Fi
Thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And three story comes from Springfield Louisiana where are you
One of these guys
Their jet black sometimes they're a little bit modeled with some gray color
They have spiky hair that sticks up on the back of their neck you know they have a long skinny snout
And they just make a big
Cacophony coming through the woods
And what could he be talking about
Wild boars of course
And in
Springfield Louisiana where Charlie Munford lives
These wild boars can cause a lot
Of damage to nearby Farms
They mess up
Cornfields and soybeans and you know
Wheatfields
They do
Route up Levy's
So they're very destructive so it's
Probably important dimension
At this point
Fat Charlie
He's a butcher
Will die in condition and harvest beef lamb pork and goats
Sure and Slaughter
And Chef kept requesting while bored at first I was like I was kind of wacky you know no one does that but
The to do just that
Charlie actually created a program in partnership with the Louisiana Department of Agriculture
Google legally Harvest
Wild boars
And this was a really defining moment because we were essentially able to
Harvest is delicious
Wild game
And at the same time help our Farmers with the problem that they're facing managed in their land
So the shaft
Get their meat and Farmers fields are protective
During the summer of 22
16 Charlie back to work
He built
The smoker and he came up with a recipe for what is now Charlie's wild boar sausages
We actually have a wood fireplace
And we have seasoned Water Oak that we use
You know it just makes a much
Richer flavor
And we built the smoker
Ourselves the stainless steel smoker that's Tina is about the size of a big pickup truck
And we did about 50 rounds
Of the recipe you know we just kept doing the recipe over and over and over and try and over and over again
And out of the final product
Well if you would think about how
Beef taste in comparison to venison
I mean it's a darker meat it's a it's a more aromatic
Me
And when you smoke it it gets just buttery and delicious this pass
Spring Charlie started selling as wild boar sausages to local restaurants
Grocery stores
And he had ambition to expand his customer base
But the sausages aren't exactly cheap they're about $12 a pound
We decided early on that since we are distinctive thing was going to be flavor and it's going to be a little bit more expensive
Nice smoked sausage we were going to need to literally get a sample into every person's mouth
The first Charlie got culinary students to do some demos and that's okay.
Great okay
So he decided to recruit some people who knew the product a little better
We hired professional full-time chefs that really love our product and you know put them in the grocery store
You're so they can speak the language of like this culinary ingredient that were using and the number of packs sold per
Damn it went from 7 to 35
And today
Charlie's selling his sausages in 70 stores around Louisiana Alabama
And Mississippi and through his website he's starting to get orders from around the country in order from Hawaii
Fulfillment company called me and they said Hey look it's going to cost like 80 bucks
Quarter to Hawaii
You know what do you want to do and I was like send it
Civic
To find out more about Charlie's wild boar sausage
Messages head to our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org we love hearing what you were up to and thanks for listening to our shows
This week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. NPR
. org please also download our podcast at Apple podcasts or however you get your podcast
You can also write us
Beach IBT at
Npr.org
You can tweet at us it's asked how I built this
Our shows produced this week by run. Bill Saturday with original music
Compose by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva grandson
Looking for clarinet
Geoff Rogers
Anya grundmann is a vice president
Programming a 10
NPR
Our intern is Dianabol stack
A Gyros
Even listening to how I built this
NPR
Hi I'm Stacey Vanek Smith from NPR Planet Money
Cast a business and economics podcast for everyone
Even if you don't think you like business and economics
Every week we find stories that help make the world make a little more sense like why is milk in the back of the store
How do credit reports get started
Where does North Korea get its money
Listen to Planet Money on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week