I would order the stuff out of Taiwan and I would give myself 60 days
Get the money together.
Read a report to come pick it up so you have to make that same time you don't know
Know what you're going to do
If I didn't I would never do it
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists at the stories
I'm guy Roz antonym
A special live recording
Story of beyond meat a company that wants to take the chicken and burgers off your plate
Replace them with plants
And do it in a way where you will never know the difference
Took to the show is a little different from the others
The story of a startup that is still in many ways
Best startup
The company beyond meat has not yet turned a profit added CEO and founder Ethan Brown
Definitely not a billionaire
We start yet
But he is part of a movement that is it takes off
Could come
Completely transform the way we think
About food
Because think about it if you are a meat eater there is nothing more delicious than a freshly grilled steak or
Or a basket of fried chicken rice
Ethan says you can have all of that but the meat doesn't have to come from a cow or a chicken again
Actually come from plants
Keys and lentils and stuff like that but here's the thing
It won't taste like a pathetic vegetarian Subs
Steven says that at some point in the future
Maybe sooner than you think
Meat eaters will not be able to tell the difference between animal meat
And plant
And find out how he's in his trying to make that happen
Set down in front of a live audience in Anaheim California
Here's part of that conversation
Welcome
Thank you very much for having me
It's an honor to be
So
I want to start by asking you a little bit about
How you grew up cuz you grew up
Around
Farms around animals rights
Right so I have an interesting childhood in it I grew up in the city
But my father is a professor
McGill now
And
He grew up in the country
And had a love for the
It really defines who he is
And so we spent an enormous amount of time
In the countryside and he bought a Farm Bureau Leon
He bought a farm just like
A farm where
She'll get a couple different ones but that was the one that was for the dominant one
I'm within my childhood was in Western Maryland
And soda can a Holstein
Dairy business
What about a hundred head
Cattle
So we spent a lot of time there as I when I was a child and then
Side hustle was milking cows
Something like that so growing up around animals and in did you eat
Animals when you were a kid but definitely I definitely ate a lot of meat
My favorite
Sandwich was the Double R burger from Roy Rogers
Wow what's that
That's so it would have ham
And I don't have cheese and her have the burger and cheeseburger
Yeah exactly and and so as I became conscious of what I was doing
What about the older teenager
I began to think about that to this is the end of the milk from the cows
Miniature pig
Orgy of of the
Different animals
So how did you
When did you start to begin to think about animals differently
I should know we should say I should
You are today a vegan you do not eat animal products right you don't even wear animal
I don't see these are these are $35
From
Target your shoes are
Faux leather
But
The early on I began to think differently about animals I wanted to be a vet
I would spend time in our attic or the employer Farm
And I would I would build large cages for for mice
No cash for the mice and Have a Heart Traps
And I put him in his cage and they were very different
Fly across the kids right
And it was it to me it was as wonderful world and I loved
Is it right now in Seoul
For me the
Experience was about getting a nosey animal
And celebrate
They took you out of work it out if it is not coherent United still
Eating meat in Wasilla
Using animal products
But that early inkling about how I feel differently about animals
The news around me
So you you go to college
Did you think that you would be entrepreneur I mean you got an MBA was that your
Should have Vision in the hydrogen fuel cell
Scepter this is after you get your MBA
Gurney yeah yeah so I worked there about 10 years
And I was answering that for reason
The climate seems to be doing
Something that was
Socially oriented
So
So when did you like Woodford
LED you to start to think about
Animals livestock
Trailer something that
Turn all that he was like it was something that even
As I was
Climbing the corporate ladder within the
The cleantech space
It just kept coming back
Go something that I felt like I had to go do
I'm going to literally that strong
And so I chat with that for a long time and I begin to think about it not just
In terms of my own feelings about animals
Child
But
Interesting Billy that's the number one issue
And today I still think about this way if you think about
Affecting really difficult problems
All at once
By changing out the protein attended play
Capri Palace affect human health
What are you having a heart disease diabetes
Cancel all these things are linked
To certain types of meat consumption
Did the climate change
Peanuts by 51%
A greenhouse gas emission
It's from from from
To put it bluntly
Burps and farts right some percent of it
A way to get your head around
So we fought about 66 million animals
66 billion around the world
All those animals are breathing
When they breathe
Aspire carbon
Toyota Corolla number of livestock
Shrinking number. If you have a carbon cycle it's out of balance
And so
That's why this last issue
Important focus on
So how did you go from
Starting to think about livestock and climate change
Just saying you know what I'm going to give up this fuel cell stop and
Like tackle this problem
I was
My twenties miss her late twenties
I was thinking about this I want to create a
Plant-based McDonald's
Then I was in a relation
I wanted to get out of work I wasn't very good at getting out of
I'd like I moved and all these other things
Send it in a way that wasn't very
Freeport
So I was
It never leave start on my career
And I was like I really have a feeling I want to go start this plant
McDonald's
Did you even know how to cook
Lydia pretty poorly and so I really want to do this
What's in your heart
I know
I didn't do it
I spent like 7-8 more years you know
Working on cleantech because that's what I was supposed to do
You know and I had this
I said this before
I remember
Seeing
And reading Of Mice and Men
Looking at Lennie and being like
Unlike big
I don't wanna be that guy likes
Virgos like sentimental Ethan
You know like I did I wasn't serious enough for me or something like that you know
I was afraid to be compassion
It's so funny when I look at guys like
When to sell a phone
Humane Society
I really admire them
But surely on there like
Is what I feel is going to act on in the world and it took me awhile to
She said
The things that I thought I was supposed to be doing
So how did you
Getting the courage to leave the stable job and
Start to
Think about
Making
Faking well
Show
First
You're a very small kids literally just born
This is kind of started
Mount Rushmore
This world
And my wife grew up in the country and until we've had meeting our house Moschino kids meeting
Justice is not
Weavers way
And I want to make a difference
And so
It started to come out
Pretzel meaning we got these pet
Pigs that we were we were
Caterpillar Farm
And they were wondering
That same time would be like on Jersey Turnpike and let the kids need some to eat
Am I fabulous
Precise Barber go to Subway
I literally
Feel
This disconnect in my life right that I got to do something
It was it was at personal calling and then it was
Sitting in this meeting
Working on climate
To clean tech
I began to feel like
We were just not getting
Take a picture
And they being big hotels like this
And we bring our hands but how do you get
Percent workers in Seattle
Find battery
Medical
Steak dinner
Just doesn't
Make sense let's attack
The real problem
And not really motivated me
I started to work at night on it
And this is the great thing about
Time period in history is the internet
I'll come home
Kids go to bed
I would just set up another the most living in Capitol Hill time
And I'll research
He would like go to Google and type in
Textured soy protein meat or
You don't need an animal
Tripolis Pizza
But that was the core belief that I'd be into half listed like
I could see that you could get
The Demeter really five things as its amino acids
It's lipids
It's a very small amount of carbohydrates
Ana.
Trace minerals
Also very small family water
What's incremental fabulous
They're not exclusive to the animal they're all absolutely present
And the plank
So the animals doing
Massive amount of plant matter
The running through their system they're crazy muscle
Why can't we take Plan B
Running through a system increase muscle and that's all we're doing research who's
Taking protein from plant
And reorganizing
And a guy two guys at the University of Missouri
You just like came across an academic paper
From Asia that I thought was really good
Nashua
Texturized pizza store that sell with quite close to muscle
Bring it in
Pain in front of woman
Selling it in
Whole Foods
In the Mid-Atlantic area at night or on the side you were you start of the second sort of a
A business where you were importing food
That's hilarious it was it was it was so I would
I would order the stuff out of Taiwan
And I would get myself
60 days to get the money together.
The paperwork
Port and I always did
One of the money
Then you get charged every day or an important
Pick it up
Right so you have to sign
How to make girlfriend to call for the thing about
I think one important thing
Most innings in history
You don't
I know what you're going to do what
People doing it to your backs against
Cuz I would put myself in that
Yeah because if I didn't I would never
Elsa toys
Letgo
And then get yourself in a position
And you'll figure it out
So you you read this academic paper
Buy these professors at the University of Missouri
What did you just call him up and say what you say
I work with you
But came out there and I started to it
And what was he doing he was making plant-based
Yeah yeah he was he was basically taking
Proteins
Could have been corn
And he was using heating cooling and pressure
Realign them so they stitched until muscle like fiber
So you go out there and you meet him and what would you like
So
What is very good what what what they were doing but I didn't think it was
Ready for Market at all
So caught up in the recent Maryland
I said I've got this
Technology
Missouri weather
Can I work with
Maryland
And improve it
So I got a grant
Citic antenna research to basically
Try to get it ready for me
That's why I was funding out of my own pocket
But I also got my
So it would this is running on just a shoestring are you independently wealthy
You had to basically
Yes oh my soul my home
It's funny you set up all these
Founders come never touch that
So you decided
You said I'm going to start a business and I'm going to sell my house
Kids at the point
Thought they were like super like you wanted to or something
Yeah but she says about everything I do
I don't know
And in this is what round 2009
And what are you doing for the first few years you just going back and forth to misery from Ireland
Running with a good as it tastes good as it was eating gross stuff too
It was it was funny so I would use
Southwest
To go from BWI
And I'll take big duffle bag to the stuff back and forth
And there was a time when we're the busted open it just fell out over all the plan was like this like this like this like chicken
Did it I was also though importing this product from Asia and selling it to Whole Foods
I think that also gave me some credibility with that I wasn't just for dreaming about something I had it going
Concerned with small
But I'm selling into Whole Foods and then and I can say very truthfully about Whole Foods that I wouldn't be here without them
Helping hand every chance I get
You didn't have a background in
I mean you you were working at at
Fuel cell
Nobody but you wouldn't know
Training and cooking or food or the food industry like
How did you even get Whole Foods to take you
How did you even
Begin to go to investors and tell them about this idea and why would they have taken you seriously
So when I got here producer the show asked me just what you're wearing
You didn't have me
Paper and pencil credentials I mean horse
How did you make the case for what you were doing and how did Jerry Ables it I'm the guy to do this
That's a really fair question
I don't know I mean I think one thing that I did learn in business school was
I think they were wrong about this
Remember that always bring back people who are like super young attractive and
Very successful be like I told this guy to go do this and he did it and you know
Who are the people that are like living in O in their mom's basement
Eating Ramen right now back to square one
But one thing that they said was you have to have
Competitive
Moat around what you're doing there has to be some
The barrier to entry for others
In order to have successful business
And I thought that was like
Stupid
I really can't answer that market right but he didn't believe that
I think I can
I just wanted this morning
That's Ethan Brown of beyond meat and we come back in a moment
The things that still keep him up at night I'm guy Rodney listen to a special live recording
And how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First to godaddy.com
They give customers the tools insights
They need to transform their ideas in personal initiatives into success
What's GoDaddy small business owners have everything they need
To get there
Online
Including 24/7 support
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology provider dedicated to
Small business
They're offering how I built this listeners 30% off all new products
Just going to godaddy.com
Podcast
And use code built
Thanks also to Trunk Club
In a world with countless Trends and so many different clothing options
Trunk Club back by Nordstrom provides a
A service designed to make it simple for men and women to make sense of style
Dress their back
You'll be connected with a stylus to find the items that fit your style budget and wardrobe
The clothes will be delivered straight to your door and then you'll have five whole days to decide what you
Keep
Anything you don't
Just ship it back to Trunk Club for free
Get started at trunkclub.com
Built
It's how I built this from NPR on Gyros
And the year to after Ethan Brown founded beyond meat
The company start to get some pretty big investors Bill Gates and the founders of
Twitter sign.
Answer to the Venture Capital company
Kleiner Perkins
So I initially funded on my own pocket and then we raised money from friends and family we got
Annie's grants
But I was running out of mine
You know what I'd I needed money yeah for the money
We're opening up in
Old Hospital building
But he's going to cost money
So you're selling doing research having facilities we ran out of money they said we needed to go raise money
A lot of rejections or was it like an easy smooth Rider people like yep how can I sign up
It was hard at first
Stop but Kleiner Perkins got involved
2010 MR2 look
And at the time it was not a
Popular decision
Guidestar
I'm grateful for that and once they got involved in another scandal
Let's talk about what this product
Started to become so how are you making it with you taking like
Soy powder and in gluten from wheat and like
Putting in a machine and it was coming out of me take me
So I think it's it it starts with
Apperception
So my argument is
That this is
They just meet
Comfrey plants
And so I think it important
Station when the company is we don't talk about people not eating meat
I don't think it's a good idea to build a brand
Telling people not to eat with a low
What is a good idea to allow you to eat more of what they love
And if you love me
I can give you plant-based me
If you can
Make our products out of
Bill lentil protein mustard seed
Tobacco leaves of grapes
So today we use
But it's only
Vince Gill.
But I think the idea is let's look for the most sustainable crops
Confirm that
And use it a great meeting
So when when were you able to when did you create a product that was ready to go to market you start the company in 2009
Calendar
Take you before
Beyond meat was as it was it a grocery store
That year I started to import something I sold into old age
But it wasn't until 2011
And really really 2012
That we started to
Put into the market this
Basic structure that we could we could license from
We should still sell
Most of the stores carry mini frozen sectioning chicken
Chicken and beef
You know I'm coming to the harshest critic of our products
I love her product
People are products
C&S products
You can see how they're not exactly like animal protein
And that's osterizer
But we have to
The collapse of differences
Akon
Would you have a moonshot
In a company
Adding bacon from a source invalid to like
Let's show them that we can produce a piece of bacon like a real piece of bacon
What is the hardest
Part of
This business
Are the things that keep you up at night to have anxiety is India are you convinced this thing is going to be huge and it's going to be successful
You think you know this could mail
Absolutely
Inevitability about we're doing
Ashley feel that way
I think my anxiety is more around execution and
Want to be better when we be better she go when he better found her want to be better
Better colleague
You don't let them down
Cause anxiety
Yeah I am a speakers
I believe in you that take a note
Although they're so rich anyway doesn't matter I mean let's face it right
When do you think for example like when do you think that you guys will
Be profitable
So we actually have turned a really big corner just recently in terms of
Everything we're doing
The progression facilities went from Kitchen to a
Quasi kitchen / Factory
To a factory Missouri and we just have like a brand new facility was a beautiful as I was there twice this week
Dallas Texas
In this new facility at that scale we get
Really really good Ma
And so and that's a new thing for us
Pictures of the casa Productions gun down
Yeah and then just in and everything
More streamlined
Prototyping
Improving out stage
2 into actually scale production is there a chance that this company could be profitable in 5 years old
NB does it matter
Is it important or is it it is enough to be sweet
It is important
But I Wrestled a ? because I believe so
Strongly in the research program we have
And I would find that at the sacrifice of almost anything else
The company because
I want to be
Part of that group of people that
Separate me from Anna
When it called
Said and done I want to look back on this effort and old people working there
Going to get these cases with a remarkable people
I want to say you guys did this
And are you guys
Thousand Years
Humans 40 million years
Consuming meat from animals
You guys were born and he died and in between that time
Physically separated
Meat from animals and you put us on a
And it's not about feeding the pesky 13 year old girl at the dinner table boy who said Mom I'm not going to eat meat anymore
It's about creating a new form
What side of the plate
The people will love
And they don't have to sacrifice to have it
It in 50 years or a hundred years
200 years
We look back on who we are today
And say wow we that was so weird we ate animal meat like we look back on
On bloodletting or
You know poor or witchcraft
So if part of us is always going to do this right. People on
You know like I go back to her Farm
Stuff like
It's just part of who who who we are
But I think in the main
You know it will be viewed as something we used to do and I think more and more it'll be viewed as a
Like when you go to Central Park
Horse-drawn carriage
Elsa's
Driving
It'll be kind of like that
I just have no way around in our job
Our obligation
To make that protein break
What can I ask you to go out there and have like a baby dog you don't like
Just want to do it
Hardwired
We have to create me from plan so there's no trade-off in wood
Trying to do that
Did the singer
I got a scale it up
Can you improve it
Ethan Brown thank you
Ethan Brown founder and CEO of beyond meat
I spoke to him at the now hear this podcast Festival in Anaheim California
And by the way last summer be on me came out with something called the Beyond Burger it's made with pea protein and actually looks
And even believe the little like a cow Burger the bloody stuff actually comes from beat
And unlike other veggie burgers Ethan has negotiated with supermarkets to display the Beyond Burger
Enemy case
Right next to the chicken and the steak
Hey thanks for listening to this special live recording of the show this week
This episode was produced by Niva Grant and Randolph Dell photo with music
Supposed I run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to sanaz meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week