Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Well I kind of freaked out and I got this like small army
Give interns to help basically be customer service to email and call all these people let him know that there
There is no chance that they're going to get their shoes in the four days or five days the website promised is going to be more like
Couple months and I literally pretty Point Cyrus took a taxi to this guy's house
Juan Torres who is making the shoes in his garage Force the time and I walked in and with the lid
Little Spanish I knew I said something like muchos Zapatos rapido
NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
They don't know
A Goodwill Mission into a multimillion-dollar shoe Empire
Create a business model online
Anything anyone
I seen before
So I should
Probably let you know right
At the outset hear that
Today's show is going to be
A little bit different
Because normally in the first half of the show we hear the story of how an entrepreneur
Painstakingly build his or her business
From the ground
And then get old
How it goes from there right and in normally it's
Just one
Business
Who is Blake mycoskie
It is not just one
Because before he even turned 30
He's already launched
For company
Pretty well
And as for his best-known business
Toms Shoes
We're not even going to get there for a while so hang tight
Blake's
Very first business dates back to the mid-1990s
Is when he was a freshman in college
Growing up keeping a pretty good tennis player he even played against Andy Roddick
Pekin High School
And Blake was recruited to play at Southern Methodist University
And everything was going according to plan
That is until one day when he injured his
Achilles tendon
I've had this big cast on in
Crutches and
I wasn't able to play tennis
Several months I have
At the rehab
But everything I can do is ask
She couldn't carry my laundry
I down to the
Facility in the college
What's dorm
And so my laundry is piling up in my room and my roommate was
Probably not like
Get that much and
This is the hard to believe but this is back
Before any search engine so we had the yellow page
And I remember looking in the Yellow Pages to find a place that would come pick up
And deliver my laundry back to maybe
Because I physically couldn't do it
And and there is nothing like that in Dallas that I can find it
The time
There come to the campus and do that and
That ultimately led to
My first business
Just called EZ laundry
Blake partnered with his roommate and eventually they figured out that the
Key to getting customers
Listen to the students
Actually through their parents
Show the next year
Quienes roommate got a booth
At the freshman orientation
So parents are kind of going there's kind of signing up for everything
The other getting the books
They're getting the death again that
Navigate to the laundry thing and they don't know how long we've been in business or if every kid on campus does it or not but
Cashiers a chance to
You know sign their kid up for something that's not that expensive Ville
Help make sure that
The kids don't ruin their clothes are freshman year they haven't been used
East Washington
Drawing your own clothes and
Say some some time that they can use
Use for the things
We are pretty good
Kitchen
Within the series like two or three days we did like
$80,000 in prepaid laundry sales for
The year
When are the actually expanded
The four other colleges
Texas
And then
They were doing so well that Blake
Dropped out of SMU to
The focus entirely on the company
And after a few years
They decided to sell it
So at 21
Blake walked away with about $100,000
And lots of
Time to Kill
And I actually took a trip out to Los Angeles
The first time I'm just take a little bit of time off is it at
Friends are going to school out here
And when I was in LA I saw these
This huge
Advertising
Displays inside the building
Lynx now
Drawing of a Texas ID
I never seen like a massive
Add
I'm for an iPhone remove ear whatever you painted on the side of a building
Yet there was a lot of that in Los
And I noticed that they're not only was a lot of it but there was almost a
Exclusively advertising movies
Asian TV shows
So this
Pacific industry the LA was
Who is known for
And I remember sitting there that she's thing at Mel's Diner on Sunset I'll never forget this moment
And I was looking at this massive ad for I think one of the first Jurassic Park
And I was
This is so powerful that there's no way you can tune out this type of Alberta
The Gap is bigger than life is
It's exciting you know I wanted to go see the movie because of that the wall skate was so exciting it
Underneath it had a name of a company van Wagner And it was a company that owned that space
Technical vanwagner in
AI company in
Want to do some
Really big in LA and a salt is added you anyways could I rent this side of this building on Sunset and it's as well
Actually have a year-long contract with
Warner Brothers for that one so we
We can't we have mother one in town
How much would it cost if I wanted to rent this one and he said something
I think you said it was like
$85,000
You were a course
Pretending like you just want to get the information
If he says 85085 thousand a month
What I'm thinking
Hold on that means that building owners making over $1000000
The year
Just by renting the side of their building and he has two sides
It's cuz the building
Face it sunset two different ways
The $2000000 on one building
And I thought there's no cost
Like all you doing is this
Painting or putting the vinyl on there's no like
Actual billboard structure
Steel and all that stuff
You have to do like this
This is incredible
I just start thinking to myself like who would pay $85,000
And like
Why cuz there's no way that can make sense
On a
No cost per thousand or an advertising metric
Images 9f people that drive on Sunday
But I think
So the reason I basically came up with my mind was
It had to be you
You had to be there like all these studios in town went there movies
On the note on the
The street they want to show the
Actor the Starlet like I can put you on this building and
Like how big a deal is that
Isaac in Nashville the time and I made it
Quick
Assumption that the country music industry
Maybe not as big egos but definitely some big egos in town and
What if I put country music stars on the side of the building
So is that
Is that what you did
Yeah so I went back to Nashville and got after it in
When found out that you know there's no one has ever done this in Nashville
I and it was very
You're challenging me
To get the city to allow me to do it ultimately I had to convince
The city
Because I have the Highway beautification Act
Twitch kept people from putting up any new Billboards I think like after year 1984 something
I'm so what I ultimately came up with after like
Arno
Countless
City Council meetings
Discussion
This and that was
I was going to
Actually make the city More Beautiful cuz I was going to create country music
Art
And so what I did was I actually would put the album cover
Of the new Dixie Chicks are Shania Twain
Whoever was coming out with an album
But there would be no like
Call to action know like
Available at Best Buy for 999
It was just that
The art of the album
And by doing that
I can visit City I was adding to the landscape of Nashville which is all about
Music
Hate had this idea all you have to do is give me the side of your building and you get
CID
Did the thing you don't ever want to do especially when you're 22 years old and trying to talk to the 50 and 60 year old people who own apartment,
Places you don't want to use the word idea
Because if it's just an idea then it's like
You're not going to inspire a lot of confidence
Because people can say I don't like your idea
I don't believe your idea
If you say I have a business
And what we do
Is wheelies
You know the side of your building
And will guarantee you this amount of money per month
And we're going to resell the side of your building
Cuz we specialize
In selling advertising
To the country music industry end
You'll make money on an asset that you never thought you would ever make
You're basically Hustler
A little bit
I mean there's no doubt like I mean anyone is an entrepreneur associates they start really young
I mean
You got a fake ID
Do you make it tender
You know and I was I was never being
Dishonest I was just saying
This is what I'm doing and they had nothing to lose like by signing a contract with me
Then they were basically saying okay if you go out and least this
The Dixie Chicks
Jose and you can lease it for 10000 bucks
You're going to give me 30
Percent of that just for
Me allowing you to do this
That's that's $3,000 a month
To a place that made with charging
$500 a month for
Mitsubishi I just created
6 new apartments
They didn't even know how did you get the first
Company or who are
Label to agree to let you work with them to put their album art like how did you even
Have those connections an end
How did you make that happen
It was just cold calling you know I mean that I found out who had albums coming out did some research and then I contacted
Yeah the marketing person said hey I know you're getting ready to promote
Get a disc this album and
I have a way you can promote it larger than life right here in Nashville it's going to make a big impact and you can be one of the first
Do it Mr all things that marketing people love to hear
Yeah and and
Who's your first client was the first
Piece of art that you put up on the sun side of a building
Amy Grant
We did it on the side of a Ramada Hotel in downtown
There's a picture of me and and my partner who is helping me
At the time
Standing in front of it you know I know
Cover the national newspaper when it came out and it was great and then what we had that way
With credibility
And then we just started
Yes I'm right and left
What did the label pay for that
I think we charge for that one about
I want to say 15000 a month
So if you work we are probably cash flowing. 10000 a month
Just for that one wall
Do you think you have the confidence to do that because you had done the laundry business and
In college
Yammy I learned a lot I've started laundry business
So I didn't you know kind of hustling and building and having employees and learning about Custer
Summer service and learning valley sings
About 4 years
So when I had this idea I had to pay a little bit more
And you have nothing to lose you know
It's like they they're going to say yesterday weren't in
I've always been good with you no like
Just Taking Chances and
And see what happen
So eventually
View
Black Nashville
What US company
So I end up selling the company to Clear Channel
Big Media Company
How hot it was
It's really big in the outdoor advertising we ended up having walls in Nashville and
Expanded to Dallas
And once I got to Dallas I realize that this is like a
A big business game like I'd had some
Small successes
But it was very quickly that the big
Companies like the Viacom
Clear Channel's bandwagoners they were onto my game
And it was going to be hard at camp
So did you walk out of that
Teal
More less
Set pretty set yeah I mean
Every everything is is relative right
But I definitely had a nice
Cash flow coming in from that that I wasn't having you know
Jumped Outlet find a job so when I moved to LA
It was more kind of
For fun
Exploring what could be next
Then I was fascinated with reality television how is
Show me some popular
Cuz like right after like the first Survivor came out
Yeah and it just fast
I think the competitiveness in me
I did Venture that you know like
All that and
My sister and I were thinking about
Applying for Survivor and we actually did have life
Survivor Wii U
You wanted to be contestants on Survivor
Yeah
And
The casting
People Survivor also cast
New show called The Amazing Race
And they called us up and said hey I
I don't think
We can put you and yours
Survivor
But they knew about the Amazing Race
Today I talked
Descend to
Thinking about the Amazing Race and so we got into the process
Disturbing interview
For that
And we got on
And then the actual show itself is 31 days so
We literally disk
Secured smartworld for 31 days and we couldn't really tell anyone what we're doing
Super confidential disappeared
Anywhere from like country to Country right yeah it's all over the world and
We're done the hard part with a show with
Can start hearing for another you know
Couple months
Week in Taiwan
What happened
You know if we won or if we didn't win how far we got
Not to spoil the ending for anyone
Because Darren 2002 but you barely
Did you almost
You guys almost won a million box
Yeah and thankfully then cuz I think that
That would have been a positive thing at that moment but probably wouldn't have
Been good
For my further Drive Minaj
General Sam
She sits The Amazing Race fans
Steve Soldier
Company
What I mean at this point you are kind of
You like 23 24 25 you head up
You're 25
You've got this check coming in
From Clear Channel
Ubitus presumably you didn't really have to
Work if you
Brave enough to whole lot
But I was never really about the money like it
Every business of EverStart has been more of it
Curiosity
And it kind of what if
Enso
As I just got off The Amazing Race in his look
Getting around and seeing how popular reality
Becoming antenna
Understand the basic
Sigmetrics of
Advertising and
And what advertisers want
Targeting and all that
I just got really excited us idea of the network
If you really having your own channel
And it would be
Please focus on reality and reality
Movie stars that like a cable
TV channel
It's just amazing to me because I remember when I was
I worked pretty hard it was a foreign correspondent was trying to
You know start my career. But
I mean
I don't know Timmy 2502 tank
Restart cable TV channel if that's
It's a pretty
Bold
Idea to have
Yeah I mean absolutely
But I felt like you know I feel like it was possible I could just
It seems like
I was in this position I started to understand
By being on the show did interest
People hiding
We're just about finding the right people that knew how to do it and then figure out highway to channel
Their energy and
Get the right capital
Together to do it
So so did you raise money for it
So I did so I basically I track down
Are the gentlemen who is the founder of the
You Channel and
Somehow got a meeting with
And then he kind of said
Looks like it's so competitive now to start a channel
No
Probably about
Play streamline box maybe $750,000 you would need
Just to get
The lights turned on
And I said why I definitely have seven
$50,000
To just kind of bed on the
That's right out the gate
But I do know some people
Who really understand Reality Tea
And you have some money that maybe they'd invest in my idea was is
To go to all the winners
So the reality shows the last
2 years
And get them to invest
You said you guys should all invest let's start a reality TV
Yeah and you got the money on a million bucks or whatever
And I got them all to invest in
And then I put some more money in it
Within a couple months I raised is 7 and 50000 in
We launched what was called reality Central
So you raise money and then
And then what do you do start
Like producing a reality show
No the whole idea was it we require the Conte
Next enough
You know I did to reshow
And then we would actually
Do, like Mystery Dinner Theater where you had someone come on it was on the show and kind of talk
Through boys happening
That's a good idea
But you know so we really don't have to spend money on the continent
Is more about trying to get the
Which ultimately was he
Achilles heel and why didn't work in
Do we have to go to LA
Comcast
Time Warner and Charter needs big organization
Guitar cable
Networks
The host all the channels
And convince them that they should give us a
The slot of the one of 500
And
Ultimately we couldn't convince
Of that
You know it's funny cuz I I sir you tell the story and I think of you as somebody who
Cuz really
Try to make the world a better place and I don't know if
If your 24-hour reality channel would have made the world a better place
It wouldn't have been I'm so thankful that it didn't work I would ride probably going to shoot myself if I was running
I mean there's something
Genius about and something really horrible service
So what happened with all the people who including you poop
Unfortunately we all lost her
It was really hard I was
Pretty depressed for a while
I'd let go everyone
It was challenging
So when that
All kind of
Collapsed
What did you do
Tide the Disco
So I mean company 3
The overarching theme of my entrepreneurial life
Which I am really think
Before has been like there's been no
Connection from one business to another it's literally been me following
Kind of
My Curiosities and the serendipitous conversations and experiences I have
And so the next business
Totally that way
I was actually at a barbecue
As we were
Kind of closing down
The reality Channel
And one of the people that work for me they had a son.
15 years old and he was there
And I was asking him what he was doing that summer
You're making small talk and
Waiting for burger or something and he told me he was
Doing driver's ed
And I said all I got to be so exciting
Learn to drive
And he responded like
Totally
An uninspiring way I mean you just said like
Yats
It's okay you know I go this
Play
Teacher boring
I pretty much sleep
Class A
I like
First off this is not good
Our future drivers in LA
Sleeping through their driver's ed class
That doesn't make me feel good by getting on
Highway in the second thing is like
I mean getting your license
Should be like this amazing experience for 15 year old in
And there's got to be a better way to engage them yeah
And I just thought guys like all these
Teenagers are starting to be online more and more
You know maybe there's a way to 10 to take this
Driver's ed in
Instruction and learning
Into
The technology
Teenagers from braids
So I had this idea just kind of start a new
Type of driver's ed
We would do all the instruction online
I'm you have to pass things
Sequential manner so you can really make sure that they're learning and they're paying attention like
It couldn't just like cram for the final test they would have to
You get the
Stage is almost like a video game
And
I recognized it
One of the ways to get them to pay attention and be more excited
About the actual learning
How to drive
Was to have driver's ed teachers
Is that were
Going to hold teenagers
Is the tension in the best way I could figure out to do that
Was I hired only
Models
And actors actresses
So you would basically
Higher like
Attractive
People as the super attractive people that teenagers
Boys and girls
Be like
You're totally idolized
And I need that one
Put spread fast on the internet
I mean there's a lot of people in La that are
You know that need part time work need flexible schedules
Between auditions
Trying to make it
And I'm lucky I found some guys that were already in the business of online
Traffic school and drivers ed in
They kind of really knew the business and we ended up being
Partners in
I was a 33
Percent partner in the new company.
We form together with these
Two other guys
How did you get the word out about a
I'm Yoona we just want to get a vendor at the mail flyers in all of the old flyer so fly her sit at high schools
You know what
Stuff that lots of
You're targeting on MySpace
But it
Gabriel Brothers
Just to clarify to list
We are going to get
Michuzi
Good that you did the world we will get to that
We will get to that so it's so you you got this
Forest business
The driver side business is going really well and
I mean
Could you have
Just continue to do this car thing
Forever and ever or did you think that that was going to be the rest
If you are life
No I never think
I meant I never thought like one business
Was going to be the rest of my life
Probably until Tom's Blake mycoskie when
When we come back have a random conversation in a wine bar in South America LED light two times
Biggest business yet
I'm guy Rodney listening to how I built this
NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message come from choiceology
An original podcast from Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of voice allergy
You'll hear a classic psychology experiment retold
William is an opera fan
Who enjoys visiting art museums on vacay
Nation and is an avid chess play
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find out
Schwab.com podcast
Or wherever you listen
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
I got a ride
So it's 2006
And Lake
Driver's ed businesses taking off
Making good money
Life
But he's feeling a little bored a little
Restless
So he decided to take a break and
Do something a little unusual
He thought
What do I learn to play polo in
Argentina
And was actually
After about being down there for about 3 weeks
When I met serendipitously a few women that were in a wine bar
That were talking to me in English which is nice
Christmas everyone is speaking Spanish and I didn't
I understand most of what they were saying
And when I
Asked about what they were doing
Explain they were doing something
Hey characterized
The Shoe Drive
And what that meant was they were going around
Collecting slightly used shoes from wealthy families in Buenos Aires
Cogitate
Two children
Who did not have shoes and couldn't afford shoes that needed them
I had to go to school
And I was just really taken by
By their passion for this project and the fact that
Kids just outside of Buenos Aires to dinner
Shoes cuz
That was something new kind of new to me and
You know I have to
Enough questions to get interested
And they
Offered me to come with him and help distribute the shoes and I said sure they said
Check out this
Yeah they were going like a week later and I was
It's going to be down there still
So yeah
To what happened
The experience was
An amazing one of me I didn't have
Really any experience
Point about volunteering
Being in a place of
Poverty in
But I saw these kids really light up
When they
Got these shoes and they won't even use
Disease where you shake
Is Bethea the kids were acting like it was new
Christmas Day
Parents are excited and
Joy and laughter we put the
Cuz she's on the kids we played with him we jump rope
It's soccer we did all these things
And it was just a great day
And so I went back that evening and I was talking to my
Paula teachers in Vallejo
About the
Experience
And
And telling him what a great day I had and how
Nioh how satisfying
Why isn't
I was going on and on
Gushing
With enthusiasm
And then he asked me a question that I really wasn't prepared for he said Blake is it this is
Amazing what you've done and I'm
I commend you and
Doing this in my country and
I know what area you were in today and that's a very challenging area for
The families
He said but what happens when the kids
You grow out of the shoes
User when they wear out of
It's your only pair they're going to wear out of them
And I said
I don't know
And his question kind of haunted
I need to be honest cuz all the sudden I thought Geist
We actually do something good or did we just
Further propagate a problem that they're going to have down the road
And I remember that night like
Actually having a little trouble sleeping and kind of wrestling with this
This question he asked
So
I woke up the next morning and when the things I've done
Since I was like 15 years old as I write in my journal I'm a servant
And I'm having a cup of coffee and reading my journal and
Cat thinking about is questioning
It all seemed like cats this idea of like
Okay well if I really want to help you
His kids which I really did I really connected
Redis group
Maybe I go and get all my friends to donate
Is a couple times a year we bring them down
I thought well
Yeah that's
Once again dependent on other people's donations and what if they don't do it and
In a doesn't seem like a very sustainable way
To give these kids
Kid shoes and then
That led to
You know what
What is the hours of business
Set up a charity
Donations what if I actually started a
A shoe business and every time I sold a pair of shoes
I would give a pair away
What what kind of shoes did you have in mind
But you know at the same time I've been Argentina for about a month and I've noticed that a lot of the polo players Neva
The girlfriend
Wearing
The shoes called the Opera
Borgata
And it was kind of like an espadrille type canvas shoe that was
Very different than
Anything I've ever seen in the US
And just like
Kind of magic
Taken together
With gosh what if I sold these shoes that everyone down here is wearing
The people who never seen them
Come back here and give away shoes to kids who need them
What did you
How do you even get started
So we just started meeting with people in town made these shoes
And asking them like a could you change this to change that
Delphi
It's crazy because what they all
The country is in Argentina what everyone appreciate that the shoe is there really inexpensive and they were kind disposable and they were
You know. Something that
Put too much investment into
People can buy them
You never
Month or two or couple months
They got a new pair
And so
They thought some of our changes was in
Make the shoe way too expensive
They didn't understand that
We had a market that
Hey cuz
If you were paying 40 bucks for paravanes if I can make something
Have the same you know kind of
Longevity then they will pay $40 for this
Small-time artisanal
Shoemakers are worthy Zia
Yeah just make it in the garage is or making them in
Indifferent yes small little Barns and factories
So we got some ideas and
They were typing really rapidly cuz they were small organization
And we made a couple hundred pairs
Looks like prototypes
And
In the name Toms
Was birthed
There are created down there too because
When I totally hear what I want to do I said
I think if we sell a pair of shoes today
Will give away a pair of shoes
Tomorrow
And will come tomorrow shoes
And our slogan will be shoes for a better tomorrow Sawzall run this word tomorrow
And
When it came time to
Put a tag on the shoe
We couldn't fit the word tomorrow
It's on to the tag
Tigers with small in the heel
So we shortened the word tomorrow's to Tops and that's how the word Tom's came
And until you get back to the US How many pairs of shoes did you
About 250
What's your idea
Could you see if this would
Work like because you could have come back to the US and people would have said
These or you could have sold them all and then
And then what
Yeah it was definitely
I try to stress this
The people I mean
Of all the businesses
Did I started this was the least business
List of the businesses
China the irony of all of it was like okay there's 250
HobbyKids in this Village
I want to come back by Chris
And give them all a new pair of
So I'm going to go sell these shoes and I'ma come back and then we'll figure out what
Like it was not a business it was
Clearly like
This is a way for me to
Kind of
Stay connected to this amazing feeling I had helping these kids
And Annex
Excuse to come back to Argentina which I'd totally fall in love with
And and that was it and I still do the driver's ed business I'm still kind of have my normal life is
Is an entrepreneur
This is kind of be my side project in my kind of
Own personal
You know
Fun philanthropic
Experiment
And so
When you came back
Tell a
How did you
How old is she
What you do
I mean first I said I kind of got
Some friends and my sister
Girlfriends
Kid stuff DeKalb IL
And they luckily they like them they thought they were cool and they were different and they like the
The style and they love the idea that they're helping
What did you charge for
Originally prices
37 box
And so
I sold a few pairs that way and then I got
The people look
Pokemon La that worked in PR that I
Had met through friends
The friends
To help me
Try to get the story out there cuz it was a really
Story and the same time
They do seem like kind of cool trendy kind of fashion stores
Don't like to carry stuff that no one else has in this is
Clearly that
Answer my first account was a store in La called American Rag
I went in there with a lily a backpack full of shoes
Some pictures of the kids that weed helps nausea
Cantina
And
You know the girl's name is Courtney she was a shoe buyer
And I sure do the shoes and she really liked them
And then I told her
The story Inn in
Just loved it
Like this is totally unique
Totally awesome
She asked me how many pairs I had to sell
I said we'll acai
Start 250 episode about 30 pairs
So 220 Avila website that selling them
As well and so she took I think like 85 pairs
Put a little display in the window at American dragon that was our
It was our first big account
Paramore the funniest and most
Amazing
Hearts the story and really, turning point all of it was
This woman Booth more who was at the time and the leading fashion writer for the LA Times
Chi
Was in the store American Rag and heard about
The story
And she asked for my information
She contacted me in
She interviewed me
I did interview at or the story
No emailed her a picture of one of the shoes
And the next Sunday
It was like on the cover of the calendar sex
Daily Times
And that day we sold
2200 Paris
On the website
Wow
But I only had like 80 pairs of my
My apartment in your car
2200 Portage
You do
Well I kind of freaked out
I also did worth
I think a lot of entrepreneurs doing
Time of dire need a start put
As many ads
For interns
On Craigslist
Is that good
And I got this like small army of interns to help
Basically be customer service to email and call all these
People let him know that
There is no chance
Said they're going to get their shoes in the four days or five days the website
Promise there's going to be more like
Couple months
Longer
Because I had to go back and make
Argentina
You literally had to
Havana plane and go back like 3 days later after I get the intern set up with
Like laptops and phones in my apartment I said okay I'm going back to make the
Tissues I took the article
Do I need that would never believe me
And I literally
Prettyboy nosara
Take a taxi to this guy's house one Torres who
Who is making the shoes
In his garage for
The time had Alejo meet me there
And I walked in
With the little Spanish I knew I said
Something like that
Muchos
Zapatos rap
And yeah I know
Just got cranking and one called some friends over and
Other people who knew how to make this
Shoes and
We got our own little kind of small little fact
Are you going in this old barn
I down there
And after a couple weeks
We got to work make about 900 pairs of
I'm out of this little operation
Imadri for weeks
So you have
2200 Paris
Excuse being in Argentina
And
Did you ship them back
Did you like
Stuff them in suitcases like we literally let me know it was like we put them in like big
Boxes in and they flew back with me on American Airlines
Send the cargo area the airplane
See what kind of LAX
With giant boxes of shoes
Erase back to your
Apartment in Venice with the interns and we started
Shipping in the house from Bach like
So did you have boxes made and emptied it look professional or did was it just like
Justice shoes
Padded envelope basically
Until we got the UPS guy
To actually
Comstock Park
I pick up every day wishes
Great sweetie Netflix
Take him all the way to
The place
So
I'm serious we are running shipping the stuff out of the apartment
Everyday and
And then because of that we're getting mortars online and we started talking
Stores
Password
You are like honor roll
And then the next big break was
We got a call
From Vogue magazine and
And that funny thing about that was I had just seen the movie The Devil wear
Can't Stop
Summer I see Meryl Streep video playing Anna Wintour
And I see how challenging she is Dan Hathaway's character and when I got a call from Vogue
Come to New York to meet with
I was horrified I wanted you to
Come there to meet them
Well I'm the one interview me and they did read the LA Times article
So
C I went and interviewed me and then later they did a photoshoot in Venice and
Next thing you know we're in Vogue and when were in Vogue
Just all kind of
What exploded
Everyone
The crazy thing is it
People just assumed like we were like a real company when we are in Vogue
And so we are getting calls
Nike stores all the country even
Celebrity start
That was also the benefit of thing of being in LA and that it was just such a radical idea like
No fashion company your shoe company has ever liked
Giving something away every time I sold it in
I think that naturally appealed
Certain
Celebrities in
And they also like
You're wearing things
Other people aren't having like
It's new and so
So we just started like without any work on her own we just started
Sing celebrities wearing the shoes and they start being photographed by the paparazzi and then it starts showing up in
Things like People magazine and US Weekly and okay and how
The craziest moment
For me was when I saw a stranger
Actually wearing
That was about
Three or four months later I was actually in New York
Trying to sign up some new stores
This is right before Vogue came out
Discouraged I was going to that airport to fly back to LA
And actually wasn't wearing my shoes I was wearing a pair of running shoes anyways I'm at American Airlines checking in
Kiosk and the girl next to me
She probably mid-thirties
She's wearing red para tops
At this point like the only thing ever seen
My parents
Friends my interns
Made my neighbor
You know and I was so excited me like yours like
Total random person wearing a pair of shoes so question
Yeah
So I says we're doing the checking as excuse me I said damn
I couldn't help but notice these shoes you're wearing
You're really cool what are they
And she like
Ligament stress out there Tom's Tom's
This is like the most amazing comp in the world I might not really tell me about it
Check when I bought this pair of shoes
They gave a pair to a child in RG
And I am right
And so I said well actually
You know
MSU Blake
I started Toms
Dead Silence
She just said
Can't believe it
And then she listens
Why did you cut your hair
A question in the fighting was why should I cut my hair why she knew I live in about all this stuff was
Because of at this point now
You know where
We're on Facebook and where
You know we're promoting on YouTube and
She had not
Just a customer
She's gone line in like learn
Everything sheep
He could about the business
And it just really started to
I kind of like
In my mind
Come up entrepreneur and mathematical stamp
Point B a quote
Bic
Everyone who bought a pair of TOMS new
Morris knew that when they were buying a pair
You guys were
Prepare to
Yeah me and you're only days I think that's
Primary
Driver of why people bought Tom
The shoes were
Frankly not that good a quality
They didn't last as long as we had hoped they would I mean
Yeah they were different they were stylish Etc but
That the giving was at
Huge huge driver in the early days
I mean I'm like a turtle
3 years behind everybody else
And I think the first time I heard about Tom's was
In 2009
This commercial
Yeah what was that about
So I
Was doing a lot of media about Thomas and so I think I was doing a CNN interview
And
The woman asked me
She said how in the world do you run your business cuz I just got back from Ethiopia on a giving trip
And she's like
You on your Ethiopia last week you were in you know Argentina 3 weeks before that and your this fast-growing business
Like how you running this company and
Being in all these places we are giving out the
Cashews and I held up my Blackberry at the time
Which I had and it's a disc
I said I can literally
Approve designs take orders
You know
To everything from this
And I can do it from Ethiopia
Someone
Who I worked at Bebe D&L at age
Who AT&T with our clients
Saw that interview
Enneathought
Man this guy uses AT&T this is the best commercial we get everything
And thankfully I did use it
They called me late
They said okay well we going to talk to you about an idea we have for
Commercial my name is Blake and I'm the chief shoe Giver at Toms shoes they went with us on a real giving trip
In Uruguay when you went and handed out
Choose when we choose
They filmed us in our office
I need a network with great coverage because for every pair of shoes that we sell
Everything was just is
Only real toy legit and they made it into
A very different type of commercial for AT&T
But it just hit a nerve
That was a turning point
What that made that turn Tom's from like
Kind of this this fashion
Nice thing to a major shoot
Yeah I mean that was it
Because now I mean your millions and millions
Have Americans at least four
Sing our story multiple times throughout the week on different shows and commercials that
And that was just driving the business and an incredible way
And by this point had you
I mean I'm assuming you you hired
18 to help you
Run this
Growing business
Cuz you were probably doing
What kind of Revenue are you doing
Every art that point we are I mean we did the first year
And business
I want to say we did
About
The second year we did about
3 million
And the third year we did
Like
15 million
In the fourth year we went extinct
We went from basically from zero
To 450 million dollars
Sales on an annual basis
Enlight
7 years
You know I think
We can the fastest growing shoe company in the world
Insane
Yeah it was insane
What did you find to be
The most hardest thing about growing so quickly
You know
But after that commercial Nephew just started like
Going gangbusters
Aladdin shoes
Making a shirt
Andy I didn't even I mean even until just
How to say recently as the last
2 years
Making the shoes has always been the hardest part 4
Because none of us
Swear Shoemaker
None of us were
You know Productions
People anyways all
Just different people I met along the journey that
You had a passion
Jennifer you know
For helping kids and doing something disruptive and having fun in like
And so the discipline of being great making shoes has always been
And something that we've struggled with
And we really just recently in last couple years gotten better at
I'm wondering about
Something happening around 2011 2012
Cuz you you decided to just take a step back from
From the whole companies
Drop off the map
Hawaii
Well
The in the business was
Was becoming
Pretty
Corporate pretty kind of bureaucratic we had
Yeah well leadership team that we had built that was
You know maybe not running it the same kind of way that we used to in St passion and
I didn't feel connected
To the mission of TOMS and
And I was questioning like is it something with the rest of my life or like my other entrepreneur gigs is it time to go and do something different
Until I just thought the best thing for me to do which I've always found is when I'm
Struggling in statistics
Getaway in
Can't be alone
Sometime
And I did that what did you do did you get you just like.
Now I'm at the Austin Texas where I originally
Love often and I just got married since my wife and I
Seidman Dawson for a year
Melissa company became super corporate and you are kind of dissolution
What happened to make you want to
Return to it
Ultimately I realized there was more to be done
You know like we had bigger
Ambitions than what we had accomplished before
Now I feel like we could use our model
How to help more people with more products
I had enough new things that kind of get my energy
Play again
You know it was just time for me to come back and is really my wife Acts
Play she recognized that I was
Kind of getting into a depressed state
In Austin
And I just realized I was gone that I loved it like I missed it I miss the people I missed
I'm being in it missed the challenges
Messing you refer to Tom's
Does a movement
Rather than a business obviously
You know there's a
People are cynical about that
Oh that's true
That's just Blake use it you know yeah he's just using that as a way to
Generate more interest as business but
Is that like is that how you see it a movement rather than a business
You know I think I think that
The movement part
I really felt that
When I cuss
Customers
AR
Rain gauge
In the
The effect that there have
And that
Maybe buying a pair of Toms
Was the first step or maybe it's
The 10th step in their desire to
To be more conscious
Consumers in human
And so
To me that is more of a movement of a way of thinking
And it is a business
Like you
Menu you've read and
And know about
Do you know over the years people have said look you know
This might sound like a
The great business
Actually X is
Disrupting markets
Days Inn
Dashie not helping alleviate
Poverty
And you know
Directions
Creating other problem
I mean try some of those criticism
AR
Aren't there some
A merit to them right
Yes I mean that the first in kind of most
Prevalent criticism
Has been like okay if Tom's really want to make a difference in the community
They would not
Just focus on a they would focus on job creation
And that criticism was really difficult to hear it first because frankly I just didn't know how to address it like I agreed
You know what yes and Theory would be amazing to create a bunch of jobs in Kenya
But I mean
How in the world am I going to figure that out
I like everything else
But ultimately back in mm
I think it was
The 12
We made a pledge to
Manufacture as many shoes as we could in the countries that we give in
And today were manufacturing over 40%
Have our giving shoes and Country
Trees like Kenya Ethiopia India
You lots of different places
We're also giving so was that was at 8 direct response
To your critics are sort of like saying you know what you're right
It was
It wasn't it was a it was a humbling experience in one where we had a
Expressing vulnerability and say okay we don't have to do this french fry
And we start small we scaled is moved on and it's actually been
You know now it's something that we pride ourselves in is part of our business
The idea of the buy one and then we'll go
Give one to somebody need really you know you
You guys are crazy you are credited with
Really starting to smiley
Probably warrant the first they were probably other companies out there doing this but
You know you did this on a very big scale incense and lots and lots and lots of
Companies
Have follow that model Warby Parker
Another
And it's been good for business.
Benadryl
Really good
Yammy I think of all the things we're most proud of
Toms like
The Legacy that we've created in in this model has become
Not just
Irrelevant model of Toms but with lots of companies around the world
And it's encouraged even companies will be on the one Ford Model
To incorporate giving more into their actual business
This model not just
A check that they write at the end of the year you know to a non-profit
I think about like the Arc of your career
I mean
The laundry business for
College students and the
Outdoor advertising company and
Reality TV channel in the knee
TN driver's ed
The school
I mean very different from what
Did you get with X write like
Very very different
Do you think that you could have done Tom's without
Without doing all those
Biggest companies
I don't think
Tom's would be where it is today if I hadn't had the
His experience
The thinking behind Tom's was always there but it was always something that was more than
In order of
Make money first
Help others second
Because that's how every other
Business person I've ever known
Have done it you know I never
Had a rat about anyone that was
Helping people as they were building the business
And I think that Tom's is
Is like my soulmate a business
Venous Lake
I get to be
Be creative
I get to find meaning in that
Yunnan
Recognize it
Amount of wealth
But now my wife and I were responsible for what
Was far more than we would ever
Men think about spending In Our Lifetime
And so we made a real conscious
Decision to take half of it
And and committed to investing in Social on
Entrepreneur so that the big part of my life now is
Actually investing in the Next Generation
As a way to solve problems
That that we are faced
Athens oh
Decton
A huge blessing in all this is well Blake mycoskie founder of Toms
Shoes by the way Tom has given away more than 70 million shoes in 70 countries around the world
Back in 2014 Blake
Sold half the company to a private Equity Group
Up until then Tom's had never had a single investor
Do people call you Tom
All the time
Would you ever say if you say yeah
People that hate Tom at the airport I'd turn around
The pit that hey Blake cuz I know who's talking
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about all the things
Your building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Think about your eyes.com
Your eyes are the windows to your soul and your health
Yearly comprehensive eye exam
Earliest sign
Serious health issues
Time when
Find an eye doctor at think about your eyes.com today
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's timeout for how you built that
And the story comes to us from
Chris Kiely in
San Diego California any other entrepreneur
Wanted to solve a problem but before we get to the problem
Here's a bit about Chris
My hair is blond
It's
About down to the middle of my back when you see me.
Pretty much the first thing you're going to notice Chris and his buddy Lindsey
And Chris and Lindsay
They're both dudes with long hair and be like Brooke Shields in 1982 long
And because of this
They kept running into a problem that men with long hair face
We go to the women's hair care oil
Search
For the hair ties that look the least girly
That's what
Guys with long hair have been doing for decades the struggle is real
It's not a very fun experience when you have to choose something that is the
Least bad option
One day in this is back in 2014 when Chris was driving back with Lindsey after visiting
It came to him I swear it just popped out that the word just popped out I got it
Hair ties
Guys in shorts a more manly man bun scrunchie
Chris wanted a hair tie that was a little bit wider
A little more comfortable
And with some cool designs he wasn't seeing in the drugstore aisle everything from surfboard
Lightning bolt
Martini glasses camouflage
Rocket launchers
Fun designs
So Chris and Lindsay.
We got this
Great idea
Let's make some hair ties
Quick and easy
But it wasn't so simple we started out buying our own material tying them off
Finally going to manufacturing connection we got the first round with our designs printed on them not what we were looking for
Finally probably five
Samples later we finally got what we wanted and it took almost two years from the time that we had
At the idea until we had the product ready to sell that was back in December 2015 and since then they've sold more than
6000 packs of hair ties to customers all over the world
Chris sells them on his website which
Is elegantly called
The longhairs
And the sites got articles to
Tutorials and tips for Men about
How to grow your hair out
And of course
Fit healthy and
Glowing we truly are a Lifestyle brand because having long hair is a lifestyle it's a choice
You are always reminded of your long hair and Brad Pitt
Styles and of course David Beckham
Celebrities who have all at some point
Warren a man bun which is it
Term Chris actually doesn't really like
So we call it a highball
Like a fine glass of scotch
It's refined
Dignified
And it portrays the proper respect of the fine men's hairstyle that it is
Chrissy Lee co founder of the long-hairs
I've been putting everything they make back
Into the company
Need for now but eventually
They have dreams
Turn the longhairs
Into a full-time gig
If you want to find out more about the long-hairs
Our Facebook page just search how I built this on Facebook and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org we love love love hearing
Stories
Thanks also for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to
Previous episodes you can go to how I built this.
Npr.org
You can also write to us at
Hidta at npr.org
And if you want to see
Tweet is at how I built
Our show is produced this week by run. Belt Ottawa
Original music composed by runtime
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to leave a grandson as Mexican for Claire Breen and Jeff
Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Rising you're listening to how I built this
NPR
Hey there I'm Hannah Rosen and I wanted to let you know that invisibilia is back
On June 1st
This season
We're asking the question how is it
The two people can look at the exact same thing
To see something
Sweet Leaf
You can listen And subscribe to invisibilia on the NPR one app
Or wherever you get your pie
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week