Support for how I built
Best and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation
Seewhy michigan
Is attracting top talent and top businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
Hey it's guy here and so begins
I'm super excited to tell you about a project
I've been working on it's a new kids podcast about science
And discovery
It's called wow in the world and it marks the first time in NPR's 47-year history
That we're launching a program especially for kids
So if you know a kid between the ages of 5 and
10 who is
Curious about the world
Check out wow in the world UK
Search for it
Subscribe app
Podcasts or by visiting npr.org
Wow
Just a quick note to tell you that this episode of How I built this is about
Whole Foods
They are a financial
Supporter of NPR
We have the story of how the company came to be was so interesting that
We wanted to tell it to you anyway so
Curious
Apple Store like with credit cards and Islam
Long as you take them to where they want to go they will help you pay for the gas but if you don't take them
The more they want to go they will try to hijack the car and throw you out on the side of the road so I
I did not trust Avicii's I liked him I didn't trust him I did not want him to take control of the company so I thought no going to go public
And then we're going to get The Hitchhikers out of the car
From NPR how I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the story
Behind the movement
How lights in a vegetarian communist fire John Mackey to start
Was it an organic food Revolution
Change the way Americans
Shop for grocery
If you happen to step into an organic food Co-Op in the 60s
70s
You would probably walk past
Isles
Bulk bins full of
Beans and
Brown rice
Dried fruit
There were no
Big Brands know
Stonyfield Farms
Are Nature's Path NOAA
Annie's
And the people who shot me stores
They were monkeys
Teeny tiny handful of Americans
Who even knew what
Kinawa or Taylor
And they were mostly
Counter Culture types
Hippies back
Nature folks
Mom
And yet all these people were at the Leading Edge of a food Revolution
That would start to sweep the country
In the 1990s
And that Revolution was
Repelled
And even though that company inspires
Pretty strong opinions
Fanboys
Heaters
There's no denying that it had a monster-sized impact on
The way we
We eat
But the person who is
Partly responsible for this revolution
Well
Here's what John Mackey grew up
How to start the day with
Cocoa Puffs
Endnote
Pop-Tarts
Very picky eaters well so in hamburgers
For lunch with nothing on it for no vegetables on the hamburgers
Maybe fried chicken for dinner or macaroni and cheese out of a
The camera box
This was the era where
Stay-at-home moms were so thrilled about the
Great innovations that
Could happen like TV dinners
Frozen TV dinners that you could
Pop in the oven and
Well I'd have a meal for your family
Where were you in life
When you first
Discovered
Food
Real food
Yeah my food
Consciousness Awakening really
Heard when I was about
And I moved into this vegetarian co-op in Austin
Call Prana house
I was definitely interested in the counterculture
I'm finding it interesting women as well I thought it was a
Amazon adventure
Yeah
Expanded my
Diet from inside to become a vegetarian
And I became the food buyer for that Co-op
And
Then I had to get a job and I went to work for a small natural
We just weren't Austin caused a good food company
And wow
I'd like I was launched on my path
I loved everything about natural organic foods
I like cooking
I like retailing it
And I thought this is something I could really
Be passionate about
Okay at this point in your life you did not like you didn't have a
A college degree
Kind of dropped
Out of college
Yeah so when I was about 20 years old
I was on track to get a degree in Philosophy from the University of Texas
I ran into a course that was required course I needed
To complete
I didn't like the course I didn't like the books that I was required to read I didn't like
Professor
And then one day the battle is over
And I stood up in the book I was reading or trying to read I threw it on the ground as I'm not going to read this book
Then I just began to read books and take courses that I was interested in so I ended up with a hundred and twenty hours of elect
However just courses I was interested in but I took control of my life I began to be authentic and true
Treating myself and that led me into this whole natural food world
So when you when you show up into the sand in this coop
You have a college degree
I'm assuming
I don't like a hippie
Type of place is definitely your parents are super excited
How does the decisions you've made
At this point in life
No my parents were
Very worried
Very unhappy yeah
The very last conversation I ever had in my mother 1987
Was on her death
Bad and she asked me to go back to school and make something of myself
I was a grocer I was a hippie grocer
And
She said anyway you have a fine mind John why are you wasting is a gross or go
A doctor or a lawyer do something with your life
Makes a difference
So I said I'm doing something in my life that makes a difference
She said you're just a grocer
I said
Mom grocery store grapes
What was it like like what
What was it like working at Whole Foods
I loved it I mean
The store wasn't very big with only couple
Car seat but the retail business was really fun I mean first on surrounded by food which I'm fascinated
With other people and I'm working with the other
7 radians work
Torrent
They're also equally interested in food
There people that you get to no overtime and a small store with nothing about that many customers so you develop relationships with
People and you serve them and I just thought that was like super fine new
I can do this the sink within my realm of competence and then I worked for about 6 months and when I
Summa an idea grew in my mind which is this is what I want to do with my life I want to open I want to open my own store
I went back to the coop and talk to my girlfriend Renee she was four years younger than me so I think I was like 23 and she was
119 and she got super excited about and I often wondered if we made so that's a stupid I did let her work how my life might
Maybe different now but she was very excited about it and we began to plot out opening around store
How did you eat
Maven get started
Well
That wasn't easy
I make a joke about it now that
And entrepreneurs a little bit like a panhandler
Except
That they're selling dreams to pee
We raise the money because we like most entrepreneurs friends and family
We thought we needed $50,000 to start the store
And
We can only come up with 45 but we decided we can make do with it
My initial stake
$10,000
What's the most
I ever owned the company
Antenna to 45000 and I borrowed all that for my
My father to with that money you were able to open up
That the first Whole Foods
Well
Original story called safer way
Thanks Safeway but safer way
And we truthfully we were always hoping that
Maybe
Safeway would sue us
Are you good publicity
And
Although selectors I had in school none of them were business class
No real
Business experience Renee didn't have any experience she was
How many open the store she was
And
Wilton we open a store in an old house not even on busy road
It was just like
We just thought this was a super cool house so we
We had a
Store on the first floor vegetarian storm
And we had a vegetarian restaurant on the 2nd
Flora caffe
And then we have an office and we lived on the on the third floor
If you if you were to walk through safe
4-way what would you see on the shelves is it like bulk
Products in Lake Mead was there sugar
Sure we didn't sell sugar we didn't sell meat
We were selling real foods we were selling bulk foods
And produce
And yes definitely everybody was a hippie
But we had about
Counting the people in the cafes a lot of networking top part time
20 people work at 15 to 20 people
So were you scared I mean you were you were still a kid
No
I wasn't scared at all you thought this was going to work
When your
You can when you're 24 25 years old
You don't have so much to lose I wasn't married I didn't have any
Kids II
For my case the worst case scenario was
I would disappoint a lot of people
And
And do something else in life
I didn't for me was a grand Adventure
Starting businesses
Fun
Fun because you're
You're engaged
You're passionate about it and
The whole
Dream just would have swept us along
And we didn't know what we were doing but
We learned very quickly
And
We got better
You must have burned through that 45,000 pretty fast
We did we actually lost half of it in the first year now
He lost $23,000 a year were you freaking out
No but the investors were
My dad was freaking iPad
But I'm
I just began to read books
I read hundreds and hundreds and hundreds I have red hundred coffee
Thousand books
Home businesses
Since the beginning
I also
I'm an ottoman optic nerve by try things
But if something doesn't work
I stopped doing it
Enabled us to learn quick
Play and we did make a small
$5,000 profit in our second
Year
How did you do that
Started managing our cost better started buying better
Less spoilage
Better management of labor hours
You know the very basics of retail
We didn't really know we had to figure it out
Local
Hippies in Austin or what did you also have like sort of
Austin High Society
So
One of the job site
I tell us because I run into people all the time
Tell me they were original
Safer a customer can I say
You know half the people that said they were original saferway customers had
I've been there whenever we don't have five times the sales went up having
I like the number of people that went to Woodstock right there
But now they were all they were all young they didn't need four people this was the counterculture and part of the counterculture was
They wanted their own stores
I didn't want to go to that traditional
Big supermarkets in very alien experience
Minsoo obviously it sounds like you guys were doing pretty well when did you when did you start
Thinking about
You know
Expand it
Well
After about
When I began to make money to suck in urine began to realize that saferway was too small
And
I just thought we needed to have a bigger better location so I began to dream about opening a real
Grocery store where you could do all your shopping there
Yeah
So
We found this location
Was this whole nightclub
On a big strip Road in Austin Lamar
That it had burned down in the crowded been a night
So
I first had to try to sell our our board on it
And try to get more money and they said this is crazy you lost half the money the first year and this is great you're making money now but
I want you to stay there for a few years and then
And I will see
If I know really got to do got to do a bigger store work
Not well positioned competitively
But they weren't buying it
And
More like I said look when I want to put more money in but maybe I can find somebody else
Turn fast
The strategy there being no one else would be stupid enough to invest in this company
What does you know
Crazy entrepreneurs
Has it been successful yet
So I began to hustle anybody I knew that had money I'd already
People that
New people in Madden
Are the Cowboys playing basketball with
That one day we finished playing pickup basketball and
He got into like a BMW and drove off
Same age of Iowa
What is Jay do
Initial J doesn't do anything
Jason millionaire inherit a bunch of money from his parents
Well I gave you a call the next day
And it just turned out that Jay and had kind of his own food Consciousness Awakening
Started shopping at Safeway love Safeway
NJ
Said he would put
$50,000 in
I was like
Wow okay
Went back to our board said
I got a guy that I put $50,000 in
And then shocked
And
Several of them decided they wanted to get more money in as well
Sosa what happen
So we we
Rented
That burned-out location
And
The story there was also kind of interesting because the owner of that building
Was this guy named Ben Powell and it been in his family lives he's an attorney living in Houston
I had to go and sell him on doing the snap
Supermarket
Building
I pitched him on A10
He started laughing kind of towards the end of my pet
I said
Interpal when you laugh
Anysex
John
I mean it sounds like the museum movie kind of recording movie he said John you are so
Full
Unenthusiastic on you think you can conquer the
Holy war
Would like to come teach a different Sun
But you remind me of myself when I was young
Let's do your God
Darn
Natural Food supermarket
And so we were able to get that store open
However while we were building it
I want to
My friendly competitors
But it opened up
After Safeway
Call Clarksville natural grocery and I really love the two entrepreneurs that we're doing that Craig Weller marshmallow
These are good guys
They work really hard
I got a good store
I pitched them look
Where can I open SnapChat read Supermarket won the first naturally supermarkets anywhere in the world
Aren't you do it with us
What are they join you instead of young
Exact
Coin-op and don't be so much fun by the way if you don't we're only a mile away from your side
Your store you're going to
Now you're going to have trouble competing with us
What you told them you basically said to them
Hey this is going to be great let's work together and if you don't were going to crush you
No I didn't say it that way I'll get cuz
Sun-Times
Funny thing is when I told the story that's how I get some charge Anita course I didn't
Threaten them
I mean I said
We're only going to be a mile away we're going to have this big storage going to be it's going to be harder for you to compete why don't we do this together
Did they have any any of their own conditions
Yes
1 pregnant marks conditions as we have to make this a real store with
So meet
We have to sell beer and wine have to sell coffee
We can't just be
Completely a vegetarian idealistic store we don't want to partner with
And I'd already thought Craig and Mark store was very successful and I talked to a lot of customers cross shop
And
They all wanted
To loosen our products
Standard
To make it more like a real grocery store
It was kind of like we know if we're going to eat these Foods
Then we need to be able to we should sell them
So
That was a
The compromise that was made to turn out to be the right compromise from a business
The business
Precision Prospect
Yeah and
So the funny thing was they had trouble making up their minds about it and they come down after they close their store up
Darfur has been constructed
And then literally like two weeks before ostrava set to open
They have seen enough and they said we're in
And so we had to we had to really scramble
When are we had to try to integrate our
Our team members together
And
Where to change the name
And this is assuming this world was
Is going to come in well
We started with the name Marcus
We are Market
And then it was like what kind of Market are worth food market
What kind of
Food Market are we were kind of a Natural Foods Market
When I see what kind of generic and cost of Natural Market
When will Kevin organic
Yeah but we don't have just one
Organic Whole Foods
And that was that
Whole Foods Market that start with R
Amazon
Smoking with her name
In the store with media success people sometimes ask how long did it take the first Whole Foods Market to be successful
And the answer to answer is it took till about 3 in the afternoon on the first day
Wow
Was that just because of
Black or was that just
Because of they were they was
Disc Institute glamouring ways an element of luck
And success in life
1 reasons I wanted to merge with those guys
Was not only because
I like them
And thought they could help us
But I thought you know what if we can get Clarksville and safer way in here will have almost enough
Sales between the two stores to break even and then if we get other customers
Will
Never look back
But again
People were so excited about the
This first or it was
It was amazing and we didn't do any advertising we just open the doors
But nowhere Word of Mouth
Was incredible hole Austin kind of
Counterculture hippie community
New about it immediately
Linda just keep
Keep going like that
From that point on
No
Like nine months after we opened
Is it now in May of 1981 Austin had the worst flood that it had in about a hundred years
And our store was located in the hundred year flood
So we're actually where we were in the hundred year flood plain but I said what what does that mean it says well about every hundred years you're going to have
What I said okay I'll take touchy
It was a Sunday night there been a lot of rain during the weekend but then it just really starting to rain on Sunday in
I don't home
Was at friend's house having dinner in
Renee started to call and said the water is beginning to rise
What are we doing. I said take the ball
Beck's pile Em Up
In front of the doors in inside the store
Because that's what I thought the water would come in through the doors and actually
They kept the water out
Till I got up to about 4 feet
But that store was not designed to be a submarine and stuff when the water got up to about 4 feet
The Punisher weight of the water
Basically broke through the glass of the doors
I just came in like a tidal wave
Renee ended up swimming out of the store that night
And
It was a Sunday and we have three days of sales
There was in our floor safe so I want to get the cash out of the store
And I went back with no lights going to
Picture it now with
All the powers out at snide
Place around the back
The flashlight
And there are actually
People wandering around the store looters were wandering around the store
One of the back I went into the office and they open up the floor safe
Was able to pull the money out
This was a time when
We didn't take nobody to credit cards
More than half our money back then was just in cash
I mean I think we had about a hundred thousand dollars
And
I'd put it all in this grocery pack
And I was wondering out the store and this guy comes up to me and he says he can find anything good in the back room
I said I'm not sure
Dark before you go check it out
And we got the money out and put it in a safe place and
And then we thought we were pretty much out of business they were cars floating down the street watching
Float away in just a moment after the flood and
John Mackey took Whole Foods from Austin to Boston and eventually to almost every state
In America and Guy Roz and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to study group
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities
These can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed return
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions and a direct low-fee model learn more at game Bridge. Lives NPR
Game Bridge is not available in all states
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
So it's the spring of 1981 and John Nikes first Whole Food store
Is literally
Underwater
It's only been open for 6 months
And they had no flood insurance
Hanging a picture with the store was like
This
Tidal wave of water come in and when you have a flood like that all the sewage lines back up as well
So you have all this bulk food and yeah we have
Meat fish and sewage and it was just a total
Horrible map
And
Stop
Anyhow
We showed up for work
And we started cleaning everything up and all those other people I kind of recognize them but they weren't team members and in
They were favored customers
Can customers and neighbors and everybody was pitching in school
Why all right hopefully should have died through that flood
We had to rebuild the store
It's going to cost a lot of money to do that and
We just didn't have the money so I thought
We're on we all thought we were finished
But every one of the stakeholders rally that if there was a benefit help for the store and
The team members they work for free
Are bank loans Money
Oh my signature which was worthless
And the investors decided to kick in more cash so we were able to reopen 30 days later
That just pulled everybody together we really United
Around that
Near-death
So did you
Focus at that point on
Just getting things
In order
No
I want to open a second store After the flood
It was like
We can't put all of our eggs in a basket in my float down the river
We've got to have a second
Store
The second store didn't it didn't start as well as a
The first story was up in North Austin and it was
In the suburbs come away from the
The counterculture community of Austin and was trying to Market
It's more conventional
In a Suburban people in it
It took a couple years for that store.
Actually turn its first profit
Give me open the third store on Austin and Southall
Now that that turned out to be
I very challenging for us because that store
Too close to our original stormed and cannibalized it
Significant
And together
We started to lose money
Play cousin attention with with
Your partners
Well
That led to a big debate because one of the
Partners mark
He really didn't want to grow because
We had this gold mine he just wanted to mine it
Yeah so
The long and short of it was that
Mark
Sold his interest
And the company
And when it's another Direction in his life so he was the first
Co-founder to exit actually Renee xidan slightly before him cuz she and I broke up
And she wanted
To travel the world
The other place
So she got a new boyfriend
And she left
And doing a startup business together either
Brings you closer together or
Rip your part in the case of Renee and I ended up working out
Depart
So then it was just Craig and I laughed
And I think a partnership
It challenge when it gets into hard times
The good times are easy
But did you ever
Did you ever think to yourself
Maybe
Maybe they're right maybe weeks at a time
Too quickly maybe I made a mess
Course I was thinking that
I mean
I was regretting that opening the South often store because
I mean almost all the sales
It got came at the expense of
Original store so
But
I really wanted to grow the business
I mean I am not saying I all the challenges were
Like oh boy another great challenges
Getting is really hard but I've always saw it is
Okay this is a great lesson for me I can learn something
Here I am learning song
I learned a lot
From
Those early failures are those are not really Kelly a store that early
Trials if you were looking to 2
Expand the business presumably you would have to raise some pretty serious money
Yes
In 1988 we decided we couldn't
Grow as fast as we wanted to grow from just
Are retained profits Tapped Out
All of our friends and family
There was no Angel Network so we needed to raise some venture capital
This was a time when venture-capital was not
Really really cranked up like it is today
We hired a banker
And we began to try to raise
Venture Capital money and we got rejected
Again and again and again are we
Trying to talk to the venture capitalist and they just couldn't get we were doing I mean
One guy who turned me down
He said to me he said you know John
I see you got a pretty good business here but
It looks to me like I look at all the stores
You just a bunch of hippies and you're just selling food to other hippies
I don't think that's a very big Market
NFL spread
Further than
Then the big companies are going to take a lot of interest in it
I don't think you can compete with Safeway
I don't think she compete with these big commercial supermarkets going to run out of business
People still telling me that today I've been hearing it
40 years I mean he had a point back then
About the
Of course I'm sure that guy is kicking himself today
But yeah he Pieology apologize to me about 10 years later that was the worst decision I've ever made
What Woody's Venture Capital companies based in Texas or did you go to like
Like Silicon Valley like where were you looking for money to go to Silicon Valley
And we got
2 based out of Houston
But
We were beginning to slowly crossover
Because we
We're not only selling natural organic foods but our quality of food was better
I'm so we were beginning to get a more mainstream Shopper coming in
And that was beginning to
To drive some
Address
So we got to investors from Houston and we got another one out of the
Out of Silicon Valley and then what did that enable
Hispanic
Yes we sold 34% of the business
An eight and a half million dollar valuation
So about eight times are earnings
Or about
I don't know what 20%
15% of our sales
It was
It's ridiculous the kind of valuations people get today
Compared to what we could get back in the
The late 1980s
When you start to think about
Going public
Yeah
But
Venture capitalist the night and wants to go Papa
They wanted us to do another round of venture Finance
But
I was determined not to do another round of venture financing because
That would have given them control of the company
And I just didn't trust the Venture God
Venture capitalists are like hitchhikers
Hitchhikers with credit cards
And as long as you take them to where they want to go
They will help you pay for the gas
But
If you don't take them where they want to go
They will try to hijack the car
And they will hire a new driver
Throw you out on the side of the road
So I did not
Tres veces I liked him I didn't trust him I did not want him to take control.
I'm going to go public and then we're going to get The Hitchhikers out of the car
So
With a little early for Whole Foods to go public or so I was told later on
But we did go public back in 1992
And we raised about 28 million dollars
Add overnight your company was worth what
Overnight be worth 100 million
An insult
What does that mean does that mean that instantly you had
All of this cash and you could
Actually
Croat
Wanted to grow
Yes the greatest thing about
Thought it was we had a
A currency
The currency being around stock
We can now go to other companies are like Whole Foods Market
You're the biggest but there were other we had other peers that you were
She was looking to buy
Yes first one was Bread & circus in
Boss I remember that Spray Company
And
Next we acquired mrs. Gooch's remember mrs.
And we did not 93
We did a big one with fresh peels
And they had 22 scores Week 1
Fatima 1990s
Winfield I had those we were able to grow much faster
So as you're like expansion
Just move.
Through the 90s
Descendants mm
Yeah I mean I have to assume that you also
We're changing how
Supply chains work in NM and how people
Produced food and and
I guess
Create new markets for Organics
That's really true we did
I mean
Wish didn't do it by ourselves obviously but
Because you have Farmers but we created much of the demand
4 National organic in United
State R6S
And
That created more farmers and more entrepreneurs wanting
To farm organic
Claremore manufacturer
Mapreduce
Organic
Manufactured
Good so we helped
We had a huge impact
We still do
What what percentage of the grocery market
Get this whole foods
And control today
I think it's about
1 + 1/2
To 2%
We don't control that by the way right yeah
What about 1 to 2% of all groceries
Which is a lot smaller than I think a lot of pee
People would assume that
Whole Foods influencer
Probably
Much greater than
The damn thing
Yeah like I said we're like a boxer punching above our weight class
Yeah meaning
It's it's it's
Surprising at how many stores are
We have about 400
I want to ask you a question about the stores
Because you of course have heard the joke
The whole food
Is Mike Holt
Check writing that the prices are so expensive
For most people so, do you think that's a fair criticism
Well
Of course we don't like that
And it's not I will not
Nickname was given to us it was first giving to us affectionately
But people who loved us
And then it became a
Clubman
People would be tan Whole Foods you didn't like us
And there's a kind of a tendency I think
For people to think
You can get the same quality stuff at lower prices
I don't think
People have the same quality Whole Foods has
I think we have the best quality
So
It's about a
Trade off that there's
You just between quality and price
You have people who
Who attacked you as well cuz you
And you've been kind of a lightning rod
With some of the things that you've
You said and written about
Climate change
Interviews of August
People that don't seem to jive with Whole Food
Well my take is a course that people that know me like me people that don't know me and
And I just read things or hear things they project
But
Yeah I've learned
I've learned a lot
I've learned that they're like
Four topics
I just don't talk about in public anymore what are they
I don't talk about politics
Religion sex or GMOs
What what what is there left to talk about
I mean
I don't even care if people hated me it's just that then they trying to attack Whole Foods yeah baby stop picking on my kid
Do whatever you want with me but leave the kids out of it
John when somebody like
Anyone listen to this
She's going to call for traffic when I walk into a whole food
There's a feeling that you get
The company
Has certain values that I think a lot of the show
Identify with
Right there as you know
There's
They're sort of an entity
An attempt to
To help make the
Replace into
Community organizations and it's
It's it feels very
I mean lack of a better word I feel so
Tattoo till our people and so
You can understand why people
Are interested in the people
Behind Whole Foods
You guys are interested in how you say
Yes
And
I don't know I don't equate liberal with caring
So I don't like going to get in a political argument with you but
There's a meta-narrative about business in our world narrative is that business sucks
And businesses is greedy and selfish and exploitative
It only cares about money
But
People don't want to believe Whole Foods Markets
A different kind of company we are we're purpose-driven were stakeholder focused
If I'm proud of anything
It's that Whole Foods Market has mated if
And are we do care
You know I'm wondering whether
Some of the critics
Shazam that you've had over the
See no evil away Whole Foods
Does busy
Has been improved whole foods that have there been times where people have said
But you know what your health is doing with this is wrong and
For protesting
Change the way you guys have actually operated
Yeah has I mean the most famous example is backing
In two thousand and
We are being picketed by
Animal Rights Act
That
We're very unhappy about this
Particular duck we were selling
Which they consider to be a factory farm.
What I got
Your dialogue with one of the actor
Abra passionate so young
A woman named Lauren arnelious
And I know after about a month or so
She sends me an email and she says
You know Mr Mackey icy after our dialogue
You are very ideal
However
When it comes to
Livestock animals honestly you don't know what you're talkin about you are not well informed on the subject
And
You know I thought about it but you know she's really right I don't know.
What about this person lamp
I decided to become an actor
For myself and that summer summer 2003 read about a dozen book
How we raise animals in America
And I was
Utterly horrified
I guess I just been living in denial it was complete wake up
And
By the end of the summer
I made two resolutions one I was going to go
Become a vegan
The number to I Knew Whole Foods needed to do a much better job that the accusations that the animal rights
People in need about
What we were doing were fundamentally
Correct we
Then began the process of bringing in animal activist
And Whole Foods people and dialogue
And that
That led to the global animal partnership which Whole Foods Market sponsored and
I tried to follow the gaap standards for the last several years
Whole Foods obviously had this explosive growth
Andrea Lee
Became the biggest
Market
Country but
As was predicted
The big guys got into this game I mean Walmart is a bigger organic
Go grocer now and
There's Trader Joe's and there's competitors and does that
Does that keep you up at night
No I mean
It's just new challenges
This is the great thing about business
I mean I just can't emphasize creating a business it
There is no point in business where you can say I'd last I have arrived
Yeah
What makes business so amazing and I can capitalism so Dynamic is that
Fat people
If you're successful
When people copy you
And that's what happened.
People copy.
That helps keep your edges and helps keep you
On your toes
Complacency is a very very bad thing to have in business
The two things that hold bring a lot of business to down once complacency and you get successful when you start
Sit on your laurels the other ones hubris
Arrogance
That you're just better than every
That's a huge mistake those are both big mess
I'm trying you still alive
Of course live in Austin so I'm assuming that now and again you must pass by the location of it
Saferway
Stored
Do you ever go out of my way to pass by a n d what is it what is it today
It's a school
It's a school in front one of my friends started that school like a belly School
And
I got a tour of it a few years ago
Anything that was so autocrat they change some of it
Boracay remembered it
Just like it was yesterday and I could see where the
Are we on our block been so I can
See
Cuz they left
The basic structure of an impact
So it was it was a trip down memory Road for sure
I need you you will not
Run Whole Foods right
Youku Vaughn retire whatever I mean
Candle Company can Whole Foods continue without
Charisma without your charisma without
Your vision
You are running
Of course
A can
And but I mean I do think when the
When the founder
I'm the last founder left and Craig was the second-to-last I think he left almost 20 years ago
And lot of the people that built the business with
Besides the founders their retiring now cuz in their sixties and they made a lot of money to over the years through Whole Foods
So they'll be no one ever loves Whole Foods Market as much as as I love it
Yeah but
Building a business with a little bit like having children and watching the children grow up is that you
You hope your
Child is healthy and I hope
Burt Reynolds happy inoki child has integrity and does the right thing and
I think it's important to have a a good
Founder and entrepreneur
The great businesses
Continue to live on after
The founder movie
Whole Foods is in that in that space
John Mackey founder of Whole Foods
From that one tiny store to
Today
Companies market cap is now about 11
Billion dollars
And despite selling lots of meat and dairy products
John is a committed vegan
Add a pretty good home cut he's been known to serve his dinner guests
Tofu with mushrooms tahini and broccoli
For dessert
Avocado chocolate pudding
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things your building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Pitney Bowes
Pitney Bowes provided
Technology that helps
Retailers turn Us online businesses
Global one
Today
Global e-commerce Solutions
Enable retailers to sell online
In 220 countries and territories
Pitney Bowes the Craftsmen
Commerce
Visit pitney-bowes. Com
Craftsman
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
It's time now for how you built that and the story is from Kyle Ewing
In Denver Colorado who got his idea for a business
Kind of a roundabout way
I got the idea when I was trying to create a product for students traveling abroad this product was
A backup copy of their passport Kyle was trying to sell backup passports online that
Would be as durable as the real thing but also tear proof and waterproof
Problem was the market for this type of product doesn't yet exist
So I was trying to create the market which proved to be very difficult and I was trying to figure out what to do when
When the phone rang and the guy the phone
It was actually somebody who said hey Kyle I love your passport I even bought four of them for my kids
Set all four of my daughter's use the SOS world pass I love it but I have a question for you can I buy a
A case of your paper and at that moment
Kyle realize that the waterproof paper he was using for the passports
Was actually a better business idea is just the passports that moment was me standing up
Out of my chair
And spiking the pencil
And doing a touchdown dance because it was an immediate
Lightbulb moment where I realized this failing business
Just Brew legs and all of a sudden I had a million and one ideas of what I could use
Waterproof paper for and the fat is a pretty long list waterproof
Restaurant menus
Waterproof children's books waterproof Maps field manuals for the US Navy nautical charts
For the u.s. Snapchat back up just a little
Kyle is not an engineer but he was working on the passport idea he made a bunch of calls to Chemical X
He told them he was looking to make a paper that was totally waterproof much more waterproof than say
Laminating something so iteration after iteration we finally got to paper that's
Both
Waterproof and rip proof and something that can also receive and hold ink when it's been pretty
Eventually found a manufacturer in the US to make a polyester pulp that could be pressed and roll
Into waterproof
Paper
Do you want to Tinker with a product himself so he moved a laser printer into his living room but
When I put it through my home laser printer
Immediately white smoke came out of the printer and it smelled like burning plastic and
The entire printer was trashed after the hepatitis very supportive wife Ashley came home that night
Smell the burning smell and she said Kyle I love this arts and crafts project you've taken on but I think it's time
Time to get you a more realistic product or business idea
But one printer and seven iterations later and Kyle says he came up with the most waterproof
Paper on the market and he has the clients to prove it including guess the US Navy and airforce
Several restaurant and hotel chains University Labs even Google
The good old days when you sit back you look at your sales or you look at the new client you just got in youth
Sing oh my gosh this is a real business
I'm building something that matters
And it actually is a success
Kyle Ewing of Denver he launched
Perris Lake
Paper 3 years ago
This year he expects Revenue to reach into the low Millions
If you want to learn more about terraslate head to our Facebook page just search how I built this on Facebook
Of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org we love hearing from you and thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more about it or listen to previous episodes you can go to
How I built this
That npr.org
Please also subscribe to the show at Apple podcasts or wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please
You give us a review
You can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send us a tweet gets at
How I built this
Our show is produced this week by run teen Arab Louis to also
Composed the music
Thanks also teneva Grant sanaz meshkinpour
Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers I'm Gyros and even listening to how I built this from NPR
Hi this is Terry Gross the host of fresh air
This month marks fresh air
30th Anniversary as a daily NPR interview program
That means
Our show is older than two of the people who work on it
So how are we celebrating
By doing more shows
You can find our podcast on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Thanks for listening
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com