Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
As Zappos was growing
It was also losing my money and we also need more money for inventory and so all this was happening at a bat
Time in terms of the.com Crash back in 2002 is pretty much impossible to raise money from
Anyone you could not get as an investment and also even if someone wanted to invest in in
The last thing they wanted to do was invested
Online shoe company
No one would ever buy shoes online
Robin PRP it's how I built this a show of that innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Roz and how old school mail-order catalogs inspired Tony hsieh to build one
The world's biggest online shoe retailers
You know it as Zappos
Billions
You only have four pairs of shoes is that the right
Yeah roughly maybe maybe fewer now
But what kind of shoes are you wearing now
Right now I'm wearing black ASICS
I have a
I'm actually not passed about shoes at all
I'm passing out
Servicing Company closer so I can
Talk forever about
Those two things but I can't
Say anything. Shoes Okay so as you just heard one of the most successful shoe salesman in the world
Some care about shoes
And also
He's really quiet he said he's an introvert right definitely
How do you cope with a huge company like
Inspire them like how do you find the
Energy to do that
I'm probably different from a lot of
Liberal CEOs where I like to use the analogy of Imagine a greenhouse where maybe at
Cool
Company
Paseo
Ibiza
Strongest and tallest
Most charismatic plant that all the other plants
Strive to
Monday
Become baby
And for me I really
Taking my
Role as more about being the
Architect of the greenhouse
The other plants inside will flourish and thrive on their own and so from a
I guess company perspective by charges
Surround myself with people that are just naturally more extroverted
We're too because I heard that when you apply to Zappos you actually you're asked how weird you are
I believe so I think our
Application form evolves baidu
As far as I know.
That question still there
So on a scale of 1 to 10 how weird are you
I would
Say maybe in
Okay there you have it
Tony Chabot the guy who built this huge company with more than a thousand employees
Doesn't really like shoes he's an 8 on the weird scale
An introvert
People who study companies and Company culture
Come from all over the world to Zappos to 2/10 quarters in Las Vegas to see how it operates
Because as many of you know at Zappos
There are no typical bosses employees have a lot of autonomy to make decisions
But at the same time there's an obsessiveness about customer service and back
As you will hear Zappos doesn't even think of itself as a shoe company
But basically
Is a company that sells good customer service
The story of
How Tony got there
Begins as these stories often to
In childhood
Your typical Asian-American parents always
Practicing piano and violin and other instruments and
During the Summers for example practice 1 hour
Channel 1 hour violin and
Emphasis
You have two kids summer vacation and so
I was actually
Get up super early
And
I would actually just
Playback recording of
Myself playing the piano
Violin
What you would play a recording of you practicing the violin to give your parents an impression that you were
Actually practicing the violin
Right so because they were
Sleeping but they get here so
So that was my
Way around that is like a Ferris Bueller movie
And strangely
Every week when I went to piano lessons or violin lessons I never improved
And so the teachers I had understand why
So anyway Tony eventually goes up
College graduates in the mid-1990s
And it's not like he goes right into starting Zappos
The first
He goes to work for Oracle as a low-level programmer
I wasn't there for very long I think I was there for five months and it's just straight out of college and
The actual work I was assigned to do was
Pretty
Boring ass
This is right about when
The internet and the World Wide Web
Started cuz I remember it didn't even
Really exist I don't think
Before or at least two summers before
And at the time these web design and hosting agencies were popping up left and right answer
Sanjay and I decided to
Do that on the side while we were both our day jobs were at Oracle but during lunch breaks in it
Would go
Start selling and designing websites for different local small businesses so you guys are like doing a side Hustle
Yeah and then we had this idea for
But at the time advertising on online
Very very rare at In-N-Out near today if you go to
Any website
Seattle
Play Spit
Back in the day
If you went to the website and it had an advertising
Actually kind of badge of honor because only the really big but sites
Like Yahoo
Have never dies in customers so you guys were trying to act like a web-based ad sales company
Original we didn't really Ashley
Intend to start his businesses
Find those things we were bored and
Let's try this and see what happens and so we literally just
Contacted to a hundred random websites.
We thought were interesting
And how would you even contact
Reba
Casino them cuz
Back then people
Alright. Com
What was your pitch when you email them
Basically that we're trying this thing out and
If you just put this little piece of code into the your website banners will start showing up and
You send us your banner and
Make sure that it's showing up on other website
The same thing that was
We weren't really trying to
Pet Shop
Virginia
Participate you basically got like a lot of small websites to join
Kind of a network and then agree to run ads on their site
And you were like the middle that right you sold those spaces on websites
Two companies that want to advertise
Yeah
Wow so incredibly good time
Hanover
Two and a half years we end up going to come here
Chicago link Exchange
It's about a hundred or so people
And then
Ultimately ended up selling the
Connect to Microsoft
In
Okay first of all Tony
This is not how this narrative is supposed to go
I mean you are so young and this is just three years after you graduate from college so
I totally overwhelming that that that that happened so quickly
The whole thing definitely seen
Very surreal but at the same time
What a lot of people don't know is the real reason why we ended up selling the
The company
And
The real reason was because
Company culture
I've gone completely downhill
And I myself try to getting out of bed in the morning to go to my own company
You just kind of weird
Feeling because when I was
Viber
We were all friends
A lot of fun we were
Kind of your typical.com startup back then we were sleeping under desk
Had no idea
Weekly was working around the clock but it is
Really exciting and
Going in as we started
Hiring more and more people we eventually ran out of
Either friends or friends of friends and
So how to do
How to do interviews
And so on in
Not everyone we hired was
Good Burger
Children by the time we got to a hundred
People
It wasn't anyone's
I was just
Death by a thousand
Is 100
Supercuts in
That's really what led to the sale
Soap silhouette
You just like cashed out and moved on
Well in Silicon Valley
Muesli
There's a four-year
Soon as a 4 year vesting for
Deer stocking
I'd only been there for a 2 and 1/2 years
So
Really had to stay for another
You're in a half after Microsoft
Acquired Us in order to get
The full amount
What the deal
It was structured for it but I ended up
You away from
That way
I guess I could have easily just sat around
For your nap
Buddy 2
So just to be clear you you could have made
Much more money if you had stayed for like
Another year-and-a-half but you walked away because you were miserable
Yeah I think I just started going down the path of just trying to make sure that I
Being true to myself and doing things
Because
It's what I want to do versus what is
Maybe
A status symbol
Or
What Society
Xvideo
I ain't the one resource that we all
We have the same constraints
Time
So
Didn't want to do
Okay so fair enough
Keep you part ways with linky
Exchange
An Endeavor that you open an incubator like where you invested in other companies
Yeah
Adventure frog
And we raised about 27 million I'd say
Roughly half of that was
My money and then the other half was from
Other early
Link exchange employees
Add money from the acquisition
And for me when I first
Got started in my thinking was so this will be lots of fun
Lots of different Founders in different internet company
But what I realized was that for me actually found that investing was pretty boring and I felt like I was sitting on the
Sidelines all the time and I really miss being part of
Building something
Almost actually didn't get on a radar because
I remember getting a voicemail
From
Founders apus
Nick swinmurn in
He said he had this idea for selling shoes online and we were getting random pictures
Everyday and so to me
Sing like me
How's your toddler bad
Who's going to actually
Try on shoes without seeing them in in person
And
Right before
Hitting the delete button on a Honda
IG thread
Facts that made us change your mind one was that Footwear
At the time was
40 billion dollar a year industry in the US yeah
And I'm not into shoes at all so that was
News to me
And then the other interesting fact was that at the time mail-order catalogs
Paper catalogs
That
Was actually the fastest growing segment of the Footwear industry in the US and that represent of 5% SO2
2 billion dollars a year
And growing
And there's
Clear proof that people are going to
Remotely
Try on shoes
And so
In our minds. Okay to use the Internet is going to be
Much bigger than just paper
Order have uggs and so
That's what made us ultimately decide to invest
Okay so when when the founder of Zappos mixed with swinburne
Can I meet you guys for the first time
What was your impression of
He just seemed like a pretty
Casual guy but he just said since you
Nick don't have any Footwear background
Ambassador
Can find a shoe guy
Turn that that
There's a shoe guy name
Fred Mosley
Was working at Nordstrom at the time and
He told Nick
I'll join it
You find an investor and so
Are we all
Not in
Ultimately fret ends up joining the company and
Working with Fred
Wow so so at what point did you realize that
You know you want to be more than two
The passive investor
You want to be involved in the
There wasn't really any one moment in time it was more
We were also running an incubator at the time and Zappos ended up
Moving in and
On the same building and so we just started
Being able to help them or in
It just slowly
Just evolve but it it was gradual thing it wasn't like
One day
Wasn't really helping
Next day it was
Like a time when people are still kind of freaked out about using credit cards online right so
In in the first year of that company where you actually selling shoes
So in order to test out
Food whole
Concept for real
Nick would actually just goes down to the local shoe store
Take pictures of all the shoes that were on the wall and then put it on the website and if someone bought something then
Local shoe store by the shoe and then and ship it
Obviously
Not making money from each of those but it was really
A really cheap and easy way to
Test the actual demand
So that's how you would get
User gauge what people are interested in
Your mom finally just whether they buy shoes online at all
Dad and then over time we've learned what brands they were interested in and then he
Eventually got to the point where
We wanted to make money and so burning through cash
Oedipus point of how how are you finding the I mean
So after the link exchange cell
Set the money aside
For investing and also bought a bunch of
Apartments or Lofts that were in that same building
AAA in San Francisco
Yeah this is right in San Francisco
And I'm basically
As Zappos
Growing
It was also losing my money and we also need more money for inventory and so
I ended up one by one selling off the apartments in
It's kind of like when in Monopoly when you you buy hotel or houses and then you have to sell them lose money
That's basically what would happen
So how many permits do you have to sell
All of them eventually really believe this thing was going to work
Yeah well so all this was happening at a bad time in terms of
The.com crash back in 2000 so is pretty much impossible to
Raise money from anyone
And there was also
Warfarin
Basically it was just
A bad
Economic environment and Israelis
Could not get
As investment
No and and also there
Huge companies like
X.com Noriko Merced
We're contemplating at the time and so
Even if
Someone wanted to invest in an internet company the last thing they wanted to do was invested in
Online shoe company
No one would ever buy shoes online
When we come back in a moment
The secret sauce that helped Zappos blow up
And hence
It had nothing to do
Which
You're listening to how I built this NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible first to Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms
Fisheries & Ranchers
Bring you all the ingredients
Uniqlo
Create incredible home cooked meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered right to your door weekly
In a refrigerated box
ReDiscover how fun cooking can be
While enjoying specialty ingredients
Exploring new flavors and
Cuisine
Get your first three Blue Apron meals for free
Plus free shipping
Visiting blueapron.com
Slash built
Thanks also to the Acton School of Business in
In Austin Tex
They're wondering do you have an unshakable belief that impact the world
Profound way
You have a nagging feeling that you're missing the tools necessary to do your best work
Acton prepares entrepreneurs to lead extraordinary lives
Build world-changing businesses
Classes are taught by legendary entrepreneurs not
Akademiks
You work twice as hard to get your degree in half the time
Break free from the rat race
And carve your own path
Start today is Acton MBA. Org
Build
One more thing
Make sure to stay with us
All the way till the end of the show because every week we're hearing from you guys about the businesses and ideas
And if you want to submit your story
Go to build. Npr.org
Let's build with a
NPR
It's how I built this
From NPR
Gyros
It's the early 2000s
And Zappos is struggling
The economy isn't doing well and
Basically at this time
Tony hsieh is
Funding the company with his own money he's doing that
By selling up a bunch of apartments that he owns
This was not a good time for the company
I mean every week or two we had to make the choice between do we make payroll or do we pay half of our friend
Or
Do we sell another apartment but
You can't just have an apartment overnight either City to actually have to lay people off
It is early days
First a couple years just the reality of
Really are out of cash and we're out of options and so had to do
They have to keep the company going
Even begin to turn around and how did you get to a place where you were
Able to make it sustainable
I think for us a dick turning point was really deciding we wanted to build our brand to be about
The very best customer service in
Customer experience that wasn't baked into the model from the beginning that they came later
Ganso in the beginning we
Just wanted to offer good service but
It wasn't until we decided we wanted to build
That's what we actually wanted or Grant the
To be about that
Most important thing
It led
Us to do a lot of things that would not have made
Resent
That wasn't our North Star and so
Examples would be
Offering free shipping both ways
Cuz
Obscene
Very expensive to do and
We were just around trying to say maximize the
Profit margins
Then we've never would have gone down that path
And yes we would have made more money in the short-term during
Those days but then we wouldn't have
Dope brand and reputation and so on and so
I think
When you actually want your brand to stand for something or just have some sort of purpose
Anarchist
It's about to be about the very best customer service and customer experience
You do things that
Kind of nonsensical
In some ways that your competition would
Yes it's
There was a point where you really
Justifying yourself like
This is your this is what
Sister company of her
Canton and there's actually a phrase that
I think
Poison our call center Ashley again came up with
Started describing us as
Where Service Company matches
Happens to sell shoes
And so for us
Is that
Welding 10-20 years around people don't even realize we started selling shoes online and
Imagine one day there could be a Zappos
Airlines Rose apus hotel that
Is really just about
Very best
My service
Customer experience use apple cable
TV
Have a great I need that we are open to anything where
Service via differential
Jesus Zappos becomes a huge deal
And then like
At your Peak
It was I guess in
2009 you sell to Amazon why
Actually approached us several years
The forest
They just wanted to
Clarus and and I'm basically becoming being acquired ends up joining
The mothership band
Beacon elicits
Original identity and so
We said
No
Very quickly
And then they actually
In the ears
Between then in 2009
They launched a competitor called endless
And it was basically
Lunch tomorrow
Compete with us in ultimately
They weren't going to
Able to class then they
What's essentially
Compete On Em and when
And so
They try that for a while but
We continue to grow
And so
I think after several years of
I'm assuming I don't know what the details are
Losing lots of money trying to
Gain market share through endless
They are precious again and said
Okay we
Well let you guys be your own separate
Subsidiary with your own separate culture in
Don't separate way of doing business in
Happy to report
7 years later they free Maine
Totally true their word and
We've been able to continue
Doing
Our own thing in our cultures
Very different and distinct from
Amazon.cin
And so from our point of view is really
Just asked if we swapped out our prior board of directors with
A new one
You are so young
I need to eat you still in your early 40s
Anytime so much
So where do you see yourself in life
20 or 30 years from now
Are you still running Zappos are you
Are you doing something else
I know cuz if you ask me
20 years ago
Apus wasn't around but I would imagine
This
So
I don't know I mean I generally don't
Try to think that far ahead
I think it's for me it's just making sure that
I'm doing what makes
Me happy
So many people are
Unhappy
Weather
Jobs
Yeah for
Various reasons
Do I get sound
The culture
Lack of autonomy
All those things are things that we wanted to
Hopefully show that there's a different and better way of
Not just work but I just think it was a spy
Anime
Little kids that show lifestyles of
Rich and famous
Yeah and like
You you became a very rich
A famous person
Tonight
Change the way you live your life
I mean right now I live in an Airstream which
Trailer like a hundred fifty square feet type of thing
Yeah
We've got dogs running around
Kids running around mashup
Two alpacas
I just love it cuz there's just so many
Random
Amazing things that happened around the campfire now you just
Go outside and I actually
Think of it as the world's largest living room
In
I guess for me I've always
Like I'm going to
Payforit
Experiences but not really for things
Just because
Experiences
I think I realized
A while ago
Make me happy in
It's funny cuz I was
Weather this morning
I having coffee with a
Friend of mine in their streaming
We were talking about
I think was a quiz or something where the question was
If you
If your house was on fire and you could only save one thing
I'm a house what would it be and how
Now that was beautifully good way of
Getting to know someone
And
I was just looking around my
Air streaming
IPhone Maybe
And
People ask me what
My definition of success success is in
I would say
For me it's
Getting to the point where you're truly okay with losing everything you have
Tony hsieh still runs Zappos
Is he fights his introversion is by forcing himself to do something uncomfortable every single day
And the day we spoke with him he decided to dye his hair red and Spike it up into a mohawk
And please don't turn us off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are built
The first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Discover
Become a new card number and
End of your first year
Discover will match all the cash back you've earned
Dollar for dollar
Learn more at discover.com match
Only for new cardmembers
Apply
So we have
Finally arrived to the very end of the show
Time now to hear another story about something
Your building
We've got a story from Dave weiner who lives in New York City
When you tell people that you're leaving your successful software career to start a bike company you get two types of reactions
If you get wow that's amazing let me hear more
And then you get the
Oh okay go to lock
About three years ago Dave was willing to take that leap
Because
Jesse loves bicycle
He basically grew up fixing them building them
Times when he wanted to go out for a ride
With Friends
Heat run into this they always say
My bike has flat tires and needs a
The tune up
And then of course me is the X mechanic
I either have to go over early and
Tune up your bike
Wouldn't go for a ride
So they decided to design the
Kind of bike wear
That type of thing
Would not happen
We really reinvented the bicycle going through every little not Bolt
Pisco
Hornet on the bike
With the focus of Romania
Enzo in a basement Workshop in Manhattan
Dave designed his first
Bike made of aluminum
And stainless steel with
Internal gears and disc brakes
What he says what really said his bike apart is that
Instead of a greasy chain
It's got a belt drive made from carbon fiber that
Feels more like rubber
So there's no grease
There's nothing to rust
There's no way to suck in your pants and leave you on the side of the road
And it lasts three times longer than a tree
Now you might think a bike like this would cost like
Thousands of dollars but
They figured out a way to do it for a lot cheaper more like
$400
And his concept was so popular that he raised half a million bucks on Kickstarter
And then found two factories in Asia to make the bikes
But about two years ago when it was time to deliver the first thousand bikes
He got into a jam
We had our our bikes produced
And they were on the water on their way over from Taiwan
When
Customs took our containers
And tell them for an undetermined amount of time while they inspected them and even worse
This was in December started to get emails from our customers saying you're going to ruin
I bought this for my spouse for my son for my daughter
For Christmas
It needs to be under the tree
In all this
Almost offended the whole company
But about a week before Christmas
Customs finally let the bikes
Through I was lucky we made it on the very last day week
That's Dave weiner of priority bicycles which now offers 6
Different kinds of bikes
And this spring they'll be opening their first retail showroom in New York City
Hate we love hearing stories over the things
Your building if you want to tell us yours
Go to build
That NPR. Org that's build with a D
Scott NPR
. org
And thanks
Thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want more or listen to
Previous episode
You can go to how I built this.
Npr.org
Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and redis review while you're there
You can also write directly to
To us at HRBT at npr.org
And if you want to set a tweet it's
How I built this
Our show is produced this week that rhyme teen Arab Louis who also
Composed the music
Thanks also to neva Grant
Santa's Mexican Port Maria Pascual
Tiaras and Jeff Rogers
Our intern this
Claire Breen
I'm guy Raz
And you been listening to how I built this
PR
And just one last thing
One day is NPR's new Daily Show inspired by the First Amendment
What day is the new show with those who makes the news
Great guests
And topical debates all friended ways
Is to make you think
Engaged
Each day one day Will Champion your exes
Speak freely
Chick at 1A with Joshua Johnson
Confirm WAMU NPR
You can find it on the
The NPR one app
Or visit npr.org
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor. Com