He really quick before we start the show I have some
Wate news for you we have a
Brand new live episode coming your way this
Barry Thursday
Conversation with the
The founder of
Starbucks Howard Schultz
My dad how he turned a
Beverage
Into a destination
So stay tuned for that but in the meantime
Here's one of our favorite episodes from the Hib T archives
Enjoy
You were basically introducing is really low fares were these Airlines trying to match your prices
Yes in some cases they were
And we told the Republic of Texas that
You could fly at the lower fare but if you paid the higher Fair we would give you a free bottle of whiskey
And so for a couple months we became the largest liquor distributor in the state of Texas
Ron NPR how I built this show
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
I'm guy Roz and Ali show how an eccentric Texas lawyer
Turn a crazy idea into Southwest Airlines now one of the biggest airlines in the world
Could you
Start by introducing yourself to caliber
Please can you just say your full name
This is her
Kelleher
And your best known as the
Founder of Southwest Airlines
How how old are you
Okay great
Perfect okay
We are very excited to talk to you about
Hamster jumping
To imagine that before we really started their interview
I had some time to just chit-chat with herb and I learned some interesting things about him like to eat for breakfast
Normally for breakfast I have
Cheese crackers
And he likes to drink
Wild Turkey Bourbon
And that he's
Gas smoker for
Pretty much is entire life
I just enjoyed the magical
Mystikal
Aroma On Site
I'll smoke
So how soon after you wake up do you have a
A cigarette
Well it's
The nanosecond
That was a quick okay
Whittier cheese crackers
Didn't before my cheese crackers
That were the story of how herb launched Southwest Airlines 50 years
66 to be exact
Herb was a young lawyer he's living in San Antonio Texas
Where he had started his own Law Firm helping clients to start company
And one day one of her clients got and Rollin King
Cosmo
Pacific Southwest it's lies only in California
And I have an idea it looks
Let's meet for a drink
And Rollin
Came to me with the idea of setting up a similar operation in Texas
And and how soon after he sort of floated this idea
To you saying let's do it let's start a company
It was a very short period of time maybe
You know like
No it was longer than that I was just joking
But was that a very short days within days
Within days
What first I was very skeptical
But then I did some research and discovered that PSA was very sad
Successful in California
The Texas
Supplies all the requisites for an intrastate Airline
Because it was a big state that had large metropolitan areas
Far enough apart to just
Justify flying
And so well Houston Dallas
In San Antonio where the obvious first
Target
Because they were the three larger
The cities in Texas
What did you know about Airlines it
Well I knew nothing about Airlines which I think made me eminently qualified
Start one
That because what we tried to do at Southwest was
Get away from the traditional way that Airlines had done business
So I started with the tabula rasa blank slate
And I think that was very helpful
So at this point in the how old are you by the way of that
Point in your life
I was 35
35 okay so you had on your family for children
For children I need to get that the successful Law Firm by lights
Was it with your
Profitable at that time
No it was not notable
Profitable
As a matter of fact
Warren Buffett
Reportedly joked about it at one time and said the
If a capitalist had shot down the Wright brothers
At Kitty Hawk in 1903
The economy would probably be better off
And so it didn't have very great return
It was constantly in difficulty
Battleship why did you
You can think that this was a plausible
Idea
Well I think it was for your lure
Of doing something different
Doing something that was exciting
I really always have
Had a great deal of curiosity
And then I thought to myself what you know
Mostly adults
The United States of America
Haven't been able to fly because of
The cost barrier
It's too expensive it's too expensive they just saw it was business people on expense account
And so what I'm saying is that
In terms of
Market analysis
There was a
Huge
Untappd
Market for flying out there
Okay see you decide with Rollin to start a company was that right
Then March of the 1967
But of course that was just a piece of paper
And we start to receive money
To the extent of about $500,000
That's a bit was quite a lot of money to raise I guess
We were set to go to competition
At the time Ecuador other airlines
That we're doing these Texas lights looks like
Between Houston and Dallas and any other places
Oh yeah they proved to be our biggest adversaries because they were not exactly
Warm welcoming and hospitable we didn't get kisses on both cheeks when we announce that we in
Intended to
Create an intrastate carrier sobran of continental and trans-texas later Texas International
Really took out after
And they kept us involved in
Political fights on
Porch and they just stopped
That they would
Apply their incumbency
And the rug
Financial strength
To bleed Southwest Airlines
Insta death before I could ever fly
They were
Suing Southwest Airlines
Correct
What was their argument what why were they saying you shouldn't operate
Well joke
The argument
Amazing Court
We're actually all kind of specious
And this is
Monell's
Expiration of where
People attempt to use to manipulate the government
To prevent competition
That's what they were up to
So how long does it take you to fight.
These legal challenges
Well
Between the time when I start working
On forming Southwest and the time we flew our first flight
It was
Four and a half years
It took a little pertinacity
Yeah
During that time
Look up me ran out of money
And a 1969
The board of directors
Had a meeting and talked about shutting
They are lying down
Shutting the company down
And I said well how about if
I litigate for nothing
And pay all the court cost out of my own pocket
Would you be willing to continue under those circumstances and they said
Osher
So high
What books have been motivated you to fight for 4 years
Colossus Airline
First of all I was idealist
Because I figured
If they can prevent Southwest Airline
Find some introducing
What Southwest Airlines
The Proposal
To provide to the
Consumer
Then
That is
Assign
That the free enterprise system is failing
And
One of the things that motivated me was
What's 2
It is that validate
The free enterprise system
And another one was of course that's it was very hot competition and
I like to win
For what was that
Like what I don't get is it was such a huge gamble anyway because you you could have spent those four and a half years
Fighting and then winning
And then Southwest Airlines might have fizzled out anyway
I'll tell you what guy you put your
Finger on something
Because
If you had taken a poll in the state of Texas after his father application
I can show you
The 99.9%
Of the population of the state of Texas would say this single never come to anything
I'm very serious about that several people told me that they said
They were glad to see
How how much the flight energize met in that I was enjoying it
But herb don't get yourself it'll never make a dime
Did you ever get Saturday
Depression how did you keep your spirits
Wild turkey helped provide a little boost
But frankly my spirits
Just don't get down
I don't
Stress very easily
I'll give you an example
They have stress classes
Was it Southwest Airlines years ago many years ago
And up
They invited me to come over and speak
Yeah I was a felt it was running to class at 7
He said to the class you said we know
Herb undergoes
A lot of stress all the time
Hotel the class how do you handle it and I said
I don't have that I liked it
That was the last time I was asked back to the clap
So
So you mean what you were going
In and out of court
For 4 years
How are you making a living at
Well I'm still practicing law
I mean I was doing a lot of other things during that time which led to very long weeks
Walmart occasion I was in the law office for two full days
And
At the end of those two full days I've went home shaved and 1/2 a fundraising dinner for Southwest Airlines
But that's kind of the
The perseverance that it demanded
To help get Southwest Airline started while still practicing law
I'm doing many other things
So what happened on the court with the
Southwest Gas
It went
Through the United States
Supreme Court
And through the Texas Supreme Court twice
Before we could fly
And the Texas
Supreme Court handed down
An order
19 hours prior to our first flight
When was that
Well that was a 19th June of 1971
We start flying on June 18th 1971 what was the flight where they go
The first flight
Want some Dallas
San Antonio
But the one that received all the publicity went from Dallas to Houston
And we were the underdog it was sort of David versus the Goliath you know not just one but three of them
So there was a lot of news coverage
About it and that's the reason people paid a lot of
Attention
2 is finally getting underway
Were you on that first flight by the way
No I wasn't I was busy working to make sure there was the second flight
Do you remember that day that that first lytic often
Remember why you feel that you feel like
Finally this is done so it was wonderful. I'll tell you the experience I had
When the first airplane came in
It was over a in Fort Worth American Tanger
So I went over there and there's this airplane
After four and a half years
Stuck my head
In the back of one of the engines
And mechanic gravity
Hold me back and you said you realize that
Thrust reverser goes off
It will decapitate you and I said at this moment I don't give a damn
So at this point Southwest Airlines start
Advertising it starts
Flying many Ripple with it was a flying more than one route was it flying multiple routes
What was Dallas Houston Houston San Antonio and San Antonio Dallas
Do one of those legs
Well on some flights we had the fares as low as $10
Those we had
There's as low as 15 or $20
We were about
45% lower
Then the other carrier
So how are you able to do that how are you able to
Recharge
So much
Such a lower fare than the other
At through enormous productivity
But but how I mean I'm assuming you a few planes
What we start out with three
And then we got a fourth one
We had to get rid of one airplane in order to meet our payroll
Right after Southwest start flying and so
We decided
That we would fly a for airplane schedule with three airplane how you do that
Ten-minute turns at the gate
We bring that airplane in and 10 minutes after
Stopped at the gate
Ditto
It would be pushing back again
And we had airplanes that univer operating
12 hours a day sometimes so each one of those additional flights
Representative Revenue generation off
Opportunity that the other cars didn't have
Okay but even so I mean those other carriers
Like braniff and Texas International right
They were charging
Much much higher fares and it couldn't just been that you turn to plans around faster
No the whole conversation you're right about that
I was just giving you an example
Out with the ten-minute turn because it's a vivid one
Addition to that
They've whereby definition monopolist
They had been under 40 years
Federal government super
Revision through the c a b
That the Civil aeronautics
Explore yes right
And during that time
If they had a little thing Angel problem
Of the cab would just give them a fare increase
I hope so
That's how their fares got so high
As compared to what we were doing
Since we were regulated by the c a b
Okay see you weren't regulated in the same way but
What were you doing other things like
Lake peigneur employees less
Well it dependent initially
We were paying them less
As the years went on
We were paying them or their total compensation
I was superior to the other carriers and in addition
When we turned our first very slim profit in 1973
We set up the first
Profit sharing plan
In the American airline industry
And I think they made a profit of I don't know I'm $2,000 that year or something like that
But that would honor course
Toopoor billion
Enter employees pocket
And your employees were
Were you nice as well
Yeah we were the most heavily unionized
Carrier in the United
States
Are low-cost were not due to being a non-union carrier
Since we were
More unionized than our competitors were
You were basic
Introducing is really low fares
Woody's Airlines trying to match your prices
Yes in some cases they were
There's no question about that as a matter of fact braniff at one point
Put in a lower fare than air
What's it called an introductory Thayer course they've been serving Texas you know for 40 years by that time but it any of that
One of the things that came out of that was
We maintained our full fares
And we told the Republic of Texas that if you paid the higher fare
We would give you a free bottle of whiskey
And so for a couple of months we became the largest liquor distributor in the state of Texas
About flying at that time with
If a madman and you know
Tumblr
Sky auction
Glamorous experience with Southwest was competing on price mean you will not
You were not doing in fly cocktails
Like what do people think of your service versus the competition
God I got a story to tell you on that
It was Thanksgiving of 1971 remember we've been in business since June
Yep
And my sister-in-law
Delightful lady called Nathan Myra law
And she said her butt
She said I just flew from Houston to San Antonio on Southwest Airlines and
I've traveled most of the world's Airlines which was true
You know she was a world Traveler
And she said I know you're going to be a big success
You got the best in-flight service that I have ever experienced on any Airline
And I said
Am I glad to hear that how many passengers were on there play she said just me
In just a minute Southwest
Goes National and Herb convinces Travelers that Airlines do not have to serve in-flight meals
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support also comes from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Great genes
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store and they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program to turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon jimenes mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
It's how I built this from NPR
And I Rise
1970s Southwest Airlines only fly within the state of Texas
In 1978
Something really important have
Congress decides to completely deregulate the airline industry
And for Southwest Airlines
That means
They can now start flying to new cities
Outside of Texas
At this point you Southwest is expanding and your competitors are no longer just taxes are lies you're competing with
American and
And and and Pan Am and TWA right National major International carriers
So we're people skeptical that Southwest will be able to compete in
In the big leagues
Oh yes
We were described as
The Texas Airline that could only be
Successful in
The state of Texas
Okay
And then we were described as a
Sunbelt Airline
They could not be successful outside
The Sunbelt
There was a
Press conference for winning the Baltimore
Where were the reporters there said that
Waiting on mr. Larry said I know you've been very successful out west but
Now you're coming to the east
The most competitive
Part of the country as far as Airline Services concerned
And I said yeah
It's so competitive that when we start out here
We're reducing your existing fares by 60%
How competitive does that sound at that time
Were you guys already serve No Frills
What we were no frills we're in the sense that we were short hole
And I got a restriction
What you can do you have relatively short flight till like peanuts
Drinks
That sort of thing but you know
When we start flying long haul lights
From San Antonio to Los Angeles
Where to press conference
You know to announce a new service
And
One of the
Reporters there said
Well you going to serve
Meals on those flights and I said no we're not
We're going to charge you $400 less
Per trip
Right
And I understand you can get a pretty good sandwich at Jason's for $400
So when I would Point did you give up your life right
Actually that was at the request of board director
Can you were still you still had your own law practice that you were doing other work for
Throughout the entire 1970s
Oh yes yeah
And I'll tell you the truth you know I didn't really hang her
The bee bar corporate life
Because
Little boys have a lot more freedom to do their own thing when and where they want to
But we hired a very excellent fellow named Lamar Muse who was the real battler
To get the company off the ground in operation
He had substantial Airline experience
Bad. He did a wonderful job
And so you don't find me a 1981 we lost
Successor to Lamar
And the board director said to me you've got to do it and did you want to do it I felt I had to do it
And I'll tell you why because the start of the 1980
You had unemployment of 10.8%
You had a double-dip recession
You had the air traffic controllers strike
Then Lamar Muse
The guy we had to get the cut me off the ground he launched competitor against just gold Muse hair
He left Southwest and then launched a competitor
Yep that's 3 years after he left gold news there be filled out that well I thought it was some Modern modest on his paw
But because he called muser after himself
We work together all these years and now you're done
We bought him later and later
Yeah when they're on the verge of bankruptcy
We bought news there
But it was there
The 1981
So I figured I'd better do what the board asked me to do
And come to Southwest Airlines
Full-time
I was making money at the time
Yes
We've been profitable every single year
For 43 years I guess now
You must be the other airlines crazy because they were
A lot of them
Have had good years
And that ears
But it seems like Southwest is just
Has never had a
Bad here
What we've had years when
You know earnings were down
But we've never had a loss for a full year
Since
And we've never throw those an employee at Southwest Airlines when the rest of the industry during that. Up until
Has probably furloughed I don't know
A million-and-a-half employees
Throughout the world
Basically
We
Look at history and said this is a very dicey
The business to be at
Delta Airline business
Yeah
So we may be flamboyant from the marketing standpoint but we're going to be very conservative from V
Google stand for
And
Established
A rule of thumb
That we're going to pay 80% of the cost
List of all brand new airplanes from internally generated funds
And actually weld up 100%
Hermosa airplane so we had
The largest
Percentage
In our Fleet of owned airplane
Of any carrier of any size
So so
What does that mean
Well I mean
You're not taking on that
Right when you do that
So when you get in the bad times you're not threatened by the debt payments
Which is put cameras into bankruptcy and out of bankruptcy and back into bankruptcy you know for
35 years
You heard from from the outside from listen to stories
The airline industry
Seems so
Brutally is it do you think it's more Savage than than other Industries
I think
That it's more competitive than other end
Mysteries
And one of the reasons for that is
That our principal Capital assets
The airplanes
Moovit 540 miles an hour
Yeah
And you know if you have a shoe factory
The fails in Seattle as an example
You can't
Within hours transport that chew Factory 2
Chattanooga Tennessee to compete there
But if
Your Seattle Air Service fails you can have your airplanes
In San Antonio or Chattanooga
Within a matter of hours so
The very mobility of your Capital asset
Breeds a lot of competition
Did you like that competition. Did you like
Being an airline CEO and
Lighting Alexa
Was it fun for you
Well I have to adopt my son
Yeah I love being with the people at Southwest Airlines
That was like a fountain of youth
For me
They were so wonderful and entertaining and
Ghetto
Great to be with
That part of it
But
When your pricing lawyer pretty much
Do Your Own Thing
And
It's a swift Pace wealth
Things to move as swiftly at first
What I came to Southwest Airlines full-time and
We're moving swiftly compared to the rest of the
Airline industry
But not compared to my experience
Were you pushing for expansion and growth and all those things
Stringer tender
Oh yes I mean Southwest Airlines
Expanded enormously
You know something very small base
But I soon realized
It was a speech
That I want to hear
We're of a guru said if you can improve a corporation five four
Percent in a year that's a mirror
Oh okay I was trying to do 25%
Maybe that's why I feel a little frustrated
So it really brought my thinking you know more in line
Even if it might have seemed like a
It was a slow process for you
The fact that Southwest was growing and
Cat prevailed in this Industries is pretty remarkable as pretty unbelievable
Given that you know so many of those early competitors don't even exist anymore and some of the Great
Hainan airlines
TWA
Can-Am
Exactly many of them
There are very few left
What mistakes did they make that you seem not to have made
Well
We just did things
Differently
Black Market
You know what Shiva
Supposed
And I told anybody say
Mansion Market
Picture I punch him in the nose
Because here all these big companies fighting over their Market
Share and losing money and following employees
Let's focus on profitability
And if we have 4% of the market were profitable that's better than having 90% of the market
And being uncooperative
What's the value of Southwest
Overall
Oh
Probably
20 billion dollar something like that
One of the biggest
Airlines in the United
At in the world
In terms of passengers
Sunbelievable
Yeah
It really is
It's like I've had too much Wild Turkey
Fantasizing
Weather when you start of the company
How much how much did you invest
Personally
I invested $10,000
Which must be worth quite a bit today
Imagine if well it's going up some
Since then
But
That's a company
That's what I thought was
Requirement
Of good leadership
I was turned down pay increases
Bonus increase
To set a good example
I thought for all of our people
Corsa stock that I got
Rose enormously in value but that was in lieu of cash compensation
SeaWorld
Mainly paid with
Woodstock hops
Yeah basically was socket I got to do is kick out just to give an Exemplar
When I did the stock option deal
In lieu of pay raises was our Pilots to look at Southwest Airlines
Stock options
In lieu of a pay increase
I took no pay increase
Along with them
I'm not trying to single anybody out but
There was a
The head of an airline that was smaller than Southwest Airlines and on the verge
Going out of business
Do salary and bonus for three times what mine were at Southwest Airlines and that's the way I wanted it
Are you from worried that some you know some young you know
Herb Keller type
Characters going to come around and put up some upstart Airline and knock Southwest APA
Spectrum
You concerned about it all the time
I wrote a letter to her employees
And
It was about my 10 for most concerns for the next decade of Southwest Airline
That's okay yeah
And
Number one
Was us
That we ignore competition
That we get complaints
That way
Get cocky
And I used to line thinks Mullinax volume will get bigger
Think they can act big and will get smaller
So could happen one day
So it's possible
You know I'm up
History buff
And if you look at the largest companies
And United States
As the 19th century
We turned into the 20th
Most of them are gone
The central leather company
+ 1900 + 1901
Was the 17th largest
This company in the United States
But it didn't anticipate
What the Advent of the Ford automobile
Was going to me
You know what it did
It made buggy whips and saddle
And never stop doing it until it was gone
And if you look at countries
Boys look at company
They perish
If you have any sense of History
You realize that and
You don't try to avoid it
If you're in the story of how you made this happen and all the work you put into it
I wonder if you think your
Chicken wire differin
To be able to
Put up with all that stuff for so many years
Well I said yeah I probably am wired a little bit
Currently some for many people and they're probably very happy about that difference himself
What are the things that
I never look back
You know I don't spend a lot of time regretting things
That went wrong
And furthermore
I think
I've always had a great deal of fun
Out of what I was doing
And you know
People would say to me why don't you why don't you burned-out yeah
You know I was working 100 hours a week
Loveland / simplywell
It's easy
When you have a passionate joy and what you're doing you don't burn out
Herb Kelleher co-founded Southwest Airlines 50 years ago
And he served as CEO and then I'm bored
Before retiring in 2008
Featherweight herb Kelleher once
It was all a trademark dispute with a rival airline are both using the slogan
Planesmart
He was all this not in court
But the challenging the other CEO
To a public arm wrestling match
Which herb Kelleher law
You can see that entire arm wrestling match
Just go to Google and type in analysis
In Dallas
And please do sit around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first to put thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Have an idea for your next big move
Use Squarespace has award-winning designer templates
Create a beautiful website
Or online store equipped with everything you need to run your business
Visit squarespace.com to start your free trial
Use offer code build-it
10% off
If you're first Purge
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that and this big story comes to us from Monica mizrachi
San Diego California years ago was packing
To go overseas on a gap year
She was going to be traveling to 14 different countries which meant that she was going to be living out of a suitcase
So we needed to find the system where she would be very organized in her travels to be able to survive out of us
Suitcase pretty much for the year
Okay this for me or maybe even you know we can just throw a bunch of clothes into a suitcase
Forget about it but Monica she is incredibly organized
I was a mathematician College
And I was
What was burning to order
Lakeland math is one solution but when it came to packing I just couldn't find the system we try
With Ziploc bags we tried many other packing Cubes but you couldn't see your things
I wanted to turn a suitcase into a set of drawers
And what money I came up with was a modular set of clear squishy plastic cubes that you can
Could stack inside a suitcase
And pull out by handle when you open your suitcase you can see everything on your suitcase and eventually
Monica ran into a friend at a barbecue
Who happened to work with factories in China so of course she showed him her plans
Then he says this looks really interesting
Then he took it to China
Penny made of prototype for me if I told him I wanted to clear and Wanda piping I wanted to have a handle
And he made
The first prototype
Soon after that Marcus scrape together some money
And placed an order for 14
Thousand of these packing cubes
And a few months later
A truck driver pulled up in front of her house
I thought I was getting maybe 50 boxes or something
We had a
20ft Container full of boxes on them like
Oh my God what
Did we do
And that was the precise moment when Monica realized she'd forgotten one very
Crucial detail
She had not gotten the word out about the packing cubes
No I didn't have a single client I haven't sold a single Q
Fortunately her son Solomon had studied business and marketing in college
So he stepped in and he said mom said we are going to work really hard we're going to put it online and we're going to
How to sell it
So Solomon started to email Mommy bloggers about the cubes and one of them posted it on Pinterest
And sure enough he says we're just got you know
Six or seven orders in like that was a big deal at the time that was like wow like this is working you know
And he actually liked the idea so much that two years ago Solomon bought the company you from his mom
Eddie called it easy packing
She still helps out with the accounting and her husband does the legal work
And her other kids how about you but
Solomon
How does the
Bulk of the work
You know what it's been an amazing honor
To work with my son I never thought I would work with my son
If it hadn't been for him I would not have been able to do it
PetSmart, is rachio
Ezpacking you can read more about it on our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to
Rebuild. Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes go to how I built this.
Npr.org you can write us that's HIV tea at npr.org
If you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
Please also take a moment to subscribe to our podcast if you haven't done so already at either Apple podcasts or however
Were you get your podcast or show was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva grandson as meshkinpour klarbrunn Lawrence Wu and Jeff Rogers
I got Rodney been listening to how I built this from NPR
I hope your eyes burn from ask me another
Every week we play nerdy games with contestants and celebrities
You're Patrick Stewart dramatically read Taylor Swift lyrics
Or lured how many quilt there are on a porcupine
Find ask me another on the NPR one app or wherever you get podcasts
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com