Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing flag
Form used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email templates a dragon
Email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com
I mean I was like Willy Loman and I was a traveling salesman that I would
Load up my car it was a Volvo Wagon at the time but I remember once going out with
38 doors and I drove around New York State and visited dealers and I went out with 38 I came home with 40
40 support because one guy had given me to bag that he bought and said this is a joke
Brown NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movement
How did Jake Carpenter turned a childhood novelty toy into one of the biggest winter sports in the world
Burton Snowboards
So imagine being on an airplane in 1977
You sit down you strike up a conversation with the guy sitting next to you you ask him what he does
Because something like I make sleds for the snow except
You standing there
Skateboard
You have no idea what he was describing you couldn't have imagined that it was in
What are years
Snowboarding would become a multibillion-dollar industry
And if that person next to you or Jake Burton Carpenter
There's no way you've predicted that one day
One out of every three snowboards sold worldwide
Would be a Burton Snowboard and not because he invented the sport he didn't
There's probably no one on earth who did more to popularize it
And it didn't happen overnight
10 years after Jake founded Burton Snowboards
Fewer than 7%
Ski resorts even allowed snowboarding
It's hard to find one that doesn't
Anything about Burton is it didn't just build snowboards
Celtic culture around snowboarding
Culture
It was inspired in part by Family ski trips to Vermont
Glenn Jacobs
My dad sort of figured I might be something fun for a family to do
When I was around I guess
Seven or eight and he would take the whole family
I just always had this attachment
Just know I mean I
Tamia with mint no school and
Still my favorite thing to do in life is go up to my kids rooms and
Those days are behind me but
Time to get up for school and then after they get up elements of snow day
Winter in 1966 there was a brief craze across parts of America foreign
Novelty toy called the snurfer
As in snow + surf was basically a stand-up slide that
You could ride down a hill
And a carpenter was one of the thousands of kids who bought one
Pretend box
It was a 4 ft long piece of wood that was about six or seven inches wide
And there ain't no edges
You stood on it on these sort of
Staples it gave you traction and yet a rope attached to the nose
It was a little bit like you were riding a bucking bronco just getting down the hill
But it was fun
And I
Brunswick made them they sold 800000 or something like that
But it developed a sort of called
In a positive sense of the word
Nike friends and
We would do it together and we would modify them
For me
Misinterpret was the opportunity
Who's basically surfing on snow
Surfing on snow
Not always Jake's childhood was
Pretty great even idyllic
But then when he was about 13
Things started to unravel
Jake's older brother George
Was killed in battle in Vietnam
And a few years later
His mother died as well
And for Jake
It was a pretty tough time
He even ended up getting expelled from his
Is boarding school
I mean I was
Wiseass
And when I was young
Victoria Falls
End
When I got kicked out of
Brooks was a school and I went up to see the Headmaster
Who was the Headmaster one
My father was
And when my brother was there
It was brewed on me and my dad made me get in the car and go 5 hours see this guy and you know for a 5-minute conversation
And then a long drive home and that is when I decided to turn my life around and start
Applying myself to whatever the hell I did
Did apply himself by figuring out how to take what he was good at
And make money
Jake's first century was a small Landscaping
And then after college
He went to work for an investor in Manhattan
In the back of his mind
Never forgot about the snurfer
Annabelle
Potential to be something much
Much bigger
Yai
Really from the very beginning of Surfing for me
I saw it as
Something that could be
Developed
And I was sure the project was going to do it or somebody
And nothing happen
But you know
In the back of my mind I always knew it could be as forward and I didn't have a business plan for a site but I did the math that
If I can make 50 snowboard today I can make $100,000 a year
And that would be
Awesome
You thought
I'm going to I can do something in the thing to do is
Makeup much better Surfer
Yeah make money on it
So I started the company in 77
And because you were living in Manhattan
The time right yes and I made my first
Prototypes in my apartment on the Upper East Side 80s
Shop in your apartment in like
People selling stuff in or I was just clueless then as you are now
I did not know how to do it I was a loser in shop class in school
Like my napkin holder was by far the ugliest for the worse
And so there I was with a saber saw on
In my apartment making them
Like out of what
Yeah I'd avoid the very first I was modifying some Surfer
First ever round and then
I said I got to move to Vermont
Midas company
We not going to start a snowboard company
Manhattan
So I left my job in New York City in
Like early
December at the Old Winter is here and I start a landscaping business
When do we spring
Start Reiki at 1 tonight
I had a car station wagon a narrative in the family on
Fox garbage bags a couple of rakes
That's what I started like landscape business with
Manufacturing is a lot tougher than
Mowing lawn
But I thought okay it's winter now it's time to start the company I almost missed the next
Literally it took so long to develop a product
Annabelle
You finance
Get the money
Well my
Because my mother died
Young age when my grandmother died
She had some dough and instead of going to my mother came to
Play my two sisters
And so I inherited almost $200,000
150 of it
Developing Burton
So
Your middle name is Burton
Yes
Carpenter so why did you call the
Mr. Borges compass
I just always had this
Interest
And the guy was named after
John house Burton and I
Doctor
Burton was a
Cooler name
And I wanted the name of Bohr's I mean boards was part of the name was Burton boards
And then I
Drove down to Montpelier Vermont unincorporated went to the
We so cold that all the paperwork and everything was a big moment for me
Incorporation
Or maybe Burton boards I sort of did
Some form of
Trademark
Petechiae next to Android n
Yeah everything official
So you okay see you you moved to Vermont and then to start the singing and then
What was your next step
Yeah so I went to this company called
Shushan Bentwood company and they made
Curved wood for people that made furniture out of solid Ash
So my first prototype was a piece of solid Ash that was just put in this thing to curve the nose
And then I
Just start writing
The money outside literally made a hundred
But all those under prototypes they weren't all solid wood I got onto laminated wood vertically laminated at haar's
Bodily laminated like
Why would I went to a friend too
Live in California who had a surfboard company
And they would let me make boards in their Factory at night
And I would take a surfboard blank which is
Six or seven feet long and maybe three or four inches thick and by the morning I have little to think down to us
Snowboard and they were just these guys were so cool but they laughed at me went to these
Factory you said I need you to give me this curved piece of water that needs a Betrayal Knows
What is a 4 what would you
You tell them I'm in the store for there was some awareness
It has been around
So I was telling him that I was
Making a modern rendition of an
And I always feared that like the minute
Ski companies caught wind of this then
They would just jump on and I'll be out of his
Nobody cares
And it wasn't just you like
With this thing like
Messing around on Hills
Dude I was so alone yet
Wow did you ever come across people like what
What is that
What are you doing yes it was
To the point
Literally if I wasn't implying something to ask me what I did I would make something
Cuz it was just too
Embarrassing
I concept of snowboarding wasn't something that it would be like saying today
Yeah yeah
Hybrid cloud
Like that's my job I make skateboards for cloud skateboarding for sure
At what
Point where you able
How to say I got it I've got this is the one I'm going to make
I hadn't thought about this in a long time but
I remember that specific moment on Mount Washington
In June
And you can hike up Mountain you know that you know would have been June of 78
And I'm hiking up there and Hillman's Highway was the trail and I had to board
Orwell just testing the final
Past and it was horizontally laminated
Rock Maple very much like Escape
What's better and more flexible
And I wrote
Down you know just hiking up Logan right is like okay
And then I've decided on the construction now so I go out and I
Rent this place that's going to be this little
Serta Factory
And I hire to relatives
And a friend
To help me
Take these pieces of
Kirkwood and
Shape them
Drill them paint them with fins on the mat on them with bindings on them
It was a long process and we
As I said my original plan was to make 54 today that was always sort of my goal because you thought that they were just going to this is going to blow
Blow up it was you were going to need
I majored in economics
Call Ajay
Classes with
Nobel Prize winners but I don't know if I really understood supply and demand
Digital shop
In Londonderry Vermont with Burton boards written on the front of it and big letters who are the kinds of people who work on
Coming into your shop
In Londonderry
Vermont
Yeah it wasn't
People
Out for a walk
Buying a snowboard in
We didn't sell any Wheat made me a few t-shirts but
Are most people found out about us that would come there and
People we would advertise in the skateboard magazines in a little bit and ski magazine to spend some money there I mean I
Because there were these pockets
Around the country in Michigan and Arizona are these places were people
Head surf
And like me and they sort of stuck with it and they got it they understood it
That first year
What kind of feedback are you getting from people
Who bought them today love it they were day like this is going to change the world
Yeah it was
I mean I was
Like Willy Loman and I was a traveling salesman and I would
Load up my car
It was a Volvo Wagon at the time and I remember once going out with
38 Star Wars and I drove around New York State and visited dealers and I went out with 38 I came home with 40
Tortie snowboard because one guy has given me to back that he bought and said
No One Is Your Love
Pua would visit ski shops
Bicycle shops yeah that was my first
And then ultimately
You know some
Surf shops in
It was in the beginning
Skateboard shop surf shop ski shops nobody wanted any part of it
Did you have more you discouraged off my first year did you think maybe this is not going to work maybe I should
Just cut bait
Yeah I had some I had a few days it was tough
Getting out of bed
Just motivating
Myself
All day long
And you're all by yourself
Yeah
And I am like I'm an emotional guy and you know you having lost
People wanting
Always happen
So I had to let go of
My chihuahua doesn't my friend very quick
And it became
Back to me
And you're too because we made enough boards
In that first winter I don't know what are we made of
We made an effort
Three years just sitting here but yeah they're pretty much done
So I had one high school kid helping me out
Part-time and now is it
How many boards
First year was 300 or 350 second-year with 700 I member one day and
That second winner of selling
Packing up the 700 Sport and thinking
Wow that's
You know that's over doubling
So what happens
Between that first year in a second
When you go from
Three hundred two seven hundred
Why why did you double
The number for
Was it just
Black
Bossier who is just getting out there Word of Mouth
I mean marketing
You know advertising placing ads in these
Ski Surfer skateboard mags
I mean I remember going to check the mailbox cuz dealers really weren't that interested in you know
Stores
And so we would send out these brochures right from your one we had brochures and
We would send them out with a little male or four minutes
And I would go to get the mail every day and I remember looking in the mailbox and would be like you
Nothing
Couple of envelopes or Sunday there be 5 or 6 envelopes
And then you open up the thing and that is cruel order form and you can get it
You'd open up the envelope it'll be
County t-shirts or something
And then you'd open up an envelope would be like
For sale boards for a family in Connecticut I mean
I can remember it so clearly Could you actually use them
I'm assuming you couldn't
Take it to ski resort and just go down
Mountain nobody was presented
I mean
Skiing at the time was 20 bucks a day and it was a lot of money so this was an opportunity to
Express yourself and have fun out and do with friends and
It was
A cheap way to have a lot of fun when it's snowing
You could not
Going to Resort
And to be honest
I didn't start as a resort
You didn't tear
No it wasn't that wasn't it was like
A low-cost alternative to
But then these kids
Then I started to hiring more
Maybe you're 3 to what
Did you help
Assemble these boards put them in boxes and get them out of the door still doing all the assembly in that place in Vermont yes
And hand
Yeah they were just help me get the board out the door
This one was or Cromwell you could drive up to this Village that was
What are the way up the mountain
So we would buy one of the car drive up to the Village
Everybody would
If there are four of us
One guy would stay in the car the other three would snowboard down the hill
And that would meet at the bottom and do it again and again and then ultimately
Snowcat drivers would give us rides and
Bribe snowcat drivers the six-pack or something you up to a point off of the Moon
It was so challenging to ride those boards
People now they have these vintage races naked on
Also work tonight for the life of me don't get it I mean it's you know
Hard but
It was just easy on rebellious I mean
What snowboarding and Burton did as we revolutionized
Winner
Life and honor
This was the beginning of it
When when this thing
Please turn to take off
Well I mean in terms of this
Sports or my company I mean it was nothing
I think in the
Now in the context
Starting a business people think of
Internet companies in Costa Mesa blow then they wanted there just was not
A defining moment in the context of
The sport blowing up I mean they were big Milestones along the way and
Take time with cordless
Calling it the worst new sport
Yeah that would have been
Early 80s
And now
Part of that time
The worst new sport was they said it was more about raging hormones and this was his rebellious young man
Bet we're making it happen and then
Cool girls
Very courageous
Women
Got into it and started doing it
And I realized okay
We're not
Going to lose any more money
We might not make money but I can you know manage
Manage this financially
Play so
It just
Grew and grew and grew but at a manageable pace
Why didn't ski resort allow snowboarders
In the beginning
Well it was
There was a
Actually famous cases Stratton which was Resort when the first Resorts lettuce and where this guy at Stratton
It's in southern Vermont
And that this guy
Broken his leg because of some
Sign or something skiing
Annies through the mountain and I think he tried to get
Definitely got a million dollars
So there was this liability
There's this
Paranoia about
Getting sued
That's all that was their fear but
They ultimately would give us a chance that we would lobby with them and their kids sometimes out than we would Lobby Reserve
Shorts and then if a big Resort like that and then probably had to come along and Magic Mountain
It took years
But it was there was no stopping it
Also I guess start identify
People who are really good snowboarders and and
Sponsor them
Yeah we'll for a minute there these kids at work for me just happened to be
The best and then
There was a rider Greg Kelly who actually wrote for this company since you started making snowboards after we did but they
Pretty well-known skateboard company and this guy Craig Kelly wrote for them but we were good friends that always.
Old Gregg
You ever had the opportunity
We would love for him to ride for us
And then Sims ultimately sold his company to bigger skateboard company
And so we got a deal anymore for me and I paid him $17,000 a year
And this guy was Greg Kelly was a godson all Wheaties Birds
He was very impressed with all over his
Yes
So having him
Represent
That was my pretty transformation
It was beyond Transformers
Cuz you're out all of a sudden not only
Give this advertisement
But you got the coolest
And the best guy
You can do all this
Cool Staffing
You got kids singing this
Well
I want to try this and I guess Burton's the way to go cuz this guy uses Burger
You know what that's
Pretty much it
Craig made the sport cool and the brand cool
When did Emmylou a snowboarding start to get bigger
The ski companies must have thought well
There's money to be made
K2 and rationality
Did they start to make snowboards
It's just so funny that the ski company
We're so
What was going on in
Front of their eyes
I mean
Talk about
Close minded
You know
Ask you earlier, I could have destroyed us anywhere all these
Rumors that some cucumbers going to start making in the neck
We went from being
In a fly in the windshield
All of a sudden
We became a threat
In just a minute had Jake dealt with the competitors
Now wanted a piece of the action play with this guy Rising you're listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor gamebridge the Bold way to steady growth
People often think of me with these are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can be
Be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at game Bridge. Life / NPR game Bridge is not available in all states
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Marcus
Industries and the global economy listen to their podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of
Topics discussed from the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud
Google Play and it gs.com podcast
Early days for Jay Carpenter
Building Burton and at the same time trying to build the whole sport of snowboarding
Sometimes lonely
Because he stuck with it because the sport car
The big ski companies as you can imagine started to notice
And all of a sudden the market for snowboards
Wenzhou lonely anymore
Okay so when when the big ski company started to to make snowboards
What happened to you guys well
By the time they started making a weird maybe on the 3rd of the resorts
Ndk
They didn't want the sport to happen right I mean these
He companies did not want sovereignty succeed
So snowboarders didn't like ski company
I mean people did perceive them as not being the real deal
And we didn't keep that a secret I mean we made it pretty damn clear that we were the real deal and
What day did
Have manufacturing ability and some of those French and Austrian companies were
Subsidized by the government
To keep their factories going
So, cost perspective they were lower-cost producer
For a minute there
But it was just they were too late
They missed the boat
Did you ever have
A stubborn really begin to take off in the
In the early 90s
Did you ever face serious threats from competitors either big or small
Well it was always like any early days was a rivalry between bird and Simsbury
We've doubled the number of snowboards sold
For the first 20 years I think of the
So
Sims with red one point K2
Was somewhat of a thread
Got more aggressive earlier on
But now we've been
We've been the number one
Manufacturer
Snowboards since
The day I
Did you
You know what I mean even though you
Had this market share near the soil customer base
He's had a lot more money to work with
And you were
Your money was coming from sales
Yeah I know ultimately we were borrowing money from Banks
It was very secure
And then
We would get bigger and bigger and obviously we're doubling our sale so we're doubling the money that we need in the bank and you need some money
The money for marketing and for what we needed the money to make the snowboards because in this industry and ski
We didn't start this
But you do shipping the stuff and whatever August
September
And then you don't get paid until
December game
So it was always working capital we never needed long-term debt
But we've always had this need for working capital
Until we would work with these Vermont Banks and we'd get up to a certain level is have like three times
And then we get those are lovely so you know this
Maybe a bad we're going to bail
Never cuz we were late on a payment or
Tell me about
Young people money that we owe them
But they just sort of figured you know this has been a good ride we're going to
Bail and then we go to a bigger bank and then a bigger bag and then
We borrow we still borrow some working capital but it has
Become less and less
At any point did you think about
Going public doing IPO
Seeking venture-capital outside investors
Anything like that
Yeah interesting way
There was this one company called ride
And they started out
And then a guy that work for us went to work 4th Avenue sort of a mid-level manager everything was a competing snowboarding company
Convenience towing company you want to work for them and then they went public
Can they at a very low price
And the stock went up to
It's split and then we're up to
35 box with up to 70 on it
Non-supportive valuation
Which was a millionaire all of a sudden and I felt this
Enormous
Amount of pressure
Like I taking care of my people and yeah I bet and like
Just am I doing the right thing here until I went and I met
With
A couple of big
New York
Investment Banking firms and I
Just couldn't deal.
The Bible I just feel like this is not us
And then all of a sudden
Right stock
Which was it 35 bucks at the time went down to
2 Box
Because they have these expectations that
Like Wall Street just they take things and they
Project
Unrealistic
Expectation
So ultimately people have realized
Working for a privately held company
Has many many advantages
I guess it was in like 98 that snowboarding became an Olympic sport
You I know that you don't like to
Say this to you tonight but
You are widely credited as the guy who really made snowboarding what it is and
This is became an Olympic sport
What did you
Think when that happened like that must have been a pretty amazing moment
It was
Not
Cool moment at all
That was not the answer I was expecting what happened well
Spell switches
International ski Federation
Swiss
You know whatever governmental body and 8
I'm control the scene and then they started having snowboard competition
When they just said
Aside from the ski races and we were wondering what they were up to
And then they just arbitrarily decide okay snow is going to be the Olympics I mean they didn't even give me a phone call they never
How old is anyting
I
Will take credit for pioneering
You would think
But you might
Pick up the phone and tell that person what you're up to or
How do you think we should do this
None of that they just arbitrarily it's like the baseball player that finds out he's traded when he reads in the newspaper
And then I go to the Olympics
We've got our team there that I get to the venue
And they got snowboarding misspelled at the venue how do you spell it well you spell it with a W snowboarding
Today at snro - boarding is in Nagano Japan alike
Not a good sign
Right so
And then they proceeded to have the
The racing thing was
Heart condition
And then
Decide it was a
Driving rainstorm
And they said okay we can have the
Monsanto we would never have this
Prestigious P event in the rainstorm
But they can go they can get
Risk life and limb and not be wearing goggles it's raining so hard
And so
But nonetheless
They've gotten
Better and they're doing a better and better job in The American or emits a form of
National Association
They care about this morning I've got some people to care about the sport they're trying to do better but
The last Olympics the venues
For the freestyle stuff which is what people care about
For the half pipe and slopestyle that the Bengals have been
Really
As your company grew
Describe the culture of the temp
Was it I mean
I'm looking at you right now and I cannot imagine you ever wearing a suit and tie
And being like a boardroom boss like like where do you have your
Meetings with your top tmall
What are meetings you know you look at my office
It's
3 sofas and
Two chairs in a coffee table and there's no desk
Senior conference room where we have our board meetings itself has
Put your feet up
Bring your dog to work day
132 registered dogs are between always heard of
Keep track of the number and
It's
Resembles snowboarding
Lifestyle
Edward tribe n we
Are so focused on the sport everybody in that cup you know damn near everybody that company snowboard
And cuz that's our source of energy that's where you recharge your batteries
And he was like
Jake I'm going to be in late today. Snowboarding
It's Scott
Pretty much
The Dramamine if it snows over two feet it's an automatic
Day off at all company
And last year they were
3 of those days which is almost too nice I mean I like people to work to I'm not
It sucks but people come in late and work late
You know people work hard there so that's
As long as people are giving us a solid effort I get it if they want to get up there and catch a few runs on.
You're a your wife Donna
She she actually at some point became
Took over as it as a Company CEO right
Yeah
And what's what story
Well she came
And went and then she was
CFO for a while this is in your early days and then
When we had kids she backed off some she wasn't working as much then and then when the financial crisis
Which was really Roger Clyne
The big one
Lehman Brothers All That
It you guys
Well
The bank
Charge this 4 million dollars to change one paragraph
A&R loan agreement
Which was call The Covenant when you're borrowing money
Your earnings had to represent a certain ratio compared to how much money or borrowing
And we
Slipped on that one
It was a very tough year
And we weren't losing money we were making money
But literally they said well you broke his coming in so
You're going to pay a $4000000 fee
And that
Boy I mean
With the right people off
We weren't making the money that we had been I so we had a recession
Yes exactly
But you know what it's always been a youth Rivermark and it's kids at I mean people would buy
Two or three snowboards a year
Can you look at
Italy or Spain to very big markets for us
And the unemployment rate amongst people under 20 was 50%
It was a very tough
Stop time
Through this process
Of this
Crisis and I think it's not unique to burn
Art
Company culture what kind of got
Destroyer
Well I think a lot of people
Wood
Blame other people
4 things
Negative things
Is there a happening in there would be finger-pointing and
The culture of our company
Was messed up and at the same time
I felt
You're no women in our top manager
And that
Felt wrong to me so
I got in there are night and Donna came along with me and
At that level we were running the company and I brought her and
Serta specifically that
Help with the culture and get
More women
In leadership positions at Burton
When you see the culture I mean I'm just trying to get in
Through the innuendo
Is it wasn't like British was it like
Male solo Macho was it like
In what was the thing you want to change
Well
I mean you're not happy when
You're being managed by
Feeder
Or
For you
Instill fear in yourself that you're going to lose your job or
It's just you need to make people
People have to understand
When and why
Stuff happen
Were you responsible for any of that
Friday events
Fear-based up
Well I think
Many of the people that were
In and around it and I think that
We were all responsible to answer I said I mean I don't think that's ever been a
Tactic that I've used hopefully
But I certainly let it happen under my nose
Do you think that that you have a hard time
With criticism
And I said because you know
It it didn't really problematic right if you're unwilling to listen to somebody
It says listen I know you built this thing
But I'm trying to make it better listen to me
No that's
Couldn't be more true but last
And less and less every year I mean I did every job and I come
IMEI made
The first Ford
And for a while there I mean we might have had
50 employees and I was convinced
In a bragging way but I could do anybody's job
Better than naked
But that's not the case anymore you know we've been Engineers now that I don't even
Have a hard time having a conversation
But
I got better at it
And I had the sense to
Surround myself with people
Where
Better
Things
Then I am but I'm not good at it
That's been good and I've learned
To delegate
That's not an easy thing to learn how to do specially when you're detail-oriented learn to let go like that
You have to trust
Beyond trusting you have to let him screw up
Can live with it and live through mistakes and if they repeat the mistakes and that's not
Burton's made everything
Mistake in the Box
But I don't think we made too many
Why can I'm sure at certain points you were offered money to buy
I just didn't take those phone calls
I mean you could I mean
You could have sold this company
You know Ben like a philanthropist and
I don't know I'm messing with a better life for sounds pretty cool it's like a pretty great life
Well I
For a long time if people ask me that question I would say well
I think I become a couch potato on
Egyptian watch SportsCenter
So you don't snowboard funny but
I mean it's the best job in the world why would I ever walk away from it that's
Selfishly admittedly
That's always
Part of it and I think they were doing a great job and we're humming along if we were
Really struggling
I might be more appropriate for me to look at that more
Seriously
Important is money to you
Is being rich to you
Well to be brutally honest
I mean I
Enjoy having
Eligibility financial aid
We're going surfing for a week in the Maldives next week my all family
And we're going to have a speedboat it's going to take us to the lineup and
It's going to be epic and the stuff that cheap
So I love that and I would be a liar if I told you I didn't
But it's not the most important thing in life
Yeah
You're a really tough couple years and
Your chest
Now
Internet recovery of it
ENT surgery
I guess in 2015
And then and then before that you had
Heart surgery
Bright
And then you
Battled cancer
Testicular cancer
Yeah
An idea what the whole process of chemotherapy which is
Dreadful
And then
Tell Linda that I was in a plane and I had a pulmonary embolism which
Really
Still
Affects me
And then I came down with that
Miller Fisher that form of gamma ray
Miller Fisher because
A lot of people know about this but
It's
I guess it's an autoimmune disease that can make you temporarily
Paralyzed
So
Like what was that
What was going on like
Why did you even discover
What was going on
Well I've gotten the knee
And then I got home
And I was with the doctor the next day in
I started seeing double and and
I told him that he's like
Check it out see if
Might just go away and
The next day I was seeing double
And
I felt really loud
And I wait till Donna went to work I didn't she
Thank you so much
With me and
I just like and so I went to Dartmouth-Hitchcock and they
Barry
Quickly analyze what was going on and
Within 24 hours of eating it be in there they said if you have always take you out tomorrow you won't be able
Swallow
He won't be able to open your eyes
And the next day you won't be able to breathe
And were they right
Yeah that's how it went down
That's what you get to the hospital and you are confined to the bed
Surprise you for 6
Squeaks
You couldn't move your body
Hours or days
And I was there for
Over 6 weeks
You're like a prisoner in your own body
Yeah
Very much so
I think it's like
ALS
Handstand do a couple of weeks
First of all
How did you breathe
Do a ventilator
And
The ventilator was
Find me
Could hear it
But I couldn't see it
Did you have feeling in your body
Yeah
Yeah my wife would stretch me every night
Can I get certain
Repeating 2
Did you think you're and I
For sure
Per minute
And then
Can my wife did
You know she told me I was getting better
Eventually I would see these little
Eye cancer
Improvement
What you start to notice
You know that I could open my eyes
And that I do.
I was showing the physical therapy right from the get-go and then I could do something a little better than
The day before
And once you get to that point then it's game on. It's up to you
Is that
Experience change the way you
Live your life
And you interact
To the people you love
Well I sure as hell don't take my family for
I do live life
But the moment I mean
Much more than ever I mean I think
It happens through some
I don't know why or how
You're dead to me
Emma's put into perspective
All yours
Success and wealth in the sink
But you built like
Obviously that stuff matters but like in the context of your life
Nothing else
Really matter
Yeah yeah that stuff could have been further from my mind
I think it is now though now I'm like prepared to die
Really
Yeah I am much more so
I could
Guide
Get hit by a bus walking out of your studio and I still
Luckiest guy
Because of life
If you had yes
Ever had imagined
When you were
And that first you need to fire your
Employees and
That you would have built something this big
I had no idea that what would happen if snow bring passport
But I did not see
Shaun White on the cover of Rolling Stone twice or snowboarding be in the Olympics
The stuff that's happened
And it's been the athletes would have made it happen and we've facilitated it but it's been
Exceeded
I wouldn't even say dreams cuz I never
Dreamt anything on the level that were on Now
Jake Burton Carpenter
By the way Burton just celebrated 40 years in business since Jake built that
First snowboard in the barn in Londonderry Vermont back in 1977
And despite his health issues Jake still snowboards 100 days a year
Always winners fresh powder
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
A dream is just a great idea that doesn't have a website yet
Make it a reality with Squarespace
Squarespace.com free trial
And when you're ready to lunch
Use the offer code build it
To save 10%
First purchase
The website or domain
Pay thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
So my name is Jana
I'm from Scarsdale New York and one day I was just so sick of opening my refrigerator and see
Brown guacamole
Brown in there right you scoop out the sock avocado Flash
Onion salt lime cilantro
Stick it in the fridge and then a couple hours later that bright green dip
Looks
Gross this is absolutely a problem that people have and I say to them would you like a container that prevents clotting
Guacamole from turning brown smell like
Oh my God so anyway about four years ago Jane started to
Experiment in her kitchen
She made a lot of guacamole and she just started to observe that guacamole change color if I
Take some and put it in a bowl with Saran wrap it turns brown but if there was some way that I could
Eliminate
That
Are in that space
Then maybe I could
Sound that age-old problem to Jane recruited her step-sister to help out
They found a designer and together they came up with a plastic container was kind of a little elevator underneath it
It pushes the guacamole to the very top
So there is no space between your guac
In the list and then you simply
Close the tab to cover the air hole
Put it in the refrigerator
Forget about it literally forget about it I mean a week however long you're going to eat your guacamole
Will not turn brown
Okay so they have the right design but for two years they ran into one problem after another
Are we using the wrong materials or the little elevator thing wasn't fitting properly
But finally last year they got it out of the factory and into the market
And they called it
The guac lock
You can lock anything up so
Tuna fish
Egg salad you know chopped vegetables pesto
Hummus in the more you can switch it and remove the air holes
The better
It's going to save
Searching this is not my main problem with guacamole because
With the lock your men of your kids at the guacamole so they don't eat it all before your guests cup
But you're right that's a good idea that is a problem in my house
That's our problem I get into the kitchen I just feel like green
Guacamole around the mouths of my children I feel your pain could be the next iteration of the guac lock you could add a combo
Nationwide like a child exactly is very funny that you said that because
A lot of people say I never have leftover guacamole then why would I need this
I would always say to them is
Now you can make in advance
Is the co-founder of the guac lock it
It's now for sale on Amazon and Bed Bath and Beyond and at Whole Foods and you can find out more about
The guac lock at our Facebook page of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks so much for listening to the show
This week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also download our podcast Apple podcasts or however you get your podcasts
You can write us our email addresses HIV tea at npr.org if you want to send us a tweet it's at
How I built this our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva grab Santa's meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Diana Mustang
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
This is Peter Sagal many years ago we began wait wait don't tell me
With a dream that if we treated the news as if it were completely ridiculous
It would someday become completely ridiculous
We just kept
Making rude remarks and dumb jokes eventually the world would change so that rude jokes are in fact now
The best way to talk about it
I'm pleased to say
It worked
Join us for wait wait don't tell me the news quiz that tells it like it really is
On the NPR one app or wherever
You listen to podcast
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing plan
Form used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email templates a dragon
Email Builder and customer support 7 days a week