Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Hey it's guy here with a quick note before we start
The show
If listening to a show this year
Change the way you think
Anyway
Please do consider supporting your local station
And tell us how the conversations you heard here helped you grow this year
Visit donate. Npr.org
Built
To give
And then share your story with the hashtag why Public Radio
And thanks
And just one more thing
How I built this team is taking a little time off for the holidays
But
Before we head out we're going to put a bonus episode in your queue this Thursday
Supima workout for a special live recording with me and Arthur Blank
Co-founder of the Home Depot
For that was that one of our very favorites
From The Archives
Enjoy
My favorite quotes is if you want to understand the entrepreneur study the juvenile delinquent
Cuz it's cuz they're saying you know this sucks I'm going to do it my own way and that's what they all say they just say this
Do it this other way and that's the fun part of business actually
Breaking the rules
From NPR how I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the story
Behind the movement
Hot metal in a converted chicken coop
Outdoor clothing brand Patagonia today he says he does not want you
Your money
If it isn't that kind of entrepreneur who's going to wow you with a PowerPoint presentation or a
Snappy elevator pitch
He's basically a surfer
Kayaker in a mountain climber who sort of stumbled into the role of business
So pretty
How can I say this
Eccentric
But in the best possible way
If I never had any interest
Becoming Richie's
Actively work to slow down patagonia's growth in profit margins and yet
Despite his best efforts to keep it small
This little clothing company he started 50 years ago
Has turned into a
Huge business
Well I never intended this
It's just
I just have this Knack that everytime I look at
A product
Look at it nice
You know I can make
It could be better
So every time we went climbing
Would come back with ideas on how to improve the climbing gear which is very crude enough
And so
You know I became a blacksmith
Pressa I've taught myself blacksmithing so that I could make
Some of the
Climbing Hardware that I thought would be better than what's available you literally like pounding
Hot pictures of metal into shape
That's exactly right
You don't do it my
Parents backyard then my father
Help me convert a chicken coop into it
Hello shop
Well as making Dino pitons
Metal spikes that you pound in the cracks and I was making the carabiners of snap blankson
Target
Yeah cuz I mean at that time mountain climbing was still
Huge commercial
Enterprise
No they were probably
250 climbers in the country why how
Yeah
And all the gear came from Europe in and it was pretty poor quality
Like the pitons were made to be used once
Because Europeans looks at
Climbing
Conquering mountains
And you just leave all the gear in place to make it easier for the next group
And we were brought up
Another philosophy of John Muir and
And also throwing
We felt like nature
Should be left alone and you should
Do a climate but leave nothing behind
And so I made pitons out of better materials at
Put in and take it out
And used over and over again
It was a lessening in quality I think because
Do European pitons for selling for
$0.15
A piece
In mind word dollar and a half
And I guess you did this for like
10 or 10 or so years
Yeah
Were you doing well
Well yeah we had 80% of the market
And anyway I guess you had no intention of ever making it that right
No not at all right I didn't respect businessman I had no idea
Business whatsoever I was a Craftsman
Yeah but you know we were making
Are they any money
We're making about 1%
Prophet the end of the year we're basically paying art
By the hour so how did you guys Branch out from
From climbing gear to clothing
Well I was on a climbing trip to Scotland in the winter
Walking by some shop and I saw a rugby shirt in the window and I saw
Pretty cool
You know it's real colorful head blue and red and yellow
Made really tough so I thought this make a really great shirt for
Climbing
You know the caller
Can I keep the gear slings from cutting into your napkin
You know at that time
Active Sportswear for men was basically Gray
Sweatshirts and sweat
That was it proven men did not worry
And so I started wearing this climbing and everybody was going wow
Where'd you get that
So it's kind of Lights came on I said well maybe I'll to import a few of these from England
And see if she'll sell and sure enough they sold
And then I started making some climbing shorts
Pantsing
One thing led to another and I realize
Islam more profitable than making
Pitons
How did you come up with the name Patagonia
Guilin 68
Height I did a
6 month long trip from California down to
South America
We drove and surfed all the way down
Tacos
Download Lena and then sold a surfboards and then climb volcanoes down in southern Chile and skeet off of them and
I kind of fell in love with that area
Patagonia
You know on those days nobody even knew what Patagonia
Kauai
Timbuk2
You know how many people know where Timbuktu is
And so I decided to call it Patagonia because
I wanted to make clothing for those kind of conditions UK
Warren
Like super high winds cold
Crazy temperature change in weather
Is it is it like
You did not know anything about
Clothing
Cheer right I didn't know anything about closing
I learned everything bites
If I get an idea immediately take a step
And see how that feels if it feels good I take another step it feels bad ice
You know it's different than people with a scientific
Lakeview where they
Take everything out to the esta Gris before they make a move
Try I learn by just doing
And one of the first products we met was a pair of climbing shorts and
I made the pattern for it I knew nothing about pattern-making I just took a pair of
Shorts apart and I kind of looked at it and I
But I want to
He don't make a really tough pair of shorts so I use
Canvas
From outdoor furniture
Or something
Palace Korean woman
For me and she had to show it on a walking foot machine which is the kind of sewing machine that
Used for
Sewing leather
Cuz
Fabric was so sick
And when she was done with him as she stood him up they stood straight up
So we need them stand up shorts and you know it took about 50 Washings to break him in but we still make those short
Chris Noth is a heaviest
They were
It seems like
Your
Main motivation was to just make stuff that you would want to wear and use yourself but love nobody's making stuff
Good enough
And you were just sort of like
I guess I have to take it
Yeah you know I I I
I used to do every
Conceivable
Sport
And then the people that work for me where all
Sports
Also we knew
What we wanted
You know what I heard somebody say that
You wait for the customer to tell you what to do you're too late
So we were our own custom
And I think that was the secret
Coming out with pride
A lot of products people didn't even know they
They want it or need it
When you start to do this
And you have to hire employees and you have to form a company and you have to
Deal with payroll like disaster to scare you
Oh yeah
Yeah that was pretty scary and we made a lot of mistakes
And in fact we were so successful in the
Ladies
We were growing too fast we're going to 50
2% of here
And now you can't do that for very long before you
Run out of money basically
On retainer ninja can't do that
And so we were also
Ramped-up to grow 50% and we only grew
25 or so
Which doesn't sound bad but when you build all the inventory for
Her that and you don't make it
Is pretty rough and then there was a recession down and and the banks wouldn't give us any more money in fact
I had to
Laying people off
Was really hard because we're
Family
Spell business
Renew everybody
Working there
That was really tough
DJ moments
During those periods
The ups and downs what you thought
Patagonia might fail
Oh absolutely
We didn't know where they were going to make it or not
We couldn't get any loans from anybody
My account
Introduce me to some Mafia guys who understand Oklahoma
Some money at 18% interest
Which I turned down but
What day does this is we got some personal loans from
Some friends and pretty much fired some management
That got us in this problem and turn things around
Why do you think it happened was it just bad luck was it
The economy or was it
Was there
A strategy that
We were just going for growth
You know not saying no
It's just so gross can creep up on you I mean we were just opening
More more dealers are opening their own retail stores
He'll nothing goes forever
In fact that's why the faster a business grows too fast
And so
Once we got out of this we decided
To put ourselves on a
Growth
Program so that
We would be in business a hundred years from now
So all decisions
Then on were made as if we're going to be here a hundred years from now
So what
Slowing down the girl saying no
To a lot of opportunities
And just being more responsible
Like like how
It just
I don't
Prime the pump I don't we don't advertise it
Vanity Fair to get new customer
Affect our advertising budget
1/2 of 1
Percent of sales
And so
I wait for the customer to tell us
How much to make
When year will growth spurt for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and opened up free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from servicenow making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive and engaged
Moret servicenow.
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Commence and personalize your suit
Just the way you want it
This week how I built this listeners can get any
Premium indochino suit for 55% off
Plus free shipping
Just go to indochino.com or any indochino showroom
And use code built
At checkout
It's how I built this from NPR guy Raz
Took that tough. In the early 1990s
Devon and his team started to focus less
I'm grilling and
Moron
Lasting
As a company
And it's hard to do things like
Use more environmentally friendly
Material
And they also started to do something
A bit weird for a business
Instead of
Telling customers
Buy their stuff
Patagonia kind of told them
YouTube
Yeah
Believe
This company is the resource that I have
And that I should use that resource
To show a different way of doing business
In fact we now have the largest
Garmin repair center in North America
Wheel repair every single
Piece of Patagonia matter how old it is
Indefinitely
In fact we've got a truck.
It's going around the country
Repairing people's clothes no matter whether they're Patagonia or not
And then we're trying to teach people that
You don't throw things away do you repair them
And then we've committed ourselves
To owning
The product forever
So when we sell you a jacket we still on it
If you get overweight already
Tired of the color of whatever you want to get rid of it will help you
Sell it
To somebody else
If breaks down will fix it
Fish finally you know completely shot
You give it back to us and we'll recycle it into
Morgarath
So it forces us
To use
Fibers that can be recycled if Forces 2
Design a jacket that you can replace a zipper cuz it's very easy
Design one where you can't replace it
Is change the whole way we do business
Yeah so like what about you how many
White Patagonia jacket
You'd be surprised at all my stuff is
Years and years old
Sitting here talking to you my pants are probably seven or eight years old my shirt is
Probably the same
But you know it's it's kind of interesting
Friend of mine went to
Garage sale in Jackson Hole recently
And there was a
Jacket
That we made about
10 years ago in those purple man's great shape
The woman wanted $3
So you offer 15 sheets
Anyone on eBay
Anna guy from Japan said hey
I'd like to buy that jacket how much you want
You don't make me an offer
Tulalip how about 750
So actually
Distance keep their value
Which is pretty amazing and that mean the thing is like a new Patagonia jacket is not exactly
Cheap stuff
Yes oh yeah I mean we have a
Lifetime guarantee and we
Can't make things cheaply
I'm for trying to make
The very very highest quality we we can and it's
You know it's like organic food is
Cost more than regular food
Is it true that many causes you no less harm the environment and so
Black people pay for that
And I'm not interested
And coming out with a line of
Inexpensive clothes
You know it's kind of like eating meat
I eat meat but I eat
Tiny little bit at a time I don't either
16 oz
Pour House
And I think
US Clothing we're telling people look sink twice
If you're going to buy a jack at the skin by one that you can also wear over your
Sukkot in New York City in a rainstorm
Should I don't sit in the closet 9 months a year
And so on phone fewer things but really good things
What is
Is party still conflicted over this idea that even with all the
Responsible things you do
You are still part of
Consumer world
Ya know that
We certainly are yet
And that's why we try to
Can I put a spin on it by
Don't tell me our customers
Twice
Before they buy
Anything not just our product but anything
You have
No
College degree
Business Degree you're not
Like you are not a businessman but you are I mean became one
Andeavor Fred that you cost
Call yourself a relaxing businessman
But do you feel uncomfortable with that title
No not at all because I think
What I did is once I decided that was it
And I decided to really study up on it I studied every book I could on
Japanese
Management styles
Scandinavian businesses
Cuz I thought there had to be a different way of doing business
And
I still want it only work
For part of the Year myself
You know I I take off from
June until November I'm gone I got a place in Jackson Hole and I go fishing every day and
I called him maybe three times
In the five months
Lamp
People know that if the warehouse burns down don't call me what can I do you know what to do
How are you able to do that
Well
You know I heard a great thing on NPR
TaxSlayer
Fattest woman at Stanford
Studies ants
She said that
You know ant colonies don't have
They don't have Bots
And everyone knows what their job is they get their job done and
Compare that with dictators
It's a lot of companies are top-down management and it takes a tremendous amount of effort to run those
So what we decided to do is just higher
Motivated young independent people
Leave me alone
Nme night I wrote a book called
Let my people go surfing and it's all about we have a policy that when the surf comes up
Drop work and go surfing
I don't care when you work
As long as the job gets done
And I know I've had other companies
Come to me and say hello I love that idea I think I'm going to do it in my company I say
Forget it you'll fail
Because you have to start with a very first person you hire
And
I've had
Psychologist
Studier
Her employees and they said
I got to tell you
Your employees are the most independent I've ever seen any company in fact they're so independent unemployable anywhere else
About the company
In the seventies you guys were doing
Maternal and paternal leave
People taking their infant to daycare for the staff and
Flexible work schedule think that we
Even to this day today are still
Not that common and in all companies
YouTube
40 years
Oh yeah I mean we wanted ever kids
What does it work
Do you know who put them in a cardboard box on your desk in
And that work for a while but then
Judson Screamers
And so my wife and I started
A child care center
And we didn't want to just
Somebody just babysitting these kids
You know we recognize it
05 is the most important
Learning time of a
Person's life
And so it's not a babysitting service
The kids are come out of our company or the
The best product that comes out
Not once been in prison yet
All these things
Cost the company
Money
Well if we're going to be here a hundred years so you know it
We're not going to sell out we're not going to go public
Cancel
It's good business
I mean I have
Probably 70% women workers
For me I have women and all upper management
And
I don't want to lose him
Where did you
I mean a lot of the people that we talked to on the show are motivated by
In a wine to change an industry or change the way business is done or to change the world or two
Make money
Nevermind I think everybody would agree that they wanted to make money
Isn't you where did you and where do you find the motivation to make
This company
Ramen fries
Well you know where my favorite quotes
If you want to understand
Entrepreneur
Study of the juvenile
Cuz they're saying you know this sucks I'm going to do it my own way
I
I have a background of
As always the shortest guy around I could play
Sports pretty well you know team sports but
When it came time for
Actual game mode
I realize that
The best thing to do is invent your own sports than you can always be a winner and so
That's what the entrepreneur does they just say this is wrong
Do it this other way
And if you want to be successful in business
You don't go up against Coca-Cola
These big companies are they'll kill you
You just do it differently
You figure out something that no one else has thought about
And you do it totally different way and so
Breaking the rules
How you have to be creative
And that's the fun part of this
I love breaking the rules
You still must live by
By certain rules
Well I've been a student kind of sin Buddhism
What's my life
I believe in you.
The more you know the less you need
I've been fishing
Fly fishing with one fly
The one type of
Fly in different sizes
It has limited myself to that
For a whole year in
I caught more fish than I've ever caught in my life
I realize that all it is
Hundreds of thousands of differ
Fly patterns
Eye colors
Shapes and everything
You can replace all of that
With
Knowledge
And
And it's a good lesson for me
Detritus Darcy in the world it's a simplify your life
Cuz everything pulls you to be more and more complex
And so I think what I learned from
Fly fishing
Is that if we have to
Either were forced or we decide to go to a more Simple Life
It's not going to be an impoverished
It's going to be really rich
Banchan ourtinder of Patagonia
He never took a penny of investment by the way salons 100% of the company
And because of that the company doesn't make the numbers
Publix open
Endless growth may not be Yvonne shanard sing
Patagonia reportedly did at three-quarters of a billion dollars in sales last year
Their best year ever
Listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episodes
How I built this. Npr.org
And if you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other people know about it
You can also write us directly at HIV tea at npr.org
Are cheetahs at how I built this
Shows produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis
Also composed the music
It's also to neva grandson has meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
And Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Did you ever consider becoming a priest
Appreciate or like moving to a monastery
Not at all
And please do stick around because it in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Gotowebinar
I trusted webinar platform with over 55,000 customers who posted over 2.3
Million interactive web events to connect with their audiences
The more visit gotowebinar.com
Podcast
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
Today we're updating a story we first ran last November when we spoke with Brett Johnson from Easton Massachusetts
What is something kind of interesting a couple years ago 2011-2012
There was a big cayenne pepper crazy kind of swept across the country
Really a lot of people were touting the health benefits of cayenne pepper and you know we kind of had this idea what if we could integrate
Cayenne pepper into throat lhasa
Cayenne pepper into a throat lozenge something they called
Fire drops
You put in your mouth and it takes about 15 to 20 seconds for the actual
Giant really hit you
You can feel it in the back of your throat you feel this kind of soothing effect
Of the spice of the cayenne pepper I know this may not sound very soothing
But Brett says that the heat from the pepper actually feels really great on your throat
A lot of customers who are singers and actors
They really like the fire dropped because they feel as soon as their vocal cords and helps them kind of heal after night of performance
Richard that for now most of the people who are buying fire drops have
Cold or sore throat
That means it's 3 years in
Company still has a small problem
We're seasonal business in summer time is a slow time for cold and sore throat
And so it becomes a challenge to figure out how to manage cash flow properly
Let's Brett Johnson when we last heard from him fire drops were selling in about 15 stores and their chest about
Break even
Today princess fire drops are in 75 stores across the country the business is now.
Turning a profit
In just a few weeks ago Brett quit his day job to work on fire drops full-time
Hey if you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing from you
Thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or your previous episode of How I built this NPR.
Or you can subscribe to this show on Apple podcasts or wherever you get your podcast
One more thing before we go just want to thank the people and throw the behind-the-scenes people who helped all of the programs
Do what they do including all the amazing research and fact-checking Folks at NPR Idaho
Prasad Berkeley Walsh Bryn winterbottom Samuel Salis Candice kortkamp
Greta Penninger Jane gilvin KD dagger saronite Susie comings and will chase
It's also to Andy huether and Daniel shoot good for all of your audio help we have a terrific office manager Camille
Miley and of course things
Do our usual team run and Rachel run clean and Casey Santa's Diana and Eva and Jeff
Unemployment is our vice president for programming here at NPR on Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com