Support for this podcast and the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Hey it's guy here so we've been super busy working on a bunch of live shows
This summer in fact
This very Thursday check your podcast to you for my conversation with the founders of Reddit
Alexis Ohanian and Steve Huffman are incredibly insightful and also very very funny
You'll hear a lot of laughs
From the live audience
In San Francisco so stay tuned for that and for more live events coming to your cities in
And towns
Throughout the year
But right now we've got one of our all-time favorites from the HIV T archive soap
Enjoy
We ended up going from 0 to 800 homes in a matter for week
And I have to tell you I thought that this was it like this was
Are rocket ship to the Moon. We made it we're here we got it right this is you build it they will come
Look what's happening and so we get introduced to 20 vest Silicon Valley
None of them reply to her email five of them for coffee zero invested
From NPR how I built this a show of activators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories
And the movements they go
The story of how a side hustle to pay rent
More rooms in the biggest hotel chain in the world
10 years ago even five years ago most of us would have thought the idea of
Renting out a room in our home to a complete
Stranger
A little creepy even spending the night in someone else's home you never met would
Probably seen weird
Especially on vacation or business
But now it's not just normal
It's actually the preferred way to overnight from millions of people around the world celebrities do it
A company that made all of this normal of course is Airbnb
Guys who started it
Had no background in travel or hot
Natality or even technology
Joe gebbia graduated
Art school at the Rhode Island School of Design
Francesca's co-founder was Jose
College buddy they play pickup basketball together
And actually graduated in 2005
Joe and Brian moved out west
Brian went to LA
Going to San Francisco
And in the first year Joe who was designing book covers at a Publishing House
Worked
Really hard to convince Brian to move up to San Francisco to start a business
Is Joe tells a story after some prodding
Brian agreed
Both of us simultaneously quit our jobs he left his I was at Chronicle Books full-time at that point
And I left
To dream of something with him and for you guys were liking your
20s need a whole lot of money presumably
At this point now
We're just a couple of college grads you know eating Ramen
Yeah
What is everybody Ramen Everybody Eats Ramen so cheap Ramen Ramen Ramen
Give rice rice cereal to Mexico
You're eating Ramen
And what you're just like spitballing ideas
We spitballing ideas that first week was so exciting the first week he comes your
You're like my God yes I mean the first week felt like RISD again
Place is full of ideas
And then
Something ominous
A letter came in the mail
I open it up it's just me
Pulled out and its former landlord
To politely
States that are rent
Is now 25% higher than it was the month before
Weight room 1-month erased by
25%
And that's legal
It was not under rent control
Wake me up with Intuit
And so we would like
Freaking out
Of course I went randomly
My online banking and it was like oh my God oh my God can I make rent next month and Bryant the same thing we realize that we we almost
Couldn't
We aren't getting paychecks at this point yeah
So
This is a moment where
Your back's against the wall
And I feel like
Call the creative training that we received start to pay off cuz we start to think about okay well how come
Designer way out of this
And that was when I
Reflected on
Previous experience that I had
Back in Providence
The day before that I laughed I drove cross-country I sold off all my stuff
And when I was having that yard sale
This guy pulls up in a red Mazda Miata
And start looking my stuff
And I'm getting pretty annoyed cuz I'm ready to go home
Bonanza buying a piece of art that I was selling so we get to talkin
And he tells me all about
How is about to go into the Peace Corps and he's driving cross-country
She doesn't know a soul in Providence so I invite him out for a drink that night
And
I make the mistake of asking him
So are you staying the night
And he makes it worse by saying
Actually I don't have a place man
What do you do
A place like we've all been there like to my house this guy
So before I know what I'm saying I'm like
How you can stay in an air bed in my living room
Balanitis intimate in the living room
And I I go to bed I try to fall asleep
I'm staring at the ceiling thinking
Oh my God
What have I done
There's a complete stranger in my living room
What did he say
So I get up I tiptoed my door and I go out
My bedroom door
The next morning we wake up
We get breakfast together turned out he was not psychotic
10 piece of art that he bought hangs in
Classroom music teacher now
And he still
Saint Joseph
Don't touch
Subjected to this is the dude that
Bible
How to become a baby so how did you
So you're in your apartment your rents going up 25%
And what do you see
Alexis rent a room or apartment
Well I'm looking at my laptop
And there's a design conferences coming to San Francisco
Industrial designers
Conference
And on the Converse website in Big Red Letters it said hotels
Sold out
You think I'm mad what a bummer
Designers want to come last minute and I can have a place to stay and in that instant I woke up
And looking around the living room
I got weight
With so much extra space here
And I have earbuds in the closet in the idea of Hosting people in air beds
I gradually become natural to me
And
The thinking is they'll be more than just
The place to sleep we can cook breakfast in the morning will pick him up from the airport
I will give him a neighborhood guide and a map to San Francisco
So did how did you get the word out about it haven't these designers know that
This is available
Well we can know we didn't want to use any of the classified websites cuz
There's going to be people in her home
So we made our own
Winning image
What we did on your website website
That said what
Well it said
Who we were it said about that this concept of
Stay with us mobile provide these things for you
This website was just for the design car
That's it for one weekend what did you call it when the website
It was a little recalled
Air bed and breakfast.com and we start to get emails
From around the world
Designers who need a place to stay emails from London from Brazil from Japan
People actually started sending us their resumes their LinkedIn profiles to 2/4 one of these bees
Limited 3-year beds for $80 a night you could stay in San Francisco with Brian and I
That's a great deal
Is it to remember who your first guess where
Yeah so is more Catherine and Michael where the first three guests and
You know what happened next I don't think we could have predicted
They stayed with us and we got to show them
San Francisco they got to
Get the feel like they they belong there in the sense that didn't feel like Outsiders
You know what I mean like
Yeah
And you'll never forget
Saying goodbye in and watching the door
Door Clicker
Close
And thinking with Brian
What if we made it possible for other people
Also share their experience in in
Gaston or home and show off their City
At what point did you and Brian location
Can I go
Okay man
I think this is
Start business
Was it like right after that door closed
I wish I wish it was but I can say that at
What's the case
Send that December we both went home
For holiday
End
Add a respected New Year's Eve parties everyone asks so what are you doing in San Francisco
What were entrepreneurs
What do you want for dinner any
And we didn't really have very much
Other than to say
Well let me tell bout this time where we hosted these three guests on air beds in her apartment
And one of two things happen
People do said
Oh my God that's the coolest thing in the world where can I do that
Or they said
That is the most bizarre creepiest thing I've ever heard
And they left the conversation
And I think one of the things that I've learned is that great ideas
I think they usually start out as
Polarizing you're not kind of like it's kind of okay
They either really talk on somebody's
Emotions are undulating desire that they have butts never been in
Before
Were they really
Determinants of life
As long as people who really gravitate towards the ATM to me that's a signal fmip on somebody
So what
What you guys do next
Well we knew that we needed a great technical expertise
And
Funny thing
The Roommate
To move doubts that Brian can move in with a guy named Naples Charizard
Meet with an engineer
Who found me on Craigslist
And as we live together
There were some similarities in
How many deny
Worked
Which is that we come home from our day jobs
And in the evening we would both
Work maniacally on her own projects
I looked over my shoulder
I remember thinking to myself
This guy had to work ethic just like I do
If I ever need an engineer
I think I'm going to call Nate
So here we are
January
So I meet Nate for a drink
Home. This this weekend experiment with these three guests
And
I need love the idea
He's like
We can use the internet tax you get people off the internet how cool is that
And he have these like this
Is coding experience
Neither you nor nor brand
Use a computer science degree from Harvard
Yeah he sure did
So
I guess at this point you have your team assembled because
Idea
If your website so when do you
What do you really decide to Launch
We all agreed that we would watch the next version of our site
Urbana Rec
At the next
Big Tex
Because
Actually we thought the original opportunity was housing for conferences Sprite
So the next big when I was coming up
What's South by Southwest
And every year the same thing happens Hotel sell out months in advance people Scramble for housing
And it's also the the the place where
Some of the tag rated lawn
Forrest Twitter launch their Foursquare and others
With audible this is perfect
We're just going to follow the rocket ship that the all that didn't
So at this point we have about three weeks to build before South by Southwest I'm doing design 18 the coding
We're just pulling on a piece together
No money at all
Just doing this
So
We get it out just in time we ship it when you say your ship
We release the next version of a site
And we think this is this is the next greatest thing and at this point there's not a single listing on ride
I got
We actually had six people
Put up listings in Austin and we had two people
Book those listings
One of them
Was Brian
So it was not a smashing success at all this was where you guys at
Sad are you laughing about it or
Now this is completely demoralizing idea that we were so excited about
And
Nobody
Took us up on the idea
So we learn two things from Austin
The first was that
Exchanging money in person
Really awkward
Especially inside of a home
So we thought we'll
Why do we pay past exchange cash in person what if we just bring the transaction online
What if we allowed people
To see monthly pay with a credit card
Semi you would for traditional combinations on the internet
But instead you get somebody down
Right
And suddenly
We realize we had a business model
We said well maybe we'll just take a transaction fee
As we
Flow the funds from guests
The Host
The second thing we learned is that there were people who did want to travel
Where the word conference is taking place
Decoding our first three guests
Cattermole Michael you must hate
I'm going to Vancouver next week
How do I stay in somebody's home I had such a good experience
I'm like woah
Is there a conference going on
I'm single
Why do we need to be, maybe this is just a trapezoid
So we went back to me and said
What's the what's the ad payments and what's make
It's a travel site
Need start warm up the idea
But had some real
Questions about
How to get a market place like that starting
So he started to build something
Even more ambitious
Well actually he moved back to Boston
To be with his girlfriend
It's kind of a dance falling apart a little bit
And that's only had an idea
Which was
What if we re-watch the new version of a service
And we do it
At the crest
Of a tidal wave
Oppress
Which in summer 2008
Was Barack Obama
It specifically
Obama speaking at the Democratic National Convention
Denver Colorado
Yeah where there was a housing crisis
Because
A hundred thousand people working
Anticipated to see Obama speech
And the river
Less than 30000 hotel room
Most of which were picked up by
Delegates
So this is a real problem in fact the mayor of Denver at one point thought about opening up the city parks
Touki bouki campout
What if we time the relaunch of a service
The third launch
During the DNC we can ride
The coattails of all the Obama press to bring what awareness to this Marketplace that's exactly what we did
We hustled Seafood in Denver we met people in the ground we got local press was turned into Regional press was turned an ash
Depressing eventually International press
Wow and so this is still weeks before the convention July 2008
What happened
Well
We did a live interview with CNN
Armor living room
And we have about a hundred people
Actually
Book and pay with a credit card through a service
Which this was like the first
Sign of a working viable Marketplace
Even if the point liquor
We're getting customer service calls
For the first time
And that just like was your cell phone
Yeah
How did it go
I hate we ended up going from 0 to 800 homes
What's the matter for weeks
So 800 homes
Are on this site called
Air bed and breakfast run
And I have to tell you I thought that this was it like this was
AR
Rocketship to the Moon
You thought we made it we're here we got it right if you build it they will come and look what's happening
And they came yeah
And then the convention ended
And all those numbers came crashing right back
So
Here we headed to London
Because at this point we'd also started talking to investors
With all this is a great time talk
Working with stories
We get
Introduce 220 vest Silicon Valley
None of them reply to her email
Five of them use for coffee
Invested
Wow
It was completely demoralizing
Yeah like 2008 was the worst year of my life
Really oh my gosh yes because you put so much into this thing
Write like
I don't have nothing else going on my life
It's the best
And to put it in front of very credible investors the guys that depict the Googles and PayPal and YouTube's of the world
And since the focus Square in the eyes ago it was weird
I'm not invested in this what did they say what what why
Well they didn't say this but here's the underlined
It's because we've all been taught since we were kids
That strangers evil Danger
No one in their right mind would invest in a service that was
Based upon
This pitch that
What we want to build a website where people
Publicly post images of the most intimate space is there
Bedrooms there bathrooms
The kinds of rooms that
Usually closed when people come over
And then
Over the internet
You can invite complete strangers to sleep in their homes it's going to be huge
So this is like
Conventions you're thinking
We got it we're going to get all this make all this money and I'll raise all this money and and all the sudden you get back to San Francisco and nobody wants
To give you any money
Exactly
Nobody
How are you keeping up the business
Going if you didn't have any
Any cash we did raise around financing we call it the Visa round
Which mission to you you max out your credit cards
You know those binders reheat baseball cards
Yeah I had one of those except they weren't baseball cards and credit cards
We would go through Visa
After Visa
Two MasterCards on final to Amex
Just maxing out
Credit cards
And that's how we funded herself
I can tell you like this not no worse feeling to get a credit card statement that's only going up
With no hope of ever painted town named for this by the way
In the startup world
There's a name for this phase of a company where you have a product in the market but they don't
It yet
It's almost like two gears that don't touch this is mysterious gap between these metal gears
That you can't figure out how to close the gap
And because the trough of Sorrow it's a long
. of time where you don't have product-market fit in in the day they are the analytics it looks like the Midwest
Steve analytics because it's perfectly flat
There's zero growth this is when people tend to quit
A moment only comeback have a Joe gebbia and
Partners eventually find their way out of that trough of Sorrow I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
Yep
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Today organizations need the agility that rapid Data Insights bring to stay a step ahead of the competition
With snowflake you can instantly and infinitely scale your data warehouse with the touch of a button delivering depends
Sites at any time for all users
Start your journey towards data-driven decision-making at snowflake. Com NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking by offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere
In 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Its 2008
Jonas Partners have no investors
And a lot of credit card debt
And I'm trying to figure out
Are raised
It was at this point that Brian and I are in the kitchen late one night like 2 in the morning
And we're just trying to keep each other's spirits up
And
During the peak of Obama vs McCain
It's like September
And we're working on this idea of being are bed and breakfast in providing maybe would give her host to breakfast cereal to give their guests
Would it be funny if it was politically themed
Oh yeah we call it like a
Obama O's the breakfast of change
Or maybe cat McCain's a Maverick and everybody
And we actually end up making breakfast cereal
Wait
You made breakfast cereal
Like actual cereal to eat
That's a good question
Which is how do you make breakfast cereal and how do you do it with not zero budget but a negative urine a deficit by the way
So you know I picked up the phone I called Kellogg General Mills
And
Check on to the pitch tonight I got hello
Hello
It hung up on me
And then it dawned on me well maybe we don't have to make cereal
Maybe we can just
Go to the grocery store
Buy some cereal off the shelf
Designer unboxing
Put the bag of cereal in her inbox see what happened and sell it that way
Just sell it on the street well maybe make website
We know how to do that
Instead of Airbnb or in addition to assure
Then the question was
How do you make the boxes
So I found an illustrator
Did Art Direction put all the pieces together
I found a RISD alumni
In the East Bay here in Sanford
The guy that
Winning
And
You know I like Ike
I poured it all out to this guy sitting
Here's the idea of the concept really excited. Here's the mock-ups and sketches
Because all right here's what I'll do
I'll make 500 of each box
He doesn't have to pay me up front but pay me commission-based underwear sale
And it dawned on us that
With 500 of each box will that was a limited edition
That was a collector's item
We could number them
On the top of the box at 500
And suddenly
We decided we could sell a box of Obama O's and cap McCain
$40
The Box
She's just a crazy story I don't even I don't even have forgotten about Airbnb where where we going
What's going on with his interview
Look it's a it's an entrepreneur Bender
So
We make Obama's. Com
We get the boxes so we put a hundred boxes together
We mailed them out to all the press that we
The Weeknd
Mailto like
Every morning show had a box of these
So we didn't get featured on all of these different shows CNN did a live interview with us about breakfast cereal
And we were the number-one politically themed video
Altenen.com for the entire day
And after that CNN interview
We ended up selling out of Obama bows
Which is incredible like where did you think you were going to go from there like well it's almost didn't matter because
$40 box * 500 boxes
Yes $20,000 in breakfast cereal
Yeah which was breakfast cereal. We just enough to pay off her credit cards
All right so you pay off your credit card bills
And then what you go back to are Ben Rector
Well we got to this this through fateful dinner one night
With one of our mentors
It was Michael Seibel and Justin Kahn
And so I brought the dinner with them and
They've been helping us the last couple months and what kind of like
At the end of the rope and they can tell and they're like
You guys need some help
You should
Participate
In this incubator program called y combinator
Red dinner we look upon our phones and the deadline was the night before
Like come on
The end up
Emailing the guy who runs in a guy named Paul Graham
They knew and they say you know a Paul there's these guys if you got this concept and and
It really benefit from being in your program
Tickle to the application
If it sent it to you and Paul right back into the give it to me by midnight tonight
Sabrina race home it's like 2:00
We start to fill out the application pretty intense yeah
Aspen X2
We get this callback
Better application got accepted
We got to the next round which is an interview
Keratin advance
Do the grill each other with
All these weights
Cheap and expand internationally
You know what's the next big future going to build
Excetera excetera
And so we going to the interview it's in the small tiny room
Hawaii, your office
And as for partners around the table
Sit down
Very first thing
A toboggan is mouth is
You mean people actually use this
Miguel
Yeah and goes well that's weird
What is that it's not a good start of any kind
It kind of went downhill from there
We're walking out of the room
Something like this is our last chance effort and it didn't go so well
And that's when I remembered that I had brought a box of Obama's
To give to him as a gift
Psycho Ronnie back in the room
I whip out the box by handsome guy Paul we got this for you
Because
Oh where'd you buy this
I go well we made it
Because what do you mean you made it
And I told the story in 60 seconds Migos wait so you guys funded your company based on selling breakfast cereal
I immediately turned around and put the box of cereal on the shelf behind the desk
On the ride home
We get a phone call
Paul Graham
To inform us that he'd like to offer us
A spot
NY Common Core program
And
I'll be waiter found out
That the reason we got it wasn't because of her idea
It was because
Through the breakfast cereal we can prove to him that we had hustle we had Grit
If we can figure out Hussle breakfast over for $40 a box
We can figure out how to make a website work
Alright so you get into y combinator
And
What what is a
Like what does it do for you
Guys what what happened there
Y combinator was a game-changer for us
And I'll never forget the first office hours
That we had with Paul Graham
You sit down with us
And he goes
Where is your Market
And
We all get each other and were like
We don't really have a market
No one's really using the website
But we go you know
New York is showing some promise we have 30 hosts in New York
You're renting it there extra rooms out in their homes in
Migas
Your customers are in New York City
But you're here in Mountain View
And yeah we're here for your program
Everything goes
What are you still doing here
Go to New York City and he points his finger at you he's got this thing ready to go to even
Finger
And it was in this moment
Sitting in this room this tiny room
We're something profound change for us
Because up until this point
We had subscribed to the ethology of Silicon Valley
Yeah wishes that you have to solve things in a scalable way
Because what happens when one day
The rocket ship takes off
You already left behind because your code held you back
And so
We could try to solve our problems by
Decoding our way through it
And if you remember that didn't get us anywhere cuz
We are in the Midwest
Analytics
Sprite and so here comes Paul Graham
Gave us permission
To do things that don't scale
Such as
Fly across the country and meet the early doctors of your service
Yeah and it was in that moment that we felt so much more free
To think
Even more creatively about how we could get our service off
The ground if you can do things that don't have
Have to scale
What else could we do
And
As we start going through the search
Results and looking at the house
Identify the pattern
And the pattern was this
People just generally didn't know how to take a good photo of your home
So the phone is really bad
Sentence of the photos you had on
Decided that timer
Crappy photos
Well you know people using their camera phones at the time it was like flip
Camera phones which of the
They're taking pictures at night it just wasn't
Different merchandising their home and away.
You would want to stay there so therefore no one was booking them
And we thought you know
I went to Art School
Photography classes
Photography my whole life in fact
The Hobby
Moon about if we just flew out there for a weekend
We could probably take some ice for photos
And we won't charge you for it will do for free
That weekend we bought plane tickets Brian life live in New York
We've emailed her hosts all three of them
We rented a really nice camera
And went door-to-door throughout Manhattan Brooklyn and then other parts of New York
And it's funny cuz he had knocked on the door and then they open the door and introduce myself
As a
I'm Jo I emailed you from Airbnb
And I kind of like looking over my shoulder so yeah where's the professional
Photography promise I guess that's me too I'm asking to take the photos for you yet
Say you're the guy taking the photos
So yeah I'm taking photos and in what school is at
The photos are looking pretty good and getting the lighting right
Composition in I'm kind of
I'm staging to place a little bit of skin fluffing the pillows and then make sure that the place doesn't look cluttered
And
I show the photos in the back
The camera said hey what do you think
Do you like these
And
These houses were like
Oh my God my apartment looks amazing I can't believe it
Do you want to stay for some tea or coffee
And so I'd end up spending a few hours sometimes in their in their homes
Just talking with them
And this is where
Instinctively we went into design research mode
Which is
Going out and talking to the people you're designing for
Such that you can understand
The world from their point of view
To inform your point of view
Yeah and so I called this
Enlightened empathy
Which is seen the world so closely in the shoes of the person that you're creating for
That you can see
The world that way they see it
You bring those inside back and you combine it with your own
Design point of view
To create something new
So here we are in the living room they caught the laptop by Sade
Could you show me how how you check your calendar
Show me how you message with guest
And
In those moments
We saw how are perfectly designed interface
Completely and utterly fail
Well with what we thought took two or three clicks to get done
People were taking
1012 Quicksilver
Stumbling around getting the Lost
Within our own website and you guys did not know that up until that point
We had no idea
And so it wasn't until we actually sat down next to her early adopters some of her most passionate
Early customers
And they reveal to us
The mysterious Gap
Betweener products
And our Market
Was the inefficiencies
R user interface
What's interesting about this is that
You don't strike me as like an egomaniac or somebody who doesn't like that you sent me somebody really wants it and it's
Surprising that it took you guys so long to discover this
I know right
I know
But once we did it was
It was like
Is like a jackpot yeah
So we came back with Oliver our discoveries
Something interesting
Are numbers
That second week
Went from
$200 a week
In fees which is what we're making for 6 months
Right which is not sustainable 3guys cannot leave out that zeref yes go
Straight
Are numbers jump to $400
In one week by week just from pictures and making a couple of
Simply well
I worked at Nasa is there a bug in the system because that's just that's just crazy
How do we double in a week
And sure enough we're done more
Reservations with the house that we had met
Which was very interesting guy is that
We didn't know what's up
The time because New York
It's such an international destination
We have guests coming from Berlin we guess come from London from Sydney from Vancouver
Cooper coming as guests
Experiencing this new service of staying in somebody's home
They go back to where they came from
And it's had this Epiphany moment Saha they go
Wait I have an extra room
Why don't I rent that on the site and they would sign up
And they would sign up
Yeah
At what point did you were you able to
Actually
Attract money from investors
Was it around that time
It's precisely around this time
What I've learned is that when the gears start to click
Investors can hear that
And they actually this time they came to us
And we get offers coming in from
A variety of different groups
And the one that shocked us the most was Sequoia capital
Which was a print it is a preeminent
Venture Capital firm
In Silicon Valley
That we thought well maybe one day
Like a year from now we'll go talk to them but actually they were not going to her.
Yardworks talk to us
Closing a deal with them
We got our first round of financing which
She'd relief
We can pay rent comfortably and we can hire start tired team
Corning it at what point do you remember
Sitting with
With name Brian
I think this is going to be really big
Well one night
This isn't it
It was probably like 11:30 at night is really tired
Mathia
This point we have an office
And I used to look at every listing that got added to Airbnb
I would go through it at night and just click through
Each of them
And I come across is one that says
Fiji Islands
Unlike
What's that
I click on it
Ensure
Somebody out in the South Pacific
Listed
A 5-acre private island
Recite
Complete with personal chef
Complete with
Water sports
And I'm looking to the photos of thing going
Holy cow this is me
Rideable
And it was in that moment realize the power the spot forum
Is that weed we put it out there and
The creativity of the people who have
This contributed back to it
Has gone beyond
Any of our expectations
So you guys have obviously grown much much bigger since then
Bigger than than most
Are all hotel chains
And you have some similar challenges to two companies like uber
I'm with some City saying hey you know you guys should be regulated like hotels
So how do you
How do you respond to that
I think about that question
In the context of Innovations over the last hundred years
End
There are three examples that come to mind of new ideas that entered the world
That had
Pretty rough start
Butter now so commonplace in everyday that you'd laugh
You thought like
Oh wow like people ready instead of one point
So ATM machines
At one point in
I think it's the 1970s
Wer
Had a lot of criticism
I think the Roxy laws
Being written against them
In certain States. The US
It was this new and different way
Baking are you have to go inside and then
And talk with her
Person behind the desk of you. Maybe Up Cellular Services you just went to
A computer in a wall in in
Retrieved money of course
Can I retrieve it at ATM machines
I know
The VCR thing is another great example was first patented in
Mid-twentieth century
Become a product until
The 80s early 80s
Because it was met with such resistance from incumbent industries that didn't want people to
Watch movies at home
The car is another example where
When the Model T came out 1908
Represented a new way to travel
But anyway to
The new form of transportation
And there were certain cities that were against the car
And they're actually
Laws drafted to
Outlaw cars
But you know after a year of trying a new more efficient way of transportation
Are the people demanded that they didn't want to go back to horse and buggy
And so the policymakers you know
How to
Modify
The lost it to what people want
Cancel
I think the world is ready for our invention
Given that has been over a hundred million people have stayed in homes all over the world
End
The good news is that our cities come
To learn about what we do and what we offer
But they tend to want to work with us
Because they see that there's an economic economic impact that
Allows
People in their cities
Different neighborhoods
To benefit
When you
I think last year Airbnb was
Value
20 billion.
Probably more
Today
Is that
Crazy to does that shock you when you think that
You just started this thing and it is an idea that really went nowhere for the first
Couple years
In your apartment in San Francisco
And it's not worth
Billions
B
Does it mean anything to you or to you is
Is it just a number on a piece of pie
I don't think about it too much
I mean
The things can change if you look at the first.com
But you know what
Garden Georgia
I was so enthralled by
Every day there was a new story of a new company that started in Silicon Valley or San Francisco
I planted a very deep sea
With me that one day I want
To be a part of that
So I also remember in
Thefirst.com of companies that were
Here today gone tomorrow
Yeah there's there's a list of 10 of the hottest companies from the 1990s
One of which you would still remember
It's because technology moves so quickly
But if you're not thinking about what's next
The world around you can change faster than you do
Joe gebbia founder of Airbnb since this episode first Ram last fall ever
Wendy's value has jumped to 31 billion dollars and in the second quarter of 2016
The company finally turned a profit by the way that company he first tried to build
Which is a butt cushion for art students this was a real business for a while there is still a website
And every now and then order still comes in and I still run down to the garage and pack them up and down
Do you have in your garage
It's a funny thing cuz it reminds me of like where I started and eyes is very grounded
What's the website is it is it crippin. Com
Only 600 left
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about what your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors Squarespace
Squarespace is used by millions of entrepreneurs businesses
Visit squarespace.com to start your free trial and use offer code build it
10% off your first purchase
Make your next move
Get your unique domain and create a beautiful website
With Squarespace
Hey thanks for staying with us because it's time now for how you built that
Check back with the very first startup we had on this part of the show a company
It is taking on a very tough problem
We could actually refer to it as trash juice trash juice juice juice
Which is the runoff from dumpsters and garbage trucks Urban dweller you walk by and you
Smell it and you do not want to go anywhere near that location of Michael vanity and its Partners came up with a device to put a
Stop to trash juice
Before it even starts
Think of it as a utility cart there is a hundred foot hose on it and when you pull the trigger at the end of the toe
Telos phone comes out of it
Scrubbing Bubbles x 1000 in these Scrubbing Bubbles are, like the secret magical ingredient here
Michael says
They're full of bacteria that eat up all the
Junk in dumpsters and in trash chute
And then the phone kind of evaporate so you don't even need water to clean it up and
No water no trash juice
We test out the product we got incredible feedback and
The maintenance guys they like you guys just cut my cleaning time in half
Michael's company is called TP phone and since we spoke with him last year he sold about 200
Cleaning cards and gallons and gallons of the garbage eating phone customers are property
Managers across the country and Michael says the company's doing well but it's costing him a lot of money
Need to get the word out I mean a perfect example is we have a really big customer one of
The largest real estate developers and property management companies in the entire country
And they invited us to come to an event in September is very expensive and very far out of our budget but if the biggest
On the Block invite you to come
You have to say yes you just have to figure out how to do it that event he's talking about
It's a trade show in Texas
And Michael's company is in New Jersey and the ship one piece of equipment might cost tooth
$1,000 so that's the big thing for us because we're equipment sales is not software or anything that's it
It's in a little briefcase
Way to be kind of very strategic where we're going to go but so far Michael says TV film is doing a pretty good job
Job managing cash flow since January companies down about $400,000 in sales
And he's not turning a profit
But if you ask Michael what he thinks about the whole thing a cracked nipple.
Because I used to be in the modeling business
I was never model but I used to be on the business side of it and very glamorous world
And
Now I
Hang out in the trash rooms
But I loved every second of it
That's Michael vanity of pp foam in Mount Laurel New Jersey
Head to our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build. NPR
I got org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more
Or you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Better yet subscribe to us on Apple podcasts or however you get your podcasts
You can follow us on Twitter is at how I built this
I sure was produced this week by run teen Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to neva grandson as meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
I'm Linda Hall
And I'm Stephen Thompson there's more stuff to watch and read these days than any one person can get to that's why
We make pop culture happy hour twice a week we sort through the nonsense share reactions and give you the lowdown on
What's worth your precious time and what not find pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pie
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week