Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
I hate this guy here and I hope you are enjoying your summer vacation as
We are
We are taking a little bit of vacation
Eating the road for a series of
Live shows
So occasionally the summer
Replay it
A couple of our favorite episode
How I built this
Including this one this is
The first episode
We ever did with Sara Blakely of spanks and if you've already heard it give it a second listen
You're going to pick up on things you missed
The first time around
Also stick around for the how you built that segment at
The end because we were very cool update for you from one of our
Very first guest
Okay
The show
In the middle of my meeting with her I could tell I was losing her and I just knew it was my one shot so I
I said you know what Diane will you come with me to the bathroom she goes excuse me I go I know I know it's low
Will you just please come with me to the bathroom I want to show you my own product before and after and
Cheap she said okay
From NPR
How I built this
A show about entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
The story of house
Sara Blakely you designed a new kind of underwear called its tanks
Eventually became the youngest female billionaire
In America
Blakely was growing up
In Florida
Exactly
Dream of Designing ladies
60 want to be a lawyer but when she took LSAT
She failed
Twice
After college she got a job at Disney world as
As a ride Twitter
She got another job
Who's selling facts
Door to door
Feeling
Demoralized
With all the rejection and the
Right here where you at
It was like water off a duck
Oh my gosh no I
Would feel very defeated and many times I would
Get in my car and drive around the block multiple times you know just trying to convince myself
To walk through the door
And sometimes I'd walk through the door and they were small offices where the whole office would turn and look at me at the same time
I'm something to completely lose my nerve and just say oh sorry I'm I'm in the wrong place and turn around and walk out so
I stumbled my way through it believe me
And I know it sounds crazy but what I was selling fax machines door-to-door I
Kept feeling like I'm in the wrong movie you know where's the director where's the where's the producer of this is not my
A movie and I was really determined
To create a better life
So hard-working there
Like help you discover
What it was you were
That that was
When I first started wearing Hosiery daily and I realized him figured out what the control top
Portion of the Hosiery was doing for me
In my clothes it was really making my clothes fit so much better
But I had spent money on a pair of cream pants
At $98 on them which for me was a lot of money
And they just hung in my closet on Warren because every time I would go to wear them you could see the undergarment
Regular underwear left a panty line
The song wasn't a great solution it also left marks
So you could stay and then
The shapewear was
So it was like the girdles were so second overdone
And I saw an opportunity for something right in the middle that would just create the perfect canvas undergarment
For women
And I guess I should say for people who have never worn Spanx
It seems like this is an undergarment made out of
Material that basically
Smooth everything around
Button size
Yes
And so
When I cut the feet out of my own control top pantyhose so I can wear those cream pants the light bulb went off
And then I started pursuing the idea
Like how to use an
Started
Build a business
Did you have any money did you
The capital Did you
Wealthy friends
I had set aside $5,000 in savings from selling fax machine Store to Door and that's what I start
Spanx with
And so
The first thing I did was started
To research if the idea is
Existed and I went to the Georgia Tech Library in Atlanta every night after work
Look for a week and a half
Researching every penny has patent that ever existed
And then probably on the
Seventh through tenth day of me being in there some guy came up to me and go to know there's a website called uspto.gov
POV and I said no what is that I scribbled it out of my notebook he's like you can
Search you're putting a patent and it'll search for you so that website became one of my best friends and one
Once I determined that there wasn't anything
That existed in a patent form
And then wanted to see if there was any Market appetite for it Beyond Myself
I literally went and asked one person I went to the Neiman Marcus down the street from my apartment
Went in and asked the sales associate if
She thought anybody would ever want something like a butler
Was pantyhose to wear Underpants
And her face lit up and she goes yes in fact I have lots of customers who've been making their own homemade version of that
Because there's no right under garment to wear under a lot of their clothes
And so that was my whole focus group guy
That's it okay there's a market demand
Had you ever
Sound anything
Were you to do a background and desire
Manufac
Your stuff
No
Did you do how did you get
Start a stick figure out like what material
I've never sewn I have never taken a business class in my life I didn't have anybody in the industry or even
Know anybody
The it worked in fashion or
Retail and so
What happened when I came up with the idea is I just started
Taking other
Pantyhose
And then I went to Hancock Fabrics down the
The straight and all these different arts and crafts
Stores and started
Trying to Paperclip
Different pieces of elastic to the bottom and different pieces of
The Blaze
And you know obviously didn't get very far and my idea actually needed to be made on a machine
And that's why I really needed a manufactured
To give me the time of day
To see if I could even make
And in the meantime
You are
You still selling
Yeah because I needed the money
Coming in in the
The health insurance and all all that comes with that so I was working on my idea at night and on the weekends
And when I kept calling all the manufacturers that I found that were mostly in North
South Carolina on the phone and not getting anywhere
I mean no one would take my
I call or they didn't you know
I had to learn from my cold calling days you got to be there in person
I took a week off
Off of work
And Drugs North
Carolina and Joe
Just started cold calling
Manufacturing
Showed up and said
Yes
So I walked in the door just cold and just said hi I'm here to meet
See the owner in their life
And you are
They always ask you the same three questions it's 8 and you are and it stays terribly
Clear Lake stay and
You're with
I'd say Sara Blakely
Sara Blakely
So you can imagine how that meeting Matt and I must have been more like have a nice day it's great to meet you you know
Were they just not in
Interested in the idea at all
We have the manufacturing plants didn't get it at all and I found it very interesting
Just seemed that all I was meeting with for men and then it kind of
It became clear to be why they probably been so uncomfortable for so hugs
Because the people that were making them worth spending all day in them
You know and so and if they were they were not admitting it
So I had a hard time explaining why this product was so important and
They couldn't wrap their minds around I was basically coming in and disrupting an entire industry been looking at something in one way
And they want to decline year after year
They were making Hosiery to be
As seen on the leg
And I knocked on their door and set guys
I just want your hosiery material
And I don't need it to be seen anywhere
Actually going to be hidden under clothes it's a newt
Undergarment
Condense a manufacturer
Take you want to make
Well it took
A few visits to North Carolina and a lot of
Really persistent
They all sent me away at first and a couple weeks after I left one manufacturer Highland Mills in
In Charlotte North Carolina the owner called me
Ready set Sarah
It's Sam
I've decided to help make your crazy idea
And I just pause it I was about to jump out of my chair and I said really why why the change of heart Sam and all he said is
I have three daughters
And so later I found out when I got the chance
To do it that he had run the idea by his three daughters over dinner and they said Dad this is actually a really good idea we think
You should give this girl a shot
And he still didn't understand it or think it was a good idea but he said that my enthusiasm in Like Mike
Confidence and how good this idea was going to be
Stuck with him
Do you know about what you were
No so when I came up with the idea
I kept it a secret for one year
I did share my idea with people like manufacturers or lawyers are people that I thought could help me bring
A product to life
But I was very careful right away was just a gut feeling I had
To keep it to myself
Because I believe that ideas are the most vulnerable in their infancy
And
It's interesting to turn to your right or left in that moment until a friend or tell your husband
And you know when you do that instantly egos invited into the mix
And then you end up spending all your time defending it
Leaning it
And not pursuing it so
I needed to be at the place where I knew I wouldn't
Turn back no matter what I heard
I'd invested enough of my time and I had enough Sweat Equity into the idea
That I'd I told people and the things I heard where you know honey if it's such a good idea why isn't somebody else
It's already done it
And we'll leave if it is a good idea Sarah you know you're going to spend your savings on this and then sick
Six months the big guys will just knock you out of the water and
That was all coming from a place of love but I feel like if I had heard that
The night that I cut the feet out of my panties I probably still be selling socks
Machine
So once
You started to
Amethyst
Felt was really
Especially
Did you did you begin the process
Getting impacted
I did so I went to three different Law Firm
I couldn't find a single female patent attorney in the state of Georgia and I even called the Georgia Chamber of Commerce and they said there isn't
So I said okay I'm going to do my best to explain his two to three men let's see what happens and
They were very nice they were
Not super
Impress
Probably with the idea and they they all quoted me between 3 and $5,000
Pot Nets
Syfy
Decided to write it myself
And I went to Barnes & Noble on Peachtree in Atlanta and bought a book called patents and trademarks
And I wrote the patent
And then my mom's an artist and so I asked her if she would
Catch me in the prototype for the
The patent and that is
The picture from the US patent and trademark office
But I went back
The one lawyer who gave me a little bit more of time of day than the other ones
And I said listen Dan
I have written my own patent
I have done all of the work except for the claims that is the
The part that I am not trained for I don't understand how to do that
Please I need your expert
Proteases are any chance you would do it for a discounted price
And he was blown away cookie Britain basically the entire patent yes
For $750 I'll do it over a weekend and I'll write the
The claims portion of your patent
Soyuz
So then you got the
Yes but you know there was a moment in this journey that was quite funny I
When we were in the final stages of the claims
The lawyer said Sarah there is I need to know it's technically in the Garment from a
Fiber and yarn level on
Okay
Only one person to call on that nut
Ted and Ted what had become my friend in the back of the manufacturing plant North Carolina and Ted had
The most
Thick southern accent
You've ever heard in your life
I mean it was intense
And so
I called
Ted on the phone I said Ted my lawyers on the phone and we're trying to finalize the patent can you tell me exactly what's in the Garment
He's like yeah
They're 70% nylon and 30% lacquer
Okay great and so my lawyer and I are riding and I go thanks Ted and I'm up all night guy the night before I submit my patent to the US
Just tied and trademark office and I'm thinking
How is there life
Hacker in this product
Like how is that possible
I called had the next morning and I said Ted is Sarah we weave
Spell
Lacquer for me
Yeah lyrics
Cra
Oh my God it's like okay okay okay thanks
Call my lawyer on my doing all change on lacquer it's Lycra
End
He laughed so hard because you know fast you would have got no patents are on trying to make pantyhose out of paint thinner and like yeah
Coming up
How Sarah got
Spanx into the department stores and
The closets
Many women
You may know
I'm guy Raz a noose
Ramen PR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Exxon the state of Market
Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics disc
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
Look and much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcasts
Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Thanks also to our 2019 lead sponsor
How I built this
Hiscox
The business in
Insurance expert to understand that
Which business is
As unique as a fingerprint or a barcode
Tailors in
Elgin Insurance Solutions
Every business has very spot
Pacific need
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote
Purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
IOffer ring account
With no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Built this from NPR on Gyros
In a story
Sara Blakely has
Designed
A new kind of shapewear
And then
She wanted to get it out in
Wenzhou market
The first
Come up with a name
The name was a journey that since the time I cut the feet out of my pantyhose
Tell the time I launched it in stores was 2 years
And I've been writing
Names on scrap pieces of paper everywhere I was you know and most of the names are on the back of rental car agreement
Because I had great thinking and in cars
And I wasn't getting anywhere with that I didn't like any of the names and I knew it wasn't right
And then I sort of narrow down my thinking at one point in time and thought Kodak and Coca-Cola are the two most recognized name
Cineworld what do they have
In common they both had a strong case down to them
And I had friends that were stand-up comedians
And I knew that the k sound makes your audience laugh
So I just called
I know I don't know but it said it's a known trade secret among
Comedian
And so I thought you know what I need to have my invention have the k sound in it for good luck
And almost as soon as I neared my thinking down that way the word Spanx came to me while I was in my car
I saw the word across like in my mind across the dashboard of my car and I pulled off the side of the road and I-5
That's it
And I went home that night I didn't tell anybody
And I wrote down spanks
And I went on USPTO. Govt at I sit and I sat there and stared at it for a while and at the last minute
My backspace
And deleted the K in the ass and put him in Act
I dread that made up words to better for products
And real word
Doing their easier to trademark
And even though it did actually have the cake and it had still the case down and so I felt great about it and the name is just right it's just
My product was all about the rear end
And it's about making the rear end look better and no panty lines and so the word spanks was
Kind of naughty and kind of funny and a little bit risky and it just all work tonight and I hit
Stand and
Think about a hundred fifty dollars with my credit card and then a couple months later I got back an official certificate from the government
Saying that I was the proud owner of the word Spang
OKC
Got a manufacturer a patent
Anime
How did you
My very first account that I called on was Neiman Marcus
Even
Get in there
I called them
Guy I just called them
I went in the Yellow Pages and I looked up the Neiman Marcus number in Atlanta and I said hi on Sarah and then to the
Product can I come and show it to you in the lady laughs and goes man we have a buying office and it's in Dallas
I said oh well what's their number
So she gave me their number and I started calling them
And I just kept calling and trying to get to the Hosiery buyer and I called for days at different times and she answer
To the phone and I took my shot and I said hey a hi I'm Sara Blakely and I invented a product that is going to change
The way your customers wear clothes
And if you give me a few minutes of your time I'll fly to Dallas
And show you
What you say
She said
Well if you're willing to fly here I'll give you 10 minutes of my time
And I said great
And I jumped on a plane and I flew to Dallas
And I was in the meeting with her and she was this
Beautiful woman impeccably-dressed I'm at the Neiman Marcus headquarters I have a Ziploc bag for my kitchen with a pro
Prototype init
A color copy of the packaging that I'd created on my friends
Computer
And
My lucky red backpacks
From college that all of my friends back to me now
You cannot go to the Neiman Marcus headquarters with that red
Eastpak old
Stingy backpack I said yes it's my good luck charm I have to admit they were
Really pleading with me
In the middle of my meeting with her I could tell I was losing her and I just knew it was my one shot so I said you know what
What Diane
Will you come with me to the bathroom
And she just pause you does excuse me I go
I know I know it's a little bit will you just please come with me to the bathroom I want to show you
My own product before and after
And she
She said okay if you walk down the hall with me and I went in the stall and I had on my cream pants that were the reason I invented this
Without Spanx on and then I went in the stall and put steaks on underneath and came out and she looked up and she goes
Wow I get it
Brilliant
And she said I'm going to place an order and I'm going to put it in
7 stores and see how it goes
I couldn't believe it I got in the car and I was shaking
And I called Sam from the manufacturing plant Lego Sam Sam is Sarah I need more I just landed Neiman Marcus
G+ there's nothing on the other end of the phone for a it seem like a minute
Either Sam or you there
Is Tara
Don't take this the wrong way but I thought you were to give these away as Christmas gifts or something for the next like 5 years what do you mean
Neiman Marcus just took it on my memory has just took it and I mean
Okay so you are
In Neiman Marcus
Are you thinking all right
Oh my gosh that is the biggest mistake that entrepreneurs make that is when the work begins
Personally I paid people basically friends to go buy the product and create a buzz about it because I was like you know I got
I have these things move off the shelf or the buyers not going to give me any
Any more chance
Wait you paid people to buy the
Yes
I called every friend I had in all the Seven Cities that Neiman's sent
The Spanks to
And called friends that I hadn't even spoken to since fourth grade and
You know kind of like hide Sarah remember me from 4th grade
Do you mind going to the store and buying thanks and I'll send you a check
And
It was really tough because I was one item
In a in a department
And a new brand and I didn't even get a whole row in the Hosiery Department I got a pocket
So
I needed to do whatever I could to maximize this chance
And
I went to the
The stores and I would have
Explain what the product was I would demo it at shut the before and after picture that my friend took
And then I would stand in the
Restore from
9 when they opened until about 5 or 6
Everyday
Yeah
And I realized that one of the biggest challenges I had was that the where my product was being sold in the store
Door was an issue is being sold in the Hosiery department and my customer was in the shoe department
And she was in the ready-to-wear department
And so I started
Realizing I got I have a challenge I've got to get my product out of the department it's supposed to be sold in
Tohatchi how'd you do that
Well I went to Target and I bought stands
You know free envelope
And I ran around the store and put them at every cash register and everybody thought somebody else approved it
So the cats remember when like Neiman Marcus and moving your
Like piles of Spanx
To the cash register and they just assumed that that way
Looks like
Some hydros
So other than that how are you
Letting people know about
But you were selling
It was a lot of a lot of hard work for me to get the word out I mean I've never advertised
Nice things to say
18 years old and we've never done any formal ad campaign or anything is so it's a very Word of Mouth brand
No money
How to get the word out
And
You did things like
Already
Send it to Oprah
Yeah I did I sent it to Oprah with a note and
Turns out she ended up.
Picking it is her favorite product of the year how did she even
Find it in the
Piles of male sheep
Well I found out that Andre
Her hairdresser got him
End
Put them in her dressing room
She Tried Him and
Put them on and
Has basically warned them everyday since
She liked
Cover shipping pantyhose the women or the Spanx all across
The world basically from my apartment
So that's an enormous opportunity and then another thing I made a decision that was really
You know unconventional at the time
I decided to go on QVC
The Shopping Channel
Yeah and
Had a lot of people say Sarah your brand is at Bergdorf Goodman to Neiman Marcus you can't also sell on QVC you'll kill your
Brand and I just
I just had guys
I'm going to be the one on QVC
And I'm going to come
Control the message and it's going to give me an opportunity to explain what this is and
You know I felt confident in that
And they gave me five minutes of airtime
And
I sold
Mm Paris
Banks in 5 minutes
And that was after you know a year of standing in department stores across the country and on a really good day I
I fell between you know
35 to
Pair in a day
MN sales muscle
Going up because I read that
Can hear you
Uni like
10 million-dollar
Yeah
That feel
It was great
It was great I never was doing it for the money you know so I wasn't really that ever that
Focused on it I mean I can even remember after a couple years of
Thanks I'm still in my apartment and my accountant kept trying to convince me to buy a house and I was like nah I'm not interest
My little brother was always calling and telling me different ways
And I just
It was really just for the art of it like I love I love being able to pay my own rent and stand on my own two feet as a woman
That was a really important thing for myself but
It was really just I love making the product
Did you have
Early on did you have people
Listen you got to steal a basket
Any money
I mean business
Company
Figure this out
Yeah I did I had all kinds of
Things coming at me in the beginning
And still do you know
15 years later but I remember one of the most
Interesting was
Within the first 6 months I started having several
People come up to me and say what
And I had no idea what they were talking about cuz I've never taken a business
And it dawned on me that people act
Restart things just
Seldom
Are you still on Hunter
Yes
You ever think
No
I was always nervous
But I was always so connected
The product
When I was so I was so creating this
Before it has
107 facts
Pusheen Store to Door
I was I was thinking about it I was writing about it I was visualizing it I was
Preparing for it
I thought you know I don't have the most money I don't have a business degree
I have no idea what I'm doing
Emilio factoring a retailer any of this
But I do care the most so let's see what happen
When you see this
See things like you do
Sara Blakely
Play billionaire
Weirdly
See that
Did you see that number that word
Yes it's very weird it reminds me of in middle school there used to be these things in the malls where you could go in and pics
The magazine cover you wanted
Feel like your friends we don't go in the booth and we smile and then we'd be on the cover of Vogue or whatever
I just does it feels very surreal to me
Assets Sara Blakely
Founder of Spanx
15 years on the company has
Continue to grow and as
Get to go public
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things that
Your building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors
American
Express open
Every week on how I built this
We bring you stories about entrepreneurs
Beat the odds overcame obstacles and made their eye
Ideas happen
It's never easy and that's why America
Express open wants to help with money and know-how
You can turn your ideas into impact
Get business done
Learn more at open
Dot-com
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Timer for how you built that and say Russia going to check back with someone who is on the show last fall
Arthur the founder of fiendish
Kholoki tender its weight of making new friends
Just a friend based on
Things you both like to do like gardening or hiking or playing music and the moment there are users that have things
In common with you
I will get a notification that you have friends waiting so once you get that notification you can meet them or you can
Keep swiping on other interest
I just spent several months trying to get friend-ish coded and to work out some of the Kinks and when she fine
Can we put a beta version up on the app store on iTunes last bring most of the feedback she got
Disappointing
The biggest criticism was that there wasn't enough people on the app so naturally
We're Basin Orlando which is where most of our users are but if you downloaded the app
Wisconsin or in Berlin or in London
There just wasn't enough users
Able to feel like the apples function
So we're going to have a bad experience
Is almost just as bad as in not downloading it at all
But then about a month after
We first spoke
To Chandra
She got some good news
She apply to be a
Contestant on a new reality show
Planet of the apps and she got it
It wasn't a typical reality show like The Bachelor where it's like
20 girls
One guy
This is the search for the next
Great idea
The show is produced by Apple and
Forecast
You have 60 seconds on the escalator to get them
Truth be a part of your project you'll know
Cuz at the end of the risky later ride that either green or red
And you can probably imagine
Happens next if
The show's advisor
Like your idea
Eventually get a big investment
In your app
Tundra can't tell us whether that happened to her because the episode
Json has
Run but she says
It was really cool to just
Be on the show you know during filming a lot of people from Apple would be on
Sad or just so you know
Kind of hear back from seasoned professionals
About your app ID and for people to look at your ID in a different way that you haven't
Considered as just it was
Amazing
Chargers episode of Planet of the
The apps will drop
90 weeks
Witches Rock
Play the same time that the
Official version of fiendish will go live
On the App Store
I hope that I'm
Becoming a success story for Orlando Tech assist
I'm quite happy
Which is still Beyond
When is Journey on the roller
GhostRobo don't fall off
How soon but
I wouldn't have it any
Either way
You can read more about Chandra Arthur and friends on our Facebook page
Facebook
Your story could have build.
Npr.org we love
Hearing what you're up to end
Listen to show this week if you want to find out more or here
Previous episodes
You can go to how I built this
NPR
Org
Please do subscribe and while you're there please also write a review if you like the show
You can write us
HIV
TT at npr.org
And if you want to send it
Tweet it's at
How I built this
Are shows produced this way
Weak by Run abdel-fattah
Original music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant sanaz meshkinpour Claire Breen
Jeff Rogers
Are fabulous intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Roz and you're listening to how I built this from NPR
If you're looking for a new podcast
Planet Money
Refresh listen
One thing people say about planet money is
How much they love listening
Even though they don't
Are my business or economic
It's just a
The smart show with great stories
Help explain our world
It's
Explanatory journalism at its best
Pretend that really need some sand reporting about the big question
Find Planet Money on NPR one or wherever you get
Podcast
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing flag
Form used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week