This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
2003 delivery of glass that was
Salty and so we ended up with some product in the marketplace that had broken glass inside the bottle
Contact with two different Whole Food store
And Whole Foods has a rule three-strikes-and-you're-out
No we can't afford as a business to lose our largest customer so we voluntarily withdrew all product on the market
Every store totally stopped our sales
It was just painful
Ramen PR
It's how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movements
Gyros and the story of how Seth Goldman Honest Tea from a kitchen
Suburban Maryland to the shelves of virtually every grocery
Store in America
So the year is 1997
Deckelman is living in
Bethesda Maryland with his wife
Three young kids
He's 32 he just graduated from the Yale School of Management
Investment firm
Chef
He's he's got an itchy he feels like he wants to start something and
Keep nagging at him
Day after
The day after
Thinking about different ideas maybe a web-based system that
Would raise money for public schools by tapping
Into alumni Networks
Came up with the idea to simplify diagnostic
6 / urinary tract infections
They were a bunch of other ideas that would pop into his head but really got him excited
Until 1 afternoon
When he finished a long-run and walked into a convenience store
Hot and sweaty and I went to a beverage cooler and I said there's nothing here that nothing seemed to be like
And it was all a hundred calories per 8-oz and the difference was there no Fizz color
Different names different bottles they were almost
Uniform
Bitter taste profile the sweetness profile
647 teaspoons
Sugar per 8 oz
Or not
Why is anyone making a drink
1 or 2 to 6 like the little bits
Just a tad sweet
So how did you go from that to
Thinking about starting a teacup
So when I
Felt that Thursday I reached out to my
Professor from busy
And when I hit Ferry Nova
When I've been a student
We had a case study of the beverage industry and we had agreed there was a myth
There was that space
Sweetness Cafe
So I reached out to Barry I said I think I'm ready to do something about this I Iran
No not a TF Britain and more importantly not a beverage industry expert no knowledge of that and that was where
Having zero knowledge of the beverage industry in the beginning was
Play competitive
Because we went in without any of the Assumption
What are the things that happened literally
The same amount that I went for that running in New York City
Was that
An investment my dad had made it 1977 so it goes
18 years ago
At the time
Came to fruition and I was presented with a check for $50,000
And
That was kind of the risk Capital enough for me to say okay well
Like I'm going to put this
This is if we lose this we lose it but this is what I'll bet
But at the beginning I mean you were thinking
I'm going into a job but
I mean you were still young enough where you could always let go back in the final
That's right so you have a $50,000 check
Dad and then and it was very able to put a little receive money. Barry had been on the board of a company that goes public
People cuz he kept his day job
As a professor professor
What was funny was that before I went to submit my resignation account but I kind of called Barry for one last boost of confidence.
I'm going to go in there you know you just had a third son but I'm going to
Step down
And this is long pause he says what
I bet if you went to Calvert and asked to go on sabbatical I bet you they let you do that
I knew I had to take the plunge you couldn't
Get investors to invest for employees
Or buyer to commit without
In a meeting
Do a quick eye checks after
Ura
Father of three kids
What's a good job
Calvert invest
And you tell your wife you're going to quit to start a Tea Company
You know nothing about nothing about that terrified you
More portly nothing about that terrified her
Yeah I think it was I believe in
Myself probably a little
Pedicurist right like I think I can do this even though I don't know anything about it
But
I am ready to try
So you quit and then basically you and Barry what did you start
I do like how did you start to get
What did you start to raise money was that your dad was a little bit of the chicken and egg so the first thing we did was I I did write a business
When these days people really
Put together power
If they don't write business
20 Page business plan
Mostly show the thinking behind the business I think every every potential investor wants
Play some thought here about
About where this goes
What how it become
I managed to secure an appointment with Whole Foods
That early even even
Before you had a problem that was lucky because the the marketing director at Whole Foods
At that time a cup fresh Fields whole
Amid Atlanta
He was a graduate of the Oakland Raiders
So he helped me get an appointment with Apple
Wow
It's one of us here
Versailles because
Somewhere I have read about you every time I look in the midst of all this happened at Whole Foods and
And all that excitement
Your son Elliot
Protect the ultimate test in compartmentalizing because literally the day before the Whole Foods
Our first presentation
When we
That's probably the most important thing in the cupboard
Everywhere we go
Amputee
And Barry and I are in the kitchen and we've got
Mugs
Bowls that we're bruma T and it was not an
Official looking mad
The kitchen
Boulevard
Sync my wife walks in with our
Our middle son
And she's got this Ashen look on her face and and I
I don't know she
Subset
Made the kitchen such a mess
We'll clean this up
Angie's List
We just came back from the doctor and lar middle son had a coarctation of the aorta
You're going to need major surgery within the month
And so
Now that's a pretty heavy news to get
How old was he
Intense
And
Probably if that it happened a few weeks early I probably went to
Because
Health insurance benefits or just the risk level
Could do that but I've already taken the plunge I knew
You can you can bet that when I was at the Whole Foods meeting I was selling with great intensity of it
Needed to succeed
And then
While Elie was in the hospital
I stayed with him that whole week
But I'll go down at
After midnight we had someone working on formulas
Plans and he would come in and meet me in the
Lobby of Children's Hospital in
Taste tea together in
If we paielli's bed
And I think
Life happens
It's it's
Part of the experience
It's part of the journey and
And I'm so thankful and
They have Ellie still with us and in such a delight in such a
Wonderful presence you know
For me and and Ferb
EMC King about
You like
Pitching
This product
Eno at Whole Foods in the midst of all this
Bring them samples it's like the Samsung made in your kitchen
Patron in English
Some random bottles or something
We we got an empty snap
But what's really funny is that Barry had sent over some Services when they in the mail
And when I met with the buyer and I
We poured out sample from the thermos totally empty Snapple bottle
Honesty
And he had said
I would like this sounds interesting will give it a try I will take 15000 bottles which of course
Both terrifying and thrilling
How did you make that
How did you make that much teeth with the other so we got this and then next thing we did is we
Basically went up and down that you
East Coast looking at bottling
We went to beer plant soda plants apple juice plants
So we ended up at a plant in
Buffalo New York that was making apple juice
I'm down on his luck that's a line time available in
Place where you can read the tea leaves
And so we
Brought in these mesh bag is large mesh bags that are actually clean a pool.
That was what we use boiling water and every once in awhile the bag with break and then
Types of wood
Claudia was it was not pretty how did you know that he was I mean that like
That was that was so funny
You know when I talked to Barry
He is very good at making things sound simple sometimes they are sometimes
You take a teabag you knocked out of water
If you multiply X 15000
That when you
Especially beginning to many tea leaves you don't get the full infusion
The back brakes when you really got a problem so we just had to keep
Iterating
It was a very
Makeshift operation
What's up once you had all the bottles had I mean how did it sell like this
To do well
So what happened was in arms we went to the shop nobody knew what it was
And so all that for some of the
This is 1998 now
All we did
Make our marketing efforts
Was me and
To intern
Giving out sand
Whole Food stores
And
We gave out more samples and resole
But by the end of that summer we were the best selling tea in the 17
Fresh Fields Whole Foods
Atlantic wow
And so what was then happening was that the consumers were starting to
For the tea which is
And then it was so different and end so what was nice is
We have most switching
Some brands
Making the cereal category if1 out of Raisin brands on sale tomorrow go by post or whatever.
Do you switch back and forth but with honesty
It's not there you don't go back and buy
Snapple or Arizona because it
The Taste of Soul
And so when we got somebody and we were clearly not for everybody
They they were very loyal
What was like what was the thing that made
Honesty difference
From
Like everything else
That was in the market
So true things first
Much less sweet than everything
The other thing in the reason the name Honesty made sense is because what we learned is most of the bottle T the US
Set the time in still today
Is not brewed with
It's it's
The powder or concentrate
If there's a relationship to the TV like the fish fillet there's a relationship to the fish
But aren't we
Bring in the TV show
The plant can we bring them there
Lemon soap
Once you were in Whole Foods
Pretty quickly after you launch it mean it seems like
You were sad because I guess the impression of the average person
So it was just a sweet was a star
And so
But we proved the concept
Yeah and so then we will go back after investor and say we proved the concept
Now it's time to expand so we got more investment money raised and then we went to the other buyers
For the west coast and we went to buy us from other stores
You know I'm mom's my Organic Market here in
Mid-Atlantic was one of our earliest accounts a day
They it was working there they started took to bring it to their other stores
So you're a mean
Give me you're making a lot
Of tea
You're growing what were the challenges
Hello there so many cuz it was still
Professional cash is always a challenge we weren't we were growing quickly but
We were spending money to do it we will head salespeople
We were doing marketing
And then just probably getting the tea
Stores right to the stores and any we were still getting rejected by all these distributor so Distributors are
The Gatekeepers are your drinks go because this is unlike
Company
No matter how good our product is
We can ship it through the mail
Beverages are a high turnover product
And so as soon as the Shelf empties of beverages
Something takes its place
And so you need a distributor to be there to to build
To keep the Shelf space
I protected in Seoul
What happened was we were going to all the Distributors of Snapple in Arizona
And they were saying
When they returned our calls they would just say it's not sweet enough
They were expensive wow
It tastes like grass it's not what were used to which of course it wasn't an
What they were where they were not
Effective as they
They were tasting it for their own
They weren't
Thinking that's
This whole population out there
That's your has a difference
Appetite
Did you amine went when you pitch it to investors who invested in life
Kinds of things did
I mean
Were they saying oh this is awesome I can't wait to jump in or they just said
We're just saying
Did you get 11 knows we got a ton of nose and the main reason we got so many noses this was run now and sort of 1999 to
Doesn't this winter in the home.com
Yeah and we were very old economy
And so are you know people would much rather throw millions of dollars it
Something.com
Then
Put a few maybe 10 or $20,000 in
Sent you a beverage Gump
Acuity versus come in and say you know you
You should follow advicent
What am I supposed to do everything in
Fancy message from Boston they said you know well you know you could
You should be an energy drink cuz that's really growing
Nba.com
You know if you made the product cheaper you can make better margins on it
I don't sound like you're interested in the opportunity accept everything that we do
Especially
But we also need it to really succeed in the long-term we had to be different than all the other big companies out
And if we
How to create a sweet tea there are
Tons of companies already doing that
But when you were in those early days
The scientist greater
Well there's no question that would have led to
The faster growth
But it would have
Diluted but we were building
This was about building something that
We could always believe in that we would
That would be meaningfully different in that
It to take people in a different direction you have to
Disrupt where they're going
Seth Coleman
In the moment when we come back that explains how honest he became an actual political issue in the 2008 presidential
Dental campaign
I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
ER
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to
Two of our sponsors
If you helped make this
Podcast possum
First to godaddy.com
They give customers.
The tools inside
They need to transform
Their ideas
Impersonal initiatives
To success
Let's Go Daddy
Small business owners have everything they need to go
Get their business
Online
Including award-winning
24/7 support
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology providers dedicated to small business
And they're offering how I built this listeners
30% off all new products
Just go to godaddy.com
And use filter
To get started that's built
Thanks also to Goldman Sachs
Insights from some of the world
Leading thinkers on markets
Industries and the global economy
The firm's podcast
Exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Does your discussions
Topics with far-reaching implications
Climate change
Autonomous driving
And the future of China's economic growth Plus
Much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on iTunes Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
Gs.com
Splash Park
What mark would say
Did you know that
Trees can
Actually talk to each other
Or that you are evolutionarily built to have a maximum of 100
Be friends
Or that virtually
Any device
Senior home care
Be connected to another one
Halfway Around the World
You can find out why this week
My other program is called
TED Radio Hour
Where were exploring ideas
Power of Networks
Check it out at
Npr.org podcast
ITunes or however you gay
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
2 mm
Honesty and become one of the highest
Selling beverages at Whole Foods
And things were going pretty well
But then
It was a hit
The time the company had its own bottling plant
Are Pittsburgh
And something happened there
They could have
Completely destroyed the company in 2003
We had a delivery of glass that was
Salting
And on their lot of blisters in the in the glass Little League
Look at it see little bubbles
And so
We ran it
The production line
Entered with limeworks is that if it ever sees a defect in the bottle it supposed to
Kick it out
Reject the bottle
Madeline didn't do that
And so we end up with some
Product in the marketplace that had broken glass inside the bottle
Contact with two different Whole Food stores
And Whole Foods has a rule three-strikes-and-you're-out
Borsalino one got hurt or injured
We did have
Pieces of broken glass
At
No we can't afford as a business
Toulouse
Biological
So we voluntarily withdrew all product from them
Every store
How much did I cost you well we were doing about
3 million for $9 in sales and
I totally stopped
Our sale so we lost several months of $700,000
Huge
It'll just momentum stop or who you're trying to build you got your salespeople are trying to sell product instead of me calling all
Nnn it was just painful
Mashable until the 8 years
When I'm spending sprees we were sharing hotel rooms and
Cutting Corners everywhere we could not in ingredients but you know just trying to
Kit to keep the lights on
So what were you like what were you paid us
My first year salary was at 50,000 literally I took that $50,000 check and it was even
It was tax-efficient cuz I invested in the company that I paid myself
I don't think I got over a hundred thousand
For probably not
Really crew
This time with their like lots of other companies are offering to it to buy you guys out
Lots of companies along the way and he was very
Parsley cuz we're growing quickly
Because we were doing something others weren't doing
So really from
From the first year we every year so we'd be approached by a
Food or beverage
That wanted to Tobias
An arid like one of those most companies was
That lady and ends and they has a kind of trendy right here
Exactly what you're doing and just do it bigger and end
We were always that was another thing I could lose sleep about competition you and Barry owned like
Like 90% of your company even though you had
7 best
How are you able to do that
Well this was one of the key
Strategic elements that Barry brought to the
It literally is
Professor of Game Theory and so
He said you know the problem with so many startups is the
Entrepreneurs give himself all these penny stocks in the beginning
And as a result
They start with
Much more stock than everybody else
And then everybody else's kind of
It comes along for the ride is it but what if
Instead you started the founders at the same place as the other investors
And only when the company grows in value
Do the founders get
More equity
That's
It was it was a reverse truck
And what that did was it helped
As we grew and we raised more money we didn't get diluted
Nelson was we relied on Angel Island
So a lot of entrepreneurs in the Venture Capital Motors
Basically
There instead of istick to own more the company during set of eyes to exit quickly
And we didn't take that kind of money and I'm very glad we didn't at the I think that was a key piece that let us
Keep control
What what did you what did you start to realize that
You know like honest
T was becoming part of life
The cultural Zeitgeist funny moment there was a moment
President Obama had becoming honest tea drinker
I guess at the campaign for 2008
And the McCain campaign ad that criticized him for being a node out of touch with the regulation what's his favorite one
Drinking organic
Stock of it in his life
And the cattle with him a few years ago when he brought over his the body man there
What do I have to have
Wow
At what point were you able to
Feel like
Well I would say so
When Coca-Cola became an investment
That was a surreal experience
Because
Approached
They approached us with a purchase in 2007 and they've had just created this group of venturing in emerging brands
And their goal was to invest in and build the next billion-dollar brand
And so
You know going to the headquarters in Atlanta sitting down with
The chairman
And and soda party was like looking down like I'm really here we're really having this conversation
So that was the first of all this is actually going to work this is going to be around
Coke
But about 30% to 40%.
And and they bought an option to buy a majority which eventually
Holi in 2011
But like this was your accompaniment did you
Feel like you were
You were giving away control well
You know the story so often
When a brand is sold the entrepreneur gets really frustrated in the end they butt heads in the last few months
The friend of my friend of mine it was a vitamin water
But he left shortly after
Coca-Cola body
First few weeks they want to know your
Pinyin
And the next week I want to know your phone number
They don't want to know you
Give Coke a lot of credit they understood this is a branded that is different than what they sell them
Target bacon
Connect with the organic
Consumer or the Natural Foods Marketplace
And so they gave us this incredible latitude in the autonomy
And there were moments where
We ran up against them around regulatory language or
Or just marketing approaches and they respected what we did so what's so
Continue to surprise me
This brand of storm Iran
And in the biggest part with the distribution we were in 15000 stores
When Coke invested never-never hundredths
So that's
That's where the difference is
I hope I never see right there
Early investors people who put in $50,000 income
Beginning
Make a return of 1.2
5 billion dollars
10 years later that's right. 26 x there
Hurley investment you know how many millionaires were created by honest
I don't know
To me what was so exciting and some of our employees were wearing
Timmy was
You know that was all Sweat Equity
That they are in so that way
What's especially
Meaningful
The question I've asked everybody who's on the show
How much of what happened
With you in Burien honesty was because
You guys are just really good at what you do and how much
I really don't believe in luck
I believe that the reason we're still here is the perseverance
And I'd citic centers luck
You know that it's the timing the way the consumer has evolved
But you know I've heard something so that you were in the right place at the right time as well you know
10 years to get to that right place so this was not a
This present
You know something that just happened overnight
A friend of mine like into to water you know eventually water finds its way
Going downhill when it gets to where it needs to go and I think
And we finally
Got to a place where we could connect with consumers
And doing the weather was still meaningful
So I'm curious as you
Metallic look back on all this
At like 1
William Quantrill
You either developed
Or have it
You think all I do
Well
You have to be resilient in this is this is something that's so important to put this on the bigger picture.
Just for like RR
Resilience
What are the best ways I develop resilience growing up was I wrestled in high school
I was the worst wrestler on the team
My first year I was one and 10 and I was only cuz somebody didn't show up and I got the forfeit
So I had
I'm learned how to fight off my back
You know an endive
Experience rejection and end
It's so important
Be able to bounce
Not just me all the time
Am I pan
And especially when you believe in it
Makes it that much easier
That's Chef Goldman founder of honesty
By the way the company has sold more than a billion bottles of
Beverage
It's all completely owned by Coca-Cola with
Annual sales of more than a hundred and seventy million dollar chef
It no longer formerly involved and though it made him a rich man
Is life hasn't
Actually changed all that much that still lives in the same house in Suburban Maryland
But he made that first batch
Honesty
And please don't turn it off
Just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the
The things you guys are built
The first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Real Time with Bill Maher on
HBO
When everyone's talking politics
Common sense
Delmar and is rotating panel
Arthur's newsmakers artist
Politicians
Provocateurs from both sides of the aisle are back
Join as a dissected new and not
So new people at happenings of Wall Street Hollywood
Around the world and especially in Washington
Watch Real Time with Bill Maher live Fridays
10 p.m. only
HBO
Real-time overtime
Hey thanks for staying till the very end because we are now at the
Part of the show where we get to here
A great story about something
You guys are busy
My name is Glenn Auerbach
And I'm in Minneapolis Minnesota
And I've created a nice mug
In the IDF for nice
Came about
It was on one of those freezing winter morning
In Minnesota
Glenn Wyn
Outside with backyard
And pick up a jug of water that
Add Frozen overnight
Nature freezes water in a jug from the outside in
And from the bottom up
So you get kind of a hockey puck type freeze at
At the bottom
But there's this really interesting cavity
That freezes last
And that's an iconic shape
And that shape was a glass like the kind of glass you would put on your dinner table
Perfectly formed
Made of clear ice
Sobini
Resourceful people that we hire with a beer in our hand we poured a beer in a nice mug was born
I mean
Say USA
Any more clearly than 8
Cold beer in a glass made of
Ice
The first thing Glen did naturally was to
Take the ice mug into his
Backyard sauna
It held up
Pretty well until
You know it
Melted
So then I started messing around with different molds and different ways that we could freeze ice
So I experimented
Glenn came up with a plastic mold that seemed to do the trick
But it was a massive challenge for me
To make clear ice
And without clear ice
You get leaked
And leaks are no fun
The leaks
Actually come from air bubbles in the ice
Plenti card for years
To come up with a mold that would make a mug
Without the bubbles
And finally
He nailed it but never leaks
I'm really proud of that
Glen now sells and mold all over the country you feel it
Does water freeze at overnight than
Pop out your own ice mug
And this past year
Some executives
Did Coca-Cola actually called them up and said hey
We want to use ice mug
In one of our ads
Yeah
Was quite a rush you know the biggest Beverage Company in the world making nice mugs put in Coca-Cola in there we just had a
Great time
For the time being
Nice Mike is still Glen side Hustle
You're not planning on
Quitting his day job
Is a Salesman
Anytime soon you know if we could send a kid through college
With the proceeds for nice mug while I couldn't be happier
And if you're wondering how long the ice mug actually lasts in your hand before
Melts
We can have nice mugs that last like 30 minutes
45 minutes
I mean I suppose
The one thing that's cool about nice mug is when your ice is melted you're done drinking
Clara box founder of nice mug
He lives in Minneapolis Minnesota
Hey we love hearing your stories about the things your building if you want to tell us
About them
Go to build
Npr.org
Build
Got npr.org
I think you listen to the show this week if you want more or listen to previous episodes
Good how I built this.
Npr.org
If you have a chance please subscribe to our show through iTunes and let other
People know about it
You can also write us directly at HIV
BT at npr.org
Between us
How I built this
A Show's producer Suite by runty Nara blue
He also composed the music
It's also to neva Grant Santa's meshkinpour NJ
Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
But something happening
The weekend of
January 14th
If you listen to the NPR news quiz show wait wait don't tell me and you love and worship Peter Sagal like
Baidu
Well I haven't
That weekend
Tom Hanks is
Hi Peter Sagal up and he's going to be hosting the show
Himself so listen to wait wait don't tell me with
Special guest host Tom Hanks you can find it
On the NPR one app
AT-AT npr.org
This is Tom Hanks
Do you know an Undiscovered musician who deserves a break
Well we have an idea for the NPR music
Is holding a tiny desk
Contest to find one great unsigned musician
The play the iconic tiny desk Concert Series in 29 states with NPR music
All you have to do is shoot a video of your musical act
Playing an original song behind a desk
And submitted by January 29th
Learn more at npr.org
Tiny desk
Support for this podcast in the following message come from fundrise the future of real estate investing
Access private Market real estate projects from high rises in DC to multi-family apartments in LA
Get your first three months of bees weigh
Fundrise.com indicate