It's guy here with the note before we start the show
When you support your public radio station
Upower the resources
Ports on big stories that affect
Your community
In other words you make journalism happen
Be informed be delighted
B connected
Keep the facts coming
Support independent journalism by donating to
To your station
I donate. Npr.org
Slash built
And then share why you have
Using the hashtag
Why Public Radio
And thanks
We found after getting it into the stores that we hadn't really thought this through carefully enough
It wasn't an effective deodorant so we did a product recall
What what percentage of your business did the owner account for that time
Enormous amount of product that you couldn't sell $450,000
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movements they built
Turn to $5,000 loan into a soap and toothpaste business
Call Tom's of Maine now one of the biggest brands in the natural products
So if you put a previous episode of the show with
John Mackey the guy who founded Whole Foods
Explain how
When you started that company in the late 1970s
Natural and organic foods were
Are the counterculture
The kind of store is that
Sold organic foods and soaps
Also sold
Crystals and New Age pamphlets and
Wind chime
It's not like there's anything wrong with those things it's just that now
Organic
Is gone mainstream
It's big business a multi-billion-dollar industry
But chasing money isn't
Terminal Warehouse
Maine
Start making the stuff because they were part of a movement
The movement that took off
L86
Season early 70
People who were worried about toxic
Shenzhen artificial ingredients
Things we use everyday
But unlike Ben Cohen and Jerry Greenfield
Jerry's or
Gary hirshberg of Stonyfield
Also been on the show
Tom Chappell wasn't and isn't a lefty countercultural type of guy
He's actually an old school New England Yankee
His dad ran a
Textile mill and he grew up in
Traditional family
Quiet
Stoic
Episcopal Republic
And literally yes I mean literally
His life
Was a Norman Rockwell painting
That's right
I'm not perfect Norman Rockwell found me
Add a choir practice in Pittsfield Massachusetts St Stephen's church
Pulled me out and asked if
I want to be on the cover of the Saturday evening post and I was 10 years old I had never heard of the Saturday evening post
Never heard of Norman Rockwell
So I just looked at him and I said I don't know I'll have to call my mother and see
And so Tom did call his mother and he
Did actually end up on the cover of the Saturday evening post
In the spring of 1950
Time eventually went to Trinity College in Hartford where he studied English
He met his wife Kate and they got married when he was 22
And then
He got his first job working for Aetna
Selling insurance and he was a great sales
It didn't last too long
Well I was the number one
Salesman
Class of 65 people
But
I was been given my raise
Are the Rays
Was a $600
I found out the lowest raise
$300
You were making you even a $600 raise
As for being the number one sales rep
Meet worst
Sales rep $300
Correct
That didn't compute
The truth
For me was that working in a large corporate
Structure
Was something I could see required a great deal of order discipline get in line wait
And I
Realize that I was not made for
That kind of a culture
Competitive did you want to be the top selling insurance agent in that office was that important
I think it's always been important to me
I've had people
Say to me
About their work I've never aspired to
Be the boss
Fix myself
Good Lord
I can't imagine that
Foster. Least one or two steps down so that they don't have the responsibility
But
I love computer
I see nothing wrong with
It motivates me
It motivates my team
So sure
Puppet still hate sounds like
Pretty quickly you realize that you
Didn't want to like climb the corporate ladder it at that
That you just it just wasn't what you wanted for your life
I mean
I saw my life is
Being
Full of possibilities I certainly had the
Intellectual wherewithal to
Question whether or not
A refined life
Corporate America
What's going to make me happy
And I decided that it was not
And I went in to tell my boss
And he said well maybe we should get you a a psychologist to talk to before you take this
Position
So you usually laugh and you and Kate move to
Region
A nemesis like 6868 April of 68
The first your plan was to work with your dad in like a new business
That he had started
I work for
Couple of years with him and then what was he doing
She had been in the textile business in Massachusetts and
Like all of the businesses in Uxbridge Massachusetts they all failed
And so he had to reboot restart his life
He did it with
His new business which was pollution abatement for
Textiles Industries in Maine and he was inventing
Things that could do the job without nitrates
And phosphates which was a
A new ID
And what was it about
Is business that
I don't know
Interesting
Well I was
Doing this for me it was
It's about
Combining business
The
In the mid-sixties you didn't
Work for a business
And be concerned about the environment it was either or you work for a nonprofit on behalf of the environment
Are you working
I knew that you could integrate the two
And so what that that makes you start to think about
Your aunt like starting your own company and and
Whether you
You could do with Easter
Things to yes
And and as of course we're going to learn you went into the
Cleaning products
Business
As well as personal products
Like soaps and and shampoo is right
Yes
So I I was
Certainly familiar with
The
Nuts and Bolts
The chemistry of cleaning
So the idea of
Cleaning the body with soaps and so forth
With ingredients that were not harmful to the environment and I certainly had
My fathers
Example and the thing
About business that I love so much that it wasn't
Business that was
In itself
It was the agents that ran the business
The could be
Sinister
One just needed to use the tools of free enterprise in a way that was more ethically
Instruct
To society as well as to
All those that are taking the risk
I did use the money to
Even start
The company
Well I didn't
I asked a friend to put up
$5,000
He and his wife were involved in the creation of this
New alternative school in Kennebunk call the school around us
We became good friends
And I told them of my idea
He had some IBM stock and took it to the bank as collateral to
Loan me $5,000
And that's what
Company was
Started on and obviously that didn't last very long
He put another 2500 and then after that it was the second mortgage on the home and
Then the SBA Loans and so on and so forth
You know it's early years maybe it's just you and Kate like making this stuff making the soap and and the
The shampoos or did you like he's presently the higher
People to help you out
What Kate was actually very much involved in
Raising the three children that we had a
She was
Probably our best
Consumer Advocate within the system
The help guide my thinking on product design and packaging and so forth and she's an artist
So she helped
With the graphics on the ark
Otherwise
I hired a chemist
Who
For us he was brilliant
He helped us with product formulations that were
Authentically grounded in natural ingredients
We had a
Warehouse
In Kennebunk
We bought used stainless steel
Dairy equipment
Around the neighborhood
I knew where to get ahold of stainless steel equipment for
A hundred bucks here in a hundred bucks they are and
Then you get your your first filling machine and
Song you just go
So all this equipment was actually
Design for the dairy industry we were using some
Soap and shampoo
Yes
Where other
People making
This type of stuff in the mid-70s where there was a lot of competition with their natural up
Companies making
Soaps and shampoos and toupee
Not really we did have
Pioneer named dr. Bronner from Chicago
Was making his peppermint oil soap
But other than that there was a shampoo made a call or Jean shampoo on Long Island
But after that no
If we were the first person to put a toothpaste together
A deodorant together a mouthwash
All of that was
We were first time
Providers of
What was what was in
In the toothpaste what was the formula
Rowlett
But of course
Wonderful question is God
The calcium carbonate
What is a natural
Mineral that is a mild abrasive to do the cleaning of the teeth leave got to
A humectant is glycerin that is a byproduct of a natural soap making process
But I had a chemist
That helped me with all that I could only talk
About the ideal I would give him my sense of the ideal and he would try to turn the
Not ideal into a
And efficacious
Formula
It seems like when you launch the toothpaste in the mid-70s that's really when the company
Started to take off were you surprised it was toothpaste for did you anticipate that happening
I had a hunch that it would be successful because there was no natural toothpaste people didn't know what or not
Toothpaste was
And I felt that the motivation for my
Customer
Was to avoid a tattoo
But
Yes the Turning Point came
Within launch of the tooth
Did anybody say to you
Thinking making toothpaste everyone uses Colgate and Crest like
Why are you even wasting your time
We have plenty of people
Advising me that it was a crazy idea to compete with Procter & Gamble and coffee
Yeah but I mean lately have point right of me why would you even
Get into a market that was
Totally dominated by
Well I think that comes
Purely and simply down to who you're serving and in our case we
I knew very well that we were serving a
Consumer that was
Discerning about what they would put
In their bodies and why
They wanted facts
Knowledge
We thought well why not service
This is a great idea
The more people
Learned
About what was in their shampoo or their soap for the toothpaste
They would question
Ralph Nader
In the mid-70s
Was successful in
Facilitating
Legislation that
Required that ingredients in personal care products had to be on the label once that happened
That disclosure
And transparency
Raise Lots
2 questions in people's minds for the first time
Cuz it's all these things they they couldn't pronounce on the lake
Couldn't pronounce
And so are our package are toothpaste box
Like any toothpaste box has four sides and one side was committed to the brand
Name and the other three sides were committed to information
And we did have a moment of courage in all of this wind
The federal government said
That any kind of fluoride toothpaste would have to
I'll be registered as having tested off successfully forever
Sea and safety on rats and we so we don't subject animals to
Studies
Reviews human trials and I said well the protocol is
Is rat studies
And by testing on rats is only taking the rats and brushing their teeth
Is anyone just have a nice shiny tea
Lyca text
Quite cruel
Yeah I mean you've got to do is cruel
Does this know pretty well
And so we refused
We went to Washington and
Met with the FDA and said we've got human trials and they
Eventually a seated and then we went on to get the American Dental Association seal of acceptance
As well
So we we kept to our values and
The change happened after that all the other companies
Stop testing on animals
We had a big influence
What was the the culture of
Times like these
Because you know
We know that Ben and Jerry
Apologetically liberal place
And very sore
Hippies and
What was the culture like
It was it was it similar to those other companies
I don't think so I think we were
More straitlaced and the reason I say that is I wasn't an activist I wasn't a hippie
I wanted to appeal
On the merits of the product
Assume at the same time as the beginning
The people buying your toothpaste in Ann Arbor Michigan or San Francisco or not
Organelle
Country Club Republicans
The Disney Store
Countercultural
People buying
At least the beginning
Well that's absolutely true and and mind you
We were countercultural to we just didn't look the part and play the part
I don't think
You would have found me in Berkeley you wouldn't have found me in Cambridge
Demonstrating
But I had the same indignation deep down inside about the way the country was being run
I just had a different way of handling it
Did you did you have
Massive Ambitions your company by the time you reach profitability in the mid-70s
Launch of toothpaste
Were you thinking yourself
Discovery Cube
This is going to be
Massive
And that's that's what I want
No I didn't think that I don't think I had the self-confidence
To think that
I think
My
Was to bring it to a certain sales level and to stay within the natural food community
Because within the
The natural food store Community or distribution system
We were the Procter & Gamble of that class
Trade
Winnetka
Particular Opera
Opportunities started to wane
In terms of growth rate
Then we looked at the traditional
Supermarkets in chain drug stores
What's the question what would
It'd be like
For us to be on those shelves
How to expand into the traditional Market
Time you did not mean
You study English
Go to business school and I gather it
In the early eighties
You brought on a bunch of
From Harvard
NBA's
And other people with the
The credentials
Bring them in to execute that strategy to two
Rotom's Main
You said into
You have to bring into more traditional Market
Totally
I had a fellow join the company as a director named John Rockwell
Who from Booz Allen in New York
Became a great mentor to me
And I remember his saying we've got to help
Transition this company from
Serving
The health committed
2 expanding it
To the people that are Health concern
So if we were going to go into
Supermarkets in drugstores
That was going to be a different
Business proposition
We brought on people from Bruce Allen Hamilton McKinsey & Company
And so from 1981 to 1986 we were X
Shooting a strategic
Plan that
Had a lot
To do with
Changing your message so that you could
Appealed
New consumer
Finding the right
People
Help on the team to build the team
In our case we needed to
Increase our prices
Figure out ways to make the product
More efficient
I guess and I guess the strategy was working because
It was in the early eighties word when you guys really started to explode and growth like
25%
Year over year
And then in 1986
You have this kind of
Personal
Prices
I guess you should have
Something is going on and you just
Feel like
There's an emptiness what
What was that about what's going on
The crisis was that we had achieved
Our
Strategic benchmarks
And I was feeling quite empty because we hadn't created a new product
4 years
And I said I just don't
Feel the meaning
Of this Enterprise in just improving the business in terms of size and profit
Ability
We were not
Creating
New products
And making a difference in areas that I thought
You should because we had become overcome with the numbers
Leadership had become
You know the NBA
It sounds to me like you will just
You weren't
In just a moment
Everyone Chapel found answers to his crisis in a place
You probably wouldn't expect
Gyros near listening to how I built this
PR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open up free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your biz
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from and
NPR I'm guy Raz
Chapel is the CEO of a
Very successful company
Tom's of Maine is hitting double-digit growth and all of its
Strategic goals
Leprechaun
He was feeling like
He had strayed from why he founded the company in the first place
And he was looking for the kind of answers
You don't find it
Harvard Business School
So instead
Emerald part-time
At Harvard Divinity School
I got up at four 4:30 in the morning to study
I work very hard it was extremely difficult
Educational
Experience with some motivating because I was learning
Things from
Philosophers like Martin buber
Who had some fantastic things to offer in his book
I am down
I would say to myself wow
Why don't more people know this stuff this is important
It didn't it wasn't just
Martin buber it was Jonathan Edwards
The whole bunch of 19th 20th century philosophers
This is like super admirable a question about eccentric
You just save your fears your staff like
I'm going to Harvard Divinity School and everyone was like
That's right
Obviously the benefit of
Having your own company in the company
An attitude that
Experian start to change. What you operate
Is the owner and CEO of a
Rodger company
Well it would change
My life first
Bald because I was getting answers to questions
In the readings
East philosophers that
Weir solutions for me
It gave me
A spiritual
Orientation
And
I actually began to see a new reality
There is a
Force of goodness
That is available to
Anyone of us
Call it what
Ever you want to call it
Force of goodness
Becomes a medium by which we begin to do work differ
Play together one of respect and mutuality collaboratively
Towards ends that have more constructive value
Then just for the sake
Of
Piling up a lot of profit
I think Harvard Divinity School gave me the
Knowledge
I was able to return to
Tom's of Maine on a full-time basis and say
Here are the things that we're going to do now that are in the name of
Goodness and performance
So it is an example of a mean you push this idea of of 5
Percent of your time for
Who work for the company
Take 5%
Have your time and just
Do some charity work
Yeah but we would organize that charity work
Or they would elect to do what they wanted to do in the community that might be
Literacy work
It could be helping on the Appalachian Trail
It was generally
Community-based environmental based
Needs then they loved it I mean they would come back to work
Excited about what we've been able to do for their community
I guess it was one of the
Big crisis
Tom's of Maine happened
In 92 with the
Wizard
It it it took you like a few years to get back
Profitability app
That what what happened what was the prices
The crisis is we were
While trying to
Find a
Source of
Humectant
And because we were all about natural and
Renewable materials
We did not want to use petroleum-based ingredients
So
We thought that we had found a substitute in
Coconut derived glycerin
And we reformulated the deodorant using
That as the human
Rather than
Petroleum-derived
And we found after getting it into the stores that we hadn't really thought this through care
Carefully enough
It wasn't an effective
Deodorant
What was the problem
Didn't smell good or that
Last long enough for me
It did not last
It was clear that we had made a mistake we had a responsibility to call that product back
And to figure out what to do in the meantime so
We did a product recall
What what what percentage of your business did the owner account for
22%
Enormous amount of product that you you couldn't sell
$450,000 worth
Yes it is a company
It created a loss for that operating year and we are able to recover the next year
But certainly I don't mean to suggest
That it wasn't disruptive it was extremely disruptive and difficult but we weathered through it
Would I have been fired in another setting I don't know
Probably
Did you fire anybody
Did somebody take take the hit for that
No I I think I took the hit for that
No we didn't fire anybody
Okay let's let's fast forward a few years
Your 62
You and Kate have
Bill Tom's of Maine
From nothing
Well you're the boss
And then you
Sold almost
All of the company
Colgate
Reporter for about hundred million.
And I guess you know what
I would expect that you would retire and just kind of like
Enjoy life
Your grandkids
Is that
Is that what you wanted to do
Well I've spent time
Thinking about what I was going to do with the next part of my life and one of my mentors in New York
Tefillin and Sean Whitehead
He said you're young man you have plenty of time
This is not the time for you to retire
I didn't feel like
Retiring
I felt I had a lot of energy I had a lot
Desire to do something and I wanted to once again
Create impact
Yeah but I also understood that the reason I was successful at Tom's of Maine is because I took market share away
Colgate
Procter & Gamble and unit
So when you can
Take market share away from the kamado
Buy an alternative approach
Struvite product development of that product and service
That's what I'm good at
Okcu
SAU
You wound up taking those those ideas in the
Scales and
And turning into another business
That's right exactly
I thought about it a business that could once again
Benefit from
A change in the way it operated
Operating with the principles of sustainability which have been so important to me at Tom's of Maine
And that's what I decided to do in the textile and the Garment industry because it is the second largest
Polluter on this Earth
Exploits
Sewing and seamstresses around the world
So we set out to figure out
What we could do
Obey an american-based a product I equal
So we make
Coats we make
Shirts we make
Pants
Polo shirts everything
We should declare for this company called Ramblers way
Correct
It is an exciting
Exciting
How important is it
For you that
This company
Becomes profitable like Tom's of Maine how important is it
Set for you
That this company really does
Takeaway Market Remington and how hungry are you and you've proven yourself you started the company you made lots of money everybody
You know Tom's of Maine
You have nothing to prove in the business world
How hungry are you what's the answer
For me
It's important to demonstrate that this is a different business model
In which you are using boobers concept
Is that the mind is twofold
That you can on the one hand
Consider the goodness
Inherent worthiness of something
And on the other hand
The utility
And as long as greed and domination what are the motivations and that's where we got into our trouble
That's my life
Legacy
That this is something that needs to be taken up by Business Schools and larger corporations
Understand
That there are vulnerable as long as they operate with a
Sole principle of maximizing profitability
If rainbows whenever
No that's not fine
I'm a businessman
How to be a businessman profitability is
Part of the
Responsibility
To yourself and to others
I'm curious how did you how are you able to
To sort of
Reconcile your
Deep philosophical
Connection to your face and then
Easier spend studying
Philosophy and really thinking about the world a different way
With the fact that
That you were actually at least on paper
The money was becoming
A part of your life
Well I never
Considered myself becoming rich
Let me explain that I read a book called The Gift
And it's really about
How to use money
And the purpose of money is to keep it in circulation
Not to Stow it away
And so we certainly traveled
And we were able to buy properties that we otherwise would not have
But aside from
That
I needed to find something constructive
To do and to use my money
Listen to I asked everybody to come to the show
When can you look back at Tom's of Maine and
Your
Career & Ramblers way in Antioch
What happened to you is be
Because of
Your business Acumen and your intelligence and how much it was
Was it because
Well I think
Having forces come together
In a Serendipity way
Is indeed an important part of
The process
Buttom
I think it's both you can't you can't do it without skill
But I do think you
For me because I live in the spiritual world it's not luck
Kids
The work of of Grace
Paying attention to what I'm doing
Nourishing
Do you get any residuals from that Norman Rockwell painting in them
I got a call from the family
Though this was probably 10 years ago saying that the painting had been in the
They're home in Milan for years
Children inheriting at the decided to put it on the market
Sotheby's
So they said it's been valued at $750,000 and they wanted me to have the first chance to buy
You did right because no problem I went home and told Kate and she said well
We have to give it to a museum we wouldn't want that in the house
So I'm afraid I if I had to pass off
Tom Chappell
Founder of Toms
The clothing company
Ramblers way
And by the way you can see that painting featuring The 10-year old Tom is a redheaded choirboy
Check it out
On our Facebook page
Instagram because in just a moment we're going to
I hear from you about the
Things your building
Thanks to one of our sponsors
TD Ameritrade
TD Ameritrade is always ready to listen and have a
Conversation about your goals
Complimentary goal planning session
Discuss your financial
Future
Tdameritrade.com
Slash pine
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you
You built that
And say we have an update for you
When we first met Paul kaster a year ago
He was a high school senior
Launching a
A business that
It makes
Wooden bow ties which car
Kind of a thing
The wooden bow tie is just like a pre-tied fabric bow tie
Except for what is made out of wood
It's a common gift if you're woodworker and you're a preppy guy in high
But as a woodworker I kind of saw all the flaws in the design
Topol decided you know I can make a better wooden bow tie one that actually looks
Less flat and more like real fabric
Soapy set up a shop in his basement at almond
And he started selling the ties on Etsy
The greatest compliment that I ever get is
I didn't know that was a wooden bow tie
And I got that one
Paul has an entire line of bow ties
How to get wood from all over the world
Maple
Cherry
Walnut
Co-op
Cocobolo
Zebra wood
What is 1
Infosys
Business was
Pretty good email about 20 thousand bucks
Action profit
Annie's doing about the same amount
This year
We're still selling online all over the world and actually it's run out of my mom's sewing room
Break so Paul has his mom fulfilling all the orders out of their home in Kansas City because
He isn't even there anymore he's in California as a freshman in college
A few months ago he actually started a spin-off business
I was at USC for orientation
And I met a guy in Ostrander shipcenter here and he is an idea machine
And so he came to me and you like Paul
I have like a thousand other things
Testing you can make bow ties out of
And one of the things
This guy talked about was carbon fiber
That's Tuff
Lightweight
Woven material that they use in things like race cars and Rockets
He said
There's this company that takes
The carbon fiber from the aerospace companies here in California
Andre makes it into carbon fiber skateboards
And he said I should link you up and you guys should make a Carbon Fiber bow tie
DePaul went to check it out and it was also a startup run as it happens
Buy a recent us CLI
The two of them working on a prototype and why
Carbon fiber boat I was born the wooden bow ties are very classic look
And the Carbon Fiber bow ties are space-age look
And so I think there's a certain
Wonder
In getting something that you can wear made of the same material that these incredible Rockets are made out of
Calling his new bowtie brand
Carbon cravat
Bishop last month you raised $8,000 on Kickstarter and has about 200 bowties ready to go for
Christmas
And he is of course doing a lot of this
Erebus dorm room it was actually I was up last night at 1 a.m. and my room is like toilet you need to go to sleep or start setting for 5
And I was like no I'm in the middle of design the website still
Spell Caster who has
Bow tie brands
Carbon cravat
Crooked Branch
Studio
You can learn more about Paul's bow ties on her Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to Bill
Mpr.org and thanks for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or he
Your previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcasts or however you get your podcast
You can also brightest that's HIV tea at npr.org could tweet us at how I built this
Shows produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by run team Arab Louie thanks also to leave a grant
Santa's meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Diana Mystic on Gyros
And you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com