Support for this in
NPR Podcast
In the following message come from VSP individual vision
Entrepreneurs innovators and creators
Stop overpaying for eye exam
Sam's and Quality Glass
You can buy vision coverage on your own
Learn more at need VSP coverage.
Unravelled biggest contract
We work we are banking on that would just raise a bunch of money about 5 million dollars which for us with a lot of money so when Apple pay
Basically said they wanted to pull the plug pulled the rug out from under arrest that was a scary time
Time do you think the company was going to collapse
It was really possible
From NPR how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealists
And the stories behind the movements they go
I'm guy Raz and email and the internet
A normal part of American life and went on to forge the biggest corporate merger
In US history
If you happen to be over the age of say
There is a good chance
First time you ever use email
What is on a computer with an AOL account
Because in the 1990s
It will make sure of that by mailing
Free CD-ROMs almost every household in the US
You pop it into your computer and within minutes you could magically type a message to someone else who had something called
Email account
And I promise you if you do not know what I'm talking about
It was magical it was a miracle
In this revolution in human communication was
Pushed by companies that are mostly forgotten that
CompuServe Prodigy EarthLink Delphi and of course
AOL
And out of all of them
AOL prevailed
In part because the company was smart
And in part as you will hear
It was like
Steve case was as Relentless as he was ambitious
In the way he did it
Well
Like many entrepreneurs
Steve what the Corporal route out of college
And in the early 1980s
He landed a job doing product development
For Pizza Hut
But at night
He would
Anchor with his computer
We went to the process of
Trying to plug it into
Alamodome and the others back.
It seems silly now but the
Not many people had PCS and that ass was right people at
PCS didn't have the ability
Connector piece
To go to the
Peripheral section
Store to buy some
They call the modem
I forgot to plug that in on the phone
Receiver on it right this way Farm receiver and then youku
Black girl hairline
It was you to set of a peripheral non-essential part of computer
And that was most
Interesting to me so what I'd
Computer I didn't eat
They wanted to get it
I could find that very frustrating process
It was kind of expensive to get online but $10 an hour
There wasn't much
Content online
People online
It was really early days but still there's something about that
I found Magic
It was that the fact that you could be anywhere
I happen to be at a time in Wichita Kansas
And you're connected people and ideas all over the world
And that is
You could just take the leap of faith that someday everybody
B connected
Be part of
Everyday life
Then I really believe that would be
Transformative
Indeed have the
The potential be as transformative as
Things like that
The telephone
Connecting on this
Rudimentary modem
You thought this is going to be transformative
I didn't know whether I'd be part of it and know how to get into it
Flowers near the idea of the intern
So what point will
Are you able to leave Pizza Hut and then
Don't completely different career path
Well when I was at P&G and then at peace I was still feeling a lot of 10
What was happening
Try to learn more about what's happening started looking something business on the side Consulting with technology company
Nice trying to
The learn from it and my brother was an investment banker in San Francisco
One day
Send me a business plan of a company that they were thinking of invest
And their Venture Capital just like what do you think
And so they did decide to
And that's why I ended up starting a consult with that company
Move to DC to join them
The summer of 1983
How do you spell control video Corporation I had a product called game live
To the timer
Lights for video
Back that most people don't have PCS a lot of people had Atari game machine
Sprite and Sergey Moana login
Turn your game machine into a
Interactive terminal that the download games in overtime iPod
Odoo email
Other things to that terminal
A market
There was a tiny market and it actually turned out to be an idea that will I thought made
Samsung Market
Agree weather
Are they launch the product in the fall of 1983
They said we failed
And his company was in free fall
This is my first
Experience on the alsea months after I was there as kind of on teetering on Banker
The layoff 7080
80% of a
Employees and so
It's only became a struct
So what happened to your job
Well if they kept me
I'm parked because I got a seven or eight people in the marketing department and I think I was the only one who survived and part it was because I was paid
At least I think I met
Anti work
The Madonna Inn
Trying to figure out some way to
Reposition it.
Some Partnerships
But eventually we decided to start over again
And two other people that were there the time
Jim kimsey young Mark Sarah
When I ended up in 1985
Starting essentially what became America online
At the time
Inabilities if you wanted to get online
What were your apps
Basically had to buy PC I didn't figure out a way to buy an integrative
Then call them out on me then
Subscribe to weather National onlineservices who were the big players
Big boy we started work CompuServe
The Source but then neither were
Protectli baguette
The time
There was some other Adventures that were coming in
Into fruition there's one of typical Prodigy that IBM and Sears
Royal CBS
Committed by billion dollars to lunch
Prodigy
Some people were piloting things trying things
But about 3% of
America was online
An average of 1 hour a week
The markets
How did you even
Go get the money
For this new Venture because I mean
Kiss you are right you and your partners
Failed
Will you your last business fail so how did you even find new investor
It was a struggle and in some of the investors from the previous company we're going to invest in a new company over in some Warren and we also
Sorry about the tracks
$1000000
Did you get a decent share of that
Because it was there
Restart in some of the investors lost their money on
Previous company Scentsy Madison
It started with zero
And investors with a hunter
Percent that you have no choice
That's why I said we wanted to continue going wait we had this
Ideal we wanted supper
For sale at the background
1985 is hard to raise
Venture capital in ESO
But I'm the only path to essentially have a new start a fresh start
Was to agree to a deal word what investors
On the company on the entrepreneurial team overtime
Got to earn their way into a part of the cup
So let me know if that time
In 1985 did
Did you just think yourself well you know
This internet thing is going to be so huge
I'll make money off of it doesn't really matter
How we structure
It's a mix I actually I did believe the
Haven't seen the idea of the internet
Computer companies
Belt on the back of the
The internet
But I was driven as I think a lot of entrepreneurs are not just by the
Economic rewards side of but really the idea that you could
Change the world
That's why I wanted to figure out some way to
Take this idea that I was so fascinated with an acre
Get more mainstream sorry Franklin matter less you know what I was paid which wasn't much how much stock I got
Got that much
My grand scheme of things
I want to pursue this idea this
This passion is dream
And what were you going to do with your product
Realize that this was still the early days of person
Computers but there were different manufacturers offering
Different kinds of
Computers and we decide what side of trying to do it on our own why don't we create a sense of custom
Private label
Online services
With each of those company
So our deals with all these companies
The Commodore
Or apple or IBM which will create the service
You Market your bundle are software with your modems or
With your computers are
Whatever you choose to do
Animal simply show the Revenant
And so
Regret something called
Qlink for Commodore we create something
AC wiring for Radio Shack
I created something
Call Promenade Friday and we pray something called apple and for Apple
If I bought like a Radio Shack computer
In 1984 it would come with it
It's like own Radio Shack online service but big your company was the one that was designing that service
Crack
What could you do with it
I do a lot of things maybe basic the core was allow you to download software because
The time that was
Nothing but he also could do things like
Emailing
Participate in message boards and
We created chat rooms otherwise we always believed that the
The killer app of the internet
SoundCloud be content
Media companies some firewood e-commerce
Piccoli the retail companies
How we thought content
Commerce would be important but the
Community
The most important so we always focused on people interacting with each other even to this day with social media Facebook and
Twitter and Snapchat essentially that idea of
Community
Hair continues to carry forward
She mentioned that one of your customers
First was Applewood
Cupcake companies well-established
So I mean
How did you even get them to partner with he was it was that easy
I know it's hard it was it was they were there skeptical and then they weren't quite sure what part of the company even to deal with
I ended up moving to
The San Francisco area
And every day for six months showed up with her off
Talk to me I'd like the marketing people talk to the software people talk to the customer service
Were the days were they said
Can you please like
Papa Gino's
Just got to keep keep going
I want to get that deal and I figured somebody
Somewhere in apple was
I just need to find a
Steve Jobs was not there
Stop. He's been kicked out.
Just before that
And so on
We work with different people
Within the company but he was
He was not there doing that. Cuz if he was there I can't imagine he would have
You're probably right because he was
You're so careful about
Controlling
It was a Friday
The first time Apple license their brand to another company
I don't need not long afterwards
In the first year of launching the Apple
Appalachian decided they didn't like the idea
I wish they had license
I'm sorry
We had a little bit of a standoff and So eventually had to rename the the service they
They paid us if you $9 to kind of go away quietly
Yeah that's when we hang out every name it's we called America online
So when that deal unravel them I'm assuming that was the biggest contract
Yeah we were we were we were banking on that we just raised a bunch of money about 5 million dollars worth
French fries with a lot of money
On the idea of
Expanding this Apple deal so when Apple basically said they wanted to
Pull the plug pull the rug out from under us
That was
Say
Scary time
Do you think the company was going to collapse
It was certainly a possibility that
That is there a lot of our investors and
Who believed that
It was going to be hard to recover from the
Slauson the idea of essentially
Moving away from
Partnering
Instead watch her own brand America online with their own new marketing
We was scary sounds like it was
Probably also
Pretty lonely time right because you were just
Likely waiting for this thing to take off
Yeah I was lonely and maybe even go to Industry conference remember one in the
LPC forum
Liberty Thrift wanted people there in to be one or two
Focused on the internet most
Pakistan
Semiconductor
Airsoft
Something else in
So we were viewed as head of this
Friends Evo hobbyist
Things most people to never believe what about the
I still believe
T-case in just a minute how Steve and America Online created one of the most
Iconic sounds of the 1990s
You've Got Mail
I got rosney listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Under state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
Play and it gs.com podcast
Support also comes from wix.com
A web platform for creating your own professional website
With WIC
Whether it's your first time
Creating a website
Or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning template
Or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology
And Powerful web features
Join Over 125 million people already using Wix to create their own website
Gota wilx.com to create yours today
So what will you create
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Winston case
Launched America online in the mid-1980s
The internet as we know it did not yet exist
AOL was basically a service that lets
Subscribers logon use chat rooms in email but you couldn't visit websites that were outside of the AOL
Well Service
Actually until 1991 it was illegal for most people to connect to the internet
At the time it was
A network of computers used by research universities and the Department of Defense
Explain how AOL then
Really started to
Takeoff
AOL
You said Congress passes legislation that allowed the internet
Become commercialized
Obviously was a huge
Franklin
And was that it was it was it was as well as buy them and convince PC manufacturers
How to build a standard part of a computer and not a peripheral
World Wide Web was also Young
Greater than that
93 ish time frame
It's all these things really kind of came together they when we went public
Tokyo public in 1992
The first internet come
Go public
And we have less than 200000
Been at it for 7
The first decade was slow and
Hard and two steps forward one step
Back
It's the second deck
Yeah that way things really
Kicked in and thankfully we did stick
But but you know it's early days
When you are still pretty young guy where you were you running the company
Overtime at a time when we started I was I think 25
Like that I was kind of young kid
I went to the crazy marketing partnership ideas
But over time I got more responsibility to come you're more rolls
I think it was in 1991 I was
Was named CEO of
The company
Sadly
For me one
We decided 1992
Publix
The board decided I was too young to be
I didn't want you to be the face of the company
But back down the idea of the internet was sort of foreign and there were not XXX
You're all the CEOs you taking companies public
How did you feel about being demoted
Lost I was
Website
I didn't think
Was fair
But same time I care about the company in
Decided to weather that storm and and I did understand it one level
Then play green with it but it understand those logic that in
Institutional investors
We didn't understand what the internet was and didn't none
Understand why whatever my mom too much
It was an even harder if it was some
I'm catching who was untested and have
Significant
Experience when you did eventually
Can formally leave the company
What what kind of leader were you what
What did you think you're
Either your role was
I think it evolved
They aren't that became much more of a force in the mid-to-late 90s
That's just the
Spokesman for a while but also for
For the internet
Sorry even when I was cui
Lisa Jacqueline just
Office of the mayor of the
Community monthly letters to R
Members talking about what's happening and what are strategies I wanted them all to
I feel like they were part of this
Efforts are really was for the
Cheerleader
Rallier
Roll
Even though 20 years ago
Give us a sense of what kind of environment you are pretty in
This is like the early 90s
How do you sell this idea
The customers how do you
Describe what
The internet is
What was challenging but it went back to trying to figure out ways to partner so even though it wasn't PC manufacturers
We partner with the New York Times
Time Magazine into what to offer their Publications about their publication also since we have the credibility there now
Names associated with AOL you could get
Headlines and encyclopedia
We partner with
Lots of companies that provided some of the services
Some of the
Contact that would made it more interesting but also made it more credible
I think anybody who's over the age of like a 35
Probably remembers having an AOL account write like
Yule log on and you hear welcome
You got mail
How did that come about
The voices when we wear them in that early 90s were trying to figure out a way to make the internet more accessible
Walmart or something
People can relate to
I put a friendly face on it
One way to make it seem more friendly more human was actually have a person welcoming into the service
And so I was talking about that one day with her
Customer service department
A woman they are basically so what my husband does voice-over kind of think so
Wake me up in
Take some
Messages inside of me I got my old pen down a Post-It note and bunch
Different things like
You've Got Mail on
And I guy Elwood Edwards
Recorded them that night and
Brought in the next day or two
Cassette tape and it sounds pretty good let's stick it on the software
And then became one of the most recognizable
Voices of
That generation
Do you remember the moment when you realize
That this was going to be a
A huge like consumer
Matches for 3% of Americans
For most people
I was going to be huge
Well let's be honest
The moment I thought that was
1980 when I first started focusing
In my heart of hearts believe that the
State where it became
Clear that was actually happening I wasn't
Set up a crazy life dream
I agree year was 1996
And we move to unlimited pricing and we had
Problem or system extras down for 24 hours number to get login
And it was a national
New story led the network TV news was the lead article most newspapers
Tell me the factory down for 24 hours with a national crisis that's when I knew that
His idea of the internet had arrived it was frustrating because obviously
We're down a lot of people counting on us and we let them down
Palazzo was just a
A sign that this
This really was
Becoming real on this
No idea the internet was becoming part of everyday life in a gun from something
We got started 95 and nobody knew about or cared about
It's hardly something that people needed and couldn't live without
I guess once you really started
Take off in the mid-90s
Microsoft says we want to get into this business
We want to have our own
Portal to the end
Hillgate summons you to Seattle to meet with MN
And what makes makes an offer to buy you guys out
They basically said they decided to
Internet world is online world was now as 42
Check priority for them they're going to
I take it very seriously they're planning to create their own service
They're planning to bundle it with
Every copy Windows
But they respected what we are doing in it
If we had a
Willingness to sell a company to them then instead of building their own thing that they would
You'll be happy
UND prefer
Kind of gone with us
And so
Little scary because
Senor we knew the threat of Microsoft was pretty
Yes there is some
Some of our investors some of the board members that feel like
We should quit while we're ahead that maybe we can't
Compete in this new era with Mike
Microsoft
Came down to a close
Both but eventually
The board decided not to sell the Microsoft
Microsoft didn't fact launch their own
Are you worried that they were going to crash
Cuz I had a lot more money than that
Take me to Power of
Distribution
The fact essentially every
Computer
Shipped with their Windows software and they were saying they're going to include in every copy of that
Access to their service for every computer
When you first turn it on when automatically your basically be going to micro
Microsoft
How did you
How did you combat
I thought how did you fight against
What did you do
First of all we tried to Rally the team to really focus on what made us unique what made us different
And we actually the fact that we knew Microsoft was coming into the brownie mix
Company and the partner is over
Bad Company
Add to be much more ambitious
Turn to what we were trying to do
So that means we can today.
Build a larger audience create more content
Cancel that actually
Ended up pushing us to do better than we likely would have done without the
Redis Microsoft
Looming over
I know that's a relief
Much different back then did you
Cinco Gates
So just being
Super aggressive and mean
It was a personal for you
I'm not sure if personal am I understood what the why they were doing what they're doing and
I think they understood why we were doing what we were
We're doing say it was
Something that we wanted to Prevail we wanted to
Yeah went in and I remember even one
Cover story of
Fortune Magazine
And in the mid
Late 90s
Basically had no Bill Gates on the cover of the magazine
Who's going to win the battle for the internet
Crossy answer was none of the above
Towards the end of the 90s
2 Chainz real
Basically
Time Warner
Why did you do that
I mix
First of all from US Financial
Standpoint
We had a pretty good run it was
What's the best
Performing stock
Kodak getting together Peak 150 billion dollars so it really had been wrong with percentage of of the
Percent
Of all internet traffic went through AOL
We were the leader of the pack of Italy the packing was called the narrow band world
Dial up modem
We didn't have a clear path of broadband which was
Is controlled by the cable companies
We tried to
Figure out ways to get into that way was
Looking like a struggle you were looking ahead and you knew you were
Going to run into
Problems if you did nothing
We knew it would be more difficult to maintain a lead and
Broadband world
So we need to figure out some way to do that one of things that was attractive to us about a merger with Time Warner particular it was they had
The largest cable network
And so
The fact that they had that Broadband footprint was really a key driver for as well so it was partly and financial we were
One from our company when we did the murder that was 5 billion of Revenue about 1 billion of prophets
Are the combined company at 40 billion of Revenue $10 and a profit
So from a financial diverse
Okay standpoint make sense as well
As you know it
It's like a classic
Case study
Express
You were blamed for a lot of it you know this you read all the
If it didn't buy the ticket to you
Sure sure
They always believe still believe the idea of the merger
Makes sense I think it really goes to execution
Hickory Run PA
People and culture
Yacht Rock
And I was very frustrated
The company wasn't able to
Achieve the kind of
Vision that I throw I thought was possible that you couldn't convince people of what you want to do or that
You just saw the world in different ways. It was the other Market itself from right after we did the merger
Stock market generally you wanted to
Decline internet sector wanted
Kind of a free-fall so that was
Unhelpful timing also is part of the
Marketing at the merger. I stepped aside as
COC
Didn't have Direct Control of any of this
AOL I was
Forcing the board itself
Summit was the
Fights within the company Time Warner historically that organizes
Water independent company so
Party idea to merge
Restaurant in the marina great away but that really never
Never happen so is a mix of different factors but at the end of the day really was
It's about execution in turkey license
They really does come down to people
How do you take these ideas and make them real in Spanish
People in it
ATMs
Were you just
Miserable doing that job
Did you just hate doing that
I went Miserables made it. Yeah I was frustrated
It was harder than
After
Basically a decade of being
Leading the charge being on the field
It was hard to be a kind of
Skybox Young
Not really having that
Day-to-day interaction
And obviously you got
Strategic differences that I had with
Others on the board and
When you left a Time Warner AOL
What did you think I mean
You were looking for something new to do did you know what you wanted
Not specifically but I knew I wanted to do something that was moron
I love the whole 20 year journey I had with AOL
But I realize that now.
The first 10 years even though it was harder and more frustrating and
Scarier and then
Lonelier
That part of it I really enjoyed
That's all that I wanted
Go back to the garage
Got roll my sleeves and
And focus on new things the same time I decided
Rapid start another company
I wanted to figure out a way to partner with
Elementor invest in
Entrepreneurs in a variety different
Sectors and that's really what I've been doing
For the past 15 years
What do you think is the most
Important
Quality characteristics that you've
So you either have or you've developed over time
That's allowed you to
B success
I think it's a mix
Let's kill some of it is
Go back to the idea that Vision side of it and
Being pretty good at seeing around corners pretty good at the pattern recognition getting a sense of what might be happening
Headache perseverance I think being willing to take a long-term view is
Discuss the
Fable Journey was a
Decade in the making overnights
Sensation and so recognizing the
Revolution sometimes happen in evolutionary ways you going to have to take a long-term View and in
Indy study there
Find the other is a respect for the role of government
The Roller Palace
Have an appreciation
Developed over the
Of that role probably because the internet wouldn't exist without the
How was the government 50 years ago that funded DARPA that created the internet it was a government
Judicial system that broke up the phone company and my bell what's on least competition and lowered prices in Telugu
Communication with the government
And commercializing it with the Telecom xideis understanding
The role of policy
Trying to figure out ways to innovate
These are going to be
UTEP challenge
Just to take on
Are earlier
TV talk about
Like being a cheerleader
Write like how important do you think it is for the CEO or the door behind the company
To be the head cheerleader
Did you think that
Social or
Or is it a little overrated
People have to believe in the mission
Don't have to believe it's
Set of a battle worth
Worth fighting a mountain
Worth climbing
The most entrepreneurial Journeys are
Circuitous
Send an email two steps forward one step back
I'm going to be sometime scary and so just
Reminding people why this
And why it's important to not just focus on the vision but also the ex
Execution priorities and things like that I think that is part of the
Journey if you're really trying to change the world really trying to disrupt important aspects of Our Lives
Steve case founder of America online
2005 he moved on to found a venture capital company in Washington DC is called Revolution
During the Obama Administration Steve was a member of the president's Council on jobs
Competitiveness and that was the first time he met Barack Obama
Steve and President Obama actually went to the same high school together
In Hawaii
He was there at the same time but no I was a senior when he was
I did Joker before he made his run
The presidency
The best noun
Overshadowed
That was a goner.
And stick around in just a moment
Going to hear from you about
Your building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Green Mountain Coffee
Green Mountain Coffee is passionate about making a smoother 2
Tin Cup
Roast
At least until they're sure every cup is
Is perfectly balanced
And now
Get $4 off when you buy
Two boxes of most Green Mountain Coffee K-Cup pods
Keurig.com
Wecode NPR
GMC
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I know for how you built that we know from reading all your stories and emails at an idea
For a business can come from just about anywhere
Infer Christina Kazakh
About us
Basic As It Gets
Walking around Providence
Hi I just kept seeing sticks everywhere
Sticks like to see lying around in the grass
On the floor kids are playing with sticks
I love building a forest
The cat and all my other friends left building forts
Tell by the way this was all going through
Christina's mind
About four years ago when she was at design school in Providence
And for her final project she was thinking
Maybe I'll make a new toy
And that's when I realized I need to find a way to get kids outside today is kids away from the screen boys
From Battery toys
The outside of engage
What kid doesn't want to be pried away from her iPad
PlayStation 2
Build a teepee made of sticks in the backyard
A challenge admittedly but Christina started tinkering with an idea
The help kids
Connect sticks
Into shape
And I started
Working with
Existing connectors and like rubber bands and zip ties
Understand how gay how do you tie a knot how do you secure something
Actually she designed these stretchy connectors made of silicone
She called them sticklets
They're almost like cookie cut out shapes
And they have two to four holes in the shapes
And all the hoes at various sizes and you can use them with little Twigs that you find or who
Huge branches that you find and you might be thinking why do I need silicone connectors to
Build a Ford I mean I could just use rope to tie sticks together right
What Christina says sticklets are alive
Easier to use especially the younger kid
They love that they're stretchy and so pliable
The ring people over and say look what I built
Like look this is the raccoons chimney and he's climbing up in this goes down we got out
Mystic anyways after Christina made a demo of her cichlids for that project at design school
People would ask her
Where can I get them
So she started to sell them for real and eventually
To sell them in toy stores and then online
But some of our toughest customers
For the parents occasionally parents will contact me and be like we'll wait don't have like step-by-step instructions
Like how do we do this I don't get it
This is the whole point of cichlids is that
Kids don't want instructions
Just want to figure out how to connect things on their own
But because parents are demanding it
She is now writing a manual on all of the stuff
You can make
Lipstick
The challenges will how do we how do we show parents the value of what they're paying for how do we convince them that it's worth of my
Money because it's a higher-quality higher-end toys
A pack of 6
Sticklets by the way it goes for about $17 silicone TSA
Expensive
But you can do some over and over and over again to find out more about Christina
Because Ikea and her company sticklets
Go to our Facebook page and of course if you have a story about something you are building please tell us about it
Go to build NPR. Org and thanks so much for listening to
The show this week if you want to find out more about who was on it go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also follow us on Twitter that's at
How I built this and you can write to us
At HIV teeth
Npr.org
I sure was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva crab sanaz meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Claire Breen on Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
One more thing there are tens of thousands of podcasts
Catherine Springer to know what's good but
WAMU and NPR the big listen has
Come to the River
Askew
Who's Lauren over introduces you to podcast you might never have heard of
And gives you the inside scoop on shows you already love
Like the one you listening to right now
Find the big listen on YouTube
What happened NPR. Org
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email template
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week