Support for how I built
Send the following message come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn Why by searching Michigan pure opportunity
You know you're you're bursting at the seams and you can't accommodate
People and your neighbors are starting to look at you like what's going on in there I mean we were actually watch
At one point for suspicious activity because they help you
Just ringing the bell and going inside they come out with bags like what's going on in there
From NPR how I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
Lisa Price whipped up some homemade body butter in her apartment sold it at a
Flea market
And then turned it into one of the biggest Beauty Brands
Women
Color
If you log onto carolsdaughter.com
You'll see this beautifully polished website
With dozens of hair products
Body creams
Butters oils
Treatments
All for sale
And you'll see this incredibly diverse range of women
Skin tones and hues
Curly hair and straight hair
And if you scroll all the way down
You'll see in
Small type
Division of L'oreal L'oreal if you don't already know happens to be the worlds
Largest
Cosmetics company
L'Oreal bought Carol's Daughter
2014 for an undisclosed amount of money but
You can safely bet that it was
For a lot
Of money
But what
Is that Carol's Daughter literally started in Lisa prices
Kitchen
A one-bedroom apartment in Brooklyn
And if you haven't already guessed
It started out as a
Because Lisa already had a career
Pretty cool
In the 1980s
On The Cosby Show what should the time of course wasn't get tarnished because of Bill Cosby
It was the hottest TV show
In America
I thought that I had found the career that I was going to do for the rest of my life because
It was an amazing experience
It was particularly incredible being you know what
And African American woman
And
What that show
Meant to me and my family
P2c
African American
Connected in you know such a
Positive light so it was something that
For me to be standing in the Huxtable kitchen the morning of my first table read as I'm listening to the
The cast read the script
The III could have just
Floated off
That point I mean
Presumably
You know
I guess looking for the outside one would think
This is going to be a career like this is what you're going to do with your life but that is not what happened
No it's it's not I could have gone on to been a script supervisor
Production coordinator associate producer perhaps
On the on the
Operational side of
Things
And if that is what I thought I was going really happy
I was
Ecstatic
And I see
Because I was
Very happy
B at what I was doing with work
When I had my downtime and I was not at work
I didn't have that desperate feeling that
You feel
When you're like oh God
I'm finally not at work and I just want to relax and I just wanted
Veg-out you know
So I've became
Creative when I was at home
How did the idea to
Start making beauty products
Even occur to you
Well what
Initially happened was I'm a huge Prince fan and have been for many years
And I read an article about him and in that article
They talked about how he always smells very good and the reason for it was
He kept
An assortment of fragrances on his bureau
And it was also rumored that he put
Chanel Number 5
His boots
So that whenever he took off his boots he didn't have to worry about his feet not smelling good
Wow I could die I could see Princeton I just love this
Idea of this blending of fragrances and creating these unique set but you weren't thinking about this
Business no no not at all for you just like just to do for me
And that's what I began to do I learned that the way that your fragrance last on your body
Is you layer it so you wash with it you
Moisturize with it then you Spritz it on
So then I said well I don't I don't have moisturizers that smell like this where am I going to get that
And at first I started
Using lotions that I could get at the drugstore and I would
Put fragrances into them
And and blended it it didn't work that that wasn't you know balanced from a chemistry
Prospective so things would just separate and be kind of messy
And that led me into
Looking into
Possibly making my own
And
One day I walked into
To dislike New Age kind of
Bookstore
And there was a book on essential oils and the Art of perfumery
And in that book
Were basic recipe
Puppies for
I massage oil or
Cream or balm
So then I thought this is great I can make my own lotion
And
You know the recipes were very like
Barebones
You know they use things like paraffin and lanolin which I wasn't too
Crazy about you saying I
I wanted to use
Beeswax and I wanted to find cocoa butter
I used the the skeleton of the recipe with in the book
And then I just started adding
My own combinations and tweak it you know if something came out runny or too thick
Thor
Too oily or too stiff
Wow so you are like a literally melting down cocoa butter on your stove top
Cooking oils together and then
Sing what came out
Yes wow so that's right you start to melt a bunch of stuff and licks it
Yeah I mean today you couldn't get old
Go on YouTube videos and get a good head start but
Back then you just kind of had
Figure it out this was this was like what that the late 80s or the early 90
That was the late 80s
I began
Selling
Because I had actually gotten
Something
That you don't
Look good and work
And my mother encouraged me to sell at a church flea market
In May of 90
E3 what she was saying
Lisa the stuff is pretty good like you're you should sell this people might buy it
That that is pretty much verbatim What
There you go I did not say I said really mommy do you think people would pay for this
She said yes she said your Butters are good that you know my skin looks great and she was using it on my little brothers and sisters
Prison
You know she said I think you should try
And I remember saying to my mom I said Mom what am I going to put them in because I just would give it to friends and family
So I put it in tupperware Rubbermaid you don't say I didn't think about
Ajar
Recycled baby food jars
I'm cuz my mom had adopted my baby sister Torah very recently so she
She had lots of babies
Pujara's well
And we you know boil them on the stove like how you used to sanitize bottles back in the day
I put the cream in the baby food jars and made my labels by hand and I took them out to that flea market
And I sold out
What did you what did you call them
I called the company Carol's daughter I did have
Have a name
And I called it Carol's Daughter because that's literally who I was
My mom was Carol and I
I was her daughter
And the products that I sold I called them
Frequent moisture butter
At the time
So you show me the flea market by the way you are still
A writer's assistant on The Cosby Show
Dislike your weekend side hustles
No by 90
3 Cosby had ended
And I
I thought I was a freelance
Person
But it was summer
Television typically in New York was very
Slow in the summer months
Because you your season would end
In May and your new
New season wouldn't be
Begin until sept
I'm so unless you were working on a pilot
You will probably off
During the summer
And that first
Summer of
Starting at that flea market
Going to be end of May
I spent most of that
Summer making money
Selling at different
Craft fairs and Expos and things
Like that and I went back to work that fall
What did you how much money did
Did you have to put into
Blastoise
That very first flea market honestly was an investment of $100
Between you know whatever the table rental was and
The ingredients that I had to purchase to fill the baby food jars that I had and
Maybe some flowers you know to decorate my table
And what I did I just kept reinvesting
Because I didn't
Have
Money that I could say oh well I'm just going to go pull 10000 out of my savings to
Start this business
So it was something that started in a very small way of very organic way
And I didn't do anything that I couldn't afford to do
So if if someone told me about an expo
In Georgia
That's fantastic and the fee to get in it's only $5,000
I wasn't going there
But a table
You know in Park Slope
35 bucks
Okay what who is
Who are your customers in that first summer
They were mostly African-American women that you know where in the different neighborhoods that I was in
I did have some customers who weren't African-American but for the most part that's who would come to my table
I was not deliberately saying this is for African-American women I was deliberately saying this is for dry
Dry skin and subsequently
When you have more melanin in your
Skin
That dry skin will show
You you look dull you look a little bit at people say ashy
And you cannot get away from that
And that's how I probably at that time ended up with that audience
Of
People who were more Brown
Because they found something
That took away that Ash
So if you if you
Pure African American women
In the early 1990s
Essentially there was very few options it did
Really
Few companies that were serving
4 Watts
Yes very
There was definitely
A community that needed to be served
Who was not necessarily being served
It was it was not something
That you could walk into a drugstore
Look at that
This is fantastic great
It wasn't there
It is now but it wasn't then
So that summer of my teeth
Three when you were like
Selling
Body butter in baby jars
Flea market
Did you think of this as you know as
Future did you think of this kind of fun little side project hang out with
People I know and
I'm having fun
At first
I thought about it as fun
And then
Of that summer
I was watching an epic
Episode of the Oprah Winfrey Show and she was talking
People who had started businesses with little or no money
One person said well
You have to know that you
You're passionate about what you
You do you can't
Start a business
This just because you want to make
A bunch of money
Because it's going to take
Too long
For you to make any money and if you're not passionate about it you will quit
Before you make a
Eddie Money
And I remember thinking
I'm really passionate about
This stuff like I I like
I like doing this and then somebody else said
She would Define passion as
If someone woke you up out of your bed in the middle of the night would you go and do this thing
And I honestly could answer yes to that question and I'm someone who is very fond of sleeping
King and I love
A good ghetto lately been kind of thing and I realized yeah I would get up out of bed to do this because I really
We do enjoy it
And I remember sitting
On the edge of my bed and saying wait a minute
Maybe this is
This could be a business
And
That day was the day that I realized
This just
Doesn't have to be a hobby this
Can be more
All right so that first summer ends and you go back to a job in t
And what happens to to the business to Carol's Daughter
It continues to grow
People
Call
And say Hey you know I bought a jar cream from you
You know what
Such and such
Street fair
And I'm running out how can I get some more
And I would look at my
My schedule and
You know if I knew I was going to be home on
Saturday as well
If you want to come by my apartment on Saturday I'll be home I'm working the rest of the week but I'll be home on Saturday what time
Would you like to come by
And that was to be
Beginning
Of people coming
And shopping in my
Apartments
And and that continued
To grow to the point where sometimes I would come home to nasty message
Someone didn't know that it wasn't an actual store
You know they heard about it from a friend and you know that your answering machine at home
So at this point
How did you get the word out
About Carol's Daughter
Flea markets in MA
Breitbart
Get more people to know about
You know my my husband calls this
The sister girl net
It was literally
One woman telling another woman
And somebody always brought a friend
With them
And if you brought a friend
Do you know get a free gift or you know something
Sing off it was all of that Grassroots type
Stuff
And if I was out selling
Somewhere and someone asked me about something
If I didn't know how to make it I figured out how to make
So
I learned how to make bath salts I learned how to make bodies
Scrubs
Different types of moisturizers
I figured out how to make shampoo how to make
Air conditioner
And it was it was just experimenting the way you would experiment cooking
And what did you decide to
Leave TV in
Do this full-time I left television in 1996
Because my son Forest
Was due to
To be born April 5th
Of that year
And
I realize that
If I can
Continue to work
I would basically just give my paycheck to a babysitter
So it just logically made
Sense to let the job go
And see if
In being at home full-time while taking care of a baby
Could the business
Grow enough
We also at the
Same
Time
We were able to change
How and where we live
So
My aunt and uncle were
Selling their home
They were selling it to someone else
And
I think there was
Three tries at the
The closing and it just didn't happen
And I finally worked up the nerve
To ask
Is there any way that we could purchase
Your home
And we did it and so forest was born
March 18th of 90
B6
And May 22nd
Can of 90s
We moved into
The home that we live in today
And it enabled us to
You don't have the space that we needed with a baby but also have space for the business to grow
And that was
That was a big turning point you know it was a huge difference
So many people coming in on Saturdays to shop you know there was a time where you would be like oh hi Diane
Hi Susie hi Charles
And that was like I don't know any of
I never met you
The voice mailbox would fill up every hour and a half
My husband and I would you no wait
When did you last check the photo I checked it at 2:30 oh my God it's five
Get me a pen and paper and it's just
You just look at it and you and you can't
You can't believe it Lisa Price
In just a moment
He'll mention from Oprah
Crashed her company's website
Gyros near listening to how I built this
ER
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy
Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from better
Betterhelp offers licensed professional counselors who specialize in issues such as
Depression stress anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment at your convenience
Get help at your own time and your own pace
Schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your
Visit betterhelp.com built to learn more
And get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Harrah's
Definitely should have started to focus on Carol's Daughter
Full-time
Things started to take off
Pretty fast
What was the turning point when did you when did something happen
Were you sad
This is like
Bedtime
Well because I've been in business for
For 24 years
And because
Turning Point
And
Success
You know those aha moments
AR
Very relative
Fluid there's been
Several of those
So
You know there was
There was the moment when my second son Ennis was born
And I was in the hospital
I'm after having given birth and my husband walks into the hospital with
Essence magazine
And I was in the November issue
And I actually had a half-page article with a picture
And my name
Which was a really big deal
How did they know about it
There there were Beauty editors that lived in the Brooklyn neighborhood where I live
So
They were always in search of something different
And then because I worked
Can television production
For so long and then my husband
Continue to in
And still does
I would have access to
Makeup artist
And hairstylist
And
If they
You know went on another production
They could reach out to me and I know I could send it to them
I remember hearing that Edie Falco loved a moisturizer of mine because
A makeup artist that I worked with on his show
Shared it with
You know and I was like
I've never met Edie Falco to this day but she she loved one of my moisturizer
Wow so by 1999 you guys were able to open up like an actual ShopRite
Yes
The first store that was not in my house
Brick-and-mortar retail space
He said had windows and a door
And
The landlord
Wanted the space to be something else
And
I sent him a gift basket
For his wife
Ana Package
With a letter about the bread
To convince him
That
My shop with
Be great in that location and because
Of my letter
He decided that he was going to give me a shot and he wanted to meet
With me to go over
What's terms
So I'm sitting in this meeting feeling so Victorious I've convinced this guy that
You know my business is what he wants
Put in here
He's so he said so
The terms of pretty basic I'm going to need
4 month deposit on the rent and Bubba Bubba and he's like talking other things and I'm quickly adding in my head
And I'm like that's 14th Ave
That's $14,000 that's $14,000
Yeah
I have no clue
Where are we going to get $14,000 from
It worked out
We had some small account set up for our sons for their college
And we took it you know my my boys were very very young
You know we took
It up between their two accounts aye I don't know something like $3,500 out of the bank
And then one of my aunts
Loaned me
Little bit more like another for $5,000
Yeah it worked out it was it was a little little dicey at first but it worked out and I paid my aunt back
Back before Christmas
That year it's so incredible to hear how $3,500 is
Excruciating excruciating my money when
Of course
In a within a decade you were going to do and you know
A hundred million stars
Sales but at that time it was scary must have felt really scary
It was it definitely was this think that that made it
Palatable was
I knew I couldn't stay in the house
Like you know you're you're bursting at the
It seems and you can't accommodate people
And your neighbors are starting to look at you like what's going on in there this oldies
People that come in and out everyday
I mean we were actually watched at one point
For suspicious activity
Because did you know I was just ringing the bell and going inside and they come out with bags like what's going on
In there and and and we found out later when you know
The police office
Officer came to shop
And she cheetah she was like I just want to let you know cuz you probably didn't know this
Somebody made a phone call and someone was nervous
If you don't realize that everything was okay
And there was nothing untoward going on but yeah yeah
You just get to a point where
You have to
To grow up in and you have to take that leap of faith in
I didn't want to live in
Well what if I had gotten the store
What if I had
What if you digest
And I would rather have had
At the store
Fail
Then to have wondered what
What did your mom think about
That store that first dortmund
Her name was was in the Marquee
She she she loved it but it but I will I will tell you the moment that she was like
Really excited about
The business being Carol's Daughter
I got to do
The Oprah Winfrey Show in 2002 and so she got to see that
You know to see her daughter on
Oprah
All of her
Her friends got
To see that
And
The place where she went
Where she would get her blood work done on a regular basis
South Medical Center in Brooklyn
Glenn called The Hip Center
At what was she what she say
Yes with an illness called polymyositis
So when she came to get her blood work done after that Oprah Winfrey show
Oh miss Carol was so happy to see you here come right in. The so-and-so is waiting for you
And then I'm going to take you down to the lab as soon as you're done
She said she was in and out of there so fast
She told me she said yeah girl
You going on television I could get you
How did how did Oprah find out about you
You threw the magazines and in the attention
You re getting there
Getting me on to the show came through
Douceurs
And the producers of
The show heard about me from another producer
Who was interviewing for a job
She went to Chicago
To interview for
Position
They talked about what they were working on
And one of the shows was
A show about women who have started businesses
Is in their home
And she said to them will have you spoken to
Lisa Price
And they reached out
They liked what they heard they interviewed me like
6 *
A week later I was in Chicago taping the show
And I was sitting in the audience
And
She looked at the screen and she sees the name of the store and she said
Carol's Daughter
Your calendar I know Carol's Daughter your camels I know camels
And I'm sitting here like oh my God Oprah Winfrey meldman I'm going to die
How did that
Affect business
When it when it was on Oprah
It affected it in an amazing way
We
Had
Our website
Go from having
People in it
And within four minutes
My segment
The audience
In the website went from
You know whatever it was 30 something people to 17000
Wow
The website Act
Crashed
I mean it was remarkable it was just remarkable
Not anything
Crazy like not what
Not what
People think that you know
One day you're on the show and all of a sudden you're a millionaire and money is just falling out of your hands
Not that but definitely a c
Significant
Lift and shift
In
Who knew about us but it was something that was manager
We didn't implode under
Did the pressure
I mean
Basically
From the moment you open their first store for the next
Decade you guys were
What is massive
You were just like
Growing and growing and growing ever
Year-in and opening more stores right
What we did
Open additional
Stores for a very long time
I mean I I I wouldn't describe it as a massive growth
Trajectory
There was growth each year
But I wouldn't describe it as
As massive
If I didn't open up another store until 2
In 2004 I took out a business
Partner
And then into
Took on invest
And you guys had some
Big deal investor
Jay-Z was an investor right
Yes Jay-Z
Will Smith
Jada pink
Smith
And the investment
Help desk
Open up the additional
Store
I'm but also helped us to get into
Two places
Like Sephora at the time
And then subsequently maze
It helped to build a better infrastructure
You know that there's there's definite
Excitement
You know Pride
And everything
Sing when you're
When you're small and your grass roots and your building but they're there comes a point
You know when you start doing
A million a million and a half 2 million
Two and a half
Hainan sale where
You can't win
You know like things half
To be
Cure
And and that's when invest
Was deaf
I need it because
There there was some winging it
That was going on and you can only do that
Her butt solo
At a certain point I mean you guys were
I'm your revenues were
You know
In the tens of millions of dollars when you saw
Those numbers
At the end of the year
Was that Strange Fruit
Could you have imagined
That happening I I can definitely
He say for certain
That
I never
Imagine
Jen that happened
And even to
This day
I still am amazed by it
It's still surreal
And that's not something that ever goes away
And I don't mind
That I feel that way
Because I think it
Grounded
And it keeps me focused on the work
That I do
Because that never change
Regardless of
You know
40 mm in sales
In a year
Or
28 million
In sales in a year
I'm still doing this
Same work
I know that your mom Carol
Passed away
More than a decade ago
But when she was alive
What what sort of role did
Play Enya
Because I mean she
Did actually get two witnesses
She she did she
She did get to see
A lot what Mommy always
Did for me was she always focused me
On the
Positive
So if I was calling her
Saying to her
You know Mom I don't know how I'm going to get the
These orders filled
Christmas
They all have to ship by this date there's just so much I just
Just can't figure out
How to get it all done
And she was
Would say
Well actually that's the easy
Depart
And I said what do you mean
The easy part I just said I don't know how to do it like it's it's really hard and she said but what if
You didn't have the
The orders
That seems to me like it would be the harder
Airport to kind of
Make people be interested
And make people purchase he says you have the orders
You have their credit card number
As soon as you get the stuff made you'll get the money
So the money is just sitting there waiting for you
You so that seems like it's easy
She said I think we just need to clear our heads
And figure out how to get it all done
And then she would say something like go make yourself a cup of tea I'm going to make myself a cup of
He call me back I'm going to figure
This out
And I would be like
Is she crazy
I would go make my cup of tea
And come back to the phone and we would talk and I'd sit there with pen and paper
And we would figure out
Plan
And
I never let that go
I know that in 2014 you sold
The company to L'Oreal
Was that
Difficult
For you to sell this thing that
Built out of your apartment in Brooklyn or
How did it feel like a weight was lifted off your shoulders I mean that
You know that.
Huge deal on one of the biggest cosmetic companies in the world buying your company it was not a difficult thing
For me to do
At at all except for the fact that the
Process to get there is
So it wasn't
Oh my God I have to
Sell my baby
I can't I can't I can't
That
Emotion had already happened
Because
In 2007
Carol's daughter took nonequity partners with pegasus capital advisors
So once you take on an equity
Partner
Your goal
Is 2
Celtics
Dziedzic partner and everyone eggs
Happy Cow
I'm so
Having someone like L'Oreal acquire the brand
With something that I knew would happen
And
I always had
L'Oreal at
The top of my list
And it did work out
And I was
Thrilled and
Proud and
Because for me it was the culmination
Of all of that work that I had
Do to fix the mistakes that I made
In my company
Not trusting my gut often enough
Not
Valuing
What I brought to the
Table and not valuing myself
As a business
This person and as a smart woman
And I had to
Find my voice again
And
So I got it back
I felt strong I felt
Power
And I stood with everyone else shoulder to shoulder
Indicted
Carol's daughter to that place
For us to have that app
Position so
I was very very high
When when L'Oreal bought
The company some of your customers were disappointed
Because
You know I mean you know they felt that well this was
Company owned by Naf
American Woman
Now it's somebody that's big
Multinational
How did you guys respond to that one
It didn't take me by surprise that there was
With some backlash I think the only thing that took
Take me by surprise was that some of the backlash
Was very
Personal
And very
Pointed end
Very cruel
And just speaking about me in
In ways that I was like how do you say this about somebody that you've never met before
More wow
That was surprising
But
What I realized
Was
People didn't know
My story
I realize that as
A group of P
People with in this world African American people
Historically
We have left
Experience with generational wealth
We may be sick
Successful in certain areas we may have B
Become
Rich recently
But we don't really know what generational wealth
Is
And we haven't
Come up in
Family
That have owned and passed down business
So they were just things that
People didn't know
And they wrote a narrative for me
On what they felt was appropriate and what they felt
Was something to do
Be proud of and I didn't follow this
And
And I apologize for how they felt
And that I didn't follow the script that they wrote
For me but I used the opportunity
And still use it
To educate asbestos
Is possible
Cuz it's going to take us
Time
To build that generational wealth
And then perhaps
Be in the place
Where we have the luxury of
Might have
To sell because we were able to build it on our own or we were able to build it
With Mom and Dad's help
And we can stay private
We own but it's going to take time to get
But it it was
It was difficult
Sometimes it still is difficult because people
Still will bring it up and it's it's almost as if
I've been asked
To apologize
For one of the greatest accomplishments of my life
And something that I'm very very proud of her for a little girl in from Bed-Stuy in Brooklyn
You did pretty well yeah pretty well
I did
I definitely did
Better than I would have had I continued to have a career in television and film production
And there's a
There's a very deep respect
That one ends up having four
Where they are where they've come from and what they have
When you go through something like that
And it and I just I just have a very very profound respect for what I've done
And I won't be that person who
Runs off and buys plane
Cars and things like that because I have too much respect for how hard it was
Together
There
Lisa Price founder of Carol's Daughter by the way even though L'Oreal
The company Lisa is still the public face
Carol's Daughter
And despite becoming financially secure for life
Lisa still lives in that
Same house in Brooklyn
She and her husband bought from her aunt back in 1996
Please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Pitney Bowes
Pitney Bowes provides
Technology that helps retailers turn Us online businesses
Global one
Today our Global e-commerce Solutions
Enable retailers to sell online
In 200
20 countries and territories
Pitney Bowes
Craftsman
Commerce
Visit pitney-bowes. Com
Slashcraft
Looking around because it
It's time now for how you built that
Asteroid today comes from Dan Gosling live
Jobs in Indianapolis
Square
He plays music
And this is how Dan made his living for years
Playing with
Trumpet in ensembles and orchestras
And giving lesson
And when you're a brass player
All those hours of planking
Actually taking
Real toll on
Lips
Swell up
Auburn extreme cases that deliver
Split
Bleed
Securely prone to getting
Chocolate
Oops all that pressure buzzing
So you think they would just
Bicycle
Chapstick right you would think that but what I heard from my musician colleagues was
There are a ton of lip balms out there and none of them work
Anyway about 10 years ago Dan was talking
One of the students who had
Just had a marching band
Accident like literally somebody ran into this guy while he was playing
Any of this horrible bruise on his lips and I sweated you too
I said I use
Arnica
And I just kind of looked at him cuz I never heard the word
What's arnica
Arctica it turns out is an herb that comes from sunflowers and naturally cut down on bruising
And swelling so
In that moment
Dan start
Arnica
Trumpet
Let me
Can make my own lip balm
And you know as ideas pop into
And sometimes they come
Come and go but this one
I couldn't let go upper it wouldn't let go of me so as you would probably expect at this point Dam
Went into his kitchen he turned into a mad scientist
Anchor with different amounts of arnica
And do research on all the other ingredient
Castor oil in Delaware
Text beeswax
And of course he had absolutely zero background
Apricot kernel oil
Calendula comfrey
Raspberry leaf
Iteration
Iration
His wife she was
Supportive but a little concerned that this may be a sort of like a midlife crisis kind of thing
And to the point where it's actually actually
Kick me out of the kitchen and then I was
Kind of formulating stuff in the laundry room
Connect remote
Different Generations
Dan found a manufacturer in Ohio
And he started sending out samples to musicians and Orchestra
Even went
Marching band competition
We would literally have little car
And I would just
Swipe a little bit of the formula on the card
That 99% of the time that person would
How to look at me and I put that on your lips and they would do it and that's really amazing
Dan kept sending out samples to Brass players wherever he
Find them and he's getting great feedback from they can play longer without getting chapped lips
And then
Something happened that
He did not
I've literally got an email from a dermatologist he said hey one of my
What happened to be a musician
Show me your product and it's really working well for her could you send me some samples
And then I realized
Oh that's a whole nother Market wouldn't that be cool and sure enough
The lip balm gradually became popular with all kinds of people not just musicians in effect
Ten Years After Dan started
Anchoring in his kitchen
The lip on was picked up by CVS and is now in over 8,000 of its stores so billion-dollar category
And I just feel like
You know in an infinite universe
There's always room for
Christian Gosling of Indianapolis
His product is called Chop
Savor
$20,000 in
And sales
Last year
He's not doing this full-time by the way but
Easton training company
The Sun
Old playroom
You can find out more about chopsaver on Earth
Facebook page
How I built this on Facebook
And of course if you want to tell us
Your Story please go to
Build
. npr.org
You Be Loved
Love love
Hearing your stories
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or if you want to go
Your previous episodes
Can go to how I built this.
Npr.org
You can write us
HIV
ET at
Npr.org
And if you want to send us a tweet it's at how I built this
Are shows produced this week by Rachel Falkner with
Original music composed by Rams
Teen Arab Louie
Thanks also to neva Grant sanaz meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey one more thing this weekend visit Viola NPR show about the invisible forces that shape human behavior
Things you would seem like a politically relevant question how is it
A two people can look at the exact same thing and see something
Weekly different
Dancer they have a musical about umpires a bear fairytale on the
The story of a man who
Breaks out of his
Is reality.
You can listen to invisibilia on the NPR one app
Or wherever you get your pot
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing plan
Farm use by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email template
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week