Support for this podcast
And the following message
Come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Where are new center for personalized health is working to predict and prevent cancer
Details at Fairfax County. Org
I said you know we should really call Diane Von Furstenberg the famous fashion designer
Fast forward a few weeks and we're driving to the second meeting and her system calls and says Dad no longer wants to see you
She's not interested in this idea and I said
We're just around the corner like what will just drop by for a second
And again her assistant very firmly
Said she doesn't want to see you what do you not understand
And I said we're cutting off or cutting off and I hung up and then I said down the West Side Highway
Highway and we were
At her office and we just showed up
NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
They built
I'm guy Raz.
How to women who wanted High fashion but couldn't afford the price tag
Decided to make it possible
The Rent the Runway
So Rent the Runway is
Now we're the hottest fashion companies
Days in the US
Growing like
Crazy
Doing more than a hundred million dollars a year in Revenue
It hasn't like
1200 employees
Core product is designer dresses
Surprise to discover as I was
But just
10 of its employees work in the fashion Department
Most of the rest
Well
They work for a technology company
Because that's actually what Rent the Runway is
It works is
You go online or you go to the app
And well dressed
Thousands of dollars to buy
Except you only pay a small fraction of that and you get to look fabulous for one night
And then in the morning after you've recovered
You mail it back
Zipcar me Netflix
Zappos
Who are the co-founders Jenn Hyman and Jennifer Fleiss
Came up with the idea when they met in Business School
As you will hear
The path of building their company was fraught with all kinds of challenges
Among them
Rampant sexism
And even harassment
Jenn Hyman is only recently been opening up
About that
Their Story begins just after she graduates College
And job working as a junior analyst
For the hotel company
Starwood
About a year into my time at Starwood when I was
I had this pieces
That we had entered
The Experience economy
And people were getting married later and starting to value
Experiences like travel
Over owning things
And so I had an idea at the time
To Launch
The first honeymoon registry in the world
Where couples could register for
Their honeymoons and their friends and family could contribute by
You know paying for scuba diving or paying for a massage or hotel night as opposed to buying them pots
Pants
So
As a 22 year old I
Was really passionate about this idea
I emailed the president of Starwood
And
I pitched him on this idea to start
A wedding list
Starwood where the Cornerstone of it would be with a
The first honeymoon registry
Just eversec
Bristle your 22
That's that's incredibly precocious but was there anybody around you who is like
Hey stay in your lane or you know was there anybody was trying to
Tell you to keep your plan keep quiet
Oh yeah
Several boxes of mine were telling me to keep
Keep quiet in
One of the experiences that really impacted me
Was
I
Had a female boss
And at the time I think she was like
35 or 36 so
Kind of about my age right now
And I would often
Raise my hand in meetings and speak and make points
And
I remember her
Grabbing me after a meeting one day and
She said you know Jen I really want to give you some feedback
It's really important for your career
And I said oh you know I'd love to hear what's your feedback
And she said
You really need to shut up wow
You're a girl
And
It would be much more becoming
If you acted sweet
In
Conversations
Because you know you're you're too confident you're too bold
And it's coming across the wrong way
And of course
I didn't really know how to take this I mean I don't even know how I would take this today let alone is a 22 year olds
I started hysterically crying I was in the middle of like an open floor plan
And a more senior man
Sami
I literally credit
The sky for my entire career
He took me aside
And because I
Didn't even understand office politics at the time and like what I should and shouldn't say I kind of just blurted out
Oh my God like this woman just told me X Y and Z and I repeated the entire conversation to him
And he said you know Jen
You keep doing what you're doing
Because that one is going to be working for you one day
Wow
End
She innocence gave me permission
To just act like myself
And
Who I was as a 22 year old
The same person is who I am today it's the person who
How to creative idea about
The Experience economy and I wanted to share it
So what did you end up doing with it with the idea you pitch this to the to the president of Star Wars
Yeah
I think he thought I was so
What are the crazy for going in and pitching to him that his response was like yeah sure whatever
And I took that as a yes
Wait he said
He didn't say yes he just said yeah that's interesting in you
Went back to your your desk and you started to
Map out how this could happen
I started to work on it I spent the next three years working on it
And
You know Starwood still participates in
The honeymoon red
History to this day
Has
Taking it to a whole other level since I left
But it was such a fun experience for me to a work on something that I loved and was passionate about
Indeed be part of the process of
Creation
So you are obviously on the fast track to like if you were still Starwood today you might be running the place and you were
Doing this at such a young age
Why did you decide to leave after after a couple years
I always thought
But I would go to visit
The school both my parents have gone to Business School
And so
I thought that the track was you work for 4 years between college and then you go to Business School
Also went
I was at Starwood for
3 + years I applied to business school and I got into Harvard Business School
So here's a question for you about cuz we're going to get I want to ask you about
What happened business coaches
Being critical to
Rent the Runway but
The vast majority of the of the entrepreneurs of it have been on the show
Did not go to Business School
You had all this incredible experience and you were really ambitious and you were
Entrepreneurial already
Why did you think you needed to
To go to Business School
Well first
I
Have always had big
Dreams for my career but I
Didn't exactly know what those dreams were
You know
Sara Blakely was
A guest on your program and
She's someone who
Has always been an inspiration to me I remember being a
Younger girl
And
Seeing her on Oprah
And she had this amazing business but she also like
Seem like a real person
Who cared about getting married and having kids and
Having friends and having a social life in
That was really important to me
I was still fearful
That you had to make a choice
Between having
An incredible career as a woman or having a family
And I've always wanted both
So
And since going to business school with a Chance.
Think those things through to think of through to get that kind of x
Straw
Potentially stamp of approval that I thought that I needed
I had lots of opportunities that I could go into
Different kinds of companies in different
Fields
But I really wanted the time to think about like
Where do I want to spend my time
Like what am I most passionate about
You are why you were at at Harvard Business School gmat
The person who become
The co-founder of Rent the Runway
Jennifer Fleiss
Yes how did you
So it's a really funny story my sister Becky
Prior to me going to business school put a Post-It note on my pillow one night
With
Jenny Fleiss has maiden name on it
Which was Teddy Carter
And
She said that you have to meet the
Scroll when you go to Business School
Because a friend of a friend of hers new Jenny Carter
And my response
Tobaccy
At the time was he know I'll meet her if I meet her
Needless to say
Jenny was one of the first people I met at Harvard biz
The school because we were placed in the same section
Because her name had been on a Post-It note
For me I was like oh my God you'll never believe this like my sister told me we need to be friends and we be
He came really fast friends and
You know the rest is history and at what point did you say
What's your business together when we leave
So we were friends
We actually through our birthdays
Together
I'm in
September of
That second year of Business School
And in November of the second-year business school I went home for Thanksgiving
And I was in Becky's apartment
And Becky had just gone to a store and bought a dress
That was higher cost than her rent
And
Azhar
Responsible older sister I was
Embarking how
She should probably wear
One of the dresses in her closet again as opposed to being in credit card debt
And her response to me was
You know everything in my closet is dead to me
I've been photographed in it
The photographs are up on Facebook and I need something new
You know Becky was a 25 year old
Like normal girl who lived in New York she wasn't a celebrity
But she was talking about being photographed and not being able to wear something again
And I like it was a lightbulb
Look for me
Cuz I realize
I was having a conversation with my sister about the
Experience
Of wearing
An amazing dress of walking into a party feeling self-confident
I'm feeling beautiful and that's what
She cared about
And she didn't
Care about
The actual ownership of the items in her closet
The other thing she cared about was
Photograph
That would exist after the party
That she could post on Facebook
I'm kind of share with everyone she knew
How awesome she felt and how confident
She felt it that way
Sweating with this idea happened on a Saturday night
I go back
To school on Monday
I happen to have lunch that day with Jenny
We were talking about our weekends I was like oh I had this idea like
What if we rented dresses
She responded all this sounds fun
You know that's like
Work on this idea together
Who do you think we should call
To figure out if it's a good idea
And
I said you know we should really call Diane Von Furstenberg
Chauncey like the famous fashion designer
Jennifer
Do you know Diane Von Furstenberg
And I said
Obviously I don't know Diane Von Furstenberg but we could probably figure out her email address
Eucalyptus
Point figure out anyone's email address in the entire world
So
Jenny and I
Roden email. Afternoon
Too many different versions of Diane Von Furstenberg email address
And we basically said Hayward were two women at Harvard Business School we have an idea
We'd love to come in and talk to you about it
And this is where luck
Please into the situation
Because
She or someone from her office
Open that email
She responded I'll see you tomorrow at 5 p.m. tomorrow at 5 p.m. and we
Drove down
To New York
That next day
Put on our dvf dresses
And walked into her office and introduced ourselves as the co-founders of Rent the Runway
You had the name at that point you came up with a name
Yeah we do
We did everything very quickly
Now we didn't really have a structured idea
So
You know we were kind of iterating the idea
By pitching
And
Initial idea actually a witch
You know we've never really told the initial idea was what if we could rent
The dresses
That she is selling on her website so what if we powered rental for
Her on dvf.com
And
You know when we
Went to chat with her
She
Was not too thrilled about
The idea of
Renting clothes in general
And thought that it would
Cannibalize
Her
Her retail sales and it would dilute her brand
And
She was ready to end the meeting with us after a few minutes
I started asking her questions about what she disliked about the idea what was
She scared about end
By the end of what was
Almost a you know a hour-and-a-half conversation we learned
That
A lot of her customers were in their 50s and 60
And not
If we were to build a business that could
Make her relevant
To put her products
Into the hands of women
In their teens twenties thirties and forties
But that might be interesting to her and she might want to work with us
So what are you guys
Nervous I mean
You're stabbing yourself business school students mean
I can imagine like what
That would be like to walk into that room and
I can't keep her attention and get her excited
What's a funny story so
At that first meeting I've always learned you know when you're in the first meeting scheduled second meeting
So when we were in the first meeting we scheduled the conversation for a few weeks later with her
Fast forward a few weeks and we're driving to the meeting
And
We got a call while we're in the car
From hearth
Assistant
And we're on the West Side Highway where about
40 blocks
From her off
And her system calls and says Dad no longer wants to see you
I said oh you know well
We're on our way
We'll just come in and say hi
And persistence like
No
She really doesn't want to see you
She's not interested in this idea
Can I set
We're just around the corner like what will just drop by for a second
And add her assistant very firmly
Said she doesn't
Want to see you what do you not understand
And I said we're cutting off or cutting off and I hung up
And then I
Bed down the West Side Highway and we were
At her office and we just showed up most people in that situation would have just been like
Crushed would have felt so dejected
Like I don't know I would
What did you said well forget it forget Diane will just move on
How did you not
Feel that how did you how are you able to just say
We're just going to do that for no walk in there
Well Jenny initially was
Actually started to cry and was a little bit upset about the situation which I think is some people would
Yeah which I think is the much more natural reaction and
I was like we're just going to do this what do we have to lose like
What's the worst thing in the world we show up and she doesn't meet us what if you walked in there and they were like
Security please escort these women out
Great
Then we have a story that we could tell all of our friends
Let me come back
What actually happened when Jen and Jenny finally showed up at the Hands-On furstenberg's office
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can
Be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital Xperia
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at game Bridge. Life's NPR game Bridge is not available in all states
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed from the tech IPO
Show landscape to China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Hey welcome back to how I built this
Stream NPR
Before the break Jen was talking about how she and her co-founder Jenny
Basically
Busted in the Diane Von Furstenberg Sophos to have a second meeting
An amazingly
Diane agreed to meet with them
She was giving them some
Pretty good advice
Actually that was the meeting where she told us you know I don't want you to do
Do this on my website
You are going to have
You sell this idea
The other day
Designers and get lots of people on board if I'm going to do this to
So in a sense in that meeting she gave us permission
To make a cat a consumer-facing business and to approach
The rest of the industry
Reroute your business plan right right there
Yeah so did you walk out of her office would like names or contacts or did you just walk out of it hurt her office
Alright cool this is this is clarified we now know
We're heading
Well we did ask her
Or
Some introductions and I think that she introduced us to one or two people in the industry
We then would meet with those people and we'd ask them for introductions and so on and so forth
But we continue to just cold coffee
So one of the next people that I cold called was
The
President of Neiman Marcus
Because
He was Botha HBS alarm so I had access to his email address
And I thought that you know if this whole
Rent the Runway thing
Falls through like
Maybe I could work for Jim gold Neiman Marcus
What he say
He said yeah
This is a really good idea women have been renting the runway from my stores for decades
It's called buying something keeping the tags on and then returning it to the store
Which probably cost them
Millions of dollars
Yeah it's
Kind of the dirty secret of retail
The return rate especially addresses
And special occasion
A tire is
Extremely high
Cashpot forsaken a-10s this question which is
I'm wearing the outfit I'm wearing today like I've worn this in the last few days
I have no shame about it and obviously there's a difference
Society has different standards for men and women
What is this about what does thing where where
Women
Do you like they can't wear the same dress
Can two different functions
I really think that
There's a value that women place on
Self-expression
And that clothes make
You feel a certain way about yourself you
You put on an amazing outfit in the morning and
It makes you feel powerful or beautiful or sexy or relaxed or however you want to feel that day
There's just a general value in
Our society right now around individuality and self-expression
And so the way that you're going to achieve that
With fashion is via variety
So I had
Scene
At the time and it's even more true today
Set the way that women were accessing variety and individuality was through
Fast fashion
An off-price
Because the only place
So you could buy a quantity of items
Was at a place that was selling them for a very cheap price Forever 21 or a
Exactly
So I think sit when you don't have to buy something
It allows you
Try
New things to constantly be playful to Experiment 2
Try things that are in colors or in
Trends were you know different kinds of styles that you never would purr
Because they're irrational
So with renttherunway it's like a Willy Wonka land of fashion
Can you can have whatever you want whenever you want
Let's say you have a job
Curfew you have a
A party you have a wedding you're going to
You're saying I wanted to arrive at my home on
September 15th and I'm going to wear it and use it for a few days and then I'm going to run
And
It's about 10% of the retail price
So how did you know for sure that
Are the women will be interested
In like
Doing this mean did you get you guys doing research
No we never did research in an academic sense we did real life research
Which which was
We went
To Bloomingdale's
We bought about a hundred dresses
All in our own sizes
So that if this whole experiment didn't work out we would have an awesome new wardrobe
We spent a lot of our savings on this
And
We
Hosted a pop-up
At Harvard undergrad
And we invited different groups of Harvard undergrad to the pop-up and
Idea behind this was to learn a
Will women rent dresses
B what do they rent how much will they pay
What brands do they want
And most importantly
If they do run
What happens
To these
Garments
Destroyed
Can you send them through the mail
How do you dry clean these items
And so on and so forth
This is like
Still like
Travis seems like
No brainer but
Is what 2008/2009
This our first pop-up was in April 2009 at that time Netflix mailing
DVDs in the mail so that was going on
Zappos
You could get shoes you can mail the bathroom still
It wasn't like when it is now then it was still new
It was and
It feels
Both so long ago and also yesterday
So you got the The Descent right away that
This that this could work because these these undergraduates
These women were like yeah I want to read this
I got the sense that it would work because I saw the emotional effect
So in this pop-up I saw girls
You know
Stripping down
Trying on
These amazing dresses and
Feeling
Beautiful
And you saw it
Their facial expressions
Change it
They threw their shoulders back and they tousle their hair and they walked with a new sense of confidence
Tencent
You know
I really thought wow
This could be a business that isn't just about offering her irrational or smart choice
But it also can be a business that is
Delivering something emotional to her making her feel
Beautiful every single day
A lot of founders
Choose to do it on their own
Like in like Gary Erickson Clif bar or even Sara Blakely
Thanks and she has a hundred percent of her company
But
You guys went for venture capital
Pretty quickly pretty early on why
We had to
Raise money because we needed to invest hundreds of thousands of dollars in inventory
2 even
Launch a business or twists whether it was
A viable
Idea
And
I don't come from a family that has hundreds of thousands of dollars of
Savings
Especially
King of savings that they're going to invest in their daughters
Crazy idea
Until when you were pitching venture capitalist how much money were you looking to raise it in the first round
We raised 1.75 million dollars
I mean with that money
What could you do I just build a website right
You could buy initial inventory in
Various-sized runs with some depth
Because we knew we needed many different designers we needed a selection right you weren't going to come and start renting
If there were only
5 units of inventory on the site
We could hire some people
We could launch a website
That was about it and take photos of the dresses and put them on the web
Tell us another funny story until 2 weeks
Before the website launched we didn't realize that we would have to take photos at the inventory
We thought of course in this industry
There's some centralized plant that takes photos of this how ridiculous is it that every retailer would have to photograph
This inventory over and over again needless to
To say
We figure out like right before the websites
Meant to launch that we have no photos
And we
Put together a impromptu photo shoot where we
Found a photographer on Craigslist
Who ended up working with Rent the Runway for 6
Gyro
And
We bring our own shoes and our own accessories to the
This photoshoot and
Are you know initials
Team
Of
5 employees in many interns at the time kind of
Figure out how to do it
So once you
Watch how do you get the word out how do you how do you get people to even know what this says
Hustling
So was I so
The hustle was we wanted to build
A list
Of as many women as
Possible
You know the Sex in the City movie had come out that summer
And we would
Go to movie theaters with women who were attending that movie and we would get their email addresses we would
Convince friend
Just send us email addresses of other friends if they're so like we were really doing anything and everything
So what are the names that was on this list
That we had built it Rent the Runway had
A at newyorktimes.com
And
I would like my old like there's someone who works at the New York
Email address and I looked her up and I saw that she was a twenty-two-year-old technology
Reporter
Invite her in
Maybe she can write about Rent the Runway
So we met with her and we decided we were going to give her a story
And
I
Thought
That
If Jenny and I were photographed
For this article
Potentially we could be on the front page of the
Business hours of photo the
Two of you
Yes
Because
It was a technology reporter
And no women are ever covered in the Technologies
So I
Say to this reporter oh maybe you know you should take maybe you could take a photograph of us
At the kuantan port warehouse
Does the dry cleaner
So we put on like these crazy dresses
And
We showed up when the photographer
I showed up to the dry cleaner
And we stood on ladders
And we told the photographer to take a photo of us on ladders
In front of
Kind of the
Array of
Addresses that were on the kind of dry cleaner
Machine
And
Because the photo was so
Utterly absurd
It ended up on the front page of the business section and
The headline A1 photo on nytimes.com
So we had a hundred thousand people sign up for Rent the Runway off of that story wow
Making orders yes
Did you have the inventory to handle all the orders no
So what you do
We raised more money so because of of
Hustling
To get this story in the luck of ending up on the front page of the New York Times
We met our first year sales projections in 3 weeks
And we had a clamoring of
Venture Capital investors
Who were kind of coming into our office pitching us on
Series I so we got we have gone from
You know a very undesirable investment to
Like people
Showing up at the elevator
In our building
To meet with us unannounced wow
Because they wanted to pounce on the deal I mean
But both you and Jenny
Unfortunately
Still rare in in the start of World War II women
Bleeding a huge company and end
The time when you were raising money
Did you ever get the sense from venture capitalist who presumably most
But mostly men
That I don't know they were like
A little bit dismissive or
Condescending or
You know
I know treat you differently
So we had
Several different very condescending conversations one
In which a partner at a very
Prestigious firm took my hand into his and he said you know this
So adorable
You're going to get to wear such pretty dresses this must be so fun for you
We both froze a little bit
We were very polite
And we walked out and we said you know thanks for
The feedback no of course we never
Interacted with
This former this investor again we never pitched them on any subsequent round we were like kind of good riddance to these people
So there's an element of
You know we
Hydac
The capital
We had choices
Because the business was growing
That's a privilege
I read an article that you that one investor says feel like
Let me talk to my wife about about this idea
Well that's something that we heard all the time
That wasn't one investor that was most
Let me talk to my wife
My daughter or my admin
Those were the three
You know
Target customers that we would hear and
Let me tell you why each is problematic
Number one the wife of a venture capitalist
Did the billionaire
So the wife of a venture capitalist
Is not Mike Target
Write the daughter of a venture capitalist in most cases
This is about 12
Because most Venture capitalists are
When they're in the prime of their careers their kind of
So
You know their daughter is not a great Target
Either
And their admin admins who work in the Venture Capital industry cuz it's such a purse
Prestigious job
Are often women who are in their 50s and
Again
Not women
Who were in my target demo so
We would
Preempt
.
By showing videos
Inviting these investors
Just some of our pop up show them who the customer was
So that they really got a son
For who we were catering to
That there's been a lot of
A lot of attention recently to
Chilling
Roguish culture of
Venture capital in Silicon Valley and
And how women are are finally in a public leaving
Come out and talk more about
Their experiences
Did you experience some of that
Culture in espresso
I
Through the process of building
Renttherunway was sexually harassed
I'm by one individual
And I'm happy to
Share that experience
However I will say that
I've had interactions with
Dozens and dozens event
Capitalist
Doesn't the firm's and
This was to
Just one individual
So
The
Far far far majority of my interaction
Have been
Incredibly positive but I
It was in a situation once where I was kind of
Proposition sent sexual text messages
Trying to raise my Rent the Runway
While I was building the company yes from someone in the investor Community sending you text messages like
Let's go on a date or whatever it was
God and things that are more explicit than that
Toot Toot Tootsie together
I was
I thought that it was
Inappropriate and enter fairly bizarre given that it was happening over text message so there was
Evidence created
Now there was also
You know conversations that were happening
In person
That
We're also threatening and
Very bizarre
Did you just
Ignore it was there anything you could have
Did you feel like you could really do anything about it except just ignore
So I initially
Ignored it
And
That was the plan
I was planning on ignoring it in
You know
Decided you know I was going to keep it silent
And then
This person
Decided to
You call one of my board members of on the phone
And so you know
Jen never
Response to me
And I think that this is a real problem and
She's a really unresponsive CEO and she's probably she's doing this to me she's probably doing this to other people and
He really challenged my
Behaviorist a CEO
Actually that board member
Came into my office to give me
Feedback
And say I need to be more responsive
Which
Was
My instantaneous reaction was
Oh my God I can't believe
Set this person after being rejected by making me sexual advances is now trying to ruin my career
And just a minute
How Jen handled that
Very tricky situation
I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to one of our sponsors who helps make this podcast possible
Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms
Fisheries in Rancho
Bring you all the ingredients you need
Create an
Credible home cooked meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered right to your door weekly
In a refrigerated box
ReDiscover how fun cooking can be
While enjoying specialty ingredients
Exploring new flavors and cuisine
Get your first
3 Blue Apron meals for free plus free shipping by visiting blueapron.com built
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So in those early days if Rent the Runway
Jenn Hyman face
The situation where
One of our investors was
Harassing her
When she ignored his advances
Took it out on her
He actually complained about her to a member of her board
Board member ask Jen about it
She decided to be totally transparent about what was going on
I
I showed this board member the text messages
At that time
Basically
You know ask my board member
How how they like me to respond
What do board member say
I mean the board member was shocked
I bet
I proceeded to tell everyone else in my board
As well as some
Key executives
We're working with me at Rent the Runway at the time
The board was unbelievably
Supportive
And we decided that we were
Not going to do business anymore with this individual or his firm
So there's that form of sexual harassment and I think that that's a lot of what's been getting recent media coverage
But yeah
End
Hopefully by nature of a lot of very brave women
Speaking out right now
That sort of sexual harassment will be
Be stamped out of
The industry in one way that I think over time
That it needs to be stamped out as bi
Diversifying
The sources of capital making sure that 50
80% of investors
Are women but let's put that aside just
4 second
The second form of
Sexual
Harassment
Flask
Gender discrimination is
Way more subtle
And it's way more difficult
But for instance
Overall
I have seen mail founders
Receive
You know sometimes
More mentorship
Or
More
Chances to be
Successful they get more
Strikes against them before their investors kind of pull the plug
In a lot of cases
Women are only given
You know it's a one Striker you're out
The CEO and founder
There are situations where
I've now come to understand that a lot of how deals get done
And how companies let they get acquired is
Someone is saying so
Something like oh you should really meet this guy he's a Visionary he's incredible yet
Get to know him
And I think across-the-board more of those
Comments are being made about male entrepreneurs than they are about phenological
Zwiazek
Society
Feel uncomfortable
Using the words Visionary or brilliant
To describe women
That's not always intentional I think it's
Ingrained in people
I would say nin in a lot of different instances
People have actually genuinely been trying to be helpful
Timmy like
There was a time early in my career where
And invest
Firm
Beto sesame
OG and you know you should really meet these other
Entrepreneurs are around
Your own age their brilliant you could learn alot from them
They're building incredible companies they're going to change the world now all of those
Entrepreneurs were men and they were kind of prefaced
Is brilliant etcetera
And
The same firm never introduced me in that same way to the same entrepreneurs even though we were at similar tenure
Your aunt
Similar stages in our company
The irony is a lot of those guys
Are businesses
You know aren't around any
And
You know I'm the one who still chugging
No I don't think that they were
Trying to be intentionally sexy
It's just that
There's a shade to which we all operate
That puts women at a bit of a disk
It's really amazing menu
It it it speaks to the
This like perception of
Apparent
Set that's so prevalent
In the in the pantry
I think that those power dynamics
Exist in so many different into
Mystery up and
I don't think that it's just
Silicon Valley or technology
Problem
Enough
Why
I think that the more
Egregious
Sending you a text message in the middle of the night
Asking to
To sleep with you sort of
Sexual harassment
Hopefully
Can
Beast
Stamped Out via just
Being more vocal about it
I think so that the more subtle form of
Harassment /
Discrimination or just lack of Opera
Trinity
Is actually the harder problems
Solve this problem is
It's the reason why
Only 4% of venture capital dollars are going towards women and
You know very very
Few investors are women
So you know we need to fundamentally
Diversify
Who has access to power who has access to Capital
In order to get a diversity of ideas and entrepreneurs out there
Yeah yeah
Obviously you have had incredible success despite
The challenges
That you faced and women in in in Texas
As you sort of
Begin to develop as a leader as a CEO
How did you
How did you make that transition how did you figure out how to manage lots of
I think that
It is a continuous work in progress
I had never manage people across the diversity of functions that we have it Rent the Runway
Rent the Runway is primarily a technology and Logistics
If 1200 employees 10 employees are in my fashion Department
And
You know
Hundreds are in my Logistics Department hundreds are in my engineering department
And these are areas
In which I had no experience
End
You know one thing that I've learned is that
Leadership
Evolved over time for small being a leader of a 1200 person company is different
Then being a leader of 100% company
And so I have to really evolve even though I've had the same title
4/8 + years like
There's so many things.
You know I've done wrong along the way
And I think that the thing that has
Made me grow and develop is
The recognition of
Failure
End
Desire to
Improve in the
The desire to get better
I don't want
People to have the impression that this was all
You know you
Freda From Success to success.
Easy never know
Low points
Because it would have been like with any comfort
And in 2015
You got some
Tough press
About
Some people who left
Company
They were quotes newspapers calling it a Amin culture and
And
And things like that from
From some of these employees
After that
Which would hurt by reading that stuff with some people were
Criticizing you and and your and your manager
Style
It was
The most difficult experience of my life actually
It was such a difficult time
Cuz
As a woman
There's two things they could really call you as a woman
They could call you the B word
Or they could say you're an idiot
And I've never really had a
Had a fear of someone calling me an idiot
But I do value myself
For how I try
Treat others
So to be called mean
N2
You know
Be quoted as having a Mean Girls culture at the company
Was so
Unsettling and
Sad and
Arbol de me
Cuz it's the thing that's the most important to me
Pino
What had been happening at the time was
The company was going through
Quite
Painful and difficult transition
From being a
You know
One phase of a startup to trying to develop some sense
Entering our teen years are adolescent years and I started
To realize
That I needed to make the tough calls and
Fire some people
That
Was very unsettling to
Because
We give men permission
As leaders and a CEOs to make the tough choices you know with women
We don't give them as much permission
To make those tough decision
And we often when when we do make those decisions are often labeled as
The b word or no
Etc
So
It certainly was a low point but
It led to the biggest outpourings
Of the port of ever had it led to more courage around
My own decision making
Because
I led the company into the best place it's ever been
And in a sense it makes
The future less scary because that article or a version of it it will come out again
And the next time it comes out
It's just not going to have the same impact
On me
You mentioned earlier in the interview how
You always wanted to
Run a successful company
Start a successful company but also have a family in and a kid and you did that Yoo-hoo
You have a child and a partner and
How have you
Figured out how to
To do in the way you wanted to do
First of all let's backtrack to being 28 and having the idea for run the runway and I just want to tell the real story
Gray hair
Because I think that a lot of women to go through this and end
They don't talk about it
One of the major considerations that I had
In starting Rent the Runway
Was
Is this a smart idea for me
Has if Rent the Runway is successful
Will I ever be able to get married
I was always confident that I would
Turn Rent the Runway into a
Consumer behavior that millions of people did and that I would be able to
You know I still believe we're going to build a multi-billion-dollar company
But
At the very very beginning when renttherunway launched
I had been dating someone from Harvard Business
The school who I was very much in love with
And
The day that
Renttherunway came out and we were on the front page of the New York Times
Broke up with me shortly thereafter
And he told me
That
Realized
That he didn't want to be with his equal
So that was really
Sad and disheartening cuz I was very in love with this person
And that's what led into this
Fear
No it ended up that the sphere was
Wheatley
Unfounded and I had no issues
You know Falling in Love
While building Rent the Runway I just think that
It
It paralyzed me
What was the number one priority in my life has
Always been having a family and having kids
So
The amount of happiness that I have now
Having a daughter I just got back from maternity leave last week
I'm
Engaged to the love of my life I can't even describe to you
The
Level of joy that it brings into my life on a daily basis
To truly
Have all of my dreams have come true
Plaster you guys
Pad Thai
You became profitable which
I should point out
Exceedingly rare so quick
And I mean your
Revenues
Over a hundred million dollars
La Quinta
Public reports
Devaluation of cumpys I don't even know what it is do you know what it is
I do know what it is
Yeah but it's
It's probably higher than you ever met
Even though it it it made
Still be on paper
This thing that you belts
Unnn Jenny built
Have made both of you rich
Show me you are even though babe
Paper you are rich your rich person
Did not grow up
Well being rich on paper is very different than being rich and reality so let's talk in a few years
Because
I didn't grow up sing I want to found a company
I had this idea for Rent the Runway I saw that it was mission-driven I saw that it was driving self confidence and making women
Feel incredible about themselves and I knew
But I had to commit my life to that
And I'm really proud
That
We have had
Many
Different women leave Rent the Runway and then raise their own venture capital and start their own companies and go out
After their own dreams
And
Jenny and I
2 years ago
Decided
Start a foundation
Where we've raised
Millions of dollars
To support
Other female entrepreneur
Scaling their companies and we've now helped
Thousands of women throughout the United States
In scaling their organizations
So
This mission
Empowering women and making women feel confident is the actual thing that I care about
Now
If it happens to be
That Rent the Runway
Brings me
The ability to provide for my family and thank my parents
That would be wonderful but honestly if it amounts to nothing
It is the absolute best experience of my life and I would do it over a million times
Jenn Hyman founder of Rent the Runway by the way her co-founder Jennifer Fleiss recently left the company
It was amicable
Both Jen and Jennifer each own 13%
Of the company
Put them on the Forbes list of the richest self-made women to watch
Renttherunway isn't just profitable
It's also become America's single largest dry cleaner
Dresses from 500 different designers
Including though it took a while to convince her
Diane Von Furstenberg
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things that
Your building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors American Express open
Every week on how I built this we bring you stories about entrepreneurs who beat the odds overcame obstacles and made there
Ideas happen
It's never easy and that's why American Express open wants to help with money and know-how
So you can turn your ideas into impact
Get business done
Learn more
Open.com
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that my name is Dustin Haugen
We live here in Seabrook Texas
Southeast Houston Texas up on a ranch and so he spent a lot of time Outdoors
Age of 10 or 11 his parents started to let him hike in the woods
I am self
And since I was a little kid I was obsessed with survival kits
But I would go to any store anywhere I would always go immediately to the survival kit section
He started to design some of his own survival gear and eventually
He got a job with the Texas state guard in the story that you hear all the time when you do this case studies of people
Who are in survival or emergency accidents as if they were never expecting to get into it
So you need some tools on you it just in case something happens will there be a natural disaster
Or an emergency that happens while you're out doing outdoor activity
You need to have those things on you at all times
But most people just
Don't have those things on them at all times I mean most people do not want to carry
Bulky survival kit around on a daily basis
They don't in the morning Coco
When they going to work put on their survival kit it's awkward it's weird
And people don't like to think about that
So two years ago Justin started to design a survival belt that you could wear everyday weather
Where you were heading into the woods or you know just
Going out to walk the dog
So when you think about a belt you think it has to be comfortable and it has will still be fashionably appealing
So the number one goal is to make sure that everything fits comfortably
And does not weigh too much or doesn't look weird so setsuna started to research
How to make this belt
He found out that
Someone else was working on virtually this same thing and that person lived about 15 minutes away
So Dustin contacted and he said hey if you know let's work together
It turns out that other guy was a former engineer at NASA
So they decided to partner up
They called a bunch of meals they found a military grade webbing for the belt
And I may have to figure out how to make
Survival tools small enough
To fit into it we had some
Invent every single small part of most
So the foil is a custom foil the duct tape as a custom duct tape
The water container is a custom water container all of the the parts and pieces
Required us to go out and test the heck out of it Justin and his partner worked with almost 30 manufacturers to
Custom Design every miniature Gadget that goes into the belt
High quality button compass
Purification tablets
It doesn't weigh a ton it's really hard to believe but if you put it on you wouldn't know you're wearing a bunch of survival stuff
Last year Dustin and his partner Nick decided to launch a Kickstarter to get the whole business going
They were hoping to raise $15,000
But they raised a quarter of a million dollars so right now they are
Extremely busy fulfilling pre-orders and getting them shipped out but they're still experimenting with the belt and test
Testing it out and Dustin says he wears it every single day
We were never dating only days I don't wear it is on laundry day when I don't have belt loops because I'm wearing shorts
Pajamas or something but otherwise
We are we are our biggest testers
It's Dustin Hoggard of Seabrook
Texas
His company is called Wazoo survival gear and his product is called the
The cash belt
Is available online
And you can read more about why do survival gear on our Facebook page just search
How I built this
Facebook
Of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org we love
During what you're up to
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or you might hear previous episodes
You can go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us.
Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want send a tweet it's at how I built this
Our ship was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with original music
Composed by ramtin Arab Louie
Thanks also to neva Grant Santa's meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
Ron NPR
Gregory Warner here to tell you about NPR New international podcast called rough translation
Each week where to take you to a different country to hear a story that reflects back on something that we are talking about here in the United
States
Maybe get a perspective shift
Travel with us
Rough translations on NPR one or wherever you get your
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
It's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com