Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign monitor
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days away
Campaign monitor.
We started out essentially designing this little game we
Working things out of wood and painting it so it looks like plastic but it was really would
Our idea was to take it to the Toy Show in New York
People like this is amazing world we sold 0
From NPR it's how I built this a show of activators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories
Behind the movement
Bushnell took his love arcade game
Facts that shape the childhoods of millions of Americans
If you grew up in the US in the 1980s
Then you were probably playing a little bit of
Best then when your birthday rolled around
Maybe you celebrated you know
Like this
Very iconic sounds Chuck-E-Cheese
The pizza joint with the games that gets you distracted for hours
And an Atari video game which could
Frankly distract you for a lot longer
Dave brat
Incredible
Is it both of these childhood experiences
Who created by the same
Persimmon seed
He found it at re just a
Few years out of college and he started Chuck-E-Cheese just a few years after that
Inferno one
The kid in Utah in the 1950s
Start a very simple lesson about business
The dinner one night Mom said boy we've got so many strawberries
We're not going to be able to eat them all
Baby wasp will give them away
I didn't think that much about it the next day I happened to go to the
Grocery store weather
And I saw that in the store in the grocery store
They were selling strawberries
First 50 Cent
The basket
I looked at that
I said
That's what the market is
So
Went home
Found all the
Extra little baskets
Were around the house
Went out picked a bunch
Strawberries
And went up and down this
Selling
The strawberries
For a discount offer
Grocery store with c
And I sold out
An hour
I mean I don't even think I made it all the way to the end of the block
And all of a sudden I had more money
Then I would make an allowance
And mowing lawns per year nice
It's a young entrepreneur
Yeah
And I read that like later on when you were in college
You worked at
Carnivals
That's correct
I started out
Actually on the Midway
Selling balls to knock down Milk Milk Bar
Man guessing
People's ages weights
And occupy
And jumping Kearney
Cyclic shouting at people like come on down
You got it
Band
And
I found out that I was kind of
Kind of good at it
How do you get into arcade games that start
At the carnival
Yes
That was sort of
Where I
God indoctrinate
Because you end up
What people don't realize how much
Coin-operated
Games
It's actually quite surprising
And so
When you look at
Each of the coin-operated games as a little busy
Typically you go into the
Joe's Cafe and say can I put my machine in your location
Then I'll split the income
These locations
This would very often do 100 to $200 a week at that time
Pinball machines there were mechanical games
But yeah no video games
Then I was working
Summers at the amusement park Winters
Pursuing an engineering degree at the University of
And wow
One day I saw
Steve Russell spacewar
What's that
A guy named Steve Russell at
MIT
Programmed this game called
Space War
And
I was mesmerized
Rice pot
More context
My brother says I got to show you something that will knock your socks
Pieces
Meet me at 1 at the Merrill engineering
I say 1 in the afternoon on Houston open all night
And so show up at the Merrill Engineering Building
And there was space worm he handed me a box that had four buttons on the top
Rotate left rotate right buyer
And hyperspace
Those were the controls
And we played
Until
Literally 5 in the
And I thought
Wow
If I could put this game in my arcade
It would make money
But then you divide a $0.25
Play into a
Half a million dollars
Computer in the math 2
But I did think to myself maybe someday
The cost will come down
And this would be cool
So you graduate college I guess I'm like the lights
And and what did you do did you you're in Utah did you start a business or did you decide to
Where did you go
My wife's sister lived in Silicon Valley
And
I was a little bit of an anarchist
At that time
Call me a lapsed Mormon or failed Mormon or whatever
And I kind of wanted to get out of Utah and see the world
And so California seems like
Cool place to go
So
That Thanksgiving we drove to
California stayed with
My wife's sister
And I paper the street with two of my resume
And got a job at Ampex
An Empire
Expose
Electrical
Who invented the videotape machine
And instant replay
I worked there for 2 years
But about
18 months in
I discovered
Egg
Computer that looked like it was fast and
To do a video
So you're thinking
Start something
It started out a little bit as a research project and then I said yeah I'm going to start something you didn't
When I was
Driving down the Sierras towards Silicon Valley I told my wife I said you know in 2 years I mean
Start my own company
I just knew that was kind of on my trajectory I didn't know if that time
Who's going to be a video game company I just thought I'd do it you know and in the back of my mind and I always kind of had the
I think I've always had it since 8
Why didn't you start this computer company dislike game company
My office mate was a guy named Ted that me this was a damn pics and I said I'm just started company
Former partnership we had this computer and the computer was
Mind-numbingly slow and
In order to make the economics work the computer cost like $5,000 free games at the time
I needed to be less than $1,500 so the way I was going to do it as I was going to die
Timeshare that one computer across three
Screens with three coin slots on a belt that I could get
$1,500 that way you were trying to design basically what would become an arcade machine like
Moschino be installed somewhere
People put in a quarter and they could play a game
Where did you install this Arcadian where was it
We put it in a bar
Call the Dutch Goose it was in Menlo Park it was right next to Stanford University
The game was
Smash Hit at the Dutch Goose I license the game to a company called money Associates
And
Realize that it did really well on college campuses so
I mean it sold a couple million dollars in
Units
Which was
Tumi
A big hit
But to the industry was kind of a mediocre
QWOP
I had a 5% royalty and so that was a
You know
$100,000
Masamune smite
Put this in context
I came to work at Ampex for $825 a month is
Associate engineer
How did you fund
The company from the beginning what did you have to go to outside investors and ask them for money
No
This was also
It's a time when venture capital
Was just getting started
And so
Ted put in $250 I put in $250 and that's all the money that went in
Atari 500 bucks
Atari
I'm in your first game was
Was a flop so how did you guys
Patrick is going to do the neck
Well
Then came
Bow Wow corn which was our first
Technical employee
Cuz we were growing and we needed to get some more.
And I gave him a
Simplest game
Like it's think of
Which was a ping pong table
When you think you're going to be in the video coin-operated video game
You write down every sport
You can think of every constructs
And ping pong was one of them
And you went off
And
He basically had
Twerking
Where to eat
It was
Really
Quick
And we are talking about what of course became
Tongue
Which was just like two lines with a ball bouncing around a screen between those lines
Correct
And
It turned out
I thought it was going to be a throwaway
Yeah there was just a training
And it just
Turned out to be fun we were staying
After work.
Play the damn game
And then I get the idea
Maybe Valley wants this game
Ballyhoos also a big coin operated game
Player
Out of Chicago
Getting the airplane fly to Chicago I have a little mock-ups that I can a portable unit
And I showed to them
And they don't like it
It's a two player game
And the coin operated world doesn't allow
For two player game if there's not a one player
At that time
That was sort of
Written in stone somewhere
Annals of quintus
World
Kind of dejected
On the way to get on the airplane to come back to California
I get a call from you
Who was the engine
And they had a service call
Cuz they
Put a basic pong game in a cabinet
And
Put it in a bar and the game
Became so popular that it filled up
The coin box lid couldn't take any more quarters
So I think to myself
Maybe I don't want Valley to happen
Because the math were so outstanding
Little Machines could literally pay for themselves
I mean the game was earning
Almost $300
Weak wow
And the total cost
That we had
Was about to
So you're thinking maybe we should just message me the machines and
Lens license
Exact
So is that what you did
So that's exactly what we did I looked at all the cash we had
And we have enough cash.
Build
Like 12 units
You know the minute I got off the airplane
Disability
The order for the parts
And we were Off to the Races
Get on the phone
I have
Literally orders coming in from all over the nation
What about pain today in its 2
Basic
Yeah rudimentary
Damn it in the context of the early 70s revolutionary
Absolutely
Put it in context
People would come to me and say
How does the
The TV station know that I turned it off
Nn
Clearly they're construct was it if there's something on a TV screen
Game from studio somewhere
And so that was kind of the
Constructs
That we were dealing with
But
You know there's there's actually some.
Interesting psychology
Looking back on it
And one of the reasons that I think Pawn
With such a massive success
Is that it
Fed into the narrative
Of what was going on at the
Time
You know just after the Summer of Love
The hippie movement
Women's Liberation was was starting to rear its head
And
Pain by its structure
Made it
Ladies choice
Because
Kim very acceptable for a woman to
Tampa guy
Sitting at the bar
Unshorn say
I want to play Pong would you like to play All by
Who knew pong's ruffle in the history of women's Liberation exactly
Nolan Workwear companies
Just calling you or establishments
Just calling you
That was
And so
Orbitz
Bibleman is we had no Factory we had no systems we had no procedures we have no employees I mean we have
There were four of us
And you guys are all in your like
Mid-to-late twenties
And in fact I think was 23 he just he just graduated from Berkeley
And we had a thousand square foot roll up which we thought was huge with six
What time is it
This was in Santa Clara California then we found out that we had a real problem
We could build these games literally into days like literally my hand with Wooten nada.
But we had neglected to buy shipping cartons
We couldn't ship them on common carrier
And so to solve that problem
We bought an old furniture truck and started making deliveries without cartons to Los Angeles
But usually driving down the 101 or something
Yeah but
Slowly we were able to get procedures in place we were able to
Get systems
And how we Finance
The company was we would sell for cash
The machine
We have 30 day terms
Most of our parts we had 68 terms so we can get the cash
Literally 60 days before we had to pay for the parts
Meditite
How many of these
Arcade pong machine
Out there and
Mm
Only if which
Atari only did about 35000
We got massively coffee
But you couldn't you couldn't prevent these companies from basically stealing your idea and copying you
I didn't have patents yet there was on those days patents were just
Swoboda
China
So there was no so basically you could do nothing
Nothing
And when we were copied
We knew we didn't
Havasu fishing to manufacture
We knew we didn't have as much money
We knew we didn't have as good a relationship
With the distributor chain
That the competitors that have been dealing with them
After 20 years
Dad
And so
I felt
My only tool
Was innovation
An understanding of the technology cuz
Copying the technology news and creating the technology
Different
So you were still not really proper
You were just kind of breaking even
Cash was always our limitation
And I tried to get
Neo investors
Everybody thought
What kind of flake
They thought who's going to pay for this thing
Exactly how did you
Even come up with the idea that maybe
We should sell this to
People and they could do it at home
One day we
Figured out
Is there was a new semiconductor
Technology called in Channel MOS and
These chips once they were designed you could buy him for five bucks
It occurred to us that we could put pong on a sink
Google trip
And hit a price point that would
Sell to the consumer
And how did you even begin to think of
Ways to do this cuz you gave me your you're talking about
Like
Building a cabinet for a
A giant
He just didn't like how do you shrink that down a house
Well
Once you had it on a single chip
Then it was just a matter of putting two knobs on a piece of
Plastic
We started out essentially designing this loaf
Game looking thing
Atwood
The painting it's a little look like plastic but it was really would
Ideal
Was to take it to the Toy Show in New York
Disa toys at toy convention like like 7475
And you should look like this is amazing world
And it was a great demo on everything
But we didn't know
Is it
The toy business at that point in time
Did not sell anything
That was more than 35.
And how much were you
You selling this
Atari console
Which in 1935
It was a lot
And so we thought
Spent all this money to get this
Think developed
Our neighbors wanted
And they were happy to
Spend 70
Did you leave that Toy Show feeling
Dejectedly
Who's abject failure must have been pretty
Depressed sfter Pinellas money of this thing
I don't
I'm not easily depressed
But I'm very easily challenge
And I said you know
There's something not right here
We just haven't found the right guy
What do you mean you haven't found the right guy
The right distribution Channel
To be so you're thinking these guys are wrong I know this is going to work at exactly
Exactly I said these guys
You're missing a wonderful Opera
And so we were thinking
RadioShack of sinking
TV dealerships
I was thinking all kinds of stuff
And then
My head of sales
Thought about
Sears
Sporting Goods
And
The previous year
Sears Sporting Goods really focuses on
The inclement weather family room
And they sell pool tables
And ping pong tables
Things like that
The year before they had
Made
The consumer
Pinball machine
For $200
And they sold out
So
My sales guy said maybe these guy
Tyson so he calls up the buyer at Sears 40
It's a song that's kind of interesting
The next day
He was honored
And they were based in Chicago at the time
They were based in
Chicago fire comes to
Find out
Comes and says I want to see what
Your
Exactly
And that we actually had to scramble cuz we didn't realize he was coming he didn't say am showing up
He just showed up
And so we were in the car for
Resume if that is okay
Do that how many can you build
We didn't have
Because we were rebuilding coin-operated games you know
Where a big run with 5000
We kind of do it
Automax put check on
And so we did a huddle outside
I had my
It's so not wanting to be sole source
I said we can do about 7
You go back to the Sears guy and say we could do 75000 after your own guy tells you
Yeah okay
Yeah I kind of corny
He give us an order 450
And
He want some delivery by Christmas by you know october-november basically
6 months
To to build a factory
The Train the personnel
To sort out the technology
Naruto has anybody in Atari freaking out at this point
Everybody is
Nolan bushnell founder of Atari when we come back
After the Freak Out
The real work begins plus a side hustle that brought together pizza games 10 day
Gyros near listening to how I built this NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible first to Blue Apron
Blue Apron partners with sustainable Farms fisheries and ranchers to bring you all the ingredients you need to create
Incredible home cooked meals
Ingredients compared with an easy-to-follow recipe card delivered right to your door weekly in a refrigerated
ReDiscover how fun cooking can be
While enjoying specialty ingredients and exploring new flavors and cuisine
Get your first three Blue Apron meals for free
Plus free shipping
Exiting blueapron.com
Splash built
Thanks also to upwork upwork is the largest freelancing website connecting businesses with top web and mobile
Calipers designers writers and other Freelancers ready to lend a hand
Over a million businesses are getting more done by finding hiring and paying Freelancers through upwork
Learn how you can get more done with Freelancers and Save
$100
On your first project
Upwork.com NPR
Who sang all this month we are asking our listeners
To tell other people about podcast
Especially podcast that you love or podcast you think
They might live
So if you know somebody who doesn't listen to podcast
Listen to podcast but doesn't listen to the one you like
Tell them about it
Even better show them how to download a podcast
And then tell us what you've been recommending
Use the hashtag
Tripod that's try
Pod
And thanks
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR I'm guy Raz
It's 1975 Nolan and his Partners have gotten a huge order from Sears to make a
Consumer version of pain
Insulin need to figure out how to build a manufacturing chain
Virtually
Overnight
We sit down
And we say okay if we were to build
How would we do it
But then
The big question
How much money are we going to make
After we spend all this money on the factory and we rely
We didn't learn
So I call it
The serious buyer and say I ate do this to you
I'm going to have to up the price what was the price that he wanted to
We were
Quoting a retail price of 59 and we decided that we needed an extra twenty bucks
Per unit and he said
That's okay
Like I can do
Then I went through the math and there was no way
That I had enough Capital to put in the conveyor belts to rent the extra
Sorry
To buy the parts and I calling up in a skillet
I really appreciate the word but I said I can't find this
Don't worry I'll introduce you to seers bank
And so
Sears Bank set up a
Bonded Warehouse
The end of the conveyor line in so as soon as
Babe consumer pong dropped off the assembly line they would Advance us
80%
Of the contract price with Sears
Donaldson
The Atari console that you were building only play Pong
And did you get it to them in time under 50000 consoles by Christmas
We did
In fact I think that year we sold almost a hundred eighty thousand they took them all
Wow
I mean at this point
You cry guess
See you guys in Benfica
Home
Computer game
Exactly
And then how did you go from making one console to play one game 2
AKA home video game system that played a bunch of games
Well we realized
At that time
When we were doing the
One game $70
That this was an interesting
Business
An end
Then
Magical thinking
A
Semiconductor Company in Silicon Valley came up with the
Microprocessor
That they were willing to sell us for $8 and all of a sudden
Their eyes were opened and we said
We can do
Von Neumann architecture program based put cartridges with ROMs in it
And we can have a program book
That microchip allowed you guys to be sleep create a
Cartridge system that week
What's the steam turn out right
Exactly
You know it was just a magic time
For technology
Silicon Valley
Time
You were as likely
To learn about a new technology standing on the sidelines
Of your kids Little League
As you were
Any other time
In several times
I'd be talking about Echo
Problem we were having with
With the
One of the other parents
Oh yeah
We had chip like that in
Development
Would you like a prototype
It's not going to be really on the market
For 6 months and I take
Yeah we we don't need production quantities for 6-month
You're not going to get that if you're
A technology company in in Oshkosh
Where I mean were there many companies
Insulting Valley the time that we're
I can't think of another one
We kind of always felt like we were the sleazy
Company who
Focusing on fun instead of all this
How many more
Megabytes can you get on a hard drive with the Sirius company is where they
Grateful Dead
We liked our
Rebel status
And we were Rebel in it several ways first of all we were all young
I was the youngest CEO and people didn't know
But think about a CEO in their twenties then we that was just off the radar
And I actually feel like I paved the way for Gates and jobs and some of the
Idea that you can be young and still a serious businessman
But more than that we got known as a real party culture because
Instead of bonuses since all our employees were in their early twenties
We have a beer bust on the back dock
And you get in
$100 for the pizza into kegs
And you had a party but that was totally unheard of and course we had a game room and we have ping pong tables
Stuff that
Silicon Valley kind of thinks is
Deer ignoring unnecessary now
Yeah it was very very different
And then we didn't have a dress code we didn't have
Turn clocks we had this attitude that
Everybody knew what they needed to do and
They were adults and they could wear what they want and they could come and go when they want and
We weren't Big Brother
Iran so we try to make this meritocracy
In which outcome
Was the only thing we counted
Is a young CEO
I think you did a good job where you
You know where you
Are you a good manager of people
The time
So so
I think I was a good manager of people I think that
I always had a little bit of an inferiority,
Amplex internet
Because my age
I felt a little bit like a poser
Which was okay with me on some level because of my Carnival background
But at the same time
I always felt
That I didn't know what the hell I was doing
And what I didn't realize has the most big companies don't know what the hell you doing
I wasn't mature enough to understand that
All companies are somewhat screwed up
Did unnu clearly you like head and I-4
You could have I for hiring interesting people I mean I think anyone knows a little of the story
Steve Jobs and Steve Wozniak
Work for you
Steve Jobs work for me
And he was a technician
In quality control use
Really good at it
I can remember him coming insane
Knowing if you allow these kinds of solder joints you're going to have
Failures in the field
Did you already tell like that
Yeah we think of him as a server Mercurial kind of
Impetuous leader was he like that even as a
20-something kid
He was opinionated but he was never wrong
In his opinion
You didn't have to worry if you empowered Steve to do something
It happened
I mean Steve had one speed
It was full on
And so
He got the
The Apple going and he came to me and says I want to start this
And I'm going to be leaving do you want to be
My first investor and I'll give you a third as a company for $50,000 and you said of course
Yeah I did not say that
I've regretted it but you know anyway
It was fun times
Exactly
Doesn't matter it would have ruined my life would have made you
Totally insufferable and I was already in Suffern
Goodness you did not
Take that deal
Exactly so all right so you're running Atari
Doing really well
And then what you decide to sell it
So I felt that we had to take the company public
Drai's
15 million dollars
It seems pulp right now but that
Was all the money
In the world to us
Time
And
The market Hiccup and they said because there's just no way we're going to do it and a little 70
This was the summer
Summer of 76
And all the sudden we had Christmas coming and I knew I didn't have enough money
Even with Sears
To be able to
Get this
New
Massive
We wonderful product into the market
Replace this is that the Atari console with the
What cartridges
Yes that's correct
So
Without an ability to
Do that I said maybe it's time to get a corporate partner
And so I started Dialing for Dollars from corporate partner Warner communication
Showed up and said will not only put up the money but we'd like to buy you and will
Pay you money and will put money into the company and you will get this big royalty stream
And we understand producen we're going to link arms and March into the sunset
And what was the 28 million bucks
I mean you know I was born boy from Utah I mean you could buy a Learjet in those days for milk
So you took the money
Took the money
And so what happened to oh so you continue to work for a Target that point
That's a lie was not as rigorous
Is I had been
I started started taking care of my personal life instead of my business life
And I found that there were a lot of decisions that were being made that will really
Really pretty toxic
Decisions about
Where to take the company
Yeah and slowly we
Brought in a president of
Consumer
Who had
All the hierarchy
No Reserve
Turkey places
Executive dining room
And all the things
That were enactment
Yeah you're going from keg parties on your loading dock to an executive dining room
Yeah and I just thought that was so
Wrong on so many levels because
I don't think you need to
Arbitrarily create an us-versus-them mentality in your company you know and
One of the things that happens when your own by New York company
They think that you're laid back Style
Is that you're not working so hard and they think the people that come in at 10 should be fired
And so the bottom of a sudden there was this Clash of cultures
That got to be really ugly and ultimately they they got tired of me and I got tired of them and
I was fired how long so so between time they bite you in the time that you were ousted
How long was it
20 months
Wow that must have been tough. For you
Actually not
I kind of you business
Like the game of chess you play the game you play hard sometimes you win some
When you set up the pieces Newport or again and you don't have eggs oh my God
Watch the game of chess what am I going to do what was me and what that allows you to do
Do is to view a little bit of sand outside or from yourself things that happened to you
So when something doesn't work out that well you can say G that was
Horrible but it was an interesting experience
Okay LNG stock oversight because
This episode
And here I would say okay that's Nolan Bushnell Visionary who founded Atari
We are not going to talk about the second company you founded which is Chuck-E-Cheese
Yeah how did that happen how did how do you even come up with this concept
Well
Math
Is very simple
Before I sold Warner we were selling games these are coin-operated
We were selling them for about $1,500
During their lifetime in coin drop
They turn 30 to 50000
So it didn't take rocket science
Meant to say I'm on the wrong side of the
Equation
I need
To be operating
These things 2 app
Stent
But I didn't want to compete with
The guys I was selling to
So I decided I had to
Create my own location
I thought to myself
What are people going to
Come to this freestanding arcade
And I decided that
Adding food would be
A benefit
Because in families could come
And that
Indicated
Pizza because there was weight
And that would be good game playing time
When we was still mulling this whole concept
Around
I went to Disneyland and went to the teacher
Oh yeah and I said
Can do this my guys can make these
Creatures can animate things
Then
I realized that I really wanted to have
Branded mask
And that I wanted it
The longer
Perform entertainment
I figured
Kids are going to be wanting to play the games parents are going to be bored
The more I can entertain them unless they're getting anybody there
Believe so I said
Let's do some animated Skits the whole idea was to make it seamless
Not have labor costs just make it happen
So anyway I went to a amusement tradeshow bought a costume
Look up costume that they live like a human. Your guys are just
Turn into an animated robot Chuck-E-Cheese which was
A rat's right what restaurant is going to pick a rat as their mascot and think that's going to work
Well understand when I bought the costume I thought I was buying a Coyote Ugly
The code the code name was coyote Pizza in my guys I said how's the coyote coming is a
What kind of acid will the costume I sent you
Oh you mean the rat so all of a sudden we had a problem so I said okay
Will be coyote pizza anymore it's going to be regrets pizza and Rick rats Pizza that was going to be the name of
Who was Danny pizza place called Rick rats Pizza
That's exactly what my marketing department said and they said they said
No wipers no that's the stupidest idea I've ever heard they said we couldn't even know they'd be on the garden
You wouldn't get our help license plate
And I said okay you name it I don't care but it has to be a happy name right and so they came back all smiles
The next week
We've got the name it's a three smile name
Chuck-E-Cheese
So hot so what happened you you opened up your first location in Silicon Valley
Yeah it was it was basically in San Jose
Who took over
8 Old Dean Witter office and it was like five thousand square
What's huge
Compared to the pizza parlor
We knew the day we open
That we made a huge mistake
Wow you mean it was that popular
Massive
I mean Lions out
The door on a Monday
With your customers little kids who who's coming
Everybody but then we sold the company and Warner didn't want to be in the restaurant business
You you sold a tie to Warner
Chuck-E-Cheese with was kind of hard because you created while you're there so
For you to keep Chuck-E-Cheese you had to buy it back from them
Half a million dollars
500000 bucks by Chuck-E-Cheese and one open store
Door was Cash 4 and 1/2 million dollars a year and
They let me pay $100,000 for 5
And that was maybe the deal of a lifetime
I had this business that was positive cash flow day one well I was
Still chairman of Atari
And I I had a team of people that have been working on it I brought them on my payroll
And we immediately expanded to the second store this one was 25,000 square feet
And I was having more fun
Chuck-E-Cheese when I was having Charlie Charlie was getting political
So when we decided to
Part ways
Focus all my time on on Chuck-E-Cheese and I was going to happy about
Been pretty liberating to work on this thing that you know you were likes
You know sometimes
I feel that inadvertence
Shines on
Because
I hadn't even thought about franchise
I got came in
And said
I want to franchise
And we started franchising and so the franchise business was hugely
So how many Chuck-E-Cheese locations did you
Eventually
Franchise
I sold the company when we were about 280 stores
And half were franchises.
So we build by 220
And Francis
What what
Opposite of mistakes do you think you made
That you learn from
At Chucky
I think that I didn't understand
The nature of
Entertainment
Now that sounds funny coming from the amusement park and all that
But entertainment is very
Fragile
It's driven on
Novel
And so
When we were first open
A unit
People would come
From all around because it was off
So that was sort of the half-life of a shine
In which you say G you know this St Louis looks to me like I need
Ward Chuck E Cheese's
When in fact what you were seeing is this novelty bonus
And that
People in normal life
Didn't really want to come to Chuck-E-Cheese
Three times a month
They wanted to come to Chuck-E-Cheese
Every other month
We got over bill because
We got another false positive
Who's of pasta
That you could
Pack the place
365 days a year
In a population of 1000000 people
Which couldn't
It's it's amazing because
Did you
Build these two iconic
Companies
I mean
How many server many many people in America
Like to find the Contours of their childhood
And you've gone to
How to start
At least a dozen other companies
Some of what you've been spit
Killer failures and spectacular successes you've had
You have this amazing range of experiences on on both ends
I guess
I'm sure the successes were
More incredibly satisfying for
Provost reasons but
Do you think the failures were
Or should have more interesting or
Appeal time for you learned more about
Lifan about you in about
Business
There is no question
That
A good failure
Is good for your soul
There is nothing worse
Then feeling like
You are invincible
And really cool
And
Intitle
Being entitled
Probably
The ugliest
That a person can be
Because all of a sudden
It's not
What you do
It's who you are
And
People who rely on who they are
As opposed to what they
Baidu
Become
Very
Banal
How long does it take you to
To become Who You Are
To realize that that's
Well I hope that I'm not there yet
I want to stay on the Steep part of the learning curve
In fact I've even
Dunham methodology on it
II
Force myself
Do something
Totally outside my comfort zone every year
And I write down
11 things that I think I can accomplish in a year
That are
Outside my comfort zone
And then I mix them up
Put a number on them throw a pair of dice and I have to in that year
Do
What did Ice tell me to do
And I discovered
Funniest thing
Maybe it's just me but I think it's a generalized principal
But when you do different
Things you're happy
That this process of
Of expiration and up
Discovery
And a
Willie Wings
Out
The game and the metagame
Is very satisfied
If you were
Able to go back to like I mean now you are a
Elder Statesman of the tech world you're in your seventies and
If you could go back to
To Nolan Bushnell in the Olay
70s early 80s and say
Hey you know I want to give you some advice
What would you tell yourself
Boy that's a real hard
Cause
Some of the bad decisions I've
Made I'm not sure that I would like my wife
Tenotomy
Anthem
And I'm not sure
That if
I were to give myself advice
And change that projector
Free I would end up
Where I am right
And I like
Bryant
Tell me about what you're working on now
Well then I'll have to kill you
Nolan Bushnell is the founder of
Ari and the Chuck-E-Cheese exactly where can I find pretty cool stuff right now and put the company code
Which makes software designed to help students learn School subjects
Please don't turn this off
Just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you guys are building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors discover
Become a new card number and F
End of your first year
Discover will match all the cash back you've earned dollar-for-dollar
Learn more at discover.com
Match
Only for new cardmembers
Applications apply
Paperback and thanks for sticking around because now it's time for how you
Go back in the story comes to us from Denise Zimmer about
3 years ago she was planning her wedding near her hometown of Fair Lawn New Jersey 240
We guests 20 tables and $7,000
Just for the flowers
Just for the flower $7,000 and it was that frustrating feeling of
I'm spending all this money on something that
You know why I want to have but I don't want to be spending this kind of money on quite frankly anything that you know is going to be
He was trying to figure out how to cut down on the
Cost she thought about a friend who is getting married the very next day
So what I did was when I was talking to the forest I was asking them you know
Is it possible to you know maybe have her Reeves the flowers maybe we can do some sort of sharing and that was kind of that
Light bulb moment when I was like okay well the floor is it telling me that this can work and I know that I'll do it and I know that she'll do it
Okay so ultimately they need and her friend could not make it work it was too complicated
But she couldn't let go of this idea
So then what am I
And she start to search through wedding chat rooms
You have
Everyone just getting advice from each other and asking its who's in the same area can we share this can we do that and so
So I think that was
Another big moment of opening of customers you want to do this I'm not the only one who's wanted to share my flowers
A few months later Denise leaves her job at another startup
To start bloomerent
And that Brides In the same city could log on to a website and then share flower arrangements with
With other couples getting married on the very same weekend
Bay Beach get a discount on their flowers bloom Red where to get it cut of the florist fee and a florist wood
Make it really well to exactly so if you know for them they got to create those centerpieces once and sell them twice
But as neat started to put her website together and then reach out to florist in the New York metro area she was surprised
A lot of them said no literally every single person that you know this is a really good idea
Yeah and I love that you're reducing waste but I just don't want to do something new and that is both the most frustrating
In the world but it's also
Ian really motivating and so did he just kept at it her first paying client was a friend getting
Married in New Jersey
And then things just kind of Grew From there until one person who uses it and another person uses and they tell their friend who tells their
Our friend and since you started the company three years ago
Denise and her business partner have expanded Bloom rn214 cities
And two other events besides weddings
Right now all of their money is being plowed back into the business they're not paying themselves yet
But this year did he says
Bill open up the outside investors and those florist that couldn't get behind Bloom rent at the beginning
You know what's funny I do actually have that list I do have a small list of people that I am definitely planning on calling in
In the next year and I'm really excited to have those conversations
That's danitza mere to find out more about her company bloomerent pet or Facebook page just search how I built this
On Facebook and please do keep sending us your stories we love sharing them could tell us all about
Something is your building by visiting build
. NPR
. org that's filled with a d. NPR
. org thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to
Find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also consider subscribing to our show on
ITunes and vaporizers review while you're there
You can also write directly to us at Hib tea at npr dot O RG
And if you want to send a tweet it's at
How I built this
Usher was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to neva grandson of meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers are interned is Claire Breen on gyro
Rise and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week