Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Really quick before I start to show
If you are anywhere near the Washington DC area this
Thursday November 30th you will not want to miss you live taping of the show
My guest will be Robert Johnson
Founder of
Black Entertainment
Television
And the first African-American
Billionaire in US history
And then a week later
On December 6th
I'll be in
Atlanta to interview Arthur Blank
Co-founder of Home Depot and
The owner of the Atlanta Falcons
You haven't been to a live tape
Peeping at you
To check it out you'll meet
Tons of other
They're fans of the show
Other people starting their own businesses in Haiti
Come say hi to me in the
After the show
How I built this live is supported by
American Express open
Come see you this Thursday November 30th
DC
And next week
December 6
Atlanta
Get your tickets at NPR presents
. org
NPR
Presents.
Ord
Okay here's the show
There were days
It is possible this thing doesn't
Scale and it's possible we won't dig ourselves out
We can't keep up with the order so the issue was not that you were framing them badly but they're just
Oh yeah we were framing that perfectly just
Took too long
We started to see
Really angry
Mickey Mouse people saying like
This was the very special gift for my grandmother's 90th birthday and you ruined
And
It felt terrible
NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
Gyro House
Only spent $1,600 framing posters
And then turned her sticker shock into a more affordable idea
Cold Frame
So there are pieces of artwork
Hang up in my house that
Cost a lot less than what it cost to actually frame them
You know you drive
Story
Get the Madden
Frame glass and soon enough
You're down like four hundred bucks
Then if you're like me
Just stop framing stuff you end up turning a closet
In your house
Do you like a
Photos and artwork
Storage Center
And this is exactly the opportunity Susan time and saw about
5 years ago
When she start to think about how to make
Raining
Cheaper and
Now at the time Susan was already a veteran of a
Bunch of startups that mostly failed
Experiences
She figured out how to raise money to start framebridge and so far
Bringing more than 37 million dollars
But unlike a lot of the companies we had on the show
Framebridge is still in its building base it's still working to become a sustainable company
And Susan is still working like
Crazy still starting early
And still staying late
What you said
She got that work ethic from her dad
Who used to run a small Tugboat business
Meaning the little votes
That's how big us
And so it really operationally intense
Business
Our family really revered
His job and
When into providing for our family and then
We ate dinner at 7:30 because that's when Dad got home from work
That's so cool like
I'd never
Met anybody who's
Is there something just iconic an awesome about.
So are you know I certainly have
Been on my share of togs and I think
My ones had a party trick when I got to be a teenager was if we were an event downtown
And there's a Target on the water you know my dad would have them
Honk their horn when they went by us
So your dad and did you were you involved
In the business of all the Jew
I mean we pinch it I remember you know
Receptionist without we go in and answer phones for my dad and that sort of thing
We are certainly
This isn't like reverence for were
And what it took that it didn't come easy
Yeah I can just imagine my dad on vacations on the phone or
Are the phone ringing late at night and
If something goes wrong and
In a business that operationally intensive it's really gone wrong so
I remember that
Drama
Do you or did you grow up thinking
Entrepreneurial like I'm going to be an entrepreneur because
A Charming world around Saint jhn
I don't remember that
BMV Parma
Culture
No I think I lost my dad and I thought I was going to be the boss but
But I didn't
That wasn't like I'm going to be the boss and great things come with being the boss it was like and all the responsibility that comes with that
And soy
I guess I had that vision of a business career
He's but you said you didn't think I'm going to go to
Call Jeanette
Like a lawyer
No I did
And I certainly had a lot of ideas
None of which were great like there should be a pancake delivery service
But you know I was always thinking along those lines always solving consumer problems
Susan went on to study at the University of Virginia
And then she got a degree at Harvard Business School
She different toes into the
Startup world for a little bit
And then
She went to work at the White House during President Obama's first term
Battleground 2011
Susan once again
How to start a bug
So at the time
Some guys I had worked with previously
I had started to start up
In a hot new space called daily deals on soda company was called living social and I
Was watching them from afar
I was just jealous
Load it was social Groupon that was the daily deal thing in there still around
And you were
Seeing
Friends of yours
And you were thinking
I got to get into this I got to get on it I am so jealous like
Truly a joke
When when one of them called
And asked me if I wanted to join assertive Hadlock my desk packed up I was like I'm ready
Wow
Cheap a cup and you are like
Great I'm going to do this and what did you do at least
How it works with a sent emails with deals to local
Merchants and shops
And so they decided they would do some specialty ones
Hired a guy to run travel and heard meet
Do anything else
So I did
You don't first
Family-friendly deals
And then HomeServe
So like what kind of deals
Yasso deals for
You don't things like Gymboree and child care services and things like that things that a family might be interested
It in apple picking
And then it was just like what else could we sell into what other group
What was that
Time like cuz I I mean this and not that long ago were talking about like
67 years ago
I mean
I remember LivingSocial here in Washington DC
It was
YouTube
It just seemed like everyone is throwing money at it what was it like working at a time
It was really really exciting
Ghetto we were all really driven
We were all really bullish
We knew that
Eid mattered and in that case in that industry really
And so it was fun cuz we had to unlearn I had to unlearn some things I was coming right out of the White House I mean you had to
Like this email doesn't have to be checked by 10 people we just got to get it out the door and
That was exciting
It was like a gold rush
I didn't speak to you remember what LivingSocial is valued at
Now it's couple billion
Yeah
Remember even the business lines I was running I got to launch when I got 280 million in sales like
Get out of here now
So was it insane re working all the time
Yeah I was I was working a lot but again it was coming from a job where I work a lot so
Clearly something I'm used to
And also it's funny cuz I had you know
A baby at home and it was a bit certainly a startup
Party culture as well and I found for myself there at
Like I meant her aunt
Do a lot of people like I was where I was a little bit older
When did you start to see
I don't know sings at LivingSocial kind of
Turn a little bit when did you start to notice that maybe
Maybe this isn't going to
Work out the way
Everyone thinks it will
Obviously you see
Metric to see growth slowed
And it makes you start to question certain things
And then obviously you see Talent
You know some people admired started to leave
Just even though
Composition of the whole experience
Penta LivingSocial capacity
What what actually went wrong
You know I think it's a multi-part answer
Some of which
Was
You know that
Exchange was really that local Merchants would get
Loyal coffee
And so that had to be the case
And I think in some cases
That trade-off didn't exist and so some of the best Merchants add not in
Anymore and so then
Do you know if burn is exciting and they didn't have the best
Restaurants in stores in southern customers
Became Legends
The idea and so it was that
It when that cycle was reinforcing it was Unstoppable but when it started to unwind
It got hurt
Did that give you an insight into
Stop
A thing of
New things new technology new product new apps like
I don't not to pick on Living Social or Groupon her appointment
Give me the times of these examples where you know one day at company's value today
5 billion dollars
And then
It seems like a year later
It's sorta like the emperor
You know MP
First new clothes everyone's like
Google what is actually what's the value here
Well I think no doubt it led me to a business that I could
So I think yeah I just learned
Give you some of those businesses are hard to
Hard to know whether they're going to be transformation
So at what point did you decide to leave
So
Growth was slowing and I think
More importantly I thought my personal development was slowing
And I thought you know I really
I want to run something
I just do and I always sort of
Just feeling that
Were you anxious about your future
I don't think I was anxious about
My future at that company I was anxious about my future
In general I just wanted to get on it
And at that time I had started to think about building my own business
I'm in and I with my head was going there when I got a job offer that sounded
Melissa and Joey
Woodworking for a taxi app
It's called Taxi Magic that was actually had an iPhone app to hail Taxi
Free Uber
And so I thought well. This is
That'll be close enough to doing my own thing
So at the time it was but certainly nowhere near
Living Social
Free snacks
Foosball the whole thing
You know that company
Sales Retreats beautiful graffiti on the walls
CTE
You were trying to convince taxi companies to adopt
Taxi Magic app or whatever and then
You would click on the app and then you can order text you that was
Align with hex magic that works exactly and how long did you do stay there
Wasn't there long I was there only about 7 months be
Because
As soon as I got there I realized
And I really want to do my own thing that I just that feeling could not be stated
In another way
Yeah and so what
What did you talk to Jesus start a canoe
Rainstorm possible ideas did you have no idea
Idea
For a long time
I met someone should make custom picture framing better how did you get the idea
Originates
Truly back probably
Eight or nine years
I had
National parks posters
I've never had bought on these annual hiking trips I went
On with my sister
And I took them to a local frame store to be framed
The terrible experience
Really intimidating and
Really expensive
Like more expensive the posters much more expensive and the framing was for
$400 each
I spent $1,600
And so you were thinking what this has to do somebody has to change this
And so
I just always had I like I had a mixed reaction even towards the posters when I finally picked him up three weeks later
I just thought I'd like headed that happened to me
I just started going about my life
And I kept noticing things
That I would like and I have
You can have that you can frame it
Chester Patterson
Because it this is I'm having flashbacks my conversation with the Warby Parker founders
Which it was similar because glasses are so expensive
And they were asking why I mean
Plastic in
Ghettos some hinges
It's right in Hawaii
Why is the framing
Why am i spending so much money
Sofer a local store
They don't
Store any inventory they don't
Store any of their materials in their store
And sew in or when you go in and you select from the thousand
Frame styles on the wall
The
That bring sword actually buying those
Materials for your pee
When you
Place your order
So it takes weeks
And it's really heavily marked up you're buying from a distributor
So our Innovation which a doesn't seem like much of one was really like why don't we
Choose frame styles We Believe are beautiful
Invest in them and make it centrally so you can't so so basically you have
Some options but not
Yep
40 styles
I'm rotate
Driven by Trends but we don't
Yeah we don't overwhelm you with a thousand Francine one
And you have the infant
Then we have
And the concept was that the
That you would roll up your artwork
Nail it in and then it would
Come back Frank
Yes that was the concept the concept was for less than half the price of a retail store
With very clear upfront pricing you choose from a
Beautiful selection
Weed Melia packaging mail us your art
We send it back to you in a couple days Reddit
You're working a taxi Magic
But if you have this idea for a long time what was the
Spark that
Actually got you
To do that to actually
Believe in
Make a go for it multiceps at
LivingSocial I sold a lot of
And so people I new customers are looking for a deal on this
This category but didn't
They still didn't like their
Experiencing
Validated it
And then
When I get to Taxi Magic I had
Ash you know
How many smart people are competing in this category
And I have a category
I am just
So eager to make better
And nobody's thinking about
You you started to tell people about this idea because a lot of people are secretive at the beginning
I'll steal it
You told people about
This idea you had a dead and it was essential I did because
You know I needed to know when people actually use
Did people think it was a good idea to everybody.
You're truly an image of me at a cocktail party already
You know
Ifriends baseball game and in just thinking about you know
Telling people the concept didn't then I kept hearing the same stories about
Either me or my partner
You know
An industry was always involving $600 worth of Framing and I bet I wouldn't believe it and I do believe it that's why
I am going to fix it
But everybody present was like saying to you
What an awesome idea Susan
But like
Let's just be honest here
A million conversations like that happen everyday
So to this day at least twice a month someone says you know me and my friends we were talking and we were
Coming up with that same idea we had an idea for a framing
Having a disruptive Raven coming
List of the medication are witches
Is is an idea enough
Yeah a lot of their lot of really awesome ideas
Now and ideas
Wheeling hour
I mean I so let's at least an hour sorry it's
It's worth
It's all that
I mean into or you
Like financially secure enough to take this leap to actually
Leave your job and try this
No
We're living a life that required
Too hard working
Parents and required to salaries for Mortgage in our two kids they were one and four at the time
Two little girls and
It's obviously child care for them
So yeah it was kind of a crazy time to decide to start a business
And I think a lot of people
Tell me all the reasons this
Couldn't work
So what was the first
Think me so the first thing you did as you start talking to people and tell him about the idea
And
What was the first like
Concrete thing you did did you
Did you know anything about Frank now
I knew nothing about framing
So certain most notably a kind of for a framing course
That I took at a Hampton Inn
And
So they actually take
Bring small framing equipment into conference room
Sponsored by
Just like somebody
Picture frame and really the advertisement is like
Look at the highest margin business
Come learn how to frame
Learn how to frame then you can start to open a shop because
Is margins are so hot
And so
It was really important for me to make sure I knew
What is getting into on the production side but also
Yeah that makes it was five
BECU
You leave your job to to learn how to frame
I leave my job to learn how to frame
And I go to a trade show in Las Vegas
Just two
Just to check it out just to check it out
Because I thought
Yelp
What have I gotten myself into
I just whispered one around looking at frame styles like they actually
Certainly
Add opinions on
On what satellite didn't and
And had some design learning but really I just thought like
What am I getting myself into
I remember standing alone on the Vegas Strip just for
Having paid my way there at my own pocket
Thinking like what am I doing like am I ever going to pull this thing
When was Ed Sheeran
Debt ratio
Set 2013 and in what year were there like taking notes and to just
And what did you want to do with that information
I was still in the you let me make sure I'm not missing
Sing face and then also like well gosh I'm going to have to get started so I have to call these people up and tell them I want to buy a quip
And one bite you know what
Try to develop contacts in the industry
There are few folks I met their who are still vendors to this day and I really give
Credit for listening
Because I do think most people just
Orton like
Oh well
Absolutely didn't
To this day I think I'm still trying to explain to people it was really kind of reverence for the end product
That I started this business so I actually think
Getting something custom framed
Really really special
And so
I believe that I just believe
More people need tax
But presumably some of these frame
Folks were like
We don't want this kind of disruption we don't want
Your Harvard Business School degree to come in and make this thing cheaper for consumers
Of course
And so going on in building this business I have
Run into that a number of times but I think
It requires someone out of the industry to be able to sort of plotted from the consumer's viewpoint
And I think by this time I
It felt like
Too late to back out
It and so at that point I started trying to
Why did you decide to go to investors
From the get-go rather than
Just pulled together
Money from family and
Anywhere you can get
A little bit here and there and do it on your own
Yeah I joke a little bit that we were
Somewhat I'm lean in the beginning
In that
We Believe
I believe
That in order to actually
Do this business well it had to be done it
Such a high
Holiday
And that was that the site had to look beautiful
Packaging had to be
Branded
You had to trust
Awesome enough to roll up a diploma and
Send it to us
And I really thought like
There is no
Really minimally viable
Product version
Of this business
It has kept me.
Like that anything to just test whether the concept worked wouldn't
We had to do a great and we had you are so
So how did you
How do you get the money to do this cuz I have to assume you need
Did a lot of money to build
An app to get the materials to hire a team like YouTube how much money were you looking right yeah so
Hilarious I remember saying I was looking to raise $50,000
And initial investors saying you realize that's not going to
To be enough money
Really we raised $2000000 so we were going to raise a real round
Cbrown navigate
And what was your pitch to investors by where you like a million half dollars value that 10 million dollars
I put you say that did you even know what to say how I didn't I didn't know any of those things and quickly learned in you learn because all of them
Meeting start to sort of melted together
And you learn those things along the way but the picture was really clear and
In a way I'm really proud of we built the business
Which was young
When inside
Look you know
I say we because there were some people on the PowerPoint
Pizza Shack
But they were just like aspiration
So yeah it was just
Kay custom rings too expensive
And
Pretty big Market it could be
Way bigger
Is someone made it less expensive and less of a hassle
And here's I'm going to do it
How did you find people to even pitched
So an investor at Living Social
But I met for breakfast he was actually wondering why I had left Living Social it was just a sort of a social call
And
I had no business bitching him at that time cuz it was really not a strongly enough developed idea but I
Told him
You know
I pointed to frames on the wall and said you know those should only cost $100
You know that
Antes
Serta leaned in and said you don't you should do this
He's a really intense guy
And so
I thought well gosh that was the reaction
You're like validated right there yeah and so I
Revolution
So so he's acting in the Mid-Atlantic
Pretty well-known investor
He is a well-known investor and yes
And he also calls it like
So I knew like it is not the one who would be
He just bought a breakfast or lunch with this guy and he's like
Go for you got to do this Susan
He said that it is a good idea
And so great we left and about a week later
He sent me one line email how far along
And I thought
Yes
Okay
And it certainly it was not a promise of anything but it was enough to make me think like
He's at this is a nitrogenous we got it
I have built this
So he said pull a few pieces
This Together come up with you know what I'm doing next
How you get this thing off the ground and come
We'll talk.
Pitch to sing for real
Find a pretty good presentation I thought of
Of how I would pull up
First guy to give you the money
And you were looking for a million bucks
And I went in and I went through everything in the deck and he said
This isn't
I don't think there's enough
Here
That we can make
Annabelle
What
He goes from saying go do this to saying
Yeah I don't I'm not feeling as a
What it what was it that he did not
Like about your
I think you didn't like the certainty
Uncertainty part of it
We had
Yeah I had ideas of how it would pull everything together but
Yeah
And didn't have anything yet
And so
I think he felt like
Can't come back and say I found this great early stage company but they haven't said anything yet
And I remember walking home that I was to distance I needed
Did the cat but I walked home that night thinking like
Oh my gosh
So that's done
Now you got to move on to the next
Yeah and by this time
You know I'm spending money at a trade show at a framing course out of your own pocket
You are not independently wealthy no longer
It was you looking your bank account and Insignia kid is a certain point where I'm going to hit a limit like
$10,000 - $20,000
What's $30,000 and I'm going to be in
Big trouble yeah I remember actually having it
Serious conversation
My sister
In
January 14th
I was staying with her new your cousin
Interesting on her couch and she was her like
Sister I'm the one who has to tell you like eventually
You going to have to give up
In a moment, Susan Tynan got off her sister's couch and into her own framing.
Garage door listening to how I built this
NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work
They want to do
Using technology
How to make people more productive and engaged
Moritz servicenow.com
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from and
NPR
Gyros
First investment pictures went
Nowhere
A lot of people told her to
Give up
But of course she didn't she convinced some Engineers to help with the website
Promise that eventually
She would pay them
I really convincing Engineers like this is all happening we're going to get money so
Start building
So based in start codon we started building
Even at that point anywhere so we're finding what the name for framebridge would be and
So I started building as though it would be funded obviously anything that required a big check I couldn't
Obtain
But otherwise certainly I could get you know
Samples of materials and things like that and so I just started
Proceeding as though it would happen
And
Meeting anyone who might
Be able to write a check and just using using your own money for bits and pieces here and there my money for bits and pieces
But that point things starting to pick up more and I think
Again a lesson in just
If you're moving as though the business is going to work the rest is going to
So that point I had gotten connected to another investor I knew as well
In the DC area in the DC area National investor
A
Female partner
Venture Capital firm
Who and we had lunch and I told her the idea and she said you won't believe this I was searching
Last week
For the solution not mine and I know it
It doesn't exist I looked
Should I love this
I get it I I know this need exists
And
GTA V money
It wasn't that easy
It was definitely a series of meetings in sort of a show me how you're putting this together
The same way with a lot of like blue show me more in the next time show me more
And so she was the first to act actually sign up
And a how long did
Prices of when you started
Raise money to when you actually raise the millionaire million 1/2 that you needed how long does that take
Meetings wise it was
You know 10 month
Really intensely probably about
4 months
Which
Felt
Really grueling but I think is
You know everything's gota ribbon easy run
4 months death of
The money so you have
Like a little over million bucks in your hand
And your bank account you're looking at those zeros
What do you do with that money
First thing I did was
Hire my first
Employee
I'm a woman and Tessa who would work for me previously
And so
Truly the day the wires hit
Quit her job and
And what you do
Everything
Everything is like
Cheap men's merchandising creative but I mean we did
Everything we
Began actually doing a lot of product sampling
So we were sitting in this co-working space and we were getting
Boxes of
Real wood chips wood mouldings being sent to us
We shouldn't really go in a co-working space so they can sing every night you know you have to bring your leave with your boxes
And so we would Uber home at night with boxes of
Example materials but we just started
Again doing everything on all fronts
Like meeting with packaging vendors meeting with UPS
Like it was just a
In hindsight I don't even know what that word plant looks like but we were just reviewing every single thing at one time and what was the plan like with them
With that c-money the plan was to build a NASA website and
Launch
Yeah so the plan was to build an app and a website and to find some framer friends
To do the initial production and remember we had for the first 9000 frames
I don't know why we said that for the first time doesn't Prince George's find someone who'll do it
Eating like an outside frame company
Okay and I think that was a way to get our initial investors comfortable with the fact that we were
Add no experience on that minivan
Ringside but you had to find a framing company that
Would do this but they were expensive right so we didn't
So we started talking to you don't framers in to see if we get them interested what we're doing and
We realized
I just a lot of questions like we couldn't control quality we wouldn't be certain about anything and both of us
Sticklers for for quality for precision and we just did
So we realize in order to even buy materials we would need a warehouse
And so
We need a warehouse we might as well get bring me a quid
And we might as well
Make the very first
And so had to tell her investors like
Congratulations
You're going to own a frame Factory
And we drove around
The DC metropolitan area which is not really an area known for
Industrial spaces
But we found a space
And started building
So you ordered like equipment to make
Frames which I guess is like
Band saws and I would like we would but did you get
So we actually
Met a guy through our travels we met a vendor who said
The guy who sells used equipment
And he's a great guy on death frame store and said like
Moonlight for you guys
And help you get this
And how did you tell him to take like from the time you get your investment
The time you rescued launched
Set up the website and
And the app how long does that take
We got money end of February by April we signed the lease on the
Facility
Production facility
And
July we did a soft launch
Yeah it was but I mean
We felt under pressure I mean we had met again
Elise
For a warehouse and not a function website
Elise for warehouse
UWE paying rent on
And wear your investors like okay guys come on
Yeah they definitely were I think every week
Pre-launch
Felt scary and unknown
I mean this was just a real
Field of Dreams right this was a iPad customers really want this service
And so we launched
We wouldn't
So you're so you launched in July
How do you get the word out
Right so hilariously we started with me it was a password protected site cuz we didn't want to be overrun
I'm which was not to be worried
So we launched with with that little beta site in July and then August we opened up and you know told her everybody menu on face
Got a couple orders
But they were all Serta
You know
One degree of separation to degree of separation I went to college with that guy texting
And so we started to send out for him
Instead
Folks Enterprise
And first couple months we got
Two big hits architectural digest and install
You just friend like random things incense
Yeah but not ran
We were like
What exactly would
What frame style would this
Editor and this
Magazine like
What is something about their life we can figure out so that
Reframing
Interesting young we were really thoughtful
And those those were really valid
What about you
Did that have a measurable impact
Show Anatomy I mean at that point we're selling stuff you anything was measurable Seuss measurable
With everything
Sort of manageable and the time we had said like will really be something
For selling a thousand frames a month
And we had told her head of production
Be prepared
And he was in the frame
Good luck girls like you. Get 2000s
True if the first month or two and then late October
Someone a home decor bloggers wrote a blogpost and we had our first real sales by quadeca
And that was the first day without okay
Like it.
How many
Orders were you getting in a day
So at that point we were probably would felt
Overwhelming were probably getting in 50 or 6
For folks who works in production we're making the frame
But
V
Team of us who were you don't make me website marketing everything where the shipping
2 at 4 p.m. every night we
Pushed aside our laptops and walk to the back of the factory
And bubble wrapped and packaged up
Including you the CEO better believe it
You are you are like wrapping up and
You better believe it I had I truly remember
An early board meeting
And I thought oh my gosh they don't know that my hands are covered in paint
It's like they don't get it it was just
At a level of all hands on deck
Continued okay but we are approaching our first holiday
And
This guy is part-time head of production came in one night and said in this is an Earl
They like
Stress
Yeah I started didn't sign up for this
I thought I'd get you guys started but I don't
And I said we're about to hit our first holiday and things are picking up like I need you I need you to help me
Frames but I don't need all this responsibility
This is the guy who's
Running
The brexit
Timeout
And you said
Well I'm not sure I can say what I said no I think I tried to appeal with the light
Please let me down
But there is really sore. He really was like I just
I took you this far
Timeout
You freaking out
You know you do everything and so that was one of the few down there probably a dozen times or you say like
Is it the end of the end
Yeah
Yeah and I think about everyone in like your investors who believed in you and then you believed in this guy who said I'll just work part-time
Time in that was fine and how did we get into this
So what you do
Don't I immediately called a friend who would work in operations
Wart LivingSocial
Put me in touch with another colleague of ours so
You don't miss a certain mutual friend colleague
I'm with in between gigs and said this will be funny I can do this I can learn
Tie me up and so truly within 2 days
We had a new
Hadoop production
I'm who had no experience in a warehouse but was
Goodman
And how long they take
Just like 2 or 3 days
And he knew how to make friends
No
But he was
Sufficiently ID and
And really thought it would be fun he just said like I can do this and we knew I mean
Yes
Super nice and super smart and
Day three he breaks his leg
In the factory
So I was like okay well we're out again
And so then
We just heard at that four of us that Regional
Corporate team had to just stand in and
And figure it out at that point
He came back on crutches
And we got through our first holiday
So you guys
Make it sweet
Christmas and then
I just couple months later you hit another crisis right
Yeah we did I really clever Father's Day promotion
Where we asked about this style of your dad and head
Unique craft paper designs if you had a preppy dad or hipster dad
I was really clever marketing but
Broker Factory bean
Required
Did they match
Not only all the components of a custom frame but also the right craft paper
And we started to slip into
A production backlog
So we started was really the daily issue and that we were selling about a hundred grams a day and making about 7
And
When we got into this Father's Day back login and
That's something diverse
Summer
There were days
It is possible this thing doesn't scale
And it's possible we won't dig ourselves out
It won't scale because you you start to realize we cannot keep up with the orders
We can't keep up with the order and that's a good problem to have
Yeah it felt like a good
Problem to have except we were also oriented to
Customer Delight
We started to see
Yeah really angry
Amount of people saying like
This was the very special gift
For my grandmother's 90th birthday and you ruined it
And
It felt terrible
And I remember having this really intense debate about do we send the email to customers who think it's going to come in three
4 days dad says it's going to come in two to three weeks
So the issue was not that you were framing them badly but they're just
Oh yeah we were framing that perfectly just
Took too long
I'm an insult that leads
Did the bigger question
Can we get out of where we are today and can this thing even
Cuz you need to confer to work
It has to be as convenient and quick
Is going to like
Your local frames
It has to be quicker are custom
Charter internet Choppers they care about
They're and Tuesday they're getting ready for something they're doing on Saturday and we
Tell me how it how you were sort of organizing your
Life because
I'm imagining
You got to talk to your investors
You're bored
You got a bazillion emails
You're also like running the staff
What did you save everyone is like scream and take your hair out
Yeah I remember hosting a board meeting
I'm at our production facility it a like a rented
Conference room nearby
Cuz I thought maybe I should bring them in on this backlog issue
Actually take a tour of the facility and see what's going on
You don't Maybe
In this case honesty is the best policy
So I remember
Touring with them and they saw these like numbers on the board like let me get this straight
You have that many yet to build in your building this many a day
I got
That math isn't
I'm going to add up and so
You can't
Yeah run to True that you have to
Yeah
Bring everybody in with what you're dealing with
How did you solve the problem
We heard a lot more framers
We got a talented
Add a production operations who
New how to dig us out
And really required all of us
Just give up
Weekends for a couple months
To get out of it
I remember one conversation where I said
We're not going down like this
And
A woman who runs product for us at
And so I was like okay
We sailed that
When I go down like this
I really was thinking
I once read that like
How fast do you
You can jump up from
Burpee is correlated with your life expectancy
And I think that's a lot like a startup
It's really how bass like oh
The production
Manager quit we got a new product
You like it
It's like that as fast as you can
Keep going
When did you start to
CDOT the light at the end of the tunnel
And euphoric
Next Christmas
So how many seasons really big for us
App for uploading digital photos to I mean Edison
The greatest gift
So we've been spiked in the holidays
And so
I think once we had
Hero up a professional operations team
And we
Live through that crazy spiked of a holiday season we realize like we've got some
Zofran Bridges is
3 years in the
Is it is it like smoother sailing with a company or do you still have prices
Now wait there's always a crisis
What will happen it's always what you didn't see coming
So I'm relatively recently the beginning of this year we were raising more money in
Assertive at this stage in a tin
Ventures cuz it's your job well done
We got a real business here and so I had spent months on the road talking to investors including my own and
Stitch together
A round of funding
And I had been told I was to receive a term sheet
The finding
The next day was it
Tuesday was so is that Monday and I knew Tuesday I was getting it from cheating so
Starting to feel a little bit of relief
My job is to
Think strategically focus on the customer but also
And so
Was feeling good I was doing my job
We had a brand-new CFO
Is 3 weeks and on the job and we were talking
Monday night and he said you know you're going to kill me
I got you taken a vacation
We got to get the same clothes
And he said no
I got another job
What
Yeah lyrics
So anyone who's ever worked for a business knows that
Cuz I mean you're like
What's going on there if you're see about leave so I
Immediately knew like
This is going to Spook the hell out of everybody
Turn trouble
Yes
And most importantly is going to speak these investor
And so my first thought was
Shut up why did you tell me that
Because it's one thing to leave but like
If you leave me right now I have this knowledge
And I have to
And so his credit he had been in the running for public Company CFO job really big job
Stream job postings happen
But I'm just could not have been
So
I left the building
Like a ghost I remember couple colleagues asked me about minor things and I like couldn't even answer them
I went for a run and it was
Sodalite
What do I do I just get the term sheet close the funding and then say I was surprised this guy is leaving you can't but you can
When inserted like
Just heard a frantically called
All the members of my board to try and get out ahead of what I knew would be
Haley
Get started with an explosion
Which it was
They reacted by sang
Thanks this is really bad you know that yes
We'll get through it by the way that you are
It's a lot of money it's a lot of money on the line and so you can
You know
People
I want to believe $17 is going to
As a company you can't blame them
Skip this
And I remember I'll never forget a one of our board members they said oh he's on vacation but I'll try and call you and you called me and I could hear was
Steel drum band in the background
And he said
We're just going to have to do so well this guy feel
And I said okay you're right that's what we're going to do
And so then they said everyone
Started to come around but I had to do sort of like
Yale Sports
Psych with everybody to say like come on you believe in this business you believe in me
We got this we're going to do this this get throw us off
I mean I really had to like
Bring everybody together like it was the beginning of the company
And so you got the money
And we live to fight another day
The difference between your company in so many companies
Turn on the shows that you're still in the thick of it
You are not
Like
Able to just sit back.
Where in the throat
Yeah like what's going to happen with her maid
Your competitors like are they going to try and lunch stuff we're doing probably
You know what we get to be a sustainably
Yashow healthy business
It looks like it but you know but it's really
Require certified Commando crawl
An insult
Crazy amount of work
All the time
Yeah it's a crazy amount of work all the time like I said they're just
So many talented people now to share it
But
I can't help myself like I
Do always want to be
Skimming
No customer
Four tickets and things like that
How much do this
Point of view race
Lee Priest 37 million dollars
Meet at some point all these investors
Oh yeah they want something they want something back and so they're going to either and their two options inside of you go public
Or you sell to somebody
Those are probably the two most
Likely
Do I think we can be a big enough company to go public
Absolutely anything we can get fundamentally good enough company to it and understandable and Evan a forecast of Alaska business to go public
I believe that
I also believe
All of those things that make us interesting
Would make us interesting
As a partner of another business
Does it I mean obviously you couldn't
Do what you've done without those investing that money
What does any part of you kind of think
I wish I could figure out how to do this
Without
Yeah I've given up a tremendous amount of ownership biting people would be shocked
By how much
So at some point
I bet I'll reflect on that but
Really I think a lot about the fact that I don't think it would have worked unless we had done it in this really
It's really high quality way and
The money allowed me to recruit
Truly the best
Terrific people
And used
Very good materials and
You don't have a very open liberal return policy and everything that has to go into
Building a great company and so I just don't think I could have done in another way
I think a lot of people
People here 37 million dollars in
Assume that you have 37 million dollars
But
Give me a heart that is that that's not the case right
So that is interesting I think that's very confusing to people
There's a lot of
This thing is real we employ a lot of people
We are growing really rapidly those are real
Swimming in money and throwing it up in the air
Is a funny thing
We still have
Cash-strapped conversation
YouTube to friends of yours.
Assume that you're like
Rolling in cash
Yeah I laughed cuz I started to get a lot of things from like all the schools I went to
A lot of like yeah but the thing is is that there's
A very hyper
Possibility that you will this will make you very rich
If this turns out
The way
Your investors imagine you imagine
I can make you into a very rich person how important
Right
It sounds
Cute but I cannot be my Folk
It truly if I take
My eye always on the ball at
On what we're delivering
It will crumble I strongly believe that
Just like
Pasadena far away the hardest thing you've ever done
Oh it is so hard
I laugh about
I work a lot of startup
Like that has nothing to do
It is not it is like barely even pepper
For this
It is extremely hard
It's like
Is only they almost think like
Come at me like I have me merging
It's so much stronger like I'd like you to throw any ham
As soon as I know that
You guys are still in the in the building mode
In face of the company
This is a question that I asked you to pretty much everyone on the show which is
Do you think that so far you know
Your success in the success of framebridge is because of your
Hard work and intelligence or
Or is a lot of it just like
Yeah of course a lot is locked
Truly Almighty early team
Wolfpack from different jobs
And so
A lot was
Being able to
Really pull at everything together and in like
It's really windy road a lot is locked
But a lot of Hustle
And I think
I think a lot about the intersection
I guess with blocking beliefs
I believe in this idea I believe that I could do it
I still believe it will be a big business
And I think that
Translate salak
I'm so light is like I just believe
Enough
You know one thing we don't always talk about on the show is just the amount of personal sacrifice
It takes two
Build a company right like
Pinotage
Spend away from your partner or your kids your family and
Probably haven't taken
You know a lot of vacations over the past 2 years
It is still worth it
Oh absolutely
Absolutely
And it's really
It's the
People understanding me
Is bream part that's worth it it really is
Walking through our facilities and seeing what people framed
Like that is just amazing it's like
I believed you had this stuff and you did
And so a truly I see someone and I have like a scar from the running of the bulls
That passes from
Disney World am I
Just like I believe
You wanted to bring that stuff and you got it you understood what we did
And you're doing it with us and that is just it's just a thrill
What is the most unusual thing that you
You've been asked
We framed a lot of fun you
Usual things
We did framed
A ponytail
Which was faster
But
Butcher
You know we're up for anything
My favorite actually won one of my favorite
What is a
Cardboard
Piece of a kid's fort and I had the rules of the fort on it
And
These kids when they were young and Mom and saved it and bring it for them when they were in their early 20s
Now they're framed
Rules of the fort but they were really
Really endearing
Be kind
The rules were really
It was like the way you should be
And I
Animal Farm Road us a note saying you know and he's kids get iPhones I can give him everything
And this
Like what hands down
The best of Christmas
And so I thought you know that was like
You get it
Susan Tynan founder of framebridge
How do I remember that
First Investors sheephead
Tige Savage
The guy who encouraged her to start
Company and then told her he wasn't ready to invest
Well it turns out Susan managed to change his mind
And Tyga
Actually invested in framebridge in every subsequent round
And today
He sits on her board
And stick around because in just a moment we're going to here
From you about the
Things
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors Vizio Sound Bars
Powered by CPS technology
To deliver an extraordinary sound experience and redefine your home theater
Savings on display and Sound Bars
Available
Vizio
Thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
In the story begins with Alex Van do Ark
Chico California who has a
A question yeah so it's have you ever Mix Concrete before
I personally have not mix concrete before
But Alex has mix a ton of it especially when he was a teenager
You're helping out with small jobs as dads
Construction
And typically what you do is you grab a bag of concrete
You put it in the wheelbarrow you break it open you throw water in there and use the trouble to mix it around
And then you
Need a wheel that wheelbarrow wherever you need a new portal
And when you do this over and over it can get to be a real
It takes too long it's messy and then pouring it is just too challenging to do
So my dad and I would say okay we need a better way to mix the stuff
And so one day I kind of want to fly really
Alex and his dad ditched the wheelbarrow and they decided to use a lightweight
Harp instead
Who are the cement and the water onto the tarp and then held it up between them
And instead of using a shovel or any other tool I would just use these four corners no kind of pick one side up at a time
Ineffectively
Fold the pile of concrete and water over itself and it would mix
Very quickly
And then you can just sort of pick up the tarp from one side and pour it into where you needed it
Okay so what's up pretty basic hack and Alex really didn't think much of it
But a few years later when he was taking business classes
Is a college
He said to his dad you know
Maybe we can make a sticker tarp to mix cement and then sell it
But for us it was like this really difficult Lee Benigno
How do we create something that does what we wanted to do without knowing how to create it
We didn't really we're not experts in the textile industry
We know how to mix concrete and that's that's it
So in order to Market a mixing bowl
That people would actually want to buy
Alex had to invent a tarp that would form the pain of a bowl when you held it so the cement wouldn't spill out
Another tarp had to be tough and water
Open even after he and his dad found just the right material is called a polyester denier blend and
It's coated with PVC
Even after they found that
They still had to find a way to make
The actual Matt
I was calling people in China and Mexico trying to just see like okay who can make the sand
I thought it would be easy
And that took
Years to do
We finally got the mat manufactured a few years ago but when they pitched it to their dream retailer
Home Depot
Home Depot shed
No
And the funny thing is I spent in probably a year learning the same lesson over and over which is
You're not going to get into Home Depot if you're a nobody
So this is where a brand new business has to Pivot
And that's exactly what Alex did
He figured maybe he could get churches and Charities to
Baidu
Text Matt Sandlin
Donate them to places that really needed them
You know a huge amount of people that are impoverished in rural areas of the world that have absolutely nothing
And they live on dirt floors of already bought the mats to help rebuild after natural disasters
In places like Haiti in Mexico
You know it started off as a slow tech product we just wanted to sell to make some money
And
It has transformed into an opportunity
To help people
That's Alex vandywork
Co-owner along with his dad
LC which make
The mix
For now the business is
Not making a ton of money so Alex is still working with his dad construction company and keeping his day job
You want to find out more about the mix mat to our Facebook page and of course if you want to
Go to build. Npr.org and thanks for listening to our show this way
Week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you could how I built this NPR. Org please
Closest subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcast or however you get your podcast
You can also write as its HIV tea at npr.org
At how I built this
Our shows produced this week by Rachel Faulkner was music composed by rum teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to leave a grandson has Michigan for Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our internet is Diana mu stock
I'm guy Raz you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Where can we debate today's big issues without getting attacked for speaking or mine
One egg
Provides a safe smart place
Tough conversation every weekday
And the Friday news Roundup breaks down the week's top stories
I'm Joshua Johnson
Check out the 1A podcast on the NPR one app or wherever you listen to podcasts
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week