This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this kiss
Who understands every small business is uni
And tailors its policies to your business is very specific need
Get a quote or purchase a policy
At h i s c o x.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
We were still not making any money nobody was making a salary we were Andy was funding everything
I didn't leave you to shut it down I said it's your 401K money
And all of our savings at that point we still weren't seeing you no progression that week
Go to pass the salary the next year in the near future so we thought we'd a good run at it we think we've had it
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they built
The person behind the brand Uno is
Kate Spade
Grew up as Kate Brosnahan
Kansas City Missouri
Then she always loved fashion but
Never plan to work inside
She wanted to be a journalist
So in the early 1980s
She went off to study journalism
At Arizona State University
And that
With her Kate met her future husband
Andy Spade
We worked together at a clothing store and I was on The Winning Side he was on the men's side and
His car broke down and then we really started off
Really great friends the car continue to break down so relationship along
And the rest of the story later they're still together anyway
Kate graduated from college first Andy was a few credits short
You're up by yourself traveled around and came back to New York and
Ventura temp agency because I desperately needed
Some some money
Arizona to be with Andy but that's where my ticket
It started and ended in New York
Got enough money to get back so I needed a job in order to do that so I started it at
The temp place I was typing and I said I don't I don't think this is going to work out
And then she called the next day and said can you get ready right now kind of NASCAR
And they have a job in fashion Department
So
They ended up hiring me they didn't want to because I couldn't type
My boss
That listen she's great and I don't need a side Lot
If we were doing fashion shoots and styling so
It wasn't as what were you doing
Well I started as an assistant so I was
Tying
Model shoes
On a photoshoot because they couldn't bend over their clothes
That are getting hair stylist
Snickers
I'm telling you whatever I irons
Kids bags
It was a lot of work
Did you were you were back in Tempe
At Arizona State University
I was back in Tempe hours to struggling with a few required courses
I think I had more credits than necessary but there are a few that I couldn't get through
But I did start an advertising agent
See my senior year in college
And so I started trading ads
For aborting food
Inside I go to a restaurant for example and I
I bring in the ad that they had running in the local paper
And I would show it to them and say I think I can do better if I come back and show you a
A better version of this
Will you either pay me in food or give me a few hundred dollars
I had like
10th Acres so I ended up with 10 accounts
How many things are going well
And Kate were you still planning to head
Back to Arizona
At that point
Yes
And I kept saying no I'm coming back
I will only stay here for 6
The first post
Text number I said I have to be honest
I kind of like my job
I loved it and I love the pain of the past
Pace of
New York
And suddenly it
I loved it
When she got a job offer for $14,000 a year everything changed
She's on sting and that's what I said well I'm going to
I'm moving to New York
And you just figured
Yeah I figured I'd find something there I had a little portfolio
Of advertisements that I'd written and art directed
I thought I took that with me to New York in hopes of finding a job
And what did you guys
Did you out like move in together
We did
I I forwarded a little bit of money that I had
Decatur
First security deposit on the cheapest
List Apartments you can find
And
I remember arriving and
It's a call me from a pay phone on the corner
When you arrive
And all
Get out of the fire escape
So I called and I walked
26 Renwick Street
And I looked up at
She was out on the fire escape and she threw down a sock with a
Akita that is true, it's easier to throw it down
Like suitcase
I had
One warm coat a suitcase
And a portfolio
Wow an integer but a cake
I know you went to an all-girls
Catholic High School parents of have a problem with
You living with Andy
They never really said much but
My mother
That's not please
She was not pleased with the doll bed
I mean I just kept saying it was a matter of economics
Did you actually land a job in advertising
I did I was interviewing and a lot of programs like y&r in Oglebay anime there
But my portfolio didn't reflect the kinds
Accounts that they're working on
Bars in IBM
What is walking to Grand Central Station and a young man in a suit pulled me over I was carrying my portfolio
He said what are you do
Looking for
Job is a copywriter he said you have a minute
I said Teresa I'd love to look at your portfolio and we stopped in Grand Central Station he went through my portfolio and
He said I think I might have something for you I'm a recruiter
It happened to see me walking to Grand Central Station
He went through it needs to meet me at my office tomorrow
2 did any set me on three or four interviews
What which which was an agency named bozell Jacob Canyon in a car
I need an opening for someone to work on the
Army National Guard and Merrill Lynch
And
He said I know you haven't had any experience on these but these types of businesses but I like your hotspot
Oh. I didn't know what it meant until I called someone
What does it mean when they say you took a chance starting own business at the positive
Until I got that job
So okay so you guys are on your early 20s
Your
Living the New York Life
Hate your working at at Conde Nast
Mademoiselle magazine
Actually it was amazing
I mean my mom
Framed when they put my name in the
Math test she still hasn't praying
And what are you doing what were you what did you start to do there
It was first assistant
For the senior fashion editor
And
Then I was promoted to associate editor
And I was in charge of all the accessories
And
I did that for a couple years and they promoted me the senior fashion editor
And if there's one thing I did learn was
How to be very resourceful
And it came in very handy
We started our business because
I mean
There was do not come back
Me with no
I mean you
Figure it out I mean it would be we have to go on a shooting
2 days and we need 8 tickets
Bahamas in
Figure out how to get us all there
I mean if we're all on different airplanes I don't care but get us there
Make it happen
So I guess it was the early 90s like maybe maybe 1991 when you decided to leave
Mademoiselle magazine
What was going on why did you decide to go
It's funny you know Angie and I were talking one night and I just said
I was looking ahead and I
So the fashion director is
How do your neck
Jump from being
Senior fashion editor
And
I don't really see myself wanting that
That job
So Andy and I were out honestly the Mexican restaurant and
He just said
What about handbags
You just don't start a handbag company
Resupply. How hard can it be
Okay really
He regrets those words
What white handbags
Well she was in accessories editor and she collected
Your handbags for fashion shoots that would have
Whatever key responsibilities
So she'd have to
Handbags from
Vintage doors
For Beach shoot straw bag she had a
Buy a Personal Collection that was amazing and then she knew every handbag company in the mark
I thought you understood it better than anyone
What's missing in the market
What was missing in the
The time things for Barry
Baxter too complicated
And I really love very simple kind of architecture
Jose
And I would wear these
Very simple shapes none of which were
Famous designers names
September
Today
Who is this that I'd say I don't know I bought it at a vintage store or it's a straw bag I got in Mexico
Soaked and they were all very square and simple and I thought
Xiaomi why can't we find something
Just clean and simple and modern
Okay so about the time that that you want to quit you were thinking
Like I'm done with fashion magazines yes
And then he was like
You know bags you know like why don't you try to do this
Design your own
Absolutely it actually said it before I quit so I kind of
Already had in the back of my mind and
I remember at the very beginning
Stay I could have
Made an income while I was working on this and someone said to me
The truth
Is you would never have done it
How do you say
Because I would have been a scrap yours I mean that it was kind of didn't do or die so
I think if I'd still been working I would have been like
A little bit more lackadaisical about it words
And you don't have an income coming in you
To do whatever you can to make it happen
So how did you even start to
Design hammock menu had no
Background InDesign you didn't even know what to do in Lakewood
Show things and
It's funny I did not know and I did start by buying
Big sheets of white
Paper
And I would cut out
Tape honestly
The shape that I wanted and then I'd look at it
Make it shorter smaller cut it
And I went to a pattern maker that I found in the back of women's wear daily
She advertises she made patterns
So I contacted her she worked out of her apartment and she was
Patient as could be with me
Because I didn't know anything and I remember being really embarrassed about that
That
I wasn't there
Student
Comparison to RISD or
Fit that if I really didn't know what I was doing
And I honestly started with paper then we'd make a sample out of any kind of fabric muslin
And then
I kind of got the shape down and I had to find a manufacturer so I called me mister daily they connected me
Me to a department that they really said we don't do that but someone in the fashion Department said oh it's so odd I know some
And he had left himself this
Production guide to start his own business
So was this guy that you found was he was he a designer manufacturer so he
Did the production
And so I brought in my samples and
He was like okay why won't some money up front and he really was very nervous that I wasn't going to pay him and
Tahiti
Took our tiny little production honestly which would be
Handbags of time you know
And how how long after
Like You music sort of start to sketch out design
What's this what's this like
Weeks Later a month later what
Did you were you working on this idea for a long time in your apartment yes
At least a year and you were freelancing
Nathan
Certain days a week
As a stylist
After getting the
Patterns made
The next
Big Challenge was
Finding someone who would sell us
Fabric and
Because we didn't have any experience none of the fabric houses
What cell has anything other than
100 yards
For example
Probably
40 yards
30 RND 25
So I called
I looked in the Yellow Pages
And I looked up
Burlap
And I found a potato sack
That's
Is willing to sell to
Annette three different
No weights
And I needed the heaviest weight so that
Substantial enough
Bram.
That was actually our first collection
Made out of burlap
Made out of burlap bags look like imagine like
Brown burlap
Kind of
Angular little bag
Yes absolutely with
Raffia Fringe
And
Webbing handle and I found a wedding company also
In the Yellow Pages
I see you get this
You get these samples and then what new how do you get
Why do you start with the first thing you do
You go to these
Accessory shows
Trade shows trade shows and you get to get accepted
And we did and
The question of your
You get the worst spot because all the famous people end up in
Citizen in New York
Trade show you went to debut the case
Spade
Burlap
Bag yes
And we honest
God brought in our own tables
Lounge chairs we bought in lamps
Apartment apartment actually are both turned into our apartment
Basically for the week
Where you guys are nervous I mean Kate were you like I don't know where that were you worried that maybe somebody from
I didn't ask
Cut be a little embarrassed or somebody would call you out and say what are you doing who you guys were you
I was I
Because the editors come by as well as the buyers
To the trade shows
And I really didn't tell my parents
Or my family about it
Or anyone for that matter
Because I thought if it doesn't work
I will be so
Embarrassed
Because everyone kept saying
Why would you quit your job
Yuan insurance
Who do you think you are I just knew my family with just
Oh you got a little hot-headed big headed there in New York and
Think you can start this company
So I kept it on the down-low intentionally didn't
They talked about it much too
Family
Because I think secretly we both thought it
Fail respond to the bag
It will
I remember crying
Because when I came home we hadn't even sold enough to cover the cost
To the booth
And I started crying and he said both
Who did you get tonight said
What we got
Barney's
Annies
Okay and I said
Fred Segal in Los Angeles news
Migas
Katie
To the best stores in America
Why are you crying I said I think we should shut it down
I'm very conservative and I said I do I have no in
To losing money
I said and we feel we've already spent
$4,000 and that that's it for me I'm not a gambler so
That's her and he was like that
Keep going
And also have to get a great deal of credit
To the editors
Nap time we weren't selling a lot but the editors were putting us in the magazine
A lot
What was it about your bags at appeal to them
I did because it wasn't
Anything anyone was doing and everyone there's a fabric show in Paris called Premier busy on that all the designers go
Same material
Mine came out of the Yellow Pages chances are going to run into any people that have the same material
So we were doing something different which was really to our advantage
Two editors for like
50 speed
Beautiful burlap bag
They thought they were
Beautiful Friday they thought they were interested
And we did we got a lot of credits then that's when my mother first found out
And she was embarrassed
Then she called the embarrassing that you didn't
Tell me and my friend had to tell me lies
I know I don't know I don't want to make a big deal of this and
It okay it's one credit that's not a business
How did you come up
How did you serve land on the name
Well that was Andy
Because we weren't I was not Kate Spade I was
Kate Brosnahan and
I kept coming up with
Cities names in Antigua
Kate
Space because we were 50/50
Key partners
Finally I just said okay and I love it
Kate Spade New York and I remember telling
To your point about
My Catholic parents I took
My mom
Honestly she burst
In Flames she was like
But you're not keep faith and I said I know but she's a
Oh now you'll never be Kate Spade now you've been jinxed it and why would you name it Kate Spade and I said
What's
My first name his last name is like
Dolce & Gabbana what the hell is that
And I said I said it'll work we hope
In just a minute why after three years of making no money
Kate and Andy almost walked away from their little handbag company
I'm gyros near listening to how I built
NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First to freshbooks the cloud accounting software used by over 10 million October doors
Dr. Mike McDermott
Start of the company
Spaceman
And spent over a decade building freshbooks
Now with their all new version you save even more time processing
Paperwork ndk
Send invoices in under 30 seconds
Accept online payments in two clicks
And see what a client has looked at your invoice
For your free 30-day trial or freshbooks.com
Built
Adventure how I built this
In the how did You Hear About Us section
Thanks also to godaddy.com
They give customers.
The tools and insights they need to transform their ideas
Personal initiative
Into success
What's GoDaddy small business owners have everything they need to get their business online
Including award-winning
24/7 support
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology provider dedicated to small business
And they're offering how I built this listeners
30% off all new products
Just go to godaddy.com
And use built
To get started that's built
And one more thing
Stay tuned till the very end of the show because that's where we feature your stories about the things
Your Builder
And if you want to tell us about
Product a company you're trying to get off the ground
Go to build
. npr.org
And follow the instructions and maybe
Just maybe
We'll get a chance
Tell your story
As well
It's how I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
So when Kate and Edith debut the original Kate Spade bag
They got orders from farnese and Fred Segal
And it was a big deal in the world of fashion
But even with those orders
It didn't mean Caton and E were suddenly
Wash with
Kasher living large in New York
Wasn't going to guarantee that
The company was going to be successful
Andy
He kept his full-time job in advertising
Beijing
The overhead yeah I'm basically the rent in the other expenses right we'll keep freelancing that started the company
And I just got lower both 29 30 years old and
It's time to do it we don't have children
Let's not quit even if we
Lose everything
Okay can I go back to Fashion job
You know I can continue working advertising
And you guys are running the company
We'd move to a loft in Tribeca because we were in a small apartment
Honestly guy everywhere
To the point where are Loft
Bad was up the stairs we crawl up
The entire apartment was just to see if
Brown boxes that sounds
We were doing very well but yeah
It really was we were still you were shipping out things from the apartment
Oh yes
At least
Two and a half years
You know you could take the train
The Brooklyn to the factory
Pick up the box
Just take the back on the subway
In trash bag floor walk-up
And she was shipping and
Packing bags and doing everything and taking orders on the fax machine I'm everything come through in the middle of the night
With your better around Wherever I Go
Excited put the orders would not be that big because it was hard to
The people that time to cut once they started selling then you get bigger order so it was really
Very gradual I mean it was at least
3 years before we paid ourselves
Maybe $15,000
And we're still working out of our apartment
It was our home office
Standard shipping
Warehouse
Andar
Home did you start to see
The first year 2
Women walking around New York with k
I did
Most of whom
We redditors who are getting them a very good discounts
Eventually we started to see it and I remember thinking
What I did
That was a big deal
And
You know I think it took people while even my family my sister was working
Gucci and actually
Called me and said we're all pitching in
Mom
Father's Day
Get her a Gucci bag and I thought
What
I never that because they really didn't think
It would be much
I still should be upset
What about the hopefully they're listening
Show all the while you're shipping bags out your getting orders in and you are still designing
Facts
Yes
See you're working like
We are and
What we ended up doing
Put sweet took on
Two partners
For Sweat Equity only
It was at my friend at least Aaron's
My best friend
There was a t
Someone that we just met through friends here in New York
So
The three of us were in cars going to
Factories
I was really doing the design the only bed
Didn't I also
Steaming the bags boxing pack
And how are you guys
It was always you
Yeah I got a job offer to work for Saatchi & Saatchi in LA and I
I almost tripled my salary
Yeah we're still funding the company ourselves
And we needed money for
For fabric and we needed money
For the trade shows
Until we both agreed that I would go to La you did move to LA
I thought I could go back and forth and at the time released
Pallet wood hold down the New York
Partner
FedEx in all my designs and materials and
I rented a little house that I called the house I never lived in
I never bought a piece of furniture and I just took the money and send it to me I put it back into the business
Did you ever get a point in the first two years
Where you thought this was going to collapse if this is going to fail
Yes and I remember calling back
Tulisan Pamela New York and I said
I didn't leave you two
Shut it down I said it's why were you guys
Like in dad or it was hard I mean it was we were still not making any money nobody was making a salary we were Andy was
Standing everything
And at that point we were all kind of putting money in family would put into Emeli Sande
I just remember thinking of
We run to your 401K money
And in all of our savings at that point
We still weren't seeing
You know progression that was going to pass out in the next year in the near future
A good run at it
I think we called the partners who
We brought in as as
Equity Partners on a handshake without any salary and we said we think we've had it
Cuz we are exhausted and they took
Left the start with you and we haven't even had it returned the deals.
So we felt like you can't remember we spoken
It said all right
I'm going to go back
I'm trying to think
95-96 95 probably 95 and I did get another job in New York a great job actually
But still the company was not making money
What was the turnpike
What happened
I would say the stores really
Started to buy more we were in Saxon Neiman's and
When the
Largest department stores started to buy
It
Kind of really took off
We won
The cfda awards which is the
The Council of fashion
Designers of America
And
There were photos from around the country not just
New York at the show that were saying
Who is this
So that really really helped us a great deal I have
Nosey word that you're most
Is smaller designers
Didn't win at the time it was usually a Ralph Lauren Calvin Klein Donna
Karen all those people
And I remember Kate when we came back to New York and we were hoping something
I think what happened that
Either Neiman's or Saks
They're buying for two or three stores and they said we're going to buy for all of our stores
That was fifty stores
More Than Words
And that quadruple our business
But what you have to realize
When that happens although it's very good you also have to up
Front
Pay for the production they don't pay you for
30 to 6
Today so I remember that
Are we going to afford it but we
Never borrow a dime
Ever
Was there something that you guys did like a business decision that you
You made
That
That was the
Key to turning this around or was it just
More people started to discover it and you just you just persevered
Through those rough years and then it finally did
Just kind of on its own
You know
Got discovered
That's exactly what happened I mean it really was just
Kind of a little bit of a Snowball Effect
No just got a little bigger in a little bit
Bigger and
I think
At the point where the largest department store Square picking us up
I think that it will be realized
Getting larger and larger spaces in stores which is very important
And maybe get a few
Basin shelves
Storm store shop and Shop is what they call them
Your name is above it really big
To walk into
I think it's more fun for my mom actually a lot of fun I have to stay in the
Opening of stores do you know weed open to store
And Soho tiny little 300 square-foot store the next day
You know we're opening a bigger Store New York and then we're opening in
Los Angeles
10 Chicago in
It was kind of at that point it became a little dizzy
A bit of a whirlwind
Thought it was fun
Until some point you guys sold
The part of the company
That was at the surf scale up or
To make it even bigger
You know it was also a safety that quite honestly for us personally
And it wasn't even Marcus and we thought that would be somebody that would
Be in a position to help us
And they bought
I'm a little bit more than 50
The company that they bought 56
Reportedly for more than 30 million dollars
Same to you guys
They were I think our biggest
Client restore the time and
We're doing very well with them and they had just started investing in other little
Little brands that they
They thought I had potential
And yeah they came to us we were
Completely
In shock
Exciting because
As we thought wow
Which everything goes goes away tomorrow
You know it will be able to
Sustain the business
I mean it was really about not being able to have
A bit of an essay going forward
The four of us
I know what that mean when one even Marcus by
More than half of the change
Kate Spade
We started going into work categories because they were
Encouraging that which a lot of the stores not just
Is that all of them
Really encouraging us
Categories
Stationary next twitch
That was right when
Phones and emails and all that word
Replacing people riding notes
Texas native
Another category we didn't mean
You know a dying category
So I think what they were implying
Shoes they really wanted some
Real substantial
Second categories are third fourth
So then we started doing shoes and
It really just started
No I think it was just a good boost
And I mean you guys probably had to go from you and Andy and your two partners II
Lots of employees
We did but we have done that actually
In the process
Slowly slowly changing
And offices and we take a floor and then
We take another floor in the building in
Who started the hiring people to hearing
Different departments in production people in
And then how many people
Have more experience
So I really had a lot of people around
And Andy did Andy really surrounded himself with
Really
Greats
Art Department
And I really had great designers with me and
I think we really developed
Employees that were amazing
When did you start to see
Kate Spade bags
All over the
Huge iconic
And when did you first kind of realized
I'd say was about
It was still
Ferry New York so I must say
Are New York Los Angeles Chicago
I think it was about 98 or 94 UTM
Did any city that you went to
Counterfeit started
That was about to get on Canal Street
Which Andy said that's actually accomplish
You know you're doing something right when
They're on every blanket on every street and celebrated for a day and then the next day that was over
You guys sold the rest of your your share of
Walked away from it what would you decide
So
We had a baby
Into
5 and I just wanted
It was a perfect opportunity
Neiman Marcus
Set the time
Was selling
Themselves to
Pacific
Paintball Des
Give them a lot of credit for that
But when we sold everything he know
Kind of like we have a
A boss
I want to leave on
On good terms if it's a
Perfect time to leave
I wanted to spend time with my daughter
It was
Beaufort so many horror stories
About people who style and then they stay and then they fighting and they sue and
That's too ugly for me so
We left on great terms we stay because of turnover
4 a year
For the transition to make sure all the employees who we loved had
Agreements to carry on
Understood
What the process was
And they understood
And
They were very gracious and I think we all handle
The farewell
It was seamless
It was a very
Quiet exit
You guys obviously have this incredibly strong
Marriage meme email here college students are still together you have a
You created this big amazing brand and how do you
How do you have a marriage and a business and
Make it work
Safe from my perspective I remember people saying how do you work together when I was thrilled
I don't wait up wait up and I'm not ready yet means
Let me tell you right now if you think that everyday
Good office together we can have lunch together
We actually worked on stepper
Florist Parma that very reason because
Then he'd be on the phone tonight
Get off the phone I have something to tell you
Or ask you
And that
We had to really I had to
Myself
Boundaries in
We had to make conscious effort not to talk about it 24/7 which is
As you can tell by her
Quickly
Slight tendency
And I also am very
A nervous person I worry a lot
A nanny could not be more different
You are like the sleepless nights person
Yes
Always another
The sky is falling
Zico
You know it's good it's fine because we
We kind of grew up together
Up until now in AR-15
And we actually have a lot in common which helps
You guys
Recently
Launch a new company
Together
What you call it by Frances Valentine
Yes in Katy
You changed your name from Kate Spade to
To Kate Valentine
I did but I added it I didn't change it I just added
Francis
Valentine into it so it's very
It's Katherine
No
Francis
Valentine
Eddie Long
Did you do it in part because
Kate Spade and become
Its own thing and
Beyond a single person
Yes and I thought it was important to make sure that we weren't stepping on any toes and
That we distinguished
Our company
And I think that was important
For both of us
I mean people still call me Kate Spade I go buy it
Seitz eye
I get confused
Myself so you can call me Francis if you want
And he told me about Frances Valentine
We are doing
Shoes and Handbags and we actually when we started
It was initially just
Shoes
Although we've only
Been in business
I'm not your just your little over a year
But we've realized that's
People expecting bag
And I mean now you're a different right because
The hunger is
I'm sure it's still there but
It's not like a do-or-die thing like
It must be that I don't know
Is it less stressful
We've air conditioning I think that's big that's a big difference right
Are there elevators in air conditioning I would stay there
It's
But I feel a little more confident
I think Andy feels the same because we've done it before
But on the same hand
You think that
People are expecting a great deal
So they're still there still alot of pressure Trestman
Personal finance
Say it again so
I'm not crazy that as I mentioned earlier that Lucy
Any money
Get out this thing go to work
Do you when you walk past
Kate Spade
Shop today or
RC bagged do you
Do you feel emotion emotional attachment to her or
Is it serve like baleen Avec that's a different
It's funny because I
I do look at it and I don't
People said oh do you have any regrets I remember thinking all I hope I don't
And I never have and I think they've done such a good job that luckily I don't have to have
And so we do walk by the stores and I have a funny story that we actually walked into the store
To buy my daughter something
Cash register and she said are you on our mailing list
And I said
So
And instead that I used my maiden name and I said
She surprised me
Send my daughter kind of kept nudging me to his died for me to say something and I didn't and then I remember thinking you know
I'm not on your mailing list but I think I helped created
Take a note
And Andy spade and by the way if you ever heard of Jack Spade bags for men Kate and Andy were behind the
News 2 end know jack is not a real person that cool name
I mean honestly people constantly are saying you know Jacquees they fight or you know Kate Jackson
And then I don't know if there's something else I owe you mean happy
Hey don't talk just yet because in a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors billions from Showtime
The Epic power struggle between two New York Titans who will stop at nothing to take each other down
Set in high-powered world
The finance is the game of big egos big money and Big Steaks
Billions return Sunday February 19th
10/9 Central only on Showtime
Catch up on the first season now download the Showtime app to
Start your free trial
Okay it's now time for another story about something your building
And this one begins about 10 Norfolk
15 years ago when
Kayaking on a creek
You're the town of Sunset
South Carolina
And there was overhanging rhododendron
That created at
Tunnel all the way down the center of the creek
Feet above the water
So you can only like lay down and go underneath these limbs
So
That's what he did lay it on top of my kayak
And went down the creek that way and it was exhilarating so that's what gave me the very first idea
And his idea
Ways to build something he eventually called a belly a cat
Shaped like a kayak
But there's no hollow space in the hall no
Place to sit
So instead
The surface is flat you can lie on top and
Paddle with your hands
What I like about you is it's like flying it's the feeling of flying on water
And you know having a high-performance freestyle kayak hog
Which is made to respond every Nuance of the
The current and feeling that through your entire body and having your hands right there in
The current
That was such a thrilling feeling
Anyway for about a year-and-a-half
Adam tinkered in an old Warehouse with some urethane foam
To get the belly
Just wright
Hey. Bill 24 different
Models
Because I would build it and I be like wow that way
Was good but I need to add a little more volume to the Baldor
What if it were a little narrow here in a little wider here so I thought I would have more question
Try that start with one question what would it be like
And after playing around with it for a while
Finally perfected the bellyak
Adam got a patent
And he was thrilled because he thought
Kayakers
They are going to love this thing
But he was wrong
People
Looks down their nose at it as something that they were too good for
And really it was because Tigers already know how to kayak it's like trying to sell it
Different type of mountain bikes somebody who are mountain bikes they already have their tool for that terrain but over time I don't realize
Is there were other groups of people who
Did like the bellyak
Swimmers
Triathlete
Surfers
And a group he was surprised to hear from the first
Disabled veterans
The Belly Up
Allowed somebody to get out of their wheelchair
And I can be mobile
They could have exercised
They can work on their balance
And the coolest thing was as I've talked to so many guys have used it have been like
And ever since my injury
I've never thought I would swim again and it's helped me get back in the water and that's been the coolest thing to see
Adam says he sold about 8000 bellyak so far
And some people are even starting to use them
In Whitewater competition
But eventually
Adam wants
To see the bellyak on all types of water
Just as you see paddleboards and kayaks on every Lake and every waterway in the country
We want to see people
Prone paddling
Port bellyak
Everywhere
Let's add a masters who sells the philiac
Out of Asheville North Carolina
Hey if you want to tell us your story please send it to us we love
Hearing them go to build
Dot NPR. Org that's build with a D
Npr.org
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or
Or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and play veritis review while you're there
You can also write directly to us at hi BTW at NPR. O RG
And if you want to send a tweet it
At how I built this
Russia always produces Weak by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to leave a grandson.
Mexican port and Jeff Rogers
Are interned is Claire Breen
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
NPR
I'm Linda Holmes from NPR pop culture Happy Hour podcast
What has pointy ears a cape a huge ego and knees that don't bend that's right
Lego Batman
To get the skinny on his new movie and lots of other
Good stuff to watch
And read find pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app or at npr.org
Splash Park
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.