One of the kind of funny things we had to figure out was how to quickly Market to
The college campus whatever early purchases was
A frog and beaver costume that we
Put on I went to Cornell I was actually going to Cornell on a recruiting trip for Lehman
And I was standing on the quad in this ridiculous costume handing out cards about
Is carpooling service to say frog costume and beaver costume
I was the beaver
At the next day at the Lehman recruiting event
A girl came up to me and said
I see you in a in a beaver costume yesterday
Running PR it's how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movement
Verizon on Today Show mermaid private cars work like taxis and in the process
Help build a service hours billion
Rick astley remember the days
Walking on
Onto the sidewalk
Your hand and
Healing a
Taxi
I mean
It feels like ancient history
But still
Even though this world of instant
Car rides
Just a few years old
We're so used to it that
If you like me
You start to get really antsy and anxious when the Uber or Lyft app says you have to wait for 3 minutes for your ride and just think
About how quickly ride sharing apps like uber Lyft
Totally transformed transportation in many cities around the world have
In most places
They've become indispensable which has also meant that
The competition between the two companies
Has been really Fierce since 2012 when both of them launched the service
It turned private cars into public taxis but the amazing thing is is
Even though Lyft is just a fraction the size of uber
It is still valued at more than 5
Billion dollars
And one of the guys behind it
John Zimmer
He never thought that ride-sharing would be his life's work he actually studies Hotel manager
At Cornell
What is interest
Really started to change during his senior year
I took a course that was really really important to me called Green cities
I have this amazing professor
His first lecture is the history of the world in 30 minutes kind of like
The book Guns Germs and Steel
And he ended the lecture saying that we're at a really important time in world history
Where population density is rising rapidly in our cities as more and more people move there
And resources
And infrastructures
That were built decades ago are becoming more and more strength
And he kind of challenges the end of the class instead
If you don't make this class most
Important thing you
Then I don't want to
Because if we don't fix this
These problems
We're going to have major economic
Environmental
And social problem
And that kind of set me on a path
Which eventually led to lift
But being that I grew up
In the east coast and
Connecticut in New York
I did feel like I had to have a financing
Experience in Seoul
After graduating I went and worked at Lehman Brothers
Hi in mm
Wow
Lehman Brothers
Like when we look back on that
Roof
It was like a yeah you know the decline and fall right there so you go to Lehman Brothers
In 2006 What will what did you do there
Samsung real estate Finance
So I was right in the heart of where everything happened
And as you said right at that moment
From 2000s
2008 was my 2-year analyst
Was it
Interesting
It was interesting for a few months but I got to say I
My interests
Declined probably after just about a year
And so I started thinking
What what else I could do
And it was actually about
About a year into it that I was on Facebook one night
And
Saw
Logan who is now my co-founder who I didn't know at the time
Posted
On a mutual friend's Facebook page saying that he was starting a website
Call Zimmer
And what like what
Was it worth it
What's his story
So Logan's background is that
He grew up in LA
Hitting traffic
He then went to UC Santa Barbara and made an experiment of himself so he can bring a car to school
And wanted to see how he could
Survive without a car
And he started a car sharing program similar to Zipcar first
Using University fleet vehicles
And he got the attention of the local transit for
The local Transit board
Elected him as the youngest member ever to be on this Transit boarding at Logan
In Santa Barbara
And he quickly grew to realize
The challenges
In public
Rotation and Encanto
The conclusion that
Across the country
When you pay to get on the bus you really only covering about 30% of the operating
So what that means is that $3 bus for actually cost the government
Tent
And as the lines get more busy
They get harder to fund
And harder to add service
Actually
The more busy they got the worst
So he came to the conclusion that public transit
Rotation was broken
And while the promise of public transit
Phenomenal
The reality
It was not and so
Eden travel to
Zimbabwe
Where he saw people
Sharing rides out of
Necessity
And got inspired to build
Website
That would connect
People going the same way
Terapia able to sell a seat
In their car
And that's why he called the web
After Zimbabwe
Yeah
So basically trying to build a website
Like that was like
Hey I'm going this way I look
Car sharing website
What used to be the you just advertise online
Craigslist or
Put on a pinboard in
Like on college campuses
Saying driving from you know
LA to San Francisco
Do you need a ride
But he was basic
Take a concept and put it on
Exactly
Like you said we had these
Physical bulletin boards or digital bulletin boards
Four people going along the
The same way if they're going home
Spring break
Fall break
But there was no identity
Or ratings behind that and so it was limited in how many
How many people actually
And so we thought how can we make a safe
And
You tied something
Like Facebook
You can have a profile of the individual organ
Going to share ride with
And follow up with ratings
Of
Of how that right
Experience was
At which would create a safer and more broadly used
Environment for for carpooling on College
So what happens to you guys then look at this stage
You and Logan still have met right so do you email him or
Call Amber what
So we got on a
Call I believe in and he said that he was actually going to be
In New York City
In a few weeks
And so we ended up meeting up
And talking a lot about about carpooling and
And I shared
Some of the thoughts that I had from that course I took
Cornell we realized that we were both
So passionate
About solving the same problem
And and began working together right after that trip in New York
Did you end did you guys just hit it off right away you like each other
Yeah
Yeah where he's become my best friend he was
Best man in my wedding
He's also very
Focused
Common thought
Apple person
It's funny story when he was
Is a kid I think he was about
8 years old
His parents had
I just got in the TV
And
I guess a few weeks later he said
He asked his parents to remove the TV
From the house be
Distracting
So I think that just speaks to his
His level of focus and
I really enjoyed
That working with him because of that that book passion
Focus and helpful
Okay so you guys start working on zimride together
You're still at Liam Brothers right
And what was what was Logan doing at this point
So
He's at UC Santa Barbara to sustainability
Dechlorinator after he's graduated
He's working on zimride as a side pot
Project TX
We did
A lot of the original
Coding of the website
And
We didn't know whether
It was a
Big business we thought it
Should be back before we were going to jump all the way and we wanted
To start working on
Do we spend
At nights and weekends
Working on
Zimride
Just like remotely you were in New York and he was in Santa Barbara and you were just
Emailing in like
Skyping and stuff all the time
Yeah yeah we have
Late night sky band
Every maybe month or two
We try to get together
Logan's on he's working on building the website on my end I'm figuring out how do we get enough people using the pie
Heartworm
So that it works it was really like a chicken or egg problem
Where
The idea
I'm having a lot of seats
Statues from on your way home
Say Cornell and UPS
State New York to go to New York City was exciting
Yeah there is
Very few bus routes
Not everyone on the car
Or had a car on campus and so
If I could go on
Zimride Cornell
And bias eating someone else's
Is car for $20 or
$30
That would be really exciting
But it had to be there had to be available we had to
Decorate both sides of the
The marketplace
So the idea was
Like, like that how Facebook originally launched which was
You would just have these
Sights at University so students could figure out
Do they can eat dried with
Exactly and so
One of the
Kind of funny things we had to figure out was
This was how to quickly
Market
To the college campus
This is kind of strange we wanted to put on
Costumes on campus
And hand out information about this service
Whatever early purchases was
A frog and beaver costume
That we
Put on I went to Cornell I was actually going to Cornell
On a recruiting trip for Lehman
But I went a few days early
And
I was standing on the quad
In this ridiculous costume handing out cards about this carpal and service costumers Beaver cast
I was the beaver
Yeah like handing out flyers
Yasso
We needed to get a critical mass
Table called a thousand people
The offering their seat so that those that went on to look for a seat could find one and it worked
And
At the next day at the Lehman recruiting event a girl came up to me while I was surrounded by a lot of
Managing directors and set
I see you in a in a beaver costume yesterday
You know the next step was
Let's sell a private Network
To the various universities
And that we were able to over
A few year. Cell to 150 universities
Companies that would pay us
An annual fee for this private key
Cartoon Network
So you were.
You weren't taking a cut off the
I got the feeling that people would charge
Share ride
Accurate
Not at not at that time
YouTube the business model was a cell this University is like
Subscription model
You were personally calling universities and pitching us to them
Yeah so I was personally calling and traveling to
Probably visited hundreds of universities
And in those first few years how did you do this
In the beginning and work at Lehman Brothers
Actual time
In the first year it was more about getting the product stood up and having a proofpoint
Not being kind of Cornell and so
The majority
Virtually all of those sales came once once I went full-time
In 2008
You would like to know it
Imma do that smile Evelyn
Yes it was
Early 2008 and it made the decision and
At my best friend's mother actually worked in the same building as me
How when I was at Lehman Brothers
I told her what I wanted to do and she said how could you leave a Shore thing like Lehman
To do a crazy carpets.
How many people send it to you by the way you're leaving Lehman Brothers
Yeah 2008
To go do something
Yes at several people said that to me and
And then three months later Lehman was bankrupt
We knew that there were
Challenges going on at Lehman but I could not have predicted that
3 months later
That they would have been bankrupt
So you moved
To Silicon Valley Inn
In 2008 to go full-time
I'm zimride with Logan green
Yes
Did zimride get become profitable
Yep
Play computery profitable or respect
I'd say respectively profit
It was a pretty robust company in
Did you see this as
This was going to be your thing this is what you were going to do with your life
Yeah I mean the dream was to start a business that had a major
An important impact on our world and specifically on the way that our cities are designed
And so
You know I think from an early. We consider this
Our life's work
When you were going to basically transform carpal you were going to do
For carpooling Circle Airbnb stand for
Accommodation
Exactly
So what happened how did you shift from like this concept of carpooling to
What would eventually become
Lyft
So in the middle of 2012
It's like four years in now
Yeah but four years of doing it
Full time
And
And we stop and look at ourselves and say
How are things going
And what would we do
If we were starting over
I think that's a really helpful exercise
End
What was true
In 2012 that was not true
When we started was the proliferation
Smartphones
And operating
That would enable more
Short-term planning
In short distance
It was him ride you had to go on a website and
Find the date on a person going right and you had to
So do it I guess
At least a day in advance
Exactly so once the technology shifted that would enable more insta
Decision-making to happen
Are our thought process
And
You guys start to think maybe we should focus on something else
Yeso
Weird scene
Uber had started
Limos on demand
Black
Yeah and we said you know that's
Interesting from a
You know using
Cheetah mobile technology
But it wasn't that interesting to us from
You're picking
In a small population
People that cannot
Or right
Have a private driver.
Because you're it was like a fleet service
The beginning it was just
These black cars
It was Sunday
Yeso
The average American household spend
Over $9,000
Every year on owning and operating
Car
Equate silver
2 trillion dollars annually
In the US
In the car sits part 96
6% of the time
And so he said
How could we
Take these
Personal vehicle
That are parked at all time
And expensive
To their owners
And make better use of
And and so the idea was
To create an app
Where you could
You could request
Someone's personal vehicle
On demand
Put the platform really at that point was just
Hey I have a car sitting here and I'm going to make it available to kind of rent out for an hour
No it was
Hey I have a car and I have time
And I'm going to go drive other people around Cry 4 for payment
And it goes back to kind of
My Hospitality experience of how do we create something
That was centered around service about treating driver and passenger with respect
But I'll see you got to remember what is now accepted as normal getting into someone else's vehicle
Was not at all nor
Right back
We had to
Work to
Change people's
Behavior and
In the early days suggest
People sit up front
And trading this
Your friend with a car hot hospice
Fatality environment
We felt that one it opened
The audience to a larger set
Of drivers
And if you go in a room of our
A hundred of our friends and you ask how many of you are willing to
To drive a taxi
A couple hands
Maybe go up
When you say how many of you are willing to share a ride
You know 75
Hands would go up
And so
We wanted to create.
The Experience around that
Not because after
Many many years
Of being
Tina told not to
And many many years
Of seeing a yellow vehicle
And thinking that that is safe
Yellow
We had a lot of
In a behavior change to the kind of push through
John Zimmer co-founder of Lyft after the break of the State of California
Killed his company
Amethyst and gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to
The two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First to godaddy.com
Naked customers
Tools inside they need
Transform their ideas
Personal initiative
Success
What's GoDaddy small business owners
Everything I need to get
Online
Including 24/7
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology provider dedicated to small business
They're offering how I built this listeners
30% off all new products
Just going to godaddy.com
Podcast
And use code
Built 30
Thanks also to betterment
Betterment combine time-tested investing principles with
Transparency and ease-of-use you expect
Great technology
Focusing on Lower fees and taxes
Refreshing betterment really cares that you
You reach your financial goals
And that's why they keep their fees low
How I built this listeners can get one month managed for free
For more information is it betterment.com
Built
And just one more thing before I get back to the show
Azure
Don't know by now at the end of every episode we're telling your stories about the companies
Star Products
You are built
Please do stick around to hear it but for now
Show
It's how I built this
From NPR
A guy Roz
So it's 2012 and John Logan we're still working on this carpool concept called the zimride and they were doing pretty
Welded pitched a bunch of investors in Silicon Valley they got some money
But around the time they decided to change course and focus on other ways
They can make car sharing accessible to Millions
Basically an early version of what
Eventually
Hollywood become live
But before they could really launch the app
They needed
Test it out so
I got in touch with him
Drivers
So the first set of of drivers we actually
Emailed a bunch of zimride
Users
And
That we said hey we have this new project we're trying out
And that we love you to try it out
Then we invited them over to the office and walked
True kind of the whole
Experience
That that we were in San Francisco area
Yes
And what did you tell him to do today
I drive around the city
Well we we first got to walk through howdy
Hopworks are all the safety standards that we had
And we let them know that
What what's going to happen is that you're going to get a request
On your phone and it's going to let you know where that that passenger is
That they could go pick up that passenger
And then take them where they needed
And that the Apple kind of help help them
Navigate
And do do all those
Pick-up and drop-off
And at the time
There was a suggested donation at the end of the ride
That the passenger can make
Through their credit card that was a
Attached to their profile
Going to be
Free if you want
To be free
It was an early days you got to remember again one that this was
Was very very
New in and not normal and
United was fault would fall in a regulatory gray area
And so one of the ways
That we we we saw around that was to say
How to make it optional for payment in the early days until we had
@ford through
The the right regulatory structure
At what point did you come up with that
Set a new name when did it go from
Something called zimride to
Before we launched it
At the working title was in Wright insta
But while going through
It's actually really
3 week. That the
Lyft app the original Lyft app was built
Very very fat now
And the brand lift
Was thought of during that period as well along with
The logo and everything
Thanks
Yeah except you couldn't get LIF
That was probably take
Yeah lafc.com is owned by Otis Elevator
Okay fair enough
So you got lym
Yeah in the middle of 2012
Again over 3 weeks.
The team moved incredibly fast to
Build the app
Come up with the branding
And meat
And background check and I'm bored
The first set of drivers and then we then we invited a few friends and
It was that we got an incredible response to this is only in San Francisco at this point right
Yes
How long did it take before
You know you open this up you made this into a decimal
Anybody could use
Since it was probably dead the second half of 2012
Where are we
It started to take off
We started to divert resources from zimride over to lift and I'm really in in January of twenty
We said
Okay we need to go all in
This is
A massive opportunity
This has been incredibly successful
With a small amount of focus
But that was a really
In many ways a tough moment because we had worked
You're for five years on zimride
And we were deciding to divert all of our attention
To an entirely new model see you guys
Sold
Exactly so we sold them right to Enterprise Rent-A-Car
And basically did the assets
Add a contract with the universities
And retained the entire team
And went all-in on unless
So that first-year how many people downloaded the app
Best gas tens of thousands
And you guys are your model as you were taking a cut out of every
Right right
Today the rate is calculated
FaceTime
Distance and time
And then lift I received
A commission off of that weather
20 to 25%
I offer the overall rate the rest goes to the driver
As well as a
I trust and service fee
So when you start this right
Did you I mean it now we look back and say oh yeah
Course is going to work but presumably like you started
Face a lot of backlash
Obstacles
Some cities that had
Pretty entrenched
Taxicab commissions and drivers and
Established
Regulations about who can pick people up and drive them for money
Yasso
About a month into launching left this was
Later
At 2012
Received our first of many cease and desist
Not from various different governments
And
It basically said you need to stop by
And what did you do
Do we read the letter and then we had already done our
Like working
Research on the laws and and we asked for a meeting
I think I was followed by a second season to Sis but we eventually got
I'm eating
With with who with a Public Utilities Commission
Okay and our approach to regulations is to to really understand
The motivations and the needs of
Of the regulating entity
Because we understand they have a very important job
And we went in and asked that we said he looked
Is this a matter in a public safety
Or is this about you know existing Industries
Anderson Public Safety of course until we said we don't own Vehicles we don't have employees driving for us
So we don't fall into
The category that you currently have
But we've looked at your safety regulation since that's the most important
Important thing
And
We've gone above and beyond on a background check
Actually still to this day for
Limos in in California are not required
We've done
Driving record check
More strict criteria
Eric rated insurance policy
But the million dollars and there's is and was 750
$2,000
We said so if it's about safety
What we'd love to do with you to create a new category
.
Allows you to enforce that we are doing this
These things that we tell you we're doing
But that we were able to do this in
In a safe
That way that brings more affordable
Transportation
California
They were threatening to sue you right
They were threatening to shut us down
Enforce against the drivers that we're driving in
What are you scared of about that possibility
Yes cuz you'd sold out of them ride and she put all your eggs in this basket and
It could have been shut down
Yeah I think I literally had a headache for 1 month
I wish I had to go
Check and make sure nothing was wrong but it was incredibly stressful time
Because as you said we switched
All of our Focus over to from zimride to Lyft
And the opportunity was massive and the regulatory obstacles that we're just
What does massive how long does it take for you to overcome
Those initial
Regulatory challenges like months years at least at least
Year early for that first year if I was to pick the one thing I spent most of my time on
Was the government relations and was working to create a new regulatory category 4 for the space
And then you know not just doing that in one state
But being able to demonstrate that in in multiple cities and states
So when so when you started
To expand outside of San Francisco and La how fast were you expanding to other cities is it like every month every
Cheat day every week
That kind of earlier. It was more
Every few months
Maybe the most intense moment was
April
2014 when we launched 24 marker
It's on the same day
Who are your competitors
Is Uber was still doing
Remind me by car
Yeah there really wasn't
There was some other companies that were trying in this in this kind of peer-to-peer
Personal vehicle space
But there wasn't a large amount of copper
Petition
There are still so many questions looming around regulatory
Franklin
That I think Nina people were waiting back to see how that played up
Your focus was on
This
What are B&B bottle where you got a car
And
It's going to be community and
The sharing economy thing like
What happened when when all the sudden Uber
Started doing a brat
Where they basic
Copy tramada
Yes so I mean we assume that because the opportunity was so large and everything we're seeing that there would be more
More competition coming
And so it wasn't it wasn't it wasn't a big surprise
And
It just you I think over the
The course of the few years we've been doing this it's
It made us better and frankly I think both both companies grow fast
How do you differentiate
Yourself from them
How do you make the case that actually you should go with us and not bad
Yes Orr Focus
In the early days was we needed to
Ensure we solved the two most important things for our customers first which was not reliability you can get a ride
Ride when you want it at the best possible price once you have parody on those and now it now we do we built up
Enough infrastructure
Enough basic driver community that you can get a ride within on average 3 minutes
In the cities then it's about the experience in today's world
By treating drivers better than any other company the ability to have cashless tips get
Paid in the same day
Create an environment where drivers are respected by passengers and nuts and translates to passengers be
A treated better
Then another service are you a competitive person like do you
Do you look at your competition and really one
Want to beat them
Yes absolutely
Like how much is a drive you
That idea
Auditor
I'd say to a large degree I used to play sports
Whether it was running track or a playing soccer
And you know I started running track as
Just to stay in shape for soccer and then
I wanted to
To win the race and I wanted to
Go under 5 minute mile
And was able to do that and so I think often now today
You know where it where in
Hello
What could be described as a mile
Four laps
And where in lab 2
You know that 3 is typically in that race the most critical.
Were you set yourself up
For victory in cell
I think we're making a lot of important moves and decisions now
That should allow us to to win the race
To take it personally like you know
Uber obviously has you know been a pretty tough competitor in a X or Ben
Accusations that the
But they've kind of
How to sabotage you or maybe you guys
Diamond
It is it is a personal 2D is it something that you really
Feel emotionally
Yeah yeah definitely
I don't mean
Is part of it well just is it just business in
Business
Days where you hate your
Your competitor but you always still respect them or is it really like no actually this is really personal I don't like them
I think we take it and I take it personally which drives me
Because I believe so strongly in what our team is working on and why were work
We believe that
By building what we're building we can make our cities
Designed around people
Instead of cars
And
By having the right values
An ethics
We can impact Society in a way that's bigger than a transfer
Vacation week
And so
I take it personally
Because
We're out to win for the values that we represent
I don't let that distract me
I let that you know fuel the fire
And
I think in the early days
When I was less mature
It would it would distract
But but today I think
It just feels
The desire to push harder
Set the company there's
About 1300
And then drivers do you to disclose that number
No we've said several months ago that you know last year there was over 300,000 and you can assume that this year
Have that number has grown quite significant
And we think about like these ride-sharing
Companies
Uber and left
As
The stainless permitting that we all fall come to depend on I've got the apps app for both companies
Imyfone sorry to have both
And
This become
Harbor Lights like there's like I can't even remember what life was like before Lyft or Uber
Friday
And yet we have to imagine Monday
Something is going to replace you guys and people think of driverless cars
Do you ever think about that
Sure I mean it's that
You know I I saw the rise and fall of Lehman right before my eyes and I think that that creates the
The right sense of
Awareness
And when building a company that that you've seen something like that
But when you look at the future you know you talked about autonomous cars
An autonomous car is not going to drop out of the sky and be able to do a hunter
That's not real
What's real is that
Over the next
Couple years it'll be able to
Do
A few percent of our trips
10% of our trips
50% of our trip
And
What that means for this opportunity is that
We're going to be able to address that ultimate goal we have of ending car ownership and providing a full out
Alternative
To owning a car in fact what you'll be able to do
Is by
Likely a miles plan from us
A monthly subscription
Hot to handle all your transportation
And over the next few years some of those trips will be done by
Human drivers in another's
That will be done by autonomous vehicles
To the point that we can provide you with amazing
Hospitality experiences on wheels
Will you look back at you know
Carpeting Logan over Facebook and then like
Look on the side project moving to Menlo Park Inn
Corn your heart and soul into the into zimride and
Then starting left and watching it turn into a computer valued this valued over 5 billion dollars do you sort of look at that
Dad and sister save yourself
Okay I can like breathe out a sigh of relief like
We're okay we've made it we've gone we've passed the hump
Or are you constantly worried and vigilant
Everyday
Yeah. I don't think there's a acai of
Accomplishment I think there is
The bar keeps getting raised and that's the bar that
That we raised on ourselves
The goal over the last 10 years
For Logan I hasn't changed
You know it was them ride
And then it was left
And then it will have
Autonomous implication
Until we've accomplished
The fact that you don't need to own a car in a city
Until we've accomplished the fact that we don't need
As many roads and parking lots
In our cities
Until we allow for our cities to be
A redesigned around the people living in them instead of the cars
That are parked in them
Then we're not happy
Where is a co-founder of left if you've been following the news lately
Competition between Lyft and Uber has suddenly become political and I mean
Political like Donald Trump political for starters Trump's travel ban prompted Lyft to make A1
Million dollar pledge to the ACLU which is fighting the ban you a lots of writers were Furious
Cast of the founder of Advisory Group
That group before that happened more than 200,000 Riders deleted their Uber accounts and all
All of that has led to a spike in business
Turn left
Please don't turn it off
Just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you guys are building
The first quick thanks to one of our sponsors Wells Fargo
Imagine what you can do with
The right business credit
From expanding your business to increasing your inventory and buying equipment
Wellsfargoworks
Can help you Achieve Financial
Test for business
Discover online tools and resources to help your business Thrive at wellsfargo.com
Wells Fargo together we'll go far
FDIC
Hey it's time now for another installment of how you built that
And this one came to us from Jaya Irish lives in Oakton Virginia
And a few years ago when jaya's daughter was
She stood up
And made a declaration
My daughter she wants to grow up to be an astronaut
I so that's when I started looking around for clothes with astronaut or space team and I realize that they were really
Four girls and shirt I could have bought an astronaut shirt or pajamas in the voice part
Her daughters
Favorite color
What is Pink
I actually looked every place
And there was nothing at all not a single pink astronaut shirt
But as it turned out
Just the right person to
Tackle this problem she actually has a
PhD in clothing merchandising
So I actually got in touch with some freelance designers and I created a few designs like I made a monster
Truck
Which was on a t-shirt
Didn't say anything boy about it
I made a pink T-shirt with a race car on it I met a girl firefighter online course
Also sketched out that
Pink T-shirt with an astronaut on it
She put her drawings online she launched a Kickstarter campaign
X-rays
30000 bucks
And I was lucky that I had the support of my husband who is always
Let me know if you really believe in it go and do it
Soak with the kickstarter money
Jaya found a factory in India willing to make the shirts
Japan expanded her lines shirts
Computer code test tubes and a solar system that glows in the dark
All for kids
But there was a problem
Be actually had a lot of parents reaching out to us saying hey we don't have anything like this for the moms of these kids
Lots of moms who work in science were
Talking about clothes for grown ups
I started designing dresses with things like the
Periodic table the double-helix the solar system
Equations
Many school teachers College professors actually on our customers
Tina Dixon feel great about teaching math and thing that hate America mattress because I love math
And if you feel like Miss Frizzle
Diet now has about 80 designs in their online store
In last year
Just one year into starting her business
She and her partner were able to pay themselves
Pretty decent salary
Seriously I did not expect it to become what it has become because when I started I just did it because
My daughter wanted
And then it just grew and grew and now it's growing so fast that you're having a hard time handling this
Sometimes that's China or her company is called Spa hot pink
It's named for her daughter who is now five by the way and the monster
How to be a singer a painter
And a doctor
Hey thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes
You can go to how I built this
Npr.org. Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and
Paper write a review while you're there you can also write directly to us at Hib tea at NPR.
ORD and if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
Usherwood produces week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to neva grandson of meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Are interned is Claire Breen on Gyros and he's been listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey thanks for listening to the show this week if you're still looking for another great
NPR Podcast
Please check out pop culture happy hour
There is
So much out there to watch it
Read discuss
I'm so overwhelming
But this show how culture happy hour
Helps you sort it out
Figure out what
What's worth binge-watching
Downloading
Reading
Pop culture happy hour calls out
The best most
Creative and most
Fun things
You can find something
Thing to make you happy every week
On pop culture happy hour from
NPR
Find the show at NPR. Org
/ podcasts
And on the
NPR one app
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
In email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.