Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
How did you even know how to make a burger I mean where you a good homes
Chef with anybody in your family listen to come from my hometown can't make a burger you can't live
We know how to make burgers I know how to cook potato that was born yet
Fried potatoes and that's all you really needed to know
From NPR how I built this
A show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
And the stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Roz and Ali family
Burger joint in Suburban Virginia became one of the fastest-growing restaurant chains in American history
Jerry's going to move
Sakura get a little closer
Okay
Can you see me okay
You ready
No
Introduce yourself please if I met you at a party I'd say who you with
Morale
And what do you do
Sell hamburgers
This is the founder of Five Guys Burgers and Fries
Jerry Murrell is 73 years old
And a long journey to get to where he is today
He was born in a small mining town in northern Michigan
His dad wasn't around that much
Que pasa
An adventurer he wasn't very family-oriented and he was a stunt pilot
That's probably why my mom and him got a divorce and a family room
Kid where he says he was
The nuns used to say when are you going to end up selling hamburger something so
I did get through school and eventually
University of Michigan I got scared there I said my God how am I going to make it this world with all the smart people around
In fact I was more intimidated after I got out of college then.
Endeavor
So after college Jerry moved back to his hometown and he married his high school girlfriend
I got a job selling life insurance and they had three sons but the marriage didn't last
Ended up leaving and taking the kids to Florida and for Jerry
That was a low Point kind of floated around for awhile lived in different cities it wasn't sure what
Used to do with his life
But he was sure of one thing
You wanted your kids to live with you
How you do that why I didn't know
Around the mid-1970s
Jerry was offered at consulting job in the DC area so he took it and he moved to Alexandria
Virginia
That's where he met his second wife
Cheney
And after situation stabilized
His kids did
Actually come to live with them
And it was also around that
I want Jerry decided
Become a financial planner
I was shocked at how much money there was in the
DC area size I'm going to go back to the
Financial planning business
I got my degree for
Bryn Mawr
And I started
Town Financial products that people
DC area
And that's what I did
To the boys move in with you
All of a sudden you got five people
Cancel the 5 p.m.
And that was basically what you did you Weaver financial planner
As a financial planner I tried a few businesses I started Oil Business
Austin Texas
I did a couple other dumb
I tried to start a water business
List of all things I thought
Selling bottled water back on living a good idea
And everybody laughed at me and hard time raising
Is in the early 80s
Clayton Middle 70
The worst one was oil because I started a company and I went down to Texas
Person found out the
They were waiting for me because I was from the East and they're going to take all my money
My wife and I went into the real estate business and we will
We were experts at
Buying real high
And then went to a crashing
How to get rid of it
Okay so if I get this right
You were doing financial planning is your main
Job
You had like all these business ideas that you would try out on the side
Yeah basically
Bright
I really didn't know what else to do
I'm just lucky I'm just lucky that
But I got the hamburger
What's a Genesis
You want to hear the short side of the Long Island where I grew up
There was a guy
Name push em up Tony
Push em up Tony
Had a little tiny hamburger place
With a picnic table with
And he had a grill
I need Ensign except hamburger
Wishing happy
Anna
Stuck in the back of my mind
Does people used to come from all over town to get Hamburg
And then when I moved to Washington
I saw something like just couldn't Ocean City Maryland
I need a place the number song Boardwalk fries there's a place are called Thrashers
20 places on Boardwalk fries
But only one place have a long line
Whenever freshers
Why does a hundred feet long all day long
Show me and the kids
Ganondorf my light hamburgers
Fry's
Cheapest simple might work
And that's where the idea came from
So what did you do did you
I mean did you go to your wife and say let's try Burger Joy
Yes what you say
Pocket same thing the banks
Chat at the time
Are you guys on your mind
But we are
We did a little different
We said let's not put a lot of money in
Unless
Find the place where the rent is real law
Out of the way
Where nobody can see it
Would you want to do it that way
And we said well if we can put it where
It's hard to find
But if we can get people coming there
Then we know we got some
And this was in in 1986
Yes
Where was the first location
Columbia Pike and Glebe Road
In Arlington Virginia
And it was like a little
Place in rent was cheap and what was the how much money did you have to put up to $35,000
What did that cover
Everything
The the rent
Equipment equipment
We found junk equipment rebuilt it ourselves
I was
Stand up only
And
Chad
Matt were still in high school
Jack chambless I think I'll be 13 or something
I said I got some money saved up
Curry College
And if you want to go to college
And now
They pretty much said
God would rather do something else
Wake up go back for a second you set your kids down
And if you had your kids college fund and you said to them
Hey look I got this college money I will send you to college
Or
You cannot go to college we can use it to open up a burger joint
Were you coming to eat
You can imagine today like a parent
Saying that to their kids and then other parents saying
Your mortgage in your kids future on this burger joint yes
Did you have any of that
Feeling in your mind like maybe this is not a great was telling us it was right thing to do
Probably look back on it was probably assumed it was Cowboys kind of crazy
It was crazy it didn't seem crazy.
For some reason we all seem to be on board with
I was really surprised
Is a kids Jump Right In and
Work tired
Jenny workout
She kept all the books
I was amazed how the how the kids
Jumped into it
And what is the story with the name how did
How did you come up the Walmart one of my lawyer said you should
Incorporate
You need to have a name
She fills out the paper
This was so well thought out that we didn't happen
So
Boise
We had that
Three Sons
Plus one more sandwich
Janie
My stepson wasn't born yet
So is four Sons with me so we should go out
Call Five Guys for now and then we'll change it
So we get the papers fill out
Okay sign on your first day of the opening day 1986 did you
Detroit grand opening
Helena first open up at 11
There's no business at all until quarter 12
And then one person finally walked in and
12:30 we were we were almost packed and we made money for my very first day
We were breaking even and we're paying our rent
I need an employee's right cuz everybody was a couple employees but
Mostly with the kids and we were
Paying them some I think the timer Pan Am 759 or something like that
How did you even know how to make
A burger I mean where you a good home chef with anybody in your family a good chef
Listen to come from my hometown can't make a burger you can't live so I'm in that we know how to make burgers
And I'm from where I'm from is
Posen was right near Bissonnet raised potatoes
I grew up in a fire that we raised a lot of potato I know I know how to cook a potato
And I know you know how to cook a hamburger
That was born yet
Gorilla burger at a fried potatoes and that's all you really needed to know
What is the ingredients
How did you know
How to Source this
We went to Thrashers
In Ocean City
And looked on the potato bags
And we found out they came from Rigby Idaho
A guy named Rick miles
Small potato dealer out there so we got ahold of him
I wish I could you show us potato
We did not know what the time that he was small
Now he's become a multi-millionaire
We buy are potatoes from him
What was so special about his potatoes
They were sold by Thrashers in Ocean City
So you said
If there's a line outside the
Potato Joy
Potatoes must
I did good
Be good
What was Five Guys offering
Was it burgers
All the toppings and all that stuff we did with her kids
Jamie and I would not
Tell the kids how much we were paying for the Prada
WeChat
Whatever pickles you want to put on there
Hamburgers
You guys pick
Pickles
So they were trying different brands and different pickles
Validate end up with the most expensive pickle
And we wouldn't say anything
Think about it would say okay that's a big what you want by those pickles
First
Okay then we will buy the most expensive cooking oil you want to cook in
That's where they cook them
City
They wanted to buy this bread from a little baker
Arlington that made really good bread
Brenner's Bakery
Best bakery in Arlington
But for
My restaurant
Expensive
We're paying about 7 times
Trump hamburger buns
McDonald's
And what was the burger going for in 1986
I think we're sound sounds like three times four times at McDonald's
What sound for a crazy would make it that way
We didn't let
The kids know
How much we're paying for any of the food
So they would just go out there in
Whatever it was
That they like it that's the way it was
And what was the thinking behind that
Strategy
The thinking was that they're going to pick the best product
They got to pick with the customer likes what they like
Give an example how ridiculous
Kids like to certain kind of mayonnaise cuz it was thick
And it would hold things together and that we were buying our mayonnaise at the time
Guy up in New York City that was really hard to get along with and so when we hired our first purchasing age
He said there's no way that Manny's is this important no way to describe it so hard to deal
So we had all the family come in and do a blind mayonnaise taste
And to this day I can't eat mayonnaise by itself so we have like nine different
Dishes with mayonnaise and tactical spoon and everybody with
Taste of mayonnaise blindfolded and he shall improve together you can't tell the difference in this mayonnaise or any
And after the Ashley took a bath salts off my wife myself and all the boys pick the same initials
Beacon New York
So why
King and I what we would do it at the end of the month we look at them
Sales
And then we look at how much we paid for the food and we said we got to raise our prices
The kids didn't know why we raised
The prices but we would always say
Food cost
Stay around 30%
Whatever we got to do
We got a raise prices
Raise prices
And we have if we have to worry about price
We don't want to be in this bed
Okay so you've got this
First Burger Joint right
And how did people find out about
How do people even know about
The only way would be
Somebody else telling them they said there's a
Great burger places little like
Why captcha
You got to try it
That's the only way they would have found out about
There was a place in DC when I first moved here at office downtown
Lunch break
What was downstairs
It was an ally
And it was nothing on the door if I remember right just a steel door coming off the alley
Butt.
All the offices around there
We go to this place
And I was on marked and it was an ally
I was always impressed with the fact that that guy could do that much business on there and I knew him I know how much money was made
He sold it
And within three months it was gone
The people were going there for the food
And it was working
And I sure want her to think I can do that then
I just will just open up in a corner and people like yourself, if they don't like us they want and then we won't be in the business
Coming up how Five Guys did stay in business
And how they grew Way Beyond Virginia even though it was the last person who wanted to do that cuz
Jerry
Play with us on Gyros and you listening to how I built this
NPR
Hey thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Business insurance expert to understand that
Which business is
As unique as a fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent solutions to every business has very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase of policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance Expo
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulator
Licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini the regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
Chokecherry the sun's open.
Tiny burger joint in Arlington Virginia
And it first
People knew about it through word-of-mouth
Record
Eventually
Newspaper started to write about the burgers
And then the lines started to get longer
So Jerry and his family started to think about opening a second location
But
They needed the money to finance it
I remember going in the bank
They said they're going to do what the hamburger place
That was just a laugh. Us
But that
Said we got friends
That their parents got a little bit of money and they know Five Guys is doing good
Maybe we'll ask them for
For a few thousand
So we got
Eventually we got about a hundred fifty two hundred people
That would be blowing anyone time to give us some money
But not as invest
Just for loans
We did it a different way we did it as investors would say
Give us $5,000
Will give you
Certain percentage of the
Gross not never that
Prophet
Cuz it was always too many ways
Cheap people that way
Do I said
We'll give you a certain percentage of the gross
Will give you the money every single month
And
Anytime you want your money back you can have it there by shield-wall that's
Stupid because you have a blimp
I was going to come and ask for the money back
But my method to my madness was also that
I said to them anytime I want to pay you back I can
Cuz I knew someday
If this thing was successful
Are you going to get better financing
I can go back to these people I'm paying back anytime I want
So you never gave them
Said they weren't Equity owner
Not in the real sense
We just made an outside
If the store does
20000 week you get
Certain percentage at every
And we gave the money
Exactly on time every month
We could always go back and ask for more money so how much money did you
Did you raise for to do store number 2
Waffle House store number to we probably only had to raise Maybe
But we had we had a lot of people that just want to throw money at I say like the burgers
They like the fact that we are making money and what they were getting paid every month
I had a boat
75 people I didn't even know on that list
And I used to say to everyone
Don't put your money in somebody else's business
It seems like a lot of people song Something Five Guys
Were you
Fully committed to this or did you or you still doing financial planning program for an answer
At what point
Do you say
To your kids your wife you know I'm going to give up
My job
And I'm going to focus on Five Guys full time
Well that was almost the day I got hit in the head with a broom
I must have been having a bad day at the office or something then I went home and I said my wife I quit
She said
You got to be crazy nice enough I'm done I'm not going to work anymore
I'm just going to
Concentrate on the burger business
She was
Pretty upset
Because she thought this is too risky
And that you thought
I think we can make this
Well I just I thought it was fun
Yeah I was told my kids I said
You don't have to be in this
If you want to be
Make sure it's fun pick something you like to do in the business
Okay so now it was like the entire family focusing full-time on Five Guys
What would like roles did everybody play
Well
Jamie is like a a general and she is very organized runs office and everything but
My kids were able to go to investors and so I I kind of if it wasn't for
For them and my wife there be no Five Guys I didn't Bill Five Guys
Isis
Set around thinking that this thing is growing so fast I can't believe that you know they came up
But most of the new ideas
They pretend they listen to me soup I have lived in in the Washington DC area for a long time off and on
I remember you know driving to Virginia
In like you know 1999-2000 to get Five Guys burger in Virginia
I want it was still just what four or five locations
Up until 2002 you grew up to five
And were you doing pretty well were you all making a decent living at that point
You guys must've been rich
No but the thing is we had figured out the nuts and bolts of the business by now
Most franchisors
Start off
Franchise
We didn't start off the franchise we had no idea we're going to do that we start off the building family business
And we put 17 years into it
We figured out
How to do it right
Yeah so when it came time to franchise
We had a
Perfect system
How did you done at that point say
You hate books franchise
Build this thing out
My sons came to me about
Late night late 1990 and started
Trying to convince me that franchise
And I was dead set against
Really.
Because I didn't think there was any way I could convince other people
To do what we were doing
How did they change your mind
Well
There was a guy
Name Mark Moseley
It was selling franchise
For another company
She been watching Five Guys for a while
And
My kids
Got me
To meet with him I didn't want to do it
They bought me a book called
Franchising
Dummies
Written by
Dave Thomas
Old guy from Wendy's
Yes okay
I'm sorry I read it and then and I
The legal stuff
I was amazing all the rules you have to follow on everything
So when they talked me into it
Because of her when you start franchising
First of all, the franchise either you're not going to worry about food cause I pretty
Sounds pretty stupid
You Got Talent franchise either you're not going to advertise I saw a priest
Stupid
You going to tell him that you're only going to sell hamburgers and french fries
We're all going to be open later we got to sell alcohol we got to watch Food cars Suite
Shop around for rrproducts
I said I won't do that
We buy from people and we're going to stick with him
That was all hard to sell the franchise
But we we got through that
And I remember Mark coming in
Cuz he was going to be our salesman
He said he's going to sound like I can't remember how many stores are first year they're going to sell but I said
50 just cut down to 25 you don't have to sell 50
And I think within a year-and-a-half two years we sold 3500
We saw the whole United States
Burgers were still a lot more expensive than absolutely
Man takes longer to get a burger so
I need the business model is different so were you worried, did you ever think
Ghetto maybe this works in Northern Virginia but I'm not sure this is going to work
Somewhere else
Absolutely scared the heck out of us
You were talking about the long way
I used to have a sign at one of our stores
That said if you're in a hurry
There are a lot of really good burger places
Near here
Daddy can't put that sign up
Can it help
I remember the first franchise store we opened up was in Rich
Alaska
Goderich
Nobody's you know who we are
Yeah I couldn't sleep tonight
Richmond that's like down the road 90 miles it's nothing
But I couldn't even sleep last
Nobody's going to know who we are Richmond Stover successful
And then I said well
Now we're going to go to
North Kim
And I said no way we're going to Florida cuz people
Nevermind
Product in Florida cuz they're older people
Florida
I got a hundred stores in
The idea of going from
Five stores in 2002
Thousands of stars
Within
Aur 2002 storage we seoul
Franchise
Those are still being built out
In the United States
We got about 1400
Palmdale Tower
With all the territory the United
Face is gone
Was that just
Mind-boggling
Mine bazzi
Anna and I was I was so proud of my kids that didn't go to their head
They're still my kids
DreamWorks or something you said they work hard on everyday
What does it mean
What's it like to work with you or
Five sons and in your wife I mean
They're all involved the coming what date did you do a different thing for the company
Well I have one son that
Just love
Doing stuff in the store
Make sure they're painted right
Decorated rice
He's really into that
So that's his job at 1:40.
About the food
So he goes around the world but not chosen how to cook things right stuff
I got another assignment that that he's really into the financial part of it
Grabbed it and I'm glad
Because I don't understand a lot of
Specialist International
Everybody's kind of found their own little debt show
Business real
Some of my teaching some light working in the field
One of them just loves
Taking care of making sure there's no food borne illnesses in The Fanatic about and she loves doing it
Amazon.com find what they want to find an app that can't be
You still buy them that will hire somebody
Is your family still
The primary owner of the company
Yes wait we on about 75% income
Me and my family
We took in a fairly big investor but when I first start franchising
They don't interfere in our business at all they gave us
Big chunk of money
Larry entrepreneurs do when they saw something
Five Guys
What percentage of the actual
Restaurants do you guys own does it does
14 1500 restaurants Whittier
We have a joint venture and Great Britain and France and Germany where we own
With our partner half that's about 6
Thesaurus and then over here we own
About 450 out of the 1400
How many countries
Total is Five Guys
In-N-Out
Where am I Great Britain
Which
I guess it's still want country advocate for now UK stores are weird
Who won France
We just opened up and
Sean's did Jose
Storm madrid begat
Several stores
The Middle East
So I
I think a lot of people when they get a little bit successful
They look back and try to figure out how they did it
I can't figure it out
Do you think a lot of it was luck
Who sings I give a lot of credit to my ballot great believer in
Intuition or a higher power
God whatever you want to call it
Great believer in not
Listening to my hunches
And
I could have got my own that's for sure
My kids are my wife cuz
Seems like to me without them nothing
Dumb
We were lucky really lucky
Real real lucky
Do you
Really your vision was not to
Open up a burger joint your vision was to get
Your kids to live with you
When you and your wife divorce
Which that was your I guess that was your real success
Getting your kids
Are the best things ever have in my life is my kids there's no doubt about that
And the best thing that's happened to their mother
To my ex-wife
Is the fact
The rambling
Do all kinds of wonder
Yeah
And you still have a
Pretty good relationship with her
My current wife
Hatuey William
We get along if she's benefited from your
The success of your sons
How did being
Financially stable
End
Set out of that change your life were you able to do things that you
You couldn't do before
Well
Most people that I know
I've known
Since I've been a kid
When I started Five Guys
Silent three or four my buddies that I went to HighSchool with
Buy stock in my company
I thought it would be a great thing for
Canadian hat
Little bit a little bit
And one of my had a loan on the money
And they're all millionaires
But we're still
Same old people I mean I just had
Bunch of money
Friends down from my Michigan a couple weeks ago on my boat
Florida
We drink beer together
34 years ago
You can lead a pretty Anonymous life like knowing you're not walking on the street and no one's like there's Jerry the founder Five Guys
Know that my wife always says
She gets upset up
Sitting on the front yard
Mercante beans
I always wear Levi's
But that
I don't
I don't know how other people look at me but
I don't I don't think anybody put on airs I hope not
Yes it's amazing what you said earlier that
That when he was a kid that the nuns said you were going to sell hamburgers
What about
Your mom
What would you thought about
What you did with Five Guys hamburger
My mom like hamburger
Shoe cobbler with. That was a good idea that my mom used to say
If you can make good hamburger
Or serve good drink
Or get a good haircut your voice
Have some to do you
Have an income
Jerry Murrell
Founder of Five Guys Burgers and Fries
Did you add up all of the restaurants in franchises around the world
He says they are approaching 2 billion dollars in Revenue
Oh wait four years
Has resisted selling milkshakes years ago after considerable debate
Some stores decided to start selling them with mix in flavors like peanut butter banana
Strawberry salted caramel and of course
Bacon
And please don't turn it off
Just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you guys are build
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Do you have an idea for your next big move
You can use Squarespace award-winning designer templates
How to create a beautiful website or online store
Equipped with everything you need to run your business
Is it squarespace.com to start your free trial and use offer code build it
10% off your first purchase
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
Asteroid today comes from Aiden emmolo she lives in Jackson Wyoming with her husband Jesse
They're two dogs the Husky is yazz named after the baseball player and the German Shepherd
Is Tuckerman and all four of them spend a lot of time outside in Jackson Wyoming so
Fly fishing trail running hiking with dogs love it the humans love it
Except for a small problem my dog Tuckerman I noticed the cloudiness
Anodized when he was pretty young like only two years old and then we noticed Yeah Yeahs was getting pretty
Visible sunburn after we spent long days on the water Jackson Wyoming
Wheely bright
And that's what happens a lot of dogs are sensitive to overexposure their eyes swell up
Cloud over
And some dogs can even lose their Vision so to find a solution
Eden's husband Jesse started digging through their old
Ski equipment
So he just started
Chopping up
You got goals and came up with these
Retrofitted goggles for the dogs which one
Weiser they got from the Dollar Store take
To the old ski goggles I'll put together with a jumble of straps and hair ties I think I probably laugh
Felt loud when we first put them on it like this is
This is ridiculous but I guess you know what better a silly looking dogs in a blind dog
Even jessicat for finding the goggles until people started to ask them where can I get those for my dog
But they weren't sure there was an actual market for dog goggles
So
They decided to ask an expert their vet
So he put the Prototype down and looked across the table at us and said well
You're probably going to need some capital and I looked over and said yeah yeah I think we will and he's like well
I think that's our next conversation
Togaf their bad actually gave them some money enough money for Aiden and Jessie to find a manufacturer
In China and then launched their very first line the lenses range from neon pink to
Neon green a lot of people love the The Crazy Ones as it's because they make your dog look like some store
Superhero robot they make him look pretty badass
2 years ago they sold more than 10,000 goggles and are planning to release for new models by the end of the year
And she her husband quit their day jobs
College reunions and you know everyone's going around and I haven't seen you the right to do what do you do what are you doing
Make dog goggles and people say what
That's Aiden emmolo Jackson Wyoming
Their company is called Rex specs
And three more about it on our Facebook page just search
How I built this on Facebook
And of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org
We love hearing what you're up to
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to hell
How I built this. Npr.org
You can also subscribe to our show on Apple podcasts or however you get your podcast
You can write to us
Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want to send us a tweet it's at how I built this
Our shows produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant Santa's meshkinpour clearbrain and Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Lawrence will
I'm guy Raz and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
If you're looking for a new podcast to try happy
Planet Money
Give it a fresh listen
One thing people say about planet money is
How much they love listening to it even though they don't
Are my business or economics
It's just a smart show with great stories that help explain our world
It's
Explanatory journalism at its best
Pretend that really need some sand reporting about the big question
Find Planet Money on NPR one or wherever you get your podcasts
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com