Support for how I built
Send the following message
Come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn
Why by searching Michigan pure opportunity
Support for this podcast
Comes from American
Express
If you listen to how I built this
Mercurius
And you probably have some
Ideas of your own
American Express open can help
You with money
Know how
You can turn those ideas
Action
Is it open. Com
Open the doors to Home Depot and is there just a mad rush of people to come in
Not as expected to be a mile safe and so we
We agreed we weren't going to talk to each other the morning
Open up into stores and my three older children
They were each given $500 1 in $1 bills so it's 6 at night
Hi there was standing from the store still handing out $1 bills so we had this grand opening and nobody came
From NPR how I built this show
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
Gyros in on this special live episode when Arthur Blank
Fired from corporate job in mid 30s
Plan for a new company
The Home Depot
When Home Depot opened it
First store in Atlanta
The world course
Other hardware store
Time there was nothing
Quite like home
For starters it was huge
Almost twice as big as its
Competitors
And second
Did I forget things like
Free workshops and staff who could
Tell you how to feel
Make stuff at home
But most importantly
Home Depot
Sheep-like
10 to 20% cheaper than other hardware stores
Initially Home Depot wasn't a sure thing in fact on day one
It wasn't
Clear it would work
But today
Home Depot is a company that does almost
A hundred billion dollars
An annual revenue
And it's one of the 10 biggest private Employers in the US
In the story of how Arthur Blank
And his mentor Bernie Marcus built it
Will inspire anyone who's ever been fired because
If those guys had never got fired
Safe
And comfortable corporate jobs
They have never started Home Depot
Arthur and Bernie no longer run the company
Anybody still on Lots
So shares
And Home Depot's made them rich
Arthur blank's net worth
Is estimated at more than four
Billion dollars
He is beloved in his adopted hometown of
Atlanta
Are they part of that has to do with his
Stewardship
Are the Atlanta Falcons
Arthur Blank sit down with me in front of a live audience
At the Buckhead Theater in Atlanta
And we started out by talking about
Boyhood
And throwing up in Flushing New York
What what
Are your earliest memories
Of of your childhood
My Lord
Probably fighting with my brother
That would be one your brother your mom and your dad
Exactly I we live in a small apartment it was a it was a one-bedroom apartment
1 bathroom
Share that share the actually my brother and I share the bedroom and my mom and dad slept in a little
Pull out
Thing in the foyer
I went out in the morning
Stayed out all day and
Came home and it got dark and
And it was of you are middle-class
Family regular middle-class family yes
What is your what is your dad do
My dad was a pharmacist
He passed away when he was 44 I was 15 at the time
Several years before that is left
He was working for his his brother in a retail drug store
And I started his own
Pharmaceutical Distribution Company to hospitals and nursing homes and doctors across the country
When he passed away my mother was only 37 at the time and
Without any business background she went in and started to run the business
My mother was
One of these
People which to know the failure was not
Part of her
Vocabulary shoes
Was going to succeed and she was going to do whatever it took to be successful in the business and
I would go to school and and
Who's playing football in in
Do my football practice come home
Start dinner
Did the family laundry and
Just did a variety of things to support
The house is best I could and and
Try to be
As good a friend to my mother's I could be I'm able periodically out that would take her and go bowling and I remember one time
She was very young look
Somebody would ask
Is that your girlfriend is it on that's my mother actually. Not my girlfriend but
She was always very young at heart very young
Spiritual up
The dance
Very much for caring
You went off to college at Babson
College is a small
Business college MSU
What song was that
Was that your intention to get into business
Set of school well I think really what happened after my dad died
We will talk about what's going to happen to the family business
You know my mother would
You know get remarried
She did
Exceeded our wishes
Did several times over
She will laugh at that too but she wouldn't she unplug my mother with me
I think that would be very funny
So
But in any event
So my brother was going to take over the
Pharmaceutical
I would take off the business end of the business so that was really the plan he went to pharmacy school I went to Business School
And was able to develop
Skills in terms of
I had to work with others and be inclusive and
I am NBA go later so
That was very important to me in college
So out of college I guess you start work as an accountant right for a couple years
Five years but
I kind of realized during that period of time
Didn't want to spend
The rest of my life
Recording what other people were doing and making sure the books are balanced and all that kind of stuff and giving good order advice
Want to be on the other side of the desk if you will
Or I would actually was going to help make the decisions and help Drive the business and build a businesses
So I guess it was in your mid-twenties early twenties you wouldn't work for a company called
Daylon
What was what was Balaam
Daelin was a conglomerate when that word was
Real fancy Andrew high PE ratios the Great Bridge are the company ended up being in the bankruptcy
I was running a chain of drugstores originally started out as a CFO there
We were the only part of company that was making any money
And had a small Home Improvement Center
Company in California called handy Dan Home Improvement centers
There were also making a little bit of money but the rest
The companies are losing money so
I had an option
Stay there and continue just to run the business as your was
Or potentially go to California I met my partner at HD Bernie Marcus
Through through Dale and Bernie was running the discount store division for them
That wasn't doing well and so that's why I was
For 5 years old
I mean I was a young man
Just ask just to clarify you were right you were the CEO of
The drug stores that very loud
And Bernie was involved with their disc
Is Right both of us businesses were sort of
Collapsing in end
You have this option to go work
Another business they own
So handy.
Was that the brother was actually very proper
Making a lot of money the pack the parent company had no money to give
Davis for expansion and I didn't want it
Be part of that I don't want to be
Just maintaining
75 stores
Chantilly I 75 years old so I
I decided then either I was going to leave whatever and they
And they offered me this opportunity in California to work with Bernie and Bernie and I have been very close
So then I went to work for Bernie
In California handy Dan Home Improvement centers
Is my wife then
Didn't want to go to California
She was positive that we weave
Consumed by a quake of some sort but she ended up
She ended up coming and
And
Weather
Male having some
Some kids there I've had kids all over your name and age have a child
So I got
I've got
56 wonderful children
And my wife has three children
So and I always consider the Home Depot to be my seventh child so
So you say you move to Southern California
You start working for Handy Dan
Bernie Marcus
Is there as well
What he's about
I guess about 14 15 years older than you
What
Was he sort of like a mentor to you
Yeah Bernie is
He's 14 years my senior in
Probably
You know a combination of brother and a father figure
Have I lost my dad and a rabbi
Pisces always consider himself to be a rabbi and
And so I
And he's a great storyteller
The great joke teller
And I'm not agree
Storyteller but I'm great audience he would tell the same stories and I would keep laughing at the same stories high was it was like
Make a great partnership because he loves hearing you know me laughing
It was like a marriage it was like a marriage
Was like a very good marriage
So what did you what did you and Bernie start to do at Handy Dandy
Did you start to
If you were trying to make this
Listen to a successful company
So what were some of the things that you were doing at that company
Experimenting with it
The company at the time
That company ended in Home Improvement centers
Was we operated kind of a traditional model 40,000 square ft 40% gross margin 40 Associates on the
Lafleur
And it was it was by far the most
Successful chain homes
Stores in the country then and we had a tax treaty with our parent company parent company being dalen
And so we would send our tax money instead of going to
To the government we sent it directly to
Today lanzhou favorite child
In that company cuz we were kind of keeping the company
Afloat if you will with our tax
At some point the parent company was bought by guy named Sanford
Sigilyph
Right
The tiny was in these Wix commercials and
Cheese whiz
His real name is Ming the merciless
Right
Maybe that's right and he actually clear Nova 2
And he comes into the company
And
She fires you guys he gets rid of you and what do you
What do you remember about that day that it were you shocked
Yeah I guess I'm shocked yeah I mean I will we were up at that time we were running the most successful Home Improvements going to come
Funny Indian Idol
States
And Bernie
In
What is new Sandy's merciless
Very
You know self-confidence drawing people
Sandy had a difficult time because basically all the profitability all the cash flow from Dale and was coming from
Buddhist Home Improvement Center company
Burning was properly and taking credit for the results that we were producing
Saint didn't like that so this is you know War of the Giants and they own more stock and
Then we did and so
Call my wife and I told her she started laughing
How can you be fired
Explain how political
Strife in in the business contacts to her and so I said she said I still don't believe you going to get in the car
Cars. Driving home and
By the time I got home Wall Street Journal to call the house the only times we call the house the Orange County
Newspaper called I mean they were
There were people on the phone that want to talk
ISO
Book now she said I guess you weren't choking why I said no
Yunnan
So
Me you were 36
Is I guess that point
Write the three children that were you
That's goes first batch
That's what they call themselves
Did you
Did you have fun just curious I mean
You know you got this job you moved to California it's very successful you've got this
Career ahead of you
I don't know where you
Were you worried
Did you feel like the
Rug was pulled from out out of remember you you know I
You know I was shocked
And but you know I mean
Given
Transfer background that I had we had saved up some money I wasn't you know
I wanted to take my time as to Bernie and think through the options that we had
You know I
He was still feel young man at that point as well
And didn't want to rush into anything so I took basic
Play the better part of the year off fight a lot of running ran my first marathon that years going to have my kid
I did a lot of things I wanted to do
Does looking at a lot of different alternatives
We wanted to think about outside the box
Oh and Bernie said well you know
If we were able to LeapFrog our own business
Handy dan Home Improvement centers
What kind of Home Improvement Center store
Could we not compete again
And so we savvy
I could never compete against the
Big Warehouse No-Frills down Market low prices great service great services
So instead of kind of
Taking that
Handy Dan model of the fours
$4000000 40% margin 47 people Etc
We said let's try to leave for the industry you know dramatically
How did you
When when Bernie came to you and said
Hey here's the business plan you were in urine right away
UE said let's do this thing where we did the business plan together and I
Burning the Bernie lived in the San Fernando Valley for those Heathen Ola it
3 Hour 3 day drive to get the gift from
Orange County to San Fernando Valley and it's so
We would
Talk a lot by phone and I would
Develop really all the business plans and work on the models
Things that nature I would send them to him he would look at always meet at a coffee shop that was somewhere in the middle with you meant at I don't know how men
Many times but
They had a table it was kind of named after all so we kept
You're developing the smile and developing and file a member one night ahead in all these papers spread out on a dining room table
Bubble on eye
You know I called Bernie and I said you know
Listen partner
Reply Buena 5 years
Experiencing
My public accounting firm
My own business experience by
Experience running a change drugstores
And these numbers
Don't add up
And I still remember what Bernie said on the other end of the
Phone
Just said
Change the numbers
Change your numbers
I change the number so I'm in his argument which she really was valid was that
This is a model
We don't have any of these
Stores where we're just
Projecting what one might do in
But you know what that
At that time I'm in so I understood us if it's got to be
Be able to present this to very
Sophisticated investors and
Have it makes some sense to be plausible but
Reality is that the investors who invest in our company 144 them
Really what they were buying into was
Myself and burning
We had the experience and they look back at Handy Dan Home Improvement centers and they said
We're betting on people here we're not going to bet on the on the on my Mac
Experience on that smallest
Arthur why did you guys
Decide to
Start this company in Atlanta you were based in Southern California the time
How did you
Pick this area
William lived in in Atlanta
The chain of drugstores was based
In Griffin Georgia
Rite Aid Griffin is the first city
South of Atlanta
I always remembered
Atlanta was a Grove City Grove Market I love the city
So we asked for any let's
You know let's go to Atlanta and you know that time this is so hard to imagine because Atlanta even today
Qualifies as a national park based on number
Countries that
Are still up in Atlanta despite all development here but there was less than a million people living in Atlanta with that time
So I drove over
Burning around Atlanta look at the sites
The 285 witch
Everybody is familiar with it
All I could see was trees
And so every once in awhile every 10 minutes when we say there's nobody living here author
Drive around for a little bit she almost walked the other division subdivisions get back on Highway Drive some more
Still not enough because nobody here at the Bahamas all these trees so we did that like
The two hours we drove around 285 and got off and with the subdivision so
Finally we became convinced that Atlanta would be an important growth Market that was even growing their antlers
Less than a million people
We open up here in 1979 and today is something not to 7 million people
On that opening day in 1979
You raise the money
To open two shops here in Atlanta
You open the doors to Home Depot and is there just a mad rush of people to come in
Not as expected to be a mile safe and so we
We agreed Bernie and I went to one store and I bought the Pat and other associates obviously went to the other side
Store we agreed to talk to each other the morning and my three oldest children
They were each given $500 1 in $1 bills and I told them
I told him I'll be back in school by 11:12 at the very latest so it's 6 at night
It was standing from the store still handing out $1 bills so we had we had this grand opening and nobody came
Then just a minute how the Home Depot went from a flop on opening day
To the largest Home Improvement chain in the world stay with us at guy Rosner listening to her
How I built this from NPR
Support for this NPR Podcast comes from American Express open
Listeners to how I built this
Curious
Curious about have good ideas became great businesses and chances are
You have some good ideas of your own but as you know
And business there can be a lot of roadblocks
American Express open knows how hard it can be to get things done
Anyone help with money and know-how
So you can turn those ideas into action
Is it open. Com
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Arthur Blank
And his business partner Bernie Marcus open their first two stores
In the Atlanta area in 1979
To say the least it didn't
Quite go as expected
It's over the next year they were
Really hard identify what
Wasn't working
And they experimented with different pricing and if
Merchandise
Try and get more customers
Into the front door
We spent really the next year in
One of our core values is to listen and respond and is listening I
Probably spend 75% of my time as did Bernie has the really most of our Associates
On the floor of the store finding out from
Customers what is it they like what didn't like in a week
Kept changing the mix adding things taking things off changing prices changing assortments
Changing vendors
Making sure we have service levels in areas they wanted them to be kept refining the model
Every competitor
Came into our stores and visit us and said
I'm in these
Bad Words lyrics
Satellite radio thing but
These whatever you want to cause they're crazy
The sores are much too big
Prices are much too low
What way too much product
Stock
They're too many services I mean the math isn't going to work
And of course the math
There in 79 was it working is great
Fine-tuned got it where it needed to be
Exploding 80 and 81 and the numbers were incredible
And we went public in 81 obviously we got a grape
You know what great reception
And
Then it's a long story after that but that point forward we knew we going to be yours
I asked you about how you and Bernice thought of the company and you have two of course I agree
On what it's going to be worth of values
The company are
So what were the core values of Home Depot
Well I think that you know we never
Really wrote them down
I remember I went to lunch with Bernie and I said you know
Will living these values
By far and away is the most
Most important thing that we
We can do but they're not
Down
And
Imma give you some shocking news today that I've kind of figured out
And know to be true and that is that
You and I are going to approve a lot of stores in the future that we will actually never say will never be in the moon ever get a chance
Imemories
Stop eating lunch
But the night before, so you're not sick
It's crazy how can we prove stores and ever go visit him I said Bernie cuz we
Will we spend about half our time and our stores and I said if you do the math of it we visit
Certain numbers
About resisting storage every year
And
We just realized that
Go to any new stores
Choice we need to document lead to write down
And
You know I think the beauty of our core values
But you're really focused on our Associates and people in relationships
Jefferson Community and giving back and
The people who was serving Drive everything that we doing
Those are the ones that we listen to those two months
Respond to those ones we care for those ones who nurture
And
That's the mentality of
The training that we
We've given to Oliver
You went Home Depot went from
0 Revenue in 1979
To 700 million in 1985
The fastest company in US history
Billion dollars
In Revenue how did you manage that growth was that overwhelming
Facestory Sam Walton
The Saints and what was
Who founded Walmart
Sam was
Speaking
At a retail conference I went to and somebody ask them in the company gone from
10 billion
Bodybuilding
Open today I don't know
What they own half
Like what
Between a man Amazon
But but you said about how did you get from 10 to
20 billion dollars
Samsung open up
And it's all we did
And so really it HD
We had a five-year plan we had a one-year budget we had all of that but we focus
On every single
Store an AR
Plan was that
Each store had to be better than the last so we opened
So we didn't have any planograms we didn't have any
You have to do it this way we didn't let the model
Frozen we didn't let it
We made the
Quotes running the store think about
This is the last or how do I make this store better
How do I own it
How do I feel accountable for it
How do I inject my ideas into it how do I make it
Every store got better
What about your
Personal life
I mean did it take a toll on the table
Time you were able to spend it
With your kids your family and you must have work been working
All the time
Heiken Ashi
I told guys do you want to talk
I think it's one of the things I'm most proud of my oldest daughter who she was running a nonprofit
Prefer
For young women in San Francisco and when they did a retirement dinner for me in 2001 she couldn't be there
Couldn't get away and she
Did a video piece
She sounded
Still remember you know
What you said there is
Is Dad you know I never realized what's going up in
Decisive
The Home Depot and
Exacerbate
Because
You always there for me you always events that were important to me always there when I was doing dancer
Josiah was always there you know important
School programs whatever it maybe and
And I
Worked around the kids schedule and I would
Work early in the morning I work late at night
Them to bed and work after that
So
I always made sure there was balance in my life
Turn and I think
You know
Often asked by Young Folks
Most people younger than me
So it's easier
Find people that want that advice today but I always tell him you know
Make sure you have balance in your life and in because
Timothy young executives
Menlo Mall women day
Their attitude is at me at work now work hard and then I'll put my career
Memphis gear and go go go and
So when you return home and
10 years you're not going to recognize you
The kids and you
Do spouses look at you and say
Who are you again
So I think it's important
How to find balance in your life
Use
Step down
Stepped away from the company left the company at a pretty young age were 58
Why did you leave
Will you just
Your time there was that time I mean I done
I'm in the early days
In the company of the first
I don't know how many years but no that was a 23-year. Of time that it was
It was great fun with all these Adventures starting a new business you know going half broke figure out how to work through that
Let me know responding to customers and
As time went on
I spent found myself spending more time in meetings more time doing things that I had to do that were part of the job and
Didn't dislike doing them but they weren't as much fun for me anymore
So when I really felt that 23 years was
A long time for
Somebody in my position first
Is President later CEO and chairman and what have you and
And in Bernie and I always
You know operate as a very close
Partnership I mean was really more like
Two brothers work
Working together two partners working together thanks
Sing Elsa and you still write
Well I talked to himself as I can be probably had
Two dinners in a lunch
Blastoise
60 days together
So I see him see him a lot and you know it
It's always great to
To do that so
I felt the time was right
That we
Began to do a search the board found a candidate that was
Bob nardelli
Get some hisses
You folks in the audience
But they bought in Bob nardelli
I see y'all appointment
That decision and
And I was
Sure happy I wasn't there during the
Six years that he was there
Sol
That would have been the worst time in my life
But that but that was a time in your life when you really made your
Biggest mark on the city of Atlanta by buying
Falcons
Can you explain what was the
I mean what did you this Burning passion
To own
The Falcons was it
Was it
Assertive a chance to
Run a business again what was the thinking behind
Behind doing
Well I was a season ticket holder
Since I had moved to Atlanta and
I didn't realize this but the commissioner before the Commissioner Goodell commission attack of Boo
The clothes you want to pull out the same you said you really see me just bought has never had back-to-back winning season
And I said Paul I didn't oppose the smartest guy in the room because you told you so
Cuz you really was
The smartest guy in the room
I said that can't be correct
So I went back and I check my turn.
So I realized all those years and I was a
Season ticket holder and I would have such angst over the Falcons I understood why because it was going to constantly
Like that song
I said to myself I can
Either
And complain about if the neck
You know 40 years of my life
Just try to buy the team and fix it
So
So I
Felt you know buying a senior fishing you seem like more fun
You watching the Play Endless games and what have you so that was in mm
And one
And I just
Finishing up part 17 Sierra
As owner
You have to know if we had multiple back-to-back winning seasons MO
Multiple championships
Play
Well last year in the Super Bowl we just
We forgot there was a fourth quarter in the game they play really well for three quarters and
Somehow
You know
This is Ben
To say the least a
An interesting year and then the NFL
Do you feel like players who are trying to bring awareness
To the way our criminal justice is
Treats
Black men and women vs
White
By not standing for the national anthem
Do you feel like that
Well I have tubal
I I I think it's
I think it's
It's less susceptible
To deny people
The first
So I think that's what's the traffic to work
Having said that
I mean I think that
Players
Should stand
And it should and should Sam especially for the national anthem
And I will tell you there was 1750 players in the NFL and I will tell you her
These players have great respect for the military
And
So it's not about the military
Just that
McCombs and
Opportunity platform
For them
To speak about
There
Concerns about social injustice
Police accountability
Their focus is on turning that platform down to progress
On these issues and making sure that
Owners and organizations in America are listening
Two voices that cannot be heard
And I think I'm more for that thing
How much of your is a question asked everybody comes in the show
How much of your success
Do you attribute to your intelligence in your hard work and how much of it took
Luck and timing
I think that walking timing is a big deal
I'm in a really do
A lot of it is
Success
Is based on timing La Cadena my place but then seizure
Opportunities I think I am willing to
To go out of your comfort zone and
I'm a big
Proponent of
Outward Bound of done
I don't know how many Alabama courses myself but we did a lot of that in terms of the
At the training at HD but a lot of it is based on their philosophies
To serve to strive and not to yield
So I think the
Having that
That entrepreneurial drive and spirit
How to get up everyday
To have purpose in your life everyday to
To become better everyday
I'm doing this cuz I have a passion for doing it and I love
Being a service to other people in whatever format
Arthur Blank
Founder Home Depot owner of the Atlanta Falcons thank you
Is my conversation with Arthur Blank founder of the Home Depot
Live in Atlanta Georgia
The theater
And in addition to Falcons Arthur owns Atlanta's new major league soccer team Atlanta United
I did that started playing in 2017
And by the way in case you were wondering
The guy who fired ua1978 Sanford sigilyph in contact with him after Home Depot
Thank you note you know every day every anniversary date when we were fire
I didn't want to do that
Anyway
Peter Survivor
Hey thanks for listening to this special live episode of How I built this
This episode was produced by
By Casey Herman with music
Impose by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant sanaz meshkinpour Claire Breen
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Dynamo stack
Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com