This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who tailors its policies to fit every business is very specific needs
Which may explain its 97% customer service
Get a quote or buy
Diane hiscox. Com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
That first day was bananas I mean women were like lining up women were pissed because
They were coming and every like it said use a walk-in I'm like
Blow out to the first chair and I was running the front desk and I was I was I was there around the clock probably for six months before I took
The day off because I just couldn't leave it and it was so fun
From NPR how I built this
A show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they built
Being a stay-at-home mom just 6 years ago to building a national chain
Dry salons
Call Drybar
When I was a kid growing up
In Boca Raton
Southern Florida
School Bus
Really her thing
No intentions goal wasn't very good at it
I was kind of dubbed the underachiever of the family I was like what the hell is Allie going to do with her life
She eventually went
Collagen
Everybody year
Dropped out
Set adrift
She lived in New York for some time and then she
Back to Florida and live with their parents
But her older brother Michael
I seem to have it all together
He was like the overachiever of the family and he was like naturally good
Student Lake
Graduation he had a bar mitzvah while I was like there's no way I'm going to
But he did it and he was right he wasn't even like the smarty-pants of the family
So well Ali was sort of floating around in her early 20s
Michael was doing pretty well for himself he was moving up the corporate ladder
And in the mid-1990s
Started to have this idea of what
She wanted
What to do with her life
TS Michael
Or vice he was the first person I talked about and I said you know I feel like I really want to go to beauty school that is
I really want to do and my parents were kind of like
They didn't get it and they have these little old lady clothing stores in Delray Beach
Boca
Next to every one of them with a hair salon
And everything's like little old ladies getting their hair done are like
That's what you want to do I know that is not what I want to do
New York City
Shows and I want to do a tutorial and you know what I had like gran
Dreams of what I would do in the Heritage way my brother
We had always been very very close to my parents were sitting here they would tell you that
Itchy raised
Keep your very very very close
He was
Really one of the few people who really believed in this little dream
That I had
So is it was living in Boca
And I enrolled in the local Beauty School
And I love
Every second
From the moment I enrolled I was like
These are my people I thought I loved and I loved the environment I'm so happy
And I soaked it all up and while I was in Beauty School I was working for
A guy who owned a local salon
And he was amazing and he taught me so much and again
I wouldn't have known it at the time but
Because he own this line I really saw how he
Managed
With an education I was getting married
Even know I was getting in
For your Emmy at that point your your ambition in life was to
What's working at Salon
What to do hair
Although
Which to get back to me
I was also a huge fan of John suhag who's
Sadly not alive anymore but he was like the Pioneer dry cutting wood
I'm not sure if I'm assuming like instead of cutting wet hair you you can cut it when it's dry
John
And he was like
Sweet like what
Like what made him hit like Moses he had one Salon in New York on Madison Avenue
Rock and roll kind of
Cool guy
Greyhound that likes at NEX
Find it I had it in my head. The only person I wanted to work for her so I moved to New York
And I remember like it was yesterday
Done interview and I walked in with my leather pants on inside tried to escape
And I remember him like looking at me and making eye contact and I was like I know I'm going to get this job
He was like an assistant job it wasn't like the world's greatest
At the salon and I was assisting him a little bit I was assisting the other stylist in the shop which meant
I was the person watching and blowing the hair
And it was a great education I was still very very new in Industry even though I had my license and was on the floor
And I've learned a very different ball game in New York
So I mean I used to do all of John's clients
Girlfriend
And it was like the best
Training
You could ever imagine that sound sounds like you had a great time
You will laugh you'd like dropped out of of like
Hair
And you went to become a publicist
Is that right
Well not even I became like an assistant to the guy who's running the music department at Rogers & Cowan like one of the big ones in New York
Represent everybody
A pretty awesome job me he represented Paul McCartney
Janet Jackson Jennifer Lopez
So now I'm like
I don't know 2526 and then I started to get
Auntie again but that was like
To find my husband
Get married
Gap Kids
Bug and
During this time I did meet my husband and
At a bar named Hell in the Meatpacking District in hell you better than hell says we are a match made in hell
I like a dive bar in them
Meatpacking District that
Obviously
Seymour today
I guess you met this guy
What was he doing at the time
He was in advertising
So we started dating and every. Very it was like love at first sight and it really weird together like everyday since
Practically moved in with each other like right away
So we
We were we got married we got engaged a year after we met and then we got married
2 years after MSN
I I think I was out here but having grown up in South Florida the winters in the yard were starting
I got to get out of here
And Zoe
Decided to move to LA and he
For him and advertising it's like he needs to
Being a big city so
So you decided to move to LA just cuz you wanted a change of scene
He thought
And you figure it out for yourself
Well that's when I was like really
A year we got pregnant and
My First Son Grant was born in 2000
+ 5
And I was like
As happy as can be and I thought I wanted to be a stay-at-home mom forever I loved every
Second of it
So great
And then we had her second son in
Ninja kids
Yeah
Yasso
It was like you got a lot of hard surface is to
And after being at home with a stay-at-home mom for 5 years
I got really antsy again
The bike
Can go to the park every day I remember my husband music
Home from work and I'd be like
Kids all that and I felt like
Man I need to do something for myself again and that's that's that's what initially started and then I was like what am I going to do I'm going to go back to work
Hair salon
I have two kids now what I want to do and
And because
Blowouts and doing hair was always my thing is my girlfriend
But ask me to go out there all the time
Good hair and so they would always ask me
No no I was just do it was especially if it was like for a party or an event or while you're something I just did everybody's hair
And I was good at it and so I remember that I
Sitting in my living room my best friend that are like babies crawling around and
Start
Mobile
Where I go around
Blowout like
My mommy friend
But I was very Emerson like
The mommy community
It's really strong in LA
So I posted on
This mommy
Group called
Headwear
It was like a Yahoo group
It was this resource for Mom
There's like 5000
Moms in LA
And they all went to the site
So I posted on there one day when I have this idea popped in my head I said I'm I'm a longtime stylist I'm thinking about starting a mobile
Would anybody
Out there Beyond
I got flooded with you like yes I'm interested
Set for blow dry
Pretty much so I started getting emails so then my husband was like any of this is such a great idea
And he said but
You need to keep website if they think
But at this point you're thinking
It's going to be like my side Hustle
What do you think about getting a van
No no I was like I thought about putting all them
To the head in a duffel bag and heading out the door that with that car
In my car
And so you would blow dry
At their humps
I like while your baby sleeping because like we are all like when our baby is napping with you until we can do any
I'll come to your house and blow dry hair
I mean this is not a very liked
Thought-out plan that was
So basic
And honestly we came up with $40 because it was like cheap and easy as I 220
Done like you put this out there on the website and all of a sudden
Yep
We want this
Calendar
Yeah they started doing this but and of course like I said to pick up my kids from preschool at like
2:00 or whatever way
But I really wasn't about the money it was much more about
Getting out there in like talking to Dothan just like doing something for myself and being able to kind of
You know satisfy that
Desire in me
Need to do something for myself again so you start
Doing this you start driving around
The westside of LA and I got really busy really fast
And it was very word-of-mouth like I'd go and do one mom and then she would tell like six of her friends
It was such a thrill
And I got to the point where I was saying
No
More than I was saying
And so that's what I like
You know this is interesting and I think that's been I started asking my clients
I said what what do you do when I can
Well
Either like begrudgingly go to my cut and color Salon where they overcharged me and want to cut my hair and there's all this pressure
Or I go to the bike
Discount chain down the street
Kind of toxin
Experience is bad in bad lighting and
Has like
There really is too bad choices are there and that's it
And so that's when I think the idea started
Percolating for me and
I was like huh
You know there's no place like in the middle and that's when I went to my brother
And he was working for Yahoo
I'm also on Yahoo is
In like
He's like the thing
Really successful end
He's watching my little business from the sidelines and he
Interesting idea but
Nothing beyond that
So I told him that I thought I should turn
My little mobile blood drive business into an actual brick-and-mortar so instead of me going to my clients they can start coming
I asked him to have basically help me and help me
Did it at any point
Any anyone
Tickly a thing man say to you
Wait you want to start a store
Blow dry hair and
What was like why would anybody pay
And they're like
They have know they're like
What
Although my husband always had this interstate inside because he knows what my hair looks like naturally and he always would say
You get your nails done but I never notice it when you get your hair done I notice it and so he was like I think this is the neck
Nail salon I think this is going to kill it let's do this
How Ali started to imagine a salon with a service most women didn't get
Get know they wanted
I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First to The Grommet
Online shop where you'll discover
Innovative products and gifts
You learn the story behind
Each product and the Pea
People who created it
You can easily find in support entrepreneurs
Small businesses
That align with your own values like
Made in the USA then ability and social responsibility
Place to buy unique and thoughtful gifts
Especially for people who are tough
2 by 4 or seem to already have
Everything
Is it the grommet.com hi BTW
To save $10 off $50 or more
Thanks also to godaddy.com
They give customers the tools and insights they need to transform their ideas in personal initiatives
Into success
What's GoDaddy small business owners have everything they need to get their business online
Including award-winning 24/7 support
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology provider dedicated to small business
And they're offering how I built this listeners
30% off all new products
Just go to godaddy.com
And use built
To get started that's built
And just one more thing before I get back to the show
Azure
At the end of every episode were telling
Your stories about the
Companies or products
You are building so
Please do stick around
To hear it but
For now
It's how I built this from
NPR
Gyros
So Alli Webb
How does idea for a business where you just
Blow dry people's hair no cutting no coloring
Just blow dry
Brother Michael and her husband
The Cameron
They were on board
So to start the company they cashed out Cameron's retirement account and Michael put in a chunk of money he made during the.
Icom Boom at Yahoo
And the three of them they tried to get to work trying to figure out the details of what tribe are would be while at the same time
I'm still holding their day jobs
That's when they were like the Moonlighting phase when I was so ready my mobile businesses near my kids my brother had a real estate marketing
And Cameron was a creative director in advertising agency which is like
You already been working crazy hours so
What would happen if
Every night Wednesday
The kids were asleep
My brother was at his house Cameron was home we all be like on our laptops in bed and
We be working and drive aren't the Cameron at night started developing The Drybar website and building out the website
How do you really knew that you never built the website but he was the designer so he could do all of that
So
In the wee hours of the night for weeks we started developing the website and Michael and I started looking at real estate and trying to figure out where this
Shoppers going to go and talking to landlords and all the side crazy stuff and I was on the phone with the cosmetology board like around the clock
Trying to figure out
What I needed to open these this job in and then how it all started
What are you nervous
Did you feel like it
This will be okay or was like
Part of youku
Like this is a lot of money that we put into this
They were more nervous than me my brother should probably the most nervous cuz he had the biggest
Faking it financially
But I had a really good feeling
A it was like one of those things in my God I was like I know there's enough women out there like me that's when we'll make one job
I'm sure one child
Released
Weird a little bit and said at that point we had figured out if we can do like
30 blowout today 3040
If we can do
5 watts an hour and we're open like I would literally like you figure out how many if you were going to have to come into
Those numbers
But you were going to do that the blocks to write I mean you were going to be
Anta shop
Blow drying hair
Andy
Yes will so that the hiring process is kind of funny
And there's a couple status
It's at work for us who remember this like ice have sizes
Come to my house and go out my hair
That was there
Are you know I would make sure they were nice
And then they did a good job
And I only hired like
I don't know about 15
Stylist and I wasn't
Sure when things I wasn't sure about is if
There was enough Silas out there like me that
That was interested in
Jeff the sailing part like I was
What was it that was going to be your like
Competitive Advantage like what was there is no competition
It was snowing
Nobody thought of it there was nothing but you owe you found a spot and where did you
Open the 1st
Location
So I was living in Santa Monica and
The first location was on
San Vicente
Which is a thoroughfare so
If you came off the 405
You were going to Santa Monica
The Palisades
Had to take that that route
And also I should tell you that my brother having worked on other big projects
He met this guy
Signing Josh heitler who's an architect
And so my brother
One of the many many thing
Can see price today but when I had this idea to have a
He went to Josh and I do want to build a hair salon for my sister and Josh
I was like
Sure and
Baton we offered him some Equity to get involved in
That was again I don't even know if I would have thought of an architect
Hanging out with my brother
What was your vision like what was
When he came to talk to you what did you
You say like how did you want it to look
Well and you wanted it to feel like a bar
And
I remember
Explaining to my brother
And to Josh
That
If
That's something that happened in my mobile blow dry business that when I would go to my client's homes and do their blowout there's usually like in their living room
I was never
In their personal bathroom in their home so I do it in her living room
Vacancy
Blowout when it was happening and when I was done with a blowout
Are they okay I'm now I'm ready for you to look beautiful get it
And so to go from not seeing your hair to see this amazing gorgeous hair was like kind of a powerful thing in ice
Play Nazi Josh into my going and so that was kind of a task for Josh like how do we incorporate
Great. Into the design of the shop
The Wii
The mirrors are behind the stations and that's very intentional that when you're the client is done stylist
Center around
I totally game for my
My love is this
So
Daddy was at the experience was going to be different
Everything that I had accumulated in
In all of my years is being a stylist and saying like I'm just going to do it the way I want to do it not the way
It's always been done
Of course it was like a bar and I wanted
Ittefaq screen TV
I thought that would be like
A fun getaway for women in leg
Polygon chick's legs
All chick flick movies that you probably wouldn't watch a movie you see them and they have subtitles you get really John in I mean I said
Sometimes it on Mike
I love this
Sleepless in Seattle
All of it and Michael my brother had the idea to
Charging stations for your iPhone that everybody's like
We got so lucky the fact that
My brother and
My husband and Josh
And me
Big storm of all these people that
Came together
To do that send that had
The perfect skill set
We were this like power has it nobody had to pay anybody to do
Artsy open
The first location in Brentwood in
In 2010
And what's
What happens if you
So I don't know if you remember dailycandy thing about
About fashion right
Yeah well it back and it's like
Original state dailycandy was
Dislike
Websider
And you get emails from them and they would be these like
Places you've never heard of nude break like business
Crazy Cathy like nuggets
Of information that nobody knew
And we got dailycandy to write a story
About dry bar comedy
That was ceramic
Three or four days
Before we opened remember sitting at lunch with my brother
Are blackberries
Before iPhones and
And we used to get
Appointment
Alexander City unless your phones are going crazy and all these appointments are became like
We fought like they can
We've had that like the system was broken really what is going on
And then someone
Centos the Daily candy somewhere like
Oh my God it's
Candyman say and so
Everybody started booking appointment
Before we leave
Open
And so that very first day we open to a very very. And so
That first day was
Banana
SME women were like lining up with
Past because they were coming and they were like it said you could walk in and I'm like
We don't have anywhere chairs and I was I was doing
Blow out to the first chair and I was running the front desk and I was I was I was there around the clock probably first
Before I took a day off
So you guys were incredibly busy like right from the beginning so so were you making a profit in that first year
Well even within that first year we turned
Everything back in
So not really
You know me we were buried
Putting anybody for ourselves and it within six months we opened our second store
And it just kept going away that how did you scale it up
Obviously
How did you begin the process of scaling up when you
Have a whole lotta cash
Well that was that was a challenge and that's where it's like thank God for Michael
To cam and I would like to create a zoom we're like
What now you know we really didn't know it
Books for business
We all knew we had something on her hand and we used
I said women coming in being like
Can you get these Beverly Hills women their own chop it was like we were the cool Club you couldn't get into but that's not very cool
And did your husband at this point leave his job he couldn't leave cuz I wasn't taking a salary I was like you still needed his
His salary so he was but he was still doing a lot of work
Flashlight app for husband
He was basically working to
Full-time job
It was crazy
Such like a life
Slap and it was
You know we just didn't
We couldn't believe
Yeah and I Cameron
Stayed
I think it was about a year-and-a-half
Before he actually left
What is job
To be able to
Take him to drive off all time
So as you started to scale up
Did you have to go
Find Outside investors
So that again I knew nothing about raising
Michael started to say hey I think
I think we should franchises
Mob the franchisor
Remember like we had
Of our first meeting with like a franchise
Consulting Group at Cameron's
Office like his day advertising office definitely pleased that we had in the office
To the conference table
Crystal.
That's why I fight so we started getting like our documentation and
Together so we could franchise
Ascenso
I was a little like
And not like super excited about franchising cuz I didn't I didn't want to give it away is how I kind of felt about it
Imagine that you would be freaked out that
You know some franchise couldn't
Equality that you wanted
Oh yeah
Wake me up at night and then we
We are very very bad
Particular about
We franchise with and made sure that they understood
The importance of all of that stuff and then like I said they're there was that fear and there still is that fear today but
Is great and it really did help
Spread our name
Much quicker than we could have if we
Franchising and then we're raising money
You guys opened
I your first store in 2010's is crazy
Locations do you have
Today
67-68
As of tomorrow
And saying that you go from
Being stay-at-home mom
To running a
Open executive multimillion-dollar
Company in like
2 years
How did you
Mentally make that transition
It's still
So my going to all of us that it
Took off and happen the way it has
It's been such a ship it is it was
It's hard and still hard to say balancing it all with the
Kids and
But I think we all kind of grew into it pretty naturally in it
There's so much
Passion
Behind what we're doing we all love it so much that
Just probably my adrenaline Rush that
It was a lot of
Figuring it out as we went along
But we did
Do you work
More now or do you work less now than you did when you start it
Different kind of work
In the beginning I was in the stores
Non stop offer
All the time
And I I remember so well when it went from like 3 to 5 to 7
Stores and being late
I can't be in all the stories I don't have one time anybody I used to be able to remember we had
Brentwood West Hollywood
Palisades
NCS City like I could hop around
Those are pretty
Easy for me to get to
Thrift store to store
And then as we started to grow
You know I slowly but surely like started bringing in people who
Regional map
Manager
Is the regional manager and any kind of kept going like that and that way and now
Now we have
Massive infrastructure now
Welders
Dada 3000 stylus
About an hour maybe seventy 80 people in our Support Center
So
It's pretty massive now and so now it's like
I don't have to be in to be
Everyday was I tweet
Good but then it's like
There's days that I'm like
Decisions get made and things get me that I'm not involved in any more which I used
To be involved in
Watching
You know it's like
Very hard for me to walk in for the walking tours and I see everything that he's
Change
Yeah where
I don't get to enjoy that much the way most quiet
Does that not only drive you crazy
People in the storks
When I come in
I think
Eating it makes everybody nervous
So weird to me why are you mad
But it does and that is
Truly the weirdest thing in
Courtney Garfield
Director she's like why don't you understand that
Understand
What
Have you learned about
You didn't have
Business Degree you didn't have to cut through the managerial Express
Trains do I need to soak
What are some of your strengths that you learned about and your weaknesses you learned about as you had to kind of take on these roles
Strength is
Was the confidence that I knew this business really well nobody can tell me I didn't know this busy
How to treat customers and Silas I knew how to make this business
I knew how to talk to people I think from
Being in PR you know everything I had done
I always felt like
It's so cheesy bites everything like led me to this moment in my life and I felt like
I had what I used to have to run the store
And then there's things that I didn't know
That that's where Michael and cam came in and Michael new to hire like me needs a president of retail is like
Even do that was a thing like I eaten so there was
So much of like the things I didn't know we're filled and I think that that was one of my biggest learning
Experiences you need to bring on people who know which
What is a lot of people listening would say
I would never be able to
Twerk as my partner in a business
Like it's a really
Hard but it sounds like you guys have
A really you know
Functional working relationship in a great marriage
Is that is a true wizard attention attention
Yes I mean they're there is a mean my husband and I is certainly a struggle and
And yeah I definitely comes in
Challenges but
Figured so much more outweighs the bad and we
We have especially now we have different teams at work under us and so we don't have to like we don't work nearly as closely as we did in the beginning
There's so much trust that you have when you're working with
Your husband and your brother that
It's
Everything I
If I said to you
7 years ago when you were
No driving around in your
Nissan
Tara
Disable songs blow drying hair
In 7 years you can have 70 stores all across the country and you can be doing a hundred million dollars in Revenue year which
You be like
You're out of your mind
Pretty much I mean I could not see
That far down
And I remember people asking us
You know what's next for you guys and I was like
We're going to keep opening stores in
I think it was
To be at sea
67 I mean
It's okay because it wasn't premeditated like
We didn't have a business plan it wasn't like
This is our goal this is our trajectory
There was not a bad it was all this very
Organic and we're on to something so we're going to figure it out and keep
Keep growing it
And it's very
Very rewarding for me personally because I was the one in the family that I really like
Oh God was Ali going to do and it's so it's it's
Particularly gratifying
My brother and I
Be together in business and we love that were able to be closed
On another level for the business
What is pretty special
Alli Webb founder of Drybar accompanied by the way is planning to expand internationally very soon
Going to Canada and also into Europe
Allie just published a book all about blow drying hair it's called The Drybar guide to good hair for all
Delete it if you met her or suffix remember but Ali's hair is actually naturally curly
I guess I should start that you are very
On curly hair right now but this is like a very carefully Style
Well I am a professional stylist myself and I happen for 20 years I actually did my own hair this morning I know how to
Baidu
And don't turn it off just yet
Because after the shorebreak
Stories on the things
You guys are building
Stay with us
It's how I built this
From NPR
Hey just a quick thanks to one of our sponsors who helps make this podcast possible discover
Become a new card number and a
End of your first year
Discover will match all the cash back you've earned
Dollar for dollar
Learn more at discover.com
Match
Only for new cardmembers
Supply
Okay we're now at the
Part of the show we called
How you built
This week
We have a story out of Nashville Tennessee
My name is
Dr Mike Butera
I'm the
Founder and CEO of artisan makes musical instrument
Switch was a natural mood for Mike
Because he plays
Spike a few dozen instruments himself
At a dinner party with a bunch of musicians
And after dinner we wanted to play music together
But we didn't have any instruments
We just had
The phones in our pockets
So they hooked up their phones to
Computer speakers
Launch some music making apps
And they started the jam
But we were just
Staring at our screens
We really wanted to interact with each other or
Get lost in the Music close our eyes
Keith Richards music
But as friends
They felt kind of pathetic staring at their screens
Dinky little speakers
And then
Mike had an idea
I thought
What is the speaker had a guitar neck
What is this speaker had
Keys on it what if it have a little drum pad
I just wanted the speaker to be
Become
A musical instrument
So am I called up some of his
Is engineer friends and ask them
Talon build one
This is what they made
The digital instrument that looks kind of like the neck of a guitar
Sounds like
Well like almost every instrument
You can imagine
It has a fingerboard and a row of buttons like
Bistro
Or tapping
Can hold it like
Guitar
You can hold it upright like an upright Bass
But you can also set it down on
On the table
Or your lap
And play it like that
Piano or drum pad
And when you put it on the violin setting
You can play it like a violin you can actually hold your iPhone out
And move your iPhone around in the air
And that will act like a bow
Mike says
It took them
6 years together
The way they wanted
Which isn't necessarily A
Silicon Valley Style
Way to do it
It's
What's more
In our case of Nashville hey
Which is going to
Studios with musicians in
And see what works
And go back in
Refine it and
And really look at the craft
A building
And to get it off the ground
Mike and his Partners actually raised
Over $1000000 on Kickstarter
They call it the instrument one
For about 400 bucks
Really I wanted this idea to be something that
Anybody could use
Rather than just making a musical instrument for musicians
I wanted to make
Fun for everyone else
Does Mike Becerra of Nashville founder of artiphon
We love hearing your stories and if you want to tell us yours
Please go to build. Npr.org that's build with a
Npr.org
Listen to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to
To how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us at hi BTS
Npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet it's at
How I built this
Usher was produces week by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to leave a grandson has
Import and Jeff Rogers
A Gyros and you listening to how I built this
From NPR
And just one last thing one day is NPR's new Daily Show inspired by the First Amendment
When a is the new show with those who makes the news
Guests
Can topical debates all friended ways to make
Ocusync and
Engaged
Each day one table Champion your right to speak freely
Checkout 1A with Joshua Johnson
WAMU
NPR
You can find it on the app
NPR one app or busy
Npr.org podcast
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.