Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
I remember at showing of The Brochure and he looks at Migos
Why do you think this is going to work
Does anybody else does this do you think you'll be
So I would encourage you to stick to your daytime job you have very successful flower shops sticks of that
NPR
How I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
They go
Turn flower bouquets into fruit bouquets
And after that
Delta multi-million dollar franchise
Edible
Okay so say you're an investor
And someone pictures you
Concept 2
Sell cool glasses online
Like Warby Parker
Or a ride hailing
Like Lyft
Or even a new type of women's undergarment like Spanx
You could imagine thinking
Yeah this might have a chance to take you out right
What are some one pitch to a business idea to take camel open
Pineapples
Strawberries
Carve them into
Flower shapes
And arrange them into bouquets
Would you jump at that
Because
Be honest if I were an investor 20 years ago
And Tariq Farid
Hitched that idea to me there is no way I would have taken it seriously
And as you will hear
Back when he first pitched it
Almost no one else did
Which is why in some ways
Today's episode is one of our most mind-blowing because
Tariq Farid had convinced himself
His intuition was right
And he defied almost everyone to build a franchise at today
That's more than a half a billion dollars
Annual revenue
But even more inspiring is how it all started
Because I tell the age of 12
Tariq barely spoke English
His parents took the family from Pakistan
Yuan to the US
In 1981
For a better life
They settled in West Haven
Connecticut
Antarctic dad got a job
At a machine shop during the day
And to make a little extra
You work the night shift
At Burger King
What happened in a few months after their arrival
Park realize
Just how tight money was
During a trip to the grocery
And my mother saw mango
And she was holding up mangoes
You know what we should buy some for
For the kids and they're like a dollar something each of my father looks seven
Sonos soundbar
WeChat
Dollar each
And this was a father who used
Cases
I'm in Pakistan you know we never had to leave you would do would eat until
Your stomach hurt
And that's why I realize the things that change
And I remember that moment that
Idyllwild
My father cataffo
Ford a piece of
And I have to help him at that point I never asked
And I started to
Kitchen
What kind of things did you do
So
Paper route
Villager News
In the summer months I would go to my
My father's machine shop
And then
You know I had a
A group of people that I clean their yards
Cut their lawn
Remove there snow
And then the
The flower shop
And that's probably the most in
Tell me about that
How old were you when you started working flower shop
So
I used to deliver papers as Charlie
Italian and Charlie's
Those amazing eyes
Nori's
Always to deliver paper
Crystal and might one day my brother just asked some
That Charlie
Are you looking for someone to water plants or
Can we help and I think Charlie felt
Charlie Charlie the owner of the
The flower shop
And he said you know what I need some help taking some flowers across
To the cemetery or watering the plants yet come on down
Come down a few days a week and do some
Thing and keep yourself
And that's why I started to
Work at the fair Sally's flower shop
Ana west
Haven Connecticut
And it was just watering the plants helping the customers
Taking orders
Bringing up thing
But the biggest thing was I was in the shadow of an amazing
End
He taught you how to do all the stuff
Not only taught me how to do that
But the genius of
This man was that
He would kind of have you follow when he would go and help a customer he would have you follow and he was to
Just amazed
So I learned
Just by shadowing him
Walking around with
Did you
Did you run the register did you make arrangements
The flower arrangements what are the things to do in the flower shop
I did everything
You know I've never really worried about what I'm doing I worry more about how I'm
So I wanted to
Press Charlie that I can
Good job
And Charlie was amazing at
Lemon said he might when my father would come to
Pick me up a drum to the car and it says you have a good kid Harry know he's a hard worker he's going to be good easy to make it easy to do something
And I just wanted those comp
Not only ran the register you know I would go and try to do things on my own so he knows he can
Count On Me
I would help people make flower bouquets and everything so by the time I was 13-14 I knew every
Three aspects of the outdoor plants out of water them hefei
What are some help customers there's a fourteen-year-old who's telling someone if you like them
Wow you're smart enough
And that pretty much started the entrepreneurial Journey
Did you continue to work in that
Flower shop throughout
Middle School
The second-year middle school I got a job at Burger King
Endorphin
Connecticut
The Burger King my father work
I can work all weekend I can make a lot of money because most of the money went to helping the
Family
When will you serve handing over your tracks to your
Two parents
Yes
Best
So you spent you know your middle school and high school
You know you were spending that
Working like working at
McDonald's Burger King or
Paper route or
Flower shop
Which obviously had a big impression on you
And then I guess at
Around 8:17
Flower shop winner for sale in your town
So my father
Since I worked at the flower shop he would always look
For businesses and I remember him
Taking me to a Subway franchise
In the Long Wharf
New Haven
Hotel where they
They presented why you should
Be a Subway franchise
Taking their and there was just too expensive
We looked at in a week
We could afford it and then he saw an ad in the paper
For a flower shop for sale but it wasn't the flower shop for sale beside the flower shop have gone out of business
And they were selling their equipment and I think
Clothes for $6,000
And he said to look at the flower shop for sale we should go check it out and I went checked it out
If you was a time that you never said
I didn't know anything about it I worked at a flower shop he assumed that
Because I work.
Probably run one
Solo
This could be good and we can afford this is only 6000
You want to do it and I said sure let's do it
What is the sea
Everything
What's a cooler in
Powder and
Refrigeration
Some inventory but it had been shut down for a while
And my father borrowed $6,000 from
Denise and Bill Holberg Hoover
His boss
Next thing you know we we owned the shop and it was just mostly the equipment is what we bought
We ended up
Convincing the landlord
Was it a pretty good location
I don't even know the
Shouldn't be a good location it was probably not it it probably went out of his
It wasn't
Location it was at a busy intersection and
And it was hidden it was Tiny was about 600 square feet
The tiny little flower shop
It was perfect
Depressed because it's something we could
1000 es6
It didn't really matter where was
Yasso with the $6,000
You have the store
And then what did you just start
I mean what did you actually do when once you sign the deal with the
But the guy selling you the shop
Made my first mistake
That's what I did you know somebody
That's why it was the first holiday was
Easter and I had never been to
To wholesale
Never I didn't know where Charlie bought
Flowers are what he got
So I looked up how to buy the flowers where we get them
Back then the nice thing was it was Yellow Pages for every
The end of found a wholesaler that I went to emboss
So I think I had like $600 that we had kind of saved up for
Initial inventory
For Easter
And I went and bought
The flowers and I didn't know what to buy on
And it was Mister
Caprotti who owns
Perrotti's wholesale flowers in in New Haven
I'll who kind of pointed me in the right direction to say you know you got to buy the pinks and the blues and
And the lighter pastel colors that Easter buy some tulips do this do that any kind of drugs me because he saw
I didn't know what I was doing so we got to help me out yeah
He directs me I pay him cash and pay good luck kid
And off I go
Show up at the shop
The cooler was shut down for a long time and I'm looking at the coup
Cooler and I don't know what temperature
You should be set back
Back then there was no Google
Flowers temperature
So I am looking at it and it has a one
And it has cooler and
Coldest or something like that and it was one
M39
And I'm thinking you know I want these flowers to do
Do well
But I didn't know that
The cooler had a freezer
Put the flowers in made all the arrangements got ready for
For Easter
When home came back the next day everything in the
Frozen because I had turned it on freeze
Temperature
That was the only money I had
So here I am I'm trying to revive the flowers.
I mean I didn't know you can't revive them trying to get him into a we know what room temperature water and see if I can save them
I can't so I show up at Mr
Perotti's wholesale
He knows I just bought the stuff yesterday
So you like what you sell out and I'm embarrassed
Tell him then I'm like
Spanish omelette
Stop and I'm picking a few things out and he notices that I pick a few things because I don't have that much money I only have
A hundred a hundred something that I got from my pee
Endyne Eagles what happened
And I told him what happened he got a laugh and he said just take whatever you
Go take pics of stuff and pay me whenever you can
You're good for it
And that was probably the most amazing kindness to some
Solicit
Incredible
Chico back and Preserve
You said it to the right
The right temperature
How do you get customers to come into the door
I learned a lot from Charlie
Set that you it's all about customer service. I know I didn't see Charlie advertise I don't know anything about advertising what I did see you
Was the great customer service he did
So we put up a banner outside get some specials
I think it'll be the people that come to you if you understand the custom
Most people want to impress or want to while someone so that's what I always focused
Don that have things that I know will sell and people would really like and make them in such a way that
Impressive
So we would make the
Beds have the flower book
Okay then
And make it real easy for the customer
The one thing we did I looked around at what flower shops did and everybody close by 5
Hawkeye State open till 7:38
And then we started to get a lot of customers coming home after work
And they would say I'm glad you're open late because I needed something that I couldn't get to the shop anyway
It was closed
All the shops are
The clothes so we started to do more and more of that that I would be open very late
And then the other thing was
So you started to get regular customer
And what does regular customer
You started to feel
Figure out what they like
And what works
And so what
What what do they like what were you doing
Well I remember about a year in that there was this gentleman that
Used to come to us and that he's to buy
Flowers for his fiance every week
At about six months in
He comes in and he goes we're getting married and we want you to do our wedding and
And I I was honest I said I am sorry
Never done a wedding
And I remember you know just an amazing guy
He goes to me why I never been married before 2 so we're both in the same boat don't worry about it
It will figure it out
And it was a large order I mean it was a couple of thousand
Dollars
And I remember doing that
Along the way
Learning every aspect that never been to a church
Before I didn't know what a alter is or
I'll run a resort or these
You know the carpet to lay down and everything but
Once we did that then after that
At the wedding
Became really big because another day was something that we did
Good and we had a reference
Who work there who actually random
Besides you
So I was in high school so
The first person that ever worked there was my
And also my mom
Released
The foundation of a
My mom would kind of wake up early in the morning get all the kids ready
BEFORE school
And by 8 you know if I would drop her off we had one car I drop her off at the shop
And then she kind of knew what to watch he didn't speak
English but she would
Watch the shop and then I hired an another
Employee to take the orders
I come back at 1
They would have
The orders ready I would
Take the orders and then I would go out on delivery so that happen
The first five or six
I couldn't really afford to pay anyone
Except that one person that would take
Take the orders in the morning and she had kids
So I have to be back by 1
So she could go back
For kids and then I would
How soon after you opened up
The flower shop where you
You profitable
I think
Breaking even or making some money we started
Going to do that within five to six
Six months because you never really had a value for how much
Get yourself you just saw that at the end some monies
And as long as there was some money left and there was a prophet
You did well but
What we did really good with us at the holidays were
I always focused on bringing customers back for Mother's Day and Christmas and Valentine's Day
And they always came back and that's when you really made the money
Services like 1988-89 87-88
End
What's the score
Start a hit its tribe did you think about expanding
Right away blow open the second store in Milford
Connecticut and how did you guys come up with
I remember writing a business plan
For a flower shop back
And what going to the bank
Say that I hate when I open this app
Quick $120,000 I need and I did a business planning
Presented it to the bank
And of course they denied
BBQ Emerson you were like
1918 years old when he went to the bank asking for money
About 18
Show images
You can't really blame them for not wanting to buy $20,000
I and I don't
What would you do then
I had to go back to plan B which was
Go buy something you can afford in
It's probably run down in it and it probably have to build
From scratch
How much was that second job
Cost about $70,000
It was a
Everybody was out fully
Functional shop
But it was a note that
The older house so he said I'll give you a loan you just pay me every month
I think I paid them off within a year
Going to half a year
Wow and by then
I had moved on to a third project
I computerized
My first shop when you say computer eyes
What do you mean
What a POS
What point of sale system
Cuz it was done all by paper
Up until that point
Everything was
This was a single IBM PC you would buy everything was on floppy disks back then
And we were just an 88 starting to get into hard drives
And so I put in a Novell networking and the reason I ended up putting it in myself was it I wanted to computerized my first flower shop
I wanted to put a POS system and bring in the wire service
Computers
And it was just so expensive it would people to come in at
$12,000 for Novell networking
Bill cost this much
And I just started
To play around with the myself and I put in the system
The myself
And once I did that
The company asked
We know there are other shops that are looking for that you want to do this
And by 88-89
I was helping other shops put in
POS systems
And by 90 I had launched a company that was to
So basically this company was
Providing
Installation service
You weren't actually making a soft
But you were doing what
2 years earlier somebody City
Do you hate you will wire your system up or twelve thousand bucks but you stop
I can do that for other people
That's right so so go from essentially like a ledger book with arrow
I like writing in
Their sales
And they're counting by hand to a
Computer system entering numbers into a computer that was then
File them away or
Create spreadsheets
Yasso
What it was
Paperless type of a
A format where what we were trying to do at that time with everything was done in triplicate with
Carbon paper or those that I
Duplicate where you would take an order then give you the yellow sheet and then the pink one would go to accounting and the white one will go to the design
Liner to make it in the driveway so this company called Daisy sister
Comes out of Memphis
Created the software and it was
They want flower shops as well
So I totally automated the flower shop
It's amazing cuz I mean obviously we take that for granted
You call
IPhone x new color
Shawty already know you are simply by the number that appears phone number that appears on there
An earphone
Up until that point I mean this most businesses were not
Using computer system
Computer sales right
And especially not flower shop
Smells like they were
Either expensive
So we started to do a lot of work and
Can I buy 90
I was doing a hundred
Percent of my working too
Automating flowers
You are
Barely out of high school I mean still got the
The flower shops in Mountain also this new business
You know we we reply
I thought you know I had more work than we could ever
Odoo we couldn't hire
People because
When I would tell them
Want to say I have this
Company and we automate
Flower shops like flower shops Okinawan you can hire somebody from IBM to come help you.
Mayflower she didn't think the industry was that big
Enormous thousands of flower shops
They all wanted
To get that efficiency your
Or manage their customers
So we were doing stuff
And then there was a lot of money in it because there was hardly anybody do
Doing it and we we couldn't do them fast enough or or process the orders fast enough
Suits you are traveling that you play on the road every single day of the week
I was probably home three days of the month and the rest of the days I was on the road
What kind of what
What are you guys doing
Oh there was a year that I did over $1000000
Wow
In in the network or flower shop in the number in the computer
So what happened to that company
Also the the
Parent company sold so in 1997
Teleflora body thesis
Customs and they ask
Would you like
To work for
You sold your networking
Prettiest part of this x-ray so Teleflora which
Which is now of course
Huge it was huge company
They bought this company and they said to you hey we we hear you do great work when you come work for us you said okay great
By then
You know I had to
4 year old and I was traveling a lot and I was ready to
Not travel as much as I thought I would really enjoy the part of working
For someone and not have to work
For myself and
And how to work as hard as I did and traveling
As much as I did
Also I thought I was ready
And how long would you last
Physically month-and-a-half mentally about
What you work for them for a month-and-a-half
Bump It Up 2 months at the mall
That's interesting I mean you must have really disliked it
I know it's not that I disliked it
I just think I missed that
Hard
Of the craziness that I thought I'd wouldn't like
The craziness of owning a small business and kind of going day-to-day and wondering what's going to happen if I am I going to be able to do this
I realize that I like
And I enjoyed
That that I wanted to go back
So what do I do if I go and start a flower shop from scratch another one
In and bought a building and end started building a flower shop in
97 and within a few months I was back running the shops
Is is that basically what you
You thought that you be doing for in Alex
For the foreseeable future
But then edible
Got in the way
Edible Arrangements
I had seen the fruit business being.
I had interacted with a where
People who are doing good
Fruit arrangements
Exactly what this existed
Yes
Aligned then there was a
Show on
Cruise ship that would make me
Big master
4 pieces of fruit
So I saw that and and
With it I started to Dabble
Into the electric how do you
Make the
Model scalable
How do you make a Ritz not a hobby or a small operation
That day I saw the opportunity in it
Kind of scaling you didn't do you know where you can open a few shops
And it really give a unique experience to the customers
And
What did you do did you start to
Experiment with
This idea at your flower shop
So yes yes
Got some tools
Got a knife and started to make
Just like Stamped Out you know
Flowers from cantaloupes
Melon balls and they like that
The same way as we did the flowers in the bag
Can you just
You just experiment you keep trying and
Until you get it right
So I spent most of 98
Doing that
Esoteric
For people who have
Kuzu no idea what Edible Arrangements are
Describe what it
What it what it is what it looks like
So it really evolved either so it started out with
Fruit arrange
That look like a flower arrangement
From A Distant but it was all cut
Fruit that yuan
Literally remove the wrap
Eat ever
Gcse bitesize
Strawberries cantaloupe
Honeydew
A pineapple flowers with a
Cantaloupe Center
So it is a flower arrangement
That you know the objective is to
Wow and then
Object is that it
Pierce it disappears really
So after you started making
Examples of these arrangements are you testing them out with anyone
Yes
Towards end of 97 and
Beginning of 98
I started to send it off
Two friends end
Samsung
Be great but majority of them thought it wouldn't work
Who's going to buy
Food on sticks in
In a basket
Yeah I mean I could completely see if I was your friend at the time I was at the same thing I was
Who is going to buy
Fruit arranged
Flowers
What a weird idea
Why would you end up think this is going to be successful
My father was so I think
Worried that he bought one of his friends
To who was a professor at a university
And my father saying I my son is starting this and
Hey I bought in Solon Solon
Nnn.
You some feedback
Any looks at Migos
Why do you think
You know and I'm like
I see the reactions
Customer
Has anybody else.
Cassano
The brilliance
Eddie goes well if no one else does
Play why do you think you'll be
I would I would I would encourage you to
Daytime job
You have very successful
Flower shops
Endom
I'm going to do this this is going to be released
Successful
You know and then I I know he asked me about a focus group I actually
I didn't know what if
Focus group was what he asked
Can you do a focus
And I kind of said something to him that I think he didn't like I said I did to a focus group I took it home
I put it on the dining room table my mother looked at inside oh my God honey this is going to be
I said he has so hated Mom said that I think it's going to be cool
Coming up how many many many more people have besides tarik's mom came to love edible or
Put this idea to a level that even he didn't think
Responsible
Gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
Stay with us
Support for this NPR
Cast in the following message come from betterhelp
Betterhelp Aubrey is a licensed professional counselor
Who specialize in issues such as
Depression stress anxiety and
Connect with your professional counselor in a safe and private online environment
At your convenience
Get help
Add your own time and your own pace
Schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built to learn more
And get 10% off your first
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
Apps that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
From NPR
Gyros
So it's 1999 and tarek
Has set up the very first Edible Arrangement
Inside one of us flower shop
East Haven Connecticut
It has a very simple layout there's a hand
I carved logo on a sign
Counter
And a small cooler in the back of the fruit
Because that first store opened right before Easter from the beginning business was
Pretty good
And I sent out brochures I made these brochures
And the phone started to ring and where people were more
Curious they would call to hit I saw this is this really what I say
Where is your shop
And then we tell them and so then people
I think we got 28 orders on Easter and I remember the numbers 28
NPR the biggest questions on the concern discussed
Merced was that hate you know
Animal doesn't really taste
How do I know it's going to be good
And that's where my mission
Came from and I remember getting on the phone with a customer and saying I guarantee you
The person who
Gets it
Will call you and use the word wow
If they don't use the word while
Will you call me back I will actually give you
100%
And really I said yes I never had to give anybody the
Money back because
People loved it
A tentative time
Where where are you getting all this fruit from
We would go to the market in the morning and by the
How did you how could you guarantee that it was going to taste good because even
Cantaloupes are always good and melons are always good since sometimes they're just have that sweet pineapple
Right I mean
How are you able to make sure that
The fruit was good
There's always good fruit
You just have to
One pay more
Second
Spend a lot more energy make
Inshore what year
You're putting it soar like
The Shoppes you know you have to stamp
Glad you have to learn about the
So now we have a whole team that does
Since we all team
The fresh team that does
No that goes all the way to the
Forms and sources
The fruit back then
Either you went and you shopped right
Even when the food cost me a lot of money and I was losing money I wanted to
The customers to get that occur
Experience because I was building a PC
Business I was trying to build a brand
So with that we made sure
That the experience of the
The customer
Was nothing short of a
And and you did that by making sure and then you threw away a lot of fruit
Because in when you buy a case there would be some pieces in it at you
And use you buy strawberries third of the Box you couldn't use
Because either that their shape wasn't right or they looked a little party
Or he knows. You pick the best one
Wanting you
Make it better but you know eventually as we
We grew we were able to Source it properly
Leanne get it right
The farm of knowing exactly the variety we want
Yeah
How long does it take before
It actually
You you you felt comfortable that it was going to take off
About a year
Maria
Did you have a vision at that point that this was going to be a national or International brand or did you think
I maybe this working will you know
I'll make more money and then I'll take that money and buy it
You know build another Outlet
Another shop
So I never thought it would be
National and that National Journey started
In 2000 where gentleman walked into our shop
And that look I was just visiting my mom from Boston
And everybody loved this arrangement
Can I open one of these in Boston
And anyways can I buy a franchise now of course I knew about franchising but I hadn't thought about franchising
Edible Arrangements
Thought about building a
Brad
That's why I spend so much time on the logo in
The name
So and I compose myself
Is that all that sounds wonderful
But we thought about
Where would you like to open
Migos Boston I said wonderful let me talk to my attorney I didn't have one
And I will get right back to you
And so I called my attorney who was a real estate at
Attorney and the egg called him up I said looking I need a franchise.
I know nothing about that
You know so he looked it up because they had this is Campo
We started that journey of then
I'm getting the documents ready
And doing everything tour
First franchise
And
One year later we opened our first store
In Waltham Mass
So after that first franchise
How did you attract
More franchisee statue
To cut connect with a
Like a
A law firm or company that does this and then they
Put it out there to the world
I never know we didn't want it at
What time so it was all word-of-mouth so up to our first
10 or 15 shops
It was all word of mouth because I was more
Concerned with
Doing it right
What happened with us was that then somebody
Visiting Boston
Calls from Atlanta and I live in Atlanta I want open one.
Please in Atlanta then I think the fifth call was from somebody in Northridge California say hey
I just saw this
I like to open a 1 in in in California
How do you say
How are you able to maintain quality like how how are you able to make sure that
A franchise owner wouldn't try to cut Corners by buying a cheaper fruit or
Cutting them smaller cutting
Pizza small
How are you able to maintain the quality that you want the youth kind of slade out in your
Store
Buffer state
It's the owner
So with that is first choosing the right
The right person
After that just having an amazing
Training system
Are you just going to train on how to make the rain
How to do the customer service we were the ones going
Each one of these shops
Literally replicating
Everything
So where you guys just
Kind of growing light
1 * 2 time
What what happened in 2004
The business started
Takeoff we started
Get a lot of phone calls I was able to hire someone that can start
Putting together structure and start selling
And
Inn at the appointed
Pretty much got automated and got bigger than me
How to stop iHeart a team
And that's when the magic
And the one I hired that team and all these things that we had automated and put into system we were by mm
Four 2005 wrestling 300 stores a year
And were you mean
At this point
I mean I think one might imagine that you had
Tons and tons of cash coming into the business or was it more complicated
It was a lot more complicated because
As soon as
We got to a certain size we open to Warehouse
Start doing the supply chain
I expanded the computer the computer business and started hiring a lot of the developers now the website was being devolved
Let you know the next generation of software was being developed
Lot of the money was going into building the infrastructure
Because I was more interested in scaling it
So there was never really much money and I and I remember. I would
Invite people to my home
And I drove around
A 1990
Before
In a Volvo 850 and people would come by single volume
I know you have hundreds
The story
And it would look me like we know it doesn't look like he's that's accessible
Hey how we cuz I lived in a little raised ranch and for me that wasn't important
I knew that I can always do that later in life
Yeah but building the brand is very
Cancel all my money at all my energy everything was invested back into
To the company and it paid off
So even after you already had like
200 stores
You were still reinvesting because right because it's really scale
I mean it in in many of the examples that we had on the show
It seems like at a certain point entrepreneurs
Have to turn to outside
Investors they have to bring an outside investor to really really
GrubEx
And is that what happened with you guys
So we didn't bring out any investors even though by 2006
2007 many people are interested in buying into
The brand
Or investing in the brand and I had many offer
Private equities wanting to
To get involved
I just
Didn't see any benefit of it at that time since I was self-funding and doing it
Why dilute
When you were working like
Dog the whole time
I think dogs even get a break sometime
Casinos Ohio
Obviously turkey work
And you did
Incredibly well and will
Talk more about that
In a minute but I mean
Is that
Is that sort of the trade-off
You know that they have a professional success at that level you
Can I have to give up some family time I mean
I read that your first marriage ended
In divorce
And then you had three girls at
Universal you weren't able to spend much time with so there was a price to be paid for
A very heavy very heavy price yes
There's a
And it's something that people
You know you have to be ready for an our business is very you
Show me when people are taking time off we're working
So on the holidays is when we're busy so when at people are going into the
Is holidays
We're just going
Started and so we're going to be busy through that
You know what I think the
The biggest thing that you look back at and
You wish you did it differently
This is probably the children you know the you know the
The kids because
I don't think they understand
I don't care if you're rich or poor you know they just want their time and they want
Your Lovin
A lot of times you're spending all this energy where you
Think you'll be big
But they're not seeing it
You're not taking Mom to fancy vacations you're not
You know you're working night and day you have no money you can't get a bank loan
So if you're telling a business to be big one day
And you know the nice thing is that they continue supporting you and they stay behind you and that's critical to someone who wants a scale app
Business and working a business and build a brand
This is you read about every Wednesday
Steve Jobs movie
To tell you how much
Albert the price they paid
For that success
It is very
Australia time
You don't know what my oldest is
Working with me and I I tell you
Every
Because I see her and end
And God willing
Hand it off to her how old is something that she could be
She's 23 and she works for the company
Dasha Belize
I'm glad my daughter is
But smarter than me
So okay see you
You're building this company
Growing really
Play fast
And then I guess at a certain point you did
Actually take some private Equity money right in invite 2012
And what why why did you decide to to
Except that money when you guys
We're doing great without it
Did I come from simple back
And you know I I didn't know anything about business I've never had any tray
My family's never
So you're always in doubt
That are you the
The person
Who can run it
Cooking scale at
Do you know what
Are you doing I remember
My attorney asking me
That he should be listed as a CEO and I'm like
Why don't I see you
And I remember reading books about wuxi
Videos are in interviewing people for
Tes position so there's always this doubt
You know you work
Very hard to build this
Company you wanted to grow
You don't want to make
Make a mistake
And so that was a thing was it was more for what I didn't know
I'm really curious about you started this company
Your company is
Door Brands your idea
You franchise it all these people are running it it's really great
You know but then in 2010 a bunch of franchisees
Did they file a lawsuit against you
I guess there was a dispute about
How long did the store should be open and
Things like that and that that lasted
I pray that lasted for like 3 years
Was that
Was that tough did I take a toll
Emotionally
Yes you know I I I put my heart in
King and I just was
So you know I know you're heartbroken
You can't believe it happened
You know I remember I have a very good friend of mine who
Susan light attorney who's going to the right-hand person
Guided me and I remember him saying something
When I Got Served
With the lawsuit
Say well you know
This just a matter of
I'm surprised
Lawsuit is part of the culture and this will happen
Pick a franchise is like a fan
Even in families are
Just disagree yeah
And end when your leader even if the leader of a family sometimes you ask
The family to do something and everybody and it sometimes everybody
To say we disagree
And we were kind of running the business from our point of view instead of the customers party
Give you flowers and Convenience Center
And and Lena deliveries and all that stuff in the world was changing
So we made some decisions at that point that we need
And we had some that disagreed
And at that point.
Legal action
What did the outcome
It was nice at the end
All the initiatives that we talked about
Did work end
Another lawsuit
Was withdrawn
And you know I think the relationship anybody that's
Thinking about getting into
Franchise should realize
That it is a relationship that you are actually now getting into a partnership with another
Entrepreneur
You don't have to spend a lot of time listening and making sure and inspiring and understanding what you're doing and you may disagree.
Times but you better have you act
Together and you better have you
Deposit together because
I'll let you feel once or twice but they won't let
That you feel too many times in her goofy things
Because it's their livelihood you're playing with if you're just simply
Putting initiatives together
That are really thought
Thrill
Do you is it important for you to be right
Are you prepared to be wrong
Oh I'm very pretty
What I learned
Long time ago
What was that
When you're wrong
And you admit that you
You're wrong everybody around you
You will help you
Tutu color
Dig out of it
And to help you learn a lesson
But if you have an ego
Or you think you are right
People
At that point not only will but have the
The right to stop
And I'm not I haven't gotten to where I've gone to
Because I've been right
It's just I've asked the right
People and bounce ideas off
People I love calling
People up out of the blue and
Just saying hey
Thinking about this what do you think
So I'll go
I'll be on a
In Bahamas with the family and we're on a phishing
You know somebody is not really doing it right
We got couple of boats
Did it this way set up this customers set up a website it sucks.
Just enjoy the
You just you kind of see opportunity in everything and
And and you think you can
Can do it because I think we as a business owner you
Your job is to build businesses
Edible Arrangement stores are there in the US Senate
Alright
About 1,300
What's a 1300
How many countries
1300 around the world
And do you have a sense of like what
Combined revenue is
Brawlasaurs annual revenue of a 600
From edible
Fruit from cutting fruit from cutting fruit
I tell people that I spend a lot of time with people bring me ideas don't underestimate anyone and
I don't underestimate the power of a kind of the market that
We have here in it and it's amazing and I realize you were saying that I have to pinch myself because I I am still I remember
You know my mother said something amazing
When I was 17 18 that really changed me for the rest of my life. You know I used to struggle I would come home
Okay what doing this much
I will not
Enough money I got to do this
Expensive
And does she she just in Oceano to she said it in your she turned around and she goes out honey
Are you have to stop chasing money be
Because money runs
Is really fast
You should go do the right thing it will chase you
And the NFL point I stopped worrying about me
Money so when the bank said no I didn't go there and say oh my God this
Homework I went and fee
Figure it out
How to make it work
Your dad came to this country
Penniless
Remote Village in Pakistan he was a machinist he was going to Burger King McDonald's on the weekend
With five kids
What is
What is to Paris make of your success
I am at me there just us
My father is
Retired now
Enjoys
Oyster travel a lot do a lot of those things
Things that you want to do
And did you want to be able to
For your father
My mom
You know never really got to see how it was 2005
Has she passed away and she was sick for a while
And she was instrumental
Avicii
Literally you know what she was that person that when I wanted to stop at
And give up and
Couldn't make
The bills
She would always kind of
You know remind me that you'll make it in
As long as you have your health
You'll do it keep going
So that that's what I missed
What's that I wish she got to see this
She spent a lot of time wanting her children
To be very successful wanting to me to be very successful
And pushing me
I think
She should be
Top of the world
Right now she was around to see what we were able to
What to do in starting out with this little flower shop that I used to drop her off in the morning and go to high school
Then she would watch the shop
And I
I know so. That's the part that
That's
And I wish it was a little bit
Want to see it but
My father is an otter
Every single
Old as we are
Tariq Farid
Founder of edible
A few years after his mom passed away
Tariq founded in elementary school in her honor
Osama Farid Academy
In Hamden Connecticut
Not too far from where
He grew up in West Haven
By the way Terex original Mentor Charlie circelli you know the guy who taught him and his brother had to run a flower
Up when they were kids
Well we call them to find out what
He thought
About his mental
I asked
Return to my brother I said
How do you like this kids
I pick my brain in the open up
I'm in competition with them but you know it was a beautiful copper
I'm happy with that kind of competition
After 38 years in business Charlie Ferris Ellie sold his flower shop this past
December
He still in regular touch with tarek and when we spoke
They were planning on meeting up for lunch
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
TD Ameritrade
For over 40 years
TD Ameritrade has followed a straight
Forward approach to working with clients
I listening
Everything TD Ameritrade offers its clients
Trading tools
Timeout resources you name it
Is built around you
Only after getting to know you do they help you develop a strategy that's aligned with
Your goals
For a complimentary goal planning session 2
Discuss your Finance
Future
Visit tdameritrade.com
Splash Park
Hey thanks for sticking around because
Time now for how you built that my name is Brooklyn Gold Bradbury I'm based in Tacoma Wash
Washington and I am a co-founder of a company called 512 apparel
What acquire something Brooklyn knows a lot about because it since she was a kid
Pretty serious volleyball player so years and years of volleyball wearing different uniforms different
Brands you really start to pay attention to what kind of materials you like and what bothers you about a uniform and what's up
Uncomfortable uniforms
You really uncomfortable in many many ways they have itchy seems or if they're too tight in certain spots are they
I won't stay down another spot since
Some of them
They're way too fake and they don't breathe and so you just their way too sweaty and gross and you just can't wait to get them off
Luckily for Brooklyn her stepdad Jeff is a designer in the clothing industry and a two of them
Start the talked about maybe going into business together to make a new line of athletic wear
Alvin apparel company it's very difficult to get started because
Consumers have the brands that they like and it's hard to pull somebody away from a brand that they know and love but Jeff
I've started to think of an idea that could set their company apart especially in a place like Seattle
If you'd heard of a textile mill in Taiwan that used coffee grounds to make fabric
Apparently it's great fabric for athletes with a very very breathable fabric but it's also
Odor Control so as you sweat and say you work out and then you go do something afterwards you're not worried about your clothes smelling
Godly like maybe some other spandex material would or like a cotton t-shirt would and in case you were wondering the closed
Not make you smell like coffee
Brooklyn decided to work with that Mill in Taiwan
And most of their coffee
Comes from the local Starbucks
The mill picks up the grounds and they extract all of the oil so that what's left is the coffee ground
Boil and then a very fine powder and that powder is infused in the yarn and that's what gives it its properties so
The coffee grounds are Blended in with the yarn that we use
They started to work on a bunch of prototypes and I started with long-sleeve jerseys
They handed them out to volleyball players and other athletes
Ask a lot of questions how does it feel around the shoulders and how does it feel when your unit bending up and down as if a
Fabric moving or staying in place and yeah that was a huge part of it before we actually launched an order our food
Full line and now that full line is out and available on the company's website they've been selling for about a year
Around $200,000 and are refurbishing a lot of coffee grounds right now
Welfare last collection we use close to 2,000 lb of reuse coffee grounds which equates to about
45000 cups of coffee or 90000 shots of espresso
And we love that idea we love it it's eco-friendly
There were using something that we all drink daily
Need to make a call
That's Brooklyn Gold Bradbury her company is called 512 apparel ads based in Tacoma Washington
If you want to find out more about it check out our Facebook page to search how I built this on Facebook
Of course if you want to tell us your story about the business your building go to build. NPI
Dr. Org
Anything for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this.
Npr.org you can also write us is HIV tea at npr.org
You want to send a tweet is at how I built this our shows produced this week but run. Delphox have with original music
Teen Arab Louis thanks for Claire Breen
Geoff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
I'm Linda Hall
And I'm Stephen Thompson
There's more stuff to watch and read these days than any one person can get to
That's why we make pop culture happy hour
Twice a week we sort through the nonsense share reactions and give you the lowdown on what's worth your precious time and what's not
Find pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pie
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.