Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource for
Tools tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Every store we open between our opening in 62 our first built
165 R Plaza De Lago store on 68 and 71
Every time was betting the company every time every time and every time
And we knew if we failed the company might go down
From NPR is how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist and the stories behind the movements they built
Gyros and the story of how Gordon Segal
Mike Carroll built the house where is Empire Crate & Barrel from one little scrappy storefront in
Chicago
It helps that single shop help change the way we furnish our homes and apartments
It was probably a good chance at
You have a piece of bike
Ikea furniture somewhere in your house or apartment
It probably looks pretty good right you know nothing fancy but
Functional well-designed kind of European looking
It's
Put back in 1861
If you wanted vaguely European looking furniture or plates or
Whatever in America
You had to be rich
Gordon Segal and his wife Carol were definitely not
We got married in the
The summer of 61
Now for a wedding gifts we really didn't get any of those kinds of things we loved me
Weed shop the department stores and see beautiful.
Designs of the new Danish looking whatever and none of our relatives
Had the money or tastes too
Tobias Wolff kind of wedding gift
So you just figured we just can't afford that so
Yeah so let's move on
That's
That's right
So we got married in
Like I say in June of 61 and we went on our honeymoon to
The Caribbean
And then the Caribbean we noticed
There were some really nice stores
There was one Scandinavian store in the Virgin Islands
My wife picked up some of the items in the set how can you have Danish 18/8 stainless
295 a place setting
It's so much more expensive than American
Danish Merchant there set
We have salesman from Europe come here and we buy direct from fact
And the very essence of their time and stuck in our minds as we bought a whole bunch of things
We got picked
Car going
I was in a real estate business
Teaching school we were both sort of bored
And then about in February of 62 on that I was washing dishes and I was
These dishes we had bought acid in Tokyo
They had to be other young people like ourselves with good taste and no money we should open a store
And what did Carol
Well
She looked at me
Sort of like I was crazy I said no no I mean it
We should hopeless
And you were young you guys were like what
When we were 23
And you just start
You know what we're about these beautiful things he's plates
Turn end
Cookware at the store in the Caribbean and if they can do it white white why not sell it in the US
Exactly
That's right
What is it like what gave you the confidence that you could pull off running a business
Because you know
We'd grown up
Her family had actually been in the retail business
Apparel
We're both very good at selling
My family been the restaurant biz
And all of those businesses
It's all about service
It's all about self
And innocence my freedom I grew up with an immigrant
Father-in-law
And the whole family on busy days had to work in the restaurant
So there was this background that we both have
And was we loved
Beautiful things
Obviously the motivation of going into business with
Find beautiful things for other young people
But if we could buy things from Europe
Directly
And just mark them up normally is if you bought them domestically not take a big margin
We could offer
Dramatically better pricing at Moore unique products
You know that people have never seen before
So how did you even start
We thought about it
And visit a trade Commissioners and we finally had all sorts of factor
Free reference
Search train
You want to Trade Commission had you
Glad you find Danish government would have a trade commissioner in every major
Intercity the Swedish government with we went to like their offices in Chicago and you anywhere like
Hey we want to open up the
Danish shopping can we play can we talk to you that's right
That's exact
Wow they had books about
Do you know factories in Europe
But that made
Specific items
Light glassware
And they refer to still some people we might want to visit
And gave us names of fact
Then we start
You know where we going to find a retail space
When we were driving around looking for anything
And finally it's so help my father man
Until us there was an area
WellStar
Street Northwest
Whatever is an old dumbwaiter Factory that was actually moving
And I'm I rented a space for 3 years for $350 a month
I mean after you visited these tradewraps and you decide okay we're going to open a shop
How did you come up with the cash to do it did you have any
Did you guys have any money
Well we had
Saved made a little money as wedding gifts
So weird about $10,000
And we figured what we really need 25
And I spent six months running around to everyone I knew had any wealth
Offering them half the business
House for $10,000
There was no such thing as venture-capital in those days there's no such things as start-up so those days
Yeah I literally couldn't find anyone who to invest 10000
You could have bought half
Crate barrel four ten thousand bucks in like 1963 that's right
The end of the day the only person who gave us the money was my father
I can't let the $7,000
Probably all the money he have in cash
Slough
Do you have 17000
Which of course I'm assuming you need to like
Order stuff
To sell rice
So we needed $10,000 for inventory and we only had $7,000
For rough
To build a store
And consequently
We had to come up with a clever way in
Taking this dirty old elevator fat
History and turning it into a
Scandinavian feeling
Place
In the walls wall torn up and damaged then we couldn't afford someone a sheetrock
Soap
We went out and found a lumber yard we found creating Lumber which we knocked up vertically on the walls and cover the walls
We literally did it I said
Identify the stuff that you eat
You wanted to sell me
Did you just
Go to the catalogs
That's right
Peach Factoria glasspack
Free weather app
Maybe an inch and a half
2 inch catalog
Red ceramic
Whatever
And we were just ordering from these catalogs
And having them ship the stuff
Maybe weird
Ford dinnerware patterns
We had
A very narrow selection of merchandise we only had ten thousand
And what like you were just like
Huge crates
Stop delivered like shipt yuan Chicago and
And you won't even open yet
Still not open
It opened
7th Ave
The December
Of a 19-6
52 but
It took a we didn't get into the space till like November 15th we only had about three weeks
So you were like
Hammering boards to the wall hanging
Sisters
Ordering a sign
Were you working all night we worked
From early in the morning till late every night
Andam
We were just
Enthusiastic
The value of being very young
Is you have a lot of energy and passion and no wisdom
And so being that young was a great advantage and we were heading
No Children lyrics
23 we had all the energy in the world
Because we had no money
Pictures
We've basically
Lake turned over the packing crates
The merchandiser
We came up with a way of stacking we found a
Some importer with some more uniform crates with some big barrels full of China
And about two weeks
We would open
We still don't have a name
And a friend of ours walked in
Looked around the
I remember I was in the basement doing some paperwork and my wife came
Down and said
Our friends suggest we call this place barrel and crate but
Gordon
Maybe maybe we should call Crate & Barrel I think that's better
And the
Approximately two weeks
Before we open the store we named
Name The Crate & Barrel
So
Opening day what happened
PECO
Who was the opening weekend and
This area called Old Town had developed
This over a decade the sort of wheat
The first week in December they called it the Christmas walk
And we open that Friday of the Christmas walk
And we forgot to buy a cash-rich
And so we actually use the cigar box
And it was until the following Monday or Tuesday that
Exit my father found an old old NCR cash register
The ones you used to have to crank up to open the
We have calculated that
We need to do about $100,000 to
To take out $100 a week to live on and their first Christmas we did $8,000 to your thinking
Well on our way to a $100,000 a year solutely goes 8 * 12 is 96
Yeah
But then January of 63 came along and we did $4,000 we got a little
Beard length
February of 63 I remember is probably one of the snowiest months
Chicago's history
And we have one day where we did $8 in the whole month was only $2,000 home and so are you freaking out
We were very scared that we would lose my father's money in their savings but you know what
When you're young you know you could start over
Slowly that spring came around Old Town became more popular they put gas lights up on the street
And people say what did you see that counterculture store down a well Street
They're selling nice things out of crates and barrels
And it was nice
And we ended up
Because you didn't know how to
Price merchandising
About half the product we sold we sold
You were selling the product at cost
Yeah
So not only where we importing it directly
The fact that we didn't know what we're doing and we're mispricing number tonight is also made it even more exciting
How did that happen
We had some major vendors who hadn't gotten us a proper invoice
So we're just guessing the price
We were guessing the price
In our customers loved
Just a minute with more from Gordon Siegel and how he took crateandbarrel National
I'm guy tries and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks
Two of our sponsor
You helped make this
Podcast possible
First of betterment
Betterment combines time test
Investing principles with
The transparency and ease-of-use
You expect from
Great technology
Focusing on Lower
Are fees and tax
Refreshing betterment really cares that
You reach your financial goals
And that's why they keep
Keep their fees low
How I built this listeners can get one month managed for free
For more information visit betterment.com
Built
Thanks also to freshbooks
Freshbooks believes that an entrepreneurs most valuable commodity
It's time
And although you can't make more of it
Freshbooks Cloud accounting software is helping 10 million entrepreneurs save time with their paperwork
I'm getting paid faster
Create invoices in under 30 seconds accept online payments in two clicks
And send late payment reminders automatically
For your 30-day free trial code
Freshbooks.com built
Enter how I built this
How did you hear about us
Just one more thing before I get back to the show
As you probably know by now at the end of every episode were telling your stories about the company's or products
You are building so
Please do stick around to hear it
It's how I built this
From NPR
Gyros
And on the show today were talking with Gordon Siegel about how he and his wife Carol
Filter retailer
Crate & Barrel
So it's
The business card took off pretty quickly
Even though you had some tough months it kind of took off
Well the first you would get a hundred thousand
Do we did end up at the end of the year doing a hunter
How's the second year 200
The third-year 300000
What was it like that in those early days it was that was making you guys successfully
Did you did you have that
Can I create a market
For for the staff are or the people just come in and say this is cool is bias
Well what happened was we were very fortunate
America was then getting wealthier in the early 67
Toot It was a lady named Julia Child's that came along and made cooking fish
Fashionable
3 jet travel
Especially Yours
MN many more people would doing it these events
Started all of a sudden
Making people aware of French cooking yeah there's a big difference in the way
You know they looked at dining in
Food was very important chefs
Important
American those days
Cooking wasn't sure it wasn't something people
Love to do and dining and serving in the dinner table
You know but
I remember in Chicago in the early sixties we had maybe three good restaurants
Boston I remember Craig Claiborne was once a ass when he was up in Boston where do you
But he was a food critic
Where did where did where do you go when you want a good meal uses
I go to the airport and I get on the first flight to New York
So it's hard to believe that the map is Boston in Chicago. Great restaurant
Because people now there's a major food culture and dining culture
15th exist when we were
And did you
I read that at a certain point you and Carol
Decided that
Instead of like
Just ordering from catalogs that you should actually go to Europe and
Visit factories
That's right
The first year in 1963 our first
School year in business we didn't have time to go to
1964 went to Europe
4/3 weeks
By then we had two or three staff members
We left the company
I need them
And we went and we traveled all over Europe
Who started in Belgium
Found a great class Factory we went to
The German trade fairs in Cologne and Frankfurt and found all sorts of Interest
Products
It was incredible nothing like that again
We spent a lot of time
Walking the streets and sing special stores
Looking at stores and seeing what were they doing in Europe why were we so excited
What was it was the visual.
Play it was the way to use color it was the way they did the storefront was the way they did their lighting
And we became students of retail
And Carol by the way
Company never will
Conceited without her
Effort she was not only talented
Helping select products
She was very talented Edition
And we're both very good at selling so when you were in Europe were there any
Like what
Mid 20s
Did you ever have a situation where these Factory owners go to YouTube
Who are you you know
Bright like that there were many people had doubts but
Rihanna we have letters of credit we had
Ability to buy we found us an agent Sweden who is the new a lot of people who helped us
Introduce
Factories
And I don't believe in
Are we met tour banasco up in Copenhagen who
Introduce the store marimekko and introduced to us a lot of Danish factories
He sold us beautiful
Product also wouldn't things
Textiles
Leather goods
This guy influenced Our Lives seeing his wife we remain friends for the next 50 years
So how did you guys start to like a really grow the business
Because you didn't have it outside
We never had outside investor
Matilda
Many years later
So how are you guys able to expand without
Any outside money
Well we basically knows they should go to a bank in your borrow money
I remember our first home was $10,000
The second loan was 25000
When we open the store and 65
You still at only one store we're doing $500,000
Which like today is like a little store doing $2000000
So when you guys decided to
2 to open that second
Install
1968 is that right
Right so then you got
A bank loan and then where you were
And I guess you were betting the company right because
Yuan with that leverage of the SEC
Score fail the whole thing would go under
Every store we open between are opening in
62 Oxford
Buildstore and 65r Plaza De Lago
Gemstone 68
Are Oakbrook store in 71 every time was betting the company every time
Every time
And every time we knew if we failed the
The company might
Go down
And then the 1975 we got the opportunity open our first Michigan Avenue
Hyundai
If we fail here that would certainly Twitter invest a lot of money
Take a big risk
But that store opened in 1975
And
After 3 months we knew was very
Successful
And from then on
The pressure was a lot less than it wasn't better company because by then
You know if we were doing enough volume and creating enough profits
So we didn't want partners
We didn't want investors
Why not well because we felt they would have different motivation
We love being mortal
We love talking to customers loved inspiring staff
And we love searching for the product
Our goal wasn't to build a chain store
Our goal was to
Find the best merchandise
The best price
It would excite our customers
Imp
Exciter staff about what we were doing
I was reading about
About the expansion of company and I guess it took like
25 years for you guys to go from one store 217 stores
Right which was in 1985 who wrote then
But then by like 1995 you had expanded to 60 store so what what happened why did you guys were
Why did you decide to
To grow so much faster
Well we reached a different era where it was important to have scale
To do the things we had to do with buying merchandise
So you had a guarantee to a factory used by a certain amount of
A product
To make sure we were the only people in the Senate
States that would be carrying it
And you began to sense that you needed scale to
That's what we started doing
1990 rebuilt of flags
Ship store in Chicago
Which really helped launch our expansion because then
Every landlord every shopping mall one of the Crate & Barrel build
And we were a big attraction cuz we drew in a lot of customers
And what happened starting in that big expansion was landlord started
Paying for a lot of the build out of the store
Building of the building and whatever
So we didn't have to take
This much of our Financial Risk ourselves
Does the landlord's built
The store has a lot of these.
So sounds like things were going pretty well for you
Without
Having any outside investors
So what what made you decide to
Eventually
Bringing outside money
What was your thinking when you made that decision
Hyatt
Thought by the time I was 65
I was thinking about 60 I
I thought I'd probably want to retire
And some
Intelligent guy said you know
You're going to you no sell your business to it 5 years
Before you retire so you can help them
The transition and whatever
And
Now you own the responsibility to both my
My family into my staff
You make sure the company was well finans than
Could take risks and could go through trauma
And survive
And I also realized that at that time to company was
Relatively very strong of retail
The relatively weak indirect marketing which at those days was cattle
Cadillac yeah
We've actually spent a year-and-a-half
Looking around the world for a partner
And we finally found out of the Auto Group
In Hamburg Germany
And they were
Second largest
Mail-order company in Europe
Today either
After Amazon there's a big
Just internet come
In the world
And the 98 we sold them about two-thirds of the
Company
And I'm
10 years later the contract was
Poems for 10 years
We sold them the the rest of the third ISO 98 you agree
Stay on for
Affixed maritime
Continue run the company
Exact
Their basic
Chick-fil-A Worcester choir
Businesses like ours and let the management continue running
In our success was we trip
The size of a company
When troubled
The profits of a company
And we were able to grow but more important
Stay after we with him a year to the said you got to really look into this internet
Then what was it 99 mm
Who said what's the internet and then they started telling us
And early and then we started developing our
Internet business which today
Represents about 38
Percent of all the sales at Crate & Barrel
And the customers buy it
Normal amount of furniture
Which is hard for me to believe
So when you
You stepped down was that
Built
Well of course it's hard
Beano
I didn't realize that have that much energy left
70 but I've enormous energy but the last
To three years I've been
Doing things in our family office of finding new Young.
Nurse week
When I advise young people today I said look at the job and say you going to love it
And it's going to be something you can devote your life to
And work 10-12 hours a day and works
6 7 days a week
I mean
Then you'll be a success
But don't go to do something cuz of
Apus salary or
Title
And I think that's the thing we picked up from the European
Friends of ours who
You know have a different pace of life in a different Focus
You know that's how it should be
I want to make a lot of money how do I do it it's
What do I love to do and if I do it really good
Then we will make
Money
How much of
Your success to yuan
U2
Just
Jarrett Allen
And you're
Smarts
Your hard work and how much do you accrue
Well
The lucky part was our timing
It was just
Set the appropriate time to
Going to Europe to find new contemporary
Designing
Tabletop
The furniture nest
I think it was
The talent of
Attracting people and making them feel like
We were all in it together
That I didn't realize I had nor did I
Pitbull eyes I was good at
For many many years but I was
And I think that had a lot to do
I was lucky to be married to Carole Segal who had the
This enormous Talent
You know we started out too
Create something that was going to be different and beautiful and wonderful
This is still in the culture that company yuan
Great depth
They're still doing very well
Ever have imagined like when you open up this thing in Chicago in a disused elevator Factory with
Boards that you hammered into the walls
This company will be doing sales of
What are Cracker Barrel's hours today
About 1.2 billion
That we went from one employer to another 7000
Could you ever have imagined that
Never never ever
We never plan we had no ambition to do that
We just had ambition to love what we are doing
I still have
Someone I graduate college and lose my first
Department
My mom bought me
Set of
Flat white
Crate & Barrel
Dinner plates
They were they were made in Japan at the time
Time I still have
Sub serve dinner on them
Well that's our problem you replace cars every 2-3 years you have dinnerware for
20 years
You know
People tell me they have product they bought in the 60s and 70s
And I Winspear
Gordon Segal officially step down as CEO crate Barrel in 2008
But two years ago the company if she brought him back to help out during kind of a rough patch Gordon
Safer year things be a more stable now he's doing mainly philanthropic work in and around Chicago
Oh and in a few months Gordon and Carol will celebrate 56 years of marriage
And please don't turn it off
Yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Cleveland Clinic
Cleveland Clinic is ranked number one in the nation
Arcare
22 years in a row according to US News & World Report
For more information or to get a c
Second opinion
Clevelandclinic.org
Heart Care
Hey thanks for sticking around because now it's time for how you built that and here's the story we got from allicattt
Avedisian who kind of stumbled on his idea few years ago when he was just out of college
He was working an
Surfing
In a fishing Village
In El Salvador
And one of my friends that was living in the community actually showed me the roofing
Haunted homes
It was colorful and bright
And so it made us just look at it again. I think that's a billboard and it was the roof was made from part of a bill
Billboard that
You'd see on the side of any road
And I was thinking
How could that
Working
Billboards
Paper right that that roof is going to
Fall apart in a day
But then he started to do a little research
And I was like what
And no I didn't know the Billboards were made of PVCs what's a heavy-duty vinyl
Material cell
Directly UV protected
Waterproof
Southern Roofing and durable enough to last me to keep the water out then they could definitely
Turn into some sort of product
Alex figured all of that bright heavy vinyl
Can be made into really strong duffle bags and backpacks and things like that
So after you left El Salvador and move to Southern California heat started
Make a few calls
I didn't know anything about billboard companies
But I just started calling and once I told him hey you know I think I can save you guys some money
Can I have a few of them
Basic yeah sure that the ad companies were happy because they didn't have to pay to
Dump the vinyl in a landfill and Alec was happy
Because it didn't cost a lot to get the stuff
Pretty much the cost of shipping
And we had his very first sheet of vinyl to cut up
He designed something he actually knows something about
I carry bag for
Is surfboard
I figured a surf bag is like a pancake there's only two sides to it so I'll be the easiest thing to make
Let's start with that
But it took him a while to figure out how
Actually get it made
So my first bag I took to a car upholstery manufacturer
Try to know anybody that did sewing
And that first bag actually looked
Good enough for Alex have one leg more
So fast forward a couple months and Alex start selling these surf bags in sport shops
Around La
And thanks for us to Branch out into other products
Phone covers
From one billboard we can get upwards of 150 backpacks and probably around a thousand phone covers
At least
Every one of the products is unique
Different shapes different splash of color because
Each item is cut from a different part of the
Cheyenne Highway advertisement
How you name it
Virgin Airlines Alaskan Airlines
Gucci Pepsi billboards
Wash
Park at a warehouse in LA County eventually found a factory in Mexico
That does all the sewing any billboard that you've ever seen
Turn it into products
The bags and phone covers are now in about
300 small retailers across
Do you ask
The company just started to turn a profit
But you know we're not there yet but oh my God this thing wasn't sure success
This thing is definitely still a hustle and a grind but that's also the fun piece about if you know
We love coming up with new marketing and
Funny ways to really tell the story
That's Alec have a DC in
Younger brother Eric on the company rareform that's
Rareform. Com
In LA County California
You please keep sending us your stories we love reading about them and sharing them you can tell us
All about your building by visiting build. NPR. Org that's build with a D
Npr.org
And thanks for listening to the show this week you can write us directly at HIV tea at npr.org
Calciphylaxis
Twitter account at how I built this
Please also subscribe to our podcast
Do iTunes or however you get Podcast in if you get a chance give us a review We love to hear what you say
Our show is produced this week
Casey Herman
Music composed By Ram teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant sanaz meshkinpour and
And Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Claire Breen
Garage and you been listening to how I built this NPR
Kiss another NPR Podcast
You will definitely
Enjoy cuz all songs
Considered as NPR's
Discussion in
Discovery podcast
Each week
Boylan and Robyn Hilton
Since you're the best of the best new and
You can download artist interviews live concert
Lots and lots
Songs you'll fall in love with
Find new all songs episodes every Tuesday
Npr.org podcast
And on the NPR one app
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email template
Lakeside drag-and-drop email Builder
Older and customer support 7 days a week