Support for this podcast in the following message come from mizzenandmain
Creators of moisture wicking wrinkle-resistant dress shirt
Shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
Come and use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
He is guy here I know a lot of you have been asked
King about our live shows
Happening this summer we have one more happening
In Seattle in mid September
And tickets for that event will go on sale soon we will let you know when they do go on sale UK
You can follow us at how I built this or at
Gyros
To find out when and when they
Available
You can buy them at NPR presents
. org
Okay here's the show
Do the same thing but I think there's also like we could have tried
To go any faster there's just not that much was in our control we didn't have a lot of money we didn't have a lot of info
A lot of connections so we're moving as fast as we could and that's kind of his that's as much as
You can do
From NPR how I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movement
Build Kickstarter and with it a culture of crowdfunding ideas
Might have never gotten off the ground
You know there's a kind of mythical narrative around
Startups especially if we're talking about tech startups and
It goes something like this
Founder has an idea
Ben founder recruit some friends than friends sit in a room and start writing code
And then they try to get the app or the website out to the world as fast as possible and then
It just explodes blows up
Millions of customers sign up and investors.
Beating down the door
But today
We have a somewhat different story
This is the story of Kickstarter and they did of course
Start with an idea
But it took eight years before that idea
Became a reality
The three co-founders did build a website but
None of them knew how to code
And he spent years refining the concept before anything even went live
And they were working with a very small amount of money
It's a path Less Traveled exam
Much less likely to 6
It's not how I would recommend anybody
Attempt to do this
This is Perry Chen what are the co-founders of Kik
Kickstarter
Harry grew up in New York City
We went to college in New Orleans where he was really into the local music and arts
And after he graduated he
Came back home
To me you are counting like a lot of college graduates
I didn't know what he wanted to do
But he knew one thing
He needed to find work
I came back to New York and at the time I've been DJing a bunch of New Orleans and I start to work on my own music
I applied some record labels like you know
Send my resume
To whatever the worst get job they have is where you like you're just stacking CDs on the Shelf
Yeah but you're opening box
And
Of course I never heard back
Answer that that didn't happen I don't think I had any idea and then I heard from somebody that they said that
A guy went to school with look
Looking for Warm Bodies
To do what
2 Above All Things
Day trade
Did you know anything about
Nothing nothing nothing he just needed people to what to show up and do like
Click buttons
Yeah you know I think at this time in early 99
What's kind of the Wild
X stock market
And
So I went down I talk to him
10 minutes
He like an idiot like an office and then had no it was like a large room
You know it was like a open floor before dressing like jeans and t-shirt and you know mostly
Guys mostly under 40
And you know he talked to me and he's like okay fine you know he's like
You come in you know will trade you
For 5 days
Then you just go trade will put a small amount of money on your account you just trade another no clients not telling anybody anything
It's just this guy's money he's like if you
Do well you know you'll get
Some of that energy
Keep down
Just don't worry about it and then you know
That's it
Yeah they were like you got it was something
Play Modest like $2,500 a month you know
I mean listen it was you. Beggars can't be choosers I was like sure what happened
Was literally just get sat down in front of a computer and
Sitting there by yourself and you can buy or sell stuff in your decisions on like what I'm reading the Wall Street
Journal or no not at all I mean you're buying and selling something and in a minute
Allow or 5 minutes or holding it you don't
You might not necessarily know the name of the company
It was like a combination of
Mario Brothers and surface in the ocean I assume and I see a wave come
Means you're like okay
It's simple it's a little instinctual
And
I did it for maybe
Little less than two years or so did you walk away from it with some listen cash
That was a little bit I mean nothing crazy but definitely decent for
Somebody in their 20s
But you know after while I mean I was kind of like
What am I doing you know I'm not doing anything I'm not helping any
Best what I'm doing is neutral MMS telling somebody on any
I think so
The traitors like to think that there
Providing liquidity from great service but
You know it's it's your doing
Nothing you're shuffling some numbers from one computer to another
So
Judge had to go back to New Orleans it's much cheaper than New York
My intent was to just kind of really focus on working on music
Sick to get better as a as a producer
I'm kind of
Pick up jobs here in Irvine
Did the idea of Kickstarter
Come to you
At that time
I think so I think it was
I always stay late 2001 early 2002 because to be honest
You know I can't remember but
You know what New Orleans jazz festival is kind of one of the
The two big breaks the year the right now other than Mardi Gras
So I wanted to throw a show
Where I was going to bring in these this to
Electronic artists
From Austria
Critter endorf
See that you fly them
From
Vienna to New Orleans and have them do a gig
Sure I mean you know the hope is that though they would just happen to be in Mississippi
Yes I mean I was not an event promoter so this is all just kind of on the Fly
But
It didn't happen
And
It just kind of bother me
And why is it
The dad
I would need to
Come up with the money and make this decision that this thing would
Have enough people,
I I thought
What if the people that
Would want to come to the show could have a say in that
And if
Enough people
Could do that before a certain point then show can happen
And if not
Ben it
That was it that was
At the beginning
And
What I remember most about like
Are good ideas all the time and and you know but within a little thinking you're going to find the Fatal flaw
And so what struck me most about it was like
Confined
Edits so it stuck with
And so I kind of
Had this feeling I was like this is
This may be something
After that feeling I was like okay
Cool
Impacts of regular life
Music
And
Being in New Orleans
Riding my bike
It's a good life like see your friends from high school or college
Coffin and start
Play careers in
Laguna Clara Finance anything
Yeah yeah maybe I should go into a career
No I mean you know what I felt was
I'm living in New Orleans
I'm working on music
This is why people work for 35 years
Retire
New Orleans twerking music
So
Am I jealous of my friend who works
70 hours a week
No
All right so you are so you're in New Orleans
Your
Doing different things you have this idea that sort of comes and goes
And I guess around 2005 you move
Back to New York
Yes exactly May of 2005
Who was the reason why he moved
I think it was a lot of things I mean I think that
Partially because I was
Moving
Away from music a little bit
I was kind of fighting with it
You know what I think
A lot of times we have an idea right and you can
Put on the shelf of your brain
Somebody will say something at certain points in a remind you
Yes I think that's kind of what happened
As I was getting close to probably in the final year of New Orleans isn't getting
Close time back to New York leaving year-and-a-half
I think I kind of came back in Moorpark
Go away
I knew that
Pepper soup
You knew that you were going to
Previous idea to educated come back to you
Yeah part of the reason being to is that in New Orleans it would have been pointless
You know I don't know of any
Tech Community
Who's there
In the early
It might have been
Certainly I wasn't
So yeah it was my plan A
When I bent my back to New York
Well
I got a job
Working at a restaurant in in Brooklyn that actually
Yeah you used to love you were a waiter there I was
And you know I'm at UNC after I've been at the restaurant for a little bit
Music at the time she would come in
We chatted a bit and we were like talk about music and
Baseball and then we just hung out a few times and end
Pretty early on we hung out maybe the second time or third time I kind of shared with him that I was working on this idea
His reaction when he told him he's had some brilliant idea
What's funny that that was not the reaction I mean it wasn't it wasn't the extreme opposite
Like I'm not sure
So
I don't know if my thought of time with that would be working together but I thought
You'll be worthwhile to
Talk to him
And we started talking more and more about it and simultaneously becoming better and better friends
I think we
It just come naturally came together and set it to work together did either of you guys know anything about
Coding orbital the website or or anything like that
Well I certainly didn't throw any technical sense
I cannot code and I couldn't code
But I think I
How to send of
What a Chick-fil-A
I know what I like I know what I think feels good when I'm on a side
But
From the deep technical stuff
No
That was not my background at all Yancey probably have been closer but
He's not a cuddler
So what did you start
To do at that point to meet you
Pinhead first
This idea and
And what were you doing during the day
Yeah it was at first
I mean I was reading blogs
On the internet
Bye
People who
Had started
Internet companies
I was reading about it
And maybe finding a friend or friend of a friend and you don't plan to give me telephone to talk to somebody
And I did it
It was slow going
But yeah you can learn a lot by just kind of
Google Excel
HP Connected to two you have a third co-founder Charles Adler
We need
Somebody was a designer user experience person
To help kind of
Mockup website
And
An old college roommate of mine for my friend freshman year
Call my friend Charles move to New York and he's do
Person touch
Charles my email to come over to my house and in Bed Stuy the next day
And
We
Work together kind of like almost everyday or every weekday
Couple months
Your hand drawing like what the said look like Man drawing or 12 go into Photoshop or illustrator in
Kind of like
You know just a rough
Mock up stuff
You're getting into detail like
Here's a button
Here's a
A video
This is what happens when you click this
Your real in depth
At the end of the document
Pages about how the sight words
0 code
What was it what were you doing who are you making this for you making this her potential
Investors or region
Which is something that you guys would have
This was to make
This is not fair
This was just
You know what we would use
When we
Had the money to
Higher
Developers to
Build it
But this is critical
Call you know you going to know what
When did you guys get investors
It was in 2006
I had a friend of mine
And her cousin is David Cross
The comedian from Arrested Development mr. show
Great stuff
And so she
Connexus
And we went and had a drink at a bar and I and I talked about the idea and and a few months later he invested
A little bit of money and that was our first investor and
Two and a half more years for free of the lock the website
From your other early investors in 2006
I took a year-and-a-half so from that point probably from there too early 2008 we raced Maybe
$120,000 in a year and a half that was all of the money you had
To basically pay for server space or whatever you need to do to find a developer code
All these people
I think you know
At first like the working title for years in my mind was critical
Because it was very much of the mechanism of life
When you reach a critical mass of
Park
Then
I think it out
Yeah but you know I think
A lot of things
Sisters
Bicycle organization in NJ
It's really you mechanical
Anyway so
I think it has been together.
Grueling process
Prezi what domain you can get
And yeah and then came out with this and
Was able to get the domain for
Appreciate
Tell me what the business model was from the
Are the idea was exactly as you see it today which is
To charge
Small fee
If and only if the project
Sounded so
You know if a product and get funded another listing for you so
We would
Get nothing you have this plan
People would put their projects up if it's funded
You guys get a cut what's up percentage cut
5%
Soak City start with 5% if it's not funded
You get nothing
Yeah
What's interesting about your story which is very different from a lot of other
Tech companies is
You didn't just like get to a minimally viable product like in 6 months and
Have it up and running like this
At least 3 years
Yeah I'm into two-and-a-half 3 years but very different from
More classical stories were it's like a couple of friends who worked in the industry who
May have connections or they can build it themselves
I don't think any of us had a sense of
Where the end of the road was or where the goal was
Who went when the three of you like when Nancy and Charles and you would would serve
Talk to other people in your life and you would say
I'm working on this and I'm trying to do this website and then you would see them again 6 months later
How long do you think people were skeptical or or whatever
You learn what it feels like to be a documentary filmmaker
Laura reiter you know it's like you still working on the book I'm sure people thought that and I wouldn't blame them I'm a
It was long in the tooth for us certainly to
Aren't you getting stressed out that somebody else is going to
Beaches punch in and do the same thing
I think that's certainly comes to mind
But I think there's also like
We could have tried to go any faster there was just
Not that much was in our control
We didn't have a lot of money we didn't have a lot of influence with
A lot of connections
We're moving as fast as we could and that's kind of his
That's as much as you can do
Why do you think you guys stuck with it
Intersecting
People wouldn't normally lose patience right
So was it just that connection between the three of you guys like each other was at the idea or was just like
You just stuck it out
I think it was the idea
You know so many things don't have access
There aren't Industries or investors whatever set up around 2 fun things.
Market Minot besides
And then even the things the market might be sizable enough that the deal you have to make to do that
You might have to contort your idea and something
Start sit
What's your idea anymore
Yeah or you just happen to have money
Like this can't be the only way that
Ideas can get
I think we saw it
You know
Sometimes you just see it
I guess you're not always right
But just seeing it
Is really critical and so
And where was changing over these years you know talking about 2005.
It only made us
See that what we're building made more sense
Not less than
Good morning
Did not laugh if you would
Engage with it more easily
With the rise of social media with the rise of YouTube
Not laugh
And so
Of course is luck involved that that was Rising as we were taking our sweet time
Getting it going when we come back
The opportunities Kickstarter had to grow into a much bigger company
NY Perry Chen decided not to pursue any of them
And I Rise you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR and the following message come from the luminary
The only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah's a new podcast
With his new show The Daily Show host challenges himself and his list
To explore unfamiliar angle
Embrace differing viewpoints listen to Trevor Noah's new podcast
Cast along with other original shows only on luminary
Visit luminary. Link / built for your first two months of luminaries premium content for free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets
Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape
The China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcasts Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com podcast
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Welcome back to how I built this from NPR I'm guy rod
Who is Perry and his co-founders continue to make
Slow progress on Kickstarter
Competitors began to appear
In fact 18 months before Kickstarter went live Indiegogo another crowdfunding site
Launched
I'm just wondering how you were able to
To withstand the uncertainty of it all.
Your recollection makes it sound like you were just sort of like yeah you know whatever will this is my thing and I have a plan B and
I want to do this but I mean
Most people I think wouldn't
Feel that way they would feel
Anxiety
About the uncertainty of
Do you think that you're just wired differently
I mean I felt a tremendous amount
Radiator
But it wasn't that excited with driving me
And I think it normalized
A little bit over time
One of the things I noticed
Not just as weird
Triangle on butt after we had launched that
Those years were so trying
But I kind of had
To learn to adjust
I kind of like stay in the middle
Hey you don't have to get too high or too low because I think that both happen like
Somebody might invest small amount of money and we be like super site
You know
Or
Hey we found a developer wants to work with us or whatever do little things
Super excited
Okay. Going to happen with
And then something happens where that doesn't come and you all look down and I think that happened so many times
Ups and downs
Dad
I think it just kind of I just maybe my defense mechanisms
Kicked in tonight
Force me to stay a bit more in the middle
Either way
Right what's the name of steamed amazing happened or what
Maybe sign that's him.
So what was the thing I mean
It was almost three years in the time that you form a company to the
The time that the website actually launch what was that
Who's the Triumph of what enabled you to actually make this thing
Go live and become a reality
Well I think that
In some ways we made every mistake in the book
Some kind of fruit did that we did one lap that way
Classic stuff like
People with experience telling us
You know you shouldn't do something
This way
And us being like well
We appreciate that but like you know
It'll be different for us and then of course it's like exactly what I said happened
Like duh
And so I think we had got a little experience after few years
But then they're just people you know we found amazing
People one of the people we met
Was Andy Baio
Who really helped us kind of
Figure out what kind of Technology we should be using and helped us interview the developers that we
Would hire and he didn't give him a first date
That was tremendously helpful
Because none of us could
Review the code that we were
The developers were
On the right track
So that was that was really critical
Those things kind of
Coming together
Yeah
When do you launch the day you launch
How did you get
The word that has people even
Find out about
I think you leading up to when we actually
Knew we were going to lunch or believes
Are we even talking to people about it
Telling people to try to build up
Projects collage on the side as well so there was that Outreach
Waiting for the lodge Detroit
Whatever their products
And I think we launched with Jenna maybe 5 or 10
Projects
The first week
Did you remember what were those projects for
I think the first
One might have been drawing for dollars
Which may be raised
10 or $15
Do you just contributed a Kickstarter campaign to that person
Draw whatever
You know I can't recall whether it was that they're making a specific drawing but as part of a reward May did you get if I return dollars
They would also make one for you but it was great I mean it's amazing see anything I backed that project
Launch go on with our friend Claudia
The first day as well which is called New York makes a book
Which was trying to get people to give $30
And everybody who did will get a book and page in the book to submit
Whatever material they wanted
And did Kickstarter make money right away like with a fees
The first 6 months I think was free
You know people don't even know what this is you know how much can you ask
Pay money for
What was it do people notice it right away that you guys
Right away
Realize it was successful or was it still kind of underground in the shadows
It was a very
Suppose by the wrong word
Steady and I think that in the sense of that it
With things on the internet I think
We sometimes
This feeling of
Oh my God one day
Just 10 million people
It wasn't like that I know it was like the first
Wait there was 10 project in second week there was 20 in the third week there was
You know what does exponential saying but it was really nice and steady and
People got it
We have to go through a long. We're like
Nobody guess this
We have to like change the whole bunch.
But it wasn't also like oh my God we have to hire
20 people tomorrow
I think we're very
Fortunate in that
You know we're able to
Hire like one person a month
Maybe
Maybe even less than that
So we could kind of
Build a culture
Because it's not one day you come in
Which is
It's hard it's hard to maintain
So as you guys in that first year as you started to kind of open up and allow anybody to to raise
You know money for the project what kind of projects are you getting
I mean it
You know it's amazing depth of the human imagination
You know like tattooing
That's wild
You know
Anything you can think of
Films
School plays
Albums
Concert
People who
Wanting to fund their residencies
Books A lot of people doing projects to
Probably
Weren't doing projects
Had ideas in this was an outlet for them like a format for them a lot of really Whimsical stuff
Podcast it was amazing to say it was really heartwarming I just loved it I loved it
Everywhere I went out and sought money
Money from Big names in the in the Venture Capital world
Sokka and and in others
How did you go over the terms and you gave them was there was there any
Because once you do that you start to lose control
ONN
Those investors they want
The only one exit strategy they want to know how quickly they're going to make money after
So how were you able to
Attract investors and avoid
That trap
I think going into it we knew that we weren't building this to sell this and we weren't
Trying to
Credit public dump
And
When we went out for investment this was
You know one of the first things we discussed
First of all
Was Chris sacca is Angelman
It was their personal
And that was kind of berry
Purposeful
You know I think that they can say hey
Cool you guys want to do your thing and you're not going to try to eat the world
And
We're done with that ends are on money and it's not that much
So it's very different than
I think that a lot of
We did have one actual
Venture capital
Again not that much money
You need to raise money to
Michelin Tire people in to expand
Kickstarter
Yeah it's a
Can I actually just tell her that you in a modest even a tiny modest one
Getting a salary at all
No I thought you know I think that there was some sort of
Irregular
Bruno 3000 bucks a month
If you're there for me and maybe me or Charles
But
Yeah we're getting ready to charge your money at this point so there's no guarantee of
That continuing
Ring for very long
In India
First year after launch what
What was your salary
Either 60 or 60
$1,000
Yeah
So at what point did Kickstarter
Become profitable
I think you know the first 6 months
Not at all no Revenue
I think we've been a year after that
I was in the first
18 months
We got in the black
And you were there
The CEO
I was
And added you
Yuan
Kickstarter became more popular
A lot of companies that were making
Gadget
Extang
Were using to Kickstarter say way too kind of
Prototype
There
They're saying that was out there some companies raising millions of dollars
I guess that at a certain point you guys just had enough we're not
Doing this anymore and you
Is the quote that I read that you gave was we're not
A store
You kind of
Stopped allowing Kickstarter to be used as a platform for
For these kinds of things right
Well it's
It's not entirely accurate I mean basically what happened was that
We created
Additional
Process
Product design
Project
And
They had more of a review process
Other projects may be more classical
Creative areas
Like an album
I didn't
And
That was really because
You know we saw that
The danger of people
Kind of
Approaching
Kickstarter her and things are being put up there
Like new Prada
I'm buying this like I'm buying something on Amazon like I was going to come exactly the date
They're saying and
We felt that that needs to be understood that Kickstarter is not a store
If you support a short film
You don't expect this short film to be the best short film you ever saw
Write 1 people by like a
Gadget
People can have
More of a consumerist
So we said
Hey you need to show where your prototype
You need to add
The risks and challenges of
In the checkout process we had
Pixar is not a store and we link to some of our policies
Just let people know
What does a product need to do to get
Hear what we might know and what we
Might not know
And
We want to let people be able to then make the Judgment of their own butt
With a little bit of context from us
A company came to the kickstarter
And you know said hey you know what the
Coolant product light
What headphones do something
King and I
And we want to partner with Kickstarter to raise money
Kickstarter will do some promotion for us feature that the headphones in the homepage Drive traffic to it
And then an exchange you know we'll get Kickstarter
I think I might like
Like 10%
Could you imagine doing something like that
No I don't think so it's probably had
Probably a game request like
In the past
Listen to site
Is open you log on your credit password
You put your project
I picked a lot of times big companies that want to do a partnership they want to sign a contract that's
If you want to go do it to go log on the side
If you want like some special stuff from us or
Whatever I mean that's just not we do it's a relatively open door but you're not
Any better than
Some young Creator who
Working on their first idea this platforms built
To do what you say you want to do so
You know
Gopher
How much money has
Internal leasing capacitor projects raised
Recently
We passed the three billion dollar
Pledge mom
Wow
So huge milestone
Yeah.
Excited about
The money that's gone to projects. Really had very little
Funding sources are really constrained funding sources are funding sources that would really
Boris The Creator to contort their projects in a way that they
Might not recognize it anymore
Force them to kind of makeup
Compromises that a lot of crazy people have to do
But they're really hard
That's definitely what I'm
Most proud of
I've seen Kickstarter describers like that the People's National Endowment for the Arts and people is even
Who discovered as likely modern-day House of Medici
Which is pretty complementarity I mean it's a pretty incredible thing to say about
About the site that
You created you
Do you identify with us
Descriptions
Not really I mean
Listening
I'm proud
But you know the medicis were giving up large amounts of money and it was a small group in a way we're trying to
Provide a clear alternative to that
We know that
Whitman had funded some first editions
By having
Subscribers that he
Brother names in the first edition get smaller amounts in Mozart Concerto in the same way
Statue of Liberty the base was funded
They actually the
They would some Miniatures for a dollar or larger one for $5
Why not that fun
Did the bass
So
A lot of stuff that you see on the web is
Has maybe B
Existed
In another form nothing new Under the Sun
Pretty much it would Kickstarter
If I was telling a friend that I was working on an album and it
Can I talk to somebody to go into a studio to mixdown
They're not going to hand me $5
Write in a coffee shop
But if I put it up on Kickstarter and I'm trying to raise two grand to go to my next off my album
That's in front of me give me $5
There was just this friction there was this social friction before that existed
And
The model has been able to eliminate that or even
But in a way that's socially positive
So it's the sentiment people have people want to help
Each other
Bring
Good
An interesting ideas to life
We have nothing to do with that
We are
Enabling
What we think is a good weight
The idea of the model of Kickstarter is just
Seems like a no-brainer not really think about
Companies like Uber or Airbnb or
You coming to connect people with other
People and in some ways Kickstarter does the same thing
And
You guys only take 5%
Which is a pretty small amount of money
You could take
Lots more money
Did you
Think about it
I mean
If you're going to try to make a lot of money you know that's almost change the fee is probably not where people
We'll talk about that we talked about
Raising hundreds of billions dollars and venture-capital quadrupling the size of the company and the international footprint
Doing major marketing campaign or
Selling the company and
Making a ton of money
And one shot
But I think there's also like
There's got to be a way
But it doesn't have to become this kind of vehicle
Only four
Maximize
Prophet
You know
It was a quote I wish I could find
The attribution bias
We basically that
If a corporation was a person
It would be such a
And
When you create something
If you wanted to
Cher
Your values
That's kind of why I ever since
The beginning we wanted to make sure to
Hold on to
Controls
Outside forces couldn't drive it that way
And then
Two years ago we became a public benefit Corporation
Which is still up for profit
Company but
It means that the
Obligations of the
Of the board and executives
And the company is to balance
The shareholder interest
With
Greater state
Including
The environment and
And your various community
And that's it that makes it again something more
A representation of people
But really underneath the Mandate is
At the end of the day and make the most money for shareholders
It's a really
It's not really a good fit
For humans and I don't think it's
It portends very well for society
If it's what we accept
As the only way to do
You are you are no longer the sea yeah right
No now I'm chair
And it was the Target on that did you just feel like a day you know it's
It's got a new place where I don't care I need to run it on a day-to-day basis anymore
Yeah I mean I think that
Once we were out there
And
Things for work
I started to see that
Especially since we
Don't want to sell
Where's this go if things continue to
Then it just continues
Just continue
But does that mean I do this
Till I can't do this then Doric do this for 30 years and then I write a book on leadership and I could give
It's like you know so I was like
And I also didn't have
Time to work on other ideas I had
In the Arts. Do companies and so
I think we were just there when I just started the window I start to see
Hey you know a gust of wind is going to blow us down we got a great team here
And so
This might be
A good Mama
Did you ever I get to see kruder dorfmeister after all
I Have Nots I've never seen those guys and I haven't heard that much I'm sure they're still out there making music
I haven't even been caught up on my crush right now you could kick-start that show now if you did for the truck
Terry Chen is the co-founder of Kickstarter
Jay-Z spends most of the time at his studio in Greenpoint New York working on his own projects
Oh wait if you listen to the segment at the end of our show how you built that we actually looked back at
All the companies be featured and at least one-third of those companies got off the ground with
Money raised on Kickstarter
Please don't turn it off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Squarespace
You have an idea for your neck
Big Move
You can use Squarespace award-winning designer templates to create a beautiful website or online store
Equipped with everything you need to run your business
Is it squarespace.com to start your free trial and use offer code
Build it
10% off
The first purchase
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
And let's just say that
Our team actually got into an argument about this next product because the problem it's meant to solve
Well some people didn't even know this problem existed
Like
In your bedroom right if you just throw quilt over your bed to make it then you may not get this
If you have a duvet or a comforter then you know the extreme frustration of trying to
You stuff it back into the duvet cover it says if you're taking it a big pillow
And trying to fit into its pillowcase but it's bigger than you are and you could Crystal Gordon from San Diego
Why do you have to you know get on top of the bed shake it so that it all fits properly and neatly and it's not all crumpled
Bullet inside of its cover and if you've never had to do this you know exactly
Something she had to do when she was a kid
Anyway now that Crystal is a mom herself she's always looking for ways to save time
And so one day about a year ago she thought Spade why don't I design something that makes it
Easier to put the duvet back into the cover
It needed to be absolutely simple that is Standalone you don't have to hook up any wires or any hooks
And doesn't require assembly or any of that Crystal actually has a background in aerospace engineering
But why can't a designing something to help you make a bed
I had no idea how to invent something so I started toying with things I I read a book on basically
Inventing things
And bought some stuff from Home Depot
But really basic stuff they're like rope some clothes pins and a kitchen sponge which he litter
Early staple together into a kind of clamping device that was my ultimate first Raw
Prototype 2 just passed my theory of
Having this cushion underneath the mattress to work as an anchor and then and what Crystal Adventure
Actually came up with is a flexible clamp actually two of them
That you can use at the top two corners of the bed
The clamps are kind of liking it to the hands of somebody else there you're helping hand the clamps
Are shaped like a spatula with his little plastic gate in the middle that can hold the duvet cover
Cover in place as you push the duvet into it and you can do this task alone in
In a few seconds with with very minimal pain and time after she's settled on her
Final prototype crystal found a manufacturer in Turkey to make it she calls her invention the
Duvaid
There's nothing like it that exists we have no competition Crystal
Biggest challenge right now
Getting the duvaid into brick-and-mortar stores
She's been selling some of them online just a few hundred dollars worth so
For now she's keeping her day job at a solar energy company and whenever she can have got my list of store
I've been trying to call with nobody picking up the phone and you know I need to start getting more creative sending them like
Chocolate the box of chocolate there's something with my card in it
Actuary more about duvet on our Facebook page
Just search how I built this
On Facebook and of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes go to how I built this.
Npr.org you can also write us it's hi BT at npr.org and if you want to send
It's at how I built this our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music
Hoes by Rammstein Arab Louis thanks also to neva Grant Santa's Michigan for Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this NPR
Hey I'll Sam Sanders hear my new podcast is called it's been a minute
Another way of saying
Let's catch up
Happy Friday I'll sit down with two guests
Smart talkers
Inside and outside NPR
To catch up on the week of news and culture
Everything
If you can't stop watching the news but you're awful exhausted by doing that
This show is for you don't miss out find it's been a minute now
On the NPR one app or wherever
Get your podcast
Thanks
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email to
Templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week