Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.
Pillsbury
Went to Independent ice cream distributors and you know till then
Those Distributors continue to deliver Ben & Jerry's that they wouldn't sell them
Haagen Dazs anymore we recognize that Pillsbury was controlling
The marketplace and they were using their power to keep competitors out so would you do we took our k
To the people we decided to go after the Pillsbury dough
Doughboy the most beloved
Food mascot in the country budgie little Doughboy but
This particular case it was a matter of survival
Ramen PR it's how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories
And the movements they built
A two hippies named Ben & Jerry turn their small ice cream shop in Burlington Vermont
One of the most iconic ice cream brands in the world
I don't know about you but
I have a feeling that most people
At some point
I've spent a quiet evening in front of the television with a spoon and a
Chunky monkey Cherry Garcia
New York super fudge chunk
Chocolate chip
Cookie dough
Because there's something
Really comforting about
Pint of Ben & Jerry's
Even though it's
Full of sugar and saturated fat
It somehow feels okay.
Maybe it's the fair trade symbol on the front or the
We buy from local Vermont Dairy Farmers on the side of the
Or most likely
Seeing Ben & Jerry's photo on it
Because
Kind of know they're good guys
That their hearts in the right place
And the thing is all that peace and justice
Quality stuff Ben & Jerry's
Tied together with their brand
It's really wasn't a gimmick it wasn't a strategy designed to attract
Customers because it's who they are
There weren't social Enterprises
Is back when these guys started then they certainly never
I am to get rich
But they did do well at
They did
Do good
And they're amazing story of building one of the most beloved ice cream brands
Actually begins almost
60 years ago
When Ben Cohen and Jerry Greenfield
We're at the same middle school on Long Island
The New York
We were both fat
S kids
We were both
You know nerdy
Not
Not in the mainstream socially
You know we were the two slowest fattest kids in gym
You know if you're running around the track and you're half a lot behind everybody else
There's another guy there beside you
You know you get
Pretty friendly with
And did you end up going to the same High School
Weekend
Yeah we went to Calhoun High School we
Graduated
Better
I was in debate
I lettered in debate
Alright so you guys grew up in Long Island you finish high school there and and did you
Where did you go
Where did you go to college then where'd you
I went to a lot of college
I went to
Colgate
Skidmore
NYU
The new school to the circus
I dropped out of
All right and then I finally joined the university without
The most
Unstructured College
The idea was that the whole world was your campus when you go out
Learn whatever you
Little Learning when you come back
To this administrative body
True that you learned it
Greek
I dropped out of there
So
That was my couch
Still too much structure for Bend yet I like to tell people about you
I went to Oberlin College in Ohio I did 4 years straight
I was
Pre-med
And
Applied to and got rejected from lots of medical schools on two different occasions
So
So you guys were I mean
Visalia
But with what happened after you graduate how did you guys win
K'Nex
Well I I was working out of school for Disturbed kids in the outer on
I was teaching pottery
Learn
Try to be a real Potter you know those who can't teach those who can't do while I tried doing it
Nobody would buy my
So I left
Deodorant
New York
In order to get
You know there's some more
Other influences on my pottery
It was so expensive
If you are
I needed to spend all my time
Making rent
Driving cab
So I had this apartment
Pretty grungy
Jerry
Showed up in New York and moved into Ben's apartment or you just you just end up
I did say this after I graduated college and after my first bout of medical school reject
I moved in with Ben in New York
City and then
I left
And went to North Carolina and after my second bout
Medical School directions
I connected with Ben again and it was at that point that we decided to
Put our fortunes together and open up a little shop witch
Yeah which turned out to be an ice cream cuz we didn't exactly think of it as a business
The Swede we thought of it as Adventure like listen to something because we're not right right that's exactly right
Let's do something for a couple of years and then
After we do that let's do something else we we talked about becoming cross-country truck drivers after we did this ice cream
Seokjin was ice cream. The main idea was that we were going to do from the beginning cuz cuz I read that
That you weren't really sure what kind of shopping
You can do
Yeah we thought we would do something with food
Because we'd always liked
To eat and
We wanted to live
Ana College
So we thought about
Picking
Food
That was
Becoming popular
In big cities but had not yet been brought to a college.
And at that time
The foods we thought about where Bagels
And homemade ice
So we we went to a used restaurant
Rock supply store to price out Bagel making equipment
This was G&G Restaurant Supply in Albany New York Louis there Louisville
Old guy with a gold chain around his neck and a big cigar in his mouth and
He he told us we didn't have enough money to buy bagel
Equipment
He also told us
I wouldn't screw you Life's too short
Guys were
I am in twenties and and did you sit down like
Hang out late nights
Putting out a strategy thinking Unisource card to
Think about different ideas you could do together and were you
Meeting and in cafes during the day or was it
I can't even
How did you even
Started
Develop this idea was it just much
Bless it was much more
Dialysis do this
This was in the old days
Four Cafe
No we did not mean caffe
But we did discuss it quite a bit
And we researched it quite a bit we sent away for
SBA pamphlets
That cost
Between
$0.15
$3
/
On all the different aspects
Running a business just like a pamphlet from the from the small business administration that you I guess we're available
How to how to calculate your break-even point
Pretty pretty basic stuff
Yeah
Our goal when we open
When was to make
Dollars a year
Which was
Which was pretty good in the late 70s right
No it was shity money
It's a long time to achieve
So when you were in New York have
Think about what you could do how did you settle on
Ice cream shop in how did you settle on
Burlington Vermont
Well we settled on ice cream because
Bagel twin was too expensive
And we settled on Burlington Vermont because
Originally
We settled on Saratoga Springs
We actually moved to Saratoga Springs
To get ready to open up
Spending most of our time working on this
Business
For an ice cream shop
Doing a lot of research and we took this correspondence course and how to make ice cream we were doing the car
Of course
Big college textbook called ice cream by
William S Arbuckle
Thank you father of modern American ice cream
Jerry could understand that
Very complex text
Because he had this biochemistry background
Medical school
So there was some other
Ice cream shop that opened up
In Saratoga Springs
Beforus
It was called Afternoon Delight
Did Disney make good ice cream
We don't know we left town before they opened up
Didn't want to compete we figured we had a better chance of success
We opened up in a place where there wasn't much
Competition
Originally we were looking for Warren rural college town
Already had ice cream
Yeah
Analyze we win
Further north than the only Town left
That we knew anything about what
Berlin
It was an hour and a half South the Canadian border is out cold.
There wasn't much ice cream
Which one applies for a sec because
I think a lot of
People hear Ben & Jerry's in saying
These guys were hippies which is true and they're you know they're sort of
An activist in end
But that was just kind of
Slap SP you guys really did actually it mean there was a method to this Mew research
Do you actually scoped out
Possible locations I mean this wasn't you were really actually
Trying to do this in a nautical way
We're very hard worker
When you describe it
Your you're and yes all those things happened but the way you're describing
Is putting a lot more
And planning into
Then
Then we actually did I mean we we just took one step at a time and we did whatever the next thing was
In front of
I think it was near that time that we
Kind of realize that
You know the word business
Essentially kind of a
Busy nurse
That is mostly common sense
And a lot of work
Yeah
And I mean
This is pretty internet so you couldn't just go online and type in how to make ice cream with you could do today or
Where do I buy restaurant quit
You had me things took a lot longer
The Yellow Pages
Yeah it's been a lot more with the phone book in the yellow vase
Yeah I mean you know what when when Ben and I talk to people today about taking
Correspondence course
Correspondence courses don't exist right I mean the closest thing would be an online
Find course but the idea that
That somebody would mail you a text
And then you read through these text books and you
Fill out answers to a test and you mail it back to your
Effexor and then they grade it and then they mail it back to you and you find out how you did on your test
It's a quaint idea
$5
Wow we split one between the two of us
When you decided when you when you told her no friends or
Parents are family
We're going to go to Burlington
Vermont and where can I open up an ice cream shop
Realize that you know
Baby 7 months out of the year
Billy Colbert and and and
Just
Might not make a whole lot of sense or did we do that covers
My parents were really happy
Finally there's Sun
Was
Giving up the idea of
Being a Potter
Finally becoming a businessman
This really
Turn them on and
They were so
Supportive of
I started
Thinking
Oh I must be
Be doing the wrong thing
Yes of course we
I thought about you
The cold weather
Jerry even came up with this idea of
A promotion that ended up in the business plan for pops at this week
Penny off per Celsius degree below zero winter extravaganza
Slowly Pops in the penny offer Celsius degree below zero winter extravaganza
You can say I'm slowly if you want credible and how did how did it work
The more you saved
Every degree below zero Celsius
Which is 32° Farrah
You got a penny off the price your account which
Was significant at the time because of cone cost $0.52
Cars you get to Burlington Vermont and lend you start looking around for the
The perfect place to open up your ice cream shop
Well we got one of those clickers we did customer accounts
Superiors corners
We didn't know exactly what number we were looking for but we did cut
Did you really used to corner with a clicker
Creeper and you
Just clicks yeah and you would just click as people pass so you would know how many people pass a location every hour
Yeah ice cream is an Impulse I don't need to
Money of the passing traffic
I mean I'm going to just
Just because that again like that is a pretty sophisticated
Technic all in the SBA
Corner of the clicker and click
Open your shop
You know I am going to interrupt your because I haven't been giving been enough credit
All these years been actually
Does think a lot of
These things through
I think
I think it was me who I something
Robot
Yeah I think Ben's a very thoughtful
Person
So after after all that research
Where was Alec
It wasn't on the main drag was block off the
But it happened to be
You're right across from City Hall Park
It was a great thing for
And ice cream parlor
Catacombs
The park and it also was an old gas station
It was totally dilapidated
It was falling apart
Nobody wants
Rent it
And it had some parking space
Susan trunk
Or the gas
Which
Who is also a
Bloom for
And ice cream shop in a city
To have some places where people could
Car jump
Going to scoop
How much money did you have to have
To sign the lease and then also buy the equipment and
Vino get the store ready
For customers
Ben and I
Each had four thousand
And that you saved I wrote
Then actually borrowed
2 out of the forehead
Father but that was fine
Cuz that was our commitment
Each other that we were
We are each going to come up
What's $4,000
And and then
We wrote this
Business plan
In order to try to borrow money
From the local bank
You know we wrote A business plan only because
We felt like
It was the only way the bank
Was going to lend us money
Projections
Like five-year projections showing revenue and profit and loss
It it had projection
I can't remember if it were
Was five years I mean I probably was
In five years the beautiful thing about the business
Show
Then I didn't know how to write
But we we have a friend
Jeff Furman who
Is mentioned off and then and Jeff used to work for the small business administration
In New York City and Jeff got us a copy of a business
That was from a pizza parlor in New York
So Ben and I pretty much copy that
Except
Every place where it said slice
Pizza
We we crossed it out and we wrote in ice cream
The other great thing about
Was when we first rode out
And figured out our praise
Projections
For how much ice
Salad how much
Cost
The projections told us
Bat
We weren't going to sell enough ice
Cream to stay in business
So
We just change the projector
Kind of like the government and I think that's the way everybody
You just make it out I got to have this idea
That people come up with these projections and they're based on something and they're just made offer true
You see it all the time
Silicon Valley
Brighten it and if they don't work
You makeup different one
Brilliant
What is a first or look like
Was it was it sort of
Verizon in
What's the clouds in the
Painted on the walls
Cows
No but it was beautiful
I mean
Ben says it was beautiful and it was beautiful
Most people would have described it as
Pretty funky
Which is probably right
What's the aesthetic of what
What you were
Selling anyway right yeah homemade ice cream very much looked homemade
And it was very low budget as well
Yeah how would you
When you open that first shot how what
Flavors what are you
Remember
Jerry probably remember
Number spinner
Vanilla
Chocolate
Strawberry iced coffee
Pretty pretty nice
Yeah the two unusual the first two flavors that we did that
You are not your normal one
Oreo mint
And I mean ever that Jerry you are so that she can make her and Ben
You were the taste and I remember reading a long time ago that you had like
Some you couldn't taste things because of some
You know China strike a number what
Things that you dealt with a hadn't ended so
You would have
Focus on the
You love the ice cream is that true
Yeah
I have a very very poor sense of smell
What's the term for that
Cold anosmia
It makes a lot of sense of and in some ways
Not having a sense of smell
Was just kind of hidden blessing right because you had to rely on other senses that maybe
Competitors were thinking about they were focusing only on flavor
Or
Sore smell rather than
Deal of ice cream
Right
How did you I mean I remember the first time I tried Ben & Jerry's in the
I grew up in Los Angeles so not until
The late eighties
I'm but it was it was so different cuz it was chunky ice
Big chunks in
Was that completely different in 1978 was what other people making ice cream like that
No they weren't they weren't Packaging
Ice cream like that
Came out of the homemade ice cream
Genre
Like with big chunks in like
Right right right right because a lot of them
Our shop and a bunch of other homemade ice cream shops
You're making ice cream essentially in overgrown
Homestyle ice cream maker
So
It's really easy
Tube
Put in big chunks
The difference
Is that
No commercial ice creams were packaging ice cream like
And
As we discovered
The reason why they weren't doing it is because the machinery
The commercial ice cream Machinery was not designed to be able to
The handle large chunks
So all you would get would be visible itsy bitsy pieces that would flow through the Machinery well.
You didn't get the requisite
Mouth feel dry
I was making the ice cream
And it was no picnic
Speedos big chunks
And Ben and I had many
Discussions
About it
Discussions like
Like what
So I was
Arguing
For having
A larger number of smaller chunks that were well distributed
Throughout the eye
And you know Ben was saying
Know what people want
And this is what Ben Moore
But what people want is
Really big
And they don't care if
They get a chance
Free fight as long as they know
There's a really big chunk coming up next
Hand
It turns out that was right
People love it
What happen if you open the first or what
Huge hit in Burlington right away
No
No we
We were hit in the summer
The first summer was great
And then
First winner
Was also a revelation
I can get very slow and
One or two
Probably a few more than that but you know it's very slow and it and it was actually during that
First winter when
Ben and I came up
With the idea of free cone day
Dad
If we were still in business
After a year
We would celebrate
And treat all our
Smurfs by giving out free ice cream
Because we thought it was so unlikely that
We would still be in business and
And we recognize
Show clearly that if we were still in
It was going to
Because of the
Support
Power custom
Was there any tension between the
The two of you at that time
Just about the size of the chuck
Ben and I have a lot of trust
Each other any
Each other's judge
So we were never doubting
What the other
The person was doing
So there was that and then and then I think another thing was we had very different
Skills and interest Benes
Tremendously
Creative
Very spontaneous
Very entrepreneurial
And I
Like a manageable
Agenda
Shuffle you notice it made sense the pain would come up with all
All these flavors and
Do all the marketing and I would sit back and make the ice cream because I start a new what I
So what
What was the Turning Point how are you able to survive that
First year we we ended up getting a SBA has this
Service called score
The service Corps of retired
You know if your
If you're a little business
You could get in touch with the SBA and say hey I
I'd like a
A mentor
And they would set you up with some retired business
Vons USB inventor
We
Ask for one
And we got more
And
It was in the middle of the winter and we were losing our shirt
Couldn't make our alone time
Again
He says all you know that's no problem just go to your task for a moratorium on your loan guy
Maddie
He was an old guy named Manny
He said well
Just tell him you can't pay your loan right now that you can pay it you know when the weather
You know the old
Look up the light just let you pay entry
And we went to the bank and we said that and I said sure no problem
Stay interesting
Extend the loan
That got us through
Wow
Images only in Vermont
Yeah yeah
The shop opened in 78 and then I guess it was it was 1981 when Ben & Jerry's
What happened to be
An article in Time Magazine
Hugely influential Max at the time warp
Words that mean when you
Is that what they call you at the time
The best ice cream in the world the best ice cream in the world is incredible
You expected but not only that it was the cover story
Of time Mags out and that was the first sentence
Undercover story
But you must understand at the outset
Is that Ben & Jerry's in Burlington Vermont
Is the best ice cream in the world
That was all we needed to read if you read it on
It continue to say that
You know blah blah blah ice cream somewhere else is the best artist in the world
You know who needed to go any further than that but you know you know
Prior to that article coming out
I started to realize that you know all these
You know reviews that you see for Broadway shows
You know where they say this is the best play ever all you'll laugh your ass off and whatever it is
She only one play this year
And then there were all these little excerpts from an article that was you don't like to
You know a page and you know the page went on to say
I really wasn't that great but you know there was a moment where you laughed your ass off
If they can do it I can do it when we come back once the Laughing guy down
How Ben and Jerry got a taste for the ruthless and competitive side of the ice cream business how the Pillsbury dough
I tried to take a bite out of the company
And how Ben and Jerry
I'm gyros near listening
How I built this from NPR
8 things tour 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
What's the business insurance expert to understand
Each business is
Is as unique as a fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent solutions
Every business has very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase of policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your
Long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
Add gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
Gyros
In the early 1980s
Ben & Jerry's was just
Wine shop
In Burlington
And it was doing well
Ben & Jerry gave up
Big
Generous scoops
Ice cream
That happy customers
But they were pretty bad and doing all the things that took two
Run a business
We weren't making a profit you know
16 hours a day that we were open 7 days a week
The standards that we had for ourselves
In terms of
How retail shop should be wrong
How to achieve
We were really good at creating
An atmosphere in the shop that was welcoming
On
Less than excellent at hiring people at supervising people
And
Most of all
We were
Really bad
Porsche Macan
You were giving away too much
Yes we
You know when you when you scoop out a nice big
Scoop for a customer
You get this
Beautiful smile and really warm response and it's
It's really positive reinforcement for over scooping
And you know better and I we wanted to make people happy
And also we want to keep our prices really low
You know in terms of the food service
In every business except for ice cream
The portions are controlled
In the back
Out of sight
Of the customer
When you're scooping ice cream
You're supposed to control the portion inside of the customer at the scoop is too big you're supposed
Take a little off in the customer
Heat
One of the reasons we started packaging our ice cream was because we weren't so good at running a shop and
One of the things we thought about was well maybe we can't control how much ice cream were putting on a cone but
You certainly
Can control how much ice cream you're putting into a
Pint container because it only fits so much
Right so
That was
That that was a big turning point for you or you when you decide to let the package of stuff before it before that we decided to
Actors in two and a half gallon
Tugs and sell it to other people and let them figure out how intro the portion in Beijing
You know I mean I was the guy who is going around selling the ice cream
To these restaurants and
The restaurants would say
No I'm not going to carry your ice cream anymore because
My employees are eating it a lot of our problems would be solved if we made the ice
Scream
Shittier
You guys start sit to sort of getting more attention and into distributor ice cream
In pints I guess
Pillsbury
Distributing other brands like
They threatened other Distributors they said stop Distributing Ben & Jerry's
To the shops right yeah well Pillsbury had
Haagen Dazs so they own them
And may they went to
Independent ice cream distributors
Who were Distributing all sorts of
Brands of
AB ice cream
Sand
You know told them that if
Those Distributors continue to
Deliver Ben & Jerry said they wouldn't sell them Haagen-Dazs
Did it start to cut into your sales
Well
You know we we recognize that this was a real threat
Plus it it seems like it was illegal
That
That it was a restraint
Crate
The Pillsbury was controlling
The marketplace and they were using their power to
To keep competitors out
But you couldn't sue them
Right in the Europe for million-dollar company and they were multi
Milly maybe billion-dollar
Well I think we I think we did
Have a legal case but we realize that that was not really going to be the best place for us to fight them
Because they were so enormous
So what you do
We we took our case
To the people we started the what's the Doughboy afraid of
Campaign
We decided to go after the Pillsbury Doughboy which
Was the most beloved
Food mascot
In the country
Pudgy little Doughboy
Peggy glass from
Well if it was started by me going
Minneapolis to the Pillsbury world headquarters
I would say
A one-person picket line
The sign said what's the Doughboy afraid of it was a hand-lettered sign
Yeah I've never really done anything like
Before
And did anybody else break come out and say okay we'll meet you or did they just ignore you like your this crazy man
Protesting in front of their headquarters
Nobody had any idea what I was doing there
I guess it was a fight for us I don't know if it was a fight for them yes it was a fight for survival from us.
Nobody knew what was going on
So did they eventually drop
Trap there
Restrictions and allow Distributors to prison be allowed to get
Stop
Forcing Distributors to
To not carry Ben & Jerry's right
Well they were there were a lot of
Steps that we took escalating the the pressure on Pillsbury
You know starting with a
Small classified ad in the back of Rolling Stone magazine and we flew aerial banners
Around the sports stadiums in Boston and we
We took out signs of the on the signs of the transit buses in Boston and we had a
And in the sleeping in the science of the same thing what's the Doughboy afraid of
This is the sign of on the side of the transit buses had these two
Pudgy white hands squeezing a pint of Ben & Jerry's I think it's
Don't let pillsbury's dollars strangle Ben & Jerry's
Something very provocative
It's amazing cuz it just doing that is a lot of work like
Organizing that campaign you were also running a business and
And trying to sell ice cream
Constantly working all the time
Yes but this particular case it was a matter of survival
You know this was like
You're either going to get shut down
And you you can't get your ice cream out
The people
Or you do whatever you can to
To get it out there
Do you remember that
Remember working all the time
Yeah I certainly felt
During many of the times at Ben & Jerry's that
The experience was like
Falling down the side of a cliff trying to grab onto whatever Branch was
There you can hold onto
So you know in that situation
You know Folia
Tailgating at the branches you're not really thinking about well I might have a good time at the
But you know you're you're you're energized you know you're using all the Spells you have eaten
Doing everything you can to save your life and you know it's it's
It's really interesting its it's
It's a peak experience
Did you guys as you start as you as you grew and grew it was it was
Claim the obvious that you are
You can both make
A decent amount of money from from this are you okay with that I mean I mean
Did that did that conflicted with your own values or were they able to come say alright you know whatever where I'm at
I mean
So for me
I think it was something I needed to
Grapple with
I mean
Part of the thing for both Ben and me was that we never really saw ourselves as bosses
You know from from early on we were scooping ice cream
Right next to everybody else who was scooping ice cream right we were mopping the floors at night
And
We didn't have a very good boss mentality we we had a good worker mentality you know Dennis the most
Anti-authoritarian person I've ever come across and here he was being an authority I mean it was laugh
Affable
You were the CEO I was
And how do you feel about that
Did you
Did you ever feel like
This is weird but I'm a businessman never signed up for
Yeah there was a time when when
Jerry and I both
Turned around looked at ourselves
Said to each other
You know we're not
Ice cream man anymore
Spending our time
Being bosses and hiring and firing
So much of what we were doing was in order to
AR loans back to the bank and
We felt like
We were becoming just another
COG
In this economic
Machine
Reaction to that was towed to sell the business
Somebody actually
We put it up for sale
This was early on this was
In the 80s
And then
I ran into this older
Restaurateur
Oh that I had
Come to know that
I explained to him
That we were
Planning to sell the business and he said
How could you possibly do that
The business is your baby
Has so much potential ahead of it
And I said Maurice you know what business
Those it explodes the community attic
Employees exploits the environment
He said that if there's something
But you don't like about business why don't you do it different
That was when we decided to
Conduct this experiment
To see if it was possible
That business could be
A tool for improving the quality of life
People
Supposed to
Making
People's lives worse
What are the things you guys you guys did was you had a policy where
Highest paid employee couldn't earn more than five times as Hillary of an entry-level worker
You also had like they care and
Heated College tuition a in bunch of things
Profit sharing
Is that what you mean when you say you wanted to try to do business differently
That's part of it but
I think the more critical part of it
Is
Using our business
To address
Social issues
Through the very
Fabric of our business
So that man like
Taking very very vocal positions on
Hot button issues but also
Doing things like
Like
Working with
Former prisoners from former employer
Felons right who were making brownies in the
Bakery in New York
That that that's
Our project with the greyston bakery and and deliberately choosing to
Use this
Ingredients supplier
Because
This particular ingredient supplier
Was driven by a social mission
Providing employment opportunities for formerly
And that's a very good example of how Ben & Jerry's demonstrated that
Able to make a profit and address social problems at the same time
So after all your success
And then in the 1990s
Eventually Ben & Jerry's
Did end up
Consulted to Unilever
Which is this huge multinational right its hold I think in mm
And it was sold by the company's board
Without your permission
That's correct
How did it happen I mean how was your company
Sold without your consent
Well it was it was a public company
Which meant that
Call anybody
Could own shares
And I
Unilever
Ended up offering so much money that
The board of a
The company
Couldn't find an alternative
For the shareholder
That they thought was acceptable
Did you guys see the board can't do this
I can't do this for over. I Need You To Survive desert Wednesday
Definitely can do
Well eventually we we had to go along with it
Why were you opposed
You know I think that the thing that was most important
Was to
Maintain the
The social mission of the company
We felt like
Another company where to buy Ben & Jerry's
They would not continue those cutting-edge social Mission activities
What does it mean practically for the two of you didn't mean that you were slow
Done going into Ben & Jerry's
Is the offices everyday
You know I think a lot of it was up to us about what it meant
That was going to continue to be an independent board
In the new entity that oversaw the social Mission and I think Ben and I could have
Remained on that board
And we both chose not to
Well I can't speak for Ben
You know I had no idea what was
Going to happen to the company and
I mean quite frankly I just didn't want to be part of it
But at that point
What did she want to be on the board
You know I don't like
Lost in a major battle in terms of trying to keep the company independent
I didn't want to continue under the ownership
Of of Unilever
So
Did you both
Kind of just mentally
Checkout
I totally checked out
Damn it's a good way to put it were you sad
A lot of people who found the show in a lot of people listening would say oh my God they think they walked away with millions of dollars like
What an incredible achievement they started this little shopping Burlington in
An innocent International brand and it's done all these amazing things like
This is their moment to shine and to take to do a dance and but but it sounds like you guys were real
Depressed about the
Yeah
You know if the goal was to
Make a bunch of money
Then I guess
You know
It would have been a different reaction
Wasn't really the goal
Bright
You guys were very vocal about
Your positions on
Guns and on
Obviously
Socially liberal
The company still does that today I'm even though you're not
Owners of it
Is that a surprise you
But they still do that
Well it's
It became
Intertwined with
The brand
You know if Unilever
Bought
A brand and bought the Goodwill that goes along with
Brandon bought the wreck
Mutation
That goes along
Jaden
Need to
Continue those activities
In order to
Keep that brand strong yeah I'm I'm
Very pleasantly
Surprised
And proud of
What company does I mean
Company
Came out in
Port of
Occupy Wall Street a few years ago which was amazing because that that was essentially in
Anti-corporate movie
Ben & Jerry's night. Unilever
Yes
And within the last year the company came out
Weather statements
Support of black lives matter
I mean the company
Does not shy away from controversial issues and that is a really difficult
Book called thing for a business to do it which is why you don't see businesses doing it and yet Ben and Jerry
It is
Courageous enough to to wade into those areas
You guys see each other
Rudy Ruettiger
But you hang out a lot
If there's one thing about your story is more interesting than anything else is your friendship I just
It really is a
Powerful part I know it's torrential sensor is happy and I don't mean to like make make you guys
Feel uncomfortable it is amazing it's really
Impressive that you
That you really like to hang out with
Good friend
You know
People say that
I don't
I don't really understand it
I mean you know lots of people
Friends
For most of their
Well I I do appreciate it more and more the older I
I must say
You know I'm sometimes
Recently been and I have been talking about how we're a little bit like
Fred and Barney
Could we drive places together a lot and
I think we just relate like that
Is it strange to think that this little ice cream shop
You started as a
Million-dollar
Well it's it's strange to I mean to me it doesn't
Feel like the same
They're just not the same
The company has taken on a life
Yeah
You know the ice cream shop
Will always to me be
Ben and me in the store
Make an ice cream scoop and ice cream Ben behind the stove
Cooking up food I mean that's
That's what the ice cream
Friendship quotes
Yeah
Your name Ben Jerry and
Tibetan a managerial
Like it's you and end in will be forever it's like
Italian paranzino Worcestershire sauce a coolie whose parent the right place someday who's hog
Who's that who's that
Is it going to call Ben & Jerry's like you're not going to
Think about the people behind it right I mean
Yearning
Yeah I know what you mean
I mean half the people think we're dead
You know when we get credit for I mean think about the guy who invented vanilla
Yeah who was that he don't get credit for now
To me it's amazing
To the degree that the company continues to be outspoken about Progressive issues
And Progressive as it's not
Its of no interest to me to have Ben & Jerry's be thriving
And whatever
If it's just selling ice cream I mean who wants to be part of that
What do guys think about
This incredible thing that you felt
How much of it was
It was because of all your hard work and
Allen and her intelligence and how much of it was just
Because you were lucky
There is
A very big part
Good Fortune
Involve
I think there's a lot of people who work really hard who have really good ideas who are really committed and
And they don't
Have the same level of success
The Ben & Jerry's
Yeah I mean I guess originally we were going to open our ice cream shop in
Saratoga Springs New York
Some other ice cream shop opened up before us and we didn't want to compete so that's what brought us to Vermont
I think if we had
Started in New York
We never would have gained the local
Following that we gained in Vermont
Vermont
If we could be
A bigger fish in a small pond
Teacher did either of your parents
What was either of them ever get to see
What Ben & Jerry's became
Yeah
Mine were still alive
Probably through the
1980s
Yes I'm from IP
Were they proud of you
A whole lot prouder than when I was trying to be a Potter
Ben Cohen and Jerry Greenfield founders of Ben & Jerry's ice cream
Play there was a study done earlier this year by the international Dairy Foods Association people to name their face
Favorite ice cream unless you can imagine
The Usual Suspects turned up chocolate vanilla mint chip but right there right near the top was
Cookie dough chocolate chip cookie dough
Which
Okay may not be all that surprising because everybody makes cookie dough right
But it wasn't always a classic flavor because in fact
It was invented by Ben Cohen and Jerry Greenfield
In that
Tiny little shop in Burlington in the 1980s
And to this day
One of the most
Popular flavors
What elephant did Cherry Garcia enter into
Ben Jerry's
We got a postcard and Anonymous postcard
We're both
Deadheads and we're also Ben & Jerry's fans
You think you want to come out with a flavor called Cherry Garcia because
Amazing your real who for the fans and dead paraphernalia always sell
What did Jerry Garcia think of it
Well
There was one
That was reported saying
Well at least they didn't name a motor oil after date
And stick around because it just a moment we're going to hear from you
U of A
The things your building
The first
Thanks to one of our sponsors Squarespace
Create a beautiful website using Squarespace award-winning templates
Head to squarespace.com for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code
Build it
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
And I'm just going to say one word right now may bring back
More of a memory
For some of you the word is
Sex and the future of plastics is not particularly great I mean
Think of all this
I need pellets from plastic cups and straws and plastic bags and all of it
Swirling around in this giant Vortex and washing up on our beaches
And that's where David Stover and his friend been coming
Their Avid Surfers
Percentages
Seeing all of that pollution so we started researching all the types of plastic there getting into the ocean
And we kind of stumbled across this issue of discarded fishing nets
Most commercial fishing nets are made of this
Belief
Plastic and when those Nets get old
They just kept
Runaway
Then that's can be left illegally in a landfill they can be burnt on beaches which happens quite often in unfortunate
In many cases the Nets can be left in
In the ocean
Dayton bandsaw set backgrounds in engineering so
A few years ago they decided to run an experiment
And what they did was
They collected a bunch of old men
From fisherman in Massachusetts
And I found a plastic slab where they could melt the nest down
You know maybe repurposed
And the Nets are melted into it's kind of like a spaghetti string it's chopped up
Like the end of the spaghetti is chopped up by little blade and put into these little pellets
You know it's it's very similar to like putting your hand into a bag of rice when you put your hand in the bag of pellets
Okay so the question is
What can you actually do with a bunch of
Plastic pallets
Will taking a bath actually figure that out when Ben was working on a project in Santiago Chile
He was at Park watching a bunch of skateboarders
And kids kept riding by on these
Cruiser skateboards and he called me like that day and was like
I got it like why don't we just make
Skateboard decks from the plastic like it's terrible with strong and
We gonna turn that idea over to Kevin and our team who is
Had worked for Boeing and he started playing around with designs of a skateboard deck from the fishing nets
Okay so 8
Total Stroke of Luck
Turns out that that
Berries and Thyme
The Government of Chile was giving out grants to fund all these different kinds of startups
So David
Act up
Move to Chile started collecting fishing net
And found a factory in Santiago to work on turning those old Nets into skateboard deck
The first couple of times we made board they were not pretty in and not writable and we had to kind of adjust
The temperature of the molding and how the material is processed and that took
You know the better part of six to eight months of going back and forth finally settled on a design that held
Shape and actually look pretty good
We designed the board like a fish which is a shape of a skateboard that has kind of a fishtail and
We put a fish eye on it and fish scales and
It was just something that you know grab people's attention
Davis company is called borello and since it's launch three years ago
It's repurposed more than
300000 lb of old fishing nets
Consoled about 8
Thousand skateboard
And David says they hope to turn a profit by Nick
The biggest question you get asked from everyone is
You know what are you guys going to do when you run out of gnats but are are kind of clever responses always been well but if we run out of fishing
Not tonight then I guess our job is done and we can sleep easy at night
That's David Stover co-founder of Burrell
To learn more about it had to our Facebook page and of course
See if you want to tell us
Your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and that
Thanks for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I be
Built this. Npr.org please also subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcasts or
However you get your podcast you can also write us that's HIV tea at npr.org
Tweet us at how I built this or shows produced this week by run teen Arab Louis who also composed of
Music thanks also teneva grandson as meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Diane
I'm Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
These days if you're exhausted by following the news but you can't seem to stop doing just that
I'm here to help
I'm saying Sanders and my new show is called it's been a minute
Every week
Budesonide process the week of news
Culture
Everything
Cuz when things go complicated it just helps to talk it out
You can find it's been a minute on the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week