Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message come from VSP individual vision
Entrepreneurs innovators and creators
Stop overpaying for eye exam
Sam's and Quality Glass
You can buy vision coverage on your own
Learn more at need VSP coverage.
I quite frankly thought I was at the very bottom of my Barrel I mean there were days where
I didn't want to live I mean the internet
Defined me the article calling me the most ugly names in the world the people on Twitter
Ugliest things but through all of this pain and struggle
I still had an itch to create and so I kind of sat down and said I can start something right
And I can change what I hate
That I see in the world
NPR
How I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
And the stories
Behind the movement
I'm gay
Witney wolves
Exit from
Hinder
Aspire to build bumble
Kinder gentler dating app
Where women
Make the first move
It was a time believe it or not
When internet dating men
You were
Desperate
Awkward or both
It wasn't something you talked about openly
But today
It's the complete opposite
Because the Internet
And dating apps
So much easier and
More efficient to meet Lots
Lots of people
And it's more less frictionless
Is no awkward phone calls or
Courtship rituals are
To face rejection
There's something almost
Transactional about the whole thing
And it's no exaggeration to say that
Even though they've only been around for
Take 5 years or so
Dating apps have
Pretty much
Transform dating
And if you love them
You can thank Whitney Wolfe
Or you can blame her if you hate that because Whitney was part of the dating app Revolution
She was one of the founders who helped create
Tender which is now one of the biggest dating apps in the world
Whitney laugh
Tender under difficult circumstances
Sansa circumstances
Can't legally
Discuss but as you will hear
It was a time in her life where she came under intense online abuse
And that experience would Inspire her to build bumble
Which is a difference
Kind of dating app
And today
Just
Years since
Launch
Bumble is one of the top dating apps
In the US
But the story of how Whitney got into that world at all
Well
Like many of our stories
It starts with
The little bit of luck
Right after she graduated from college at Southern Methodist University
In Dallas
I was just
Kind of going day by day
Flooring and and being okay with that right
I think
To my family I almost
Was
I don't think it was
Proud
Oh my daughter went on to do that
It's right I was in this
Weird place
So I kind of moved in with my mom in California
And I went to LA one afternoon
To visit A girlfriend of mine
And ended up at a dinner
Where
I
A couple
People
One of which
Went on to be the CEO of
Tinder
This was Sean rad
Yes
And he had told me how he was
Going to be the general manager of this
Incubator that would be launching all sorts of
Alternative
An apps and they were looking
At the time they were focused on one app which was a consumer loyalty app
Call Cardiff I kind of like a digital punch card
For your favorite coffee shop for your favorite whatever it is and he just told you about this
At this dinner party yeah we were just at a restaurant having dinner or just a few of us and
I said well that sounds really interesting and when he asked what I was doing is that you know I'm really looking for a job I think I could
Probably help you Market your app
And he said why do you call me tomorrow and come in for an interview so I called him at 8 a.m. the next day I think he was alarmed and
Surprised that I actually called him
And end up going in for an interview it worked out
Started working from home right away and then I moved to LA
For this
Tortoise incubator
Yes for Cardiff I was the
There been really no talk
Tender yet and my job is very much focused
Chordify so I started working full-time
And while we were getting kardify off the ground you know I spent a lot of time going door to door to door in LA to
Different
Restaurants and
Boutiques
I struggled with it because there's too many moving parts right and so
I mean you have to get the store on board
And then once the store is on board you have to help
But the customer has the app
What were the stores interested when you came in but they like it
No
To be honest
A very few people were interested
I think it was really how you positioned it and I learned I learned a lot
True true that experience
Because
You know one pet for go one way and you say something a little different the next time you go in a completely different way
And so I really
Realize that it's not so much about
The what
It's the
The how or the
Why you should do this right like this is why you need this instead of
What you what you need right and so it was really interesting crash course in
In marketing and sales
But you were not
A cat purrs
Necessarily you just really interested
I wasn't even interested in Tech I was just interested in the
The the way it had reach
The way that Tech
Hood
Expand beyond the walls
Right
I went through college with no Instagram and so
Instagram really be
Huge right as a graduated
And then you
Thoughts of four billion dollars and I think everyone kind of went
Yeah and this was kind of like a
And I opening
Moment for my
My peers
And so
Didn't I mean
Did you whistle like a sense of excitement.
Put on something big or did you know pretty soon after
How do you join that the thing wasn't
Not going to work
No you know I think everyone was really excited and very hopeful and it was a beautiful app
I think if we really wanted it to happen and I remember we're all sitting around like we're going to be then let me know next big thing and
And then shortly thereafter I think we started getting excited about this fight project Matchbox
Which
With what became tender but
At the time it was Matchbox
Which was supposed to be a dating app
Yeah I was like
The flirting app
It was like connecting people to flirt right
And after we were really unable to get kardify to gain significant
Attraction
I think we all know
The first few of us
Kind of like
Maybe we need to shift gear as you know and I was
22 years old I had just come out of college I was thinking very much like
College students
This will work and I think I was so excited about the fact that they're
What's something that I and my friends would use First
If I twitch
Show something I personally would have never used
And again it was not a
New idea you have to think about what existed already
Dozens of dating apps flirting apps
Connecting apps
I mean there was already the Behemoth which was match.com right
And we sat on the same floor as match
In LA
Sosa was
Was building tender
Like Parvin idea to build like more of these
Dating type
Products Aurora
So tender was not my idea I've never said it
Was my idea ever I became a co-founder of Tanner via my marketing contributions in my early
Involvement in getting it launched and getting it out there
So
I've heard about 30 completing
Stories of
What the original idea was Andrew who really cares at this point
I mean it is what it is and it was to connect people around you you know if you
See someone that you want to talk to
2 across the room how do you
How do you talk
Without
You know
Feeling awkward I think
Where we went
In a very unique Direction was marketing at Millennials and I just don't think that had ever been done in a successful way
And what was the actual product
What was the app what it look like
It was very similar to what it looks like now is just a very early version of it so you would just
Swipe
Left or right on people that actually
But I first saw that there was no swipe
It was like a tapping like a card game originally and was it called tender but
No we played with so many different names I mean
Maybe going to be flirt and then it was maybe going to be
I mean there's so many different things
I thought it was going to be and
Tender ended up sticking
So you're so you're thinking I like this thing has legs
And so what did you do how did you do
Yeah I remember thinking to myself that it would work at SMU
And I remember I
Took the guys into a meeting
And I gave them my little sorority fraternity
Roll out pitch
Inside
I'm going to show up on Monday when you go to chop your meetings going to run to the sororities and fraternities I'm going to get everybody on it
And then it's just going to take off at SMU
Yes at SMU
I'm so I got the green light
Go do that and we had
Very very very very minimal marketing materials I think I had three or four t-shirts
That we took
That had tender on it and then I had to get really crappy so when I landed in SMU
Funny I was talking to my girlfriend about this the other day
My good girlfriend who now does the weather in La she was a year younger than me so she hadn't graduated yet
And I took a picture of her
And then I took a picture of one of my guy friends on campus
Drop them into the match
Screaming like a
Tinder screen
And I wrote a big thing on top of it saying find out who likes you on campus
And I save the file and I took it to the FedEx
Across the street from SMU and we printed
About the copies
And I
Offered a bunch of people around campus $20 bills
Help me
Put them everywhere I mean
People's windshield
Under dorms
Everywhere everywhere everywhere and then
Monday night I rallied all of my friends that were still in school cuz again I just graduated had a lot of friends
Younger
And we've made our round
We went to the sorority houses and gave a pitch
Got up on chairs and told all the girls
You know you have to download
Because
College is all about meeting people and right now you only have access to
The people that you hang out with every weekend and it's a really
Close minded it be no experience and you guys need to meet all these
Describe people on campus and there's all these really cute guys waiting for you on the app
We rushed and got all these women to download the app
And then we ran as fast as we
Because to the
Fraternity Row
And when
The Frat houses and said a different pitch and said
Hey guys
No other way to access you know hundreds of sorority girls right now
Download the app because they're all waiting for you they've all just downloaded this app and they're waiting for you to like them
And so
Yeah I know it's so ridiculous
But you have to picture you had to go to work
You were hustling this thing
Yes I think that would be an accurate
Representation
And so the next day I remember
You know we looked at the download numbers and hundreds of people had downloaded overnight and hundreds was bigger than the downloads
We got on chordify over months and so you know I'm looking at hundreds of downloads and I'm like we made it
When the next Facebook right.
Just being
Super
You know a little disconnected from reality probably not that
Distances we would eventually discover so you go back to LA
Like what's the next step
I can't remember if I went straight back to LA if I went straight to Utah because
I went and did the same thing at University of Utah
Which seems weirdly
Cinderella a new people there you know and it's funny I called this a long time ago I said to everyone on the
The team I said guys watch
BYU
Will be one of our biggest markets one day because
In the BYU at the LDS College in in Provo Utah
And they're all expected to get married by
By the end of college like that is the excitation
That's why I said I promise
I think BYU will be one of our biggest markets and I think
Half of Utah will end up getting married because
Tinder
Tinder became massive
In Utah BYU campus oh yeah
Wow
2013 you know
Wizard feeling like this is just
So amazing is so exciting
Are you kidding yes
I mean
I lived
Breathe dreams
I was in golf
I mean my friends didn't want to talk to me anymore then I go cash
Contact Tinder again
No it was such an exciting time and
Again it's worth noting
Tinder was group app
Right it was not just me it was not just
One of the guys is not just one of the other guys
This was really
Teamwork
So
I'm going to do something
We need that we don't often do in the show which is
I would you skip over a / 8
A few years went
Tender was growing in
Dating app
Millions and millions of users
Because they're legal reasons
Why you can't talk about certain things
And I'm just going to say I am going to
Explain briefly
That you left
10 Durant way
Under pretty difficult
Is I'm you had been
In a relationship with one of the other co-founders
Where's that broke down
So you
Left
And it was a sexual harassment lawsuit and that
Settled in
Ask about that
But all the sudden you were you were all over the tech press
These people
People caught wind of this lawsuit
Text message
Pictures that were sent to you
Q70
Republican flodgin
And all this time you were the public eye in and you were
I guess liked
Rifle 124
25 of the time
I was 24 I turned twenty-five just a few days later
The main target of of a lot of the attention
So real quick I'm going to jump in in
Just say I have absolutely no comment on anything
Lawsuit
And I've no comment on
You know any of the allegations or anything
But
The way the people online
Spoke about me
The way
Both
Reporters
And complete
Strangers you know internet
Twitter
Comment section
It was
It it jolted me
In such a way it it completely robbed me of every last
Sounds of confidence
Ants that I may have ever had
Listen I was not
I was not
A famous person in my life
Salt Lake City
Parents
Quite frankly just
A normal professional right like that's just
Who I was
And to have
The New York Times calling
Extended relatives
And to have
The Daily Mail knocking on the back window at your apartment when you're not even there
And
To have
Your
Personal
Emotions
Being turned into caricatures on
Tech blogs and mainstream media
TMZ I mean
It was
Really truly
How did you display get through the day
I I quite frankly
Thought I was at the very bottom of my Barrel I mean there were days where
I didn't want to live
I didn't want to get out of bed
I felt
Like it was stamped
Across my forehead
And when I say it was stamped across my forehead
That was fifty different things
That was the article calling me the most ugly names in the world
That was
The people on Twitter
Saying the ugliest things
I mean the internet to find me
For a moment
Time and
I
I wanted to die
Yet I had to
Make this
Bigger than myself
Right like this is bigger than me
Meaning
I have people in my life that I have
Be there for I have parents
Cuz I have friends
I need to continue my career I'm 24 about to be 25
I am not going to
Just
Call it a day at 25 I mean am I you know like there was a lot of that
And
After I was able to pay
Take myself off
The bath mat crying
I
I was able to
Through the fog
See the real problem
And the problem was not
Or the media or the story or what happened the problem was
The lack of online accountability
That
Human beings are exposed to every single day
And what it made me realize was
You know whatever I felt
What's going on online
This is what goes on on a 13 year olds phone all day everyday
And it scared me
Was it impossible to ignore that 7 could you have just shut that out
No
It was a possible
It just became this
Obsession and
It really messed
With my psyche I mean it and it made me
Really
Not right for a while I mean I didn't really socialize I
I kind of
Became a Hermit for
2 years and what I did during those two
2 years was I work
My tail off I mean
I worked
So hard
And
What I
Had realized was you can't kill ambition
You can kill confidence but
Can't kill Drive
Through all of this
Pain and struggle
I still had an itch
Inside of me too
Create
And I miss
The feeling of
Creating all day and
Building
And think something grow and
Engineering it to grow right you know marketing it
And so I kind of sat down and said
I can start
Right now
And I can have an impact
And I can change what I hate
That I see in the world
When we come back
How Whitney took that idea
And turned it into bumble
I've got Rodney listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from the United States Postal Service everyday and
Innovative companies are Reinventing the way business
But none of that is possible
But without the right
People people who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery
Affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce
The United States Postal Service
See why they deliver more e-commerce packages to homes than anyone in the country
USPS.com future
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Honda state of Mark
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play and it gs.com podcast
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
24 years old
Whitney Wolfe had already helped launch what are the world's biggest
Dating apps
Tinder
But after she left the company in everything that went with it
Online bullying in
Severe depression
Get away from all that you wanted to get away from dating apps and build something new something
A little more kind
So I started working on this concept called Mercy
What it was going to be was
Female only social network where
Women only use compliment
They would no longer be able to
You know comment on appearance or hurt their
Are each other's feelings
Or use social media to bully right
So is the antidote to what I
I experienced online
And
I
Started working on this end
Had
You know my marketing plan mapped out and I
I was thinking about doing that and I was approached by
My now business partner Andrey andreev
And he is
Incredible
Talented
Norm based out of London
He is built
So a lot of berries
Successful companies
His current very successful company is called Badu and it is the world's largest dating platform
It is massive
Overseas
I mean we're talking
I think I have something
320 million
I like they're part of that club of only LinkedIn and Facebook and Instagram like those
Big big big crazy numbers
And he said
Sorry to connect
You know the summer I know that probably not the best time for you but I'd really love to hear what you're up
And so
His initial intent was to hire me as their CMO their Chief marketing off
Baidu
And I said you know I'm flattered that's
Great however
I'm essentially Not For Hire I'm going to start my own business and I want it to be mission-driven and I don't want to work and date
Like
Going to be my future
And he said okay so tell me about the
This vision of yours and
What are you going to do in
How you going to build this into a huge social platform and I told him I vision and
Yes and you could hear and feel my passion for
This platform and he said you know what
You need to build this but you need to do it
And
Ignited I'm not doing yeah and I said I don't think you understood me
I'm not going back into dating like that's not happy
And he said no no no this
This hat.
What you're trying to do
Needs to be done at dating
And I thought to myself you want maybe maybe he's got a point maybe dating is broke
Right like maybe
Maybe connecting is broken Beyond just being a young woman talking to a young woman in junior high maybe this is something that if
Text us at all ages
And so we kind of did a handshake deal instead of here working build a company
And
We formed an incredible partnership where
I was founder and CEO I could build my own team my own Vision my own brand
But we would have access to his resources Beyond just money and that was
Something that was never going to happen
Twice and you didn't know at this point you didn't know what
That was going to
No
It's a really wasn't until a couple of weeks later when we brought on you know
I called
Crystals in skin ceramic who had work with that Tinder there really
Really Talent
The designers and you know in order to build a great
Brandon
And product you have to have a great team of designers and so
I brought them on board they had their own apt
Times that they wanted to come on as consultants and so
Once we were all kind of together I think there was like 10 of us in the room or so
We're sitting outside in
Andre said okay so what is this
Product line
And I said
I think I have it
And
And I said
I always wanted to
Text the guy first
I always wanted to go after what I wanted
In terms of if I saw a cute guy in class I always wanted to talk to a guy but I was never allowed to
Because society and my friend said no
So I said we're going to reverse-engineer this
And this is how the products going to work
You're going to mutually match with
Each other but
Women hats
If 24 hours to do it
Because it would give them you know
Kind of incentive
And if they don't the Masters
And
This will
Change the Dynamics
This will put the ball in her Court
For any same-sex matches
You follow the same rules minus
Women making the fur
Rights of two women match either woman can reach out if two men match either man can reach out however they do so
Still have to follow that you go first in 24 hours and then you follow with
24 hours
Like completely different from from everything else that was was out there at the time
Completely
And he didn't exactly
Dating apps
I think I imagined
Are most mostly guys are signing up
Well
My theory at that time was
They hadn't been built for women yet
Let's just look at this
From from the basic
Men are raised
From very early age
To be the go-getter in a in a heterosexual relationship
Go get her
GoGo make the move right
And women on the flip side or trained
Play hard to get
So sure you're telling men
To be overly aggressive and hear your telling women
To be the inverse of that and so now you're at your training to human beings
To act in
Opposite directions
And so what you do when you do that is you
Set both
Upper failure
You set the man up to be constantly rejected
And you set the women up to be at risk of
Of aggression
Abuse
Right and so
Here we have this world
The behave this way now add another element which
Does a profile write a digital
Shield
Where you can hide behind a username or profile photo and you don't have to be accountable
And so
When you when you put women in control you completely reversed
Soaps
She now
Has
The confidence to go after what she's into
And the man on the other end doesn't feel rejected he feels flattered
And then all of a sudden you've balance
The behavior
So what's the word what are the name bumble
The name bubbles actually really funny so a woman who was
I really actually a great
Mentor to me for the first
A couple of years a bumbler name
Michelle Kennedy
She named it on a whim one day because it was such a struggle I wanted Bumble to be Moxie Moxie like
You've got moxie
You've got courage right
Because you'd have Moxie you made the first move
And unfortunately there is a really powerful company that exists somewhere in America
Trademark
Every format of the word
So we couldn't get that and then we were sitting there for weeks oh my gosh it was a disaster we had probably a thousand words in the Run
And then one morning she said you know
I think she
Funny enough I think she called her husband a bumbling idiot she's got this really horrible British accent
She said what about Bumble
And I said
No
Way like ethics Bumble that the Bumble and Bumble the hair product I hate it
And then Andre was like bumble bumble I love Bumble and he checked the domain and we could get their domain
It was a miracle like in what world do we get Bumble but we couldn't get Moxie we couldn't get all these other words
And so
After that I was talking to who she ended up becoming one of my she was mine
Third higher
Her her
Her family are really close friends of mine
I was talking to her mom in the kitchen with a k
About Bumble for a nap and she was like oh like be the queen bee of bumble
Find your honey on Bumble and she
Started throwing out all these really cute slogan I don't like it done cuz I've done perfect branding opportunity
Hives and bees and building your your hive and queen bee the women make the first move
Just perfect.
So you
So Andre
Contacts yuan July 2014
If I'm if I timing is right
You launched
Bumble by the end of that year
Cracked we worked
Really really hard when you when you first launched it
Were most people signing up man
Initially
No no no no
Even even split how did you
How did you get people to sign up how did you get the word out about it cuz there's a lots of competition in this place has tons and tons of dating
How did you
How are you able to tell people that and get to know
What to do
Well I kind of had a little bit of a
Play Buckeye it may be done at 1
So far so
I went right back to SMU this time
Decked out in yellow and
I went back into all the sororities
And I I spoke from the heart listen
I have lived
Through
The pain point
Of
Male-dominated release
I have
Felt it I know what it feels like and guess what
Every Other Woman in that sorority house
Chances are she's healthy
So you know I'm speaking from the heart and I'm speaking to them about how they can be empowered and they make the first move and they go after what they want
Me and my early team members I mean
There's the girls are at my office right now they're still with us
We went in there and we
A pizza boxes with stickers on it and offered a piece of pizza to the fraternity boys that would get on at we
Wrapped cookies in Bumble stickers we took
All sorts of goodies and
We kind of growth hacked our way to
Success
I just jumped out of the story for a sec
Because
I asked you about this idea that
That
Dating apps even even Bumble with
Your mission or purpose to empower women
Even an app like bumble
Contributed
Culturehook
Well
So here's Within
If the hookup is taking place
And the woman is empowered and feels comfortable and confident in that
Then I say more power
2.
You know I don't care what you do on Bumble if you want to
You know spend the rest of your life with someone you meet on Bumble phenomenal if you want to hang out with him for only
A night
But you're going to wake up the next day and you're not going to feel terrible about yourself
That's what this is
It's all about it's about reverse
Engineering
The Dynamics
How men and women
Feel
And Bumble is not just a hookup I mean
I can't tell you how many emails I get a day about
Bumble weddings Bumble babies double engagements now we're launching bumble bizz
We have
Hundreds and hundreds of thousands if not in the millions of the
This point of active
BFF users which are
You know young women matching with other young women kind of in that merci capacity of spoke about earlier
They're finding roommates
They're going on trips together they're building Social Circles in new cities
It's really not a dating app anymore
I rather that that you guys have zero
There's zero tolerance for sexism
On Bumble but if
Two people are communicating on Bumble how do you
Police that how do you enforce
So that's a great question and it's actually very true
Ricky 1
I'm so
We have
Zero tolerance for bad
Behavior but it requires a little bit of work from our user
Because we also want to
Respect your privacy
Write however if somebody is in a conversation and someone says something inappropriate
We have very easy reporting tools and once something is reported we do review it
And if there was bad behavior that user is banned
Your life there are no Second Chances
We really take it seriously
If you need us like
Work one click away
Do you ever
Rent any backlash from from yunnan people
Who say
You know who are offended in some ways
The disempowers women that image is it does it make
Yes
Bumble gets a lot of that you know just last week we became under attack
From the
This website called the
The daily Stormer Anthony
Seaside
And we had upwards of a hundred men sending a
Rats
We actually had a
Police at our office all we bow
They're emailing my employees
Calling my employees calling me
Leaving the most vulgar messages
Because your your self
Feminist organization
Female empowerment is not something that they
They believe in unfortunately
Do you know we get this to that the bullying
Now I don't let that doesn't hurt my feelings anymore cuz I know these people are just
Atrocious but
If you lose me the anger fuels me to try harder at work and try and
And and you know changed
Misogynistic
And so now we're putting such an emphasis to get all these people off of our app if there are any we're hoping there's not
We now have
A whole new set of moderator is looking for
Hate symbols and Hate
Speech on our platform
We're really just trying our best
To build a clean Safe Community
It's been 2 and 1/2 years
You launched
Cracked and you have how many activities
20 million registration
That's I mean that's pretty amazing
20 million downloads of the app
Since you launched
Yeah and when will you know that you have really
Creativist
Hugely powerful
Sing when you got a hundred million
A billion
I'll never feel like we've made
We we got to just keep going I am mean
It's funny I used to say to myself
When we have 1 million we have 5 million when we have 10
And now we're here and I'm like you know what we always need to evolve and be better and try harder and
Have bigger reach-in better region
Once we have that reach can you start over and do it in a different vertical how much of of your you know of
Your story
Through Tinder and Bumble now
Is lock and how much it is
Scaling
You don't luck is a funny word I don't
I don't know if I call any of those lucky
Feel
You know
I think
Luck is probably a certain element but if
People think I just you know
Was at the right place at the right time and just
Snapped my fingers and World a couple times
Here's bumble
I mean
The really wrong this is been
We're talking all day everyday
Down
Highs lows and
And Laser
Focus
So you guys are still
Really young company
Do you
Do you like
Stay up at night
Worrying about a competitor or somebody else
Coming in and just
Yelp
Totally replacing you
We
Really truly aren't super worried about comp
Petition for 1
I really believe anybody can copy
Be a product to anyone
I'm at the UT campus
Speaking to you right now I could go to the engineering school
Probably find five really talented young engineers and they can build bumble
With the right support
Somebody could rebuild any piece of
Technology
Engineering
However
You cannot just copy someone's brand and the
Become them
There has to be
Authenticity when you build a brand and there has to be true purpose
And so yes
You're right anybody could go and build a
Competitor version of bumble
But where I don't think they can just come in and and
Sweep us off our feet is
I don't know if there's another group
People with the exact same
Story or the exact same
Mission and motive and
That goes back to what I lived
True that summer of 2014
What landed on my phone
Every morning
And it was
I almost
Built My
Remedy to
The the heart
Ship that I personally was
Bumble safety
Whitney Wolfe
She founded the dating app bumble
By the way according to Forbes Magazine
Bumble turn down an acquisition offer of 450 million dollars this past August
From the match group
Match as in match.com which also owns OkCupid
And tender
For the record bubble has never confirm that report put it true
Not bad for a company that's only been around for three years and as for Whitney
She recently got married
Guess how she met her husband through through bumble
They met through friends
And please stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
Your building
But first I quit thanks to one of our sponsors
Delta Airlines
Delta Airlines wants to make your travel experience easy and enjoyable
With the fly Delta app
You'll stay connected and informed
Download the fly Delta app from your
Your favorite app store today
Hey thanks
Sticking around
Timeout for how you built that story comes from Michelle Ennis
San Diego and the problem she said out to solve starts with her husband jacked who likes to go
Go sport fishing
Weekend
Comes back so stinky in your house in the evening watching moving until
Touch me don't touch me because Jack's hands always smell like stinky fish
Not soap not lemon or baking soda get rid of that smell
So Michelle decided to Tinker around in the kitchen and make her own soap to try and kill them
That fish smell and getting the formula
Wright took months and months Rochelle did come up with a formula which of course is a secret between
We do know that one key ingredient
Is star anise the stuff that smells like licorice neutralizes the fish smell
Magic and so my husband was filleting fish
And I've said try washing up afterwards with this
You honey dip
Oh my god it works
George is a pretty soon after Michelle started selling her soul would she called D fishing so
At local fishing stores in getting really good feedback I have people come up to me still
That's a
You saved our relationship
Michelle ran her small business mainly from the kitchen for about 10 years
But four years ago when a family member got sick she decided to sell it
We had calls from all kinds of people
And I don't I don't like them I don't want to sell it to them
Because it was my baby but finally when I met Nate and David
They were the right people
My name is David Leon I'm based in Carlsbad California
So David and his business partner Nate are both in the fishing
And back when the show is advertising on Craigslist to sell her business the two of them had just quit their day jobs to start
Or something new or what
But then they saw Michelle's at and they were like this is it this was really interesting
Down to San Diego to meter
We are excited from the business perspective but I think we were been intimidated by the actual making
Of the Soul
And initially were looking at this and we're like we're going to have to learn how to make this but once they agreed to buy the business
Michelle gave them the step by step instructions on how to make the soap in their kitchen and she
Eat them all her equipment to we loaded all these things up in the Navy
Track and
We going and back it into our place
And we start unloading it and these are like big
Industrial plastic drums
Beakers
Graduated cylinders and I remember telling a time like our neighbors are going to think they were opening a meth lab
Nobody reported them to the cops and they didn't they started to grow the business
First by selling the soap online and then by pitching it to National retailers
I actually flew down to Bentonville Arkansas to meet with a buyer this fire at Walmart managers over half a bill
Billion dollars in spend
And we went in there with some canned salmon
And we said you got to dig your hands into this and that
Steppenwolf
In the buyer was impressed or maggots really relieved to get the smell of canned salmon off of his hands in any way
Now defishing soap is selling at 1200 Walmart across the country
David says the business is not a Ramen profitability which means that they're rolling in cash but they are
Making enough money to feed themselves
Ramen
The original soap Lady Michelle
She's still a cheering them on
Just left my kids I'm so proud of what they've done
You can find out more about defishing soap on our Facebook page and of course of
If you want to tell us your story go to
Build
Npr.org
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or your previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org please also down low
Lodar podcast at Apple podcasts or however you get door podcast
You can write us that HIV ta10
Npr.org
You can also send us a tweet
It's at how I built this
I sure was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with original music
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to novigrad
Santa's Mexican poor Clare Breen
Jeff Rogers
Our internet Dianabol stack
Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey I'm Kelly mcevers and embedded is
Is back
I recently realized it's hard to assess a pot
Titian who Hasbro
Virtually no political rights
But with Donald Trump
We tried anyway
And we wound up with stories and lessons from the record he does have
ITV
Listen on the NPR one app or where
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email
It's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.