Support for this podcast in the following message come from mizzen & Main
Creators of moisture wicking wrinkle-resistant dress shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main. Calm and use code NPR at checkout to receive $10 off your dress shirt
Support for this podcast comes from American Express open
If you listen to how I built this you're curious about
Ideas and you probably have some ideas of your own
American Express open can help you with money and know-how
You can turn those ideas
Into action
Is it open. Com
Get business done
Every single person I know texted me
Inside you got to go back to just felt like
And I wasn't even kind of a CEO mentality is Marcus like an engineer who knew how it works
Hand-washing is trolls run rampant on Reddit I'm just thinking I know how to fix this
To know the mind of a troll give me access to the code I can
Running PR how I built this entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movement
Gyros not Today's Special live episode two College roommates built-in internet community
With a population bigger than Brazil
Search where the
300 million active Reddit users
You probably think of it is this incredible place in a home where you can find your tribe groups of people talking about
But the weird stuff you're into
But if you are not interested
Can seem like this super intimidating Insider Club
Hard to penetrate
If you land on the homepage in you're not familiar with it
I think you accidentally stumbled onto the internet Circa 2005
Because that is what Reddit looks like
It's a discussion site filter
Byerly with user-generated content
Which means depending on the time of day
Anything from photos of
Cats wearing Renaissance Era costumes to Serious discussions about US foreign policy
In this simple little site
It's also worth it
Enough money
Actually it's most recent valuation put it at 1.8
Billion dollars
And all of this from an idea that Steve Huffman and Alexis Ohanian
Came up with a road trip to Boston
During their senior year of college in 2005
Reddit and the founders have been through a lot of ups and downs Reddit users
Nearly shut it down in 2015
A certain point parts of the site were hijacked by trolls who used it to spread hateful messages
Alexis and Steve went through a long. When they stop speaking
The recently read it started to hit its stride again be specific
200 million-dollar cash infusion from investors
With plans to make the site into a more user-friendly place
A couple weeks ago in San Francisco I sat down with Alexis and Steve in front of a live audience
I hear about how they came to invent what's become known as the front page of the internet
Steve I just wanted to
Begin by asking you
Really important question which is
You are wearing a purple sweater with a dinosaur on which a robot
Is riding the dinosaur
That's right and you talk a little about that your sweater with with pleasure thank you for asking
Yes
So
The advice that you're often given is
Dress
Like the person you want to be
And so
I went to Google and I typed in
Awesome
Sweater
And
Click on images
And I just scroll down until I found something that spoke to me
I'm not I'm not making this up and then
I found that
Cool
Create
Now we can start the interview so how did you guys meet
Tell me the story that you remember
Sure as I recall
We
We we met first the first day of college at University of Virginia on our first day
Wahoo
Anna
It is so I right before Alexis and round simple and our rooms were across from each other
And everybody's
It erase rooms had their names on the door
And so mine said Steven David and across the hall where Alexis and Mike
And my first thought was
This is sweet their girls on our Hall
So needless to say
When I met Alexis my first emotion was disappointment
I was elated
Because he was playing PlayStation 2
So I was happy to meet you
We got over the fact
I was not what he expected
And became fast friends and like super close friends
Yeah yeah we can park gaming rigs
Play a lot of video games together
And live together
4 years 8 years in college shared many experiences and college together
I will not go into detail
And I am your best friend
And what would you say
I was history and business major
So nothing to do with s humanities
Nothing to do with technology at all
No I mean I took classes in high school and I fancied myself a programmer until I met
Steve and realized
I was not going to be a programmer for letting you were a computer science major exactly and so I had always drawn up wanting to be Abyss
Business major
Until I met Alexis
And I decided that engineering is the path for me
So when you guys were at
Yuan College were you
I mean were you talking about business starting a business
Doing something together was that
Something you would talk about and doing your video game sessions
Eventually
Jose the first
Three years were really
Just video game
And I act
It was it was hard last year sometime around that I don't remember the first conversation we were we were in
When's the hockey game in DC but I don't know when that was last year was Junior cuz I as history major I thought
The only way I was going to
Have a career
Was to go to law school
And I obsessed I spend all my time the library obsessing over my grade studying for the LSAT
And then on a Saturday morning
Walked out of an LSAT
To go
And I went to Waffle House
It's a great place for epiphanies and Waffles
And I had both there that morning
And realized if I wanted these waffles more than the LSAT
I probably shouldn't be a lawyer
And and they needed something to do with my life and so naturally I went to
My smartest friend and said hey Steve you always have these great ideas
For Technologies like let's try to make a business
And did you have an idea
I did have an idea another business unique to the
Mid-Atlantic
Sheetz gas station
And
Sheets had at the time
If you can get subs
Sub sub sandwiches his wife where else would you want a sub sandwich
Plush
Electric POS
So you got an order from tusk
Gas thinking
Does an electronic ordering system inside I can just convey my order to that machine
The fella inside could be making my sandwich
And that I would have to
Weights
And it's so that was the idea for
My mobile menu
Did this would have been like
A pre-op cuz it's pretty iPhones it would have been like on a Blackberry or a cell phone or something or
Yeah this is what we learned later that yeah yeah
Was actually ahead of its time
The
Cell phones
IPhone Xs
The cell phones
Didn't have apps
We agree name though
My mobile menu
Alfie Deyes
You can make that little logo for that too
What is 3 oz
So did you guys
How did you decide to
Pitch this idea
Not very effective
We had this fantasy of
I would work for my
The job I work for a startup all through college
Button in Virginia
During that time we can call and startups we call them small businesses
And
If I work for the small business office school and I had a job offer
Continue on after I graduated
The plan was I would work
There during the day
And then Alexis and I would work on
My mobile menu in the east
And we
I considered
Like asking my parents for funding
But we'd actually didn't even know how to do that
So
We did
But then we had a life-changing spring break
Yes it's so this is spring break of senior year what was life changing what happened to Cancun
How are the only kids in Virginia who didn't
Because Katie
Saw the program is having a talk
So am I girlfriend at the time
I knew that I was a Paul Graham fan
Hologram hologram is
Well
What's the founder in the lead of like hominy
And
Wrote essays evangelizing
Startups
I am
Nerd culture and
An engineering and how peacefully you can
I build yourself a new life on the internet starting companies
If I was a fan of
And we learned that he was giving a talk at Harvard
Over spring break
Call Toyota starter start so
Alexis and I decided to go
Sao Paulo
Which at the time is really he just stands there and
Stares into his paper and reads an essay
Nevertheless
At the end of The Talk
Alexis
Biscuit Dragon up to the front of the room to meet Paul
Antenna Lexus SC does
Introduced himself to Paul you said
Hello doctor Graham
And please send my friends book
And and I had my dog-eared copy of his list programming book
And I would totally be worth the cost of buying you a drink
To get you to come out with us we came all the way from Virginia and we have a startup we want to hit you
Because
You boys came all the way from Virginia
I do shock we had trains
And agree to meet us later
So you take him out for to agrees to go
4 drink with you and we we sat down at Cafe Algiers
I hope you still there
In Harvard Square
We have a plant you pitched him
My mobile menu
And what
And what was his response
He he said
This will be the end of line
And I was like
No apologies I don't understand
What I want to do is get my sub when I'm pumping gas
And he went off he was so hyped
And we left there feeling
Amazing
Cuz this was like one of your Idols who said that we actually had a really good idea
So
We got back to Virginia
And a couple days later Alexis
That's me hey Steve you should send Paul an email
Thinking
Him for meeting us
And so so I did
He responded back those two guys
Virginia
I just
Announce this new program called y combinator
Where to invest in
People like you
You should apply
So we did
And you're thinking we've got a sure bet because
She already told us it's going to revolutionize lines
And we give you interview of Our Lives
Yeah although there was a
A moment's where
I was explaining to Robert Morris
One of the probably best
Engineers programmers on Earth
I would have web server
He already knew
Upon myself to
Really tied up
We nailed it we nailed it
And then they said they're going to call us later that night you guys are high-fiving each other and your
Ready for the call I got the call and I picked up
Hello
Anytime sorry
We're rejecting you
And and I really sucked
That really sucks we were going to prove them wrong now
We went out drinking and we were going to prove them wrong
So you went out drinking you were like
Dowsers guys
Make this thing anyway
And then the next morning on the way back
He called
Paul Graham called
Play cool
Hello
Has Paul and he's like
You still don't like your idea why would you call to say that
You be like you too
Did you change your idea
Will invest
I got to go to play cool
I will think about it will get back to you
And I think at that point we were already convinced
We need to get off this train. Offer that in that moment my bubble menu side
So quickly
And we got right back
The next train going north when we're back side that was Paul
Paul and what what do you start doing you started like brainstorming with him
Basically yes
And so we are talking about
Like things we could build
There's a couple of websites that we both like that's time
One of which was delicious
And so delicious
It was a social bookmarking website
And there's a
Patient
Popular
And intuition / popular you could see things that were being bookmark
That day that were popular
And thinks that were being bookmark more often would hang around a little while
The thing is when you bookmark something it's because you can't
Finish in one sitting
So it's reference material
Things you can't get through things want to come back to later so delicious
Popular was basically this really
Cool
Index of the most boring content on the internet
On any given day
And so
Slashdot news for nerds stuff that matters
Still online
And Slash.
Had this incredible community
Yeah you go there for news everyday but really the magic / that live in
And so the idea was can we take the
Mechanics of delicious
User submitted and
And kind of Pop Billboard Top 40 effect
And combine it with good content in a good community
And that was the
Genesis of red
And
This was
A chance
Basically get $12,000 from an investor we really trusted
To just try something after 3 months
And at worst case
You know what the other summer may we just would have
I don't know come back to Virginia
Did you come up with
Fully formed idea Band by talking with Paul because
Going from my mobile menu
What became Reddit is a radical change me did you
Come up with that concept
Don't you went back at the Boston start brainstorming and that came out of this
I have that note
It's it's in my desk at work
The notes I took during that first meeting
And
I'd actually written down in that notebook
Front page of the internet
That's what we are going to build
Gigi is terrible in naming companies but when he nailed it with that phrase
It was he said to you you want to make music
We said okay and so we did
Nothing right like he was this big concept that we've sort of agreed to work on over the span of an hour and
It was 12 Grand to just spend three months working on it
Just be clear you meet
Hall on spring break
F2005 so roughly March
Maybe early April of 2005
Reddit in June
Of 2005
We actually only worked on it for about 3 weeks
Before we lost it
I didn't write the first line of code until June
And I had never built the website
We were kind of Paul special projects
Little bit of how we got into YC
Email
What does ideas and
You know things like
I think it's two
Best piece of advice or
Your name is awful you need to get rid of that little bug
I still have that email that one in the book
I really think small
Yeah she had a lot of
Really good ideas have that there that you want its name it Reddit
Alexis wanted to limit Reddit
Great thank you
You like more than
We couldn't afford snoo which was the name we wanted which was the idea was
Keyboard ask
Oh what's new
We say exactly it's what's new online
And Sons that Alexis was like they'll say
What's Reddit I hope I hope people would say I read it on Reddit
Unfortunately, cost $4,000 which we didn't have
Third of our fun
Could afford it
Name the mascots new instead and it was available please free so Reddit
That the mascot where my Mikey contributions
How my LinkedIn profile
Sew-in in that are in that sort of
Does beginning the beginning
Pierre time see if you were coding you are doing that
That certain type
Exide
What and what were you doing are you handling this
Only non-technical founder
And it was a very curious thing for all involved aside from naming the company and drawing the mascot
I have the important responsibility of everything else that wasn't technical
From like ordering the pizza
To keeping the spreadsheet with all the receipts
Do I'm haggling cell phone bills down
And
If you have to be an eagle this job as a
The founder because
You just have to get this done
Because anytime
Anytime Stephen if I'm an engineer would spend doing something that's not
Michael is a waste of time
And
I like to think
Over the years
Prove my worth
I'll be back there in that was a very common question
Ivory, question
People to post stuff
At the beginning
Funny you ask that
Time we cheated
So we had
A special version of the submit
So for most users
Of which there is none
They would see
Title and URL
Is there a little
Arthrolysis and I was title URL and username
So you
Put in the link you wanted to submit and you make up username and hit submit and it would register that username if it did exist
I'm Horsham it as a username if it did
And that's why the first
Hundred
Or so
Reddit users were
Either
Characters from World of Warcraft
Or
Pieces of furniture in our living room
Not very creative
Book at level 60 that summer though
What's the level cap in Warcraft
So how did you get the word out how did you actually get real users
Well so Paul did that for us
He
Was like hey you guys into launching into launching his lawn smells like okay we're almost ready to Launch
And then he wrote an essay
Where he's linked to rett
Without telling us
I had my my
My computer
Emmett Idaho screen extra record see the error log
Of of things by buying all the sudden one day
It's just really fast
Sounds like what
Is going on
And
What happened espalda
Launch.
And
So
That's just me how it happened so our first real users were actually
Program fans
People reading
And I kind of set the tone
For the
Early days of Reddit
You have to be Scrappy cuz I know five there was no social network
Speak of them Facebook existed but it wasn't
Your college at work and we dat we emailed every one of our friends remember two of them Morgan and Connor
Thank you actually signed up and started using it
But most people just didn't care and you just
Beg try to beg bloggers to write about you
And I'll never forget though a changing way was the name of some random person's blog and it was the first random person
Whoever took the time to write about
Reddit
And I found this post years later I mean it took a little work at the Wayback machine
And if you look some random
IPad block
Ranch
I'm the first two comments are from you and me
Remember this
What we actually look like
Thank you so much this is so great if you need anything let us know where the co-founders
And it's an especially in 05 it was a really isolating experience to put something out in the world
And and feel like no one
Care
It's the first time someone cared felt amazing that's how I found this guy's website
A decade later
I was cuz there was enough of it still stored in my brain to someone
Kerrigan we reached out and thank them
This is old school just
Giving a damn
Try to get anyone to write about us or talk about us
At all did you have a like
A business model in your mind I mean
You $12,000 so
Like did you think well will eventually get advertising
It was
Web advertising wasn't
What it is today. Existed
It was not a priority for us
Just have ads
It's better I think of how you were going to make it
Sustainable
Not really
We weren't really thinking in those terms
Be honest
Because of the way we got into YC
We
Barely I didn't even really think of ourselves as a business
This is more of an adventure
We didn't have
A Target destination of Northstar admission we're building towards
It was
How do we notify everyday without looking stupid in front of Paul Graham
And then once we get in August
A few months and what's good real users
It became was just not with the user
And that was our mentality for actually quite a while
After Paul Graham wrote that essay
And link to Reddit who's that is at the moment where it took off
No no that was the moment when we started getting
Real traffic
I was in August is when we started getting real user
I remember that day
We used to Alexis nursing all the content we had a rule back then
I'm fat
All of the
Content on the front page had to be less than 24 hours
The front pages 25 links lawn
So if there are fewer than 25 links submitted that day
There be fewer than 25 likes on the front page
Independent air quality
And
It's a sometimes we go to site there be like 7 links there and then we'll just be white
Inside taking a day off for whatever reason
Late afternoon
Shoot I haven't thought about it all day
I bet the front pages completely dried off is completely blank
And when I when I checked
Pussy full of c**
From usernames that I never seen before
That was the day when
We realize that this is a thing
These are real users were not just propping it up with her
Fake accounts
That was a really special day I spoke it really kind of excited when I think about it
Because
That's what I motivation changed
And that's when I was really bored I think
That summer that you guys launched in 2005
Alexa
What's your
Your life
Went off the rails
Tickle summer for you what was going on
Well it's 2 months after we launched
My girlfriend had a pretty serious accident
Falling out of us
5 story window in Germany
I'm really loud
She's been about
For 5 months
Tacoma
And and
Finally thanks
Came out of it
I'm going back to the States
December that year and actually
Has made in year
Full recovery
Switch remarkable
But it was a hard
That was
That was hard
Say the least
And a month later
My mother was diagnosed with
Terminal brain cancer
And so
Can you go from feeling invulnerable at
Wanting you you want
And startling
Munson's
Starting a business
Feeling like you
Take over the world
And then being really hit in the stomach
And realizing
No no no that's real life and I knew at some point I had an amazing life
I've been that point very very lucky and I knew at some point the comeuppance was going to come
And
I'll never forget that the first meeting I had back
With my mom
The first words out of her mouth
Or I'm sorry
She felt so bad because
I'm that is the kind of woman she was that she was always thinking of of me
Of other people ahead of herself
And
That
In a lot of ways came to find my entire experience at right it's till this day is imbued in what Reddit mean
Seems to me
Because it is the best of her
I know that
Cuz
Of everything she gave me in confidence and motivation
And support an unflinching love that I could never fail the redis could never
Really fail because she released me of any of that concern and so I can start up sucks.
Socks
But it ain't that bad
Compared to what you do if you're going through chemotherapy or you're like my father supporting some
Who is
And it was
And I'll get that I'm still grateful for because it keeps perspective on every trauma everything that I say
Face
Because nothing's really actually that bad when we come back
Why Alexis and Steve decided to sell Reddit and how it took a toll on their friendship state
This guy Roz and you're listening to how I built this Live recorded in San Francisco
Support for this NPR Podcast comes from American Express
Open
We know that listeners the how I built this are curious curious about how good ideas become great businesses
And chances are you have some good ideas of your own but as you know in business there can be a lot of Road
Roblox American Express open knows how hard it can be to get things done and they want to help
Put money and know how so you can turn those ideas into action visit open.com
Hey welcome back to this LIVE edition that's how I built this
Recorded in San Francisco
So it's 2005 and read it has just launched and the site is growing really fast
Until around this time
What are the founding partners of Y combinator
Jessica Livingston
Suggested that Alexis go to New York to help spread the word about Reddit
And one of the meetings on that visit
Buddha life changing
You said just go down there
Tell a couple people
That you're
In town on a press tour and see if they'll meet you for coffee
Antichrist on a friend's sofa
And had meetings and one of the meetings was a freelance reporter
And I thought I was bitching her for a story but we actually kind of hit it off
And and shelter Lee was like you know what I don't feel like we should I want to write a story cuz like
Like I think we're friends like let's not make this a business thing like let's just stay in touch and be friends
Whatever like I'm just your on a press tour
And you know I got a lot of stuff going on so I got to go
And
I don't know if you weeks later I get an email from this guy named kurosh karimkhani who is the head of BD
At Conde Nast
Digital art
Kind of mask
Explain to me that his wife
Who is an editor at wired
Had heard from one of her writers Rachel the one I meant about this company called Reddit
And he wanted to have a quick phone call
And during that call he basically pitched this idea of making a white label Reddit
Lipstick
As like
Project and then have five months
Slater
We're talkin about acquisition
I mean I think you glossed over
The five months where I was the head moderator of lipstick.com or an expert
Expert at celebrity gossip
So
I mean it's it's pretty amazing I mean
A year-and-a-half
After you
Start redis
You sell it
The Conde Nast
Somewhere between 10 and 20 million dollars
So presumably
Was that the reason were you guys like you are 22 23 and you were thinking cool we can like walk away with a couple million box
Basically
Yeah I mean guy
This was 60 months of work
That was going to be more money for me than my entire family had made my mother and father had made their entire lives
Like are you kidding me
Remind me to GB
Like
Like this was not
This seems like a joke
The best phone call of my life was calling her up saying hey Mom it was worth it like all of that song
Support all of that everything like
We did it
And and that I would never ever trade that phone call I will be the greatest phone call for the rest of my life
I regret from a business standpoint yes we sold it early but I have no regrets whatsoever
A decision because I got to make that phone call and she lives she lives
So
Once that happened you guys
Become employees of Conde Nast
9 not in 4 Times Square though
They didn't put us in the fancy cafeteria
So we yeah but that's where we work so I'm right there on the corner in that organic build
That was your commitment you had to stay there for three years and then you could
Do whatever whatever was he want
And we both
Love's redis
Contracts ended Alexis but you know why I left
Because
I wanted to start another company that was involved in the exchange of money
So that
I wouldn't have to contrive a business
Cuz I'm right at we are at still we hadn't quite figured out at
That's right we lose a stiff Eliquis
I didn't realize how
Cool right it was I thought
If you just build something
It'll just grow
That's how things go on the internet
And I didn't realize that right was so special about the Spy
The fact that we didn't know what we're doing and the spite
The fact that like
At times were very unproductive
It just grew
So when's that time ended you went and found it
A new company hipmunk
Kim Alexis
What you motherland
You went to Armenia Armenian which is where your dad
For a couple months
And were you just thinking I'm done with
Techworld like I've finished
Ish
I just wanted to unplug a bit and I felt really guilty because I had never been
And so I felt this tremendous guilt for not having this connection and and had an amazing experience there and could just kind of hit reset
And and then came back and I figured I was going to live in New York
For the rest of my days
How to draw mascot for hipmunk
Steve butter
Briefly
Yeah it is
Call access point
Alexis Night by 2009 had lived together for 8 years
From 2001 to 2009
Nn
Remind me to buy time we left Reddit
We were not on the best of
We hadn't
So we've been through a lot together
And we've never really discussed it will never discuss the roles that right at front of the boundaries who is response
For what
We we didn't really have a
Resolving disputes
And
I wouldn't see a ton of each other
Is it there
I was in a move to San Francisco
Ravenous old Alexa State on the East Coast
Family for
A year-and-a-half
It's on a contract expired we just kind of said hey you know
Great see you later
Unless it was like
Resolve tension
Let me look there was a lot that went on during that. For sure
But we never really exercise the muscles
That Founders have to exercise that best friends don't and there are lots of found
It's great to be able to start a company with one of your best friends
The conversations you have to have as co-founders are very different as friends and we didn't have enough for
The hard ones often enough and it was just unresolved and faster like I don't think it was I didn't feel animosity
No I think it was like neglect
And you threw yourself into activism at that
Yeah I don't want to see their not get messed up
I like spending time on it I have a career because of it
Right place at the right time
Sopa and pipa
Nettleton have a job
That was really helpful
Yeah can you talking about what that was about a newer Super Active in the sopa campaign
Net neutrality in
What what what was allowed
Well-intentioned people admit most of them are well-intentioned in DC
Writing bills for technology they don't really understand
Without people around them who are themselves technologist often lead to things like soap and pepper
And those were two bills that were
Design to stop
Copyright infringement
That would have him practice
Basically broken the internet
One of the house building was
Why was the Senate bill
I was
Was it one of the best ways to ever get first exposed to DC because they
Told us all that it was going to be
Inevitable
When we
Got involved
And then maybe 5 or 6 months later
Because of Americans
The phone and calling in the internet
Working out
They were on think
Legislators were running from these bills
And it was a great demonstration of the power of people to actually affect
Change DC which I didn't think was a
The thing I didn't like
That's what you dream of
Is how DC works and
I found a way out
And during the time U-verse
Mulan it Hitman
Trying to get that company
Yeah I mean I mean
Starting any business hipmunk
All of my hoes travel
His travel
Yes yes we were in the Glamorous business of slinging
Plane tickets and hotel reservations
Fun
I will take a lot of pride in the work we were doing and we built I thought of very
Nice product
I mean we always really enjoyed saving people time
Travel is very
Throat and we didn't
We didn't realize that going
That would be so that's like a lot of our attention and
And stress
Sterno Sears
And you guys were just done with thread
That you are not involved
At that point at all eventually read it was still wholly owned by
This point
But I was involved as a
But not in the day
How's my day today connection died
When we when we left there at 6
Me Alexis Chris
David
Jeremy and Mike
And I
Chris and David came with me to Pitman
Eventually
And I was my last connection to redis
Really
Until there was a time when I was at hit my quirk
I knew 0% of the people who worked at Reddit
That's a little weird
Didn't feel
Painful
In July of 2015
Francesca
Nuts
Moderator start to
Shut down
Subreddits
What was going on
What were you were at hipmunk United Reddit
Did you like
Check out red and start to notice
Read it like a couple things are happening over the course of 2,000
I'm ready
I just raced 50 million.
I'm going to see you all the time you Sean
Misguided midlife crisis
Unless the rough
I'm so Alan Powell
Took over
And read it went through a series of crises
That year
Mostly content-related on the site that
Toxic users
Had
Kai gotten out of control
And it's one thing after another and right as getting killed in a press and everybody just feeling like
What's going on
And at the same time
Alexis and I were
Kind of repairing
I don't I don't remember exactly how it started enough my point of view I just had this thought of like Hey where's my best
Around that time you said I want to February
2015-2016
You know what and what you decided that you were just going to reach out
Basically
I think we have dinner
And
We started this process of
Flags
2.5 years since we left
And we just started kind of talking through things
We agreed I'm over that first dinner that he wouldn't put some effort
Just repairing our friendship
We actually
Saw
My therapist
Saw him together
The two of you went to therapy together
When
Wednesday fishing out of he was like look my therapist is really good idea
Let's come together
And
Picture
So
We will actively kind of working on things until we are in
Closer Closer contact
And then things that are really starting to go
Yeah
And they reached the boiling point
In July of 2000
They took the moderates who control their communities
All communities on Reddit
You know that many thousands of them are created by users and run by you
Moderators
And
They were upset
Y'all for a sound like you tissues and also just like
Just general frustration
Until they took their communities.
And is effectively turned right at all
For a couple of days
Alexis and I were talking about this
Alexis who it was close to the right of the time on the board
Apps like what you got to get the site online
Like this whatever you got to do
Like you just got to like broker a peace
To get us back online because
We were
Very fortunate that
Our
Largest competitor for years dig
Made a blunder
A few years prior and basically commit suicide
The front of the whole internet thing was 5 times bigger than us
Release the new version of their software that was so
This life I user something just came to read
And inside this stuff that that could happen was a very real
Fear of
And at the same time
Every single person I know
Texted me
Inside
You got to go back to
Then and that's kind of what got the ball rolling
All happen against the backdrop of Ellen Powell
Resignation she
Was very public about the abuse that was heaped on her she wrote an op-ed in Washington Post basically sing the trolls
Around the time the Southern Poverty Law Center releases this
Port that says some of the most virulent and violent
Popaganda
Describe racism misogynist anti-semites
And you
Go
Back to this
Yeah my friends ghost
I made the decision to go back at my buddies
30th birthday
And you also do decide to go back
Yeah we both came back full time then but like
Getting Steve installed as CEO with something that
Really only one person in the planet could do
And it was Steve never my friends are like why do you run into that burning building
And it just felt like it's time I had no choice
I like really really loves Reddit and part of me it wasn't even kind of a CEO mentality is more like an engineer
Who knew how that works
And watching these trolls run rampant on Reddit
I know how to fix
I to know the mind of a troll
Give me access to the code I can
Exodus
And that was
Kind of those kind of my feeling and I know we can do this
Am I don't want to see Reddit
Now taken over by these people is it is it possible to
Bully
Get me to remove
The racist misogynist
You know
Horrible horribly
Cruel people meaning
Can you do that
Bullock
Anything is Possible
But that's not the goal
What we want Reddit to be is
In many ways over a reflection
Of humanity
Humanity is not perfect
But what you get on Reddit
Is an authentic representation of what's going on in the
And we believe that is
Very very powerful
And the good news is it what one of the things I read it as taught me
Is that people are fundamentally good
People in large numbers want to help each other when you put people together night contacts
They will do really incredible thing
And
There's no reason why that needs to be undermined by bunch
What does it mean
Exist
But we can we can make a conversation more balanced than that's really been our Focus
Consider
300 million people
Will visit Reddit
This month
That's almost as big as the population United States
And
Vast vast vast majority those interactions and engagements
Are not
They're never reported by another user
And they're actually
Niner actually good
But
If anything
It shows us how much more we have in common with each other than a park
Because when you're on R / skincareaddiction
You don't know anything else about the
The hundreds of thousands of other people talking about
Acne scars other than the fact
You have this year
And and whether it's about that or
Putting arms on birds
R birdswitharms
You find out you're not the only one who weirdly wanted
How to put the Rock's arms on a parakeet
And that's okay
Because all people of all Creeds should be able to come together and put
Dwayne Johnson's arms on a parakeet
Do you not agree
You look skeptical
Would someone in our / birds with arms put guys arms
On a bird
Please download from
You're welcome someone here is going to do it Silicon Valley View is a place with
Dreams come true guy
Personalized
Cuz a lot of people want to know about you or Steve
So first of all
Ask him anything
Yeah I'm going to ask you anything you know do you do you have a personal life have you been able to
Cuz you work so damn hard
I don't think somebody walks around wearing a
Sweater
Robot
Wearing riding a dinosaur without making a few friends
I got a personalized thank you
And
Lexus
Yeah you are a lot more boring
I'm very much a homebody and your
Way more impressed
Serena Williams partner you are expecting of a
I'm so excited little baby
How did that happen
Well guy what a man and a woman love each other yes
How did we meet
A couple years ago I was hungover overslept
I was just I was actually at a conference that I really didn't want to be at
But
It was it was a good thing I went
Cuz I overslept
I need to coffee
And they send me outside
The sit by the pool
And
And there was a table next to me where they sat or where I sat
There were four people there an item happens on I was just working on my laptop
And then
One of them
Australian guy goes on mine
As a rat
Bile table
I was like one that's fine like I'm up from Brooklyn to see rats all the time
I'm thank you but okay
And I know you trying to get me to leave cuz I wanted that table for the rest of the team and end of the world
Woman who's next to him turn around was like I really enough not scared of rats and I was like no
And
And she's like what you doing here and I'll
Tech conference she like oh you here to see speak
I was like I'm speaking and
And the
And then someone else to the table was like oh wait what
Talking about it
Reddit
General idea what read it was did you know who you were talking to
But I've never literally never watch Tennis I didn't care for the sport
I'm being honest I really do not care for the sport I want to I want to add something here with
My favorites
Serena story
Okay not something we talked about ahead of time but let's just do it live this is Trust
So this was a
As well
It was like one of my first days on the job
With Alexis over there on a Saturday
It was during Wimbledon
So
Wimbledon live streaming on a screen near us
And Alexis kisses text
And it's just like
Wall2wall kissy emoji
Then I was like Serena
And just then
I look on the screen of Serena is coming
Out of the tunnel
On her phone we still will never know we'll never know
Sounds like that I just watch Serena Williams send you a wall of wow
Wow
So you guys are back in Reddit
You are
Running this thing
You just just raise a bunch of money
I asked this question everybody comes in the show and I don't want to ask both of you to answer
How much of what you think happened to you professionally is because of your skill and your talent and how much of it is
Somebody observe this that I thought was very smart
Sunnyside
Success is the
Products
Intelligent
Hard work
And lock
You can't have a zero in any of those
You know we started
Internet company in 2005 when
The kind of Web 2.0 the second wave of
I'm smarter funding and smarter people were coming into the ecosystem
I don't sometimes the that with the wind blows your way
I'll tell you this
If I went back 10 years ago and do everything I knew now
It had to start right all over again
I don't know if we
Right it's just
It's a Fickle thing these social sites
And
It's really all about the users and in what are they into
And it's
It's it's hard to say if we could do it
Again all over
With even a perfect
I'm personally heavy on the the left side
I don't want to totally remove agency because
Haunted work
Bottom
I like that dirt you can't have a zero in any of the columns
And it's so easy to look back on it and
And just think
All the dots
Connected but
There was no other forces at play to make it all work
Alexis Ohanian Steve Huffman founders of Reddit
Thanks guys
And if you're wondering if someone actually
Will you put my arms on a bird they did you can type my name into read it to see it
Or you can go to work Twitter handle at how I built this where my team has Kylie posted a photo of my arms attached
A parakeets body
Hey thanks for listening to this special live episode of How I built this
It was recorded in front of a live audience at San Francisco's yerba buena Center for the Arts this episode
Was produced by Rammstein arabloo you also composed the music special thanks to leave a grant Jeff Rogers
Michigan floor and player brain our intern is Lawrence woo-hoo Gyros and you've been listening to a special live
What episode of How I built this from NPR
Hey y'all Sam Sanders hear my new podcast is called it's been a minute
Another way of saying let's catch up
Happy Friday I'll sit down with two guests smart stalkers from inside and outside NPR to catch up on the week of news
Booze and culture
Everything if you can't stop watching the news but you're awful exhausted by doing that this show is for you don't miss out
Find it's been a minute now
On the NPR one app or wherever you get your podcast thanks
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com