Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
We made a big mistake and our editorial processes I was sick
50 years of great journalism reputation for integrity
Volume stuff and then there was a couple of really bad judgment calls were made on a very sensitive story
It blew up on our face that was probably the biggest one that was always there's just one thing that happened
Brown NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists the stories behind the movements we go
Sex drugs and rock and roll
Magazine and built a publishing Empire out of it
Notice about
The people who get on the show is
They all saw an opportunity and they took it
Sure there was locked
Hard work failure persistence all that
What's the difference between say Sara Blakely and the rest of us
Is that in the 1990s
He saw an opportunity to improve women's undergarments and she seized it
Rod canion son opening to make better personal computers in the 1980s o
He don't come back
And for you
He was also in the right place
At the right time
1960s student journalists at UC Berkeley
Right at the time when San Francisco in the Bay Area we're becoming the center of youth culture in America
Just being there wasn't enough
What you did was to capture the moment it take that energy and create a Gathering Place
People magazine
Spoke to them in their language
Is this small small town
Yet at the same time as that
Beautiful picturesque town which was very tolerant of
Social behavior center and the Arts community
There was a beatnik
Allen ginsberg and Kerouac
Controlling netty and me
All found a home in San Francisco
People like
Lenny Bruce
So
It had a thriving
Beatnik
Alternative lifestyle community and so they were there for was extremely tolerant
Other Rock & Roll groups are springing up
Even weirder
Then the beat
And a hat Coffee House scene in
Consistent
San Francisco's Longstreet
Of being tolerant of different kinds
The political movements aren't just
Because of course I'm pretty strong
50 movements at Columbia and nn
Boston butt
San Francisco Berkeley
That was the center of
Student activism in America are arguably in the world
I think so yeah I mean that Colombia came several years after that was 96
C8
So I think it really started in the San Francisco Bay Area it wasn't coming by
At the very early days of civil rights
So a lot of students were going off on March 8th
Down south
Participating
Think so
I think look like as a man
Among students
Really was generated in the Bay Area
What was it exciting exciting
Oh yeah I mean cuz you look men
The possibility in
These post-war baby boom just trying to come of age soon become
Call students incensing
That that was their turn on stage and it lives there right or responsibility to
Try and make America stand up for me
And behave in such a way
At work we were taught
School America
We're about
Liberty get a lifetime
Tell me how you met
Ralph Calise
Cuz he he would Fusco to figure Bay probably in
The founding story
Who was he and how you made a moral principles
Jazz comments for the San Francisco Chronicle
New Edition coming Jazz he would write about
Some rock and roll
Things Dylan Beatles
Gallstones
Stuff like that and he was one of the few voices
Around anywhere in the country
And in San Francisco
Deadpool saying hey there's real Merit
To these artists to Dylan
Are beetles and what they doing is important is important
Is culture important
As a rock and roll fan I would read that
His
Three times a week call him
So
He was somebody you pay close attention to die
Met him
Battle Rock and Roll Show in San Francisco
Kemah Boat Show
I was called a tribute to
And you just went up to me and said hey I'm young winner
Data California
So
3 challenge like that and then met a couple more times or had lunch or something like that or
Kept seeing each other dances
Also I got the sense that I was he was taking me under his wing and he likewise doing Thug
Bright energetic and
You know you tried the company how much older was he than you
Probably 20 of the time he is 40 so he's an adult to music
At what point did you
Say to him hey
Why we start a magazine together
Well he kind of looked after Mike rewrite I went after in the summer 65
I was in London
Living there
Can a wild eyed kid came back the states
He said he did there was something available
Something called ramparts magazine
In San Francisco when I come back and got me that job and ramparts
Magazine Subs cranberry
Is the left wing
Investigative
Journalism magazine
I was in charge of that at tender ages of the Arts entertainment coverage Richard since I was in charge
Minnelli towards rock and roll and
And I hippie culture
Soca
It's much of the stuff that it would end up ignoring some
After that job ran out about nine months later
I was kind of lost it what to do I
The 20 years old ahead of time
And
You have no Career Training and no immediate job prospects
This is a Gob to go back to Ralph for help
Well we are very we are big fantasize looking to Route 4
Time for your advice and guidance or something to do with him
Hudson Square selling some Patagonia
Think about
The way we saw the world
And we tried a couple of different ideas help
Edit a book
Balaji
Yeah something centered around music
An
I guess
Seether here I said
Why don't we start a publication about
Anna
Brazos High bar together orbital Obama visit. Newspaper on newsprint
So was going to be any type full-scale Magazine launch
And was going to be
Focused on rock and roll
Was there anything like that in nineteen
67 nothing like that
So help me understand this
This guy
Ralph Gleason in notable
Well respected Jazz critic for the San Francisco Chronicle
Young man but middle-aged
Has enough confidence in a 21 year old kid to say yeah rock and roll Magazine with you
Has sound implausible now doesn't it
I don't
No I mean
We got along really well and then we share the same vision
And he had when he was young
Start a publication called Jazz quarterly
Which was
Good summer to stay with fans
Magazine about that
Belle Chasse
So I think
Probably saw in me I may be a younger version of himself
He saw the possibilities he saw
That I had some kind of level of talent ambition that might be able to bring some
Something off he even gave me money for
What was the ambition did you guys sit there and say we are going to make the biggest magazine in America
No
I mean I don't even know if you knew what the biggest maggot
America was but that wasn't for us to do something
That was new and fresh and about music and
What drug was no longer you know dance time is started having some very serious music on political content
Associate
Nissan
People assigned to articulate a member of velious stance towards Society they were
Concerned about me like Bill Monroe
Alienation and
The Beatles were writing
Lot about Tramp
Social mores in how people should be treated and
These four things are beginning to wrestling
Equally with a new Young
Generation of which I was on the Leading Edge up to Ralph says okay let's
Let's do this he has a little bit of cash to put in
He had some cash to put in and I got some $2,000 to my mother or my mother
Mother-in-law to be and some money from a college friend of mine and and also for my stepmother
Assembled together was
$7,500 and that was what we started
And what did you do for that pointed you assemble a staff did you start to write articles that you have to find a place that was going to
Starting something today you could just put it online
But then I'm finding a
Printer
Expensive
Expensive proposition
Distribution
Yeah I was all, but you're not too expensive but we need to find a office
This is how we
Went to the
Printer that we had used it
Sonny ramparts agreed to
Give us offices upstairs in airplane
Facility since we're going to print the magazine there
We assembled friends of mine and people I met at ramparts
Berkeley
Or other people running about the rock on scene last of all the volunteer
Diapers to write articles
Pictures of help put it together so
It was really a volunteer effort
How did you come up with a name
A lot of games
The one that kept sticking was rolling stone
Bob dylan song Like a Rolling Stone
Anna was a title of an essay that Ralph is written
For a small publication called The American Scholar
In which he laid out his
Is thinking about
The meaning of rock and roll lesson
New America belting Americans
Society
Just walk me through this in 96
She 7 I mean because today of course the lawyers
LLC in the documents of Incorporation
Did you have to do any of that or was it just
Fly by the seat of your pants
Does fly by the seat of my pants I mean nothing by magazine publishing and distribution
Out of vague understand what editorial was and it what should be like
You had a right
Port Royal Pets mixed drinks with the record companies
And it was just right up
Assembly print
But I mean you were creating a business did you how did you even know
Where to start
I had no clue
None
You know it was just
We pay what we can pay for the money we had on hand
That would be as far as he going since we're paying salaries weren't paying rent
I only costly was
Printer paper
Randolph
Now the cost of distributions which I wasn't even aware of
Until two or three months later when all these Trucking bills
Yeah
Soup from the time that you raise that $7,500
The time the first issue came out what was how long did that take
About
3 months to months
Beerfest RPI
And and so what was the tell me about the first issue what was it what was that
John Lennon was on a cover-up
A photo of him
As private group reading a movie how I won the war and that came back to the league
Take a picture of Elena but just whatever free publicity photographs are flying around the time we're looking for
Or something and there was a package of of a pictures that movie was just coming out me just took that one of John and
Dress up as a soldier in training to be Bryant-Denny
But looking back at it the choice of John Lennon Harper cover our first issue was you know
More than for 2 minutes and what was inside
Reviews of shows in San Francisco
Navigation to what has happened to the money that have been earned at the Monterey Pop Festival give me a charity or not
So you looked into that along with
Traditional journalism
So tell me about just
Getting them articles in the deadlines we are writers going out and and making deadline
Working around the clock to get this thing out was it a weekly was it a monthly or every other week
What we had very few Riders
And it's very hard to push them too hard for all volunteer if you're not paying anybody
Asking
Do things like everybody's like
In view of the same spirit and enthusiasm for it
Anna
You know people really pitched in and
And didn't we are look at that thing out of it
Without fail from then on out
I'm assuming that you despite the fact that you were
In the store the center of the sex drugs and rock and roll
You know culture you kind of
Couldn't really take partner too much cuz you have to run a magazine
You have to publish that
Well
How can I ask
You could do both
But you really want to have to sacrifice for the other I mean
Once it gets going
Andaz
Pru trying to print something every two weeks
You really have no time
To think of anything but
The next day more copy more
Car stories
And all the little things that go into
The Mailroom as well as the other
And how did you fund it did you have to also
To put
Well we tried to sell Adam again if you had your NetSpend
There was not
Much revenue
$500 an issue.
So how much runway did you have with that $7,500
What's her no cuz as that one
Go out then we start getting some buddies in from
Selling it at newsstands in there be checks
Banana from advertisers and people might be
Start subscribing paying $5 a year so I need that so there's enough to
To keep it going at it sooner or later e
Hire first employee.
See $25 a week
N
By the end of the first year
We were of viable business with three or four people
Being paid getting it out regularly
Selling Thirty or forty thousand cops an issue
People will respond with the breadcrumbs at like 8 we're getting letters and correspondence and recognition from very sorry
In the first year we
Pop's long interview with Pete Townsend interview
Jagger
So it was making it was good Gathering momentum people like what they saw
Did you have that Advantage because you were the only
Magazine like this out there
Well
Yes
Nobody else is trying to do this I mean the primary mainstream press didn't care at all about this
Figure corner of American culture or give much Credence or thought the idea there's a kind of a booming new general
Duration about to take over the Baby Boomers going to have a big impact that time still
Music was looked down upon
Has Teenage nonsense or ephemeral to say the least done by people look really strange in a long hair
You're not really acceptable people
But
Nonetheless music was become tribal Telegraph the drums are beating for Yankee
People around the world but you can never communicate with each other to other people like them around the world we're doing until
This is the way young people communicate there was nothing else
So do you remember
When the magazine started to get
Attention was it
Year two three like 100 start to become something people just talk about
A twin brother
Time to get live intentions on the first year anniversary
We printed
The cover the band 2virgins cover the Alma John Young
John Lennon Yoko Ono
The other one
Shod Diamondback sizing
Then
Picture of them
Completely naked so
We're a nose at first
Anniversary issue
Amazon article about
Ourselves in San Francisco Chronicle First Press which was
Deadline
Nude beetle
Perils s
But we had we sold out the printing we print more than just kind of got more more people talking
And then I think
Is it big
Specialist young group
And that cost more
The photo portfolio bigger part about
Burleson Paul bands
Surrounded
Associated with that
MetLife article
Time Magazine about us
We're starting to get a little on a national radar then
No sales or can I pick you up
Big cities
Around Izakaya spreads by word of
And then
Finally made a deal with
The more of a national
Magazine wholesaler
Resume
Company in San Francisco
And start appearing more more around the country
The More We Fear the more people liked it more subscriptions came in more Revenue
Came in so we thought we really had a going business you know after the first year I don't think
We had a question about
Survival at 4
Turn on the road tell me how you came across Hunter Thompson
It's fair to say he was your first
Really big breakthrough writer
New Hunter's work before I start rolling stone here in the book
Call the Hell's Angels
And so I just wrote him a letter after a startling sound asking
Time to write something
And he Robaxin Gees he didn't really
Reading limestone is terrific
Second grade
He loved to write
Pretty good right now
Because he was busy involved in running for Sheriff Aspen
Colorado
So I wrote him back that will wanted you right about that
And what she did and which we publish couple months later
This called
The Battle of Azeroth
Freak power in the Rockies
And of course the idea that he's running for
Aspen
Cotton or synthetic
Retention
You know in media place around the world Moab Sun News
Inundated
Reporters in
Film Crews
New York from London so far like that
That was once again it started just a reputation growing more
1972 I mean that when I was a huge
Found her Thompson's work when I was stressed when I was younger
And I mean
You had this guy
To cover the 1972 McGovern campaign
A serious presidential
Campaign
Was any part of you like me this is a risky this guy's you know he's coming
Use what drugs in these a little bit nuts and maybe they'll maybe that's what it took
I'm by that time hundred written a couple
Serious
Deep investigative pieces for us on
Like East La Mexicana movie
He said we're done
Fear and loathing Las Vegas and he had become our
Star Rider star reporter size always on the lookout for both be the next right thing for under to do
So the
Election comes along
Does the first time
The AC
Franchise to vote
Is it in a
War situations was the anti-war election
And Hunter
Had this kind of global background everyone for sharing mean
Having bad actually covered Nixon years before
So it was just kind of natural thing I mean
American politics why not send out an expert on the Hell's Angels
What to do American pop
In just a moment by Rolling Stones San Francisco
For New York and how it became the most influential Music Magazine
In the world
Listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your law
Long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Marcus
Industries and the global economy listen to their podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed from the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcasts Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com podcast
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR I'm kyroz
So it's the early 1970s Rolling Stones
Trying to get a lot of national attention at this point is operating out of a brand new office
Publish in color and acid dropping
Auto journalist
Cover the 1972 presidential election
Nothing nothing says that you can take a stand and tell her that maybe even better than without asking
Traditional journalism look if you're trying to make a presidential election at that time
Interesting to young people
If you are basically turned off the political process
You have to make it interesting and McGovern was an interesting personality and Nixon
Set timer well-defined villain so it was kind of setup for doing
Really good writing and Reporting and
The traditional coverage hours
Bloodless
Another one in
I broke all that app
And became the most compelling
Writer and reporter on that campaign
As everybody well acknowledge what was he like to work with me and was he
Reliable was he
Reliable
Erratic
A lot of what we call hand holding
I mean he was
Erratica news
Yeah Moody and energetic and
All of the map but he was also
A professional
Superba Porter brilliant writer
Deep sense of responsibility about things
And though he would
Working till the very last minute deadlines
And almost drive you crazy and
Bring you right to the edge
In the end he always still ever
It always count
So I was I had a great time
Took a lot of my time
It was raining
Exhaustion can do
But the net effect was
Patricia Brewing Pizza
To work in the terms of company in Tyler
I was also
One of the key things are like
Finally put Rolling Stone the map in a big way
Everybody depressed quiz
Everything everything
And people around kangaroo riveted by what he had to
But by that time
We are pretty serious
Rock Roll magazine free
Why do Spectators starting a lot advertising lot advertise
And that we were on our way
That was no help Growing Pains
Well after about three years we
Went to a real
Rush
With running out of money
Which lasted
Who is moved Austin sounds
Rent free loft Independence Place to a big
You know expensive new
Expansive office
So then all the overhead that entails and
We are spending money without really thinking about it all so real so much
You going to run out of money
And we switch to a big National
Also not print run
300 400000
And once we got to that
Restart
Professional
I mean really
I can bring him
People who are
CPAs
Or have account
10 degrees are at some reasonable business background
Manage things in
Back to the money
And
Over here. Just got more more professional
Once we move when we move to New York
77 I mean that really was
And I was really hitting the
Why did you New York via why'd you do that why'd you leave San Francisco and 7
2/2 ovens
What's going to happen
We had a lot of
People Lottery
So
It was clear we had to do it in one place and also the magazine business
Was in New York so if you want all that
Resources
Talent
They were available in New York
Industry
So it's kind of a no-brainer
Doing
We went and did it and ended up on
5th Avenue
At the time Ian you were quoted as saying San Francisco is a cultural Backwater
And that's why we're moving
Did you
Beach resorts in Trinidad
There was that Heyday only started
Which had not only this thriving rock and roll
But it's private
Political call
Alternate
Are there left of the black pants and all sorts of things are happening
Sort of by the time you move
I'm New York assigned to have its moment
Starting to come back
And we arrived just at that
Male rosary
Andy Warhol
And then
Closure backwaters is
It was just
The provincial
And I was out in the cold
It was awful to me
It wasn't
Putting up this big unique
Cultural thing in music anymore
Yo-yo
That New York office
1970s
Rolling Stones basically espousing a kind of
Counterculture
Aesthetic
But you were the boss when you were the man
So how do you balance
Running a counterculture
Magazine for also
And tired of having to be a jerk sometimes
The people who weren't
Being productive or whatever
Well I mean
It wasn't
Too difficult I mean really. I never quite believed in
The counterculture
Welchol patent alternate
But definitely you don't you answer
Value systems
You good
Trying to be fair to people instead of being
Have less money only
So it was always a bit of a balancing act but I think everybody quite understand it
They everybody wanted to go
Get paid you know
If you have family you want supper
I'm so I don't think anybody
Really deeply questions
The need to have a
Prophetess taking a
Professional
I mean it was somehow Courtside critics in early days of
Oh your friends
The best for your hippie capitalist
Contradiction
Both
Give me a stop
Wasn't nothing
And at that point were you did you start to really get interested in the business side of things are you looking at p&l
Are you looking at the bottom line where you
Doing that too
Well I guess I wasn't myself doing his I was always
Had some of their eyes
CEO CFO
Who's read the daily response
And that person report to me and I look at it and over
You'll have oversight over it
Try to understand
Try to give Direct
Directions to tricks
Kid YouTube
I didn't have control the day
Operation
But when you're
Involved in something like
That stage isn't that when things are
Growing all the time and getting better and more more money is coming in
You don't have to be
Hof
Commander
You know
You're the victim of
Success from outside
You know just
It time
Brings along the true test of
Of how
Have a businessman URL showed his when things are not going so
What was your time after you move to New York with things were not going well with a magazine
Wake me up at 12
Came up we had spent a lot of money
Moving
And moving to fancy new off salt
Stop at the same time
I started a new publication called outside
And left that in San Francisco
And there came a point where it was just too much
We can both magazine
Play sold out
Did you did you sell for profit
Sold it for
About what I
Put into it
But I couldn't afford to be sustained both magazines
Did that did you feel pressure to I mean I mean
Magazine today of course is not as
Isn't this a different business and it wasn't like 70s
But did you have sleepless nights over whether you know you're going to payroll and he got his own
By the time we moved New York
Fully up in Opera
Framing Rolling Stone
Was getting to a circulation 1 million,
1 million
You're you are a solid
Stable business
That's a lot of money coming
Did you ever have to find additional outside investment fund funding at any point
Actor that now
I know you would totally self-sufficient
Yeah
So tell me about your I mean how you started to grow because Rolling Stone was this thing of the
Your baby in
Outside you bought and sold and then you moved on and started by other Publications right
Restart US Weekly and restart monster
But the Rolling Stone gulou
Because it was so good
And because it's so relevant to people's lives
He got a big big readership
An advertise Has Fallen
I mean I guess
A certain point
XI the criticism of Rolling Stones that time and end in you know this wasn't
It was about
Things like the things you would cover right and you you're focused on
Try to grow the magazine and make it
Relevant and
Some people would say well you didn't cover disco frogs
But you were you missed the punk movement like what is that was very true that
No
That we are right on the park
Viton discount
People hated Disco
The haters for covering
Have you hated for covering Punk
But we're always get
That's good to hear
How do you know
We're going to stay with
The news or what's
Of Interest
People
Currently going on popular
We're going to cover it as Leading Edge and sometimes
Popular culture is terrible
Sometimes it's good
You could have and it was a very smart I know you didn't do it for this reason but it was a very smart and lucky moved
How to get into publishing because
That enables you to make a lot of money worth today it's a different
The different story
21 today
I doubt I would
Consider magazine
People are looking all
Electrical in something digital
Digital delivery of food order digital delivery of news or how to hook up
So
If you want to do a magazine date Mike
Cancel beaches
Make us a small
So that's supported by its readers not by
Advertise
Yeah
Reading content is there so much
Free country
10 today compared to win
You know
The Heyday Rolling Stone
Right at 8
It's a different
Beast now menu
Your content that you the people have to pay money for
They may not get as high quality content
For free but there's a lot of available right so it is a dog
There's a lot available distract everybody
In every single way
Every possible kind of entertainment so fine people actual
Sit and read
Does a shrinking number of people
Find Maggie
Having said that
We still have a huge reader
You know of a million
Yeah
I want to just read a list of some names of Rolling Stone alone
Hard times
Of course Joe Klein Cameron Crowe Joe eszterhas
PJ O'Rourke
Any leave its Lester bangs Matt Taibbi will inquire Kurt loder
Michael Hastings
Incredible
List of people
What's the story how do you
Find people do they come to you to you are you just good at identifying good people are you lucky how did you go
Get these right
Thought the combination some people approach you you seek other p
People out you always on the search
I'm always open to
That's what
Put wrong Stone over it wasn't
My brilliant
Management
It was a factory publishing such great stop
I just have a
Instinct
For townspeople and how to work with them
Thinking back
Ralph
Recent interview with somebody want
Sunset
The proof
Of how good an idea rolling stone
Is that it survived Ian
What's management
Cuz you are crappy manager
How to make a
Big buck
I should have no business back
Yeah
Hanergy
Anika died
Degraded
You know you have all the things
Only one of them
Of course
Is a woman a leave of this one most famous song
The world that I want
If you get a chance to do it again
Do you think I'm in a lot of the great writers that you brought in were Madden
What you have
Would you work harder do you think it was a different time of course but you think it would work harder to bring in more women
Well
It's something you'd work we were just looking for talent what and whatever shape or form came in
Man woman
Ebony color
Funny shape inside
It didn't matter to me but
It's just that
The general side just didn't produce
Great woman journalist at that time there are few
Who wrote for the times but
Not
Many
Who wrote Narnia
We would
Go after women is
Is anybody else
Teepublic Nora Ephron
Well it's at that time
Emerson
Great
Group of women editors
At the center of the teddies Matthew Publix Patti Smith
Was Patti Smith
And today we got three or four released
Hot women ride
Janet Reitman
Text Morris
Emerges
Count Basie
You know so if you're talented
You got to play
We wanted you
We can look back
I've read that that at a certain point
You had a falling out
Can you tell me what
What happened what you remember about that had a falling-out with
So I can't really tell you that anything happened I can taste it
Hunter like that
Go round
Talking about how awful his bosses were
You need to always have a villain
A foil for his writing
And if nobody else is available Nixon was not available to meet up
Then it was me
And I just took
We're very fast
Friends for years
And Dickie I mean I guess you didn't live right next to the magazine
You know his Heyday was a 7
Chinese rice
I mean after the campaign if you can't pay me late
Pieces like
About Watergate
He just
BK mumper.
And remain so for many many
Put it was it you
Just because of the lifestyle
I think it was
Betaflight wave
Did you keep in touch with him until he
He until he died we're always in touch
You know
Frequently and fig
Don't lie you know we always go
I was always trying to get in the right something else
Something else I'm finally in the 90s
He came back Evil 2
Wonderful
Huge long
Pieces fear and loathing
Melco n1a
About the publisher
Roxanne Pulitzer
Richard
ASA writing
You know about your management style
Is anyone in your position is going to have haters right
Of course
Loyal soldiers and people who love you and people
Despise you right now this normal right
Right
But I have to dispute the fact that
I got
Bad people people don't like me or
Think I'm sure this Christmas by think
My reputation is more from being fair and Equitable and
Reasonable
People being a tough and demanding boss absolutely
I don't think anybody say that is unfair
Peanut worm in your cruel
I want to learn about
Managing people is that
You want them to be happy what they're doing you want smart
People you want
Loyal people loyalty
People
If their unhappiness job won't do a good job
And I believe you
Should keep
Free people justly and fairly II
Tough in that manner but I'm not
I don't shrink too much when a decision has to be made it has to be made
I'm off 142nd
I'm always happy people II
I want to ask you about
A crisis that you guys had
Around the
DVA story the story about
They publish a few years ago about a rape on campus at University of Virginia
You know which that the central story Turner
False that was a big deal in that was national news so what
What was the situation like
Are you guys the magazine is it
That was difficult
But not next
Existential crisis
Made I mean I'm not allowed
All City
Lawsuit
Amicable settlement
We made it
Jim bignell
Latoya process
Yeah and I obviously understand that either
Because you can't talk about but wait what
But you are able to talk about how about that
I don't know how did that affect you first
Why did you
I was sick of it
50 years of great
Journalism
Reputation for integrity in
Volume stuff and then
Stackable really bad judgment
Reverse sensor
It blew up on Ark
But
The general port on Redbox
White Acura
Illustrated Man
Story
The rape victim
That was
Made up by then raping
And we pray that without adequate
For the checking
As you eat as you know
Journalist
It's enough right the minute you get something like that it doesn't matter
Sooner or later you're going to get some
And I believe the New York Times about
Was that the ethics it seems like
Up until that point of me of course every publicans going to make mistakes and you guys
I've had your mistakes over the years but that mean it seems like
About that was
Probably the biggest one
That was always says this one thing that happens
Do you still own 100% of your company
Is its value publicly about public you keep that private
Upward of let's say when our media report of a quarter million dollars
Whatever you want say I need would you ever sell it
You know who knows I mean
Heyday Rolling Stones
Fortune
You know that hate is passed
But I don't regret having not sold
The Heyday for
And the most you guys went on to have another
1015 is of delightfully running
My own company in my
On magazine
Not working for anybody else
Yeah when you sell it you end up working for somebody else
And I have every right to tell you what
I'm just not a person
Highlights
What to do
You are
Gunplay started this magazine
50 years ago
That's right
Are you you still going everyday
I'm pretty much yeah every day but I'm here in New York
Gone about four months of the year by months
So when do you
When do you stop being involved in throwing some ever
Well I don't know as long as I can make a good country
I think I still do it
I can still feel and I
Going to have an idea that good story ideas are good
Good instincts
A story should be in
Make those kind of contributions
Story ideas
Then I'm happy and
Delighted in one computers
Do that
The men I see a padlock
Failing and coming outside he's always looking at me
Old man
And I think I'm down
Daughter of Rolling Stone magazine and it seemed like he doesn't have a plan for Rolling Stones future
Not entirely true John's 26 year old son Gus is poised to take over the family business
When God stepped down in fact Gus was the one who wrote us and said hey you should put my dad on the show
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things that
Your building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors American Express open
Every week on how I built this we bring you stories about entrepreneurs who beat the odds overcame obstacles and made there
Ideas happen
It's never easy and that's why American Express open wants to help with money and know-how
So you can turn your ideas into impact
Get business done
Learn more at open.com
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I know for how you built that and this week story comes to us from Joel Crites
Hi guy Joel is from Cleveland he's a huge Cleveland sports fan
A few years ago he was at an Indian's game with his 16 year old son
It was a beautiful summer night of baseball and Joel was loving it
But he just wasn't into the action of the game you didn't really care about the outcome and you know it wasn't into the
The standings
This is boring let's go and I said something to the effect of know I paid to be here tonight
Are you going to sit there and like it many of us have been in a similar situation this is no fun for Kobe
It's no fun for Joel
So in that moment Joel suggested a game
He tried to Kobe and he said
Hey why don't we try to predict what the next batter is going to do
Strikeout hit a homer walk whatever
And whoever predicts correctly
Winter Haven fine and within the very next at-bat
We were laughing and high-fiving and I thought I had just struck gold
SOA actor that every time Joel went to see baseball he played the game with his other kids as well and he started to
Tell his friends about it especially Friends With Kids
He realize that a lot of fans were already doing the same thing people have told me I play this with my grandpa
When we predict the at-bats and we use you know this and that to keep track of the score
And people in the bullpen hoverboard when they're watching again evil do some version of it till about a year later she wondered what
Whether he might turn this idea into a smartphone app and app that you could play at home or in the snow
Stadium against other fans were all watching the live game in real time
But he needed to set up a way of scoring
How many points for a predicted strike or a home run or double play
Well fortunately in his day job
Joe is an accountant I quickly got out my spreadsheets and started downloading statistics to figure out
What should the different predictions for an at-bat be worth based on their statistical likelihood
So there's groundout worth two points strike out his three points
Single
Four Points eventually higher developer to build out a smartphone app
He put it out into the world I literally print it off flyers and I stood outside of our local Stadium
Just asking people to play and that's how I got it off the grounds initially
Is one one thing because I'm a huge baseball fan to a lot of games
Magical about being in a stadium or Arena
Gaming and having our devices off I don't know I just feel like I feel like you surrendered
Sad note this is a reality and I'm just going to
I'm just going to go with it is in some ways I have but in the times we live in I mean the baseball
Average age of a viewer nowadays is gone from age 53 to 57 in the past decade so
You got to find the way to reach the kids in this is this is what I've come up with Joel's already license the app to a few
Do amateur baseball teams and even a few professional softball teams he's only made a few thousand dollars
So far but he's hoping to expand the idea to other sports like football and basketball and May
Maybe eventually even to sports bars the focus is to honestly make its new standard for fan engagement across the world
Because there's nothing to prevent us from offering it in Latin America and Korea and Japan and everywhere
Joe Crites lives in Cleveland Ohio he founded micro fantasy if you want to find out more about micro fantasy check out
At our Facebook page just search how I built this on Facebook and of course if you want to tell us your story go to Bill
Build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
Don't forget to subscribe to our podcast on Apple podcasts or however you get your podcast if you want to find out
More or listen to previous episodes you can also go to how I built this. Npr.org
HRBT at npr.org and if you want to send us a tweet it's at how I built this
I sure was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music thanks also to neva grandson
Anna's Mexican poor Clare Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Lawrence Wu I'm guy Raz and you've been live
Listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey there Paula Poundstone here
I hate to interrupt
What maybe you might like to listen to my new show
Live from the Poundstone Institute
Where I talked to researchers about interesting studies
It's like hidden brain except our brains are really well hidden
Find it now on the NPR one app and wherever you listen to podcasts
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com