Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Hey everyone it's Sky you're just a quick note to tell you
There is a little bit of bad language in this episode so if you've got small kids around
You just may want to be mindful of that
Thanks
She came to me and she knew I had to fire a lot of people cuz you could just see that
Everybody knew something about shake. And she said one should probably fire me if you fire me
You said no one else could be angry with you when you fire them and she was right so at that Monday morning meeting we always had at 9
9:30 I said so surprised how bad things are going to have to make a lot of changes and it's going to be
Very hard for me to do but the hardest changeables required my mother
NPR how I built this
A show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
And the movements they built
Jersey Girl conquer the streets of Manhattan
Delta real estate company worth millions and then
Reinvented herself as a shark
I'm Shark Tank
What are surprising things
About the entrepreneur
Least surprising to me
Isn't most of them
Unnecessarily book smart
Street Smart
All of them
Only a handful of people with hat on when
2 willeke universities or Uber academic genius
Most of them
Figured stuff out along the way
And use the tools they had
Which princess did Barbara Corcoran
Probably the most
Like a bull shark on the TV show
Shark Tank
As you're about to hear
Barbaro
Wasn't the best student in fact
She didn't excel at school at all
What she had
Rather has
You something so much more valuable
Charisma
How she'd eventually build one of New York's most
Successful real estate firm
Barbara grew up
Quora
Big Irish Catholic Family
9 brothers and sister
Hampton Apartments
Edgewater New Jersey
Even though
They have almost nothing
She remembers a childhood that was
Basically happy
I mean we all had our issues as every family does
But
It was well-organized my mother was like a drill sergeant so even though we all
Lived in such Close Quarters was meticulously clean and everything was put in order when my mother snifter
We had a side yard
Which we controlled it was a skinny little side yard but
Most of the house in Edgewater were back-to-back so we felt wealthy even though we're renting the ground floor we felt Wealthy by
By comparison
And also my dad was a printing press form and I had to wear a suit to work
And every other guy in the town seemed to work for the lunar Factory or the
Coffee company in a uniform
So I kind of thought of us as like
The Kennedys like
Whoa We were something
At school it was a different story
Barbara struggled a lot
But everyday when she get home from school
Her mom
Was right there
Ashy
Never
Told you what was wrong with you
She always told you
What she thought was amazing about you and sheep in one thing on each kid so each kid knew what that thing was
I have a wonderful imagination
So when I couldn't pass any subjects in school and I was really upset I remember distinctly one
The nun from Hell sister Stella Marie told me I'd always be stupid I was so upset to hear that word stupid I get a label finally
And my mother said don't worry about it with your imagination you learn to fill in all the blanks so I didn't learn to read
But I slept okay I can fill in the blank today I fell for
You know and she's right
Because I did have a good imagination or at least
Maybe I'll learn to have
Because of her
By the time she was 22 Barbara was working as a waitress at a diner in New Jersey
And one night
During a shift
An older man
Dapper
Confident charismatic
What's in for a bite to eat
And when Ramon Simone
I walked into my life
And set up
My counter
Call what you wanted was a lucky break
It was like you could
Hell
That he was some
Elsia
And he had a suit on
And he didn't have just a suit
Breast collar
With a shiny toy
Shiny shoes
And he had all navy blue Aviator Shades I couldn't really see his eyes
Also
He told me
He was from The Basque
I know where that was what I
It wasn't a New Jersey
And he told me it was a warrior tribe or sometime
Cool
Now later I learned his name wasn't Ramon Simone with an accent
Mother Vicki who I got
How many years later
Said his name was Ray Simon Big Dipper
And he wasn't from The Basque country was 440 5th Street Harlem
But good for him again what a merchandiser
And so he had a lot to do
Teach me
Okay and
I got a new family with your his three girls we moved in with us after I moved in with him I didn't know you had
This is your first
True life I love you
Sure it was a true love but
Someone who is different
Can anyone I have ever met before
For older
Successful in life had a big car
I hate the
Biso
Detritus to say that impress me but it was a Lincoln Continental
With real leather seats
And when you offered me that ride home from the diner that
That first night I remember thinking he had sprinkled talcum powder on the
All of his seat because I was sliding around
That's just called real leather you know
Was that
But your life is going to
BMW
Have bigger ambitions
You know honestly I have never had that
And I I can even say
Along the way
A building a successful life
It's not like I really had any big thoughts about when I be successful I just had more of a
Curiosity
Let's just see how far I could go
That was it
Curiosity
No one in my family has ever gone to college when I got into a college I just couldn't believe it but it was old girls
A college that had previously the year before been a nunnery that made nuns I forget what
And they're only 30 spot so just opening they took
That basically not realize I took anyone
But that was just a lucky break
And it didn't interfere with my work I was holding three jobs all the way through
Please work
So
It just kind of happened you know that I one thing led to another
How did you find your way to real estate
I was working as a receptionist for the jacuzzi Brothers here in New York City answering their phones a million times a day good morning GIF funny brother
Quit my job is
The waitress who are the different Brothers
Joseph Giovanni was a large
Real estate holder in Manhattan hand probably 50 apartment buildings in yorkswell
Yeah they were there very well
It was Joe and his other
What kind of gadfly a brother
Andrew
Who ran the business but show is really
Play the power
They hired me
And then within a couple of months
Ramon satrina with your personally barbecue be great at real estate sale
Okay I'll try it on your why not added
I think I turned twenty-two draws maybe 23 by then
I said why not
Give it a whirl
And they gave me $2,000 charge
Just like that
Yes
Circus Ramon gives you a thousand bucks and then
How did you
Did you start your own real estate
The only person I knew was Mister phony
And I asked him if he would just let me rent one of
Apartments the same building where I answer the phone every
And he gave me a listing
Try to rent
Apartment 3L
And so when I saw three out and what he was asking if he was
330 a month
Roughly there
I looked at everything I know how do I
It's it was a dungeon he gave me the worst
It was a challenge maybe nobody
In the back was like a super
But when I saw the list
And looked in the New York Times and saw
Reams
Reams of ads red identical
Play one-bedroom 341 bedroom
33051 it was all the same I'm thinking how do I
Spend my three-line ad why is it was remember I had $1,000 I provided it by my overhead
And I knew I had seven weeks to stay
According to my map
And so I asked him if he build a half wall
To divide the
Dentistry part of the living room from the L next door
With a double entrance and I told him I thought I could get him 360 a month
What's the weather
20 $25 more than you wanted
Yeah he said he
And I got it for him cuz Maya
1 bedroom and den
For the same price that everybody else was working on one bedroom light.
The first Sunday I must have gotten 60 phone call
And so easily rented that apartment and then got others and got us an adjustable
And you were you were
Basically making a
Mission Beach rental
I made exactly what the
What the
Monthly rental was I when I rented that first apartment I did the the smartest thing in the world knowing I was ahead of the game
Because I collected the commission within a week that's what's beautiful
You have to wait for a sale closing
So I collected that
Check for misophonia
I cached Citibank and I ran right over to Bergdorf Goodman's and I blew it on a new coat
And it was a smartass and I could have
Because I dress like a
A poor kid from it
Nothing was being I just looked not the park
But I thought the fanciest damn code
A brown and white herringbone is real pearl buttons down
Three quarter length
Real fur not fake
And I wore that coat
For the next 3 years
And you want to know it was a smartest thing I could have done with the money cuz in and I felt powerful Joe
I'm cool man I'm a cool girl
Which best college business
I was called Corcoran Simone
With an accent on the Simone I kept the acting so I really thought it was
Pretty sophisticated
All right meniscus cuz Raymond on part of it
Yes
So why you were like why you were going out and working as an agent to rent apartments what was Raven-Symone doing
Ramon Simone
Little flask
I'm Ramon Simone was building one family houses in New Jersey
You should question
Three or four houses in making a very
Good living
And that went on for probably
3 years or so hazard
Call and then one day a week
Drove to his accountants
Office in Hackensack New Jersey
And he had me wait in his car with the car running comes out in
Guess what
I thought it was a joke and I moved immediately out of his fancy apart
I moved into his mother's
Hackensack house
And that was the bed
Your ass where are we
Not undercover but had a
Up from the Earth all over again he did he was a great entrepreneur
I took about 3 years and those were the
The very very
Tough years
But lucky for both of us on the rental business was
Paying for itself and we're able to eat
He got a salary you were running this from your
From from that apartment
No no no no no no I had an office I initially ran
Corcoran Simone
A from an apartment I shared with two roommates
On 86th
But then when I could afford to I subleased a desk from an accountant
On East 60th Street
And by the time we moved into Ramon Simone's mother's house
We still have the office on 60th Street
We already had
I guess maybe 10 or 11 Des occupied by rental
So you were going into
Manhattan everyday
Yes
It was like it was like the Land of Oz you know the minute I stepped foot into Manhattan
I saw for what it was like where have you been all my life
Clown
This is like
The
The violent 90
1870s New York
Minecraft
Son of Sam
What was it like
2 I mean
Is it hard to to get
Tenants to rent
It's crazy to imagine today of course but back then was it
Was it hard
To get people to read
No it's saved my ass in those days
Was you have Corporate America
Very well implanted in Midtown granted
It was dangerous you wouldn't dare Park
Car on the street you know
Gets broken into Sirens were always going off everywhere
So was not easy but fortunately
You had him
Please
Young employees coming into New York City who had to live there working for these corporations
If not for that I don't think I would have stayed in business because I went door-to-door and knocked on all these corporate
Personnel departments to try to get business I saw with the traffic
I was coming from
And I had
Great
I said that
People to me one act
Another after another
And so I had a huge Edge over my other small competitors
Because I had a steady stream of
People coming out
Yeah that was kir I don't think I could have stayed in business
How did you make the transition from renting from looking for renters to
Selling
Really quite by accident
I had gotten a referral of a young engineer from Union Carbide I don't
I called his name and I lined up a whole bunch of stuff
How to show him like I usually did cuz I had to learn by then and sales of
Control someone's time
They can't go to anyone else I would say
I'll pick you up at the Drake Hotel
Snow new name
At 9
And be aware we won't be finished till at least 5:30
Entertain going with
With another brokerage
And then I would tell Midway to I've got everything set up for tomorrow to just control Park them in your garage and don't let the cat
I had this young guy
And I showed him the first two apartments he said well what am I going to see the ones for sale
I said oh no these are Ferengi said no I want to buy something
I was like
So I said well that's X1
So I said I was going to take him on a tour of all New Yorkers was very important for him to learn all the neighborhoods to see what he could choose for
Nike react
2 best
And that the next day we would show him the Sayler Park
Of course I had no
So I got them in a taxi walking around every street showed him every every place in town and then that
Night I went home and I
Hit the Floor running
I dropped them off at
Like 515 as early as I could
Cold every single
Apartment where the owner are which was very common those days and said I have a young engineer he's looking
Exactly four
Your apartment on Sutton Place he's looking for a small tear that read them had back and go but he must see it tomorrow
Yes come on over and I
Book everything that night
And the third apartment we saw he bought the neck
That's what got me in the sale business and when I got back
Commission check in my head was 38500 switch
At 6:12
I can't do the math anymore shame on me but 6% of that
Do you know what I I got that check in my hand on closing and I thought God has given me this to open up a
Apartment I hired two sales agent
Turn that was the birthing of the sales business
And all the while you were still
Let me Ray is still part of this thing you still in your life
Yes Ray was still part of my life
Because that was within the first seven years we stayed together for 7 years
Until he married my secretary
Really like
Like so emotionally
Encouraging
Real up house
He cheated on you
With your secretary
Yes
She was kind of innocent they fell in love I was angry with him but of course directory
Women tend to do
And so when I wanted to fire her
Miss I said I can't come in the office every day and see your fiance they were getting married 3 months is very fast
I'm mortified I was mortified
And and then he moved Tina into our combined office I had to look at them through the glass world
Stupid thing I must been so young at heart to be so injured over some stupid
But here's the thing I said I have two fires and no I'm looking trolling partner
You can fire her he owns half of this company and Nelly owns 51% and
That's how I found out the value of that 1%
That's how it works
Yeah but that didn't last long one year later I I stopped in there finally Built My courage and told him I was sending the business
I said
REI
I'm going to end the business today in this is how it go
We're going to do it like a
14 salespeople you can pick
First I'll pick the second I got a thing
So we each got seven
Like their children in a divorce I didn't know what was happening
And we also had close to $77,000 in receivables which I remember at the time thinking half of
That would get me through month-and-a-half of over
And so
I had the ability
To take my half of the money and start all over
And lucky for me I went to my landlord in our existing building
We were on the 8th floor
And I asked him if I could release another floor we had always
Pay the rent on time and he rented me the 11th floor bar
Havre which I love being above him is not weird I'm sick
I really need a shrink he started he
He start his own company and then you stayed there and renamed it
Poke Simone
His wife's name is Poe
And I moved up to 11
It my seven people I told my Monday would be
Moving in there like
Wow where we moving to I said
It's a surprise
Was wasn't surprised
To me even
But by Monday you could open an office in the
You could buy the
Just John decrepit 42nd street and have those guys asked
Basically run the desktop
You could order a phone which I did on late Friday morning and had installed on Saturday
And by the time they just came in I called him over the weekend gave him the new address with you
They came in that all their stuff in a neat box on top of the new desks like nothing had happened
Here's a question
Is it are you are you just
Sort of
Hardwired as a
Tough person means
I mean mostly the best men pretty
Play Rock right I mean in this the guy that you're with for 7 years
You think you're loving and in the meanwhile
Peas
Well
Hey listen the truth be known I'm not at all hard person
I mean the idea
Ask any woman who's been cheated on any guy
You feel like such a fool and you burn so deeply inside no
I can barely walk
I received estimated by that
It wasn't that I
Even so much lost faith in him
I mean you're allowed
Fall in love
Be real with somebody else
But it was that I fell out of love with me
Myself
I actually thought
My God I was nobody
Before he found me
He got me to believe in myself he put me in business
Eno with my mentor
He's a man of the world
You know and all of a sudden
Keystone off of somebody else
It was like
I'm nobody I never actually questioned
Whether I was capable of any
Until
He insulted me on the way out
What he saying
He said you'll never succeed without me
Weights
He
He was having an affair
And then he rubbed salt in your wounds by saying you're never going to succeed with
Yes
And you know what
Janome remember we live together
Almost seven years I was his business
He may have even been wanting to motivate me knowing that I'm good when I'm insulted and you know I have learned
Was every one of my great successes building the business the ones that were Bellwether changes that I thought water that may
Make a change
There are always a result of an inch
Fuel to your fire says this and you are
I mean obviously
Devastated inside but you
You just think
The greatest revenge is I'm going to
Cruise
Said he's wrong
What wasn't even a Revenge thing honestly it was like I couldn't
Stan the idea that
He might see me fall
Worthy opposite
And you want to know something I got to believe
That was all tied into cuz it injured so deeply
And became my motivation
I have to believe that that was tied into being a dumb kid at school
He was basically damning me to hell
Yeah and that's how I felt in school every
Like I'm a loser you'll go nowhere
And so he hit my hot button
Pusher
And I'm for sure
So did you
From day one when you go to the 11
Inflorescence
Can you start your
Are you thinking
We was he your main competitor was his company the one that you were
I moved off of
I just I was in survival mode
Figuring out the math
Knowing had six a six-week run to stay in business 6 weeks
How much cash
Yeah because I had a bigger overhead by then you know in the beginning with my thousand dollars gave me a little bit longer
This was just one ad per week in the New York Times three lion head
Whatever cost then am I sublease charged
When I move to the 11th floor
I also have 14 desk
But I only had seven age
Problem
And that's a big overhead no no income
Are classified ads were really expensive at that
Well they always were
Going up in price yes so they didn't go very far but you know that was the bloodline of the real estate
Was pretty internet if you wanted to get a leave
You put an ad in the paper
Were you
Freaking out
Kenosha
Actually no I never freaked out about
I never have
Because it is what it is
You know I can't have matter-of-factness
Another word for okay
Give it a shot
If I'm going to fret about oh my God oh my God it's going to get again
Cocky and big head this is no big deal
I'm going to get cocky
So I just kind of okay this is what I got let's see how
Hard and fast I can run
However
I did have one vision
I must admit
Did they open the kor'kron
Group
I remember sitting at that
Desk and paying extra dollar a month for a pink princess phone you pay $2 extra to rent
Was pink
I remember answering a phone sitting there
And thinking
I'm going to
Dean of New York real estate
Barbara Corcoran in a moment how is she
He actually did become the queen
Gyros near listening to how I built this
4mypdr
Hey thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
The business insurance expert to understand
Each business is
As unique as a
Fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent solutions
Every business is very Spa
Pacific need
Explain their 97%
Customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance
Support also comes from wix.com
A web platform for creating your own professional website
With wix
Whether it's your first time
Creating a website
Or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning template
Or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology
And Powerful web features
Join over 100
25 million people already using Wix to create their own website
Gota wilx.com to create yours today
So what will you create
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Barbara story
She may have thought she was going to be the queen of New York real estate but
Who's going to be an uphill battle
She's broken up with her mom
Split everything up
She had a pink princess phone in her new office
And
Figure out how to get more attention for
Company
One of the world's most
Repetitive
I distinctly remember the day
I sat and pause and said to myself
Holy Ship
We are going to be success
What happened
I came up with the idea
I'm taking our
11 sales for the year
We had 11 sales so far whatever time of the year that wasn't dividing by
It's good I was always
11 * 2
And I came up with an average sale
Pricing I typed in one piece of paper
And I named it after myself the Corcoran
Report and it looked lonely one number average apartment price I didn't say
Corcoran group I just put average New York City of
And on the top I put
The quokka
Report
And then I thought it needed something more
The empty and I put
Market I can't remember some long-winded like market report of conditions and Trends in the greater New York City Market area
Nothing to fill up
I mailed it out to everyone wrote for the New York Times
Everyone
And I never heard from the times
At all but about two weeks later
I open up
The real estate section wechat
Portion the main generator that an automobile sex
Buffalo New York
Times before the internet
And I opened it up and the front page read New York City prices
All Time Low
We're in a recession again
And the first line said according to Barbara Court
Present of the Corcoran
Holyshit
Can't believe this
I knew my business was going to be successful
You just made this isn't this amazing
Particular sales numbers
Property
411 Culebra is you divide that decided up and then you said
Hey this is the average price of a Manhattan I didn't really say hi where I put I put
Average New York City
And price and snow that sounds really I could see now from where I sit that is mostly I didn't intend it that way
You know I didn't tend to trim it up with that long
Conditions in Friends
But
You know it was amazing to me
That
The newspaper
Printed my number
Do you like your new added
Newsletter
Yeah but also there were no number
Remember there was there was Dell public data
Of apartment prices in the vacuum
Of no numbers I supplied a number and they wanted to do a story on the bed mark
Can I put a label on
I bet it was right so did you start getting calls
From people who set up
Group
We got instant credit
We called the listings on the
For sale by owner ads
And most of them had heard of us in one day
Well everybody read the time so if you aren't page if you were looking to sell your home your reading the front pages in your
Real estate
Without a doubt
And when they didn't hear of us
My broker started thing
Things like I'm sure you've read about us
Today's times will last week's. That didn't take them long to use it
So we got listings more easily we got credibility more easily and we got more phone calls
All
Claws
We are quoted as
That's it
Wow internet
Presumably that was the first of the carpenter part you even that didn't stop
Sending that
I got it out every three
3 months
And eventually was normalcy credible
Based on thousands of sales you could really trust them
But initially if I had been a big company
And I'd run it by attorneys wedding
Committee decisions it would have never gone out
The Beulah had a little guys I had the freedom to run
70s in New York
A more welcoming place for a woman to
Typically a company or was it still I mean you know you care about that
Menu
He rui women were sort of in a relegated to being secretaries and type business like that
Did you feel like you were
Respected and treated
You know what things
No I never paid attention
I don't give a crap
Really
You know
The whole business was 90% female wasn't like women we're not in the real estate broker's fee
But it just happened that all the firms
Bosses were all men
Okay so yes so they weren't
Female only businesses that I competed with but that was
Was not even important detail what an important detail my mind
Who's that I have for teenager
And the largest company in town at that point Douglas Elliman
Headlight
Maybe 80-90 agents
That seemed to me like
IBM it
Yeah how am I going to compete with them my I was on that bull
How did you know
Barbara
How to even
Run defense I mean I know we're talking now right
Early 1980s and you've been working with Rafe
For few years
You don't have an MBA you don't have formal business backpack
Richmond issues how to deal with how to pay people with battery
Price
It's a I think you make it sound more sophisticated than it is
All you needed to know
Is
How to work with
And that's how the business ever is all the work I do today
It rests entirely any successor
Failure rests entirely on my ability
To work with the people at hand
So learning how to recruit people
I learned
How to recruit
Because I made friends with every store clerk every waitress every stewardess everyone I ever met I made
Friends with cuz I'm very friendly
And if I saw a spark in them
Which Wich said to me sales personality I would say have you ever considered doing real estate sales I recruited
Everywhere
Everywhere I went I recruited
And from what I understand you yourself actually didn't go out
How many minutes
Isil
I sold the engineers first house yet
And then from Merrill Lynch I Got a referral of David
Palmer was a really big wig and I sold him
Chew apartment side-by-side
Eight on the Upper East Side and East 89th
Condominiums
And that was it that was that you didn't sell any
Property I guess you recognize that your talent was not
In
Selling property but in
Managing people
No I was great at renting apartments
However
I realize
But if I reach continue to sell because it's time-consuming to be
Great salesperson
I'm very time-consuming
I realize that if I were to continue doing that
I could only Bill my business on the side and I just took a leap of
Faith especially when I sold David Palmer
2 Apartments side by side
For total value of
Little bit more than 350,000 which today would be
The Killing of Satan
How is a landslide
I took that check I remember collecting it from the developer and 89th Street and walking it to 60th Street in my office was skip
Skipping down Madison Avenue
And seeing Georgie
To myself
I quit that Day sales
And I decided to use that money to hire
Three new cells
Right there I knew I could afford it and then I heard six more and then 10 more
And then before you knew we had a thousand people I don't want to make it sound like it's overnight
But it was just that same methodology whenever I had spare money
I would / an overhead monthly
Figure out how many bodies I could
Afford like a mother paying for the
Kids and then I would go out and hire that many
That's it was a symbol for I never changed it was really very useful
Yeah I'm wondering
Let me sounds like
In the first years there was no
Pirate success but I mean in a short period Of time you must have hit
That the
Read message
Huge
That was a bloodbath
For a good reason
When the economy crashes or even really waivers
Is a terrible thing happens if you're in the real estate brokerage
Is this
Buyers and sellers
Do nothing
Nothing is terrible for brokerage
A big sellers Market is great cuz action
Horrible Market is great
You'll have to sell
But in the beginning when nothing happens you go out of business well what happened was the great majority of my competitors were
The band used to that is it's hard to stay this is a very good news in that
Is I realize
I lost half
That's a motive
What happened to you guys
Oh well
I was really on the brink
Declaring that it was over
But I was ashamed and trying to make back the money I owed
To various suppliers like my Ad Agency the New York Times
But I owed over $300,000
And there was no business coming in
There's No Business know when the market stops
Like the silence yeah it's a terrible terrible the end
You have to remember you have sales people
How many of them
Supporting the family
Who have no money coming that's the worst
Never mind the business
Lots of pressure on
Did you have to let people go
Oh my gosh
I always let people go anyway
But it was interesting I have my mother working for me then
For two years of my life
Because all of her kids are grown and she's working at the 5 and 10
On 215th Street walking across the George Washington Bridge and she's getting older
Send Mommy can't do that you got to come over
She said she was delighted
So she was a file Clerk
Boy did she keep
Color coded
She was a
A genius at that
But anyway when the shit hits the fan
Which is what my mother always
By the way I get it from her my filthy mouth
She came to me
And she knew I had a fire log
Black people
You can just see that
Everybody knew something
She got it was fast and she said
One should probably fire me if you
Fire me
She said no one else could be angry with you
When you fire them and she was right
So at that Monday morning meeting we always had at 9:30 I said
You know I forgot it's no cuz I was surprised how bad things are going to have to make a lot of changes
And it's going to be very hard for me to do with the hardest changeables me firing my mother
LeBron
Really close to going out of business if
If you had to make
Deposition
Well I was going out of
The business
I owe the 300 some 1000 but I came up with a great idea to sell
A burning mendix
Apartments and nobody wanted which is owned by Equitable insurance company he was like a big real estate
That's one of the he until his death about gets 10 years ago
He was the largest developer New York him and Larry Silverstein
Apartments for rent
World Trade Center you know that name
Anyway he asked me to look at 88th Apartments scattered throughout the city and a number of properties and he said I want
Find out from you how you can sell them
I knew every broken china been in to see
There is a dregs of the market that is someone didn't have kitchens Okat Midstream when the market collapsed
So they were in a c-rated buildings
Everything was wrong with it
Anyway I went I visit maybe 8 or 9 of the apartments
Through the super is in right away
They were dumps they could not be so we need a market to sell my desk
We had no Market
So anyway I went back and I told him there was no way to sell it except the public auction
Do you want to do a public auction you said it
We can't go public auction we don't want the publicity of
A failure
And I saw the snow with a way you can sell these
And I'll never forget what he said he said Barbie you're a smart girl you'll figure it out
And I went back and thought about it and write in my head
Came
A memory of my mom taking like seven or eight of us however many would warn them down to
Toms River New Jersey watching a puppy sale with the Farmer Lane
Christmas tree
For my grandpa's
And my mother status on the grass and watched all these fancy New Yorkers arguing over
The puppies are little Jack Russell
He's really cute
And anyway my mother said to us
Look at all these fancy
See people do you know why they will want those puppies
Because Lewis was smart enough to invite them all here at the same time
And so that popped in my head
And I went back to Bernie mendik the next day at a time
Plant
Ameriprise
All the apartments alike
Same price
Well I pray all the one bed
Like a $10,000 difference
Between
But somewhere on 22nd floors with Gorgeous views somewhere on the third floor with no kitchen they was so on TV
First-come first-served have a secret sale we're not going to advertise it
I'll not sick to my salespeople me let them bring the best customers
But I need you to give me two years free maintenance you're not going to unload these two years anyway
Maintenance is like a association fees monthly maintenance
Erase the terrible maintenance and they had nobody thinks Beyond two years
And price in the mall like it's going to create hype.
And so he said okay give it a whirl
And I said we had a secret
All to myself
Closing the business that's how close we were both unconscionable
What pressure is a wonderful thing in life
Makes you think
And so I now to to my people as a but get there early
Don't bring too many people just a family member if you want and you're single best cuss words don't bring don't spread it around weed
Don't have enough to go around
And I'm telling you a ride and 80
The first tree where we had that makeshift
Office that morning at 7 a.m.
And we had a line of 60 people waiting
Casitas
To see those apartments
And I'm chilling hour and a half later more than $1000000
And I closed it was a closing
They sign the contract
Is like a fire sale
People happy they got the deal of the century
Yeah I bet they're really happy today but not as happy as I
Was that day cuz I went from being
New desperation of being filthy rich in real estate
Chelsea rich
You got it I went right out and I rented myself
Full floor at 660 Madison Avenue cuz I had the cash to do it
And it's like everything I've heard about you people say you know Barbara Has Talent wasn't
About selling homes
The marketing she was
Credible
Marketer is that apps absolute
Italy right where did you is it just an instinct
Is it just trial-and-error is it is it just being
You know kind of Hustler
Oh no I think it has more to do with
A creativity
I saw a black and white game marketing
It's a the softer side of things right
It involves exaggeration
Involves
Acumen for seeing what a storyline is or what would
Capture people's interest in
It definitely includes
PeopleSmart
And you know what I actually started realizing I was best when things are bad because I would go into any bed real
Real estate cycle in se
Say 15 position pecking order within the industry
And I would come out of it nice position cuz a lot of people got knocked out
You decide
I guess in
Mm mm M mm
To sell the car
Get out
Yes
Why did you decide to sell it and you love the game you love that
Steel energy in that
Like pressure so why did you
Two things happened when I had my first baby at 46 I gave birth to my son Tommy after 8 years of envy
That was nothing short of a miracle something I desperately wanted if I
Once I had that child
My heart chain
And it played out my heart everyday I was home and my grand old age nursing my son and feeling guilty about it
Because my kids heads at work or whisper
And so it took me about 4 years and then I'm
Wonderful thing happened when he
Astronaut were doing the Corcoran report numbers are
Yes Esther my business
We're doing the Corcoran report numbers one night because hours
Because we wanted to have accurate numbers or verb
I don't know why my first
Report had no accurate
It was just on
By then we're very respectable and making sure all their numbers are
And we also did monthly
Port of who control the market share on listings buses was no mls in New York
Destihl menu
Multiple listing service that showed you
You who had what listing
Like if you could just go to one
Place to see
See all the listing
No
And we broke the market
Enterprise categories in Easton Westside uptown
Downtown
So we had those category
And we would go through the listing
Together
And she'd say
575 / west side
Distraught
How to categorize
Buy all the top agencies in town the top set
And then that night
We did all the ad up and we could clearly see that Corcoran was no
We had more listings in every category
The highest to the lowest Uptown downtown east or west
Smidgen over Brown Harris Douglas Elliman
And I turn to ask Jonathan let's sell this Joy
Big bottle
Also
To be a fair
It was the first year
That I
He had made over million dollar
Myself
And I figured
It's probably worth something
You sold it for 66 million dollars
Because I remember being on a ski lift
Is my roofer brother John who still lives in Edgewater
We are out in Utah I think I'm going up a chair lift and I get on my cell phone call from my attorney who said I've got great news
He said I have an offer
3 million dollars are you seated
Acetone 23000000
Dollar Tree does yep
One piece
$3000000 all-cash
And I said
Great comeback when you get 66
Cash and he said
Y 66 million
Because it's worth it
And I hung up
And I said to my brother
23 million think of that John Maginot 723
Anyssa but why'd you say 66 at the Opus that's my lucky number
And would you bake those that those accountant kill themselves to try to figure out why 66
It was until the closing
That's great satisfaction tell him a whole bunch of hell with my lucky number
It was approved
Did you want when you sold the company did you
Did you
Regret it
I would have to answer that honestly on some level yes and in
I'm more important level
A knot
I felt enormous sense of freedom
To be a phenomenal mother
And so that was exactly what I wanted and I had the enormous satisfaction
Of knowing I had
Become the queen of New York real estate
And financially now
Set for life
Yes
But I never understood
How much I loved
The people I work with and how much that
Teen meant to me
It was my lifeblood
I found them
Routed them train them live with them
Got into Good Times bad times
Times ahead sales managers 11 of
That I'd ordinator toward me we were such a tight
And I felt
Happily lonely
And I really thought I was going to get depressed and probably need to shrink
Because I really didn't know what to do with myself
Yearned
For good morning Barbie good morning flower good morning Barbara
And all the hoopla that went
With being somebody in a business it was
Who's gone so that part
Adult
Baidu
What did I do to myself
Until of course I
I don't want to say reinvented
Myself
Starting all over again and trying to
Build a new career
That's that's the same way
Because obviously you did
Go on an envelope second career most people listening to this
Would know you as as one of the sharks on Shark Tank not as the head of the Corcoran group
Do you wait when you're on that show DUI
It seems like you have a bias
Star people who
You know who have someone back
To come from now
Money
I'm very fine
They have a much better shot at succeed
Why
Lottery
The Mosasaurus
They've never had the fancy fake
Vacation
The delicious new car
The
The private schools the higher education of minions
And they aspired to it
So they get more satisfaction out of
Climbing that ladder in getting to
End
Are they
Hasina parents struggle
Through life to give them whatever they've given them the more appreciative they don't take things for granted
And you know what else
Which I should have started with it totally free
From expectation
Do you know
How
How lucky I was
To never
For a second
Ever think I wonder what my parents think
Well it was was just let's see how far I could go I had nothing to lose and nowhere to go but up to you have a friend that is to take risks so that
Did not risk of arson
And you strive
So I really am biased I'm not saying that you can succeed I mean God willing I have
I have privilege children
Can I hope they'll succeed
It's much harder for me
Not to let them feel my success even if I don't say a word
And so they're not as free as I was you know God bless them
Thomas Hardy
Keith deal I mean when you were a kid you were told that you are smart
Do you feel now
But you've convinced yourself that you are far
Well yes or no
I'm certainly Street Smart
I'm certainly
PeopleSmart
I have
Instinct
When trouble is brewing
Where's the best accountants in the world way to the wall
Should I trust my math instinct
I think I'm a smart person for sure
More than that
I think I'm going to normalcy hard-working
And I have great Confidence from my ability to work
Hard to do anything
And I think I'm very good
At not feeling sorry for
And I think that's a boy
How much of your of your success do you think
Is is because of
Just
Skill intelligent hard-working and how much it is luck
Well I do believe in luck I've had many
Many many lucky
Brakes including meeting Ramon at the diner then
Yeah or the very good luck of having my parents as parents
Not bad right
Once you grow up
Are you make your own
Definitely make
I think all the lucky breaks I had were more result in me staying in the game
I just believing something would break
Just hanging around
That's more important than luck in my
Being aggressive at every opportunity
And standing up for yourself yes more important than
Barbara Corcoran by the way she was in
Initially rejected for a spot on Shark Tank
They went with a younger woman
To Barbara wrote a letter to the producer
I said
I consider your rejection a lucky charm
Because everything that ever happened in my life
Came on the heels of failure
The next day
He called her
Said he reconsidered and
Know what happened
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the
The things you're built
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Pitney Bowes
Pitney Bowes provides
Technology
It helps retailers tourney Us online businesses
Global one
Today our Global e-commerce solution
Enable retailers to
Excel online
In 200
20 countries and territories
Pitney Bowes
Craftsman
Commerce
Visit pitney-bowes. Com
Craftsman
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I know for how you
Who built that
And this one comes from Arielle Rivera he lives in Weston Florida and about 10 years ago are y'all found himself
Scrambling at the last minute to buy something thoughtful for his girlfriend's birthday
Well that's very good foods just I think like a box of chocolate just some random get that I'd given her
So a box of chocolates not super creative right but are y'all actually is creative infected
Designer so you thought maybe I'll at least do something cool with the wrapping paper I think I had my picture just
On my computer
And I just flipped out the head really quick and I I decided to just repeater on a piece of paper with a funny background
So he duplicated his face
15 times and then he Photoshop them onto a backdrop
Like a Cheesy yellow Starburst pattern design onto plain paper
Wrap the chocolate and then he handed the gift to his girlfriend Vanessa and
Reaction oh my God this is hilarious what did you do and why is your face on this
It was so funny and clearly it worked because it's three years later Vanessa and Arielle.
She also happens to be a graphic designer and now again
They would do the same thing that would make
Wrapping paper for friends and family and put
Their faces on it
And just about every time we give to somebody that I used to start a business out of this you should
You should make a website you should make website
So eventually
Ariel and Vanessa did
Just that
And at first it was it was tough because we are not web designer
Tina I mean now I guess we are
But after some trial-and-error they started the website and then they named their business giftwrapmyface so
You upload a photo
They duplicated and print dozens of your tiny little faces onto whatever image you choose we have
Have the statue of David
The Mona Lisa the cupid
Bride and groom we have Vanessa launched a few years ago
I got a few hundred orders at first
And about a year-and-a-half later
Oprah featured the wrapping paper in her magazine
When you finally hitting BC over holding our paper in the I think she was in her kitchen holding up
A box that's wrapped in our paper which I know that I printed for her
It was wild
It was really wild
And thanks in part to Oprah
Arielle and Vanessa sold about 5000 orders of wrapping paper last
You're not enough to pay
Pay themselves just yet
So they're still keeping their day jobs as graphic designers
Right now they've got two printers they're still working out of the garage and also
Raising two kids
So it's either talking about the business or talk about the kids
That's Vanessa klaviyo and Ariel Rivera of West
Destin Florida
More about their company giftwrapmyface
Head to our Facebook page
And of course if you have a story about something your building
Please tell us about it go to build. Npr.org
Hey thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episode
You can go to how I built this.
Npr.org please also
Scribe to the show if you haven't already
Your iTunes or however you get your podcast
You can also write to us that's HIV tea at NPR. Org
And you can send us a
Tweet is at how I built this our shows produced this week by run. Bill fata
Original music composed by run timeout of Louis
Thanks also to neva grandson of Mexican floor and Jim Rogers AR intern is Claire brain on gyro
Arise even listening to how I built this from NPR
Hi it's Rachel Martin NPR news
Anal
We're doing something new
And we want you to be part of it it's called up first
It's the Morning News podcast
From NPR
It's a way for you in about 10 minutes
To get up to speed on the news of any given day the most important stories
The biggest ideas
It's the stuff you need to know as
As you go through your day
Up first
You can get it at NPR one
Or anywhere you live
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week