This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this kiss
Who understands every small business is uni
Impaler's its policies
State your business is very specific
Get a quote or purchase a policy
At h i s c o x.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Peyton wants to sing before we start to show
I'ma want to let you know that we are heading to the West
Post the summer to do to live shows which
Super excited about the first one is in sand
Francisco on August
Second
I'll be talking with the co-founders of Reddit Alexis
Auntie Anne's
Hoffman
And if you're in Seattle on September 14th
Save the date because of
I'll be talking with Starbucks founder Howard Schultz
You want to find out more about how I built this
This Live Events
NPR presents
I had read a lot of
Literature about women entrepreneurs and I had learned the statistic that only
2% of all women owned businesses ever break $1000000 Revenue
Yes isn't that frightening but I'd sit myself that goal so
So I just did rot once I get to a million in Revenue I've done something that most
Women entrepreneurs
Unable to do
From NPR how I built this
Show
Entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movement
They built
Australian mother search for the right blankie for her newborn
And when she couldn't find it
Tri Delta baby blanket company
I'm making a hundred million dollars
A year
So back in 2013
You might remember the birth of a
Brand new royal baby
The heir to the British throne
Duchess of Cambridge has been delivered of a son
I was looking at these pictures from Buckingham Palace
Day after he was born
Mom and Dad sit outside st. Mary's Hospital in Paddington and introduced Prince George
To the world
Going to give her lungs are not Patrol Big Boys by heavy
And as the camera zoomed in on baby George
You could
Make out
He was wrapped up in a white
Cotton swaddle
Printed with
Baby cartoon birds
A little internet's losing people track down the maker of that swaddle
Aden & Anais
It's a baby product company that sells swaddle blankets for about 15 bucks
Recipes
Of course the effect was instantaneous within 4 hours
The company's website crash
And then
Crash together next day
And for Aiden today's co-founder
It was a pretty big shock because
The company was barely seven years old
An over that seven-year.
Aiden and the Nae had been through a lot of UPS
Some doubts
Starting with the recession in 2008
And then eventually
Traumatic breakup between Reagan and her business partner that threatened to dissolve the entire company
A company by the way with yearly Revenue now over a hundred million dollars
How did she create a company Aiden anime
Well the Story begins when Reagan and her husband Marcos moved from Sydney Australia to New York in
After he got a job
Breaking up a time
She didn't really have any plans
I came here without a job without a work
These are
And I thought you know what I'll do
Teased off all fluids
Spanish quiz my house
Husbands Chilean
And I'll fill my time that way
2 years instead of traded is just
You know
A new and different Journey rather than being in a hundred miles an hour with my working my study
And that didn't kind of workouts
About four months in
My husband initially was working
From home because
You know that were released
Things out from the
Ground
Here in New York
Anda
He walked into the living room and I was lying on the couch living in my pajamas you know
And he just said to me
What the hell are you doing come on you got to go to get up and shake this off and
Find something to do we would you were getting depressed cuz you were bored I don't know that always.
Depressed I just I didn't know anybody in New York and
I just sort of
Fell into a rock
I think an eye
Underestimated
How
Much I needed
To be the person that
You know I had a very
Full
Schedule
So rather than using the downtime
Productively RJ
Use the downtime to lay on the couch and
Watch
Morning talk shows
Yeah that does sound
It was it was horrible
Eventually Regan's Visa did come through so she could start working and the year she landed a job as a
Sales rep
For The Economist magazine that I was really good at it
You know the wonderful thing with Stiles is you live and die by the number that you are told to his
And I was very
Fortunate that I never didn't hit the numbers did you like it did you have fun I did
Fun I
Did I loved it was it was
Was it my passion
Slightly North
And I was very frustrated that
Wasn't really taken seriously in terms of
Being able to vape
Promoted and everything I was very much said have kept in my
Box of what I had always done over differ
An Aries
If the business over 10 years
But that was
That was a huge frustration to me that
It was obvious I was never really going to
Go anywhere within the economist
Did you like what you dreaming of leaving
And starting your own thing
I wasn't going to leave
Is it for another job
I think I have always being an entrepreneur I never
Defined myself
Is that there was always a desire for me to do something
On my own
I just never had that had an idea I've had lots
Spidey's but none that I felt
Wilwood
So if you know diving in the deep end
Informing at some point
You got an idea TV idea that would become aden in an a
What's
Well I had my first of my four daughters
That's what happened
I was pregnant with an A and always
You know you're getting ready as we all do when we are having outfits baby with all the paraphernalia that you think you need
And I went out looking for these muslin blankets that were
Extremely common
Back time in Australia so common that
You could buy them in
Uno supermarket
It was mind-blowing to me when I went looking for them in the US
But they didn't actually exist you couldn't find the end I guess just to explain.
To somebody who doesn't know what
Muslin blankets
It's sort of like a really soft
Cheesecloth
Yes it's it's like a goal is
And dumb
Not only was it
In my opinion and still in my pee
Canyon
The only thing you should wrap your baby in because
It's lightweight and breathable and big enough to be able to
Securely swaddle the baby
It was the fact that this one blanket
Did multiple things
You could use it as a
Fitbit clock
Can use it as a portable crib sheet
Could use it as a nursing cover
You could use it as a stroller cover you could
Yeah you just use it to
Mopop
The message that
You know any available when you have newborn babies
Is that sort of thing so
And the thing with muslin is the more you wash it the softer it gets
So in Australia this is
Normal life
All babies
Trapped in these babies cotton muslin
Bratz
Yes
So that was
You know it and I
Just thought
Every every Australian can't have this wrong and if I introduced
Product
To American parents
I was just
Absolutely 100% certain that they would respond to it the same way as I saw these
So you
Presumably took leave at Wacker and I was born
And then went back to the economist
Yes
I had
3 months
End
And did you go back to the economist
India turning in your head
And how do you then
Start to
Make this a reality what it was the first thing you do
Well
I had no
Supply chain or operational
You know experience or knowledge, styles
Ngoi Sao
I had to
Find out how I would even go about making this stuff
And that took a long time
So
Had the idea in mm
3 when I was born
At at 2
It took 2 2006
Work out how
To make it and and get it to Market
So did you start this process all by yourself
No I had to I had a partner
The one person that my husband knew
Australia
He's best friend
Girlfriend Gloria
Who ended up marrying in America
Can guy and that was the
The first person I met here
Employer is
Aiden's mom she was the other co-founder of Aiden and Danae
Wow
So you guys got together and she agreed she said that this is crazy that you can
Well she had Aiden
About 7 or 8 months after I had a night
So I had been in Australia and I was
Coming back
From Australia and I would
Stop
And hang out with Claudia
And mock her husband
In LA to break up the
Trip and I distinctly remember sitting on Aiden
Nursery
Flow
And
I just did to a weenie
We need to do this Claudia live
Yeah we need to find a way to my
Happen
She actually said what why don't we just try and become a distributor for the company that already makes it
Hialeah
Alright
And I said well why would you do that I said and I want it to be
Better than what
Is already available in Australia
And I I remember seeing a week
You can call the company Aiden and Danae off
Did the baby
And that was sort of how it old
Got started
All right just like
A logistical question
Cuz you kind of had a growing sense of
How to make
Start a business
What about the design side of it I mean
Did you have
Were you going to design
The blankets were you going to design the patterns in the
And the shapes are on them
That's a great question
Because I am not
The mice.
Person actually
Jeremiah.
Skills. Guy Beyond
Stick people I really can't draw to save my life
But I am
Very opinionated and I have a very
Provision of
What I like
Aesthetically
Json
Effective and I am
So Taipei
You know that
I was very much
I want these colors I want these images I want it
To look like you know and we
Cody and I hired you know outside
Freelance design
People
How to come up with our initial designs that
It launched the first product
So where did you find
The manufacturing facility how did you find somebody who
Who can make these Muslim
Cotton blanket
This is actually an inch
Story guy because
I was standing at the river
Reception desk
At at The Economist
And the mail arrived
Epistemology
Women's wear daily
Magazine
So I'm sleeping through this
Indonesia
Who paid Judas
An Asian
Text dolls
Sourcing
Trade show that was happening
In New York
City
3 days
Elijah
So obviously I'll wait
To that trade show
And
I walked the entire trade show with probably
4C vendors and then
I got to
Mitch Leigh the last
Venda
Before I was about to walk out
And I woke driver and I
I'm trying to
Someone that can make this
Fabric
Blow me
Gold muslin
He said I have no idea what
But I would
Drum major
Manufacturing company
It in China
Let me type this
Back
And see what I say and
Two weeks later I got it
An email saying we
Can make this for you and that was it
Show
It was literally the last
Boosie went to
Absolutely true
Story I was
Out the door by 1 booth
And they ended up
Becoming my menu
Affect heuristic
10 years
Unbelievable
So when they they sent you the first sample
Debate do they get it right right away
No
A myriad of backing
Enforce in terms of getting the quality to where I wanted it and
I am not
Textiles technical person I have no idea I understand the basic
6 now having beignet
Assignment to use that
I couldn't tell them the grade of cotton I couldn't tell them the warp and weft
Counts I could
Couldn't tell them anything I just basic
He said
Make it like this but I need it
To be softer and then I worked
Fit the factories over the years on
The way to wash it and what
Put in the wash to make it
Soft and obviously his mom
I wouldn't
You'd let them use anything that was in any way
You know they used to use formaldehyde and dies on a baby but that that stuff
Play my mind so obvious
Display
That was very important to me that there was none of that in any Iden & I products
Send it was a long and laborious
Process
A hell of a lot of
Failures along the way with
We had food containers
Product it
When I arrived in the US
The fabric and turn yellow is so that you know there's so many stories about
The trials and tribulations of actually
Perfecting the fabrication
Would you
Still working at The Economist
The point yes
I stayed working at The Economist
Until May of 2009
Sorry did you tell your colleagues about it they find out not
Nobody knew
Were you keeping it secret cuz you
Did my didn't want anybody
Looking
Questioning
I go back to
I was just South post and I never ever didn't make my budget
I didn't want to walk out that door
And then have tableside will it's all good and well that she's
Created this business but it was the ethics
Spencer's
The economy
Yeah right
At this point I guess 2006
Nae Nae is
At 3 and then
Did you have another child by that point I actually had
Three is Michael Jordan's by that point
Okay so you are still working
Full-time at The Economist
Simply flying back and forth to LA to work with Claudia on the side business
And you were also raising three kids and cabbage make all of this war
It was really really hard
It was a conscious decision that I made
So
When I got home from I used to call The Economist my real job and I got home from the reboot
I was
Well
In Mommy Mode and I focused on my girls and then when the girls went
Bed
At 8:30
That's when I would stop my day of working on Aiden and an A and I would do that until you noticed
Free City
Every morning well
And because it was a conscious decision on my part I should have never
I just never really
Complained about it it was what it was
So it's 2006 you have your free make your first big
Order
How many what was that order like
What do you remember
Well
We started we both started
Putting $15,000 in traffic
Tori and
And that we
We did the minimum we had a boy pack a go pack
Wattpad
Towel and washcloth
And nausea
Just went door-to-door
In
LA and New York
To every baby store to every you know I
I picked up the phone I called Buy Buy Baby
Yeah that that was
The child school coming out in me and actually jumping ahead a bit
A year later the target fire calls made
Called me and said can you come in
I took in Universe excuse thinking they might take 102 and how much is a SKU
Who is like one full pack so
I presented sticks for packs thinking they might take
One boy and one girl and Target
Kohl's
Wow and roll it out into Old Target
Stores from Taiwan
Once you got orders for
Police big hump
I mean you had to then make the order
With a factory in China and I guess
He's a money how did you fund
We
Initially it was
Wedowee
Savings
And end
The money part of it was actually
What brought about the demise of
What are your my partnership I don't know if you want me to talk about that that I can because you know the pot that thing is
As always
Will often a story with Entre
Sopranos right now
Kodi remote for very wealthy
Marco's 9 not so much she know we were doing fine but we didn't
Have
You know millions of
So
Marcus and I kept up
At Freddy's long as we could met you know we put in
15000 and we put in another
30 then we put in another 48 you know that and we kept up as long as we could until we got to a point where
We couldn't keep up anymore
There was no access to Capital you know we started the business
Did the beginning of the worst
Recession
Great Depression
Cody said we just need
To borrow money off
United Moc and and his family which I absolutely did not want to do it with
Last Resort
But it got to the point I think we borrowed
100000 off career and Mark and then we borrowed another 200
Mark's dad
And very long story short
It was more marketing that was just
Not comfortable with the fact that in his mind they were funding the business
And
It just got
It just got to the point where you know I go to De mando
You've got 30 days to come up with this
Bios sad if you can't do that we have the right to
Pay you the same and if we can come to an agreement
We going to dissolve it
When we come back in the moment
How Riggins company and
Friendship with Claudia
Changed forever
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
Ron NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
What's your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini the regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Welcome back to how I built this
NPR
And I Rise
So when Reagan's friend and business partner Claudia
Told her she
Wanted out of Aiden anime
Reagan and figure out how to hold on to the company
When claudere exited the business in mm
A very early 2000
And
It was
It was me
It was just me alone doing all the work I was
Sales
Customer service Manufacturing
Near marketing Finance
Set my husband was helping with the finance side of
So
I hide one person to at least alleviate some of the work that I was
Having to. Doing it
8:39 at night once my girls went to bed because that was also
Illini
J very deeply in the sand
To myself
These little girls
Did not sign on for me
Free entrepreneurial mother
But I did believe in the business
And
I went out to
A few
Of my other friends who were watching what I was
Doing to raise the few hundred thousand
Dollars that
Laurdiy
You know wanted
For another work that she put into the Beast
The star Spa
Fire route
To buy her out so
Three other people came into the business
+ 4
49% of the business for like
Well
This is a really important story because
We don't get to hear the story 2 off
Talking about
Set the reality of of starting a business with a partner we're at the beginning it
Their suspicion of a favicon
Utopian
Business and there are Partnerships that
It really works
IPhone X cases
Small like this where
Money gets involved in
Tension builds in
Can people get nervous about
Investment and you can kind of understand what Claudia and Mark were coming and you could I mean
I mean they were getting nervous they're worth a lot of money in the
But I mean
I have to imagine that it had
What's the toll on your friendship
Who is she never spoke
To me again
Cuz I just responded and said clothes what are you doing breaking my heart here we can talk through this year
I was legal guardian
Children that tell lies
And dumb
It was horrible
But he's horrible that you know it was
I wanted to talk to her she just in her mind it was also very looking at
I get it she was under the pressure of
The family and it was her marriage and all of those things so I don't I don't know I'm just
And Wyatt have
Yeah it was just dumb
It was just heartbreaking that it did
Did you
Did you think that the business was going to clap
I never thought that I
I thought I might collapse
Of i n I questioned whether or not I
Keep going because obviously it was Nick
Extremely emotional time in
But no eyes
I've never ever doubted Aiden and Danae
Was there any tension in your marriage of Marcos
Fully supportive he was the one who actually
When I started to
To get a bit shaky
Through the hole
Drama with Claudia
And I said to him look I don't know if I can do this
And he said to me
Do you believe in the business and I said I absolutely believe in the business
He said well then fight for it don't give up fight for it
Have you ever
Claudia Center
Is The Break-Up absolutely none
Unfortunately the friendship was
Very much a casualty of
Of the business
But she must know
Where the company has
Has curse her child's name is I know
People ask me why I didn't change the name and I
That's why I still refer to myself as
The car sound
Even though
I Claudius been gone
Forever
I co-founded this
Business
So I did
Didn't feel right to me to just
Soto
Hot her out
Story
So so you buy out Claudius year will I die
Get new tires part of do and you
And you move on you you continue to grow this business believing that this is going to work
And at what point were you finally able to leave The Economist
What was the the Milestone you hit in the company that made you comfortable that you could
Focus full-time on this day
Well I had read a lot of
Literature about women on
Hypno's
I had to learn the statistic that
Only
2% of all women irons
Businesses
Ever
Break a million dollar revenues
Yes isn't that frightening the shocking a
So that I'd sit myself that goal
So I just did rot
Once I get to a million in Revenue I've done
Something that most
Women entrepreneurs
Unable to
To do
So at that point I allowed myself to
Quit and focus on I-10 and iPhone
When you
Finally when you leave the economist
I'm assuming you told them
No you didn't
No I didn't I just said I've got another opportunity and
His my two weeks notice
And
My then-boss to I wasn't a huge fan of
I was having a discussion
And I think Lee remember it was about a week
Before I was
I handed in my resignation so I knew
Coming
And I sat in his office and he said to me oh what would you know you do not have an entrepreneurial burn in your
And then he's he's even this story gets even better that far
Ended up working at
Crying
And we have won multiple Awards with crying
As
The Fosters
One of the fastest
50 growing
Spring aerial business
New York
I mean to do experiences like that with your boss
Do they add fuel to your fire are they
Powerful motivators for you
I do know what my biggest motivation
Always was
Guyana
Never about making a lot of money
Mine was very much
Proving to myself I could
Could do it
Because I had been told by many people over the years
That I was only capable of
When in my heart of hearts
I always
Thought I was capable of why
But I was
Just never afforded the opportunity to prove it
Okay so so by 2009
You you leave Economist and then
I guess you your profitable by the way what what is your Revenue
We closed
2009 at
Just drive
4 million
So as soon as I focus
You know a hundred percent
Change the game
And then we
We more than doubled every year
Obvious off to that
I guess I guess it was around 2010 where you took on some outside
Investment that's correct I took out my first private Equity Firm in 20
Why did you do that to me up until this point you are
The majority
I want her you know you're doing well for a million Revenue would that enable you guys
To do what
Descale
So it gave me
Send money to
To be able to highest
The mole people buy more inventory cuz we would literally be
You are the code team it was about eight of us nine of us
And we would be sitting there light at night going okay well we need weed
We do our inventory planning
We say okay well we need this
And then we look at it guy what we can only afford
And we just have to cut half of
What we really needed
We could never keep up with the demands
So when need private Equity sometime in it just allowed us
To be able to get
Even today I can't keep up with
Bet it
It enabled us to get closer
To it at Lake
Respect
I know that I'm like at a certain point celebrities started to
Like Us Weekly like that it just like us they swallow their babies except the swaddle
Swaddle blankets
When did you start to see celebrities using
The blankets
One week after we went on the market when I say wait on the market
May walking the product to the stores and handing it
To the store rhinos in LA
Adam Sandler and his wife who just had a baby with photographed on Malibu Beach
With a baby in a carrier with an Aiden and a blanket draped over the front of the baby and it was a fool
Page picture in Oswego police so we had celebrity press
From a week after we went on the market did anybody know what the blanket was
We actually named 2Pac Paparazzi wants
So this is a Note 2
How many photographers photograph Al blankets with the
Celebrities trying to
Hide a baby's away
Back in in 2013
Prince William and Kate Middleton
Call Linda
The Duke and Duchess of Cambridge
They had a baby Prince George
The leave the hospital and what did you what did you say
They left the hospital in an Aiden and Anais blanket which blew my mind having been raised in
Australia
Because that I would have bet every penny I had on the fact that we
Was never going to happen
Because there's Royal protocol and no royal baby is have it come out in any
Anything other than
White wool blanket that is being royally appointed
Family you know
And lo and behold I walk out in
Aiden and I in the world goes
Wild and so did sales go crazy
Yes you know the typical reaction the Royal effect website
Crash twice
We sold out of that around the world people will coveting it
To the point without paying
Three times the value of this
It was inside outside
Guys we've got other
Patent over here if the time that they owe just wanted
What the royal baby
What was the pattern that
It was interesting Lee
It was from a PATCO jungle Jam which was
The third path
I ever released
So that particular
Design
Had been on the market
AES
When the royal baby
These are not like super crazy expensive 4 pack
I will now it's 4990
5 when I started it was
$44 and that was always
I never
Set out to build
A luxurious
Celebrity you know indoors
Brand
I wanted to create
And make all the mothers away
Of this amazing product it as a
The mother IG
Just didn't understand how they
Have baby
He's without it
When you arms
Around I guess around 2000
Thirteen you guys
You guys got a big
That's correct
Swander Pace capital
Into the end
And they became the majority
Shareholders
Now and I deny however I
Still Remains
The single largest individual shareholder in the
So explain how this works they they bought
A big share of the company
But that allowed you to
Cash out some of some of the value of the company that's correct I bought they both
The whole camp
What I did was brought back in as a major shareholder in
The company I mean so in a sense that
I guess that made you
Set financially for the rest of your life
Baby blankets have
Just boarded my
Family
An incredibly
Wonderful Life
And you're still the CEO
I am
Pretty incredible
Result
Yes
It is
Although what I will tell you guy is
I much prefer and I believe I'm much fish oil
At
The entrepreneurial
Building as a company now that we're over a hundred million dollars
It's just very different you know obviously the way you run a hundred million dollar company to the way you
Piranha
You know it 20 or even if 30-40 million dollar company
Yeah you can get by with running your business on it
Excel spreadsheet
30 million
It doesn't
Can cut it a hundred
30 million I was still very much involved
A lot of
What's the date today
Where is now at this size oh my gosh there is so much that
You know I'm only getting updates once a week I'm just
Not involved in
Winnetka news
Why anymore
So I definitely do not enjoy this
As much as I did when I was much more
In the waves of the
And I am
You know I am missed that
Given that you got this
Big payout do you ever think
I don't like
Stop
Working and just take up a
A hottie or do something
Completely different for a while
Well
It's
I could never be the lady that lunch
Just not let you remember back to the story of May on the
Couch too much time is nautical
Interesting Lee I was talking to my old
Just order an ID of the night
What do you think baby is
You know
Mom stop being the CEO of Aden & Anais
Yeah I could spend more time and then she's like please. Mom
How come I'm good with food with the amount of time that we have you around
Zoloft High
At bedtime
Not only do I see
Think that
It would be good to me that if I maybe wasn't
The CEOs
Business it might be good for the business
To bring in somebody who is run a business
50 size and
The scaled from
300 because I really believe that that
Which way this brand is going in
Do I think I could do it I know I could
Could do it
That I would do it make
Hell of a lot more mistakes
It's in somebody who is
Season 2 a
Down at the
I'm at
I'm a self-taught
Ciy move
I've never run a hundred million dollar business
This before child is she one more hundred million dollars
There are people out there though he was done that
Many many years and have a proven track record that
Let you know that
Would probably do a much better job of it
Then
Then I do end
And selfishly
Being the mom is full little girls
My voice
Not made
Would be
In
Time when I am sitting at a bar with my for girls as
As
Adult women
Not being able to turn to Aden & Anais
Company in the Brandon say hey your mom did that
When you would tiny babies
At our kitchen table and
Now look at it it so you know
A half a billion dollar Global brand
So that's my
That's my ultimate goal for
The house
This story is going to play out
Raegan moya-jones she's the CEO and co-founder of Aden and an a by the way a few months ago
Post ran a story called 52 things I learned in 52 weeks of parenting
And number one on the list was
That nobody can
Pronounce Aiden and I
So you kind of know you've made it as brand when you're number one on the list and a half
Pechino article on motherboard
Instagram because in just a moment
Hear from you of
Things your build
The first thanks to one of our sponsors
TD Ameritrade
TD Ameritrade is always ready to listen
Have a conversation about your goals
Complimentary goal planning session
Discuss your financial
Future visit
Tdameritrade.com
Splash Park
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that story comes to us from Shenzhen
My name is Sam Boyd and I'm the founder of guided Imports
Incept
A lot of times we do interviews
People on the show who invent something and then build a prototype and then they
They find a factory in China to make it
And Sam
He is the guy
In China who finds a factory
Elvis started about 5 years ago when he
He was in college and studying Chinese
And one day at a restaurant
Two locals walk up to him
We started talking and now they did they see a foreigner in this small City and they want they want to know what's what's going on what is he doing here
And I asked what they do and you know it sort of led to them talking about their Factory in them asking me do know anyone who's in
Interested in purchasing our products
And I said yeah sure I don't really know anyone but I'm going to find someone for you
Okay but the product these two guys were talking about pretty specific you were talking about sterilized
Best Packaging
Like the kind of thing you might use for medical equipment
And Sam
Didn't have a clue how to find buyers for
Something like that
But it didn't really matter because
After that conversation in the restaurant
He saw Ann Arbor
China is incredible in terms of it being such an entrepreneurial location
And
Fortunate enough to
Have a western education having grown up in America
I said I can be doing this
And by this he was thinking
I can be the middle that I can be there
Person between people in the west who want to sell consumer goods
And Chinese factories that want to make them
So learn more about how all this work
Temperature of a company in Shenzhen that makes
Electronic gadgets
And when I saw how things working it I really just explain it as my I open my eyes and soul
Now this is how business
So that was the experience that I had where I said why do I have a boss right now
I don't want to but I want to be the boss cuz I can make something big
At the time sandwich
I was 22 years old
In that day
He quit his job at the gadget
And set out to become an American Middleman
In China
I was on the other side of the world from friends from Family from every type of safety net that I've ever had in my life
And the the Monday of me going to work
Going to work with leaving my bedroom and going to my
Kitchen table in my shared apartments in Shenzhen
It was just
Oh my goodness what do I do
Suzanne started scrolling through
Reddit pages
And blogs looking for English-speaking entrepreneurs who wanted their products made in China
And I started just saying hey I'm an American if you're looking for products let me know
And I can try to help you find them
Address for
Dear Sam signed up about
15 clients who wanted to make stuff
In China like watch boxes and jewelry boxes
Wallet
Toothbrush replacement
Just Sam
I'm and is assistant
The two of them would call places all over China to find factories
To make the product
And it's funny cuz I remember at my roommate
He wasn't too happy with all of the boxes that were just coming in and filling up the apartment
Stacking boxes of just products that we were getting ready to ship out a product
Now Sam's been in business for
3 years
He has an office with
15 employees in Shenzhen
And the company helps clients find a factory they
Quality control to handle all the shipping
And they do all this for a flat fee about a thousand bucks
And last year
Sam boyd guided Imports
Made almost
Half a million dollars
Once I started
Building the this company I said I'm going to stay here for 5 years
Well
Now I look at it and I already said I'm going to stay here five years I'm overstaying that
So I don't necessarily know what the future is it could be another five years it could be
You know 50 more years
Let's Sam Boyd he lives
Is in Shenzhen China
You can read more about his company guided Imports
On our Facebook page
Just search how I built this
And of course if you want to tell us your story please go to
To build
That NPR. Org we love
Love love hearing your stories
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or if you want to get previous episodes
You can go to how I built this.
Npr.org
You can write shipt at
And if you want to send it
Tweet is at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Falkner with original music
Composed by ramtin Arab Louie
Thanks also to neva grandson as meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Lawrence Wu
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
If you're looking for a new podcast
Planet Money
Kiss fresh listen
One thing people say about planet money is
How much they love listening to it
Even though they don't
Are my business or economics
It's just a smart show with great stories that help explain our world
It's
Explanatory journalism at its best
Pretend that really need some sand reporting about
The question
Find Planet Money on NPR one or wherever you get your package
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email to
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.