Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
This campaign money
An email marketing plan
Form used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com
Hey its guy here with a quick note before we start the show
You have more
Control over your news
Entertainment
Ever before there are thousands literally
Thousands of podcasts out there
And this year
You chose
This one
Podcast is your thing
And you're listening choices are a part of who you
Will the choice to support your favorite NPR programs
Is yours too
And you could do that by visiting donate. Npr.org
Slash built
And then share why you did
You can tweet or create
Public Facebook post with the hashtag why public
And thanks
The Pampered A1 was
Open my damn laptop and just start hustling
And I did and I remember it like I was taking anyone who would meet with me I was asking for people who would give me advice
I was looking for advisors just literally paint
Literally fire during a Starbucks and I really do want to work for my company my company was
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
Traumatic experience
Learn best
A company that simplifies financial planning
And how she
Forever rumors
Order of a
Billion dollars
Most of us
You me your friend's spouse is whoever
Do not know how to organize
Our finances
I just just think about it
The average US household has at 16
Thousand dollars
Credit card
And 2/3 of us
Have less than a thousand bucks in our savings account
One more
The median amount of money the average American has saved for retirement
$1000 switch
And I hope I'm not freaking out here
This is not enough money to get you very far after
You stopped working
Even her well-educated friends
Think much about financial planning
Especially because the whole process can seem in
Frankly something
You do when you're older
Let's face it it's
But it's super
Back in 2006
What's an opportunity
The opportunity to build a company
It could demystify financial planner
Especially for young p
People people without a lot of money
Had a big party idea came from a traumatic
Experience that
She had as a teenager
Alexa grew up in Jacksonville Florida her mom was a nurse
Kitchener
And her dad
What's a pediatrician
So I
Would go to my dad's office
Notify alive clean up all the toys
And actually I think
My dad wanted me to like observe
Other families going through
Do challenges
Some days I eat kind of pull on that more than I
Even realize now that I have my own family
I think
Basic minimum wage
Fun things I want to do but yeah I got a job really early and actually one summer I even put into a
And I are a witch my dad
Kind of taught me early about financial planning in that way
So your dad was Doctor your mom was a nurse nurse practitioner
I'm so it sounds like you had a
Economic science
I did all the my mom was like a developmental
Specialist
So I always joke that I think my parents probably like secretly had me take like six or seven different tests like whatever they were
Trying out at work I remember just like
A few times sitting down and
People take my cake
Go just like
Computer test really quickly
I was joking they were testing me for hyperactivity because I have so much energy
But yeah really
Sciency luke kuechly signs he like my daddy
Make potions to turn fire in the fireplace
Purple and blue
Putting some chemicals in it I've no idea what they were
And that's kind of what I would do with my dad is going to geek out on that stuff and I'm sure in some very subtle
Way that really influence kind of my own patented
Technology
So
Pretty stable childhood right I mean get you to pretty kind of
Stable
Middle upper middle class
Stop ringing
In Jacksonville Florida
Yeah I was a really stable except for when I was 14 my dad unexpectedly passed away and I think that
Kind of seeing
Throws and it gives in an axe
I didn't say it was very much like
Noise stop sound stop time stopped
Can ask any child who lost their parent they
You unfortunately remember
Every minute every day
Of that whole period of time it's like
It's burned into your Pinterest
Remember
The day that
It was 1998
June 9th of 1998
My dad is going to work I was supposed to go
I work with him that day
And I I didn't because
I was here that.
Beginning to be an adolescent and I was like I asked you want to go and you'll hang out with friends today
And I remember cuz I'm pulling up to my house
Just saying tons of police lights and
Frankly was like the like I literally felt like a horror scene
And
I just knew something was real
Really bad and my dad
Got in an accident and passed away and
I remember
Literally processing this is my worst nightmare.
This is my worst nightmare
And
And I said that kind of weeks my by after the biggest thing that really stuck with me.
Is
Life is
Literally so short like one second you can breathe in the next second it kidding just literally the over
And I think that was the thing that was grappling with the most of those few days because I wasn't physically present and I didn't see the app
Accident
It was just like wait but he was here this morning saying goodbye to me and then all the sudden I'm coming home and it's it's
I'm here
I know we're going to get
Tennis later on
You're at your mom and your Marianne
Successful career
Is there a day that goes by that you don't think about your
It's such a good
Question
In the absolute truth is like
No not a day goes by it's like the
Totally getting choked up
The truth is that every day
It's really really simple
Small Things big things
The songs that we sing to my daughter now
Her song that he loved
So
No and I think any person who's lost someone they really really love
Nose.
I think when we think about
Losing somebody
In our lives we
Obviously and of course we think about the emotional impact of that
Don't think about we don't
Talk about witches
The impact on
I have family function to me often times
There's one
Current kind of handles things like finances and
Bills and
The household
Stop and
It's complicated when one of them
Pass away
Exactly
Tencent kind of dishes where some of the idea of her learnvest and
Might my own like
Unclear ultrasabers really born which is
First
That kind of alluded to
What's my parents
Very skilled very very capable people
But still tradition has its
Ring on a family right so I
My mom managed the budget it's definitely where I get my skill of being very frugal from
And then my dad managed all of our
Investments in kind of the bigger picture and
To be clear my my mom's a tough cookie like she's
Very brave
Very very smart
Tom there's nothing that she really tries away from but she didn't manage our investment so I think that's the best way to put it
I think it's true for millions of households by
My dad passed away one of the really clear things I remember was
My mom just didn't
Have a really clear handle on
Where everything was in what the picture look like
Night remember my mom being like
Not
Quite sure
Like how many was going to work
Imaginative
Potentially
Paralyzing thing for for for any family
You're so I think this is one of the things
Guy that really stuck with me is
Just 14
Just knowing that like my mom was even questioning that like
It kind of made me sick to my stomach that there was one other thing that she the worry about
And so it is really like the last song
Impression
When your life is
Crumbling in Lakeview are devastated whether it is an illness or an unexpected accident that like takes away a loved one
Or losing your job or are your partner walking out on your life whatever it may be all the things that Crush people
I don't want you have to worry about money I don't want money to even be
Flash in those times I wanted to be like
You're good right
Which
College and I started getting
Starting things I'm interested in
I ended up
Literally
Financial planning class
Like how many credit cards should I have and you know how do we think about these things in like just basics
And there was no class and there were no
There was there wasn't a program and I just remembered kind of being appalled
That I can't teach myself this life skill
Easily
And you know that kind of is some of the seedlings of like
Really where learn bass was truly born
Did you have like an entrepreneurial kind of mind in in college
Maybe Rich business even part of your thought process
It's so funny
Which was never something that seems like exciting if that makes any sense that said I always
Thought like
CEOs of companies were like rockstars and because I just find them so
So interesting and I just want to learn everything
That coupled with if you ask my mom my mom would tell you I was an entrepreneur at like Age 4
Because I was
Instead of having a lemonade stand I was actually thinking things out of my house that I wasn't allowed to have
And selling them like
I got in a lot of trouble a handful times cuz I once took a piece of art off the wall but I just didn't think we needed
So you are at your first
Job out of college was was with Morgan Stanley right
Trader
I kept saying like Okay just like a good foundation of job that will give me the foundation of what
But I think I wanted to but I had this
Really constant energy of like I want to build I want to create I want to make
Nerd with kitties like really wild notebooks of like list of ideas of things I was excited about
I'm glad you have learned that had already been kind of boring in my head of like why don't we learn about money why isn't there a better way to do this
Why isn't there something out there
And I'm just wondering
Back to when I was in college and
I really wasn't thinking about financial plan on going to be on Sunday like I wasn't
It wasn't something
That we ever crossed my mind not
Jamie maybe I was irresponsible or maybe I was just not that intelligent but I just did
Think about I thought
What's going to be interesting
I like studying history it's interest
What that was
Extent
So I'm
I'm trying to figure out how was it
You suck
Financial planning this is something that more people should know about
Cuz you're like in your
Early Twenties that just seems like a boring
At that point in life
It's so boring and I'm not I was like
Here I am saying accepted the job at Morgan
I remember sitting there being like I work
At like a great financial firm
It's like I'm on a trading desk
And I am sitting here struggling with like do I put money in my 401k or my IRA
Write like basic
I just would like if I feel this way and I don't even know
Have a family I don't even have a mortgage I don't even
Going to have kids like
I feel pretty lost
With my financial planning
How do other people feel so I started asking
I asked everyone who would talk to me
How do you feel about your wallet is it stressing you out
And
It literally it was amazing everyone I would ask what date
I have no idea
Young old
Money no money people who had like you
Golden parachute
McNair family excetera
From that I was like
This is a knife
That was the beginning of learnvest
That's how I started working on it and I embarked on it being like this is the sexiest idea cuz guy there was another
Part of me that struggled with
I need to do something that is so cool this wasn't cool
I knew that
Honestly
Core part of me that just scared
So damn much
That that's what was right I just I was like
I was hooked
Stuck and I had to go.
You are at Morgan Stanley
Wrangler
Yes so I was at Morgan Stanley
An essential that gave up having a real social life
Like nights and weekend I would like
I put together the 75-page ish business plan that nobody read
I was all my thoughts in one place on what this
Futurelearn bass company learn bastard for learn in.
Even though by the bad guy
Build what I was going to look like
But I started feeling like
Get it like this is what I meant to
Places around 2008/2009 2016
You got this idea for learnvest
And and you leave Morgan Stanley
But I guess right about this time you actually
Start going to Harvard Business School
So I enter business school in September 2008
And I actually took my
Leave of absence
School on December 8th
Saddest thing about 90 days
And I drop my business
Is plan and when
Basically the economy crash like
If you remember guy that followed 2008
Blood. It was a nightmare and that actual
Kicked my courage
Steven hire Garibay
Because
I said to myself this is literally a time when
Anyone in my family anyone I knew was like should I be
Selling my all in all my retirement Into Cash
People were putting money under their mattresses like
Everyone was
Terrified
So in the midst of all this chaos you thought paid leave in the school and start a business
Yeah and I was like this is a Time in America needs more financial planning than ever
It literally was the scariest big decision that I had had to make personally and so December 18th
And then I said I'd like to take a leave of absence where you get like a one-year and then you can keep it
I did that and then I would literally said to myself I was taking a plane ride from there I'm to New York and I said
I literally cried the entire play Silent like it was like one of those
You know you see people crying on the street
Straight talk I was just crying on this plane to myself
Thing like what
Gabby that something like you were an a student you went to Harvard Business School
Clearly you are a good student clearly you followed rules
I hope you don't strike me as a, cuz you risk taker
What what what what is this stability
And just go into
I'm I'm I'm laughing because the
Truth is I am a rule follower but I think there's this other
Greeley
Another really really deep
Part of me guy that is where I go to to make my decisions which is
I always say there's a little to one of the things I learned in Psychology is that
If your a sponge a nine-year-old
How to say hey what are you regret
They never regret
The stuff
That they did
They never regret that I kissed a boy or I
Quit this job or I did these things are spent this money
Ever
US 9 year olds
They always regret the rest they didn't
So you
Leaving school
And you
You move to New York to start
Learn.
That's where our office is
We're going to be that's where I was going to hire p
People New York is the finance capital
The world
Very early startup day so really important to say out loud
There there isn't a lot of likes
They're like there was not a startup
Community truly in York and I kind of Base
I wish I had this myON
Funeral Cinderella moment
I got 9 month
Savings
Basic Finance
A plan I knew that if I hadn't raise money like an angel round 2 actually
Get going
I wasn't able to find this out of my pocket and hump
So I had them from all of my bonuses and everything from Morgan Stanley about $75,000
Enough to
I mean you could start with yourself
It wouldn't be enough.
Give you that much
One engineer
That was about $10,000 a month
One really high quality engineer New York
And you knew this was going to be a tech company
Who's going to be web-based or
At the time I wouldn't have said it was technology
Company I was like I'm building a
Consumer
Internet timeout
The right like
I need to hire engineers india
They all made
At the minimum 152
$20,000 a year so like my money was indenting anything
So how did you get that the seed money to start
Yasso
I'm the ghost Ray 750000 the plan for day one was
Open my damn laptop hinges
Start hustling
And I did and I remember it like I was taking anyone who would meet with
With me I was asking for people who would
Give me advice
I'm looking for advisors
I'm in little by little over the next
Do you mind I started gaining
Actual company
Buckeyes
I'm Iris said me working 30% of 40
Percent full-time on a startup does one thing me working a hundred
Percent of my time like literally not do
Anything else
You just I just started seeing results and it felt like this little bit of snowball in
This is actually my husband
Speech at our wedding
Cuz he's like everyone always
Alexa
Success he's like that I watched it
And he and his big joke
If you would come home from work
11 p.m. and I'd be like furiously still working
And one of two things is happy
Meaning I was either clutch
Like a bottle of wine
Or some days by The Wanted
Cookie and he like new boats
And I was just like heads down in like
Just literally pinky bone equity
Pictures of phantom
The company was working out
And I heard my first
Intern who would like
Princeton
Student who took the train up and I literally hired her at a Starbucks or name's Andy
Girl
And I really do you want to work for my company and my company was looking to eat
When we come back
Pal Alexa went from hiring that one person in Starbucks
Managing hundreds of employees in millions
Abusers
Gyros near list
To how I built this
From NPR
Support also comes from choiceology
An original podcast from Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of toy silage
You'll hear a classic psychology experiment retold
William is an opera fan who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation
And is an average chest
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find out
Schwab.com podcast
Or wherever you listen
Support also comes from wix.com
A web platform for creating your own professional website
With WIC
Whether it's your first time
I'm creating a website or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning template
Lights or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology
And Powerful web features
Join Over 125 million people already using Wix to create their own website
Gota wilx.com to create yours today
So what will you create
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Took before Alexa
Learnvest
Chief course needed to raise
Some of the money to do it
$750,000 to be exact
In 2009
Raise more than 1.1 million dollars
She met with
Everyone any connection she made during those 90 days Business School connections from her time
Morgan Stanley
Anyone else
She could think of
Andy knew I would pay for them to get coffee with me and bring them lunch in like I was like I know it's like a gopher I was at whoever or meat
You really grind people waste my time for sure who were like
Totally uninterested in and those socks
Can I leave an object demoralizing that I have to suck it up
It's 5 minutes later and my next meeting and I should run and how did you make the pitch how do you convince people
Even
You
With all of your intelligence and talent were so young
At that time
I was and I will tell you I'm at you know
Just turned
I'm I was not proven I've never done this
Before
But I think one of the things that I kind of really rested on
Guy was that I'd written the 75
Researched it I knew my stuff and if if there was going to be someone in this
Space that you
Could care about
Like I
I was all in
In that nine months of trying to raise money this is like
Collapse in the country's collapse and there's there's a huge bailouts in
Stimulus packages in p
People are freaking out
I'm trying to figure out how you were able to
To convince people to
To give you money
A time when I can imagine nobody
Monica take
Breast because
You nailed it I would say
A year-and-a-half
Sounds like just take
People's names in following up with them instinct
Persistent
One Direction
She said no to me then
Came back and buy the summer
Was like you know what I mean like
Crazy like your
Totally committed
One of the things I really held onto through that time as I even had a few people that were like mentors to me who were great entrepreneurs ahead of
I never liked you can do it in this environment you can do it anytime later
They're like they're like the entrepreneur
True survivor
Literally like
Multiple like jumping through knives and hoops
You can get through it like
Uconnect
Thrive
It was true
But you were you were saying to people
I'm going to offer
What
So what I was saying to pee
People AIDS
We are going to go after a younger Millennial audience
We are going to be the
Searching for their money
For them understanding
Everything to do with their money
And everything was
With sound really Broad
The point was it with content in providing the education
And the tool so we built our own swover you could aggregate
All of your money in one place
And then we launched
Advise and advice
But you could call in
Talk to someone
So you would talk to one of our planners
We are going to apply
Super modern world today
That's so
Open 24 hours a day
Super super
Refresh
Banks
Timer
Stupid ads on
TV that were like we're open on Saturdays from like 11 to 2 when you were like
What is a cat's so irrelevant for
A young person who doesn't even want to walk to the bank
See you on the site I think in in mm
How'd it go
Like just like all good Founders have the
Storysite went off
Daily candy cupboard Austin weather
News outlets cover.
Site crash
I think around that the first day the next day with episode back up another few thousand
People sign up and in that first tweet about 10000
Wood sign.
And just
To your point
Boring
Like you say dailycandy in another p
People like
Was it pitched as a
Hey this is freon
People are this is for women or this
Mike Howard
How was it
It was literally pitched his like
Anybody who wants to get like their butt kicked about their wallet in in a way that's like plain English and
Go to learn bass
And we had
10-day email program that was basically going to give you like a
Simple overview on
Every
Young fortnite to find younger
I think 40 is Young
Person young person
I need Center steamer wallet
And we 10000
PayPal sign up
Any open rates and engagement with the site work
Massive
And I remember being like
While this data is
Really compelling
And we had a bunch of advertisers jump out
Addison sofa
By February 15
I remember cuz
She's right on that Valentine
Wednesday
I'm literally we are in a play
The spot where
We had
Haunted Adventure
Italiana New York
I was like
Wow okay
So we ended up taking just under 5 million dollars from Excel bench
Partners in a bunch of other really cool people
Nearest threw in some money at that point
And in short what we felt was
TurboTax
For financial planning
No
A way for you to come
Very affordably get a financial
A plan
I'm most Financial
The plans cost
Is $5,000
I don't know about you guys but if you're in your twenties and thirties you're not really ready to go spend
No $5,000 on a financial plan when you're trying to figure out
Do with the $5,000 do you have
Extra
So is it I mean so
So you didn't have to hire a lot
And lots of financial
Advisor
People to say
Here's that you should do here
You should do because
As you were developing
Essentially
A software that
Give you answers based on the on the day that you that you
You put in
Correct
Helping software is not
Easy or inexpensive things to do and you need
Not just like
10 Engineers you need tens of engineer's
Very sophisticated Engineers with certified financial planners
And to develop this software so essentially what we started doing was we started
Asking people we had their data sing what are the questions you have
I'm in really listening and eventually we developed
Software that I liked
Think of it as GPS
Fairmoney
It gives a real several sense
And then from there we didn't kick
Kick your butt we would hold you accountable we
Gnu action items
Go close this account go open this
Account
What we would see was it was
Just a very Innovative way to
Answer your
The entire business model is built
Around
Scribers rather than
Getting you know
Commission from like steering people into a specific investment are fun
Cracked
And then on the
Business-to-business sideways
We sold learnvest at work
And that was weird
Really big companies
Started coming gas and actually
It kind of shows you like the nimbleness of an entrepreneur
I remember we'd a really big
Big Brandon Carter
Become. Since they hate
Buy this for employees
And things you say yeah of course we can figure that out
12 like
You guys have raised
25 million dollars are even more when you were growing so fast
So much attention
Dislike
Caught the attention of big companies
Is Charles Schwab in other
Or other companies offering financial planning
Yep
So why I would say bye like 2012-2013
We were having active conversations with
Either for Business Partnership
Or sponsorship sponsorship deals or they wanted to license or white label our software so
All of a sudden lots and lots of business interest
Coming. But nobody was saying we're going to
What we did was really radically different and so
No one was quite set up the way we were which was
Kylie humans we still really believed in the power of humans and still do to this minute
And we were just really convicted because of our principles of every American deserves a financial plan
It needs to be cheaper it shouldn't you one thing I said over and over
Initial planning should not be a luxury product
Yeah the big brokerage firms don't really want to talk to you unless you have over $250,000
It doesn't
And I just a vowel what if we
Tip it on her
Non-attachment
And really make this
Do you
Is any
Part of you motivated
Buy competition likes
Do you want to win
This is a really good question
I'm hyper motivated I get up I get up with like a spring in my step I want to go
Do things
But my whole life I've always been like
I don't joke
Additive if that makes any sense
What I figured out is there
There's two types of people there's competitors
And there's a cheevers
Cheevers wake up at their own 2
To do list of things that they want to do by the end of the day
And
Focus on getting those things
And it's very much
You know within your own swim Lane
Competitors actually are looking to
To the people together swimlanes want to beat them
I'm not a competitor
The achiever in me is super
Focused on
You're raising the bar for myself and things I think
Compilation
And it was just a really good distinction in one of my best friends
She goes I wouldn't be your best friend if you're a competitor alright so you guys
Rock the race
Cuz you're doing really well
You're growing and then
You
You get acquired by
My Northwestern Mutual was that
Was that part of your
Your plan for the beginning that that you would have that exit
So
I always have a good on
Preneur
It's not that you don't ever say
Think about an ex
Prodigy
But it's not your goal
Gomez let's continue to stay in business and get bigger and bigger and deliver more more
Keep making this work
So Fast Forward 2014
Literally Northwestern Mutual
Emailed in
I'm asking to invest and and and
And you're my board said yes
Ambassador
April 2014
Buy that thing
Giving
The CEO John
Rashad Smith
Can we spend some time
Weider really good conversation and it
Quickly turned into him saying hey
We both believe in the same things which is
We believe in the power of
Human advice and we really believe that Americans deserve access to
2 plans
And he was like What if we teamed up
That was now December and the next thing you know
We're signing a term sheet to be acquired on March 25th
Alexa
And you don't have to confirm this
But the reported number
About sale
What is a
Order of a
Billion dollar
When you are 14 and your your dad passed away
Your mom was like so
Let's figure out the finances and in the finances of family which
Obviously created some instability
And that you that decision in in 2015
Made you and presumably others around you
Financially secure
Cure for life I mean
What does that mean to you
I mean no
I think
A few things in this world like a very personal story
That I actually told the board after we sign the document I sent them all a video of the board of Northwestern Mutual
I sent them
Now the 3-minute video is kind of surreal at the time cuz I actually didn't intend to do this but
It just felt right and I just went with my instincts
Tell my dad passed away without you in Northwestern Mutual life insurance policy
Stabilize my family
And I knew the power of
I want Financial stability really provides to family
And I
Just send them a video and said here's why I'm doing this
Here I am I
Having helped build this great products that helped America innovate on Financial Planning and if I can put it
In hand
Of their 8000 financial planners
Provide more but I felt at 14
I can really get behind that
You are in your early
I'm your mom you've got
Do you have your old and then one on the way
You you have
Like your whole your whole life is ahead of you
But you're an age where most entrepreneurs start their first business
And obviously right now you still have a role at
Northwestern Mutual you that
Cheapest lobsters
When do you think you'll
You'll ever go on to do something else like what you start
A new business
I don't know right I kind of like to solve problems all the way through
Kind of what I care about right if I'm going to start something I want to finish it
I'm quite busy right now I will say that I see very very very full plate
Hundreds and hundreds of employees in a lot of work on my Horizon
And for me I
I like big
Big meaty challenges
And I
That that's the one thing I know about myself
Self self
What's next
I don't know
I've been really really honored to have lots of exciting options
Diet that I want to see things through and I still work today
You heard me ask a question before
People
Ask it a question
How much of
Your
Success do you think is due to your
Intelligence and hard work and how much how much business do to lock in circle
So I know there's all the cliches
People always exciting too much
The Locking bubble blinds
I would say
Definitely not my intent
And definitely not luck
I would say it was
Contributed to
Incredibly powerful
Team of passionate people
Frankly
Stop through walls
And we
Saw a better life
And for me I having had such
Traumatic experience when I was younger
What I really learned wise
Kind of the fragility of life in like someone that you love is really important to you as a live one second and
Literally meaning
Later gone
It kind of helps you just
Get rid of
A lot of the
Your focus gets really clear
And in fact
Did almost
Getting me a superpower in some way because
Inow process
Things a little differently which is
Does really matter raven like a really big stressful stupid thing is happening
Are we alive are we breathing okay next
At some point when you shift into a perspective that like
They're still oxygen in your veins are still breathing the people you love are so alive like
Nothing stopping video
I think you do your best work
Alexa Von tobel founder of learnvest
She does a chief
Digital officer for Northwestern Mutual
Play something Alexa did not mention
Is that a high school
He was a competitive diver was actually recruited to compete
At the division 1 level in college
Even though
I don't love height
That said you know I've gone bungee jumping and I've gone skydiving in so I'm not like
As scared as your average person probably with height
I don't love them either
I think I just like to face fear
Please do stick around cuz it
Just a moment
And hear from you
About the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Gotowebinar
Trusted webinar platform with overflow
Thousand customers who posted over 2.3 million interactive web events
Connect with their audience
Amorphous
Gotowebinar
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
For how you built that
It's right here from Dylan Hill he's a student at UC Davis
Years ago
He co-founded a nonprofit called
Gamers gif
Yeah so our biggest thing right now is
Is bringing virtual reality
The headsets
Two
Veterans Hospital
Assisted Living
Facilities
People with
Abilities idea goes all the way back to the fifth grade when Dylan's best friend Chris
Was diagnosed
Cancer had to spend months in the hospital
I would visit him every single day and what I saw was my friend was no longer the kid that I knew
My solution was to bring the video games
Because I knew that those would make
Smile Chris eventually did get better and he and Dylan stay friends
And that experience always stuck with me
And I remember looking back on it as
While those video games really helped us
Anyway fast forward to senior year in high school
And Dylan is now doing volunteer work
In his spare time
But he's not all that happy with it
I volunteered at a food shelter
And instead of spending time with the homeless
I was in the back
Packing bags
And then obviously all these things they help
But it would just wasn't rewarded
Dylan kept thinking about the video game
Maybe there was some way he could use them to tell people
Chris we're doing a little random Googling
And Dylan said hey I wonder what it would take to start
Own Shirley
And we googled how to start a nonprofit in we saw
Wow this is simplified into
6 step
First make an LLC
And then skin touch with
The Franchise Tax Board
Actually some of the stuff does not sound so simple but eventually Dylan got his mom to guarantee
TD Bank account
For their nonprofit
And they became a 501 c 3
I think we've probably Google every single line on the tax paperwork
Because we had no idea what a lot of it meant but
I mean we have the internet you know we can figure out anything
Cancel after they got it sorted out Dylan and Chris started to raise money to buy video game
Samsung VR headset
First they sold baked goods door-to-door
Then they got some donations through an online service
And by the spring of last year
They were starting to visit hospitals and other places in California
Sharing VR and games
The children
And adults
So for example there was this man Dominic who's living with cerebral palsy
And he's always wanted to drive a race car
Now he's only able to communicate by moving at at up or down
But we can put a headset on him and we can push his wheelchair around his living room and we can emulate
Him driving a Formula 1 race car
Right now Gamers gift has about
20 volunteers who
Have brought VR sets
Sore computer games to Neely
40 facilities around California
And they're hoping to expand
Yeah I would love to but because you know
This technology and in the time that we spent with
People
It doesn't have to be limited to a particular
Geographical location
And I think the communities were already serving
Are the ideal communities
Especially people just
Yeah because they will never be able to
Experience
Scuba diving
But we can take that
And there's no reason why that should be limited to
California
Let's still in hell
Who co-founded Gamers gift
Along with his friend Chris Betancourt
There's a lot more to the story and you can find out about it on our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us
What's your story go to build. Npr.org we love
Hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or your previous episode
Can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also subscribe to this show at Apple podcast
Or however you get your podcasts you can also write us at HIV
Npr.org
Twitter stats at how I built this
Shows produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also Geneva Grande
Sanaz meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers
Our internet is
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email templates drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week