Support for how I built this and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corp
If you want to start or grow your business
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn Why by searching Michigan pure opportunity
We registered for the New York gift show which is the Holy Grail
I'll trade shows and we thought that this is going to be the ticket to R6S
But you were wrong it was a complete disaster
Running PR is how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories
Behind the movement
The story of how he left China for America use Campbell's Soup cans to make
Candles
Turn that into a multimillion-dollar company
So almost
Everything about the way Macy's life
Turned out
Is improbable
The fact that she started a business
That she makes candles that
Keenan lives in America
None of this was supposed to happen
And she describes it
Growing up in China in the 1970s was
I like living in a movie without
Color when we grow up there was apps
Sweet Nothing everyone wear the same thing everyone would be
Eating the same food everyone had the same small apartment life was very happiness
Signs that you don't have to be jealous of each other you don't have to
To be wanting things you cannot have in the 1970s
China was still a black box
Closed off too much of the world
Actually the government realized it needed better diplomats people who spoke foreign languages
Sail around the time a turn
12 1979
The government decided to open up some boarding schools to
Praying that next generation of diplomats
And may she
Was one of the lucky few who got it
So
We learned
Western culture American studies
Renaissance art
All in English
And I knew more about Smithsonian and the locations of each art
The many Americans
And this was the thing about
Learning a language
A language is really living it I remember it was very funny that I was watching
Godfather at 14
Which has a lot of violence a lot of sacks in a lot of murders
We were enjoying it we we thought it was
You know something that
Everyone in the United States to honor every given day
It was a pretty Charmed Life
Especially compared to other Chinese
May was on the fast track to becoming a diplomat
That was one problem
In the spring of 1989
Chinese students started to organize demonstration
Kids calling for more reforms
What we now know as the Tiananmen Square
After 6 weeks
Chinese government
Crackdown
Help me she wasn't an activist
Time
That didn't matter
The government decided that
Educated young people like her
Wharf rat
So they were sent out of Beijing
The assignment
Ode to a northern city
Very cold
Not even the city a suburb
My job
For the whole year is going to be
I'm watching a warehouse
For minerals
Spit out going to
Black sports
So I have a clipboard
I have 2 highlights of a day
When the truck comes to pick up one load I put a check
And then it came again in the afternoon I check
That'll be the day
Follow you
You must have been miserable
I was beyond miserable
At that time I was already dating my
First husband his name is David
So we were very close and being
Far away was obviously not a good
Arrangement on top of that
What I worried most
What is that for 10 years
I was practicing
In speaking English
And language is very easily
Forgotten
I barely speak
Chinese let alone English because my boss does not like to talk
He's a man with
Few words
He smoked most of
What time
And that's my life
Simei
She decided to quit
She dated thought about what to do
He was a trained geophysicist and she spoke English so
They decided to apply for temporary visas
To come to the US
And after 2 years of waiting
They got them
So I flew to Washington DC
When we arrive at Dulles Airport I was very
Sleepy because up to jet lag and I saw to size
Kiwanis
American citizen and the other is a Lea
It's just as you arrive at immigration vs Aliens
Was
Kind of confusing to me because I remember aliens from Star Wars
You know
Go science
And I was so excited I said wow
They actually have a
Section 4 alien
And
So I got very excited I said let me see
I'm certainly not
American citizen so I guess I'm
Going to have to go to the ATM part
That's great cuz I can see them
I never knew that the word idiom means the nun American language
I guess they realize
At 2 they changed the
Do something
A little bit more
More human
What was it like to adjust
To the US and you had
Immerse yourself in American culture your entire childhood
But then you finally arrived here
Did it surprise you to disappoint you was it
Lonely
Well I don't find it particularly difficult to adopt
What I find interesting is that in Washington DC
People kind of avoid icon
That's something I stood
I think was my first impression of the city
I was riding the subway
And I found a very interesting that
As quickly as I look at someone they merely change their eyes
And they try to focus on reading
And I said to myself I said wow this is a r e d
Deep City because everybody's always reading
David Icke volume
Apus where you able to find a job
Yes
Psiphon job in New York
It was a job for American medical device companies to ask for
Equipment
To Chinese hospitals
And was it interesting work if you enjoy it was boring I have to be honest with you it was a lot of paperwork pushing and
Import export documentation working with
You know different factories about
A SKU numbers and
Pushing that line of credit
Through the banks
But what's interesting out of all these
Not so interesting thing is that
They put me in a hotel
Next
Bloomingdale's
Why was it interesting
Well imagine a bird out of
Paige I have always been interested in
Fashion
Many people wonder you know if you grow up in a country without any fashion how can you really have an eye for it
And
When I was there
You growing up in the foreign language Middle School China at that time already started exporting
Fashion
And they would have those
Rejected fashion
And they put them on sale near the universe station
So we would be jumping from one
Place to another looking for
Cheap fashion you know
So that was always something I'm very interesting
And when you're put next to a Bloomingdale
That was the best thing that can possibly happen
So what you would just go in
Bloomingdale's
Everyday I would go starting phone
The first floor which
You Don't Own Me
South ladies that they spray fragrances and everybody hate them not me I love them since free on me
I like
Being
Sort of in the middle of
Something that launching and be able to tell what's in in the fragrance that I like and dislike
And then look at the packaging packages always fascinating to me because I grew up in a country with
No touching at all
But what interests me the most is a fashion floor and it's usually the second floor
And just
Being amazed
And I love the women in New York the way they are so confidence and they dressed in those colors in those
The shapes and they look great
And then I would always end in the home Department
And it would always
Give me a lot of question because
It look like it's in the 1920
It was supposed to what word look like
Furnitures will very ornate it has a lot of
Dairy
Gilded finish
And then the place I like
Laura Ashley Princeton a very small Grandma's
Wallpaper
Floral
And I'm just wondering the person who is so confident walking on the street will go home to
See this
It's so disconnected
So I keep saying that to
David
When we talk on
On the phone he here in DC in DC I was in New York and I would get up at
5A Monday and took
The first train
And I'll get home at 9 on Friday so it's not really
A very good quality of life and I was
Calling him about what I discovered was very exciting and then
I continually
Bring up how disconnected
The fashion and home
Apartments
Finally he said may you seem to be really upset about this commute
So he said
Maybe we should start something
Cu
Quest and you
And then then what was the plan but what was the business you guys were going to do so we knew if it's going to be home because we know where is home
Home Goods because the fashion business is dominant by Brent
And we feel
The home business is left without
And that's what we see opportunities so
It's close the gap between home and
Fashion
So that's how I do it we don't know what product
We just quit.
At the same time will you just like started brainstorming in your in your apartment or your house
The time I try to figure out what
To do not only without each other but we reach out to a friend
So
We brainstormed with our friends
And as a result of that
When we started the business
In the middle of
I would quickly got a lot of feedbacks
People send me samples me
Pictures
And we
Zoning on
About four categories
The first you'll be surprised
Silk flowers I don't know
Fake flowers that never die
The second category is accessories for your car so
Seat
Cushion something to make you
You feel comfortable when you drive for a long distance
Add a third category because I know this American Doll was so popular
Is a kind of doll that can rotate
Quit music
And the Lost
Something that I did
Even think it's interesting but I
I think it might have an opportunity
Is a candle candle
Every category mentioned
It's a huge business in this country there
Getting some dollars that are in each of those Counties have access to
Because the Internet wasn't available now
It wasn't and I don't
Really no
What difference we will make
Other than
You know making it two times better
But I didn't even know how hard it
Is that actually good
That you don't know everything that you don't know how hard it is that you just have
That something can be done to make it better
There's no amount of research
That can prove
And idea
But there's one thing you can always do which is to take your product
The market
So that's what we did
How did you get the products by the way
Date they sampled us they'd send buyer
FedEx Store franchise
Can you import into the US
We haven't imported them witches sample
Play December by DHL FedEx whatever it is said
Silk flower seat cushion flowers I think David brought some of those back by up breaking his
He's back also
And by that time
It was September 1994
All the major wholesale trade shows take place
Twice a year in January when people replenish their goods after holiday
Adding summer when they're buying more for Christmas
But it was September so the only show we can possibly go to is saying Charlotte North Carolina
Why what happened
90% of a business
Came from the can
And what did the candles look like where they just
Candles
Fair that you don't see them anymore they're called glow candles that round
And they look like stained glass
And when you burn them they are glowing
From within
So people came up to your booth and they were not interested in anything else is up flowers of the car says it was
It was at that stained glass looking cattle
Because holiday
And it was gift-giving season
And it's a great gift
Pakistan after the show
His orders
How did you
How did you deliver them how did you get them to the customer
We rent a very inexpensive Warehouse with office in the front
I was kind of Ford many people four times we just have one part-time
To help us
We were able to use our savings and our family and friends
Helped us
To the first container was a 20-foot container not even a 40-foot container
And then we ship them
Very fast we got reorders
Yes
So what was the candle
Retailing for
$15 the most
We probably will take
50%
Margin on them
So it was
Almost half a million dollars of business we did
Informant
I mean were you David just like shocks by the candle thing do what we were taken surprised by
We would not expect it to do so well for the first
4 months of our business
And we were shipping everyday
I'm
I was a sales manager
I was assistant
I was accounting
I was
Taking products out of the
Containers I was everything
Okay so you shut this container from China and then you deliver all the stuff to your clients
And then what did you guys do after like what was what was the next move for the company
The second year I decided since the trade show it's so important
We registered for the New York gift show which is the
The Holy Grail
I'll trade show
So we went to the New York Gift Show
And we thought that this is going to be
The ticket to R6S
But the show which is 10 times bigger with an international audience told us that we were wrong
It was a complete disaster
You
Are trying to sell kidney sink handles that you're importing
From China and
They're not selling
Fennel salad
And
I was devastated
Because it's a very expensive trade show
I'm assuming at this point I mean
You must have
Certified senior mind that maybe this candle business
It was a fluke maybe the fact that we did so well that first
4 months
Just had to do with Christmas
Exactly
That was the thought
But I wasn't giving up I was always more International minded
I was already scheduled to go to visit
Frankfurt
Germany
Because every year in February there's a big
Home Products show called on Beyonce
An Ender
Be my very depressed
Moments
I need it
To go there to see what
Could potentially be the next thing
Because what I envisioned
For home
It's already
Be there
The design is very streamlined
Everything France
Home furniture
2 lighting and table
The colors are very bold
They have oranges lavenders
And they have those beautiful contrast
With white
And
I was so happy that I went there because it's confirmed
That home and fashion could be in sync
Soap soap is it change your trajectory Avenue still
Have a candle business where you're bringing these like stained glass window candles
In from China
Yuan Frankfort you see these beautiful streamline designs
And you think
What
So I could use that design elements in candle design
That you would design your own candles
That was always my thought even though you were trained as a diplomat
People end up doing what they're trained to do but that's
Training is very helpful because I was
Exposed to a lot of Art
Education when I was
Very young kid
So I started
From the very high level of Art
And that trickles down
Fashion
It finally goes to home on the Frankfurt Rachel how did it change your approach to two
You're doing so I came back
Very refreshed from any invigorated from what I see and really I was determined
That I'm going to really start to do something
And another thing I discovered by starting to pay more attention now to candles
Is that my competitor in the US
Vapcell candles
In the Millions
And probably the billion
And I ask myself
Why do they buy it
All year round
It's not because they have it
Patton it's because of the freeway
The power of fragrance has been
Men and women over the years have been wearing fragrances
For many reasons
But for home
It takes on a very new meaning
So that was it you
You basically decided to
That point to start making
Scented candles
Yes
At that time we were for the first time joined
Buy a permanent
Employee which is
A friend of David's
His name is Richard
And he and I went to visit
One of the fragrance vendors in New Jersey
Need to learn how to make candles
So he and I went in
Speed up
Hunchback
And
For 4 hours we learn everything
That one need to learn
About making frozen candles
So many people think about candles and they say how hot can it be I can make it with my eyes
Say that you just pour some waxing perfume and then you pull that with there and then it's going to be a candle
But if you want to make it a business and you want to make sure it doesn't burn someone's house down
She actually have to study how to make it because
A candle is both
A piece of art
And a lot of signs
Five things that are interacting with each other
Is the fragrance
It's the base which is the wax
Is the color
Pigment
Eastwick
And finally
Is Sebastian
Which is the glass or a container
And if you don't do all those five things perfectly would like what was the wrong
Well have you ever seen candles that has a lot of black soot
That's because the wick is too big
Or you could have
A candle
That simply tunnel burn into the middle
And you don't
Smelling
That's because
The formula
And the WIC
Optimize
So half a day you visit there and
What you drive back to Maryland and you start to experiment
We were forcing out of excitement we sell wow we're going to start making freaking
Is candles for the first time and
We decided to experiment what we learned
We have two modes when we were
Home
So instead
We will always
Eating a lot of Campbell's Soup
You were startup you waiting lot of Campbell's Soup
Exactly a lot of Campbell soup noodle soup
So we said these are great sizes
Just so let's use them
Foremost
Pamoate so we started mixing in our kitchen
With our regular pods
Oils with wax
With colors
One thing we forgot in our excitement is a chemical that blend the oil really well with a wax
So that when you
Take it out of the modes it looks very smooth we forgot that chemical
What happened is a random Harvest because
When we took the candle out of the mode
The candle look
Fossilize
Fossilized because of the oil not blending very well
So can I have this aged look around if it has a snowflake on
Endnote
Candles I like
What is snowflake would be on different part of
The candle
Everything looks
Handmade
And on top of that
I blended fragrance differ
I put vanilla with
Lavender
I put
Watermelon with mint
Where many people just have that straight
Vanilla or straight
Watermelon
Is that the secret sauce
The fragrance
Yes
And many people say
The reason why they burn fragrance
Is the finishing touch
Touch two
Cleaning at home
When they want
Finish
And since that
Thomas ready for the
You know friends and family to come
For entertaining or when their husband and children come back to home
You want to put something
To markdown
It's a clean house
So they put a candle
It smells like a cookie it smells like
Fresh cotton
That's why people continually by the can
Because they need to fragrance
As You Are
Really kind of honing in on what what
This product is going to be is that when you came up with the name
Yes
So think about those collar
Beautiful cobalt blue with a lavender with a honeydew green
Not home to Greenwich everybody use
Sunflower yellow white
Think about what it means
Sit means energy
It means fresh
And this is where we give the name
Because we were living in a placenta
Annapolis Maryland Annapolis Maryland
And many times I would take my dog for a walk
I like how Annapolis
British steel today is to very quiet
It's not the Hampton store
Any other
Yuno sushi
You placed a very down-to-earth
It's very real it's very
Christina sent that to me
Coming from China
It is very untouched
And
It stand for natural
And I want
Communicate that because our
Candles are not touched by a lot of chemical
Natural finish on AR
Texture
So we just called Chesapeake Bay candle
When we come back how many she wound up making an enemy out of the one person she needed to get her candles
Listen to Target and eventually she recovered stay with us it's how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First to godaddy.com
They get customers the tools insights they need to transform their ideas and personal initiatives into success
The GoDaddy small business owners everything they need to get their business online
Including 24/7 support
GoDaddy is the world's largest technology provider dedicated to small business
And they're offering how I built this listeners
30% off all new products
Just going to godaddy.com
Podcast
And use code built
Thanks also to freshbooks the cloud accounting software used by over 10 million entrepreneurs
Thunder Mike McDermott started the company in his basement and spent over a decade building freshbooks
Now what they're all new version you save even more time processing paperwork and get paid faster
Send invoices in under 30 seconds accept online payments in two clicks
And see what a client has looked at your invoice
Are your free 30-day trial or freshbooks.com built
Adventure how I built this
In the how did You Hear About Us section
Who sang all this month we are asking our listeners
To tell other people about podcasts specially podcast that you love or podcast you think
They might live
So if you know somebody who done with the pot
Listen to podcast but doesn't listen to the one you like
Tell them about it
Even better show them how to download a podcast
And then tell us what you've been recommending
Use the hashtag
Tripod that's
Try
Pod
And thanks
It's how I built this from NPR
A guy Roz soap
Picture experiment in her basement with Campbell's Soup cans
Nishi is
Stumbled across a new kind of can
Bold colors mix
Fragrances
And now
Chesney
Convince someone
Dubai
So I called Bloomingdale
And I was
Working with the secretaries
Bagging a
Pleading that I have a great product
So finally she gave me the name of the buyer
The fire is really important
They are the eyes and ears for any company and particularly for Bloomingdale's
You can imagine that
That the standards really high
When I described a candle
The textures
Fragrances
And the colors
She was very intrigued
So I got it
Appointment
By the way
You know when I went there didn't even sit down
They started
Taking a candles and show
Everybody around in the office
And you New York Gotham
So I take it Bloomingdale's maiden maiden order
They loved it
They just showed it to their
Bosses
And we got
First order
To ship to
The store said I have been
Going so many times
How did you
Produce enough candles to
Still that order so here comes the best
I was frustrated because
At that time China did not have
The home fragrance industry
To produce that kind of oil
You need a chemical compound
Facility
And they were not used to that
They used to
Zelda cinnamon said they're Jasmine's overseas
The French and the US will then
Turn them into
Oils for fine fragrance oil for
Food flavors
But I don't have industry themselves
So is it the Chinese weren't weren't
Making fragrances like this
Like how are you able to do even
So I talked to a few factories in China
They look at me like a
You know that's a problem because
They certainly wouldn't take on a project
Like that
I was frustrated I told my sister about this
And she too
Was very determined to help me
So she said I'm going to quit
And she said I'm going to start a fact
In 1995
So that was the year
When we started have our own Factory which changed everything to me perfect look is it you can do that you can just
The factory is already 95 so you can put ukulele in that part of China
Spherion pineiro
There are Villages that make nothing but buttons
Or Village that make nothing
Candlestick
So
Having a factory is possible
But we have borrowed very heavily from friends and family
To build that
From scratch
So your sister build his Factory and start manufacturing the candles and
We do working like crazy where you always working
I'm always thinking
Because I'm
I was always thinking about the next color
The next fragrance that can mix
Packaging that we can play
So
I was always doing a lot of things have the same
What were the things at that time that that
Kept you up at night what were the
Anxiety
I was never have time to worry I'm a very optimistic
Sick person but I was always wondering who is our next
Customer so we stole
To Nordstrom right after Bloomingdale they're very similar companies
But in 1995 and 96
My eye started
To search for
Who is this
Company that's
Trending
Represents some demographic change
Stop
Shopping list
Yeah and I I started to focus
Why Target
They stand for style and Design
Versus Walmart which stands for value
And it really inspired me
Because I really subscribe to design for all
That philosophy because I came from a country
A lot of people that are very poor
I know a lot of teachers of mine
Who has
Great taste
Who would never be able to buy things
Bloomingdale's
So
How can I make it more fertile
How can we make it so we can sell it for $20
$80
So
I knew it's going to be the
Growth for us if we can get in
Because it's already 705
50 stores
National
And they have
Two dedicated Isles
With 48
Feet of
Candles
So who do you who do you call there
So it was pretty straightforward
You can find a name of a buyer
There's a telephone
Extension
End
You can leave message
And you
Call a person so this is the time when I always say you
You cannot give up even if you call for a whole year which I did a whole year every month at the same time
I called and left message
And you said
I said Haim
Same thing I did with Nordstrom and same thing I did
Like I said I have a great candle and now I can't even say it
It's sold at bloomingdales Juicery
Target buyers
Listening and those say wow they already at those doors we want to be those
Or so they would usually return your
Your phone but not
The buyer
And nothing silencing silence
So how did you
Had you finally break through what so I have to say this
Probably one of my biggest failure is that I started to get frustrated and I sent to the receptionist she's not rich
Returning my call
So she said I think you could
Call her boss
And make
Which I did I basically say well you're one of your buyers have not met
Any return phone calls
2 minutes later to buy a call
And she said this is so and so
And just so you know this is not a way to start a relationship
And she hang and she hung up on you
Wow so you were
Finish time
Every time I call her again if it's her voice I didn't even leave my voice message again kept calling
I can't call that you were shut out of there
I basically
So I waited until the next year in April
And it was a very different voice it was a very cheerful voice
It was a new buyer it was a new buyer
And I left my message and I got it back in 2 days
Finally
Come
Because as you can imagine every new buyer wants to make a difference
I want to make that
Denmark
And she hurt me
So she said why don't you come
And I did
Razer headquarters
TPC Minneapolis
Right
So I flew there
And she was very young she was probably in her
Late 20's and she coming
And she was sitting down listening to my pitch but
Halfway through Shattuck
And smell the candles from the bottom
Candle buyers
You should want to smell the candles
From the bottom
That's when the oil settle into the body
And you smell the most
Song about
And so what you saying to Chief
Panora
She basically in a big store
It's a lot
Process
They asked you
Capability questions pricing questions
Cherry pick what they want
So I didn't expect
Anything to happen
But
Jasmine
If I put it in my store how soon can you ship
That was the moment when I froze
Because I said what do you mean
Are you going to test because I heard they test a lot
That do testing 50 stores
100 stores
She said no me
I wanted
Put it in 750
And I said
Oh in that case and I started
To calculate in my head
How fast
My sister's company can produce
With 700
Des tours
And I set
6 months
I just have perfect that would land Us in October and you can ship it so it arrives
In December
And that's when we set for spring
An end how big was ever
That order and up
Bing
Over $1000000
And the forecast for the year
And it being over 3 minutes
How did Jamie soap so basically it mean when you call your sister and you said
We have a sword from Target we have to make how many
Can you even remember how many candles you had to make it's probably
Half a million candles
How many candles
What was
Zachary Abel
Mapreduce
That was going to stretch them
They were going to have three ships
Everyday of the week
Just like 24/7
Yes we will have to hire people
To work 7 days a week
And the thing about the to Target
Shipment is that is really daunting
When you think about people scaling that business
That's one of the things people
Overstock
Think about this Finance how to finance a big water
I mean it.
The second email ask is legit
Physically how do you turn over
20 containers
Oquendo
In two days
And we don't even have to
The physical space
To turn 20 containers in 2 days right
So we rented
A very big empty
Warehouse in Laurel
In Laurel Maryland Maryland where are
Other warehouses
But there's no electricity
So we parked up
Two cars
Used to headlight
To light up the warehouse in the evening
And we literally
Packed and unpacked
Using aqua love you you
David your husband shirt
And two or three of our warehouse workers five of us all together
Witch Hunt over 20 contains your company was five people in the US have the time
5 to 6
Full-time people
And we went into holiday season some somewhat absent-minded
Waiting to see when the product will show up on the shelves
And showing up right after Christmas
Are products with their
But it was radio silence
There was nothing coming from the buyer from Target
Until when
Hunter 2 weeks after it was set
And I get panic order
Call from the buyer
Samara
Big trouble
Oh no they didn't get all the
Products or
Then I'm moving at all
No
We are under forecast
We could have sold 8 million dollars off your candles this year
And you need to go back to China and build a bigger factory and we need to catch up because I don't want to be empty shelves
In April or March
So is that what you did
That's what we did
And we found a much bigger facility
And we all fit it
So that
By March
We started shipping out of the new facility how many factors do you have
So we have one in
Hangzhou China
As the first factory
Now we have whining haiphong in Vietnam
And now in Glen Burnie Maryland
Cloud
It's a lot more expensive to
To manufacture candles in the US
Why are you doing it
I came to this country
And I'm a citizen for many many years
Always want to find product that said meaning
USA when I go back to China
And I couldn't find them
Everything is always made in China
Made in Indonesia Made in India
I think made in USA
We may have not realize
People believe that
There's integrity
Andeavor stock
Cool fact
With product says made in USA
And we haven't explored that
As a country
Did you think you had a competitive
Advantage
In part because you are an immigrant and a part because
Everything in America was new to you and your kind of
Knife
I think that's
Precisely
I think immigrants are self-selected
They are self-select
The group that is
Dairy Pig
Taking risks
In some ways they have
The same Trace
It sounds pretty hurts already
Instead of taking what's easy
What's already
Familiar
They choose
Unfamiliar the unchartered
Because they have more confidence
And they have more curiosity
Sew in
Selecting themselves as
Immigrants
They're already
Facing big risks
From a company that you started
Is it is an afterthought with
Silk flowers and car seat covers
To accompany that
I seen does
Reportedly like 60 to 70 million dollars a year in Revenue
It's a pretty amazing
We could you have imagined that when you came to the US
A temporary Visa that
That you would be running a company that
It's so big
So remember the alien story
Yeah remember I thought I was
You know going to meet an alien and discovered that I was
Actually the alien
How cool is it that an alien
Next president of United
And talk about
How to create a job
In America
That was me
In mm
I was creating jobs in the United States
Cuz I'm a factory and
The president's office
Took note
And he invited 13 of the biggest manufacturers such as
Ford
Intel
And I was invited because I was a small business
And
I was giving advice
As to why it makes sense to revitalize
Manufacturing in this country
But why
That we have not done enough
For those company
Needs to bring job
So I feel very fortunate not on me
Was I accepted not
Just as a learner you know I was able to giving a path
To realize what I want to do and more
OKC Thunder of Chesapeake Bay candle
By the way to this day Target is by far her biggest customer
I need to know the average price of a candles is around fifteen bucks
American spend more than three billion dollars just on candles
And 90%
About by women
Please don't turn us off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you guys are building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors Cleveland Clinic
Cleveland Clinic is ranked number one in the nation in Heart Care
22 years in a row according to US News & World Report
For more information or to get a second opinion
Is it clevelandclinic.org
Heart Care
Hey thanks for sticking around it's time now for how you built that and we can hear from Louise bigger who lives in
Toronto and describe the product
They're these fruity tones that
Travel through your mouth at different times and then Citrus notes
Undertone Cedar citrusy notes
Louise Baker As You Guessed sells pepper
Pepper
As in this salt to your pepper actually peppercorns
Louis
Came across this was very special kind of pepper on a family trip a few years ago at a plantation
In Cambodia and when is grown
Cassidy using centuries-old harvesting techniques and the proper soil in the proper
Time it then it takes on the flavor that is entirely different and we felt like we tasted Pepper for the V
First time it was amazing return to Toronto from their trip every time they would be
Peppermill on the kitchen table tastes like ordinary boring pepper they've been spoiled by
Cambodian peppercorn
Maybe there's a market for complex and nuanced artisanal pepper
Here in North America about
25% of the world
Spice trade
Is peppercorn so everyone uses pepper and when we started
Take me to the felt
I could do this
So they emailed back Farm in Cambodia
And got them to ship a big bag of Capricorn
Louise built a website of course and then designed a nice little package for them and then
Givens the printers the green light
And then realized
That's the dimensions weren't quite right so we would have ended up with 13,000 packages that we wouldn't have been able to use
Good-looking corpse husband launched their
Business they sell black and red Cambodian peppercorns to foodie is it a few retail stores but mostly through there
Website and the color company drum pepper stream in Danish and I'm I'm Danish
Via the trip that we took that was a long-standing dream of ours and setting up the business with social something we dreamt about
So beautiful dream theme throughout
Leslie speaker she's the founder of drum pepper in Toronto Canada
More about her company had to our Facebook page to search how I built this on Facebook
And please do keep sending us your stories we love sharing them you could tell us all about the things you're building life
Visiting build. Npr.org that's build with a d. NPR
. org hey thanks for listening to the
Show this week if you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this.
NPR. O RG please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and
Write a review while you're there you can also write directly to us at Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this our show was produced this week by run. Delphi
Music composed By Ram teen Arab Louie
Thanks also to neva grandson of meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers are interned is Claire Breen on gyro
Rise and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com