Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here before we start the show.
Quick note to tell you that
If you're listening with
Children nearby
Yeah you know you might want to
Did you just do that
Sorry I didn't realize there was a wall there
Anyway I just heard you mention children and I thought you were ready to tell everyone about her
But was going to wait until
You know what
Nevermind
Flip2it
Everyone meet my friend Mindy Thomas
So many hosts
This amazing kids Morning Show on Sirius XM
Kids Place Live Channel
And for the past two years I've been joining her each Friday to talk about new discoveries
Science stories
In a kid friendly way
We decided to take go and so if you are a pair
Friend or someone with
Kids in your life I'm here to tell you about a brand-new podcast
Elementary school-aged kids
It's NPR's first ever kids show
It's called wow in the world
And it's hosted by me and Stand By Me
And every week we'll take you and the kids in your life through awesome adventures
Some of the most wow-worthy events
Science
Technology and new discoveries
Last will introduce you to the
People's words
Changing our world as we know it
So as many of you know I am a parent and so am I and both of us struggle with the challenge of
Screen time
4rkids soap
You know we decided
To come up with our own solution a podcast
Kids and their grown ups
That inspires
Wonder and Imagination
With no screens required
Except for the screen Unity
To subscribe and you can do that right now
Wow in the world premieres on Monday May 5th
But you can hear the trailer bison
Describing to wow in the world
An apple podcast or however you get your
Alright midi I think I'm going to have to kick you out now because I have to get back to the show and I got to take that walk
Still can't believe you busted through that wall
The magic of radio guy Raz new podcast
For Curious Kids
And a grown up
Subscribe now on iTunes now called
Podcast store
However you get your podcasts
And now back to how I built this
It grown so fast
We had television going we had started investing heavily into the digital side of things a lot of stuff
When 9/11 happened
People stop traveling on travel guides then just stopped
Did you think that there was a
Possibilities
We just have to let people go
We just have to come back the number books
Ramen PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
And the movements
Backpack along the Asia hippie Trail in the 70s
And turn them into the
Biggest travel guide company
In the world
So much of how a company comes together
Happens
By chance
I mean
Sergey Brin and Larry Page never met
Would there be Google
If Kate and Andy Spade never worked in the same clothing store in Tucson Arizona
Kate Spade bags of Heaven
Same thing for Airbnb your Instagram or Warby Parker
They all happened because
A moment in time that
Could have passed
Which is a story of Lonely Planet guide books
Because it all started on a bench in Regent's Park in London on a knife
October afternoon in 1970
Marie wheeler was
Looking for a
Quiet place to sit
And as I was walking around the park
It was only one bed
Will try several times because on the bench was also a young man and I thought if I sit in that but then she's probably going to try and pick me up
And I really don't feel like that
This is 1970 I can sit wherever I want so I sat in the sunny bench
I'm trying my best
To be a man and started reading my book
It's a polling now.
Magazine
New edition of it and I was just reading that
What are you doing
Hide I said it's 10 place to read on a Thursday afternoon
Hand shear
Reply positively
Get lost and then then
He's got my sauce and I liked it
So I said
I don't know I have a big head that
We started chatting and
After a while Tony ask Maureen if
She want to go see a movie
They went and I'm on the way home and got lost
We wandered around
For quite a while
Before I realized
He was lost because
Just sent over the confidently in
Keeps going thinking he's going about
And the thing is that sting or
Anyway that first date
Led to a
A second and then to
3rd and then
12 months to the day later we got married and has proposed
Silva's very precise we was was May
Inmate
And he said I would have known you a year on October 7th
I need to get married and I
You don't get married
Because you've known each other for a year
And she said no
But we would save tax
The Business Schools
Excuse for that I'm afraid it wasn't the most romantic
So once you got married did what did you think you would just start get jobs in London and start your life
That was pretty much the plan that
We met just at the start of my two-year course and London and
We got married halfway through that 2 years
But time sometime in that second year together we decided we were going to take a year off
Go traveling and that's certainly
Change things
How did you guys
Make that two
What was the converse
Don't know if it was very much a thing to do with that are there
Later on they started calling it
Happy trail
And we we just coated the Asia Overland trip that you
You left London and you headed east
But this was the air right now the music of the time was
Riding the Marrakesh Express Wilma
The Beatles were off in India so that was a lot of sort of cultural significance to it
But we joined what became known as the hippie trial and we
Headed east
So this is I guess around
2 ish
In what was the
And the plan was to
Drive from
London
This car breaks down will
Get out of it and leave it by the road
We were going to go as far east as we could go have to dispose
It would break down would sell it one of the other
Start driving
To Europe and then
And then what
You just keep driving you going to the Border
The turkey in around and you go right across the road and then you go right across
Afghanistan annies
You just keep going for Pakistan and then you go through India and then you couldn't get across yet the flag cross Brahma
And then we just carry on the plan was
We get to Australia
And then we would stay in Australia and work for a while
I would save up enough money and would fly back to London and that was
That was the plan
We had so little money we left London with 400 lb
So that was our money and
You just stayed
Slept in the van
We did a x but generally we can
Most of the time across Asia in 2 weeks
How to use in Afghanistan
In Afghanistan you know a lot of the hotels in those days
Debbie and Gardens when you could camp in the god
How did you even know
Where to go in
And what to do in
And how to
Get the right bus I mean how did you
Figure all that
I mean if you walk into a bus
Stationed in Afghanistan and you're kind of pointing towards the Border
Somebody will put you on the right bus
You know if you're wondering gonna straight with a bag and you're looking to look at you look like you look your loss
Some of the hotel or you'll see something that looks like a hotel
It's easy
Because you just pull out your Lonely Planet
Really immature you know you manage and actually you know what was right is that you can travel for weeks with that
Sing another Western
But then suddenly apollon summer like Kabul or somewhere that you know
Are Harry and the others and you just spent an afternoon just trading information
You know when you get here this place is good this place isn't you'd swap information that way
Pacific old fashioned communication
And what look all along you are keeping a journal Tony or both you guys are
I did keep a diary I've always been
Reasonably assiduous about documenting things and
Keeping records of things
Where we stayed and what it cost and
How many miles to Carthage
And they did I know I think about the Palaces in the walls in the Fortress
This is important but those days it was very much
The information which is a good thing
Later on selling
And doing all this would like
The no money right
We have to do everything is cheap
If possible so it was third-class Trail and it was hitchhiking
We hitchhike from
Bangkok to Singapore
To get down there and then we went across
By boat to Jakarta and then we went by bus
Diwali and then
In Vale we were really run out of lock the airline that was supposed to that we were supposed to have tickets on to take us
Australia
Broke down
And didn't have any more
Planes
I'm so
We met this New Zealander who had little Yalta and he was looking for crew
To get done to Australia so we got on his yacht and crew
Australia
Like a scary at all
The only time I think I go
I got really we had a huge storm in the boat
And if I had to have more sensitive being terrified but they're so busy hang onto the boat
And then the thing thing
Australia and I remember
Standing on the out looking at this
Coastline
Nothing
Nothing at all
Bicep
Miles
From anywhere on there was nothing there snakes
Spiders I don't even know if I have no idea
What are you doing
What did you think you would do that
Did you think you would hang out there for a while because that
Connections in
Australia right
No
We went to Sydney Festival I mean if you're going to go to Australia
Sydney's the Golden City that you you will head towards sleep
The yellow brick road leads to
Azure crossing the Sydney bridge on our last ride and I said and done it was not long after Christmas so
Quite close
Holidays
I said to Tony how much money have we got
Left
$0.27 in English money
So what did you do
I had a camera so we we went to the area or sitting
Dispose of dinosaur things at 11 Shopkins on
We got $25 for my camera
I pulled back a week later
In those days you can get a room for a week for $15 so we
Single beds
Who's romantic married almost 2 years
You're the best
That afternoon instantly
Kind of
Corner shelf but they did sandwiches and things at the end of the day they let me take the sandwiches home that were left
So we ate
And I worked there for a little while until we and then we both keynote but good job
One year trip and not become a three-year trip
So what did you
What kind of job did
I got a marketing job for a thumb typical company
Maureen you're working a job another
What was job you're doing
I was a PA in a wine company so you're working for a wine cup
How do you get to a point where you
You
Start selling a travel book
Tony Tony has all the great idea
It's like it's from around the world let's go guide books I mean
I will say Tony is the architect in on the carpenter
This was off to read we met so many people that every time you went to some sort of
Party on
Met friends restaurants in Saint always someone would ask us
Where did you go how did you do this that was a lot of interest
Minnesota trip we did
Wake up telling them in writing things down and
Will actually information.
Able to get my typewriter and bring it home at night and
I've already Guillotine when we were trimming all the books and I'm on one of those massive Cypress to be stapled together
So in a way are we kind of the arrival to get enough equipment to do this
Printed but it was it was a very basic little boy that was a very it was actually done already was done on our kitchen table
Because actually we only had two kitchen
In the bedroom
We found a big commercial printer
Gaia hypothesis
Prince and Me
Basement under his apartment
And he printed them for us
Folded them and put them together and stapled
Facebook
When did they were finished and done we had them in boxes at our apartment
I took a day off where can I buy went straight to the Bookshelf that it said that
Buy 50 copies of it and said okay here I am
Write me the order
Phantom
You know I attended the day I sold a surprising number I was sending
What was the price
Tolerating 96 pages that sold for $1 AT&T cover
All the country
Old is old major in 96
We got her big break
Bookshop and she said
You want to buy this book and she said
To accompany us and I said Lonely Planet
She said I've never heard of them
And I showed her the book and she said off
What's your telephone number in case
I want to
Get my books that we didn't have a telephone
So I had to give him
Work number
She called me and she said
My flatmate is a journalist
She wants to interview you and your house
Husband on television
So we went on television to talk about our trip and doing this book
That was our first big publicity thing wasn't it
Yeah I was I was waiting for your first guidebook the pamphlet
Anime
There's some pretty different things in their right like I mean like it tells you where you can find marijuana
Where to get a fake ID and stuff like that
I have to assume that you
You know you guys
Could not have been
Stone hippies
Because you were pretty motivated to write everyday and to go places
We were actually really boring we didn't do a lot of that
Occasionally
But very rarely
Years later Lino's Lonely Planet
Became
Only skate
People who wrote using any kind of known and what they were really
Who people use.
Antonio and I would be at the
The cafe in all the cool people
Just didn't look
Cool and yet we were the ones who
Interesting
How did you come up with with the name Lonely Planet
There's a story behind that we
You never had we had everything we had a title for is it was across Asia
On the cheap
I'm weeping out to the restaurant and drinking too much red wine
How many just mean to say that a rock and roll band on the
Roadkill Mad Dogs and Englishmen
Joe Cocker and Leon Russell
Traveling around the US in the late 60s great film
I'm one of the songs in that that that movie in that that help MS
Joe Cocker singing a song called space captain
On the first line of the song goes
Once while traveling across the sky
This Lonely Planet put my eye
Humming the song
Peanut Sunrise what do we call the company Lonely Planet
Twitch Maureen said
Actually
First line is lovely planet and I wish you would stay
And he said bologna can't even better and I said how he said
It's a Great Dane
As well you know we're learning to live together on this planet
Soaked to the first book
Like make any money
Didn't lose money on its but it wasn't that
A real money making proposition
Better run that time when we were thinking of that okay
This is when we quit and head back to Europe
I'm done with my kind of thinking has sold surprisingly well
Maybe we should do another book
And what we thought was
Towards the end of the trip from London
With come down through Southeast Asia
Articles about time the Vietnam War was still winding down so
Southeast Asia wasn't seen as a
No hotspot for a
Holiday
It was able to place next to a war zone
But we could see that was about to change we saw it okay
What we'll do is we'll travel around
Southeast Asia
I will write the best book anybody has ever seen on Southeast Asia
We had a Yamaha
Trail bike
That was our kinds
And at this point Tony did you think this is
No I still think you know we would we realize we took we kind of sweet spot we found we were doing something that
People really liked
One of the things I've said a lot over the years is it it wasn't like you
Dot-com more
You know social media set up these days they start them one day and
A week later they worth a billion dollars
That was industrial weed
A business proved very slowly and I think it was
It was more like a snowboard
Rolling down hill
You got to keep pushing it at first and then it starts to develop momentum and starts the
Get larger as it rolls down the hill
When we come back at Tony and Maureen grew Lonely Planet
And then shrink it
Almost
Lost it
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
NPR
Sportframe
PR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
These to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to study
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to hedge Market
And earn guaranteed return
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions
Send a direct low-fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Lives NPR
Game Bridge is not available
In all states
How I built this from NPR
Gyros
Tony and Maureen were traveling around southeast Asia once again
And they're doing research for their second
Lonely Planet book
When it was just about finished I had a dummy of the book
That was one big book shop in Singapore
Geico
Appointment with the buy of that bookshelf
I talk to myself you know he'll definitely
Sydney by 10 copies and if I'm lucky you by 20 or 50
You listen to my Spiel and then I looked at my tummy of the book
I saw him riding southeast Asia on a shoestring in the
On the order form
How many Stanley order ride a push it across the desk to me
How do you put a thousand copies
DIY walked out of that Sam that office in
What about the race back to the hotel
Fantastic
Trapeze artist
Successful at book what
I mean
What was your name
And we did another one
Another one another one
People started coming to us with ideas for other books
Good morning did you think I mean so so by the mid-70s
Or late seventies
Did you still did you
You think that this
She's going to be
You're working me did you do
Could you both
Focus full time on this thing now
Pretty much
Although I was at Universal
But you know if I have plenty of time left
The funniest try not to travel first year though
Sitting on you Maureen salary while I worked on the books
I didn't think it was going to
They are life
It was still Tony and I
Living in a little rented house
With a pile of boxes boxes everywhere full of books
Address them with put them in the back of the
The car and take them to the post office I mean you don't really see
Multinational conglomerate
Fox to pick the books out when they came in from the printer and then sending them out again you know
It still felt very much like a cottage industry
And it wasn't like you went out and raised
Any money you were just until they would give us any money
Yeah basically know if you told a bank and what we were doing books on that site
Get a life
We didn't have any money and we weren't making a lot of money
To keep on doing books
But we did find other paperwork coming to us know that used up book and that's a
You know I really liked your book traveling around Southeast Asia
I've been living in South America or you know I could
Write a book about this place of that place so we
We started getting other people coming to us with similar ideas
I'm ready by the end of the 70s bad about 20 books
Turning Point what was the book that
All of a sudden
What you thought okay
A lot of data
And we respect that in 1980
This is the first time we that we've been able to
Put a team into a place
Morgan I have a one-time only had two other writers and we
So divided the country at the middle
By the week before I flew to India for the five months
Trek around India
Pregnant
Traveling Man India in
Templates and brochures and endnotes and
Yeah very much so you know
Little circle
Every brochure every time table every map
I mean we go was hardly anything
Sex and come back with his mask
Pilot
Information
Yeah yeah much easier these days when you put on a memory stick
Honda suddenly we had this book that was over 700 pages and
It's sold for
Yeah double-figures it was $12 or $14 or something instead of
I need your soul
It's always on a hundred thousand copies
Wow it was the first
All India book
Guy that told you everything
It wasn't like that but it was all of that huge interest in India at the
What time Minnesota
The company
Double DIN size of an item week
Suddenly started taking on more ride tourism
Looking at other big projects
So what did you do I mean how did you
Eight month old daughter what happened with us
And every
School holiday
Ridgewood
Just go left
Asia or whatever ended travel with us
Just for that period of time
Every time we go to a chance we
Go and travel as a family but mainly
20 was doing the writing and the
Planning and all that and I was doing the
Carpentry
Keeping it together
Yeah I would actually move.
Kind of ramshackle office
Kind of
Loose
Contractor
In and out do a bit and Float out again and we paid them
By the hours for the same so it was beginning to take shape
As a real business
When at what point did you stop having
Sleepless nights
About whether you work
Every year
I would say it actually towards
Late 80s early 90s
Increase more when
Became
I'll be a set this thing
Momentum and its
Who's carrying us
As much as we were
Pushing it I'll talk to people who are doing that and handing the publishing it out that time
And they said it just seems like
We couldn't do anything wrong
But every book we did our souls and
I think when we started doing Europe guides
Cuz we
We were just little publisher at the other end of the world
Who started off doing Asia
How many finally did get around to doing Europe
We would think enough by that point we could really do it well
And I think people in the office pretty girl
Kick out of that but it was such a thrill
Doing that
Taking out anybody in the world who wanted to try and compete with us
Everywhere you went
When using any kind of guy
Thrill you know you can a New York sing someone coming with a German
Copy of Chinese
You know whatever I just died
Was there ever a moment where
When doing well
Not looking very good
And I haven't arrived around 2000 and
Beard growing so fast
The point where we're doing so much
We had television going we had started investing
Heavily into the digital side of things a lot of stuff a lot of
You know we created a whole lot of death
Publishing before receiving the term
The money the books were still selling like crazy but we were just doing so much and
In the middle of that
When 9/11 happened of course
People stop traveling on travel guides NJ
Stopped
Did you think that there was a
Possibility that
I died
I mean
His charms but it's also one of the most infuriating things because
We were definitely looking
Had a really bad
That time we were looking at
Let people go
Back on our offices
Embassy Suite
The number books we did
And it was
Looking
Blazer
Is possible to housing pictures
In retrospect I think it was much more accurate the month
People start pulling everything
Together
I guess it was a wrap around that time and where do you
Selling the company
I think we both felt that it wasn't
Same company anymore it was
It was turning into much more of a digital company in that has a way of taking over
Everything
Chicken excited about kids
My kids are both worked in the company of one stage
Neither then we're going to take it over from us
Panda
And we just began to feel it was time to
Ubuntu something else
You did it feel
Wait to sell it
Teal
Sad
One of the saddest
I remember walking to the ABCs
Tony designer
Define opaque
CBC
Poop poop
Yeah and I said to Tony do you have your passport
And he said no I said no
Did you know guitar passwords I just go
Straight up the hill and get out of here
We could still Escape
I think I drove the sale
More than Tony did
And I always wondered you know if afterwards
He would really regret that
I haven't
I know his son
It took
Months
For me to
Like I still find it very hard
How to go back
To the office
You know I do
It's just hard
I mean from from
Somebody listen to this
Outsiders perspective
Tiger this week
You just live the dream I mean you got to
Travel around the world
Create a company
Yeah you sold it inside yours anymore but it made you
You rich and look at your life
Every year we do
Are there every year I go places on my own
Lino Maureen would not want to go to
I wanted to check the radiation to hobos these days
My consumption of up
I'm curious
I interviewed
John Mackey the founder
Whole Foods
The show and
He was talking about early relationship
If you had with
The woman that's the help
Start Whole Foods in and how it really
Destroyed their world
Broke down
He says you know business can really bring people together
Now I can do both
I mean you you guys are approaching V
Years of marriage and
It just sounds like you
Credible partnership in
Were there times
Weather time from you were building up his company where there was two
Tension and there was
Shut off fight Savannah scrubbles and always been playing silly
And you know you cannot
You cannot run a business will you bring
Step into the office
It was funny but Lonely Planet people over the new
First of all you coming
Talk to me about an idea
And I'll tell you whether it's worth
Tony has what's What's called the five
6 seconds equal to 5
Second window to engage attention
You know it's like the lights
Span of a mosquito
So they would come to me and say why not
I think this is right what do you think is good and they say
Tony
You let me talk
Talk to him first
How much of your abs
Your success and what happened with his company and
Everything
Using is due to lack and how much because you're just really smart and skilled
You definitely need that saying about you know whenever I'm working really hard I
I seem to be lucky
Interesting places near parents did
Element they were a big mama
I don't know
Skill
Came into it with Tony and I there was
Judgmental
Supposed end
And the fact
That we were doing something that we knew everything about
But it's clear that
His company could not have become what it became without without the both
Me and you both brother
Different skill sets
An amazing what you know
Dislike chance meeting on a bench and region
Is Park resulted in this in
Credible company what did
What were the
Traits
Both of you had like
You brought to the
Amor incense me nonsense
Honey
Lonely Planet would never
He
Was the dreamer the vision but he also
Channel 8
New hires going to
Lonely Planet
I'm very early on
And he never ran out of that pit
I got kind of mad
Fousey
How is you through so many things
However
He was not
He never wanted to
Spring meetings he never wanted to
Bankers
He liked all the stuff but you know he didn't want to hear what their problems
It wasn't terrible it was just
Really
You just wanted to know what me book we're going to do
You know how big was going to be in where the maps and pictures of the book so we did
Fabulous
Execute
Prison inside they just
Better and better looking each
It was good
I don't know that was Tony you know 22
Needs this
You know this is what we need
To do with this
So I would say that
I guess I've always
Could never visit
Mr. Tony
But it probably wouldn't have
Held2gether long without me
Not agree with it
Tony and Maureen wheeler
Founders of Lonely Planet by the way and its height the company was valued at a quarter of a billion
Dollars
The wheelers are no longer formerly involved with the company they sold all their shares but Tony
Did recently score a gig writing a chapter for a new Lonely Planet book it's called epic drives of the world
And as I speak
Tony is a size 3 and 1/2 month drive from Bangkok to London in a classic British mg sport
And one last question for you
When you travel like what is the thing you have to have in your carry-on bag
My passport no credit card
Percussionist cozy and comfortable
What kind of Cadillac
I never seen that you have never noticed
Please don't turn it off
In a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Do you have an idea for your next big move
You can use Squarespace award-winning designer templates
How to create a b
Beautiful website or online store
Equipped with everything you need to run your business
Is it squarespace.com to start your
Free trial and use offer code
10% off your first purchase
Hey thanks so much for
Sticking around because
Inow for Howie
You built that
The story will
It starts with a
Plastic bottle and I have one
Right here in the studio with me slightly full of water but a quarter of the way up
Okay and that sound that is the sound of me
Flipping this bottle a full 360 degrees
So that it spins in the air
Right side up which by the way is not an easy thing
To do but it is the type of thing that middle school kids can become
Totally obsessed with the fact it was really popular
Which is where Michael Mendocino comes in everyone at school with my friends come over to my house
Just a flip bottle sometimes and we just see how many different cool trick shots we could do basically and just
Do cool stuff with it show Michael Pease 15 and his family in Celebration Florida
Night last November
Michael and his mom Nicole were at home watching TV we were just sitting around watching Shark Tank
I was actually bottle flipping and
We just came out
But the perfect idea to create a board game and turn bottle flipping into a board game
And we looked at each other and we said this is one of those just simple aha ideas
Instantly it wasn't
Like we had to discuss it but we just said let's do this but of course is Nicole Michael's mom anyway
Next day after Michael and his two younger sisters
Got home from school we actually sat down and all evening we worked on coming up with
A really crude prototype
We just got out the board games that we had in our house
And we just started brainstorming
So the game that came up with comes with
A bottle of bored with a
Target on it
And a deck of cards that have a bunch of
Different bottle flipping challenges on the
Play put your arms in the sleeves your shirt like a T-Rex
Send flip the bottle
Keep your eyes open without blinking and try to land five in a row before you blink
The Mendocino has found a manufacturer in North Carolina who agreed to make an initial run of 10,000
Board games
We actually had the product available to ship on December 21st so we just barely made it
Before Christmas
But of course I had to still get the word out
Yasso
Most of the products
That I want to buy I see people playing them through YouTube
So originally I started by reaching out to a few people that I watch on YouTube
Eyeglass them hate can I can I send you this bottle Flip Game and will you take a look at it
We actually sent them the game and they put it on the channel and right now we have over 5 million views
All around from all different channels in their very first week
The Mendocino sold over a thousand games
And starting in August bottle flip will be sold in about a hundred Target stores and
If you're wondering about the sound of the bottle flipping
The closest hearing it over and over
Can drive a lot of parents
Crazy
So that's definitely been like a hurdle as far as marketing goes
But Michael says
He's already started to notice
When the parents played with the kids they realize how fun it is and now the parents are kind of addicted
Bottle flip is still a side hustle for the Mendocino family
Both Nicole and
Her husband are
Dignity jobs in
Real estate
But the game is already done $135,000 in sales
Since they launched it
In December
Anacortes
She's already dreaming about the neck
Best idea for a boy
Hey do you want to find out more about bottle flip visit our Facebook page just search how I built this
And of course
You want to tell us
Your story
Go to build. NPR.
Iorg
I love hearing from you
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or less
Previous episodes you can go to how I built this
NPR. Org
Please also subscribe to the show at Apple podcasts or however you get the show on
While you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us that
HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send it
Gets asked how I built this
Are shows produced this week by Rachel Falkner
Original music
Pose by Run
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to me
Sanaz meshkinpour clearbrain
Jack Rogers
I'm guy Raz Melissa
How I built this
NPR
Summer movie
ABCs and gets louder and
And longer ever
I'm Linda home
For God's through the black
Buster's you know about Anna
Surprise bright spots
You might not
Pop culture happy hour have you
We'll tell you what we're
Looking forward to what we
Secretly dreading
And what might you
Sneak up on Olive
Find pop culture happy hour on
On the NPR one app
Or wherever you get
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I be
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week