Support for how I built this and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corp
If you want to start or grow your business
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn Why by searching Michigan pure opportunity
So what happened to the business
It was over and I didn't have the cash flow and the phone started ringing and it
It was the landlord of that building saying you know what rent hasn't been paid you know all of my vendors you know
You started calling me my house was under foreclosure and my wife
And my mother-in-law
Ended up pawning their wedding rings that you know that that's the save the house right now
I never considered suicide but I know why people do
From NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
Lego
How Troy Carter went from the rough streets of West
Philly to launching the career of one of the biggest pop stars in the world
Lady Gaga
It usually takes a bit of instinct
Sim failure and a lot of luck
Figure out what customers are going to want to buy
Seth Goldman
He figured a lot of people would want a barely sweetened
Ice-T
And with honesty
It turned out to be right
Herb Kelleher
I thought people wanted cheap flights with no frills and
Well we got Southwest
Preferred Troy Carter
It wasn't just that he
Fat Lady Gaga
Huge
It's that
He had no choice
Because at the time he met her and this is just
10 years ago
He had lost all of his money he was
Totally broke
But somehow over the next few years
Troy essentially built
A company you could
Call it
Lady Gaga ink
A sprawling Empire of writers dancers
Choreographers costume artist
Roadies musicians
Producers Engineers marketers publicist
And Troy-Bilt that without any family connections
Or money order
Formal training in fact
Much to his mother's disappointment
Troy dropped out of his high school in West Philadelphia in 1992
To pursue a
Dream
Bad dream
Ways to become a rapper
We had this idea that we were going to be does rap
You know call to too many and it was me and two of my best friends
A 10-week we called herself
Too many because it was
We only had enough money for one of us so it was always two too many of us
And
My best friend said If We Ever Meet Will Smith Jazzy Jeff
Fresh Prince that going to give us a record deal
So that we had the soul
Focus and sole purpose of meeting Jazzy Jeff
Cuz those are the guys from Philadelphia
They were the only God can fill it up
They weren't they were from our neighborhood
They were successful they were like gods in Philly
And they were they were too way out
That was plant that was
Esplanade
GNC
So did you
Yes we we actually hop the train
And you know we don't have money so we just went in a wait for the train to pull up and jump over the turnstile and take
The train down the Delaware Avenue
And we knew Jazzy Jeff had a recording studio there and we just wait outside
Recording studio
Nothing we did that for almost 6 months and Jeff used to see us outside
But would never let us end I think
She thought we were like
Stalkers or something
And then one day we saw some friends in the studio that let us in
Will Smith and just happened to be in the studio and
We walked in and we played our demo tape
And he listened to it right then and there
He listened to it
Ni
We actually went outside it was snowing
And we said well we want you to see how to dance to so we ask
Ashley started dancing in the snow
I think we quickly found out we suck
But you know
Well saw some potential in US
Antioch he said look how you know how you guys getting home and we said we don't know
And he
I drove us home at night and bass
Sickly told our parents that
You know he had discovered
We're going to be okay
And what was it was a track you play for
Did you remember how close
My God it was
Pretty terrible
You have to give a sandwich
It was a song called where's the
The party happens like
I'm not telling you how I actually
I'm even said the name because you're going Google Now
Where can I find it
I know you are
Girls
It's not it's not so bad
We thought it was really good will thought I had some potential we put it out
And it went doublewood
So you made no money
We met zero
Zero money I probably still owe Will Smith Money
For that record that you establish a relationship
Was Will Smith
Which is kind of a big deal
Yes and you know what and we'll has a partner still to this very day named James Lassiter
You know he was in the studio that day we played the demo tape
And he was Jazzy Jeff in fresh Prince's manager
He actually got the
The job is their manager because he was the only guy in our neighborhood with a car
And James had become the sort of
Mogul in the industry
And
I wanted to be jeans
So in my soul
I wanted to be less
Fresh Prince
Amore Jean so I just kind of put myself under James
And James became mighty
CCU
Basically move away from from being a
Perform at that point in did the James give you a job
Yes James gave me a job I had a few jobs
Within the camp but I was James's assistant I was Jazzy Jeff's assistant
I ended up moving out to LA
And working with working with James at his production company what will
How old are you by the way
I was in my
Late teens early 20s
Sort of that transition.
And I was working at will and James's production company
And I was having the time of my life and I'm very hard headed thought I knew everything
And I don't have a car
I thought it was going to be like Philly where you just can't take the train everywhere and then La everything so separate it
And I was taking this
Car service
From the office
To visit this girl probably two or three times a week or whatever
But I would pay
The bill at the
Every two weeks when I got my check
I would pay like the office managers they hate a Bills going to come in
I got you
You covered it whatever
And one time I think I pissed the office manager Office
Over something
And she told James that I have been using this car service
What is the visit this girl
And James came in and fired me and sent me back the Philly
Wow so on the spot that was it you were done
Done
James basic
You know he saw the route that I was going and I was taking a lot of shortcuts
And I was kind of living this la
A fast life in
Soda stereo tip
Book or fake
Executive thing
You know I thought I thought I was much bigger than what I was at that party
Tequila time
He kicked me out of LA
Like you said go but you're going back home
So
Like
You're in your early twenties
You lose your job and you go back to Philly
Yeah I went back I went back to
The Philly soda with my tail between my legs
And my cousins and Philly had started a small management company and sort of a product
Shane Company
That they asked me to come in and run
And one of the clients with a girl that I met when she was 16 so she and I had known each other
And we started working together and and it was the rapper Eve
But I had absolutely
No clue what I was doing
And you know it started off you don't even come to me and she said luck you know I need your help and you know it
I'm figuring this out
And at first I was kind of helping her find a manager
Finally she said look I want you to do it
And of course I said yes and jumped at the opportunity
And
I think initially the job was
Protecting my friend
So instinctively
The decisions that I was making was really about
How do I protect her and make sure that you know she had the best
Possible chance to make it and everything else was you know learning as I was going along and you know
I remember the furs
Tore that we went on with this cash money Ruff Ryders tour
I got on the bus and it was
What does old bus driver
And you know scruffy beard and he said
You got the flu
I said I'll be right back
And I you know I got off the bus and I called one of my buddies who is done touring for a long time
Blessed dude
Float
And he said
It's the money that you give the bus driver for gas
Kohl's
Fuel you know everything else or whatever
So I got back on the bus and gave him the money and he knows
Sa here
The float
Anna and I sort of floated my way through the resta
Next three years I got a float at my way through kind of figuring it out as I was going along
What did you have to
Do as a manager for
Book shows in NJ
How did you even know how to
How to do that or how to promote
Her Brandon had to get her out
The world you know what that the way it works is
The manager's sort of
You know it's like the Hub
Of an artist
Career
So you know I go out and I hired a booking agent who who
Who books the shows
I hired a publicist who who who does interviews and television
I bringing the record label who
Distributes the music
So sort of like you know a CEO of
Even cover up her busy
And that
A pretty big business
Yes she she actually became
One of the biggest
Female hip hop stars of all time
And
I was lucky enough to have the The Fresh Prince blueprint so they kind of understand
That a rapper could do TV
In a wrapper could do you know things outside of their Core Business
And Woody we ended up building you know a clothing line
A television show she
Are going to do you know
Barber Shop you know what would
With Ice Cube and and
Cedric the Entertainer
So we ended up building something really special and something unique for a female rapper at that puts
How did you know what
Tudela
I mean negotiating is really really really hard
Workrite in MN you are so inexperienced that time like
How did you know
What's negotiate
You know what I think a lot of it is you know
Is is West Philly spidey sense
You know so
When you have to
Negotiate for survival
And you have to know how to read runes
And you have to know who the bad guys in the rooms are
Who has the gun in their pocket
Who's jet who's just going to brandish it and who's going to who's going to actually
We pull the trigger
So I think that's just a natural instinct.
Comes with
Coming from where where I come from
So
Being able to take that to Linton negotiations are on reading
People in Reading rooms and reading circles
I think it's very very important
And then also knowing
What's important for
That person on the other side of the
Table
And what's important
The client
Yeah and a lot of times
Is not conflicting till it so both sides can kind of get what they want out of it
So
I mean personally this point in your life
You're still
Really young guy like you're thinking I'm set I am
At this is all like
This is all
Unfolding exactly as I had hoped
Yeah you know I was
I was on cloud nine because you know this is
Everything that I've ever dreamed
That's all I ever wanted to do in my MMR
With with music
And because I was a failed artist
I was asked
Ashley able to help
Somebody accomplish their dream was
You know definitely fulfilling
And then the trappings that came along with it as a young guy
I was I was loving it were you making money at the
I was making Hood money
So I was like I was ghetto Rich at that at Peppa
Italy time
So if you had you know
The nicer house out of the
The 40 row homes on that side
The street you were doing okay but by no means was I
Was I rich
You know my goal with the make $1,000
If I can make $1,000 a week
That was it
Funny I would say
That was my that was my goal
What was the name of your company by the way. It was called Irving wondering like
And I and I did it out of Philly for 5 years and then I sold that company in in mm
Before you sold it to another management company
Yes it was a big company in the UK called
The sanctuary group
And I'm so I sold it to the sanctuary group and then move to LA to help them open up there earlier
Why did you sell the your master
That you
The real reason was
At that particular time it was
The largest liquidity event that I would have
Experience that was a lot of money
Yeah I was hustling you know I was living check to check
You know walking around venues with you know a backpack full of cash from venue to venue
So you know it wasn't
Weed wacker
Mastication and in a way we operated the business
And then the guys from Sanctuary you know they were managing guns and roses and you know a bunch of
Huge Rock axe
And it just done a deal with Matthew Knowles who was who's Beyonce's Dad
And bought his company
And he approached me and said look
This company can help you scale your business
They can help you grow your business you know in a way that you can't grow it internationally
And you know you don't have to live check the check you have a young family and he said look this is going to take you
Due to the next level and I and I ended up doing it
What is a pea
I Can't Tell You Why
Dependent players that NBA expired
They pay me more than I ever made you know but you know I'll tell you it was it was
That it was a 2 million dollar check
Actually
The actual number was
2 million
Buy $275,000 worth
The actual number
Because I remember when the wire when a wire went
Through
Add
Call and check the automated bank machine
About 10 times to make sure that the money was still there
Because I never I never had $1000000 them in my in my bank account
I never had even close to it
And you know in in the bank at one time
And
Here it was now it's like okay you know what it's
This is this is very real
And I just
Yeah it was very well
What was it like working working for sanctuary
I hated it
I hated it when you know it was it was fantastic at first
And because I was so excited that you know to get the check
Wheatley overlook
All of the red flags
What were they
You know what it just was 30
Things and certain behaviors that showed up during that
.
That I chose to ignore
Because I
That's it I'm just going to take
The check
And I'll and I'll deal with that and maybe he isn't such a bad guy
Maybe don't
Maybe they are at the kalander need some of the things that was happening
During the negotiations
I'm so coming in I just didn't do
The diligence on them that they were doing on me
So how long did you last
You know what probably I remember waking up
And
Talking to my wife
A couple times about buying a company back
Because I'm talking about you know
Me growing Up Loving music worship and you know Berry Gordy's and all of these guys in like
This is my
Dream and I didn't
Have a plan B in it
Is all I wanted to do
And I was
Dreading getting up in the morning going to the office
Like I had knots in my stomach
Going in and I was going to the office and I will pull my shades down we had glass office
And I will pull my shades down because I didn't want to work
People there
In about 2 years in a year-and-a-half and it was
And you were managing
Yes I was
The know when you lost Sanctuary Sanctuary you were still
Pretty much financial aid
Security
Yeah I thought I was invested
A lot of money back into the business
Into this new business
Did the new business that you started after you left Sanctuary after I left sanctuary
So
One of the things I realize was $2000000 isn't actually $2000000
Buy a house
Cheap 8 seater you pay taxes
You buy a couple new cars
And it's gone
Is gone I invested in and I invested in this new business
Anna
He was going with me so I said you know what
I know exactly what we're doing this is going to the next level
You did a build-out and he's beautiful offices on Wilshire Boulevard
And then started this new this new business
What happened to it
Are you not even walked in one day and I think maybe I'll
Probably about a
Year
Maybe a year or two into the into the new business
But she came into my office you know she sat down on the couch and she said I think I want to go
In another Direction
And I said what what do you mean
So well
I think I'm going to find new manager
So wow
Why
She said why I think
I want to go to the next level and
I want to go with a manager who I think could get me to the next level
That's it why are you thinking about anybody specifically she
He said yeah
Yeah I'm thinking about
This guy shot cam
Sasha Kim
Seconds
Mentor and good friend
So
She ended up signing with one of my good friends
Fomantis
And I mean she was like your
She was your ticket to making that new business success
Also
Even more she wasn't even she was my friend
And we
No really close you know she was there through you know
Girlfriend and do my wedding
Peanut birthday
Getting on my kid
Shenzhen
It was a heartbreak
Yunnan number one
In terms of how it ended up happening
You know and then the business what was highly Hedge
Ah not on that success what you know of her you know it was a single client business pretty much a day
So what happened the business
It was over
This was you know this kind of bleeds into you know going into probably
When
You know I didn't have the cash flow
And a phone started ringing and it was the
Landlord of that building saying you know at rent hasn't been paid no all of my vendors you know started calling me
And then it kind of spilled into home my
House
Was under foreclosure
And my wife
And my mother-in-law
Ended up pawning their wedding rings that you know that this
To save the house
And even down there that you know the kids were in private school and
Having to to tell you no
That this
Harrow school
Asking them to yunnan
Please keep
The kids in school
You know and I'm going to pay tuition I just need a little bit of time
But you know scared that when I gave the waiter my credit card for a couple of bowls of oatmeal that it was going to be declined
You know so it was it was
It was tough
And you know super humbling
Not not just as an entrepreneur but as a dad
Immuno and having a live
Through
That really that really dark dark dark.
And Hip-Hop is a very small community
And it will you know
We had a couple of buddies who were like
Need a real Executives in our business
What committed suicide who are you don't had success
Spell careers and everything else or whatever
And you know I'm with me at you know I never
You know considered
Suicide
But I know why people do
Obviously you had
Already demonstrated some Talent by managing
Eve and bite all the promotional work you done
But in your mind did you swear you able to save yourself okay I'm talented I'm going to pull out of this
Were the moments where you just.
I'm doomed
I am not going to
Get out of this
Now you know what
It's it's
You can't fall off the
And
I was on the floor
No nowhere to go right
And
Mom mom
You know she was a single mom we grew up where a lot of times we had to choose
Between
Whether we were going to have a phone line in the house or electric
And I remember us being on the bed with a penny Bank
And it was a bronze penny Bank shaped like a pig
And she was stick a butter knife into the slot
To get the coins to come out
And we would divide the coins up to get that you know so me and my brother
We have bus fare to get to school
So we grew up
Tough
Yeah
My mom caught the bus everyday
Day
To go to work and walk
Sometimes
30 years
Straight
So my mom
Work ethic
And spirit
Is in My DNA
And
I was always working
I wanted to make my mom and my grandmother proud
That was always a big thing
For me
And
Sorry
Are you know
I want to do that for my wife and family
And I and I think
Having somebody who has your back knowing you got somebody who has your back like that
The big deal
Two in the
In the midst of this
Just like really tough
.
What happened how did you
How did you turn the core
Wow
A good buddy
Vincent Herbert
Who's like this
Very jubilant guy
This is like a character but he's
Super talented
You know he was a child prodigy
He was like 16 or 17 producing records
Celine Dion and
You know Whitney Houston and and
Toni Braxton
And we were the same age
And every time he was in LA he will pop by and just
Yeah we would
Just talkin and
Ketchup
And he called me and said
You know
Carter I got this girl that I saw Myspace that I want you to check out
And any broader in
And she played her music at
It was great
And
It was Lady Gaga
In a moment the story of how Troy Carter came back from Financial ruin
And help to build a superstar
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
NPR
Support also comes from made
Where the motto is
Good days start with great jeans
How did they make them so great Madewell starts with premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
To turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated
Licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini the regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
I'm Gyros
Troy Carter is probably at the lowest point in his life
Houses in foreclosure
His businesses
Falling apart and
He's basically Banker
But around this time
Gets introduced to a young singer and piano player who calls herself Lady Gaga
Did you know
This is going to be here
Yeah you know what you
The real answer is you don't know
You think
And you hope
But you don't know
Whip people see now
Is what she was you know except for his you know she was a brunette
Nnc she didn't dance at that for
Tequila time you know she was behind the piano
Actually Ellie Reed
Dunya show
I just dropped it from Def
But you know what she did all fairness
The LA
Cheat she was a piano singer
Yeah and she going to West Virginia
Fried on a grandmother's couch afterwards because
Her dad gave her a year offense
School in basic
Oakley said you got one year
To figure this out or you need to go back to NYU
So she thought her dreams were shattered
I think it was that sort of thing you can't fall off the
The floor and so you know she had the spirit
And her that
You know when you feel that sort of pain
You never want to feel it again so she was a
Incredibly hard worker
So she just worked hard everyday to get better and better
So what did you guys
Start to do I mean how did you mean you are almost
Bankrupt
We Financial your bankrupt
And she's like oh
Please can you manage mean you're like
Yeah sure okay
You know we made music
That that was the big thing like then Vince was incredibly talented at
You know helping her sheep the sound
I knew
How to work with with female artists
You know I knew about the fashion business from working with Eve
You know got signed to Interscope
Put the same label that you was on
So I had a you know grape
Rapport with the
With the label already
So it was it was very
It's all natural kind of navigating it
And we know
I think we worked in a muse
Vamos
9 or 10 month
And then we took it to
The record label in the record label said all those songs are great
Let's give this to the Pussycat Dolls let's give this to Britney Spears so she ended up becoming a great songwriter
A few of the songs we
We actually
We fought for and we said we just not giving these racks
Heads up and we went out and we
Took those songs the radio
And it was a disaster
Radio wouldn't play it
It was the song Just Dance nobody would play that song
Nobody will play Nobody what plant did you start to
Build her career what did you do
We you know it
We ended up
This is as Facebook and Twitter
And my space
Lee sin YouTube all of those platforms
Restarting to
Just emerged
Places where you can read
Niche audiences
Is directly
And we started using a platform they were
Free
Where we got lucky
Is that a lot of them were global
They were in markets outside of outside of
The US
So we started reaching audiences and places where
We we didn't travel Geographic what would you do what you just liked post
Text or videos are like is like
Messages from Lady Gaga
Yep both how would people even discover
You know what is be sort of underground music community that wanted that want to find things
Before others
People find
And I'm and I remember we came up with this
This concept called Gaga
For YouTube
And it was like these 3-minute video clip
Basically
These are clips of her and her dance
Her and you know but we will have the better music
Underneath and it was
Suppurative
Mystic and you know she was
Brillion and in a one of the first
Music voices
Who really knew how to use and leverage social
And it really work
So we started building a soda underground following throughout the world
But it wasn't big
It was
75 to a hundred people in clubs that we would play
But we
Wii Super serve that
Community
Because just a few years or year-and-a-half
Before that you're in a
High-rise office building in La glass office building
Living this life as a
Corporate executive at this
Management company
And you are now like going back to
Two traveling in Vans and like sleeping in them and trying to get this artist into small clubs
Yep
Start started over
Wow. It over
And also you know this was Newt for me because this was pop music
Totally different front from Hip Hop
It was it was it was a different skill-set
And so so really start starting over
How are you able to even fund
Like the videos and hurt or like
Like you didn't have any money at the time so how are you able to do it
Interscope Records
Okay. So so Interscope stepped up
Nna funded
It sounds like they didn't think she was going to be as big as you thought you
No you know it was a shoestring budget
We didn't need alot
You know I remember her
Cheating on she didn't have outfits
So
She had this idea for this sort of mirror bra
Panty set
Oh whatever.
She couldn't afford so she took a mirror and she actually broke the mirror up with a hammer
Krazy glued
On to onto a bra and panties
We had this in for all of the early guy fans you know from the from the early days
You know she had she had this latex cost
Tomb
You know what these big shoulder pad
That she wore
Every single show
Not multiple outfit
It's one outfit that she wore to every single show
So you know so we we've basically bootstrapped
Is staying in an in every dime that she did make
She reinvested it back into her career
I think when you married you marry that with
The Perfect Storm of
I don't have a plan B
She doesn't have a plan B
Vincent doesn't have a plan B
We we have to make this work had to work
The Hat
Had to work
I'm getting anxious just listening to story cuz I'm thinking
Oh my God
Crazy Eights
Crazy risk
Okcu
So you're trying to convince State radio stations
Play her music you're building up a social media network but
What was the moment where
She just
Blew up
The moment that I knew
Like you know because it wasn't just
One moment right
Just was like
Grind over a one-year period to get it on the radio
And so I remember we were playing at
Theater
It was The Wiltern Theater in LA
And you know this is that things are feeling better
Yeah but I remember
Did we were so nervous about The Wiltern no
Because it's a thousand seats
But we had sold out a couple of nightclubs
So we like maybe we can stretch it will
Keep the tickets at $20
So you know so it's super affordable or whatever and we can give away whatever we don't sell
We can give to the radio stations or you know
I'm kind of pad the venue right like 2008/2009
Yeah right around that time
And I remember driving down the street
That morning because I had to go downtown for something
And I drove
Down in pasta
The theater
And kids were sleep outside
To get tickets to that show
No they had already bought tickets
Today Show
And they just wanted to get in first
And when I saw those kids sleeping outside
I said we did it
We did it because when you can get them to line up you got something special
You got something special
You know what it was pretty incredible you know we gone to places that I never dreamed about
Met people you never thought you would me
So
Not only did she go to an incredible level in her career it actually took me to a level and Maca
Career that you know I thought
You know what I would do with Eve I thought I was at
You know what this height was Zero your urine yo Mount Everest
Did you guys you and and Lady Gaga
You ever have moments
Where
You just had a quiet moment and you just look at each other and say how did this happen
Amazing
Oh yeah you know meet me
Me Gaga invent somewhere like this
Trifecta
And we will always have those moments like
My
God
Can you
Leave
Wow
You know you look out at
Krowd
Or you know
I remember seeing her play stings
Ring Forest event in New York
Where you know Stinger bring out you know Legend after Legend you know Elton John Bono
Stevie Wonder
You know just all of the greats and Harvey and the only
Young artist they are playing with those
Those guys
Seeing her hold their own with those guys and I'm just take her under a wing unit under their wings
So you know it just all those moment so it just you know very very special moment
Is it to drink during this time
Scissor like
2010's
You also start to
Like I said I'm going to Branch out right now
Yeah because you started a company
Around that time was called Adam fact
Yeah I started atom Factory
Three actually so I started Coalition Media Group
Was the original name of the come
Things started
It just say it was
What's the disorder of energetic shift
With that within a company
And you know I not gone through you know terrible time. I said you know what I want to change the name of the
Company I want to bring a new energy into it
And I said I wanted I want this company be to be something small but yet powerful
And just to be honest with you that the thing was
I just said I want to wake up everyday and Duke
That was
The mantra for me
Personally
And so whether that included management organelle producing tea
TV or whatever I just wanted to do things that that inspired
Yeah
So
See start this company
And Lady Gaga's careers
Doing great and
One day she walks in and says
I'm leaving
Yep
Walk walk in and say I want to go in another Direction.
Which is a story you had heard
Yeah so it's I can't say it felt any different than if it didn't felt the first time
But you know what is
It was a different experience
The first time I went into
To panic mode you know when that went to happen
Into me
This time you know I think I think I was able to
The sit in the middle of that storm
And and watch the
Storm path
Why did you
Want to part ways with you
Are you know what it's I think it did it happen
I think I did differs in opinion you know on what happening and why happen
But ultimately are you know I respected it
And took it on the chin
Are you guys still friends
You know I wouldn't say friends but cordial
Yeah cuz you was probably the closest person to you outside
Family fruit
Like a lot of years
You know that's the thing about management
You know you
I can't do it without
Pouring my soul into
I can't do it without investing one
100%
And internet relations
Episode
I didn't go into the relationship
Where
Guy guy with my guards up you know because of the thing happened with
Eve
You know so it just doesn't work that way
Phormium
Is just no Grey for me I'm on my the all-in or all-out
Is it
Bittersweet
To see her perform at the Super Bowl
112 and you know what is not not even better soon
Sweet I think it just
You know
That the songs that she sang at the Super Bowl
You know aren't those old records that you know I know the origin
I know the story behind
Let me know
We were part of
I was part of getting those records
Super Bowl so it's a part of my life
That you know I'm always going to be proud of
Completely different side of your career which
Which is arguably a much bigger part of your career which is
Investing
Basically
At a certain point decided
I want to invest in startups
Yeah that that sort of came about
Through
You know we were doing all of these things and Technology with these
Startups Wiki
What Gaga you know in order
Yeah just to promote the music
And the music industry and just Hollywood in general
We're in litigation with most of the United Technology Company so it was this sort of
This wall between technology and content
And we embraced it and so I started building a lot of relationships
Silicon Valley
That
Introduced me to a lot of young entrepreneurs
Who started asking me you know can I buy sir companies can I put in some
Traduction
You know that I want to invest in their companies
And that that ended up turning into you. I think I've been vested in close to a hundred early-stage technology
Companies now
Yes
Kriti Sanon flight
Uber Warby Parker Spotify regularly industriales
Yeah yeah Spotify Warby
Uber Lyft
Dropbox
Flag
Really great companies that
We're proud of
So like looking back at that
That 2 million-dollar check that you got
20 years ago mean you are
Let's face it like your
Very rich guy now
You've done very very well do you feel
Secure now do you feel like you'll never get back to that
Point you know 2006 worth up the banks are going after you and trying to
To take back your house
Is itsfunneh tok talkin to like pee
People who grew up poor
You suffered Financial PTSD
XOXO
Going through financial PTSD
You always have that fear that thing must have it
Yeah you all you want you always have it
So
I'm just
I'm a simple guy
Appreciate in life and the things that make me happy
10 not that have to do with with the money itself
More importantly is
Have an ability
You to live a life that I can wake up every morning doing what I love to
Nothing's more important to me than that
You never went to college
You don't have
An MBA you don't have
An advanced degree either
Being
I think to Harvard Business School case studies about you and Lady Gaga which isn't that great irony but
Ever feel like you didn't
The law that you weren't
I don't know that like you are around people who have credentials and
Made you feel intimidated
At times right you know in
If I had a 5th grade teacher
Teacher named Miss Moore
And I was always the littlest
Guy in the class
You know you take this to school pics
Pictures of you get in line
To go to lunch in the hallway I was always first in line cuz I was dead
The smallest guy
But she used to call me the big guy
And she made me feel like I was six foot five
And like she get it was something that she did
Psychology
Did that like
Really really
Made me feel
BL
Not only did I belong
But that I was special
So
You know sometimes I'll go into rooms
Where it's
This person has a lot more experience than me that much smarter
Then I am
But I know what I know
And I think I bring
A very I bring a unique point of view
You know just
With different experiences
And I'm
Confident in that point of
Elsa singing with the story you told about your mom
Early Iran
And she must be so amazed at
And how turned out I mean you
Meet you dropped out of school she was super disappointed
And
Look where you are today
United she she passed away
3 years ago
And yep and
She was 63 years old when she died
And she spent the last
3 years
With me and my family
But I remember
Man
We were at an award show
They were giving me some award
Forney Chief Montano in the music industry
And she was she was sick
And
She was my date to the show
And we saw Berry Gordy
She said that's you
Do you like Oprah you bring out the tears
Troy Carter founder of atom Factory
By the way Lady Gaga was not the only star they managed over the last several years the roster is
Secluded John Legend Priyanka Chopra Meghan Trainor and John Mayer
Quit rapping when he was a teenager it was probably a good one because too too many song where's the party
Are you the earlier it's been on YouTube for 10 years
It only has 13000 views hey thanks so much for listening to
The show this week if you want to find out more about it you can go to how I built this. NPR. Org
Please also subscribe to our show on iTunes or however you get your podcasts
You can also write us at HRBT at NPR. Org or follow us on Twitter that's at
How I built this and one more quick thing this week we've taking a little break from our how you built this segment but we're dead
Definitely could be back with a new one next week so if you want to tell us a story about something you're working on
Go to build. NPR. Org
I sure was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to neva grandson as meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Claire Breen on Guy R
Arise and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey if you're still listening in a lot of people ask me what podcast should I listen to
And I listen to a lot in one of my
Favorites is NPR's Planet Money
It's full of
Superfund
Insightful stories
Explain all kinds of things about the world you don't even have to care about
Finance or economics to love it
It's a great show and yuan
Can find it right now
Npr.org
Podcast or
On the NPR one app
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email templates drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com