This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who understands every small biz
Business is uni
Impaler's it's Palace
State your business is very specific
Get a quote or purchase of house
At h i s c o x
.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
We are told by the record executive Ross Janice I want you guys to take take the Chipmunks
Down the road we want you to take them these are the 7 cities we want you to go to an
Make this album I hit in these 7 cities and if you do that we will give you a big Nash
Channel promotion we hit the road we in fact make the album a hit in each one of the
The Seven Cities we come back to the record executive the record Executives tells Janice and
Well
We're not actually going to do the national release in the Big Marketing
I said you told us that if we would be said if you don't have it in writing
You don't have
Ramen PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Realist stories
And the movements they built
Billion dollar brand around three singing chipmunks
If you want to build say
Pantheon or Mount Rushmore
Saturday morning cartoon
Tunes of the 1980s
A statue to Alvin and the Chipmunks
Thanks would be right there alongside the
Smurfs the gummy bears
Inspector Gadget
It was one of NBC's
Biggest hits
Singing Alvin Simon Theodore
And they're exasperated
Kind manager / foster dad Dave Seville
Has anyone seen my Thai
You're wearing a diaper
All these voices Theodore Alvin
Diamond Dave
Two people
Ross bagdasarian Jr
And his wife Janice
I'm Theodore
And I'm Alvin and Simon and Dave
Do you want us to talk at house
The Voice
The characters
The pretty much ran and run the company that is Alvin and the Chipmunks
The movie is
Merch
TV syndication the live
Shows
All of that
Rotten
Billions
Billions of dollars
Studios and networks
Katarina
Even quite a bit for rocks
Part because
I'm like most other creative people in Hollywood
Ross and Janice the Chipmunks they own the intellectual property
And Toad
Chipmunks Inc
Is pretty much a family business
Run out of Ross in
Genesis House
Near Santa Barbara California
Actually invent the Chipmunks the actual image
Ventura was Ross's dad
Rossini
Singer was a struggling songwriter
Looking for a break
Figured out a way to change the pitch
Elvis singing voice
Are the results
The Witch Doctor song
The song became a hit and run
Soon came up with this concept that it was sung by these
Anthropomorphic rodents
Call the Chipmunks
Are all the sudden Rush seniors career took off
The Chipmunks became a radio show and then
Cartoon on
Television
Infer Ross Jr
He watched his dad
Become famous
100% it changed
Literally overnight first with witch doctor witch
It was like March 1958
And then of course
The Chipmunks were
That November December
So we got a swimming pool
Also I was I was much more impressed that we had a swimming pool than that my dad
It was on The Ed Sullivan
Show doing the witch doctor or Dick Clark's
American band
Stand weather
I remember he would always bring my brother and sister and I
Into his Dannon play
Whether it was Witch Doctor the Chipmunks song or whatever and we loved
When Alden started talking back
To our dad
We just
Fell in love
With nausea
The song but the audacity
Of that little character
Because we didn't really talk back
To my dad that much so we thought Alvin really
We had a lot of spunk
That we admire
What was your dad like was he
Elysium
Saying what the witch doctor
We see this impresario was he charismatic was he silly or
You know what he was all about
Guy he was
Bigger than life he was served the Armenian version of
The Zorba the Greek
So are all 5-7 up him but you always thought and everyone a mess
Thought that he was 6-5
He just carried himself that way but he was
Funny
He was incredibly creative
If he loved me
Music in really thought of himself
As a musician
He loved songwriting
Started writing songs
When he was 16 years old
Driving a truck in The Vineyards of
The Fresno
Dinosaur song was
Call nuts to you
So,
From nuts
Game little
Yeah
So when you were a kid Ross
Did you think that
You would be involved in in the family business
100% no
You know
A growing up
I didn't even want to go to the recording session
Since my dad would say
Do you want to come and let's see how we do this and what
I go yeah I know
I got a big little league game here so
I'm going to not make it to that
But growing up
As I start
Realized
What kind of a career was I heading for
Are the only thing I was certain of while my dad
Still alive was that
I wasn't going to
Be involved with the Chipmunks or what my dad done not because I didn't love what he had created but because
They were such big shoes
To fill
That I didn't want to try and step into
I know rostad
SeaWorld
3 when
When your dad died
Brett young like
Is early 50s
What would he want you to do
With your life
My dad passed away and before he had passed away he said
I really want to encourage you
Go to Los
School and I
I just hated that idea but when he passed away
All of a sudden
You saw the kind of
Folks coming out of the woodwork that would try and take
Whether it was music
Publishing
From the family or
Wineries and Vineyards
He had built
Stop over the years and I realized
That my dad wanted me to go to lhasa
School obviously not to become a lawyer but basically to have a
Kind of a
Mental martial arts
Protection
Because he always
It said look there's creating
What you do and then there's
Continuing to own
You doing and those are tough things
To do at both X and less you know
How to protect yourself
Open and contracts
Boxing Sulphur soap
After he passed away I immediately enrolled Plus
School so I graduated
3 years later and 75 pass the bar wasn't going to
Pasquale butt
Wanted to know that
With a music publishing and end the things that I was hoped
To create
Later on
I wanted to know how to
Hold on to them as my dad had done
Did you I mean at that point where you
Already thinking about
Getaway stat to revive
The Chipmunks
Yes
After my dad passed away
I would go up into his office and just listen to
The song
30 and done why walk
The old TV shows
Sofia done at the Alvin show
And
I just thought
I didn't want the Chipmunks
Pass away as suddenly is my dad
And I wanted to figure out
Someway.
Try and bring them back
So when I met Janice
And she had loved
The characters growing up and
One of the shows at her
Folk sweater
Mercy
So I now had
Another believer with me
And I said
Jenna just want to see
If we can do this for you don't just a year or two
Bring you no kind of a trip
Get to my dad and then
And imma go and do you know of course all the other things that were interest
Janice
About where you were
Because you were
You were like you are an actor
Yeah
Could you yuan Ross
Well we met at a Health Food Vegetarian restaurant
When I'm in LA
Saw
A friend of mine
Who is
Having dinner with raw so I didn't know
I went up to her to say hello and
Was introduced
Mr. Ross
And
The following day I got a
Bouquet of flowers
Where is where I was born
Working and
The next day I got another
Okay and they were all signed
By Ross
But I
I hadn't remembered his name so I didn't know who is sending me these flowers
I made quite the impression that you can tell ya
For several weeks
And
Finally he called
He said hi
Agenesis rothys
Ross
Thank you for those flowers there
Beautiful
Who are you
And it it took about
3 years for me to come around
3 years
And so he took me to his father's office
At at night and it was
And I'm going up the elevator and I'm thinking
Where we going in
I didn't tell anybody I was going out with this guy and what are we doing in this Phil hanging
Put on the weak spark into an office and they put on the old Chipmunks
And I thought wow
He's staying and then he told me he was the son of prospect
Vissarion
And I said oh my God that was one of the
Douche few cartoon shows I watch
Austin and love them
So then he said you think they would be viable today and I said
I would think so
And I had it listed her
On my impossible Quest
Stud My Little Don Quixote
Fighting fighting these little windmills
The Chipmunks exactly
You just like
Start trying to
Pitch people on on the
Yep we'll first
We went to CVS because they had run the old shows the Alvin show so that seem like an act
To go in and
Listen we thought we loved what your dad did
That we thought it was great that we
We think history is moved on in and it had its
Wonderful time and that's
That's really over
So then we went to the music
The side of things and I don't know if they just spoken to the people at CVS
They said you know that was a wonderful wonderful characters and your dad had a great
Success but we think that's a
Time has passed in and you guys should move on to something after young and capable and off
Hugo
Continue to happen
Just go to
Studios and production companies in and they would
Just turn it down three months are in 4 years
And Super Why did you stick with it I mean
You eat at that point your
I guess you're in your twenties and you've got a lot of Grease
Possibilities are married at this point
How long should you
You keep going out and getting rejected and how long was it
Set period of time
First of all although
A nose
Fuel Dross
And then actually fueled me as well
So
Write their name
When we make this big
We're going to
What we see them again oh now you wanted well we're not going to give it to you and I like a fool to take out my little
You spell your last name for me
I mean really how did you keep going at it when when all these people are saying
No no no I mean work
Dejected
Just feel like humiliated or did you know honestly I didn't
I just felt
Hopewell
I am going to show them they're wrong I know this
This is going to work
Janice believes in it there's two of us for goodness sakes so no I was just more
And more
Asset
On what however long this took
Yeah but I mean look
The Beatles Advocate you can understand from moment you can understand what why a television
Executive at
Time somebody who who who
Next big thing to do it
Would certainly look at your proposal today at the throwback to the
The 50s were doing like
Roomba crazy things now
Nina Ross taught me the power of tenacity
Guy he pursued me for
For three years
Every single day
Because because because I knew we were right I knew what this was.
Perfect person for me
And not to equate Janice Wu
With the chipmunks butt
But I honestly believe it when you really believe in something so clearly
Play it's so
Clear for you as a as
That was for me I didn't
Care what anybody else
Said
We were going to make this happen if it took
Took a year
Orphan
Why did you believe that it would work any why all of these experts
Noah
What all of these people who
Experts on television
Look this is a
This is oldest
Tire franchise like Beano just enjoy life and
Why did you think they were wrong to to two things number one
What we came to realize is that there actually are no a
You know nobody
Really
And so I was just willing to
To put my belief
Above
What other people were
We're telling us in and Janice felt
The same way we thought they were
Yeah I felt I felt that
Let you know in listening
The Chipmunks song in the witch doctor
Doctor in Alvin
President
That there was this relationship
With Dave and this
Chipmunk who kept pushing his buttons and I believed that relationship
And so did millions of
Other people and and he really enjoyed
That that Dave and Alvin really endeared themselves
To us and I thought
If we could get that relationship in the shows
Then it could happen again
So what happened what was the turning point
The turning point was a disc
Stockings
Philadelphia
See you at 3 in the morning
Play the blondie song in
Set it up
And told his listeners that it were
Who is the latest song from this
Album chipmunk Punk he was being completely
What was the what was the blondie song
Call me
I just spit up a little
The Chipmunks
And his a switchboard lit up
And
All these people
Book called wanting to know where they
How to get the album and a record company back east
Found out about this and called us up
And said that would you be interested in doing
A chipmunk we didn't even listen to the end of the sentence
It was just some random small was in a small room
Would you do a chipmunk
Punk album would you be interested in a chipmunk Punk album
But
We were
We're very up
For it and as a
It turns out it
It's sold over a million
Albums
Overnight and
Then the people
At CVS
You know of a sudden they wanted
Have lunch
And was it relatively cheap
Mapreduce
I don't like to say cheap
I would say NXT
Wow so you put that record out it just
Cells
Crazy a man what in the
Television
Follows telling company start to call you will right after that as Janice mentioned not only were the TV
Folks who we'd gone to much more receptive and now interested
But it also gave us a
To chance to look at doing
More music
Because obviously it is sold so well
So we were approached
To do not only
Christmas album but also
Okay what would be
You know the
The farthest
Thing away
From
This album cuz we didn't want to
Do a
Pidove that
So
Urban cowboy hat come out and we thought you know what
Let's go to Nash
Bill and Ruth's
Record
Urban
Chipmunk
So we
We took songs from Kenny Rogers and
The whole bunch of love a rainy night and got him a
Country boy all of these different songs
But one of the things
The chance wanted to do in that album
Was now create
Some dialogue some stories
Do some personality and nausea
Nacho song song songs
Yeah and said that I said
Draw so how do we do this
How did your dad do the voices
End
The dialogue
And he said I have no idea what did I know
Went back to the house and I played his
Fathers
Tapes
Saw that he
Talk to task
Until I went back can I said okay
This is what we do
So you're you guys are recording this like
You're speaking beerus
Clearly and
Slowly so then what are you
Speed up the tape it sounds
The same speed is we
Speak but it's at a higher pitch
Right
Just a dresser like a lady
Disco question
When you started
To do the voices
How did you just give me a sense that give me a little taste of obviously everyone listening knows you are Dave
Like how do you record album like
Just give me a line of
How you would record I will do that but I want to also say that
Janice was
Just wonderful is Theodore right from the beginning and I was
Still so tied to what my dad had done which was
Barry
Clear and
When my dad did Alvin it was
Hello Dave
How are you doing today
Very stilted and it didn't feel real
So
Janice
I would say
Ross you know what
Don't try and do an impersonation of your daddy there's David's
Seville Orange
Salvatore Simon
Loosen him up make it a little bit more your own
And so
Now after
All of these years
I've obviously gotten better and so now Alvin is
More fluid
For me and even though I have
How to talk more
Slowly
Dave listen okay I know
You can continue to talk about
A blah blah blah whatever
Santa I'd like a word with you and your l
And I I would
Would say
Flower
Right right
I remember what you
Said the last
Time
So can I please just
Leave
Can I talk to you a minute
There's nothing more to say Alvin
No
So what television
Actually then end up
Happening cuz it happened I guess an in 1983 that the Chipmunks cartoon
Comes back on TV right before that guy in 1981 Jensen I've been taking around
The Christmas idea
Christmas special
From probably around 78 or so
So so after
Chipmunk Punk comes out and does so well and then Urban chipmunk
NBC said to us hey I know we told you we thought that was a
Terrible idea and we didn't like that
Chipmunks butt
We now
Think with those two of platinum albums
Maybe that Christmas
Specialist a good idea
Did you get any Executives that have
Previously rejected YouTube
End up meeting with salmon and and having
We're likely begging you to come back
Yes
And I'm not going to give you names but many of those people that were on our list
A lot of my old but so when they approach you they said we want to do a Christmas
Special did you have a concept of what the cartoon would look like a howdy animated and
Did you already have that late already trying to figure that out we didn't even we had never
Written anything be
Before and when they they sit so who do you see riding it raw said
We're going to write it
And I looked at him
Across the room
Declared him
Saying
And
And again because of necessity
We wrote it
And then
No we didn't have a look we didn't have
The voices we
Still warned expert
Add
How did you even know what
Do I mean obviously
You know you're both super
Smart and talented
Animations
Studio overnight you're standing up
Animation Studio
Which by the way United
Very expensive cars
Is it still hand drawn
Stop right
Exactly Ross and I have done everything everything we've
If I ventured into we've know nothing about
So it's
Stay in start from stupid
It's the hardest way in the best way to learn
And you just go step-by-step okay
We need to create Carrick
Okay we need to know what this world looks
Like and
We were really
Very fortunate
Because
Some of the
Rate
Animators from Warner Brothers
Including Chuck
Jones and
Phil Monroe
Virtual Ross and these guys who have done
The greatest bugs
Bunny cartoon
The 40s
Were available
And they weren't being used in
Janice and I hired
All of them to make
Hobbit the Christmas Special A Chipmunk Christmas
After that crisp
Especially
DC
Clearly
Success because in NBA
AC
Car deal with you
What was that first year was
What's today
A11
Season of
About in the Chipmunks
Yeah it was always that that sort of Wonderful
First
The first series
Steel so it was
It could be as long as five years but it's
Was one year at
At a time
And
We got
Very little money for back in those days
Like $210,000
Half hour
Shows
So there wasn't much
To cover all your
Absolutely sew-in weave
Oh yeah we were we were used to going into our own pocket yeah
What is the show launches in in 90
E3 this was on
Saturday morning
That's right
And we were against bugs
Bunny
On ABC and CBS
Who didn't want us we had gone to them first
Cuz they said why do we need the Chipmunks we've got Charlie Brown
Snoopy
We could be you know you could have to split up Snoopy at
Anyway so we turned out to be a Again Sports
Charlie Brown and Snoopy in
And the Chipmunks
Series with a
Giant hit right from the beginning I remember
So I mean it's interesting because
What you think about
The consumer right you're thinking about
Mickey Mouse now then
Bugs Bunny
The Peanuts Gang and they're all great like we love them all we have
These warm feelings about that but actually
From the perspective of the creators of these
The characters like
Azure competitors
You're going I guess I never see them is
Competitors
You didn't like what I just Crush Mickey
No arms around
We Are Young we honestly always felt it was like our
Conversation with CBS when they said well we've already got
You know Snoopy & Charlie Brown
Always thought that
Good
Shows or good characters
Can coexist we didn't feel like we needed to go to war with anybody
Buddy we just wanted to
Create something that was
Unique toss but guy to be honest
It you know it
If if the
Executive Search
In a rude way why do I do we want to crush the exact today
You know Snoopy executive
In just a moment a deal gone bad that
Put the Chipmunks
On life support
And how Ross and Janice
Revive the franchise
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
8 things tour 2019 lead sponsor
How I built this
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
You understand that
Each business
As unique as a fingerprint
Or barcode
Tailors in
Elgin Insurance Solutions
Every business is very
Pacific need
Explain their 97% customer service
Get a quote
Purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance
Support also comes from NPR
Sponsor gamers
The Bold way
To steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex
Sore only for retirees
But annuity
Please can be a smart way to hedge Market
And earn guaranteed return
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Bag with clear condition
Send a direct low-fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Lives NPR
Game Bridge is not available
In all states
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
A guy Roz
It's 1985
And Ross and Janice get through the first season
4 + b
BC and even though
The show is reaching
Huge audiences
Start making a whole lot of money
Remember the
Deal they signed with NBC was for
$1,000 for the whole
But what they did have was
Something much more valuable
The right
The Chipmunks
I mean you guys own
Everything else
You own that you own the master recordings you only animation
Characters
NBC
She didn't say
Hey if you want to deal with us
You know we on the right
This thing in all the lights
You know because my dad had
And not only is you mentioned
Set that up he was a
First songwriter
Who not only owned
The publishing
Abbott also
The master recording
That's what I enter
Trustingly when we met
Berry Gordy years later he said you know I learned a very valuable thing
When I was writing songs
I decided to
Found Motown
Because I wanted to own the master recordings the way your dad
So it was
My dad was really
Not only really
This Great Neck
Pics of creativity but also very
Really smart about business and and so
I knew that
Is my dad mention there was creating
Wonderful
Product
But then there was
Holding on to the right
NBC said we will make this
Into a cartoon
Searching for you
And you guys have been
Pitching
Desperate
Sears I mean if NBC would have said to you but these are our terms
I mean
Walks away we would have because what we said is look
Will produce it
We'll make sure we get the financing together we'll get a license
Some speed from you we brought in
Kellogg's o Kellogg's
Was our sponsor
And Janis and I
Wrote the shows and then we produced it and
Dr.
First season they came to Janis Ian
Is it okay we'd like
To expand it now we want you guys to do an hour
Not a half
And we we just said
We can't even make a half-hour we're proud of
So we when we can't work any longer unless you make more than seven days in the week so we're going to turn it down
She said note By Janice nobody turns down more shows
But we did
So you are you making these shows Randy
See you're obviously
You just not making any real money from
Definitions cuz it's going to pay the production
But you are getting all this
Visibility so
But you're also running a business
At what point did you guys sit down and say
This is a business like let's think about how to make
Centos something
Really really
What was the
What it what was it that you start to think about
You know
Guy we were just sitting at home all the time
So we didn't you see the numbers
You see the ratings
But they don't really Translate
Into people
You know you can imagine but
You just don't get it
Back in those days we were getting like
40%
Of the ADI
Like 20 million a week or 15 to 20 million a week so
Finally got an
Invitae Tweed did a live show
And it was at Madison Square Garden that people dress up
Yeah we did the voices and
Design the costumes and got a story together
And we didn't have time to
Torrid but we
Go to Madison Square Garden
And when we went to the box office
The guy said no II
I didn't know you were coming I sold your
Tickets
Sold out
Reconstituted
See the shot yes
And he's
And I said what we are
We are the
Anyway he let us sit in the aisle
And
For the first time we saw a fans we saw kids
Waving chipmunk banners and screaming and the place was filled and it was such
A moment for us it will never for
Forget it was like oh my God
There are
Sit there people be like the show they like the character
I mean your business
Really became the Chipmunk
It was
The television show on NBC
Sea with record
Merchandising live shows
And I guess like syndication
Yeah and
This is one of the funny
Business stories and I found it interesting only
Only because later on it turned out to be such a windfall that we did not know about
But they said
Look up
What's going to happen is it
CBS Viacom is going to run your dad
Old shows
The Alvin show
Against us
Because now that you're bringing the Chipmunks back Sosa
Successfully with the albums in
Christmas special and now the new series
You have to get
Viacom
To not do it on Saturday morning and we want you to offer them the syndication rights
For the new series
Esl just
Not run up against us and so Janice and I not knowing the value of syndicate
Haitian what did Viacom CBS and said okay
If you just won't run against our new shows on NBC
Will give you the syndication rights
H2r new series
And they
A very full of themselves said no we're not going to
To do that deal
And then a couple years later we
Sold those right
425 million dollars
Score something
Wow and that's and that was where the money
Which we did not know we would
To the syndication rights were yours
No not at NBC didn't get a piece at all
Tremendous amount of money now but
But in 1980
More money I mean
What is that mean to that
I mean I think anybody listening
Just assumed that that was it you guys were
Set for life
Yeah well first. Was very exciting and end it was just a number I was always a
Even when I was watching the
You know the price is right as a six-year-old
I knew what
The dishwasher would go for or the
And my mom would always say
How do you know that you've not bought dishwasher isn't there but I
But I always had a sense of what
A price for something was going to be
So I had just set that price
And I didn't change until we got it
And
Janice and I
So wanted to
Make something we were really
Proud of not
Just something that was
Successful
The TV show
Was obviously tremendous
Successful
But we were never able to give it
The kind of quality that we had hoped
To do
So
Yes you would think we would be sad
But
Because we always wanted to
To do something we don't
Proud of
We
Took most of that money and made an animated feature the Chipmunk Adventure in in Quebec
Which came out in the 80s
And that that movie did
Pretty well right you did it it did well but we didn't at least in that initial that we didn't get our money back back in though
Those days cuz unfortunately we
Signed on with a distributor
That was going to put
X number of dollars into marketing and
Distribute we were
They spent less than 900000
Marketing the the movie
And including the prince and add
Advertising so
It it it
Did
It did okay but it did not
Remotely get a
That's my money back until
Many DVD sales
Ross wrote a little article on that
Experience
Making the movie
He called the agony
And the agony
Hard to find a bright spot at night
Different stories about because the show airs
Is on NBC and you are doing original
A new episodes until 1990 and then
I guess it's in syndication
And then you guys decide to move on you
You basically
Leave NBC and Curry deal with
Universal to bring the show back so
What was that about
So one of the things that they wanted
The do
Was create their own Mickey Mouse
Send end
They had had Woody Woodpecker
4 years
But Woody didn't have
A disorder residence for Generations
The way Alvin did
Then certainly didn't the way Mickey Mouse
Stay the night
Had seen that
When we had gone head-to-head what it was
With Mickey Mouse in it
Album or a TV show
Or what have you that
The Chipmunks
Not only held their own but
But it's very very well and you
Came out on top
So Universal love
That Jesus
Alvin could be our Mickey Mouse
So the idea then was
They were going to create a
An animation
Unit for us and Janice and I were going to run that we would of course not only do more more
Chipmunks
A lot of other things that we had showed them that we
Wow
Yeah. We were going to be in their theme parks and end end
That part actually did happen but
It was going to be this
Whole shmorgasborg of opportunity and so for Janice and for me
Oh my gosh this sounds fantastic
Did you have to give up some of your ownership
Perfect date they bought a 25% share at that
Point-in-time Ananda
In the end.
For the opportunity
For what
Felt like a
Really
Exciting offer
Opportunity to
Grow the business in a month
Larger way
Felt like a great thing
Did that the money was going to help
Uscale yeah yeah and they were going to be
Also
Putting money into
Development and production of all of these
Thanks
And then shortly after we sign that deal
All the folks who wanted to do that
We're gone
What do you mean they're gone
They all left
So now you are
Yeah we wound up in a place that
Wasn't the same
As we thought
It was
What's what you mean like
All the all the people trying to do with universe
Oregon do you still have
Deal with the universe
The commitment
I mean I guess
Personally to make movies in
How to do the
All kinds of stuff so
Why would you just do it
Yeah well we certainly wanted to do it but you idiot ask that you have to ask
Somebody new comes in and they have a
Envision yashow those were not our happy years and we wound up
What are standards
What happens if you stop answering your calls because
You were presumably working on ideas and
Will you pitching it and they were saying no
Or what were they just ignoring you what
Was there was a, dynamic yeah I know it was a combination of
It started out
Very excited
And then
Some of the folks would brought us in
You know
Would leave
Then
It'd be harder to get through to them then it would become
No return calls and end
Yeah it was just you felt very much like the orphan child that
That was brought in to be
You know the favorite son and then all of a sudden you
You aren't
Soup to did Alvin and the Chipmunks
Drop off the map
Pretty much
Yeah pretty much demand and so that's why we said to them
Listen
We really want to do this that and the other we've got a lot of Opera
Opportunity if not here at Universal
There's all kinds of Interest
Outside so we can do
Folks in
Pan want to put
Chipmunk stores together
Folks in Europe wants to make more so we'll just do all of those things
And they said and they said no no
We can't we don't want to have too many
In the kitchen
Can I set
There are no cook in the kitchen so there's not a pot not app and there's nobody
There's no Kooks here
You guys are just hanging around
Pulling your hair out trying to get things off the ground and nothing
Yuck
Wasn't
At all the kind of opportunity that we have hope
Foreign and finally in 2002
2001 we were able
Call to go our
Broadway and student ID to get back your
Yeah we we we had
Do you know you
You unfortunately
You have to protect your characters in and sometimes
You tried
Did every other
Because you don't want to go into this
Telling everybody
Listen to you
Exhausted all other options
And you're up against the wall
But once you're there
You just have to be committed to that and we always win
Really do stand very United
What does it does it
Eat at you it's like
It's got to be something
Can't get out of here
Heaven Must affect your
Sleep Inn
Just your thought process and it
It just must become all-consuming
Yeah and you don't understand why
And what we've realized is that logic
Does not play a part in any of the
And that's the thing that
It's so strange
Tossed because it's like
Okay hold on a minute
You have no
Kristen Ness
AR
Dedicating our entire lives
To wit
We should be able to find a way
Separate this out
And
Go on our merry way
And I tend to try to
It's something in a day
Perspective
I say to Ross this is such a miserable
Experience
Let's get something out of
Let's make that you know this is
This is sort of fascinating
I didn't find it fascinating the personal life
Do I have to put it in a different
Category
Then miserable
And so I think okay well I'm going to learn what this process
Is like and how do I make this as good as I can make it very healthy
He approached the lawsuits I have to say I'm I inspired I'm just wondering though
From what from
What would I rather be
It was only settled really in mm
For Sophie
2000-2004
. were you basically in likes
Suspended
Limbo
No no no no no because no because
2001 was really the end of
At the 2004 part was just
That's when the last
Payment
That we had to
Make to them was actually
Done to get our company
So now it doubt not now it was Guy now is about
How do we
Resurrect
The franchise
Again
After
It basically
Fell off the map how much should you have to
Pay them to
Buy back your ownership
Two and a half million dollars
Nothing right you guys a lot more
Okay so you guys get out of that deal
And then you're
Free and
I guess it was at
This point that you sign this multi movie
Deal with
Urban Cowboy
Off the radar for
Lots of your so
To that effect
Your ability to call a shot
Well you know
Not totally although you know
You don't ever
Necessarily get
The kind of deal that you
Wonkette
But we were very
Clear that you know we world as we have always been
Be involved in every aspect in and then we say you know right from the start listen we are very proprietary
Terry
If you don't want to work with people like this
Please you know
Don't because we'll get the window from the outside
I don't think we are think we're like very reasonable and
Protective of the characters no I mean if we were a pain in the ass I would say so but I think
Think but we're protective of the characters
So is it
Free movies
You made a fox now
I think think some of the first one
Where the villainesses record executive David Cross
Is that is that it isn't like it's going to be eight and unsettle you know
Experiences in this is a new one of these stories
You know with our music
Situation with it
In in 1982
We are with a record
Company and I won't go into specifics of
Who or
And we're going to
Protect the guilty
To hear
So
At we're we're we're recording and the album comes out and we are told by the
Record executive
Ross Janice I want you guys to take
Take the Chipmunks on the road
These are the
Cities we want you to go to travel across the country to the Seven Cities
And
Make this album a hit in the Seven Cities and if you do that
We will give you a big National promotion
Great okay
We hit the road
And I won't get into all of the
Crazy stuff that happens but in any event at the end of the
Of the tour
We in fact make the album a hit in each one of the Seven Cities we come back to the record
Executive so excited after a pretty bruising couple of weeks and
Yeah
Felt like 12 years
And any event we're all excited wanna now talk about the national plan to they're going to do and this is
Does a quote and it's explained why David crosses as Ian
Is that character
The record executive
Tell
Janice and me
Well
We're not actually going to do the national
Releasing the Big Marketing
If you don't have it in writing
You don't have it
Wow
So that was a
Brutal lesson
A lot of lust
For decades
Full of lessons
You
These movies that fox make
Killed it they did
Really well read
Almost a billion dollars what over it
Their box office is about a billion 300
Wow and if you include the DVD sales
It's over 2 billion.
Well I'm one of those
DVD buyers
You card right here on out here in about 10
Exactly like you get a tattoo
Can you get a tiny
Cut of that one point
3 billion
So inevitably it's going to lead to some kind of
The Clash it seems like it's
The way these deals are set up
It's like if all of a sudden
It goes well beyond anybody's
Citations
They're delighted
Will the economics of it wouldn't have been the
The frustration for us cuz once when we make a deal we lie we live by the deal so that isn't the frustration
For us the frustration for us
Is
Wanting to tell
A certain kind of story with
Reflecting
Certain kinds of scenes and and and dialogue and so forth for the characters that we
Have spent four decades with that's that's
Honestly where the where the issue
Would be not the how the economic breakdown I know that you guys fight
Filed a lawsuit against Fox because of some of this frustration I know you can't talk about
All the details of it
It was settled
You know you have legal action
This company is essentially you work with and then you settle it
You still have to work with them after I mean they're like
There there must be some bad blood so how does that
How do you interact with with Folks at Fox is it
Like perfectly cordial normal everybody puts on their
Big boy's shorts and gets to work
You know we
I have occasionally on the show interview
Husband wife
Teams you have
Kate and Andy Spade
Sherman Dodge
Doug
And you guys
Sand
I'm always really impressed
When
When I
Been married for 37 years
And you obviously clearly like
Not only
Love each other a butt
You really respect each other's judgment and
And you carved a different role shirt
Yourself what's
Just like serendipitous Aleworks or do you do actually
There's actually a really simple approach
That we have an in
And it in this was right from the beginning
Because of our respect for one another
If Janice had a different point of view and she felt more strongly about it
Then I did
Then I would defer to her
If conversely I had a stronger feeling about it than she did
She would defer to me but right now because she's
Writing shows and directing them into
Designing them and so forth she really is
The driving force
Of the show
And I'm
Thrilled
You know to play a part with Alvin and Simon and and Dave and Jenny gets frustrated with me when I wake him up at 2 in the
Morning
I think you could do like 27 better
But we do respect each other we work really well together and I thought about that
Tattoo about
The husbands and wives and I
I think that it either works and I could be wrong about this but I think it either works or it doesn't work
If a couple is committed to
You know going into therapy and really working on their Communications maybe two people that wouldn't normally be able to work
Together
To work it out but
But we we just
Charlie work very very well together
You you guys
Scaled disc
Concept
In a way that
Animation
Tell your dad I mean
ABC
He did well he made lots of money off
Chipmunks and was able to
Build a great life
Curtis family
You guys took it to the
Stratospheric
Sweetly different level
The ashes of this
Native
Alvin the Chipmunks
Well first of all he would be
So proud but but but also because my dad
Had a very limited
Attention span on things
I'm sure he would say
What the hell
How are you guys doing 40 years later
But I also have to tell you this
Serendipity
This story We Were
In the eighties we would have to drive down with
Finally moved to Santa Barbara and we would drive down to LA to do
Do pick up lines
Went because the show is going to be on two days later
And we
Do our work
And whatever else we had to
Filling for the
The story
And we drove back
Write a probably 3 in the morning and I just
Automatically turn on the TV to
Unwind
And I said oh my God
My dad
I just can't imagine because the show wasn't coming out
The way we wanted and Ross it on my
My gosh I can't imagine what my dad is thinking and I said no no
Know your dad
Would be very
Proud
At how hard were working hell
How much were trying
And on
The television
Was his father
On Discovery Show on Earth Greatest Show on Earth
And my dad is in the audience
Applauding
And we looked at
The tell I couldn't believe it
And
We start to cry
But that was that was serendipitous
I have to
Janice Karman and Ross
Bagdasarian are the duo behind Alvin and the Chipmunks
By the way the Chipmunks
Actually named after Executives of the original record label
Alvin Bennett
Simon piranha Quran
Theodore keep
Were the chief Executives of Liberty records
In 1958
If you ever call you Dave
You know what sometimes
But sometimes they do
Or they'll say
You know
You sound so much like that David Seville character did anyone ever tell you that
And then and then you got to do it
Okay well I'm out and hopefully I'm not going to burn the mic up here doing this
Alvin
And please stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you
Things your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Think about your eyes.com
So much of what kids learn
Come through their eyes
Take care of them by visiting a
Eye doctor yearly
5 1
Think about your eyes
Dot-com
Pay thanks for sticking around because it
Time now for how you built that
If a story comes from Daniel Webster Clark of Chicago
About a year ago Daniel and
Three friends
From business school we're sitting random
On a Friday night getting ready to go out and one of the Mask
And the three guys in the group were sort of lamenting the fact that
It kind of felt like our options were to pick among the standard set of khakis and jeans and which button down you're going with and that was kind of
Extent of the creativity that we had our at our fingertips
As the great Morrissey one saying
I would go out tonight
But I haven't got a stitch to wear that's the point at which Elaine said it's funny that you guys
Feel like you're so limited here
Now I got new Romper I got you know a new piece to add to my
Collection you know it's a real shame that you guys don't have those in your wardrobe
And at that moment the guys in the room like
Excuse me
A romper
Emily's light yeah you know what this one
Piece outfit very lightweight fun
Colors she goes to full Romper pitch phone she says why actually I have a ton of rompers in my closet and I can
And wear them anywhere I want I can leave the office on Friday I can wear them to the beach
And so right then before they even went out that night
Elaine Daniel and two other friends started to ask each other
Could this be a thing could there be a market for rompers
Just for guys
But essentially someone said a lot of guys you know what necessarily want to wear that and then someone in the group said
Around him instead of her
Someone said I call it a romp
Him like Ro mph
I am
I'm sorry we had a moment of a stupid laughter like haha okay that's kind of a dump on but you know whatever
And then we stopped and said
Blachly that
It's kind of catchy in and could get people talking and let's go ahead and see if these things exist
And surprise
Surprised these things did not exist mean
Maybe you could see them on like a high fashion runway but not for the average guy
So one thing led to another Daniel
Business school friends made some sketches
And then they found a factory in Chicago to make a prototype the simplest way to describe it is if you took your a button-down t-shirt
And a pair of khaki shorts and kind of soda together and rompers
For women
The romphim has fun colors and interesting prints
And once they got all of the Prototype
Daniel and his Partners started to where the robbers around town
Including
For a brunch date with his girlfriend and her parents
And you would see
People on both sides of the table for tapping their friend on the shoulder
Turning Heads
To watch ads
Yeah I just walked through the restaurant in my Romper with my
Girlfriends parents
Laughing at the spectacle
Blackened definitely attested
There's some head-turning elements do it
So this past May
Just before they graduated Business School
Daniel Lane and their two other partners launch
A Kickstarter camp
Raised 350
The thousand dollars
It also got them lots of love but as you might imagine
Some haters to y'all maybe 50% of people hate it or think it's
Childish or looks like pajamas or whenever we're it
But 50%
Love it
And if you want to find out more about romphim check out our Facebook page
Just search how I built this
On Facebook
Of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
. npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You want to write us our email addresses HIV TN npr.org
You can send us a
Tweet it's at how I built this and please do subscribe to our podcast
Apple podcast or however you get your podcast
Usher was produced this week but run teen Arab Louis also composed
Music
Thanks also to neva Grant Santa's meshkinpour Claire Breen Lawrence Wu
Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign mon
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days a week