Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days away
Campaign monitor.
Over one month.
52 people got sick with ecoli will you freaking out well
We got no freaking out has the right the right way to describe it all in
It was like it was really intense
You don't know you wouldn't wish this on anybody
You know that anyone would get sick from the food that you serve them is really a tough thing
Ramen.
It's how I built this a show of activators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind them
I'm guy Raz
Has Steve Ells turned his love for San Francisco's mission style burritos in to Chipotle a restaurant
Rocket launched America's fast casual food craze
Ted Talk by a guy named Barry Schwartz paradox
Choice
Barry explains it virtually all current research on human behavior supports this idea
Human
We don't really like to have too many choices
Is anything beyond 4 to 6
Actually makes us anxious and unhappy
Which could help explain the success of Chipotle
Because if you've ever been in one
You can probably tell me the menu by heart
Burrito bowl
Salad
Tacos for options that is it
There isn't a whole lot to agonize over
And it's one of the reasons why Chipotle
Exploded in mm
On the eve of the millennium
Company headshots today
Chipotle has nearly 2300 locations across the US
For other countries
It's value is around 14
Billion dollars no Chipotle as you will hear was never meant to become what it became it was supposed
Be a one-off burrito joint in Denver
A burrito joint that would generate enough cash to finance a high-end restaurant
That was details his plan he's actually a classically trained chef
He wanted to make Michelin star food not
Foil wrapped burritos
The earliest recollection I have
Being in the kitchen and in cooking
In the third grade and we lived in Germany
And I remember cooking
Scrambled eggs
How do you make them to just grab them before.
Do cracked eggs into the pan of scrambling or did you scrambling before no no I scrambled them
With a fork
And then I my mom had a
A very well seasoned
A cast iron skillet
I mean it was very very
Smooth
And I almost
Non-stick
And I used to push
The Kurds
Into the center
In a square shape a perfect square maybe three
3 or 3 and 1/2 by 3 and 1/2 cents
My God
And then and then it was when it was just set enough I would flip it over
And dumb I mean it was very controlling my can says a lot about me cuz I'm
I'm a little bit of a
Of course I had no idea then but
It's an interesting it's an interesting memory
Okay what point did you start to
I've read like stories but you in college where you
You dare parties in Tempe
What is this butter that you better eat
Duck confit and stuff like why did you even
NOAA
How did you get into Foods at such a young age
Yeah well you know my mom was a very
Adventurous cook and a really good one
And she had a garden and
She got all the cooking magazines that have a lot of cookbooks and and I used to
I used to spend time in the kitchen and an in follow along
At some point I started watching
Cooking shows
Julia Child
Graham on the Galloping Gourmet
PBS series The MasterChef series
I really love those and and would duplicate
The recipes
And then like to cook for
You know my family and then
When I was older in high school I started having people over
You go to college
In in Boulder right
Yes and you stay art history
Of course it made
Zero sense to my father
What do you do with a art history
So what do you do at our history degree of course you know I don't know
We'll see we'll see how this unfolds and improbably I was thinking that I would continue and Go to graduate school
But my roommate
Suggested to me that I go to cooking school she said this just weeks before
Graduation why did she suggest that you knew I was into cooking and I think she had visited the culinary
Institute of America
And 50 of what you would love this place
So I applied and I went and and only went because if I knew exactly what I wanted
It was an adventure but I would say
There is a there's a halfway point
Where you go for a
A few months and work in a restaurant
Of your choice and I chose to work at Stars restaurant in San Francisco most famous
Best restaurant like one of them in America
Jeremiah Tower right it was the was the Hedgehog
It was a really important restaurant and I had eaten at stars
Few times when I was in college
And loved him in like Mario Batali
Formal tons of really famous chess
Anthony Bourdain like Presa documentary about him what was he like to work for
It is hard to describe I really what what he's like I will say that
An amazing Visionary and quite a perfectionist and so it was high pressure
Sure and it was super super stressful
Really really hard work
But you would
Put your dishes up in and all the cooks will put their dishes out and injure my would come along and taste and you know it was
What's up you can range from you know an odd liking a good job to picking up the plate and throw it in the trash which was
Really traumatic but I loved it I really did and I'm lucky to have
I've been able to work there when you were first in San Francisco.
Did you
Did you encounter
Burritos are food that you would eventually
Change your life
Sure
The idea for
Chipotle
Is a
Combination of
Food
Borrowed from Stars
And
Technique
And a service
Format
Borrowed from the taquerias
In the in San Francisco in San Francisco Mission District special about those
Taquerias
Through a few of them in anyway
Quite good
And I used to I used to go to these places before work
The first time I went
A friend of mine took me
And I got the
Are we.
Probably a Carnitas burrito giant flour tortilla
All the things on the
On the inside
The rice to beans meat salsa
Jesus excetera
And then wrapped up in a rap
I take it
To the counter and I and I unwrapped it
And he's like what you doing
Unwrapping my burrito
Take the foil off the foil pack and
Rewrap and try this again
I love that I just I was intrigued
The growing up in
In Colorado
This is not how we ate burritos burritos were
On a plate and then smothered
Green chili
So that really
Interesting experience for me in and I went a lot
I just started
Counting the number of people going to the line
Tamagotchis are five bucks a piece.
I just quick math
The couple guys cooking
Disturbing
But you know on the napkin I was like
Oh okay this is a pretty good economic model of course I wasn't called calling it an economic model then I was
I said I could probably make some money with this and in with that money
I could afford to open up my
A full-scale restaurant
Just understand you
You Saturday 8
Taqueria could earn you enough money that you could open up a fine dining
Well I I mean that that seems logical to me that I mean that seemed like the way to do it now and you know these
These these burrito shops these taquerias were small the investment would be low
The red circle
It was low
And and there were lines out the door
And I thought that
That I could make enough money
To fund my full-scale restaurant
And
So I knew I wanted to move back
Colorado
Start this
Why
But there's nothing like it in Colorado
I certainly didn't want to compete with all the taquerias in the mission was not
It wouldn't be novelty
Yeah maybe it would be
Really good
Maybe I could make better burritos but again I thought
I wanted to go to a place where no one
I've seen the style of service before by the way how did you figure out how to do the rest
Obviously you're a chef but
You know there's techniques in his ways of of really making
Refried beans
Are pinto beans or whatever it was
Carnitas how did you come up with
Short well
Stars was really good training
We would we would come in at
At noon
And
You know we would learn
At that time what we were going to cook that evening
And you know there wasn't a set menu
Per se and there weren't recipes for sale
You had to
Figure it out based on
Style of the restaurant in and what you know Jeremiah and Mark
The executive chef wanted
And so
Wasn't like I had to
You know labor over the
The recipes it was it's it's relatively simple food
Or I should say it
It's really simple food Chipotle
So you wanted it you want to go to
Quebec to Colorado
End
Maybe opening up in Boulder Colorado
Yeah I thought I would open it up in Boulder
And had trouble finding a location
But I liked
But I could afford
Nothing seemed right
And a friend of mine was working
In Denver
Somehow
Commercial real estate broker
Went to his office and made a pitch
And just sit here here's what I'm thinking of doing and I described
Chipotle
Pretty much as you see it today
Description to what was it going to be
Well
You know I described
The food I describe the service format
I said
First of all you know it's going to be an open kitchen
And we're going to be grilling Meats
And cooking whole beans
And mashing avocados for guacamole
And grating the cheese
Dicing tomatoes
Pano's
Onions
Chopping fresh herbs like cilantro and oregano and
And you know he's deeply stupid seems very excited about the
The prospect
And so on
He said he'll give me give me a about a week
Identify you know a few
Potential real estate sites and will go on a tour
And the
We saw a Dolly Madison ice cream store was the first sight we saw
I near
University of Denver campus
Square feet
It was in terrible condition
It needed a lot of work
I think the rent
What's $800
Basically nothing and so
Convince my father to
Lend me the money was actually
Buena Park
Investment art loan
What's 93
Can I forget how much I
Holdem initially but it ended up being $80,000
$85,000
So so it was a
Substantial but not insane
Momentum I need u u Bass
I needed that money to
Clean up the place and make it look nice
Yeah I mean I had to
Strip off the
Vinyl
Tiles on the floor and reveal the oak
Wood floor underneath which I refinish
Painted the walls and
Kitchen
Child it
Stainless steel
On the walls
Well so I had an architect of record to get the to the permit
And found the contractor and then sort of designed and built as we go and I was there every day and I was
Hands-On
Build-A-Bear
Do you have a
Just natural design aesthetic is that Sly Caillou is your is just so you know something that you're next
Well I would say that the design aesthetic came out of the
Necessity to be frugal so that so the table bases were pipes
The service counter I was faced with barn metal just just materials that were inexpensive
And that were easy to to install and I remember making the table tops with the with contractor
Or any and we were applying the stainless steel to the top of the plywood and
Anthony wanted to put stainless steel on the edges also and I said no no no you have to you have to let people see
Plywood they have to see the striations the plywood have to see how it built and so the esthetic for Chipotle was
Was very much about how it was put together and I think this spoke to the food
So as you looked past the counter into the kitchen you could see the basic ingredients you could see
See no
Chicken and steak and avocados
Rice beans and all things and how it was simply put together and so I think this
Connection to the built environment was something that made the brand special
I don't think it was obvious to most people I know think that man wasn't even obvious to me at the time so you so you open
The first
Right
And it was it was going to be like
Temporary thing
This was going to be one restaurant in this was going to be
A cash cow that could
I fund and help support
A full-scale restaurant
You know I knew I knew that full scale restaurants
But we were a dicey proposition I mean they go out of business
Offender is
Hard to make margins
Very difficult to operate
And so I wanted
Chipotle to be a backup
I deliberately made it very simple
To operate only a few items
And symbol
Cooking techniques
Not a lot of
Ingredients
And
Able to operate with just
I'm just a handful of
OVO crew members
How did you come up with a name
Chipotle cuz I remember
When I first
Sorry Chipotle
I knew what a Chipotle pepper was but I was like
How is that
Pronounce
Is it in this is like in the you know like the mid-90s
Chipotle
Eartha Kitt Poteau
I could not have been the first one so how did you come up with that name
So I knew always that I was going to use Chipotle peppers
In the marinade
You know for the Braves for the barbacoa
In the beans
And I and I want to use Chipotle because
It really adds
The depth
It's not about the Heat.
Smokey
Character
I think really
As complexity
Lni was introduced
Chipotle peppers
Stars
Jeremiah was a big fan of
Southwest
Cuisine
And it just occurred to me
As I was
Looking at a can of
Of Chipotle peppers
That's the name
I'll call Chipotle
And of course
Nobody knew what it was
And every thought everyone wanted
I thought I was
Silly
Choosing a name that people couldn't pronounce Chipotle
What
Oh yeah so imagine choosing a name that people can't pronounce and they don't know
What it means name
Chipotle was not an easy
Place
I remember customers coming in
What is that place to poodles patil
Jose
All kinds of all kinds of pronunciations
Canal 5 hurt at all
And then you had to walk up to the counter and actually
Build your
Burrito in this was
This was confusing to a lot of people they said what do you have and I said well you have all these things.
Burritos
In the burrito rice beans
Beats
Salsa's
I mean if you look beautiful now and it just seems so obvious how you
You would use Chipotle but in the early days
It was a very novel experience
Was also a novel experience to have an open kitchen so close to the customer I mean the grill was just a few feet away
Away from customers and so they were really
They were really involved in the production
That was
You know the cooking in the
Service
And it was it was by Design I mean
You know every time you have a dinner party
People are in the kitchen people want to be in the kitchen and so
So Chipotle
I was designed to to invite people in to bring them close to where the action is the shaft
And also
Cashier and you had like
Couple people helping you
It's Beginning
Wide open I opened with
Really only a handful of people
And I asked
Some of my
Friends
If they wanted to help work the line and and
It was him. Really
Cobbled together
And did you did you just
Make
Stafford is your IP address
I want none of this
Down
Guy that the menu was developed
The day before I opened
Yeah and it was interesting because when I trained the Kooks
How to make all the difference
You know ingredients it was it was how I learned it stars it was
It was about
Technique
And then about tasting as you go
And
Stitches didn't
Hurting me to write down recipes yeah
A because I wanted people
Taste of food and really understand the techniques
Of cooking not just think about adding you know
A cup of this a tablespoon of that
And and be done with it
Probably when we open eyes
Can't imagine it was another fast food restaurant
Where
The crew actually
TASTY food
I just I just don't think they
They did that
Right yeah
UEC start this restaurant and like what
Are people immediately
Is it a hit right away because
Because you said a burrito in Colorado is this
Sting on a plate smothered green chili sauce owed it did
All of a sudden
Burrito San Francisco style burritos here in Denver
So I remember opening a July 13th
And open for dinner
It was mostly friends and I think the sales
The first day or proper
$40
Like that
And the next day
A little bit more
And we sort of we got faster and more efficient than
And word spread
Pretty quickly
And
Students got got back to campus
September
And so that helped business a little bit
But the turning point
I was in awe
October
Of 93
And
The restaurant reviewer for
The Rocky Mountain news
Was named
Bill st. John
And he came in a few times
And then introduced himself and said have been in a few times
Writer
Restaurant View
How's it how's the review going to be
I'm not going to tell you
Okay
And
The next day
A review came out
And it was it was a really glowing review
And it was one particular
A sentence that that stood out
And in it and in a paraphrasing but it went something like this
Chipotle is unlike any fast food
You've had
Everything has depth
Character
Nuance
And layers of flavor
That I really struck me on my butt
This guy has got it because
Because when I think about
Cooking and seasoning food I'm thinking about those things
And
What happened next though we were completely unprepared for what happened
A bit a line out the door
Did not stop
And we ran out of food
The first day
And so we got
Bigger or the next day and ran out of food the second day and just
Could not
Keep up
And that started a chain of events that would forever change the way we think
A fast food
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can
Envious smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that
Places fine print and phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge
Is not available in all states
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets
Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO Lance
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcasts Spotify Stitcher
SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR I'm guy Raz
So it's October 1993 Chipotle has a single store in Denver that's been open
He was a great first review from a local paper
And people started showing up to buy burritos like a lot of people
It was crazy crazy busy and remember this is 850 sq ft total and so
A little less than half of that was the was the kitchen so you were presumably
Profitable in your first year I was profitable in the first few months
And I remember paying my dad back blown part
At
You know I was probably that year and still taking a salary for yourself
That point
I was living
In the basement of a friend's house couch in the basement I slept on the couch I was working from first thing in the morn
Morning until you know late at night
And doing that
Well everyday and I remember I paid my dad back and he said they'll Steve
Wait a minute you can't be
I really I think it's doing very well and you know he knows he knew that I had
Taking any business classes in
I'd never demonstrated an ability to balance my checkbook or befrugal about
Organizing my finances
So you really ought to get a
Aboki price why do have one
Really what
Let me sit down with him or the next time I'm in town I'm like all right
Remember we sat down with the with the bookkeeper
And he was blown away
Looks like this thing is really
Efficient
Making a lot of money and
Continue to get busier and busier and busier
And then everybody started asking me when I was going to open up the next Chipotle
Were you still in your mind
Planning and
It on opening a fine dining restaurant
Oh that was what I was thinking about Usher
And I had no intention of opening another Chipotle
And
Maybe I'll open one more
I called my dad and I said you know everybody pressuring me
All right
Soap
Think maybe he put in a little bit more money but it was mostly cash flow that open II restaurant
And that opened about a year-and-a-half later
It opened up
Much busier than the first one
It was extraordinary
And so
Good alright
Elephant one more
Wow
In all in Denver
Home Depot pricing list
3 in Denver
That's one of my dad's questions
Denver connect two of these
I think so.
Analysa 1 / 50000
At what point is
I mean to somebody say or do you say or
What do you think
Maybe this is it maybe this is the thing that's going to
That we should be pursuing maybe we maybe this is bigger than just
Well so that happened after I had
Dozen restaurant
Maybe less maybe 8
Honestly I
I forget
But I thought I would go to Kansas City
It seems like a neat Foodtown
People really into
BBQ
Strong BBQ kosher there
I like that and I thought there
Burrito culture
For 2
And so
You know it didn't open up
Super strong
But it did pretty well and did you was at the idea to do but you just going to keep it
Expanding like one sore after another
Well
The idea of expansion
It wasn't about
Building an empire
It wasn't a number I was going after I never thought oh my gosh if I
If I could only have
You know 10 restaurants or 20 or 50 or a hundred or thousand
Was never
Was never like that but I mean you were still expanding so how are you
How are you finding that
My my dad
Funded the first restaurant
And then I started
Signing up leases
Restaurant 4 5 6
7th and then I went to my dad I said you know I'm signing up Lisa's I think I'm going to
Need
A cash infusion
Would you like to invest
And luckily
Yes
We open those restaurants
Successful
And I symbol
I'm going to continue to open up some more
Would you like to invest again and he said
Why don't you go raise the money yourself
And I said well how do you do that
Why you need to write a business plan and you have to
No go pitch it to
People who are
Qualified to invest clear that you would already had a bunch of stores at this point you did not have a business plan
No no
Georgia was no business making burritos
I was I was just making this up as I as I as I went along
And
Remember I
I hired
A college buddy
Who
Went off to get his MBA
So I hired him in and see what we have to put this business plan together
And so as we
Put the business plan together what emerged was this
Economic model
Investment
Sales
The resulting margin did you understand any of that stuff by the way
I like that didn't as we were contemplating
The business plan but after having two
Picture
You know if it was my NBA really
How to spell is my
Quick and dirty
Business School
And so
During the
The time where I was pitching it I met
One of our
Early investors who
Turned out to be a board member
And and he was really instrumental in helping me understand
How special
The economic model was
Chipotle
What was it about the economic model that was so special
What was very very efficient
The investment cost was
Was very low
And in typical fast-food
Time
Had to have room for a drive-thru
They're usually
Free-standing
So all of that
Acquired
Sizable invest
Chipotle we were going into
Strip malls
Often in the inexpensive
Center
Units not the more desirable end caps
It was early on
The investment was very very modest
And
Our
Production system or the first service format really was an assembly line and as
Volumes increased as we serve more customers you you would get a higher and higher margin.
Contribution margin in soap
The resulting Returns on investment were extraordinary and again nothing
Like this in the in the restaurant industry at the time did you go to like private Equity companies or venture
I did so I I I started to go to institutions
And then one of my initial investors albelda key suggested that I
I I send a plan to McDonald's and he had met someone in McDonald's that was thinking about new
Restaurant ideas
I thought well that's
Really bad idea how
You know Chipotle McDonald's are so completely different just send them a plan see what happens
So I did
And within a few weeks
I got a call and a visit
And a couple of weeks later I got another call and they said don't can we bring some more people and is that kept going on for
About a year
It culminated in a visit from the CEO and their CFO
What is a eventually made an offer
To invest in Chipotle did they want to buy it out
Right. I think they wanted to buy it outright and I wasn't
I was willing to sell
And so they made a very
Very small investment
Enough to
Open a few restaurants in
And and then they can open the annually they would do it put in more money
Over a seven-year period I think
Put in 300
60 million dollars or so but the majority of that was in the last
McDonald's investment which Maven tiny for that
Multibillion-dollar company
That cash infusion for you guys
With tens of millions of dollars that was
Transformational
Completely it wasn't there was no
Mean I was very lucky in that
I don't think there's anyone else who would have been able to invest
That way
And bet on the come
And what I mean by that is
You know we open some markets
California's great example where sales were really
Soft and in the restaurants were making money
But McDonald's was very patient
And and they believe that the sales would come in in some of the markets
Softer
And indeed they did
Should they eat they basically put in some money and that means McDonald's had a chunk of the owner of the company
Point right on the majority of the
Company toward the end of the 7-year.
But
As we develop a relationship over
The years
We realize that
You know
Our way of doing things was more appropriate
Then what their system had to offer yeah because you guys
Do things like Source your meat
From a specific
Ranch farm with you found this Ranch that have a free-range pigs and
Do what you want with them rice
Right
I was reading a
Quarterly magazine
Call The Art of eating
This particular issue that I was reading was about
Diamond Ranch
And the pork
Farms
In Thornton Iowa
And at the time I was reading this I was
Thinking about changing the recipe for our carnitas
And so
As I was reading this article
I was learning about
Yeah you know the way they
They raised their pics which I guess it was much different than
The typical way that
The Bix race
And United States
Vast majority of pork
That is raised in confinement
So if you contrast that with
With what I saw at
At 9 Ranch
That means just
Such a stark contrast
After sampling
Airport I decided that I wanted to
Switch all of my
Reply to Diamond Ranch
The year to get there eventually we did
It was McDonald's ever saying to you hey look you know that I make
Sense that you're buying you know
These expensive
Look at our supply chain coefficient is
You know you can save a lot of money could
Increase
Profit margin
You know why they would ask questions
Not dissimilar from the questions
You asked but they would see the results
So are you know
I remember when I put Diamond Ranch pork
On the menu
I had to increase the
The price of the car needs
Burrito and I think
Increase by about a dollar or something
I'm so in the world of fast food
That was just not
Understood
I mean remember this is the time when fast-food had the the 59 7999
9 price point
That was a Taco Bell in the
And the dollar value mint
Can you add things like this
Here here I am raising the price
Carnitas burrito by dollar
And after we did that
We started selling more
Carnitas burritos
Obviously your business approach
And there's word
Totally
I would imagine
You were
You weren't going to last
Partnership
Forever race
Right
Well
So McDonald's has a very strong franchise and their franchisees
I'm obviously wanted one or two part of Chipotle
And
If you have certainly they would have been capable of
Of operating Chipotle
Are there out there a lot of good operators in McDonald's
But the economic model
So good
That we wanted to own it and you did not want to franchise a business
We didn't
That was that was
Perhaps
Biggest point of
Right
McDonald's
You know sort of had a duty to their franchisees.
To offer Chipotle
As as a as a growth vehicle
It just did it wasn't going to be a fifth
And we felt like we were ready to
To go your own way
The expansion of
Chipotle was
Unbelievable I mean after that McDonald's
Investment it was like
It was like a rocket
You know I mean in everybody and their
And their brother and sisters wanted to
Create the next Chipotle
How did that affect your your personal life I mean
Would we just like on top of the world
So
Signs about this or were you
Stressed out about the
That's cuz you went from 13
3500 stores
Very quickly and then
From 500 stores to
Thousands now but
Did you
Enjoy that was addict
Exciting or
We overwhelmed ever
So if you think about my original plan for Chipotle
Yes
I failed
Okay cuz my intention was to 2
To start
One little Chipotle
And then to be able to step away from it
And in use the funds from that restaurant
To open and operate my full-scale restaurant
So
Failed because I never stepped away
Chipotle
I don't
I don't think I took a day off
In the first year
The only time I left
Was when I had to
To run out
Take the money to
The banker
Go to a
Suppliers
Certainly do a stress to it but it was really exciting
On the other hand though as it
As it got bigger
And the challenges Scott
Much larger the challenges of operating a large
Business
I just always wondered if I was
Qualified song
Business School
I didn't think of myself
CEO
Eleanor the Meg
Learn to do this
So so there was a lot of gout
Self-doubt alarm
Cuz it would be I would not
I want to feel confident that you didn't have sec
Your your chef
And you are all of a sudden
The Helm of this
Massive growing Empire
Cons of employees
Scaling quickly
Deal with personnel and management all the stuff
I'll give you what you learn along the way
And there have been so many
Transformations along the way
And so for the last 24 years
It's about
You know Reinventing
Yourself
In a learning new things
But I got
Good at finding
Really good people I think I think that's probably what I'm best at
So you go public
Fisher Price
Skyrockets and
Legacy Inn
In mm
And then you have a
Pretty
What was
That like for you to
Kentucky
What was outside
Sure about that
You know that anyone would get sick
From the food that
That you
Serve them
We're really a tough thing and
So I immediately
Yeah you know we try to figure out
What could be causing this
And it was it was a very difficult thing
To figure out
And there were a lot of experts
We brought on immediately and end in a
CDC in lhasa
Investigations
This started in August
Pacific Northwest
Young people got
Sick from from
So so yeah over over one month.
From basically mid-october to mid-november
52 people
I got sick with E coli
Will you freaking out
Well
I mean
We got no freaking out has the right
The right way to describe it
You know we were
Really
But I was just it was
All encompass
It was like
It was really intense
You don't know you wouldn't wish this on
On anybody
Back up and think about it
No nobody was bringing in as much
Fresh
Food as much
Fresh produce and meat
As Chipotle
So what we realize
How is that we needed to
Develop protocols
Prevent any kind of
Pathogen vim
I'm coming into the system
Impossible to do
100%
You can never say 100%
Yeah but you can you can get very close to
2-0
So yeah I'll give you an example
I think about an avocado
Potentially
Pathogens on an avocado
But you wash the avocado right the avocado was washed
After his Harvest
But what if
That
Avocado
Could be infected somehow
Falls on the ground and hits
It's a little rock or something and that and just that little spot where the pathogen is pushed under the skin
And now you wash it but you
You don't watch that little spot and what if
As you put your knife into the avocado
It's that exact
110 million things I cut at home and I don't wash them
That's right if you you have dozens
We cut millions millions
And I'm not saying that the avocado is rotten
Responsible for for this
La particular incident
But we've looked at every single
Item we bring in and we've ensured that there are
A number of interventions along the way and see what we do with this Avocado now is after we wash it
We plunge it into boiling water for 5 seconds
Yeah and it's not long enough to cook the avocado
But just long enough to bring the temperature
Of the skin and the area under the skin just high enough so that it would kill any
Pathogen that might be there we do this with
Lemons and limes and bell peppers
Jalapeno peppers is a process that is
Very very thorough and in the chance that
Pathogen can survive through that
Is certainly near-zero
Did you have this incredible
Rotten from the
Literally from the first store you open
Profitable
And then you hit this crisis point in
2015 and
I can't imagine you ever dealt with anything
Even remotely close to that
So
What are you mentally prepared for it
Well you should own I'm here now so I got to go
Got through it
We weren't
Prepared
As an organization
For it obviously
Nnn since that incident
For two years away from
We are at we are a different company
We have
Top notch
Board of directors
That are
Independent and
Very critical
In a good way
Challenging way
And and we are
Prepared
Now
A lot of success
I mean what would you think of that
Devaluation
The company this number
It's taken a little bit of a beating because
ICC face
It was what like
420 billion dollars
The 2121 billion I think
Highest winning 1 billion.
For a burrito
Restaurant started in Denver in 1993
Pretty insane
You know when you think about that
I already sit back and say
Wow how awesome is that or you don't even
It doesn't really work that way if it's not big stair step
Increases
It's relatively linear you know and inserted just
Get getting bigger taken on more responsibility the evaluation officer things
Empty sink and into is it that amount of money just abstract
Is it mean anything I mean that cuz I would sink
I would be incredibly proud of that you know that that you grow this thing to such a
Huge place
So again I've always
When I before I started the first restaurant
I used to tell people that I wanted to show that just because food is sore fast
Doesn't mean it has to be at 2
Typical fast-food experience
And that evolved
Saying that I want to change the way Americans think about
Any fast food
And
I remember when I started saying that we weren't very big
That that sounded like
Big
Audacious goal
But but the basic idea behind our purpose
Is that
Food that's raised right should be
Peoples
Everyday Food
And as I see others
Who have
Open restaurants
That are based on
Chipotle model
I'm very excited about that
That's that's what
That's what drives us
How much of of your success
You think it's because of locking
Your hard-working
So
You know my
Success
In the early days
Was
I think I
Caused
A lot of that
Success
But
I then have to layer on being in the right place at the
I was lucky to
To have a father who could
Who could invest $85,000 in my first restaurant because I couldn't have raised that money myself
That
McDonald's
Allowed me to
Basically
Run the company and tap into their resources
No it's a combination
Also a lot of it is a
If I
I go back to this
This concept that I learned in cooking school
It's this French term called Museum + everything is right place and everything in its place and it's and it's basically
Now you could think about it
You know before service you have your music Lawson and that means that one service starts everything you need for
A successful service
Is laid out
Just so
Yeah and and so I think about
I think about
You know my
Overall mise-en-place
Setup setup set myself up for success
And that seemed to make sense for me
Steve Ells founder of
Chipotle by the way despite the fact
Steve could finally fulfill his dream and open up that high-end restaurant
He says that moment has
Kind of pasta
Besides there's a lot of money still to be made in burritos
Chipotle stores sell close to two hundred thousand of them
Every single hour
And please do stick around because it just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things you are building
But first quick thanks to one of our sponsors Delta Airlines
Now you can enjoy free mobile messaging while flying on Delta
You can use iMessage WhatsApp and Facebook Messenger simply by logging into the in-flight Wi-Fi
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
And our story today comes to us from Alexander hurry
He grew up in New York City and sisters would sit down for meals
It was always
One thing one condiment on the table
That they
Ready much slathered on everything they ate would put it on baked potatoes all the time
We would have it in yogurts we have it on Chicken on bagels and cream cheese on eggs
On Burgers which magical condiment
Actually tastes good on all of these different things Geathers their sriracha
Besides sriracha za'atar
Zaatar is this Tangy earthy Middle Eastern Spice made with different types of time abc
Oregano other spices like acumen
Sage
Some sesame seeds even chickpeas I mean it is a cultural food staple and you're asking me
Eastern Parson do you know what za'atar is it's like asking an American do you know what apple pie is
He wait a few years ago Alexander who happens to be of Lebanese to send started to notice is that our wishes
Showing up an all of these unexpected places like
In corner hipster restaurants on Instagram on social media
Sounds like no way
Za'atar becoming a thing yes in some parts of the countries that are was becoming a thing
Alexander wondered why nobody made it the way his mom did
Mixing the spices with olive oil into a spread it brings out the flavor of
Herbs to know the essence of the herbs out more
And condiments are cool
Everybody loves condiments right so I was thinking about all of this last year and at the same time he was working at a res
Search firm on Wall Street
The job he wasn't really crazy about
Until one night
He was having dinner at his parents place. Are was of course on the table and I'm looking down my head between
My arms telling them what's going on and boom
It just hit me I'm staring at
And I said
I got it
It's his light bulb moment Alexander says we have got to make za'atar the way you make it mom and wiishu
Should sell it like as a spread we've been eating these foods are whole life we always joke about it we should have started hummus or we should have
Who started Greek yogurt
So he much later Alexander walked away from his job
He moved back in with his parents
You found an industrial kitchen he Googled where to find the spices the olive oil the little glass jars
He made his first batch of spreadable za'atar and he started going door-to-door to sell it to specialty store
Stores in New York I had these little gift bags I had a jar zesty Z pita chips recipe
Chevy cars in our sales sheet and I walk in
And say hey I think I've got a great product or customers would like
And I'll follow up in a week with you and when he did follow up in a week a lot of people said
No no we don't like this we don't think this will sell you don't like the taste
Sarah Sarah Sarah
Dealing with that you know people who say that it's business it's not personal whoever came up with that
A quote that says that
Never started a business because I would disagree with that for sure after he got all those
I got an email saying thank you so much for the thoughtful package we absolutely love this will take two cases
And when I got that email starts cry from their Alexander started they get a bit more traction
He's now selling his za'atar spread on Amazon and in Whole Food stores in New York City and he hopes to
Band even more I want to share what I ate growing up with everybody else and that's what I want to do with my life
Alexander says he's made a healthy six figures enough to pay himself a small salary and
Move out of his parents place
Alexander's company is called zesty Z the za'atar company
He co-founded it with his mom by the way
And learn more about 10 to our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to bed
Bill. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to our show
Show this week if you want to find out more or your previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also download our podcast Apple podcasts or however you get your podcast you can also
Nhibt at npr.org Twitter handle is at how I built this our shows produce
Is this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music thanks also to leave a grandson as Mexican for Claire
Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Diana mostack I'm guy Raz and you been listening to How I
Why built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
Alexa drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com