This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who tailors its policies to fit every business is very specific needs
Which may explain its 97% customer service
Get a quote or buy
Diane hiscox. Com
Hiscox
Business insurance
Support for this podcast comes from American Express open
If you listen to how I built this you're curious about
Ideas and you probably have some ideas
Of your own
American Express open can help you with money and
Know how
So you can turn those ideas
Into action
Is it open. Com
Get business done
Nike come out in Ariana's having breakfast so that we have our meeting she's talking about you know
What you want what you want I don't even really remember I just was kind of a Gino's like juice charming and smart and you know
Find a talk to you and then a little while later she's like you have to meet feel angelini's who's running for governor of California
And then like Ariana's introducing me to fill angelini's but a terracotta is like
It's like introducing me to feel like he should be our head of digital
Digital genius I live in New York City
Even know that feeling Julie needs was you know a person until
This morning and now I'm going to be a head of digital
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists story
Lego
On the show today at Auntie Corporate email inspired Jonah Peretti
I need to build two of the most powerful news organizations
Internet age
So if you want to walk into an office building
And get to an elevator with whole bunch of other people
You wouldn't necessarily pick out Jonah Peretti
Is the media Mogul in the elevator
Looks more like a graduate
Pretty young pretty casual end
When I met him a few weeks ago for a conversation in front of a live audience in New York
He was a course
Pairing a hoodie
I want to I want to start by asking you the question about
This were the tech uniform cuz everybody wears hoodies
What
What is the story what is it I mean the country wife hoodies
People get mad if you don't wear them
You know
You know if I like wear a nice button-down and go to a meeting or disappointed
Kind of wanted it's like a startup hers right
So even though he might
Traditional media mogul
By almost any definition
He is because Jonah Peretti co-founded The Huffington Post and new site that
Totally disrupted the journalism world
And if you stop there that would be impressive enough
He didn't
Wow at Huffington Post he started to Tinker around with an idea that would become BuzzFeed
A company that just six years ago
Didn't even employ a single journalist and today
It has a bigger news team than most newsrooms in America isn't a journalist
She's not a coder he's not a businessman and he doesn't come from money
T might be wondering
How do you do this
Just after Jonah graduated from
College classes in Environmental Studies at UC Santa Cruz in Northern California
I had to decide
What to do next so I was trying to decide whether to be a teacher or work at a startup
And then I love teaching and I made money by teaching
I saw there was some
Thing where you could get hired as a teacher
And I just
On a trip with my
My mom and I walked into it
And they were like I was like I don't like you don't need one
And there was a school in New Orleans that
That hat was just starting a
Computer education program
And they had gotten a grant they got all these computers
And I flew to New Orleans the interview for the job and it was the Newman School in New Orleans in their logo is a
An alligator
And I
Present to a bunch of
Second semester
Seniors
I taught them how to
Do web design and make it animated
And I animated the school
Mascots of it
The alley I'm just right now you can't
Ally audience that make alligator with my finger.
And I
And it's like would move its tail and open mouth
And they were like
Oh my God by the alligator thrashing about the coolest thing
And I talked to do web design and I forgot to like clothes one of the tags on HTML and so that none of the pages works
The lesson totally failed but this
Animated gif alligator save me inside
I got hired and seems like that experience cuz you were there for 3 years
Yeah School experience was
For you meaning you started to
Look at technology
Especially the internet
He starts for develop
Early
Ideas about
Eventually lead
Where you are today what were you exposed to where were you
Thinking about
I mean I was thinking about how to connect with my
My students
And send to get them to learn things and get them excited
And that is something that
Had heavily influenced the way I think about
Because I didn't give you think about content from a
From at the time print and broadcast
You think about making
He's something that you push out
My audience
But if you're in a classroom teaching
25 kids that are in front of you
You really start use quickly start to learn that the really good teachers
AR
Shaping the curriculum based on the feedback they are getting from the
Students are trying to
Read the room and read the audience and get
The more engaged
So I was denied I was designing
Virtual
Role playing
Historical role playing in virtual world
Some of these like early the ER things like the late 90s
And so we do social protest letters using the Microsoft Word wizard you know we could do kind of a neat
Topic of technology
From the reaction of the students I could get a sense of what was
Getting their brains going and do and do
So how did that lead you to
Tube to go to MIT to study
At the media lab
I went to the media media lab because there were really smart people in educational technology artificial
Intelligence
People who are thinking about learning and Tech
So it was an extension of the of the
The interest in Education Plus
Technology
So in 2001
You're at MIT your
And you decide to order a car
Custom pair of Nike
Can you
Explain
What that was all about
So I was procrastinating which is what students do when they have to write a long paper someone told me that Nike had launched
A service we can customize your shoes
Which was a new novel saying
I went and so I think first try to four letter word in it with ject
And so I was trying to figure out how the system work and
You could you could just ask just to clarify you could
Get any word you wanted printed
Nikes
Air Nikes
Yeah they have blacklisted a bunch of words I was trying to figure out which words they Blacklist and
And then I put the word sweatshop
And and
It went through sounds like and get a pair of Nikes that say Sweatshop under the Swoosh
And
The
Next day I got an email
From a Nike Rock saying that the word Sweatshop is inappropriate slang
And so I just responded the email and said it's a note in the dictionary me the shop or factory workers toilet around a healthy condition
Can you can you send me the shoes and then they wrote back another excuse and we're having this back
Which if you're procrastinating writing paper this is
Perfect right here just like back and forth
And then eventually they said we reserve the right to not put them until you have to change the ID and I said okay I'll change the ID but can
Can you at least send me a picture of the 10-year old Vietnamese Brothers
Together
And then I didn't write back after that
You were the first internet troll
I'm sure there's trolls that predated that
So you didn't get
Where you buy where you like an activist did you was a something I was near and dear to your heart
I wasn't an activist a dread
News articles about
About sweatshops but it wasn't an expert on it and then I ended up
And I pasted his email together and sent them to a few friends and then if it came with
Yeah the exchange with Nike I pasted together sent to a few friends and then it became an early email forward so if you were my
Remember the Dark Age
Use of social
Everything's called email for
Where people would forward something they thought they liked their entire address book
So this ended up I started getting emails from
Strangers
And then it's already hit the activist community of people who really knew and cared about the issue
And people who
We are with 70.3
Brett the marriage proposals and I like various
Goodbye Stranger sending me things which in 2001 is weird that all of a sudden strangers are emailing you people even using the term viral and
It was not anything that anyone really thought about a real anyone's radar it was pre before Facebook before YouTube
You know it wasn't something people thought about today
BMO horror it starts at 2
Spread and
I get thousands of e-mails back
Strangers and then reporter start calling me and I didn't know much about the Sweatshop issue but I ended up in this Today show with knife
Maggie's head of global PR
And
Katie Couric like talking about in a sweatshop labor and I never been on
TV before I don't know anything about these media you all these questions by Sweatshop labor and you have to represent that position
Did you do some homework beforehand
So Katie Couric is a pro and she sensed how weak I was
You know so
So like when you have David and Goliath on your show you don't go hard at David you know so it was I was very nervous but it
Wasn't
She wasn't too hard on me
Do you do you know how many people that email exchange reach
There were various news for the pride to ask tomato this probably reach 9 million people or this but you know back then
Email forwards and things like that where it was really hard to measure it really hard to understand what's going on at saliva
Topic
How does the step work How can I
Student with no context in the media reach millions of people
About an issue he does knows very little about
And
This does not seem
Like the way the media
Supposed to work it's supposed to be there's an executive or an editor or someone who determines what lots of people
Will see and this was just a emergent thing we're sending it people resulted in
More people seeing it
People became the
Distribution the way that
It's Brad was
The audience became the network yeah
Do people at MIT at the time cuz I mean
They were
Epidemiologist
I studied contagion and
Wingspread
We the people went up to you just said
This is a
Total fluke
This is a one-off
Candy repeat
Well my my good friend Cameron Marla who went on to be the
First data scientist
Data scientist
Facebook
Was
Observing this
The Nike women spreading and he's pea-sized exactly that
He said
These kinds of behavior phenomena are rare and the hard to predict sand and so this is not
This is not something that you can
Repeat until that kind of drove me to say oh let me try to make more of these let me let me prove Cameron wrong
So he's saying to you this can't be real
Located in your saying
Maybe I can
Yeah and then Duncan Watts another another friend who became the
Because I was looking
Ladder stand is he figured out the mathematics
Six Degrees of Separation
SmallWorlds
I'm worried people had this concept that everyone is connected through
Perfusion jobs
He also had a very pessimistic View
And would say okay
It's hard to make things go viral
Antarctica
Replicate this
And so both of them
Try to find a Trader
So would you do
So next thing I did was with my sister's stand-up comic
People ready
I'm from Brooklyn Nine-Nine
Chelsea that's so
So Chelsea was not on Brooklyn Nine-Nine band though she was like
Doing the Parkside Lounge to terrible audiences and like just starting her comedy
Career
But we created something together called in New York City rejection line and the concert was in your city rejection line
Is it was a phone number where someone was hitting on you and wouldn't take no for an answer you could give them your number
But it actually what it was a local New York number
And when you called you get an audit automated rejection message
So it would say
The person who gave you this number doesn't actually want to talk to you or see you again
You can press one to speak to a comfort specialist you can press
At 2 to hear a sad poem written by a kindred
Spirit
Or you could press 3 to cling to the unrealistic hope a relationship still possible
I don't see how various comic friends record each of the
Messages in the phone tree
And then after that we tried to call black people love us
Which was a website
That look like it was created by these two super white people Sally and Johnny
Thor so proud of having black friends they created whole website to celebrate it
And
It it really like depicted what now people would call microaggressions you know so it's like testimonials like Sally loves to touch
My hair you know and
We ended up on Good Morning America with Diane Sawyer talking about race in America
So well
Andy of projection line was like we are on CNN talking about relationships
So it was this weird thing where you could make something that would take off and on the internet spread to lots of people and then
And reporters in traditional media with the NBA Live
Oh I discovered this on the internet
And we each project
The timeline for the spread. Shorter
Does the Nike email diffused over something like three and a half months
And then rejection line was like
2 months
You know and then like a little
Two free weeks
That you know so
We should we start to see and I was just 2001 2002-2003
We don't want to hear
And and the internet and social got much more connected or even just
Send spam 2001-2003
And by the time you get a 2000 6 7 8
People are trying to make things go viral and it starts to become a science
Social in a YouTube is
Get you know taken off in
People are thinking about this as being away this
Distributing media for the
First time even though
Small
So how did you meet us around 2003-2004
You get on the radar I guess
People who wanted
The Huffington
How did that happen
So can
Lair
Was a
Retired from NFL retired executive and he had
He really cared a lot about
Gun control
Sharon wanted to figure out how to use the
The internet
To do political ad
The political Act
And so he
Put together a group of the smartest people on the in the Internet space that could come together and advise him
And
I was not one of those people haha
Duncan Watts was
Enzo Duncan Watts the guy
Before about the Six Degrees of Separation Guy Kenny at Red Duncan's book and it said you have to come to this thing
Play Duncan calls me names like this
Is rich guy wants me to come to this thing to help him figure out the internet and like you'd be much better at that than I was
And I think I said well
You know
I don't know like
It seems kind of like going to Midtown
Seems kind of like a hassle
He said well you know and Duncan hit broken
His leg skiing
Season cast
He's like whoa
This guy told me this guy has a driver
And he says that after the meeting I can take his car and go anywhere in the city
With Anna and I was like oh that sounds kind of cool stuff
Because it's like we're get to drive around
You know I'm there and
How does he disappear
Like Jeff Jarvis is Taiwan about blogs
Someone doing mobile stop telling about that
And I talked about the Nike email and
Manteno Macon
Diary of things that are
Shared on the internet and he's
Cont sort of ended not just with me but a few other people like yeah let's do let's do it let's do it
And so I ended up working on a project with him
And it was
A lot of fun and use Greg
Fun person to work with and had a lot of different Springs that I didn't have like I've never done anything in business
I'd been a teacher in
Orchid academic environment
At the end of the end of working together for a while he said let's
Let's start a business together like I know you know the internet I know business
Like let's do something together
And you said yes right away
And I said yeah sure and we like shook hands and and
And we didn't know what the business would be though
You know so it's kind of like
And then and then he ended up meeting Ariana subsequently
I came back from the meeting
Does everyone in
Then business and media and
New Politics
And she's bringing it all together and imagine if you could bring that online
I-30 he started saying no
Lennar company with Ariana and I was like
What am I Googling her
Then I was like I have to meet her at the LA to go meet Ariana
What was your first impression ever
Well I got there late at night and she's an end so I went and I didn't meet her I just went
Sleep in her guest room
So I wake up at 7 like 6 in the morning which for me is
Super 7 it whatever it was it felt so early to me and I come out and Ariana is having breakfast
So then we have our meeting she's talking about
You know what she wants what you want I don't even really remember I just was kind of what you know is like talking to her and she was
Char meaning
Martin
Really you know fun to talk to you and then
A little while later she's like
You have to meet feel angelini's he's running for governor of California
And then like Ariana's introducing me to fill angelini's
Ariana is like
He's like a digital genius.
I live in New York City I don't work
Didn't even know that Phil angelini's was you know
A person until right earlier this morning and now I'm going to be a digital
Do I fly back to New York and Kenny's Lego what are you thinking I was like yeah let's do it
Wow so I did I kind of thought it will be it'll be an adventure it'll be to apply these ideas
About
Virality on the internet to a bunch of different one-off project plans a company with a new thing and so it's
Felt like an X
Stagefright to do that the division of Huffington Post
It's going to be like a left
Swing
Drudge Report
Yeah I think
He said you know what every industry if there's a
The coke there's going to
Barbara pepper
I see and The Drudge Report out there by
By themselves and it never
Political mediator
Strong
Right-wing thing there's always room for a left-wing
And the internet was being
Underutilized by left
Winger Progressive site there was a kind of you to admit it was a kind of utopian
Left-wing blogosphere but there wasn't
A
Site that was run like a
Accompany in a
Business that way
That have that perspective and I think any had a strong Vision that that would work
Ariana as well
And I was like I was more of a I had ideas about
How to grow some
The Intern
I was still kind of in that
Mine said it wasn't that I was
Shaping
The division of
How can I post in a way I was trying to think okay how do you make the most out of
The Ariana's Network
Bringing those people into the blogosphere and how do you make the most out of
A sticky front page with links
People come back I was thinking it kind of those kind of
Yeah and we
Didn't even have article page
We have block we don't have blog post which were the only permalinks on the site and then the headlines all clicked
Out to others
Other sources
And so
Really the election drove a lot of the early growth
And as we go
Approach the election we had to think
How are we going to continue to grow after the election
We're going to just
Died after the election 2018
Yeah yeah
About with dates
Yeah I know so
Within a year
Rhe months
Starting
Almond Avenue
Can post you started this side project
Thing you called BuzzFeed lab
Before we talk about what it was what
What was it that you couldn't
Do it happens in
Post-it
That I don't know that kind of gave you the snitch
To do something on your own
I couldn't play an experiment
Much as I wanted we were right from the start
Building a company and trying to grow it
Really fast Huffington Post
You know I think I when I
Ariana asked me
What's the earliest
If we could launch
Stopping in post
And I think I told her a date and then
She announced
Austin the Press like
3 days before that or something or like everything was like
So
Rushton
Fast N
If there wasn't a real are in Dior
Experimentation
A research
So I learned a lot having a post about building a business
Startups
But there was feeling that way to figure out media how media work what does it mean when people can
Can share media to come to disc
Distribution
Throwing things out
Still trying to understand I couldn't do it half
If I started the lab or I could
Continue to play and do
Research you were trying to figure out
Why people
Share things rather than white people.
Just click on
Yeah why do people share things
What what's going to happen to the media industry if
The distribution is
People sharing with each other
Consumer powers
It felt like that was a big chef
And you're from the Nike
Email wear
What does it mean that a student can reach
Millions of people without a gatekeeper
Blessing
And what's that going to do to
The entire media industry and entertainment industry what's the politics
Like that was a fascinating big question and it gets into
Psychology what matters have you bought gets into social psychology of how do people want to represent themselves to other people what do people want to
Share with other people and why and what value do they get when they share all those kind of questions
That I was fascinated by and
John my partner BuzzFeed
Wegmans
John Johnson
Diving
Is a more academic type guy as well and so he was very
State in
These questions and also in funding BuzzFeed he gave you some seed money
It started when we started John just paid every month
At least like your other Founders stories right Rite Aid like mysterious millionaire who like
Like fun size totally unviable business
In just a moment we'll find out how Jonah turn BuzzFeed into a very viable business
I'm gyros near listening to a special live episode of How I built this from NPR
Port for this NPR
Podcast comes from American Express open
We know that listeners to how I built this are curious
Curious about how good ideas
Businesses
And chances are you have some good ideas of your own but as you know in business
There can be a lot of roadblocks
American Express open knows how hard it can be to get things done
And they want to help with money and no house so you can turn those ideas into a
Visit open.com
To get business
Hey welcome back to the
Special live episode of How I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
Joey trap 2008
And Jonah Freddy's
Still at the Huffington Post
But he started the side project
BuzzFeed labs
He starts to Tinker with an idea question really that
I'm still pretty new at the time
A question was
How do you use the internet
The spread content
The vision was to try to solve the bigger problem of
What does it mean when
When the people become the distributor
And what does it mean when people sharing
It is how people too
Discovery do anything it took to solve that problem
So it might be developing tack
If you double a tack it might be
Hiring really creative editors
You can make
Listen quizzes
Eventually as news started to be shared on The Social Network so is building a journalism function but that happened later
Really it was
Finding things that you thought could be viral like
Well like I mean Bowie
Cat videos
Right or like the dog on
Skateboard
Was it
Was that
What you were experimenting with originally
We had something that was similar to block decks with where it where we would crawl sites and look for acceleration we had a chatbot that
It would then send out links
Two people but you can only have one
20 people can
Connected to it so
Didn't wasn't
Scalable business
We
Built some tool that was great left-wing and right-wing sites and and then show the differences
Between left and right
Lefferts right thing
We're just doing lots of experiments to try to understand
Who is reading BuzzFeed was it I mean
The time how many
People were clicking on this
We basically double Their audience every year from when we launch
And it started with something like
$200,000
People a month and where was your traffic
We had some of it coming from a small widget
On Huffington Post
Because having it was only at politics content so we had a little little link SM other content
And then someone was coming to react
To the site
And
Then when Facebook and Twitter became bigger
That's really when BuzzFeed was viable because the whole thing we're obsessed with was
Social
And the first
Social unlocked
Internet memes and humor then it unlocked
It you started to have things like cute animals and
And things like that
And then eventually you news and then
Entertainment video and kind of everything
And so as as social became bigger we were able
The grow long with it
And how did you
How did you do that I mean you were
A major
Person having imposed
You've got the side hustle what were you doing where you like doing it
Nights and weekends how did you
Will you going back and forth
I was just sort of walked between Chinatown in SoHo
I would pick up Vietnamese sandwiches for the Outpost people on my way on my way
You would you would not have sandwiches on a day-to-day basis
There's a jewelry store in Chinatown that has these amazing sandwiches in the back of the jewelry store and so I would walk from BuzzFeed
BuzzFeed when it had a people
And then I would do is a traffic meeting at HuffPost with all the editors work focus on growth and traffic
People asked you
What is a Busby thing that you're doing did you say I intend to build a Mediacom
How did you think of it at
What early early on when John
Was funding it and we had no revenue and it was like a lab I mean we were technically company but we were
Exploring experimenting
It was only when we started to get a little bit bigger we launched
The website BuzzFeed we started to have
People there
The workers jobs
Was was
Tide BuzzFeed that I thought
We should raise the money
It isn't from John I also did never took a salary at BuzzFeed in the early days but live entirely off
Opposed
And I feel guilty that my friend was like funding this
Company and I wanted to go find some
Outside Capital to build Buzz
I mean I just imagine you're going to
Potential investors
You're like well we're trying to create this
Staying when I really sure it is really Justin viral
Content
Sister before
People really
Talked about that
Were there that's what you were like
I don't I don't believe that what you're trying to do
You're nobody wanted in bath
I have our first pitch deck is
We we put it online
And so you can actually go see our first pitch dial
And
I don't know now that BuzzFeed has done well and grown people think oh that's a good pitch that you should pattern your fish I caught that but everyone rejected
Our pitch
And really the first
If the first
Time we were able to raise money
What you know is from SoftBank which also has invested
Post and they
Then there was another
A firm that wanted to invest
But they told me I had to leave huffpo
And so once there was another friend that said you
You have to leave her post in the hippos investors like no don't leave well if that's the best you think that's great you know
And so did you I mean
Were there any moments even before
Because this is still
BuzzFeed
This is still before you
Started to create original Khan
Was there a point where
I don't know but if you could
They've been under
I mean
I think
We
We were able to raise money before we ever
We're about to run out of money but it was hard
And so I think any
Any startup
He in the early days you're questioned the viability and you question
You know
Is this going to
To let you know grow the way we want it to grow
Why was it important for you
To essentially
Transition into creating
Mortar Media company that made
I mean you could have just been an aggregator
And found the best
Cat videos and dog out Neo dogs on wheels
End
Probably still been profitable
What was the turning point in your mind that where you thought you know
What's higher team will start making our own
Stop riding around
Investors didn't want us to hire journalist
Our reporters are
Many people other than
Engineers in business
You look at all the big
Tech companies in
Silicon Valley
There their monocultures of Engineers in business
They Don't Really hire people who make
And create content
It's expensive and they'd rather have a model where are you
Just go to the platform and then
The content comes for free cuz that everyone post their their baby pictures are their own viral videos or whatever it is
And so that was the main feedback from investors we don't want to invest but
Because you're going to have to hire all these people and that's it
Expensive
Nne and our first investor deck was like why are some people but their test pilots for technology and maybe won't hire
That many people could you probably wouldn't have been able to even raise money if we
If we said or plan
Has the higher
Lots and lots of reporters
But I wanted to solve the problem
Like I wanted to understand how do you make things at so meaningful that someone wants to share it with someone else in their life and in order to
To do that you can't just build a platform cuz if you just build a platform people will
You're not involved in the attacks
Procreation and if you look at my the earlier work we're talking about it's things like rejection line black people love us tonight
We are making the content and Trust understanding how it spread in
By varying the content of tweaking the content improving the content finding new sources
The inspiration
New sources of creativity you actually it actually has a huge effect on health
Thanks read it so I wanted to solve that problem so I needed that I needed creative people
Bolted to do that
It seems me outside and it made
Be different from the inside versium
Insidious of the big train play was in 2011 when you hired been
A Politico
To be the editor and chief
BuzzFeed
That was obvious
I always assumed that the
Golub
Yadiel
And that was to really
Expand your
Your original
The main thing was that we were doing
BuzzFeed started the iPhone hadn't come out yet
Twitter was what you had for lunch
Facebook with how you met up with you
Your friends
And the only content peopleshareworks cute animals
An internet memes
And
That's the kind of stuff we made in the early days
We started to notice that people are sharing news on Facebook and Twitter and that was new and we got very excited
Now we can go into the news business
And we we felt left out of that because we started to see news being shared and we on a day when there was lots of news
Like we were kind of didn't have much
To do
And so we could hire Ben Smith
And we are
Alexa another general election coming up we learn from Huffington Post
That building at
News business in the run-up to the election is a good time to do it and go band join hired a really great crew of
Reporters beat reporters covering the election
And we built our news business and in that election and then we're safe were they able to grow it
I want to I want to just a question I asked you about
A very controversial
He took earlier this year.
Post the contents of the Trump dossier
Right which was
Which which suggested that there are all kinds of things that happened in the hotel room
Russia etc etc
Buzz the administration
Before you mystery
Christian was inaugurated
Crazy
You think that's the point where they went crazy
Do you think that that
I mean do you think that you would have done that again you think that was the right
Decision to make
Given that
You know there really isn't a whole lot of
Consensus about whether it was a
Accurate
He is
I definitely think it was the right the right decision and the reason
We publish today
Was because
You had everyone in the senior levels
The government and media talking about this document and referring to the document
Even in public
Communications
You have the president present like any brief
On the on the document
But the public was totally in the dark
You know he had CNN say no this document exists in here recently talked about people should at least have exposure to
So this was something
Could be hugely important to the
The country
And
The public didn't know
Didn't know what was going on I just knew something was up
Yeah and it felt you know so we we think
The news is really
Particularly with the internet news is really moving from.
A long. Where you would trust a few news anchors to tell you this is the truth than you had to kind of believe them based on their Authority
To the public really wanting to see the work and understand what's it what's actually happen
Opening day
Doesn't it in a sentence
Feed into this narrative that that Donald Trump has that the news media is fake news
Just went when
There are things that are
Is there a danger of
That is well well I think that definitely
There is a danger of having the president call everything fake news
And it makes it very hard to to know what is that word even mean yeah we were very clear and careful what we published
This was a document that was circulating that some things in it we were able to
Determine were not true
And that there were many unverified sayings
Send a document
And in that we are publishing it to the public
Could see what was being done
That we weren't publishing it saying this
This is a bunch of
Things that
We're verifying its
Atreyu on the contrary lyrics
Reporting out
What was X
Play happening what the conversation
Something message to BuzzFeed
In your your business model is
Is around
Advertising
And one of the things that you guys really pioneered was
People called native app
Sponsored that branded
Which is which is controversial in the you know the news
Is basically
Appears to some people
To be alone
To be indistinguishable from
Reported piece
What what
Tell me
The thinking behind an and why
Did you think that was the right way to go
It actually isn't that first pitch deck which it it it it was I looked it
The best
Businesses
Is on the internet
And they tended to use some form of native advertising
So Google
How to search engine
You enter a keyword in and it would give you a bunch of
Relatedly
But it also give you a bunch of related tables
And that's how they made their money
And what that meant was the core engine that Google built
Search
Would help
Serta consumer with Organic links and would make them more money with paid links and they can invest that money back into making search
And so
That was a very different model than when you looked at Publishers like at Huffington Post it was so frustrating to me that we build all these tools and
Allergy to grow Huffington Post
In the way we made money was banner ads that were powered by some other technology company that we didn't control
The often slow down our site
And made it harder to read or blocked so you know the content on the site
Emily got better at making a technology for for editors and writers and audience
We didn't actually get better at making money that was like someone else
Jobs
And I want to make that same mistake I want
B
Core engineer BuzzFeed which is
Creating amazing content people love and want
Share across the Social Web
To also be our business model where we we can take all the things we learn at
And apply that four-door advertisers
The one likely example
When
Quizzes got really big
A month after that we could have a branded quiz for HBO which is how will you die in Game of Thrones
And you answer questions and I'll be like you'll be trampled there you'll be beheaded
And
Like
It was
Summit got a million views users loved it the byline with HBO it was clear it was about HBO
But it allowed us make advertising
It didn't suck and we got better at making something like quiz we also got better at May
Making money and so that was that was
How do you know
How to make something go viral. Cents for it
I mean are you
Is it just
Something that you intuitively know how to do
It's as complicated as human psychology
Which is why it's so interesting
Does Ubuntu think the reason humor works LOL
And the reason cute animals work so well is that their natural ways people bond with each other and do you go out for drinks with your friend
And people are telling jokes
The next day
You don't remember the specific jokes
You just remember you last with your friend and you feel closer
Why do you Pat the family dog and everyone gathers around you feel closer to the doggy feel closer to everyone in your
In your family
Feeling the same emotion at the same time or laughing people is a way of bonding with people
And so
When we started BuzzFeed everyone thought of content of information to get in people
Are people going to read it and get the information
We had it inside the content was on social
With a way of connecting with someone in your life and building a closer
A relationship with
And then from there it started to
Expanded whole bunch of different areas
You
Share this content you express your identity
I'm from you know if if I'm from Oakland and I see something in about Oakland that's like
What signs you grew up in Oakland
I will share that
Cuz I want my friend to Ulta broken open to connect with me but I also want people who didn't grow up there to know what it's like so that I can
Can feel closer to them and so we started it always think of the perspective of the audience and what are their social needs what are the jobs that they
Want to achieve in their life what are the things that matter to them and can we use content as a
Kind of glue
Tattoo help him do that
While you were
And why you were Building Company in
And as you continue to develop
The company you are the CEO
How did you
Learn how to
Tubidy
Do that job I mean
That wasn't what you were trained to do you go to Business School
Have that
No I'm very unqualified for the job today
That I have to figure out how to be
The CEO of
I'm see I'm still figuring it out
It's a constantly learning in the company changes so much every year that I have to
To learn about I read lots of books
Ira lots of Business book
I read Harvard Harvard Business review on airplane
That's like really yeah
Because
I didn't go to business school and I didn't know you know so
I'm actually Harvard Business Review is a
A good example of
Pick up of
Why people share
The people liked
To say that they read Harvard
View or share article from Harvard Business review
Because it
Seems like they're smart
And like
And it has the word Harvard in it
And so even if
Even if I didn't
Read Harvard Business review
You might still might say that
So people would think
How he's qualified to be a CEO he read an article
In Harvard Business review
You guys are still a private company
You
You got an offer from Disney
Tempted to buy BuzzFeed
I guess in mm
From what I've heard a pretty pretty
Nice offer
How much money by the way do they have
I don't remember
So so why why did you turn down
I think that part of it is it as a
Got thing or an emotional thing where you
I just didn't feel ready I felt like there's a lot more we had to build
I'm at the time we were really a website and our video business it just started
Was growing so much
And I knew that that was going to be a big part of our fee
Future
I valued our independence a lot and thought that there were a lot of things
We could do
On our own
I worried about being part of a big company
And being so so small relative to
My Donuts were
I feel like we wanted to figure out how to invent
The future of media and how things should work in the future and wanted to make sure we had the independence to do that as so-so
So could you maybe it would have maybe would have been great but I see
You know I'm happy with the decision and
We we've been able to do a lot of things
Company
You your company that the last valuation was like 1-1 1/2 billion dollars and maybe value higher
Now
When you when you
Think about that number one and a half billion dollar
It is made you whether you like it or not a rich person
You're rich man
Does it mean anything to you does it
The paper number
Do you sometimes think
I'm so rich now
I mean I feel
Fortunate that we available
Build the company 2
To be something that is valuable that other
People think is
Is worth
You know what is a valuable entity and the
Real thing that I value is that
That the valuation is set
Through investment and the fact that people have invested
Dennis has given us
Resources
To build big things
In the future and said not
I think day-to-day like
How are we doing this quarter how are we doing
This weekend
Think be able to think much more long-term
Play weekend
Wework what are things going to be like in
2 years and 5 years and how do we build towards that
And you can't do that unless you have a high valuation
And people willing to endure
A lots of money
How much of your success
What happened to Yuan
The creation of BuzzFeed
Is due to your
Brilliance
And talented
Hard-working
How much of it is
I don't know the people self-knowledge on these things is the best
Knowledge
I I think that in general
There's a huge amount of lock
I think there's also there's concept of
You know
Mark Zuckerberg who runs Facebook
Partly he gets smarter by running Facebook like once you have some initial success you get access
Two people and ideas and data
That allow you to synthesize things and so
I think that is
Is also
Yeah really important
And then if you know if you can grow something
7% every month you can double it every year and if you do that for a few years
Goten
Size of atoms
You stay at something long enough and you learn as you're doing it and you prove it you do it
Initial little bit of initial lock can be turned into something much bigger over
Overtime
But there's a there's a huge amount of Lock and privilege
And an opportunity of where you're born and how you
And I think that
Is a
Is a prominence
I think for a lot of people hearing a story it would say
It would sound very
Seamless
Jonah you know does this
Spiral thing with Nike and then
He gets
Connected to the people who start hockey
Pekin post and then that happens and then he's able to
BuzzFeed
And
You know in bus
Just scales
What is it
About startups
That
That either you didn't understand or other people that Utah
Ask about Starbucks.
What
Like it's harder than it looks
What kind of scan is it
I mean is that right
It is very it is hard yeah
That's really hard
I think you have to love
The fact that
First volunteer to get the money question you're asking
It's not a good way to make a lot of money
Sometimes
Fortunate make a lot of money in startup
But mostly
Fail and when I think about the New York texting in the people
That I knew over the years
Lots of really smart creative people
So much effort
In the building startups that
Various reasons often outside of their control
Didn't succeed
It so you have to love it and you have to love the struggle and you have to love that it
It's hard building something new and having lots of
Petition having
About what you're doing and having
Big big incumbents trying to
Higher your people or businesses
It's it's hard it mean it's it it requires
Being
Really liking
How to do hard things
In a push against
Against struggle like I think I think
When you think about
Any worthwhile Endeavor though
It's hard like
Exercising
If you want to get in shape it's like
Gets hard he know or
You know if playing video games
Like you know certain levels are really hard like there's anyone here play video games I mean
And at like
With video games if you start it on level 26
Terrible you just I get destroyed right but if you play your way up to level 26
Then it's fun it's so hard
Jonah Peretti co founder of BuzzFeed and The Huffington Post
Thank you thank you
How do I get in 2015
BuzzFeed reporter in New York track down his lost iPhone to a rural Village in China
The reporter flu there he met the new owner of the phone at 2 Man became friends
That story and the photos were posted in a blog on BuzzFeed that went
Viral
The two of them then went on a tour of
China
And eventually made it under the Ellen DeGeneres Show
Soon
The story will become a feature film
Co-produced by BuzzFeed and Ellen DeGeneres
How is that for meta
Hey thanks for listening to the show this week
We recorded this episode in front of a live audience at the SVA theater in New York on July 12th
Special thanks to Allie Prescott and Jessica Goldstein at NPR for all of your help
This episode was produced by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music
Neva Grant makes it all come together thanks also to Santa's meshkinpour Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers and
Intern Lawrence Wu
Stay tuned for more live episodes this summer
I'm guy rosney been listening to how I built this
From NPR
I'm Linda Hall
And I'm Stephen Thompson
There's more stuff to watch and read these days than any one person can get to
That's why we make
Pop culture happy hour
Twice a week we sort through the nonsense
Siri actions and give you the lowdown on what's worth your precious time and what not
Find pop culture happy hour on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pocket
Support for this podcast and the following message come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Where one in four jobs are in technology sectors
And we're nearly 60% of adults have college degrees