Support for this podcast
In the following message come from mizzenandmain
Creators of moisture Wick
Wrinkle resistant dress shirt
Shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
And use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
When I walked into Ross Perot's office I felt like I was at the
Like I had tried everything I had tried to access everyone and I knew either
He supports this or I just really don't know where else to turn so I I literally told myself
I won't leave his office I'm going to glue myself to the chair in his office and I'm not going to lie
Until he commits
Running PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
Convince
Graduates
Some of the top university
To forget Wall Street
Forget Law School
Forget big money
Become a teacher
So today
From other episodes you might have heard
For starters you will not discover a Wendy Kopp made her Millions
Because she didn't
Money was never the point
Wendy's still a realist
Successful Builder
You can say what are the most successful non-profit Founders in recent times
Anyways or story is
Case study for how to start a business
If I could probably why there's an actual case study about her at Harvard Business School
Because Wendy built teachforamerica from an idea in her head
Operation with a budget
Hundreds of millions of dollars
It's a program that sends
Thousands of college graduate
Switch to some of the most neglected Public Schools across
The US
Each and every year
Utf8 isn't without its critics
You hear about that
But is also a program that's changing lives
And schools
Wendy during her time
Student at Princeton
Even though she didn't really have any experience working with underserved students
In fact
Corona bringing in Dallas
Was practically another world
And honestly I grew up
In a community in Dallas Texas that
Referred to itself as the bubble
You know pritzker
Lack of diversity and disadvantage me my parents had
Really made it
Point to
Buy a place in this community so that we could go to the
You know, notably strong public schools there
And
Somehow I managed to grow up really without understanding the extreme disparities
North Country end
The fact that where you're born really does so much to determine whether you have access to an excellent education
And I
You can never become aware of that really in its full extent at Princeton but
On any campus and entrance in included you can see
You know evidence of that that
Reminder freshman year roommate had gone to public schools in in the Bronx and
When honestly one of the most driven brilliant people
To make it to Princeton but still threw her and and threw her friends made from work kind of other first-generation college
I realized how differently prepared they were to do while so many things pet turn me on
This fact that our country that
Claims to be in really aspires to be a place of equal opportunity really isn't one
Just thinking about this tougher or did you
Did you started to do something
Well
Actually I had organised a conference alongside some other
Students at Princeton about
Improving our education system
And it was at that conference where we had
Pulled together students from Oliver
The country and they were some of the
Most incredible student leaders and
They were saying
We had no idea there was a need for teachers in in urban and rural areas we would teach
And it was really sitting there that I thought of this idea
Like why aren't we
Channeling
People energy into teaching
And
What struck me was this idea that we would
Essentially build a movement among
The rising generation of leaders
To channel their energy
The Cheech in urban and rural Public Schools
Knowing that that would have really important immediate impact in in classrooms and schools and in the life
Kids
So
I became obsessed in the minute I thought of it I just thought this would change our country
Can we change the consciousness of our country and it became the answer to everything like that I need to propose in my senior thesis
So you decide to turn this idea into
Into your thesis your like your research project
Yeah I mean I do know I looked at different things I looked at
Other models that guy looked at the
Peace Corps and
There was a federal teacher Corps in the sixties
And this time and I really went back
I analyze the policy
Context do you know what this actually work could we get these folks into classrooms
And also the mood on college campuses having it all the factors and ended up in this thesis
Proposing the creation of a national tea
What was the idea
That
They were
All of these
Talented college graduates every year who
More willing and and
Could
Contribute
Set a few years to teaching kids in
Chicken in low-income areas I mean
And if it just was
That bat resources
Underutilized
Yeah I mean I felt like
You know when I was
Thinking about my own self and all of my peers
Princeton
You know
Folks were really searching for
What do we want to do
Not a whole lot of people knew exactly what they wanted to do so they were
Doing what
In front of them
At the time this is late 80s so all the recruiters were
Literally investment Banks manager
Consulting firms
Couple of brand management firms in Phoenix
I was at Princeton liberal arts majors at Princeton I mean those were the
Companies that were banging down our doors
And so
My thought was you know how different would it be in Ark
Country if we had many of the most promising
Future Leaders instead of
And working on Wall Street
Tears right out of college teaching for
Two years in
Urban and rural areas
And how was the thesis receive like when you are visor
I called you in to give you feedback
What they say
Well
He called me in and said can you come into my office and I was thinking hoops
I guess this didn't go over
But he loved it you know he did he said
I thought this was
Bryant
Wow so he was like let's let's make this happen for real
Well
The last week of writing a thesis I decided I'm just going to say in the thesis that I'm going to go do this
So
He liked the idea but he thought it was really crazy to think that I was really going to try to go do this so I had this plan
And one of the things I had looked at the origin of the
The Peace Corps and
There's this
Credible paper and
The paper was this beautiful analysis that
Concluded that it had to start with v
Hundred
Core members that that was the smallest possible number that would seem nationally
Important
But that it was a workable number anything bigger would be unmanageable so that became my number
Like okay we've got to recruit 500 people so the whole plan was to inspire thousands of people to apply in the
The first year on selected training place no fewer than five hundred of them in
You know five or six communities across the country
And I had a budget saying this was going to cost two and a half million dollars in the first year
And my thesis advisor became really obsessed with that number like how are you going to Race 2 and 1/2 million dollars
He said you know do you know how hard it is for $2,500
And he sent me down he said I'll tell you what I'm going to link you up with
The head of development Princeton is going to explain how hard it is to raise $2,500
And this is 1989
Yeah
And so does that happen to juice it down with a development
And you said hey I've got this idea
Una Familia box
Yes
He was very nice
He he did explain how hard it would be
But meanwhile
I had
Look back at this and I too wonder
What
Possessed me
I thought I was blessed with the advantage of
You don't know you have at 8 and I was really obsessed
So this idea I mean I just thought an end really it was an idea whose time has
Tom I mean I would
Tell people this idea and they would just a dozen this already
Obsessed in fact I spent most of the thesis writing just looking for it I was just
Convince someone must be trying to start this
The really was a mood on College
What campuses are people really were searching for something
It would enable them to make a real difference and
You know the fall of my freshman or of my
Senior year
There was a
The front page article in Fortune Magazine
Saying
Corporate America takes on edges
Education reform
And so I
I thought
These people will fund
So I wrote letters to everyone quoted in the article
And a few others by the way I would
Pick out like you know Delta Airlines and write to the CEO of Amazon
You don't leave management
Experience
The believe it or not I got seven meetings up
Those letters not with the CEOs but with
People who they would pass
There's down to
And
One was the head of the Business Roundtable
Who was the CEO of Union Carbide
And you know the Business Roundtable was the group that it said we're going to take on education
And they had no plan
So
You know
I think my timing was just perfect and he said I'll tell you what I'll
But you use our office in Manhattan
And I'll introduce you to some other folks
And I met another executive at mobile
Who was just love the idea and said you know
What do you need to
To try to make it work
I said I need a $26,000 I had developed a budget saying that's what I needed to do to you know needed to spend
3 month sleep liner all over
The Country Inn really trying
And he said okay I'll tell you what I'll do it if you can get Princeton to be the conduit of funds
So I called the head of development and literally I mean this is amazing I now realize but
In two hours he got the president sign off on being the conduit of funds what was the condo to fun what does that mean
Meaning like they could write the check to Princeton and then Princeton would just give it to
Even though we didn't have our taxes
Exempt status
Wow so so
Hawaii
Was that important to us
Well I have no credibility in and you can't give him as a foundation you can't
Give funds to an individual like me
So
Other ngos
Can figure out how to be a conduit to startups but
You know you have to jump through hoops
To be able to do that so you got person to
Who created to launder this money you to hell
Help you a lot
Teach for America
Right off the bat you suck I've got to just go to
The corporation
Get funding for this
Well I had to find
Yeah I had to find some
Funding before I
It's what I had something
Live on
And that was my biggest thing was her you know that was very stressful day April
I'm thinking I've got two months to get some money
Yuan
A lot of
A lot of students right
College
Reese's right like mine was on gladstonian liberalism that was the last time
I expose myself to Gladstone and liberals
Two decades ago
But you
Here we are
You know
Your thesis is been your life's work
What do you think it was that
Compelled you to stick with this idea did you
Go out and graduate and say
I'm going to pursue this
What is a relay
It is good idea right like one of those ideas that
If I hadn't pursued it
Someone would have figured it out in the in the
Couple years after I'm really
Cancel that I mean it's just one of those ideas it's so foundational with so many other things
You know somehow I just landed on
On a good idea
Okay so you got
$26,000 in NC money
And then you got this office space in the Business Roundtable
And are you guys at this point already calling yourself
Teach for America
Well we we had named ourselves
America and then we found out that that was the name of the medic
Supply companies
3 months trying to think of an alternative until one night at midnight
In the subway ad
Just thought for
Teach for America
Thank heaven rate
Because Teach for America is such a better name
You keep saying we so I'm assuming that you and Emma I guess a couple of friends
Planned launch this thing
Yes well our plan was let's
Show people
So I mean that was pretty much
Cuz we were hearing no one was going to do anything the school districts were telling us
You got these people from these colleges with a list of 100 College
And they would look at the list I remember meeting the head of Human Resources in Los Angeles and I mean it had its legs kick back
He started laughing when he looked at the list of 100 colleges and said
Okay I'll tell you what
You get 500 people from these colleges to want to teach in my schools and I'll hire all five who is the LA
Poway Unified School District
So you went
To meet with
Seattle hiring there and said I had this plan and what it calls to you want them and he said if you can do it
Sure I'll take them
Yes and and he wouldn't have to pay any of them because you were going to get the funding for this
Although he was going to hire them
Regular teacher salary so I had gone through in
Was really testing the fee
Feasibility will the districts hire them
And I was hearing yes if you can actually get them and then the funders I would need these
Potential funders and they would say wow
It's a good idea but you know it
Not going to work
Is the college students
I want to it so the whole plan became let's just show people that the college
Didn't want to do it
So what we did was to decide okay we're going to find
Two students at each of 100
We're going to
Find one and tell them to go find someone who represents a different
You know what sort of diversity on that
And then those two piece
People are going to
Actually put flyers under doors and try to inspire
How to apply
So you you said hey if you want to teach in a low-income
Sun School
To train you and then
Place you in a
School and that was it and then
Can you put that out there and
Did application started
Yeah I mean the pitch was even it was like
If you want to be part of the movement to improve education
An American
Ensure that we live up to our nation
Promise to be a place of Eve
Equal opportunity then
You know apply to this
And you'll teach for two years and then you'll be part of a
Group of leaders who work for the rest of their lives
How to change the
And
One of the first
People we found was a guy
Yale actually who
Drafted this flyer
And he was really the first one he put it under doors
And within one weekend
He had 170
Voicemail messages on his answering machine
Saying hey I want to play I want to know more about this yes
And then there was a
Man his son
Of your listeners will remember Fred hechinger
Who is a columnist at the New York Times
You know I'd met him along the way and he just couldn't believe he know where is this out Purina
Idealism kunming
Open the me generation so he told that story in an article in The Faults probably a
October
And so one thing would lead to another people start realizing wow I mean this generation does want to do that so you know the donor
You know making a decision decided some of them okay we'll get behind this the school district started
Taking it more seriously
So everything was coming together
The only
Massive problem was
That we were nowhere near prison two and a half
Million dollars
You
Are going out and
Basically advertising
Tencent
Hunter College
Apply for the
But like you didn't really have a guarantee
Ironclad guarantee that that you could actually
Place them in any job
She was really just kind of
And you were kind of
Hoping it would work out
Yeah well
That is as I look back
Like you that maybe how it looks me that the time it didn't
Seem soap
Precariously
There were real
Shortages in these
Districts
Talk to
Folks in many of these districts and realize that they really
Wanted
To hire these folks
And so
It didn't seem as precarious as it sounds now
So how many
Applications did you get
We had 2500
People apply
How many spots
Could you
Can you were aiming for 500
So
Wow I mean how many of you were now
Running this organization like
Before 5
Well
You know it just kept holding on
South Bend
We had all these
Occasions we had underestimated
Of course everything
What to do
Do with 2500 go through 5
Yes
That's a very good question
That we hadn't thought through
But one thing we did was say okay we're going to send teams of 2 out in
You know actually
I got the head of
Hurts to donate Rent-A-Car so we had
Five rent-a-cars and we were going to send two people in each of them
Off to interview
So they would each take parts of the
The country and they would drive from campus to campus and would do these interviews and we had
Created a day-long application process that you know
Start with an essay application and then they did a sample teaching session and
An interview and we have had someone go out and develop this kind of
Selection process
And by the way this is about when I mean you know we have these teams out on the road
And there
Interview
Spoke and
I'm thinking
We don't have it
Money
When we come back
Scrabble for money
A mutiny in the ranks
The struggle
Just stay alive
Play with us
Gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Market
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast
Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com
Thanks also to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this hiscox
Hiscox
What's the business insurance expert to understand
Each business is
Is as unique as a
Fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent
Every business is very sick
Pacific need
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote or purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So it's the spring of 1990 and Wendy is about to train pfas very for
First class of teachers
The only problem is
She's short on money like two and a half a million dollar short
Kind of a Hail Mary move
Wendy decides to contact Ross Perot
Who at the time was one of the richest businessmen in Texas and
Because he ran for president in the early 1990
He's from Dallas and I'm from Dallas and and he's really into education reform I mean what I was growing up Ross Perot as a boy
Business leader in Texas was
No really fighting for all this legislation to improve the school so I had never met him and but I
I just had in my head he was going to fund this and and Ross Perot dozen
Doesn't think I wrote him 11 letters before he agreed to see me but
We have different memories
Actually thought it was a friend of mine cuz everyone knew I was trying to get to Ross Perot and someone yells down
The hall
Ross Perot is on the line and I
Pick up the phone and say yep
I'm thinking this is one
My friends
Pulling a prank
And I hear his voice on the other end you know which is very recognizable of Michael my God and
And I said to him I'm coming to Dallas I'm going to be there next weekend
Can I come see you and he agreed
What happened when you went down there
Well when I walked into Ross Perot's office
I felt like I was at the end
Like I had tried
Everything I had tried to access everyone and I knew
Either
He supports azure
I just really don't know where else to turn
So I literally told my
Myself and I've often wished I could
To be as per
But I won't leave his office I'm going to
Glue myself
To the chair in his office and I'm not going to leave
Until he
You say to him
This might things my program and what did you ask
For how much chemical
Well I asked him for $1000000
I need a
You know another 2 million
Basically
And
Keyspan I mean I was in there
Probably 2 hours
And
He spent the whole time thinking about his
Friends who would do this to me really love to the eye
Idea
And he kept saying I think Sam Walton would do this and
I kept thinking out loud
I know where all this leads like no like you are the one I know you're the one who care about education
You you're an entrepreneur you understand this
And he finally I actually think he decided I wasn't going to leave and he said I'll tell you what
I will give you $500,000 if you can raise the other one point five
And that was the moment I knew it's done
Like I knew that his
His credibility
And that
Have leverage
I could just go back to everyone else and that they would all
You can go back to her house to say Ross Perot is coming
Is $5,000
Guys I need your money
Yep in order to leverage that
Yeah
All right so so did you I'm assuming you raise the money
After Ross Perot Museum
Yep
So one year after I graduated I was literally looking at an auto
Train full of 489
Recent grads who were all in that auditorium at USC
Year after you graduated rest of the season
You got it you got this
College graduates in this room
Ready for 45 week
Trained at 8 weeks at the time they were all going to go to the LA Unified School District well they were during the summer they were
But then they would go to the one at 6 places
That's where we had decided to Cluster them and where the school district
New York City and the NLEA New Orleans
Baton Rouge in Southern Louisiana and then to World sites in in World Middle Georgia and in eastern North
Carolina
And they had to make it to your command
So I mean
Ifi'm remember correctly in that study
Did not have a teaching credential like how did you know how to train
I didn't know an end
You know that's why we
Found this
Experience teacher Educators in an experience
Teachers who had a specialty in
You know preparing and supporting teachers in urban and rural areas and we really just turns the whole thing over to them
So how did that first summer go of a train
It was terrifying
You know I mean
It was the first year we had 489 people cooped up in dorms for 8 weeks
A diverse group not as the verses
You don't we would all hoping is Teach for America is achieved at this point but
And we had a
Max
The folks who had never been
In an environment like this and we're never
Many of them
Who hadn't been working in
Urban rural communities so there was just a lot of
Tension and a lot of issues to sort
It was
It was very
And I was exhaust
You
Start teaching and you see the micro
Prakasam of the world playing out in your car
You know you see kids
Are facing
All the challenge
Pictures of
Poverty
Lack of adequate
Healthcare news
Nutritionist
Racial discrimination the whole bed
And
It's very overwhelming
So
Pioneering first Corps members
Hi-Tech
Find their way to solution
You know often from other teachers in their schools and
Ultimately we're learning
Once that first class of teachers went
Go to their to their schools and start
Start teach
Did you just have to get right back on the fundraising
Hamster wheel
I mean this in a non the recruitment
Sidon it's a cycle rate like every year and so yeah the fundraising never stops me not to
Just kind of an ongoing
Underlying
Constantly
Cuz that was where all of your Revenue was going to come from
Different fundraising right
It's a
Nonprofits is very different from
This is mention the other companies
Is weed on the show
But it does business
I mean you were a Christian business
Yeah
When the hardest pieces you say was around
Recruiting selecting training
But then
There was how you managed
When I had no idea what
I was doing
I mean I hadn't really
Really idealist
Notions you know we should all make the same salary in there shouldn't be any hierarchy and all sorts of things
Which now I might think maybe this path to some of that but it
What time is it
Chaos
And and then ultimately
Most importantly be there also
Political parties you know how do you navigate the
Politics of education but probably most fundamentally kafka
He can't do any
Without reason
How are we going to
Sustain this thing financially because none of those donors
Thought they were going to stay
Stick with it
And we were losing donors
Like half a million $1000000
Trunks
And
How to completely convert the funding base
Essentially over
And that kind of threw us into
What I think of as the dark years of
Teach for America you don't like
Every paycheck
Every payroll
You know there's a question about whether we work
Can I meet at
Was there something
It happened during during a period that was pretty
Particularly deaf
If there was so much
Probably the most
Excruciating moment
Was
When President Clinton
Launched Americorps
List national service initiative
Teach for America with one of those first
Partners with Americorps and said that Federal funding really gave
Big Boost
But the second year
There was
Them all sorts of question actually about our
Financial viability
And so
The defects were operating Americorps
Wouldn't
Approve
I granted
Teach for America and
This is about
Doyoon
And we have five
Teachers who think the
Going to training but we didn't have
Have the money to even
Fly them there
And so I felt like
Is that
Either we get the government alive
Approval
Or
We shut it down
We were ready
To FedEx
Letters to all 500
We can't make it
You're not going to be able to come
And
We could not get
Anyone in the government
You know I'm still in my
20 is 20
Whatever we still had
Only so much credibility and we're dealing with these governmental
Officials
And you know
We were taking ourselves a lot more seriously than they were taking us let's just say but
Ultimately at about
1 minute before we would have
Person.
Plan B after shutting it down they finally came through but that was
One of many many examples of the
Extreme stress of
La Terra I mean
What how much money did you need
Tatume payroll
Artem TV
Well
I mean I think that Grant was
Just a big one you know is probably one and a half million
Price of that
When and why did it come in at the last
I mean we were calling every
Single
Personal
Lever week
Could possibly
Come up with
And ultimately I guess we wore them down
But you know these things happen
Like this is what happens in Vegas
Bureaucracies and it's
Happens to social lunch
Panera's you know I mean ultimately it all works out cuz
You can appreciate the ecosystem
Environment and that's why
From here to Old
Thrived but I think it's kind of the definition of social on
Her Shipley
There aren't natural funding sources so you you almost have to
Create them and ultimately by your existence help shape them in
Until that happened it's just
Excruciating
How to make it
Wendy I guess
Maybe maybe it was about five years into
America
The staff like
For my bed like
Dave Dave revolted a rebelde
Brenda quit
What was going on
Oh gosh that was even earlier I mean
I think it was our second year actually we were all at our training and
Cute and
I was still I had this notion of no hierarchy
Which was a genuine notion I just thought
If we're all on the same
You know we're on the same Mission why do we need a higher out of a self-directed
But people decided this was because I wanted to control everything and they just decided unless we
Can make all Decisions by vote we're all walking out the door how many people
Who said that
Well it was everyone sitting in a room
People without
If we can't vote on every decision by democratic
And so would you do
Well at this point I didn't know what to do I was honestly still remembers like midnight
I'm so exhausted
And one of our
Staff members who turned into my husband later much later
Raises hand and said
Wendy
I was making no sense and wasn't being responsive
So what I'm hearing you say is that we're not
Going to make all Decisions by vote is that right
And even then I had like I should have said yes
But now if so we all left and the next morning I sent out
Note saying
You know
We're not going to make decisions by voting you know what no one lie
Was there any truth in what they were saying like were you autocratic and in your style
Let's just say
I wasn't on
Autocratic in Mayan
Tension
You know I really did have this thought that everyone should know
Just do the right
Fang
You know so it was just not playing at
Itself out of
Intended so I'm sure that there was some truth
On all sides
When when you are
24 whatever
25 however old you are
The time in
The whole team is like hey we want to
Vote of no confidence
Even even if it wasn't but it kind of fun
That kind of Lies
Did you did it shake you
Did you sleep feel like
Exacerbating self-doubt
Oh yes
It did
But I didn't
Know what to do
I mean part of what
Was leading me
Stay in it was just
A sense of responsibility like
I couldn't figure out how to get
Get out of it I mean honestly if someone had a
Peered
So I felt like could get us
Out of this
And get us to
Stability or something I wouldn't
Turn the whole thing over to them
There's no doubt about that I mean I was just
In fact I was
Looking for
Let's play
I couldn't seem to find the answer other than to keep put my head down and
And keep going out until we could get out of it
Once once you get out of bed
You know
Became more financially stable
Were you able to
To start seeing the impact
Teach for America
Well I think
I mean we were seeing even your five we were
Starting to see real evidence of
Beyond the immediate impact
What are teachers what some of our alumni were starting
To do
Like we were starting to see
The big idea play itself out
These people aren't leaving their dedicated themselves to this they're becoming the pioneering leaders we thought they'd
Tissot
That's what kept us going through these dark years like realizing that acts
This really
Is killing it really is working
Because we were seeing enough evidence in classrooms
And enough evidence
Even a whole school's that actually
When you meet kids
Who are facing a lot of challenges and have a lot of assets
You know with high expectations and the extras
Support they need Dell excel at an absolute scale so
That
Recognition is what really inspired us to say okay Halloween
Pastiche America really start to take off
And grow and grow and get more
Mark Hutchins
You also
With more disability comes more criticism
And I just
Trying to think of me you were
Still pretty young
You had no teaching experience
There were
Professional Educators who are kind of going after you
Criticizing Teach for America everything from
This is your wife
Eternalism of middle-class wealthy
Poor neighborhoods
Color to
You know there's not enough
Training to
You know they're only there for two years
Detection disruptive
Did that
Did the curse of hurt you did it
They keep you up at night
You know we were working very hard to get better you know when the criticism actually started pretty early on it mean
You know this was a constant
Fred
During our first date
In a way we were our own harshest critics and we were
Tearing ourselves
Buttonweed
Felt that we needed
Things a lot
Better
So
I guess our assessment was
The World Isn't
Going to be better
If we shut down
Teach for America
So there's really only one option
What does to get better
So you just it didn't it didn't faze you
Well
It's not that it didn't I mean the fact is it made the work so much
More difficult you know
It's easy now
Justify a decision to
Go off
To work for the consulting firm
For two years to Teach for America really good
Sing like there's enough
Question out there in the
Blogosphere you know and Enzo definitely made the work more difficult but
You know it was the criticism became
Probably at its most extreme
We were seeing
Palatable
In communities
I mean when we started placing teachers in Washington DC it was the lowest-performing of all the major urban districts
Kids for 2 years behind the kids in Harlem and now it's the fastest improving Urban schools
System in the country
Yeah everything
Graduation rates enrollment rates everything moving in the right direction
The fact is if you took the teachforamerica people out of that City not just the teachers during the two years right but the
900 teachers who are still in the system and the
The school principals and the last two schools chancellors who presided over the system for a decade and one of them
Save an alarm of everyone
And that one city
Name a city I could tell you the stats against really they become such
A leadership Force
14th in the city soap
Take it all you want
But
I guess my view is
Proposed the alternative we have here
Frenched
Systemic issue
That cannot be solved from within classes
Right
No amount of teaching is going to solve this we need incredible teachers
But we also need some of those people who understand what you understand
Keychain
And decide I'm not
I go because
School principal in schools and some who say I'm going to work
System I want some you say I'm going to run for office cuz we got to change the policy
Contacting some you say I'm going to start something that proves the child welfare system
Is that
Until we do that we will never solve this problem
And that's what Teach for America trying to do so
I know that and I know that we need to stay the course because I have yet to see another thing that's made a bigger
Difference in really tackling
The systemic challenging
It's full complexity
And the critics
You know I wish they dive in and help us do better.
Essentially
What's Teach for America
Budget today
It's about 300 million
Wow
Cute
It's gone from Two and a half million
If 300 million
Teachers disease
Supreme does it there about
You know seven to eight thousand teachers at any given
And 50000 alumni
I wasn't alone
Most of whom I will say are still in the work
Wendy mean
I think anybody hearing this
To conclude that you could have been a
Start up business
A for-profit company
And
Probably
Metronome
Colors that you do you have a talent
Skill
To do that and
And I wonder whether
You could have gone on a
And on that and let's say you had three hundred million dollars now you could have just been a huge philanthropist and given three hundred million dollars
Cars 2
Education
Projects in your name would be everywhere to be the Wendy Kopp building for Education reform and people messing up to you would have
Who knows but I
Just not
There's really not a bone in my body I feel like I don't even know how I would
Do that like
You know what everyone's cut out
Things in NY
Shaped by early experiences
Horse butt
I don't even I have not won in
To do that right like I'm so to this day I'm I've never been more energy
Like 27 or Harvard
Many years in
You know like this is really all I've ever wanted to do
Founder of
Teach for America
2013 she stepped down as
She also co-founded
For all
Partners with organizations all over the world to recruit teachers
Work in Erie schools
Today that network has more than 14000 teachers in 45
And stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the
Things your build
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Get your unique domain
Creative
Beautiful website
Using Squarespace
Award-winning template
Had to squarespace.com for 8
Trial
When you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code feel this
To save 10%
Your first purchase
Website
Thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that and when Chris Waters
Wakes up in San Diego on most days heads to his usual job he's an account manager at a stop
It's just
Phone usually talking to relatively unhappy people to talk to
Tivoli happy people which explains how he started his side business
A few years back he was on the website Reddit and read it has this thing around Christmas
I'm where the connect you with a total stranger
And then you can send them a gift
And then I eat that match for this guy who live 20 minutes away and I was thinking about what to give him
What I could do with this great opportunity where you live so close and Chris was thinking Way Beyond the scope of this
Hold secret Santa thing
Send a boring gift card or a
Snack box
And fortunately I was hosting a weekly poker game with my friends and I had just happen to one five weeks in a row and so
I had a lot of extra money like almost $2,000 in extra money and Chris.
Pay it forward and put together this
Really elaborate and expensive secret Santa gifts
I like doing things for the people I like creating something
I don't know special and magical and if you have the opportunity to do something truly spectacular for someone
Including an internet stranger
You should
Take that opportunity
Okay so it's important mention here that Chris is really into scavenger hunt
10 buried treasure in planting Clues and stuff like that
Jokes for secret santa guy
Chris wound up planning this incredible day-long Adventure at 8 a.m. a century-old
2 case
Filled with envelopes and a box with a chain wrapped around it
I was hand delivered to his door
This is all happening around Scottsdale Arizona by the way they got to a place where there was an envelope with two tickets to the zoo
And at the animal pens there was kind of a cipher that you used to decode the message
And then it sent them to a restaurant where the
The server said
We've been expecting you like Chris wind up spending something like $600 of his poker money on ticket
Get some chachis include meals
Old for this total stranger
And at the end of this incredible day Chris actually met up with the guy at a local bar his name is Blaine and as you
Blaine was
Pretty blown away and couple days later plane posted to Reddit
And it just blew up Plains post about his secret santa experience went to number one on Reddit front page
I told Crystal to get inundated with messages just people commenting and privately messaging thing that you need to do this in
The biggest you need to do on here I live in England can you come over here and do this
I'm in the business is saying we would like to be a part of this and that
Is how Chris started his business constructed Adventures he puts together these personalized scavenger hunt
Excursions for people's birthdays and marriage proposals and stuff like that and
It's pretty good money minimum
Probably going to cost them about 1 to $2,000 for the whole shabang
Chris is made about
$20,000 for the past
2 years
Just doing it part-time but
Listen breaking news here is that boring office job you talked about
This is his last week he is just submitted his letter of resignation and he has decided to do construct
Did Adventures full time it is exhilarating I honestly I should be more nervous and I should be
Scared but if I can quit my job and spend my life doing that for other people
I'd say it's a pretty good
You can find out more about Chris Waters and
Constructed Adventures
Facebook page and of course
If you want to tell us your story go to
Build
NPR. Org
We love hearing
What you're up to
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this.
Npr.org
Please also download our podcast
Apple podcast
Or however you get your podcast
You can write us
Are email addresses
Is Hib
Bta10
Npr.org
If you want to send it
Tweet it's at
How I built this
Hush it was produced this week by run. Dale f***** up with original music
Composed by
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant Santa's meshki
Can poor Clare Breen Lawrence Wu
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Dianabol stack
Guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
I'm telling you cover
And embedded is back
President Donald Trump has no record of public
Service but he does have a record in busy
On TV
In our latest round of Stories We introduce you to the people who were there at
Built an Empire and
And the name
Listen on the NPR one app or wherever you get your pot
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week