Support for NPR in the following message
Did come from Pushkin and dust
Resetting the podcast
Broken record
Rick Rubin Malcolm Gladwell and Bruce Hedley
Sit down with the musicians you love
To talk about their lives work and the music
Listen to season 2
Wherever you get your podcasts
Just sitting on my doorstep
Stupid I invited him into the house and he tells me that he's going to close the
Legend group down on the Monday and I definitely get angry but I just lit relates to
Pushed him out of my house and told me wasn't never welcome theracane which is the best thing to
Dto Bank
Ramen
NPR
How I built this
A show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
They built the story of how
Richard Branson took a record shop
And built it into an airline a bank
Space tourism a cola
And more than 200 other businesses
All under the name virgin
What a lot of people think of the word mogul
I suspect many of them would put Richard Branson at or near the top of
His company virgin
Is practically everywhere
Fairbanks
Phones cruises
Trains playing spaceships
But the thing about Richard Branson
Is that
He's also failed
Feel pretty badly
Add a lot of the businesses he started
Today on the show a lot about those failures Richard Branson as a teenager
A high school dropout
Decided
Start a magazine
Well I started when I was 15
50s
And
And those dates why don't you know
I didn't know what I what I want
Do was
Scots magazine the campaign against the Vietnamese War
Have a
That boys pee on people
Let's go
How to run the magazine you launched this magazine school student magazine
Yeah even know how to
Typesetting magazine and publish it and like
How did you know to do that
The best way of
Running a business
Throw yourself in the deep end and learn
Nice things and ask lots of questions and listen listen listen
And that's what I did when I was
Young enthusiastic
People with very willing to help
I managed to track
A lot of people who believed in the idea
Inmate in the quest
And I
But a quick learner
What was Maisie like what kind of charcoal to the run-in you know he would buy it
I had a circulation which is quite thickening and it over a hundred thousand copies of this year it was
The glossy magazines
YouTube people didn't
Think that it was just a magazine for students
We got all the best cartoonist
What Frets we got
Yes I'm the best
Octopus in the wild
You know we had
Celebrities like Vanessa Redgrave and
Jean-Paul Sartre
John le carre write
16 or 17 years old
I suspect
Fitbit
I didn't know tavius though it digest somebody would say no
Wouldn't have been able to understand
And I remember James Bolden was visiting London and I found out which hotel he was in
I turned up at the hotel and those days the tape recorders with 3-foot by 3-foot so I was lugging this
Master tape recorder
The real tapes
And
Somehow I think he took pity on me if you don't think it helped me to 16in
And yelling and entice me in and then and I have one of the best interviews of my life
Uranus magazine
You are
Dyslexic
Like you are just like
So you already had like
Some trouble with
Making a word
How did you
Did you do that
I interviewed
Eloquent people
Side
I would make a point of that energy into being people who he spoke well Psych
Transcribe the words with the word annoy
Editor of the magazine I said
I'm not the kind of magazine this game to embellish what people
Wrightwood is going to give you a question
And was it
Was it making money
Profitable where you like
It was the Bible based
We've had enough
But I seem to pay for the
Cuz we didn't have any
Financial backing a tool
Bring up Coke and tell him to Pepsi with advertising and then maybe get Coke and then ring up Pepsi
We did everything we could just get enough advertising to get the magazine out
The magazine
Became the vehicle
Cool brother things
I've been through the magazine I ended up setting up an advisory sent to the young people
Yunnan people
Contact the magazine with all sorts of problems that loneliness
Suicidal psychiatric
Venereal disease
Pregnancy issues and so on
So we set up a sensor that was a gay free help and advice
Young people
Anna Monday
Largest funeral
Like that saying
Veteran records 10 to 6
Send up any album on any label
And I'm going to pick response
Nobody that was sold music
Get a cheaper price than the
No more retail
Price
And it was a starseed legend
First record
Yeah
Could you please add something we will sell you records
A discount rate the how did you get the how to get the records how are you actually able to buy them
A good question record companies wouldn't supplies the records cuz we didn't have a credit so
We get to meet with advertise we get people's money and then we go to local Wrecker
Toboggan
Let me know we can give you $3,000 now
And then
In the end
It became so successful that we had a tick legit Lori's coming up behind this tiny but the record shelf nothing okay
How many wood
Taking them off the Lori through the shopping in a tree the shopping to have vehicles the other side in
And in the end the record industry decided that baby to deal with this directly
Stop the charade
Tips of Virgin Records began as one
1 records
Yes I'm only open to record shout when the when the post office went on strike for 2 months
Email order
Company developed in Peril set
And we went to Bobby's Shoe Shop in Oxford Streisand found an empty space and
Through some records and pillows on the floor and headphones and then
We had a
Acute
About half a mile long
People getting through the shoe shop out of the winding stairs
It became the very hip
Singing
In the 70s with people to do
And then I guess this was around the time when you stumbled across a cannabis Shady scheme
Well it was I stumbled across it by mistake
We had an order of records from Belgium which we never had before
I'm done 3 filled up a banner week we drove
Belgian that on the way they're going through France they said have you go to Connie
We had no idea what the colony was
1990's old
They said that's a piece of paper to prove that you're going to leave them
What why you say you're going to leave
And so they sent us back to England but we still at the records in the boot of a car
You don't we
Go to 55% reduction cuz they
English Taxman thought that we'd exported them
Your records of the lower price
Yeah so if you Expo track what you done
You don't have to pay
Confetti Pops in tax so hopefully we wish you could sell them in England
Anyway I got chords
And the number of the record show
Don't sit in the same thing
Talk about hands
And
Amanda told me like that
Sleeping by the time
So how did you go from
Criminal record store
Shop to
Turning into
A label
Well one day somebody paid me a tape
I loved
We didn't have a record company side
P27 recommence nobody would put it out
Attendance
Gothic script let's do it let's let's
Start her own record company record this album
Let's see if we can
Get some traction with it and then
The album it was a 15 year old
Glad over all these beautiful
Instruments and no words to toes that's why record company store
Upholstery South
This Record was
I was mike oldfields tubular bells with show like
Million copies
It's how many exact copies
Wilson managed to get
But you didn't see the Exorcist which was
Completely the opposite
I think the style of transacted a Exorcist
Of course yeah right
That helped
Break it into number one in America as well
Yeah but it wasn't in the media
You like Mike
Very shy retiring person
He wouldn't do interviews
Which is not easy way
And on the way to
The fest concert that
He constantly degree to do what I would pull together
Stevie Winwood and traffic is tied up and Rolling Stones the lullaby the Great
Autistic play with him
On the way there you just deduct Richard like, go through with it I can't go on stage and face people
And I was driving
An old beaten up car that I've been given for my wedding
I'm done
So I pulled in and setup mic
I know you can't psychologically make it but 10
If I was to give you the keys to this card you think you could overcome your psychological fears
I'm done
People is for a second set.
I think I might be able to hear after oral sex
I lost the car but that concept was very instrumental in
Is Success you would like
2223 the time I guess
You can drop out of high school
How did you
How to get the confidence to
Deflect
Do this to start a record label
You didn't know anything about record label
That you were young and you figured
What the hell
If you can run one business you can run
Any business in a people
Say how can somebody from the record this is going to be alive is so old and so on
A business
Is an idea
That's going to make other people's lives
That's what business is I know you got such an idea
Then
Find people who can help you turn that idea into reality
Find people who got experience in that say
Find people who don't have experience in that site to can coming
You bring fresh ideas and check out the particular sectarian
Have a lot of fun with it
That's been my
Philosophy
I mean that
That hasn't
Work out for you every time right because even with
Things like
Virgin Airlines
It wasn't just
Easy lunch
Start
Yeah
What actually happened was
I'm driving sent it to 747 and
We didn't get the insurance
Until
We've got power airplane
Certificate
On
Very very very first test flight
I fucken packed right into one of the engines
Which meant that
It's going to cost about $700,000 to fix overnight
If that $700,000
Supposed to say bra limit
The bank that
Yeah gave us our overdraft facility
Basic Atlantic
Yeah
Can a guy come back and find it back on just sitting on my doorstep
Stupid I invited him into the house soon
And he tells me that
I'm becoming slightly over overdraft facility in the scanner
Close the hole that can group down on the Monday
IO
I done told me get angry but I just literally got stood up and
Pushed him out at my house and told me wasn't ever welcome very kind which is not
Maybe the best thing to do to your bank manager
Stokes what happened
Over the weekend we
Ryan
Libraries record companies around the world and we
Scrape together the money in
By Monday
Weed
Ethika
Facility down and then
Instantly by the Friday we found another bank that
Instead of giving us
Tremont and avocado facility would give us a testament in time that we drop the city based on
The same set of figures
You know sometimes I think people get to wedded to
Is that the doctor they know or the
Accountants in Ohio the bank they know and it's important to be willing to
Test the water with
Are you not with the competition
As much as possible I think yeah
So you had two
I mean to keep the airline going you had to
Make a decision about the record
Yeah
British Airways quite quickly
Don't stay what
Became famous he knows the Dixie Chicks
Campaign
So we we had about four planes flying and they went to extraordinary lengths
Stupid is that a business they had a team of people illegally accessing a computer information and ringing up
I'll passengers and pretending that they were from Virgin telling them that flights are cancelled and switch to the month
NBA they had people going through my rubbish binson
I'm trying to find incriminating stuff that people get a gamecock club sand
Go for the rubbish bins outside of clubs and looking for needles so they could these stories to these scurrilous press about
Drugs in the clubs and so on
We won the biggest
Damages in UK history and it was Christmas time baby
We have two brother hope to be able to do this again every Christmas but anyway
We realized then that we needed the Top Pot to deal with ba
And it would have to keep
Mula jumps protected at Virgin Records and Airline
I need to sell something and soap
Very sadly we sold Virgin Records
We got a billion dollars for it
So it would make sure that
WeChat vaonis
But I hate sending things cuz basically accompanies a group of people and it was a
Very mixed feelings
I heard that you cried when you
Because I ended up choking tossed off and then
Running back to my house download brookgrove and I
Literally identity is streaming down my face and then I ran passed a sign that said
Branson sells for a billion
And I thought I hope
No photography
Catch me decide which is streaming down my face look very very strange
Is that a hard decision to make.
The full things are do you feel like
It's a necessary decision in order to protect everything else you have on occasions you know we can have
80000 people duet version
The FED livelihood that jobs had children everything depends on that I didn't say sometimes you have to make
Decisions along the way
So just out of curiosity would you if you had to fly on British Airways today what you doing
Yes I'm in
United Check In
Maybe put up
A basket over my head
I might get a might get the neighbor next door to take the food fest
Infinite white Richard Branson put on a wedding dress
Why he decided to
Shake It Off
I'm Gyros and listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks
The two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First to Alliance
Credit Union
Alliance believes that in today's hectic world
It's important to simplify your banking
Easy mobile banking
Competitive rates and all the product offerings of a big Bank
Baking with a lion Credit Union
Is the smart way to Achieve Financial Zen
Visit Alliant Credit Union
My alliance.com NPR
Learn more
Alliance
Federally insured
Ncua
Thanks also to ZipRecruiter they understand that posting your job in one place isn't enough to find quality can
If you want to find the perfect Tire
You need to post your jobs on all the top job sites
Now you can
Ziprecruiter.com you can post your job.
Plus job sites
Quitting social media networks like Facebook and
Twitter
All with a single click
And right now how I built this with Nerds
Post jobs on ZipRecruiter for free
I going to ziprecruiter.com
Built
One more thing
Make sure to stay with us all the way till the end of the show because every week we're hearing from you guys about the businesses and ideas
And if you want to submit your story
Go to build. Npr.org
Let's build with a D
NPR
. org
It's how I built this from NPR
And I Rise
Tears after he sells Virgin Records
Richard Branson decides
To take on
Two of the biggest brands
In the world
What type of erosion called
Okay what was the thinking behind
This is 94
What's the thinking behind wangjing beijing
Somebody
Turn off my office one day
And said
I want to do a blind test with you
Kb3
Drinks to drink
And they said right which one do you like the best and I
Find Philadelphia High Point
It's a Wonderful Life
Sebastian
It wasn't Coke and it wasn't Pepsi it happened to be
This other one in the same test
Little kids school
And the same thing turned out overwhelmingly the
Love the One
Pepsi
So we decided to
Because based on that test
Kids school
So
Is exploded in England I mean like right off the bat right off the bat I'm in a big game unit like
The headline of the biggest
Newspaper in England via minutes version cuz I loved it
Yeah man hit somebody taking on the biggest company in the world which in a foolish
We had some big smiles and some days thinking
Yeah cuz the best-known brand in the world
I'm done in a very good topic I we thought it would be
Anyway
Besides loans in America
And then we got a Sherman tank
Arrived in Times Square as you do in the meantime
We trust all these Coke cans
Stand
Repair attack
Out the Coca-Cola sign the night before
Ben X go without anybody knowing about it and then turn the tanks on it
Because it went up in flames
You look like a tit
Anyway
We would not have votes in America and what was going on at Coke
Was
They went to any country
That we we're doing well and they started in the year
UK
Anderson Kelly just disappeared from all the shells do they do they just went to retailers and Blake had a baby
Went to retailers they gave them off as they couldn't
Refuse
Tescos
It had
You're like shells and shells by Dakota South May
It wasn't a very systematic knee-capping job did you see it happen right before your eyes
Free watching this
Happen
I was I didn't know what was going on
Except that I knew that
Retailers with something
Delisting a
And it was a couple years later.
My new bank
Lloyds Bank
Took me out
Dinner and
She
I just joined Lloyd's
And have previous job at being a
Coke and she probably told me how she decided to drive is that
It's like The Godfather or Goodfellas all the sudden someone like something just disappear
I exactly now I'm in it is that Stephanie a business
Fashions of the garden
Are there BPA plated on this
But fortunately
We work much better quality airlines that we survived in that case
And then
When coach ride is on this I mean the problem was the
You know we didn't have
Something completely unique you know we we had a great brand
Coco Grapevine
I need the taste of
Color with maybe mods in the back of it
Since then what I learned from that was
Only to go into businesses where
We were palpably better than overcoming
At what point did you decide
This isn't going to work
Just stop doing
When I realize that we are the number one coder in Bangladesh and nowhere else I think I'm finally just has to cook it today
Trade show folding virgin Cola was not a
Is agonizing
Selling
It wasn't because
Soft drink unhealthy
Chicory
Hunting soda ready to
You didn't have to say men
Got no reply then
I'd already moved on to new Ventures new new challenges
I mean I'm somebody that
You know I'll fight tooth-and-nail to
Make something
16th Amendment
Exceed
The next day
I would have forgotten about
Move on to the next Venturian
Yeah but I mean
Sting a little bit
Yeah look at it
If something's not working I mean
Is the Vantage the virgin
Hot
Relatively quickly
What's that we had cash to try things out
What's important when you do have cash is that you to try things that they're loaded
A company's when they get cash they want to conserve that cash the frightened of
Taking any risks with it
But
You know you cannot ready be a true entrepreneur if you don't have failures along the way
But you're not pushing
But you're not pushing the limits
If every single thing you do turns to gold
Soapstone ask about another
This was just an idea to sell Bridal Wear
Right as it was launched at the end in 96 what was the Genesis of that
I love the name
Open
Of course was that
The wind today
I'm done so we had no clients
But why would you want to go into
Kelly Bridal where did you look at inside
A narrative be tapped
It disrupted and
And said that you wanted
A bridal shop and she gave me lots
Why are the bridal shops went doing it well and sewing
I'm done
And you liked her
Like you like for energy and Herb
Yeah exactly I was investing in her
Honda
When we don't use the shop
I was made to
Dress up in a beautiful bridal gown
It wasn't the prettiest sight
Looking quite a few things
That we just tried
And attraction
I think
By trying things you learned about an industry and then you see whether there's any way that you can
Make a difference
And when do you know when to
Shutdown event
Like is there a moment when you actually
I know is it's as simple as just looking at a profit and loss sheet
Ident ready I'm dyslexic
Now I think
Yeah it Adventures.
Losing money
Exactly
Be on Red Alert
I'm in my mind
I'm done
I will think
Very hard about how we can turn it around
NSO cutting your losses
Recently idea is a good idea I haven't always been
Good.. I'm in prison fudge megastores Wheatley Klingon
Aren't you lonely
But you know sometimes emotions can get in the way
When you're thinking about starting a business where did the
Ideas
I mean is I've said I think
The best business is come out
The frustration
If you have a bad experience
Peanut with with
Another business
Somewhere in your life
You think
Constraint we could do it better than this
Even if you don't know much about it
Just do it you to get in that I mean like
Many years ago
I want to invest money in
Somebody gave me a bit of paper in the bottom of the pit of paper
Britt said
Did office spread
5%
Happened to say what what
What does that mean
I'm done
He said that means we take 5% of your money before
We start investing it
Screw this I'm going to set up around Bank
And then
Will make sure that you know there isn't any jogging like that
At the height that real chalogy
Will be very transparent very open.
Beijing money is now
Unity
Prime
Challenger banking in Britain
And I didn't know
Mike's parents are banks with bad managers coming and banging on my door and trying to put us out of business so and I didn't know a lot about you.
Thumb people know about it
Who run it and
Let's get on with it
So when asked about
Your latest Venture Virgin Galactic
The witch
Is pyure most ambitious project yet
Yes something
Tremendously
We're planning to put
Hundreds of people into space hope to thousands of people into space
2500 people have been into space
Unit 601 declension is working day and night
To make it a reality it's taking a lot longer than we
We thought this mean
Heartache on the way
You know we we we hoped
Fitwear
Post upon you being there
And when you're dealing with something so complex
Space travel ride
And chicken
The craft that you are
Building
There is going to be failure mean there's always failure
Huge
Course you had a
The big one
Years ago
Crash how did you
How do you feel
When you find out about
What do you mind
Got it I mean it was most I was on Necker Island
Banana
He told me to my son who is
In a centrifuge unit
Training
Spaceflight because you play you're planning to
Launch that we went we went to many months away
I'll test pilots who
Test pilot sub
Did the bravest people
In the well don't miss
They had to put
Put everything through it
Sadly one of the made a mistake
I cost him his life
Unfortunately
Hello
That survived
Attitude as you
Keep up morale in that
And the company
After that happened
Apus
Tutu
Old about stuff
Matt the relatives
An adult pedal with the price what you have to do
Infant purple 12s
I wasn't sure whether it was worth continuing
You know once we realized it was a
Paletera. Teknikleri be able to tell the engineers that was nothing to do with them
That the
Basic crafts
Sound
And
And I would once again you have to learn from it to make sure it never happens again
I'm done
The team would have done
And when when do you think you'll
Get to space
I made the mistake of saying when I think I'll get to space before and I've been trained
By my Piazza
Not to give out dates in case we missed them
Said we'll see how we got
Do I have any companies
Are there now under the virgin
There's a couple hundred companies around the world
I've been vegging know how many ever you like
I don't know the exact time
Why are so many companies
Dinner is a hell of a lot better than just having one
If you have fun company then something goes wrong you don't have any companies we have 250 and one goes wrong
Got 249
I mean I tried lots of things
Sometimes
Got. In my face sometimes
They succeed and sometimes they succeed
Overwhelmingly
Little soap
Life is a lot easier
I'm in this I found great people.
Run things on a day-to-day basis
I sit back and look at the bigger
A picture
And then you dream about
Exciting new projects which is ready and entrepreneur is all about
Richard Branson is founder of the Virgin Group by the way when he dropped out of high school his Headmaster said
Gratulations Branson I predict you'll either go to prison
Or become a millionaire
If it's right on both counts Branson did spend the night in jail for failing to pay taxes on those records back in there
1971 and for period of time he was a millionaire
What is
Before he became a billionaire
And please don't turn us off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are built
The first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Discover
Become a new card number and
End of your first year
Discover will match all the cash back you've earned
Dollar for dollar
Learn more at discover.com match
Only for new cardmembers
Apply
Thanks for sticking around because we are now at the very end of the show which means
It's time to hear about the things
Your building
This week we've got a story coming out of Southern California my name is Allison Hans and I started
A company called living zesty and living zesty does
Before she launched the company Allison Spence
Two decades
Raising her kids which is a full-time job
You know when you're in your busy and your mom you're driving everybody everywhere
And then all of a sudden your youngest
Gets her driver's license and when that happened
It meant that all of a sudden
Allison had some extra time on her hands
And
I'm kind of Serial entrepreneur
And I'm always thinking on what can I do what can I sell
The idea of what to sell didn't come to Allison right away
One day last spring she was visiting her sister-in-law
And she thought workers
Pulling up the grass
From the front lawn
And replacing it with artificial turf
Will do so just unroll it's like carpet
They'll just cut around where you going to leave
Flower bed is ending so they can't really use this
Kind of odd shape so they take it back with them and throw it out because there's been a drought in Southern California
A lot of homeowners are doing this with their lungs are just taking out the lawn and replacing it with artificial turf which means they're
There is a lot of artificial grass
Leftover night thinking
You know what we can make use of this
One more time
So one day last spring
Allison grab some of the leftover scraps from her sisters front lawn
She went to a garage
Box cutter
And she carved out a circular doormat
Native artificial grass
Is surprisingly soft
And I only like real grass like this clean
Antigen going to landfill so like
Green and clean right that looks so cool that Allison posted a picture on Facebook and she said paid
I just did it
Went for coffee Forest leader come home
And there's like 11 people like I want one and no I'm not texting anymore.
I might be onto something here to Allison started to collect more scraps of artificial turf effect
Installers were so happy to get rid of it they gave it to her for free
She got her son to design a logo
And tomato run website are pretty shoestring 199 GoDaddy
Domain name
Svet
How I did it so there's not huge
Since Allison launched a website a few months ago
She sold about 50 of the match but she says
She hopes this is the beginning of something much much bigger I liken it to
Growing out charm you know when you're fishing
A lot of my day sometimes is throwing up that Chum into the ocean to attract the fish
Shinso some days you just don't get any
Bite but you know then some days there's a bite
That's Allison Hans she lives in Mission Viejo California
Intercompany
It's called living zesty
We really love hearing the stories about the
Companies in the things and ideas that you're building and
You want to tell us about them
Go to build
That NPR. Org that's build with a D
That NPR. Org
And thanks hey thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or listen to previous episodes you can go to how I built this. NPR.
O r g
Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and who's favored Riders review while you're there
You can also write directly to us at Hib tea at NPR. Org and if you want it
Set a tweet it's at how I built this
Russia was produced this week by run. Defatta with music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to neva
Maria Paz Gutierrez and Jeff Rogers are interned is Claire Breen
Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this NPR
Pete just quitting
Latina USA has something really special.
Guitar radio documentary
About the controversial Puerto Rican Independence fighter
Oscar Lopez Rivera
Who is getting clemency by President Obama just
A few days before.
It's a story with secret identities
Safe houses in FBI Manhunt in
Even a little bit of revolution
You can find Latino USA on the
NPR one app
Npr.org podcast
This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
Like the only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse start your Journey 2
Towards data-driven decision-making
Making its snowflake.com NPR