This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this kiss
Who understands every small business is uni
Impaler's its policies
State your business is very specific
Get a quote or purchase a policy
At h i s c o x.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Able to quickly before the show starts
We are super excited about a live how I built this recording happening right here in Washington DC
November 30th
Supported by American Express open
I guess we'll be Robert Johnson the founder of bet Black Entertainment Television
And tickets are on sale right now for that event
You can find them an NPR presents. Org
And now here's one of our favorites from the archive
The story of Instagram
Enjoy
It was nothing more exhilarating than seeing all those people screaming and nothing more crushing than then seeing
Are people posting on Twitter on their blogs and say like another doesn't know how to scale like Alexa
Clowney
We are both
Running on zero
2 days devastated and I was like this is it we've built this great thing and we totally messed it up
From NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements
Walk on the beach spark that idea that turned all of us
It's a good photographers and made Instagram one of the fastest-growing apps of all time
Okay it's 2009
And, sister a mister
The figures out of Stanford and doing the Silicon Valley thing
Travel startup by day
Teaching yourself to code
At night
Airfare from college Mike Krieger is
Is also in the area
Pretty much doing the same thing
After a few months of experiment
Kevin build an app
He calls it Bourbon and
The check it out
You can tell your friends you're at
Coffee shop or bar or wherever
Kevin thinks this app has
You know
Some potential
I mean at that time there were so many checking apps there was four square there was gwalla and there were a bunch of others trying to make
I'm in of course following
You know,
The trend I was like there's something here about
The devices in everyone's pocket
It's being available to share new types of
Information
And I was like location is
Is the type of information people are gone
I don't want to share
I think the inside Mike and I had along the way was that
I'm actually there were more types
Information the fact
These devices had a camera
That would lead to a visual communication Revolution we're like all of a sudden people aren't
I'm just communicating
Text invoice
But they had the chance to communicate with
With an image
But initially art that was on location and
Franklin
Very happy that we
Discovered the image thing while I'm away
Some people were using this app
Yeah
You know it was just compelling enough to get like a handful of beta users but I would you know basically come home
Night and just Tinker with this idea
And
You know along the way
I prototype it enough that I was willing to give it to a hand
Four friends and those friends give it to
Handful of friends
And before you knew it we had I don't know maybe 80 90 people using it and only at that moment
I did I decide that like hey maybe this thing could be a company if we actually tried
Then like
At what point did you say we
We should travel
Like raising money for
I went to a bar
We're a bunch of investors were getting together
And
I like I kind of mingled around the room and people are kind of showing their prototypes on their phones two different investors
And I showed it to this one investor is named Steve Anderson
And he was one of our First Investors
And he was like this pretty cool let's set up coffee
You know
We can meet up and you can tell me more about the app and
That was like the biggest combo
Richmond today.
Oh my God there's an investors willing
Talk to us
So I went and I had that coffee and I sat down and
As we were
We're talking actually I have an alert
That would alert on my phone every time someone signed up
Because I was really excited
M80 user stated 5u
90 user
And I'm as I'm sitting there with him like a bunch of people are signing up and I wasn't entirely sure why but he looked at me and was
Did you plan this like
That you have a bunch of people sign up while you were done with me I said now I
Like honestly don't know
People are
He looks at me is like alright Count Me In
But he actually said one thing to Migos
Before I do this
You have to find a co-founder that's willing to do this
And at that moment I was like all right
Got to find someone awesome
Partner
To Mike how did you guys like
I mean how did it happen
Like you came to Kevin you're like I like this
I think it's cool I want to work with you I mean
Gee whiz are more formal than that
I think of where that came from was we had a kind of shared kindred spirit of tinkering so on the weekends a lot of times I would be
Coffee bar
A great coffee shop here in Sanford
Cisco and I'd be working on iPhone app
Just for fun and bourbon
That the checking itself I didn't find ask
Compelling but
Having a sort of visual status was really
Compelling soap
I got excited enough that I think I
Yeah, but Kevin is like luck if you ever do this
Real life
Have a conversation
And I think that first meeting we had about it actually I was like
Count Me In
Like I'm I'm excited enough to do it and not like the the cliche of your life flashing before your eyes like my future
Future flash before my eyes were talking to heaven right then
I just imagined
Myself
Working one-on-one with him on something that I was really excited about in San Francisco
Trying to make something of it and I was like
There was something in me that just stared at that time
So just got my first check
When you met that invest
He just he was just like
There's a bunch of money
Well
He was like okay
I'm willing to give you $50,000 to
To do this and that's more money than I had ever heard of in mind
Entire life for a business cutting at the time
But the second someone shows any interest in you and selection Valley all of a sudden you have a bunch of other people that really want to invest as well
What's the Mystic mistbox right no one wants to miss the next Google the next whatever and that
Initial check 1 from 50000 to 250
And then there was another investor in
Andreessen Horowitz who came in and
And and put 200
$30000 in
So you're two guys with like basically a prototype
And a couple of computers no office
Who raised a half million dollars and we're looking at each other like
We think we can make this last I mean we were we were living on
Peanut butter and jelly song
So how did you guys
How did you turn bourbon into
What became instant
What was
Who's the Genesis of
I think the best thing for any entrepreneurs
Failure and
4 oz
Where was
Is the lack of
Momentum we are mentioned we got to
We got about a hundred users using this app
No no no a hundred like you can fit them in our room
And Eric Reese is this guy in Silicon Valley likes to you no talk about
The Lean Startup method
One of his on
One of his lines is like don't ask like
Don't use your startup ask why the
The people who continue to use your startup
Keep using it
And when we looked at our our user base our whole hundred people
Each of them loved
Did the photo aspect
So that's why we ended
And photos but they were already
A bunch of photo websites
Even photo app so
So how are you able to come up with
An idea that
That would make
Your thing different
So we're both kind of burned out
We had
Decided the bourbon was going to do anything
We had you know $495,000 left
Open the bank because
$5,000 to buy a couple
What computers right
And I'm here like all right it's okay if this idea doesn't work out we can really string this half a million dollars
Not for a long time so
We're going to come up with a new idea
So we started focusing on photos and we were both burned out I was like right like I got to take I got to take a break
So my now wife and I
Nicole went to Mexico
And we were working on this idea photos of Mike was like alright I'm going to prototype this thing while you're on break
You come back and then we'll like reconvene
So Mike started prototyping this app
And as I'm away I'm
Walking down the beach
Nicole in Mexico we were in this little surfing town called Todo Santos
And
I'm like you know Nicole I think we're going to focus on photos and she goes oh yeah. That sounds like a great idea I love all the food
Photo post
John Berman
But she goes I don't think I'm going to post that much and I got to go why not and you guys all my photos aren't that good
I said well
They're great and she goes well they're not as good as your friend Greg and I was like well Greg uses a bunch of filter apps to like make them
You should probably add filters I was like oh that's it
Like we we just need to be able to make people feel like
Their photos are worthy of sharing
And I remember going back right from the beach I sat in the room with the little dial-up connection
That that little Hacienda had
And I I literally just like
Research how to make
The first filter
Which ended up being called X pro2 and if you scroll all the way back on my account to the very first photo
There's a Nicole's foot and a little stray dog in Mexico and that's because that day I made expert 2 and I went out
The taco stand
For lunch to test it
And I took that picture and posted it on
On the Prototype that Michael
So
That was kind of that the intersection of the ideas of photos and filters and all came through
Consumer insights was just like
What problem are we solving
Share something that people love
And make sure that they feel great sharing it
Tosa how long did
Take from the time he
You decided to
Move away from Bourbon and then
Launch Instagram
It was only eight weeks from the time we had basically sketched it out to when we
Put it into the Apple Store
We press launch on October
Temp
I've mm
It was like about midnight
And I
People just started streaming in
It was crazy
It was like like how fast
The first 24 hours with
People sign up around the world
Sound of big toe
The time
Incredible what were you expecting that
No I mean
Couple things that showed how naive we were at the time the number one
Midnight
In San Francisco
It's 9 a.m. somewhere
And we didn't quite realize how Global harvests could be
So turns out everyone who's signing up at the
The beginning actually lived overseas so when we looked into the database more like
Who are these people
They all had
Email addresses
Germany
Hong Kong and in various places around the world
And before you knew it we actually had overloaded our system and ever
Was a very small
Naive system is a single computer in it
Colocation space somewhere in LA
Yeah it was it was nothing more
Exhilarating than seeing other people streaming and nothing more crushing than then seeing
Are people posting on Twitter on their blocks and saying like another startup it doesn't know how to scale like Alexa
Clowney we are both I mean at that point like
Running on zero sleep for 2 days
Devastated and I was like this is it we've built this great thing and we totally messed it up
And to be clear there's no reason we should have
Succeeded like
I mean the server was just like it was down every other hour and like
People just kind of forgave us and they would come back and they would share their photos and
At the time mobile networks weren't that great either
So people would actually blame their connection and not us which is great
But those initial weeks I mean
It was just like
Trial by fire and we had to learn everything on the job and we had so many chances to
The failed we just kept
At it and
And kept working
Pulled a bunch of all-nighters
The amount we learn to not first years
Crazy was like 5 years of
College all-in-one
And yes pretty exciting
And tiring
How do people even find out about insta
How do they know
Did they should download this
Like this app
So we had this intuition that
If you're going to throw a party
Which is kind of what an app launch
Really is
People screaming to the door
You want the next sort of know
How they should act
And who else is there
So one of the things we did was
We have you have a hundred
Invite
You can have before you launch your app to the app
Apple store where you can invite people to
Try it out and we like are we going to
People and we used them a combination of some
Journalist that we've gotten to know over
Know the last couple of
Of yours
Going to Valley
We also went on the site called dribbble.com
Just sort of like
A place where designers Go and show off their best work
And we figured photographers might not instantly take the Instagram because like
They want like super high-resolution or if they have other
Constraints
Set designers love photography but it's not their main
Job
So we picked basically
The 10 top designers on dribbble
And we emailed them and some ignored us
Defining some Rebecca Thatcher I'll try rap
And it has great cuz coming in day 1
People who
What explorer things are going to popular pages
Set the time that show the most popular
Photos across the whole community
Blackbough you can take that on a phone like we take this for granted a little bit now and
The cameras have improved every year
But I think part of what we showed two people back in 2010 was that there was something really amazing you could do with
Would just the phone in your pocket
Tonka backhoe
President Obama Snoop Dogg and about 500 million other people started to use Instagram
And what happened after Facebook bought it for a billion dollars
I'm guy Raz you're listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Support also comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to study
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that were
Places fine print and phone tag
Black with clear conditions
Send a direct low-fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Game Bridge is not available
In all states
It's how I built this from NPR
Garage
So it's been a year after its
X launch
And it's grown to
Million user
And Mike Krieger and Ken
Sistrum
Ariix
Expanding their staff very very
CenterPoint
Did you guys have like
Investors
Banador
We have said investors office
We'd be like trying to keep the servers up and we have someone would like tap on her
Actually I need like I am someone so from
So-and-so invest
And partners and I'd like to attend
Take you out for lunch I'm trying to keep
Napoli's
But we met you know a bunch of people along the way and
The ones we did make time for we're the ones who are most
Watchful of that time
I knew what we were going through anchor
Help
So very shortly after
Launch this thing
But it's valued at in
More than 20 million dollars
Yeah
Was I think our first round was like
I don't remember it was like weed
We took $89
Financing online
20 president
Roughly a 30 million dollar valuation
There's something
And I mean again
Attestation lifecycle
Never heard of it
Company that's worth
This is crazy
I didn't really think much of it I just wanted to get back
To work and I think Mike felt the same way we were just like so focused on building
What we're building
It just like
Growing and
The question was
I got Mike and I
Every single day worth
What scale can a
Just got you and
I think it really started to hit us
When we would be out
And see people using it
In the real world
It was kind of cereal over time
Deserve it like from the outside the store just seems like
Clear
Linear like
Jumping for
Success to
Success like it
EZPawn
Put it up there
All this money in the
Stratosphere
But we're at moments in the beginning even even after that initial
24-hour.
And Beyond where you thought this
I mean all the time
Like 3 weeks in
Kevin turned to me and he said Mike
I don't know how big is it going to be by think we're on
Something and I will see and every morning I would wake up
Expecting that that was the morning that
Bratz doll
And that was it
And if I knew what I know now about metrics and how to measure the weather people are coming back over one day 7 days
30 day.
I would actually been I think a lot calmer because I think it would have shown as
Babe that shows now that
People who join Instagram tend to stick around and become more active and that's really exciting at the time I didn't know that other guy they're signing up are they
Can I come back tomorrow like is it all going to change
And that was sort of an internal
Worryin externally
Now as we launched and grew
Became a very competitive face and
We would see in a company's got announced
Had
Tens of millions of dollars in Investments even before launching in real life
Man like these guys have so much money
They're going to come in and you know attack us
Going to be really hard and
That's the other lesson learned which is
You know your valuation and the amount you raise it can be helpful in building your product but it does absolutely nothing
Thank people and users don't care at all how much money you raised the care if you're providing some
Car value
I'm in the product
Lesson learned over time that you know you have to earn it everyday
I'm curious to get your
Your take on
Why it continue to grow
There are a lot of
Cool apps
That you and I both know of the launch
Years ago that were amazing at
People use that that
Dawn and
There are lots of people who work really hard or really creative a really smart of Amazing Ideas
And put out a really cool
Cool products
So why
Why do you think Instagram
Survive and thrive
I think there was this opportunity that we spoke of that
Back in the day that
People had
Cameras in their pocket
First time
And digital photography was clearly going to be a thing
But the second that camera got added
To the phone
Emmanuel hot
That with you at all
All times
And that doesn't mean that you're going to
Take photos on an obviously the quality has to be high enough
But we started the company right at the moment we're like
The quality of those cameras
Just kind of met up
Shoots and because of that
Everyone starts
The phone
But they had no place to
Or if they did it
It was hard I mean they would look at face
Maybe like well you know like have to upload them
I like on a desktop or
I on Twitter like doesn't really showing the timeline
I'm so they had this problem like there's no place to easily share all these
Please photos. I'm taking
All the time
And we just happen to be the right
Cool for that job
At the right moment
And
Who created I believe the thing that kept
Dick growing was quitting open network
We sat down
Very early on
Product design
Oyster sauce okay
Do we want to be
A place where you
Send a friend request
You have to accept it in order
Courtesy
Those photos or do we want to be open where anyone
I'm so glad we ended up
Choosing the open model
Because now
You can follow someone from
Japan you can follow
You know a chef from New York City
You can file your favorite celebrity or you can follow your friends
A not like haven't really been done before
In photos if you look at
Every photo service
Rest before then
It was basically a closed only
Friend's only Network
And we were the first ones
It's really open that
Yeah that was a moment
In my other radio show that
TED Radio Hour wear
PPL be like
How big
The show
Became when when pink
The pop singer
He's about to shut we like wholly
She looks like
She was in the show
Did you guys have a moment we would like
Jesus like
They're using this thing that we built in like our basement
I think for me
The biggest one was the White House or obamacare's Obama joint first
I think it was part of
Champagne
That he was running
And I remember like
Knows what Instagram is in the north how to use it and I remember
You know every
You know every time somebody is using our appetite either see or hear about a mic
Hope it doesn't crash I hope it works perfectly
I hope they like don't have any question
Keep them from using at so that was I think that a big infection moment and I think the other one was
I noticed that the New York Times when they would cover his head stop saying Instagram,
The photo-sharing app and then it was you
Instagram Aiko we are we have now reached the point where they they can assume that most of their readers
Know what we are
I am old enough to remember when in PRC
Would say
Google
For me is I feel embarrassed because you had a really good example about like the president using
For me it was like our first celebrity of Snoop Dogg
Do you remember Snoop Dogg signing up
We were like
Is this actually Snoop Dogg and then I got an email that was like Snoop Dogg's people want to meet you guys and I was
Oh my gosh
I don't even know what does it mean people like
Snoop Dogg has people
And I remember Justin Bieber signing up
And and
The world going kind of
Bonkers
Forgot as well and by world I mean
Teenage girls and
They basically started using the app incessant
I kind of took off with like
A bunch of really young people
People as well
You obviously everybody knows
Eventually you sold
Instagram
Facebook
Billion dollar
I mean
Incredible
All that to years
That happen
You couldn't have planned for that you couldn't have
Even have been in ambition
Yeah I mean the first day
That we went home
After pulling that all-nighter to launch Instagram
There's a guy sitting on the muni here answer
San Francisco subway system
And
He was using Instagram
Oh my God like we did it but someone in the world is using this thing out in the wild
That feeling and that moment
Is the currency that you maximize
When you're not
It's like seeing someone using your product
And loving it is like way more rewarding
Than any amount of money
In the world
You guys now or within the Facebook
Family right
Independent
Company but you are part of Facebook
How to change the
You are obviously a lot bigger
Yeah and usually that was actually
Pretty awesome because
We had all these problems killing our services in like
The Facebook infrastructure
Can we come over and we seen that before here this is what you do
So I made our lives actually a lot better
And we were able to hire someone
The best people in the world end
And share talent I like to call ourselves the older brother or the other sibling where were the we were the first company to Facebook
Fire dancer
Kept running and then since then you've seen Oculus
Send WhatsApp
And
I can do a lot of things that we figured out early on income
Relationship
The office space
Hiring
And I think we
Off
From both sides of
Of the table I purchased it from
A spirit of hate how can we make Instagram better through these Integrations rather than
How can you make Instagram more like Facebook in or try to
Adapted to be exact
There was this
This controversy that happened
With Instagram where
You change the terms of service and people aren't
The impression that the
The photo store
Your property in
A lot of people like
Black Instagram
Grandma.
Moment
There's only that I mean that's
Yeah that was a
Learning lesson for Fugue for you guys
Huge lesson
Number one
People read the docs that
You know
You put out an
You should care about them as a
The founder so your terms of service basically what happened we have these terms of service that we had
I think effectively copied from some other site way back in the day and just
Find and replace their name with
Instagram because we're a startup we didn't know what we were doing
But we eventually got to a place where when we join Facebook Facebook is like hey you actually need a real one that like
Fits with the way you guys working working to make all these changes and we went through it
I was like a great this makes sense and I didn't really read it all that carefully
And one of the sections
It reading it again today if I look at it
Can be interpreted that we were going to take
User photos and somehow use them in advertising
That was definitely not our intention and like no one in the Company of Thieves
Thought of that idea
It just if you read the sentence that way you could see that maybe it would worry people
So immediately
You know we had to
Big protest in
People
You know
Leaving the service I mean if we have a graph of account deletions at that
Skyrocketing
And Mike and I sat down / like what do we do
And
And we felt helpless time it was like all over that was that first day all over again
It's like we screwed this up how do we make sure people know
I went back to my house like
Why don't we just apologize and say we're wrong
And I posted this Punk post on our block you can probably still find it online
And I was like we're sorry like
We didn't mean this
That's absolutely not what we're trying to do
We tweeted about it and actually the graph
Deletions at that moment
Drops to zero
And sometimes you just have to say sorry
Sometimes you just have to say you were wrong
And reassert what you're actually trying to do
I'm at interaction with
The community still sick
And my mind is some
That we try to do every
Every single day we
Be really transparent
People put our community
81st because like at the end of the day
Without them where a photo sharing app
How much of what happened
To you guys
Instagram
And this whole story how much of it
I'd say 50%
Actually I have this thesis
Bad
The world runs unlock
The question is what you do with
Everyone gets lucky for some amount in their life
And the question is are you
Are you alert enough
To know you're being lucky right or you're
You're becoming lucky
Are you talented enough
Take that advantage and run with it
And
Do you have enough
Grits do you have enough like
Resilience to stay with it when it gets hard because everyone gets lucky
In minimal ways every week
Can you find a Dollar on the ground or you know you got a break at work to work on the
Project are you meet someone really interesting
The difference between people I think
If you succeed in the long run and the Pea
People don't is frankly that optimism that like
You got lucky and now it's yours too
Yours to make awesome
And that first day I think we got lucky by having the right ideas the right time
The right place we
We were lucky to have met each other I mean
There are a lot of co-founding Paris
Intact who have not worked out and Mike and I are like great friends
Least I think so right Mike
And
The question is
Can you take that lock and capitalize on it
Instagram co-founders Kevin Systrom and Mike Krieger by the way
After the sale of Instagram to Facebook for a billion dollars those two became very very rich
But today Instagram according to Forbes is worth more than 50 billion
Dollars which makes Instagram bigger in dollar terms then places like Alaska
Maine Rhode Island
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things you are building
But first quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Delta Airlines
Now you can enjoy free mobile messaging while flying on Delta
You can use iMessage WhatsApp and Facebook Messenger simply by logging into the in-flight Wi-Fi
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And today we're doing a story we first ran in January featuring
When you tell people that you're leaving your successful software career to start a bike company you get two types of reactions you get
Wow that's amazing let me hear more
And then you get the
Oh okay go to lock willing to take that leap because
Jesse loves bicycles
He basically grew up fixing them building them
A lot of times when he wanted to go out for a ride with
Was friends he'd run into this it always say
My bike has flat tires and needs a tune-up
And then of course me is the extra mechanic
I either have to go over early and tune up their bike
Wouldn't go for a ride
So they decided to design the
Find a bike wear
That type of thing would not happen we really really invented the bicycle going through every
Little not bolt piece component on the bike with the focus of low maintenance
Enzo in a basement Workshop in Manhattan
Dave designed his first
Bike made of Aluminum and Stainless Steel with internal gears and disc brakes
But he says what he said his bike apart is that
Instead of a greasy chain
It's got a belt drive made from carbon fiber that feels more like rubber
So there's no grease there's nothing to rust
There's no way to suck in your pants and leave you on the side of the road and it lasts three times longer than a tree
Now you might think a bike like this would cost like
Thousands of dollars but
They figured out a way to do it for a lot cheaper more like
$400
In his concept was so popular that he raised half a million bucks on Kickstarter
And then found two factories in Asia to make the bikes
But the matter years ago when it was time to deliver the first thousand bikes
He got into a jam we had our our bikes produced and they were on the water on their way over from Taiwan
When
Customs took our containers
And tell them for an undetermined amount of time while they inspected them and even worse
This was in December
We started to get emails from our customers saying you're going to ruin Christmas
I bought this for my spouse for my son for my daughter
Christmas
It needs to be under the tree
And all this almost offended the whole company
But about a week before Christmas
Customs finally let the bikes through
I was lucky we made it on the very last day we could
That's a weiner of priority bicycles
When we first spoke to him in January day was working on opening his first retail location in New York City and
Right now he has a showroom
It's downtown in Tribeca
And things are going really well priority bicycles now has Partnerships with more than 200 hotels
Resorts and college campuses around the world
And they're launching a line of accessories including some bike bags that just came out this week
And in August
Wired Magazine called his bicycles the ideal city bike
If you want to find out more about Dave's
Priority bicycles head to our Facebook page
And of course
You want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing
Our show was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music thanks also to neva Grant
Claire Breen and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Diana mu stock if you want to find out more
Or or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org please also subscribed
2R podcast at Apple podcast or however you get your podcast you can write us that HIV
Tea at npr.org and a Twitter it's at how I built this by Guy Raz and you can live
Link to how I built this from NPR
Where can we debate today's big issues without getting attacked for speaking our minds
One egg
Provides a safe smart place for tough conversation every weekday
And the Friday news Roundup breaks down the week's top stories
I'm Joshua Johnson check out the 1A podcast on the NPR one app or wherever you listen to podcasts
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com