Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Diamond Burr I'm telling my investor my heart's not in it my fault
Just terrible I mean this was likely be worst sort of a few weeks of my life and I remember
I was certified being myself at the up at that point in time because because I sort of kept on my side
I should have known that I was in passionate about this I should I should have known this and so much like how much money did they end up losing
I think they they lost the the million dollars
NPR how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Behind the movement
Couchsurfing computer programmer to founding a billion dollar company
So if you ask me what it is I've learned about business from
All the entrepreneurs we've had on the show
The number one thing is
There's a problem
If it could be solved the world will be
Be better off
And here is the proposed solution
Throwing some hard work
And lots of luck
Got a business
Which is what eventually happened to apoorva Mehta
He couldn't stand going to the grocery
Hated the parking lot the lines lighting the whole experience
Is a programmer
She knew there was a
Technology
Who is problem
And the proposed solution
It's called instacart
You open the app
Check out the grocery items you want
And those groceries are delivered to your front door
The company is now valued at more than
Billion dollars
And it was founded barely five years ago
Buy app
He was just
26 years old
And I'm like lots of Wonder can
Entrepreneurs in the Silicon Valley
He didn't go to Stanford or MIT
I actually grew up in Canada with college there
Any studies of course
Computers
When he graduated
The job in Seattle
Working on
Supply chain
Amazon
To be honest I love that II
Wasn't even
Sure why they're even paying me
I was having so much fun I was learning so much I
Was
Working on
Most interesting problems that I'd ever worked on so to me this was
But
After zeref about you don't want it half years I realized that
My learning was plateauing I wasn't really necessarily going I wasn't being challenged
It's always I sort of
Except bacton and reflected on what I wanted to do
I realize that it wasn't
Play a different role or a different company would change that
It was that
What would be fulfilling for me is
To make a material difference in this world and I wouldn't be able to do that working in a in a in a bigger company
And so
One of the ways that I thought that would be
It would allow me to make it at Material differences is to be an entrepreneur and
I
Thought that
Being an entrepreneur will be cool and but I know anything about it
I'm so
I
Started to go to these
Tech meetups in Seattle
And
I remember the first one that I went to
They had invited a bunch of these
Tech luminaries
To the meet-up to speak to us
Who is there it was Gordon Bing
Or so I think it's been going
He wasn't executive from Electronic Arts EA which is a
Really big game company and
I members are listening to this talk and
They could have been.
Talking in Hebrew
But you had no idea what he was.
I had absolutely zero idea
They were talking about things like
Enterprise.
To me if you're talking about an Enterprise startup
It meant like
You're talking about the car rental
And told me
Since you were a computer geek you did not understand the language of business
At all
But I liked it so I threw thought that I was going the right direction
And then I realized that work was getting in the way
And the the fact that
I would come up with all these ideas that I would want to build into companies
And I wasn't able to
Put my full attention to those because
I was going to work
You are still at Amazon
Yeah and
Tumi
The way to do this
Fully was to actually quit my job
In a couple weeks after that I decide to quit
I didn't
Have a clue what my startup was going to do
But I knew that I wanted to do this in Seoul
Did you leave Seattle FF
Yes as I read more and more about Entre
Urban Airship in as I started to
Find all these people like that that I would be able to talk to or service
Prolific entrepreneurs in
Investors
Datejust had something
In common which was that all of them
Where in Silicon Valley
To me it was like
If you're acting you're probably good idea for you to be in Hollywood and so
It wasn't like I was you know I had a job to do so
Oh you know why not move to San Francisco
Pantene a picture for my where you like
Did you get an apartment in San Francisco and you had like at your computer there and
You just tinkering on it all day or were you meeting with people and cuz I'm assuming you
I didn't know that many people there did you
When I move to San Francisco I only knew one guy here and
Lucky for me he also had a couch and so that's where I was
I would never sleep on the couch and wake up in
Start
Anchoring in
The right code for the new idea that I was working on
That was pretty much my life
For the next two years
And when you said running Cody you were writing at that point
App Store redeem code
For websites
Both whatever the the idea require
For example one of the ideas that I was working on was
It was this thing called office hours
And this would allow
Anyone
To connect with tech luminaries or luminaries in general in
It would be like a one-on-one session with someone for 30 minutes or an hour
And
That was a website that was a nap and what happened to cool
Yeah so turns out that you really can't
Get that many
Current Tech luminaries to spend
Enough of a time on this platform
Because they're all busy
And so it didn't work
So
All the all the while you're
Living with a friend
And
You don't have to pay a coder because you're doing all the back end
Technology right
That's right
Super exciting are you having
It started off being really interesting and fun because I was learning a lot of these interesting things like how to
What business models work
And what don't what how to build a prototype really really fast
How to advertise
But then
After going through all these ideas I
I was getting pretty tired I was getting tired of sore feeling
This was a pretty low point in my in my life
When I was like all I might even cut out to be an entrepreneur at all then
You know I remember there's one idea.
It's something that it had been
I my mind and I thought
That this ideas
This is brilliant this is going to be the one that
It is a home run
You know it's going to be awesome
The idea was
A social network
For lawyers
You clearly don't know many lawyers they do not tend to be social that is
Something I overlooked
What Jetty behind it
Was like assertive
LinkedIn
Yeah so the idea was that LinkedIn was just
To generic and it was not for everyone
But if there were specific features that were billed for lawyers
Then it would be useful to them and they would be willing to do use this product
And if they were willing to use this product maybe there are ways to monitor
His well until you have this idea
And in what
You ran with
Yeah in fat guy you've been raised about $1000000 and financing
But I realized very quickly that
That as soon as I went home after work
Stop thinking about work
I stopped thinking about Lord I didn't care about lawyer that I don't care about what they did on their
I need a life is just didn't matter to me
You know after about
About a year of doing this
I just realized that I
I was going in the wrong direction
Just wasn't going to work
And what's the company was a concept
Proving to be successful in any way or was it
It seemed pretty clear that
I think that
It could have worked but
What I've been doing
So far and as my my journey as an entrepreneur was
That I had been looking for good encoding code business ideas
And they were not necessarily
Business ideas that I cared about they were just
Business ID
Windsurf that's when I realize that
The odds of success in a startup or solo anyways her have to go
You have to put
Everything that you have it in it you just can't do that for an idea that you just don't care about 4
And then that's when I said that I I just can't do this and
I quit my own startup
What is
Remember like
What were you told your
Yeah my
I remember
Telling my investors
The same thing which is that my heart's not in it
IPhone
Just terrible I mean this was likely the worst sort of
A few weeks of my life
Yeah I remember having to
Alvin look I
I'll do what
You think is best
If you want we can
Return the money
The good thing
Here was that
These guys were very experienced
Investors in
Did
Seen this happened before and then you that
It was the right thing to do for the company and it was the right thing to do for me
And they were extremely supportive during
So
How much like how much money did they end up losing
I think they they lost the the million dollars wow
I'm swimming
Yeah I mean I think there is a
Feeling that
I should have known this I should have known that this
Was not going to work I should have known better
And if this is a certified continuous feeling that happens to me and I think that I was sort of being myself
At that point in time because because I
I should have kept telling myself I should have known that I was in passionate about this I should I should have known this and
Yeah yeah yeah
Games perspective I was
Take me to I'm not American and so I didn't have
Any income and I was in the in a country where I
I only had a limited amount of time that I could really be here
Because I am an immigrant
And sew in
You know during this time my
Mom also was was going through some health issues as well and
This is just build the worst time in my life I remember
So many nights when I was just
Wake up and cry because there's nothing else like
Are you able to turn around I mean it's it's hard to
Pinpoint one sort of single at the moment but it was feeling in my mind that
It had been developing go over the
The whole entire year which was that I should be doing something that I care about I should be doing something that I'm passionate about huh
Event turned out to be
Something that was her
Pretty close to home and that was the fact that
Ever since I can remember you from childhood memories and talk
I had always hated
Every aspect of grocery
Going around around in the aisles in a grocery
East Aurora
Waiting in line at the checkout or
And in some cases you know frankly in memories of
Being in Canada and waiting for the bus with all the bags in your hands in your
Your fingers are just
Freezing in the cold
You know everything about it
Demi was just
Painful
And
The last
2 years of my life I just worked on building
Oldies cool apps in products and so on
Then I realized that
I did everything online
I didn't
Bought stuff online
Book bookstore
Whatever and I met people online
I want
TV online I was doing everything online
But the one activity that I've always hated in my entire life
I was still doing
In the most inefficient way pause
Tumi
That was a problem that I cared about that was a problem that I was so passionate about
That I
How how long did
Did it take you to go from that
That low point when you left
Lawyer shows
Network company
2 when you started
Was it
What's today's weather
Months of being depressed or
Or longer
It was a few weeks and I remembered it this is
This is really interesting because
They were weeks where I was so depressed at the lowest point in my life
And as soon as I started thinking about this idea
I was in
Edit High all the
Write like
This was just
But you know so it's already like the feeling of
Falling in Love
You can't stop thinking about
What's a parameter in just a moment
How quick thinking and a six pack of beer
Get instacart on the radar of Silicon Valley
Biggest investors
I'm guy Raz you're listening to how I built this NPR
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from the United States Postal Service
Everyday
Innovative companies are Reinventing the way business happen
But none of that is possible without the right people
People who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery
Points affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce
The United States Postal Service
See why they deliver more e-commerce packages to homes than anyone in the country
Usps.com
Future
Support also comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulator
Licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR
Gyros
Soca hits 2012
Apoorva Mehta has just come up with the idea
Idea for a grocery delivery app
Are you sure it's going to become huge
But at this point
The company
Is just
Apoorva
The first version of the app I
Found that there was a
Website
Called safeway.com
Grocery store in
I
Saw that they had all their their inventory available online and so
I just scraped it and
I was like great I have all the items that I am going to have in the first version of the app
Until I can get over there over the next few weeks I I built the app and I
Place the first order
But because
I was the only person
Company at the
This time I
I placed an order and then I
To the grocery store pick the order in
Delivered to myself
So was the whole
Contact already mapped out by that point
Yeah that idea was that we would connect to all the people who wanted to get their groceries delivered with all the people who
I want to earn money while picking and delivering groceries
You know I started to
You sharing this with it with my friends
And it was really interesting because
You know before instacart I would share products with my friends and
Use it out of guilt
It was just
Oh yeah we want to
Help for buyout
But this one was different
It was
Very clear that
The people wanted to use
It was really cool because
And then the first version of the app
Anytime anyone would place an order
I would get a text
And every time I would get a text I would look at it and say ho
Let's see who placed an order
Enzo for the first
Few days for few weeks I I just saw my friends using that on a regular basis
Really cool
And then I saw people who are using the app
Why didn't even know
And so what happened was that my friends were sharing the app with their friends
This word of mouth was starting and people were telling each other about pay you can get your groceries delivered
And so that's when I realized
That I needed more people to pick and deliver the groceries was it called instacart
At this point I already beginning
Yeah the name was calling because I didn't have the domain name
At the time so
It was called get instacart.com was where you would find that yeah
And to me the idea was that
Customers
You should expect instant gratification
And anything less than that
Would essentially mean that there was just another barrier in the customer
And there were there R&B
The time that were other
Delivery services right like a Peapod and
Amazon
Even had had one and two
Still has one.
Fresh Direct in others
But I guess they're their models were complete
Different
Presumably because they were actually they had inventory you did not have any inventory
Yeah I realized
Even from day one against
Instacart the our biggest competitor
Was going to be a man
Your former employer
That's right and
I realize in order to survive
Really compete with them
I would have to do something that's meaningful you different
Front end
It couldn't be something that was just it was like cheaper or anything like that because Amazon has gobs and gobs of money so it wasn't
It wasn't that
It just had to be something that
They just want to be able to do and it turns out there are a lot of retailers across the country where
I really want to shop from people getting there
Their favorite types of groceries from
And they don't like Amazon
And so to me it was
The ability to serve build something
Weather for the Retailer's
To be able to compete with Amazon
What is the weight of go in what that would allow other the customers to do is
Get their groceries from their favorite grocery stores
And get a much better selection then you would be able to get on Amazon just because
Every single grocery store is on this platform until you have just
Any more items in a different types of items
Then you will be able to get on Amazon
Chip from the time that you built this and 30
Hestia
Time to the time when you thought all right
I better go out in like
Get some money
Scaleless how how long was it
Few months
Yeah I think it was just
Two and a half months
Hand
I mean it was it was becoming pretty clear because I was just too hiring all these people would my very limited
Money and
My bank balance at a time
Actually hitting zero
I knew that was
Good and how are you finding how are you finding p
People to hire get music
Personal shopper
That would do the grocery shopping how are you able to
Define the people
What first it was just Craigslist I really I have just posted an ad in and get a bunch of people to to enter
View Inn
Remember the first guy who hired as a shopper
He was wearing a suit and a tie for
I was like
This is a
Job for picking and delivering groceries but if he's wearing a suit and tie better hire
And so that's what I did
How are you able to make sure that the shoppers
So you are hiring where are you know
Anniston
Reading and all that stuff right it wasn't easy
That we had lots of interesting
Experiences there where
In the early days of
Instacart one of the ways that
Shoppers with checkout at the grocery store when they would
They had bought the groceries for someone else
Is by using gift cards
So you know you have to trust them gift cards
A prepaid credit card that's right that turns out to be great for a lot of people most people are pretty trustworthy but
For some people if they were just buying their own groceries with it
What would happen if the store was
What kind of avocados are some
Yapko freak
Example
If you
Don't have
The Heinz Ketchup that you ordered
How do you make a substitution for
We realize that we would have to make
The app
Pretty smart because they would have to understand
Apus items out of stock what should I do to replace this with
The cost around the same
But if something to the customer will be happy with
Excessive what happened to Shepard
Call the customer said hey they don't know how to catch up with you got Hans
Do you want that
Yasso initially
We
Tried would not climb
Hey customer
Probably fine
Find Esprit intrusive
But then we realize that no
Actually customers
Love it when guy when are Shoppers call to customers
Because they feel so special there like
Why can't you have this person actually
Looking out for me when that papaya has gone bad
The The Shopper will call the customer and say Hey you know
I could get you this papaya but it's not the best quality
Right in the end. That's a very
Their intimate experience
Yeah
We
You know we we in cursive
How much money at the beginning to the
Take
Dictate keep us going before you had any outside money
I think it just took a few thousand dollars because you know you're paying all these Shoppers and you have to pay
Pay them with the hours that they work
In the money that
And the customers would pay would show up a few days after into there times where
I would just not have any money
They say it was very clear
So how'd you added you find investors
I realized you know from sort of going through the start-up ideas that I hadn't
Which was that
Who you raising money from the quality of investors was really important so
Tumi
The way that I would be able to attract Saint the best investors in
Silicon Valley was
If I went to an incubator
Like y combinator
Saudi incubator
Insult
There's only one problem with
That was that
You know I had missed the application deadline
2 months
Which meant that what you have to wait another year basic
That's right
And
Time to wait
I
Stats on people that I met into
Disco
To connect me with the
Partners in in y combinator
And then finally I got one response
When it was
Garry Tan one of the partners at y combinator he said
Look at
Likely not going to work but you can
You can fill out a late application
So I filled out a late application and then finally I got a response room and he says
Nope
MassLive
This sucks
As the Koran is like
This guy does this even know what instacart is has even tried out the product does even know
Wife different
And so what I did was
Open the app I ordered a six-pack of beer and addressed it in for the Y combinator head
And half an hour later I got a call from Gary Tammy is like
What is this
Sounds like oldest thing to cart and I guess the beer must have been pretty good because
He asked me to come in then the next day for an interview
And so I
Job interview the next day and then soon after that it was accepted
So that's how
Oyster card got funded
And that the business model was based on the idea that
It would be a delivery fee
Plus IV
Obviously 8
Epremium like
Pants slightly higher price
A product
Then you would if you had
What's the storm body
That's right early on because we don't have any retail relationship
We would have to mark up the items
And
Divya small delivery
Caswell
We didn't know you know
Keep customers would actually want to pay that and
Turns out there a lot of customers who are okay with that
But then we realize that if we partnered with the
The grocery stores
We could really
Reduce
Supreme your arm make it to be frankly
The same price as a store
And that
Dramatically changed the way
That people interact
So when you say partner I mean
You able to reduce the cost of
The groceries
Because the supermarket
Partnered with Dashie
He paid you guys to do that service on their behalf
That's right so today
Hundreds of retailers across the country pay us
Affiliated
To be honest
And I guess
The question is why wouldn't a big
Grocery
Like I know you do a lot of Whole Foods
Camp like why wouldn't they just make their own instacart
Is it just is it
Cheaper to work and more efficient to work with
A company like yours that already exists and has the infrastructure
Boat so it's definitely cheaper because that mean you know we
Have
Aldi's grocery store has already work with us and so
Definitely that but
I think the main reason is that
That we are technology company and
Allowed the grocery stores are
Very good at
Managing grocery stores managing the inventory in the grocery stores
Managing how to produce
Is this place fresh and Salon
What they're not very good at is
Solving technical problems
I like some of the problems that freaking if I was working on it Amazon so the logistical issues
How do you make sure that
Did the Shoppers when they're picking the groceries in the store
They are doing that in the most efficient way possible
We know where the items are already located we map them in many key
Do those types of things
Are things that are soft
I had a software company would be able to do in
That and I'm not necessarily a grocery store
I will be able to
I mean in those
First two years
We're investors like beating down your door to the best of us as people started to download the app and use it
You know I wish that was the case
It you know it was it was
Pretty hard to be honest I think that
Early on
Wasn't very obvious
Did most people that
This
Become something and
Because there had been other ideas like this before like webvan back in the day
During the.com era
And that was one of the biggest failures of all time
Like it literally lost billions of dollars I remember one time I was
Pitching a venture capitalist
You know we were in the conference room and then he suddenly
Gets up and he leaves the meeting
Confuse I was like why was in the middle of the presentation
He came back with a floppy disk
Easter slams it on the on the table
And you like
Go home and study what's
Inside the five
Because it has the webvan business model
Until you need to understand that I really well and why didn't work
How's life
This guy is just so smart and
Well-known
A person in Silicon Valley and
Like I must
Be completely wrong
But thankfully I guess I didn't have a way to open the floppy disk is it just have floppy drive but
So I never really looked at that the business plan their butt
You know it was just
It was
If there's a lot of self-doubt
Haven't you ever cut myself. How did you know that
Or did you just kind of
Live with it
I think at least me I've just gone through these
Roller coasters of emotions
Every single day
You know there's
Wishing you were here
Some
Master telling you something like that were
They completely rule out your ideas on asking to work or
Someone in the process something
The other times you're growing really fast in customers love your product
The right into me it was just
That I just felt like this
Should exist I was really solving a problem that
You know I wanted to solve in
So I was okay with going through a lot of
Just
Terrible times to make this a reality
Yeah I wonder how you how you deal with a the roller coaster
Xtratuf even
I write because
Of course is always going to be criticized
Always gonna be people who
Lesson plans for me how do you
How do you manage quality how do you maintain in a
A quality of service
Cross
7th place
Yeah I'll
Start with saying that we're learning
And we have a long long way to
And we go
Went from
Having zero Choppers
Having tens of thousands
People on earth
Platform I really really quickly inside out
I don't think we're doing it
We've had
Luck so far in
Building a very strong culture and
The teams in the store have
My metrics that they are assigned in terms of
A fast they're picking what is the quality of their ear picking how
How how many
Good replacements are they making it
They're sort of all working towards a common goal
And I think it. Has helped
Build that camaraderie in the culture that I truly care about
What what what
Keeps you up at night like like
Drones delivering groceries to people and or
Like what is it that you were your words
Could could like knock you guys off
I think that
It really is just
Our
Lack of execution
That I think will be the cause of our failure if
That's what keeps me up at night is
It's little things like
Add small element of a meeting
I'm just did not go well or
Project is not going well even though it may not be the most important project
But to me that's a sign that
They were not doing their job well overall in
The Transformers 2 two other important things in so to me I think
It's making sure that that the
The team is working on
All the little details and then they're paying attention to the details and doing a great job
Is very important at night when I'm done. Doesn't
Every stressed out
At and how many how many
People work
Directly for insta
We have
Around
3000 employees
Islands
Easter cards
And we have
Over
Contractors
Why The Purge
That's right
Started this
5 years ago
Depression or funk
After failing
Billion dollar Gamble
Nuts
Yeah I mean
I'm in I'm so lucky
To be
Where I am
Today
You know being
Surrounded by some
People who work
Very hard
It just really really lucky
I mean obviously
Super smart guy in you worked really really hard but
Is that do you think that luck is is a bigger part of it
Oh I think luck is majority
I mean you know there's so many elements of lucke-zone
Times when luck
I play the part but
I think it's
Specifically true in startups because
It didn't start out so you have is this moment in time when
Companies
Anything before that
It's too early anything after that it's way too late
And there's too much
The timing being there at the right place at the right time is everything
Apoorva Mehta founder of instacart a company as we met
Mentioned earlier now valued at 3.3 billion dollars tomato poorva
A rich young man on Forbes list of the richest people under 40
Apoorva comes in at number 3100 and is late night instacart order
The perfect oldest it's ice cream cheese crackers and figs
Please don't turn it off just yet in a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
You guys are build
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
TIAA
Whether it's investing
Vice banking or retirement
TIAA believes
Smart Financial
Conversations should enable life not
Define it
Because real success isn't just measured in zeros
It's having a career that delivers meaning and purpose
Connecting with family
Friend and it's giving back
TIAA calls list
The new success.
Anyone help you achieve it
Everyday
Learn more
TIAA
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for Howard
You built that and I can tell you when we heard about this next product
At first we thought
A joke
Because well I'm glad we called it the inventor Tim casa
Have there been people ever into you at the end of invest like what were you thinking this is crazy
It's anytime
Something comes in and disrupt an existing Market
And the backlash is coming from some of the most opinionated people on earth
Parents
But before I tell you what's going on
2 about a year-and-a-half ago Tim became apparent himself when his son jack was
So I was literally feeding my child every hour for 20 minutes
Set a time is a great bonding time
You know there's a lot of interaction
During the day
But there's also a lot of feeding times at midnight
Do you know where
The child is basically asleep
Entering those moments
You could of course be
Getting stuff done accomplishing important tasks
So that's when the idea came to me that I think I can solve the problem and make a device that connects your smart
Turn to your baby bottle and give you the opportunity to
Multitask when you never thought possible yes a problem that many parents did not know needed solving
And Tim solution
A plastic device that clamps around a baby bottle with an arm that
Clamps onto your smartphone
You hold the baby in one arm with clamp holds the bottle at a perfect 45 degree angle
And with your free hand you can just
The scroll and swipe to your heart's content there's no harm in when your kid is half asleep and just maybe
Being able to catch up on some
Read an NPR article or right now play Candy Crush
Parents are already using their phones while bottle feeding or just providing a more secure method of doing it Tim has the perfect
Name for this device because of the swipe and feed
And every head that lightbulb moment give me the first one for himself in his basement. Some actual
And
Layered a bunch of pieces
Tim made a mold out of the tin foil heat flatten it out of plastic
And then use the heat gun to bend the whole thing into the right shape and I made my first very rough prototype
Kept making this prototypes were probably the first couple months
And just talking to people
Especially parents
And you're after some parents. This is definitely something that they would buy I thought we should I sell
So Tim started a Kickstarter campaign to raise $13,000 enough to pay for his first batch of in
Inventory and he eventually found two manufacturers wanted Michigan the other in North Carolina to make
Take the plastic and silicone parts of the swipe and feed and then he assembles them right there in his house
So I get boxes and boxes of plastics
Pieces that are assembled and finalized in my basement
And I'm shipping from the same desk and I'm talking to you from right now in my basement in Reston Virginia
Since January Tim sold almost a thousand of these things but for now
He's keeping his day job
As a corporate recruiter what I love for this to be my full-time job or do I think it could be like asking some
I'm sure you know this this could be a great day
Okay but back to the backlash part parenting blogs have been lighting up and some parents say the swipe and feed
Utterly destroy the parents baby bond for apps
You can bring an end to civilization as we know it
The Kim
He's optimistic
Spend all your time focusing on the people who just
You know are there to try and bring you down then you never look for you never get anything
I mean it
It's not like you made an ashtray connected to a bottle feeder that would be bad
It's just new you know and there's going to be some Buzz around that and then you have two stomachs and you know that buzz with a p
People saying great things are the people saying bad things that buzz is still good when you're bringing your product
That's Tim Casa of Reston Virginia to find out more about his company swipe and feed go to
To our Facebook page
And of course
If you have a story about
Something in your building
Tell us about it
Go to build
NPR.
LRT
Hey thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or listen to
Two previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us at Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet it's at
How I built this
Please also help us out biceps
Describing to our show on iTunes or however you get your podcast and wire there
Leave us a review
Our show was produced this week by run teen Arab Louis
Loss of composure
Music
Thanks also to neva Grant sanaz meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Calabrian
I got rise and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Heights Rachel Martin NPR news
Anal
We're doing something new
And we want you to be part of it it's called up first
It's the Morning News podcast from NPR
It's wait for you in about 10 minutes
Or so to get up to speed on the news of any given day
The most important stories
The biggest ideas the stuff you need to know as you go through your day
Up first
It starts April 5th you can get it at NPR one or anywhere you listen to
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
It's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com