This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who tailors its policies to fit every business is very specific needs
Which may explain its 97% customer service
Get a quote or buy
Diane hiscox. Com
Hiscox
Business insurance
I was learning much more running a business on the streets versus studying in school and iron
Remember sitting down with my father who's a liver transplant surgeon wow but I remember having to sit down to him and just say Dad
Got some good news for you and I presented it is as good news cuz to me it was good news and I thought if I could get him a
Excited you might agree with me and I told him I was leaving school he said you're dropping out of school to become a junkman
Ramen PR
How I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
I'm Gyros and old pickup truck
Idea inspired junk hauling service in the world
By this point if you've been listening to the show
You know all about the inspiring people who
I had an idea and then ran with it
Whether it was Sara Blakely with
Spanx
Tony Shay Zappos
They had a vision and they pursued it
But almost all of them
They had to go through a complicated process to get from idea to implementation
Which is why today story
Is such a contrast because
Well junk hauling not sound sexy
Brian scudamore zydia welcome
Terribly elegant
And symbol
He didn't need a whole lot of money to start he didn't need any outside investors
And he didn't need to hire anyone
The first
And to be clear Brian did not dream of a life
Hauling away other people's trash
But he did dream of starting a business
Even as a kid
In Vancouver Canada
Etsy seventh grade
I remembered in Vancouver
Starting a car wash one summer
I saw my neighbor across the street
Eric it started this car wash
And he was charging
3 box of car
And I thought wow what a great way to make money I saw him washing cars and making money so I went and took a piece of plywood made my own
Sign
And I decided to charge to box you undercut your neighbor across the street
I undercut my neighbor
Buy a full dollar
And I thought
This is cool and there I was learning about a price war and it was awesome because literally cars would show up on my side of the story
Free wash their cars
You get more cars we start competing on price
So the funny part is I got down to $0.65
You were a ruthless
Rules heartless businessman in 7th grade
You know it's funny we've both made money we both had fun and we would do this
Several times throughout the summer
And we
Weed up the marketing so I'd get some friends you know a couple of girls that were in my class and I get them to go
So hold signs at the busier Street a block away to flag people over and
You start to learn about
Pricing and profit
And I was making so much money that I just I couldn't even believe it would you like a
Genius students
Like where you super
Go to school
Whatever the polar opposite of Genius student would be would be who I was
What happened is things like reading light
I just that was one area I got stuck
I'm so add that I couldn't focus on the words my mind would go to other things and I
I would have a hard time with that so
I learned to read but I didn't learn to understand
And that became a challenge through school and
Andrea Lee
Serta help me back from from learning through books
So
I failed
Many years throughout High School
I ultimately was 1/4 short from finishing High
12th grade
Didn't finish
Didn't graduate
But then I saw all my friends every single one of them get accepted into colleges
I said I want to be left out
Yeah so I went to one of the universities and said I don't have
My high school graduation
I'm smart enough I can do this
I wrote them letters and I
Spent time
In the admissions office and finally they said okay
We're going to let you in
So you were
So you were what 18 I guess
The time we were you working like a
For your parents helping you out how did you even have money to go to school
My parents
When I approach them and ask for some money for
Her school they said are you kidding me you didn't even finish High School why are we going to find your college education and
Turns out they were probably smart
But what it taught me is I had to get out there
Fund my own education
And what I did was I was in a McDonald's drive-thru
In Vancouver I saw this beat up old pickup truck plywood sides
Chunk filled up in the truck
And have a sign on the box that said Mark salling
I was having trouble finding a job I didn't know what I was going to do to pay for
College
And when I saw that truck
I immediately connected with that something I can do
I looked at the truck and I thought
I started those car washes as a kid
You can see how easy that was to get out there and
Advertising
Wash people's cars
And so to me this was
Buy truck and haul junk
Rhapsody to be like rush out and go
Woodford
Yeah grab the classified
Section of the paper
It started looking for trucks
And I found one that I
Google 5000 love with it but I certainly could afford
It's price tag of $700
Add $1,000 of my own money
And I spent $700 on a beat up truck of my own and it was this little
Blue Ford F100
And I got my
Girlfriend's father at the time to help me build plywood sides on there and
If I went I spray-painted 738 junk which was the phone number I was able to get from the phone company
Has my phone number and my company was called the rubbish boys
You know lipomas we are here about them but the reality is there in the arm
Many lipomas usually
Iterations in trying things and failing in life
This was a lightbulb moment that just
Happened to pass by you at that moment at the McDonald's
You would not have seen that truck and you may not have thought of that idea absolutely true but I would have found something else
It's in my DNA it's how I think
And so sure
How to jump truck
Hey I'm not passionate about junk I never will be but I love customer experience and I love building
Businesses I love building things
So I didn't see the junk truck I could have seen
Completely different I could have seen a carpet cleaning business and said hey
That's what I'm going after
So you two you go out
You get the truck
And how did you even know what to do with it
The charge peep
Customers
Orange
DIYs I just started looking around in the classifieds
I started looking and going okay
There's other people
Doing what they called rubbish removal
And they say they charge by the truckload or the portion of a load
I called them up and find out how much they charged in
You call someone up and you say I've got a couch they're going to tell you
Anthony hundred bucks hundred fifty bucks dumping fees whatever it would be
And I would pay attention and
Make notes
And then I decided I started my my charge rate
At $80
Truckload which is pretty cheap
Yeah it was pretty cheap but it was it was probably too cheap because
In the beginning I wasn't really making money I underpriced myself thinking
When you go out as a business specially as an 18 year old kid starting to company
How to be the cheap
How are you getting the word out
How did people know that you were even
Available to do this
So
I painted my phone over on the side of my toe
738 junk it was just the emblazoned on there was
What's bigger than anything else you could possibly see
And I would park my truck
It at a high-traffic intersection
It so people would see this and then call
And I really quickly
Figured out that people tell I thought you were your 78 junk truck parked at
Arbutus and 12th how much you guys charge
And so I I learned very quickly that that was my mobile billboard
And what would you do you do to a house
And you would
Yourself no help clear all the stuff
But they wanted removed
I wouldn't just go into the attic to basement wherever the junk was in the garage and and haul it away
But I realize there's a lot of things like refrigerators and deep freezers that were too heavy for just myself
I need employees
And I recruited my best friend David snyderman
He became too connected to the junk I mean we're still best friends today but it was pretty funny because
He would just look through the junk
It says check this out you know the history behind this and he would keep things and I'm like
This is not going to work out
We need to work here
So how did you figure out what you do with it
You have to
Pay
Fbm seeming to like I
Site like a landfill site where did you
Where'd you find this
I called up the city the municipalities and they said
Where do I take a load of junk if I've got summoned
They gave me the addresses of all the different places and
I tried them all out somewhere we're closer than others
Somewhere cheaper but farther away
Experimented a bit by
Pretty easy stuff I mean it really was a business of
Pick up someone's junk
See the smile on their face
Take their stuff off to the dump or to be recycled
And repeat
So simple
How how how long does it take to
Are you actually
You know you paid off the truck
The cost of the cross
So within two weeks I've made enough money that had paid for the business
Adjusted my prices
This quickly I worked hard
And I made $1,700
Net profit
That summer 1989 roughly 1989 all I remember was that $1,700 was a
Enough to pay for my school
And some leftover
And I would do this every summer
Until I finally
Have the Bold decision to drop out
I was learning much more
Running a business on the streets versus studying in school and I remember sitting down with my father who's a liver transplant surgeon
Wow just got done more school than anybody I know and very successful very smart man
But I remember having to sit down to him and just say Dad
Got some good news for you and I presented it is as good news cuz to me it was good news and I thought if I could get him excited he might agree
With me and I told him I was leaving school
You're dropping out of school to become a junkman
I mean he was just
Destroyed
My oldest son is leaving school to become a junkman and then I said
On the glamour Spectrum I mean it couldn't be
Closer to the bottom
And I just said now Dad I'm learning so much more he said you know bright you got a year left in your University education
Costco finishing
I said Dad
My business opportunity might not be there forever
I said I guarantee the University of British Columbia will be there for years and years to come if I ever choose to go back
So we agreed to disagree and
I dropped out
At this point this became your your full-time
Get right
Look at this point
It's you and
Is it you in a partner over
Miss you alone
So when I dropped out
I ended up having a guy went to school with me
John and John Redal and I
We went from one truck
The three trucks
Right after I
Quit school
And whole thinking there was
These mobile Billboards work
If I can add two or three mobile Billboards around town we're going to get that much
Busier and things are going to grow when we're going to have this
Little Empire
You weren't even
Paying for advertising cuz you g
Just had
It's on the side of you
We weren't paying for advertising and
My girlfriend at the time said
Why don't you call up the local
Compress call the newspaper and tell them
Your story
So what story
And she said well that you guys have created your own job it's a
Tight summer
Labor market nobody can find work
You guys created your own job and I said okay
I picked up the phone
And I called up the Vancouver Province our biggest newspaper at the time
It must have been a slow news day be
Because
I said I got a great story for you and they said what is it and I told them and they sent a reporter and they sent a photographer
And the next day boom We are on the front page
Of the paper
We got a front page ad
For free
With your phone number on it yeah and I remember the photographer saying
You guys are going to be busy tomorrow
And sure enough he was right we had bus drivers driving down the street
Waving their newspapers with our picture on it
Out of the window going that to you
And that was pretty fun
By the way did you ever have to
Like get a bank loan or or
Outside money
I didn't I was lucky I
Built a business out of cash flow
You and your partner and you were just
Hauling the stuff out
Yantai ultimately bought my partner out after about a year
And what I did is I just invested everything back into the business to grow it
But I never
Expanded beyond my means
Not in the early stage
What's the kind of stuff that died
Yuki Woodhall out of
We would haul away old furniture
Appliances
We're very much a
Keep up with the Joneses type world and I think unfortunately
We people renovate too much and always want new furniture and the latest and greatest in TVs and so
We haul away their old stuff
We try to recycle as much as we possibly can but
Furniture appliances yard debris when someone cleans up the yard
And
It was a simple model but it was
It was fun because you
You find weird things
I remember there was a woman who
Had Soup cans should a whole wall of Campbell Soup cans made it look like a real live
Art piece
Right end and I remember you know looking at this and going
What are you doing in jail she just said well
If she was saving up for the next big war and then just wanted to have all this food stocked away and
Finally her kids to said like
You even if there was a war you couldn't eat
That stuff it's no 50 years old so we ended up cleaning out a whole wall OU Andy Warhol
Wallace
Campbell Soup can
What were some of the challenges that you faced
What were there any
Regulation that you have to get around or
Competitors that tried to you know shut you down or anything like that at all
And the biggest
Challenge I faced in the early days five years and we are about a half a million in Revenue
And I realized I wasn't having fun any longer
I was avoiding spending time with my employees
Nigist
Have the wrong people and I realize that One Bad Apple spoils the whole bunch and
At 9 of my 11 staff were bad apples
I just decided to
Clean house and II
I got rid of everybody and I did it in one city and then
I took responsibility as their leader and said he had let you guys down and I'm sorry but
This isn't going to work out
What was the problem with
They weren't clean-cut they weren't professional they didn't see what I saw
And it was a simple as
I don't care about the customer
They were hauling away the junk
Taking it to the dump and they didn't have the sense of lips
Allow the customer to have that sense of relief
Set their junk is gone
They've got their space back
Let's chat them up a little bit and make them happy
And
They weren't aligned with
My vision
How are you able to
Like how he able to run the business
Stay all the sudden
You fired your in
Fireteam
And presumably you had jobs
Ways to do then
Next day in
That was hard I went from five trucks down to
The ability to only run one at a time
And so I had my truck I have my cell phone I was the call center I did the booking the dispatch
The junk hauling I did everything
But what it taught me was
PE build a company that's all about people find the right people and treat people right so I got out from that day.
Never make
The same mistake of course I've made hiring mistakes but relatively few
I really focused on finding people that I wanted to work with
When we come back out Brian scudamore pleaded with the state of Idaho to get the number
1-800 got junk I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to Head Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone.
With clear conditions and a direct
Mophie model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
8 / NPR
Game Bridge
Which is not available in all states
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Text Honda state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape
The China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com podcast
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's the mid-1990s
Brian has
Fired all of his employees
And after a rough few months
He begins to rebuild the team
But at this point
His company is
Still a small business
Running in
Just one city
When did you decide that you know it's going to be bigger than just like a
Junk Hauling Company in Vancouver
So you know what that this point 1997 we are actually two million dollars in revenue and I joined something called
Yeo the young entrepreneurs organization
And found myself surrounded by people who had some pretty cool businesses
Tech companies in
Growing ad agencies and just stuff that seemed a little sexier than junk removal
And so I think I found myself feeling sad because I was comparing myself to others
And I didn't feel good enough
So what I ended up doing was I
Went to my parents summer Cottage that this little cottage and I
Saddled on their dock
I said okay this isn't who I am I'm an optimist
So I pulled out a pen and a sheet of paper
And I said okay what if I could just
Dream up
Possibility
What could this business look feel and act like
5 years down the road
And I said we'll be in the top 30 metros in North America even though we were only in one
We would be the FedEx of junk removal clean shiny trucks friendly uniform drivers
I just started to put these
Big hairy audacious goals down on paper that we would
Be like the McDonald's of of junk that we would you know just what Ray Kroc did where you got all these owners on board
We would do the same thing with a junk removal business
And I took Paul guy who was the
Operations manager of mine in Vancouver
And I said you're going back and forth
Toronto
Every couple of weeks
To see your
Why don't you move there why don't you take a truck
Why don't you start the first franchise
Did you even notice structure
Efrangeliz how did you figure out how that would work
I looked at other franchises I looked at Subway I looked at
Businesses and thought
What kind of royalty are they charging
What what's the business model
I got out and talked to a bunch of experts so again being a guy that doesn't learn from school
Just picked up the phone and I called people I called
And I approached a bunch of XP
Burt's and said this is what I'm thinking of doing what do you think
They gave me some
Feedback and advice on how to structure
Fees and royalties I
I brought on a franchise lawyer who still with us today
And I remember that he helped to give me a lot of the advice in the systems
He believed in us and knew that we build something
Much bigger than where it was at
About time
So you get your first franchisee in
Toronto and
How old
It was funny because I got a phone call from Paul guy so he took them I don't know a week to get to Toronto you made a few
Stops and he calls me up within the first couple of weeks
And he said
This isn't going to work here
Hello what are you talkin about Polly Sidwell
I found out that the city will Holloway
Anyting
For free
He said you can just put it out on the curb side that got special garbage collection days.
Take fridges stoves couches you name it it doesn't matter
I said Paul you've driven across
Country trust me please just try it
Until he did
Any start to get business
And he started to hear from customers
That
You know someone was doing a renovation maybe they didn't get a city permit so they didn't want to call the city to all the way the junk or maybe the junk
Was in the garage or the basement
The city workers wouldn't come collect it from anywhere but
The curbside
And Paul started to realize wow
Okay this is going to work
You get a million dollars in Revenue
In this first full calendar year
So at that point you're thinking okay we've got to expand we've got to move Beyond Vancouver and Toronto
And what was the next step was next place to go next place to go was in the United States
And just to clarify at the beginning is called the rubbish boys when did you come up with
Did you become 1-800
Paul was in my office we were working and I said
We're going to go for this franchise model and build something
Across North America
I knew the word rubbish was going to be a problem it was more of a
Canadian British term
And the other problem we had was people would either think of the company is being the rubbish boys and some people thought of us at 7
3 junk so effectively they sauce of two companies
Remember sitting down with Paul and we were
We are brainstorming and
I said
If we did a 1-800 number
Something like 1-800 Flowers something that was more descriptive
So we started brainstorming in the whole got milk campaign that was running at the time
Inspired me to
1-800 got junk
And
Are phone number at a? In it and it would ask the question got Shopkin of course I do
Then give us a call and so
And so I try to find who owned 1-800 got junk
It wasn't available it wasn't available
The phone company said they couldn't get me the number so
How to dig around
I ended up making about 60 phone calls I had people friends and family in the United States
Calling the number
It was only working in one state
And that was the state of Idaho
Kuna Idaho had this number
The Department of Transportation in Idaho own
This 1-800 got junk phone number
They didn't know it's spelled got junk
They were using this phone number
And I thought okay I need this number so I called into their office
Called up there's main switchboard asked for the phone room and I got the sky Michael
And Michael ends up
You know talking to me any
Because why do you want this number and I just said it's it's a business idea I really want it
That's why we're not really isn't it that much
It took three phone calls to him before he finally said okay
Here's the AT&T forums
Fax them over to me
The number is yours
I signed and wechat
How to deal with the way he just gave you the
Gave you the
The phone number for
I think he wanted to get rid of me I think he was sick and tired of me calling you really needed that phone
That was incredibly lucky break
It was a lucky break that you make your own luck I mean I could have given up after
Call number
Or 55 I just kept going and
I've heard so many stories of going to Colonel Sanders knocking on 183 doors and then the hundred 84th the guy goes yeah
I love the recipe
And so
He just can't give
So how did you expand into the US
So we
Expanding through franchising
We found a lawyer
Started networking for a Canadian lawyer found a great attorney in the US we created a franchise documentation
You got approved by the FTC in
I said okay
Off you go
And then we just really started to aggressively go after the US press
The big turning point for us
I said that the big media hit in the US
Was Fortune Magazine
Why did you think it was so important to get
I saw that
When we were
This little local businesses the rubbish boys
And we would get stories in the newspaper
People would repeat our stories back to us
Like wow
You dropped out of college in your building this business and
What a great thing that you're doing and you know
It's an awesome story
So we just started telling the story
So okay so you get this article and then what
Like as a result
People calling you saying hey you don't want to buy it like I want to buy a franchise
Guess we ended up getting article Fortune Magazine they saw one of our trucks in San Francisco
Adam lashinsky the writer called and said
Saw this truck
Heard about you guys
Seems like a crazy business
Casino you're building a brand
Junk removal
Who does that
And
Story came out
Hit the ground on a Thursday
And we ended up getting 506
Phone calls
From Thursday to Sunday so that we
We were flooded with
These are people who are interested in buying franchises
Yeah
M506 calls imagine listening to that and trying to write them all down and calling everyone back we were overwhelmed
So
I got on the voicemail
I said due to an overwhelming response from Fortune Magazine we are unable to call people back
If you would like to learn more about our opportunity
Please call into this conference call at this time
And what we did is we have like a hundred people show up on a conference call
And we would do a roll call
Of you know okay what city are you from in and we going to go through one by one all these different people
So everyone's like what I got all this competition I want to get in
And it drove the process quickly
And we ended up doing 53
French ideals that year
Which was just unheard of in the franchise space
And
Things to start at the hockey
Completely explode
You are to adjust from running a small business too
Pretty big company like almost overnight riding with all of a sudden you had
Always new franchise Partners in a huge
When the beginning it was
Great exciting
Things were
Building all this great momentum and we
We raced
Pretty quickly to a hundred million dollars in Revenue
What year what year did you
And so
It was exciting and in there was an energy in this momentum
But what was interesting about that time is it 2006
I realized I had my
President of my company my cool Cameron Herald
I was the best man in his wedding great friend we're still friends today
We Grew From together from 2 million to 106 million
Very short period of time yeah but what started to break
Was that
You had to add
Fire Ready Aim types at the top of the company
Yeah and and that just doesn't work
We we started to make poor decisions together
Like what you do
We would overspending in areas where we would we would take some risks and we wouldn't really think
Through with any rigor and discipline
How would affect our franchise partner
We had a truck roll out program where we said hey
Everybody needs more trucks
Get more trucks out there and we
We put it in the franchise agreement that our franchise Partners had to increase their fleets by a certain. Of time and
There's some Rebellion
I mean it and I don't blame them
It was too aggressive
And
I realized it we were making mistakes and you can't have the two add types
Topton
And I needed to find
A new leader and
Having to tell your best-friend that this is no longer going to workout is
Tough tough painful thing to go through for both of us
But we filled and moved on and and you know Cameron would tell anyone today Bryan made the right decision
So obviously I'm assuming you
Someone else to tell Romeo
Operation Saturday
I did so
One of the biggest mistakes I made was the second person I brought in as
Is it the second president
And I brought in
Annex Starbucks
Cool
And this person had
Can a president of one of the US divisions of Starbucks
And done amazing things for that
30000 employees
To report so you're thinking this person
Sister slam dunk they're going to do a great job for me
Oh yeah I'm
Jackpot
This is just unbelievable
But
We almost bankrupted the company
Wow
After 20 years of growth
We went
From
119 million in revenue is what
Weedhead about peek at that time and we drop down to the 80s
What happened
Will the recession-hit witch
Didn't help
But I don't buy for a second that that was really
CSUB
Because what really happened was
My president's leadership
In my vision
Weren't aligned
I needed an Executor who could translate my vision and say
Here's the vision let's translated into a plan here's all the steps let's make these things happen I needed somebody that believed in me
And where I can also believe in them
So I
I got that person out of the business
How close to the company to falling apart
We couldn't have been closer
I mean I I would have given us another 90 days if we continue down that path weed overspent so drastically
On big bats that didn't pay off
And Ida hunkerdown I had to lay off 52 people
I needed to elevate another team
The middle level managers up
Can I said
You know I know you might not agree with my decision
You probably think I'm crazy but I need your help and
What's the hardest. In my
Professional life
Well my middle level management team who is elevated continued to run the business
I scoured the country for
The Right leader
I interviewed 75
Potential president / cos
I said I need to find someone
Whose strength
And talents
Wood
Take all the things I'm bad at
And make them happen
And I painted this little vision describing exactly who I was looking for
I got it up to my network
And three different people totally unrelated
Said the person you describe is Eric Church
Because you've only described one person on the planet
And
I reached out Eric and I got connected
He was very happily employed he was president of a big travel tourism company
And when the magic happened
Just okay
We can see building this thing together we can see how we would
Each contribute
Strengths to the rest
And we entered this partnership and
It's been almost 6 years
And together we just
I mean we can
Bait
Discuss
And work together on the culture guy
Division guy
He's implementer the rigor
He's the team building guy and it's
I mean it's
At what point did you stabilize they'll appoint were you able to say okay
Totally passive
Would Eric Church came in
The first thing he did is he had the goals that I had put in place
He lowered them
He said listen Brian it's not that I don't believe
In you and that I don't believe in the goals
We're going to lower the bar
Because we're going to teach people
What it feels like to win again
We are going to make sure we win we are going to put the bar low enough
That there is no way in the world we're not going to win
When people start
Feel and taste that winning Feeling Again
Confidence will build
Team will come back and so he thought about it a very strategic plan for way and we made money in the first year
Fear of this new this new business
Really taking 1-800 got junk and restructuring honking country down with we made money
Cities did you guys operate in now
We are in every major Metro in
United States Canada and Australia
So you name the city where there
I talked to obviously lots of entrepreneurs
Michelle Wright and
Some of them go to the franchising route and then some of them
Decide not to do that
Why why did you
How to do that
I think the answer ties to the person I am and what motivates
I've never been a Money Motivated
I probably would have made more money in the long term
If I done a corporate model in an IPO and raise money
But what motivates me more than anything is
Taking someone who's got the American dream
Build your own business
But they don't know how
Giving them a recipe giving them the cheerleading in the support and
Team of other franchise owners who can come together
And so the franchise model to me was the
You got skin in the game this is your business
And we could build something much bigger together
Versus what we could have ever done alone
NFL schedule
Who is Europe to go back to the
18 year old Bryan
Like in that McDonald's drive-thru
And you could you just there and you like dude
I know it's going to happen
To you over the course of your life
Listen to me
Would you say that
I would say Brian
Listen to your gut
Make the right decisions that you know with
All your heart are the the decisions that need to be made
Don't be afraid to make them interested everything's going to work out and I've learned that
You have storms in life
Just like any storm
In real life
They don't last forever
Yeah
One more question for you Brian which is
What is the weirdest
Thing that you ever hauled off
I the weirdest thing I probably hauled off was I had a
Entire truck load of
Escargot shells
So some company who imported escargot went bankrupt
And I we loaded the truck and it was very light
Kissing of the shells were all there
Sky says to Migos
Come on you can fit more in than that and I said you got a full truckload so you can see the trucks full
So he came up with this idea on the customer is always right so we did it
He said
Go up into the Second Story the office
Jump into the back of your truck
Collapse all those
Shells
And set another load
So I we did it
It's kind of fun you know screaming who is your jumping out the window into the back of the truck and we did we got another load in and
We had fun he was happy Brian scudamore founder of 1-800
Got junk
How do I get last year the company and their franchise Partners made close to 8
Quarter of a billion dollars in Revenue
Calling of people John
Sometimes that truck is
In recent years
They've come across
A Bible that belong to
Did John Wayne
An old airport X-ray scanner
And an ATM machine
It still had $26,000 in cash
Inside
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about what
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Squarespace is used by millions of entrepreneurs businesses
Visit squarespace.com
Start your free trial
Africa
Build it
10% off your first purchase
Make your next move
Unique domain name
Create a beautiful website
With Squarespace
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I know for how you build that
And a story comes to us from Robin Gerber who works for a bank in New York
And she wanted to solve a problem that actually has nothing to do with
Her day job
Super frustrated looking for parking
If I'm driving if I'm a passenger in a car
It's probably one of the most annoying things about having a car and a big
City people fight with their spouses
Trying to find a parking space
When you meet why they didn't try there fast enough
So it's really a source of tension
Her dad actually come up with a kind of low-tech solution for the
The city's parking problem
Key devices system where he would put a piece of paper on his car window with a :-) if you
Who is leaving the next morning and drivers in his neighborhood began to look out for his car if they saw the :-)
Air Force One Robins
I thought to myself there should be enough for this
Robin actually
Did something she got a friend to help her do the
Decoding and then she made an app
App that allows drivers to
Share information
About parking space
We have a find a spot option in a host
The spot option so if you are looking to find a spot you could
Click that button and it would search
Search for all the spots within your vicinity
And it would show you the XX closer
So you choose the spot you want to snag you get the make and model of the car that the leaving
And then you navigate to your face
And they are actually tracking you on GPS
Do you know if the person is on time you can chat with them and each person has to say if it would
Successful or not
The course for the app to really work
Robin needed hundreds actually
Thousands of New York City drivers to download it and
Start sharing their spaces
Soap to get the word out
She made a music video
No I'm not trying to be rude but let me get that box off of you I wish we had a bad way then I let good spots
Gold weigh
Okay so that is my cousin Brad Meyer
And my whole family
Either singing it or dance in it
Even though cousin Brad pulled off his best R.Kelly
Cuz my car
The video did not exactly go viral
Robin
Pushing she put flyers on
Thousands of cars all over New York City
People chase after me when I'm handing them Flyers asking for more flyers to give her friends that
Living in neighborhood
They they loved us and
That enthusiasm is what
Keeps me
You know pushing forward Robin calls her at par car
And since you launched it last summer she's side up more than three
Thousand active users
Including of course
Her dad but he still has a Smiley Face on butt
I think we should frame it actually and put it on the wall
Let's Robin Gerber of New York City by the way she's hoping to
Spread the idea.
Two cities across
The country
Find out more about her a parked car
Add to our Facebook page and of course if you have a story about something
You are building
Please tell us about it go to build
. NPR
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more about who
Who was on it
Go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also follow us on
Twitter that sat
How I built this and you can write to us
@h IBT
Npr.org
Is the Sweet By Casey Herman with music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva crab sanaz meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Claire Breen
I'm Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Heights Rachel Martin NPR news
Is anal
We're doing something new
And we want you to be part of it it's called up first it's the Morning News podcast from NPR
It's a way for you in about 10 minutes
To get up to speed on the news of any given day
The most important stories
The biggest ideas
Is the stuff you need to know as you go through your day
Up first
You can get it at NPR one or anywhere you listen to
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email to
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor