Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com to find your
Perfect pear
Well they take over and push everybody out
In February of 1984 IBM introduces their own portable into the
Our order stopped because before it actually was introduced they were showing it to
The dealers and customers in they just stopped arguing ours that was that was a very very life for us
We have his Factory running full speed and no place to go
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movement
Canyon personal computer startup Compaq to go on the biggest computer company in
In the world and one
If you have a PC at home or at work and
Some software like
Word or TurboTax
It doesn't really matter if you have a Dell or an HP or Toshiba because if it's a PC it will
PC software that makes perfect sense right
Believe it or not in the 1980s in the early days of personal computers
That is not how it works
If your computer was say in IBM
Well you needed software written for and IBM
And IBM was the biggest player by far
Some people thought that IBM would eventually Crush all the competition and become the only piece
All that changed when Rod Canyon started Compaq
Wasn't your typical Restless entrepreneurial guy infected he had a good and stable job at 10
Texas Instruments as an electrical engineer and he was pretty happy there
One day in 1981 is managers assigned him to work on a new project and it was something
Believe would not work
Until he started to get frustrated
Basically was being told to go spend the next two years of my life being my head against the wall
And end up in failure
So at that moment
Rod started to talk to to close colleagues at Texas Instruments Jim Harris and Bill mirto and
Basically said maybe we should leave
We met
And talked about how we're going to go start a company
And a lot of startup companies in California and Silicon Valley
One of the first things we realize is G these guys are having fun they're making a ton of money in
Running smart and we are they just
They're just out doing it themselves
There's also this awareness that something really big is going on in that personal computer Market when I be
Diameter the market in August of 1981
We realized that
That market
It was going to explode
And then what happened is fall comdex came along
We went out to the conference and saw all of the companies and all of the things going on in twitch
That did it we went back to Houston and talked about
We're going to miss this if we don't get going so
Jim Harrison III turn in a resignation
Right away
Amaretto
Waited because
His wife was about to deliver
Their first child
And you had a family to write
How many kids did you have
Were you nervous at all about just quitting without any income coming in I mean
Were you worried at all about doing that
You know I don't remember being worried about it
The three of us none of us had any
Money to invest so what we did was we saved up
Money and the idea was
We'll give ourselves a runway length
The six months
Come up with an idea and go get funding
You know I think
This was an adventure
Let's go see what we can do
So what did the three of you serve land on the idea that that
Eventually turned into combat
Well the the idea came to me
Actually one morning
It was strange how you remember those
Pivotal point in your life but
I was thinking about the idea for a portable computer there were
A number of them that existed at the time
Probably
Just guess
15 or 20
Well most people
Remember the Osborn
It was made out of
Cheap molding and sort of
Strung together
It had a 5 inch diameter screen
It had two floppies but you could have mediately see some ways to make it a lot better in a week
We decided we could do a 9 inch screen in about the same size box
Well that seems small
Turns out it's about the same size is
What the
Original iPad screen is
And we could make it rugged so that when you carried it it was
Not damaged
But
Not worth really spending the time on unless we could
Get some software that already existed
Cuz
I had learned that the key software like spreadsheets and word processors in and others
Every different brand of computer had to have its own version of the popular software program
So I said well
What if we could make
This great portable run software that already exists
I knew that the IBM PC
Was relatively unprotected it would be a
A challenge but it could be reverse-engineered
Legally
And we could make our computer
Run the same software
And that was the idea that the send a chill down my spine wow
What's wrong with this idea there's there's got to be something wrong with it it's too good to be just
Hanging around here
At what point did you say okay we have an idea let's go look for money
So I called up Jim Harris and then later got bilmar to involve and we
Thought about it talked about it and decided you know that that would be a great product if we can do that
Let's put together the business plan and so that was the next thing we did I mean
It was very quick from the 9th of January
To when the idea came up to the 22nd of January when we met with a venture cap
We basically
Put together I am a very short for page business plan and prepare to meet and discuss
And what did they say when they die
Well
They were coming into town for another meeting and we
But this business plan in front of a man
Begin to describe it
And
Then they started
Talking to each other either one of them said
Yeah I had this idea you know like three months ago
And I said well
If you think it's such a good idea why aren't you more excited about it and I said well
Look
We like the idea we like you guys
But we're new in this
Industry
So what you need to do is we need to send you out to Silicon Valley and go meet with Kleiner Perkins
Enough
They all the best then we will
So we
We basically flew out to
To Silicon Valley and we went in to meet with Jon Dore
And we spent
A good morning probably 3 or 4 hours
Being
Questions
And
Turn off
About a week later
We got a call that they were willing to invest in
So
It was a go
Okay so it's 1982 I guess and and you've gotten your investors and in what
Did you get to work building a prototype
Well first thing we do is
Begin hiring people
The three of us
We're sort of
The head of each area but we need
Engineers mainly to go figure out how to reverse engineer in hell
Designer things how so we hire three engineers
And importantly they basically had to build something
Pretty similar to an IBM PC
Except pretty similar didn't cut it and you had to be
Exactly the same in order to run the software
From an internal temp
So they are
They came to Workforce right away
And again
First reverse engineering a product
And then designing our own
But were you convinced that you guys were going to succeed
You know it never crossed my mind that we wouldn't
Succeed and as I look back now I think
Well that was such a long shot
You know our expectations were very low
What is exceed mean if it didn't mean become an industry leader it didn't even mean become one of the leading cup
Is it Matt build a company that doesn't go out of business
That has a product
That solves a real need
And you don't lose money on it
We felt like we know how to do that
How long does it take
For you from that point in
I guess the first story has early part of
Nice 82
Until you had a working prototype
So we
Start the company February 16th
And from March until
Early June
We had our first prototype ready
The deadline was determined by the national computer conference
What's just happened to be held in Houston that you're the only time I think it was over in Houston
The show 2
Potential dealers
Central Computer store owners who would sell it
Tube magazine writers who would write about it when it came out in a to get feedback
And others basically to find out
What people thought about this product
So you come up with this prototype
And at that point
Where are you even Manufacturing
These these computers
We built
Factory
Inside a leased building
The north Houston
We heard manufacturing people Vape
Put up reproduction Lionheart people trying them on how to build it and
Began to build
The product
And we had a plan
That basically allowed us to build
Probably I'm going to say 20 25000
Computers
By the end of 83 we didn't begin actually turning out
Finished units until January of 83
Just to be clear
Portable computer in 1983
You're talking about a
A machine that way
28 lb
This is not even hand luggage on an airplane
Well we did use it as hand luggage but there was some skepticism about that
Nelly that you had to plug in Ethernet
People began to call them
Transportable computers which is more accurate
It was also very rugged
One of our key engineering Talent
What was the building
So that it
When you dropped it
Survive
And of course your portable would run any software
Written for the
And another competition did that right
That's right
And basically
Layton 82 as we had our first prototype
Bill murto and then I joining because there were a lot of computer stores around the country
We would go out and make an appointment and go in and and show
The computer store owner
Our product
And
Show them the computer they like the way it looked and when we
Show them how it works it was very nice
Screen was nice
But when we told him okay just pick a
Any of the IBM
Software
Off-the-shelf tennis shrink wrap box
And put it in the computer and see if it runs and when they did that and it ran
Their eyes
Lit up
They got excited I thought about it a minute and they wanted to order some right there
Let me say something like okay I need five of these next week or I've got it I'll give you an order for 25 if you can ship them
In the next month
Bill and I got back to Houston and compare notes
It was like women every one of these dealer said the same thing
What we just stumbled onto is this
Pent-up demand
For portable version of the IBM PC
It seems solid but we've never thought of our product that way
This is a portable computer if it's a niche
And you have software because it runs all the IBM software
But if you just step back and turn that over and say
Everybody out there has an IBM PC and they're off
And what they need every one of them needs one more one or more of is
A portable version of it
And we happen to have that product
People were wanting to take
Leasing home for the weekend or even overnight 2
To finish their work they want to take them out to customers to show them
Their work and so it was a much bigger
Market than anybody anticipated wants
We had all the ingredients together
Weren't weren't you worried in 1982 when you are going to dealers and showing them your product that
And it's saying hey you know this is basically
This could do everything and IBM could do
Acceptance portal where you guys worried that IBM would come after you
No because we hadn't broken any laws
Yeah we did reverse-engineer the wrong following
Advice from
Top notch
Intellectual property lawyer so we were very careful around that
The product was not protected by patents and any other way they unfollowed more or less
The General Industry Direction and so
Building a computer that was
Similar or close to it was not a problem at all the fact that we
Took the time to figure out exactly how there's made the software work
And made ours do the same thing it was not illegal
It sounds like you guys really want this in a stealth way that IBM probably didn't even
Care about you thought you were just probably just above a flyspeck of a company
That was making this product
And when you launched it in 1983
I don't even even know who you were
Oh no no they had no idea nor did they care I mean even after we began to the store to get some positive
Live results and getting into stores remember we were portable they didn't have a portal so initial
Play it was very easy for them to ignore us because we were truly
Fly in that first year 1983
How did the company do we sold 111 billion dollars worth of Compaq computers
Wow
Expanding like crazy
Beginning of that year you just had
A few hundred maybe like less than a hundred people working
We had about
About a hundred people at the end of the fur
That's about right and about 600 by the end of 83
So you can imagine
How much hiring we were doing
And expanding and
Now this was not a one thing at a time this is a multitasking
Bringing on very competent people in every area so they could
Here's what needs to be done and go get it
How how much were you selling that
First portable computer for
It was it listed for 2995 for a single floppy
Unbelievable
And who your customers was it businesses was it individuals
It was mostly businesses
But
Surprising number of individuals could see the value in it
And if their company wasn't buying it for them then they would do
They would buy it for themselves
3000 bucks for this computer in
Tens of thousands
IBM is starting to notice
Oh absolutely
Absolutely
Hey
You know in February of 1984
IBM introduces their own portable into the market now
I order stopped because before it actually was introduced
They were showing it to dealers and customers head
They just stopped ordering Arce
What's the song that if IBM Market they take over and push everybody out
We have the factory running full speed
And no place to go
That was that was a
Very
Very life-threatening
So you guys are freaking out
We're freaking out the industry speaking out it's like they're girls compact you know they're there
They had a good run but it's over when we come
I'm back at ride Canyon made sure that it wasn't yet over stay with us
How I built this
NPR
Hey thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this hiscox
Hiscox
What's the business insurance expert to understand
Each business is
Is as unique as a
Fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent resolution
Every business has very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase of policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Harrah's
83 was a really good first year of sales for Rock Canyon and compact
But to put it in perspective compact sold about 53,000 computers
IBM
700 in
50000 computers
And so in 1984 when IBM decided to come
Pete with combat
Head to Head
Everyone knew it was a major threat
So tried call together the management team
For an emergency meeting
You know what do we think we ought to do well the manufacturing of people said
We got a lot of temporary people
We were hiring so fast
They came out as temporary is initially in
And we can lay all them off immediately and we can really cut back production
Got docker cost
And it was it was a I have to say a very dire
Down to the meeting everybody was like you know it's all over
Took all that in and added it all up and I realized
You know if we're going to come out of this
With a happy ending
There's only one way that's going to occur and that is
Let's assume for a minute that IBM's product is not better than ours
That maybe it's a limited Supply and the Dealer's once they see it
Begin to order our product again
We need to have product available to fill those orders
So here's what we're going to do we're going to keep building these things we're going to store them and wait for the artist
To come
But the orders never come yeah we're in deep trouble but you know what we're in deep trouble anyway if they order
That was the plan
I'm not sure everybody was
I'm bored with it but that's what we went off and did
Weird storing these things in the in the trailers
Tractor trailers 18 wheelers back and parking them in our garage
Parking lot when that filled up
Borrowed space and Friends parking lots around the
The town and buy
Mid
February we had about 20 of these trailers full of computer sitting around you
So what happened how did you survive that
Well
What happened is IBM introduces the product
The kick the tires
It's announced that it is in limited supply for a while
It was not a better probably want to buy a product they just wasn't better
And so just as we had hoped almost there
Best possible situation is the orders came in and we had the computer
To feel them it's like they had been holding them back and so not only were they arguing isn't normal right they were sending all the orders that they
I have been holding
Everything fell into place
Just at the right time and then we took advantage of it
So what explains
What explains the fact that they didn't
Fresh you I mean it it sounds to me like it was one of two things it was either
Total luck
Or it was that the IBM portable computer just wasn't that good or maybe both
Well anyway you look at it it was luck
I mean
It was it was a lot of luck involved but what happened is
We have had a year
To build great relationships
With the dealers the dealers actually liked having
Somebody other than IBM
Because I be almost the yuan on the 500 pound gorilla
In any case we continue to sell like crazy and outsold I've been portable throughout the year I think by the end of the year we
Route selling
Seven or eight to 184
By the end of 84
And
We tripled
To 329 million in our second year
So by your second year you've tripled
Sales
What was the first time you remember
Compact becoming part of lyca of the mainstream conversation in america
Well it depends on how big the mainstream is I think by the end of 83
Everybody in the industry knew about Compact and we'll sort of
Marveling at what was going on here
Now this idea that
People can use all the same for referrals
All the same things that were designed and built to run in the IBM PC with it was software or Hardware would work on our computer
IBM may be underestimated as they didn't really study what it made our products success
They could have easily put us out of this
Did they come out with a real comprable
The product
Yeah and it wasn't once you guys show that
You could build an IBM clone
A lot of other companies
Realize it was possible to do the same thing right
And the fact that we took off and set sales records main everybody else
Did including by the way the big guys h p t i
Violate followed suit but by then we had
Really establish ourselves
In the market in
You know the thing that took us
From 600 million and 80
6 to 1.2 billion in sales in 87
We came out with our own desktop which was
Essentially three times faster than IBM's desktop for about the same price and begin to establish
I'm selfish not only the portable company
But also the high-performance company
The PS2 in 1987
So it could not be cloned right
Yeah
That's right
That was an attempt to take this thing that has gotten out of control mainly due to Compaq
And bring it back under IBM's control
Comes out with their
New architecture and claims that this is the way to go
That that all architecture has run its course
It's going to run out of gas very soon and so
You don't want to follow it to the end you want to get on this new horse
And IBM has it
And so let's go
And
That's what IBM
Marketing
Strategy got them in trouble
Because
This thing not only didn't run all the softer it didn't run any of the software
IBM's new computer did not run IBM's own software
It didn't
Now they came out with new IBM software
So if you wanted to buy this new product
Youku
Buy all new peripherals and all new software
And they would claim that it would help
Performing ething else in the market
Set the time the right and you're saying that
Emily companies many companies already had
PCS and software IBM was saying
Buy the Snoopy s2o and you're also going to have to invest in new software
You make it sound crazy to them it was normal that's the way the industry had always worked and then
They still hadn't bought into this end up
Standard
People
Believing that
An understanding that it was important to be able to run your old software on a new computer
It never happened before
Compact pioneer.
And then they wanted to get rid of it as quick as they could
Was there a moment where you were worried that that actually would succeed
Oh yeah
No they never questioned it
They had a
Good chance to
Succeed now what kept us going and what
I guess gave us
Confidence that we had a pretty good chance was
We outperformed to IBM's best products
Every step of the way
Until there was
It also significant part of the industry that looked at the IBM's claims
Lionel magazine
Aren't afraid to write
Compaq outperformed cibm by
In spite of it being a BM
We're holding onto a pretty
Solid position in the market
Because
Ours was always higher-performing
It seems like at any juncture
In your first several years
IBM have they just done
Something a little bit smarter
Strategically
Could have crushed you
There's no doubt IBM could have crushed us a number of different ways
And at that point in time
I can ride so it's it's a five years from the time you launch to to the time you're doing a billion dollars in Revenue
That's right
How to change your life your own personal life changes all of a sudden you like
I'm assuming you're you become, rich guy
Yeah
It'll certainly compared to where I had been I was rich but then again we
We knew that that was a fragile part of it
I did get a divorce in 1980
I know it was
Sad part of
Of what happens in the
And a terrible
I'm sure it has something to do with the stress associated with
All the work
The time I spent at work
So in 1987
Going through divorce
A simple divorce
Hard
IBM comes out with his new computer
Designed it to basically
Put you guys out of business
How did you deal with cope with all that happening
Looking back on it I would say it's probably denial
That's pretty effective tools not letting things
Impact you as much as they might end
Other situations is something
You have to do there I'll be done
I felt like I was
Learning as I went and I was
Doing a good job
Louis personal turmoil
If you want to throw up another layer on top of that
RadioShack tried to buy us in late 86 in early 87
So that was going on
Same time all this was happening
So you were just
It says your personal life you were just kind of
You compartmentalize that you were you just had to
Put that in a box and focus on the stuff and not let that
Depress you
Yeah
No
I've got three kids
And they're getting to be
Teenagers in
There's a little league and there's all of that and I'm trying very hard to get away at the right time you'll see a school play
That's where most of the stress came from trying to do it all
If you could just cut off part of it and say I'm not going to worry about that it would be one thing
But
Trying to do it all in and not drop any balls that was pretty stressed
Where you going home
Eating like takeout Chinese food I mean
Crashing usually yeah I know I
See pictures now
Of media
During a fast food in a McDonald's bag or a Wendy's bag
How you just ate when you could that was sort of secondary
Getting everybody
You taking care of getting the meetings done getting
Decisions made
Yeah you can look at my role as making decision
Yeah I was making all the decisions but all of the key once I had to be involved in
And they're always a lot
I guess about
Like what 10 years after you guys lunch
Compaq
You
Drafted to the board of directors
Did they fire you
Almost exactly 10 years later in the front
Why what was going on
Well
There's several levels of
Looking at the Dynamics there that on the surface it's a matter of disagreement over how fast
Move into the lower-cost arena
Like-like lower-cost PC
Yes
The chairman of the company Ben Rosen
Thought we ought to move very quickly and so quickly that went back we got to go buy a product from
The Taiwanese or Japanese or Korean
Supplier
And my argument was look
It's Not What It Seems
We can get the market as fast
Is anybody
With our own design and I think it's a board meeting
The board decided to replace me with the number two guy with every fiber
Hot headed
How'd you get that news
Well we had a board meeting were been proposed
That idea and I left the room and I
Deliberated it
For quite a while and then made the
Decision to make the change
But it was clear that was the direction they were going on I knew that's what it was going to be
I was also somewhat burnout and I was
Strange mindset
Yeah I kind of wanted to get out of that
That pressure it was
It took me a while to really look back and understand that I was
A big part of the problem of why it ended up going down that path and I and I regret that
But it is what happened and
I guess under the stress I was under and kind of
Gotten into this Frame of Mind where I need to get away
The
Disagreement over the low cost
Speed to Market
Was just the Catalyst that
Allowed it to happen
Almost
Guided it to the point where I
It's going to be far
So when you were at me this is the company that you found it
Who built
Yes
And then you were
Removed from the
I think a lot of people hearing that would say God that sounds like ocean and just
Cuz it's your idea
You created it was your sweat
And then
Who is taken away from you
Brazil
From your perspective
That was fine you you weren't kind of your time
Was was over there
Nose be clear
Where are you
Fortune 500
Corporation
In a world leader in a big industry
And just because you started the company doesn't give you any right to continue to run the cup
Are the dates to be run by somebody that can make
Good decisions and can manage
That complex in operation
Which I think I was doing
Okay or maybe even
Very well up to that point in time
So that's
I don't see that as the reason
That I needed to leave I think it had more to do with
My friend of mine and sort of a burned-out
Situation
You were in your mid-forties at that point so so pretty
Pretty young guy
Accomplished a lot
Did you walk out of the company with a vino financially secure for you except for life at that point
Yes absolutely
No course
Continue my life actually the the home life
Became a much less stressful and
Then I got involved in investing in and some startups in early-stage companies and try to help them succeed
Not all of them dead
But then
Probably evolved to where I really just like helping entrepreneurs start their company in
Try to help them avoid a lot of mistakes
Do companies make
Compact was such a Powerhouse in the eighties a Fortune 500 company
Does billion dollars in Revenue with a
In 5 years
And then you think about all of the companies that
That it was associated with her that we competed again
Do you know
Apple IBM
Dell
Microsoft
Texas instrument
All of those companies still exist
And compact
Doesn't
Existing Wireless folded into 8
Being a brand is no longer
Here
In anyway is that a cautionary tale for some of these powerhouses we see today like
Snapchat or Uber
Or Facebook I can't even imagine not exist
You know it really is that's certainly something I
Didn't Envision when I left I guess I just wasn't thinking that far down the road
Yeah of course you never know the future
The decision to merge with HP was a financial decision
But the end result of the way it happened is it compact no longer exists and that is sad because
It's got such a great
History and played such a key role in actually forming the way the world works today
And yet
Most people you run into on the street
I've never heard of
Compact
Crazy in it
It is crazy yes it's sad but
It's also life you know that's that's a
At least we started out to build a company that would last
And I think that's the case with ain't you don't feel like it
Dell or Microsoft or Apple
The leaders of those companies maintain enough control
To make sure that it never
Got into the hands of somebody to look at it
Purely from a financial
Standpoint
If I had been there
If I'd been leaving the company
We would never have sold
We would have
Figured out a way to
Solve the problem
How much of your of your success at compact was
Because of
Just your hard work and and and smarts and the hard work of Jim and Bill or
And how much would a wizard lock
If you would ask me that in
The 80s
Play the ladies
I would probably have said it was
90%
Intelligence
And insight and work
And 10% luck
But to tell you how
Perspective changes with time I would say today it was
It's the other way around
We did a lot of good things we came up with a good idea
But if you look back at any of the things that could have gone wrong
And what if
Either slows down or stopped us
I mean there's a
Endless list of those
So the fact that
Yeah okay we dealt with those issues as they came along but the fact that there was a successful path even available
Is pretty pretty doggone lucky you found it
Compaq computers with bill murto and Jim Harris in 1982 Rod still lives in Houston
Where he mainly invests in other people startups
Tell me the story of compact David and Goliath struggle against IBM was the subject of a very
Cool documentary
It's called silicon Cowboys what kind of computer do you use today
Pair an iPad Pro
IPhone you started the PC Revolution
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about what
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace is used by millions of entrepreneurs businesses
Visit squarespace.com to start your free trial and use offer code build it
10% off your first purchase
Make your next move
Get your unique domain and create a b
Beautiful website
Squarespace
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
Capital share a wall with your neighbor
He'll Melanie colon story
I just resume
I was sleeping and all of a sudden I heard this huge pounding on the other
Side of the wall and what was going on is my neighbor was watching some sort of Thriller movie
The base was literally shaking my bed I have been there Melanie anyway
Imagine Melanie first try to talk directly
To them one time I went to my neighbor's door I knew they were in there I could hear them talking but they wouldn't answer their door
Melanie and her husband Louis tried everything
Stomping your foot on the ground
Ask her friends in the apartment industry is there anything that we can use to help us with this and
There is absolutely nothing
And so we thought Abby neighbor to neighbor notification tool where neighbors get notified each other
Completely anonymously and confidentially about a disturbance from the neighbor into finally about a year-and-a-half ago
Melanie and Lewis hired a team to start developing an app which they named
App that as an apartment app and search that works the property management agrees to use the app
Send over the blueprint of the building
And then when neighbors have issues they can log onto their app
Anonymously contact the actual unit they're having an issue with Joe has a name
A bird that is playing their music too loud upstairs he can select that square
Choose a preset notification so this one would be betting for a please turn down your music
So he can feel like that and then send it to the neighbor upstairs and then that neighbor is able to respond with
Resolved or sorry not me property manager can also see if the neighbor has responded or
If an intervention is required
Donnie Lewis beta tested in a big apartment complex in Missoula Montana with a hundred units
It went really well everyone is really excited about all the tools that were available
And how easy it made communication with staff and residents
And last November Melanie quit her job as a nurse to work full-time on app that there's definitely been time
Times where we thought you know what we are literally putting all of our money into this and how easy would it be
To go back to our day jobs but at the same time it causes so much stewing and us.
That we can't even stand the thought of it and we get right back to work
That's Melanie Kalonji founded app
App with her husband Louis
The partnering with 32 apartment buildings in the Denver area where they live plus buildings in Missoula and Chicago
I will start using ACT up this summer
They're hoping to Branch out to student housing and even hotels
If you want to learn more about abject head to our Facebook page just search how I built this
On Facebook and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. NPR. Org we love hearing from you
And thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or listen to
Two previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
You can also write to us that's HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send us a tweet it's at
How I built this
It was produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant
Sanaz meshkinpour Claire Breen
Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week