Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com
Really quick before we start just wanted to share some really
Exciting news with you we are taking
How I built this
Live
To Chicago
On Wednesday July 18th
I'll be interviewing live on stage
Peter Rahal the founder of
RX bars
Event sponsored by American Express and get your tickets
Go to NPR
Presence. Org
And hope to see you in Chicago
And one more thing
It seems like you can walk into any store these days
And choose from
Dozens of bottles of
Artisanal water or
Juices
But before any of that
Seth Goldman was trying to come
Convince the beverage industry that yes
People will buy a bottle drink
That is not loaded with sugar
And as you will hear it
Took a lot of convincing
The story first ran last January
But it's worth
Working again
Hope you enjoy it
2003 we had a delivery of glass that was
Salty and so we ended up with some
Product in the marketplace that had broken glass inside the bottle on Factor two different Whole Food stores
And Whole Foods has a rule three-strikes-and-you're-out we
No we can't afford as a business to lose my largest customer so we voluntarily withdrew all product on the market
Every store
How much did I cost you totally stopped
Our sales it was just painful
Ramen PR
How I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movements
The story of how Seth Goldman and Barry nalebuff took honesty from a kitchen
Sync in Suburban Maryland to the shelves of virtually every grocery
Comerica
So the year is 90
Is living in Bethesda Maryland with his wife
Three young
Kids East
To he just graduated from the Yale School of
Management
Tempest great job at
Investment firm
He's he's got an itch
He feels like he wants to start something
Keeps nagging
Daya
After day
After today
Thinking about different ideas maybe a web-based
System that would raise money for Publix
Schools by tab
Tapping into alumni Networks
He came up with the idea to simplify diagnostic
Urinary tract infections
They were a bunch of other ideas that would pop into his head but nothing really
Got him excited
Until 1 afternoon
When he finished a long run and walk
Into a convenience store
Hot and sweaty and I went to a beverage cooler and I said there's nothing here
Nothing seemed to be like
And it was all a hundred calories per 8 ounces and the difference was Visser no Fizz color
Different names different bottles they were almost
Uniform
This profile which was you
647 teaspoons
4/8 Oz
Or not
Why is anyone making a tree
1 or 2 to 6
A little bit
Just
That's sweet
Did you go from that
Attitude
Thinking about starting a Tea Company
So when I
Felt that Thursday I reached out to my professor
And when I hit Ferry Nova when I've been a student
We had a case study of the beverage industry and we had agreed there was a
There was that space
A Sweet Escape
So I reached out to Barry I said I think I'm ready to do something about this I Iran no not at
Probably not a beverage industry EX
No knowledge of that and that was where
Having zero knowledge of the beverage industry in the beginning was actually competitive
Because we went in without any the assumption
I'm one of the things that happened
Literally
The same amount that I went for that run in in New York City
Was that
An investment my dad had made it 1977
And So It Goes
18 years ago
At the time
Came to fruition
I was presented with a check for $50,000
And
That was kind of the risk Capital enough for me to say okay well
I'm going to put this
This is
If we lose this we lose it but this is what I'll bet at the beginning I mean you were thinking
I'm Goin In
A job but
I mean you were still young enough where you could always like go back in the finance
That's right so you have a $50,000 check
And then and it was very able to put in a little bit of seed money. Barry had been on the board of a company that goes public
Because he kept his date
As a professor professor Yale
What was funny was that before I went to submit my resignation
The Cowbird I kind of called Barry for one last boost of confidence I said I'm going to go in there you know you just had a third son but I'm going to
Step down
And this is long pause he says
I bet if you went
DeKalb
To go on a sabbatical I bet you they let you do that
I knew I had to
Take the plunge you couldn't get investors to invest or employees or buyers to commit without you knowing me big commit
Do a quick I check temperature
Ura
Father of three kids with
What's a good job at Calvert Investments
And you tell your wife you're going to quit to start a
Tea Company
Which is Nathan for you know nothing about
And nothing about that terrified you nothing about that terrified her yeah I think
It was
I believe in
Myself probably a little bit of hubris right like I think I can do this even though I don't know anything about it
But
I am ready to try
So you quit and then basically you and Barry what did you start to do like how did you start
Start to get what did you start to raise money was that your dad was saying he was so the first thing we did was I I did write up
Business plan B Sales people really
Put together PowerPoint
They don't write Business Without a 20-page business plan
Mostly show the thinking behind the business I think every every potential investor wants.
There's actually some thought here about
Where this goes
I would become some
I managed to secure an appointment with Whole Foods
That early
Even even before you had a Prado that was lucky because the the marketing director at Whole Foods or just at that time a cup Fresh Beat
Whole Foods
The Mid-Atlantic
He was a graduate of Vehicle Management
So he helped me get an appointment with the buyer
X1 pause here
Versailles because
Tomorrow I have read about you every time I look in the midst of all this happening at Whole Foods and and all that excitement
Your son Ellie got
Reset
Well it was the ultimate test in compartmentalizing because literally the day before the whole food
Our first presentation
That's probably the most important day of the company's history
Freeware word
Identity
And Barry and I are in the kitchen and we've got
End
Bowls that we're bringing the tea and it was not an official-looking lab
The kitchen full of all these things my wife walks in with our our middle son
And she's got this Ashen look on her face and and I
I don't know she's so upset
Maybe kitchen such a mess on a
We'll clean this up
Angie's List
We just came back from the doctor and Ellie are middle son had a coarctation
I need major surgery within the month
And so
Pretty heavy news to get
How old was he
Intense
And
Probably if that it happened a few weeks
Early I probably went
Because
Whether the health insurance benefits or just the risk
Level
Could do that but I
Are you taking the plans I knew
You can you can bet that when I was at the Whole Foods meeting I was
Selling with great intensity of it needed to succeed
And then
While Elie was in the hospital
Can I stay with him
That whole week
But I'll go down it so after midnight we had someone working on
Formulas
Glenn said he would come in and meet me in the
Lobby of children
Hospital
Still together
Sleep by Ellie's bed
And I think
It's it's
Part of the experience is part of the journey and and I'm so
Thankful and
To have Ellie still with us and in such a delight in such a
Wonderful presents
You know and
For me and and Ferb
Thinking about
You lie
Pitching
This product
Hino at Whole Foods in the midst of all this
Do you like to do
Bring them samples
It's like the Samsung made in your kitchen
Put them in in in
Like some random bottles or some
We we got an empty snap
What was really funny
Is that Barry had sent over some Services when they in the mail
And when I met with the buyer and I
We poured out
Samples from the thermostat of my empty Snapple bottle
Honesty
I will look this sounds interesting will give it a try I will take 15000 bottles which of course was both terrifying and
How did you make that much
That was the other scary parts so we got this and then next thing we did is
Basically went up and down the East Coast
Looking
At bottling plant
We went to beer plant soda plants apple juice plants
So we ended up at a plant in
I'm Buffalo New York that was making apple juice with a little down on his luck
And so
We brought in these mesh bag
Large mesh bags
Better actually clean a pool like oh yeah yeah
And so that was what we use boiling water and every once in awhile the bag Woodbridge
Types wood
It was it was not pretty
How did you know the tea was
I mean that's like
Well that was that was so funny you know when I talked to Barry
He is very good at making things sound simple.
You take a teabag you knocked out of water if you multiply 2 * 15000
Theoretically that works what we found is that when you in a special the beginning to infusion
Yeah the bag breaks when you really got a problem so we just had to
Keep iterating
It was a very
Makeshift
Operation
What's up once you had all the bottles had I mean headed
Like this do well right away
So what happened was in arms we went to the shop nobody knew what it was
And so
All that for some of this is 1998 now
All we did was
Like our marketing effort was me and two interns
Giving out samples
Whole Foods
And
We gave out more samples and resole
But by the end of that summer we were the best selling tea in the 17
Fresh Fields Whole Foods
The Mid-Atlantic
Wow and so what was
Then happening was that the consumers were starting to a
Witcher 3
And it was so different and end so what was nice is we have most which
Hilton brands
Making the cereal category of one's been out of Raisin brands on sale tomorrow go by post or whatever.
Do you switch back and forth but with honesty
It's not there you don't go back and buy
Snapple or Arizona because it
The taste of soda
Yeah and so when we got somebody and then
We were clearly not for everybody
They they were very loyal
What was like what was the thing that made
Honesty different from
Like everything else
That was in the market
So true things first I'll just much less sweet than ever
But the other thing in the reason the name Honesty made sense
Is because what we learned is most of the bottle T the us at the time and still today
Is not brewed with fruity it's
If a powder or concentrate it Bears a relationship to the TV like
Fish fillet relationship to the fish
But aren't t
Bring in the TV
To the plant then we Brew them there
I'm in soup
Once you were in
Pretty quickly after you launch it mean
Seems like
You are sadly the oppression of the average person
So it was just a sweet was a Stark
And so
But we proved the concept
Yeah and so then we're able to go back and say we proved the concept
Now it's time to expand so we got more investment
Money raised and then we went to the other buyers and buyers for the
For the west coast and we went to buy us from other stores you know
Mom's my Organic Market here in
Mid-Atlantic was one of our earliest accounts and they
It was working there and they started to it to bring it to their other stores
So you're a mean
You know it's
Give me you're making a lots of
You're growing what were the challenges
Hello there so many cuz it was still
Will Frisco cash is always a challenge we weren't we were growing quickly but
We were spending money to do it we will head salespeople
We were doing marketing
And then just probably getting the
T2
Stores right to the stores and any we were still getting rejected by all these.
Distributor self Distributors are there The Gatekeepers they decide where your drinks go because this is unlike
Uno Attack
Company
No matter how good our product is
We can ship it through the mail
Beverages are high turnover products
And so as soon as the Shelf empties of beverages
Something
Texas place
And so you need a distributor to be there
How to build
Pinkie Pie shelf space
A protected and so
What happened was we were going to all the distributors
Snapple in Arizona
And they were saying when they returned our calls they would just say it's not sweet enough
They were expensive wow that's not what were used to
Which of course it wasn't
What they were where they were not
Effective as they
They were tasting it for their own power
They weren't
Thinking that's
There's a whole population out there
That's your has a
Did you amine went when you pitch it to investors who invested in
I mean
Were they saying oh this is awesome I can't wait to jump in or was it just said
We're just saying
Did you get 11 knows we got a ton of nose
The main reason we got so many nose is this was run now inserted 1999-2000 this winter in the hold. Combo
Yeah and we were very old economy
And so are you know people would much rather throw millions of dollars
Something.com
Then
Put a few maybe 10 or $20,000 into a
A beverage company
Acuity versus come in and say you know you should follow or bison
What am I supposed to do every everything in
Fancy message from Boston they said you know well you know you could
You should be an energy drink cuz that's really growing
Ba.com
You know if you made the product cheaper you can make better margins on it
I don't sound like you're interested in the opportunity accept everything that we do
But we also need it to really succeed in the long-term we had to be different than all the other big companies
And if we
To create a sweet tea there are tons of companies already doing
But when you were in those early days
Taste grader
Maybe they're right
Well there's no question that would have led to
But it would have
Diluted but we were built
This was about building something
We could always believe in that we would
That would be meaningfully different of that to take people in a different direction you have to
Disrupt where they're going
Seth Coleman
In the moment when we come back so that explains how honest he became an actual political issue in the 2008
Presidential campaign
I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
We are
Support for this podcast on the following message come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Located near DC
And home to 8900 technology companies and 144,000 technology jobs
Details at Fairfax County Eda
Support also comes from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world that's 300 cities were many people do the same thing
You do that's 300 cities where people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones who know of
About that one place
And 300 cities where people miss someone and one of Delta's other 299 cities
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people together
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first place
Delta
Keep climbing
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
By offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
It's how I built this from NPR
Harrah's
Early 2000s
Honesty and become one of the highest
Selling beverages
Whole Foods
Things were going pretty well
It was a hit
At the time the company had its own bottling
Are Pittsburgh
And something happen there
They could have
Completely destroyed the company 2003
We had a delivery of glass that was
Salting
And on their lot of blisters in the
Glass water leak
And so
We ran it
The production line
Entered with languages that if it ever sees a defect in the bottle it's supposed to
Kick it out there
Reject the bottle
Madeline didn't do that
And so we ended up with some
Product in the marketplace that
Had broken glass
What's inside the bottle
Contact with two different Whole Food stores
And Whole Foods has a rule three-strikes-and-you're-out
Fortunately no one got hurt or injured but
We did have
Bottles with p
No we can't afford as a business
Toulouse
Biological
So we voluntarily withdrew all product
Every store
How much did I well we were doing about
3 million for $90 in sales in
Totally stopped
Our sale so we lost several months
$700,000
But huge
Is momentum stop or who you're trying to build you got your salespeople at trying to sell product instead now they're going to be calling all and
Nnn it was just painful
Retractable until the 8th
You're so mean
When I'm spending sprees we were sharing hotel rooms and
Cutting Corners everywhere we could not on the ingredients but you know
I'm just trying to
Kit to keep the lights on
So what were you like what were you paid us as
My first year salary was at 50,000 literally I took that $50,000 check and it was even
Who is tax-efficient cuz I'm done with the company that I paid myself
I don't think I got over a hundred thousand
For probably not
BAC stock
Really gross
This time with their like lots of other companies are offering to it
Are you guys out by lots of companies along the way it was very
Parsley cuz we're growing quickly
Antarctica's we are doing something others weren't doing
So really from
From the first year we every year so we get
Search by image
Buddha Beverage Company
That wanted to Tobias
An arid like one of those
Most companies will
Jet Li and ends ends has a kind of friend you write with
End
We were always that was another thing I could lose sleep about competition
You and Barry owned like what
Like 90%
Even though you had
Invest right
How are you able to do that
Well this was one of the key strategic elements that Barry brought to the
Professor of Game Theory and so
He said you know the problem with so many startups is the
Entrepreneurs give himself all these penny stocks in the beginning
And as a result they start with a
Much more stock than everybody else
And then everybody else's kind of
She comes along for the ride is it but what if
Instead you started the founders at the same place as the other investors
And only when the company grows in Valley
Do the founders get more equity
That's
It was it was a reverse structure
And what that did
Was it helped
As we grew and we raised more money we didn't get diluted
The other thing was we relied on Angel
A lot of entrepreneurs in the Venture Capital Motors
Basically
There instead of istick to own more of the company
Incentivize to exit quickly
And we didn't take that kind of money and I'm very glad we didn't let the I think that was a key piece that let us
Keep control
What when did you when did you start to realize that
You know like honesty was
Is it becoming part of like the
Cultural Zeitgeist funny moments there was a moment in
President Obama had becoming honest tea drinker
I guess if the campaign for 2008
And the McCain campaign ad that criticized him for being a node Out of Touch lyrics
Drinking organic
Stock of it in his life
A few years ago when you keep brought over his the body man there
Wow
At what point were you able to
Feel like
Well
I would say so
When Coca-Cola became invest
Stern 2008
That was a surreal experience
Because
They approached
They approached us with a purchase in 2007 and they had just created
Venturing and emerging brands
And their goal was to invest in and build the next billion-dollar brand
And so
You know going to the headquarters in Atlanta sitting down with
The chairman
And and soda party was like looking down like I'm really here we really having this kind
So that was the first moment this is actually going to work this is going to be around
Coke by about 30% to 40%.
And and they bought an option to buy a majority which event
Holi in 2011
But like this was your accompaniment did you feel like you were
You're getting way control
Well
You know the story
So often
When a brand is sold the entrepreneur
Really frustrated in and they butt heads and that you are transferring around last few months this friend of my friend of mine it was
Vitamin Water
But he left shortly after
Coca-Cola body
Please ignore the first few
First few weeks they want to know your
And the next few weeks I want to know your phone number
I don't want to know you
Medicredit they understood this is a branded that is different than what they sell them
Connect with the OrganiCann
Consumer or the Natural Foods Marketplace
And so they gave us a saint
Incredible latitude in
And there were moments where
We ran up against them around regulatory language or
Or just marketing approaches and they respected what we did so
What's so
Continue to surprise me
This brand of storm Iran
The biggest part with the distribution we were in 15000 stores
When Coke invested never-never a hundred.
So that's that's where the
I hope my numbers are right that early investor
People who put in $50,000
Beginning
Made return of one point
$5000000 10 years later
That's right. 26 x there
Hurley investment how many millionaires were created by honest
I don't know
To me what was so exciting and some of our employees were where
Timmy was
You know that was all Sweat Equity
So that was a special
Meaningful
The question I've asked everybody who's on the show
How much of what happened
With you in Burien honest
T was
Because
You guys are just
Really good at what you do and how much
I really don't believe in luck
I believe that the reason we're still here is
The perseverance
And I took centers luck
You know that it's the timing the way the consumer has evolved
But you know I've heard something so that you were in the right place at the right time
Took 10 years to get to that right place so this was not a
This present
You know something that you
Just happened overnight
A friend of mine liking it to water you know eventually water finds its way
Going downhill and it gets to where it needs to go and I think
We finally
That's a place where we could connect with consumers
And doing the way that we still meeting
So I'm curious as you
Metallic look back on all this
1 Train
William portrait
You either developed
Add
Or have it
You think
All entrepreneurs need
Well
You have to be resilient in this is this is something that's so important
To put this on the bigger picture.
4like RR
What are the best ways I develop resilience growing up was I wrestled in high school
I was the worst wrestler on the team
My first year I was one and 10 and I was only cuz somebody didn't show up and I got the forfeit
So I had
I'm learned how to fight off my back
You know Nann
Experience Project
End
It's so important
Be able to bounce
Not just
All the time
Am I tan
And especially when you believe in it
Makes it that much easier
Add Chef Goldman founder of honesty
By the way the company has sold more than a billion bottles of
Beverage
It's all completely owned by Coca-Cola with
Annual sales of more than
170 million-dollar chess
It no longer formerly involved
And though it made him a rich man
His life hasn't
She changed all that much
Steph still lives in the same house
Suburban Maryland
Where he made that first batch
Honesty
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about
The things your building
But first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
American Express
No matter what you do in business
From building a
A better mousetrap to building a better app
It's easier when you
You don't do it alone
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business
Without it
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
It's time now for how you
You built that
The story we ran
About a year ago
What's 1 * 1 Jaya Iyer was Raising her three-year-old daughter in Oakton
My daughter told me that she wants to grow up to be an astronaut
So that's when I started looking around for clothes with astronaut or space team and I realized that there was really no
Turn on for girls
Ensure Jaya could have bought an astronaut shirt or pajamas in the boys department but
Her daughters
Favorite color
What is Pink
I actually looked every place
And there was nothing at all not a single pink astronaut
But as turned out Jaya was
Just the right person to
Tackle this
Problem she actually has a
PhD in clothing merchandising
So I actually got in touch with some freelance designers and I created a few designs like I made a monster
Drunk
It was on a t-shirt
Didn't say anything boy about it I made a pink T-shirt with a race car on it
Cool firefighter online course child also sketched out
That pink T-shirt with an astronaut on it
She put her drawings online she launched a Kickstarter campaign and she raised
30000 bucks and I was lucky that I had the support of my husband who is always
Let me know if you really believe in is going to do it so with the kickstarter money
Jaya found a factory in India willing to make the shirts
She then expanded her lines shirts
With computer code test tubes and a solar system that glows in the dark
All for kids
There was a problem
We actually had a lot of parents reaching out to us saying hey we don't have anything like this for the moms of these kids
Lots of moms who work in science were
Asking about clothes for grown ups
Tocaya started designing
Dresses with things like the
Periodic table the double-helix the solar system
Equations
Many school teachers College professors actually on our customers
It makes them feel great about teaching math and thing that hate America mattress because I love math
And if you feel like Miss Frizzle since we first spoke with Jaya last year revenue is
Toronto about 1 and 1/2 million dollars in
She sells items for men like
Cufflinks
Ties and socks
China culture company Spa Harwich
Is the name of her
Her daughter who
By the way
Is now a 6 years old and no longer wants to be an astronaut
That may be a singer or robot designer
And if you want to find out more about swap or hear previous episodes of Good how I built this. Npr.org
Also if you want tell us your story please go to build. End
Npr.org we love hearing from you about the sea
Things your building
Hey thanks for listening to the show this week
Please also consider subscribing to our show on iTunes and who's favored Riders review while you're there
Write to us at Hib tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
I sure was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis also composed the music thanks also to neva grandson as Mexican
4 North Quincy and Jeff Rogers our intern Stacy Howard
Guy Raz how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com