Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Really quick before we start the show Twilight let you know that
Tickets for 1 day how I built this Summit
Are now on sale.
Any world-changing entrepreneurs and hundreds of other builders
Just like you
It's happening October 16th
In San Francisco
Getting sponsored by America
Express
Get your tickets
Npr.org
Flash Summit
Grand Cayman to the studio for her interview
She was
Well kind of as you expect
Interesting funny
Full of stories and help
If you had to cut up a weed eater
Some of it ends or just a warning if you're listening with
Younger listeners
This episode originally ran in
In April of last year
Well worth caring again
Already heard it
If not enjoy
She came to me and she knew I had to fire a lot of people cuz you could just see the
Everybody knew something was going to shake out and she said one should probably fire me if you fire me
She said no one else could be angry with you when you fire them and she was right so at that Monday morning meeting we always had at 9
9:30 I said so surprised how bad things are going to have to make a lot of changes and it's going to be
Very hard for me to do with the hardest change rules required my mother
NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
Jersey Girl conquer the streets of Manhattan
Delta real estate company worth millions and then
Reinvented herself as a shark
Gymshark tank
Surprising things
About the entrepreneur
Least surprising to me
Is it most of them
Unnecessarily booksmart
Street Smart
All of them
But only a handful of people we've had on when
To Willie conversity zorawar academic genius
Most of them
Figured stuff out along the way
And use the tools they had
Which princess did Barbara Corcoran
Probably the most
Like a bull shark on the TV show
Shark Tank
As you're about to hear
Barbaro
Wasn't the best student in fact
She didn't excel at school at all
What she had
Rather has
You something so much more valuable
Charisma
How she'd eventually build one of New York's most sick
Successful real estate firm
Barbara
Quora
Big Irish Catholic Family
9 brothers and sister
Department
Edgewater New Jersey
Even though
They had almost nothing
She remembers a childhood that was
Basically happy
I mean we all had our issues as every family does
But
It was well-organized my mother was like a drill sergeant so even though we all
Lived in such Close Quarters was meticulously clean and everything was put in order where my mother snap turf
We had a side yard
Which we controlled it was a skinny little side yard but
Most of the house in Edgewater were back-to-back so we felt wealthy you know we're renting the ground floor we felt Wealthy by
By comparison
And also my dad was a printing press form and I had to wear a suit to work
And every other guy in the town seemed to work for the Luna Factory or the
Coffee company in a uniform
So I kind of thought of us as like
The Kennedys like
Whoa We were something and up
At school it was a different story
Barbara struggled a lot
But everyday when she get home from school
Her mom
Was right there
Achieve
Never
I told you what was wrong with
She always told you
What she thought was amazing about you and sheep in one thing on each kid so each kid knew what that thing was
Should I have a wonderful imagination
So when I couldn't pass any subjects in school and I was really upset I remember distinctly when
The nun from Hell sister Stella Marie told me I'd always be stupid I was so upset to hear that word stupid like get a label finally
And my mother said oh don't worry about it with your imagination you learn to fill in all the blanks so I didn't learn to read
But I thought I could fill in the blanks
I fell for it you know and she's right
Because I did have a good imagination or at least
Maybe I'll learn to have
Because of her
But it was 22 Barbara was working as a waitress at a diner in New Jersey
And one night during a shift
An older man
Dapper
Confident charismatic
What in for a bite to eat
And when Ramon Simone
I walked into my life
And set him
My counter
Call what you wanted was a lucky break
It was like you could
Hell
That he was some
LC
And she had a suit on
And he didn't have just a suit
Kid like a pressed collar
With a shiny toy
Shiny shoes
And he had all navy blue Aviator Shades I couldn't really see his eyes
Also
He told me
He was from The Basque
I know where that was but I
It wasn't a New Jersey
And he told me it was a warrior tribe of some kind
Cool
Now later I learned his name wasn't Ramon Simone with an accent
Mother Vicki who I got
No many years later
Said his name was Ray Simon
Big difference right but good good for him and he wasn't from The Basque country was 440 5th Street Harlem
But good for him again what a merchandiser
All right until he have a lot to
Teach me
Okay and
I got a new family with your his three girls who moved in with us after I moved in with him I didn't know we had
This is your first
True love
Well I'm not even sure it was a true love but
Someone who is different
Can anyone I have ever met before
For older
Successful in life had a big
Car I hate to
Biso
Detritus to say that impress me but it was a Lincoln Continental
With real leather seats and when he offered me that ride home from the diner that
That first night I remember thinking he had sprinkled talcum powder on the
All of his seat because I was sliding around
That's just cold real leather and
Was that
But your life was going to
BMW
Have bigger ambitions
You know honestly I have never had that
And I I can even say
Along the way
A building a successful life
It's not like I really had any big thoughts about when I be successful I just had more of a curiosity
Let's just see how far I could go
That was it
Curiosity
No one in my family has ever gone to
The college when I got into a college I just couldn't believe it but it was old girls
College I had previously the year before been a nunnery that made nuns I forget what
And they're only 30 spot so just opening they took me
The basically not realize I took anyone
But that was just a lucky break
And it didn't interfere with my work I was holding three jobs all the way through
Please work
So
It just kind of happened you know that I one thing led to another
How did you find your way to real estate
I was working as a receptionist for the jacuzzi Brothers here in New York City answering their phones a million times a day good morning
The funny Brothers
Zephyr quit my job is
The waitress
Joseph Tiffany was a large
Real estate holder in Manhattan xi'an probably 50 apartment buildings in your
Yeah they were there very well
It was Joe and his other
What kind of gadfly a brother
Andrew
Who ran the business but Joe is really the power
He hired me
And then within a couple of months
Ramon said Trina with your personally barbecue be great at real estate sale
I said okay I'll try it on your why not added
I think I turned twenty-two draws maybe 23 by then
I thought why not
Give it a whirl
And they gave me $2,000 *
Just like that
Yes
Ramon gives you a thousand bucks and then
How did you better you start your own real estate
I'm the only person I knew was mr. Tiffany
And I asked him if he would just let me rent one of his Apartments the same building where I answer the phone every
And he gave me a listing
Try to rent
Apartment 3L
And so when I saw 3L and what he was asking if it was
330 a month
I looked at him thing or not how do I
It's it was a dungeon he gave me the worst one maybe it was a challenge maybe nobody
But when I saw the listing
And looked in the New York Times and saw
Reams in
Reams of exits red identical
Play one-bedroom 341 bedroom
33051 bed it was all the same I'm thinking how do I
Spend my three-line ad why is it was remember I had $1,000 I provided it by my overhead
I knew I had at 7 weeks to stay
According to my map
And so I asked him if he build a half wall
To divide the
Dentistry part of living room from the L next door
With double entrance and I told him I thought I can get them 360 a month
What's the weather
20 $25 more than you wanted
Johnny said he yeah he build the wall
And I got it for him cuz Maya
1 bedroom and den
For the same price that everybody else is offering a one bedroom light.
The first Sunday I must have got 60 phone call
And so easily rented that apartment and then got others and got others in adjustable
And you were you were
Basically making a
Commission office rental
I made exactly what the
What the
Monthly rental was I when I rented that first apartment I did the the smartest thing in the world knowing I was ahead of the game
I collected the commission within a week that's what's beautiful
You have to wait for sale closing
So I collected that
Check for misophonia
I cash in Citibank and I ran right over to Bergdorf Goodman's and I blew it on a new coat
And it was a smartass and I could have
Because I dress like a poor kid for me
Nothing like being I just looked not the park
But I thought the fanciest damn code
A brown and white herringbone is real pearl buttons down 3/4 length
For real fur not fake
And I wore that coat
The next three
And you want to know it was the smartest thing I could have done with the money cuz in and I felt powerful Joe
I'm cool man I'm a cool girl
What is called a business
I was called Corcoran Simone
With an accent on the Simone I kept the axon cuz I really thought it was pretty so sweet
All right meniscus because Raymond
Yes
So why you were like why you were going out and working as an agent to rent apartments what was Raven-Symone doing
Ramon Simone
Little flask
I'm Ramon Simone was building one family houses in New Jersey
Usually classes
Three or four houses in making a very good living
And that went on for probably
3 years or so hazard
Call and then one day we
Drove his accountants
Office in Hackensack New Jersey
And he had me wait in his car with the car running comes out
Guess what
I thought it was a joke and I moved immediately out of his fancy apartment
I moved into his mother's
Hackensack house
And that was the bad years
Where are we
Not undercover butthead
Up from the Earth all over again and he did he was a great entrepreneur
I took about 3 years and those were the
The very very
Tough years
But lucky for both of us
I'm the rental business was
Paying for itself and we're able to eat
He got a salary you were running this from your
Confirm an apartment
No no no no no no I had an office I initially ran
Corcoran Simone
A from an apartment I shared with two roommates
On 86th Street
But then when I could afford to I sublease to desk from an accountant
On East 60th Street
And by the time we moved into Ramon Simone's mother's house
We still have the office on 60th Street
We already had
I guess maybe 10 or 11 Des occupied by rental
So you were going into
Manhattan everyday
Yes
It was like it was like the Land of Oz you know the minute I stepped foot into Manhattan
I saw for what it was like where have you been all my life
Clown
This is like
The
The violent nights
1870s New York
Bankrupt
The Son of Sam
What was it like
2 I mean
Is it hard to to get
Tenants to rent apartment
It's crazy to imagine today of course but back then
Was it hard to get people to rent
No it's saved my ass in those days
Was you had Corporate America
Very well implanted in Midtown granted it was dangerous you wouldn't dare Park
Car in the street you know
Gets broken into Sirens were always going off everywhere
So was not easy but fortunately
You had him
Please
Young employees coming into New York City who had to live there working for these corporations
If not for that I don't think I would have stayed in business because I went door-to-door and knocked on all these corporate
Personnel departments to try to get business I saw where the traffic
Was coming from
And I had great
Counselor
Said that people to me 1 hour
Another after another
And so I had a huge Edge over my other small competitors
Because I had a steady stream of
Coming at me
Yeah that was kir I don't think I could have stayed in business
How did you make the transition from renting from looking for renters
To selling
Apartments
Really quite by accident
I had gotten a referral of a young engineer from Union Carbide I don't recall his name and I lined up a hold
Bunch of stuff to show him like I usually did cuz I had learned by then in sales of
Control someone's time
They can't go to anyone else I would say
I'll pick you up at the Drake Hotel
Snow new name
At 9 and be aware we won't be finished till at least 5:30
Entertain going to
Another broker
And then I would tell Midway to I've got everything set up for tomorrow but just control Park them in your garage and don't let the car
I had this young guy
And I showed him the first two apartments he said well when am I going to see the ones for sale
I said oh no these are for rent she said no I want to buy some
So I said well that's X1
So I said I was going to take him on a tour of all New Yorkers was very important for him to learn all the neighborhoods to see what he could choose for
From to see what he react
2 best
And that the next day we would show him the sale of Parma
Of course I had no sales
So I got them in a taxi walking around every street showed him every every place in town and then that night
Hit the Floor running
I dropped them off at like 5:15 as early as I could
Cold every single
Apartment where the owner are which was very common those days and said I have a young engineer his leg
Exactly four
Your apartment on Sutton Place he's looking for a small tear that really had back and go but he must see it tomorrow
Yes come on over and I
Book everything that night and the third apartment we saw he bought the neck
That's what got me in the sale business and when I got back
Commission check in my hand was 38
8500 switch
What's at 6:12
I can't do the math anymore shame on me but 6% of that
Do you know what I I got that check in my hand on closing
And I thought God has given me this to open up a cell
Apartment I hired two sales agent
And that was the birthing of the sales business
And all the while you were still
Let me Ray is still part of this thing you still in your life
Yes Ray was still part of my life
Because that was within the first seven years we stayed together for 7 years
Until
He married my secretary
Which is really like
Like so emotionally
Discouraging
Tell me a real up
He cheated on you
With your secretary
Yes
She was kind of innocent they fell in love I was angry with him but of course directory
And so when I wanted to fire her
I said I can't come in the office every day and see your fiance they were getting married 3 months is very fast
I'm mortified I was mortified
And then he moved Tina into our combined office I had to look at them through the glass world
Just stupid thing I must been so young at heart to be so injured over some stupid
But here's the thing I said I have two fires and no I'm looking trolling partner
You can't fire her he owns half of this company and Milian 51% and
That's how I found out the value of that 1%
That's how it works well
Yeah but that didn't last long one year later I stopped in there finally Built My courage and told him I was sending the business
I said Ray
I'm going to end the business today in this is how it go
We're going to do it like a
14 salespeople you can pick
First I'll pick the second I got a thing
So we each got seven
Like they were children in a divorce I didn't know what was happening
And we also had close to $77,000 in receivables which I remember at the time thinking half of
That would get me through month-and-a-half of overhead
And so
I had the ability
To take my half of the money and start all over
And lucky for me I went to my landlord in our existing building
We were on the 8th floor
And I asked him if I could lease another floor we had always
Pay the rent on time and he rented me the 11th floor
Of Ray which I love being above him is not weird I'm sick
I really need a shrink he started he
He start his own company and then you stayed there and renamed it
Poke Simone
PS wife's name is Pogue and I moved up to 11
It my seven people I told my Monday would be
Moving in there like
Wow where we moving to I said
It's a surprise
What's a surprise
Give me even
But by Monday you could open an office in the
You could buy the desk down on decrepit 42nd street and have those guys asked
Possibly run the desk
You could order a phone which I did on late Friday morning and had installed on Saturday
And by the time they just came in I called him over the weekend gave him the new address which is
They came in that all their stuff in a neat box on top of the new desks like nothing had happened
Here's a question
Is it are you are you just
Sort of
Hardwired
Tough person means
Mostly the best men pretty
Clear off right I mean in this the guy that you're with for 7 years
I mean you think you're loving and in the meanwhile
Peas
Having an affair
Well
Hey listen the truth be known I'm not
A tall heart person
I mean the idea
Ask any woman who's been cheated on any guy
You feel like
Such a fool and you burn so deeply inside now
I can barely walk
I received estimated by that
It wasn't that I
Even so much lost faith in him
I mean you're allowed
On Love stats
Be real with somebody else
But it was that I fell out of love with
Myself
I actually thought
My God I was nobody
Before he found me
He got me to believe in myself he put me in business
He in love with my mentor
He's a man of the world
You know and all of a sudden
He's going off of somebody else
It was like
I'm nobody I never actually questioned
Whether I was capable of any
Until
He insulted me on the way out
What are you saying
He said you'll never succeed without me
Which
He
He was having an affair
And then he'll rub salt in your wounds by saying you're never going to succeed with
Yes
And you know what
Janome remember we live together
Almost seven years I was as busy
He may have even been wanting to motivate
Knowing that I'm good when I'm insulted and you know I have learned that
Was every one of my great successes building the business the ones that were Bellwether changes that I thought wow that my
Make a change
There are always a result of an insult
Play Weird Al's like fuel to your fire says this and you are
I mean of course I see
Devastated inside but you
You just think the greatest revenge's I'm going to
Cruise
Said he's wrong
What wasn't even a Revenge thing honestly it was like I couldn't
Stan the idea that
He might see me fall
Who are the opposite
And you want to know something I got to believe that was all tied into cuz it injured so deeply
And became my motivation
I have to believe that that was tied into being a dumb kid at school
Was basically damning me to hell
Yeah and that's how I felt in school are we
Like I'm a loser you'll go nowhere
And so he hit my hot button
Pusher
And I'm for sure
So did you
From day one when you go to the 11
In floor and
Can you start your
Your company
Are you thinking
We was he your main competitor with his company the one that you were
I moved off of
I just I was in survival mode
Figuring out the math
Noah has six a six-week run to stay and visit in 6 weeks
How much cash you had on there because I had a bigger overhead by then you know in the beginning when my thousand dollars gave me a little bit longer
Long run
This was just one ad per week in the New York Times three lion head
Whatever it cost then
Am I sublease charged
So now it was more complicated
When I move to the 11th floor
I also had 14 desk
But I only had seven age
Problem
And that's a big overhead no no income
And classified ads were really expensive at that
Well they always were
Going up in price
I said yes so they didn't go very far but you know that was the bloodline of the real estate business hours
Pretty internet if you wanted to go to leave
You put an ad in the paper
Were you
Freaking out
Kenosha
Actually no I never freaked
What about pressure I never have
Because it is what it is
You know I can't have matter-of-factness
Another word something okay give it a shot
If I'm going to fret about oh my God oh my God it's going to get again
If I get cocky and big head this is no big deal
I'm going to get cocky
So I just kind of okay this is what I got let's see how
Hard and fast I can run
However
I did have one vision
I must admit the day I open the kor'kron
Group
I remember sitting at that
Desk and paying extra dollar a month for a pink princess phone you pay $2 extra to rent
Was pink
Remember answering a phone sitting there
I'm going to
Dean of New York real estate
Barbara Corcoran in a moment how is she
She actually did become the queen
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast in the following message come from choiceology
An original podcast from Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of boy salad
You'll hear a classic psychology experiments retold
William is an opera fan who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation
And is an average chest
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find
Schwab.com podcast
Or wherever you listen
Thanks also tour 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
The business insurance expert to understand that
Which business is
As unique as a fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent in every business has very specific needs
Explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance Expo
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR and Gyros
Barbara story
She may have thought she was going to the queen of New York real estate but
Who's going to be an uphill battle
She's broken up with her mom
Split everything up
She had a pink princess phone in her new office
And
Figure out how to get more attention for a company
One of the world's most
Repetitive
I distinctly remember the day
I sat and pause and said to myself
Only
We are going to be successful
What happened
I came up with the idea
I'm taking our
11 sales for the year
We had 11 sales so far whatever time of the year that wasn't dividing by
11 which is good I was always good
11 * 2
And I came up with an average sale price and I typed in one piece of paper
And I named it after myself the Corcoran
Report and it looked lonely one number average apartment price I didn't say
Corcoran group I just put
Average New York City
And on the top I put the
Cochran
Report
And then I thought it needed something more so
Empty and I put
Market I can remember some long-winded like market report of conditions and Trends in the greater New York City Market
There are some long thing to fill up
I mailed it out to everyone wrote for the New York Times
Everyone and I never heard from the X at all but about 2 weeks later
I open up the real estate section
Portion the main generator that an automobile sex
Shuffle the New York
Before the internet
And I opened it up and the front page
Hatred New York City
Prices hit all-time low
We're in a recession
And the first lines that
According to Barbara Court
Present of the Corcoran
Holyshit
Can't believe this
I knew my business was going to be successful
You just made this in this I just took your sales numbers
Properties
411 Culebra is you divide that decided up and then you said
Hey this is the average price of a Manhattan I didn't really say hi where I put I put
Average New York City
I'm praying since now that sounds really I could see now from where I sit that is Missy I didn't intend it that way
You know I did intend to trim it up with that long
Conditions in Friends
But you know
It was amazing to me
That
The newspaper printed my number
Who likes your daddy
Yeah but also there were no number
There was no public data of a partner
Are prices in it in the vacuum
I've no numbers I supplied number and they wanted to do a story on the bed mark
Can I put a label on
I bet it was right so did you start getting
Pause
From people who set up
Group
We got instant credit
We called the listings on the
For sale by owner
And most of them had heard of us in one day
Well everybody read the time so if you aren't page if you are looking to sell your home your reading the front pages in your
Real estate
Without a doubt
When they didn't hear of us
My broker start
Saying things like
I'm sure you've read about us
Today's times last week
Start that didn't take them long to use it
So we got listings more easily we got credibility more easily and we got more phone calls and
All
Claws
We were quoted as
That's it
Wow internet
Presumably that was the first of the carpenter part you even that didn't stop
Sending that that is
I got it out every 3 months
And eventually was normal
Incredible
Based on thousands of sales you could really trust them
But initially if I had been a big company
And I'd run it by attorneys wedding
Committee decisions it would have never gone
The beauty I had his little guys I had the freedom to run
In New York
Real estate business was it
A more welcoming
Place for a woman to
Typically a company or was it still I mean you know you hear about that
I'm in here at women were sort of in a relegated to being secretaries and diapers and things like that
Did you feel like you were
Respected and treated
You know what
No I never paid attention
I don't give a crap
Really you know
Diadora
How business was 90% female
Wasn't like women we're not in the real estate brokerage for you
But it just happened that all the firms were owned by the men
Bosses world
Okay so yes so they weren't
Female only businesses that I competed with but that was
It was not even important detail
What an important detail my mind
That I have for teenager
And the largest company in town at that point Douglas Elliman
Headlight
Maybe 80-90 agents
That seemed to me like
IBM itself
Yeah how am I going to compete with them my I was on that ball
How did you know
Barbara how to
Even
Run the Spinners I mean I know we're talking now right
Early 1980s and you've been working with re4
For few years
You don't have an MBA you don't have formal business background
Management issues how to deal with how to pay people with
Pattern pricing
It's a I think you make it sound more sophisticated than it is
All you needed to know
Is how
To work with people
And that sold the business ever is all the work I do today
It rests entirely any successor
Failure rest entirely on my ability
To work with the people at hand
So learning how to recruit people
I learned how to recruit
Because I made friends with
Every store clerk every waitress every
Stewardess everyone I ever met I made friends with cuz I'm very friendly
And if I saw a spark in them
Which Wich said to me sells personality I would say have you ever considered doing real estate sales I recruited
Everywhere
Everywhere I went I recruited
And from what I understand you yourself actually didn't go out
How many minutes
I saw I saw the engineers first house yet
And then from Merrill Lynch I Got a referral
David Palmer
Was a really big wig and I sold him
Chew apartment side-by-side
On the Upper East Side and East 89th
Like Condominiums
And that was it that was that you didn't sell any
Property I guess you recognize that your talent was not
In selling property but in
Managing people
No I was great at renting apartments
However
I realize
Just that if I were to continue to sell because it's time-consuming to be a great sales
Very Thai
Time consuming
I realized that if I were to continue doing that
I could only go my business on the side and I just took a leap of faith
Faith especially when I sold David Palmer
2 Apartments side-by-side 4
Total value of
Little bit more than 350,000 which today would be
Still cool enough certainly.
I was a landslide victory
I took that check I remember collecting it from the developer and 89th Street and walking it to 60th Street in my office was skip
Chipping down Madison Avenue
And seeing Georgie
To myself
I quit that Day sales
And I decided to use that money to hire
Three new cells
Right there I knew I could afford it
And then I heart6 more and then 10 more
And then before you knew we had a thousand people I don't want to make it sound like it's overnight
But it was just that same methodology whenever I had spare money
I would / an overhead monthly
Figure out how many bodies I could
Afford like a mother paying for the kid
Kids and then I would go out her that money
That's it was a symbol for I never changed it was really very useful
Let me sounds like
In the first years they was
You know
Cyber success but I mean in the short. Of time you must have hit
That the
Pragmatism
Huge
That was a bloodbath
For a good reason
When the economy crashes or even really waivers
A terrible thing happens if you're in the real estate brokerage
Is this a buyers and sellers.
Do nothing
Nothing is terrible for brokerage
A big sellers Market is great cuz action
Horrible Market is great
You'll have to sell
But in the beginning when nothing happens you go out of business well what happened was the great majority of my competitors win
Out of business
I've been used to that is it's hard to stay in business
It's very good news in that
Is I realize
I lost half
That's a motive
What happened to you guys
Oh well
I was really on the brink
Declaring that it was over but I was ashamed and trying to make back the money I owed to various
Suppliers like my Ad Agency the New York Times
But I owed over $300,000
And there was no business coming in
It was no business know when the market stops
Yeah it's a terrible terrible the end
You have to remember you have sales people many of them
Supporting the family
You have no money coming that's the worst
Nevermind
The pressure on
Did you have to let people go
Oh my gosh
I always let people go anyway
But it was interesting I had my mother working for me then
For two years of my life
Because all the kids are grown and should work at the 5 and 10
On 215th Street walking across the George Washington Bridge and she's getting older
Mommy can't do that you got to come over
She was delighted
So she was a file Clerk
Boy did she keep
Color coded
She was a
But anyway when the shit hits the fan
Which is what my mother always
By the way I get it from her my filthy mouth
She came to me
And she knew I had
How to fire a lot of people
You can just see that everybody knew something
What kind of shake out and it was fast and she said
One she probably fire me if you
Fire me
She said no one else could be angry with you and you fire them and she was right I thought what
So at that Monday morning meeting we always had at 9:30 I said
You know I forgot it's no surprise how bad things are going to have to make a lot of changes
And it's going to be very hard for me to do with the hardest changeables me firing my mother
Really close to going out of business if
If you had to make
Deposition
Well I was going out of
Business I owe the 300 some 1000 but I came up with a great idea to sell
A burning mendix
Apartments and nobody wanted which is owned by Equitable insurance he was like a big real estate
That's one of the he until his death about gets 10 years ago
He was
The largest developer New York him and Larry Silverstein
Apartments for many years who built the World Trade Center I'm sure you know that name
Anyway he asked me to look at 88th Apartments scattered throughout the city and the number of properties and he said I want
Find out from you how you can sell them
I knew every broken china pendants
There was no way to sell
There is a dregs of the market that is someone didn't have kitchens Okat Midstream when the market
Collapsed
So they were in a c-rated buildings
Everything is wrong with
Anyway I went I visit maybe 8 or 9 of the apartments
Who the super is in right away
Hayward
They were dumps they could not be so we need a market to sell Mendes per
We had no Market
So anyway I went back and I told him there was no way to sell it except
Public auction
Do you want to do a public auction you said if we can't do a public auction we don't want the publicity of
A failure
And I saw the snow with a way you can sell these
And I'll never forget what he said he said Barbie you're a smart girl you'll figure it out
And I went back and thought about it
Right in my head
Came
A memory of my mom taking like seven or eight of us however many were born then down to Toms River New Jersey watching app
Puppy sale with the farmer lady
Christmas tree
For my grandpa's house
And my mother status on the grass and watched all these fancy New York
Arguing over
Puppies are little Jack Russell
And anyway
My mother said to us
Look at all these fancy
See people do you know why they will want those puppies
It's because Louis smart enough to invite them all here at the same time
And so that popped in my head
And I went back to Bernie mendik the next day.
Enterprise
All the apartments alike
Same price
Well I pray all the one bedrooms like all the Avengers are like a $10,000 difference between the category
But somewhere on 22nd floors with Gorgeous views somewhere on the third floor with no kitchen they was so uneven
Yeah first-come-first-served have a secret sale we're not going to advertise it
I'll announce it to my sales people only let them bring the best customers
But I need you to give me two years free maintenance you're not going to unload these two years anyway
Maintenance is like a association fees monthly maintenance
Erase the terrible maintenance and they had nobody thinks Beyond two years
And price in the mall like it's going to create hype.
And so he said okay give it a whirl
And I said we had a sick
How to myself closing the business that's how close we were exact belt unconscionable
But pressure is a wonderful thing in life isn't it makes you think
And so I now to my people as a but get there early and don't bring too many people just a family member if you wanted your
Single best cuss words you'll bring don't spread it around we don't have enough
To go around
And I'm telling you a ride and 80
The first tree where we had that makeshift
Office that morning at 7 a.m.
And we had a line of 60 people waiting
Casitas apartment
To see those apartments
And I'm chilling an hour and a half later more than $1000000
And I close it was a
Closing
They sign the contracts
It was like a fire sale in bulk blue or people happy
They got the deal of the century
Yeah I bet they're really happy today but not as happy as I
Was that day cuz I went from being
New desperation of being filthy rich in real estate
Chelsea rich
You got it I went right out and I rented myself
Full floor at 660 Madison Avenue cuz I had the cash to do it
It's like everything I've heard about you people say you know Barbara Has Talent wasn't
About selling homes
News about Market
She was in
Credible
Marketer is that apps abs
Italy right where did you is it just an instinct
Is it trial and error is it is it just being
You know kind of Hustler
Oh no I think it has more to do with
Creativity
I saw a black and white game marketing
It's a the softer side of things right
It involves exaggeration
Involves
Acumen for seeing what a storyline is or what would capture
People's interest in
It definitely includes
PeopleSmart
And you know what I actually started
Realizing I was best when things are bad
Because I would go into any bed real estate cycle in say
Say 15 position pecking order within the industry
And I would come out of it needs position cuz a lot of people got knocked out
Yeah
You decide
I guess
I like mm
Mm
To sell the car
Get out
Yes
Why did you decide to sell me and you love the game you love that
Steel energy in that
Like pressure so why did you
Do things happen
Open one I had my first baby at 46
I gave birth to my son Tommy
After 8 years old
That was nothing short of a miracle something I desperately wanted
The finally happy
Once I had that child
My heart changed
And I played out my heart everyday I was home and my grand old age nursing my son and feeling guilty about it
Because my kids heads at work or whisper
And so it took me about 4 years
And then I'm
Wonderful thing happened when Eve
Astronaut were doing the Corcoran report numbers that we are
Yes Esther my business
We're doing the quarter report numbers one night
Because hours
Because we wanted to have accurate numbers or verb
I don't know why my first
Report had nowhere
It was just a
By then we're very respectable and making sure over numbers were
And we also did monthly a report of who control the market share on listings buses was
Melissa New York
Destihl menu
Multiple listing service that showed you
Who had what listings
Like if you could just go to one
Place to see all the listings
No
And we broke the market into price categories in east and west side of town
Downtown
So we had those categories
And we would go through the listing can
Together
And she'd say
575 / west side
Distraught
How to categorize
By all the top agencies in town the top 7
And then that night
We did all the ad up and we could clearly see that Corcoran was numb
We had more listings than ever
3 category 4
The highest to the lowest Uptown downtown east or west
Not by a lot but a smidgen over Brian Harris Douglas Elliman
My turn to ask Jonathan let's sell it
Bigfootville also
To be a fair
It was the first year
That I
Had made over million dollars
Myself
And I figured
It's probably worth something
You sold it for 66 million dollars
Because I remember being on a ski lift
Is my roofer brother John who still lives in Edgewater
We are out in Utah I think I'm going up a chair lift and I get on my cell phone call from my attorney who said I've got great news
He said I have an offer
3 million dollars are you seated
I said turn 23
Million dollars old cash
And I said
Great comeback when you get 66
Cash and he said
Y 66 million
Because it's worth it
And I hung up
And I said to my brother
23 million think of that John Maginot 723
Anyssa but why'd you say 60s
That's my lucky number
And would you bake those at those accountants kill themselves to try to figure out why 66
It was until the closing of
Got grease that is bad
Action telling a whole bunch of hell with my lucky number
It was I proved it
Did you when you sold the company did you
Did you regret it
I would have to answer that honestly on some level yes
And in
I'm more important level
Enat
I felt enormous sense of freedom
Be a phenomenal mother
And so that was exactly what I wanted and I had the enormous satisfaction
Of knowing I had become the queen of New York real estate
And financially
Loud sex life
Yes
But I never understood
How much I loved
The people I worked with and how much that
Teen Mental
It was my lifeblood
I found them recruited them
Train them live with them
Got into Good Times bad times
Times I had sales managers 11 of
That I'd ordinator toward me we were such a tight
And I felt
Happily lonely
And I really thought I was going to get
Depression probably need a shrink
Because I really didn't know what to do with myself
Yearn
For good morning Barbie good morning Father good morning Barbara
And all the hoopla that went with
Was being somebody in a business it was gone so that part
Adult
Baidu
What did I do to myself
Until of course
I I don't want to say reinvented
Myself
Starting all over again and trying to
That's that's a thing right
Because obviously you did
Go on a Nintendo II Korea cuz I didn't most people listening to this
Would know you as as one of the sharks on Shark Tank not as the head of the Corcoran group
Do you wait when you're on that show DUI
It seems like you have a bias toward
People who
You know who have similar background
To come from nowhere
Money
I'm very fine
They have a much better shot at 6
Why
Lottery
The Mosasaurus
They've never had the fancy Vape
Location
The delicious new car
The
The private schools the higher education of minions
And they aspired to it
So they get more satisfaction out of climbing that ladder in getting to
End
Are they
Hasina parents struggle
Through life to give them whatever they've given them the more appreciative they don't take things for granted
And you know what else
Which I should have started with it totally
Free
From expectation
Do you know
How
How lucky I was
To never
For a second
Ever think I wonder what my parents think of
All it was was just like see how far I could go and nothing to lose and nowhere to go but up to make a friend that is to take
So they did not risk of R Civ
And you strive
So I really am biased I'm not saying that you can succeed I mean God willing I have
I have privilege children
And I hope they'll succeed
It's much harder for me
Not to let them feel my success even if I don't say a word
And so they're not as free as I was you know God bless them
Thomas Hardy
Do you feel
I mean when you were a kid you were told that you aren't smart
Do you feel now
But you've convinced yourself that you are smart
Well yes or no
I'm certainly Street Smart
I'm certainly
PeopleSmart
I have
Instinct
When trouble is brewing
Where's the best accountants in the world way to the wall
Should I trust my math instinct
I think I'm a smart person for sure
More than that
I think I'm going to normalcy hard-working
Person and I have great Confidence from my ability to work hard through anything
And I think I'm very good at not feeling sorry
And I think that's
How much of your of your success do you think
Is is because of
Just
Skill intelligence hard-working and how much of it is luck
Well I do believe in luck I've had many
Many many lucky
Brakes including meeting Ramon at the diner then
Beginning
Yeah or the very good luck of having my parents as parents
Not bad right
Once you grow up
Are you make your own luck
Definitely Maybe
I think all the lucky breaks I had were more result in me staying
In the game
I just believing something would break
Just hanging around
That's more important than luck in life
Being aggressive at every opportunity
And standing up for yourself yes more important than
Barbara Corcoran by the way she was
Ashley rejected for her spot on Shark Tank
They went with a younger woman
To Barbara wrote a letter to the producer
Acid
I consider your rejection
You lucky charm
Because everything that ever happened in my life
Came on the heels of failure
The next day
He called her
Said he reconsidered and
You know what happened
And please do stick around because it just a moment
From you about the
Your building
The first
Thanks to one of our sponsors SC Johnson
Family company
Everything is chemistry weather
Natural or
What matters is whether it's safe for
For your family
The environment
See what's inside their products
What's inside SC Johnson
Dot-com
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Timeout for Howard
You built that
Update the story we had on the show last year this one starts about 10 years ago
When are y'all Rivera was
Scrambling
Get something together for his girlfriend's birthday gift was actually very good food chest I think
A+ it just some random guy that I'd given her
Arielle actually is created
Who was the wrapping paper I think I had my pictures on my computer
And I just flipped out the head really quick and I I decided to just repeater on a piece of paper with a funny background so
So he duplicated his face
15 times and then you photoshop them onto a backdrop
Like a Cheesy yellow Starburst pattern
Any printed the whole design onto plain paper you wrap the chocolates and then he handed the gift to his girlfriend
Vanessa and her reaction oh my God this is hilarious what did you do
It was so funny and clearly it worked because
3 years later
Vanessa and Ariel got married
She also happens to be a graphic designer and now again
They would do the same thing that would make wrapping paper for friends and family and put their faces on it and
Just about every time we give to somebody that I start a business out of this you should
You should make a website you should make website
So eventually
Ariel and Vanessa
Did just that and that's first it was it was tough because we are not web design
Cena I mean now I guess we are but
They started the website their business gif
They soak you upload a photo
They duplicated and print dozens of your
Tiny little faces onto whatever image you choose
We have the statue of David the Mona Lisa the cupid
Bride and groom we have Vanessa launched a few years ago
I got a few hundred orders at first
And about a year-and-a-half later
Oprah featured the wrapping paper in her magazine
When you finally hitting BC
Oprah holding our paper in the I think she was in her kitchen holding up a box that's wrapped in our paper which I know that I printed for
For her it was wild it was really wild
Even with that boost from Oprah
Sales have been
Modest
Since the company launched about
3 years ago
But very soon
Vanessa and Arielle are hoping to partner with a
Printing service
That will let them move their production out of the garage
In the meantime they both
Still have their day jobs and another
Pretty important one
Raising the two kids ages 6 and 3
That's pretty much our life now
Find out more about the company
Giftwrapmyface head to our Facebook page
Of course if you have a story about something
Your building please tell us about it go to build that npr.org and thanks for listening to the show this week
You want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org you know so
Write to us at habt at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
Shows produced this week by run. Original music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to Newark ootsima grandson is Mexican for and Jeff Rogers I'm guy Roz and you been listening
How I built this on NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email templates drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week