Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
What happened to that name well the trademarking attorney called me at the eleventh hour
And we were getting ready to launch it was the year 2002 summer and she said I think you're going to need
Change the name
And I just thought you're joking right I'd left working at Whole Foods and
We're supposed to be watching that we don't launch and everybody's backing out because nothing's happening
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
American through dates cashews and dried cherries into
Cuisinart and turn that mushy mix into Larabars one of the best selling energy bars
In America
Sophie recently walk to the energy bar section
The supermarket
You might be surprised were overwhelmed by the number of
Choices
I need for starters that are hundreds of different types of energy bars
Which is kind of
Protein bars
Paleo bars
Whole30 and vegan and gluten-free in
Cacao infused with matcha powder
Probably an energy bar out there
For each and everyone of us
And that whole Revolution
It really got started in the 1990s
Clif Bar
84 previous episodes of the show you might have heard our interview with Gary Erickson who actually invented
Does Clif bars
Well in the early 2000s
Lara merriken
Camp Jose
Pretty simple concept that shockingly wasn't really out there in the world
It was an energy bar made from two or three Rodriguez
Like almonds
Are cashews
All bound together with
Dates
No alarm
Big deal today right
You can get them
Pretty much anywhere any 7-Eleven
Put back in the day
End of revolutionary
And how she even came to inventing them to building this brand
Well there was no Direct
Pat Lauren never intended to start her own business or even to sell a product
She grew up in the Denver area or parents rent a pretty successful high-end clothing
And Laura was really into sports was actually good enough to make the USC women's volleyball
Graduate from college with a degree in
Psychology
Wasn't really sure what to do
So she came back to Denver and got a job as a social worker
And she turns to work with kids and teenagers
You needed help
It was hard
I mean just emotionally
Difficult job it was
Intense it was always chaotic
We were on call every
6 weeks I think this is a timer attic. Page around remember the pager days
And if the pager went off at 2 in the morning because somebody ran away from our treatment facility you had to answer the phone call
But it was
It was intense work in the sea
15 year old girls actually 13 year old girls with kids
And I had to manage their care with the
The judicial system I went
Wordalot I made recommendations
It was one of the most stressful jobs
Ever had in my life and I was in my early twenties
How long did it take you
Before you
Jeopardize
A year-and-a-half so if you're doing this and
You decide
This is not
This is not for me
I knew I needed to change what the landscape look like
So
I wanted to help these kids but I wanted to do it in more of a recreation
I didn't want it
Feel like I was the police all the time
And so I be
Became a
Community involvement leader and I got
These kids involved in the community
How long did you do that for
About 4 years
I really loved
In the more recreational component with
These kids and kind of
Opening their eyes to a bigger world
And hoping that
They saw opportunity for themselves that was very gratifying
Like you would play
Like sports of them and take them
For like
Nature walks
I would do anything and everything
I mean we went to a natural food grocery store one day and got a tour of that and
Then I would take them to Rockies games cuz somebody would donate the tickets and then
We had the
Cat petting club and I take them to the local animal shelter cuz they couldn't have pets
And their home
And then we would have our community garden and
So is a year-round program they come after school and then during the summer I basically ran a summer camp
And then I would teach him how to cook and do arts and crafts I mean anything I could think of to do I would do so dislike your MB
Yeah that was your management training
It was good it was
It was really fun I mean
To this day I still
Is children and I wonder
Where they are was happy
What they're doing
So during this time that I was being a social worker
Working as a social worker I was also
Cultivating this passion for now
Well
So let's go back to college
College volleyball
Our coach had a
Rule of
No sugar and no red meat
So
At the time I was totally in the junk
What I was 18 years old
You know my favorite place to eat was any fast food restaurant you can name
Then I opposite of started to stop eating sugar and
No red meat
Inspector he felt that
No red meat no sugar wood
Results
Inveterate
Performance from his players
Yes and did he did he like enforce this rule
Oh yes
Now this was
Fairy real
Like it was a rule in the team and
And that was a it by the way it's been an intense
Demons that Division 1
Volleyball
USC Utah
Majorly
Pac-10 School
Oh yes
I remember thinking I can't believe
I have the opportunity to play volleyball this
I will do anything this man tells me to do
And
Then I also said I'm starting to stop eating sugar
No red meat
It was really an interesting experience so I start feeling better
So
That was the first light bulb
Went off for me
Post-college I mean I'm working as a social worker I start doing all this reading
When I start having migraines
I started getting migraines out of nowhere I've never had them
But I got a blood test and learned that I was actually very allergic to wheat
Wow you've been eating wheat your whole life and an africology
Yes I mean
Wheats
Everything everything
So this is in the early 90s
The time in there wasn't really many options and their their solution to this is
Stop eating wheat and I'm thinking what what am I going to eat
So at the time
I didn't even really know
My cookbook
You know I grew up with two working parents
My mom went to school
It was just
I'm sliding over these
A stove is very much Convenient Food oriented
So I really didn't know how to cook why to learn how to
Cook for myself because I had such a limited diet
And I got introduced to Natural Foods
So things like kale and quinoa and all the things that we kind of know now is normal
Totally for it
Especially in the mid-nineties
It's like
It was weird.
First and then I had
I thought well
I'm going to embrace this
And so I would
Read everything I could
About
Recipes and nutrition and I just
Got into it
And I made the most of it so that I started thinking to myself in the background of going through this whole experience and feeling better
I thought
I love naps
Make such
This is common sense to me why don't people know about this why isn't somebody teaching us
About
Healthy food
And so my passion started to build
So I guess it at a certain point you stopped working with
Kids and did you find another job or did you
Which kind of starter
What you want to do
Well
I knew I had an excitement and passion for Natural Foods I just didn't know how I was going to make a transition
Between
Being a social worker
A natural foods
They were two completely different worlds
What was going on in your personal life or you single at the time I was married
And I was in the middle of
Getting divorce
So is
A huge
Change for me
And I realized that I needed to get a divorce in the middle of all of this
See where you were young
Young woman married and getting
Yes
And I'm thinking about changing my career
In a matter of like 6 months
And what were you
Thinking about doing
I didn't know
But all I knew
Is that
I needed to
Find the courage
To take a leap of faith
And somehow someway I figured that out
For myself
And
I left my marriage
I left my job
And decided I'm going to go back to school and I'm going to study
I want to get into natural
Medical school
Naturopathic is like
Natural homeopathic
Yes so there's
That's cool in Seattle Washington
And 1 in
Portland Oregon
Naturopathic medicine
And I thought
I'm going to practice.
Which covers all natural medicine
Nutrition acupuncture everything and that's what I really
I think that's
The direction I want to go
I looked at the school for years
Really renowned school I thought this is what I'm going to do so I started take
Can chemistry
Physics
Ali size classes at the local Community College
And actually move back out to California
My parents were living out there
So I'm on my path taking classes
I made a friend of mine
A dear friend of mine now one day eating at the local health
Bistro Reading lunch
And he drags me
To this
Raw food
Classen
I have one of the most amazing meals I've ever had in my life at this class and I
Wow
What foods are kind of amazing
And it just never had a curtain
And meanwhile I'm taking my classes I got accepted to this program to
Schools 1 + Seattle + 1 +
Washington and I thought I'm going to be a naturopath
Pick doctor that's what I'm going to do
And I went to a meeting with all the doctors in California and they were very limited in their scope
Practice there at the time
Because
The laws weren't open
There and I went to this meeting and it was like April
I was moving to Seattle in
July of this is like
This is
The year 2000
Mm okay
So I was three months away from moving to Seattle I was thrilled to death I got into
The school I went to this meeting with all these
You know naturopaths that has been naturopaths for 20 years
And this meeting
Scared the living
Why because
All of these p
People
We're passionate
But because the state of California didn't allow them to really practice their scope of Medicine
Because the the laws limited them
It just look like a giant struggle
Frustrating
To be able to have a degree in something and not
Gilda really do it
And then I went back to Colorado over Memorial Day weekend visit one of my dearest and oldest friend
And
I went hiking
I was just
Kind of eating a trail mix and thinking of food and raw foods and
Thinking about moving to Seattle and all of a sudden I'm on this mountain and this light bulb goes off for me
And I say
Why isn't somebody made
Fruit nuts and spices like something very
Just pure simple
Real foods
What is portable inconvenience
But it tastes indulgently
You shouldn't be eating
Like junk junk food I mean
I don't know that day at that moment it was like the surge of energy I got I could feel the
Excitement over an idea it's not like I hadn't had ideas before I mean people are walking around everyday with ideas
But for whatever reason it that day in that time and all those little experiences that built up
I just felt it
So what you do did you like run home and and an insert like writing things down or drawing pictures
Or do you just kind of mullet over throat for a while so I ran on the mountain
Can I start writing down ideas and then when we got back to Denver
But how can I take fruit nuts and spices and and turn them into something really exciting and I would
Get ideas from pies and cookies and cakes and I think okay how do I take cherry
Free pie and make it just in my Cuisinart basically a Roth raw unprocessed food
And make it taste like cherry pie or apple pie or banana bread
What have you
Did you immediately think
Hey I can turn this into a business or was it more like
Experiment and see
See if I can make this
Back
I did think
I think I can turn this into a business
I don't even know I think it was like a day later
And the next thing you know I'm thinking
I'm going to start
Business
And I'm going to do this in the next 3 months
I mean
Can I use that to think that you're going to start a business in 3 months
And I called my parents
And
Everybody thought it was
Completely out of my mind
Do they think it was like an early
Midlife crisis
I don't know what they thought
They just thought
We Center
You know
2 through private
High School
USC she's graduated she's 32 years old
Oh my God what's what's going on here
But it was actually great that
People question me
And wondered why I was doing what I was doing
And especially my family because it made me dig in more and
Recognize that
I really did want to do it
That I didn't need to get approval from anybody
But that I needed
I had found something that was important to me
And
I just could not be stopped
I arranged to stay with another friend of mine
Moved in with her and then I would
Take these concoctions that I would come up with him with using the Cuisinart
That I had for years by the way I've never actually used it I didn't even know how to use
And for some reason I
Got the Cuisinart out and
I would
Do what's called
Officially called a focus group I didn't even know the name
And I would
I created my own little survey and I would ask people why do you
You know what do we need energy bars for why do you like them why don't you like me
In all these things
People would sell them out
And then
I would
Give them my concoctions and say please tell me what you think
Is that how you developed your recipes
Yes
The interesting thing is the recipes came fairly
Ino because I would sample my friends and they would give me feedback
I really like the Cherry but I don't taste Cherry in every bite
And I would
Go back to the drawing board
Think I need to add
Mortuaries
You should taste cherry and everybody
You shouldn't be searching for it
Then it doesn't taste like cherry pie
Right
By the way how did you make
Like how did you
I think of Cherry Pie Liqueur
Is dried cherries and
What else
Well
So I would go to this natural food store
Because
Everything was less expensive there
And I would buy dried cherries and dried bananas and dried apples and
Then I would come up with the idea of cherry pie
Okay let me see if I can make cherry pie with these cherries
The dates of the almond
And they sold these tart unsweetened cherries I will never forget they were the best tasting thing because it actually
Real Cherry without a bunch of sugar in them yeah
And then
What is today larabar cherry pie
Is from these cherries
And you're in your kitchen
Which Cuisinart I'm thinking you put a bunch of updates and like
Nothing
Ball rolling on the queen
Sticky
Sticky ball of a mass
And then we would like to take it out with your hands and
Like I was rolling out with a rolling pin and then
Got to Qatar
And I would like I would cut it out
Just in your kitchen and I would make samples
I mean
Batch after batch after batch
And did you have any of your own any cash to get those sort of ask your parents help you out in that year while you were not
Dino World getting a salary how did you
Within
About a week I realized oh I had a little bit of money saved up
And then I saw it
Restart this business but I have to
Work I have
Job
You know
So
Whole Foods open their first store in Denver
At exactly the same time and I started seeing the building go up and they
In the neighborhood I grew up and actually
And
I thought
I'm going to get a job with
I'm going to work in their Nutrition department doing what I love
But I'm in a cigarette
The business and how it works
And use it as a learning opportunity
Almost like a paid internship in a sentence
Like incredibly
Prescient
It's really amazing planning reminds me of
We interview Ben & Jerry's
Is and a
People think that they were just
She's happy easy but they actually likes
Turn a street corner with a
Counter to count how many people pass the
The street corner when they were looking
Looking for a location for their Ben & Jerry's you like
That is a real
Planning moment you were you were sort of looking ahead and say all right with him to do this business
At least learn that
Whole Foods
Look up
Cashier Whole Foods
I got a job in the Nutrition department doing what I love which was working around
All the nutrition products
So I thought okay I'm enjoying myself but I'm also going to
I'll have a first
Hand view of what it's like
Have a product in their store and what does that mean
From the standpoint of
The vendor and it was one of the
Best decisions I ever made
So at what point
You think yourself
Okay this is going to be
Really
Is really going to be at
Big deal like this
I'm not sure I ever thought that
It was such a gradual progression so I first
You know got my recipes together and I would give them out to friends and then friends
Should say
I would buy that
And that
That little tidbit of
Asking me to buy it would make me feel
So excited
And motivated to get to the next place which was
How in the world am I demand
The facts are these
Yeah
Where am I going to get dates and almonds
And cherries
I didn't even know I'm buying them at a natural food grocery store in little baggies
What do I know about almonds and dates
And all that stuff
What do I know about manufacturing a
And at the time
I started questioning am I actually going to do this or should I just go to work for Whole Foods
If you want to do that
And just to clarify again how are you
Just like sort of funding The Spinners like buying the ingredients and stuff
Will you using your own money
Again I had a job at Whole Foods and then I had a credit card and were you nervous or anxious
I don't know I have moments where I would be really gung-ho and I would
Get all kinds of great information and a month would go by and I would find out about a piece of manufacturing equipment
Or just little things
And I would be so motivated and somebody want to buy bars and I'd make them a a batch of bars in these little ziplock bag
Eggs in a little Chinese takeout box
And I would
They would pay me like $22 or something for a box of bars and I would think how
And then another month to go by where I couldn't get anywhere I felt like my feet were stuck in the mud and
Then I would just get really unmotivated and nothing would happen and this went on for
The three-year period
Between my idea phase and when I actually launched
I'm trying to figure out how you
Maintained your
Optimism in confidence about all this
I mean
You're 32
Your divorce
And I imagine you probably have some emotional ups and downs of this
I don't like was part of you
Did you ever get the feeling that people look you in kind of think
Oh yeah that's Laura
Weird Science
A lot of people thought that
I mean
I would see people I went to HighSchool with and they would come into Whole Foods and
You know the dirt dirty climbing the ladder big jobs in finance and all kinds of things and they say oh
I didn't know you worked here and and people would see me and
Even if I had those moments with people were
I would
Notice the fact that I wasn't on that trajectory I finally just said this is your path in life
And you have to go for it and embrace it
Make it happen when we come back
Hella embrace the uncertainty and slowly slowly
Figured out how to turn her kitchen project
Into a business
Stay with us and Gyros and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your law
Long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open up free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this
Stream NPR
I'm Tyrone
2001 American is working at Whole Foods Denver into trying to
Figure out how to start a car
But you don't have a whole lot of money and she doesn't have any professional equipment
Or even a way to process and package her energy bar
So eventually I went to a packaging company in Denver and they weren't even taking me seriously and they just
Tell them you said Hey how do I make the sun on a bigger scale
What I said I need packaging and then they they look at me and go
They couldn't take me seriously didn't even have a business in that they give me a giant book that looked so tedious to read through
And they will read some of this and come back and we'll talk to you about packaging and then I would read enough that I would come back
Partially educated and then they
They started realizing I was serious about it
You want it you were looking for somebody to you
LED food-grade packaging package or bars
Yes she's in the Cuisinart I was trying to find a giant Cuisinart I was trying to
I didn't even know what that was called is called a vertical cutter mixer I learned and and then that led to
Some guy that they knew that had a piece of manufacturing equipment that lo-and-behold was the exact thing that I need
And so because I had the tenacity to ask
And I wasn't afraid
At a time when a lot of people question what I was doing
But I knew
That I needed to do it it it gave me the motivation to keep asking questions and to be curious
And
Tenacious and so I called the guy with a piece of equipment and I'd meet him and then I talked to this guy and he
He said well I'm not really using it if you want to use it you can
And
That's how it all kind of piece together
An individual and you have the name by that point
Larabars
Well no
It was a different name
So
I was going to name it Mana
And your Mana is your vital energy review
What
What happened to that name
Well the trademarking attorney
Called me at the eleventh hour
And we were getting ready to launch it was
The year 2002 summer
And she said I think there's going to be a problem
And she said there's actually manna bread manna
And
I think it could be confusingly similar
And I think you're going to do
I need to change the name
And I just
Thought
You're joking right I I don't I don't want to deal with this
That's right now
Naming is one of the hardest things
So
I got the phone call finally came to terms with the fact that that was going to have to happen
Friend said you know
Which color bar
You may come either your bars that sounds kind of
Like a good
It rains larabar do you know
I thought no way
I am not putting my name on this product I don't want my name in there
No way I'm not doing that
And then I just kind of sat with it
For a couple of weeks
And I finally thought
Larabar
I guess that could work
And if I thought you had raised some money
Help me write a business plan
I had a few friends and family interested
And
Between the renaming of
Larabar montamarta larabar and
Manufacturing issues
I was going to launch in Fall of 2002
And that got delayed until April of 2003
And during that time all of my interested friends and family
They because they got
Yeah it was just getting too late
Yeah
And all these people
Are starting to slowly back out because things are not happening I left working at Whole Foods
It's like mid 2002
And we're supposed to be launching that we don't
And everybody's backing out because nothing's
So
What you do
Well I had to
Had to raise the money
And my dad
Had decided he would like he wanted to get involved in the company
Get a great business background in the retail business
He knew operations and how to run a company
And he called me one day and he said
Hey
Would you
Would you want a business partner
And then how much money did you
You decide that you needed
There really wasn't an amount
It wasn't really his specific I think
I think we came up the amount because I had to print Packaging
And we had five flavors that I was launching with
Cashew cookie cake
Cashew cookie
Cherry pie apple pie
Banana bread and chocolate coconut chew
There was a minimum print run of all of those and I actually printed
At this company Minnesota
And I remember it costing somewhere around
You know a hundred 250
$2,000
And the manufacturing wasn't working out I've been to now for manufacturing places that did not work out
And I had a giant vertical cutter mixer in the back of my old Land Cruiser that I would haul around to each facility
Whether it was
Two hours away an hour away 2 hours away what have you and
Them installing a facility ideally you bought this thing
I borrowed it the giant the giant Cuisinart
Join quizizz 400lb it was on a
Pallet
And they got the forklift
Into the back of my Land Cruiser
So I was running around the state of Colorado trying to find somewhere to manufacture and when your
Noodle business nobody take me seriously
They didn't even know how to make your product you know they just want me to sit into what they're doing
And so I'm running around trying to find a place to manufacturing all the additional
Investors have now back
And I remember it was just like
A dark night in January and
My dad was getting discouraged
So I said to him you know it
I believe that this is going to work out I really have faith and I
Think the right people will come along
At the right time so
I started talking to some other friends about it friends in yoga class friends I worked with the Whole Foods and then all of a sudden
Holy group of people came that were just
Throwback
66 people
I said we'd love to invest money
And how much did you raise
What was the total of $150,000
150000 bucks and that was going to get you through
Some production and printing
More less and then a little bit extra just for operating cost
We were operating out of a tiny duplex in Denver so that overhead was
Extremely low
Manufacturing in the printing nail down but how did you
Then find the stores to
By and then
Set alarm
Well
Let me let me backtrack
To wear it when I was working at Whole Foods before I left
So one morning I was there because this is also
Part of what you're asking me
So I was on the early shift
At 8 a.m.
And one of the grocery guys he said
Lar the guy you need to meet
He's the regional buyer from Austin and he's
He's the guy he's coming in
You know this next week he's the guy you should talk
Talk to you about your car
So here I am I'm taking trash out one morning
It's about 8:15 in the morning
And
He walks across my path on the back dock
Of the store
Aspire
And he says oh hey how are you what's
What's new
He was being friendly he'd seen me before he didn't know who I was
And I
In that moment
I thought
This is my mom
And I said
Ojai you know
This is what's new I've been working on this
Product
Creating my own
Nutrition bar this and that and
He literally kind of dead stopped and started doing this
Lucius
I didn't really think it at me I didn't mean that and I'm I'd like to run away from
Free right now
He said well
I'm only here for two hours
GFC apples and he's just trying to
Get rid of me
And I said
Actually I do have some
I'm leaving in 2 hours I said I can go home and get them at it I mean I had an answer to everything
Is pride
Make me go away and I wasn't going away
And
He said okay bring me the samples and just cut it
Walked off
And so I
Send my coworker I have to go home right now to take my break
And so I gave it to him
And then
Like an hour later he's sitting there and he goes
Laura
This is the most Innovative product
I've tried
In years
Wow
And I'm standing there
I couldn't even believe my ears
You know I knew I made a great product
But he's a buyer he's a regional buyer
And he said when you are ready here's my card
He said give me a call let me know he said dot your eyes cross your t's
I will let you bring it into
Colorado store
And that was just such a motivational
I bet
I mean this is you know
Two years in
And I'm
Questioning what I'm doing and why I'm doing it I'm tired
I don't know what I'm doing and he says this and I think
Wow
Larabars enter the World ride
Yes
Finally have raised all the money we wanted to raise
And Manufacturing facility it was the fourth one
How many bars did you have to make for the first
Big puss
The first watch they didn't make the bars
We made the bars how many to make
500 Bars by hand
So I had rules of Packaging
Edit vertical cutter mixer essential as you in a bunch of like friends and
It was me my father and then any friend that would help
And it took us about 15 hours to make 500 bars because
I had to hand cut each
Rapper off of the rolls of film
Make the bar in a roll it out
With a p
With a rolling pin in a pizza cutter and then stuff it in the package in heat seal
This bars like Whole Foods and then
Like set up a table with the samples and and try to
227 people who are shopping list or
Yes so what I learned
Working at Whole Foods in the three years that I was there among other things was
When you sample products
For free the people
It's this kind of non risky trial
So in my mind
The marketing plan for me was to do that
Is to stand in the store
Talk to people educate them because what I was doing fruit and nut
And everybody was afraid of a piece of fruit at the
Did the whole carb thing
The Atkins thing was very big and everybody thought like eating a carrot was a very bad thing so I'm thinking what am I going to do with
Cherries and dates and then in the nuts have high fat in them that's good fat and
So there was a lot to explain but I had to make it
Digestible and simple for people
So my whole strategy was to
Get an each store and
As often as I could
Lunch and dinner
Demo my product cut it up and you were Manning the table and you were like hey you want to try to alarm bar
I was Manning the table in fact
I have pictures of me doing all the demo
And within two
2 weeks
Abingdon Whole Foods
Because one of my friends still work there
He's a liar you have
Have to go look at the movement chart upstairs and I said
What he said
Larabar is the top
Once your 5 top selling products in the entire store
Right now it out sells olive oil and water
You are one of the five
Best selling products
Insane
I mean I knew I knew in my heart
From all the feedback I've gotten that people were excited about what I was doing
But I also on the other hand knew that there was going to be challenges and
That was the I remember the day I got into the stores and I brought it after making those 500 Bars by hand and remember
Standing there and I was just
I was excited
Exhilarated anxious
Scared to death I mean it was like putting a piece of art
What do you think
I mean
What explains
Wyatt sold so well I can now you think about
How many people are paleo
Paleo and
People are doing Whole30 and all these and that's a raw food
Jalama mainstream now
Open 2003
You know that consist a really big
You know an answer
Some of these ingredients
We will survive
Comment a lot of people think I will I don't know
Knots in the fat
What
Explains how it took off so
It was simple
10 or less ingredients
You know what these ingredients are
Xiamen state
Cashews
Cinnamon I mean
Depends on the bar but
Cherries
You know what these things are and we
Been eating these
Items you know they're grown on trees we know what they are it's not a question and then they were made to taste
I blended them to taste like something you want to eat so I didn't feel like you had to sacrifice
So it's healthy but doesn't taste good I wanted to blend both and I wanted to make it something that you were so happy
Phoenix
2 3 4 5 ingredients the average
All right there
Like my all-time favorite
Kashi cookies me too
I love it it is cashews and dates it's so simple
And I think that's what resonated with people is people had never seen something like this before
Which is in that category such a simple idea
Complicated with simple ingredients even my dad asked me one day how come somebody else thought about this
I have no idea but I have
And I wanted
This is why we're doing this
Once you launch and Whole Foods and you realize that your top five
How quickly did
Did Whole Foods generally into the whole foods are all Whole Foods companies actually
It took a little time I mean it was over the next year
That that started to happen that wasn't as easy as it seemed
But it but it did come together
There was a journalist in Denver that works for the Denver Post and he wrote an article about me Memorial Day of 2000
And it's literally put
My company on the map
Just from that one article
I will always be grateful for that and
From that the industry paper
Caught it and then all these stories from California
Started calling and so I started launching in California
And
It just started to build how are you making the bars faster
We were doing anything and everything we could to me
My father started taking over manufacturing operations
And then we started
Just getting help
You have to hire
We are we are we are
And we were really riding a great wave
You are told you are getting a lot of
I mean we we were two years in we were
Basically a national brand now and show Revenue
You're too I want to say like
V.
Million-dollar
About 5 to get we were jumping
Crazy growth
Your whole life from light
Mm
To launch and then
In the middle of this song
2000-5000
Will you be working like crazy or by the time
You're hitting 5 to 7 billion in sales
Were you like kind of kicking back and your dad's room
Clinking champagne glasses and saying alright we can chill out a little bit
Never
The bigger we got the more I felt like
We can never rest on our laurels
I just felt
Like I had to work as hard as I could because I was leading our team and if I wasn't showing that I'm
Working hard
And showing up everyday then how could I ask people that did that for
You know we're building a company we can't say
Sorry we're not available until Friday you answer the phone anytime
Somebody calls about
Some of these big retailers would call
In the most random moments
And say you're interested I would like to bring you in can you come out and meet us at our national headquarters
That's right
So as you can see
Musicradar
Five seven
20 million
How many employees did you eventually hire
We had about
Sales and Mark
And then Manufacturing
I had about
Q
In mm
8 I guess
You are pro-choice
Starting in mid
Do you start to get approached by big
That were in
Starion talking
DaVinci salted
General Mills
And they were not the only company
Approach to you
They were not
The first phone call I got from a really large company with
And
Early 2000
5 so like a year-and-a-half in
Well they said hey
My
One of my investor friends who work
Work for us with answering the phone
And she said
Sandwich so from this company's on the phone and I went
What
It was
A big
Huge
Yeah
It's a competitor of General Mills and
I was in shock I didn't I
It never occurred to me
That I would
Sell my company or be approached by these big
Japanese
It wasn't in
Where my mind
And then it became a distraction in the middle of
Growing the company in running
And and so
You know my business partners and I had to decide
Really going to be serious entertaining
An offer or we just
Cuz it's just too much distraction
Yeah
So we finally decided in
2007 that
We would entertain
An offer if it was the right cup
If we feel like it
Who's the right company because we didn't
So we were very
You know financially stable company
For me I was starting to get
Really tired
And just
I was I was getting worn down I bet and Anna mean you would spend
Most of all of Russia Alder thirties
Really
Finding this out right and so
Presently you wanted to kind of
Focus on yourself a little bit
Yeah I just wanted a little relief and
And then we started to talk to some of these companies and then I met
With General Mills
And
I just needed the day I walked in that building and how they approached me and
The meeting we had I knew
I felt that there was a connection and authenticity
That if there were companies that were big that they would be
The great said I felt like they understood my brand and respected it and all the brands made hats have been around forever
So they're not just turning Brands out
Putting them on the shelf and getting rid of them
I just felt this energy
Almost nobody we had on the show
Michelle
I'm even thinks about money when they're starting their computers
Committed to
The products are packed is a passionate
Problem they want to solve
And then one day they find themselves with this money
Ginter financially
You start this thing
It's 3033 really
Tell 3484
You sell it and
All of a sudden you and your dad you have
This money
And this
Thing that you built
It took
A while
During the sale process I had to be
You know they had to do all of
Kind of the research of our company without us
Tell your employees and that was very nerve-wracking
So I had to have this very
Compartmentalised life for 3 months and I
Felt like I was going to have a nervous breakdown but
Cuz you don't know if it's going to come together until literally the day before
So that was very stressful.
For me exciting but also
Really unknown and then
We put a deal together and that was
The day before it turns
And
Then
All of a sudden I had to go from running the ship
Realizing that a whole nother team of people wanted
Needed to come in and do that and I needed to let them
Do that as a result
You know
I had a little boy I'm involved in his life I you know
I could just
Spend time pursuing other things important to me yeah and still keep my hand in the business and do the things that I love
Love for it
But without all the stress
Remember
Kate Kate and Andy Spade were on our show
I asked Kate Spade do you know does not has no ownership
Skip over
Anymore
She doesn't own the brand
So weird to just go to some city in the world
Kate Spade
Shopper walk around New York where she lives in
See her handbags
In her brain is her name her name above the door all of the city
And she said you know she told us
The story about how it's really cool.
See that and you must experience I mean
You doing any 7-Eleven or any
Whole Foods or Safeway or Trader Joe's there their they're Larabars
Right by the cash register
Everywhere
Your name on this
Honest brand
Honest products
Actually have
I was in
Target one day with my son
Is a couple of years ago and
He was six
What's the time
And
We were
Dino wandering around
Find what and then he saw the Larabars
And he said
Did you make all these
Sparse for the store
And I said
Indirectly yes
And it was the first time the light bulb enough for him about what I had done and what
Larb
But to see him in the store and it was
It was really exciting
Really positive
Antiemetic
Yes he has had a Snickers and he does love him
Yes
Laura how much
Of
Of what happened
Cusb
The black and how much
I mean I feel lucky that
I have opportunity in my life and that and that
I've surrounded myself with
People that
Care about me and
That you know along the way when people thought I was
Completely out of my mind for starting an energy bar
Comfy I remember thinking to myself
You know
You need to surround yourself with
People that believe in
Really important
And actually I remember thinking to myself I have more to lose
If I don't
Find out
Then I do
If I try this
And it doesn't work
And I'm so glad that
For whatever reason I had that in my mind because it compelled me to move forward and
Make Harbor happen
Lara merriken
Founder of larabar
By the way if you've ever struggled with how to pronounce larabar maybe you thought it was larabar
You can blame that umlaut above the A and Lara
You don't like the one using Haagen-Dazs or Motley Crue
Which serves no real purpose or function
Largest
Thought it looked pretty cool
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors synchrony
Synchrony has
The payment tools Technologies and insights
To help people realize their own unique ambition
Synchrony
What are you working forward to
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it
It's time now for how you built that and the Story begins about 25 years ago
Guinea in West Africa where Rahim Jolla was growing up
And what are the things you loved as a kid versus sweet injury
Pineapple juice called
Gingin is actually a really popular drink in that part of the world you know you go buy a snack on the side of the road you are
Nothing has when a woman that have a little cooler of of Ginger and that they sell along with it eventually.
Do ostriches like
Lemonade or iced tea or maybe milk to a lot of the kids
Early Childhood in Guinea was pretty great but around the time I turned fifteen the political situation
And the country became unstable
And unsafe
Sara Haines parents sent him and his brother to the US but
Raheem overstayed his Visa
And was eventually caught by immigration officials
And he ended up spending almost a year in detention
Honestly looking back at it it's now that I appreciate how difficult of a time you was
Young and too naive to understand how
How much trouble I was in that he was eventually able to get a green card
And then made enough money to go to Community College and then to Michigan State University
Whole time
He was missing home
His mom is friends and even then pineapple drink he loved as a kid
When I'm playing sports
When I'm running around and really hot
Summer that usually don't plan for Coke
I think about Ginger
Now you can find homemade pineapple ginger juice said some African restaurant but you can
It just walk into a chain store and buy that the shelf so maybe we should start
Making it and selling it and when they started doing research the timing seems perfect
What is that the traditional the Colts the pet scene
Aldi's of the carbonated artificially flavored
Brian I'll have been losing market share
The point where
They have all started to buy up smaller companies that are developing
Fresh organic
Products okay so a great opportunity for something like ginger but
As much as they love the stuff
They did not know how to make it
So they called up their mom and guinea and ask for the recipe fresh ginger
Corvettes pineapples
All fresh lemon juice
Vanilla and 2014 and the two brothers are living
New York City Gin Gin in Bahamas apartment and Raheem
They give out samples to customers at the bar where he works. Try some folks would find a ginger to be too spicy
I need to have a little too much lemon or too little lemon
Or the pineapple is not pronounced and also it is later after trial and error
Muhammad get the recipe exactly where they wanted
And they decide to launch gingin at an African Festival in Harlem
He was one of those moment to realize that we really want something everyone that came by the world from West Africa.
You are the product
Goodnight just buy one bottle you know I did buy
Poetry take a picture and send it to a friend
They sold out
All of their bottles and then a really big break
They wanted $25,000 a competition for budding entrepreneurs so they moved into an in
Industrial kitchen and eventually they pitch Ginger and Whole Foods and well we're definitely let missing from those
What's showing them because we knew Whole Food one adult to get a distributor and their distributor was interested in
Because they know we're talkin Horford
So we can update them against one another
And it worked out well in 2015
Ginger has made it into a five Whole Foods in about 100 independent stores they made about 3
$100,000 bill my profitable but they're having a great time or my God I'm having a blast
To find out more about Rahim and his company jen-jen Brothers
Check out our Facebook page
And of course if you want to tell us your story going to build. Npr.org we love hearing about the
Things your building and thanks so much for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or here
Previous episodes of How I built this NPR. Org please also subscribe to our show at apple pie
Podcast or however you get your podcast you can also write us that's HIV tea at NPR.
In a Twitter address is at how I built this was produced this week by REM teen Arab Louis
Also composed the music thanks also Geneva grandson as meshkinpour, Slough and Jeff Rogers
Turn Newark could see a guy Roz and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com