Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey everyone just want to let you know that we now have fewer than 100 tickets left for
How I built this Summit in October
Supported by American
Express
Don't miss out on your chance to learn from some of the world's most inspiring entrepreneurs
Here today
Partial list of who's coming
Joe gebbia Airbnb
Katrina Lake
Stitch fix Jenn Hyman rent
The runway
Lisa price of Carol's Daughter
The founders of method
Cleaning products
John Zimmer of Lyft
And many many other entrepreneurs
And mentor
You'll also get to meet hundreds of other innovators
Builders
People just like you
But there aren't many tickets left soap
Please do hurry go to npr.org
Summit
Get your tickets and hope to see you in San Francisco
I'm not one of those entrepreneurs that that thought he
He was going to be super successful and I was just trying to survive and I'm very
Very pessimistic unlike maybe some of the guys that you've done
You know the shows
Message Debbie.
Running PR
Is how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movement
A Steve Madden tote high-end shoe design and prices turn his name into a
3 billion dollar shoe rack
So when I was a kid if you want to wear brand names
And you couldn't afford the prices
Eudora Mervyn's or Marshalls or Ross and you look for things called
Irregular items
Maybe it was a pair of Guess jeans missing a zipper or an asprey shirt with one arm
Slightly longer than the other
It was no big deal because you still got the brand and you got it at Marshall's prices
But then starting in the early 1990s
Brands like H&M and Zara started to go Global and it meant that all of a sudden
Many more people had access to high fashion designs but at a much lower price
This is the way that Steve Madden not only tapped into but in a lot of ways
Pioneer
Especially when I came to shoes
With Steve maddens
You could all of a sudden by a pair of black stilettos for 70 bucks
Viciously like a $900 pair of Manolo Blahnik
Or a $60 pair of Lego like heels that
Borat knock off of
Thousand dollar Balenciaga
This was the genius of Steve Madden
He managed to carve out a very sweet spot between Nine West
Tan Christian Louboutin
This approach didn't come without consequences
The world of high fashion is an exclusive club and Steve Madden
Is largely unwelcome
Pedigree
Steve didn't Apprentice at one of the great fashion houses he didn't start out in Milan or Paris effect
Steve didn't even study design
And he's also kind of brash and the bit of a loud enough
In fact that he was willing to break the law to get ahead
Steve's been 2 and 1/2 years in prison for financial crimes
It's an experience that completely changed his life and we will get there but long before that
Secret weapon Long Island New York uses scrapy middle class
Papyrus
I was sort of a leader type charismatic sort of always pretty similar to the way I am now.
Small
A big mouth
And
Blue ambitious and
A little obnoxious probably will get in trouble at school
Yeah I always got
I had attention deficit disorder I didn't know what then yeah
Nobody nobody yeah yeah that was the sixties and
So
Didn't really talk about
But I couldn't sit still
Yeah and you should say
I had shpilkes
So school is not your your Forte
No
The only difference is that I was
Rosarita
So and I loved history
And I used to love to read about the Mughal
You know what that was I was obsessed with summary I was drawn to this thing about
Louie B Mayer and
Samuel Goldwyn and these great entrepreneurs that
I mean it's a very young man
It was like
Drawn to it
DIY
I don't know why I mean you know I was I guess it was the
The intersection
I've art and commerce
Yeah it was very interesting to me
And still is
And those guys came from nothing
Yeah and they were artists but they were businessmen so is that kind of thing
Yeah
Your dad's in textile business voice
Just address it was your dad
Entrepreneurial did he have that kind of
Mind yes my dad was but you know he grew up in the depression
And you know he was very limited
Filled with fear
Because he had seen so much poverty
So his he sort capped is upside
He wasn't a great mistake but he was a smart man he was a businessman
But it never really made the big bucks
Because he was very safe
Which in a way I admire
Because he stayed in
It's easy to criticize people like that
You know but he was always provided we weren't there
We were right in the middle I mean we weren't
Yeah Rich or anything but
We weren't the poorest but you said you know
People got a 10 speed bike
And they got Schwinn
I never got a Schwinn
You want to be the kind of person who could
Buy that stuff one day
I did I always did
You always wanted to fly first class you know
Like I'd be riding in coach
You know I was like
Get me in the front of this plane without anything
Working at a shoe
Shoe store NH
Why work in a shoe store
In high school
Yeah the neighborhood sort of cool
Shoe store the old it
The guy that
Started the store
I went to high school with my brother John
So with a job it wasn't like hey I want to go working shoes with
A job fell into it
Yeah but I fell in love with
Would you follow up with
So it's hard to explain but
At that moment in the shoe business you know it was a very exciting time because
This is like the
Early to mid-seventies like 74
Before I even started platform shoes were very big
For men
It was just very interesting
You know
I was into it
I was into the
The creative
Sort of
Vibe of the whole thing what do you remember about working in that store
I remember working
Very hard
Very motivated even at a young age
And what's that I mean when you were there was were you thinking
Is this is me this is my calling or was it more like I like selling stuff
I love selling stuff
I do but I also like creating stuff
And I like creating stuff to sell
It's always been sort of a course with a philosophy of mind
I've never been like oh that's creative but you know
Nobody wants to buy it
And then on the other hand you know just to
Cell without any
Kind of creativity is boring to me too
So you are working at 6 here in the store the stores by the way is called Toulouse
And what
This great guy
His name is Lance Ruben and I really most of what I know
I got from the sky you were 16 and he was in his
Yeah and the thing about this guy was so interesting because he was up
A young man
Was successful in creative
And I never saw that usually the people that had
But I thought of his business and we're like my father
Yeah they build the railroad and they were those long coats with the hats
Macdon Draper
Building with landscape artist and designer shoes
And also the wholesalers that sold him
Would be asking him for input on designs
Yeah cuz he was an up-and-comer you know like a young gun
So you are a high school student working at the shoe store but you have plans to go to college right you were going to go to college
I went to University of Miami
In Florida
To study with study
Golf and Sun tans
I mean I love
Learning
But it was I was on my own and it was
Too much how long do you last there
It's a bit of a blur but I think it was about 18 months and it wasn't
It wasn't for me my dad
Did me the biggest favor by pulling me out of school
When I say pulled me out of school he refused to pay
Another $0.50
Bring me to fool around in college so I went to work he went back to it to Long Island
I went back to back to a to a shoe store went to work for another shoe store and shoes because you had
Screens doing that experience so
Was kind of a famous story
Long Island call Jill door
Which most people know in New York
So you are and there you are also a sales guy
Just dealing with customers in the store
Yeah I was just a sales guy on the
Floor
Didn't say you're out of you serve a College Dropout you're working at this shoe store selling shoes and
I don't what was your dad or your mom was a saying
Steve what are you you're not working a shoe story
Pro-life do they say that at all today can just leave you alone
There are people that said that to me
Guys my own age
Making fun of me for working in the shoe store for sure
Yeah my father did not make fun of me
My father recognized that
Good hard work was good
To you you work in a shoe store and and I guess a certain point you go to
Tri-Cities New York City
The guy that owns loose Lance
Open up a wholesale company called LJ Simone
And he calls you out of the blue yes
Pretty much yeah
And he says come to work I'm cell
That's what I did
Sick a little wholesale company
Yeah and what happened was I went to work there and we blew it up man how did you blow it up
Like boom
We made it nice company out of
And what he was sourcing shoes from Shoe factories and then what year he was designing the shoes and I was selling
So he would design them
They would be made
And then you would go from door to door how to
Design shoes
Well you know this certain tricks of the trade and knowing what people like in
Working
The different Construction
It was just a few guys involved
But you know I was wondering
I was at the beginning and
It got very successful
We sell to Macy's and
Department stores
Resulted
The Bootlegger I don't know if anybody's from wash I don't know anybody
Which country
What's at that point where you you start to
Think about maybe doing this for yourself or did you think
This is great I'm going to keep them red
This is Eminem
Ride the train
You know what some point I thought about doing it for
For myself I was very happy there
You know but at some point I thought
You know I could do this
When you were working for him how much money would it make
I would say they were doing Maybe
40 million a year
Which is like big
Maybe something like
Yeah yeah
And so what happened why did you leave
You know I had taken it as far as I could
And
I just didn't want to have a boss any
It was just time
You know it's ready for me to
Soda chart my own course
And I was like 30
You were so you were there for a long time
I was at 4:31
And just it just because at this point you are single not married no kids
Best single pretty well
By Lance
Replied get making a decent living
I was I made a lot of money
In a relative
And then you were worried at all about risking
Risking all that
I'm still worried about
I was I'm a worrier you know I'm a worrier
Yes but I just wanted to do it on my own
Yeah
This was also a mean is Cornel Wilde
Time Miami you were
Do drinking heavily you were I was
Started using drugs
And drinking
House pretty much
Pretty inebriated most of my 20s
Alcoholic hits bottom there's another level of bottom to go
So yeah it was pretty bad well you know I could tell you
A lot of stories about it
But basically I couldn't stop and you know I was embarrassing myself and it was starting to affect
My work and
How to stop
Or die drugs and drink
Yes
Cocaine everything
I would work you know what went iwerks
At work work work and then get
Sound at night in a hammock
Because you were working so hard it was just like the thing you did you just yeah I thought you deserved it or
You could justify some but
When when did you how did you how did you get out that I had some friends
You know that pointed me towards a place where I could get some
Did you go to AA or did you go to a clinic
And I helped
Save my life well yeah
After you recover that
That you
Started Steve Madden
Yeah I was sober when I started Steve Madden
That man was just a mirror
You got started I was got sober I started this company
And you know my life completely changed
And when you started the company did you
Did you the cash to
To do exit to halacha
You know why
Scrape together a little money
Basically now
Iran money
And what was that what was the idea what was the
The first
I gave you the idea was basically do the same thing design and sell yours exactly the same
Lucifer show
My first shoe
Was a clogged
What is a backless
Clogged
And who did you think would be your
That's a very good question
The time
Ghetto
I would say would be my contemporary she knows I was like 32 you know
2330 woman
Yeah I would say
Cuz I didn't really think about it I just wanted to make shoes
It wasn't something that I thought what happened was
I ended up making shoes for the Gen X cusp
Custom Alexa be people around
Today
Right after I guess that's right after the Baby Boomers
Yeah and I discovered this Market
By accident
It was it they were very El Cerro
Yeah basically we stepped into that at Steve Madden
And how many did you make
Show
Udo the way it was you know we made it we made some shoes and
We just got this
Fabulous
Reaction
But not from the people I thought I was going to get a reaction from which would my contemporaries which was from
Younger kid
I would like the phone was ringing
Where you get that shoe and all that stuff
We knew that something was going on
So that's the track that we went on when you decided to
Start Steve Madden
Did you have an office where you working at if you're not worked in a shoe factory in Brooklyn
And and you work with them
And then you made I guess
She was and then what did you do did you go
To your former
Contacts that you had from Macy's and
Anybody that carry shoes ISO
And then I would go to the National shows and sell them all over the country
Elect first
In the first year 1990
Like you would go to stores and they would take
Compare with your you go with your
Sample case
And
You'd like your shoes out of people would buy them
And that was it
Soap
What was happening
Was
The market that I was selling to everybody in the shoe business walked away from
The teenagers you know and stuff like that but Young
And
Choose a different generation
Until they had their own thing their own music in their own
Style
We just tapped into that whole thing
And this was a market explain some of the time that was
Abandoned by Moshe Nine West
It was a company called Nine West it was dominating the industry but there was Nike and Reebok
But nobody was like making like funky little shoes it was kind of a throwback to the 70s
You know from that other are so I kind of brought that back
Can I was just in the right place
At the right time
Were they designed to be
Like
Cool but also
Affordable inexpensive
I've always been sort of democratic with my shoes
Do you remember
How many
How much revenue did in in the first year
I probably did
I don't know
500000 is pretty good pretty good
And you named it Steve Madden because
Seem like the obvious
It seems like an easy name
Did you ever think about using a cup
French name lookup European sounding
The first couple of shoes with gold soulier
Alright
Larry gold like the French word for slipper
I'm so you know there was some dispute about that brand
Well maybe I just wanted to call and see bad and I can't remember but
I switched it
Pretty quickly
Because you work there was one guy that called me of how dare you
I bought you lie I don't want Steve Madden who Do You Think You Are
Yeah I was telling a guy still he still in the shoe business
And I was taught
Alright so you got this
Pretty good
Business going
And Year One
What are you thinking are you thinking okay I mean did you have Ambitions at that point already to make this into something here
So when America started the business
And you know I just
That really don't have much money I'm just so
Working hand to mouth
And
A friend of mine who I grew up with went to work for this brokerage firm
And they were raising money for small company this is Donnie porush
Danny Park
And
600 Grand and then we'll get you
6 million looking for a brokerage
And he said to you hey you need to expand your money
I've known you my whole life
What would you do if you got 600 thousand
Can a hundred thousand is like 600 million
Yeah. Only will I get to 600 Grand
But I'm going to get you six million dollars when I take you public
And I laughed at him
You know because
I probably have $30,000 in my
Hot to my name
And so of course you're like what 3330
Something like that yeah 600000 bucks
That's right so right so Danny
Help you go pee and he helped me go public in his firm wisco Stratton Oakmont
A very famous name for anybody who's seen The Wolf of Wall Street
My name is Jordan Belfort
Do you write turn 26 I need 49 million dollars that would really piss me off
3 shy of a million a week
Call me pump and dump
And they were basically
It's a really crappy companies
Toys R Us
And so they basically we're going to do this
Steve Madden Wright
They wanted to do it Steve Madden I was the perfect guy for them
Because
I had a company and do was small and
They could do there
Thing with it
You know fit the profile
It always you don't know me
My name is Steve Madden
Now we know who you are
Amazon The Box
Country Buffet
So that scene
With me talking in front of them it was very Act
We should explain
You go up
In front of all these
He's like traders in the spoils about my shoes thinking that they were
Taylor leiby interested
Tell me what they really were and I was just a piece of
It's just a piece of paper and a piece of meat
Which is really the truth
It's a fat girl shoe believe it or not though the Marilu is actually
Same as the Mary Jane but it's black leather I want to just
To digress for a moment
Because
People listening to this
Budding entrepreneurs
I'm not one of those entrepreneurs that
That thought he was going to be
Super successful
You know I was just trying to survive
And I'm very negative
Very past
Unlike maybe some of the guys that you've done
You know the shows yet
I think I'm going out of business every other day
So it's at that time
This is like 93 I guess when
92-93 so we went public
What and how did the stocks do
Well they were totally manipulated the stocks they went up
And if that was a
It was a classic pump-and-dump
And only Steve Madden was a real comp
Yeah sure if you kept that stop
You would make on that day in 1993
And you own 10000 shares
I haven't really done the math but I think you would be worth
A lot of millions and millions of dollars today
To The Stratton sell the company goes public strength
Public yeah all of a sudden it raises how much money for you
I think the public offering was about 7 million bucks
Wow so we use it
I took it and then
Barry
Short
Period of time from
A half a million bucks I was doing 40 million
50 mil
And what is that within 36 months
You get all this cash from from the initial public offering
Did you ask any questions
I mean
These guys were totally breaking the law.
At that point they were artificially inflating your stock
Are you suspicious at all about Danny in about
Did you think
Knew it was too good
Yeah I knew it
So
We know I lied
To myself
And I told myself that it was a gray area
You know the trading in these stocks and the
Flipping they would sell me the stocks and I would sell them back to them
Just demands.
Show
I lied to my son
You know everybody's doing it
You know like that but I knew in my heart
But it was illegal and I was wrong
Who's apart of it
Grilling that you are getting away with it
Well making that much money is certainly throwing
Fisher
But damn
I wish
I hadn't done it
And
But you know more than wishing I had done it because that's
Superman empty thing to say
I wish that I didn't feel compelled
I wish that I didn't have that feeling that money was every
Because it's not
It's not every
So I was greedy and foolish
Yes I'm trying to figure out who you are
This creative guy
Yahoo create shoes you design shoes
And you got a really successful and growing business
And then on the side you're doing this
These weird stock trades that
You are shady and
Slim Shady ultimately illegal
Why would you even do that stuff on the side and Lori have the creativity in the business
Get out
You just get caught up
Just get caught up
In this thing
But it is certain point it can't be about money it has to be about fulfillment and
Weren't you fulfilled by just the creation of your shoes and and seeing your shoes out in the world
Well that's a very heavy question
How one gets fulfilled
I'm still grappling with that today
You know
So there are moments
But I'm very fulfilled do you know
And there are moments when I'm not
I was raised to think that money was everything
You know
Money is the center of the universe
And if that's what you're
Core belief is
You know you'll do anything
And you will
Break the law
You know
Second money is like a drug
And
We got in trouble in
In just a minute has Steve Madden pays and pays hard for his crimes and eventually
How he comes back to the company he started
To make it even bigger stay with us you listening to how I built this
NPR
Support for this podcast and the following message come from Delta
Delta flies to 300 cities around the world
Best 300 cities where many people do the same things you do
That's 300 cities where people in those 300 cities think they're the only ones
To know about that one place
And 300 cities where people miss someone
And one of Delta's other 299c
Delta isn't flying to 300 cities merely to bring people to go
But to show that we're not that far apart in the first
Delta
Keep climbing
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
Sense and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable Leo
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Hits 2002
And after being implicated in a stock manipulations game
Steve Madden
Goes on trial he's convicted
And sentenced to three and a half years in prison
In the space of just a few years
He goes from being one of the most
Famous and successful shoe designers in America
Just sitting in a
Prison cell
What you think do you think I'm finished my life is
Yeah pretty much
You know I thought
I thought I was cutting my Goose was cooked
Butts
I did have the sense that I could get through it
Were there people who knew you didn't like you
TWRP
Feeling like that he got his comeuppance osher
Yeah it made such a success in the shoe business
I was a bit of a rebel so now people going to Hawk
See
That's what happens when you do that
Where did you work where you were sent to a minimum security prison
What they call a camp
And what was your boys are living
Lived in a barracks
It was like a
Military
Make your own room
I live in a cube
Live in a cube
And that with another guy
Or two
How did you pass the time
Well that a lot
Exercise a lot
And I took some classes when I was there
Did you when you got there and you knew that you were going to be there for at least
Are you there for 31 months but but
6 year sentence
31 month
Did you ever
Get depressed if you're thinking
I don't know how I'm going to stay here for 30 minutes
Yeah my first night I looked up at
The ceiling
And I said how the heck am I going to do this
How am I going to get through this
Did it go by faster than you expected
It seemed like 31 years
Wow Shannon but
I quickly
Ascertained early on that whining and
Moaning would not do me any good
And running around saying I was innocent would not do me any good
So I would try to get through this
Try to
Better myself
If it sounds corny but
Exercising breed
Learning
You know
That kind of thing
So I did
When you went to jail
Steve Madden is doing very well right
When I went to jail it was doing well
Were you worried about the brand
But the name your name was the brand that store at Great people working for me I was
I was really worried about surviving
And getting through it
You personally or company
The person I was really more
Focused on getting through that experience
Did you think that you would
Ever go back to Steve Madden company built
Yeah
So you had that Horizon
Do you think this is a really weird question for accuracy
To hear your take on it
If you could trade
The time you were in prison
For being a continuing on and not not not having that experience
Would you
Would you do it or or do you think that
Strangely enough.
The time being incarcerated was
Important for your development as a person
Yeah that's exactly right II
Very big believer in you know Destiny and your path and all that corny stuff I just believe it
Viscerally
So
I'm so grateful for my life
After prison
America great girl
I had great kids
I don't know that I would have had children had I not gone to prison
So
I regret some of my choices
You know shortcuts that I took or
You know thinking that money was the most important thing I regret decisions like that
But I don't regret a day in prison
An amazing experience
Very painful
I mean the only thing I can describe try to describe it to people
Your heart gets broke every day
Yeah when you're in prison heart breaks every day the living in prison
It's not as terrible as one might think
But
You know your heart's breaking cuz you're not with the people you love
That that's the difficult part of prison
It sounds like you became a much more empathetic
Person
When you are there
Saw
People who unlike you who did not grow up like
Came from different backgrounds
Who had who kind of ended up there because of circumstance
But particularly the
The African American Experience really
Touched me
And
Young man dealing drugs
Getting
Huge sentences
Unfair drug laws that really were biased against black people
So that was
You know to see
Problems in those communities talk to
Young black man and
It's very complicated.
You know issue
Yeah
Yeah I just think
I'll give you an example
Is a little thing
Did you know
When I grew up
I went to
Grade school in the six
It's right
We we we learned that Robert E Lee was a kindly gentleman
He was called a hero like he left
He defended his homeland of Virginia
And that's just that way that's just
Complete
Racism
But we didn't realize it's the subtle form of race
So that's the kind of thing that
You know those kind of feelings
Stuff that came up in prison do you know that kind of
That learned and read more about it
Okay so you I think you get out again in 2005
Do you remember the day that that you were released
You know that such an interesting question because
I don't really
Is a bit of a blur
I think of it now
I thought about that day when I was away for so long
What it was going to be like
And I can't remember it
I really can't
My wife picked me up
We should mention that while you were in prison you fell in love yes
Yeah and she pick me up he was an employee when I know that we had sushi
And I just
I just can't remember was so
It was such a blur
It was so much coming at me
You know when you're locked up
After 30 months
You know everything is like amazing
Like slice of pizza is like
Oh my God like this is the greatest thing ever
So you
You're out
Your back
Back in in society baggage
Freedom
Back how long does it take you to get to address
To having control of your own schedule your day today schedule
Well there's a transition. You go into a halfway house but I was fortunate cuz I had a job
And I came right back to work so
Is an amazing time
Lose your position when you came back to to your company
The same position I'm in today what is the founder
Which is the
Chief cheerleader
We have fabulous people running Steve Madden
I wasn't a great CEO
Why weren't you a great CEO
You know I'm just
Not detail oriented
And
My talent is suited and other things you know
When did you when did you realize that you were not cut out to be a CEO
For what it's the pits of small you can kind of be the CEO so you know everybody
You live and breathe and then you could be a CEO
Because you touch everything
But then a business kiddo what's a business gets past a certain
Point
You know it's impossible for someone like me
To to do that job
In 2005
I think within the four years
Steve Madden net revenue of
Of over half a billion dollars
So what happened in that time with the company grow
What was the strategy that
Allowed you to grow so much
So our goal was to
You don't make great shoes and
You know I think that that
Kind of like 1/2 at the end of the day
The marketing was in Super
Fantastic it was just great shoes
Great prices great value and
You know I think that we just wore everybody out
With that you know more people are giving us they're open to buy
And we open more stores you know anything in our internet business exploded
But the big thing about Steve Madden I have to say and I've said this many times
Was the people it's the madness that I've hired so many great people
It starts with recognizing my own limitations
I'm weak at that so when I get somebody that can do that for me
And
Yeah that's really the story its people
So you come you come back to the company and
Yuan
By the way
You had
Funny Money
You could have sold your shares walked away very rich man
And just kind of
I don't know done something else are focused on
Yourself why why did you want to go back to
The company actually it's if that's an eternal
I grapple with that all the time
So I love the idea
Making shoes
The people want to buy and I love seeing my shoes being worn
And I just love all of it and I love making money
Let me be clear about that I love it I love the whole thing because you don't need more of it so what do you love about it
Well
Okay that's a good these are great questions
And I want to ask other entrepreneurs rather
People like so how do you stay motivated you know that's all you've got
You know a few dollars in the bank and you know that
Use the rent is paid and all of that
So what keeps you going
I want to ask Haim Saban some more question you know how to spot is right the median mobile
Yes
Screw up like dirt poor and Alexandria Egypt became from boudoir
Right and
What what's the big deal cuz he was waiting to sell
His company to Disney for
I don't know
More than a billion
Yeah
And I said
No I want you take 500
Million
I forgot to
He said it wasn't worth that I want to see I want to be a billionaire
And it wasn't about the actual dollar amount
It was
For him it was a mark
It was like a musical Mark you could say okay I've reached this point
And then I can meet you this
And then it's this point and it
It's like a demarcation point of success
Yeah it's a heavy question
It really is
But of course it's a luxury that people with money have to be able to talk about this stuff
You know there's somebody
Out there that
Listen to this
You know they've got to pay their rent next Friday in the same listen to this
Idiot talking about
You know what I agree with them
I know but but it's something I think about a great deal
Because
I feel so good if I have had a great day at work
Where I'm inspiring and inspired
At the same time
It's such an amazing feeling there's no amount of money that can replicate
Yeah
So I guess that's what I want
You know Inspire and be inspired
What was the last shoe that you designed to say curiosity
The last shoe I designed was last week
Sneaker with studs
You designed a shoe last week
Yeah we have a factory in
Outside the East River in Manhattan
But I'm always fiddling with shoes and
Thinking about shoes
Course I have a great team that does most of the work and I take most of the credit now
You don't
Seemed to be a super obsessed over your own
Personal style you like you got the baseball cap bingo in Endicott.
But you're not wearing like
Designer like Runway outfits everyday
I look like a garage mechanic Sundays
I'm at Runway
Yeah I wear t-shirts and jeans I'm very lucky that's why I don't take that
For granted I'm blessed that I'm
The ability to wear
But I scream t-shirt everyday
Did you ever feel like I don't know like some of these
Fashion folks Conover snobby about you that they
I know they don't let you into their Club cuz you weren't from you know Milan or
Didn't go to art school or
Yeah you wear baseball caps in the
And you were so kind
Kicking their butts with with with you
Shoes that were
LeFrak the price
Did you make that disappear
There was
Big time
It's not so much anymore
Used to bug you
Yeah but
Bug me a lot
You know I will or I would going to a high-end department store like a Barney's
And
Steve Madden
People working in the Star Wars Steve Madden drive me crazy
Yeah
That happened so many times
And still to this day there's a bit of that going on
It's frustrating
But it with you step away from the balcony like me looking at this I would be like
Who cares can you crush them all like so big deal
Well I once was upset because
They put Puff Daddy in the cfda
The CFT is a club for what
Something for designers at FDA
Very very posh
Empty put coffee in there I thought to myself coffee
Are you in there
I'm not there when you are even allowed in the building
They would say well you copy Pinot Blanc siaga or whatever it is
You know I'm weak
We definitely are aware of expensive shoes that are out
Some ways a lot of these
These hide and designers
Connect if you could make the case that
The younger crowd
Will enter the market by buying Steve Madden shoes and then there's this aspirational to buy
It's a gateway drug if shoes Steve Madden
You're not buying
Louboutins manolas without starting with Steve Madden
Salmonella should give me
Tons of love for that
I reach much many more people than him
To think that there will be a point where you are
Acknowledged by your peers
Is it important to you
I'm acknowledged by a lot of people
Probably too much
You know young men coming up really know
And identify with the struggle in the grind and
What I've done so I think there's a difference
Kind of respect going on
Not what I had thought but another kind of respect and I feel it all the time and I'm walking down the street people shout out
How to me
You know it's
It's the real thing
How much
Of your success do you think is because of
Your skill and intelligence hard work and how much of it is
Because of lack
I think a lot of it is luck
I do I think
My own sort of philosophy is
That the window of opportunity
Opens
For you several times in life for 1
And I think the intelligence
Comes from
Knowing when that window
Is open
And
You know being able to jump through that window
Because you can have all the talent in the world but sometimes the window is just not open
Besides the stuff that lands you in prison what
Other mistakes that you made
Early in in the business that you would have done differently knowing what you know now
Let me just say that
Mistakes can be a very good thing
You know so there were some mistakes that we made that we did so many great things
And the thing about that is
If you start getting gunshot
I stopped being afraid to make a mistake
You'll never have the brilliant ideas you never have the big ideas
You know if you just try to hit the safe
The safe ones
You know then you're
You're doomed
I feel like
So you need to make mistakes
You need to make mistakes you need
You need to go
Cuz if you're not goofing a few times it means you're not reaching
Steve Madden
Sounder
Steve Madden shoes
The company's market cap recently hit more than three
Billion dollars
The highest level ever reached
How many How many pairs of shoes do to you actually own
I don't know why she's what the fanciest Brandy what you are
Ione Johnston & Murphy
Johnston & Murphy shoes they're the greatest yeah my dad word
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
If you're ready to start your new business
Make it stand out with a new website from Squarespace
Visit squarespace.com building
For a free trial
Then use offer code build it
To save 10%
Your first purchase
Set a website or domain
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that and say story starts back into
2002 Chris dimino was a design student working on a
Class project assignment was to repurpose a typewriter
Given that it's now obsolete ideas
Chris spot and old smith-corona typewriter at a garage sale
Staring at it for a while ago so hungry at the time but I think just staring at a long enough it eventually came to me that this looks like a
Waffle to me
And a few seconds later and then I thought okay
If I use this as the base
Have another thing on top and it would be sort of like an old waffle maker
Make a waffle iron out of typewriter Keys instead of the typical cast iron grid
So it went to Salvation Army and picked up this old waffle iron for 7 Bucks
And then I basically rip the keys off of the typewriter
Off of that old smith-corona
Use them to make
Plastic mold and they put the mold into the waffle iron so
It looks like you could make a waffle in the shape of a keyboard but
This thing was just for show it looked incredible but it didn't have a heating element so
Couldn't make anything
Play the story might have ended their except Chris posted a picture of this
Websites people started sharing it and people started emailing me about it and like 2 years later at 7
Clean hits on that page in particular
And of course a lot of people were asking Chris
Where can I buy this thing
The more the people ask the more I ask myself
Hey could I do this
It was almost like
Universe is like you're going to make this
And people don't like it
Okay but this pose a problem
How to make a real waffle iron
Well for starters Chris decided to give his original idea of pillow makeover
And go with the
Computer keyboard instead is basically the standard
Five rows of
Keys
Escape key is aliki the spacebar
And then put it into an existing mold for an electric waffle iron
But then he discovered that most waffles
They're pretty square and he couldn't find an electric waffle maker that had that long
Angular base he needed
So then he's okay
I'll just make the bass myself but it turns out
That wasn't going to work either
It's a really steep
Cliff
Price wise
To get into that game
Yep
Certifications in
Not to mention just a manufacturing tooling so
It always scared me away from
Going that way soon. Maybe I shouldn't even bother trying to make an electric waffle iron
Maybe I can just do one that sits in a stovetop no electronics no
I ended up making one real aluminum version carved out of a block of aluminum
Super-heavy having dancing pic
Guy poured battering
And lo and behold on the first try and made a very very good waffle
He launched a Kickstarter campaign and people were really into it
And they're like oh my God finally you're making it now I can't believe you're finally making it
Chris raised over $60,000 on Kickstarter
And with that money he was able to find a factory in China that was willing to make the waffle iron and yes
If you look at his video the thing definitely does make waffles in the shape of a computer keyboard
Alright design this so that
With all the keys there it sort of has parts that are thick
And then basically between the keys were thinner so my hope is that those be sort of crispy and Airy and then
The other parts of these or more dancing
You need to find ways to have fun with it with toppings and putting berries in the keys Chris Costas
Products what else did keyboard waffle iron
The past three years he's sold 7000 of them mostly on Amazon
But for now
He still got his day job as a graphic designer
If you want to find out more about the keyboard waffle iron or here
Previous episodes had to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell
Your story go to build. Npr.org we love
Hearing what you're building and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe at Apple podcast or wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us at Hy-Vee tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet it's at Howard
Our show is produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis who also composed the music thanks also to newer coetzee
Cramps osmoconformer and Jeff Rodgers
Our intern is JC Howard
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week