Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here and I got a random bit of trivia for you
A year after Jack Kerouac wrote on the road
Came out with the second book
Just called the Dharma bums
Intruders characters actually
Inspire the name of a real-life company
One character was Warby and the other was Parker
And the company is well
Yes
You're all about that and a lot more on this episode which originally ran back
We haven't told anyone that the site was lying if you didn't want to drive any traffic to it because we weren't sure
I get an order and then 10 minutes later we get another order
And then another order and another order and kind of go from there
Feeling of elatement to a crap
From NPR it's how I built this
Shellback innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movement since they built
Gyros and
Founders of Warby Parker tell the story of how they first and idea idea that disrupted the
The entire eyeglass industry in America
Andrew into a billion dollar company
So back in 2008 and Eagle Blumenthal and Dave gilboa arrived on the campus
Best of the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania
They were there to start business school and they met each other and two other students Andy Hunt and Jeff Raider the for them
Delmonico found Warby Parker but in 2008 at that time they didn't know that yet but they didn't
Know something that they all had in common was they were really frustrated with how I glasses worked
It's 10 from this thing that will most people probably experience at some point they kept
Using the glasses and Dave and back right before he started a business school at accidentally left his
Glasses on an airplane and it cost me $700
And I just can't justify the full-time student paying that much for a new pair of glasses
The new iPhone 3-g had come out that way tomorrow at the Apple Store paid $200 for and it did
All these magical things
And meanwhile
The technology behind a pair of glasses is 800 years old in it
Didn't make sense
And what you're like okay I've got this
This amazing iPhone this magical
Portal 2 all of you knowledge eyeglasses made out of
Plastic
Are like
Super expensive I was complaining to anyone that would listen about my glasses were so expensive and then and
Cat losing his glasses
And you was buying everything online but can figure out why you can buy new glasses online
Affectively sunglasses on my right because this like 2008 and
I mean by that point wasn't like it
Do you like selling things online
Brand new idea
Yeah and so
We kind of started this conversation where we are
Kind of frustrated by different
Pieces of the eyewear industry
And we knew that Neil had spent
A number of years
I'm working for an hour not profit and
And probably knew a lot more
About this and we did and so
We're on the computer lab one day
And that we start asking me all about
Question then
No pun intended that any color eyes are open that there was this massive Viber
What do you remember about that meeting in the
Computer lab me I will acordes
It was
Servite choir glasses so expensive then when I was
Working at nonprofit
Visionspring I've actually designed eyewear
And I would go to the factories
Mapreduce
Glasses and
So I knew a little bit about the optical industry
And it's dominated by a few very large companies
Is wonderful H's luxottica
Exotic has a market cap of
About 30 billion dollars
They
Jamon Oakley Ray-Ban Oliver Peoples
Persol and Arnett
They license almost every major fashion brand Under the Sun like Ralph
Florin and Chanel and Prada and Dolce & Gabbana
They also own a lot of the major
Retail chains like
LensCrafters in
Pearle Vision in Sunglass Hut
All those things that's crazy Sears Optical Target Optical
Persol Rayban
All owned by the same company
All in by the same company end they on the second largest vision insurance plan
In the country I met
So
You walk into a LensCrafters you don't realize that most of their selection
Card frames
That they've made
And the vision insurance
Music is all
So you do this
The brain exactly
So we just
Thought like a
Well now it's a lot clearer why glasses are so expensive
So we thought oh
Why not
God says I am
The light bulbs went off in
In all of our minds
And then later that night
Like you know when you have a feeling
Or just an ideal you're so excited about yes you have trouble sleeping
Exactly
It was that feeling
Things like 2 in the morning
Shut off an email
And then it like 201 Davis
Responded and 202 Jefferson an alien spotted in like we were all
Up thinking about
Next day
We decide hey
After class let's all get together and when she sat down at a bar right on 23rd and Walnut
Andover beer we're discussing this more
And
Should we do this
Should we really go after this and we also said yeah
How do you say
Business school and you were thinking what did you do
Play quite a business plan that you start looking for all of us we talked about how
Excited we were about this idea and he said well we're at business school to learn how to write a business what better way than to actually be
Ourselves so
We all decide to take the same class in entrepreneurship class
Without thought of that class is edible business plan and we spent the next several weeks
Really researching every element of our idea of getting
I'm a bunch of great insights from professors
Running a bunch of surveys standing for hours in different optical shops in and then that culminated in
40 page business plan
We entered the Wharton business plan competition and we got
Got eliminated in The semifinal round
They just kind of put a chip on her shoulder
Why are we sad okay well now we got something to prove and
At that point we felt really fast
Going to work
Taper Avenue
You still did not
Money I'm assuming
You didn't have a product
You didn't have a manufacturer so
Why were you guys
How are you even able to
Detest the idea
Yeah we talked to everyone
That will give us five minutes
That's about the idea initially we got a bunch of pushback
It said well gatea buying glasses online is
It's kind of strange to me
Kahoot
Basically all our friends in class
And a lot of people told us that
Creating a brand is hard enough
So is crating
E-commerce site
Like one of those but for us the magic
And creating a vertically integrated brand
I'm so behind in on this issue that we had to figure out
People can try on glasses
People are saying
Nobody's going to buy glasses online because
You got a touch of me to feel them
Exactly
Surreal moment of self-doubt
Journeys are always
These moments where you feel like it
Complete idiot
I this was like one of those challenges that
Really made us question
Should we continue to spend
Time time on this versus
Is the million other things that we could
Be doing at school
So how did you
Stinky to get over this
Problems of people
You know thinking they needed
To touch them to try them on
So we just thought a lot about how do we
Remove every obstacle
To purchasing
And the thought was well if we offer
Are free shipping that will encourage people to buy if we are
Offer free returns
That will also
Make it less risky for our customers
And that's
Should have led us to this other idea to do a home try-on program
So you guys decide
Let's send these
France people let them try
And they like them
They just send them back and we'll put the lenses in and that's it
Did you guys have any other problems that you
Anticipated
As you were thinking
True
Jetix other element
Was that we were trying to sell a product normally cost several hundred dollars
And
We were selling for
Less than on
Hundred dollars in so
There was inherent skepticism about the quality
Inside Wayside log
How do we just
Get as many of our glass
People's faces possum
Yeah and that's when
This light bulb
I'm trying program
How much really know
No company
I was offering
Until that time
Beside we just want to get
Product auntie
People's faces
White people by after work
So you guys wanted your glasses
Competition
Even less than a hundred bucks
How
How did you decide on the
Our initial thought was to sell glasses
For $45
We remember going into the head of the marketing department
That's office at Wharton
And we sit next to him
Slide the deck on his desk
Say hey
Where can I transform the optical industry
We're going to charge $45 for a $500 pair of glasses
How many kinds of sloths.
I said no I won't work
Black sweet you didn't even like retard act like every graph goes up and to the right
And he said
I'm sorry guys I first of all
Prices
Biggest indicator of quality
And it's just outside of the realm of believability that
You can sell a product
4/10
Surprise
So we walked out this meeting pretty deflated
But it led us
To investigate pricing a little further and
It showed us
That
Yes prices
Time indicator quality
There's a psychological barrier around $100
So one thought was she
We charge $99 and we thought that was too discounting and cheap at wework building an aspirational brand
So we actually settled on $95
Using just our instinct
Thinking that this doesn't sound cheap and that it looks deliberate and Visually looks
50 Cent
How did you guys
Come up with an a
Because it sounds like like an aristocrat from like you know
Northumberland
In England or something like Warby Parker
The hardest thing that we did in those early days was
Set 11 a.m. that all four of us like
Thank you still have our spreadsheet that over 2,000 names that we tested
On our very patient friends
Yeah
Too early Jack Kerouac characters
That data actually discovered when he went to the New York Public Library exhibit on Cadillac
And
To the characters wear Warby pepper
And Zack Parker
And that's a good thing
Military and now everybody that
I joints Warby Parker
On the first day on their desk together
Copy of Dharma bums
Come out with a few other goodies
That's near Blumenthal of Warby Parker after the break Neil and co-founder Dave gilboa
Removing that well-thought-out business plan
Paper and into the real world I'm guy Roz and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
8 things tour 2019 lead sponsor
How I built this
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
To understand that
Each business
Is as unique as a fingerprint
Barcode
Taylor's intelligent Insurance Solutions
Every business is very
Pacific need
Explain their 97% customer service
Get a quote
Purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance expert
Support also comes from wix.com
A web platform
For creating your own
Professional website
With wix
Whether it's your first time creating a website
Or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning template or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology
Powerful web page
Join Over 125 million people already using Wix to
To create their own websites
Gota wilx.com
To create yours today
So what will youku
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I'm sticking be open from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR on garage and Taylor show we've got Neil Blumenthal and Dave gilboa two of the founders of Warby
Parker
Come up with this idea and they thought it through and
Now
The only thing left
What's the exit
How much money did you guys
Raise initially.
And how did you do it
So the next thing about business school is that most people work
For a few years before going back to school and so
Collectively the four of us 2
Our life savings from
When we were working before school and invested into the business
We invested $120,000
Between the four of us
To get the business
Stop the ground
Yeah we work for year-and-a-half
Helping yourself salary we didn't have an office
We did win a couple of grams
From Morton to that that helped as well.
We were very Scrappy and
Famous bootstrap
Quite a while and we ended up
Launching a business and then when
Another
18 months
Before we
Raise our first round of funding
The Hedgehog
Ashley find the manufacturer to make the glass
Did you kneel to have contacts from
When you work at that
Nonprofit
Yeah
Wheel ever show all the relationships that I had then
To visit the factories
And we actually
Prepared
A PowerPoint
Because even though
This was going to be a vendor that we are
Buying from
But we have to sell them on our vision
And that we weren't.
Need serious and
How far to pay them
Forsyth Tech
What's the payment up front
Okay so you pay for these frames
That the manufacturer makes them
What did you even
2 with all those glasses
To remember getting
Boxes and boxes of these
Frames
Ship to
Our apartment and it was a doorman building the doorman had
No idea what to do it literally took us
A couple hours to load
Do all these runs
In the elevator
Into our apartment
Then stack all these
And then unpack them and we
Ourselves
Inspectah deck
Every single frame
Yeah and this was all the while
We were
Working today
Figure out
How are we going to watched
We basically
Need to start a business only ambassador
Free things
Our initial inventory
Our website
Handsome PR
Knowing that you only have
One shot
Should have launched
A brand
Even before you
You launch the company
You had a publicist going out trying to
Chadron public
Had meetings with
Almost 50
PR firms
Part of it was us evaluating them but
I'm at the same time we had to sell ourselves to the
Does PR firms
Nothing less sexy in the Fashion World in for mbas for Morton
We knew we were going to launch
Sometime in the
Spring of 2000
And we really wanted
To be in
Premiere magazine does
Approval
So what we were targeting
DQ in love
And so
We had some production samples
We didn't have a website up
But we really pitching
How these magazines as
Exclusive launch partners
We were
Thrilled to hear that
DQ envogue organize run stories we have no idea
What does stories were look like
What the content was going to look like
Totally hustlin
I mean
Why would these huge magazine
Lake Trust
A bunch of
Business school students
Didn't even have a company like if you went to the website at that point there was nothing up there like
Crazy to think that they
They would have done that right
I can do a few things at work in our favor right one was identifying
The right
PR
Person to help represent us
But we often say that
Tiaras
Like 30% the messenger 70%
The message
Address the message
Pretty novel at the time right there was
Nobody selling glasses online so the idea of selling glasses online
What's novel
That $95 price point
For $500 glasses
Funny novel
The home try-on program was novel so in fact
GQ actually called us the Netflix by we're in the article.
They put
So I think they were
These hooks that writers and editors could get excited about
So how much of an impact did that does that have on
The launch
Yeah we we were
Just blown away by that
Impact that it hadn't
The traffic in sales so
We got a call from
Are publicist
The day before.
Kiki was going to hit newsstands and we still had a landing page up
He went to warbyparker.com it said coming soon
Please enter your email address
GQ sitting tomorrow
And our website still had a bunch of bugs in it we are working
1 developer
And we were on the phone with him kind of frantically
Working out some of the most critical
Bugs
Senesite
And we finally at 4 a.m. Saturday
Guys listen
Stable enough
We all need a couple hours of sleep before we have class tomorrow
SILive
And
We were sitting in class
The next day
We haven't told anyone that the site was live our
Parents don't know the site was live are best friends didn't know the site
Would live
But we didn't want to drive any traffic to
Because we weren't sure it would wear
Had my phone set up to
Be notified anytime we got an order
And so is around 10 a.m.
And so I get an order and then 10 minutes later we get another order and then another order in another order
And we can go from this feeling of elatement
Oh crap we have to have this much inventory
And we hadn't contemplated building in any sold-out functionality or weightless functionality of the site
So you are literally selling out of glasses but people still ordering them because it's the website
Didn't know when you would run out of that we had no inventory tracking at all because we knew we were assuming one to two orders a day
And got a job that peanut nothing else my mom would buy a hundred pairs of glasses from us
But we are we really have tempered expectations because we also recognize that what we were trying to do was build a brand
And that takes a really long time
So we called an emergency meeting after that first hour-and-a-half class and we were debating
Okay what do we do here or do we just keep taking orders and then figure out what to tell
Bellator do we take down website
And while we're having the 2-minute discussion I'm looking at my phone and we have 10 more orders am I get to delete we got to do something
And tell
We place an emergency call to our developer
And miraculously was able
The building
Is weightless functionality on the
NF lie
And within
FR week.
Meat sold out of
Our best-selling Styles we had to wait
List of 20000 customers
Did you guys sell
Yeah 10000
You just did not I you would not ordered enough glasses from the manufacturer like you you literally
Couldn't and they couldn't make them fast enough for you
You know it I think
I think we were ambitious in terms of the number of frames that we purchased but also
Not overly risk-tolerant
And I think we've
Approach this business in
In a way that yeah that's not bankrupt ourselves on the inventory or you're also constrained and we hadn't raised any money
Investors
Yeah it was our our lifesaver
Things that we poured into there was
Really a
A limited
Number of frames that we have the ability to
Purchase
I mean
Sounds like a good problem to have
That you you have a waitlist
Pokeball user
Out of the gate
Killing it
Is that am I right or was it actually
IPad Pro
I think we've learned a lot of important lessons in
Early days where
We were terrified that
May we had all these early adopters
Excited to place an order from us and we didn't have anything to sell them
And for a lot of customers it took us
Numbers of 9 months
How to get through the weight
So we were terrified who are these people are going to
With a bad taste in their mouth
They were waiting a lot of companies
Not survive that
Yeah yeah I think
Did have some positive effects that it created
Surah that
Wow this is
Andrea Lee Height
Nothing creates cool like scarce
But I think we also learned
At 11
Terms of
Being empathetic to customers
Founders we reached out to everyone on that waitlist
M4
People that were had
Bad experiences
We're really disappointed we could give them
Glasses
People discount
You know what I think
From the gecko we wanted
How to create a
Impact in the world
Part of that
Treating
Customers Fair Lady
Treat them fairly welcome
What's the price
Treating them
Fairly
They call up and
Complain
Bantu apologized and explained
Make mistakes and then have something that
We did from the very beginning
Premier League
We're still trying to figure out
How to run this business
Apartments
I'm students
Our customer service line
What a Google Voice number that we set up when someone
Call
It would simultaneously
Clearing all four Founders cell phone
Santa Barbara customer service
And so we looked at our class schedules and their 12 hours
4 week when all four of us were
During class at the same time
And
We said it why we should hire someone who can answer the phone when none of us are available
And so we hired
The name Rin
I said you're going to be working 12 hours a week and transfer
Are doing and
I make that first weeks ended up
Working 100 hours
And now she's running our custom
Experienced team has about a hundred
50 people
And says as I kind of Off to the Races from day one
So did you guys I mean how quickly
Did you guys come out
Get together
Holy hell
This is real
Can I make it
We were too busy staying up all night to emails and
I remember when the first couple days like we actually decided to go to one of the classes that we were all in
And
We were all typing
Previously on our computers cuz we weren't really paying attention and we were just responding to customer emails and helping to process
And everything in the classroom got really quiet
The four of us are left.
Everybody was staring at us including the professor and here we were typing away when clearly they were done
Let's to be happy
With obvious you are not
You are not listening so we just stopped going to that class
I mean I remember waking up every morning
With the laptop on my chest
Because I fall asleep
Persona custom
There's an overwhelming amount of work in those early days and so
We don't have
Even a minute to breathe in and take a step back
And think about what was happening
So after this line
And after the company obviously
Peanut starts
Contraction
When did you guys decide
You know like we we better
Checkered racing money
And we went
And try to get
Because we figured like why give up equity
We could just get some loans to help us
Find the Symmetry that we needed
We went to 18 different banks
And only one
Would talk to us
And again this was
2010 so soon after
The financial crisis
And what all these loan officer status
Hey we've never seen such
It's a beautiful business plan we've never seen a company that has such great early results
But
We can't give you a loan
Because you don't have two years of tax returns
So what did you guys do
We ended up
Getting
$200,000 SBA loan
We had to sign
Pride 400 documents
Including one that said we weren't going to use the money to open a zoo
And
We really try to think of other creative forms of financing
Business
And so we working
With a third party will just
Text company that managed
Summer inventory
And
CL leather brand are business in
He was asking what can he do to help Drive growth in our business or that
They can have more business
I really constrained by
Are billion purchase inventory of this
Pyside Wild
You guys seem like a really good APR
Our company need some help
OTR what if
You do some PR Consulting for us
And
We'll pay you a few hundred thousand dollars
So I guess you launched in 2010
Today you have close to me
800 employees
You sold
I'm sure millions of pairs of glasses
How much do you think you are successful
Was because of
You know you guys are
Smart angular
Really hard workers or
Or how much of it was black
To say that there's a lot of it
Deliberate serendipity
For example we were really lucky to be exposed to our marketing Professor that helped us think through
Pricing
We had created Goodwill by
Being friendly and doing well in his class and he was willing to dedicate time to us
So I think there's a million examples of that or
I'm our friend
Calling in favors on our behalf
Want to think that we were just straight up
Blocky on his timing
Right timing is everything
They are coming off the financial crisis
How the public was looking for Lacey
To save money and I think a brand like ours
Even resonated
Even more
Last year I read that
That you guys raised like
A hundred million dollars
Soap
What's what's the company valued at
At our last valuation was over billion dollars
When will you hear that a billion dollars
That's crazy
It's pretty crazy
Yeah you know
It's exciting but not nearly
As
Exciting
Psych coming to work
Everyday and
Being in an office
Is that we've actually designed ourselves
Seeing people in the subway wearing our glasses like that one
Never get old can you recognize your glasses
Oh yeah
A10 fact
The first time
We saw the glasses in
In the wild
I remember
Seeing this percent of corner of my eye what's on the subway
Fireman
Union Square
And I just start following the person and UNLV
If someone's following you on the platform like
You've got a dirty look but I just big like ear-to-ear smile
That's Neil Blumenthal Warby Parker
Neil and Dave gilboa co-founded Warby Parker with two other friends for business school generator and panty hot
Company actually partnered with the nonprofit where Neil used to work fish in Spring
Bring my glasses to people around the world don't have access to them
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you
About the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors netsuite
Buy Oracle
The business management software that handles
Every aspect of your business
Easy to use
Cloud
Skip the free crushing the five barriers to growth guide
Netsuite.com
We are
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
It's time now for how you built that
Updated story
We ran about a year ago this one started when
Kayaking
Freak near Sunset South Carolina
That created a tunnel all the way down the center of the creek
The water
Secretly like lay down and go underneath
So
That's what he did lay it on top of my kayak
And went down the creek that way and it was
Exhilarating that's what gave me the very first idea
And his idea was to build something he eventually called a belly a kits
Shaped like a kayak but there's no hollow space in the hall no place to sit
So instead
The surface
You can lie on top and
Paddle with your hand
What I like and it shows it's like flying it's the feeling of flying on water and you know
Having a high performer
Freestyle kayak Hawk
Which is made to respond to every nuance
The current and feeling that through your entire body and having your hands right there in
Current
That was such a thrilling
Feeling
For about a year-and-a-half Adam tinkered in an old Warehouse with some urethane foam
To get the bellyak
Just wright
And I feel 24 different
Model because I would build it and I be like wow that was
Was good but I need to add a little more volume to the Baldor
What if it were a little narrow here in a little wider here so I thought I would have more Quest
Try that start with one question
Would it be like if
And after playing around with it for a while he
Finally perfected the bellyak Adam got a patent and he was thrilled because he thought
Kayakers
They are going to love this thing
But he was wrong
People look down their nose at it as something that they were too good for
And really it was because Tigers already know how to kayak it's like trying to sell it
Different type of mountain bikes somebody who Rd mountain bikes they already have their tool for that terrain but over time I don't realize
Other groups of people who did like the bellyak
Swimmers triathletes Surfers
And a group he was surprised to hear from him first
Disabled veterans allowed somebody to get out of that wheelchair
And I can be mobile.
They could have exercised they can work on their balance and the coolest thing was as I've talked to so many guys have used it has been like man ever since
Since my injury
I've never thought I would swim again and it's helped me get back in the water and that's been the coolest thing to see
Since we first spoke with Adam last year
He was a guest on the TV show Adventure capitalist just kind of like Shark Tank accept all the products are
Outdoorsy like bikes and skis you know that
Anyway one of the investors on the show offered to put up $100,000 for 20%
Adams company and he
Shed
No
He did not want to give away that much equity
So for now is growing his
Company slowly
With no outside investment
And so far
He sold about 1500 belly
And if you want to find out more about atoms
Company check out our Facebook
Search for how I built this and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build. NP
PR. O r g we love hearing about the things your building and thanks for listening to the show this
This week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes and go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also do subscribe to our show at Apple podcast
Or however you get your podcast you can also write us at h i b t
Npr.org
You can tweet us at how I built this our show was produced this week by
Herman with original music composed by runty mareblu
Thanks also to neva grandson. Meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers AR intern is newer coetzee
And you been listening to how I feel
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
And email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cussed
With mobile-friendly email to
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week