Support for how I built
Best and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development Corporation
Seewhy michigan
Is attracting top talent and top businesses by searching Michigan pure opportunity
Hey one quick thing for the show
You know that we just announced
Brand new detail
About the how I built this Summit in Ark
October sponsored by
Express
We're going to have breakout sessions where you can learn all kinds of
Skills from
Acquiring new users
Pitching investors
You'll also be able to get the
The support you need to build a great culture for
Company or overcome imposter
You can see the full schedule of breakout sessions
And the main Stage Show
Npr.org
Summit NJ
Just let you know our early bird special
Ending
Soon so bye
Your tickets before
June 1st
To save $100
That's $100
Can put back toward what
Everett is
Your building
I got a call in the middle of night
Got up
Clothes on jumped in the car
I live just one mile from the mill
And I was up on a hill
And the mail was down in the valley and when I came around the corner and I could see this
Fire reaching into the heavens
And realizing that that was
My business
NPR how I built this
Show about entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
I'm guy rosin on Today Show passion project
Grind his own flour turned into a whole grains Empire called Bob's Red Mill
One of the biggest names
Whole Foods
On the show
Stories of a lot of Technology
But today story
It's about as low-tech as it gets actually goes back to the Paleolithic era
And a technology invented
Grinding seeds and grains in the flower
Is an actual industry people have been making a living off of this for at least 10,000 years
Disruptive idea here
Bob's Red Mill
Mainly sells whole grains and flour
And not just a weed or corn but
Things like Millet and sorghum income booted who actually knows what commode is
And even though it wasn't his intention
Bob has
Turn all of that grain
Ended gold Bob's Red Mill is a 100 million dollar a year business
Go to Moe supermarkets today and there is a good chance
You will find Bob's Red Mill products just
Look for Bob's friendly white bearded face on the package
And what's really amazing about the story
Bob started the company after he basically retired when he was almost 50
The years old
The time
He decided to study theology at a Christian seminary in Portland Oregon
Bob was not a rich man but we'll get there
Here's what you need to know
In the LA area during the Great Depression
His dad
Track selling Wonder Bread
Around the time of the second World War
All the young men went off
The fight
But he was old enough to work
Absolutely
I rounded up a
Job
From the May Company
In Los Angeles
Guess which was their headquarters I believe
I got a job in the warehouse I had a master Warehouse
It said the other May Company stores
And because
There wasn't meant around that
People that were running the warehouse where all the old guys
At least in my mind
They were really all
And they weren't draft
Edible and I can remember after working at the May Company warehouse for
Quite some time
I was called down to the office
And
His name was
Mr. house
Smoked cigars
And he was
Ominous
In my mind
Wife
And I knocked on his door
And of course I thought they were going to fire me
And I was just shaking I was so nervous to go in there
Mr. house circles stem Bob
And
He asked me if I would like
To have a department of my own
At 16 years old
Guy that was probably the
Greatest thing
That Society did for Bob Moore
What's to give me that kind of
Responsibility
When I was that young
And I
I almost
Cried
And he said
We will pay you a dollar an hour
Nice that was a lot of money at that time
But I walked out of his office
I didn't walk out
Flew out
Justin 7th Heaven
And it was probably one of the most
Magnificent moments in my life
Was having that happen
Batumi
After High School he joined the army for
3 years
And we got back to Southern California
He met his wife Charlie
Eventually they had three boys
Free couple years Bob work for an electric motors company
I thought that's what
He would do for the rest of his life
But then
His dad died
Expectedly
I have a picture of him in my office
Was taken the same year he died
He looks
Freshen
Normal is anybody at
49 years old
Certainly didn't look like he was ready to die
And
Just keeled over one day and the doctor said he was dead by the time he hit the ground he had a massive
Heart attack
To this day I missed
My dad and me
You were I guess in your early
Early twenties when he died
Why did that change your your direction that
Well
Dad and I were always going to go into business
Well that didn't happen
And up
One day
I was
Driving down Crenshaw Boulevard in Los Angeles
And they had just put up a big
Sign on a corner that said coming soon
Mobil gas station
And I wrote the phone number down
Call it
Cuz I wanted to find out
How much it would cost
Got a gas station I didn't even think there was enough money in the world for me to do that
But they came through with a figure
That seems
Fairly reasonable to me
And so
We put the house up for sale and sold it immediately
And got the money we needed
To buy the gas station
And that's what I did
How much did you need to buy that gas station. 6000
And
I can tell you that the excitement
Of having my own business
Still with me
Guy is still with me
It fulfilled every single thing my dad and I had talked about
And only I was
I didn't hit my dad
So if you were enjoying things
At the gas station
Will you
You like sold it
A couple years later and
Got out of La why why did you do that
Well la had a lot of problems it was very smoggy
It was so
Intensely uncomfortable
That we talked about
Well now that I have a gas station
We could really move any place week
Could get a gas station in
Any town
And we decided
That Mammoth Lakes
What's the right place to go
The Mammoth Lakes
Watch
Had just built
Big Ski Resort
The top of the mountain
Which I believe is still a very
Yeah sure active
It is the area
And that's all
I sold my station
And we sold that house
So we had enough money I think
The time we had about $17,000
Which in
All guy
It was a lot of
And so as a you move your family out to Mammoth
Haidian
And how'd it go
Nothing
No business
It was crazy
There was already a Shell station
Turn up there that had been there for years and years and years
And everybody loved him and went there for their
Gas and for everything else
And
Frankly
A guy by the
Almost one year to the day we just ran out of money
And there's only one way I could go in this to get ourselves out of there
Which idea
And Charlie and I and the three boys
Took off for Sacramento
Where I
Change my direction in life
So what did you end up doing
Year after
Mustang fails at one year almost to the day we got down
Sacramento
And I got a job at Sears and Roebuck
And in the hardware department selling everything
I mean lawn mowers
All the stuff that was there to sell when you move to Sacramento what was your family's Financial
Situation
Well I think we were at the lowest point we moved in we had a minister of the church that we
Decided to go to with the time
He was caretaking as an apartment
3 unit apartment and one of the units didn't have any
Showers at work
And he said well Bob can let you in Charlie and the boys live in that for a while
And we took him up on it because we didn't have any money
I remember about the kitchen was very small
And Charlie and I put up a mattress in the kitchen and slept on the floor
And the boys the two youngest boys slept together
On a
Fold-up bed
And can the oldest that time
Slept in a sleeping bag and that's how we slept
We don't have any furniture
So that was about the lowest point in our life when we were living
On somebody else with the three boys
You know when you get down you feel helpless like a baby yeah you don't there's no strength left in you
You don't even know how to retaliate or fight
We really
We needed a helping hand
But at some point. Maybe was in the earlier midnight
Ever that you came across a book
That's right that
I think it's safe to say probably change your
Your life what was that book
A book called John goffe Mill written by George Woodbury
I have it in front of me right now
And George
Wasn't was a very well educated
Educated
Archaeologist
You got a letter in the mail it said that he had inherited
His family's Mill which is about 600 acres
In Bedford
New Hampshire
Well I mean if you got a letter like that you're going to go down and see what you had
And that's exactly what
George dip
He went down to
The mill
And spent the next 10 years of his life
Restoring
John goffe Mill
But you still down there and said this is at Like A Memoir of his life
Restoring that's exactly right and struck a chord with you what
What why all of a sudden he makes a statement in the book that
The most delightful thing was
Whole grains
When he ground all these wonderful whole wheat flour and
Jolla rice flour and cornmeal
And all this at the public beat a path to his door I remember those words
I underline them
Tagum
I showed it to my wife
If we could do this
If we could get a meal
And do the same thing
The public would beat a path to our door
And we would be in business
So you see
Can you get really into
This idea of May
Maybe starting a mill in lots of people get laundry room ideas and get obsessed with
With
With things for a time being it and so what did you do
Did you start to think about how we going to buy milk
Did you start to talk to your wife to Charlie
Dubai
Yeah I did a lot of talk
I did a lot of talking to Charlie a night in the boys were all in their teenager
By that time in
And I got them interested to
And one thing I did was I went to the library
And they had a
12 volume group of
American manufacturers of equipment
And in there they had two pages of companies who made flour Mills
And equipment for Mills and
I wrote some letters rather naive because I really
I was talking about
Stuff in the 8th
And asking them about Stone Mills
And I wrote about 10 letters
And
I think I only received a response back
From about two of them
One of them gave me the name of a fella
Who they knew had a Stone Mill his name is Dewey sheets
And you lived in
Muncie Indiana
And he had been in the Milling business for
Yeah a lot of his life
And Dewey was such a help
Found me
Amil
That was
To be torn down
Fayetteville North Carolina
So I ended up
For not a whole lot of money
Where's
My garage
Stack full
Of old
Very ancient
Stone Mills dated
18:6
C.1880
Bringing like large
Stone
Yeah wheels and just all the equipment you need to
Grind up grains and into flower
And
With I guess we all with with the intention of Adventure
Getting it up and running and starting milk
Anybody that you knew saying
Thinking
Cat losing his mind
This hockey thing I'm starting until it seems like he's taking it a bit far
You know. I don't know why
I didn't have much resistance
I didn't
Feel that I had them back up anybody
Or apologize I think that
I felt it was
Climb
We're healthier food to come along
Are World needed better food
Needed more whole grains that needed most of the nutrition
Put back
In the food that
We were feeding people
Through the grocery chains
And the whole thing
Began to take on a real form
And make sense to me and
When I talk to people certainly my wife
And others
It made sense to them to
So well maybe you should try it
I guess after a couple years you throw to save some money and then you were able to buy
My wife started to save money
Are you able to protect liver was good at it
After couple years you were able to move to a
A small farm
Five Acre Farm you have you amass all this equipment
Because I guess the
Late sixties early seventies at this point
First of all how did you how much how we going to get the
Cash to defined as a land to build a Flour Mill
Well we didn't build a Flour Mill we rented a piece
Property that had a building on it
There are so many things that happened in our favor
I got a job
At Penney's JCPenney company
In Redding California
Opening a brand-new Auto Center
So we ended up in Redding California
There was a delight
Full.
Quonset hut
On the south end of town
And I was vacant
And we built walls inside built
The store
A real coin store with
With cedar planking on the walls
We covered the whole front of the building
Made it try to make it look like a Flour Mill
And called it Moore's Flour Mill
And we converted this building
Into what was
A reasonable
Facsimile
Of a mill
And we had
Stone Mills
That we sat here and there
And begin the process
Of grinding
Flower
Whole wheat flour cornmeal
Social Services 1974 you open the doors to more flour mill with
Your boys
And and you're making wheat flour corn flour what else
Oh actually we I created the 10 grain cereal that were using now on
We ground whole wheat
There's a lot of kinds of week
There's a
Durum wheat which is
Hard white wheat
There's a red wheat which is high in protein
And makes wonderful bread
Alden soft weed
There's a soft white
Wheat
Pastries and
And biscuits and
So
You you get
A little knowledge of what
Grains are
And how to use them than you
Create some recipes and
Put them in a bag
And then you pendulum
And that's just what we did we put large
Windows
Across the wall from the store into the mailroom
And they could see it one or two or three meals running all the time
So this was like
Almost like an artisanal
Mom-and-pop kind of
Store Friday was he was never designed to be anything bigger than that
Yes no no no
No I kept my job at
Pennies for 2 years and Charlie of course
She worked the store
And talked with people and she was a great believer in whole grains and
It was all very nice we were having a great time
You must have still been
Like kind of restless because
You I guess it was around the time you
How to make a radical shift
Like you decide to
Retire
When your son's takes over the mail and then you
Take off to go study
At a cemetery
That's right
I had a
Intense
Desire
To learn to read the Bible in the original languages
Hebrew and koine Greek
And we did a little scouting about found here
That Portland where I am right now
Was one of the greatest
Spots for seminaries
And we enrolled in
One of the seminaries here
And
Begin to learn
To speak your Bible in its original languages
This is a mean this is Jake Bugg
At this point when you decide to
Completely change directions and just go and study at a seminary you are about 50 years old
Just a little bit older than the age when your father
Died
And this was going to be
This is going to be your retirement the beginning of the user of winding down from work I go
Where I Canada all my
Buckets that I had and I said the Charlie I think we could last
We could live this way for for 5 years
And I think I could get my education and once I got that
I would get some kind of Direction I felt whether it was spiritual direction or what
And would be able to
Reroute my life into something that was worthwhile
And we both agreed this as what
Step you'll do us both
So that's what we did see you start at 7
School end
Fulfill all of your dreams and hopes and wishes
No
I don't know what happened
What's part work when you haven't been in two languages
Guy is a tough one actually
I had to do a lot of studying and Charlie was right with me
What really changed the whole thing
Was one day we were walking along
Weaver reading vocabulary cards
Back and forth
First we had
Greek verbs on one side and nouns on the other end
So anyway one day we walking down April
Particular Street
And much to my
Surprise
I looked over and there was a
Amil
Had it been there for a long time
And in front of it was a for sale sign
I couldn't believe it I said to Charlie
I said hun that is an Old Mill
We walked over
It's probably six blocks
From the cemetery
And I got to run up on the steps
And I looked in the window and I could see bucket elevators grain cleaners
I could see all the Milling equipment
I could not believe what I was looking at
And there was a phone number
And I called the number and I got ahold of the guy that owned the property and when I
Told him I was interested
He says what what are we talkin about here you owned a lot of property
I said that
The Old Mill
Milk Bill mail
Oh he said yeah that property UCI we're going to tear the building down
And we're going to have the property is 2 Acres
And we're going to have it for sale so it's going to be a really
Goodbye without that Old Mill on
What you going to do for dinner that Mill.
And I thought this is just the most fantastic thing in the world
I can't believe what's happening
Seoul
Well basically I bought the same
And
Changed my
Tire life
Let me come back out Bob opened his new mail started to grow the business and then stood on a hill
And watch the whole thing
Go up in smoke
Garage stay with us you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy
To add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from servicenow making the world of work work better
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive and engage
Moret servicenow.
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
Hits 1978
Bob as wife Charlie
Stumble across an old male
About to be torn down and
They decide to save it
To create a new company
And they call it
Bob's Red Mill
I took three months I gave myself three months to the day
To get the doors open
And
I begin a
Concerted
Effort
To make my life
What I thought I was
Capable of
Doing
Witness building now the building was everything
It was just a
A god-sent
To be honest with you I think that's a good term
People like when you open the doors after
Three or four months
From the moment you buy me
Today
Take and your processing grain
You get the word out of you just waiting for customers to show up and buy
Flour and Grains
Well I have
Water help
I put the every Tuesday was the
Food At
The local paper
And I put a two-column
The Millers
Now
Running
Come and enjoy
Fresh stone-ground
Whole wheat flour +
I'm a pretty good
Shouter
I can yell at out pretty loud and make it
Work pretty well
And
Channel to hear
Came out with Kathy Smith
And within two weeks of opening the mill
I was on the evening
Newsfile Kathy
Saying the nicest thing to do
And then
I could fill a parking lot in notes
And people were buying your Granger
She like
Your flowers
Just coming in and buying buying all that stuff
Yeah but what else came in was we had a group of
Markets
Fear called Fred Meyer
One-Stop shopping
And their buyer came in he was a vice president and he said Mr Mayer
Would like to open
Health food stores in all 44 of his stores
And we'd like to put your products in there
And they gave me a list of the grains they wanted the flowers they wanted
And
Of course with the Fred Meyer chain
Others came to a Safeway I know
And Albertsons in some of those
And ask us
If we
Had enough production wow to keep
Them going
And without
Too much effort
We
Got a pretty good business going to say this is the mid-70s
This is like
Really what the health food
Praise kind of starts to
Take off in America
We had a
Yeah we we had a lot of help like Reader's Digest
Came out with an article on brand and why that was so healthy for you to eat
Your bowels
In good order in
Just one thing right after another kept
Coming out and of course everybody had a TV
And there were shows on Nelson
We really begin to realize
That we had a
Kind of a tiger by the
The tale
Over this whole thing you know I'm
There's a lot of
Revelation
In this stuff we didn't start out with any
Hugin 10th or anything it just
It just seemed like the right thing first off
We were eating this stuff ourselves and we all felt
The
Benefit
It's have all this
So that's one thing
That you're
In a business that you believe in
And I think that's so one of the biggest things that made this thing work
Yeah so are you
Just jump ahead
The first 10 years
Growing
Shtetl you're still pretty small
About 10 years in
After you launch Bob's Red Mill Inn in 1988
I'm going to see her you had a
Fire
Wheatley destroy
Canal
Yeah I did
And it was intentionally set was set by an arsonist
Well we're waiting
Credit crazy people running around I didn't know this
Person at all and it wasn't any like an ex-employee or anybody mad or what
Any grievance or anything
I don't think any of us
New artist coming
And boy I'll tell you
With that old wooden building that was really old you know
Why it is
Really caught fire and it was full of grain
It was a very active
Company lots of paper
Just everything
Did you find out about it
Well
I got a call in the middle of the night
Bob
Bob your Mills on fire
So I got up and
My clothes on
Jumped in the car
And
Quran down
And as I went around the corner I would I live just one mile from the mill
And I was looked up on a hill
And the mail was down in the valley and when I came around the corner and I could see this
Fire reaching into the heavens are and realizing that that was my business
You don't know what to think
You don't know how to think
If you don't know whether to cry or or what I just
Got down there
Pretty quickly the fire chief came up to me who I knew that used to make inspections of the mill
And he said we got all of water we need
But if you could tell me what part of the mill is
Is the most precious that would keep you going in business I can direct the whole fire
Department
At that point
Of course the millstones were the most
Important part of the whole thing
We walked over to the male is pretty hot there but
You know the end of the fire departments
We're pulling a lot of water on the on the building
But we walked over and then I pointed out on the building side of the building where
The Mills were inside
They immediately had a saw
I just whack a big square hole in it and he planted one of the firemen there on the ground with a v
Fire hose
Aim through the hole
And it for the entire
Time of the
The fire
He kept Direction inside the mailroom
Which actually saved all three meals
So when the fire was
When the fire was put out
And you're
You're looking at what was left of
Bob's Red Mill
I'm assuming
Was not a whole lot
Teach you
Did you were you immediately thinking words
Rebuilding
And start up again really soon or did you did you think
Maybe it's time maybe this is a sign to
To pack it in
Well that's pretty much what I thought
But there was some things that
Change my mind
Mind
And even that very nice
David
My
Is that time my oldest
Employers wife came down
Eileen was such a lovely lady she was our bet she worked at the bank where we bank and that's how
How David met her
And we took them the two kids
On their first date together for dinner
And they got married we went to there
Wedding and everything else end
David has been with me almost 10 years by that time
And that night
Within a few minutes of my arrival
Their Charlie came
And she and Eileen were talking
And I overheard them and Eileen told Charlie
Oh Charlie I don't know what we're going to do
We just signed the papers
On our home
David doesn't have a job now
And you know that sunk in pretty deep
Charlie looked at me
And I guess what she was saying and what I was thinking in my mind
Is it there's probably not going to be any thoughts
Not continuing this thing somehow we'll make it work
There's an awful lot of things that have motivated me over the years
And
A lot of those things came out
Because of
David Den
Eileen
And the fire
So I felt
That I had a
Weighty responsibility
Staring me in the face
And there's a lot of things that goes through your mind and in those kind of situations and certainly I had every
You thought you could
But you kept it going you decided to keep it going
We tried first
Courser rebuild a melon that was impossible but I had
A warehouse across the street about a 10000
Square foot
Warehouse directly across the street
So
Even though the mill burned down I had some resources
I was able to save the millstones
So we almost immediately
Moved across the
The street to that ten thousand square feet
That we had it wasn't enough but we tried it
And I kept
I had the business
Guy had
Awesome business people wanted are Prada
He kept bugging me when I was going to open a read my retail part which
Of course burned up
And
We just kept trying and trying to keep Machinery going yeah remember now I started many years ago with my sons and
Redding California
My wonderful son
Bob
Had a Milling operation that we had all built as a family
And he allowed
One of my peeps
To go down there
And grind
My whole wheat flour my cornmeal and things like that at night
You know and then they put it in the truck
Brought it back up
So all these things
Begin to work almost immediately
They gave me
A pretty good degree of of
Of comfort with getting things going
Listing things
Baba seems it after the fire
Is really when the business started
How to take off mean
10 years after
The company almost pinotage
Just like a business
Conspire
What happened what was the reason why was there a strategic
Decision that you made was there someone you met was there
A lucky break that you guys got that just
Allowed Bob's Red Mill
Product go
National and then beyond
Well actually I there was
I was told that I never go anywhere be anything unless I
Became a part of the national
Natural food
Or industry
So I joined that wasn't very expensive
And
We went down to Anaheim California where I just got back Famous Amos natural food
Who's X
Yeah and we got a little 10 x 10 boots at the back of this thing
And we brought all the products that we were making
Has quite a few actually several hundred
And I tried to have all natural
Whole grains
And every form of them we could take one item corn for instance and we can make corn grits
We can make
Fine cornmeal
Regular cornmeal coarse cornmeal
I ended up with funeral
Six or seven products over 1
Basic crane I did the same with weed and I did the same
Boats and everything else so I mean it was a unique way of doing it I wanted every
I didn't sell as well some soul
Better than others
When the industry down there in Anaheim saw this
I had some people come to me and they said they wanted it
That is a Hoosier distributor and I said well I don't have a distributor
So those people over there to show to
They went and got their distributor
And they brought him down they said we want these products
So they took my products on
Almost overnight
We kind of hit the jackpot and we had to go back and work pretty hard to catch up with their orders
Don't you found Distributors and
And you started to you products are there really
Takeoff
It wasn't that long before you really started
The revenue for
Company
Was growing I think my 2007
You're sales topped
45 maybe 50 million dollars did you
I know you didn't go into this for money and
Did you ever look at that number
UCF over just a Halo
The Revenant
Crazy
This little girl is doing this kind of Revenue
Well we did forget
Pretty good
Black guy
People were always wanting to buy us I mean it was just
The constant you are getting offers from company different investors who want to invest in me
And actually different companies that just simply wanted to buy me
It was a lot of it and you just said no
No I said no because
All right I didn't
It wasn't any money any way besides
I knew as soon as they bought me out
Even though they always tell you that everything's going to stay the same
But everything changes
Is an and I didn't want my life to
2 Chainz I thought it was really swell
It was it was a good
Good life guy
Alright so you have this
It is now doing at least a hundred million rub
Yeah it's
It is it's
It's well well over a hundred million
And I think it was in 2010
You announce that you want to
And the company over to your employees in
They didn't like 2/3 of it right
That's right
And you are also giving away a lot of
Are most
Money is so sound like
And you a long time to eat
A long life ahead of you but it sounds like you are slowly
It says that you are slowly
Aiming to
To end
You know to enter time here on Earth as a as a poor or a no Relic
I got a guy with no money
Guys there's anything I can tell you
I'm giving it away because I want to
Time in the Bible to me was so clear
To do unto others
As you would have them do unto you
Now That's the basis
Of how I think and how I feel
If you do these things
The feeling the return
Your life is is
Appreciably
Improve
And I have that feeling I know what that is it's a different feeling that I had when I was
Yeah
Yeah of course
How much of what of what
You experience
Throughout the course of your license
Incredible success
For this company
Future Beetle lock and how much
H2
Just hard work and your intelligence and you are skip
Call Guy
I've always worked hard I'm crazy
I got up at 6 here I am almost 90 I give at 6 every morning
I go down to my own
Store
My own restaurant and have
Cereal I don't like it
Hot cereal cook syrup
And then I get in the bed a little bit early but I work till 5 or 6 every
Everyday so I
I've always worked hard so if working hard is a secret
Success
I've done that I know what it feels like
Can I probably never will do anything different
You talk a little bit about about about your face in your Christianity
I'm just wondering how much
How much is a guided you
You know
Over the years like your
Your decisions in your thinking
Why think it permeates me is far as asking
The whole concept of whole grains
I got from the very first page of the Bible you know when you
When you go to Seminary they start you off with
The first page
I have it at it with me I can read it to you is only a couple of lines
God said behold I have given you every plant yielding
Seed which is
Is upon the face of all the Earth
Free tree with seed
And it's fruit
You shall have
Them for food
And I read these words and
14 div
Translations
And I learned to figure it out
In the original Hebrew
It still says the same thing simple unequivocal comforting
Just made perfect sense to me guy
And the fact that I can establish a business around it
Was was just
Unbelievable and and I'm not doing too bad at it it's
Working pretty well
Bob Moore founder of Bob's Red Mill
In 2007 the company moved to a bigger facility
Outside of Portland where they make about 400 different products
Still using the old Court Millstone from the 1800
Billy Bob actually keeps a mason jar full of the very first product to come off of the Stone
Red wheat flour
Round in his original Mill
40 years ago
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
Thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
If you're ready to start your new business
Make it stand out with a new website from Squarespace
Visit squarespace.com
Build it
For a free trial
Venues
Cipher code build it
To save
10%
Your first purchase
Website
Or domain
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Timeout for how you
You built that
Play story starts back in 2000
15 when Mike bolo
I was working as a lawyer in Chicago
And then move to a new firm and new office
My new desk was just
One of those typical dances kind of mounted to a wall
But yet in downtown Chicago at these beautiful floor-to-ceiling windows out to my right
Overlooking the city of Florida ceiling windows
We can relate to the main problem right it office desk that is not in the right place the person
Place to be with you the window
Get this beautiful view in the natural sunlight I'm like there's got to be something out there for that
What Mike was looking for was
Wedge really
That could be mounted
Directly
Two window so I started looking online couldn't find anything
And that's when kind of like I always like to do I headed to Home Depot in Amazon and started to buy the parts I need the
Ubuildit the first thing on my list
Suction cups that could attach a desk
To a window and could support what's on the desk
Laptops
Books
So I shot then I found some good suction cups that you know held about
40 lbs they said
Mounted them with some string that I bought from Amazon and
Critters really rudimentary almost kind of cat bed looking thing
It wasn't too bad for a first try but it was bouncy and it was too narrow to really work as a desk
And it was at that point that I stepped up and I found the
Types of suction disk that they use to install commercial grade glass windows in high-rise
I was like this is perfect these are Ultra durable ultra-strong and intended for this purpose potentially
Okay so Mike
Critical section he needed to affix the desk to a window
And from there
He built 18 prototypes and finally he had the desk he been dreaming of
People started walking by my office saying what is that I want that in my office that's cool where did you buy it
Kind of light bulbs
Well I should really think about mass production and really bringing this to Market and around that time I went to a party
Are you worried about a guy named Jason then
Told Jason about the desk he built
Immediately the light bulb went off in my head yes more light bulbs
It turns out Jason grohowski was a real estate advisor
It was huge job to help businesses improve the design of their workplaces
So Jason's are real potential in the desk that Mike had invented
Yours Jason
I've seen how culture within spaces is changing how all the new buildings are glass how
Everything is about bringing in the natural light for employees and just productivity and health and wellness within spaces
And so I just got super excited other we need to we need to do this we need to take this to the next level
Mike and Jason soon started working with a design firm in Chicago and made even more tweaks to the bass
And by January 2017 they had a prototype ready so
They launched
Kickstarter that April
And made $25,000 in just the first day after we closed out the kickstarter we had to fulfill
Fill these orders so then it was
Let's go get this made
They had all these orders and no manufacture yet
So a month later this is May of 2017 they found one in Singapore and by November
Chase and Mike went there to check on the desks before they got shipped
And I look at the unit unlike something doesn't seem right
And I play with it
And the lovers
At that point we had 2,000 units already made all the components made
And we were like this is
Something that we can't let out the door
So after a month of sleepless nights and many design revisions json and Mike
Finally got the Liebherr right
In December they started shipping their desks from their Singapore manufacturer to their customers and more than 40
Countries they're not both working full-time on the company is called spu
And their desk comes fully assembled so you can install it on your window in just a few minutes and then
Enjoy The View
Refocus
So
Closely on our computers all of our work day is just streaming our eyes to look at close objects
With dust you you're actually allowing yourself to relax your eye and look out further
If you want to find out more about desk you head to our Facebook page and of course if
If you have a story about something in your building please tell us all about it at build. NPR
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episode
Npr.org you can also write us at HRBT at npr.org
And if you want to get SATs how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Falkner with original music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to Newark could see the immigrants on us Mexican border
Jeff Rodger
I got Roz and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email template
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week