Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Hey really quick before we start the show
I want to let you know about a new addition to our already amazing lineup
Play the how I built this Summit and
October
Sponsored by American Express
Eric Ryan and Adam Lowry the founders
Method cleaning products will be joining me for conversations on the main stage
Along with founders of
Companies like Airbnb stitchfix lift and many others
You can get your tickets and see the fullest
Npr.org
Flash Summit
April 2008 you launch minted and and you're like the doors open the shingles
You're excited you pop the champagne Corks And nothing nothing absolutely dead silence
No orders so is not a cell to be had it was terrifying and horrible horrible
And we almost I really contemplated that Mama this is a failure we need to shut this business down we need to give whatever remains of the money
Back to investors because it's it's it's a total failure
Robin Thicke
How I built this entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind them
Online stationery store into one of the biggest platforms for emerging artists
Stop the process transforms business
Personalized stationery
End of the 1980s
At age 13
I was getting ready to officially become
I'm at the stage in which according to Jewish tradition
Boys enter manhood and they have a bar mitzvah
Party
Set up a chair and paraded around a dance floor you serve salmon
Chicken you get the idea
About eight or nine months before the big day
I remember going with my mom to a stationery store to look at
Kinds of invitations amp
Which act out fonts
Paper Stock
Colors
Going with burgundy black and gold
You put down a deposit
It was a long process
Compare that to when my son was born 25 years later
Illini uploaded a photo of his
Pink little face
Uploading my address book put in my credit card details
3 days
Everyone on my list received a beautiful birth announcement in the mail
Thank you internet
Now this is the revolution Miriam nafisi tapped into in 2007 when she launched minted
But what differentiates minted
Is a major pivot Marianne would make early on
Because instead of just
Selling personalized holiday cards are wedding invitations
Miriam
How to build a platform for artists
To Showcase their work
And she did this by tapping into another Revolution
What was happening in the early 2000s
Crowdsourcing
But before minted was
Even a thought in his mind
She written the.com wave of the late 90s
For the company called e
It was a website that sold
Cosmetics
At a very young age
Miriam and her partner manage to sell it
Before the.com
Anything about Miriam is that
Launching to successful companies
She never intended to become an entrepreneur
Miriam grew up in
Tehran
Her mom was an artist originally from
China
Her dad was in
Harvest
From a rock
And toward the end of the 1970s
As the situation
In Iran became more volatile
The family
Decided to
Backup
And flea
You know the environment
Was unstable and
We did not realize it was very clear what was going to happen
I think that we were we were really worried
About what would happen to us
In the new regime so
And I guess my dad thinks of us as refugees
Which is when you leave on willingly when we got here
Hey was the
Hey yes soon after we arrived these hostage crisis started
And that was not a
Great time
To be Iranian in the US
And being a kid in school that was
Really gif
I basically really honestly tried to americanize and fit in as fast as I possibly could
I really wanted to integrate and I when I came here I actually had a pretty at a strong accent
I was
Two years younger than everybody in my class all the way
Through basically school I was
2 years younger so I was
Small Smogon
And I just I'd really wanted to be American and honestly I sort of feel like the whole time even when I wasn't
You know an outsider there as well as you're always
If you're like me and your
You move around alot in your
I've mixed cultures you're never really going to feel like you
Belong to one place or one culture right you're always going to feel a little bit like The Outsider who traveling through time and space as an observer
Will you break a signal ticket
I was I was I was
Nerdy girl who sat at the front of the class with glasses on who everybody wanted to get
Help from their homework
Quiet
I would say quiet and I'm pretty competitive
And
As a kid did you
Have any real
Business Iran
Entrepreneurial
Stuff
No might my parents
I come from a completely non busy
Family
And
Honestly
You know what Iranian upper-class
Yeah you didn't you didn't you didn't set up business assertive vivanta thing that one goes into
Things that were in in my family very
I admired with things like being a doctor
Going into Foreign Service in the government
So when I was growing up in Chevy Chase not once did business crossed my mind I was thinking
Law and I
I do remember my mom
On the first day of
First grade
Bending down
To say to me something
And she said I want you to go to school and I want you to be all of the boys
To you you actually went onto to call to Williams College
What did you do
What did you do after you graduate
So
That's where I did do the the expected
Saying is some of my fellow
Classmates who were in economics and policy were interviewing for jobs
I'm lost
Management consulting firms and those firms had these huge process he's on campus recruiting process
So I went to Goldman Sachs as a financial analyst in their Investment Banking division
And you loved it
I can't say that I love being a financial analyst that it is sore Like Loving bootcamp
I don't know if you're familiar with it but you you end up
Working very long hours
But
I will say it's a great training ground as to what work ethic really means
Because you can't imagine working harder than then
What you actually physically pull off
As a financial analyst like 22 or 21
And you probably moving to New York end
And all you were doing was working
All I was doing was working so I was 20 and I was where I was eating breakfast
Just lunch and dinner at the office
And I was actually selling I had a desk on the bond
Trading floor and I was selling bonds
As well as doing it working with client
So before I could actually drink I was selling bonds
So if I could drink legally
So you AHS if you were doing this for
A couple years and then
Addison Point you
Decide to go to
To business who are you
Were you thinking your mind like okay
Business school and then
So what happened was
The first was just thinking
About
Going to business school because
I'd actually
Johnson
Investment banking
A management consulting and
I thought perhaps I would want to go into
Consumer products
Fairy Tail but I didn't get into Stanford the first time I applied
Shop for business school and so I decided to
Take your off and try to boost my
Resume with something that was a little bit more differentiated
And
Went to work for an entrepreneur
Maurice werdegar
In the restaurant business actually
Who was the
Stanford grad
And he became a key mentor
Starting a chain of restaurants
In Palo Alto
Oliver California
But I was
Sew in
Tired and bitten with the entrepreneurial bug during that experience and more importantly said to me
You really
You really could do that youku
Start a company you think
You should really consider it
Because we would spend hours talking about
Ariel ideas
Capital
And just got becoming completely obsessed with the point where I thought
Why go to Business School
We lunch but it doesn't go to this yeah I'm not even interested anymore and that that's why I thought all right
I'll play one more time because my boyfriend who became my husband was applying at that alright let's all throw my hat in the ring one more time
Antenna Stanford
Accepting me
So you go to Business School
Wow at Business School
The hell is book called
The fast track The Insider's Guide to winning jobs in management consulting
Investment banking
Insecurities reading a book
Thistle like 50000 copy
Is that very precocious and that's like super like that is
Overdrive
Precocious
Yes of the reason I did that was I thought well one it's a market
Recruiting at the two firms I was working at that I knew that there was a need for the book
And I wanted to experiment to see what happen if you created
Consumer product that you know that there's a need for can you can actually put a frog together and sell it
And I also thought it would be a good project to demonstrate that I had some
I guess it's fun to be able to get in at Stanford
I sold the book right and then I
I knew I'd sold the book to a publisher Broadway
Before I
As I was applying and I think that help differentiate me
As well
Pay for school
So at stanford edu
Did Russia have a business
Planner idea that you want supper
Put together
Well I started the second half of the year
First of all
Second half of the year at Stanford I was taking every on
Tornado class I could and trying desk
Early to get into the Best glasses
So is auditing Sam sitting on the floor of others
And then working on plans and
One thing I need
That I wanted to do is find a partner that I really liked so I called a friend of mine in New York
And tried to convince her to come to San Francisco and start something with me and we had two ideas
And she said well start
A company if we if we pursue my idea
Which is selling Cosmetics online
Mine was to do market research online
Find sort of like a survey monkey
What was her name
Varsha Rao
So we decided to pursue
Cosmetics that I thought sure why not I want to work with you and I need to get
Typical visitor come out to let's work on Cosmetics II views Cosmetics before
We can figure this out
And so I convinced her to move out
To come to San Francisco
To help
You start a
An online
Cosmetics
And she
Slept on the couch in our studio apartment or 1-bedroom apartment
And in the morning we get up in our pajamas so we wouldn't wake up
My now-husband
And we sit on the couch and call all the New York
Cosmetics companies from our couch
Papa John's
And
Canvas people
Go to sign on with us
To distribute on this thing called the internet
Which most people
We were extremely suspicious of
So that was a
So the business was going to be
An online store selling
All kinds of Cosmetics did I ever even brands that was the idea
That's right so the idea was
To create ever
Replenishment brand
Cosmetics
What's a good many things that you want to replenish skin care hair care you know your favorite Angela replenish it because
At that point everybody was telling us
Nobody was going to buy Cosmetics online that they've never tried
Moreover women don't shop online
That's a fact
Yes women don't shop online and nobody will ever buy
Make a call in line and I'll just stay in my career
It has happened repeatedly right where people will say
But everything all of those things have been said
So when you approach a small brands
I'm just saying online ourselves why were they
Attracted to what you guys referring
Well in those days
Solution that would easily allow small brand are so online I know it sounds crazy but there was no solution
And so
First of all nobody wanted to sell online we would have to go in there and convince them that the internet was not bad
We also actually hired a woman from
Macy's
It was formerly from me at Macy's has a big
Manager of the Cosmetics business
Said she ended up being our River guide
Making introductions
For us helping advise us
If you go to Chanel where the Chanel nail polish for example that was that wants to die
They'll recognize their colors on you
2 Yuan varsha Empire
Michael
Michael is a
YouVersion like Alexa listening in this apartment
Yuan varsha decide
You are going to start an online
Cosmetic store which today doesn't sound like that
Big big deal but I guess in 1998 that was kind of revolutionary
Right nobody was selling Cosmetics online nobody
Can you believe literally know what though
I wish I could go back and start a Cosmetics company
Yeah and then he notes
Start a company yo I basically took a white sheet of paper out and started drawing a website
On a white sheet of paper in my kitchen along with another sheet of paper where I was
Trying to come up with metric
As to what I would call
Different
Things like people coming to your site and
What would you call the metric or someone converts into a customer
And everything had to be invented Little League for the first time
Then we went through
Really
Insane
You're so if I graduated in 1998
We
Immediately started fundraising
But what was it was it
Easy to raise money in 1998
1998 it was
Getting pretty easy 1999 was crazy
Just cuz it was a.com boom but it was getting there and I sent
What's an opportunity from for me to get Capital even though it's 27
And
Had no work experience
They love our pets they loved us and they loved our pitch and we had a lot of interest
And
We ended up in an interesting situation where
We we did experience
Some collusion actually this is a really difficult part of that Journey where
In the old days
You can have easy friends
Gang up
If they could find out who else you were talking to
They conclude and basically
Work with each other
And partner together
Drive your price down evaluation down
And I had heard about it at business school in a lecture and it sure enough it happened it happened to me so
Wait a couple timesheets come in
Farrar
First round
Financing
And it was ideal Ava plus a couple of others
But
Two of the firms
Decided
The first I found out about
We were talking to Andy decided to collude
So we signed a term sheet with one player
And they were valuing us
Straight out of the blocks Justice
People images PowerPoint presentation at six million dollars
Pretty good right
Yes it was meant that we were very happy we it was a
A prestigious firm office on Sand Hill Sand Hill Road
But they turned around and actually
Decided to partner with another firm and they called us and said
We're sorry
This is now their deal
The times are changing
The terms now became
We need to move
Cities to where this other firm is
We're going to bring the valuation down to 4 million
And it was a collision
Straighten like a textbook collusion
This is like Darth Vader territory like that
Terms have changed
Explain to me
How that work
How that was like allowed to happen
Yes at the term sheet is
Unfortunately not
Binding it say
Indication of Interest that's really a buildup of good faith
And so if you could do and get away with it absolutely it happened a lot in
You know in that the night late 90s when
You didn't have online
Transparency in tenrec
Meditation
Where other entrepreneurs can learn
About what people are doing to you
And so there was no
Consequence
And so
Become an investor much more abusive
So what did you
What'd you tell him
They said this for million bucks and they hear you
So
What's fascinating is we had not yet
Call Bill gross to tell him that we were turning him down
So gross
This was the guy who
Idealab
In Pasadena so we had had the third term sheet
And we were planning to call him but we just didn't have the time we hadn't had the time to call him
Instead of calling him
How to turn him down we put the phone down with the other group we pick the phone up
We called all gross and we said we're signing your timesheet will be in Pasadena tomorrow
And we
Exit at the side door
See you at you raising money
It's 98
How long
Between a Time
That
You went to investors
Receive money and you actually launched the website
We took the money and in 1998 and we launched in July 1999
And what describe
Play what you mentioned the name of the website was
I'm sorry that your name was eve.com
And like Adam but Eve Eve yes
So when you launch t.com
Did the people find out about right away I had these people didn't know where to go and have a look
Yep so we we ended up with a massive amount of press coverage
And
She had a lot of money for marketing
And we were encouraged to spend it
At that time it was landgraab time everybody was trying to grab market share as fast as they could
We launched in and they were for competitors who launched right behind us
And
One of the big things I learned to do is just
Completely block out
Any fear or notion of a competitor's keep your head down
And to the minute we open the doors of literally the product
Started
Selling ridiculously quickly. I mean we did 10 million dollars in sales in our first year
Merryweather runaway you're given that it was our first year business
Amazing you were so young and you were like yeah
But we were
Lest anyone be confused are we were
Working till 10 at night every night in the office and this is what investment banking background keto candy cuz we were trained
To operate like that
Any of my husband would come meet me at the office at 10 and we have dinner at 10:30 every night
To you
In mm
A year-and-a-half
Do you watch
You guys get an offer
And
You sell this company eve.com sold for 110 million dollars
I don't even want to ask a question why I'm it seems obvious
It was a lot of money in
A no-brainer is
Yes right
Bright so
This is a time when we were trying to raise a series D and honestly the market
Was starting to get a little skeptical when you're ready to make a profit what's going on
And so I start for the first time in that
For the 14th
60 month. I started realizing that getting the next round was going to be difficult
And we could take
Have Safe Harbor for the company inside another company
I thought it would probably a wise move and
We closed it in April 2000
Two weeks later the market
Starcrash
Plow
So you made it
Just like butter
Scan your teeth
Yeah we we yes
Premier the foot-in-the-door
At the doors closing
What are other people in your position
In the industry who maybe didn't
Have as good
Penang
As you guys did who were
I don't know
Baby brezza
Temple of
Black Air Force
I think there were a lot of cases where people
Were convinced by investors or convince themselves to
To keep going and wait for the public exit
Because clearly that's when everybody was in everybody was
Enamored of the IPO
And I do think people were resentful of us
For this in the end they considered it
Lucky verses
Is any type of hard work or Intuition or anything else
And
That that was unfortunate as we worked our butts off to build this business
I mean we were working lived at the office
During this time I never laughed
So
Without a pretty good business in a year it was
10 million dollars our first year
Yet yes people were I think we're very resentful that we have sold at the right time
So
Did you just like
Go to Hawaii and Light
Kick it and drink pina coladas
I did take a year off and my husband and I traveled around it's true but
About two months into it I got I was absolutely miserable I felt like I was missing out on what would happen
Nnnnn fundamentally
There was a perception that
We got lucky
Woodtv.com
End
I had this
Feeling that
Yeah you did that saying once
You're lucky twice you're good
I wanted to
See if I was actually good or not
And so I think I needed to prove to myself that I could do it again
In just a moment how Miriam got into the stationery business and almost abandoned it
Right before stumbling on an idea that would transform the entire
Tire industry
Play with us you listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Sitcom from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
Support also comes from NPR sponsor Gameboy
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees
What annuities can be a smart way to hedge Market
It risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone tag with
Clear conditions and a direct
Low fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Lives in PR
Game Bridge is not available in all states
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I'm Stickin be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR
Garage
2002 and after break
Mark decides to get
Back in the game
Unturned out the body shop
Wants to create an e-commerce
I asked Miriam to run
But after a few years working for a big
Company
Miriam Stark
Getting that entrepreneurial itch
Once again
Will you have entrepreneurial Tendencies sometimes you'll see something that
You can't resist
And
I saw I saw a change in what consumers are willing and excited about consuming and so for example
Bloggers were starting to emerge that were disrupting
Journalist said it really established institutions and
Consumers are willing to read them over those established institutions
And there was great talent coming to the four
It's okay
I would think to myself that perhaps in product design they would be
A similar opportunity
That you could find talented designers
That people would rather buy than the not talented
Interested in the idea of having design competitions in this idea of crowdsourcing
And so I
Decided to take stationary which was an interesting model for me
And mash it up with
Kind of experimental idea
Which way is crowdsourcing
If you better a friend a copy
Coffee shop
And they said
You would say
I'm working on this
This business is going to do
What like what what what
At that point I would have said we're going to sell stationery online
What sounds
Sounds pretty clear
Yep and it was one foot back in the old world is just take the brands consolidate them online and sell them
There is a slightly embarrassing idea I had which was to
Garden design competition around the side and crowd-sourced designs
They weren't available through
Established
Stationery Brands and I was going to do that
On the side
In other words you at you said I'm going to have a site to sell stationery and then
I'm outside we're going to run like design competitions end
And maybe we can develop stationary based on the winner of that design competition
That's right exactly
The idea was focused around stationary retail and it had fantastic economics
Associated with that good margins it was
Inherently viral product
Cuz your name is on the back of the card your
Your company name
The shopping experience offline mode
Was pretty archaic
If you go to a store there be a piece of paper you to fill out
Order some custom cars that have a fax it in
To this supplier it was an archaic
Slow and really inconvenient process
And
I thought in my opinion the design could be improved greatly
And that gave me an opening
For crowd
On the one hand on the other hand
Is a little bit honestly a little bit risk-averse and I thought
That
I did not want to raise Venture Capital again because I
Had had some bumpy experiences
In the first in the first go-round
So I thought
I need to find a business model to apply this idea to
That is very very cash flow positive
And doesn't require a lot of cash
And I'm going to run it as a castle busy
A business that can
Just self-fund right
Because of the rapid ride yet
So you didn't want to have to raise a lot of money but you still had to raise some money
Right
So at this point I was going to friends
And because I had to
Successfully sold Eve they were willing to listen and so
I was actually able to raise a
The pretty big angel
Around
Up 2 and 1/2 million dollars
Switches bag furniture
So you decided you weren't even going to go to BC
That's right at this point I
Wanted much more control I decided not to have a co-founder from the outside
And so I
Put the plan together
And what I found was many of
My friends were a little bit they were very very supportive incredibly supportive
But they were all a little bit
Wariye crowdsource
Because it was
Not a tried-and-true model.
What was tried-and-true is Ecommerce 1.0 which is
Is take all the brand names
Put them online
And provide convenient
Access online
Yeah that's what I did I signed up all the stationery brands
Online and in the end in the background I
Tire decoder who's in college
In Portland
And
Add work at night
On the competition structure which was my real passion
Which was to try to crowdsource
Series about 2 and 1/2 million dollars and Angel
Funding and you
Are ready to launch this site
Which is going to sell stationary by the way how many people did you
Hire did you bring a board to help
If you launch it
To launch minted I had virtually no one
The word Maybe
Five of us
Something like that and I
That's when I raised
I finished the angel round
Wassup blood little bit of space in Jackson
Square
Family started with just a few people first year and who built the website
How did you do that
So we spent almost all the two and a half million on an in-house team
Two came on board at engineer
And the key challenge was how to render
The customization of your stationery online that was
And that was that was assuming we could buy off the shelf
From anyone
So we have to build it ourselves
A way to be able to see what you are stationary would look like
That's right so our Engineers built
A way to see
Your customized text
Appear on the screen in inside your stationery design
And that you couldn't buy from any other
Technology company
So
I spent most of the two and a half million dollars are raised
Going around signing up all these exclusives with stationery brands that
You would see out of Papyrus store for example you you see them
They've already gotten distribution their well-known wedding brands
Thick eyebrows
I spent most the time in the money doing that and then
I just couldn't let go of this other thing that was
Really risky unproven which was to have a design competition
I really really wanted to let myself do that but I just couldn't let myself do it was a
The top of the stairs so
At night I worked with a college student who I found on rent a coder which is embarrassing to admit
We worked on this at night
After everyone that message went home I would build the competition structure with the sky
And
I really wanted to do that full-time but I just I just didn't let myself
April 2008 you launch minted
And and you're like the doors open the shingles out
You're excited you pop the champagne Corks And
Nothing
Nothing absolute dead silence
It was not a cell to be had it was
Terrifying and
Horrible
Woody will we open the doors in the makeup was just
Flying out from day one
This massive amount of sales
There is not one thing sold in the first 30 days not one sale
And we almost I really kind of late at that moment this is a failure
We need to shut this business down need to give whatever remains of the money back to investors
Because it's it's it's a total failure
Did you at least have
Positive Buzz around it
We had a really negative article from TechCrunch
What does it's a terrible idea this Christmas fail before
But I think that they didn't even understand that we had you know it's so successfully sold the company for as much money as we did
Yes
So they just made some assumptions and had just terrible
Like I was a freshman RW and
So what happened why this is what was really fascinating when you look back on it is we just didn't have enough data and so what happened with weed and
Traffic to really
Assess whether we were successful or not because nobody nobody knew about us and nobody was coming
And then when they did come what they were buying where the
Tiny little Kraut Source selection that I mentioned to you that I was my little personal secret hobby passion
Explain how that work
Prefer mom yasso
So when we open our doors in April we had our very first design competition for what people called save-the-date cards that people set up
About to get married
And and we had very few entries
And I think what would happen is we pick something like
Cards
Out of that competition based on voting so the way that made it works is everything
Is submitted To Us by a design
We picked about sick
Designs
And we launched
Those we had
Hundreds if not actually thousands of skus that we were carrying
Established
He said save the date
That already said the save the date or wedding with it was all all sorts of things wedding invitations other things
People provide
And we lost all of that station a wedding station
Free product online and then just our little tiny collection of 60
T6 crowdsource save-the-date
What was
Really different is that
Immediately the submissions that we're coming in
Or breaking
A lot of
Barriers a lot of
Molds that have been assumed about that
Category product for example
People started putting photos
And I remember our printer who we signed up to do this tiny little bit of business at West you know what
In our industry people don't put photos on Save the Day card
They don't do that
I said I understand but
That's what's actually being submitted and that's what the winning
So we're going to sell them
Yeah so what happened was within a couple of months we started getting
Let's say
One order a day
Seriously one order a day maybe by June
And then
No a month after that it went
What two orders a day
Maybe three orders
Still nothing to write home about and then probably not
You're running out of cash
Absolutely
Are Runway at this one is running out
Are conversion rate which is a critical metric that e commerce
Companies use to determine success
Was something like .1% meeting out of all the people who come
.1% by
And that is really really low
You're in trouble
Mike nervous
Yes and we have seen a couple hundred thousand dollars left in the bank
But then we start seeing the tiny set of life I thought well maybe what I can do
Is
Take some Capital at least save this business
Just to be Coop the initial investment and that's it
So
My good friend and Angel one of my really good friend
Alex lieske called me and said
No I'm skinny
Getting nervous about this Market
I think you should take some Capital institutional capital
And I thought you know I feel the same way
Hittite I should get on it
So I went out and I decided
To break my own Rule and x-ray Centre
Capital
And we raised in
We basically
Close our first
She's around
Of capital so that's where we raised a couple million dollars how were you able to
To do that if you
If you
If what you had to show for was a company that was getting
No orders
You're losing my quickly
Like why would a venture capital
Term give you cash it up
That's a great question guy
Yeah that's a great question
So
The reason why they invested in this
Southwest
Personal reputation
That was a delivered one thing successful
Play before and
This one braid investor
From idg
Now Ridge Ventures
Alex Rosen decided to take a chance on
And that's it that's the only reason
And nobody else was into
Do you think I don't want to I don't wanna put you in on
Position
I am but do you think that I'm going to do it anyway
Question
Do you think if you would have been a man
There been no doubt
Oh yeah stationary sounds great here's the money
I think that if I were a man I would
Probably
I have gotten a little bit more credit for what I previously delivered I think a personal reputation effective would have happened with Eve would have
But I don't think stationary was very and design was right interesting to a lot of mail venture capitalist and I
I don't think that
When I say Silicon Valley doesn't have design confidence I mean the
Investors in Silicon Valley
Don't really understand
Design and why it's important
So when you so explain that the business model I mean obviously
You are selling
All of the stationery
Play from from other brands
And so you would get it cut it
Thunder
Business words spelled that would bring in Revenue
But also you had this crowdsourced
Decapitations from designers
And then
How that work like they would
There their designs would be
Imprinted by you guys and then they would get a cat a bath
The way it works back then was that we had the stationery brands
Basically in a wholesale relationship with we would take the product and resell it and
And earn a cut
And we had the Kraut source
Seidwear
Designers would submit
End
They would receive a couple things they first of all they would receive
Peer critique and feedback from their peers will be built in a
Critique face
Which was
A benefit
And second if they won they would receive an upfront cash prize that was completely at our rest meaning
It's never so they can still keep
The cash
And then on top of that if the product sold
They would receive a percentage
Of every cell and so
That's how the business model launched but because
The only thing that sold with the crowdsource product in not
What we spent the entire year
Launching which is all the stationery brands
We actually
Made a hard cut over and buy
Christmas of that year
We went
100% crossword
And so we turned it around we actually decided to move into the holiday cards
Against the advice of all of our
Investors who
Probably rightly said you should focus on what you started with his wedding
We decided to ignore the advice
Launch the holiday cards
And we were
We had an
Exceptional first Christmas Amy Weber
So
Oversold
It was actually shut off our marketing research marketing there are points
Because we're getting too many orders
So the that's when the company went
Two huge
Increase in sales
So what point did you
Decided drop
Selling
Other station
Yeah so that was really rough because
I had gone
Minted as a partner to all of these stationery Brands and I felt very
Ethically
Sounds like a you know I've made a commitment
Explain why we brought them on
And now instead this crowdsourced
Design coming from unknown designers from all over the country is
Just taking off
And I felt very
Uncomfortable and I and I was lingering in that discomfort for many months
It took me at least nine months to say
Escada cotton run
We're going to lose all the money we put into those
Building out those brands on our site because you just cut that
And she said all of that work all that money and all those relationships and weed
Completely pivot towards
A crowdsourced model 100%
I'm assuming you had a lot of
Tough conversations with
Clarion partners
I did
But I think also they they understood why why tie themselves up selling online at minted if
If that's just not why
What's working in the sales aren't happening
In the meantime
We couldn't print fast enough
The work of the
Emerging designers who the customers themselves or picking
So as you start to gain traction those first two years
Did any
I mean
Did any competitors
Yes
We have
Two printers
We had a Oliver Hardy card orders when does 50
Force at the other one is another for
First week of October
My cell phone rings at about 5
It's a CEO of a much larger
Competitor
And
They basically say
We want you to hear the news from us
We have bought
This printing company of yours said that you use
Vista 50% player
I would love to talk to you about how we can continue supplying you with printing services to the holiday season
This is my two two weeks from the start of the holiday season when
All of the you-know-what hits
The fan meeting you have to be prepared your spending you know 10 months that you're preparing for this moment because the seasonality so
So high for holiday cards
And
Basically he said we know can you come in next week to talk to me and invited me I think for the kiss
Meeting
Next Athena the following week
So I went into the meeting and
After a Lil Bit of chatter
He said we'd like to bite you
We like to we like to buy your business
And
I realized in that moment that that whole thing have been constructed to basically Force us to
To sell a business
They basically bought that
Printing
Knowing that you guys would be
Like
That's right
So what did you do when when he said we want to buy you mean I mean
Well I was in his office
Kind of stuck there are so I had to say something so what are you basically said was well let's talk about it let's Howe Avenue
How would this work and I thought in the meantime God I cannot I got to get out of this meeting right now and call my
Supply chain
Start working on this immediately like yeah I left the meeting and I called
But the team is awaiting a
We had a conversation and they were racing around the country
Try to find
Actually have to sell
No I never feared that we would have to
Not once I knew we would find a way around it
I just I just there's just no way I would let that happen
So what did you do I mean
Where'd you go
So we found we found another two printers who were gracious enough to
To take a saint and we
We called
Still inside the company is called printer get in Edmonton
Because the amount of work and he'll our people went through to
To do that integration at tops
Speed with
Dreadful
To this day
That
That that has left
Taste in peoples mouth
Yeah
Around this potential competitor that still I think it's still there
You know
At the time I mean
What was when they were going after even there were
Other companies
Jordan what you were doing like it would ever come
Companies doing custom
Stationer that you can buy
That's right
So the first generation
Companies have been around that
Captivated people just by the sheer fact that they can make custom stationery for you out of diesel
The Price is Right that was just
An outgrowth of the printing in manufacturing industry frankly
We came along with real design
Vision
Andrea Lee
Try to change that
Entirely into a branded
High-end European stationery product with lots
2000 West Alden really changed
It's the industry
So that yes they were choices but we felt the design
Could be better
And more exciting
And then as this community creative Community blossom in developed we realized that
We were a creative community of all kinds of different
People
Some people
Who were former lawyers
Oil rig worker from Alaska
There's a
Plumber a master plumber in New York City's winning stationary challenges
There are all kinds of people
Who want to be creative and he want to earn money creatively admitted is
A platform for these people to be seen
Discovered
Is minted
A profitable company
Yes so we are in the low hundreds of Millions
The dollars in sales
And we are even dollar cash deposit
Are you able to kind of just
Relax out
No and no
Your business
Is fine you'll be fine.
Can you go on vacation and
Disentangle disassociate yourself
From work for a while
And not
He calls like is that
Or do you still ice
Always
Think about the
The survival of your
That's a great question because I think for the first
Believe it or not
5 reasons
6 years even longer of the company there was constant survivability rest
Now I feel differently
I feel like this good company given that it's profitable given that it's going so well
It's a great feeling and yes I can breathe this is this the
Paranoid paranoid immigrant mentality that I have
I think
Grown up with
And then of course
But yeah couple
Crashes in other Market
It is make sense to make you a paranoid person eaten not to forget any of this
It just it just stays with you
But yes I can I can now
Say that a yes I can guy go on a vacation for a week and not worry maybe even two weeks and not worried at all
How much of
Of yours
Success is
Purses
Indulgences
I think so much of it is lock I mean
Think about
What would have
Happen if I
Had not been able to
How many people are in areas around the world where
The cat
Escape
What the situation that their governments are creating for them
Think about all those talented people
Call who won't ever have a check
And an N I guess I would say the other thing is
Just share wanting it very badly right I mean there are there a lot of
People who are smarter than I am
And I think it's just a really focusing on something I'm happily extremely passionate about and love to think about
All the time
And I would say that
Luck and passion probably outweigh the
The Rascals name to CC
Founder of minted
And it's also become one of the biggest crowdsourcing platforms for emerging artists
Tens of thousands of artists submit their work to the site each year and only a tiny handful of chosen
To have their artwork and Designs sold on minted
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about
Are the things your building
But first
Quick thanks to one of our sponsors
American Express
No matter what you do in business
Building a better mousetrap to building a better app
It's easier when you
You don't do it alone
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business
Without it
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you
Go back
And three story comes from Lynn Massachusetts where
Two sisters have perfected
Family recipe
I make the stuffing
That's
Casey White
Timex Adele
And that's her sister Vanessa
And the dough and stuffing
They are for perogies
Polish dumplings filled with
Cheese
Potatoes
I'm sausage
The grandfather used to sell them at the family Deli
Massachusetts in middle school I would go there on Saturdays
Can help pinched perogies in
And we always had them in our freezer kind of like our Kraft macaroni and cheese
That was at the river
We just had Frozen for a few days and one
Your mom would bring them coolers full of pierogies from the deli
And by the time I graduated
They were still eating their friends were two
I'm sure they could get pierogies Trader Joe's or wherever but
The who wanted those
There wasn't really anyone
Making perogies like family
And we finally said it was one of those ideas where you're like someone Zeppelin
Can I do that
We realize after a while that
No one was real that we don't maybe we should
Maybe they should make pierogies and sell them
Guess what this point it was 2015
She's grandfather was
Is no longer alive
But
He had written all of his recipes out by
So they went to the deli
And they got them
We brought them back to
My house
And cake
My table
I hate flower
And so began the Pierogi making for 10 hours
Every Sunday
Vanessa would do
The dough should be not too thick not too chewy
And Casey Wood
Do the feeling
It started with three flavors we started with potato and cheese
The pineapple and cheese
And sweet potato caramelized onion
I do not believe they grow pineapples in
It is very strange
Knowing that something you would find back in the old country but
It actually was one of their grandfather's recipes
Anyway every weekend Casey and Vanessa would make the pierogies
Freeze them
And then sell them at the Farmers Market
In Melrose Mass
Chusetts the first farmers market but about 50 boxes
Sold out in an hour
And realized that there was a market and one reason they were selling so fast
I think dumplings are the ultimate cuff
Whether it's ravioli art empanadas or it's
Asian dumplings
It's very nostalgic
Play all that ye Urban smkc would make and sell pierogi
The Weeknd
And then go to their office jobs during the week
But there was a point where we had to go to the neck
Except cuz we were just
Making only so you know we can only make so much than that
That long 10-hour day
We couldn't grow unless we
So we quit our jobs
Hand after taking that leap
Sisters move their pierogi operation
From Vanessa's house to a commercial kitchen in Gloucester Mass
Massachusetts
They hired a few
People to help
Make more pierogies
Spud Vanessa
She is still doing the dough
Stretching it out
Running it through the dough sheeter
And then cutting those circles thousands of circle today
For the rest of our staff
The Felon pain
Vanessa and Casey call their company Joshua perogies Joshua
Polish word for grandfather
This month they're about to open their first store Front in Somerville
She sits and by the
End of the summer they're hoping to sign a deal that
Would get their Frozen pierogies and some major grocery chains
Across the Northeast
Pineapple and cheese stuffing
They no longer make it
Apparently people don't like
Pineapple with their teeth
But we went to Poland a few years back
Neither of us are pineapple and ndk
I want to learn more about judging perogies head to our new podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if
If you want to tell us your story going to build that mpr.org please love hearing from you
Thanks so much for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or hear a previous episode you go to how I built this.
Npr.org
Please also subscribe to our show at Apple podcast or wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there
They're please do give us a review you can also write to us at HRBT at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
That's how I built this
Are shows produced the sweets rmt naira blue who also
Compose the music
Thanks also to neva grandson of Michigan for new recruits
Jeff Rogers
Our intern JC Howard
Anti-rust even listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email template
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com