Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days away
Campaign monitor.
It's guy here and in case you missed the announcement I want to tell you what this
Incredible
An exciting event we're planning this is the first-ever one day how I built this
Live
Summit
It's an all-day gathering in San Francisco for innovators and
Just like you
It's sponsored by American Express
Andhra hosting it this
October 16th
The Yerba Buena Center for the Arts
I'll be doing live interviews
With some of the most dynamic entrepreneurs
In the world right now like Lyft John Zimmer airbnb's Joe gebbia and
Katrina Lake
Stitch fix
Crossing at workshops
Experts in
Guide there
To give Utah
Advice
You want to find out more or get a
Tickets go to
Npr.org
Flash Summit
Meet you there
Making spinach croissant
We buy the spinach Frozen we didn't have a way to to get rid of the water and somebody came up with the idea with it
Clothes dryers that will dissipate the water
It was a great idea until one day we flew the top off the the dryer in Nigeria ended up with
Spinergy nor 3000 square feet of the production space
From NPR how I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
How to build a successful bakery called Obama pants and then took a big bet
Build an even bigger restaurant chain
Panera
Shake isn't a household name like say Howard Schultz
But you could argue that what Howard Schultz did for coffee
Ron Shack Dead for
Cheddar broccoli soup or the asiago cheese bagel
Because like Howard Ron wasn't just focused on a product he was interested in creating
A space a place where people could hang out for a long time maybe even have a PTA meeting or social gather
Really linger over that
Bagel or cup of soup this is the famous third-place concept that is Howard Schultz
Enron Shake wanted to tap into
Panera became one of the fastest-growing restaurant chains in the world
Invested $7,000 in Panera stock in 1999 sitting on more than half
Half a million dollars
I 2017
If you met Ron shakes a in high school this is not the path you have predicted
Ron wasn't even interested in business his
Passion with politics
His parents were raging liberals and Ron grew up going to rallies and volunteering on campaigns
Oliver New Jersey
Eventually went to Clark University
Where naturally he majored in politics he was quickly elected to Student Government
And that could have been Ron's life
Except for one day
When something happened to Ron and a group of friends
Small but something that when you look back on it
Probably changed his entire life
Yeah so we we were in a local convenience store called store 24 across the street from the main entrance to the
The Clark campus
And they accused of shoplifting and tossed us out
While we were shopping but if I came back to campus
And I was in my dorm room with a couple of friends I said
So why are we shopping there
I like to make sure he's like this where what supports that store
So what do we need for we can do we can do this ourselves
We can have our own convenience store
I said you know this isn't going to be that hard let's go do it
And we approached the university they weren't so keen on this
But
I move the question
The student body
The Boulder Dam
Supportive it
And
Lipase agreed to spend that summer between my sophomore
In junior year
Opening this convenience store guy
Wow so
Would you guys sell
We sold it
Everything from
Drinks
Munchies 2
Cookies and candy in
You know
SAR System Manager
Would come
To my apartment
5 in the morning
And we actually would go to the Steep discount
Supermarket
Bye
10 of 15
Basket
It's full of merchandise that we stock the store with and we hire
20 30 different students to work there
I will
Be very Frank and think it was more interested in that
Store
Then I was in
My own
Academic life
And and your guy who's
Still focused on public policy and government but I guess this
Was kind of cool you like
She kind of like doing business
You like running a business
Yeah and any no I didn't see myself as that kind
And it took me
A while
To make sense
But it's so many ways
Running a business
Is no different than a campaign
Infected campaign
Is a business that that essentially has
One day in Wichita
A business is a campaign
It goes on and never ends
So at this point in his life Ron wasn't
Quite sure what he wanted to do
Business or politics
But people around him saw how much he loved running at convenience store and a lot of people said hey
Why don't you get in the NBA
Sobrante enroll at Harvard Business School in 1976 and when he finished
I'm like a lot of his classmates who wanted to Banking and finance
Brian decided
Going to retail
And he took a job in the Midwest and a place called the original Cookie Company
20 stores in shopping malls we grew at about a hundred 25
I took the job as a third year of the NBA what I mean by that is
I took a job
As a district manager base Iran 10 or 15
Of these cookie stories half the United States
And I spent my time running around the country
And I ended up opening
Thousands of these
Cookie stores around the country
So a certain point if you see your learning about the cookie business I guess and then we're at a certain point
You get this idea like hey wait I can do this myself I can have my own
Cookie store
Yes and I can literally remember traveling across Indiana
On my way to Fort Wayne to open a new cookie store
And hit me
I said why are we opening this in a mall
There's a huge
Can you open these in an urban setting why don't we
And I remember going to my boss
I remember him taking me to meet
The CEO of the company I said
I want open Irving
Cookie store
And it looks amazing
We don't do that here
We open wall base
Retail unit
That's what you're not going to do it I'd like to go do it
Why shouldn't we
And I'm the kind of guy
I say I'm going to do what I want to go do it
And it led me to actually
Resigning my job
Remove back to boss
And
I started looking
Real estate
The reality was
Nobody would release me space for a couple of days
Cookie store because they thought it wouldn't make enough money to pay the rent cuz I had no credibility
Real money
I had
So you don't know balance sheet to sign a lease
And so I went to my dad
And I said I want my inheritance
Whatever it's going to be I want the opportunity to use it
And I had about $25,000 my dad
Essentially
Let me gave me $75,000
And that hundred thousand dollars became
The grubstake the equity
That allowed us to build that
First one square foot cookie store
Wow in downtown Boston
Wouldn't you in the store
We needed the cookie jar
And I can remember we took the Toll House recipe right off the bat I bought a small mixer
And I would pass out cookies in front of the stores we were building it
And I start to adjust the recipe based on what I learned talking to customers and you were the baker you were making the
Cookies yourself
Yeah we opened there were three employees
I mean it was me
And two folks
I will never forget that day
It just seemed like people never stop walking
Coming in
A person get 50,000 people day going by and I'll never forget it I got to the end of a day walking
Yeah but I got to the end of that that first afternoon we open to one guy
And by 6 we closed and my back was hurting my legs were hurting
And I counted the money I
We'd only brought in $400 and I mean
You forget when we talk about business what it is
The cell
400 batches of cookies in a buck each and the amount of energy and work that goes into it
That sounds
Pretty good though music special
The first day
Well I get no guy
The reality of the cookie business
Pain in base of the any businesses
You got to pay the rent
The staff is essentially going to be there
So the question is
What's your volume
And
I was there maybe
Or five months in a we were surviving we're making a lot of money
A fun game
I wanted more what was your vision
For cookie jar did you imagine it being like that
Cookie Company work for in Ohio that it would be
A big chain
Cookie stores was that what you were thinking long-term
You know it's
Funny I have never
Started
With a
Thai goal in mind
What I have always done
And to this day still do
Seeing opportunity
I Wade out into the water
And I try to figure out where that opportunity is going to take me it's a little like bodysurfing when you go on vacation you go to the
The ocean
Are you get out
Far enough away from Shore
You start to watch the waves come in
And then you choose a wave
And you think that's going to be a powerful wave
And then you get on that wave and you see where it takes you and you start to the navigate
And negotiate your way to shore
Insult for me the cookie store was not an end
What it means to take me to the neck
I just love the process of figuring it out
I love the doing of the work
I was working a hundred hours a week
End end
Never felt like work
It was Joy
Oh that you
That it wasn't enough that you wanted more so what
What was your plan to
Cookie jar
Go to the next level
Well it was really interesting I mean
I saw these 50000 people a day going by
But nobody bought cookies before 12 noon
Myself wow what can we do with this
I thought
What do we put in
French bakery it's a sin to be
Growing in
Popularity
People are buying quests on
And the like
And I went to a local
Company called hobo
The small just a local Boston chain
Like two or three location at that point they had three locations
And I became
Their license AZ
For the one square block around my little cookie so in other words you sold what there
Croissants
What I actually converted my store
Two word have to logo
Go sit had the old bumper
Logo
And I have the cookie jar logo
And you could get
French bakeries that we baked
On premise or you could get
The cookies in the afternoon and the thing started doing very well
But
Is an operator and I'm an opera
Rappers of these businesses
You know which of your vendors or any good
H art
And these folks
Audubon pain
I was very clear to me they were out of
I love their product their product was great
What is a business
They were disorganized
Sleep
Sometimes say delivered sometimes they didn't sometimes they billed me
Sometimes
To this day I'm sure I still owe money they just
Didn't have the basic processes
Discipline
And that's typical in many small businesses
And
I saw a powerful opportunity
I put myself
Wow
I really could straighten this business out I really could operate
So what ended up happening guy
I became
Friends with
The
Gentleman was running
The three of them pennsic I later became a
Partner locator
And it was clear.
To him and to me
That Obama pain
Was not going to be able to continue growing
Overstaying a business there and so
I came to them and said look at
I think I can
Fix this
You give me 60% of the company
You and your investors
Keep 40%
I'll put my cookie store which was making money
And with your 301 pants and will create a new
And it was in that process that we created what
Peking
So once you did the deal with
What was Luann in open pan
What did you do like how did you even start
What I knew
I knew how to fix their business
I was committed to doing whatever it took to
To get this thing off the ground
So after we took over Obama
It was a mess
You know we didn't have a way we were making spinach quests on
We buy the spinach Frozen we didn't have a way to
To get rid of the water and somebody came up with the idea with it
A dozen
Dryers
Like hair dryers are no clothes dryers and well but put the spinach in the clothes dryer
And that will dissipate the water
From from
Well that was a great idea
Frozen spinach into clothes dryers
Well we let it defrost first guy
But we put defrosted spinach in clothes dryers
I'm letting it run off the water
Was a great idea
Until one day we blew the top off the the dryer in
Ended up with
Spinach in
In all three thousand square feet of the production I used to love those spinach croissants at Oban pan
You do know how they were made did you
But I can literally remember guy
We didn't even have the ability to maintain our
And
I would use
My auto mechanic
Outfits according to what else to call
And
We had a
Dough divider
That
Was essentially being held together
Daily wire and paper clips made out of mechanic was trying to keep it going
Elmer using
Hanger
As the handle on this dough divider
I was in a
Bakery at about
3 in the morning
And all of a sudden
UC
Sparks come off this dough divider
And this guy
The individual who is working the dough divider
Jumps
Like a deer that have been shot
Falls on the ground like a Raggedy Ann doll
Wow and I and everybody else
In the production era came running over to the sky
Then I can just remember thinking to myself
Please dear God let this guy
Survive
Question my mind Bakery shut down you know Baker
Killed yeah I could imagine a wall
And we're all over there in this
The sex
Vietnam
Veteran
Tattoos all over his body working the big
He comes over and starts to do
Mouth to mouth resuscitation on impounding on his chest
And then
All the sudden this guy who's on the floor open tonight
My nieces
Will you please take your tongue out of my mouth and that's that's what I knew we were going to be okay
When we come back
Aaron took a bone pain from a small business in Boston to a publicly traded National
And then
How you put all of that success on the line
Grow another come
Panera Bread
Gyros and you listening to how I built this
Ron NPR
Support also comes from Madewell
Where the motto is
Good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium denim
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously every
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program to turn old jeans into housing insulation for communities in need
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated
Licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon jimenes mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account at gemini.com bill
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Hey welcome back to how I built this
NPR
You're going to notice
About
Ron Shake
And the story of how he eventually build
Panera Bread
Is just
How many times along the way
Seize new opportunities
That's the improvise adapt
Again
And again and again
Ron come to a point where he has to make a
Big pivot
Transformers business
Annie 1985
3 years after
Ron
Byers
Small French bakery
Boston
A business that's really struggling
He manages to turn things around with his partner lucane
But it's still a small business
Vectron himself work
The sales counter during the day
But doing that
Actually helps him figure out almost by accident
In 1984-1985
I would be in a restaurant
And I have a customer walk up
Could I have that back at Rite Aid and they slice it
I hand them the loaf
And they pull out a bag from the local
Supermarket from local Stop & Shop
And they put roasted turkey and maybe
Cheese on it
And you know you didn't have to be a Harvard MBA
This a
Wow
The real thing here
Is that the
Again
Is not the end
It's the platform to sell Sam
And in my whole view of business
If you really focus on listening you will see amazing things you'll learn amazing
And these customers in their behavior
We're showing us
The opportune
And so in 1985
We created
The first French Bakery Cafe
In the Copley Place Mall in Boston
See the side that you were going to make
This a new experience
It's a new experience for people could come and
Eat lunch and buy bread
Yeah we were going to go from being simply a bakery to a bakery
In almost instantly
Is broken down company became very hot people wanted this I can remember the second day
That we opened
Copley Place
We had 50 people in line
Before we open the doors
And were you serving there
We were serving sandwiches
And some soups
Meat on her bread and croissant
But they were differentiated
Kinds of sandwiches
Is they were Roast Beef in and pours on
Real French baguette
It would be
Roasted turkey
And Brie cheese
And I think what happened was providing
And I don't think we had language for it
Back then
But what the bakery cafe was
Was an alternative
Down and dirty fast food yeah
And fine dining
And for people who were working in White Collar jobs increasingly
In urban settings
This was the first
First example of what we later came to call
Fast casual
This was an attempt to do something that was
Better
But in a quick service mode
Someone suits are still inside the area of
Printing cafes and bakeries
It was after the races you just a minute that point it was clear that
You were going to begin
Pretty rapid expansion
Well can I tweet you know as soon as we came up with this idea of a bakery cafe
We saw
All kinds of
Interesting that we became hot
You know every major office building 1
And we found
We developed
Big competitors
Pepsi came after us
They decided this was going to be the third leg of Pepsi Food Service
And they'd created something
Call La Petite
Cheap lingerie
Sara Lee came after
They bought the
Chain
Call Michelle's back at they were going to open
100 store
There's a company in your part of the world down in DC called Vita France
And they were off and running
And we were
Quite frankly the smallest of the
And the interesting part to me guys now
Is every one of these large competitors had people
With resumes Atwood run rings around Argyle
All of them had far more money in an ounce
They were going to open more store
But every one of them hit the wall
But they didn't have it
Our people
For much more connected
Our guys weren't wearing about their next
Career move our guys were committed
In the Steep and profound way to making this concept work
So we ended up out operating all these larger companies
And by 1991
We were validated when we went public Morgan Stanley took his public
And we really had won the battle
To be the dominant bakery-cafe operator in the mirror
Alright so something something happens
Early in this period Shortly after you go public which is
Olympian acquires this
Small chain of st. louis-based
Sandwich shops called the Saint Louis Bread Company
What what's the story there why did you buy this like
Small chain in St Louis was it that was the idea to to turn them into Au Bon Pain
No I you know I I talked
To everybody in our
There's nobody I don't learn from
And I was asked
Buying Investment Bank to me
Several gentlemen
Who owned a company called st. Louis Bread Company
And it hit me
Doing volume
Almost as much as we did with an Au Bon Pain
But doing so in Suburban St Louis
Struck me this was an opportunity
To acquire
St Louis Bread
And maybe we could build it into a 300 400 500 stores in the Suburban Market
Follow ball pen wizard
Urban Style
So in November of 1990
E3 we bought the Saint Louis Bread Company
Those 19th stores
423 million dollars
You
Are looking at this thing just wait
We can use this as a way to get into the Suburban Market what was the St Louis Bread Company doing that was different
Then why would it appeal to
2 Suburban consumers More Than a Woman
Well it's interests
The Saint Louis Bread Company was in location sites
They were significantly larger
And that enabled it to have
Shall we say A Gathering Place or or
Show Business
Saint Louis Bread Company
Was generating volumes nearly as high as Au Bon Pain
But doing so in real estate that cost half as much is he is the chill business like literally like
Chill out
Tell you mean when you say that
Yeah we called the Gathering Place or Childers ice cream place
But basically it's you know when you and you and you don't want to go back to the office
When you want to play
Stuff to read a magazine to do your bills
Go on Wi-Fi where do you go
It's like the Starbucks this is a Starbucks
Right
Yes tell the difference between us and Starbucks in Starbucks
They're tight spaces so you generally go in with your headphones on and try.
Separate from everybody
Panera
Because we have the space
It's the kind of place you really do want to sit and do an interview
It's the kind of place that that
For a Bible study group or a
A team meeting
You can fit 6 8 10
Alright see you choir Saint Louis Bread Company
It's going to be sort of the Suburban
Alternative to i-mobile pan and you will not going to
Give it the name of them had it was going to be
St.Louis
Thread company or did you initially did you immediately realize you going to rename this
Well we rename the
Concept
Panera Bread in all markets other than St Louis
But we renamed it Panera Bread
Cuz we went to Newmarket
People often thought St Louis was more associated with
Knight's Tale horses
Pol
Right and so
We wanted an empty vessel
Personality we could form
And
Harborview
Was we bought this
Something good happen
Let's take a couple of years and studying
So what you do
Soap
We went off
And I literally spent two years on the road
With yellow legal pad
Talking to people
And it was very clear to me I'm always searching for what's the D for tractor
Post World War 2 fast food with special
You fast forward it 2 1990 with 60000 drive-thrus in America
Fast food had become
Self-service gasoline stations for the human body
And the reality of it was
Adore many consumers
They're holding their noses
21 in to feet
They wanted more than a lot of food cheap
It was very clear to us the same phenomena was happening and bread
You start to see the growth of specialty bread in
In the east coast in the West Coast
And we began to understand
If this phenomena
Offered a powerful opportunity somebody was going to dominate specialty food
And with the power of combining with a specialty bakery
We saw the potential to do it
So at a curiosity in that by 98
You're watching St Louis Bread Company a really start to
Row
Remember how many stores you had at that point
Whitney did you expand beyond the original 19
Yeah by 1998 we were awfully had a hundred fifty
Tea stores
And I was having one of those moments that all
CEOs have
Of self-reflection
I think that was kind of bummed
I was looking at
Panera Bread
As one of four divisions in this
Multi-divisional
Restaurant condo blancpain Teitelbaum Penn International
I have Panera in Audubon Penn manufacturing and I was with a friend
I said you know
For every hundred people
I talked about having a nationally dumb in a concept
Whatever makes
To do so is so difficult but I said this one has that potential and my friend looked at me
What would you do
Panera on douban pan
Not open panels Panera
I said you know I take all the resources we had
Put it against Panera becoming a nationally dominant
And I take myself and the very best people we had and I go down there and make it happen
You were proposing
To sell
Au.bon pain
Antiques proposing to sell everything
Are all the human resource
And myself
And go down to make
So basically you're saying these
Out of the four sub businesses
Let's get rid of these three take the cash and pour it into Panera cuz that
The place that's the thing that has the potential
Yes so you go to your bored and you say let's
Do this and your board is looking at you like you're nuts because they actually
Got into this business in because of a bundt pan
Literally that's what happened guy
It was a huge boardroom struggle
Because I had two votes
Are Venture capitalists had three
And all of them invested in Au Bon Pain
Let's just say there were very heated to
Discussions
Yeah and if I hadn't pulled this off
I probably wouldn't
App state is co
I mean you had a gas when you sold a lump and it was like
Like 250 store something like that
50 * 2
And the Panera only at 180
You really were downsizing
But you thought we need to downsize in order to ethics
Blowed in growth
But I wasn't downsize
I was focusing
I could see the booty
Angela Panera
In retrospect
It looks brilliant
Stock has been up a hundredfold since then
But going through it was horrible
Those businesses Au Bon Pain
Was like my first child
Yeah I birthday die
Gruit
I lived it
I loved
But sometimes
You just have to March 4th
You have to know what matters in Panera's would matter
And you have to get it done
And so we live for the sale of all three other business
And
We change the name of the public company
From Au Bon Pain to Panera
And off we ran
And back then you could have bought our stock
For 3 and 1/2 $4 a share why didn't you tell me why didn't you call me then
You know God I was telling everybody nobody wanted to listen that 3 bucks a share
The truth is nothing to prove until it's done
So you
You are
Taking a big risk in 99 when you sell a bond by 2003
Panera Geneva
Billion dollars
In sales are you doing a Victory lap are you like high-fiving
People in saying see I told you
Guy I never do a Victory lap
The reality is
The time to worry
About tomorrow is
My jobs
Discover what's going to happen
I have what's called a retailers nightmare
Fear that that somehow someway nobody's going to show up tomorrow and then what
You know I get up on the stage right and I I speak in front of
5000 Penelope and I sit there and I think to myself as I'm speaking
I got these people are counting on us to make the right decision yeah
Their mortgage is their kids education
Their livelihoods their lives their careers are counting on us to make the
So I'm continually asking myself
Where we going to be in 3 & 5 years
What do we need to do to get there how do we make sure we don't make a mistake
How do we care for this
How do we store it in the right way
What's interesting to me is that
This growth
Explosive in the early 2000s end
I guess by 2009 there was opening like a new store every
5 days
Basically every three days
Ice insane
Middle of the
Worst financial crisis
How did that happen I mean
How did the financial crisis end
The classic Army not affect you guys
Are whole View
Ways to make smart bets
And one of those smartbets
Comes from a contrarian
Pre the recession pre the Great Recession
The whole world was
It was in a go-go kind of country
Everybody was Levering up their balance sheets
Putting on Deck
Borrowing money to buy backs
Stock broker
At that time we held back
Real estate cost for high
We didn't leverocks
When the recession hit
Is Warren Buffett
To put it that's
The time you make a fortune
Our concept was still strong people are still visiting us we decided to invest our resources
Growing even more quickly during the recession
Real estate cost for down 20% construction cost for down 20%
Simultaneously most of our competitors were ripping Quest out of their p&l trying to chase
The cost down as their sales were defending it was a vicious cycle
We said this is a time to build competitive advantage and ultimately we tripled the stock through the recession
Run I don't I don't want to end
Without asking you about
About Luke
Can your lungs
Time business partner
Is it it seems
You guys have this
Amazing
Very successful partnership and and I know
Lou passed away
In mm
I just do it like how did you
Is most people most Partnerships
Breakdown
People fight they get jealous
Angry to get resentful like
Did you add
Did you have an agreement how are you able to work so well together
What first of all describe love
Lewis R version
Blake Carrington
He was direct from Central
And he looked the part
People lovely
And Lou
Probably
Was at his best
In relationships in building
Relationships and end
I was the guy who
Who really thought deeply about the business
Who ran the business in May.
In lieu and Ice partnership worked
Because we understood each other
Turn up six times more stock than him
But most of
The the community that point
Undoubtedly thought the company was loose
That was twenty years his Junior I was the guy
Who is yuno work with low
He was
Harper College and major fundraiser for Harvard
He was on the Covenant staff in the Marine Corps
In lieu
Was able to
Through his relationships
Develop the real estate
And he had the real estate
And I couldn't
Turn into something
And so we were perfect
Each other and both of us
Till the day he died
Took care of each other
So last year Panera sold was acquired sold to a a German
Company JB holding
Why did you say
Real simple
Because what had allowed us to have this
Powerful success
Was his ability to make long-term transformative smart.
The reality is in the public market
I was deeply worried we would not be able to
Continue to do that you were on Wall Street to answer the Wall Street you cannot do that
No I do know what the truth is I probably could cuz I voted seven
19% of the stock and I had this reputation this credibility
The problem was what happened if I wasn't there
Yeah I see
And I'm 64 I'm not going to be here forever
How does Panera continue to do the things that I created value
There's a pervasive sense of short-termism
That is invaded our Market
The reality is
When you have such short-term pressure on our CEOs
They react
And what that ends up meeting is cost-cutting
And avoid the kind of transformative
Events
That you wrote the success of Panera
Anything of value when you have a
A hundred thousand employees as we do
Can you have as many stores as we do takes time
And so the reality is as a CEO is a leader
I got to figure out where the world is going I got to know how the world is unfolding
And I got to make sure my company is positioned
As the world arrives there
Can't do that
You
Toward the end of 2017 you you announced
That you are stepping down
Are you finally now that you are
Kind of slowing down and stepped out from the day-to-day stuff
Able to enjoy
Cambridge go
Why you didn't
What that way
Are you able to enjoy some of that
Money is freedom
And so I wouldn't
I wouldn't be foolish until you
Am I don't enjoy it
You know I bought them in on this
Panels where
I'm the token entrepreneur
And you know it that business schools in the world
And I always under so wonderful look what you created
I'm usually talk about the money
Yeah I tell him look at you don't understand
You know
Don't like the people you work with
If you don't like the doing of the doing the creative process of it
You're never going to get there
It's not about going to lunch at
The club it's not about the finance
And you better be clear about the entrepreneurial life
The business Anjou you don't own it
And this business was with me it still is
Every Minute Of My Life
Turn off in the shower
When I'm sleeping
The way
You develop it that's the way you grow it
And that's the way you run it and if you're not willing to pay that price
You don't want to do what this is all about
He was CEO for 36 years before officially handing over the reins of Panera Bread in early
2018 late in 2017 after Panera would private again
And 20 years after selling Oban pan to focus on building up Panera
The company actually bought back
Obama Panda 2 brands are once again part of the same family
Do you have to eat
Lunch at Panera
Panera
Go I don't know
Four five times a week now slow down
Yeah my kids are in another four or five times so we still love Daenerys
And stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
But thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Easily create your own website with help
24/7 award-winning
Customer support
Visit squarespace.com build it
Retrial
And then use offer code build it
To save 10% off your
First purchase
The website or domain
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
I know for how you built that and today story comes from Tyson Walters who lives in Los
Angeles
Is dog Harley my Saint Bernard is actually 9 years old now
And she was a true inspiration behind
The product
No Harley like a lot of dogs is lovable but
Also like a lot of dogs
She sheds all over the place
Which initially was a big problem because
Tyson wanted to take her everywhere not just to the park but to friends houses
So there was a lot of conversations to people before I brought her over as in you're going to vacuum when she leaves
Or even riding in cars no one wanted to ride with me because they knew they're going to be full of
Of hair in Tysons
Take this problem very seriously the research and resource like what could I do and there was no solution
So I kind of started
To create it
This was around 2011 when Tyson just got out of college and moved
Back in with his parents and they didn't want Harley shedding all over the house either
So they thought maybe we can design some kind of bodysuit for you know something's are really good
Get all that hair and
Keep it in
And something that was possible for the dog to
So
You know the first idea started from just a blanket and kind of messing around with. And trying to make some leg holes
Everything from like more of a net probably imagine how this all went down
Tyson and his mom worked with an old sewing machine in the living room
Tried a bunch of different designs and we finally kind of came up with Alexis look like a baggy shirt that the dog wore
But the shirt was too baggy in the fabric wasn't breathable enough until
Tyson and his mom basically hit a wall
Craigslist and he found a professional seamstress she could see it in her head better and
And then she would recommend different materials to Stats when she started bringing you into stretchy material kind of like the Under Armour and
Nike athletic shirts
DC
That's when it finally came together and what day eventually came up with
Who is this
Form-fitting suit kind of like body Spanx for dogs different colors
And 9 different sizes
From Chihuahua
The Great Dane
Most dogs are actually okay with it
The fabric sew stretchy really doesn't hinder their movement at all
It's a very lightweight
And I would double-check with beds and stuff like that and I'll give it to you okay as well but remember the whole point
Is to keep your dog's hair from winding up all over your house or your car all there is is contained
Pretty much in a suit so you just take it off outside you can shake it out
Weird looks going to get from your neighbors
Most people's reaction as they laugh
They last and say what is this and you have to see this to believe me because
What I looked at all the pictures of these dogs in their Spanx
I almost wondered whether they were kind of embarrassed
Are you a Tyson called his dog suit the shed Defender he found a manufacturer in San Francisco and
Things really took off when a website called dodo.com posted a piece about them give us a real
Big Boost once we launched and it's all been free advertisement
Susan of these shed Defenders and his company has grossed more than $1000000 since he got it going back in
In 2016
And by the way it is not just an
Indoor suit a lot of owners use the shed Defender outside the
Keep their dogs Clean and Free of ticks and if your dog needs to go
Well there's also a zipper so you just partially unzip it the space is wide enough
For the dog too
Use the restroom and then once they come back and you can just
Zip it on up
You can find out more about shed defender on our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening
You are show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes
Please also subscribe to our show at Apple podcast or however you get your podcast
He also write us at HRBT at npr.org you can sweet us to at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman from Teen Arab Louis composed the music thanks also to me
Grandson has meshkinpour Tamiflu Newark could see and Jeff Rogers and Guy Roz Angeles
How I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
Alexa drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week