Support for this podcast
In the following message come from mizzenandmain
Creators of moisture Wick
Wrinkle resistant dress shirt
Shirts that require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
And use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
Support for this podcast comes from
American Express
No matter what you do in business
I'm building a better mousetrap to building a better app
It's easier
Don't go too long
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
And one more thing before we start this episode just a little warning that my interview with Peter Rahal has
Salty language in a
Peter
Definitely drops a few
POF
So if you're listening with kids
Just bear that in mind
And
Puritas
You got this idea you have a plan
Did you think it was funny
So that was actually our initial plan a number of a deer and I like talking about the guy who didn't raise money from
Am I ever asking my dad like do you know any of y'all rich people acting like
You can connect me with us give us some money and you
And my dad was like he's old school is like super traditional things like you need to shut the f******
Install a thousand bars
From NPR how I built this show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
Peter Rahal turned egg whites cashews
$10 brand called
Website like
Amazon
And type in energy bars
Can you start counting all the different
Types of bars that come up and I mean brand
Flavors
Brands of energy bars
You will probably lose count
Around 300
And the actual number is a lot higher maybe as many as
Thousand
No one really knows
The point is is that
Energy bars
This is a really crowded sector
But six years ago
Peter Rahal walked
Into that extremely crowded space
Heather energy bar
So Peter and his co-founder started RX
Bar in Chicago
With almost no money
And know it
Experience in the field
What they did have was an interesting idea
A way to market energy bars
People at thought of before
Cannabis side door into a very jam-packed Marketplace
And that side door
Making energy bars for a very nice group of
Fitness Room
Even though they started small you can now find RX bars in just about any major grocery
Free chain in America
You've probably seen them that got those
Distinctive packages with the ingredients listed right on the front of the label
Egg whites
4 almonds
6 cashews
Etcetera etcetera
That label and that app
Approach
Peter drahos little start-up into the
In 2017
Less than five years after launching and Peter's parents
Basement
RX bars sold to Kellogg's for
A hundred million dollars
It's an incredible story
And I was super excited to hear Peter tell it when I sat down with him
In front of a live audience
Athenaeum theater
Uchicago
Meter wow
You are
I think some of your friends are here
Yeah amazing
Amazing
Tell me a little bit about
Your home life as a kit using grub2 far from here about
20 minute drive or something
Yashow
60 miles from Chicago
A pretty picture us
Suburban both sides of my family are Lebanese and I tribute a lot of my
Strengths and weaknesses
Is to that DNA
And so what did what do they mean like did you guys eat like Lebanese
Food did you
Like I don't know whether like cultural things that you did Growing Up
Yeah
I think
Comfort and conflict
Valuing trade and commerce
But like I mean around the dinner table was their comfort in conflict
Yeah yeah I just normal
You know you going to fight in the next 100 years
Nothing's wrong
Yeah
It's unusual for an American culture
That's how our
Sunburn
Our family was
Yeah
And what what what is your parents do
Water bowser business
So am I
Father Works in
He's a broker Trader agent for
Juice concentrate or different industrial Fruit Products
I'm so they represent
Processors in Europe
South America Asia
Like-for-likes Ford apple apple juice concentrate that represent
The processor in China and then
Sell it
In the United States
So
Global trading
Brookridge so-n-so real foods
So you kind of grew up a little bit in this world of of the food industry
It listen to my dad all
Metal hours
Talking about
You know
Selling loads of apple juice and drums and all this language in jargon and
And like for me I just knew the food is all I really know yeah so he he really
Introduce the business to the family
Business his business was part of his life
Inside
That was like normal
What about school was school easy for you or was it
Yes school is probably
The first bit of adversity I face my life so
I was miserable at school and I'm not
Meant to do anything
Vanira
For example
I remember specifically in like
7th grade words
My friends were going to study hall
And I was pulled out of the normal study hall
And
I was put into a special study hall
And so for me I've always
Misinterpret
I'm not normal or I'm slow or I'm stupid
I kind of always planted School informal education
Yeah did you
I guess
Your your mom had you tested
Brake for
What's wrong with him
You were dyslexic
How old were you when you when you do that
Wrong when I think I learn to read
Like wait later like speech therapy all this s***
Yes
I mean from from
Second grade
22 I just thought I was like Nazi
You think about it today in our society like
When your 12 years old are 16 and even in high school and college your performance or success is determined based on your mark
School
Mei was a d student
Like and I tried
I worked really hard like I was a good deed I like had to climb a hill with a airplane on my back
So it was great conditioning for me to kind of go on and survive and I think about some of the early
What is borax or particularly
Gerardus like survival
Yeah
But you did get into the marijuana business
Is it over
In high school first of all
How do you know what to do
So is it
A child I was always fascinated by
Cycle of life with gardening
Seoul
Yes
It's really fascinating that you can make plant a seed
You take care of it you put it in a good spot
You nurture it and then it grows
In to say a tomato
And then you can Harvest it
It's for real as a kid I was into gardening
I'm headed vegetable gardens in them
Securus
16 year 17 year old
This Is Why I'm Hot you said season apparently doesn't have seeds in it anymore
I got
Mad Season I just
Innocently
In my
Yea germinated inside with a light
And then my parents ruined my prayers have a beautiful house and the roof is really flat
And
It's one of those houses that's in the forest a little bit on a hill
And so is put on a Roof Inn
You know and it grew beautifully and
And then it came to harvest again I'm not a good salesperson
I was trying to sell but no one wanted by it's really a really just gave it to all my friends and I was just one process right
The next year I grew it again
I got more sophisticated
But then
The landscapers saw and my dad had enough
Took it down
And I planted in the yard but then they
They mowed it over
Habitat
That was the end
Alright so it's time to go to college right I guess and you were
As you as you say you hate you were not a good student
I'm what did you
Did you hard time getting into college
Yes my family's Legacy was through Denison
And I applied and I didn't get in
So
I went to school where I could get in
And I don't make a whole process I just like I didn't want to thank my mom filled up
Well I mean he was probably
Dyslexia is not a joke I mean this right
It's hard to explain but
How do you how do you explain the people in the Civil War is it where's that you mean
Can you not read easily like what does it mean
I think
Best way to describe it as any sort of sequential tasks
Tasks in a sequence is really challenging
Paying the bills when you think about like something as simple as that
Dyslexics have a really hard time falling those things
Understand what they're good at
And so
What dyslexics are good at is pattern recognition so I can facial recognition
Recognizing shapes
Elastic thinking
Things are really good in strategy did you know that at the time when you were in college
You just thought I cannot read I can do
It's my brain just
Doesn't work that way
Yeah I just like I didn't know what I was good at
Honestly a lot of entry-level jobs required sequential tasks money or thinking
And I'm just now
I think that's why you see a lot of entrepreneurs who are just
So
You made it through you graduated you're done you get your cap and gown and what did you do your first job
So my father was grooming me for to work in the family business and that was like my
So then was to go work at Rahal Foods
You've been going there since you were in diapers
Yep clear nose so what what was the job that you
But you did so I had a bunch of internships at different fruit processing plants and see what they do is they take
Like say apples
And then they will press them and they turn it into it like different products
Juice concentrate
Industrial Products so that they could use company like moss would buy and put into their
Products
And so
My father is able to give me an opportunity at Monday foods which is in Belgium
I'm in there a red food processor so red fruits are
Strawberries raspberries
And I want to learn the business right
Just learn
Pair me for the family business and
It's alright graduate in May and I
I have one week off
Ending of next
Friday I was on a plane with a suitcase
To go to Belgium to move into an apartment
To start Monday
Yeah
The number showing of my first day of work
I showed up in a suit that was like oversized and look like s***
And no one's wearing suits
I didn't get the memo
And was there somebody there was like I know your dad men come on Inn
I mean a Sprite I think your dad had been in this industry is whole life so
Naturally
He wanted you to get experience experience
Raisin raspberry mini red fruit
Springer absolutely and how long did you end up
Staying there in Belgium
Like 13 months
And and I guess there's a. Like server
For your. After you graduate college where you did that job
And then you kind of tried different things you went to
So Lebanon and
For a while for how long did you go to Lebanon for
I was there for a year
What did you do there
I was a student
Not working for a degree
Haha
Insert for me I have great pride in my
Family's origin and
I had to be there
Empathy when you are seeing how other people live
Really valuable experience ism
Alicia Smith
So when you came back to the US
Did you like your dad's okay Dad
I'm ready I've done my internship and
Where's my office of real foods
No
I came back
The origin coming back I was like sick of being a foreigner
But I came back because I
I felt like I was being selfish in pursuing these
Self-serving things and be away from my family and I felt
I felt like my tree wasn't getting anywhere like
So I came back and I kind of knew it
I knew I need another experience so I want
My dad was like No just
Go get in the shower
Where else
He said go get a job so if you wanted to go work at real foods
I think
If they wanted it I would have said yes
For sure
I didn't
Spell
Let's just pause here because had you gone to work for real food your life would have been totally different
An end you might not be sitting here on the stage telling the story
So
But at the time
Did that sting at the time
I was
You look back
My history was used to eating s***
Because you are a bad student
Feeling was not something foreign to me
And I've read that at that time in retro
Respect
You describe yourself
Is an Angry Young Man angry what were you
What would it would it would that mean
In combination of like hunger and drive and then being lost
And
And I think probably honestly a sense of entitlement
You don't even like I should be going here and
I just was short-tempered and
I wear my emotions on my sleeve I was unable to self regulate
Soften my edges a little bit
Were you living with your
Folks would have parents that time
Yes
So you're like 24
No job what is so what did you do what what did you go work
So
I worked for a transportation brokerage
In in Chicago
Another great
Place to start
Does places hire like crazy to like Mills you know
Yeah people Mills Transportation brokerage
So
They get like moving
Something from ADB writer is someone who need something moved
And then there's like
The person who's going to move it
The middleman between
The person who runs the truck
And in the shipper
How are you able to do that with
Dyslexia where you able to kind of
Navigate that job without having to look at spreadsheets and no I mean I wasn't good at the job
I mean
I cannot sell stuff sometimes
I'm easily distracted and
I think
Ashley ditto
Okay
But like 9 months
You're there for 9 months and
Obviously we know what you went to
EcoStar butt
The idea
An energy bar even
Come about
Two origins of that so one
Is
Adam miserable job
I needed a new job
There was that drive to go
Solve a problem right or finding opportunity
I was a early adopter of CrossFit
I was introduced to it playing rugby and I just really fell in love with it is painful at work to gain resolves is
Great community
They advocated for like a Paleo dairy-free sugar-free
Insulite started obviously being influenced by that and
The question was like why isn't there a good tasting
Barden
It's that
That was missing right
And then
Working on a CrossFit Gyms you start to see like
Oh my gosh
There's a group of people that
I'll do the same activity that prescribed the same nutrition values and
Get there
They're selling water they're selling T-shirts into like
Can I see a Retail Landscape
There's nothing like that I mean
It was no
Energy bar that
Fulfilled paleo you know criteria
Larabars
Which one protein receptors one called amramp nutrition
Picasso
Inside sou circuit
So 2012 the wheels start to turn in your head
And
When you
First approached
Let's say your friends
Anywhere like yeah
I want to quit my job and start an energy bar company
In the most possibly the most crowded sector in the food business
If I was your front of the time I'd be like
Dude
You are that
Names of bottled water business
Yeah and I think a lot of people
When United Beaver excited about her we talked about it
The look on their faces like that's a dumb
Dump
Wrong
Necessarily
The market didn't another protein bars
For sure but you were like novice I think this is going to work
Or did you just not talk about it too many people
I don't have any friends and so there's an advantage of that I say okay having many friends
I was kind of private about it
We're just focused and we get some feedback but
You know if it's negative
Iphuck offered is going to do it anyway
And did you again
Like pretty early on did you decide to call your friend Jared. Jared Smith
Did to join you
You can hold them and you said what
Tri-City Ellis liquid
Your sound like
There's a moment we're going to do any commit it's like
Processed foods
You looked at it you looked at the ingredients of other bars
Yeah exactly so we just kind of like disemployment Arie market research and then
Start learning
Really
And what did Jared bring to
This that you didn't have
So one of them
Main advantages of
Being dyslexic
Is you know very
Fairly early on in your life which you're not good at
So it was like I knew I couldn't do it by myself
But you couldn't like to the spreadsheets and yet
Any way I can do a lot
And I knew I needed someone
To rebalance me out
Jared's
Temperament General like
Nevermind
Weird amazing rapport
Known since first grade
It was a natural fit
And and what did you guys do like what was the first thing you did like
You bought a bunch of ingredients
And you will like a Vitamix and you just threw it in there and blend it up like I did you start to
Even
The first was we went to Whole Foods
And just toward the market
On that were like let's start playing around ingredients
Division for like what the product
Be like
Real life
The jargony term is like a minimal ingredient
Fruit nut
Protein bar
Image of like principal
Or philosophy around the product is likely
Whatever part of the formula we needed we wanted to make sure the ingredients for the best
So you think about like binders
Honey herb
Tapioca syrup like we wanted the best binder
Fruits real food
And then meme of protein you can do soy or whey or these other things in
But they're not paleo no in from our world like
Egg whites
Superior
Protein Source the highest bioavailability in
Americans in our culture like
We text everyday so closely associated with Health and Breakfast
In bodybuilding even like they crazy my legs
That's like a protein side right and then the other side like inclusions are flavor components or like
We want almonds peanuts and then
Chocolate like
We searched the US to find 100% chocolate no sugar no sugar added
We found he's like
100% chocolate
Basic cow
And so that was like
How we approach
Glossier products
How much money did you put into this business
Start was like $5,000 each
A $10,000
Can I borrow the five
And
And what kind of equipment did you have like a Cuisinart like I I interviewed Lara merriken
Created Larabars you may have heard this episode I mean she just
Two dates and nuts and put them in a Cuisinart
And then
Ruled it out and shaped it in that was how she did how did you do it in your
In your little
Yo kitchen
So making protein bars is pretty similar to like making cookies or any sort
Joe
So we just use a Cuisinart
And funny that you use a Cuisinart
What anybody interested in the Stream Energy bar business get a Cuisinart
Yeah
They're really good machines
And so the funny thing is in our in our lab or
What we do
Apricot almond today
We have the same
Red mixer that the
First recipe was made as a red queen
Still that's the original one
So you guys would take dates
And stick him in the Cuisinart and you have cashews or
Cashews came later we had
We're so obsessed with being differentiated we want to be differentiated from our bar so we actually used
Dates and figs early on right
So that was a Guy Ritchie
The formula
So who was testing them were you
Giving it to friends and asking for feedback
Yasso
It's like August
2012 to March 2013
You know we did like logs of this RX Bardot and
I'm never showing up to the
CrossFit gym that I would
Was a member of
I was a weirdo with like
Tupperware
Of this stuff and and was the first flavor that you made
Coconut chocolate
So you would you actually
Made the bars put in my Tupperware and went to your CrossFit gym unpack to some Tupperware Ginger do the same at
Jim Hughes ambra
Why was pretty entrenched nextmuni so I can do the owners I knew everyone I was like obsessed with working out so
Everybody was like
It wasn't just once it was all the
You know we collected tons of data
Is this do you like this do not like this what would you like
Would you pay that yeah
Just ask
On a question
Yeah what point did you say okay we got it we can actually start to
Try and sell these
So like ideation was August 2012 in the first time we like collected revenue or made some sales
March
13th
We moved pretty quick so we're really small like we started in my parents basement
Didn't have much exposure we are manufacturing ourselves we're doing
Literally
Every part of the
The business from filling it website ordering ingredients yeah
Like literally designing packaging printing it
Labeling it
All of it
How did it what is it what is the packaging look like
I actually have some all right
Not staged
Quora podcast audience i should describe his package cuz it
It could have been the same package you sold marijuana in high school
It's just say yes
A brown package and there's just a sticker on the front with some coffee beans is rx bar coffee to count on the back it says
No bunch of stuff
Are we couldn't afford
And I proper packaging
So we just designing a PowerPoint and then we would send them we would sin
Send the file
To like
Staples and I remember Jared
Going to Staples in Naperville and like negotiating with a guy to get better rate
Eventually developed a relationship with a guy named Steven
That this was going to be safe that it wouldn't go rotten that it was going to be shelf-stable like
Did you was there a point where
You have to hire somebody to do that or
No
So the hypothesis was all these ingredients by themselves
Star Stable alone
Okay
So you put them together they'll be stable
Simple as that yeah
In like in early stage of a business you can
You can't break the law but you kind of have to break the rules a little bit in life
And we're fine and
But but
I mean all the ingredients are stable and if so
It really wasn't a concern
With it and let you know you look at the market with larabar
Has the Aquino you kind of connect the dots
And how did you come up with the name rx.bar
So from the early days like
Dell strategy was to
Make a product that
Is 4
CrossFit
Architect Market in
For the
Helio consumer in
Build it online we go to web store and sell directly to Jim's then by product that would be like
Consumers coming directly to us
And we would scale that eventually
Cross the chasm in
Could a co-packer and then go into more traditional retail
How was it that there was no energy bar that was
Directed toward the cross
How is it that no one thought about
What I think a lot of people look at it
Niches
And or look at
A Smalls
Segment
And then
It's not big enough for them
Ha
It was like a side entrance almost it wasn't like
We'll start the Whole Foods it was
Start with crossfitters
Yeah and we were very disappointed that I remember being like I rather
We rather have a
CrossFit customer in California than a local Chicago independent
Just cuz
In a grocery store among the Sea of competition we had no awareness product didn't really make sense for everyone
Where is in a CrossFit gym we're by ourselves is literally engineer to design for
For that occasion
Just perfect and so we really focused on
Aladdin
And actually
That's the name I remember sitting in Jared's apartment was she still lives in
And
I member funny story like
So we had to go get the domain
Right right in this the guy some you know
Cybersquatter had the domain
RX bar
And you wanted 10004
That was all your money
Jersey
What's offer $1,000
He offered a thousand you gave it to
Ann Arbor realtor
We should offer 500
Wow
Thousand bucks
So
Early on did you think it we had a lot of people on the show who early on go out and seek funding
Did you I mean you got this idea
If you have a plan
Did you think
Let's go raise money
Yeah
So that was actually our initial plan
A number of a deer and I like talking about guy who didn't raise money from like
Harassing my dad like do you know any rich people I can like
You can connect me with us give us some money and yeah
And my dad was like he's old school
Super traditional
Seems like you need to shut the f******
Install a thousand bars
Coming up
Just a minute
How Peter and Jared sold those first thousand bars
Whole lot more
I'm gyros near listening to a live episode
How I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast comes from American Express
Tracy Chapman
Is Vice President
Global
Experiential marketing
Team created
Amex business lounges at
Chaotic trade shows
Is Tracy I have a lounges of adapted
Fit customers needs
When we first came up with the idea for business
We filled the wounds with laptop
And with printers
We found with the people weren't really turning on the laptops and they weren't using our printers they were sitting down and they wanted a place to call home
The kids
End
That really helped us evolve what we were doing
We need a lot of soft seating we need to put quiet areas that can absorb sound
We were able to recognize these people is more than just business owners
When customers are using our lounges we hope that they walk away understanding what it means to be an American Express customer
It means that everything that we do accounts for the human behind the job not just the job that you're there to do
To learn more about how America
Express to have your back in life
Business
Is it americanexpress.com do business
Hey welcome back to this live episode of How I built this from
Chicago
It's 2012 and
Peter Rahal status
Just told him no I'm I'm not going to find some rich people to loan you money to start your energy bar company
You have to go out and
Prove yourself first
Enercell sandbars
Took Peter and his partner Jared
Well
They listen
And you know. Jared and I are entitled kids you think
Raising money will solve our problems
That message is really powerful because it allowed us to focus on what's important and Arc what was important was proving it
Was important
Figuring it out
And so
Just let me know instead of going to a kitchen be like
Move my parents basement
Instead of going to a designer we went
PowerPoint
Like
Instead of going to a printer we went to
Staples
Instead of going through third-party designer like website we like winter Shopify
That could do other like right when you are very limited resources basically so we both quit our jobs and
And
Started hustling like
Emailing calling
When you would say hey we have these can we send you some to test out
Wolf first we would try to like cell
A Mike Haver selling this
$2 results
You know if there are reluctant or unwilling we would give it a
Consignment we do anything
Bright
And I mean if your cold calling a CrossFit gym
Where they receptive do they blow you off what was their response
So is there an interesting time in CrossFit where like
The idea of retail was just beginning
So a lot of CrossFit
Gyms are very principled and like our job is
How to focus on training
Physical fitness
Not selling Goods
And then some were like more
Open to it
There's a little bit of Education like hey you know
Your customers are your training them you're doing a great job but they're going to buy a cross the street to buy product
Don't forget about is like
Capitalizing in in selling out it's actually like
Delivering
A great good and service to your customers
It's for the CrossFit world really shifted and became really explosive in popularity and you'd start ucg members
Becoming good operators and starting to build retail a front of
Mike Stallings t-shirts and Andrei
Developing the retail site with $10,000
How are you
You know making enough bars
And then bringing of Revenue back
Beginning in the middle of 2013
So one of the advantages of
Manufacturing
Ourselves and
What to give an idea
From
8 a.m. to
Nude everyday during that would make like
327 batches
Which Wich produce how many bars
Is like 440 bars a batch
And we had a team of girls that would pack them in the afternoon and then we would go back but I was our day and so
Empires that you
I don't know their status was but
Did you hire your mom at some point help you pack
Bars to
Yasso
AmeriFirst launching my parents basement
Mrs. Smith and misses
Rahal
Volunteered
We know putting labels on the front and back of this was the biggest pain in the ass
And requires a lot of standing line
Accuracy
My poor mother is
Label them correctly and mrs. Smith was just nail in it and
I was like Mom you got it you can't put the front panel on twice on the package but in in she's like
Romantic idea of her son starting your basement switches love with it
After like two or three times and like this isn't working
So
Your to fire your mom
Yeah
Basically well
So yeah so I mean you guys are making about 440 bars or so a day
Temp 10001
You can make 10000 in how hello
A shift so
8 hours you can make 10000
Two of you
And like
People to help you make them
Did you eat you
No longer working in
In your parents basement this is you you went to work at like a professional kitchen the place to be like rent out
No is a place called Allison flavors which is a
Repacker of juice concentrate used to be across from my fathers
So we just
Got thousand square feet there
And then started operating in his food safe as a grape
Play some would make the product they're make it ship it cell at work work out of it it was actually like
Really proud moments like move out of
Your home in like it was like this is real
So
The advantages to manufacturing and doing it
Small batch
Is
You keep your inventory really low yeah so that's where your cash ultimate Lays
And so we didn't really need to raise a lot of money because we
Made a hundred bars and then went online and sold it we think about selling it online
You're collecting that cash how did people know about it online just Word of Mouth
We had a really clear early adopter like we didn't have these Ambitions of like going National or like
We are we are solving a problem for CrossFit crested aquatic like we wanted to preserve them cuz when your
Quick protein
Oh yeah and it's convenient right there
Or in the morning if you want to like
Do workout have a protein chicken and grab a bar to go for later like
It was a perfect fit
So that's how they're wearing is really like organic in that community in like we talked about like product-market fit it just fit
Early Wellness were
A lot of the organic word-of-mouth traction came from
Mission
9 months of launching this company
You guys did 600
$1,000 in sales
Yasso April 2013 to end-of-year
We did
It's unbelievable real traction early on there's a lot of
Demand
What we are making into
3 News special
We didn't realize how
Special about today
Become
So by the time you hit $600,000 in Revenue in Year One
That all that money is coming back into the business using it to buy more supplies
And were you able to keep up with demand
No
So how long was the wait time it's like
With a CrossFit Gyms that had to wait like weeks or months
So like our capacity was
Space around
Are mixer in our people
So
Like between send an email for example or like promote too much
Because it would stimulate demand and then we won't be able to
Show it
Which is actually a good constrain
It was as healthy we can grow too fast
And most important thing is we had a great empathy for the whole business
I guess production and demand became so intense that by the middle of 2014 you just hired an outside
A manufacturer to make it you guys decided concluded you could not make this yourselves anymore
Into the whole plan was to manufacture so
Skeletal point and then commercialized
So find a good partner to
And the partner was in here in Illinois
No region is upstate New York
And
Good to go right
Knows quite a disaster
Trey
I'm sure
But manufacturing Foods really hard
So I went to go overseas production and Jared is a HomeBase
Making sure filling orders
You were going to New York Upstate New York production over there for a week and
You know this is like my
Baby until
I'm like a lunatic like yeah
Walking around making sure the bars are made right in like
Overseeing everything and
So you come back home and I might Jared this is
Permafrost
Feel it when you were there
Yammy their leadership like
For example I was posted up
In an office for
4 days next to me was the president
And
I we were the only customer there
She didn't
Even acknowledge my presence he just hit in his office
So if you think about
What that says about the company in the leadership there in
But it wasn't a good vibe in
Two two weeks later after that production run
Jared gets an email from
The president when the remix of his hand
Who's next to me and what he say
Just basically like Peter's not allowed at the plant anymore
He was disrespectful to our employees
Your pricing is going to go from
16 Center like whatever double
So Jerry and I are like
Yeah. Retains
Software product like
You never did shelf life studies birds
Too busy like playing offense I guess
There's are some stability issues with it and why was that
Well we only learn because
You know we should make back to sail until the first time we
We Trust lies we made
200 plus thousand bar okay
Selling it through and then
Basically
We had customer saying like AIDS
Jason funny or whatever and so
Add shelf life issues
Antara product
Yeah and so
Yeah I think
One of the things we did
But I'm really proud of his
We took an insurance claim all that inventory
Adding most branches got rid of it cuz it was not up to your standards
And I can reflection
Most brands I'm pretty confident with a sword through it
And
It was a really dark
Without inventory worth at retail
$300,000 for $100,000
And I think about that and maybe did like $500,000 in sales by the end of that like
Process
We are out of stock for
Two or three months
Why were you like found a new partner
We would then be like August we did a hundred
20000 mm
Sign into that year 2 million in Revenue yet I know exactly
Not being able to sell stuff
Still primarily CrossFit gyms in people buying online through word-of-mouth
Okay I remember
First seeing these
In
2016 and Trader Joe's
And
I go out on Paleo sometimes easier
But I said I was going to paleo face
And I saw them eat this
How did you get into Trader Joe's
He has a Trader Joe's has a huge milestone for us
Did you think about it for the first time
When someone asks
The company like
Where can I buy an RX bar for the first time our answer wasn't like will where do you live
Yeah
So
It was really amazing to have that like hole footprint how did they even had did you get in touch with them did you pitch them to they come to you
So is that a trade show expressed some interest and then are like a buyer and come by your booth
Yep I was like a product
That was under-resourced probably tablecloth and just piles of RX
Yep
So you get
Getting it how long does it take you between a trade show in the time that these bars are in Trader Joe's it along
So is like January to June
Was that an instant game changer for you guys
Yeah
Yeah it was kind of like all right we're in the big league
It's a hard place to get into
You think about it like
If you go to the death set it's only the
Top brands they don't carry local our little ones like
That was like oh s*** this is really working moment and then
Are performance there
Just continue to grow in
That year
Million dollars in Revenue
Qunar aggressive forecast was like
16 to 18
Progressive
But I mean
Did you even have time to sit back with Jared and say
Well
It's crazy
No I think
We're just too focused on like the but snacks when I
Growing it I think
In reflection now we wasting by the fond memories but in the moment we were we were pushed the garage keep going
Keep going
So there was just a huge
Bombshell announcement in November
Kellogg's
Why is the company outright
Six hundred million dollars
This is a company that was started in 2013 and your parents kitchen
Your basement
Yeah
Yai
The number
You know we never dreamed of any sort I'll come like that
I think
That number reflects like television just buy a brand
That valuation whichever looks at his
I really weigh more than just a bar I mean
Under the hood with really special people
You're great company Reddit great value
Yeah
So you are now a Kellogg's employee
You are the CEO of the company as you've always been
And
You are 32
Yes
You got all of this money is it weird
When did Jesus live
Process it is a change
Anything practically
Does it change anything about the way you the way you live your life or how you feel
No it doesn't change me I mean I still dress like s*** and have
Same shity shoes that people make fun of me
The only thing that changes is like where you sleep and how you
The opportunity
Where you can travel and I think the biggest thing is just Freedom like Financial Freedom
You have to worry about
Providing for your future and that's I think it's a burden that
It's really hard and so I think
You know me Jared's still lives in his
400 square foot apartment
Think about that
Probably
Some capacity for sure I want to do good I think it's a responsibility
Like
I've had some success
And I think you owe it back
Get some in some way so
So
You were the podcasts before
I know some folks in the audience have
I always ask one question at the very end
Which is how much it would happen to you
Do you tribute to your skill
Your hard work you're in
Intelligence
How much to lie
You know I think I'm very lucky to be born in the United
States I think I'm very lucky to
Have a family in
And you know if I didn't have my father and mother
Raise me the way I did I would be drunk at a bar miserable
Call United mean Mike
So I'm very lucky for those things and very lucky that I I met Sheridan
Humble
Partner to do this with
I'm very lucky to be dyslexic and
Are the attributes and strengths and weaknesses with that
I'm very lucky this is the Golden Age of
Entrepreneurship in food
So
I think
A lot of it is luck but
Telecaster play a variable in it
But it doesn't happen without good timing in lock
Peter Rahal
Founder of RX bar thank you so much
After removing
I spoke to Peter at the Athenaeum Theater in Chicago and
Peter sat down with me
Even though it was kind of a crazy time for him
Few days before he was set to get married
He told me that
11e standards
The wedding was a pretty intimate Affair just a hundred and fifty or so guests
I know the menu was not paleo
Peter and his wife serve lots of to salad hummus
Mountains of
Pita bread
Hey thanks so much for listening to
Live episode of How I built this from Chicago
Shows produced by routine Arab Louis who also
Pause the music
Are live team in Chicago
Ellie Prescott
Alemania
Thanks also to neva Grant
Michigan for Jeff Rogers
Hyundai
Our intern is JC Howard
Gyros even listening to how I built this NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor