Support for this in
NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from VSP individual Vision play
Entrepreneurs innovators and creators
Stop overpaying for eye exam
Sam's and Quality Glass
You can buy vision coverage on your own
Learn more at need VSP coverage.
It's got here
Took Melissa & Doug Bernstein
Originally planned to make
Educational videos
For kids
But when that plan
Didn't quite work out
They decided to shift
Toys
And the rest as they say is
Well you'll have to go the episode to find out
Melissa & Doug story first aired
December 2
Basically what happened is when we called the
Let's can I send you some more no it's not selling and we
We would always say but you're not selling it with me to take note it's not selling and this happened
Time and time again and then after about 2 months it was like this stuff is taking up too much space I wanted out of my
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind
The movement
Story of how Melissa & Doug Bernstein multimillion-dollar
Single screen
Video game or app
Okay so
If you have a small child in your life may be a niece or nephew or a grandchild
Pick your own tree
At some point
You will find yourself in a toys
Store and you will be
Frantic
Looking for a new Trans
Former or Shopkins or
Angry Birds video games
And while you're doing that
You might
Stumble on toys made by Melissa & Doug Burns
Sirtoys
I do not have to be plugged in or
Or charge
Upgraded with a lathe
Software
A simple old fashioned toys wooden blocks
Puzzles and
Easels
And the company which is
Actually called Melissa & Doug
Was created
When Melissa & Doug Bernstein we're still dating
Back in 90
And the way they met
They were actually introduced by their parents
What's it like love at first sight was an instant connection
I think from Alyssa with love at first sight would be my gas
Ino it was very interesting.
Because we're both very strong
Drawing people
So
I would say it was
Interesting yet contentious
Social what were you guys
Doing at that time in your life
You know I've
Always been
Wild creative but never
Believed that
Could turn into a vocation
So of course
Instead of pursuing creative
Things I ended up as an investment banker at Morgan
By the way did not like numbers because her
What were you doing Doug
I
Was right out of school I was planning on going in touchy
Education and
I wanted to
Work at a university and
Right when I was getting ready to do that and head off into a
Career in higher education
Got a call from a person I worked Summers for Jim McManus
One of the
Greatest mentors greatest marketing people in the world and
Mr McManus said
Nope you're not doing that you're going to come work for me and
BMI
My assistant be my right-hand and so I went there right after
School
Work
Fur mr. McMahon is for a couple of years and had
An incredible
Experience
But it wasn't what you wanted
It wasn't something that I wouldn't want to do I'm like Melissa and her Investment Banking experience
But no but there was something inside me that tugged and wanted to
Two things one wanted to do something
4 children frankly wanted to
Do something of my
Own creation also
Bright suits
You do well we
Booked ourselves into a little
Bed and breakfast in Lenox
Massachusetts I think was called
The cliftwood
And we walked ourselves in the room
And
Did what everyone would do if locked in a room in Lenox Massachusetts and brainstorm business ideas
We literally said let's close this door and we are not leaving this place until we know what our path
That's what we're going to do what was the idea you came up with in that hotel room in Lenox
I think we walked out of there knowing that we wanted to start by doing some
Interactive
Products for children things that they could really
Interact with rather than be
Passive recipients
So okay so you get back to Westport Connecticut and like what did you do
Within a week's
Quit your job
We did
Weed
Determine that this is what we were doing we literally took
AR
Savings accounts
Put them in one joint account which was
Meager at best
And we
Decided we were going to use those funds
To create our first product
Set this point Melissa are your parents
Regretting that they
That's funny that you say that and I would have to say
My parents were
Scared to death
I bet I remember when we were in Melissa's kitchen we were right
Talking about doing this I remember them being
Concerned
Play because
She had the greatest thing going and
She was leaving it to do
Well we weren't
To certain exactly what we were going to do for kids
No problem yeah you know they were up as as
I guess depression-era
People they were
Just very fierce
And worried
About secure
Whereas
We couldn't have been less
We felt like
He warrant
Living out your
Your passion
Wanting to go to work everyday running to work
Everyday
Then it didn't matter how much
You're making or
Zoe
She was got this like
Small no money and he
Savings account
And
What's the product
So what we decided to do first was
We both had
A little bit of experience with
With the television and
Vision programming
And we decided that we wanted
How to make a
Program for
For children
That would be groundbreaking in that children wooden
Sit there
Watch it
They would actually
Participate
With the program
And so we literally wrote
Scripted
Produced
Directed
Cast
Wrote music Melissa song
Sweetest Thing lyrics
Like a VHS
Video
Ultimately three of them
So what you were
You like
Participated you were on camera
So we
We wrote a script
For this and
We literally went around to stores and parks and we cast real chill
We didn't want
B
Contrived or fake weed
We didn't go to cast
We literally would sit in
Grocery stores and look for animated children
And approach them which
Probably
We literally in parking lots
I would watch for children that are interact
And we had eight children that were in this video
And then we shot it at some friend's house
Houses in Westport Connecticut
Schools
Was it kids singing was it dancing dancing
And it was
Encouraging children who are watching this 2
Participate along
He was literally teaching them some of the songs teaching them
I want we're dancing
Talking directly one of the things that was so unique about it is
The boy who led
The program
Talk directly to the kids
Sit home and
Truly befriended them in
In a very
Honest
Sincere way
Do you remember if you remember any of the songs
Go ahead most thing it
Ready
Special friends special friends we will be
Special friend
That was like the the emotional one at the end
But the others were very
Dooby dooby all sorts of making sounds with your body making sounds
With your lips so how much money did
Did you guys have sink into Pro
To make films
Like it is now
What's a lot
Probably I think all told the first one we probably spent about
30 or $40,000 to produce
Well it did it took all of our savings and then
Finish this we said wow
Is awesome
And then we looked at each other and said
Will wait
What do we do with it we had put no thought at all
Into what do we do with it
This product
We now have to figure out well how
How are we going to be no pay for the next lunch and and what are we going to do to get this
Is product out there
So
Do you make
Thousands of copies
Went to start
So we did and we got our first little lessons in business because right you want to make
Some copies and
You find out
Well we won't make you
U4 copy
Make you 5000
Some copies
And we said what in the world are we going to do with 5000
Some copies we made lists of our relatives and that didn't
Got us fully to 5000
And so we literally bought a little
Combination television VCR player
Put it in the back of my father's station wagon and we started driving around
Knocking on doors of retailers
And the funny thing was this was right around the holidays
The time when we
Refinish this product
And so all the little toy shop
Throughout the New England this was there
Busiest time of year and we would walk in there and apologetically carry in our
Tape player in our TV and put it on their counter and beg them please can we just show this to you please
And I think after enough begging the
Figured out the only way to get us out of their store was to
Take a few of these and present them to their customers so we would leave
Very happy that they decided to take a few of the
Tapes and try to sell them by the way this was another thing that was
Completely against what was happening in the Indus
Because
As a manufacturer you never went
Directly in
You actually had middle people
Call
Pictures rap
Who represented your product
She the smaller stores
But we
Realized that if we used one of those and they would never do R1
Tiny little products
They had hundreds and thousands
The products
And that if we wanted to get our product truly distributed
That we were going to have to
Do it ourselves
2 hour sale
At the beginning people were not buying these
From the store
So they were baiting in the stores and they were remaining on the shells which is not good for long term
Business proposition
And so we learned
Yet another few business last
One was that we learned
Are packaging was interesting
Because
You looked at it and you had
No
Idea
What does product mean
I called the mysteries in a box
When you have something that is in a box
And you have no idea what it is and you're not promoting it on TV or advertising
It's very hard
And the second thing
We learned was that for something new like this
You need to help seed
Some knowledge
Support about it so
Melissa and I then started
All of our week
Driving back around
Stores all throughout the Connecticut New York New Jersey Mass
Chusetts
And we would have play dates in their stores
And we would sit down and
The carpeted area in the store and we were
Sing songs with children weeaboo
Hope and pray that there would be one child there
For two children there and
Maybe they would tell a couple of friends
But it sounds like I mean
Not to be like
Cruel or crude but like
I would say it depends on how you define the word failure there
Because it probably was a failure
In terms of having a
Product
The instantly saldan instantly was successful
Yet it was
The biggest success we ever had in that what we learned
From that and all the learnings came from that are precisely
Every single thing that are
Is based on
Today
Complicit
This point you know
The idea of having direct relationship
With all these customers
Doing anything that they want it I mean they would call us in the middle of the night I have a problem with one of you
Your tapes the phone was on our bed we would answer in the middle of the night
Everything we do today we learned I would say in that first
First couple of years and frankly
Maybe mosto
Currently just the fact that not everything is going to work
So at this point where you guys called Melissa & Doug
Your company
We actually weren't
Our first company name that we called ourselves
What's lights
Camera interact
And the reason the company is called Melissa and Doug it's funny
Because
Weed from day one
Every
Single product
Made we were signing our names
And we were riding on the back of
If you have any comment
Please call Sunny
Anytime Melissa & Doug
And so as we started to get more and more products out there people would call our company
The end we would answer the phone or someone
One would answer the phone
Sensei
I'm sorry I have the wrong number I
Melissa & Doug
And so one day we said well wait let's just answer the phone so I wasn't.
And that's how we became less
Send.
Like one or two years in
We are three years into it at this
Explain so focusing in Thailand videos
Basically it was a video year we produced a video year for three years we have three videos out there in relationship
It's now with I'd say probably
I'm going to guess a couple thousand
Retailer
Yet so how did you like move from
Videos to
Toys like to have you like start to think
Start making
Other things
Well honestly like most things it was another brain
We were talking
In the car about some of our favorite childhood
Toys andme
Talking about on PATH Academy
And Pat the bunny yeah right
Of course books that had
The Tactical
I'm pieces on them you could touch them and
Pat the bunny
Thinking about exactly and we said
I don't know
What made us a at but we said well wouldn't that be great in a
A puzzle
Do attacked
Puzzle
And
We brainstormed
Not having a puzzle that had animals
And that the
Height of each animal was
A piece of plush that had the tech
Extra fat animal in the look
And came up with this idea for what we caught a fuzzy puzzle
And
How to design a puzzle in where to get a manufactured and
Produced in
Where where did you can begin
I would say four
Most of the things that have happened along the way we had no idea
And we learned as we went and we would
Almost the way you were asking the question now we would ask ourselves
The question then so
We need
Animals
Artist
How do we do that so we went to the library week
Look at
A lot of children's books
We look for an illustrator that we liked and we would
Contact illustrator
Let's see who might want to help illustrate this
I'm in each step of the way was
You know a new
New face of learning but at no point was there ever
A a magic answer or an easy answer was a lot of making mistakes and falling down and
Some
Horrible learning experiences along the way
How did you guys a fund
Your company
How are you able to like
NOK for
Take loan to G
Let's go see got investors
You know this is why we grew rather slowly we wanted
To be self-funded
And we lived incredibly frugally
For at least three years we ate
Ramen noodles
Switch rate for a dollar and
Turkey hot dogs
Bugs on a hot plate
About 50 cents a meal
And we lived
With our parents for a few years
Until we could
You know you literally get one room in someone's home above their garage
Help them with errands for
You know what decreasing rent
And we
Middlefield every cent
That we made back in
Into image what I would literally were not we did not take
Play out at that point
Crater that
Play the fuzzy puzzle we able to
Oh gosh I wish it were that easy
Not quite not quite like that so now so so once we had the design for the puzzle I mean everything
Sing again was
Trial and error
I could tell you one of the things that happened early on was the
Very first time we went to a very large
Toy
Show
Where you would exhibit to retailers and show them
Your products
And the agent who we hire to help us make our puzzles had a
Display setup just down the hall from
With our exact puzzle when he was selling who's busy
Selling your puzzles as his own
Yes he was and this
The someone that we had entrusted
And he told us the reason was
Because
We wanted to
Grow slowly and bro with r are independent neighborhood stores
And he wanted us to immediately take them in
Put them in the mass Market in
And because we didn't want to do that he figured he would just do that on its own with our product
So that was his good reason
For doing it
So
Just curious like
Your reaction at that moment was
Was it the Gautam say what what are you doing
What's going on
Did you confront him
No we weren't confrontational about it we're at a huge show thousand
The customer
And when they
I came to us and they started
To tell us that this
This is what this person
Was doing
And they assume that we were part of it or that we knew was going on when they found out that
The truth about what's going on
It was amazing
How many custom
Where's came up to us
And literally in
Rhonda Buss
Ripped up orders
That they had placed
This person who was our agent
Inside here you can
Can show this to him
Now that we understand what
What's going on we will
Absolutely never In Our Lifetime
Time order anything
Sing from that purse
I think that cave
A little glimmer of hope to Bliss
Myself
While on one hand we had a little bit up in the
Exposure to the hump
The darker side of the business world
I would say simultaneously we had a really nice ass
Exposure
To that there are lot of pee
People out there who
Will appreciate the loyalty.
That you have to them and everything that we've done
I'm in the first couple
Years
And are now saying to us we don't care even if he wants to sell it to us for
Less money than you are anything
It doesn't matter we are loyal to you for everything that you've done
Missing you guys were able to
Recover from iTunes
Like move on with puzzles
I guess
We we started to see our way you know it's always about right finding the path through the forest
And it was like this was the category that
Sort of was our path we said oh my gosh I think we're onto
When we come back in a moment
The story of how Melissa & Doug Ruby on puzzles
And then made the biggest investment of their lives
Sonic toy that became a million-dollar
Mistake
And I Rise
How I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Game-braid
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative too complex or only for retirees
But annuities can be a smart way to Head Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuity
Please in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print in
Phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Game Boy
Is not available at Allstate
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape
Two China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple
Cast Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
It's how I built this
NPR
And I Rise
Soap
This point is
It's the mid-1990s
And toy company Melissa & Doug
Is literally
Just Melissa & Doug
Two-person operation
Melissa designs
All the puzzles
Doug tries to get them in
The stores
But then
They decide to start making other toys
You know all these made up until that point
Are puzzles
And we look backward at what was
Wonderful
And incredible from the past and we saw wooden toys that category and we said
Okay here's another category wooden toys
Wow really expensive
Completely inaccessible
2 average
People
The aesthetic
Very
Unapproachable to kids
It's not very playful
And here's a category that we can go in and week
Can really be
So at this point like
Kids are playing with
Plastic toys
Battery operated toys and
Will you guys thinking we're going to be auntie
Battery Toys
We are not going to do that
So
We thought it was so
Interesting that every toy cup
I was chasing
Running forward
Right chasing the hottest fads and Trends in hotline
Kids playing with in the midnight
Was like you know probably Cabbage Patch dolls and TV advertise toys and a lot of sort of hot toys
And that was kind of the market
And we
Saw in this
Experiment
Wood puzzles that ended up working we saw
Oh my goodness
People actually still want
Things that
Are nostalgic
Make them remember their past
But they don't want them Dusty
And like I found them in some old attic
They want them
You know injected with Pizzazz and brought to today
So what did you start to make
What are first line was about a dozen based
Basics reinvented
Pounding and sorting and stacking
Manipulating
And doing them at
Credibly low price points and
Packaging them in a way that it never been package with open the package or designing all of this Melissa
Yes
It's all made out of like
Plastic
Or would
I mean
50% of what we make it
Stillwood
And then
Other materials we use a lot
Meadowview
Canvas
But mostly not play
So at this point are you guys
Do you have an office do you have a look up
Place where you working at up or are you
Still just the two of you or does now do not have some employees
Heights at this point we probably had a couple of part-time people that were helping us we have
So we have a person who's coming up on his
20 years this year his first job with us was
A mix between helping us
Change our baby Brandon's diapers
Helping us
Weed the driveway
And also when trucks would come and deliver products to our house
If you would help us unload the truck and load the products in and
Help us pack up
Products and ship them
So when you really like transitions from puzzles to wooden toys
You're still just selling them mainly in like small
Independent stores in New England
Yes
Occupy this time we ate expanded Beyond New England but definitely the small independent stores
We were firmly convinced that that
Was the only way we
We could really get our products out there
So I mean sounds like you guys were pretty steady path
And did you make any
Big mistake
We have actually never made a mistake it's the
Craziest we have had so many failures that's why we love that word because
Failure is a word you have to get comfortable with and you can't fear the failure
So tell me about some
So behind my desk
I have
About I can't even fit them anymore maybe 500
Toys that were all my very
Toys that failed
In a big way
Some of them entire categories because
Everyday I want to remind myself when I
Come to work and come to my desk that the line but
Between success and failure is as fine as a spider web
And you really never know what were some of the
The toys that didn't work
Oh my gosh
So many but one of the lines that we were most
Excited about and I think was a
The huge investment was a line called puzzle world
And it was an entire world
Made out of puzzle pieces
Not only horizontally they connected to form a base
But you could build up vertically and don't skyscrapers
It was the most amazing
Line ever
Elaborate undertaking and above more Tulane more Machining
It was by far our largest Endeavor ever hear of development
Expensive and costly to buy inventory because unlike other products the retails were about 30 to $100
Forceps they were sold in sets
It was not and we had all our prototypes which took us over a year to create and only
We brought it to Boise Fair and had our play table out
And the reaction
Was actually incredible amazing best ever of we have
I believe we had a thousand assortment
And we literally by the third day of toys are we sold out
But we made it clear to our retailers
That
This was going to be a big undertaking for that because this was not an item that was TV advertised
It was expensive part understand
And it was going to take a lot of
Vacation on their part educating their custom
About the merits of this but we told them
If they do this
It will be an annuity
They will
Have
You know years and years of the selling and generations by more sets and will create more
Each set connected
Get to the other side it was all interconnected and it even connected to the popular Railway sets at the time the Thomas and the breed
So it connected into any
Existing set you had as well
And they agreed and we
Set it out
And
Do you want to
Oh Sherrie she
But that's not she tells all the exciting ray parts
Yeah so my part is yeah and it failed and it all came back to us
In the warehouse
Receiving it all back that was my role what happened people
Just didn't buy it
Basically what happened is when we called the stores two weeks later you know hey let's can I send you some more
Nope can't
It's not selling
And we would always say
But you're not selling it
Take a note it's not selling
And this happened time and time again
And then after about two months
It was like
This stuff is taking up too much space
Yes I wanted out of my store but it just didn't it just it never took off
The stores never got behind it
To sell it
I mean I think it had
Potential to
Take off but it's hard you know it
It's hard to run a store and you have thousands of products
And you've Lots
Also competing in
And here we are thinking
Well field
Just focus on our product
Reminder There's a higher burden on us
Because we take our product
Really personally
We think that everyone in every day is going to
Take all the time too
Explain everything about it the way that
We the inventors
And that's not always the case that can't be done
So we realized our job
It's our job
To design it in a way that
Speak
Still there
Customers
And that's really what we started
What to do after that
Do you know when they like how do you know when a toy is
Is going to work
It's amazing you know really
I mean we don't have you know where nada
I hit driven company
Joke that we have a lot of singles and doubles
We don't really want home runs
Because we don't want it here today gone tomorrow we're in Evergreen company we want our
Forever even when she's working at a product of Our Own
Test laboratory with our six children at home is always
Using rrr products with their own children
I would say the initial ideation I mean you're obviously
Feeling a good God that your you have an idea
It's going to work and then throughout the process
What we do a
Huge amount of
We call it Mom testing and Mom is synonymous with caregiver dad
You know anyone who's playing
Teacher
I am we get
A good
Sense as we're going through the process
Assist but the truth is that's the
Joy of it you never know
For sure at all and there's surprises everything
Yeah
I need attention because
You start this company in night
10 years real
Before
The internet start
Takeoff
There was no reason why wooden products
An analog toys
And it's so it's so unlikely and in fact every reason why they wouldn't
Succeeding
And I think that's been a part of you note to the extent we have a
Model
I think that's been a part of it all long is
To not go with the tide not go the direction not look at things and say
That's what everyone is doing that's what we should do because our feeling has always been if we copy
Every good model out there at very best what does that mean
We're going to be mediocre
By definition because we are simply following and
I'm copying whatever one
Elsa's doing
So it was there ever a point though so when
I don't know like investors or somebody
Set you guys like you've got to do something with batteries or you've got to do something that
You know Electronics or something
An integer
Are they say to us every single tab
That that's and you know that is
One of the things I think
That has kept us successful is we stayed true to Mission
You know
Ever since we started with our very first puzzle
Did you guys
Basically did this on your own for
Pretty much until a few years ago right in you were
A successful company
But I guess
Just a few years ago you decided to
You to see outside
Investors correct significant ownership and we brought in
Some investors who now will
Sit on our board and
Participate very actively with us also in health
Because the truth is for the first 20 years we really did this without mentor
You know it was literally was fighting her own way in a very dark room what did the investment
Allow you to do it
The company I think
Two things one is they have rolodexes that are much larger than ours then introduced us to folks that can
Can help with things and then financially also frankly Freedom 2
Grow and expand more exponentially if we want to
Expand our footprint internationally and so
Open up those doors to
I'm curious
How did you guys I mean obviously if you got I mean
Directions to Arby's
But it seems
Like you have a great relationship and
Your great business partners but also a great
A couple with parents
We got kids wealthy
What's 6 kids
Yep
You were just trying to figure out how many kids she was going to stay with her first husband
I was going to say do you consider Doug a child or not
Six children and then.
Stupid like honestly
Was it all like
Blissful
Joyful and laughing ORD were there moments of tension between the two
You mean this morning or in general
It's a combination the good news is that we
We absolutely do have things that we disagree on which is good and which is healthy
But I would have to say that I think
We have
Our respect and admiration that that keeps it working
Perfectly
You know both from a business and a personal
I mean in terms of
The business
We never would have been able to make it
Without each other
I mean this is
Absolutely
A partnership and a partnership is necessary to go through
Everything we've gone through I mean this
Although it seems Blissful and easy
Are the 28 years has not been easy and we have faced every challenge imaginable and it goes on and on
Everyday Melissa & Doug Bernstein run the toy company
Melissa & Doug
The company has grown from just the two of them to almost a thousand employees with revenue of more than three
350 million dollars a year
And they still make lots
Lots of puzzles remember the letter puzzle you take the letter out and says it's a
You hear the sound of the letter
For some reason one or two letters weren't in the right slot
Fall asleep in my kids room with them in the middle and I just heard
Jay
Where's that coming from Over the sensor
Is that what this is all about you want to reply to do you want a replacement for that
You need to sleep tonight
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
QuickBooks
When you work for yourself
Every receipt lost
Cash lost
The end of the year
Snap and sort your business expenses with QuickBooks
Maximum tax deduction
Smarter business tools for the world
Hardest workers
QuickBooks
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And the story we ran about a year ago this one is from Joshua esnard grew up in Ithaca
New York we were immigrants
From St Lucia in the Caribbean and my dad being an old-school Caribbean guy
Everyone knows about the old school parents they cut their children's hair they did but his dad's
Version of a haircut
Was not exactly Joshua's idea of a haircut
And I wanted to edge up my hair and have a
The cooler hairstyle so I realized that I need to find a way to give myself the Styles at all the key
Cool kids ad
To pay a barber
And what he tried giving himself a cut with his dad's Clippers
Well I ended up
With bald spots
Let's just say that I spent
A lot of time in middle school with hats on my
Joshua is 13 at the time
The kind of kid who loved
How to draw and design and I realized that if I can cut some pieces of plastic and cardboard
And mess them together for
Certain designs and stencils
I may be able to use that as a
As a guide
To help me cut my
My hair invented
Basically he head stencil
Press it against his head
And then head shave around it and the first haircut was
Perfect Liker
The Chris
Curves on my sideburns for just amazing to the point that
People like man you went to the barber
Who's your Barber
Me I'm the barber he would say
And Joshua kept
Using his stencil through middle school and then High School
And in his mid-20s he decided to patent his invention
In a few months
The cut buddy was born so I actually took the product
And I shot a video of me cutting my own hair
With the cut buddy
He put it on YouTube and
I'm sales but also
Maybe this is because Joshua doesn't have the best
Care for the sort of thing
Some people started to
Control him
Oh my goodness he has a receding hairline
His products suck
But what they didn't realize was that
The main issue was obviously me as the model
So Joshua cast out for guys with
Perfect hair 2
2 demo his product on YouTube
And those videos they actually started to work
He started selling like a few dozen cut buddy
And then
What a popular DIY sight post
One of the videos
Went viral
I'll never forget it
I'm putting on my clothes
And my phone just starts going
Ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding
Notification
All this happened in March of 2016
And Joshua started to get hundreds of orders
The cut buddy
And since then
He sold about 90
You also get a chance
To go on Shark Tank
And where the Sharks gave him a
$300,000 investment
And with that money
He's starting to get the
The cut buddy into some major chain stores
Target and another piece of good news his wife
Recently had a baby
Baby's name
Is Phoenix
We love hearing about
The things that your building and if you want to tell us your story
Go to build
Npr.org
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this.
Dr. Org
Please also subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcast or however you
Get your podcast
You can also write us at Hib tea at npr.org and you can
Twitter stats at how I built this
Or shows produced this week by Run. Defatta
Music composed By Ram teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva Grant
Sanaz meshkinpour Thomas Luther
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is newer coetzee
I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
Alexa drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week