Support for this podcast in the following message come from Madewell where the motto is good day start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com to find your perfect pair
Patriots guy here
You know I usually get to ask
I guess the question how did you get to where you got it was
La course Killer part work or what
With high and Sivan
I actually never got around to asking
But in this episode you will still here a lot
About luck a lot about hard work and he
Ton about hyams
Special skill which is
Knowing a really good idea when he sees one
This episode first ran in March
Last year
I hope you enjoy it
I have to tell you that the biggest hits
That I had in my life ending music and hunting television and heading business
I have been always as a result of significant projections
And the repeated rejections so every time I have an idea that people tell me no don't do it
From NPR
How I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movements
A group of a spandex wearing teenage superheroes called the Power Rangers help turn Haim Saban
One of the richest man on earth
If you ask the Haim Saban what he does
I used to describe myself as a cartoon schleper
Cartoon flapper
Yep
What I did for years is I
Went and knocked on doors on
Try to sell
Cartoons
All over the world
That's what a slapper does
And he slept some of the biggest cartoons of the 80s
The 90s
Inspector Gadget
X-Men and of course
His biggest hit
The Mighty Morphin Power Ranger
Which has just been revived is a blockbuster Hollywood feature
Kids found a spaceship buried underground
I'm pretty sure I'm a superhero
But we're getting ahead of ourselves here because long before the Power Rangers long before
Haim Saban was flying around the world on a
Private jet charter
Hangouts Beverly Hills mansion with Bill Clinton
He was just a poor Jewish kid living on a Dusty Street
In Alexandria Egypt
We lived in
Very narrow Street
We were kind of
Lower class
Family my father was a Salesman in a toy store and my mother was a seamstress
We had
Family friends were Egyptian Muslims Egyptian Christians
Greeks Italians
It wasn't pretty Cosmopolitan city Alexandria in 1956 shortly after
The Suez War many Egyptian Jews were accused of being traitors so I'm Stanley had to flee.
Israel Highway 12 at the time and no one in his family spoke in Hebrew in fact they didn't know
Anyone in Israel and when they got there they were housed in a tiny apartment in a rough part of Tel Aviv
It was one room in an apartment that had three rooms and the other two rooms
Who are occupied by another couple and by
A hooker and her pimp
And it was the five of us
And
My father basically had a job
Selling pencils and erasers
Door to door
And some days you would tell three pencils and some days
No pencil
To say the least a very hard
Life yes
And do you remember
Going to school right away
Well I didn't want to go to school but my father thought I should be a lawyer
I mean I I wanted to make money you know because
Living under these conditions was not
Avairy
Exciting prospect
That's all
We compromised that I would
Work during the day
Study
At night
So
I'd wake up at 6 I go to
Be a runner in travel agency
4:30 the afternoon not go to school until 9:30
Antonia come home I do my homework
In the staircase
Because obviously I couldn't do it
In the room
The family was
And
Go to sleep and then
Everyday was the same routine
What were you a good student
I was a pretty bad student
And
The principal called my father and said
Your son most probably is going to make a lot of money one day but
A student and academic she ain't going to be any ain't going to be no lawyer so take him out of school so my father
Father sat me down and said
I need you
To finish
High School
I'm finished with high-grade
And then you can do whatever you want
But you must finish High
And did you finish with high grades
Yes
Did you feel in any way
Being a Jew
From an Arab can
Free in Israel
The time
That
I know you were you were
Racine assertive
Lower
Citizen buy
I choose from
From European country
Yes
I had a girlfriend whose parents were from Poland
And her mother said to her
If you bring
That's what's higher than black
Animal
To the house
I'm going to jump off the balcony and kill mice
Wow
Yasso
We would make out in the garden
Then I joined the army I was indeed
Infantry
And were you actually in combat or did you have
It was at the beginning in combat
Unit
And then
They realize that I would be
Much more efficient at organizing entertainment for the soldiers that's what they put me to do so my job
What's to put together
Bands I'm go from one
Post to the other for example I remember right after the
Six-Day War
We went down to the Sinai
And drove from one position to the other
Wedding entertainers
And entertain the soldiers in each position
That's what we did
Obviously.
Foretold what you would do with your life you would become a person in the entertainment industry but
What was that your first exposure to
Jumping in
Entertainment
Environment
It's actually
Organizing this thing
Yes well that's a job that gave me you know I don't know why they gave me that job I have no
Background in it
Out of the fact that I
Play guitar little bit
But that's a job
They assigned me to so I did
The job I was assigned and was that
What led you to kind of thinking maybe I
I should pursue
This after f
No
What led me to join a band
After I left the army
I was simply
The necessity to
Make some money
And get out of that room and support my family
So that my father
They didn't have to go
Door-to-door selling pants
At the time there was no television in Israel
That was radio
And I used to play
You know Beatles song
And
In our band
The lead singer
Sounded exactly like McCartney
So
We were pretty successful
Even though I was a pretty lousy bass player
I've read that you actually were so bad that you would turn down the apps
We're just at the beginning
So where did you eventually get good at it
No
I was never good enough
It was just why one day the two brothers that were kind of the basis of the band the lead singer and
By the way
Solo guitarist came up to me and said that
Why don't you be your manager
And cuz you're holding us back music
And I couldn't be happier
So one of the happiest days of my life was the day I put down my guitar
My last gig
I became a manager and then
You manage one band and you manage to bands and then
You build a business
Surrounded
At some point you left
Israel
I became a to promoter and as well and I bought
Mini Aussie
Just toys route from Ray Charles to Jose Feliciano
Blood Sweat and Tears
Many others how are you doing this is a 20-something year old
Can you were just hustling you were
Convincing people
That you were the guy to
Mark Zuckerberg a24 has built Facebook
Before I was able to bring Jose Feliciano to Israel what the heck
You're supposed to be
Doing stuff
Get all your nuts supposed to be sitting in
Counting on your parents
Okay so so at some point
You moved
Tattoo ideas
Paris
When did you decide to do that and why
Well I move to Paris
Simply because
Israel was really
From a business standpoint
Too small on
And
Despite
My success quote on quote
I was in
That
Of $600,000
Wait you were you at $600,000
How old are you
By the time that happened I was 29
Did you accrue all that dead by the way well I had a big group of harpists from
Japan in October of 1973
Ready to pull the country and the Yom Kippur War 2 castle by surprise
So obviously there were no contest there was no shows there was no way for them to
Do even leave close to the airport was closed I had to return the money I had paid them in advance
And I had a couple of other bumps in the road again that has nothing to do with
With me which is the devaluation of the Israeli pound which meant that
We had big shows lined up where all of the expenses were in dollars and the revenue
What an Israeli pounds would the devaluation of the pounds we played
Two full houses and losing money every night so these two things compounded
Dockmate to $600,000 in debt
What are you freaking out I mean thinking how am I going to pay this back no I don't think I was freaking out
I was in a state of panic though
You know freaking out the fumes
You still have some control but when you're having massive panic attack you have no control what did you do
So I moved to France
And
So I signed this nine-year-old who sounded
Like an adult and Eagles
Is a fantastic singer in 9 year old singer in Israel
You said he was going to help you
You pay off this debt
Well
I got very lucky I got very lucky
How did you get lucky
Oh you know what
Being lucky means it means having the scale
To grab the lock when it's presented
What was the last that was
Wildest first record that I produced
Went platinum with his nine-year-old
What is 9 year-old what was his name
Noah and oam
The song OG
Deficient
Basically
Strike gold with this or platinum a gas
Circus record and you've got a career I guess
France like it at this point to you
What did you do did you start a production company in in in France
And I started production company that I set up my own label
And
I sold over period of 8 years that I live there
On my own label more than 18 million records
Wow
How did you even know how to cut
Deals in Paris like me you get there and Israel
Obviously you
Spokes in French
But how did you even know how to
Wheelin dealin and
You know get a studio together
Define
Distributors
I have no idea
You just started knocking on doors
Oh yeah knocking on doors as what
Guido Wright comedian
You know all business people knock on doors
Old salesman knock on doors
I learned it on the job I guess
You know I don't know I never produced the record in my life
When I produce that trust tracker
Why did you
Did you decide to move to the US I guess
In the early 80s
Well I bought a house here in 1978 and I moved here in 1983
Yeah and what did you intend to do in LA
I was planning to
Basically continue doing the same thing which is creating
Producing and distributing music and
Therefore I built the studio
In Studio City
And
We started
Creating music for cartoons
Why cartoon how to draw
Steven
Get into that
That world at all
Well I
Studied
How music is
Paid for
In America
By ASCAP and
BMI
Is the publishing
The agency
These are the publishing
That's right
8 or they are as Representatives
Collection agencies
Is what they are they pay royalties
And I pay royalties
So when I realized how
Much money there is
And this I thought I
That would be a good idea
And was it because of her
Meet with music in cartoons or just
Any music
It's any music but music
Cartoons music can be very profitable and here's the reason why
If you look at the sitcom
Darryl musical stings
So they have cumulatively maybe two minutes of music
Maybe three
Banana cartoon you have wall-to-wall music
And because these collection agencies pay
Based on the number of Munich minutes that are
You would make a lot more money
Drama music on
You know a little known cartoon
Then you would make on The Mary Tyler Moore Show or The Cosby Show
A lot more money on the cartoon
How did you figure that out
I called ASCAP and I said can you explain to me please you have at the pocket in pocket
And I called BMI can you please explain to me Mickey booty bukaty
And then I shut down and I calculated and I concluded
That being a member of BMI is the right way to go
And I went for it
And how did you
Create cartoon music what did you do
Well I want on that knocked on door of different
Cartoon producers
And I made them an offer they couldn't refuse.
And I said to them
I'll give you the music for free
If you let me keep
Bought the publisher share
As well as
The composer
And people said well that's not a bad deal we don't really pay all these composer for that then you'll do it for free I'll do it for free
I'll just keep the royalty
So what cartoons do you
Did you make music
Daba daba daba Inspector Gadget
Yeah there you go
Amongst many others
We went from Hanna Barbera Ruby Spears
Indeed
Filmation He-Man
Just you know tons and tons of cartoons at one point
My music partner and I wear the top Riders at
BMI
Do you remember the Heathcliff 1
Heathcliff Heathcliff
If y'all don't know no no no
Heathcliff no one should
Terrorize the neighborhood
Are you
Are you a fan of my music
Huge fan
Okay
This is good
How are you getting all of this music
Decompose
Well
At a given point we have so much work that was no way
That
One or two composers can
Satisfy
Get all the hundreds of episodes that we were scoring
At one point had 12 Studios studios just making music for cartoons
Plug Studios making music for cartoons when people ask me what are you doing side make music for cartoons
Could see the compassion in their eyes because they thought it was no room for compassion
I was making money hand-over-fist
Of course
Turning point in your life I guess
Happens when you discover this
Japanese
Live action
Show
Which
Of course became
The Mighty Morphin Power Rangers with tell me how did you
Come across
This whole concept
Well in 1984 I was in Japan
Now stretching on my bedroom
On the TV on the wall
Only three channels
Two of them showing game shows
Alarm some other reality base
That I do not
Understand a word
And the channel had these kids in spandex
Kicking monsters butts
And I thought
Hey
This looks like
Fun
It's all of a sudden dawned on me that once they turn into
Superheroes meaning in the power Rangers and they have their masses are on and they're
Kicking monsterbots it could be anywhere
Show all of the action scenes
Which is what
Cost the most money
We're basically accounted for so I thought if I shoot an American segment with American Kids
Being an American environment
And I died this up
Into the action sequence
I can create a show
Very little money because all the action scenes I would purchase
And
That that sounded to me like a great idea never mind the fact that I truly
Enjoy the show
It's funny I remember cuz I was
What are the child
World we live in Japan
From 1979 to 90
U2
And I remember when I saw Mighty Morphin
Power Rangers on television America I recognized it immediately as a show that I watched
The kid in Japan
What's the show called in
In Japanese
Jewel Ranger
Meaning 10 Rangers
In Japanese
Since you bought this in
I guess 1980s
Surround them
No I bought it in 84
And I slept it remember cartoon slippers leopard
And I slept at 4:18
What do you mean you would you try that you went around trying to
People on the show
Yes
Well
I just
Loved it and I thought that these card
So many Alamo
That we do
At the time didn't see
On America
TV
And then
I said to myself my
It's been on
For like 20 years old
Something in
Japan results
Success
Why in the world would need work here
I know that some people look at it as a
Campy cheesy I don't know I heard all kinds of definitions
To me it's a lot of fun
Shaw and everytime I look at the pilot
Over and over again
That I was using
Couldn't figure out why people don't see it and what are they say when you shut it
They said
Why do you embarrass yourself
Haim Saban creator of the Mighty Morphin Power Rangers enrollments to find out how he not only found
Play home for his show but figured out how to buy his very own kids TV channel
On someone else's dime I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support also comes from choiceology an original podcast from Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of choice ology you'll hear a classic psychology experiments retold
William is an opera fan who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation and is an avid chess player is it more
More likely that William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find out Edge schwab.com podcast or wherever you listen
Support also comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers licensed professional counselors who specialize in issues such as depression stress anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment at your convenience get help at your
Your own time and your own pace schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your
Therapist visit betterhelp.com built to learn more
And get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes Capital One what's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's 1992 and Haim Saban has been trying to sell his idea for the Mighty Morphin Power Rangers 2
Anyone who would listen
I'm pretty much no one is interested
That is until he gets a meeting with an executive at Fox
Names Market leche
And unlike everyone before her
Margaret
Actually likes it
She's the only person who said
There's something there
So she orders the show to air in 1993
And
We go and produce
40 episodes
Group b strep
On the fox kids network which at the time is the number one Outlet
For kids
I'm producing it meaning I'm just there
With every script every outline
Every frame
Every daily every sound effects every piece of music every casting I'm not
You know letting this thing go to anybody
Basically
What's wheat producer
There's a mutiny at Fox
Books from Rupert Murdoch on down and the group of a failure to basically say
This is horrible with nothing to air it
This executive Margaret
She goes to pack
So what she said she said look
I can fight
All my bosses
The Tetra I understand all of that
So I'm going to air it
Early in the morning
In the summer
And I'm going to Eric for 8 weeks right
Disassemble
Some of my teeth
Correct
And I'm down I'm going to take it off and will College
I said you know what I'll take it. I'll take whatever you give me and did you buy the rights to the show
100%
So you take this deal because you will have no other choice you
That's why
And she believed in it
Stephen told her that she's playing her career by putting this show on just scrap it
But you believed in it and she just
Put it on and within less than a week it beat every other show
Across it generated the highest rating of any show on Fox schedule
At the time you had Looney Tunes or Tiny Toons you had Batman you had all these
Shows that Weatherhead softbox kids and he delivered double triple the ratings of oldies show
Tell course that 8 weeks
Was renewed right right away
Because it was such a monster head for her
Yeah I know I asked you this but I'm still trying to figure it out like
How did you know this was going to be
It's called in Yiddish kishka meaning in my cut
God is many times more important than brain
I have to tell you that the biggest hits
That I had in my life ending music and hunting television
And hunting business
Have been
Always
As a result of significant which action
And the repeated regex
So every time I have an idea that people tell me no don't do that oops
You I mean
When that happened when that show was a hit
You go to other people's at
Told you this
Who's going to record
Before you just I didn't have time to go then people whatever I got my
What do you want from me
Okay so Power Rangers
Is doing great
You got the directions
Saban entertainment
Yes
And then about a year later
Fox
To buy your
Well I'm approached by Rupert Murdoch himself at the time
This is what round 90
Before 95
And
He has all kinds of concept that he's putting on the table
And I was holding firm
P**** money with exchange hands
We would put our content into a joint venture
And he would put
The network
Walk into that joint
You were basically saying yes I am not looking
Sell my car
Create a joint
Adventure with you
Correct I realize that they
Sweetie
Great to have a great piece of content that is a game changer for a network
But to own that that work
What's the weather like outside
Fox new kids coming to you and saying
We want to buy your production company and all your cartoon
And you're saying
American Electric
If you give me half of
Fox kids is that right
Yes
Figure out why Rupert Murdoch with
Take that deal and he couldn't
Do all this without you
What he asked Margaret
Was running Fox easy to duplicate buchheim has done
Including his International distribution and presence
Worldwide
How long will it take
And she said
I can do it but it might take me five years plus
And he wanted to know work right away
He walked it
Presence
And that
Categoria and by doing this joint venture with me
He was instantly in the worldwide
Kids bus
So he basically agreed to give you
Half of fox
Kids networking
Exchange for
Your distribution Network
Cartoons that you had
But then at that point you owned
Half of the
The kid Network
Yes
I mean the pretty incredible
Gamble Utah
Rejected is a
Original offer
Yeah I mean I wasn't going to do anything
I wasn't going to
Bring in a partner in a company I own 200
Yeah
So
What what are you guys doing
What's your next move
What's the next movie called Chase Carey and Margaret last one day
Chase Carey was a chief operating officer
And I said look I got this idea we should be
And the 24/7
Yeah and that is only one channel
That is
Knox
Part of the big conglomerate
And that has folded
Distribution
That we can buy and that's
The family
Old buy petrol
The Taliban
Correct
Basically you wanted Fox
To help you convince
Pat Robertson to sell it
Right
And they said to me
Well
Did he would never sell
Icilome
Well how about we ask
How about that
So they meet with Pat Robertson Pat Robertson they call me afterwards
They say about Roberts
Monticello
But I chase is going to meet with his son pin
Tim Roberts
Pat Robertson's son
And maybe the try to find some kind of copper
Joni Mitchell
Dim
A few days later
And I say can I come and you said no no no
I'll handle it I said okay fine if you didn't want you there because they thought you were going to be
Pain in the neck
Abacus
Maybe they were concerned that I would be too pushy or I don't know I don't know I don't know I just
Care all I cared about was a result I didn't care
So he goes to the meeting with Tim he comes back and he says
Nothing to do
I said okay you're done
You said you would. I said okay I want you to come
To a dinner with Tim and myself
Always not there
You
Should be you should have a dinner with
Tim
And you said let me have a shot of
Just let me see it
Right and we set the three of us at dinner and I said what I said
We left the dinner with a deal in French
What did you say to him that I don't want to get into what I told him I want to get
Into I can tell you that chase told me at the end of the dinner you're crazy man
What are you doing
I said don't worry about it we'll figure it out
Housemate has a bit of a negative
Not true
Natural natural you speak English better than I
I was hustling
Andy Robertson then says okay we have a deal. We had some sort of a joint venture
Concept
That's what we agreed upon
That brutal negotiation
Evolve
Into basically
Us buying the whole chat
Pay the whole thing and what they pay
1.9 billion
Which
Sounds like a lot of money what was it a good deal
No it was.
It was a fantastic
OKC
You have the deal
And you bought this
What were they Christian
Cable channel
And then you transition into a kids
Shell was that
Is it hard to do that
No look I mean we converted the channel from the channel That targeted people
80 +
80 years old plus survey they was a disaster Zone
Demographic standpoint so we struggled for a couple of days
And then as we were turning the corner
I realized
We had built the company
That was
Worth between 5 and 5 and 1/2 billion dollars
Competing with companies that will work
10 to 20 times
The Disney Store
And so on so
I came to the conclusion
That it's time to sell
So so wait this is about
5 years in
Yes
And so you have this channel
Fox Family
And then what
You decide you want to sell it right
Can you own half of it
But then Spock's don't
Like how are you able
Seoul
I had the right
Based on my contract
Red fox
To put my share today
Which I did
And we said
Negotiate
They told me that they thought my share was worth half a billion I told them that my share is worth 2 billion
Let's sit down and talk
Yeah but half a billion dollars
A lot of money
Why not 2 billion is more
But you could have walked away at that point with half a billion dollars
Would have been up I wasn't going to walk away with a half a billion dollars that was not a shot in hell I was
Going to do that okay
My stake in the company's what do William that's what I thought
So what did you end up doing so I didn't want to get into a pissing match with my butt
Give me a property to sell it
If I can sell it for four and a half billion dollars would you sell it with me so you're sure they said yes
That I ended up selling it for 5.3
How did you do
Whatever two potential buyers
One was CBS and the other one was
And Disney was
Really
Very interest
Dead in the asset
And they ended up putting up
The right amount of money
Tortillas
I mean that that mad at you
I walked away with
Easily with more than a billion dollar
1 + 1/2
How to become a billionaire
Overnight
Yes
Why was it so in
Important for you to
To get a billion
Rather than
Half a billion
Was it the money that was
What was important was
The principal or was it
Something else
What about
Important to me Utah
Cozmo robot
What is fair
I mean that was the
The fair price
Anyways money
Was getting becoming really rich
Did that Malaysia
You know it's awesome
Only
But it was also
Money is a marker
Success
Yeah
Continue this conversation
You bought Univision
Sex
And then you know
Investment fund like that
Is it
Is it work is it
Getting to a higher number is it
Is a recognition what is it
The joy of working
What is it that
You going
Everyday
Look I don't collect stamps
And I don't play Go
You know I don't have
Hobbies other than playing my guitar this is
My hobby
Getting
Deals done and
Making investment
Vincent salon
It look it allows me to do things that I truly enjoy
Witches
Give a lot of money
Back
This incredible
Country that has given me so much about Unity the United States
And Israel which took me in when I was a refugee
So there's a lot of gratification in that
When you look in the mirror
Good morning
Do you see
Haim Saban the
Billionaire Mogul or do you see
See that kid
Who was
You know doing it
In the stairwell
Modest apartment build
I see neither
I don't see myself as a mobile node do I see myself as a
Impoverished
Child
I just see a guy hurrying up to you
The next phone call
Next meeting
Let's Haim Saban today
Call the Saban Capital group in last year
The rights to the Power Rangers franchise to Hasbro the toy company the deal was reportedly worth
522 million dollars
I'm glad that you remember
The theme song
Gabba Gabba
Inspector Gadget
Write what I saw
It is one of the best theme songs I think
Yeah it's almost as good as Go Go Power Rangers
That's a that's a power Pops
Yeah I know that's a classic that's like you know Moon River
Yes yes I thought that would calls you a woo
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things your build
Thanks to one of our sponsors Microsoft Surface
Introducing the new Surface go
The smallest Microsoft Surface ever
Just over one pound as a
The 10-inch screen
The new Surface go has
The performance of a laptop
But with the portability
Tablet
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I know for how you built that and today we're going to the story we ran about a year ago
And back then Chris Waters wake up every morning
And hedge was job as an account manager at a software company
Desk phone usually talking to relatively unhappy people now as you can imagine Chris prefers to talk
Relatively happy people which explains how he started his side business a few years back he was in the
Reddit
And read it has this thing around Christmas time where they'll connect you with a total stranger
And then you can send them a gift and I got matched for this guy who live 20 minutes away and I was thinking
About what to give him and what I could do with this great opportunity where you live so close
And Chris was thinking Way Beyond the scope of this hold secret Santa thing you don't send a boring
Gift card or a snack box and fortunately I was hosting a weekly poker game with my friends and I had
I just happen to one five weeks in a row and so
I had a lot of extra money like almost
$2,000 in extra money in Kristen. Just paid forward and put together this really
Inexpensive I like doing things for the people I like creating something
Special and magical
And if you have the opportunity to do something truly spectacular for someone including an internet store
Grainger
You should take that opportunity
Chris is really into scavenger hunts and buried treasure in planting Clues and stuff like that so
First secret a guy Chris wound up planning this
Credible
Day-long Adventure at 8 a.m. a century-old suitcase
Filled with envelopes and a box with a chain wrapped around it was hand delivered to his door
This is all happening around Scottsdale Arizona by the way they got to a place where there was an envelope with two tickets to the zoo
And at the animal pens there was kind of a cipher that you used to decode the message and then it sent them to
Restaurant where the servers said we've been expecting you
Hundred dollars of his poker money on tickets and chachis and clues meals all for the total
Will stranger and at the end of this incredible day
Chris actually met up with the guy at a local bar his name is Blaine and as you might guess
Blaine was pretty blown away and couple days later Blaine posted to Reddit and it just blew
Blaine's post about his secret santa experience went to number one on Reddit front page
Started to get inundated with messages just people commenting and privately messaging thing that you need to do this in Vegas you need to
Anyone here I live in England can you come over here and do this and then business is saying we would like to be apart of this and
That is how Chris started his business constructed Adventures
He puts together these personalized scavenger hunt Cindy long excursions for people's birthdays and marriage from
Puzzles and stuff like that
Pretty good money minimums probably going to cost them about $2,000
For the whole shebang anyway just days before we ran Christmas Story last year he's actually
She submitted his letter of resignation at that boring office job
And he started to do constructed Adventures
Full time I honestly I should be more nervous and I should be scared but if I can quit my job
And spend my life doing that for other people I'd say it's a pretty good life
Since we last spoke to Chris he's plans 24 more adventures and he's made around $100,000
Dollars in revenue and he's also been approached by a production company that wants to do a TV show about it
If you want to learn more about
Constructed Adventures or hear previous episodes
Head to our podcast page how I built this.
Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org
As always we love to hear what you're up to and thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can sub
Describe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review you can also write us directly
Hib tea at npr.org and you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
Our show is produced this week that runty never Blue Eagle also composed the music
Thanks also to JC Howard nor could see neither grandson as Mexican floor and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Mia venkat I'm guy Raz how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing
Platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email templates
Drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week