Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey everyone soap
It's Thanksgiving week and at some point some of you might be killing time in a long line at the grocery store
We figured it was the perfect moment to rerun the story of how
What is grocery store in particular
Got started
This episode first ran back in
May of last
Oh and one more thing
On Thanksgiving Day
This Thursday
Going to be posting another interview from the how I built this Summit in San Francisco
It's My Life conversation
Adam Lowry and Eric Ryan
Method
We talking about
Chemistry
Partnerships
Okay
Here's the show
Venture capitalist for like hitchhiker's with credit cards and Islam
Long as you take them to where they want to go they will help you pay for the gas but if you don't take them
Where they want to go they will try to hijack the car and throw you out on the side of the road so I did
Did not trust Avicii's I like them I didn't trust him I did not want him to take control of the company so I thought no going to go public
And then we're going to get The Hitchhikers out of the car
From NPR how I built this show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists story
Behind the movement
A vegetarian inspired John Mackey to start
An organic food Revolution change the way Americans
Shop for groceries
If you happen to step into an
Organic food Co-Op in the 60s
70s
You would probably walk past
Isles
Isles of
Bulk bins full of beans and brown rice
Send dried fruit
There were no big Brands nose
Stonyfield Farms
Nature's Path Amy's or Annies
And the people who shot the me stores
They were money
Teeny tiny handful of Americans
Who even knew what
Keno or
Taylor
And they were mostly counterculture types
Hippies Back To Nature folks
Mom
And yet all these people were at the Leading Edge of a food Revolution
That would start to sweep the country
In the 1990s
And that Revolution was
Largely propelled
Even though that company inspires
Pretty strong opinion
Fanboys
Damn haters
There's no denying that
It had a monster-sized impact on
The way we eat
But the person who is
Partly responsible for this revolution
Well
Here's what John Mackey grew up eating
Irestore
Today with
Cocoa Puffs
Milk
Pop-Tarts
Very picky eater as well so hamburgers
For lunch with nothing on it from no vegetables on the hamburgers
Maybe fried chicken for dinner or macaroni and cheese out of a
Can or box
This was the era where
Stay-at-home moms were so thrilled about the
Great innovations that could happen like
TV dinners
Yeah
Frozen TV dinners that you could
Pop in the oven and
Value.
Meal for your family
Where were you in life
When you first
Discovered
Food
Like real
Yeah my food
Consciousness Awakening
Really
Heard when I was about
And I moved into this vegetarian Co-op
Austin
Call Prana house
I was definitely interested in the counterculture
I'm about I meet interesting women as well I thought it was a
Amazon adventure
I've expanded my
Diet from inside to become a vegetarian that I became the food buyer for that Co-op
And
Then I had to get a job when I went to work for a small nap
Whole Food store in Austin called The Good Food Company
And wow
I'd like I was launched on my path I
I love everything about natural organic foods
I like cooking
I like retailing it
And I thought this is something I could really
Be passionate about
Okay at this point in your life you did not like you didn't have a college degree Riley
Kind of dropped out of college
So when I was about 20 years old
I was on track to get a degree in Philosophy from the University of Texas
But I ran into a course that was required course I needed
To complete
Didn't like the course I didn't like the books that I was required to read I didn't like
Professor and then one day the battle is over
And I
Stood up and the book I was reading or trying to read I threw it on the ground if I'm not going to read this book
Then I just began to read books and take horses that I was interested in
So I ended up with 120 hours of electives that were just courses I was interested in but
I took control of my life I began to be authentic and true to myself and that led me into this hole
Napa Fish World so when you show up into this
Drama college
Degree
I'm assuming it's kind of like a hippie
Typo
Play playlist definitely
Your parents are super excited at with the decisions you've made at this point your life at 23
No my parents were
Very worried
Very unhappy
The very last conversation I ever had in my mother 1987
Was on her deathbed and she asked me to go back to school and make something of myself
I was
Grocer I was a hippy grocer
And I
She said anyway you have a fine mind John why are you wasting it is a gross or goats
The doctor a lawyer do something with your life
Makes a difference and I said
I'm doing something in my life that makes a difference
She said you're just a grocer
Mom grocery store great
What was it like like what
What was it like working at that Health Foods
I loved it I mean it
Store wasn't very big with only a couple thousand
Squishy butt
The retail business was really fun I mean first on surrounded by food which I'm fascinated
Buy with other people and I'm working with the other
7 relatives working to the store and
They're also equally interested in food
There people that you get to no overtime and a small store with not in about that many customers so you develop relationships with
People and you serve them and I just thought that was like super funny new
I can do this to sink within my realm of competence and then I work for about 6 months and when I
Summa an idea grew in my mind which is this is what I want to do with my life I want to open I want to open my own store
Went back to the coop and talk to my girlfriend Renee she was four years younger than me so I think I was like 23 and she was like
119 and she got super excited about it I've often wondered if Rene had so that's a stupid idea to never work how my life might be
Different now but she was very excited about it and we began to plot out opening around store
How did you eat
Maven get started
Well
That wasn't easy
I make a joke about it now that
And entrepreneurs a little bit like a panhandler
Except
That they're selling dreams
The people we raise the money because we like most entrepreneurs friends and family
We thought we needed $50,000
Start the store
And
We can only come up with 45 but we decided we can make do with it
My initial stake
$10,000
What's the most
Iavarone to the company
And 10 of the $45,000 I borrowed all that
My father
So with that money you were able to open up
That the first Whole Foods
Well
Original story called safer way
Thanks Safeway but safer away
And are we truthfully we are always hoping that
Maybe
Safeway would sue us
Are you good publicity
And
Although selective I had in school none of them were business class
No real
Business
Strength Renee didn't have any experience she was
Can we open the store she was
And
Wilton we open a store in an old house not even on busy road it was just
Like
We just thought this was a super cool house
So we
We had a
Store on the first floor vegetarian storm
And we are vegetarian restaurant on the 2nd
Flora caffe
And then we have an office and we lived on the on the third floor
If you if you were to walk through safer
Play What Would you see on the shelves is it like bulk
Products in light jeans and was there sugar
Sure we didn't sell sugar
We didn't sell meat
We were selling real foods we were selling bulk foods
And produce
And yes definitely everybody was a hippie
But we had about
Counting the people in the cafes a lot of new Morgan talk part time
20 people work at 15 to 20 people
So were you scared I mean you were you were still a kid
No
I wasn't scared at all you thought this was going to work
When your
You can when you're 24 25 years old
You don't have so much to lose I wasn't married I didn't have any
Kids II
For my case the worst case scenario was
I would disappoint a lot of people
And
I do something else in life
I didn't
For me was a grand Adventure
Starting businesses
Fun
Fun because you're you're you're engaged and you're
You're passionate about it and
The whole
Dream just would have swept us along
And we didn't know what we were doing but
We learned very quickly
And
We got better
You must have burned through that 45,000 pretty fast
We did we actually lost half of it in the first year
I lost $23,000 after you freaking out
No but the investors were
My dad was freaking iPad
But I'm
I just began to read books
I read hundreds and hundreds and hundreds I have read hundred thousand book
I'm business since the beginning
I also
I'm a man. I'm an entrepreneur fly try things
But if something doesn't work
I stopped doing it
Enabled us to learn quickly
And we did make a small
$5,000 profit in our second year
How did you do that
Start managing our cost better started buying better
Less spoilage
Better management of labor hours
In the very basics of retail
We didn't really know we had to figure it out
Local hip
Bees in Austin or what did you also have like sort of
Austin High Society
So
One of the job site I tell us because I run into people all the time that
Tell me they were original
Safer a customer can I say
You know half the people that said the original saferway customers had
I've been there whenever we don't have
5 times the sales we stopped having
I like the number of people that went to Woodstock right there
But now they were all they were all young
They need four people this was the counterculture and part of the counterculture was
They wanted their own stores
I didn't want to go to that traditional
Big Supermarket saving very alien experience forum
Minsoo obviously
It sounds like you guys were doing pretty well when did you when did you start
Thinking about
You know
Expanded
Well
After about when I began to make money the second urine begin to realize that safer way was too small
And
I just thought we needed to have a bigger better location
Finding a dream about opening a real grocery store where you could do all your shopping there
Yeah
So
We found this location
Was this whole night club on a big strip Road in Austin Lamar
That
It had burned down in the crowded been a night
So
I first had to try to sell our our board on it
And try to get more money and they said this is crazy you lost half the money the first year and this is great you're making money now but
I want you to stay there for a few years and then you know we'll see
If I know really got to do
Going to a bigger store workwear
Repeat it or not well-positioned competitively
But they weren't buying it
And
More like I said look when I want to put more money in
Maybe I can find somebody else
Turn fast
The strategy there being no one else would be stupid enough to invest in this company
What does email
Crazy entrepreneurs
Has it been successful yet
So I began to hustle anybody I knew that had money I'd already
People that new people in Madden
Are the Cowboys playing basketball with
That one day we finish playing pickup basketball and
He got into like a BMW and drove off
Same age of Iowa
What is Jay do
Eliza J doesn't do anything
Hot racing millionaire inherited a bunch of money from his parents
Well I gave you a call the next day
And it just turned out that Jay and had kind of his own food Consciousness Awakening
Started shopping at safeway luvs safeway
NJ
Said he would put $50,000 in
I was like
Wow okay
Went back to our board said
I got a guy that's going to put $50,000 in
And then shocked
And
Several of them decided they wanted to get more money in as well
So we we
Rented
That burned-out location
And
The story there's also kind of interesting because the owner of that building
Was this guy named Ben Powell and it's been in his family lives he's an attorney living in Houston
Sometime I had to go and sell him on doing the snap
Supermarket in his building
I pitched him on A10
He started laughing kind of towards the end of my pet
I said mister pal what are you laughing at
Anysex
John
I mean it sounds like let me see in a movie, corny movies said John you are so
Full
Unenthusiastic on you think you can conquer the
Holy war
Well I'm going to teach you different son
But you remind me of myself when I was young
Let's do your gosh darn
Natural Food supermarket
And so we were able to get that store open
However while we were building it
I want to
My friendly competitors
But it opened up
After Safeway was call Clarksville natural grocery and I really love the two entrepreneurs that were doing that Craig Weller Mark's casa
These are good guys work really hard
Got a good store
I pitched them would look
Working opens Natural Foods supermarket when the first answer was he born
Anywhere in the world
Aren't you do it with us
What are they join you instead of young
Exactly
Play join up and go by and by the way if you don't we're only a mile away from your side
Your story you're going to
Now you're going to have trouble competing with us what you told them you basically said to them
Hey this is going to be great let's work together and if you don't were going to crush you
No I didn't say it that way because sometimes
Funny thing is when I told the story that's how I get some trailer to meet it was I didn't
Threaten them
I mean I said
We're only going to be a mile away we're going to have this big store it's going to be it's going to be harder for you to compete why don't we do this together
Did they have any any of their own conditions
Yes
One Craigs and Marx conditions is we have to make this a real store
We have some meat
We have to sell beer and wine have to sell coffee
We can't just be
Completely a vegetarian idealistic store we don't want to partner with
And I'd already
Thought Craig and Mark store was very successful and I talked to a lot of customers cross shock
And
They all wanted us to
To loosen our products
Standards
To make it more a real grocery store
It was kind of like we know if we're going to eat these Foods
Then we need to be able to we should sell them
So
That was a
Compromise that was made that turn out to be the right compromise from a business
The business decision perspective and
So the funny thing was they had trouble making up their minds about it and they come down after they close their store up
Northward then construct
And then literally like
2 weeks before I throw a set to open
They
I've seen enough and they said we're in
I'm so we had to
We had to really scramble
To we know we had to try to integrate our our
Our team members together
And
Way to change the name
And this is assuming this world was
Is going to come in well
We started with the name Market
We are mark
And then it was like what kind of Market order food market
What kind of food market are we where we're kind of a Natural Foods Market
What kind of generic a car sells natural food market
When what kind organic food mart
Yeah but we don't have just organic
Whole Foods
And that was at Whole Foods Market that's how it went with her
Amazon
Spokane weather name
In the store with media success people sometimes ask how long did it take the first Whole Foods Market to be successful
And the answer to answer is it take till about 3 in the afternoon on the first day
Wow was it just because of luck or was that just because of they were
There was
Disc Institute glamouring ways an element of luck
And success in life
1 reasons I wanted to merge with those guys
Was not only because
I liked
And thought they could help us
But I thought you know what if we can get Clarks Hill and safer way in here will have almost enough
Sales between the two stores to break even and then if we get other customers
Willam
Never look back
But again
People were so excited about the
His first or it was
It was amazing and we didn't do any advertising we just open the doors
But nowhere word
Emmaus
Was incredible hole Austin kind of
Counterculture hippie Community knew about it immediately
Wow and it just keep
Keep going like that
From that point on
No
Like nine months after we opened
Is it now in May of 1981 Austin had the worst flood that it had in about a hundred years
And our store was located in the hundred year flood
So we're actually where we were in the hundred year flood plain but when I said what does that mean it's as well about every hundred years you're going to have a
What I said okay I'll take touchy
I know the Sunday night there been a lot of rain during the weekend but then it just really starting to rain on Sunday in
I'd gone home
Was at friend's house having dinner and
Renee started to call and said the water is beginning to rise
What are we doing. I said take the ball
Beck's pilum up
In front of the doors
And inside the store
Because that's where I thought the water would come in through the doors
Actually
They kept the water out till I got up to about four feet wow
But that store was not designed to be a submarine and stuff underwater got up to about 4 feet
The Punisher weight of the water
Basically broke through the glass of the doors
I just came in like a tidal wave
Renee ended up swimming out of the store that night
And
It was a Sunday and we have three days of sales
There was in our floor safe so I want to get the cash out of the store
And I went back with no lights going to
Picture it now with
All the powers out at snide
Place around the back
Flashlight
And there are actually
People wander around the store looters
Wandering around the store
One of the back I went into the office and they open up the floor safe
Were they able to pull the money out
This was a time when
We didn't take nobody to credit cards
More than half our money back then was just in cash
I mean I think we had about a hundred thousand dollars
And
I'd put it on this grocery pack
And I was wondering out the store in this guy comes up to me and he says hey
Find anything good in the back room
I said I'm not sure
Just grab his bag there probably something back there for you go check it out
And we got the money out and put it in a safe place and
And then we thought we were pretty much out of business they were cars floating down the street watching flow
Floataway
In just a moment after the flood and had John Mackey
He take Whole Foods from Austin to Boston and eventually
To almost every state in America
I got rise and you listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities
Is can be a smart way to hedge Market
Risk and earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces
It's fine print and phone tag
White with clear conditions and a direct
Sophie model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge
Which is not available in all states
Support also comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers licensed professional counselors who specialize in issues such as depression stress anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment at your
Get help at your own time and your own pee
Schedule secure video or phone session
Plus chat and text
What your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built to learn more
And get 10% off your first month
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
So it's the spring of 1981
First Whole Food store
Is literally under water
Is only been open for 6 months
And they had no flood insurance
Hanging a picture what the store was like
This
Tidal wave of water come in and when you have a flood like that all the sewage lines back up as well
So
You have all this book
Food and yeah we have
Meat fish and sewage and was just at
Total
Horrible mess
And
Stock
Anyhow
We showed up for work
And we started cleaning everything up and all those other people I kind of recognize them but they weren't team members and in
They weren't they were customers
Can customers and neighbors and everybody was pitching in school we should have died three.
Flight
We had to rebuild the store was going to it's going to cost a lot of money to do that and
We just didn't have the money
So I thought
We're on we all thought we were finished
But every one of the stakeholders rallied and there was a benefit held for the store and
The team members they work for free
Are bank loans Money
Oh my signature which was worthless
And the investors decided to kick in more cash
So we were able to reopen 30 days later that just pulled everybody together we are really United
Around that
Near death experience
So did you
Focus at the point on
Just getting things in order
No
I want to open a second store after
What it was like
We can't put all of our eggs in a basket in my float down the river
We've got to have a second store
The second store didn't it didn't start as well as the first story was up in North Austin and it
In the suburbs coming away from the
The counterculture community of Austin and was trying to Market to more conventional
No Suburban people in it
It took a couple years for that store.
Actually transferred profit
And
Give me open the third store in Austin in South Austin now that
That turned out to be
I very challenging for us
Because that's tour
Was too close to our original stormed and cannibalized
Significantly
And together
We started to lose money
Like has any tension with with
Your partners
Well
That led to a big debate because one of the
Partners
Mark
He really didn't want to grow because
We had this gold mine he just wanted to mine it
Yeah so
The long and the short of it was that
Mark
Sold his interest
And the company
And when it's another Direction in his life so he was the first
Co-founder to exit actually Renee exited slightly before him cuz she and I broke up
And she wanted to travel the world and see other place
So she got a new boyfriend
And she left
And
Doing a startup business together either
Brings you closer together or
Rip your part in the case of Renee and I ended up ripping us apart
So then it was just Craig and I laugh
And I think the partnership
It challenge when it gets into hard times the good times are easy
But did you ever did you ever think to yourself
Maybe
Maybe they're right maybe week's attitude
Quickly
Of course I was thinking that
Talimena
I was regretting that opening the South often store because
I mean almost all the sales
It got came at the expense of
Original store so
But
I really wanted to grow the business
I mean I am not saying I all the challenges were
Like oh boy another
Drake challenge
Hitting is really hard but I always saw it as
Okay this is a great lesson for me I can learn
Something here I am learning some
I learned a lot
From
Those early
Failures are those are not only failure for some of the early
Trials
If you were looking to 2
Expand the business
You would have to raise some serious money
Yes
In 1988 we decided we couldn't
Grow as fast as we wanted to grow from just
Are retained profits tapped out all of our friends and family
There was no Angel Network so we needed to raise some venture capital
This was a time when venture-capital was not
Really pretty crank up like it is today yeah
We hired a banker
And we began to
Try to raise
Venture Capital money and we got rejected again and again and again are we
Trying to talk to the venture capitalist and they just couldn't get we were doing I mean
One guy who turned me down
He said to me he said you know John
I see you got a pretty good business here but
It looks to me like I look at all the stores
You just a bunch of hippies and you're just selling food to other hippies
I don't think that's a very big Market
And if it's going to spread further than then
The big companies are going to take a lot of interest in it
I don't think you can compete with Safeway
I don't think you can feed with these big commercial supermarkets going to run out of business
People still telling me that today I've been hearing it
40 years I mean he had a point back then
About the
Of course I'm sure that guy is kicking himself
Yeah he Pieology apologize to me about 10 years later that was the worst decision ever made
Companies based in Texas or did you go to like
Silicon Valley like where were you looking for money to go to Silicon Valley
And we got
2 based out of Houston
But
We were beginning to slowly crossover
Because we
We're not only selling natural organic food but our quality of food was better
I'm so we're beginning to get a more mainstream shopper
We're coming in
And that was beginning to drive some progress
So we got to investors from Houston and we got another one out of
Silicon Valley
And then what did that enable you
You said it's just
Hispanic
Yes we sold 34% of the business
An eight and a half million dollar valuation
So
About eight times are earnings
Or about
So I don't know what 20
Percent 15% of Versailles
It was
It's ridiculous the kind of valuations people get today
Compared to what we could get back in the
The late 1980s
When you start to think about
Going public
But
Venture capital is the night and wants to go public
They wanted us to do another round of venture financing
But
I was determined not to do another round of venture financing because
That would have given them control of the company
And I just didn't trust the Venture God
Venture capitalist for like hitchhiker's hitchhikers with credit cards
And as long as you take them to where they want to go
They will help you pay for the gas
But
If you don't take them where they want to go
They will try to hijack the car
And they will hire a new driver
Throw you out on the side of the road
So I did not
Tres veces I liked him I didn't trust him I did not want him to take control to come
Going to go public and then we're going to get The Hitchhikers out of the car
So
There's a little
Early for Whole Foods to go call liquor so I was
Toll later on but we did go public back in 1992
And we raised about 28 million dollars
Add overnight your company was worth what
Overnight be worth about a hundred million
What does that mean I mean does that mean that instantly you had all of his cash and you could
Actually
Row at the
You wanted to grow
Yes the greatest thing about
Thought it was we had a
Occurrence
The currency being around stock
We can now go to other companies are like Whole Foods Market
You're the biggest but there were other we had other peers so you are
So you were looking to buy them
Yes first one was Bread & circus in
Boss I remember right company
And
Next we acquired mrs. Gooch's remember mrs. good shop
And we did not 93
We did a big one with fresh peels
And they had 22 short week were there in 1996
What's good to hide those we were able to grow much faster
So as you're like expansion
Just move data
The clap right through the 90s
7 to mm
Yeah I mean I have to
Assume that you also
We're changing how
Supply chains worked in NM and how people
Mapreduce
Food and and
I guess
Create new markets
For organic food
That's really true we did
I mean
We didn't do it by ourselves honestly but
Because you have Farmers but we created much of the demand
4 National organic in the United
State our success.
And
That created more farmers and more entrepreneurs wanting to farm organic
Claremore manufacturers wanting to produce organic
Manufactured goods so we helped
We had a huge impact
We still do
Yeah
What what percentage of
The grocery market
Does Whole Foods
Gun control today in the US
I think it's about
1 1/2 to 2%
We don't control that by the way right
Yeah but about 1 to 2% of all grocery
Which is a lot smaller than I think a lot of people
People would assume because
Is Whole Foods influences
Probably
Much greater than
Thank you I like I said we're like a boxer punching above our weight class
Yeah I mean it's it's it's surprising at how many stores are are do you have to
We have about 460
I want to ask you a question
Stores
Because you of course have heard the joke
The Whole Foods
Is Mike Holt
Paycheck writing
The prices are so expensive
For most people so
I mean do you think that's a fair criticism
Well
Course we don't like that
That's not at 1
Nickname was given to us it was first giving
2 as affectionately
The people who loved us
And then it became a club
People would be on Whole Foods you didn't like her
There's a kind of a tendency I think
For people to think
You can get the same quality stuff at lower prices
I don't think
People have the same quality Whole Foods ass
I think we have the best quality
So it's about a
Trade-offs
That there exists between quality and price
You have people who
Who attacked you as well cuz you
And you've been kind of a lightning rod
With some of the things that you
You said and written about
Like I'm a change in unions that don't
Interviews of I guess people that don't associate with jive with Whole Foods
Well my take is a course that the people that know me like me people that don't know me and and they
I just read things or hear things they project
But
Yeah I've learned
I learned a lot
I've learned that they're like
Four topics I just don't talk about in public anymore what are they
I don't talk about politics religion sex or GMOs
What what what is there left
Talk about
I mean I don't even care if people hated me it's just that then they try to attack Whole Foods yeah baby stop picking on me
My kid
Do whatever you want with me but leave the kids out of it
John Wayne somebody like
Anyone listen to this has been to call for
When I walk into a whole food
There's a feeling that you get
At the company
Has certain values that I think a lot of the Shoppers identify with
Right there as you know
There's
They're sort of a n
An attempt to to help me
Make the world a better place since
Community organizations and it's
If you
Very
I mean lack of a better word it feels
Tattoo till our people and so
You can understand why people
Are interested in the
People behind
You guys are interested in how you
Yes
And
I don't know I don't equate liberal with caring
So I don't like going to get in a political argument with you but
There's a meta-narrative about business in our world net narrative is that business suck
And businesses
Is greedy and selfish and exploitative
It only cares about money
But
People don't want to believe Whole Foods Market
It's a different kind of company we are we're purpose-driven were stakeholder focused
If I'm proud of anything
It's that Whole Foods Market have me to do
And I we do care
You know I'm wondering whether some of the
The criticism that you
You've had over the years
See no evil away Whole Foods does
Is business
Has been improved whole foods that have there been times where people have said
Hey you know what
Who is doing with this is wrong and
And and and
Or protesting Hadassah change the way you guys have actually operate
Yeah has I mean the most famous example is backing
In two thousand and
We are being picketed by
Animal rights activists
That
We're very unhappy about this particular duck we were selling which they considered to be a factory farm.
What I got
Your dialogue with one of the activist
Abra passionate so young
A woman named Lauren Cornelius
And I know after about a month or so
She sends me an email and she says
You know Mr Mackey IC after all
Dialogue that you are very idealistic
However
When it comes to
Livestock animals
Honestly you don't know what you're talkin about you are not well informed on the subject
And
You know I thought about it but you know she's really right I don't know that much about
Personally I'm just
I decided to become an expert myself and that summer summer 2003 I read about a dozen books
How we raise animals in America
And I was utterly horrified
I guess I just been living in denial it was probably wake up call
Call for me
And
By the end of the summer
I had made to resolution one I was going to go
Becoming vegan
The number to I Knew Whole Foods needed to do a much better job
That the accusations that the animal rights people inmate about
What we were doing were fundamentally
Correct we
Then began the process of bringing in animal activist
And Whole Foods people and dialogue
And that led to the global animal partnership which Whole Foods Market's ponsford and
Trying to follow the gaap standards for the last several years
I'm trying you still
Portia live in Austin so I'm assuming that now and again you must pass
By the location of
Storedog
You ever go out of my way to pass by and what is it today
It's a school
It's a school in front one of my friends started that school
And
I got a tour of it a few years ago
Anything that was so hardcore they change some of it
Karachi I remembered it
Just like it was yesterday and I could see where the
Are we on our block benzoate
See
Cuz they left
The basic structure of an impact
So it was it was a trip down memory Road for sure
China Eastern Point
I need you when you will not
Run Hozier
Retire whatever I mean
Kent Candle Company can Whole Foods continue without
And we have to
Charisma without your charisma without
Your vision
Of course
A can
And but I mean I do think when the
When the founder on the last founder left and Craig was the second-to-last I think he left almost went
Years ago
And lot of the people that built the business with
Besides the founders their retiring now cuz in their sixties and they paid a lot of money to over the years to Whole Foods
So they'll be no one ever loves Whole Foods Market as much as
If I love it
Yeah but
Building a business is a little bit like having children watching the show and grow up is that you
You hope your
Child is healthy and you hope your child is happy and you know it
How has integrity and does the right thing and
I think it's important to have a a good
Founder and entrepreneur
The great businesses
Continue to live on after
Remove sky
Whole Foods is in that in that space
John Mackey co-founder
CEO of Whole Foods and last summer just a few months after this interview first ran
Whole Foods was purchased by Amazon
Can a deal worth nearly 14 billion dollars
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsors Microsoft
Who wants you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family
The Surface Pro 6
Has up to 13 and a half hours of
Battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Wherever work takes
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you
You built that
And today we're running a story we
First man
About a year ago
Steve humble
History
Starts
At the movies
Where Harrison Ford is stuck in a room is
Burst into flames
So there's two scooters chair to the only place that is not on fire
Which is the stone fireplace
And then and I think you know where I'm going with this
The fireplace suddenly
Spins in Indiana is it a whole crew in this room
It's full of Nazis
Steve heese
A mechanical engineer
Some years ago
He was living in Salt Lake City renting a big house
Some friends and there was a
Spot in the house that was a big
Stone Hearth
I have always been kind of fascinated with secret passageways
And I thought I could totally make
Secret passageway like what I seen the Last Crusade
Because let's face it how awesome would it be to have a secret passageway in your house
And more Steve mull it over
The more he thought you know I've been other people who want one too
So the first thing you did was to Google secret passageway building companies and there was nobody
Absolutely nobody anywhere but could make be secret doors like we're in the movies you know motorized and and maybe
High security stuff
The times he was pretty bored of his day job
So he starts a dream of creating a business that would build secret passageways
And he called up some contractor friends
Witcher clients possibly be interested in something like this
And I got overwhelmingly positive feedback
So eventually you know I decided I'm going to do this thing
I quit my job
I had to move
And with my parents
Steve moved to his parents place in Mesa Arizona
Restart the tinker and his dad's garage
And it just so happens in an old high school buddy was building a house nearby so you said
Hey why don't I build you a secret hiding place
He had a niche in the wall with a recess
And he kept
A vase in there
And I made it so that when you twist the vase
A painting on the wall opens
And it exposed fingerprint scanner and then when you scan your print
The niche itself would slide upwards towards the ceiling
And it was replaced From Below by a gun safe
A hidden gun safe
Took this point Steve started to Market his idea
You got a story in a local paper and with a year people started to find a big people
People you would have heard of and they are building multi million dollar houses
Of course we ask them for the salacious details but I wish I could
Secrecy
So anyway to Steven suddenly in his dream job he's flying around the world he's working on palatial homes putting in
False
Fingerprint scanners and secret doors for people whose names he cannot reveal
A little bit like an imposter you know I show up at his house where there's
This incredible
Team of talent
But I kept reminding myself that nobody knows how to make secret passageways in a better than I do certainly no
Any more than I have
So I guess I am the expert at this
A custom-made Secret Door starts at around $9,000
But Steve's recently introduced a cheaper line of a secret doors just
1500 bucks and then make it look like anything other than the door
Frank Mir
What is a bookcase
One is a wardrobe
And another one who can install one secret doors in front of your spare bedroom or
Closet
You hide what you want and then you trigger the door by remote control
And Steve says he's barely advertised
And he's already selling about one of these a day on a clear trajectory to surpass
Our Core Business
Cheese company is called
Creative home engineering and today
Those cheaper
$1,500 doors are in
Selling faster than
Fancy custom-made one
To keep up with demand
Steve has hired
Some new employees has a new Factory in
In a suburb of
His company is set to hit 2 million dollars in Revenue this year
To hear more about creative home engineering or he
Previous episode
For podcast page how I built this
Npr.org
And of course
If you want to tell us your story
Build
Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to
The show this week
Describe wherever you get your podcast
Why you're there please
Apus review
You can also write to us
Hidta
Npr.org
And if you want to send it
Tweet
It was produced this week but run teen Arab Louis who also
Composed music
Thanks also to JC Howard nor could he leave a grande size Mexican floor
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
A guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Don't this campaign mod
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com