Support for how I built
Best and the following message come from Michigan Economic Development
Corporation
Seewhy michigan
Is attracting top talent and top business
By searching Michigan pure opportunity
At that seed stage like it was a hundred percent just an idea
I would come in and I'd say like you. Here's the beta that I did like 20 people and here's how I think the business model of shape up
And then probably talk to 30 angel investors who said No and when your
I'm doing something that nobody else is doing you are either the smartest or the stupidest
Ron NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist in the story
Face behind the movements they built
How Katrina Lake defy the investment world to build a tech company that transfer
Warm clothes shopping online
Every year seems there's always a
1password or idea that everyone in Silicon Valley
He seems to be talking about
Couple years ago
Cryptocurrency recently it's been
Blockchain
But is also a widely-held idea in the tech world that
The days of Rage
Retail stores
Our number
Of course this
Is a combination of wishful thinking and hyperbole
There is something to it
Especially with
Big retailers
Macy's is struggling Bon-Ton and Toys R Us
File for bankruptcy
And in October of 2017
Lord & Taylor sold it
Flagship building in Manhattan
That amazing Italian Renaissance Building on 5th Avenue is now worth more as a wework
Then as a department store
And the main reason why of course is that
People just aren't going into big department stores
They're buying a lot more stuff online
Note convenience is a major reason of course but so is
Time
Time is increasingly Limited
That's really work Katrina Lakes idea begins
Because she got older and
Busier with work
She found that she had to last
Time to go shopping for clothes
And only rich people could afford personal shopper associate
Why don't figure out a way to make that more affordable
Unless time
And that was the Genesis of Stitch fix
An online personal shopping service
Not today Stitch fix has
2 million customers with Pinnacle Revenue close to a billion dollars
And in 2017
Katrina became the
Youngest female CEO ever to take a company public
It wasn't necessarily going to be a
Slam dunk business
In fact
Katrina had a hard time raising money
In the beginning
Jesse grew up in San Francisco in
In a bicultural home
Mom is Japanese dad
What is American
And at the age of 15
Her parents decided to move the family from
The Bay Area
To Minnesota
Which if you've seen inside out
Is the exact
Opposite of what happened
Flight movie
Like to go from in San Francisco at
More diversity and like the high school that I went to was
Percent Asian and then to go
2A School in Minneapolis where
I think there were
Three Asian people at three and a half if you include me in my class and
We were a very bilingual bicultural household
And so we my mom
My mom spoke only Japanese to me still does
And my dad obviously
Facebook Oh My English
And we celebrate a lot of Japanese holidays and
Point would bring lunch to school
I think it was we had comes like a schedule and three days a week it would be onigiri which is rice balls that have something in the middle
And then two days a week with sandwiches
Katrina went to Stanford for college and initially thought
She's going to be a doctor
Like your dad but she ended up majoring in
Economics
And after she graduated
Working at a
Consulting
Advising other businesses
22 years old and still not really sure what
She wanted to do
You know honestly at that point I wasn't thinking that I wanted to do something on
Entrepreneurial
But like I had all these ideas on what these businesses
You could do better
This should be personalized
Don't like this is just a transaction it should be an experience and likewise in your head or ideas that you actually told
Both
Like there's an example we working with
A large rate
And they actually said like that they wanted ideas
What's the
Future going to be like in this event
Mm
Sex and was literally before the iPhone
And like I had this idea where I was
Like why are you in a store
Why do you have to have every single size
Whiskey on the floor it seems silly that is it a person has to walk in and like
Find the sizes
Rescue and then
Take it themselves to a fitting room and lie
Are they, this idea where you like half of the store is
A warehouse industry
And the other half
Is like a museum
You walk around and see all these beautiful merchandise things and
You log in when you come in and you get a wand and then you can just put the wand in front of the outfits that you think
Like and then
You walk into the back
Hi guy like yours your fitting room
Real bad
All the things that you wanted or whatever would be stacked up there and then there'll be recommendations and
You know you could have one size up in one size down and
You know it could just be like
Much better experience and like going in
Weeding through rocks
I like people looked at me like I had seven
And you feel like eating in retrospect I'm like
That was crazy like if I was a CEO that retailer I feel like
Interesting idea totally impractical
23 year old
Teletubby birthday ideas
And so you know I mean I didn't share all the idea then I wouldn't say that all of the ideas that I shared were well-received but like
I had tons of ideas about how things to be done.
Do you work for this consulting firm I guess
Like 2 years and then you
Decide to go work for a venture capital
Company
Why
You know I look back on that and I really laughed because I was
Like really unhappy with the amount of work
And so I took this job at a VC fine which like I did
Actually want to be an adventurer
Capitalist and night you know I didn't
It wasn't that industry that was appealing to me but
I would like if I'm going to work at
A place that's going to be the crazy retail idea of the future like
This is the way I can meet
Oh wow so you actually thought
I'm working here I'm going to hear all these pitches and maybe I'll find a cool company and join it
Yeah and so and I did and I'm at hundreds of entrepreneurs in
Am I eating right for you a
Like a money person where you managing money or
Were you on the analysis I'd were you
In a room where these people come and pitch and you would throw like Shark Tank questions
I was in that
But I was more like the note taker
I'm like I took the notes and I would create investment memos that were like
A summary of the opportunity
Play I could have my opinion almost
For sure but I wasn't an investor
Yeah and
It was also it was a weird
To be adventurous
Because I was there from
Host
7 tone
You know we had the right of it
Versace
It was a weird time to be in bed
And
I didn't ultimately find
The company
Heard tons of ideas
Totally I probably not over a hundred on
The printer is in the
And I was there
And the most important learning
Actually was that
All of these people were just like
Super unqualified normal people with lots of ideas just like I was a superhero
Words with like
They were just really good at I guess
What kind of like
You know making the case for
And so I think it was actually the more powerful thing was that I realize that if I have all these ideas about what
Should be happening like I don't need to be in the peanut gallery Lobby my idea that people like I should just do it
Myself
And I could do it myself
But
It still wasn't
My like First Choice like my first choice would have still been
Like if I had met an entrepreneur who is amazing compelling and
Creating the retail of a feature like it was probably still my first choice to join somebody that just started myself but now all the sudden
And I had this other plan which is like well I guess if I don't find that maybe there's a way that I could do it
So when you
Conclusion that maybe you can do this yourself
What did you do
I don't know that it was like a moment I think it just entered my mind is like this is another possibility and
I actually ultimately applied to business school which
To do that
Instead of just sleeping into starting business
Yeah and that wasn't even a choice like it wasn't like I can start a business or go to Business School
I I was not like my risk profile I was never going to like quit my job and
Milly got was just
That was never a choice in my mind
And so I was like I can
Take these two years I can be a mediocre student
And you know my end goal by the end of the two years is I if I can have a company-funded if I can be paying myself a salary
If I can be paying back my student loans the day I graduate
Then
The risk profile about your partnership with tenable
Me and then my plan B would be well if I can't do that I'll have this NBA
Harvard and I'll be able to join a great company in the great founder and do
Something interesting
She gets a Harvard as a goodness
Student in 2009
And
Did you like it
I did
It was intense place right
It was very different from
Maybe all of the experiences I had
I mean we've heard these stories from especially from professors there
Do women
Who talked about in the classroom the discussion
Pretend to be in the hands go up our man of the voices that
You here mostly are men
Did you
Find that and was it a place where you felt comfortable raising your hand in
Talking
I did I mean I did and I think
That stereotype is probably
Probably was true
But I did feel comfortable talking I think
And I had a hard time disentangling Eno is it gender is it
Being from California and saying like
Like what were the things that
Created this to be true but like I did feel a little bit underestimated and
I really tried
Actively strip like out of my vocabulary
Your people say that even like a Southern accent makes
People think a certain thing and I felt
Sounding like I was from California also did the
The same thing and so
Yeah I didn't feel like
I was
The
Most likely to succeed in the classroom
Have the idea for
What would become Switchback switch
What's a early idea that came to had it even began were you given an assignment where you
Told to analyze a problem like
Wow what was the beginning of it
So I had a bunch of
I kind of collected a bunch of CiCi's and ideas in my head
If you look at
Industries in probably had like a little bit of an academic approach and how it looked
Did these things but like the hunting and fishing and
It's I know
It's a huge industry
Massive PP
You are super passionate about it it's really fragmented but also
Concentrated words like really Mom and Pops are all serious like
Orvis end
Anyway it's a super interesting industry because it's massive and there's elements of fashion
Actually worth like it whether it's technology or actual fashion things go out of style
And so I rented a car and I drove to
New Hampshire
Unlike visited like
Two Gun Shop
And like the fact by that's the second one I was like
Disrupt the whole gun industry
I just was like I don't care how big of an industry this is like I'm just not super fashion about it and also like
I am not
The person to like
Disrupt the hunting and fishing
I think there probably is
It is all the same like I was actively exploring a couple of ideas
I like this
Is a real thing and it has a reason to belong in the world
And the idea of
Stitch fix was one. I also texted and
Explored in the way I did that was your idea
The idea was how can you
I mean they're couple different Beast
He's the one pieces overall was just like
More and more dollars are moving to
E-commerce stores like this is the map that I found was super compelling for my time and Consulting was dollars are leaving stores in
Funny Commerce
As dollars gradually leave every one of those dollars is
Usually
Hurtful to a store as it loses
Because all the sudden you can't pay your rent
People in soap be like a 10% 15% decline in your store volume can kill a store
And 10 or 15%.
Nothing like all that much
Watching soap
There's this kind of like
Death spiral that I
Kind of anticipated would happen with
And Netflix is blocked
You're kind of like the best example of it. Like
Even if
30% of the people in your town are using Netflix
70% of 2
The people in your town are going to block
Republican
I mean the writing on the wall
Then the death spiral component of it is like that one blockbuster
Store closes
And now
The 70% of the p
People who lived in that town
Have to decide do I drive 10 MI
Another Blockbuster I do I try this Netflix thing
At 30% the minority of people in my town or are doing
That was a probably a big
Conversation at that time because Netflix was killing blockbusters
Yes it's fascinating so I
Expected that would happen in retail apparel
And then on top of that I felt like there was this massive depersonalization of
I'm retail that was
Happening which one you're buying toilet paper iPhone chargers or diapers is
You don't need that to
But that totally ignore this
Category of apparel which is like deeply personal and
I'm deeply nuanced and r
Product categories that are super emotional like you're not kind of emotionally buying a box
Kleenex felt like you were very emotionally buying that plays early and so I felt like all of the emotion and
You want to Ben
Stripped out and you Commerce and that that wasn't
The right
Approach
The idea was
How can you deliver a really actually personal experience
And apparel
And use data in
Technology to make that
Scalable in makeup better
But why I mean why wouldn't you just you know
Offer up a bunch of options and just let people can a scroll through
Legacy I love the beauty of online shopping is really that time was infinite choices right you could just
Scroll through it and find a thing you like
Yeah and I think four
Some customers you know that the way that they want
Rashad Butler
Like I'm five
And so there's
A whole world of
Apparel that's like
Literally not Rowlett
Just simply because they're not going to fail because I'm the wrong height
And the things that you know if you're living in California you can go on a homepage and they're trying to sell you
Cashmere mittens and it's like that's totally irrelevant
So if you feel back like what Stitch fix does it's like
Yes like if you could instead of going to a mall all day or instead of spending
You know your entire evening with 30 browser tabs
Open to try to compare and contrast
Different genes you want to buy
If you could get a box sent to you
That had
Two pairs of jeans are even better one pair of jeans and they fit you great that is an infinitely better experience than
The other
This idea about
Business
Send a subscription box
2 closed
People but how did you
Because you can begin to think of
About house
So is the way it works is basically I would have
Friends of friends fill out a survey and you would let me know what size and style what thing
Things you like Brands you like all the form to company and named
This isn't 2010 I was experimenting
As a student essentially
Writing to other friends and students in
The benefit of being in Boston to is like I didn't really happen
How many friends in Boston and that was easier to meet strangers
And so one of the things that I needed to prove to myself was like it wasn't going to be scalable for you to tell
Tell me okay on these are the 7 Things I want and then for me to go buy this
But the math doesn't work for that too
Scalable
And so you need to have a set of inventory or working from and so
I was buying
Inventory at retail
Front booty
And
I would keep track of like
I did have a 14-day return policy or a 30 day return policy and then I would use I wasn't making any money doing this but I would use that as
Is my inventory
So that when somebody was thought their profile I would then put together a box of things
That were relevant based on what they
Sheridan their Pro
File and then they would try things on and then if they wanted to buy things they would write me up for
Personal check and I would
Sell it to them and if they didn't want to keep it and
If I ultimately didn't sell it within my 14 days
Return window I go north
How did you buy
Stop add a credit card at the
$6,000 limit
No dice
And you would buy them and then sell them in the market
No I was just telling them at the price that I was right so I wasn't making any money I just wanted to like how to see if it would work
And how many
Friends were in
Peanut
Funny baby
What did you find from
This group of 20 people what did you discover
I discovered that
Do you actually could learn a lot from somebody and there's just this thesis around like do I have to like be with you in person
Understand your style and who you are or can I do that
And like I felt pretty confident
Like you to do it
There was a number of items
I started out with 10 items
And the reality was like people working to try on 10 items it's a lot it's
A lot of work
And you just look at something in your like now there's no way I'm going to like that and you just don't
Denso ten
Was too many
Did I learn
I think I learned the brand thing of Vicodin
You know people were actually
Surprisingly very open to buying from brands that
They weren't aware of and in fact found some value in finding brands that they wouldn't have normally have found on their own
When did you pull a trigger and say
Alright let's let's leave form a business that's supposed to get an LLC on let's like
Make this real
It was
We didn't actually the company wasn't formed until February
Mm
But
I kind of became all in on this and not other Concepts I would say like
Late 2010
So when you
When you really can't lie
Got this going in at that time it was not just
Be right wasn't you were not the only one about
Yatika founder of the
She's the wife of my
And so how are you
Grain is business an
Also being a student
I scheduled my classes so that they were a lot they were all lumped together in the middle either in the middle of it and of the week
I did something with my scheduling that enabled me to be able to spend almost a week in California
And so in January and then again in February I spent almost a full week
Out here
And what I would do out here was meet with Angel Investors and
On Valentine's Day
A 2011 we got a term sheet
Steve Anderson
Steve Anderson is an investor that you met through other people and he gave you money to give you
He gave it to him sheet
4/2 million dollars inside now go talk to other Angel Investors
And try to find others
Dwayne The Rock
And then probably talk to
30 other people who
Said no ultimately even though he had already
Said yeah yeah
In that
NSR winter in Spring of 2011 when you
You took the research you gathered from these 20
People
And you went
To meet with investors in the Silicon Valley
Did you just you show them this day then you should see I try this on 20 friends in this is what we found right I mean
You can understand
You can understand I guess
Why they might have been
I know I would come in and I'd say like you. Here's the beta that I did
Like 20 people in here's how I think the
Model shape up and like I would bring a box in
And I feel like yours in exam
Will the box look like
Laminated cards
Any of the Box wasn't like
All that nice
Spent any money on Brandy
I'm at that seed stage like it was a
100% Jessie
Explain wow you explained
What the business model was
Because I just to clarify Stitch fix today
You sign up
You paid 20 bucks a month
You get five items
Do you every month
Option end if you
By the mall you get a discount
And
If you return them all that's
It's fine it's free but it's
$20 a month
Essentially for 8
Personal Style
Yeah and it's $20 and to be very clear like you don't have to do it on a monthly basis you could do a quarterly you can do it all a cart like
Like you don't you know you don't need to commit to any time for him but it is every time you get a fix you paid $20 styling fee
$20 is credit towards anything
Is Dubai
But the heart of it was really this like
We're going to buy inventory we're going to get to know you were going to become experts on
You client America mask
On products
And then we're going to generate really
Great reputation
Action of those two
Set a big investment right act like what we did and what we did that and what we do now is like
We are like a department store
You keeping her have the exact
When's the when I would go and raise
Half million dollars
Steve Anderson
Half of that was literally going to buy dresses and clothes
Adventure investors
I hated that
But I'm Not only would they hated that but
You
If in your business model you said
Where can I personalize
Human being
Involved in picking
Stop I mean Venture people
They don't like to pay
People like they like companies that that are like they like user-generated content or they like to pay for
Human resource
People said like this is going to be an inventor
Gory nightmare like
And it was good feedback because
Ultimately
Inventory
We are very good at managing inventory and we
And you have people saw that and people
Wordscapes
You'd be able to
Over that period of time when you're trying to raise money
And all everybody
Except for Steve said no
I'm was that
Demoralizing
Disheartening or whatever
I know Waterford
Dinos
Both
I'm like you just you had to be able to have reason
4 confidence in
What you were doing regarding
Adventure
And so you did have to have the
6 get about it and you did have to
Let It Be
Stop
But at the same time
What we were doing like
Nobody else is really doing
I feel like a very long time
And
When you're doing something that nobody else is doing
You are either the
Smartest
Or the stupidest person in the room
When we come back why despite early growth the money man in Silicon Valley
Want to give Stitch fix the valuation Katrina thought it deserved
And how she fought back
Play with us
I'm. Rosner listening to how I built this
From NPR
Sports
NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
They can be open from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's the spring of 2011
And with the seed money she got from
Single investor
Katrina Lake got a small office in San Francisco
And got to work
Yeah is that where they got the term sheet
In April it funded in May I graduated and then in June moved to San Francisco
In San Francisco was important to do it because this is where you want to live or because of the
The tech industry or
Honestly
Another smart way to talk about it as the tech industry but honestly like when I first started the company okay we have to be in New York
And then like a couple months and I realized
New York lots of companies are here like
I think it would have been
Really hard to do what we did anywhere else because we have
Many many data scientists and many many engineers and
In retrospect
It was not just about me being comfortable about it if we wanted to fulfill on the vision if using technology to
They deliver our service like it would have been varied
Were you able to build a website with that money
No we're not yet yeah so the first
7 months of Stitch fix like we didn't have a website actually it was their first name was Rock habit which lasted for about three months before
We got
It was very clear that Nordstrom would have sued us for it if she knows.
Five seconds of looking at was like this you got to change your name
Kissing you used to call it Stitch fix
Yeah
Asleep on website yet and what is it for
Cheese look like
How do you go to stitchfix.com
And it said
Coming soon do you want any part of a dice
And then it said if you if you clicked on yes I want a part of the beta it would
Cluck-U / 2
I forget if it was a Google doc or a SurveyMonkey but if something
And then you fill out all your information and you say your interests
And we actually had a weightless
Just for a long time because
We didn't have clothes to send to you that we're relevant and demand
Paste kind of what
We had for a long time
And so once I was ready for you I would send you a link that said like
Stitch fix is ready for you
And then I would
I would send you a pic
PayPal request
For $20
And
I'm so the history of The Styling fee that we have was that I was worried that
You could be a boss or somebody who's going to steal money for steal my clothes and so I felt like if you were willing to
To PayPal me $20
Before I'd even sent you anything
You are probably a legitimate human being who wasn't going to steal
My clothes you could take the rest
Right and so
I would PayPal request you for $20 you give me $20
And then I would
Sanju
A shipment of five items
And inside there was like a paper return survey cuz we still didn't have a website and so it was a piece of paper that was like in
An Excel thing that had all the items and then you would fill out with words what you were going to keep what you aren't going to keep in explaining why
And then we would have taskrabbit to type that
Into Excel so that we had to go back in that information so that
We had it
And then
Based on what you were keeping and not keeping a net of your $20 styling fee I would send you a Paypal invoice for the neck
And that was kind of hot worked in the ending where were you getting the closer
And we're buying at wholesale and so we were buying six items at a time
We would go to it like
There's any shows you can go to and you can go introduce yourself to Brands and
You know most of the brands weren't that interested in working with us but you know someone give us a shot and say like I don't know that's an interesting
You can buy
6 items from us and literally would buy Six of one thing at a time
Will not
Yeah definitely
And who was
Scott who is peking cook how did you
I mean you obviously you know how to dress well you are well-dressed right here but I mean
That's a big responsibility till I beat a personal stylist
Yeah even a hundred people even 30 people
Yeah and I mean it was
Aren't we hired our first stylist
Like February
At first light
Gear just
It's like it was probably me
Yeah under the time it was a weird one packing the Box you are in San Francisco
And it's
You know you're potentially doing everything and you've got this
Website
And
Are you getting the word out
It was literally just
People telling other people
And dope
It was 29 minutes 35 and was 110 then
235 and then
It just like
Over that summer of 2011
Yeah
Yeah those are the actual cohort numbers for each month and then I think after that it started
Getting the attention of on
What I would call like
Small to medium sized
Weather in Bogota
Write it certainly wasn't in Vogue and it wasn't like the bloggers at public millions of
Followers but it was
People who have like 50
2000 followers
1000followers about it
Yeah I would I mean if that I would
And that was a really big driver
For us for a long time
So now you're
Starting to get some momentum and obviously you're
Growing you need more money you need millions of dollars
When you would show up
Seeking money
Was it challenging I mean
But let's be honest I mean Blues bass majority of
Of people intact
Are men and in
The space you know going to be seized are probably used to sing mostly men
Was the gender Dynamic ever something that was
Present that you
Felt that you
Southworth
Against you that made it harder to
Raise money or generate interest
Raising money was really hard
And
I think there are a lot of factors that
I mean certainly the inventory side like that's real like
Silicon Valley venture investors
I'm want to buy software engineer that they want to buy a
Like they don't want to bike
The gender Dynamic was real
Also
You know 94% of venture investors are man and
Probably the majority of men don't feel passion
About dressing lemon
I'm curious what you know with respect to your experience with venture capitalist
Because the Dermatology about them and the genius of Entry
The capitalists in
You know how they
Great rest
Seeing if they can invest in hundreds or thousands of
Failures and they just need one or two
Till like
Come out and look like geniuses
Mythology of the oracle
You know like this
Oracle venture capitalist
You know
Gifted and can just pick winners but
I don't think that really matches with real
Yeah
And it is like it creates another dynamic
To where
And I don't think I realize this is
The time but you're right like they want billion dollar
Businesses and they would either rather they want you to be a zero or a billion
Everything in the middle is not that
And so
People were like this is a real business and it's really working
But you know I don't know if it can be more than a 30 million-dollar
Revenue or more than like a hundred million dollars in Revenue
Do you like I just don't think it's that big
And likes to a normal person
3 million dollars are a hundred million dollars in science
But like from a venture capitalist perspective like
They make the most money when
It's a billion or 0
And so
Are there a lot of people were like hey what you're doing is traction and it's real and it's working
But like I don't think it can be big enough for
Yeah
Depending you still raised
Baron money
42 million dollars
You know In the Beginning Witch
Which sounds
Pretty good but I guess you still needed to.
Vicky Pattison
Yeah I mean
Once I had a little bit of
Traction in some weird ways it made it
Harder because now all the sudden
People are like
You're trying to put that billion dollar price tag
Trying to figure out like
You know is this
Big enough
Yeah and so in the middle it was really hard and
In the middle yeah that to raise money it was
Is really fun though you are
Profitable or on the way there
Probability
And
I hated it like I hated raising money I didn't feel good at it
Like it wasn't my intention when I started the company let me do this with his little
Capital as I can
But after a couple of experiences with fundraising
I was like I want to do this is
Littlest iPod
The meatball
Company is growing and then I guess we should we should mention here that
You guys employ a lot of data sign
Huge number
Assertive
Become like
Company not
The fashion company
May I mean
Honestly from Day Zero with we were always a day to come
Like even like those recurrent surveys that I just
Even when
We were physically shipping the fixes out of our office and we didn't even have a website
We were collecting the data about
The product the attribute
Is the product
And we were collecting
Physically with pen and paper your fee
Feedback about what you like
What you didn't like and what you thought of the
Tyson Howard
And so
The data element was always super important but you know I don't think we were employing
True
Data science I would say
Until I mean I don't know
Is Eric
Are joined us in 2012
And air quality
Sindhu
HughesNet
And he was a Daily Guide Netflix in your thinking
Wow man that doesn't get better than Netflix
Know what you want to watch
Grab the remote control
Sprite and especially the time is it
Before they're doing original Concha
Don't like their whole thing with algorithms
Recommendation
And he was like I'd Netflix we show you like a hunter recommendations at once and he was like we were just having this conversation
We're like if we were really bold
We would only show you 5 or 3
Or if we were really bald
When you open Netflix Regis start playing the content
That you would want to play
And
He's like that
Kind of what you're doing here with
And so he was very attracted to
The fact that recommendations were like actually at the core of what we are doing you able to describe your company
In shorthand or did you ever described as Ehrlich on
I don't know but I don't really use that on a
But you know I think there are elements like we were
100% of our revenue is
Tide
To recommendation
Like that's a very
Compelling thing to a data scientist who loves recommendations feeling like that's going to be at the
Quorum
At what point did you become profitable
I'm we turn profitable we had a profitable quarter I think in mm
So it took you three years
Just actually
Super fast
How much
Do you think about
Competition
Because there I mean
There are all kinds of
Potential competitors after other obvious from being Amazon
Massive
Right and they
Little fingers in every pie
You know
What's the weather like
Killer Avril like that thing that you guys have that
Makes you
Sustainable and resistance
22 Big Chill
Yeah I mean we
I would say that we pay attention to but don't obsess over
Petitioning
I think when we think about what special about Stitch fix it's the one to one human connect
Shenzhen in the recommendations
And so
You know some of the things that are really hard in today's e-commerce are like
If you want to find a pair of jeans that fit you like
It's not a great user experience that have literally a million pairs of jeans
Did you ask Robin try to filter and sort
You know that's an example of a place where like the human element of like
And these jeans have strep through these Street
Jeans don't have straps in these are great for
People who are your height and we know that with data like all of those attributes
Are hugely important in helping you find which one of those millions of pairs of jeans are the right ones
Sing for you and so
You know there's a transacting part of e-commerce but before the transaction there's the discovery is like what is the thing that you're going to love
And that is a really hard problem to solve in today Z
E-commerce in one that I think we are uniquely good at
How many people by the way work for
I'm leave over
5000 in
And have a stylus
Twerk because you got
Hybrid model rightware
All these humans are
Collaborating with
With algorithm
Yeah we have over 3000 Style
And and the way Stitch fix works of the integration of humans and data is that
They're both very kind of
Richly combined
And on and we see it as like they both are uniquely got it
And so
Like a stylist should never have
Have to worry about like you hate yellow or love
Like the data can take
And so I'm the
Yellow and salmon
I need the Styles can see that but the data is going to
Exclude that from being able to be even available
Hair stylist
And so on The Stylist will later on his or her own judgment over those records
Condition to choose the right thing
News for you
And so in some cases the data science is going to be really active
Sheraton like
Trying to figure out which jeans are best for you for example of the place where data science is
I'm enormous
Helpful
And then there were other times when I'm this Stylus is layering on hue
Human judgment
You took this company public
Remember
Yeah people come at the first right
Youngest
Females
CEO
To ever take a company public
You know
Probably this year you will appear on
Forbes
List of
Wealthiest self-made
Women
As you became more and more prominent and
And the company became more profitable and you start to get more attention
All of a sudden you are sort of
A successful woman and Tack
Kind of
I'm symbol
Did that irritate you or
So did you
Embrace it
Initially or
How did you feel
You know that's an interesting one where I think
My mind is
Change time
Maybe even in the last year or two years
At first I was really resistant to act like I really didn't like
Being a successful
Female CEO
Like I was like I just want to be a 6
And you know I think was changed about it now is that
When I wrote my application essay to HBS like I wrote about Meg Whitman
Female CEO in like
There were so few people like I I still very much admire her and I did admire her then but
They're very few people for me to choose from and saying like who I want
To be like
And I
Now that being able to be
Part of what
Opens people's lens of possibility more I think is really powerful and
I'm so I think now like I'm
I don't know kind of
Proud to be able to be part of that and
Like I'm very happy to wear that label and I'm very
You know I think it's
Good for people to be able to see more examples of what
Success can look like that maybe are different from what it's
Look like
There was a story I don't want to keep
Now I bet you're so go that at a certain point
In your journey through his money
You experience harassment
From a prominent
Partner at a prominent Venture Capital firm
They released a statement of Entry saying something like you know we should have done better
Like that
What was that a common experience for you
But I can't speak to that
Specific example
But
And I think that there were real challenges with
That power Dynamic I think of
You know who has
The power and who has the money and who
Doesn't use standing in front of a room of
Man
Yeah
And I think the
Dark elements of it.
Just feel structurally unfair that
And I don't think that solved unless you
To change the
Proportion of
Men and women that are in liters
And so
You know I mean they're examples where like I was
And I was at a conference
Anchor soccer was on stage like
Hundreds of people at the room like this isn't a secret he was
Things publicly
And Chris like he's at he's a venture cap
Yeah and one of the things he was saying was he was like look like I am
You're not a typical Venture capitalists like I don't have an office in San Francisco like I just I live up in Tahoe in like
Be entrepreneurs they come to me in like
They come and hang out with me and Tahoe and they like drink beer is in my hot tub and
Like I get to know them in their businesses and like
Yeah there's part of that that you're like oh cool like that's different but like if you think about it like I'm sitting in the audience
I think I was pregnant
What time am I sitting in the audience
I'm pregnant I'm like
I'm not going to come meet you
Bikini and I can't
Even coming to your hot tub because I'm pregnant and I can't drink your beer is because I'm pregnant and like
You know there's just all of these structural elements that like just make it harder and more challenging in like
You know you just
Realize like well I guess I'm never going to be able to be in his Pipeline and like that's okay but like it's just
There few or is it just challenging
Yo is there a nurse
Tone deafness
Diane and I
I'm wondering if
Since you know more and more of this
Stuff is coming out in more people talking about it
And we had Jenn Hyman on the show and she's
Talk about her experience
With Rent the Runway
Whether I'm some of that
Is trickling down in a way that
Starting to change
Behavior I don't know do you
Are you hearing that
But anyway
I certainly hope it is
And I don't want to make it seem like everything is super unfair and that everybody Zachary feel like that's that's really not the case
Say hi
Great partners
Asterism by and large I think
You have good intentions
I do genuinely hope that it
It's getting better and then
People are at least more wear
And so you know my hope is at least
Being able to see this
Success stories
Create another
Pattern
Jennifer bench
That you will lose to earlier which is that
In the midst of all this like in the midst of building this company
You've got married and had a child too
Yeah
Alger canal
He is
17 months
I mean
That's a lot of hours
Yeah it's a lot and it is
I don't know that I ever actively was thinking like I have this company and like I also need to
Have my life and you know I
But it was like I in the time of the company
I met my husband I got married
Baby like me I've gone through a lot of life
Transitions through the company and
And I think it's really healthy because I think you know in a lot of ways your company feels like
Your
Kind of baby and you're only thing and
And I think I was
Lucky fortunate like
You know whatever it is to be able to have had the space in my life to also be able to do
Have those miles to your mom yet
So I should admit that I get knocked
James from
To listen who said you know you
You you don't ask
Batman about
Their children
As much as you are
Ask women and so I've been more mantle
Doing that
I think the one difference though is that you know
As a woman you are caring but
A child for 9 months
And running the company
I mean that
That's very different that is a
That's a really
It's a challenge meme
Physically
It's challenging and then
You also have to put
Put your emotional energy into your business
Yeah right
No it's and it's
Different you know like you show up at meetings and you're like 8 months
And like
Your people didn't really know how to react
Should I unlike had a hard time navigating and I don't blame them because it's like
Like I took a 16-week maternity leave
I was out of the office
16 weeks
Unplugged
Yeah I mean I'd there a couple things that I did I did some recruiting things like there are some things that I see you like only I
I could do I like
I pretty much didn't set foot in the office
For 16 weeks
And you know that's the example that I have
Very female employee
Dislike
If I'm not honoring the maternity leave policy that we have like how are people going to feel comfortable
Yeah feeling like it's the right thing to do
C weeks
You're the sentiment
That I want to ask you
Churches that
Pretty early on
In Billings
Are you
You parted ways with your
Co-founder
What's the story meaning
Just have a different sense of
What you
Wanted to do
Yeah it's a microphone and I we parted ways and
The summer of 2000
June 12th
And
It was a me night
Define a lot of
If I can share on it but
Like it was really hard and it
Like in a divorce he talked about like irreconcilable differences and like
I feel like
Through that I really understood what that meant a like if you can be in a place where you really deeply care for somebody
+
The same time you
See things so differently and
Can't
Can't see
The future in the same
Do you
Do you think that would that be
People who start up businesses are better off doing it on their own
Oh I don't know I mean
Starting a company is subject
Team sport
You know I look back and I
Could not have done it without
The many
Employees who believed in at the many clients who believes in that the like
My friends
Coup
I didn't go to their wedding because I would like to pour into busy at the time and like I mean there's just like it's
Such a team
Sport and you have to
Surround yourself with
People who
Help you to achieve those goals and
Does that mean you have to have a co-founder or not like I don't know but like
I couldn't imagine
Having done it without having a network of people who believe Katrina Lake founder
Love Stitch fix a company which by the way is now valued at over
2 billion dollars
And on the day the company actually went public
Katrina had some help from her one-year-old
Who is ringing the NASDAQ Bell while she was holding him
He was holding the stuffed animal and I was holding him during the dress rehearsal like practice
The thing that in a go to the motions and he was like really chill at happy to be up there and I was kind of like
All right we're going to get this way he's going to be up here and this are going to do it anymore so you spit up all over me in the
I mean that that's the funny thing is like if I had planned to have them up there there's no way it would have worked like he was
He's a year old whatever like you wasn't going to cooperate but
The Stars aligned and
It worked
And stick around because it just
The moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first I quit thanks to one of our sponsors Starbucks
For the first time in 43
3 years
Starbucks
Introducing a second
Nespresso
Starbucks Blonde.
It's smooth and subtly
So whatever your drink is
Triad with
Starbucks Blonde
Nespresso
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you
You built that
This is Brian Sonia Wallace
Tapping away on his
Vintage Smith Corona typewriter
Apartment in Los Angeles
He uses it for his business which is
Writing poetry
On demand
Poetry is
Like the ultimate non-commercial
You know unless you're a professor or an Instagram celebrity poet you're you're really not usually making aloe
Living doing this
What about 4 years ago
Brian sort of stumbled into the poultry business
When he was laid off from his job
Writing grants for a non-profit
He always likes reading
Poetry
Hey you know maybe I should just
Set up a typewriter in public in
Sell my poems to
People passing by
I thought okay let me see if I can
Pay my rent for one month it was this experiment in
Whether you could make any money off of this poetry thing
Surprise started to show up at Arts festivals and other events around town with his
Typewriter
And a small table I originally had a sign that said give me a topic I'll write you a poem pay me what you think it's worth
And it turns out people would pay anywhere between five and $40 for a custom poem
About their boyfriends or their girlfriends even about their dogs
End of that month
Brian had earned enough money to pay his rent
And his utilities and it was funny because after the month I was like okay well now I'm going to hang my typewriter up and focus on other thing
And I kept getting calls from either people who I had met on the street or people who had seen
Something about it
Asking me to do private event
But when it came to private events
Ryan had no idea what
To charge my remember there were a couple early ones once in particular I remember I'd like an investment banking conference
And I didn't really understand that you could set up Baseline price and that people had
Budgets and would pay for event entertainment at the Mall of America where people lined up
App for custom poems
Including one particularly interesting custom
Did my usual open Hi how are you what do you need a poem about
She thought for a minute she said you know I've actually just come from
A week-long silent Meditation Retreat
It was really
Intense and emotional and so I just came to get some Dippin Dots as a reward
Sir Brian got to work
And a few minutes later
He presented her with
The poem
It's scary
How hectic
A week of Silence
Canby
Left alone with our thoughts
And no release valve
Do we implode
That woman ended up hugging Brian after he read her that poem apparently it happens to him a lot
Finding a lightness that starts deep
In the corner of my belly
And ends
With Dippin Dots
At the mall
Brian Sonia Wallace as business is called rent
Poet
This year he expects to make about $30,000 in
He no longer does this solo
He works for the whole team of Freelancers who make money
The Poetry if you want to hear Brian's entire poem you can visit our Facebook page and
And of course if you want to tell us your story
. npr.org
And thanks for listening to our show this week
If you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this.
Npr.org
Please also subscribe to our podcast at Apple
Podcast or however you
Your podcast
You can also write us HIV
TT at npr.org
Twitter address
Is at how I built this
Our show was produced this week by Run.
Abdel-fattah
Ramtin arablouei
Compose the music
Thanks also to
Geneva grass
Sunrise Michigan
For Tamiflu
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Newark Uso
Gyros
Have you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com