Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here
You know Sadie Lincoln still remembers the name of the
Very first person who signed up for a membership with
Barre3 back in
Which is pretty incredible because at the time she was also.
Teaching 19 classes a week
And cleaning the bathrooms at the studio
Today there are barre3 studios in 33 States
Sadie also joined us for our first-ever how I built this Summit last month and she shared some helpful tips on
How to build a grape
Company culture right from the start
If you want to check out a video of Sadie from The Summit
Just posted it
At our how I built this Facebook page
Go check it out
Anyway this episode with Sadie first roundabout
A year ago
One evening we put the kids to bed I'll never forget that swear in
In the living room and Chris came up to me and he pulled a spreadsheet out of his pocket
And he said Sadie I've been holding us in my pocket for a couple weeks
Open it up and it was a spreadsheet a model of how we could
Seller home all our possessions and drop out and not work
And that was the spark to building
Running PR
How I built this
A show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
Lego
Lincoln turned a room with mirrors and a ballet bar into a multimillion-dollar company
Let's not one of the fastest-growing fitness programs
Us
So if you want to take a little bit of
Pilates in some yoga
And then throwing some ballet into the next
You get bar
It's actually been around since 1959 when a former ballerina named Lottie Burke invented the whole car
Concept in London
But you didn't really begin to take off in the US until this past decade
And today there are more than 700 Barre studios around the country
Companies like core Fusion physique 57 and Pure Barre
The people who go to Barre classes
Overwhelmingly women
Most of them are just
Going to the exercise is there actually connected to the
Culture around the whole bar movement
It's about building confidence in a steam but it's also big business
The whole Boutique Fitness sector which bar is definitely a part of
Is now a 30 billion dollar industry
And one of the best-known faces of bar
Sadie Lincoln
Her company barre3 now has about a hundred and Thirty locations all around the world
And the company is still privately owned by Sadie and her husband Chris
Just one outside investor
All of this has of course made them rich and in Sadie's case
It's made her a celebrity Fitness Guru
Which as you will hear
Has made her very uncomfortable
Because Sadie isn't actually is flashing and slick as her online videos would suggest
In fact her upbringing
It was pretty unconventional
My mom and her four best friends
Dropped out their part of the counterculture
Translate they live in California and they just dropped out they were living in California yet they found each other
They're kind of gypsy like they're traveling around together they ended up in Taos New Mexico
And each of them
Ended up having a child
The dads off
And they
Basically raised us kids collaboratively
That's what I mean was that there
Your plan like to all these women to move to tylosand
You know basically have children and then
Ultra raised up these children together
Because it
I mean that's how it works out
Is that how they thought it was going to work out I don't think they had a plan
I think it just happened and it was a time of
Serration
It was a time for them to
Go inwards
Look inside
Live close to Nature
Chester intellect
And create and discover a new way of living
Number 5 kids
All together
Soul artists
8 years older than me so she's sort of like an honorary Auntie anyway but lark
Sophia
GI
Kyle
Megami
Sussex
First Fitness
Part of your Early Childhood we used to do what we called the Tea Party
Tanya rad record and Boogie
Dance our butts off
Bob Dylan Willie Nelson and Chuck Berry
The Beatles of course
We did that as a family often
So that was my first introduction to just
Loving moving
Does your mom like make ends meet
Well first of all we are off and on food stamps
I do have memories of going to the
Store with food stamps with a note for my mom that I could use them and thinking of this is I have different money than other people
But
They did and that
I meant went once they got secure and they had some
Ability that they created their own
Are they created a newspaper called what's happening and then changed it in later years to Eugene weekly which is still the weekly
Publication in Eugene
Yeah did you sometimes
Feel like a weird kid like a different kid
Yes I felt like a weird kid
And
Then I
Tried to play Norma
You know I thought I played normal for a long
Kind of I don't want my friends
That I had this alternative
Out of the box family I was really attracted to
Normal kids normal families
Were you embarrassed
Oh yeah
Yeah I was in bear
I mean my mom was wearing Birkenstocks before they were cool they were smoking weed
Before it was late all they were
Outrageous annies
Now I think
It's wonderful that back then
You know I wanted to
To be I was like Alex Peak
And Family Ties
Kind of
I was like
You know I became a cheerleader
You know which is very you know of course they all supported me because that's what they do unconditional love no matter what your choice is
Ana's really social
I just want to be normal
Were you a pretty good student
In my school
Horrible skin
Really bad
I went to Alternative School called magnet Arts
I developed a great deal of confidence there
You know we did
Pottery and dance
And music and
But I didn't learn the basic
And then Middle School I entered middle school and I didn't have the foundation
Nor the interest
And so I just kind of survived on
Having fun
So After High School Sadie took off for La. Should become an actor
And in the meantime she started to take classes at Santa Monica City College
Actually liked it
A couple years and she transferred to UCLA
And it was during that time she got really into fitness classes so after college
Sadie decided to look for work
In the fitness industry
Yeah
I landed a job with a company called 24 Hour Fitness
And
The reason I took that job really was I wanted to move to San Francisco to live with my girlfriend I lived in on her dining room floor
Four letter lie
And
They were based on the bay area and Fitness
What was the job that you were hired to do
I was hired to run
All of the group exercise for I think 25 gem
Wow is it
We were acquiring gems
Got to wrap it
Okay so I started I think we had around 50 gems
I ended up staying there for 11 years
When I laugh react 430 location
So this was just
Massive explosive growth
Explosive growth I thought I was going to work there maybe to one to two years and
I ended up
Reporting directly to the founder and CEO
Mark masterov
And he just kept igniting interest in me because he gave me all these incredible projects along the way
So everything from sales
Brand strategy which is my favorite I mean it was the ultimate
Learning
Experience for me I traveled all over the world
Alter Scandinavia and
Asia and
Spain
Italy
Mark had other businesses besides 24hourfitness that I got to be apart of gems in Russia
So he's like a major
Fitness Mogul there is no one
Greater I mean in the fitness industry he's known even Tuesday yeah oh yeah
OKC to you are at 24 Hour Fitness
Exploding in growth
Is that where you met your husband Chris
I'm at Chris in San Fran
Just outside of
24-Hour Fitness
QuiBids work
Game for a startup software company
I met him at a Super Bowl party
And we connected instantly his last name is Lincoln
And I meant he introduced himself as Lincoln everybody called him Lincoln and I remember in that moment thinking Ash my name is going to be Mercedes link
My real name is Mercedes so I knew that insta
Wow yeah I knew
I know
Q41
And
He
After a couple inches with Mark
Mouse Drive
Mark pulled Crescent to the loop
As well so he ended up working direct for Mark as well
And so Mark now had me and Chris and he would put us on Project
So it's a wonderful testing ground for us as business partners
To see how we work together
Chris is really analytical really grounded
I'm more the new shiny thing
Dreamer
Ennui
Bought a house
Which is like climbing Mount Everest in the Bay Area
Which is really exciting to find a moment for us for me especially I
I rented
Michelin Tire
Life growing up
So how actually owning a home with Incredible
We had two children back-to-back 18 months apart
So I mean
You're living in the Bay Area and you've got this gig with Mark and both you and Chris are kind of doing projects for him
And
What what happens if you have a scissor some sort of Crisis that kind of propels you to make a big life change
Will the first
Prices for me
I think happened before I was pregnant with my first
Child eye
Even though I was part of this booming business and my career was booming
And I was making it
Great salary and you know we're buying a house and all that good stuff
My own health was declining
And I didn't feel good
You know I've just been immersed in the fitness industry but it wasn't working in my own body I was
I was
Really uncomfortable in my own skin I don't feel alive inside that make sense
I
With working out really hard everyday
Running on the treadmill counting how many calories I was eating and how many calories I was
Spending because that's scientific
Calories in calories out doing all the right things
That I had learned where it was the formula for success in this is
Multi
Billion dollar industry I was in with working
Selling like hotcakes
And
This attachment to an idea
I was sort of drinking the Kool-Aid
And
I was shameful that I wasn't looking that idea or feeling that idea
So what changed
When I got pregnant with Audrey
I think
Being pregnant is the ultimate
Opportunity to realize
Because
If you think about it inside your body
I I was craving a baby without
Thinking about it
And I never felt more alive and connected and happy
For me becoming pregnant reminded me
Add my grits
My auntie's
The power of intuition what healthy really Wyatt's with living close to Nature being intuitive forces following someone else
The formula
And I had this a high thyroid to do yoga at home
And I had this
This Moment of clarity I'll never forget it
At where
I literally said
Myself
Maybe I'm not feeling sadness
Maybe Fitness is failing me
And
I'm probably not alone
Even though in the fitness industry is booming the vast majority of us it's not working I mean that's the new
New story on the news everyday
It's like Abby cities on the rise people are more stressed out than they ever have been
There's all these magic spells magic answers formulas that were also Desperately Seeking
You having this conversation with your husband
Chris
I would say the conversation
Chris and I are having more at that point versus Fitness is failing or not
Was we were alone
Really lonely as a couple
We were having a hard time finding belonging
We don't have a strong community
And like is this it likes it just you and me you know
What's going on he was having a hard time relating to
Business as he was
Managing
Vista Studios he was managing with 24 Hour Fitness in
You know I just I remember this one moment walking into the room and
You was on speakerphone and the manager that was working with
Coaching him there on a conference call
The guy and he was did it with such great intention but he would
And nobody could see each other so he was saying okay everybody raise your right hand
Now put it on your back
The lift it up
Now put it back down
Now lift it up
Put it back down
So he was having a run on the conference call Pat there and back
And Chris instead of doing that was flipping off the screen
Right
Something needs to change
So we felt empty there wasn't a sense of purpose
So what did you do
So we started
I mean over the year is over like maybe a two-year
He was coming up with all kinds of different business
Plant watering business
The pizza
2 Nail Studio tour
And
So that was sort of in the backdrop
But also it was like I had this good gag I was working from home I had two babies
I'm he had a
Good job I mean
We had bought our house
So I feel like things are kind of moving along pretty pretty well
And one evening
We put the kids to bed I'll never forget that's where in the living room and Chris came up to
Tumi
And he pulled a spreadsheet out of
And he said Sadie I've been holding us in my pocket
Her
Couple weeks
And
And I just need a sheriff
Can you open it up
And it was a spreadsheet
A model
Of how we could
Seller home
All our possession
And move to Bend Oregon
And drop out
And not work
Well and
Yo I'm the one that's usually thinking of these outrageous ideas he's more conservative and
Super analytical first
Himtoo
Bring me this outrageous
Idea
Was honestly one of the hottest things
Because I was just like you see me
Eufy Adventure
And
It's also a reflection of how is
Raised
It gave us permission
Think outside
Of
Any kind of
Donburi
If we can not work for a year
What can we really do
So that idea morphed into
Let's sell the house
Every single penny
Into
I dream job
That might fail but we don't care let's just try to
Build a life for yourself
That
Will feel like dropping out that will feel
Free
And
That was the spark to building
But we.
And so with the money you move to
Bend Oregon
Deciding on Portland
Because
I wasn't as excited about then you know I wanted to be in a more thriving
Urban Market
How much cash did you guys have to live on
I don't remember the exact number but I can tell you this we went down to one car we packed all of our belongings into
The car
I'm moving van we moved our two kids are cats Portland Oregon we rented a small little house
We just went down to the bare minimum
And how much did you have to
Put towards
This business
So our only investor
This day is marked
So he he said hey
All all work with
Yeah it so he gave us
Small investment
I want to say I like under 200000
And then our house
Which
So we probably had maybe
Three or four hundred thousand
And that was with a Christian Life
Poured much of that into this business idea
Yeah so what what was the
The concept that you guys started to work on when he got
Oregon
Well
I became enamored with
Studio
And
Going to yoga studios going to Barre studios in the late 90s early 2000
Barb
Reigniting and New York and in Sanford
It's just for people who have no idea what bar has
Can you explain it a little bit
Little bit more
Yeah
Well bar back then was
Based off of the Lodi brick method
Which she was a dancer who we happen
Kristoff basically at a ballet bar and
Her first instructors start at the first Bar Studios
Confusion
57 Bar Method there's a bunch of them out there
And they sort of had a Renaissance
In the early 2000
And I started to take those classes and I was as intrigued by them
How come
For one thing they reminded me of
Part of a contemporary
Jawzrsize
And then using the ballet barre
As a prop
Just has this
Instant Grace and art and Heritage
That was really attractive
Tumi
And when you got into when you decided to
Open a bar
There were
Competitors
So did you think
How are you able to say well we're going to be different
This way or track customers by doing this
Yeso
We moved to Portland
A conscious decision where there was no bar
Around us
And I love using the ballet barre I love the isometric work of Lotte Berk
And the small movements
Animusic
But I wanted to create a studio
That instead of
Being something didn't answer being a methodology I didn't want to be the Sadie Lincoln method or the barre3 method
I just wanted it to be an exercise
Experience
From the very beginning in R instructor manual
The very first sentence
The one thing that never changes at barre3
If we're always
At the very beginning of class
Commissary instructor will start by saying
Walking to barre3
I give you full permission to do something different than I say
Your only job
Adolescent
Not to me but yourself
I'm your guide
Turn the music on I'm going to show you how to line your body and then I want you to make it
Your own
The chest as an idea to introduce people I mean obviously
The people on the show up
Taking the classes right but
Like
When you passed by
The studio
You saw this
Barre3
Carrie
A lot of people may be sick from speeding
For men I guess I don't know
Probably betraying my
Stupidity
Would say what is Bareilles like what is this thing right and so I can't be the only person
Thought that when I first saw it
Nobody knew how to pronounce it nobody knew what it was I had a tagline at the beginning where ballet barre meets
Yoga and pilates
Wichita
Right to it too it was a descriptor to explain what it was
How did you come up with a routine did you spend like
Weeks in months kind of
Writing it down or
White hot for about 20 years all different concepts
And so I started a piece together
The
Concepts that balance the body so
I really focused on working opposing muscle groups in every x-ray
So if I work the bicep I was going to
Weekly work the triceps
So I had this host
When you open your doors and is August 2018
Was it right away was it like a hit two people over people like letting us come in Wizard of curiosity
Got before I even opened our studio I taught free classes
Upstairs
At what is now Whole Foods but at the time
Kind of Wild Oats
And
Never forget the day we finally got our
Permit to open the doors
I sent out an email to the community that was coming to my free classes
And I said hey I got my
Certificate of occupancy
I'm going to teach a class 2
And I thought maybe a couple people that show up you know my friends my good friends that I've made
On 12 people showed up
That night
And I sent out the email at 2 and I think I taught it 5:45
And I will never
Forgot that moment
The sun was coming in
I played my opening song with seal amazing
And
To this day when I hear that song it's such a visceral memory of
This is going to work
Sadie Lincoln in just a moment
How she took barre3 from a studio above Wild Oats
Two locations across the country
And in the process
Almost became someone she didn't want to be
I'm guy Raz stay with us you're listening to how I built this from NPR
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow amp
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of taxes
And make clear recommendations for your
Full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own webs
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
It's 2008 and at this point
Saadia krisar
Pretty busy running their studio in Portland
Let me spend so much time there that they actually have to hire a babysitter to be at the studio
So that their kids and their clients kids
Can also come to the studio
I was a busy mom with two kids and I think the most important thing to both Chris and I as we wanted to have it come
We wanted a place where we could attract people that were inspirational
Thoughtful
Connected
Exciting to be around it was just the two of us at the beginning and then one of my girls
Friends who would move from the Bay Area
And she taught one or two classes
But I checked everybody in
Open the door as checked everybody and clean the bathroom let me know how things hot all 19
Teen classes 6 a.m.
Time to 8 p.m.
I was there
I knew every single client Maryellen I remember she was the first person to sign a membership she's still one of my clan
And if you were a drop in at that time how much do you have to
Cepeda
$20 to wasn't it wasn't it was probably as around $5 more than yoga
How much runway did you
You have
Before this had to actually start make
I think
Our return was maybe in
16 months or so
Is that pretty quick return
You know starting with 19 classes a week and having those classes have at least 10 to 12
People was our goal and that's exactly what we did
I mean you must have been stressed out
Even though you were doing 19 classes a week and you probably got a lot of your
Stressed out that way you still must have been stressed out 19 classes a week is not healthy
And if not
Yeah right
It is not
The chart of the story of my body
Literally my back went out
And I remember my mom saying to me
Honey you're embodying
Because I was like walking around like a nine-year-old woman you know with my back slumped over like whining
Hurting and it was like
Yeah
Shoot
You know this
Isn't good
So that was
A moment I was training instructors at the times I did have some relief
But I learned that
To be healthy
It really is okay to pause to not move cannot achieve and do not have an outward expression
I've what exercise means
You must have like
You know
Pull out of this because you
You still managed to open up a second location pretty fast right
Pretty much right away I mean the first
Year
We are open we put up a tab on our website
But that grow with us
And we got
Instant
Interest
Me and you liked by start your own barre3
An industry where we knew how to run multi-unit operation so going into barre3 we thought unilift open Maybe
20 of these
And that pacific northwest from the get-go you thought
Armada should be franchise
We have this unique knowledge and wisdom in the industry's so
Instead of raising money
To open our own
Let's look into this franchise model which is really ultimately about empowering someone else
Turn back
In this idea that we have in our wisdom and open up their own business pension to instead of going to
Venture capitalist
Thanks or whatever
Yeah you didn't have to
At 1:10 we don't want to be beholden
To institutional money
Instead I was really excited about still am excited about the idea of being the Holden and two other people just like me
Who had a dream and wanted to open their own business and have their own skin in the game
And
Be able to make it their own
So where was it the second location
Our first
Two partners design
Wer
The Philippines
In Manila
And Bend Oregon
Wow should you franchise immediately to
Manila
Yeah
This woman came in her name's Tanya town and she was in the states
And discovered ice and her family is very entrepreneurial
Are they have a family business and then their children each have different business models and she's the youngest of all the children and she
And because you and Chris had this
Experience at 24 Hour Fitness
Franchising you understood how to structure
Idet
I was weird we are bullish that way and
I mean it was exciting it was an adventure but we knew we could do it we knew we could do it internationally
With the right
And then Darcy and bend was close enough and she was coming to class and really a part of our tribe
Shortly after that was Carrie who opened in Vancouver Washington which is
220 minutes away
So most of our franchise Partners were
Or our clan
So they
Came to barre3
Loved by three
New barre3 where owner Opera
So
Unlike some franchises are franchises owner-operated so if you're going to franchise I thought you're really going to live and breathe the product are going to teach
Action management
And I'll be the face of it
It's interesting cuz we had Jerry Murrell on the show the founder of Five Guys
And which is like
The fastest growing
Very different business from yours Burgers and Fries
But you never
And
He was supposed to it like all of his sons part of the you know of the Five Guys
They like to do this
And he really didn't want to do it because
To him
It's a burger that they were serving in the fries at they were serving was
It was great to keep control the quality
You just completely opposed the idea obviously
Slickdeals differently today
Two weren't you nervous about handing over
Your concept is somebody who could
Like
Screwed up
No I I think that's one thing about I have unbridled optimism in people
Sometimes to a fault to be honest but I really do believe in people
And here's the thing we don't
Our product isn't a burger
It's a person
It's someone
Teaching
A class
And
I cannot pretend to be able to control that
Because I can't control other people nor do I want to
But how did you
I mean there's no way
Is a creative person in this concept that you spent
Gill years on
Honing
There's no way
That you just hand it over and said go run with it like
You have to get there mentally I have to assume
Well it's person by person
You know we would meet with these people
And see if there was a deep connection
I believed in our training program
I believe in my ability my Master's is in education
I love training and develop
And that's what I wanted to bring to Fitness is this idea
Teaching and a true teacher at the teachers that I left the most going back to
Santa Monica City College
And the teachers who really
Brighten Academy
It wasn't that they were all knowing
And that they had the answers
They spark something inside of me
That made me realize I have the answer
And
I love doing that with body
I love doing that
I like showing people that
You can
First of all run your own Studio
And you can do it your own way here is our blueprint
But you
Now get to go
But your own fingerprint on it
Because I do not want you to copy this is not the Sadie Lincoln
I am not a guru where the anti Guru
And
Your true power
All of my owners is is in Collective with them just like I was raised
We didn't even use
The word chain
We still down for a family of owner
Are all of the partners just like everything was with just about perfect fit it all
It all worked out great cuz that's what it sounds like you didn't really run into any problems
We did I mean I think the biggest problem with this emoji
It's scary and it's
And
Does first Partners take a big wreck
Can I send me check a bag
Uno jump in leap of faith trust all of them
Every owner to this day of
And when you franchise
The Campfire Song
Can you franchise
Right there your you're
In a park
And it's for the long-term
And
Me and Chris are job is it always keep that value up so they see that Importance of Being connected to something bigger
And you know that's really what drives me I'm beholding
To all of these
Partners
You're the CEO of the company
How many
Locations
Do you guys own
We own
Stix locations
And then we have a hundred 24 franchise
As you guys or just
Expanding
Exploding in growth
I mean
At what point
Did you just
Did you impress you say
This is crazy I mean it must have been like a hamster wheel that just never stopped
Going
Yeah I mean right in the middle there I kind of lost my
We are booming we're being acknowledged as like
We're getting great press
You know we really
Hit means
Stream
It went from this really insular like
Word of Mouth
Table
Kind of secret
Stage
And
Worldstage really
And I was at the center of that so that was
Kind of crazy I got lost
A little bit just being a public figure
In a way yeah
And I started to fall in
Marketing machine
Which I had
Laughed when we moved to Portland weed
Excitedly shut out all traditional marketing
And a weighted like a
Express ourselves we don't even like
Tetanus
I'm in an office and I kind of got back into that machine
Shein
And I was in Publications
Was working with
The producer in LA and everybody was telling me that
This way
Talking about Fitness this is the way you
Speak about what you're doing come to you sing Sadie we can turn you on
Jane Fonda
UNF you go to the website and you still are the face of it and then videos of you and
But you don't Embrace that
Well I did want it because the idea of growing and serving the company that way was really it's
Exciting to me and to be able to get that kind of attention and
Interpol our business was super exciting
I meant really helps
Soulfully though it went against
My
Intuition about not being a guru
And I don't want to see the messages that are already
So loud we've got the message is loud and clear everywhere yes
If you work out
Can you do these things are going to look like that
And
I was getting trained by
Produces and stuff
To say thanks
While you're working out your always have
How to say you're working out this muscle so you can have a thinner waist for bikini season
You're doing this so that you can have this
You know it sells like hotcakes
This is the way you're supposed to do it
I tried it on
Precise they also said
Get hair and makeup
You don't get a stylus
So I did all that so we have online workout
And I just little era of online workouts
Were you can see where I did this to us we've pulled some of them but
I hired a makeup person
I started to be more
About what I wore on camera and then I started
Speak in a different language that was more like quote-unquote results-oriented
And under the videos the people who are commenting
They were checked
My clan
People who are part of my movement
We're checking me out the door
They were saying
Honey you don't need to wear all that bronzer your beautiful as you are
And you know what you don't need to tell me to get teeny tiny arms
Like I'm doing this cuz I want to be
I'm sure there are people who are Saints
Do you want to be a
Next million-dollar company xxxx
And then you can do that and you can become like Jillian Michaels are like another
You know
Jane Fonda
10% by the way I respect all this
For all these Incredibles
People in my space
Who are booming right now
Incredible women
And I think
We all
Want the same thing
In terms of
Growing bigger
I'm actually not focus on growing bigger any
We pause
Franchising
For now
We're just holding
Being still and we're being uncomfortable and still
Being still is uncomfortable to bury a neurologist
10 class and we're still
In closet when you try to meditate I don't know
If you ever have
Yes I'm comfortable if I do everyday and
It's hard it's hard to be still because it's a real like intermere thing
You have to check in and see things
So if you look at a company as a person
We've decided Lee
Decided to meditate
Easter
What was the reasoning to do something
What happened or did you impressive
Just put some pod
Why I mean in any
Other business people would say we're growing withdrawal it's growing program
Which is exciting
What we was trying to be courted by a lot of inside
Anchors
Pure Barre was sold for 100
21 million dollars
A bar
Champion Powerhouse
Right and like the story we kept hearing this who's going to be number two who can be number two and you could be valued at gazillion dollar
Where is and
So we started entertain a bunch of
Conversation
You could have just cashed out
Like majorly
Yeah
There's lots of choice out there right and
Kind of feel like
I want to be a bit of a rebel
So I am
Right now others
CEOs other Founders other people in this world who are going at it alone
So I just want to protect
But I had
Versus
Make it Giant
And I want to show
Business community
Do it that way
There's not that many
People saying that in the business community
You know the value of not
Growing
The value of not
Sign
You know it's interesting because there's is kind of Drive
An intern segments of the business world to do that
What are plenty of companies including
Episodes in the show with you with with with Angie's List
Companies that are not
Profitable but they're sustainable
They are
More like breaking even if every year
That has enabled them to hire
You're more than a thousand people and in their lots of companies at
Aren't as focused on profit but our focus on sustainability and just
Creating jobs
Syncreon careers for
4 people
So it doesn't
Have to be about growth and expansion and growth and expansion
That's right
That's really what I love about my product is that
We literally embody ideas and barre3
So we're teaching exercise but wearing body and
Stay with me for a second I know this is strange.
But I think what you just said is so analogous
Chuze Fitness
You can do a 30-day
Extreme programming
With your body
You know
Exercise
Every single day
Eat nothing White
You know drink tons of water
Get 10 hours of sleep every single day
You know lift lots of weight
And get tremendous results
Dislike
Exciting
Write a tremendous like change in your body
Is that sustainable
To exercise every single day until to be. Regimented and disciplined
Not from us
It's a short-term
And that is the story were sold over and over again
The story which is listen tok
Cicada know a lot of people but over time I think they really get it is this
Sustainability model
Exercising
10 minutes a day
Being in touch with the food you're eating
You know that it's okay to drink a glass
Relationships are just as healthy as X
And that developing a long-term relationship with exercise that's
Sustainable is actually
Going to benefit your posture you'll live longer
I'm feel better in your skin
Yeah you won't shed weight in 30 days Nessa
The Sara Lee but in the long-term you will
Listening
I've been meaning to ask you about which is
We had like Melissa & Doug on the show who came up with Melissa & Doug toys for kids and
Incredible Partnerships the married and they are they built these incredible businesses
Together
But then you know I've talked to other entrepreneurs to say there's no way I could work with my partner there's just no way I mean might might might
The person who I have a family with like that we would just
Kill each other
You and Chris have built
A business together
Is it just
Your personalities mesh and you
Naturally find your way or is there ever any tension or
Yeah I mean
There's no way
I'm sure there's a way by can't imagine a way of not working
Yesterday
Saul start
We're different and that he's really analytical and his
Those are different
A very thoughtful he doesn't talk very much he thinks about things for a long long long time
Whereas I just got in the sting
Yeah we're both starters
We're both entrepreneur all we both are
Really into our children
And our dogs
I have my best
Friend
By my side my rock
He's the one that gives me courage
To be
And to make crazy decisions
And so it just works for us
Are you always talking about the bass
We talked about it a lot
Like we talked about the business more than we do our kids
We are joking we're talking about how
How many businesses
Decisions have been made in bed
But then we are laughing about how funny that sounds
Because it was nothing about that sexy it's like Carol and Mike Brady
Like
That's why we are in bed
We are laptops
What color should it be orange okay
What's your name be part 3 sounds great
But it's kind of beautiful to
How much of
I asked
Too much everybody's feeling show about
This question was just how much of what happened
To you guys
Acid with locking how much
Evan has to do with your skill
An inability
Oh God
I think
Timing was great for us
This Boutique movement started and
People wanting connection and community
I was I'm a teacher and group exercise became hot again
I'm moving to Portland and just the right moment
Being shut out from all the noise so we weren't
Competing with anyone we can just do it exactly what we need
Scratch around Edge
So that's like anyway but the movement you know
At the right time
But a lot of hard work and enter work and
Paying our dues out there in the business world
Certainly was a part of
I think probably like most business is a combination of all the factors
Sadie Lincoln
Founder of barre3
By the way if her childhood story sounded somewhat familiar
It's probably because you heard her brother Miguel's version
Previous episode of the show he's Miguel McKelvey
Founder of the multi-billion-dollar company we work
Miguel also grew up in that all women's Collective
And like his sister Sadie
He also rebelled against it by going into business
Was it better than Miguel
Hahaha
So much better
But I will say I was really excited because my high school
Took me over him for the holiday
Oh that's good
San Miguel
That's Heavy kids you know
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsors Microsoft
Do want you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family
The Surface Pro 6
As of just 13 and a half hours of battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Wherever work takes
Hey thanks for sticking around because
It's time now for how you built that
And today we're going to the story about Alexander
That we first ran last year Alexander grew up in New York City and what Anna sisters would sit down for me
It was always one thing one condiment that they
Watch slathered on everything put it on baked potatoes all the time we would have it in you
Yogurts we have it on chicken
I'm bagels and cream cheese on eggs on Burgers sandwich
Actually tastes good on all of these different things gathers their Sriracha but besides sriracha
Za'atar
Is that tire is this
Tangy earthy Middle Eastern Spice made with different types of time maybe some oregano
Other spices like Acumen Sage some sesame seeds even chickpeas
I mean it is a cultural food stable and you're asking Middle Eastern person do you know exact are is it's like a
Askanamerican do you know what apple pie is
Anyway a few years ago Alexander who happens to be of Lebanese descent started to notice is that Harwood show
Going up in all of these unexpected places like
Is Corner hipster restaurants on Instagram on social media as I can
No way is that are becoming a thing yes in some parts of the country is itar was becoming
Nothing but Alexander wondered why nobody made it the way his mom did mixing the spices with all
Olive oil into a spread it brings out the flavor
Of the herbs you know the essence of the herbs out more
And you know the condiments are cool everybody loves condiments right so I was thinking about all of this last year
And at the same time he was working at a research firm on Wall Street the job he wasn't really crazy about
Until one night he was having dinner at his parents place. Car was of course on the table and
Looking down my head between my arms telling them what's going on
And boom it just hit me I'm staring at
And I said I got it it's his a lightbulb moment Alexander says we have got to
To make za'atar the way you making mom and we should sell it like as a spread eating these foods are whole life
A joke about it we should have started hummus or we should have started the Greek yogurt so let's do it
Pokemon Slater Alexander walked away from his job
He moved back in with his parents he found an industrial kitchen Googled where to find the spices the
Olive oil is a little glass jars he made his first batch of spreadable za'atar and he started going
Door-to-door to sell it to specialty stores in New York I have these little gift bags at a jar zesty Z cheated
Chips recipe cards in our sales sheet can I walk in and I'd say hey I think I've got a great product to customers would like
And I'll follow up with you and when he did follow up in a week
A lot of people said no no we don't like this we don't think this will sell we don't like the taste setter
Cetera dealing with that you know people who say that it's business not personal
Whoever came up with that quote or says that you never started a business because I would disagree with that for sure
But a few months after he got all those knows I got an email saying thank you so much for the thoughtful pack
We absolutely love this will take two cases
And when I got that email starts crying that email was from one specialty store in Brooklyn
And from there Alexander started to get a bit more traction
Even got a sucker spread into a few Whole Foods in New York City
And now a year after we first ran the story does that tire spread is in 450
50 Whole Foods Markets across the country and Alex is planning to roll out for new products next year
Is Mom well she's still at the center of things she's the head of research and development I want to share
What I ate growing up with everybody else
And that's what I want to do with my life
Alex's company is called zest
Easy to learn more about it or here
Previous episodes of a show
Podcast page how I built this.
Npr.org and of course
If you want to tell us your story go to build
Got npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts you can also write to us at HIV Tia NPR
. org
It's at
How I built this
I sure was produced this week by run. Dill feta
Music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to JC Howard nor could see the Immigrant status Michigan Port Jeff Rogers
Internet
Mia venkat
I'm guy Raz
You been listening to
How I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week