Support for how I built
And the following abbr
Should come from Michigan economic developer
Seewhy michigan
Attracting top talent and top businesses
By searching Michigan pure oportun
It's got here and I just wanna let you know that we
First Friends episode
Last May and
We're bringing it back.
Totally put you in the mood
For the summer travel season
Especially
Did you happen to be going someplace
Very far away in a
Cheap car and with a knot
A lot of money
Enjoy
It grown so fast
We had television going we had started investing heavily into the digital side of things a lot of stuff
And in the middle of that
When 9/11 happened of course
People stop traveling on travel guides then just stopped
Did you think that there was a
Possibility that
Yeah we just have to let people go we just have to cut back the number books we did
Ramen PR
How I built this
Show
Innovators
Anniversary ideas
Stories
And the movements
Backpack
Betrayal at the 70s
Jot down some notes
And turn them into the biggest travel guide company
In the world
So much of how a company comes together
By chance
Sergey Brin and Larry Page never met
Would there be Google
Same thing for Airbnb your Instagram
Warby Parker
They all happened
Because of a chance meeting just to
A moment in time that
Could have passed
Witches
Story of Lonely Planet guide book
Because it all started on a bench in Regent's Park in London on an October afternoon in 1970
Marie wheeler was
Just looking for a
Quiet place to sit and read
And as I was walking around the park there was only one bench that had son on it and I
What can I several times because on the bench was also a young man I thought if I sit in that then she's
Neutron pick me up and I really don't feel like that
This is 1970 I can sit wherever I want
So I sat in the sunny bench
I'm turned my back to the young man and started reading my book
What were you doing today
It support
Atacama gisin
New edition of it and I was just reading that
When this heat young woman came along
What are you doing I said place to read on a Thursday afternoon
Hand
Reply positively
How to say get lost and then
He's got my thoughts and I like them so I said
I don't know I haven't been here that long
We started chatting and
After a while Tony ask Maureen if
She want to go see a movie
They went
And I'm on the way home and got lost
We wandered around for quite a while before I realized you
Cos 20
Just sits over the confidently and keeps going thinking he's going and not be the right
And the thing is that's being our entire lives.
Anyway that first date
Blade 2
Play second and then
3rd and then
12 months to the day later we got married
And when his proposal was very precise
If we was at was May
Iran in May
And he said I would have known you a year on October 7th
Get married and I said
You don't get married because you've known each other for a year
She said no
But we would save tax
But I think I know I wasn't a business schools
Excuse for that I'm afraid it wasn't the most romantic
So when she got married did what did you think you would just have to get jobs in London and start your life
That was pretty much the plan that died
We met just at the start of my 2-year
Course in London and
We got married halfway through that 2 years
But time sometime in that second year together we decided we were going to take a year off and go traveling
That's certainly
Change things
How did you guys
Smack That
Decision what was the
Don't know it was very much a thing to do with a deer at a later on they started calling it
Happy trail
And we we just coated the Asia Overland trip that you
You left London and you headed east
But this was the air right now the music of the times
Riding the Marrakesh Express Wilma
The Beatles were off in India so that was a lot of sort of cultural significance to it
But we join what
Became known as the hippie trial and we
Headed east
So this is I guess around 90
Shoe issue
In what was the plan
The plan was to drive from London
There was this car and it was so cheap that breaks down will
Get out of it and leave it by the
We were going to go as far east as we could go have to dispose
Hollywood breakdown would sell it one of the other
You just start driving through
You're up and then
And then what just keep driving
The check in around and you go right across the room and you can ride
Afghanistan
You just keep going for Pakistan and then you go through India and then you
Couldn't get across yet
And then we just carry on the plan was
We get to Australia
And then we would stay in Australia and work for a while
I would save up enough money and would fly back to London and that was
That was the plan
We had so little money we left London with
400lb
So that was our money
And you just stayed
You slept in the van
We could have X but generally we camped
Most of the time across Asia until we really understand
In Afghanistan you know a lot of the hotels in those days
Debian Gardens and you could camp in the garden
At that time
How did you even know
Where to go in and
What to do in
Get the ride bus I mean how did
Figure all that stuff
Hart bus station in Afghanistan and you're kind of pointing towards the board
Somebody will put you on the right bus
Mature wondering Dyna straight with a bag and you're looking at you now look at you look like you look like you're lost someone will punch your Twitter
I'll tell her you'll see something that looks like a hotel
Haven Restaurant
You just pull out your Lonely Planet
Really immature you know you manage and actually you know
What book was great is that you can travel for weeks without
Sing another Western
But then suddenly it pollen summer like Kabul or somewhere you know
Are hair up and did the others and you just spent maybe an afternoon just trading information
You know
When you get here this place is good
This place is a need swap information that way
Pacific old fashioned communication
All all along you are keeping a journal
Tony about you guys
I did keep a diary I've always been
Reasonably assiduous about documenting things and
Keeping records of things
Where we stayed and what it cost and
How many miles to Carthage
And they did I know I think about the Palaces in the walls in the Fortress
Just as important but those days it was very much
The information which
Later on selling
Nmd
All this would like next to no money right
Yes
We had to do everything is cheapest
Como solicitar cast real and it was hitchhiking we hitchhike from
Bangkok all the way to Singapore
To get down there and then we went across
Boat to Jakarta and then we went by bus
Diwali and then
In Vale we were really run out of lock the airline that was
Supposed to that we're supposed to have
Tickets on to take a
It's just Riley
Broke down and didn't have any more
Planes
We met this New Zealander had little Yalta he was looking for crew
To get down to
Australia so we got on his yacht
Ocregister
Was that
Like a scary at all
Anytime I think I
Got really weird
Storm in the boat
And if I had to have more sensitive being terrified.
But you're so busy hang onto the boat
And then the thing thing
Australia and I remember
Standing on the out looking at this
Coastline that has nothing on it
Nothing at all with coming out of place
Miles from anywhere on there was nothing
Spiders I don't even know
I've no idea
You know what are we doing here
What did you think you would do that did you think you would hang out there for a while because neither
Connections
Australia
No
We went to Sydney Festival in Australia
Sydney's the Golden City that you you will head towards sleep
The yellow brick road leads to
How's your crossing the Sydney bridge on our last ride and I said and done it was not long after
Christmas song
Quite close
Holidays
How much money have we got left
27 Cent
How much is an English money
So what did you
Even though I had a camera so we we went to the area
I'm just supposed I saw two things at 11 Shopkins
We got $25 for my camera
If I pull back a week later
$25
In those days you can get a room for a week for $15 a week
Single beds
Who's romantic
2 years
And I go to jail
Stop that afternoon instantly and and a little kind of
Corner Shop but they did sandwiches and things at the end of the day they let me take the sandwiches home that were left
So we ate
And I work there for a little while until we and then we both you know.
Spa one year trip become a 3-year
So what did you want what kind of job
I got a marketing job for a thumb citico company
Maureen you're working a job another
What was job you're doing today
EPA in a wine company working for a wine cup
How do you get to app
You
Start selling a travel
Will a tiny tiny house
Looks like it's from around the world let's go guide
Books I mean
Texting on the carpenter
She said look
We should do a book
This was off to read we met so many people every time we went to some sort of
Party on
Met friends restaurants in Sun always someone would ask us where did you go how did you do this
Minnesota trip we did
After while we saw pain
We could just telling them and writing things down and
Will actually be information.
Able to get my typewriter
And bring it home at night and
I've already Guillotine when we were trimming all the books and I'm on one of those massive stay ProSobee stapled a book together
So in the way are we kind of the
We're able to get enough equipment to do this
Printed but it was it was a very base
Kitchen kitchen in a bedroom
We found a little bit commercial printer
Prince singing in the basement under his apartment
And he printed them for us
Folded Dunham
Put them together when is Morningside stapled
When did they were finished and done we had them in boxes at our apartment
I took a day off where can I buy went straight to the Bookshop
By 50 copies of it and said okay here I am
Bright meteor
Phantom the end of the day I sold a surprising number
What was the price
Door $80 1896 page is it sold for $1 AT&T covered all the
Tracy went through 96 pages
Suppose I went into one book shop and she's
Buy this book and she said
What company are you with
Is it Lonely Planet
Never heard of them and I said no you wouldn't
Show to the book until she's at all
What's your telephone number and case
I want to
Get my books that we didn't have a telephone
So I had to give her my work number
She called me and she said
My flatmate
Is a journalist
And she wants to interview you and your husband on television
So we went on television to talk about our
Tripping doing this book
That was our first big
Yeah I was I was reading for your first guide books
Pamphlet
Anime
I'm pretty different things in there right like I mean like it tells you where you can find marijuana
Oh yeah
Where to get a fake ID in
I have to assume that you
You know you guys could not have been
Stone hippie
Motivated to write
Everyday and to go places
The catalog we were actually really boring we didn't do a lot of that
Stuff at all occasionally
Very rarely
Years later Lino's Lonely Planet became
Better known
All these people
Who wrote using any kind of Uno and what they were really cool
Old people use.
Antonio and I would be
At the cafe in old coop
People but we just didn't look
Cool and yet we were the ones who
Sit there quietly
Interesting
How did you come up with
With with the name
Lonely Planet
There's a story behind that we got the book done you never had we had everything that a title for is there was a cross
On the cheat for the Publishing House
I'm weeping out to the restaurant and drinking too much red wine
How many just been to see the rock and roll band on the
Roadkill Mad Dogs and Englishmen
Joe Cocker and Leon Russell
Traveling around the US in the late 60s film
I'm one of the songs in that that that movie and that that help MS
Joe Cocker singing a song called space captain
On the first line of the song goes
Once while traveling across the sky
This Lonely Planet caught my eye
Peanut Sunrise what do we call the company Lonely Planet
Which moron said
Actually the first line is lovely planet
And I wish you would stop singing
And he said bologna plants even better and I said how he said what Just Dance
The Great Dane
You know we're learning to live
Together on this planet
Soap to the first book
Like make any money
Not much
Didn't lose money on it but it wasn't.
A real money making proposition
But around that time when we were thinking of me okay
This is when we quit and head back to Europe
I'm done with began to figure that has sold surprisingly well
Maybe we should do another book
And what we thought was
Towards the end of the trip from London
With come down through Southeast Asia
The Vietnam War was still winding down so
Southeast Asia wasn't seen as a
No hotspot for a
Holiday
It was able to place next to a war zone
But we could see that was about to change and we thought okay
Bubble Jose will travel around
Southeast Asia
I will write
The best book anybody has ever seen on Southeast Asia
Yamaha trail bike
That was our transport
And at this point Tony did you think this is
I think this is
Where can I do
No I still think you know we would we realize we took if we try The Sweet Spot we found we were doing something that
People really like
Pregnant
One of the things I've said a lot over the years is it it wasn't like you
.com
You know social media set up these days they start them one day and
A week later they worth a billion dollars
That was industrial weed business group very slowly and I think it was
It was more like a snowball rolling downhill
You got to keep pushing it at first and then it starts develop momentum and starts foot
Get larger as it rolls down the hill
When we come back at Tony and Maureen grew Lonely Planet
And then
Trinket
Banana
Lost it
I'm garage near listening to how I built this
NPR
Sportframe
NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting dismay
Gemini is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy
Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
These to your long-term
Investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely answer
Early on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art Cyber City
Launch your crypto portfolio to
And open app free
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from servicenow
Making the world of war
Work work better
They're cloud-based
4 man salute
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole come
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the
They wanted
Using technology
To make people more
Productive and enjoy
Moret servicenow.
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with
With no fees or minimum
Apps that can be open from anywhere
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in Uruguay
Na
How I built this
From NPR
Gyros
Tony and Maureen
We were traveling around Southeast Asia
Once again
And they're doing research for their
Second Lonely Planet
Honey was just about finished I had a dummy of the book
That was one big book shop in Singapore
Geico
Appointment at Bookshop
I talk to myself you know he'll definitely
70 by 10 copies
If I'm lucky you by 20 or 50
You listen to my Spiel and then I looked at my tummy of the book
I saw him riding southeast Asia on a shoestring in the
On the order form and then write some number then
How many Stanley order ride a push it across the desk to me
1000 copies
DIY walked out of that Sam that office in
Yes what about the Grand Hotel
Fantastic
Traffic saw the success of that book
What I mean
What was your next
And we did another one
Another one another one for the books
Good morning did you
You think I mean suits
Baidu
Or late 7
DC band
Did you still did you think that this was going to be your work I mean did you
You both could have
Focus full time on this thing now
Pretty much although I was at University
I have plenty of time left to work
You have a full-time job and mean are you even living on you
Marine salary while I worked on the books
I didn't think it was going to
They are life
I couldn't say it was still Tony and I
Living in a little rented house
With a pile of boxes boxes everywhere full of books
Island swimwear
Address them and put them in the back
The car and take him to the
I mean you don't really see
Multinational conglomerate
To pick the books up when they came in from the printer and then sending them out again you know
It still felt very much
Like a cottage industry
Yeah basically know if you told a bank and what we're doing books on that say get a life
We didn't have any money and we weren't making a lot of money but we were
To keep on doing book
But we did find other paperwork coming to us now that used up book and that's a
You know I really liked your book traveling around Southeast Asia
I'd be living in South America you know I could
Write a book about this place or that place so we
We started getting other people coming to us with similar ideas
I'm ready by the end of the 70s
What was the Turning Point what was the book that
Like
All of a sudden where you thought okay
Plot of the Dead
Was very easy to that one of the
And we respect that in 1980
This was the first time we that we've been able to
Mauryan either one team we had two other writers and weight
So divided the country at the middle
And I found out I was
Is pregnant
Before I flew to India for this month
Pregnant
Traveling Man India in
Pamphlets and brochures and endnotes
Yeah very much so you know
Guido's of collect
Every brochure ever
Timetable every map
Time in Waco
Hardly anything in Iraq.
And come back with his massive
I love
Information
Stop
Yeah much easier these days when you put on a memory stick
And suddenly we had this book that was over 700 pages and
It's sold for
Yeah double-figures it was $12 or $14 or something instead of
How did your soul it's always a hundred thousand copies
Wow it was the first
All India
Book of that kind of guy.
Told you everything
Huge interest in India
What time Minnesota
It just took right off
The company
Double the size of an item week
Suddenly started taking on more ride tourism
Looking at all the big project
And and you had a baby
So what did you
You do I mean
Eight month old daughter
And every
School holiday
Would would just go laugh
Forgot
Asia or whatever and then travel with us for that.
The time
So every time we go to
A chance we could go and travel as a family but mainly
20 was doing the right thing and then it says
Planning and all that and I was doing the
Carpentry
Keeping it together
Yeah I'm actually moved out of the house
A lot of kind of
Loose
Comfort
In and out do a bit and flowed out again and we paid them
By the hour
As a real business
When and what point did you
She stopped having
Sleepless nights about whether you were going to
It's nice
Every year
How to say actuator
Late 80s
I think was more when we
Became
Obviously
Sting
Momentum and it was carrying us as much as we were
Pushing it
Can I talk to people who are doing that and handing the publishing it out at that time
And they said it just seems like
We couldn't do anything wrong
Did every book we did Zeno sold and
I think when we started doing Europe guys because we
We were just little publisher at the other end of the world
Who started off doing Asia
How many finally did get around to doing Europe
We would think enough by that point we could really do it well
I think people in the office really got a kick out of that but it was such a thrill
Doing that
Taking out anybody in the world who wanted to try and compete with us
I mean people everywhere you went
When using any kind of
I mean I used to give me a thrill you know you going to New York sing someone coming with a German copy of
Chinese cup
You know whatever I just I still love that
But anyway
Were there ever any moments where
It wasn't going well
Not looking very good
1000 and grown so fast
We had television going
We had started investing heavily into the digital side of things a lot of stuff a lot of
You know we created a whole lot of desktop
Publishing before receiving the term
The money the books were still selling like crazy but we were just doing
So
And in the middle of that
When 9/11 happened of course
PPL stock
Traveling on travel guides then just
Stopped
Did you think that there was a possibility that
Stunning
His
Charms but it's also on his list infuriating things because we were definitely looking
At a really bad time we were looking at
We just have to let
Go
Back on our offices
Embassy Suites
The number books we did
And it was looking I honestly didn't believe that
Possible housing pictures
In retrospect I think it was much more accurate the month
Deadpool start pulling everything
I guess it was a wrap around that time I guess it's the mid-2000s where you
You wound up
Selling the company right now
I think we both felt that it wasn't the same company anymore it was
It was turning into much more of a digital company in that has a way of
Taking over everything it's not something I'm excited about
It wasn't going to be a dentist going to hand it on to our kids
Arcades in the company of one stage but
Not going to take it over from us
Panda
Now move on to something else
And I mean that you
Fuel
Great to sell it
Still sad
One of the saddest days
I remember walking to the BBC with Tony to sign the
Define
CBC ubota
And I said 222
Your password
And he said no I said no
Signal github password
Cuz I just gold
Straight up the hill
Get out of here
We could still Escape
Yeah I think I drove the Salem
More than Tony did
And I always wondered you know if afterwards
He would really regret
I haven't
I know his son
Add Worcestershire to my
Grief about it
It took
Months
For me to
Like I still find a very high
Hard to go back
To the office and you know I just
It's just hard
I mean from from somebody listen to this like
An outsider's perspective
People who said
You just let the
The dream I mean you got
I can travel around the world in
Company
And yeah you sold it and it's not yours anymore but it made
Rich and look at your life
Like that everyday
Every year we do trips together
Are there every year I go places
Rhino morning would not want to go to
Chernobyl
I wanted to check the radiation to hobos these days
My consumption of output
Serious because I I interviewed
John Mackey
The founder of Whole Food
The show and
He he was talking about in early relation
He had with with
The woman that
The help him start Whole Foods in and how it really
Destroyed their
If it broke down
He said you know business can really bring people together
As apart I can do both
I mean you you guys are approaching
50 years of marriage
Sounds like you would have credible
Partnership in
Border X
Weather times when you were building up his company where there was tension and there was
So we we've had our fights even our squabbles haven't always been playing silly
And you know you cannot
Couldn't run a business will you bring
Stuff into the office
You can't avoid it to some extent
And it was funny but Lonely Planet people always knew
First of all you come and talk to me about an idea
And I'll tell you whether it's with
Tony has what
What's called the 5c
Second
5 Second window to engage.
You know it's like the lifespan of a mosquito
So they would come to me and say why not
I think this is great what do you think
Goodness
You let me
Talk to him first
How much of your
And what happened with his company and everything
You think is due to luck and how much because you're just really smart and skilled
You definitely need person is that saying about you know whenever I'm working really hard I
I seem to be lucky
More interesting places near parents did
So is that element they were a big Market
I don't know that
Skill
Him and it was Tony and I there was
Judgement
I suppose and
And the fact that we were doing something that we knew everything about
But it's clear that the
This company could not have become what I became without
Without the both of you
Me and you both brought
Different skill sets
An amazing what you know this like
Chance meeting on a bench in Regent's Park resulted in this
Incredible
Company what is
What were the
Traits of both of you had like
That you brought to the company
The Mooring sends me nonsense
Tony
Let me find it would never be
He
Was a dreamer the vision but he also very
Kind of late
New hires going to place them
I'm very early on
And he never ran out of that
That kind of mad
Enthusiasm
Which parish you through so many things
However
He was not good
He never wanted to sit through meetings he never wanted
Bonkers
He liked all the stuff but you know he didn't want to hear what their problems
That wasn't terrible it was just really
He just wanted to know what we were going to do okay
You know how big was going to be in where the maps and pictures I mean with the book so we did
If you look at our covers and inside they just got better and better looking which was good
Animals
Tony you know 20
Snead's
You know this is what we need to do with
So I would say that
I guess I've always said that Lonely Planet
I could never existed but that Tony
But it probably wouldn't.
Held2gether long without me
Not agree with it
Tony and Maureen wheeler
Founders of Lonely Planet
By the way and its height the company was valued at 8
Quarter of a
Billion dollars
The wheelers are no longer formerly involved with the company that sold all their shares but Tony didn't recently
Score a gig writing a chapter for a new Lonely Planet book it's called epic drives of the world and as
Cuz I speak Tony is a size 3 and 1/2 month drive from Bangkok to London
In a classic
British mg sports car
And one last question for you
When you travel like what is the thing you have to have in your carry-on bag
My passport my credit card
Bruker customer support
Cozy and comfortable and when I get on a plane and I'll put them on the neck
Kind of Camelot
I never seen that
And please do stick around because
Just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
But the things your build
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Smart Water
Taking inspiration from the
Clouds themselves
SmartWater 1 Epsom
By adding electrolyte
Clean Chris
Taste
The water you deserve
Smart Water
Vapor distilled
Purity
Electrolytes for taste
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built
And today we're going to the story we ran last year
One that you can
Probably relate to If you happen to live in apartment building and share a wall
With your neighbor
Which is exactly what happened
To Melanie cologne sleeping
And all the sudden I heard this huge
On the other side of
The wall
And what was going on is my neighbor was watching some sort of Thriller movie the bases
Literally shaking my bed I have been there
First try to
To talk directly to them
One time I went to my neighbor's door
I knew they were in there I could hear them talking but they wouldn't answer their door Melanie and her husband Louis
Tried everything you know the creative note leaving or hitting the ceiling with a broom Earth
Stomping your foot on the ground and none of it
Woodworking for
So we looked around for a solution we asked her friends in the apartment industry is there anything that we can use
To help us with this and
There is absolutely nothing
And so we thought of being neighbor to neighbor notification tool where neighbors can notify each other
Completely anonymously and confidentially about a disturbance
From the neighbor until finally Melanie and Lewis hired a team to start developing a
An app which
They named
After
As an apartment app
Answer that works
The property management agrees to use the app
Send over the blueprint
Of the building
And then when neighbors have issues
They can log onto their app and anonymously contact
The actual unit they're having an issue with
So let's say Joe has a neighbor that is playing their music too loud
Chicken selects at Square
Choose a preset notification so this one would be bidding for a please turn down your music so he
Celexa and then send it to the neighbor upstairs
And then that neighbor is able to respond with
Resolved
Or sorry not me
Property manager can also see if the neighbor has
Responded or if an intervention is
Is required
Johnny Lewis beta-tested it in a big apartment complex in Missoula Montana with a hundred units
It really well everyone is really excited about all the tools that were available
And how easy it made communication with staff and residents
Since we last spoke with Melanie xi'an Lewis
Started working with apartment buildings in
The Denver area
Where they hope to sign up
About 75 of them by the
End of this year and they also want to Branch into a new market
University Housing
And by the way Melanie quit her job as a nurse around the end of
2016 and is not working
Full-time
On app
There's definitely been times where we thought how easy would it be
To go back to our day jobs
But at the same time we can't even stand the thought of it and we get right back to work
If you want to learn more about apptapp or here
Previous episodes head to our new podcast page how I built this
Npr.org
And of course
You want to tell us your story goat
How to build
Npr.org
We love hearing from you
So much for listening to the show this week
Subscribe Apple podcast or wherever you get your pocket
Please do give us a review
And if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Falkner with original music composed by Rammstein Aaron Lewis
Thanks also to Newark could see Santa's meshkinpour Neva Grant
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is JC Hower
I got Roz and even listening to how I built this
NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign mode
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
Seven days
Campaign mode
Weather.com