Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is
When is Good Day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim style
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here
Just a quick note before we start
The show we have
One week left in our annual public radio fundraiser
Shrek and you to show your support
For how I built this
And for your local public radio station
That you've heard me say it all month
Just take a moment
To give your gift
Before the end of the year
Just going to donate.
Npr.org
Built
To support your local
NPR station
Thanks
A little bit about
Today's episode
This time of year I can
Pretty much guarantee your
Can be out in the world
The restaurant
Mall wherever incessantly at a distance
Some of you might
Really love this song and others
Watch but either way it was the very first time that
The Chipmunks
Appeared on the scene
As a singing Trio this was sick
60 years ago
And now well we can't imagine our childhoods without them
In the massive brand they built
That's pretty much what this episode is about
The first ran
The fall of last
Messier and it's
Super fun episode
We are told by the record executive Ross Janice I want you guys to take take the Chipmunks
Down the road we want you to take them these are the 7 cities we want you to go to an
Make this album I hit in these 7 cities and if you do that we will give you a big Nash
Channel promotion we hit the road we in fact make the album a hit in each one of the
The Seven Cities we come back to the record executive the record Executives tells Janice and
Well
We're not actually going to do the national release in the Big Marketing
Is I said you told us that if we would be said if you don't have it in writing
You don't have
From NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Stories behind the movements they built
Billion dollar brand around three singing chipmunks
If you want to build say
Pantheon or Mount Rushmore of a Saturday morning cartoons of the 1980s
A statue to Alvin and the Chipmunks
I will be right there alongside
Smurfs the gummy bears
Inspector Gadget
It was one of envy
Biggest hits
3 singing rodents Alvin Simon Theodore
And they're exasperated
Kind manager / foster dad Dave Seville
Has anyone seen my Thai
All these voices Theodore Alvin Simon
Dave they were all boys fight
Two people
Ross bagdasarian Jr
And his wife Janice
I'm Theodore
And I'm Alvin and Simon and Dave
Do you want us to talk at house
The Voice
The characters
The pretty much ran and run the company that is Alvin and the Chipmunks
The movie is
Merch
TV syndication the live
Shows
All of that
Rotten
Billions
Billions of dollars
Studios and networks
Venison
Even quite a bit for rocks
And that's
Because
I'm like most other creative people in Hollywood
Ross and Janice and the Chipmunks they own the intellectual property
Enzo Chipmunks Inc
Is pretty much a family business
Run out of Ross in
Genesis House
Near Santa Barbara California
Actually invent the chip
Moxley actually
Mentor was Rodger dad
58 Reisinger was a struggling songwriter who was looking for a break
Figured out a way to change the pitch
Elvis singing voice
The result
The Witch Doctor song
The song became a hit and run
Soon came up with this concept that it was song by these
Anthropomorphic rodents
Call the Chipmunks
Seniors career took off
The Chipmunks
Became a radio show and then
Cartoon on television
In Frost Jr
He watched his dad
Become famous
100% it changed
Literally overnight first with which
Witch Doctor witch
It was like March 1958
And then of course
The Chipmunks were
That November December
So we got a swimming pool
Also I was I was much more impressed that we had a swimming pool than that my dad
Was on The Ed Sullivan
Show doing the witch doctor or Dick Clark's
American band
Standard what app
I remember he would always bring my brother and sister and I
Into his Dannon play
Weather was Witch Doctor the Chipmunks song or whatever and we loved
When Alvin started talking back
To our dad
We just
Fell in love
With nausea
The song but the audacity
Of that little character
Because we didn't really talk back
To my dad that much so we thought Alvin really
We had a lot of spunk
That we admire
What was your dad like was he
Elysium
Who sang What the witch doctor
We see this impresario was he charismatic was he silly or you know what he was all of them
That guy he was
Bigger than life he was served the Armenian version of
The Zorba the Greek
So are all 5-7 up him but you always thought and everyone a mess
Thought that he was 6-5
He just carried himself that way but he was
Funny
He was incredibly creative
He loved Muse
Music in really thought of himself as a musician
He loved songwriting
And started writing songs
When he was 16 years old
Driving a truck in The Vineyards of
Fresno
Dinosaur song was
Call nuts to you
So,
From nuts
Kim little
Yeah
So when you were a kid Ross
Did you think that
You would be involved in in the family business
100% no
You know
A growing up
I didn't even want to go to the recording session
My dad would say
Who do you want to come and let's see how we do this and what I go yeah no
Popeye I got a big little league game here so
I'm going to not make it to that
But growing up
As I started
To realize
What kind of a career was I heading for
Are the only thing I was certain of while my dad
Still alive was that
I wasn't going to
Be involved with the Chipmunks or what my dad had done not because I didn't love what he had created but because
They were such big shoes
To fill
That I didn't want to try and step into
I know process
Hero 2423
When your dad died
What would he want
Your life
After my dad passed away and before he had passed away he said
I really want to encourage you
Go to Los
When I
I just hated that idea but when he passed away
All of a sudden
You saw the kind of
Folks coming out of the woodwork that would try and take
Whether it was music
Publishing from the
The family or
Wineries and Vineyards that
He had built up over the years and I realized
Did my dad wanted me to go to law school and obviously not to become a lawyer but basically to have a
Kind of a
Mental martial arts
Protection
Because he always
It said look there's creating
What you do and then there's continuing to own
You doing and those are tough things
To do at both X and less you know
How to protect yourself
Open and contracts
Rocks and soil for sale
After he passed away I immediately enrolled Pascual
So I graduated
3 years later and 75 pass the bar wasn't going to
How to spell all but
Wanted to know that
With a music publishing and end the things that I was hoped
To create
Later on
I wanted to know how to
Hold on to them as my dad
Did you I mean at that point where you
Already thinking about
Going to waste it to revive
At the Chipmunks
Yes
After my dad passed away
I would go up into his office and just listen to
The song
City of duenweg water
The old TV shows
Sofia done at the Alvin show
And I just thought
I didn't want the Chipmunks
Pass away as suddenly is my dad
And I wanted to figure out
Someway.
Try and bring them back
So when I met Janice
And she had loved
The characters growing up
And I was
One of the shows
Folks letters
Mercy
So I now had
Another believer with me
And I said
I just want to see
If we can do this for you
Just a year or two
Bring in a kind of a trip
You to my dad and then
And imma go and do you know of course all the other things that we're interested
Cash go back for seconds I want to ask
Janice
About where you were
Because you were
You were like you are actor
Yeah
Yu Yuan Ross
Well we met at a Health Food Vegetarian restaurant
And I didn't inhale a
Saw
A friend of mine
Who is
Having dinner with raw so I didn't know
I went up to her to say hello and
Was introduced
Mr. Ross
And
The following day I got a
Bouquet of flowers
Where's where I was work
Working and
The next day I got another
Okay and they were all signed
By Ross
But I
I hadn't remembered his name so I didn't know who is sending me these flowers
I made quite the impression that you can tell.
Several weeks
And
Finally he called
He said hi
Agenesis
Thank you for those flowers there
Beautiful
Who are you and then he asked me on a date
And it it took about three years for me to come around 3 years
Right
Took me to his
Father's Office
At at night and it was
And I will going up the elevator and I'm thinking
Where we going
I didn't tell anybody I was going out with this guy and and what are we doing in this bill hang him
Put on the weak spark into an office and they put on the old Chipmunks
And I thought wow
Interesting and then he told me he was the son of prospect
Cesarean
And I said oh my God that was one of the
Douche few cartoon shows I watch them and love them
So then he said you think they would be viable today and I said
I would think so
And I had it listed her
On my impossible Quest
Stud My Little Don Quixote
Fighting fighting these little windmills
To get the Chipmunks exactly
You just like
Start trying to
Pitch people on this
Yep we'll first
We went to CVS because they had run the old shows the Alvin show so that seem like an act
To go in and
Listen we thought we loved what your dad did
We thought it was great but we
We think history is moved on and and it had its wonderful
Time in that
That's really over
So then we went to the music
The side of things and I don't know if they just spoken to the people at CVS
They said you know that was a wonderful wonderful characters and your dad had a great
Success but we think that's
Time has passed in and you guys should move on to something after young and capable and off
Shego
Continue to happen
Just go to
Studios and production companies in and they would
3 years
And Super Why did you stick with it I mean
You know that point your
I guess you're in your twenties now you've got a lot of possibilities are married at this point
How long should you
Yo keep going out and getting rejected me how long was a period of time
First of all all those
A nose
Fuel Dross
Find an Ashley fueled me as well
So
Write their name
When we make this big
We're going to
What we see them again oh now you want it but we're not going to give it to you and I like a fool to take out my little pony
You spell your last name for me
I mean really how did you keep going at it when when all these people are saying
No no no I mean work
Injected engine
Just feel like humiliated or did you know honestly I didn't
I just felt
Hopewell
I am going to show them they're wrong I know this
This is going to work
Janice believes in it there's two of us for goodness sakes
So no I was just more and more
Asset on what however long this took
Yeah but I mean look
The Beatles Advocate you can understand from moment you can understand what why are television
Executive at
Time somebody who's trying
The next big thing
Would certainly look at your proposal say all that the throwback to the 50s were doing like
Roomba crazy things now
Nina Ross taught me the power of tenacity
Guy he pursued me for
For three years
Every single day
Because because because I knew we were right I knew what this was.
Perfect person for me
And not to equate Janis with the Chipmunks but
But I honestly believe when you really believe in something so clearly
Say it's so
Clear for you is that as
That was for me but I didn't
Care what anybody else
Said
We were going to make this happen if it took a year
Orphan
Three-decker
Why did you believe that it would work any why all of these experts
Noah
And all of these people who
Experts on television
Look this is a
This is oldest
Tire franchise like Vino just enjoy life and
Any why did you think they were wrong to to two things number one
What we came to realize is that there actually are no a
You know nobody
Really knows
And so I was just willing to
To put my belief
Above
What other people were
For telling us in and Janice felt
The same way we thought they were
Yeah I felt I felt that
Let you know in listening
The Chipmunks song and the witch doctor
Doctor in Alvin
Presidents
That there was this relationship
With Dave and this
Chipmunk who kept pushing his buttons and I believed that relationship
So did millions of
Other people in and he really enjoyed
That that Dave and Alvin really endeared themselves
To us and I thought
If we could get that relationship in the shows
Then it could happen again
So what happened what was the turning point
The turning point was a disc
Stockings
Philadelphia
See you at 3 in the morning
Play the blondie song in
Set it up
And told his listeners that it were
Was the latest song from this
Album chipmunk Punk he was being completely
What was the what was the blondie song
Call me
Better than potatoes
The Chipmunks
And his a switchboard lit up
And
All these people called wanting to know where they
I could get the album and a record company back east
Found out about this and called us up
And said that would you be interested in doing
A chipmunk we didn't even listen to the end of the sentence
It was just some random small was in a small room
Could you do a chipmunk
Punk album would you be interested in a chipmunk Punk album
We were
We're very up
For it and as a
It turns out it
It's sold over a million
Albums
Overnight and
Then the people at CVS
You know of a sudden they wanted
Have lunch
And was it relatively cheap
Mapreduce
I don't like to say cheap
I would say any
Wow so you put that record out it just
Sells like crazy on then what and then
Television
Follows telling company start to call you will right after that as Janice mentioned not only were the TV
Folks who we'd gone to much more receptive and now interested
But it also gave us a
The chance to look at doing
More music
Because obviously added sold so well
So we were approached
To do not only a Christmas album but also
And we thought okay what would be
You know the
The farthest
Staying away from
This album cuz we didn't want to
Do a repeat of that
So
Urban cowboy hat come out and we thought you know what
Let's go to Nash
Phil and
Record
Urban
Chipmunk
So we
We took songs from Kenny Rogers and
The whole bunch of Love a Rainy Night Thank God I'm a Country Boy all of these different songs
But one of the things
The chance wanted to do in that album
Was now create
Some dialogue some stories
Do some personality and nausea
Nacho song song songs
Yeah and said that I said
Draw so how do we do this
How did your dad do the voices
End
The dialogue and he said
I have no idea what did I know
Went back to the house and I played his
Fathers
Tapes
Saw that he
Talk to task
Until I went back can I said okay
This is what we do
So you're you guys are recording this like
You're speaking Barrack
Clearly and
Slowly so then what are you
Speed up the tape it sounds
It's the same speed as we
Speak but it's at a higher pitch
Right
Just a dresser like a legit
Disco question
When you started
To do the voices
How did you just give me a sense give me a little taste of obviously everyone listening knows you are Dave
Like how do you record Alvin Lee
Just give me a line of
How you would record I will do that but I want to also say that
Janice was
Just wonderful is Theodore right from the beginning and I was
Still
So tied to what my dad had done which was
Barry
Clear and
When my dad did Alvin it was
Hello Dave
How are you doing today
Very stilted and it didn't feel real
So
Janice
I would say
Ross University
Don't try and do an impersonation of your daddy there's David's
Seville
Salvatore Simon
You don't loosen him up make it a little bit more your own
And so
Now after
All of these years
I've obviously gotten better and so now Alvin is
More fluid for me and even though I have to
To talk more
Slowly
Dave listen okay I know
You're going to continue to talk about
A blah blah blah whatever
I'd like a word with you and your l
And then guy I would say
Ross
Flower
Right right
I remember what you say
Said the last
Time
So can I please just leave
Can I talk to you a minute
There's nothing more to say Alvin
No
So television.
Actually didn't end up
Happening cuz it happened I guess in in 1983 that the Chipmunks cartoon
Comes back on TV right before that guy in 1981 Jensen I've been taking around a Chris
Christmas idea Christmas special
From probably around 78 or so
So so after
Chipmunk Punk comes out and does so well and then Urban chipmunk
NBC said to us am I know we told you we thought that was a
Terrible idea and we didn't like that
Chipmunks butt
We now
Think with those two of platinum albums
Maybe that Christmas special is a good idea
Did you get any Executives that have
Previously rejected YouTube
End up meeting with them and and and having
Glade begging you to come back
Yes
And I'm not going to give you names but many of those people that were on our list
A lot of my old but so when they approach you they said we want to do a Christmas
Special did you have a concept
What the cartoon would look like a howdy animated and
Did you already have that laid out or did you figure that out we didn't even we had never written anything be
T4m
And then when they say sit so who do you see riding it raw said
We're going to write it
And I looked at him
Across the room
Declared him like what
Saying
And
And again because of out of necessity
We wrote it
And then no we didn't have a look we didn't have
The voices we
Still warned expert
Add
How did you even know what
Do I mean obviously
You know you're both super
Smart and talented
Animations
Studio overnight you're standing up in Animation Studio
Which by the way United
Very expensive
Is it still hand
Stop right
Exactly Ross and I have done everything everything we've
If I ventured into we've know nothing about
So it's the
Instart from stupid
The hardest way in the best way to learn
And you just go step-by-step okay we need to create Carrick
Okay we need to know what this world looks like and
We were really
Very fortunate
Because
Some of the
Great animators from Warner Brother
Including Chuck
Jonesing
Phil Monroe
Virtual Ross and these guys who have done
The greatest bugs
Funny cartoons in
The 40s
50s
Were available
And they weren't being used in
Janice and I hired
All of them to make
Author the Christmas Special A Chipmunk Christmas
After that Christmas special event
ABC
Clearly
Is a success because in NBA
Car deal with you
What was that first it was
What's today at 1
One season of
About in the Chipmunks
Yeah it was always that that sort of Wonderful
Full first
The first series
Steel so it was
It could be as long as five years but we
Was one year at
At a time
And
We got very little money for it back in those days
Like $210,000
1/2 hour
Shows
So there wasn't much
To cover all your
Absolutely so and we were you
Oh yeah we were we were used to going into our own pocket yeah
What is the show launches in in 19
This was on
Saturday morning
That's right
And we were against bugs
Bunny
On ABC and CBS
Who didn't want us we have gone to them first
Cuz they said why do we need the Chipmunks we've got Charlie Brown
Snoopy
Yeah
We could be the hero you could have two weeks with a Snoopy at
Anyway so we turned out to be a against
Orbs
Charlie Brown and Snoopy in
And the Chipmunks
Series was a
Giant hit right from the beginning I remember
So I mean it's interesting because
What you think about
Consumer right you're thinking about
Mickey Mouse now then
Bugs Bunny
The Peanuts Gang and they're all great like we love them all we have
These warm feelings about them but actually
From the perspective of the creators of these
Characters like
These are competitors
You go ahead I guess I never see them is
Competitors
You didn't like what I just Crush Mickey
No I wanted to get my arms around
We Are Young we honestly always felt it was like our
Conversation with CBS when they said well we've already got
You know Snoopy & Charlie Brown
Always thought that
Good
Shows or good characters
Can coexist we didn't feel like we needed to go to war with anybody
Buddy we just wanted to
Create something that was
Unique toss fat guy to be honest
It you know it
If if the
Executive says
In a rude way why do I do that today
You know Snoopy
In just a moment a deal gone bad that
Put the Chipmunks
On life support
And how Ross and Janice
Revive the franchise gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Search come from Toys R Us
An original podcast
Charles Schwab
On the latest ever
Boise allergy
You'll hear it
Classic psychology experiments retail
William is an opera
Who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation
And is an avid chess player
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist
In a major Symphony Orchestra
Or a farmer
Listen to find out
Schwab.com pot
Or wherever you listen
This message comes from NPR
Sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
Vince and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality and mobile app
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR
Car for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR
Gyros
It's 1985
And Ross and Janice get
Through the first
Season
NBC
Even though
The show is
Reaching huge audiences
Start making a whole lot of money
Remember the
The deal they signed with NBC was for
$200,000 for the whole set
But what they do
Did have with something much more valuable
The rights
To the Chipmunks
I mean you guys own
Everything out
You own that you own the best
Recordings yuan
Animations
Characters
How is it possible that NBC
He didn't say
Hey if you want to deal with us
You know we own the rights
What did you know because my dad had
And not only is you mentioned
Set that up he was
The first
Songwriter
Who not only owned
The publishing a but also
The master recordings in and that's what interesting lie when we met
Berry Gordy years later
He said you know I learned a very valuable
Simple things
When I was writing songs
I decided to
Found mold
Town
Because I wanted to own the master recordings the way your dad
So it was my dad was really
Not only really
This great mix of
Creativity but also very
Really smart about business
Listen and so
I knew that
Is my dad mention
There was creating
Wonderful
Product but then there was
Holding on to
Bremen NBC said we will make this into a
Cartoon for you
And you guys have been
Pitching this
Racing
I mean if NBC would have said to you but these are our terms
I mean
Will we we we walked away we would have because what we said is look
Will produce it
We'll make sure we get the financing together we'll get a license
Speed from you we brought in Kellogg so Kellogg's
Was our spawn
Answer and
Janice and I
Wrote the shows and then we produced it
And
Dr.
First season they came to Janice and they said okay we'd like
To expand now we want you guys to do an hour
Nada
Half an hour
And and we we just said
We can't even make a half-hour we're proud of
So we when we can't work any longer unless you make more than seven days in the week
So we're going to turn it down
And she said no and Janice
Nobody turns down
More shows
But we did
So you are you making these shows for NBC you're obviously
Not making any
Real money from
Finishes cuz it's going to pay the production
Cost but you are getting all the
Disability so
But you're also running a business the Chipmunk
Did you guys sit down and say
This is a busy
Let's think about how to make the
Did something really really big what was the
What it what was it that you start to think about
You know
Guy we were just sitting at home all the time
So we didn't you see the numbers you see the ratings but they don't really translate into people
You know you can imagine but
You just don't get it
Back in those days
Sky we were getting like 40% of
Of the audience
Like 20 million a week or 15 to 20 million a week so
Finally we got an invitation we did a live
Show and it was at Madison
Square Garden address
Yeah we did the voices and
Design the costumes and got a story together
And we didn't have time to
Torrid but we
Go to Madison Square Garden
And when we went to the box office
The guy said no I didn't know you were coming I sold your
Tickets
It was sold out
Constitutes
To see the shack
And he's and I said
Are we are the
Anyway he let us sit in the aisle
And
For the first time we saw a fans we saw kids
Waving chipmunk banners
Screaming in the place was filled and it was such
Ammoman
For us it will never forget it was like oh my God
There are
There are people
A&B like the show they like the characters
So that mean your business really be
Can the chip
It was
The television show on NBC was record
Merchandising live shows in
And I guess like syndication
Yeah
And this is one of the funny business stories and I I found it in
Interesting only
The only because later on it turned out
To be such a windfall that we did not know about
But they said look up
What's going to happen is it
CBS Viacom is going to run your dad's old shows
The Alvin show
Against us
Because now that you're bringing the Chipmunks back so successfully with the albums in the
Especially now the new series
You have to get
Viacom
To not do it on Saturday morning and we want you
Offer them the syndication rights
For the new series
Esl just
Not run up against
Dusk and so Janice and I not knowing the value of sin.
When did Viacom CBS instead okay
If you just won't run against our new shows on NBC
Will give you the syndication rights to our new series
And they
A very full of themselves said no we're not going to
That deal
And then
A couple years later we
Sold those
425 million dollars
For something wow and that's and that was where the money
Was which we did not know we were and was
Actually yours NBC
No NADA de NBC didn't get a pee smell
But in 1985 you more money I mean
What is that mean to that
I think anybody listening would just
Assume that that was that you guys were
Set for
Well first of all was very exciting and end it was just a number
I wish I was always a kid
You don't always watching the
The you know the prices
Is right as a six-year-old
I knew what
The dishwasher would go for or the
And my mom would always say
How do you know that you've not bought dishwashers
Had a sense of what
A price for something was going to be
So I had just set that price
And I didn't change until we got it
And
Janice and I
So wanted
To make something we were really proud of not just something that was sick
Successful
Cuz the TV show
Was obviously tremendously
Successful
But we were never able to give it the kind of
The quality that we had hoped
To do so
Yes you would think we would be set
But
Because we always wanted to do something we'd also be
Be proud of
We
Took most of that money and made an animated feature the Chipmunk Adventure
Churon Inn
Quebec which came out Navy
And that that movie did pretty well right you did it it did well but we didn't at least in that initial that we didn't
Get our money back back in those
Because unfortunately we
Signed on with a distributor
That was going to put
X number of dollars into marketing Addis
Distribute we were
They spent less than 900000
Marketing the the movie at
And including the prince and advert
I think so
It it it
It did okay but it did not remotely get us our money back until
Many DVD sales
Ross Road a little article on that
Experience
Making the movie called
The agony
And the agony
Hard to find a bride
Different stories about because the show airs
On NBC
And you are doing original
A new episodes until 1990 and then
I guess it's in syndication
And then you guys decide to move on you you
You basically
Leave NBC and
Cut a deal with
Universal to bring the show back so
What
What was that about
So one of the things that they wanted
The do was
Create their own Mickey Mouse
I'll send end
They had had Woody Woodpecker
4 years
But Woody didn't have
A disorder of resonance
For Generations the way Alvin did and certainly didn't
The way Mickey Mouse
Didn't they it
Had seen that
When we had gone head-to-head weather was
With Mickey Mouse
Album art
TV show
Or what have you that
The Chipmunks
Not only held their own but
But did very very well in
Came out on top so Universal loved that
Jesus Alvin could be our Mickey Mouse
So the idea then was
They were going to
Create a
An animation
Unit for us
Jenison Auto
We're going to run that we would of course I'd only do more more chipmunk stuff but
A lot of other things that we had showed them that
Wow yeah that we were going to be in their theme parks and end that part actually did happen but
It was going to be this
Whole schmorgus
Spore goodbye
Opportunity and sulfur Janice
Send for me
Oh my gosh this sounds fantastic
Did you have to give up some of your ownership
Perfect date they bought a 25
5% share at that point
Time in end
In the end that
For the opportunity
For what felt like a
Really exciting opportunity to
Grow the business in a much larger way
Felt like a great thing
Did that the money was going to help you scale
They were going to be
Also putting money into
Development and production of all of the
Thanks and then shortly after we sign that
Deal
All the folks who wanted to do that
We're gone
What do you mean they're gone
They all laughed and so now you are that we wind up in a place that
Wasn't the same
As we thought
It was when I
What you mean like all the other people trying to do with you
University of Oregon do you still have this
Deal with universal I mean they would still have the commitments
I mean I guess personally to make movies into
Do all kinds of stuff so
Why wouldn't you just do it
Yeah well we
Certainly wanted to do it but you idiot ass
Do you have to
Why they didn't win
Stop doing much of anybody new comes in and they have a different vision
Yeah so those were not our happy years and we wound up
What are standards
What happens if you stop answering your calls because
You were presumably working on ideas
Will you pitching it in they were saying no
Or what was it
Just ignoring you what was
It was a, then yeah I know it was a combination
It started out various
Excited
And then
Some of the folks who brought us in
You know
Would leave
It'd be harder to get through to them then it would become
No return calls and end
Yeah it was just you felt very much like the orphan child that
That was brought in to be
You know the favorite son and then all of a sudden you
You aren't
Soup to did Alvin and the Chipmunks basic
Oakley drop off the map
Points pretty much
Yeah pretty much him and and so that's why we said to them
Listen
We really want to do this that and the other we've got a lot of opportunity if not
Here at Universal there's all kinds of Ventura
Outside so we can do
Folks in
Japan want to put Chipmunk
Stores together
Folks in Europe wants to make more spit so we'll just do all of those things and they said
Oh no we can't we don't want to have too many cooks
The kitchen
And I said no cook in the kitchen
So there's not a pot not a pan there's nobody
There's no Cooks Here season you guys were just hanging around
Pulling your hair out trying to get things off the ground and nothing
Yuck
Wasn't
At all the kind of opportunity that we had hoped for in and finally in 2002
2001 we were able to
I'll go wash
Separate way and you sue them to get back your company
Yeah we we we had to you know you
You unfortunately
You have to protect your characters in and sometimes
You tried exhausted every
Other
Because you don't want to go into this
Yes I'm telling everybody.
Exhausted all other
And you're up against the wall
But once you're there
You just have to be committed to that and we always win
Really do stand very United
What does it does it
Eat at you
Looks like it's
Got to be something that you
Can't get out of your head
Heaven Must affect your
And just your thought process and it
Just must become all-consuming
Yeah and you don't understand why
And what we've realized is that logic does not play a part in any of
And that's the thing that's so
Strange to us
Because it's like
Okay hold on a minute
You have no interest in this
We
Are dedicating our entire lives
To wit
We should be able to find a way
Separate this
Out
And
Go on our merry way
And I tend to try to poop
Put something in a different
Perspective
Ice Age
To Ross this is such a miserable
Experience
Then let's get something out of it
Let's make
This is sort of fascinating
I didn't find it fascinating the personality
Have to I have to put it in a different category
The Miserables
And so I think okay well I'm going to learn what this process
And how do I make this
As good as I can make it very healthy approach to lawsuits I have to
To say I'm I inspired I'm just wondering I mean
From what from what I read the
It was only
Acceptably in mm
For Sophie
Mm mm
M4.
Were you basically in like
Suspended limbo
No no no no no because no because
2001 was really the end of at the 2004 part was just
That's when the last payment
But we had to
Make to them was Act
Actually done
To get our
Company
So now it now it now it was Guy now is about
How do we
Resurrect
The franchise tag
Again after it basically
How much did you have to pay them too
Buy-Back
A two and a half million dollar
Nothing right
Did you guys a lot more exactly
Okay so you guys get out of that deal
And then you're free
Free and
I guess it was a
This point that you sign this multi movie
Deal with fox
The Chipmunks
Heaven Catholic
Off the radar for
Lots of year so
To that effect
Your ability to call a shot
Watching that negotiate
Well you know
Not totally although you know
You don't ever necessarily get the kind of deal.
But you want that
But we were very clear that you know WeeWorld
As we have always been
Be involved in every aspect and and then we say you know right from the start listen we are very proud
Dietary if you don't want to work with
With people like this
Please you know I don't
Because
Well get that
Waco from the from the outside
From the outside
We are think we're like very reasonable and and protective of the characters no I mean if we were a pain in the ass I would say so
I think but we're protective of the characters
So is it 3 movies you made with fox now
I think pink is enough the first one
Where the building is this
Record executive action beard goatee David Cross
David Cross and is that is that
It is it is it like it's going to be eight and unsettle you know
Experiences in this is in this industry will tell you
One of these stories
You know with our music
Sick situation
What's that
The end in 1982
We are
With a record company and I won't go into
Specifics
Who or what we're going to protect
Guilty here
So at we recording and the album comes out
And we are told by the
Record executive
Ross Janice I want you guys to
To take take the Chipmunks on the road
These are the
Cities we want you to go to travel across the country to the Seven Cities
And make this album I hid in these 7 cities and if you do that
We will give you a big National promotion
Great okay
We hit the road
And I won't get into all of the crazy stuff that happens but in any event at the end of the
Of the tour
We in fact make the album a hit in each one of the Seven Cities we come back to the record executive
So excited after a pretty bruising couple of weeks and
Yeah. Like 12 years
Any event we're all excited wanna now talk about the national plan to they're going to do and a
This is a quote and it's so it explains why David crosses as Ian
Is that character have to record Executives tells
Janice and me well
We're not actually going to do the national
Releasing the Big Marketing
If you don't have it in writing
You don't have
Wow
So that
Was a brutal lesson
What we've learned a lot of lust
For decades
Full of lessons
You these movies the fox
Killed it they did
Beanie Wells
Almost a billion dollars what over it
Their box office is about a billion
300ml
Wow and if you include the DVD sales
It's over 2 billion.
Well I'm one of those.
DVD buyers
You can you can send me a
Thank you card right here on out here
Exactly like you
Tiny
Cut of that 1.3
3 billion
So inevitably it's going to lead
To some kind of
It seems like
The way these deals are set up it's like
If all of a sudden he goes
Beyond anybody's expectations
They're delighted
Could you guys get Squall the economics of it wouldn't have been
The frustration for us cuz once when we make a deal we lie we live by the deal so that isn't the
Frustration for us
The frustration for us
Is
Wanting to tell
A certain kind of
Story with
Reflecting
Certain kinds of scenes and and and dialogue and so forth for the characters that we
Have spent four decades
Swear that's that
Honestly where the where the issue would be not the how the economics breakdown
I know that you guys filed a lawsuit against Fox
Because of some of this respiration I know you can't
Talk about all the details of the
Was settled
You know you have legal Act
This company is essentially you work with and then you settle it
You still have to work with them after I mean they're like
There there must be some bad blood so how does that
How do you interact with with Folks at Fox is it
Like perfectly cordial and normal everybody puts on their
Big boy's shorts and gets to work
Have occasionally on the show interview.
Husband and wife
Teens you have
Kate and Andy Spade
Sherman Dodge
And you guys and
I'm always really impressed
When
When I talk
Been married for 37 years
And you obviously
Clearly like
Not only
Love each other but you really were
Each other's judgment and
And you carved out different roles
Yourself what
Is it just like serendipitous Aleworks or do you
Do you actually
No there's a there's actually a really simple approach that we have and in
And is in this was right from the beginning
Because of our
Respect for one another
If Janice had a different point of view and she felt more strongly about it than I do
Then I would defer to
To her if
Conversely
I had a stronger
Feeling about it than she did
She would defer to me
But right now because she's
Writing the shows and directing them and designing them and so forth she really is
The driving
Force of the show and I'm thrilled
You know to play a part with Alvin and Simon and and Dave and Jenny gets frustrated with me when I wake him up
At 2 in the morning and say that
Grande
I think you could do like 27 better
No he's not.
But we do respect
Each other we work really well together and I thought about that too about husbands and wives and I I I think that it
Either works
And I could be wrong about this but I think it either works or it doesn't work
If a couple is committed to
You know going into therapy and really working on their Communications maybe two people that wouldn't normally be able
Go to work together
To work it out but
But we we just naturally work
Very very well
Together
You
You guys
Scaled this
Concept
In a way that
Anime
Your dad mean
He did well he made lots of money
Alvin and Chipmunks
Build a great life for
What is family
You guys took it to the
Stratospheric level
Completely different level
The ashes of this
Native
Alvin the Chipmunks
Well first of all he would be
Proud but but but also because my dad
Had a very limited attention span on things
I'm sure he would say
What
The hell are you guys doing 40 years later that it I also have
Tell you this serendipitous
Story We Were
In the eighties we would have to
To drive down with
Finally moved
To Santa Barbara and we would drive down to LA
Pick up lines
Because the show is going to be on
2 Days Later
And we do our work
And whatever else we had to
Fill in for the story
And we drove back at
Right I probably 3 in the morning and I just
You know automatically turn on the TV to just
Unwind
And I said oh my
My dad
Just can't imagine because the show wasn't coming out the way we wanted and Rossi
Said oh my God
I can't imagine what my dad
Does thinking and I said no no
Know your dad would be very
Proud at
How hard were working hell
How much were trying
And on
The television
Was his father
On Discovery Show on Earth Greatest Show on Earth
And my dad is in the audience
Applauding
And we looked
Until I couldn't believe it
And
We start to cry
But that was that was serendipitous
I have to say
Janice Karman and Ross bagdasarian are the duo Baha'i
Find Alvin and the Chipmunks
By the way the Chipmunks were actually named after Executives of the original record label
Alvin Bennett
Simon and Theodore keep
Were the chief Executives of Liberty records pekin 1958
If you ever call you Dave
You know what sometimes
But sometimes they do
Or they'll say
You know you sound so much like that David Seville character did anyone ever tell you that
And then and then you got to do it
Okay well and hopefully I'm not going to burn the mic up here doing this but
Alvin
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first
I quit thanks to one
Our sponsors Capital One Savor card
Earn 4% cash back
Dining
Attainment
2%
Grocery stores
1%
All other four
Now when you go out
Cashier
What's in your wallet
Hey thanks for 6
Sticking around because
Time now for
Today we're updating story
We first ran last year
It begins with Alex vanderwarker
Of Chico California
Here's his question
Yeah so it's have you ever Mix Concrete before I personally have not next concrete before
But Alex has mixtape
Especially when he was at
Teenager helping out
With small jobs
His dad's Construction Company typically what you do is you grab a bag of concrete
You put it in the wheelbarrow you break it open you throw water in there and use the trouble to mix it around
And then you need a wheel that wheelbarrow wherever you need a new pour it when you do this over and over
Can get to be a real
It takes too long it's messy and then pouring it is just
Too challenging
To do
My dad and I would say okay we need a better way to mix the
The stuff
And so one day
I want to fly reel
Alex and his dad
Ditch the wheelbarrow and they decided to use a lightweight
Heart instead
Poured the cement
And the water onto the tarp
And then held it up
Between them
And instead of using a shovel or any other tool I would just use these four corners no kind of pick one side up at a time
Ineffectively
Both the pile of concrete and water over itself and it would mix
Very quickly
And then you can just sort of pickup
The tarp from one side and pour it into where you needed it
Basic hacking Alex
I really didn't think much of it
But a few years later when he was taking business classes at
College
He said to his dad you know maybe we can make a sticker tarp to mix
Cement and then sell it
But for us it was like this really difficult leave and you know how do we create something that does
What we wanted
To do without knowing
How to create a
We didn't really we're not experts in the textile industry
We know how to mix concrete and that's
That's it
So in order to Market a mixing that
That people would actually want to buy
Alex had to invent a
A tarp that would form 10 of a bull when you
You held it so the cement wouldn't spill out
Another tarp had to be tough and waterproof
Even after he and his dad found
Just the right material is called a polyester denier blend and it's
Is coated with PVC even after they found that
They still have to find a way to make
The actual map
I was calling people in China and Mexico
Trying to just be like okay who can make it
I thought it would be easy
And that took
Years to do
We finally got the mat manufactured a few years ago but when they pitched it to their
Dream retailer
Home Depot
No
And the funny thing is I spent
Probably a year
Learning the same lesson over and over which is you're not going to get in the Home Depot if you're a nobody
So this is where a brand new business has to Pivot
And that's exactly what Alex
Did he figured maybe he could get churches and charities
Used to buy them
Bats and then donate them to places that
Really needed them
You know a huge amount of people that are impoverished in rural areas of the world that have
Absolutely nothing and they live on dirt floors
And Alex has several donors have already bought them at
To help rebuild after natural disasters and places like Haiti
Mexico
You know it started off as a slow tech product we just wanted to sell to make some money
And it has
Transform into an opera
Trinity
To help people
Bats Alex Van Der Waal
Co-owner
LLC which makes the mix match
The company's Revenue has multiplied 10 times we spoke with them last year
Elsa partner with a non
Prophet called bright light and starting in
April
Double using the mix match to build homes and schools in developing countries
If you want to learn more about mix match or here
Previous episode
Edward podcasts
How I built this
Npr.org
And of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build
Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us
Hidta
Npr.org
Do you want to send it
How I built this
I sure was produced this week but run teen Arab Louis
Who also composed the music
Thanks also to JC Howard could see the Immigrant
Size Mexican 4
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
The Avengers
I'm Gyros and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 200
50000 cup
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days ago