Everyone we're gearing up for our
First ever how I built this
Summit in San Francisco in October supported by
American Express
And we just confirm some
Great news which is that
10% of the tickets for The Summit
Will be absolutely
Free we're calling it The how I built this
Fellowship
If you want to apply for a
Free ticket
You can join our new community group go to Facebook
And search for how you built that
I'm sure there
The application is
Pin to the top
Of the page and applications are due soon July 9th
So join how you built that
On Facebook
ASAP
So here's a question
Have you ever wondered why the list is spelled with a y
Instead of an eye
I was really trying to grab
Attention
Company
Trying to solve a problem which you will hear about in this episode
Which first ran last February and
One of the kind of funny things we had to figure out was how to quickly Market to the
College campus
Whatever early purchases was
A frog and beaver costume that we put on I went to Cornell I was actually going to Corner
On a recruiting trip for Lehman
And
I was standing
On the quad in this ridiculous costume handing out cards about this carpooling service is a frog
Beaver costume beaver
And at the next day at the Lehman recruiting event
A girl came up to me and said
I see you in a in a beaver costume yesterday
Ramen.
How I built this innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind them
Gyros
How did John Zimmer made private cars work like taxis and in the process helps build a service
Hours billions
So did you actually remember the
The days of walking onto
The sidewalk
Hand
Inhaling
Hey Taxi
I mean
It feels like ancient history right but still
Even though this world
Car rides
A few years old
We're so used to it that
If you like me
Answer youth anxious when the Uber or Lyft app says you have to wait for 3 minutes for your ride and just think about how
Weekly ride-sharing apps
Like uber and Lyft
Totally transformed transportation in many cities around the world have
In most places
They've become indispensable which has also meant that the competition between the two companies
Has been really Fierce since 2012 when both of them launched the service
It turned private cars into public taxis but the amazing thing is is
Even though Lyft is just a fraction the size of uber
It is still valued at more than 5
Billion dollars
And one of the guys behind it John Zimmer
He never thought that ride-sharing would be his life's work he actually studied hotel management
Cornell
What is interest
Restart
How to change during his senior year
I took a course that was really really important to me called Green cities that I had this amazing
Professor
His first lecture is the history of the world in 30 minutes kind of like
The book Guns germs
And
He ended the lecture saying that we're at a really important time in world
World history where population density is rising rapidly in our cities as more people move there
And resources
And infrastructures
That were built decades ago
Are becoming more and more strength
And he kind of challenges stand in the class and said if you don't make this class
Mosto
Something you do this
Then I don't want to teach
Because if we don't fix
These problems
We're going to have major economic
Environment
And social problems
And that kind of set me on a path
Which eventually led to lift
But being that I grew up
In the east coast and in Connecticut and New York
I did feel like I had to have a finance experience in
So
After graduating I went and worked
At Lehman Brothers
Hi in mm
Wow
Lehman Brothers in 2006
Like when we look back on that and
Roof
I was like hell yeah you know
The decline and fall right there so you go to Lehman Brothers
In 2006 What will what did you do there
I was doing real estate Finance
So I was right in the heart
Where everything happen
And as you said right at that moment
Text to 2008 was my 2-year analyst
Was it interesting
It was interesting for a few months
But I got to say I
My interest declined
Probably after
Just about a year
And so I started thinking
What what else I could do
It was actually about about a year into it that I was on Facebook one night
And
Saw
Logan who is now my co-founder who I didn't know at the time
Posted
On a mutual friend's Facebook page saying that he was starting a website
Call zimride
And what like what
Was Elizabeth
What was the story so Logan's background
Is that he
Grew up in LA
Hitting traffic
He then went to UC Santa Barbara and made an experiment of himself so he can bring a car to school
And wanted to see how he
We could survive without a car
And he started a car share program similar to Zipcar first
Beijing University
City fleet vehicles
And he got the attention of the local Transit
The local Transit board
Elected him as the youngest member ever to be on this Transit boarding
Logan Brandon in Santa Barbara
In Santa Barbara
And he quickly grew to realize
The challenges
In public trans
Invitation
And came to the conclusion that
Across the country
When you pay to get on the bus
You really only covering about 34
So what that means is that $3 bus for actually cost
The government 10
And
As the lines get more busy
They get harder
Dafont
And harder to add service.
Also they actually
The more busy they got the worst
So he came to the conclusion that public transportation
Broken
And while the promise of
Public transit
Phenomenal
The reality was
It's not and so
He then traveled to
Zimbabwe
Where he saw people
Sharing rides out of necessity
And got inspired
To build
A website
That would connect people
Going the same way to be able to sell it
In their car and that's why
He called the website
After Zimbabwe
Yeah
So Logan was basically trying to build a website
That was like
Hey I'm going this way I look
The car Shine website
What used to be that you just advertising
Like Craigslist
The store puts on a pinboard in
On college campuses
Saying driving from yuan
LA to San Francisco
Do you need a ride
But he was basically trying to
Concept
And put it online
Exactly yeah it so
Like you said we had these
Physical bulletin boards
Azure digital bullets
Turn boards
Four people going along the sea
Same way if they're going
Spring break or fall
Call break
But there was no identity
Or ratings
Behind that and so it was limited in how many
People actually
And so we thought how can we make a safe
If you tied something
Facebook
You can have a profile of the individual you're going to
Share ride with
And follow up with ratings
Of of how that ride experience
It was
At which would create a safer and more broadly
Used environment
For for carpooling on College camp
So what
Happens to you guys then look at this stage
You and Logan still have met right so do you
Email a mortgage
Did you call Amber what
So we got on a
Call I believe in and he said that he was actually going to be
In New York City
In a few weeks
And so we ended up meeting up
And talking a lot about about carpooling and and I shared
Some of the thoughts that I had from that course I
Cornell
We realized that we were
Both so passionate
About solving the same problem
And Ambien work
Come together right after that
New York and did you guys just hit each other
Yeah yeah he's become my best friend he was best man at my wedding
He's also a very
Focused
Calm and thoughtful
Pearson this is funny story when he
He was a kid I think he was about
8 years old
His parents had had just got
The TV and
I guess
A few weeks later
He said
He asked his parents
How to remove the TV for
From the house because
Distracting
So I think that just speaks to his
Is level of focus and
I really enjoyed
That working with him because of that that book passion
At focus and thoughtfulness
Okay so you guys start working on zimride together
You're still at Liam Brothers right right and what was its Logan doing at this point
So
He's at UC Santa Barbara sustainability coordinator after he's graduated
He's working on zimride
The side project project he actually did
A lot of the original coding
The website
And
We didn't know whether it was a
Big business
Retarded
Could be
But before we were going to jump all the way and we wanted to start
So we spent
Nights and weekends
Working on
Zimride
Just like remotely you were in New York and he was in Santa Barbara and you would
Like emailing and
Skyping and stuff all the time
Yeah yeah we have
Late night sky band
Every maybe month or two we try to get together
And
Logan's on he's working on building the website on my end I'm figuring out how do we get enough
People using the platform
So that it works it was really like a chicken or egg problem
Where
The idea
Of having
A lot of seats
To choose from on your way home
Say Cornell in
New York to go to New York City with
Exciting
Yeah there is
Very few bus routes
Not everyone on the car
Or had a car on campus and so
If I could go on
Zimride Cornell Edition
And by seeing someone else
What is Carrefour
$20
$30
That would be really exciting but
Had to be there had to
To be available we had to create both sides
The marketplace
So the idea was
How Facebook originally
Coupons to 12
You would just have these sites at University so
The students can figure out
Exactly
And so
One of the kind of funny things
We had to figure out was
Was how to quickly
Market
To the college camp
Just kind of strange we wanted to put on
Costumes on campus
And hand out information about this survey
Whatever early purchases was
A frog and beaver costume that we
Put on I went to Cornell I was actually going to Cornell
On a recruiting trip for Lehman
But I went a few days early
And
I was standing
On the Clyde
In this ridiculous costume handing out cards about this carpal and service dog costume with Beaver costume
I was the beaver out flyers
Yasso
We needed to get a critical mass of let's call it a thousand people
The offering their seat so that those that went on to look for a seat could find one and it worked
And
At the next day at the Lehman recruiting event
A girl came up to me
Love surrounded by a lot of
Managing directors in
Did I see you in a in a beaver costume yesterday
You know the next step was let's sell a private Network
To the various University
And that we were able to over a few year. Sell to 150 universities and
Companies that would pay us
An annual fee for this private car
So you were not
You weren't taking a cut off the
I got the feeling that people would charge
Share ride
Accurate
Not at not at that time
YouTube the business model was a cell this University is a
Subscription model
And you fold a hundred to go see you were personally calling universities and pitching us to them
Yeah so I was personally calling and traveling to
Probably visited hundreds of universities
In in those first few years how did you do this
In the beginning and work at Lehman Brothers
In the first year is more about
Getting the product stood up and having a proof
Not being kind of Cornell and so
The majority
Virtually all of those sales came once
Once I went full-time
10 mm
You would like to know what Imma do that smile leave Lena brother
Yes it was early 2008 and I made the decision and
At my best friend's mother actually worked in the same building as me when I was at Lehman Brothers
I told her what I wanted to do and she said
How could you leave a Shore thing like lemon to do a Crazy Cart
How many people have brothers
Yeah
To go do something
Yes at several people said that to me
And then three months later
Lehman was bankrupt
We knew that there were
Challenges going on at Lehman but I could not have predicted that
3 months later
That they would have been Bank
So you moved
To Silicon Valley Inn
2008 to go full-time
I'm zimride with Logan green
Yes
Did zimride get become profitable
Yep
Hugely profitable or respectable
I'd say respectively profit
Who was a pretty robust company in
Did you see this as
This was going to be your thing this is what you were going to do with your life
Yeah I mean the dream was to start
A business that had a major
An important impact
On our world and specifically on the way that our cities are designed
And so
You know I think from an early. We consider this
Our life's work
When you were going to basically transform carpal you were going to do
For carpooling Starwood Airbnb stand for
Accommodate
Exactly
So what happened how did you shift
From like this concept of carpooling to what would eventually become
Left
So in the middle of 2012
4 years in
Yeah about 4 years of doing it
Full-time
And and we stop and look at ourselves and say
How are things going
And what would we do
If we were starting over.
I think that's a really helpful exercise
And
What was true
In 2012 that was not
When we started was the proliferation of
Smartphones
And operating
That would enable
More
Short-term planning
And short disk
It was him ride you had to go on a website and
Find the days and the person going right and you had to
So do it I guess
At least today in the van
Exactly yeah it so once the technology shift
Did that would enable more in
Decision making the hopper
Are our thought process shift
And
You guys start to think
Maybe we should focus on Sunday
Yes so weird scene
Uber had started
Limos
On demand
The black
Yeah and we said you know that
Interesting from a
You know using
Mobile technology
But it wasn't that interesting to us from
You're picking
In a small population of
People that can
4 right out of a private driver
Because Yuri was like a an elite service
Set the beginning it was just has black cars and it was from their craft fancy
Yeso
The average American household spends
Over $9,000
Every year on owning and operating a
Car
Equates to over 2 trillion dollars
Annually
In the US
In the car seat
Part 96
Percent of the time
And so we said
How could we
Take these personal vehicle
That are parked at altar
And expensive
To their owners
And make better use of
And and so the idea was
How to create an app
Where you could you
You could request
Someone
Personal View
On demand
For the platform really is
At that point was just
Hey I have a car sitting here and I'm going to make it available
Rent out for an hour
No it was
Hey I have a car and I have time
And I'm going to go drive
Other people around Cry 4 for payment
And it goes back to that
My Hospitality experience of how do we create something
That was centered around service about treating driver and passenger with respect
But also you got to remember what is now accepted as normal getting into someone else's vehicle
Was not at all normal
Right back
We had to
Work to
Change people
Behavior and
In the early days suggesting
Will sit up front
And in trading this
Your friend with a car hot Hospitality environment
We felt that one it opens the audience
To a larger set of
Drivers and if you go in a room of our
A hundred of our friends and you ask how many of you are willing to drive a taxi
A couple handmade
Baby go up
When you say how many of you are willing to share a ride
You know 75
Hands would go up
And so
We wanted to create the experience around that
That because
After
Many many years
Of being
I told not to do
And many many years of seeing
Yellow
Vehicle
And thinking that that is safe to
Because it's yellow
We had a lot of
In a behavior change to the kind of push through
John Zimmer co-founder of Lyft
After the break
How the state of California almost killed his company
Play with this and gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your lawn
Long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from wix.com
A web platform for creating your own professional website
With Wix whether it's your first time creating a website
Or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning template
Or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology and Powerful web features
Join Over 125 million people already using Wix to create their own websites go
Go to wilx.com to create yours today
So what will you create
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So it's 2012
And John and Logan were still working on this carpool concept called zimride and they were doing pretty well they pitched
A bunch of investors in Silicon Valley they got some money
But around this time they decided to change course and focus on other ways
They can make car sharing
Accessible to Millions
Basically an early version of what
Eventually would become Lyft
The before they could really launch the app
They needed
Test it out so
I got in touch with him
So the first set of of drivers we actually
Emailed a bunch of zimride
Users
And
That we said hey we have this new project we're trying out
And that we love you to try it out
Then we invited them over to the office and walked
True kind of the whole
Experience
That that we were they were all in in the San Francisco area
Yes
And what did you
You tell him to do today
Drive around the city
Well we we first got to walk through how the
Hopworks are all the safety standards that we had
And we let them know that
What what's going to happen is that you're going to get a request
On your phone and it's going to let you know where that that passenger is
That they could go pick up that passenger
Take them where they needed
And that the op what kind of help help them
Navigate
And do do all those
Pick-up and drop-off
And at the time
There was a suggested donation at the end of the ride
At the passenger can make
Through their credit card that was
Attached to their Pro
Going to be
Free if you want
To be free
It was an early days you got to remember again one that this was
Was very very new and not normal and
United was fault would fall in a regulatory gray area
And so one of the ways
That we we we saw around that was to say
Kit to make it optional for payment in the early days until we had
@ford through
The the right regulatory structure
At what point did
Did you come up with that
When did it go from
From being called zimrides
Before we launched it
At the working title was in Wright insta
But while going through
Actually really
3 week. That
Lyft app the original Lyft app was built it was
Is very very fat
And the brand
Lyft
Was thought of during that period as well along with
With the logo and everything
Thanks
Except you couldn't get LIF
That was probably take
Yeah lafc.com is owned by Otis Elevator
Okay fair enough yeah right
So you got Lya
Yeah in the middle of 2012
Again over 3 weeks.
The team movie
Incredibly fast 2
Build the app
Come up with the branding
And meat
And background check and I'm bored
The first set of drivers and then we then we invited a few friends and
It was that we got an incredible response
So this is only in San Francisco at this point right
Yes
How long did it take before
You know you open this up you made this into a decimal
Anybody could use
It was probably the second half of 2012
Where are we
It started to take off
We started to divert resources from zimride over to lift
And I'm really in in January of 2013
We said
Okay we need to go all in
This is
A massive opportunity
This has been incredibly successful
With a small amount of focus
But that was a really
In many ways a tough moment because we had work
You're for five years on zimride
And we were deciding to divert all of our attention
To an entirely new model see you guys
Sold
Exactly so we sold them right to Enterprise rent
The car
And basically did the assets
Add a contract with the universities
And retained the entire team
And went all-in on unless
So that first-year how many people downloaded the app
That's just tens of thousands
And you guys are your model as you were taking a cut out of
Every
Right right
To the the rate is calculated
FaceTime
At distance
Sometime and then left at receiver
A commission off of that one
20 to 25%
I offer the overall rate the rest goes to the driver
As well as a
Trust
Conservice fee
So when you start this right
Did you I mean now we look back and say oh yeah
Of course this is going to work but presumably like you started
The face a lot of backlash
Obstacles from City
He said had
Pretty entrenched
Taxicab commissions and drivers and
Established
Regulations about who can pick people up and drive them for money
Yasso
About a month into launching left this was
Later
At 2012
Received our first of many cease and desist
Not from various different governments
And
It basically said you need to stop by
And what did you do
We read the letter and then we had already done our
Like working
Research on the laws and and we asked for meeting
I think I was followed by a second season to Sis but we eventually got
A meeting with with who
With the Public Utilities Commission
Okay and our approach to regulations is to to really understand
The motivations and the needs of
Of the regulating entity
Because we understand they have a very important job
And we went in and asked that we said hit Locker
Is this a matter in a public safety
Or is this about you know existing Industries
Anderson Public Safety of course until we said we don't own Vehicles we don't have employees driving for us
So we don't fall into
The category that you currently have
But we looked at your safety regulation since that's the most of
Important thing
And
We've gone above and beyond on a background check
Actually still to this day for
Limos in in
In California are not required
We've done
Driving record Texas
Whitmore Street
Period and we create an insurance policy
But the million dollars and there's
Isn't was 700
$50,000
If it's about safety
What we'd love to do with you to create a new category
.
Allows you to
Enforce that we are doing these things that we tell you we were doing
But that we were able to do this in
In a safe
That way that brings more affordable transfer
Irritation to
California
They were threatening to sue you
They were threatening to shut us down
Force against the drivers that we're driving in
Were you scared about that possibility
Yes cuz you'd sold of zimride and she put all your eggs in this basket and
It could have been shut down
Yeah I think I literally had a headache for 1 month
I wish I had to go
Check and make sure nothing was wrong but it was incredibly stressful
What time
Because as you said we switched
All of our Focus over to from zimride to Lyft
And at the opportunity was massive and the regulatory obstacles that we're just
What does massive how long does it take for you to overcome
Those initial
Regulatory challenges like was months years it's at least at least
Year early for that first year if I was to pick the one thing I spent most of my time on
Was the government relations and was working to create a new regulatory category 4 for the space
And then you know not just doing that in one state
But being able to demonstrate that in in multiple cities and states
So when so when you start
To expand outside of San Francisco and then La how fast were you expanding to other cities is it like every month every
Everyday every week
That kind of earlier. It was more
Every few months
Maybe the most
Intense moment was
April
2014 when we launched 24 markets on the same day
Who are your competitors
Is Uber was still doing
Let me buy car
Yeah there really wasn't
There's some other companies that were trying in this in this kind of
Peer-to-peer
Personal vehicle space
But they're there wasn't a large amount of competition
There were still so many questions looming around regulatory
That I think knew people were waiting back to see how that played up
Your focus was on
This
Airbnb bottle
Or you got a car
And
It's going to be community and
Sharing-economy thing like
What happened when when all the sudden Uber
Started doing Uber
Where they base
Copied remodel
Yes so I mean we we assume that
Because the opportunity was so large and everything we're seeing that there would be more
More competition coming
And so it wasn't it wasn't it wasn't a big surprise
And
It just you I think over the
The course of the diffuser years we've been doing this it's
It made us better and frankly I think both both companies grow fast
How do you differentiate
Yourself from them like how do you make the case that actually you should go with us and not bad
Yes so are our focus in the early days was we needed to
Ensure we solved the two most important things for our customers first which was not reliability you can get a
Ride when you want it at the best possible
Once you have parody on those and now it now we do we built up
Enough infrastructure
Enough basic driver community that you can get a ride with in an average 3 minutes
In the cities then it's about the experience in today's world
By treating drivers better than any other company the ability to have cashless tips get
Paid in the same day
Create an environment where drivers are respected by passengers and nuts and translates to passengers be
Being treated better
Then another service are you a competitive person like to you
Do you look at your competition and really one
Want to beat them
Yes absolutely
How much is a drive you
That idea
Auditor to a large degree I used to play sports
Whether it was running track or playing soccer
And you know I started running track as
Just to stay in shape for soccer and then
I wanted to
To win the race and I wanted to
Go under 5 minute mile
And was able to
To do that and so I think often now today
You know where it where in
Hello what could be described as a mile
Four laps
And where in lab 2
You know that 3 is typically in that race the most critical.
Were you set yourself up for victory and so
I think we're making a lot of important moves and decisions now that should allow us to
To win the race
To take it personally like you know
Uber obviously has
Okanogan a pretty tough competitor in a X or Ben
Accusations at the
That they've
How to sabotage you or maybe you guys have
Dongzhimen
Is it is a personal 2D is it something that you really
Feel emotionally
Yeah yeah definitely
And I mean
Is part of it well just is it just business in
Business
Days where you can how you hate your
Competitor but you all still respect them or is it really like no actually this is really personal I don't like them
I think we take it and I take it personally which drives me
Because I believe so strongly in what our team is working on and why were were
We believe that
By building what we're building we can make our cities
Designed around
People instead of cars
And by having the right values
An ethics
We can impact Society in a way that's bigger than a transfer
Rotation week
And so
I take it personally
Because
We're out to win for the values that we represent
I don't let that distract me
I let that you know fuel the fire
And
I think in the early days
When I was less mature
It would it would distract
But
But today I feel
Think it it just feels
The desire to
Push harder
Santa company there's
About 1300 people
And then drivers do you to disclose that number
I know we've said several months ago that
In the last year there was over 300,000 and
And you can assume that this year
Have that number has grown quite significant
Do we think about like these right trying
Companies
Uber and left
As
The stainless permitting that we all fall, depend on I got the apps of for both companies
Imyfone sorry I do have both
And
They become
Harbor Lights like there's like I can't even remember what life was like before Lyft or Uber
And yet we have to imagine Monday
Something is going to replace you guys and people think a driverless cars
Do you ever think about that
Sure I mean it's that
You know I I saw the rise and fall of Lehman right before my eyes and I think that that creates the
The right sense of
Awareness and when building
A company that that you've seen something like that
But when you look at the future
Are you talk about autonomous
Cars
An autonomous car is not going to drop out of the sky and be able to do a hun
That's not real
What's real is that
Over the next
Couple years it'll be able to
Do
A few percent of our trip
10% of our trips
50% of our trip
And
What that means for this opportunity is that
We're going to be able to address that ultimate goal we have of ending car ownership and providing a full out
Alternative
To owning a car in fact what you'll be able to do
Is by
Likely a miles plan from us
Amethyst
Description
Hot to handle all your transportation
And over the next few years some of those trips will be done by
Human drivers in another's that will be done by autonomous vehicles
To the point that we can provide you with
Amazing
Hospitality experiences on wheels
Will you look back at you know
Packaging Logan over Facebook and then like
What kind of side project moving to Menlo Park Inn
Corn your heart and soul into the into zimride and
Then starting left and watching it turn into a company the value of its value over 5 billion dollars
Do you sort of look at that and sits or save yourself
Okay I can like breathe out a sigh of relief
We're okay we've made it we've gone week
We passed the hump
Or are you
Corydon vigilant
Everyday
Yeah. I don't think there's a acai of
Accomplishment I think there is
The bar keeps getting raised
And that's the bar that
That we raised on ourselves
The goal over the last 10 years
For Logan I hasn't changed
You know it was them right
And then it was left
And then it will have
Autonomous implication
Until we've accomplished
The fact that you don't need to own a car in a city
Until we've accomplished the fact that we don't need
As many roads and parking lots
In our city
Until we allow for our cities to be
A redesigned around the people living in them instead of the
The cars
That are parked in them
Then we're not happy
John Zimmer co-founder of Lyft since we first ran this episode last February
Lyft valuation has more than doubled over 11 billion dollars
By the way or how I built this Summit in San Francisco on October
16th there's lots more info and tickets available online at npr.org
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things you are
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors rocket mortgage by
Quicken Loans
But it comes to refinancing your existing mortgage or buying a home
Rocket mortgage lets you understand all the details so you can be confident
That you're getting the right mortgage for you
Go to Rocket mortgage.com
Built
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
Time now for how you built that
And savory updated story we ran about a year ago this one comes from Kyle Ewing of Denver who got an idea for a
Business in kind of a roundabout way I got the idea when I was trying to
Create a product for students traveling abroad
This product was a backup copy of their passport
I was trying to sell backup passports online that would be as durable as the real thing
But also tear proof and waterproof
The problem was the market for this type of product doesn't yet exist
So I was trying to create the market which proved to be very difficult and I was trying to figure out what to
When the phone rang and the guy the phone
It was actually somebody who said hey Kyle I love your passport I even bought four of them for my kids
And he said all four of my daughters
Use the SOS world pass I love it
But I have a question for you can I buy a case of your paper and at that moment
Kyle realize that the waterproof paper he was using for the passports
Was actually a better business idea
Pain just the passports
That moment was me standing up out of my chair
And spiking the pencil and doing a touchdown dance because it was an immediate lightbulb moment where
I realized
This failing business just
Through legs and all of a sudden they had a million and one ideas of what I could use
Waterproof paper for and the bat is a pretty long list
Waterproof
Restaurant menus waterproof children's books
Waterproof Maps field manuals for the u.s. Navy nautical charts for the u.s. connect to back up just a little
Kyle is not an engineer but
He was working on the passport idea he made a bunch of calls to chemical expert said he told them
He was looking to make
Paper that was totally waterproof
Much more waterproof than say yeah just laminating something
Zoe duration after iteration we finally got to paper that's both
Waterproof and rip proof and something that can also receive and hold
When it's been printed on eventually found a manufacturer in the US to make a polyester pulp that could be
Depressed and rolled into waterproof paper
Do you want to Tinker with a product himself so he moved a laser printer into his living room but
When I put it through my home laser printer
Immediately
White smoke came out of the printer and it smelled like burning plastic and the entire printer was
After that Kyle's very supportive wife Ashley came home that night she smelled the burning smell and she's
Said Kyle I love this arts and crafts project you taken on but I think it's time to get to a more realistic
Take product or business idea but one printer and seven iterations later and Kyle says
He came up with the most waterproof paper on the market and he has the clients to prove it including
Yes the US Navy and airforce
Several restaurant and hotel chains University Labs even Google
Nekudot funeral days when you sit back
You look at your sales or you look at the new client you just got
And
You think oh my gosh
This is a real business
I'm building something that matters
And it actually is a success
Since we last spoke with Kyle last year is revenue continues to grow he give us specifics but
Paisa to say it is in the million it has a team of ten employees and his list of clay
Science is growing to include the ups and the LA Kings
If you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org
We love hearing what you're building
And thanks for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or here
Previous episodes in go to how I built this. Npr.org please also subscribe to the show at Apple podcast
Or whatever you get your podcast on while you're there please do give us a review you can also write to us at HIV
Npr.org I built this
Our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman ft never blue decomposed music thanks also to neva Cranston
Import newer coetzee and Jeff Rogers AR intern is JC Howard
Gyros and even listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week