Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Support for the how I built this Summit comes from American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible Funding Solution
PetSmart Savi way to fund your business
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply visit
Americanexpress.com business
Hate this guy here today we got another brand new episode from the house
Built this Summit in San Francisco that happened this past October
This one is for my live interview with Joe gebbia the co-founder of Airbnb
October of 2016 for one of our very first episode
And you haven't heard about the wild rollercoaster ride of starting Airbnb
You should definitely go back and get that episode of listen
Because Jonah co-founders they really went through major changes and pivots and disappointment
Send failure
Before they hit on the idea that today
We all recognize one of the most iconic travel brands in the world so when I sat down with Joe Bacci
October
I want to spend time talking with him about why they never gave up
Even when lots of people were saying
That idea
Was never going to work
Joe
Guy
It is
It is actually amazing a 10 years ago
No one in this room no one listening no one in the world
Imagine that people will be sleeping at the homes of random strangers
Soap
Let's start with the idea
The beginning of Airbnb go back to 2008
Really at this point
Nobody wants to invest in this business
Does Hugo
If you remember the podcast
They email 20 investors
10 replied 5 coffee with them none invest
I mean I'm not surprised
The time people are telling you
This is a stupid idea and it's not going to work
Right because that's what you were hearing
We got that I can tell you all the times and show you all the emails from
I'm really credible investors like people that
Disturb investors that picked
Google and PayPal and YouTube and Facebook and all of the kind of Internet Grace that came before us
And so
Sitting there offices you know
It was just demoralizing
To be
Sitting across from somebody who has
A good Instinct for a good idea paint lead based on their portfolio
And to look at you in just say
This is never going to work
Or
There's one investor that will go unnamed who said
You should really focus on Church groups
And then he said but you know what church groups aren't a big it's not a big market so I'm going to pass on this
Cuz he couldn't get over the hump of
How could you possibly
Build a company that's based on Strangers
Posting pictures
Of the most intimate
Parts of their home there
Bedroom Gallery kitchen or bathroom
On the internet
If you are going to pay to come stay in their home yeah
That's going to be big
But in their defense Joe like
I think
Most of us in this room probably would have
Agreed to send 10 years ago I mean I think that
It was a weird idea
It was so weird that was kind of a
Dom ideas
4053 North
Westport outside
I mean
People were probably sing that you over and over again like this is just
Like move on do try something else
Is that was it happening that was actually happening in
You know the truth is if you made decisions based on what a spreadsheet tells you
Are spreadsheets said
This is not going to work
Get a job or start something else
Like it was highly irrational to keep going with their product
And I'll never forget when we went home by Bryan my co-founder and I
He went back to Upstate New York coming back to Georgia
So the holiday been home for Christmas
2007 you go home for the holidays and what do people ask
What are you up to what are you doing
How's your day going for you and so
You know neither of us really had a lot to say about the year except this one time and people say no
Our apartment design conference
And
One of two things happened like
People eat with either way
Oh my God
Tell me more
This is really interesting
Piedmont ohmygod
You're insane
Yeah and they would leave the conversation
And there's something about that visceral reaction that it got out of people
We're Brian and I were like
Maybe there's something here maybe this is there's there's more this to me thinking
There were enough people to wanted to hear more about it that said yeah I tried like that or
Noah Nelson college of us through your travel through Europe and you know I get off the train station or not
I want to be standing there is a pension with a sign we don't stay in her place
So people started telling stories about actually you know
People are already traveling this way it's just not
Formalize
It's not easy
Yeah smart people
That you respect
Tell you you're wrong
Tell you your idea is bad
When do you know that there are
Did you think they were wrong or did a part of you think
Maybe they're right
This is the part where in your head is an entrepreneur you go a little bit crazy
Because you bounce back and forth between like
Wow that's a really smart person they said this idea sucks
And then you go home you're like no
I'm sticking with this I'm going to make this happen
Like they can't tell me this is wrong
And
I think
Maybe it's a personality trait
For me
You know that kind of stuff actually fuels me
Yeah that there were times at
Study design at RISD where
Professors would tell me something couldn't get done
And that was all I needed.
I mean
In this because
Not everyone's wired that way in and maybe you you aren't either maybe sometimes
You were
You did kind of give up
Will actor hear something very important to know about our story
Is that
If you look at Airbnb from 2008 onward
You're missing
A big chunk that took place before Airbnb
Because I've worked on a lot of ideas that were really bad
You just haven't heard of them cuz they never went anywhere
And so
I think it really takes
Eugene
What I would say in the gym of Entrepreneurship
Were you just trying things and it doesn't matter if it pans out or not it's about
Going through the process
I was at working on the street here at Chronicle Books as a book designer
University. San Francisco
And
Every dad leave and
In the room right where I was the exit was there was a Giants industrial size trash can is gray big trash
Afghans overflowing is white books
One day when I can pick up the books and discover their completely blank
And I went to my manager at the time I said hey what's going on at these books Gozo those are the proof books they do before they make
A big running back of a book
I said all the trash
I have them
Sure
What's the deal with me really weird like what do you want trash
I was like these are perfect just like sketchbooks or journals or other things
So actually co-opted these books I throw my bag in for like a year and a half
I didn't gather these books I have a $2,000 books
In my garage
Down the street
Did I collect in the cool thing is everyone is different notes you're exactly the same and I came with the rubber stamp I give it a brand
I sold them online I saw them design fairs
And I
Yeah
Have a silly idea if
Didn't go anywhere
But it was just like
But you see something and you do something about it
Yeah
I mean so we we've done an episode was about Slack
Stewart Butterfield who's actually here and in the audience
S&M
Really the story of slack is a story of
A completely different idea it was supposed to be a game company
Uglich
And that
That didn't work didn't work out with a beautifully designed
They kept out of the capital and they kept pushing forward but eventually
They had to give it up
And that was it was that was going to be before the end of the story and slack was kind of an accident because it was his intro message
Charging system that they
Created
Just so the engineers could talk to the marketing people and
It was this amazing serendipitous pivot
How did you
How did you guys know
That you should just keep pushing forward was it where you talking about this
Was was Brian sang with we got to keep pushing forward you saying it figures
Where I go to when I think of that question
We had an experience that those investors did
We had three people stay in her home
We for 5 days we knew exactly what that felt like
It was magical
I'm getting to Shogun San Francisco getting to
Like really go from strangers to friends but in such a short Arc
The time
Russ was like really inspiring and
And one thing you just reminded me of is
A piece of advice that Paul Graham who started y combinator
I'm gave us and gives all the startups
Is very simple
In a startup
Do one thing
Don't die
Keep going
Just figure out a way to keep going I think your story about
Stuart is so on point because it's just like Heat going you don't know like
What
Yuan cover or what
Other idea you'll stumble onto
Idfc if you haven't tried A and B 4
If you get off on a forget about it
But an end
Be mindful of a folks in this audience who are early-stage entrepreneurs
There are times when
It's better to kind of packet in or pivot or give up on
That idea and accept the failure and move on right
Yes probably
I think it's also worth
Remembering that
The way that our service started
We thought the big Grand idea
Wizz Air Beds For conferences
And we actually start it was very laughable thank you
We thought that
We were going to be at an event website where conference is it sold out
People can inflate an air bed in their living room
And that was the big idea so
Our next iteration
For South by Southwest in 2008 was literally conference website
After the dove that launched
We regrouped
And listen to people's feedback and only wants to give the DNC
And that flopped
Let me watch the fourth time a year after that
And that's where the numbers finally started to click the product Market actually had a fit
And so
I think the important part there is a
We were constantly listening iterating
We got wrong four times
In a row
The good news though is that you can watch and it's a dud you can watch it again because nobody knew about the first one so
Today is not easy
It was easy more people would do it
So like their tastes like
Psychological
Strength
To stick with it
Even when there's no hope in sight and when spreadsheets tell you to do something else
But is that an inherent
Quality or is that something that can be learned
I think an absolute be learned
My experience
I've looked back in my life I've seen I've ever has a pattern
That whenever I've been
Uncomfortable with something
I-10 not all the time but I tend
See that as an invitation to engage in
So freaking sample
I was reminded recently was back on rizzi's campus a couple weeks ago for a one-night weekend
And I was
Why can't I campus I remembered that
How uncomfortable I was public speaking
At that time in my life
Could not get in front of audience I was terrified sweaty
Palms of a nervous shaking car
A common feeling
Totally right on and I knew that about myself and so I purposefully signed up
To be a tour guide on campus
Because I knew it would force me to be in front of people and 1/2 Bossier therapy some
I didn't know that
Okay
So I think that's one of the
See what you would force yourself to confront things that you weren't comfortable with and that's sort of how you practiced
This this kind of always do that
There are times where
There's something in front of Mike I don't want to do that I want to talk to a person I'm nervous and intimidated
They're more important me that about like whatever the excuses that goes on your brain yeah
Like
I think an entrepreneur can reframe those things sake
Opportunity
Yeah
You really describe the
Emotional rollercoaster
Of of doing this and in something that
So many founders
Experience and just kind of grind through it even even if it's difficult to put this in context for everybody so
Over the years
Restart you do everything
So what do we do every goal in the company
I remember the earliest days
Realize
He already has our service and we probably need a number for them to call if there's a problem
Enable
Last minute decision
I threw my number up on the website
As customer service
And I
My phone almost immediately started ringing
I'm from that point for the next probably
Gosh I don't know what year and a half
I was very closely associated customer service
Eventually we hired a team
And they took it over and I got to
Get out of little bit
But the people would call like in the middle of the night
Hey I'm trying to check into my place in Berlin and
I can't find the host how do I get the keys and I have to like go scramble get to put my laptop with their account like
Like 3 in the morning in San Francisco
Just remind another story where
I'm about to go to bed at 11 tonight I am just so tired
And we're still working at her apartment at this point
And I'm about to turn the computer off
And I got houses check the Gmail inbox one more time
I'm about to close it out I hit refresh and sure enough right of the top there's a big bold black
Email
Subject line
But this is like help with like 12! Voice I click on it sure enough
It's this couple young couple in their 20s
Checking into the marina
Here in San Francisco there's summer in the marina there lost their host isn't answering the phone or phone doesn't work they found wife at a cafe near
Nearby
They said
Standing at this intersection
Of like Laguna and something
And so
I just
Jumping my Jeep
And I drive to the intersection
It's at night
It's 11 it's dark
Dena street lights
I'm driving slow with headlights on
And sure enough
On the corner
I see a couple of it
You know the big roller bags
Oh my God I have a scarf in like
I just like
That's them
So I pull up in a window
And heading out The Meadows coming so it wasn't like this random guy in a car
I said hey it's Joe I'm here I made it
And
I'm at this point I'm like
When you get the car will find a place for you but I had no option
To take them to I'm just like
We're going to make this up as we go here
And so
We start driving back to our apartment and I'm talking to how was your trip really sorry about this
We'll get to the bottom of it don't worry
And
As I'm driving back
I realize there's a
I friend-zoned apartment below as an extra bedroom cuz room had moved in yet
The only thing is it wasn't furnished
I think I myself okay I've got a room
How do I get it furnished
The clock is ticking here we're almost back to the apartment they think I have a solution for them but I don't
And
I get them in the apartment I take bring up the living room in like a beverage of some kind
And it said just hang here for a minute I'll get the room ready for you
Meanwhile
I Blitz down the hall
And
I ripped the bed sheets off my bed
And I grabbed my mattress
And I
Baguette through the hallway thank God they couldn't see this part
And I bring it downstairs I've been corresponding with my friend apartment
And
I get in the room I got to go to
Biggest earthquake
They make the bed I run back upstairs to
The couple
I say your room will be ready in just a minute
And then stay in the room and their stay in San Francisco in just one amazing
Joe gebbia join me live on stage at the how I built this Summit in San Francisco
Happened this past October
Yerba buena Center for the Arts
We got two more episodes from the summit coming up
Keep an eye on
Podcast feed
And check out our Facebook page for a new bonus video from another Summit speaker Morra aarons-mele
She's the author of the book
Hiding in the bathroom
And you spoke at the summit about networking for introverts
And thanks for listening to today's episode was produced by Casey Herman with music composed by rub teen Arab Louis
I got rise and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week