Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey just a quick thing before we start Today Show
I have some very exciting news to share
Our first-ever how I built this 1-day Summit
Sponsored by American
Express
The Summit
Will take place on
October 16th
San Francisco's yerba buena Center
For the Arts
You have a chance to
To hear from and interact with some of the world's most in
Hiring entrepreneurs
Like Airbnb Joe gebbia
Katrina Lake of Stitch
John Zimmer of Lyft
And many more
Will have breakout session
With experts and
Guides but most importantly
The summit will be a chance to meet other innovators and builders
People
Like you
Go to npr.org
/ Summit
To find out more and to get your tooth
Websites
So you guys a launch
Hotplace.com
Lowes.com
Set the classic every grandfather clock. Com very hot category online
People searching for that
We did
Robin PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
They go
Online search for
Bird houses
LED two College roommates
That inspired Wayfarer
E-commerce company that sells almost five
Billion dollars worth of HomeGoods
Soap
Pretty much everyone we had on the show
Had a passion for a product
That they needed to put out into the world
Lara merriken believe the world needed Larabars
Jeni Britton Bauer was convinced that her ice cream
Going to change how people thought of
About ice cream
Even Jimmy Wales founder of Wiki
Wikipedia thot
Everyone should have
Mastiff
Free knowledge
But I'm here to tell you that
That is not always the case
In fact sometimes the product isn't
Drive the starters
What really drives them
Is the Challenger rather
Solvang
The challenge
And that's basically the story behind Wayfair
Neither Steve conine nornir in shop
Don't that strongly about home furnishings
But they did
Feel like people should have
Choices
No matter where they lived
Because there was a time when
If you lived in say Evansville Indiana
You couldn't easily get the same type of
Cool copy table or sofa that someone in San Francisco or New York
Note today
Particular article or new but back in the early 2000s
It was a revolution
And today
Wayfair sales almost
Five billion dollars worth of his stuff
Every year
I was actually the third Company Steve and neeraj started together
Teenagers at a summer camp for Math and Engineering nerds in the early 1990s
They quickly lost touch
Almost a year later
As if fate herself was watching over these guys
They both ended up in
His first years
Add Cornell
Assigned to dorm rooms
On the same corridor
Did you know both of you in each other the other one was going to Cornell
No it really kept in touch
So I think it was
It was a surprise
How you been this past year
So were you friends like right away
Yeah we were part of it you know I think when your freshman year you start to have a small group of
Of friends that you
Connect with
And spend a lot of
Your time with it and we were
In that group together
And then Junior your near tonight start
Country a lot closer and live together that he
Junior interior
With it with a few other
Peapod
Yeah
Did you guys hear tissue did you and Steve used to talk about
Starting a business
When you are in college
I don't know that we were talking about it per se but
Last semester at Cornell
We took an entrepreneurship course
This is one of our electric
And in this entrepreneurship
Of course one of the things yet to do is
Credit business plan
And what really happened is through the process of doing the project which is creating a business plan we basically start our first
Yeah it was 95 and it was a very early isn't the internet the Netscape browser
Can I come out
That year or idea was actually
Developing internet Direct
Tree services
And we can try to pitch company is something is five bucks I have a listing on in our internet directory
Of course we look at us like we're nuts a few would say Hey kid that's interesting but
A homepage like all the time
Could you help me build a website
And you know baby was different and what would that cost me and so
The business turned into an internet Consulting business that film sites
Four companies
And you can kind of knew how to do the basics because you were engineering students
Exactly so you go from Project to project and
Cummings were trying to move very quickly
You know different people would ask other people then who could we hire so I'm so far who won the few shops that actually done thing
When you would meet when you guys are going to meet
The clients did you ever get that feeling from any of them
They look at you and think
What is like a 22 year old
Yo we did it we're both we're both pretty good sales guy.
I don't remember that being
Smacking me too hard
I think that either the prices were charging versus like what they would be looking at
Consultancies I think a lot of these bigger shops
Look at it just like
Play money where they're kind of like well whatever how bad can it go to the
A couple costume
NTR Donuts Forest
If it works out phenomenal it doesn't work out you know
Whatever we have
I guess by that summer
You graduated from
Poor now and then
You decide to move
To Boston to to launch the company
Yes sir we had
What happened very quickly as it started was clear while it's because not really the right place
To be
New York and Siri would be very logical place to be but we both had more of an affinity
Play for Boston and we thought from Boston we could easily work with your clients would have you so
We actually decided
Removed
The Boston
At the beginning of that summer how are you guys managing I mean if you were getting
Project
Coming in
There's only one of the two of you to do the work how are you managing all
You're working pretty hard to get her working on her.
We're basically
We set up the living room we got an apartment
And that we put coins on who got the
The bigger bedroom
And then he want it and the living room was basically the office
Sprite soda
Decks with a temperature and wework
How much was fine cuz they're working from like 7 a.m. to midnight and then you're sleeping for a few hours and doing it again
Exciting
I feel like you guys were
Building something really big
Yeah yeah it was for their first year out of college and it's over young full of energy it's very very good
The internet and get everyone serve got their eyes on it looking at how in the potential of Technology
Envisioned
Quickly
Awesome to be in the middle of
What you guys called company
Spinners fidget spin the web
World Wide Web at the time it really goes Spinners you know if you're a spider spinning web
Spin the web like a
Buy Terro that's clever
So how long did Spinners last
But for years
So we started it in the summer of 1995
I guess it's three years with fall of 1998 to maybe a little over 3 years
When we sold it
He's a little over 3 years
We're about 40 people when we sold it
And the Internet and heat it up a lot
And they were starting to be some much larger consultancies doing the type of work we were doing
And we didn't think we could scale is fast
These other ones so we opted in the end
Celta 1
What would you guys self
We sold it for
Competition CashNet
I think it was 5,000
Castle
The cash is that sound right
I think I've been a little more than that I think we might have each gotten like her
Half a million
And then
And some stock Equity that was worth a few million bucks
But then kind of a
The.com boom kind of went up tremendously and then
Came all the way
Like all the way
Down to zero
That's where it is
So you guys didn't really walk away with
The whole lot of money
From from
Enter
No no
Merrill statement that says I was worth 27 million when I was probably like
24 year old 6 months later
At one point you were worth
27 million dollars when when you're injured
What is an n
It was really some paper it was just on paper but boy what a good lesson to learn as a young fellow
So this is like the early 2000
Mm
And
And the two of you against decide to
Start a new business
We did yeah we had a lot of
Fun and success in the first one to Die the song
Easy let's
The game 2001
And we're like thinking of different ideas and we're not sure what we want to do
Long story short we came across this idea Round mobile
2001 was still pretty early
For mobile phone
But we found a lot of companies were starting to have a lot of mobile phones but they weren't really managing well because
That effectively having a thousands of phones but they reach a different
Contracts and they were on the wrong ones paid too much
For some two little brothers so
Our idea was we would build a software platform
That would allow the companies to better manage all their phones and their contracts
And we thought overtime we could build that in
The basically being a virtual carrier focus on
Enterprise's what's a virtual carrier
Virgin Mobile in the EU
UK where either use a virgin brand name and actually operate on top of
Bridget
Tom's Network
It's a different branding on top of
Got into the consumer feels like they're buying Virgin Mobile they don't provide British Telecom.
What was the company called simplify mode
Simplified
Yes but you just call up companies that hey can I talk to the person who handles your mobile phones
Yeah I'm Steve Supply Mobile I'm you know
Carly great offering help me save money rule phones would you
If you're not love to talk to whoever is that for you
Medication to get someone right yeah we did have one
Keep flashing customer that we had lined up
Who is very interested in doing what
What is Merrill Lynch
Yeah
Yeah they have big fun spot
And so
That was looking Wicked and then unfortunately what happened in 2001
Was
New site September 11
It wasn't huge
Impact everybody in and particularly for financial service Commision
McKay's Merrill Lynch they lost use of their headquarters in the world financial center
And they are priorities obviously had
Dramatically change
So
With that we lost or the flagship customer that weighed anchor to round
Answer the combination of everything causes that
Become much less bullish on
That the odds of it succeeding
She's interesting because
Many people that have been on the show
Have had similar experiences but they've said you know what time we just kept at it
Shadowsocks
And then the second year was the last sake but we just kept at it and
It eventually took off like a rocket
But you guys
Just because I came to the conclusion that was not going to work
Yeah I mean we were in a it was a business where you look around and we are the only one
Doing it
Scary Spotify as well and I think he thought about the market potential in the odds
What we've learned in the intervening year
I mean we spent by the last
Three months of that business
Literally just pounding the yellow page
Just coming in and just like taking rejection all day long trying to see if we
We could try really hard to try to sell it
And I think we've been a big fan of saying like
You got to start with a sale if you can't sell anything you don't have an idea
And so being after validating that I guess we
It was that rejection
Hartford
For you to handle with it
Humiliating
You where you
After a while
Not
Too bad of a lot of fun I remember might my dad gave me some advice he was he was a stockbroker
Is it look when you're going to go in and call us in the Yellow Pages
This is like the thing of suzhou
Is it your goal needs to be
When you get 30 rejection
Is that what you look at it every rejection is a good thing
Just get to closer
So keep you motivated working at it
You learn alot more from when things are going bad
Also I think we saw
We both fight went out and started thinking about just
Job interview nephew
Places in serafino taking time maybe I should go to mortgage
Did that Friday we both do
That's a little while and then
How do I slept being explored
Mobile kind of like
Fizzled out
Did you guys both were started
Approach your 30s
Bright
Pretty young
Did you have a sense of what you were going to do next
Of course you can get in the furniture
Information on the internet
It's all that
So what did you guys do
China's business down
You're still thinking what's
Continue to work together
We went right back to the drawing board so we started looking at that point we got very removing my face but at this point
That's right side
Senior downstairs bedroom
Yeah that was living there because we got a brainstorm stuff right and then my girlfriend at the time moved up
From New York
And tell my honey is a great deal we can just live here in the deal was he bought the groceries
Nurseries in
That only lasts about 2 weeks ago before she decided that we really should get our own place
That was the end of the free rent
But what happened after simplify mobile what we do
Decided
We spent basically
The first couple months of 2002
We ended up talking to a lot of dick
Business owners and there's a steam that emerge
Because if you lived if you read the New York Times
Making Believe with a journalist said
You would have been left believing that e-commerce was
That was what all the Articles talked about
You know, he's a crash I think there was even at that time there was a lot of skepticism that
Amazon
As you know there were a lot of people talking about Amazon's
Imminent demise
And so
We got feeling about to go to work at we should start
Looking at internet ideas we know we know internet went to internet software she looking at ideas and then she look at other ideas that we think are just good
Business ideas working operators until we start making lists of ideas
We started looking at businesses that were for sale
Thing that maybe there's something small that we could buy with really grow and
Through that we ended up
Tripping over these Ecommerce websites that were for sale
And we would talk to the owner operator and they would you tell us how they're growing 20 or 30% year-over-year
E-commerce what were they selling
I remember there's one lady who was selling bird houses you're storing them in the garage everyday shoes
Take all the orders and collecting all the items out of the garage and packing them up and take him to the post office and selling them
Yeah Albert houses.com we found was really simple consumers and
Realize they could go online and search for any product category they want it
There were a lot of product categories like bird houses that are just not really available locally we could stay at
You want to buy a birdhouse locally where you live today
Where would you go if you want a decent selection
You go to
Like a local store can you find
Like two or three
Different bird houses in the nude
After
Pick one of them
Exactly
And yeah pretty basic Styles right cuz they're only going to have three or four
For rent in seoul
All the sudden people started realized why don't have to be stuck with that I can go online and find a hundred different
Exactly
I can order whatever I want I save the time of the trip the store
I'll show up in the mail
Super easy
And so
About a month's worth of research
Kind of help us figure that out
And so what we ended up doing
Is we end up deciding that there was a big opportunity and buying these but
So the first website we ended up launching
We launched the cycle racks and stands. Com
The very end of August
About year which was
TV stand speaker
Entertainment furniture
Did you have a particular passion for Auntie
Mechanical engineering at Cornell
These things are sent those days Yahoo on Yahoo search
You could type in terms they would tell you how many searches a month there were four that I am
And on some of the product comparison site they would tell you their top hundred categories
And so both of those terms run the top hundred search product
So people were looking for
TV and speakers why would they just go to their local
Like
The same thing about your selection of only two or three
Can't find a good song
What's the furniture stores want to focus on
Living room bedroom dining furniture
So where would you go
Yeah so wait till you you're thinking all right
Our first one is going to bring in a selfie
TV and speakers
Century I see where did you go where did you even go to
Find
Tri-City Christian
Well in the beginning what you do is you go online and then you look
Four companies that made them here also look at what the other online retailers
We're selling what brands do they have
Anybody audiophile magazine
Put through and see what brands are Irish
Did you just buy a bunch of
TV and speaker
Understand
Your apartment in Boston
No sew at the time there was a bunch of electronics.
Distributors that actually Woodstock
Small amounts of
Speaker stands until we initially started off buying
Through them so we'd buy out of their inventory so we had no inventory risks I was all Dropship.
Distributor
And somebody would
Go to Yahoo or Google and type in speaker stands and that was one of the things that would match
Exactly
They click into it ended
The Promised Land If you're looking for in a speaker stands
So when did you launch the website
August 29th
Mm
And how long before you had your first order
Hours
Yeah hours
When we come back
In stannes.com
Then all barstools.com then
Every grandfather clock. Com and on and on
Eventually
Turned into Wayfair
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to study
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuity
These can be a smart way to hedge Market
And earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions
Send a direct low-fee model
Learn more at gamebridge. Lives NPR
Game Bridge is not available
In all states
Welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Garage
It's 2002 and Steve are on their third business ID
They're selling TV stands on the internet
It's a site called rack
And stannes.com
And this is a time when a lot of people start eCommerce
Was dead
But neeraj and Steve
They thought it was very much a lot so they started to advertise Google had just launched
Switch is the keyword
Grandpa where you pay money for you better get to advertise
Underwrite your text ad and you'd basically pay per click
And we would track
Every time we got an order which advertising
Unit drove into weedeater bid those up
Forbid them down
They were non-productive
And what kind of advertisement
Were they with what they say
Libby text assistant you know largest selection available TV stand TV stands for less available
Braxton stamps.com
So if you are a consumer you click on this
And if you are adventurous in 2002 you would put your credit card into the computer
And then it would go to you guys and then you guys can order from one of these companies and then have that company
Need directly shipped to that
Customer exactly correct we launched at the very end of August so
September to Remember December the 4th month
December 2002
We did about $250,000 in sale out in the category
Racks and stands
And we grew to be
The one of the largest or the largest online seller in the category
And what happened is our supplier start telling us hey you know you've become my biggest online retailer of TV stands
Center speaker stands we're having
But you know
My other online guys sell more of my beds
Or matter only guys some more of my desk
And so we started learning
That in fact these other Furniture categories
Is that we hadn't Focus
That they were doing quite well online
End
I have to assume that
Just like getting us off the ground that expense
Sit right it didn't require a whole lot of capital
No didn't let me some computers wepay
I don't know $15 a month for hosting on a
Shared hosting platform
And we are computers in her office but it was very expensive we didn't pay ourselves
A dime
For the first
Year-and-a-half
To that was the big the biggest Leverage
Was that we didn't need to pay ourselves
And that we knew had also build the software and do the
Do that do that work with him to hire anyone
And did you did you have a guess
The number on website
Customer service number of the people who call in
You know I don't complain or phone lines in my house
Set that it would ring
Right near my bed
And you were
Like one hand you were like programming the technology the other hand you were
Hang up the phone yeah well this is the beauty of that set up those nearest nice little tiny table and we have 4 phone lines your kind of juggling for phones
Can we take
Customer calls and
Let's hope we get off a call with a customer and we change what we're working on that
I dated like it I'd probably change what I was programming
I feel like we should be like you go on a few products
And we do I got customers asking for that she just figure out
Restore additive
Recite those two activities
Rapidly made this a lot better and it got to where we couldn't juggle
4 phone lines
So once you start selling racks and stands
I do pretty well what's the next
Category
Mounts TV mounts we were surprised at what happened in that timeframe also that
Timer
Is a two different things
TV mounts
That we're not widely available so we had a gym and you want to hang some TV mounts like you don't know where else to buy Amazon
The other thing that happened is flat screen TV started running popular
Yeah and some people want to hang those on the wall
And so our timing on that was quite good so we
Tell us huge sales sort of start
I'm kind of momentum so then we built the site just for that
Have every type you know was it called
Mounts and more
Gore.com really matter what you call it right because you would make her at the search engine
Brilliant branding and high traffic
Was primarily driven by Baidu search
If I did the advertising would do
Paid search than other forms of advertising that we would do so
The key to the name of the site wasn't so much that it was something someone with type in or know what member board
The picket over other items
There's more that it made sense as a place you would go for
This item for TV mounts and the and then have that too
That it's normally while we were the mount Kings of the internet
God
In N so then what will connect
Then we I think we started a new beach headed outdoor furniture
And so we started cycletique wicker and more
Best outdoor furniture
I mean it's so interesting because you didn't have to build a brick and mortar store and you didn't have to
Stata timer
With a sandwich board
Say come on 10% off today triarch example if you will just meet you
Put this out on the internet
You figured out the search
A search work
And
People that was the sandwich board
Taken any outside investment
Anil at that time because
The revenue from
Each expanding
Website was
Peopling the business
It was this business is cool as fish from that day
Earlier. It runs a positive cash
How so you know
Cuss words with chaos right away and we don't have
Cafe suppliers
For 30 to 45 days
And so you had this kind of natural cash cushion
So yes it was
It was weird self-funded
Very well
Do you remember
How much
But I knew you were doing unilateral bite like
Mm
2002 was our first year we did about 700,000
1 mm
3 was our second year I think we're about to
7 million
And then the following year 2004 I think we had 20
I mean you probably
I could just hire tons of people tons and tons of people fast
Yeah so we started hiring
As early as January 2003 we heard a couple people then
If I ended that year with you know
15 people or something like that in the end then
That became the model to grow is
So you know we wouldn't be reinvesting aggressively by hiring people
That we could
Expanding the selection and expanding the categories
Which then give us more things to advertise
Which then would get us more customers you know and then I was a virtuous cycle and we would take
The money that resulted and we would invest that in the growing the team to keep driving it
Pictures of Jessie when people asked you like what are you up to what are you doing these days would you say
I'm selling I'm TV stands
How would you describe
Never one time I was very
In describing what we're doing it and a lot of Indians in the United States
Doctors listen to the doctor
No no no
So I tok show no I'm not a doctor
Furniture
Silences
The conversation
That's a good way to wrap up the conversation
So obviously when you were doing it
Wayfair but at this point
Used
You guys are killing it
CSN stores right
Country we adopted that great name CSN stores
Did you get a bunch of Consultants to help you figure out that name
We can get it for 12 bucks a year and there is no Trace
I think you're just came up with it was our initials kind of conglomerate 909 Steve
It was a generic
We could use across any category you know it helps with to keep
One is we need a company name
That you know sort of implied we had a lot of
Tell Brady I didn't want to just named it after one of the names right
The second is a lot of the suppliers very traditional compass
So when we will go to like the High Point Furniture
And approach
Suppliers you want to be able to get into a conversation with
And during this time frame 2002-2003 2004
They're still not very
Keenan e-commerce
They're not they're not dead set against it but their experiences have been poor
And so what happens when your badge to CSN stores and where you're based over in Boston or in Boston over right in Back Bay
We have an office on Newbury Street oh great I'll wait with you guys cuz I know well
Really focus on entertainment Furniture Double D karaoke Carrie Brandt this brand that brand so the brand
You get into a conversation and
Until what it would it would be interested in what would really
Peter said in the selection we could go do well for these reasons that
And they say oh well you know how big is your store is at that point you'd you'd say you know you'd be honest
We actually we sell online
And if you had to discuss online too early in the conversation you get kicked out of
They didn't watch you they don't want to
E shop.com
But now they've got into a 20-minute conversation with you and you sound very rational and you're carrying a bunch of good brands
Recwell
You know I don't really do much e-commerce business but maybe
Maybe this doesn't make sense
Let's have a little more.
To the generic name helps you get deep enough into a conversation for them to get really
Consider and understand
Which is really important.
To read some of the websites
You guys launched
Think they're amazingly
Straightfromthea.com I'm assuming that sold hot
Yeah
I'm all barstools.com
So why you think that song
Flights
Every grandfather clock
A very hot category online
Painful the ship
Who knew people searching for that
We did you can look online
That was a mean you would find categories and then you would
Basically
And you
Started to build a huge business that way
Yeah
You got. 250 these
How are you managing
250 different website
It would be a very good Tech platform that was built around a d if we have
Centralized product catalog
And then when calls came in our
Call system would tell you exactly where the calls coming into seeing you how to answer
The phone
Did you ever have a situation where somebody call the customer service number
For a
Orexin
Stannes.com and then said
And then throw thanks you I'm still looking around and then call the car
Customer service number for email
Mouse.com and then gets got the same customer service rep
Oh yeah when I was just your hard work isn't it
T-Rexes dance.com
They usually didn't put it together
It was fun
They just they wouldn't put it together
By 2000
Can you hit almost
400 million dollars in sale
You'd almost 5 million test
And and you like this this aggregation of
50 website
Like nobody would have known what CSN stores
Necessarily why is no one knew who you guys were I mean people just
New
All barstools.com or my dinner plate
Yeah they didn't do that well
Yeah I crazy to you guys at that
Who's coming in or will you just
Too busy to even stopping
I mean it's like watching your kid grow up a little bit like it's just happening so incrementally and you just following the
Play Buffy
They've got this working well
That
You know didn't I don't I mean when you step back from it
Huge
You trying to do
To do that too much
Cuz it gets scary
And how about your you're
Need a relationship
With a tooth
The two of you I mean
It's just you guys are wired
Nnss way where you just
Control that you get along and you don't
Have any tension I mean it
It's good
Crazy that you're still
After all these years from Lake High School year
Do you work in together
No we
Cassius interesting
When we were when we first started working together
Remember having
Argument
He was usually right he was telling me something I needed to hear that
But I really didn't want to hear it
And of course my motion
I remember having to walk out of the room
I got to go walk around the block
Cursing anime
My breath out of me
For half an hour
We got into this business you know we were a lot more
Sure as individuals and it been through a lot of that
Had both gained and lost a lot of money together and so I think
You know greed is one of the things I can create a lot of tendon in the heart
Membership I think we gotten
Passed a lot of that
And we'd also gotten to where we
Valued each other
Advice edit got
And come to the point where like look I trust will you tell him
Because he cares in the actual
Is trying to make me better make us better
As a compass
Yeah nearest would what do you think
I I think the
Two key things I think I've always helped this one is that we gravitate to different areas
The business in the second is
We definitely have always found each other to be very hardworking and very committed to it I think those are
Not be taken for granted because I do think
They those traits may not be as common
As I
In 2011 I guess
It was when you
Decided that you
You needed to scale this either
Bigger and this is the first time you
Actually took in outside investment
Why did you allow Venture capitalists get involved in
Andis company
We're definitely ones who would rather to
Responded ourselves self-funded business and have it funded self
The challenge became in 2011
We believe the big opportunity to
Continue the trajectory into really capture the big opportunity we needed to build a brand
And the amount of capital we thought
To go through that migration in to build a brand that it would
Take was not an amount
Cuz you did not have a
CSN was not
Consumers didn't know that brand it wasn't
You want a brand that one you know you think hey I need to shop I want to redo my living room
You want someone to think I go to waste
If you wanted to be a top of Mind brand
Category writing that is not
That's not easy to do
And even if
If you figure out how to do it it's not an expense
By any stretch
So
We wanted to be able to do that
The other
Just my dynamic
Happiness investors
It started to change their pitch to being
Are purely from we want to invest in by part of your company to
Hey woman passing by prettier company invested in
But will let you got to take some cash off a table
As well and you know it at that point in our lives
What we both got married
Ikea
Be able to take it
A bit of money
OpenTable
Department
Those things kind of tied together
See you had
250 website
Under
CSN stores
How did you come up with the idea for wife
But we knew
Knew we wanted a different name the CSN
Names using first name was difficult for people to remember recall
We've always been relaxing use Consultants but we'd we hired a branding agency
And they came up with the name Wayfair
Skin a tomato word
The two word Wednesday are we like
The Domain name
Available
It said you were going to go out and spend you know
Millions trying to buy domain names from people
You can just register it
Be Off to the Races
So it took about a year for all these
Consolidate
To the consumer Wayfair seems like a
Rams new thing right
It did ya
Yeah it just kind of came out of nowhere and people are kind of like
Place to shop for home
It and it's
The fact that you guys got into HomeGoods
It had to do with me with
What type of people were
Searching for the
You could have
Ends up being a company
It sold like personal grooming Prada
That's right
The one thing I would say
You know home the beauty of home
Most categories
People Want it All by the same thing as you
Write 17
Double a batteries by Duracell or Energizer the private label
There's only a couple categories were a huge selection
Is really
Puppies were Visual and
Anesthetic considerations are very Paramount where people want unique items
And the two are really fashion and home
And we
Basically by focusing on home
With the logistics are quite complicated in different
Where there are no brands
Where the visual merchandising is critical where people have a very unique Style
There's a lot
Value can added
Retailer
If you're in any of these other category
Certainly there's a big business there
But that's effectively the business that the Walmarts in the Amazons in the target
Costco's
They're all in that business
Selling the same exact items
And
You can
Fight that out and try to find an advantage but typically the advantages either in price
Speed is really no other way to do it
And the beauty and home
Is that it's it's more multi
The faceted and it doesn't
What if someone
A winner in the other categories it doesn't automatically make you a winner at home
Your public company you are listed on the stock exchange right
And the company
I believe is today is valued
Billion
Billion dollars
But you guys
I I've read that you're still not
Strand of weed
Profit does that Maxine matter
The time being
Well obviously a company needs to be able to generate cash
Gdb run out of cash
She got a business
So that's really important
I think what folks confuse is
A company that's willing to reinvest in smart ways
With one who fundamentally has
Business model problem
And it's not going to be a
Successful
In our case the United States
It has been profitable
You know if you look read our financials we break out the adjusted ebitda International
Yeah
The u.s. is 90% of our business and that's been profitable for the last 5 quarters
And if you look at that you'll then see while International losing money while International is much smaller we're certainly investing a lot of money
I need to build that up and rectangle be
Very big and successful
But we're very fortunate position
If you have we have 600 million dollars in the bank
We have the ability to invest in these very ambitious
Things that help customers
I think in that case you're actually better off being an aggressive investor in
To the experience and making experience better and better cuz you learn more loyalty and more custom
Could you imagine obviously
Pussycats
Pretty younger in the mid-forties
Is there other things you could do conceivably do for life
Could you imagine an Amazon or Walmart
You know coming to you and saying hey
Guys who want to buy them
We're going to get you
X billion dollars
Did you ever imagine
Accepting that are green today
You need to be proven right so
You mean all those folks you've course
Have conversations with anyone who wants our conversation last year when we did 4.7 billion in sales
We grew 40%
Your private well so if you take a number like 4.7 billion dollars in sales to grow it at something
Decent sized growth rate some high growth rate
Are the companies getting bigger at a fast rate
And if you believe you can do a lot for the customer that is more than anyone else can do will why wouldn't a container grow too fast
That's really super early days if in fact we can be the best
So it would be very premature to think about selling it
If we think we can win
How much of
Success of
Your partnership
End end
The businesses you built
Is because of your intelligence and your skills and how much should be
Just locking serendipity
John Deere G
Scale I just showed you
Look to the office daily
You know it's obviously a bit about I don't I don't know that there are dramatic
Intellectual skill differences
Inhumans
General Tso I think it tends to be you know your ability to
Focus and keep doubling down on your own
Believing in yourself and your work ethic and in
16 to focus on an errand of set of things
You can win
And weave
Been good at 10
Dating
Focused on that
And not listening to
Tell other people that try to go try and do other things
Serendipity and luck but we play a little bit of a roll right so I think that definitely is a PC you think about it we
Happened to be in college at the last Metro
College rapping to be the beginning of the commercial internet commercial internet has created a huge amount of
Well it was a different point in time where there been no opportunity no
But that would be opportunity
Would it be as big maybe maybe not would have been different possibly would have been as well suited to us I don't know you know
Fighting is a mix in there
And I think
I do think a lot of it is is how hard you go after something and how pragmatic
With all this
List of the Home Furnishings that you've done or either
Any good at interior design
Lyrics like to think he has a designer
You like the comment on design
I very clean modern aesthetic in
In my house and he has a much more traditional
Luck your wife
If I kill me when she hears me say that
Exactly
Going to find this clip and send it to her
Nearest shop
Steve conine
Founders of Wayfair
The website now offers over 10 million different items
For sale stuff
They used to sell more than 250 different website
Weirdest domain in USA
What's a rooster decor
Call rooster decor.com
That's that's why the best one yet
Rooster Decor rooster
Vases pictures planner Scott
You name it
It's got a rooster we're going to try to find it in stores didn't sell it to you
Maybe I'm weird
Someday you let you visit someone who's got a lot
Please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things you're built
But first I quit thanks to one of our sponsors
Microsoft
A digital workspace work teams can
Create collaborate and communicate authentically
Bring together your chats
Meetings files and apps all in
Place
Visitoffice.com
Learn more
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
Understory
Starts in 2009 when carin luna ostaseski
Was working in marketing
New York City after work one day a friend asked me if I wanted to grab a glass of scotch
And I said no I don't drink Scotch that's
That's my grandfather
But the friend took her to one of those places that
Specializes
In Scotch and that night I tried four different brands and I instantly fell in love with a brand called Oban 14
And I loved
The beauty of the nuances and the complexities of the spirit
Until almost instantly Karen became a scotch Drinker she started reading about it and then
I'm collecting it and then eventually evangelizing about it
I became that friend Tina that was always trying to convince everyone else so you should try Scott's and everyone always said the same thing
You know it burns my nostrils it tastes like gasoline it's too expensive Joker in begin
I already have all this amazing scotch in my
Personal Collection
Maybe I could just
Blend my own
One is designed specifically to change the way that you think about Scott
Very smooth approachable
I have a lot of vanilla and caramel and citrus and just a little bit of smoke
So starting out
In her kitchen I would take two brands that I thought would go well together and I'd take a measuring cup and 3 glass
Isis and Eric put
When that was measured 50/50 another 25 75 and the other 75 25 and then I have to renew blends
And I did this quite a lot and I came up with some really bad not so great tasting Blends like even to summon know that just
Dump it before even tasting it
But eventually after about six months of experimenting Korean came up with the blind you really liked
At this point she was living in San Francisco and she started to call and emailed dozens of Master blenders
In the only country that makes scotch
Witches Scotland the time and time again I just got so many nose in fact they were a dinos dinos
Boys Club more than anything right especially being
Of all things an American woman living in California
I think from a third-party I heard oh yes that's that crazy American woman that's trying to create a scotch brands
Finally the 81st person was the one that said yes we can help you
It was actually two sisters that they work for their fathers Scotch whiskey importing business and it was Justice
Amazing moment that I realized that this can actually come together
Corinthian launched a Kickstarter campaign to raise $48,000
And use the money to blend her first bottles of scotch
And it's doing pretty well it's one of you prestigious challenges is be that brand that have been there for centuries
Sia Scotch is now on sale in a thousand stores around the us and is on track to bring in
$600,000 this year
Oh and the name Sia it comes from Scottish Gaelic to the name Sierra means the number 6 and they're sick
Whiskey's in the blender and a friend recently pointed out to me that it could stand for
Scotch is
Awesome
If you want to find out more about
Karin and her Scotch you can visit our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us yours
Story go to build. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to our show this week if you want
Want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org please also subscribe
Drive to our show Apple podcast or however you get your podcast you can also write us that's HIV t
Npr.org you can tweet us at how I built this show was produced this week by Rachel f*** her
Teen Arab Louis composed music thanks also teneva grandson has meshkinpour Thomas Liu and Jeff
Rogers our intern I'm Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile friendly email temp
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com