Support for the how I built this Summit comes from American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible Funding Solutions
PetSmart Savi way to fund your business
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Visit americanexpress.com
Business
Hey it's guy here and today we're releasing our final episode from
How I built this
Summit
San Francisco
And today's conversation
Is with Lisa Price the founder of Carol's Daughter
If you don't know her story that you may want to listen to The Original Episode 1
Ran back in June of last year
It's an incredible story about Lisa began making lotions and body creams in her kitchen
In the 1990s
Geneva brand after her mom Carol
And eventually
Turn it into a major line of beauty products
Primarily for women of color
And then
She sold her company to L'Oreal about
4 years ago it's a classic story about starting small and growing big
Am I spoke to Lisa at the summit I wanted to ask you about that and about some of the hard lessons she learned
And when she was expanding her company
One woman show
Into a major brand
Thank you for coming Lisa
One of the biggest beauty products brands that was enacted discovered mainly by women of color
What's up with the idea
I'm take us back to the early 90s
How did you
Had the start how'd you get the idea
Well initially It Started From Me making
Fragrances
I have
Always loved fragrance for as long as I can remember
And I read this article about prince who
It's my favorite musician of all time
Yes thank you
And
In this article it said that he used to blend different fragrances on different parts of his body
To create a unique set
And I was like okay I'm sold that's a great idea
And I started
To blend fragrances for yourself for myself
And then I realized that I needed
To have moisturizers in the center
It's because that's how you layer your fragrance that's how your fragrance laugh
And I started to
Add the fragrances to
Lotions that I would buy at the drugstore
But they didn't blend well
They would get messy
So then I started to make my own
The kitchen stove
And then I began to share it with friends and family
And my mom said
Why don't you sell it the Saint Mary's Flea Market
That was May 25th 1993
I mean you were buying like off
The Shelf cocoa butter and melting it down and
Like in your kitchen like a on the stove for Amazon Prime
Peace and crickets were not as easy to find as they are today
And if you remember the episode that Lisa was on at the time you start to sell out of your apartment and people body here and there
Still was your side hustle for like 3 or 4 years
At at what
Point cuz a lot of people here
They kept side hustles going I met many of them amazing amazing products that people are trying to create
At what point did you were you able to take the mental leap and say
You know what
I'm going to turn my side hustle into my main my main gig
Well in 1996
I was
Pregnant with my first son Forest
Teesnow 22
But he was born in March of 96
I basically looked at
My schedule
And
Figure it out
That if I try to
Continue working
Along with trying to take care of a newborn
I would basically have to give my paycheck to the babysitter
So it just seemed to make sense
At that time too
Let
The job go
And give the business a try
Since I would
Just had my paycheck to someone else anyway
Were you
I mean
Were you worried about making ends meet
At that point I mean
Is it because you have a pretty decent paying job in in TV and presumably you weren't making as much
Watch from from the
Lotions at that point
I wasn't as worried
When I first started
Because it made such large
Medical Center
Where it got
Scary was about a year later
When my husband lost
His job
And then it was just a business
To take care of every
That's what it really.
That's scary and at that point we purchase
Home as well
So now we had a mortgage
A second baby on the way
And all of a sudden he had no
And we managed our expenses as best we could we can be very a frugal people
But we need to be
And thankfully it worked
And the business continue to grow and within about
Six to eight months
My husband Gordon was working again
But that's 6 to 8 months without him working and with another child on the way it was
How was your
What is the idea what's your vision to turn this into a
Massive company or did you think
This is going to be something for me my friends and anyone who wants to buy it
I did not think of it being a mess
Company at all I really thought that
What I defined as
Success in the beginning
Was
That I would make enough money
That I could contribute to
My household
And I maybe I would run a business out of a garage
Yeah
But I thought we'd get here like a bigger place
And I did and I didn't think that I would
Be traveling and
Bandito doing the different things that I have to do
You know for the business today
And and had no idea
You
Got something happened in 2003 which is
Oprah Winfrey profile
Put you on the show
Ten Years After
Amazing
Ten years after a church
Church flea market
She puts you on the show it was it was
So what happened after that did it
Demi was just like
Crazy
Spike
It wasn't crazy like a lot of
People think like a lot of people think that because you meet Oprah Winfrey and you shake her hand that when you shake her hand
A wire transfer takes place and you're suddenly a millionaire
That doesn't happen
But
Our website actually crash
We told the people that were hosting it is going to be a lot of traffic
Oh we're ready we're ready they were
But we were still able to capture a lot of orders capture a lot of
Email addresses
And it was
A good build
But like a
Steady bill
It wasn't something that we couldn't manage
And it continued
The Climb
So I appeared on her show in June of 2000
And
Then pee
People magazine had been thinking about doing something on me and that cinched it they were like oh yes
We're doing a spread on you
And the show re aired in October
The People magazine article came out in November and I had a book deal
By the top of the following year
It was a very good fourth quarter
So was it sort of like
Just a spike in the 4th quarter p&l
Well it didn't fall off and how did you manage that
That level of scaling I mean all of a sudden
You got to hire people you've got to
You could expand your inventory you got to
Increase the production what was good about it was the show wasn't about
A specific product
So it was about women who started business
So they just profiled the business
Oprah happened to mention
The foot cream
That I had a foot lotion and I had a foot butter
I didn't have a foot cream
But what we did
We put the foot products on
The first
Page of the website so when you went to
To the website
Foot products were there
And we had a week
Between when I taped it and when the show aired
So the staff just Beast up production on foot butter and foot lotion
And we were ready
Well when you started it was you and like a stove top
And
And the table at the flea market by 9th but you know by 2003-2004 how many
How many people working with you
About 20
And then how big did it eventually get
By the time we were acquired by L'Oreal we had about 40
Two employees
So what does that mean
What was that like to go from just you and a kitchen to overseeing 42 people I mean was that
It's a different Beast
So it's very different
If you're not in HR
Person
Or a
A manager in that way it's a very different skill-sets it was something that I had to learn how
How to do
Because you sort of assumed that
Everyone's going to follow your work ethic and your styling
You're just going to tell people that this is what they have to
To do when they're just going to do it
And then you have to remember wait what did I do when I had a job
Did I always listen to my boss
No
Yeah
I'm the boss
Now and then
This is their job
They don't like
Got it
Did you eat a one when you were on the show I remember you saying something like
That
As we grew in
Sort of felt like
The company kind of got away from
In a little bit oh yeah you remember remember what why what happened
Well I had investors who had come into
The company
And
Then we had equity
Partners in and when you have Equity partners
More money comes in
As things get very professional so
Now
Either sitting at the table you have someone who's been in sales beauty sales for 15 years
Can someone who's been in operations for 10 years and
Someone that's Run Beauty companies for the last
12 years
And there was all of this
Experience at the table that I didn't
And half
And
I decided that I was going to take the position of
I'm not going to sit at the head of the
The table I'm going to sit at the table with everyone
Because there's so much that I need to learn
And unfortunately
That was proceed
Saved as
A weakness
And it was perceived as me choosing to take
A less important role in a less import
And I began to notice that
People worry
Coming to me first
With things
They weren't necessarily
Valuing my opinion in the same way that they should
And I
Began to lose my voice within
My own brand
And I had to get it back
Did you were you able to
I wish I was able to we hired a
A person to be the president of the
The company
And that person
Was a person who
Decided that he wasn't going to make changes
Without
Me
And without mice
Support and he was someone
And who
Taught me
Instead of just told me
You know other people would tell me what was happening or they would say oh don't worry about it we've got it
And
Richard
Explain things to me and I could see
We asked him questions
Without feeling as if
I was less than b
Because I didn't know
I can understand that instinct right went when your smell like you you start this business
You got the passion but then all these sort of x
Spirits of God
Years decades of Industry experience come in you think okay
I should come take a back seat cuz they've got this expertise like I can understand that instinct to
Want to want to pull back but at the same time
When you did that
You had to kind of
Give up a lot of your
Stamp on the company what what do you think you would have done differently if you
If you had a chance
To be in that position again
I would trust my gut
More
I am not
I'm not
Sad that I did it because
That's how I learned so it
Would never happen
And
I think I had to go
Through that to learn that
But it's
It's important to understand that no matter how much someone else
Nose
They still don't know
Your breath
And if you if you can
Pair your brand to
Your child
There maybe you know a teacher or a tutor
Who's just a miracle worker and they're able to break through
And and get to your kid in a way that you haven't been able to figure out
But that doesn't make them a better parent for your child
That just makes them a really good tutor or really good teacher
But it doesn't make them there
Apparent
And that was what I had to learn that even though there were some people along the way
Who knew better things about the business
It didn't mean that they understood her
And that they really knew how to
Help her grow
And how to translate her for other
That was my job
And I should never have let anyone else try to do that job
But you say that you kind of had to go through that to learn
But you made a mistake
And you now know that
But here in this audience and people listening to
Today's podcast
Are are going to be in a similar position right
Where are they they made
I created something and it
Rose and lots of experts
Come in
And say you know
Let me take take this over
What
What should they do what
I mean
What are the wraps
Well no one's ever going to say let me take this over
They won't be that over
It happens quietly
And indifferently
You know
Your gut
And you know when something is right and you know when something is wrong
And there were times when I knew something
Was it right
But
I let my gut
Go
You know I said well he's been doing it for 12 years and this is different and this is a different level
So let's just see
And
You know we would let's just see
And it wasn't
Right
Don't let that
Happen
You know speak up
When your gut
Feels like it isn't right
And
What what I what I learned from it was
When I do speak up it doesn't necessarily mean that every single time
People are just going to listen to me
And they're not going to listen to anybody else
But at least there was a conversation and it was a dialogue
And sometimes when there's a dialogue someone will explain to me what you know the reason that we wanted to do this is
Is because of this
And if we learn this
Then we know we should go in this direction and then I say okay I can understand why you would want to do that
Because we're going to learn something different
So then I would learn from that process and they would learn from that process but it's awful
When You Say Nothing
Even though inside you know
This isn't quite right I wouldn't do it this way I don't understand why it's going in this direction
So you have to speak up
Because you don't want to live with that what if
And if I had just
Stano if I had only
You don't want to live with that
You we just discussed as a load of the podcast you got a little bit of backlash from your hardcore fans when
When Carol's daughter was sold to L'Oreal because
I'm sickly in a some of your
Irfan said hey you know
Self-made African American business woman selling his company to Big multinational
It's a sell-out blah blah blah you heard that criticism
Did that sting and did you
Did you kind of take that personally
Oh yes
It stung a lot
And I did take it personally for a short. Of time and then I let it go
Because
I realize that
You know people had written a story for me
And if that was okay
That was what they understood
And that was what they thought and they thought that I should go in this direction but they didn't really know
The whole story and they didn't
No
That the way that I had built
The business
My investors needed to exit
And they didn't know
The work that it took
To get a company to a place
Where a company like L'Oreal would buy it you know a lot of people
Think that
You know you're not doing so well so they pick you up for a song
It edits
It doesn't work that way you have to be profitable you have to
How to be doing well
Have to have good profit
Margin
And they have to
Growth coming
From you
So it it hurt and it stung for about 36 hours
And I let it go
And you did very well
Thank you
Very briefly Weebly play Nadia Montage at the beginning of the day where you said whether you're doing 40,000 and sales a year
28 million
You still doing the same work
What do you mean by
You know
It's very interesting being a notch
Open or cuz technically right now I'm not an entrepreneur
I'm an employee of L'Oreal
But there's so much that I
Do that is
Still
The same work
You know I
I push
I believe
I rally people together i-lead I inspire
There's so many things
Stat I do too
Today that I did
When I was selling in the flea market
I just might have to do
Less
Great work
If you will
But a lot of it is is the same and it takes
It takes that same
Drive and passion
And love for what I do
And
I've got I've gone back
Making things in the kitchen
Just for myself and just for fun
And it's amazing to be in a place where I can do it and give it away
You know like I'm not relying on how much each bottle is going to
Bring into
To pay whatever bill now you can just make a batch and just go to my neighbors and be like here
Occasion
Amazing
Lisa Price founder of Carol's Daughter compatible start the story thank you
I spoke to Lisa this past October at the how I built this Summit
San Francisco
And this has been the final episode from the summit mainstage
You can check out the previous five interviews
In your podcast
And stay tuned for details about how you can attend the how I built this live event in the future
Our episode was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with original music from Rammstein Arab Louis
Gyros
You been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign mode
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com