Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com
Pictures of wood thing before we get to
The show I have some amazing news which is that we are doing another live shows
Coming up
It's happening on
February 8th
In
Columbus Ohio
And I'll be talking with jeni Britton Bauer the founder of
Jeni's Splendid ice cream
It's supported by American Express open and tickets
Will go on sale in
Just a few days you can get them
At NPR presents
. org
And because we're gearing up for that we're going to reach into the archives today to play one of our very favorite episodes for you
Free time but really this one is
Incredible the story of how
Kate Spade turn her name
The one I most popular
Handbags
In the world
We were still not making any money nobody was making a salary we were Andy was funding everything
I just I didn't leave you to shut it down I said it's your 401K money
And in all of our savings at that point we still weren't seeing you know progression that we've
Next year in the near future so we thought we had a good run at it we think we've had it
From NPR how I built this
Show the innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they built
The person behind the brand Uno is Kate Spade
Grew up as Kate Brosnahan
In Kansas City Missouri
Then she always loved fashion but
Never plan to work inside
She wanted to be a journalist
So in the early 1980s
She went off to study journalism
At Arizona State University
And that
Kate met her future husband
Andy Spade
We work together at a clothing store and I was on when inside he was on the men's side and
One day his car broke down and he asked me for a ride home and we really started off
Really great friends in the car continue to break down so relationship along
And the rest of the story later they're still together anyway
Kate graduated from college first Andy was a few credits short so she decided to backpack
You're up by yourself traveled around and came back to New York and
Brentwood temp agency because I desperately needed
Send money
To be with Andy but that's where my ticket
It started and ended in New York
And
Got enough money to get back so I needed a job in order to do that so I started it at 10
Place I was typing and I said I don't think this is going to work out
And then she called the next day and said
Can you get ready right now caught in a skulls and they have a job in fashion Department
So they ended up hiring me they didn't want to because I couldn't type
My boss
That she's great and I don't need a side Lot
If we were doing fashion shoots and styling so
It wasn't it
What were you what were you doing at
Well I started as an assistant so I was
Tying
Model shoes
On a photoshoot because they couldn't bend over their clothes
That are getting hair stylist
Snickers
I'm telling you whatever I Ironton
Carry bags
It was a lot of work
Say that
Did you were you Rebecca
In Tempe at Arizona State University
I was back in Tempe hours to struggling with a few required courses
I think I had more
Credits the necessary but there were a few that I couldn't get through
But I did start an advertising agency
Can see my senior year in college
And so I
I started
Trading ads for
Barding food
So I'd I go to a restaurant for example and I
I bring in the ad that they had running in the local paper
And I would show it to them and say I think I can do better if I come back and show you a
A better version of this
Will you either pay me in food or give me a few hundred dollars
I had like 10 takers
So I ended up with 10 accounts
I mean things are going well
And Kate were you still planning to head
Back to Arizona
At that point yes
And I kept saying it when I'm coming back
I will only stay here
Woofers photostream
Can I move to to sex
I said I have to be honest
I kind of like my job
I loved it and I love the feel of the fast-paced of
New York and San Leandro
I loved it
When she got a job offer for $14,000 a year everything changed
She's on sting and that's what I
I'm moving to New York
And you just figured
I'll find something
Yeah I figured I'd find something there I had a little portfolio
Of advertisements that I'd written and art directed
So I took that with me to New York and helped
Defining a job
And what did you guys
Did you go out like move in together
We did
I forwarded a little bit of money that I had
Advocate for security deposit on the cheap
Is Department chief
Find
And
I remember arriving in
It's a call me from a pay phone on the corner
When you arrive
And all
Get out of the fire escape
So I called and I walk to 26 Renwick Street
And I looked up at
She was out of the fire escape and she threw down a sock with a
Akita
It's easier to go down there
How to walk like suitcase
I had
One warm coat
Suitcase
And a portfolio
Wow an integer by decadence
I know you went to an all-girls
What high school does your parents of have
The problem with you living with an e
They never really said much but
My mother
That's not please
She was not pleased with the doll bed
I mean I just kept saying it was a matter of Economics just being practical
Did you actually in advertising
I did I was interviewing and a lot of programs like y&r in Oglebay anime there
But my portfolio didn't reflect the kinds of accounts that they're working on
Cars in IBM
What is walking to Grand Central Station and a young man in a suit pulled me over I was
He said you do
Looking for a job as a copywriter
He said you have a minute
Bacitracin I'd love to look at your portfolio and we stopped in Grand Central Station he went through my portfolio and
He said I think I might have something
Sing for your recruiter
Did you happen to see me walking Grand Central Station and
He went through it needs to meet me at my office tomorrow
To did and he sent me on three or four interviews
What which which was an agency named bozell Jacob Canyon and eckhert
I need an opening for someone to work on the Army National Guard and Merrill Lynch
And
He said I know you haven't
Had any experience on these
Types of businesses but I like your hotspot
I didn't know what it meant until I called someone
What does it mean when they say I'll meet you after you took a chance starting own business at the positive
Since I got that job
So okay so you guys are on your early 20s
You're living a New York Life
Tate you're working at
At Canada
Right at Mademoiselle magazine
Amazon
Actually it was amazing
I mean it by Mom
Frame
When they put my name in the
Math test
Pizza Hut pray
What did you start to do there
It was first assistant
For the senior fashion editor
Then I was promoted to associate editor
And I was in charge of all the accessories
And
Did that for a couple years and they promoted me the senior fashion editor
And if there's one thing I did learn was
How to be very resourceful
And it came in very handy
We started our business because
I mean
That was do not come back to me with
No
I mean you
Figure it out I mean it would be we have to go on a shoot in
2 days and we need 8 tickets
Did Muhammad sin
Figure out how to get us all there
I mean if we're all on different airplanes I don't care but get us there
Make it happen
So I guess it was
CertiFit the midday early 90s like maybe maybe 1991 when you decided to leave
Mademoiselle magazine
What was going on why did you decide to go
It's funny you know Angie and I were talking one night
And I just said
I was looking ahead and
Saw the fashion directory
I would be your next
Jump from being
Senior fashion editor
And
I don't really see myself wanting that
That job
So and I are out honestly
Do the Mexican restaurant and
He just said
What about handbag
Honey you just don't start a handbag company
Resupply not how hard could it be
Okay really
He regret those words
What white handbags
Well she was in accessories editor and she collected
Your handbags for fashion shoots that was one of her key responsibilities
So she'd have to
Handbags from
Vintage stores
For Beach shoot straw bag she had a
A Personal Collection that was amazing and then she knew every handbag company in the market
I thought you understood it better than anyone
What's missing in the market
What was missing
At the time things for very
Bags for too complicated
And I really love very simple kind of architectural shape
And I would wear these
Very simple shapes
None of which were
Famous designers names
If someone wear today
Whose is that I'd say I don't know I bought it at a vintage store or it's a straw bag I got in Mexico
Soaked and they were all very Square in C
Simple I thought
Xiaomi why can't we find something
Just clean and simple and modern
Okay so about 2
The time that that you want to quit you were thinking
Like I'm done with fashion magazines
Yes
And then he was like
You know bags you know like why don't you try to do this
Design your own
Absolute heat actually set up
Before I quit so I kind of
Already had in the back of my mind and
I remember at the very beginning
Stay I could have
Made an income while I was working on that since someone said to me
The truth is
You would never have done it had you stayed
Because I would have been a scrap yours I mean that it was kind of been out do or die so
I think if I'd still been working I would have been like
A little bit more lackadaisical about it words
When you don't have an income, then you are doing whatever you can to make it happen
So how did you even start to
To design handbags me you had no
Background InDesign you didn't even know what to do in Lakewood
So things and
Put rivets in at all that stuff it's funny I did not know and I did start
Taipei
Big sheets of white
Paper
And I would cut out
Tape honestly
The shape that I wanted a knife
Look at it and make it shorter smaller cut it
And I went to a pattern maker that I found in the back of women's wear daily
She advertises she made patterns
Should I contact her she worked out of her apartment and she was
Patient as could be with me
Because I didn't know anything and I remember being really embarrassed about that
That
I wasn't going to
Student
From Parsons to RISD or
Fit that I really didn't know what I was doing
And I honestly started with paper that would make a sample out of any kind of fabric Muslim
And then
I kind of got the shape down and I had to find a manufacturer so I called me mister daily they connected me to
Shoe department that they really said we don't do that but someone in the fashion Department said oh it's so hard I know someone
And he had left himself this
Production guide to start his own business
So was this guy that you found was he was he a designer manufacturer so he
Did the production
And so I brought in my samples and
He was like okay why wants the money up front and he really was very nervous and I wasn't going to pay him and
He took our tiny little production honestly which would be
10 bags of time you know
And how how long after
Like you
Assertive start to sketch out designs was this was this like
A few weeks later a month later what what did you
Were you working on this idea for a long time in your apartment yes
At least a year and you were freelancing
Knight Inn
Certain days a week
As a stylist
And
After getting the
Patterns made
The next
Big Challenge was finding someone who would sell us
Fabric
Add
Because we didn't have any experience none of the fabric houses would sell us anything other than
A hundred yards for exam
We only needed to make six packs
A shape so we only needed probably
40 yards
30 RND 25
So I called
I looked in the Yellow Pages
And I looked up
Burlap
Potato sack
That's
Who's willing to sell to
Three different
No wait
And I needed the heaviest weight
Substantial enough
Bram.
That was actually our first collection
Made out of burlap made out of burlap
So what is the bags look like they were imagine
Brown burlap
Kind of rectangular little bag
Yes absolutely with Raffia Fringe
And
Webbing handle and I found a wedding company also
In the Yellow Pages
I see you get this
You get these samples and then what you
How do you get
How do you start with the first thing you do
You go to these
Accessory shows
Treacherous
Trade shows and you get to get accepted
And we did and
The question is
You get the worst spot because all the famous
People end up in the front seat in New York
In New York
This is the first
Trade show you went to debut the Kate Spade
Burlap
Back yes
We honest-to-god brought in our own tables
Lounge chairs
Tiffany lamps
Come on apartment apartment actually turn into our partner
For the week
Nervous I mean Kate were you like I don't know where that were you worried that maybe somebody from
Honey mask
See you in a few a little embarrassed or
Somebody was her call you out and say what are you doing who you guys were you where you get asked me out
I was I
Because the editors come by as well as the buyers
To the trade shows
And I really didn't tell my parents
Or my family about it
Or anyone for that matter
Because I thought if it doesn't work
I will be so
Embarrassed
Because everyone kept saying
Why would you have quit your job
You had insurance but you know who do you think you are I just knew my family with just
Oh you got a little hot-headed big headed there in New York and
Think you can start this company
So I kept it on the down low
They talk about it watch 2
Family
Because I think secretly bug thought it would fail
How did people respond to the bag
It well
I remember crying because when I came home we hadn't even sold enough to cover the cost of the booth
And I started crying and annies
Who did you get and I said
What we got
Barney's
And he's a
Okay and I said
Fred Segal in Los Angeles news
Brahe to the news
Migas
Katie
To the best stores in America
Why are you crying I said I think we should shut it down
I'm very cool
I have no interest in losing money
I said and we've been out we've already spent
$4,000 and that that's it for me I'm not a gambler
So that's her and he was like that
Keep going
And also have to get a great deal of credit
To the editors
The time we were
Tell me the lot but the editors
We're putting this into magazine
A lot what was it about your bags at appeal to them
I did because it wasn't anything anyone was doing and everyone there's a fabric show in Paris called premiere
Busy on the all the designers go to
Sometimes you could end up with the same
Materials
Mine came out of the Yellow Pages chances are I wasn't going to run into any people that have the same material
So we were doing something different which was really to our advantage
Two editors for like
Beautiful burlap bags
They thought they were
Beautiful tiny they thought they were interested and
We did we got a lot of credits then that's when my mother first found out
And she was embarrassed and she called
Embarrassing that you didn't
Tell me and my friend had to tell me I said
I know I don't know I don't wanna make a big deal of this and
It okay it's one credit that's not a business
How did you come up
How did you serve land on the name
Well that was an
Because we weren't I was not Kate
Spade I was
Kate Brosnahan and
I kept coming up with these names
Kate
Stay because we were 50-50 partners
Finally I just said okay then once I'd love it
Kate Spade do you work and I remember telling
To your point about
My Catholic parents I told my mom
Honestly she burst
In flames
But you're not keep say that I said I know but she's a
Oh now you'll never be Kate Spade now you've been jinxed it and why would you name it Kate Spade and I said
What's my first name his last name is like
Dolce & Gabbana what the hell is that
I said it'll work we hope
In just a minute
Why after three years of making no money
Peyton Andi almost walked away from their little handbag company
I'm gyros near listening to
How I built this
NPR
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from wix.com
A web platform for creating your own professional website
With Wix whether it's your first time creating a website
Or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning template
Or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology
GM powerful web features
Join Over 125 million people already using Wix to create their own websites go
Go to wilx.com to create yours today
So what will you create
Thanks also chart 2019 leaves sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
A campaign monitor they took email marketing and made it radically easy
So the big thinkers could focus on
What they do best
Developing Big Ideas
Choose from hundreds
Professionally crafted templates
Turn key design
To create campaigns
Get results
The best part
Drag-and-drop editor gets
The job done in
Record time
Try for free
Campaignmonitor.com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and business
Unforgettable
It's how I built this from NPR
I'm gonna rise
Soap when Kate and Edith debut the original Kate Spade bag
They got orders from
Barney's
Fred Segal
And it was a big deal in the world of fashion
Even with those orders
It didn't mean Caton and E were suddenly flush
With cash or living large in New York
Wasn't going to guarantee that the
Company was going to be successful
Andy
He kept his full-time job in advertising
Paying the overhead yeah I'm basically the Rams and the other expenses right we'll keep freelancing that started the company
And I just thought what we're both 29 30 years old and
It's time to do it we don't have children
Let's not quit even if we
Lose everything
Kate can always go back to Fashion job
You know I can
Continue working advertising
And you guys are running the company
Apartments
We'd move to a loft
Tribeca because we were in a small apartment then we move to
Honestly guy everywhere
To the point where are Loft
Bad was up the stairs will be
Crawl up
The entire apartment was just to see if
Brown Boxer
But that sounds like
Very well fit.
It really was that we were still
You were shipping out
Stinson Beach Apartments
Oh yes for
At least two and a half years
You could take the train
The Brooklyn to the factory
Pick up the boxes
Just take the back on the subway
In trash bag
Walk them up a 5 floor walk-up
And she was shipping and
Packing bags and
I'm doing everything and take it words on the fax machine I remember they come through in the middle of the night with your better
Excited put the orders would not be that big because it was hard to
The people that time to cut once they started selling then you get bigger order so it was really
Very gradual I mean it was at least
3 years
Before we paint ourselves
Baby fifteen thousand 15000
And we're still working out of our apartment
And it was our home office
Please enter shipping
Warehouse
Andar
Home
Did you start to see
In the first year two
Fat women walking around New York with
I did
Most of whom
We redditors who are getting them a very good discounts
But eventually we started to see it and I remember thinking
When I did that was a big deal
And
You know I think it took people while even my family my sister was working
Bucheon actually
Called me and said we're all pitching in
Mom
Mother's Day
Get her Gucci bag and I thought
What
Because I really didn't think
It would be much
I still should be upset with him about that hopefully they're listening
Show all the while you're sleeping bags out you're getting orders in and you are still designing
Facts
Yes
So you're working like
Crazy
We are and
What we ended up doing
What's Peter Kahn
Two partners
For Sweat Equity only
It was supplied by the way
Terrence my best friend
That was 80
Someone that we just met
Define seer in New York
So
The three of us were in cars going to the factories
I was really doing the design the only the
Didn't I also noticed
Steam in the bag box and packing
And how are you guys funding
Was always around
Yeah I got a job offer to work
For Saatchi & Saatchi in LA and I almost tripled my salary
Yeah we're still funding the company ourselves
And we needed money
For fabric and we needed money
The trade shows
Until we both agreed that I would go to La you did move to LA
I thought I could go back
Bedford Hotel New York
Partner with you
FedEx in all my designs and materials than a regular house that I called the house I never lived in
I never bought a piece of furniture
And I just took the money and send it to me I'll put it back into the business
Did you ever get a point in in the first two years
Where you thought this was going to collapse if the
Yes and I remember calling back
Talesun Pamela New York Mason
I didn't leave you two
Shut it down I said it's what wow are you guys
Like in data
It was hard I mean it was we were still not making any money nobody was making a salary we were and he was funding everything
And at that point we were all kind of putting money in family would put into Emeli Sande
I just remembered thinking up again it's like
We run to your 401K money
And in all of our savings at that point
We still weren't seeing
You know progression that would go to pay the salary that I
Year in the near future
A good run at it
I think we called the partners who
We brought in as as
Equity Partners on a handshake without any salary and we said we think we've had it
Exhausted
Leftist art
With you and we haven't returned the deals.
Not working it's a we felt like you can't just walk out and I remember we spoken
We're going to go back
I'm trying to make
9595 96-95 probably 95 and I did get another job
New York a great job actually
And so
But still the company was not making money
What was the what what happen
I would say the stores really
Started to buy more we were in sacks
Bethany Menzel
When the
Large department stores started to buy
It
Kind of really took off and
We won
The cfda awards which is
The Capitol Fax
Designers of America
And
There were reporters from around the country not just
New York at the show that were saying
Who is this
So that really really
Help us a great deal I have
How's the word that
Your smile designers
Didn't win at the time that was usually a Ralph Lauren Calvin Klein Donna
Karen all this be
And I remember Kate when we came back to New York and we were hoping
Think something would happen
Either Neiman's are stacks
They're buying for two or three stores and they said we're going to buy for all of our stores
And that was
50 stores
More Than Words
And that quadruple our business
But what you have to realize his
When that happens although it's very good you also have to upfront
Pay for the production they don't pay you for
30 to 6 today so I remembered
Are we going to afford this but we
Never borrow a dime
Ever
Was there something that you guys did like a business
Decision that you
You made
That
That was the
The key to turning this around or was it just
More people started
Covered in you just you just persevered through those rough years and then it's
Finally just kind of on its own
Ghetto
Got discovered
That's exactly what happened I mean it really was just
Kind of a little bit of a Snowball Effect
No just got a little bigger and a little bigger and bigger and
I think
We're the largest department stores we're picking us up
I think that it will be realized
Getting larger and larger spaces in stores which is very important
At first you wanted honey little table
And maybe get a few
Basin shelves in the next
Stores to shop and Shop is what they call them where your name is above it really big
Seizure to talking to
I think it's more fun for my mom actually but it was a lot of fun I have to stay in the
Opening of stores do you know we'd open the store
And Soho tiny little 300 square-foot
Pet store the next day
You know we're opening a bigger store in New York
And then we're opening in
Los Angeles
Westin Chicago
It was kind of
At that point it became a little dizzy and
A bit of a whirlwind
Thought it was fun
And so some point you guys sold at
Part of the company
That was at the service scale up or
Like to make it even bigger
You know it was also a safety that quite honestly
Lee Brice personally
And it was Neiman Marcus and we thought that would be somebody that would
Be in a position to help us
And they bought
More than 50
Keepers of the company that they bought 56
And reportedly for more than 30 million dollars was that
And same to you guys went with when it was they were I think our biggest
Quieter
Restore the time and
We're doing very well with them and they just started
Investigate other little little brands that
They thought I had potential
And yeah they came to us we were
Completely
In shock
Is exciting because
Cuz we thought wow
Which everything goes goes away tomorrow
You know it will be able
Sustained
I mean it was really about not being able to have
A bit of an essay going forward
The four of us
I know what it mean when winning in Marcus by
More than half of the change
Kate Spade
We started going into more categories because they were
Encouraging that which a lot of the stores not too
Mancino's Zach all of them work
Really encouraging us
Categories
Stationary next
Switch that was right when the phones and emails and all that were
Replacing p
People writing notes
Texas native
Another category we didn't mean
Dying category
So I think what they were and flying
Shoes they really wanted some
Real substantial
Second categories are third fourth
So then we started doing shoes and
It really just started
No I think it was just a good boost
And I mean you guys probably had to go from you and Andy and your two
Two partners II
Mexican place
We did but we have done that actually
In the process
Slowly slowly changing
Offices and we take a floor and then
We take another floor in the building
Started hiring people hiring Department in different departments in production
Can people in
And then hiring people that
Have more experience
So I really had a lot of people around
And Andy did Andy really surrounded himself
Really
Greats
Art Department
And I really had great designers with me and
I think we really developed
Employees that were amazing
When did you start to see
Kate Spade bags
All over the place
Huge iconic
And when did you first kind of realize
I'd say was about
It was still
Ferry New York though I must say
There a New York Los Angeles Chicago
I think it was about 98 or
90 / UTM
Did any city that you went to
Counterfeit start
That was about
Which Andy said that's actually a comp
Something right when
They're on baby blanket on every street in order to be celebrated for a day and then the next day that was over
You guys sold the rest of your your share of
Walked away from it
Why'd you decide to do that
So
We
Panda baby
In 2005 and I just wanted to
It was a perfect opportunity
The point was it
Neiman Marcus
Set the time
Was selling
Themselves
To text
Pacific
Paintball Des
Get them a lot of credit for that
But when we saw them everything
Keynote
Kind of like we have a
I bought some music I want to leave on
On good terms if it's a
Perfect time to leave
I wanted to spend time with my daughter
It was
You've heard so many horror stories
About people who style and then they stay and then they fighting and they sue and
That's too ugly
Before me so
We left on great terms we stay because of turnover
For a year I think
For that transition to make sure all the employees who we loved had
Had agreement
The carry-on
And I'll make sure it was understood
The process was
And
They were very gracious and I think we all handle it very well
It was seamless
It was a very
Quiet exit
You guys obviously have the same
Incredibly strong
Marriage meme email heera college students are still together you have a
You created this big amazing brand and how do you
How do you have a marriage and a business and make it work
I mean
Safe from my perspective I remember people saying how do you work together when I was thrilled
I don't wait up wait up and I'm not ready yet means
Let me tell you right now if you think that everyday
Office together we can have lunch together
We actually work on separate floors
For that very reason because
Keep you on the phone and Isaac
Get off the phone I have something to tell you or ask you
And that we had to really I had to myself
Find boundaries in
We had to make
Conscious effort not to talk about it 24/7 which is
As you can tell by how quickly I talk like tendency
And I also am very
A nervous person I worry a lot
A nanny could not be more different sleepless nights
Always another
The sky is falling
You know it's good it's fine because we
We kind of grew up together
20s
Up until now in AR-15
And we actually have a lot in common with help
You guys
Recently
Launch a new company
Together we could you call it by Frances Valentine in case you changed your name from Kate Spade
To keep Valentine I did but I added it I didn't change it I just added
Francis
Valentine into it so it's very
It's Katherine
No
Francis
Valentine
Brosnahan Spade
Eddie Long
Did you do it in part because
Kate Spade and become
Its own singing
Beyond a single person
Yes and I thought it was important to make sure that we weren't stepping on any toes and
That we distinguished
Our company
And I think that was important
For both of us
I mean people still call me Kate Spade I go buy it
Seitz eye
Myself so you can call me Francis if you want
Tell me about Frances Valentine
We are doing
Shoes and Handbags
So we actually when we started
It was
Initially just
Shoes
Until there we go
I'm not your just your little over a year
But we realized that
People expecting bags
I and I mean now you're different
The hunger is
I'm sure it's still there but
It's not like a do-or-die
Sing like a
It must be that I don't know
Is it less stressful
We've air conditioning I think that's think that's a big difference right elevators and air conditioning
I would stay there
It's
But I feel a little more confident
I think Andy feels the same because we've done it before
But on the same hand
Do you think that
People are expecting a great deal
So they're still there still a lot of pressure Trestman
Personal finance
Again so
I'm not crazy that as I mentioned earlier
Losing any money
You know this thing go to work
Do you when you walk past
Kate Spade
Shop today or
RC bagged do you
Do you feel emotion emotional
Ashland to Aurora
Is it serve like about you know that that's a dick
It's funny because I
I do look at it and I don't
People said oh do you have any regrets I really think you all I hope I don't
And I never have and I think they've done such a good job that luckily I don't have to have
And we do walk by the stores and I have a funny story that we actually walked into the store
To buy my daughter something
Went to the cash register and teeth are you are failing
And I said
EXO
And instead that I used my
Maiden name and ice
She surprised me
And my daughter kind of kept nudging me to his died for me to say something
But I didn't know that I was thinking you know
And I'm not on your mailing list but I think I helped create it
Looking for the ending thank you this is a note that Kate
And Andy spade and by the way if you ever heard of Jack Spade bags for men Kate and Andy were behind
Those two end know jack is not a real person
Stay cool name I mean honestly people
The constantly are saying
You Know Jack deep they fight or you know Kate Jack Spade and then I don't know if there's something else I owe you mean happy
Lookout
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear about the things you're building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors
QuickBooks
When you work for yourself every receipt lost it
Cash lost
End of the year
Snap and sort your business expenses with QuickBooks
Maximum tax
Directions
Smarter business tools for the world's hardest workers
QuickBooks
Can you
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
I know for how you built that
Update story of how Dennis Darnell solve a problem we can probably
Bubbly all relate to when I used to get home you can come in the house
And there'd be that one fly flying around you have no idea how it got in there but it's flying around at the buccaneer
I think we can all relate to that problem
One summer day in San Diego where Dennis lives
Joyland
We're sitting in the kitchen and they were watching him
Fly Buzz all around we sat there and watched it
Trying to get into the garbage can
And what if I said
Why do I drill a hole in the lid
And let it in
But put a trap
On the underside of the lid
And that is how the garbage can
Fly trap
Was born flies
Of course love
Garbage
Soap Dennis designs trap where
Drill a hole in the lid of your garbage can
Then you pop in this little
Plastic doorway for the fly
But there's also a second part which is the cartridge
Which is lined with flypaper
And so why the fly thinks it's going down into the garbage can
It actually walks into the Disposable cartridge
And because
Stuck cartridge gets
Full with like a hundred flies
You don't have to look at that more touch anything sticky or gross
Stand just push the button on the lid
And the cartridge falls into the garbage can that's Dennis turn out since we first spoke to him
A year ago he started selling his products on Amazon are still selling the original fly traps
Spell Dennis has their best selling product is a pet waste bin that comes
With a fly trap
Unless you're their sales jumped from $300 to $25,000
8 if you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're
And thanks as well for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes
How I built this. Npr.org please also subscribe to our show Apple podcasts or however
Were you get your podcast you can also write us at HIV tea at npr.org
Tweet us that at how I built this our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman run teen Arab Louis composed
Music thanks also to grandson as meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers AR internist
I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
Ramen PR
How much would you pay to avoid morning traffic
Why are plane tickets to Boise so expensive
I'm Cardiff Garcia co-host of the indicator
And every episode we take on a new unexpected idea to help you make sense
Today's news
Listen every afternoon on NPR one or wherever you get your podcast
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week