Support for this podcast in the following message come from mizzen & Main
Creators of moisture wicking wrinkle-resistant dress shirts that require no ironing or dry cleaning
Head to mizzen & Main. Calm and use code NPR at checkout to receive $10 off your dress shirt
Hey it's guy here and before we start the show I just want to remind you that we have sold out for
Both of our upcoming live shows in Chicago and in Boulder Colorado
Please do make sure to follow how I built this on Facebook and
Twitter
Keep your eyes peeled for
Last minute
Ticket availability
Plus you can still get tickets for the first-ever one day how I built this Summit
In San Francisco
That event is on October 16th and it's sponsored by America
Express you can get your tickets at npr.org
/ Summit
And now
Aunt the show
We hit the ground running on what we called our Southeastern fundraising
And packed up coolers full of chicken salad to hand out to opossum
Investors and we pitched to anyone that would listen every single
Meeting that we had we heard you want us to invest this much money for a
Minority share of a business that does not have a single franchise open
Thanks but no thanks laughed out of the room
Running PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
I was stay at home mom went from selling homemade chicken salad
The building where the fastest-growing restaurant chains in America
How's it
Chicken salad
Check
Okay so chicken salad
Never really had strong thoughts on it
Either way
Totally solid lunchtime option
But if you live in most parts of the Southern United States
Then you know that much more than
Just a salad option
It's like a lobster roll in Maine where it might seem like it's the same thing everywhere
Nuances
Delicate differences
Fuel passionate debate over which Lobster Shack is the best Lobster Shack
What kind of bait Southerners have over chicken salad
These are the kinds of debate Stacy Brown would have with her friends
She happened to make really great
Chicken salad
Chicken Salad Chick is one of the fastest-growing restaurant chains in America
It was a struggle just to make ends meet.
Will get there
What you need to know for now is that Stacy grew up in Rome Georgia
Ended up at Auburn University in Auburn Alabama where she eventually settled with her first husband
He worked
Full-time
Lost AC stayed home to raise the kids
But always knew I was going to start a business
Always
But
Also knew that
You can't do everything at once
And it was my time
To be
A full-time mother
And
It happened that
The Perfect Storm for when
I would start that business
Came in the shape of a divorce
And at that time
Carson my oldest was sick
Jack
What's 3 + Lydia
Was to
Wow
And you've got to figure this out
Yes to no
Okay I'll have these three children
I've got to make ends meet I have to
Support them
In a divorce is a disaster
It's a financial disaster it's an emotional disaster
But when you know you have
Small children to take care of
The instinct to take care of them first
Lets you push through that b
Because you know
You have to take care of these kids
So all that other emotional stuff really
It's pushed to the back until you can
Get through this survival
Because
There's really no time to sit down and cry
Kcur
Trying to figure out what
To do and what
What did you start to think
So
When I was in school dinner time
In my homework
Really sacred time
My mother cooked every meal
And the four of us
Sat around the dinner table every night
And
Remember that my father
Started conversation
That
Revolved around what
Problems
Did you come across today
And
Our dinner table conversations were about
Solutions and how could we solve everyday problems
Just started
I think ahead before dinner time
What am I going to present tonight
To Dad yes
And that really was
Started
My entrepreneurial spirit that
Question process of
What problems can I solve
When the divorce happened and I was in this situation and all of a sudden
What
Do I have to offer the world
What am I an expert on
What have I perfected over these last years as a stay-at-home mom pit people would value
Well I knew that I was a good cook
And I happened to be obsessed
With chicken salad
Obsessed with chicken salad absceso by abscess what I mean by that is first Falls of
Obsessed with eating at not making it
So every restaurant
That I
Frequented if they had
The chicken salad on the menu which everybody should note that anybody that serves lunch
There is chicken salad on the menu which should have told somebody something
And I was so fascinated by how different it all was and who was going to have
The best recipe and I was always in search of
The best recipe because as a southern woman if you found a great chicken salad do you want to share that information
With your friends and you won't be able to tell people where to go get the gold because it is a southern staple
So it was just
A silly little Quest
Do you know that just
If it was on a menu then
I ordered it
I had
My hometown favorite I had a favorite in
Dalton Georgia Columbus Georgia Auburn Alabama where I attended school all the towns that I lived in
So I knew that I could cook and I felt like I was a connoisseur
A chicken salad
So you thought
How to make chicken salad
If I could come up with a really good recipe
I could just make it from home
And I could sell it door-to-door then I could be with the kids just like I've always been
And maybe it's going to be enough to make ends meet
What was your basic chicken salad recipe at the time
Well when it started
I
Didn't have a recipe you not eating a lot I didn't have a ride
So I thought well
I loved
The depth of flavor
From my hometown
I love the texture
From my Auburn
I love
Date moisture content
From my Dalton paper if I could take
What I love about all of these different recipes and put it into make mine
Maybe this is going to be the
Perfect recipe so
I start
Doing that it's just like a science
Experiment and oh my gosh I went through
Cooking
Whole chickens on the bone I cooked
Chicken breast on the bone
I cook boneless breast I cook tenderloin
All different
Types of chicken would yield different amounts which
Effects
Everything
Side effects the recipe it affects the food cost all of it where you like roasting chickens and then
Mixing it up with mayonnaise and celery and
Epsom salt and spices in
That was basically it
So I boiled chicken
Whole chicken
Well I started with holes
Chickens I moved
Breast on the bone at
Skinless breasts and I ended up with tenderloins
And I found the
All white meat tenderloins
Yield the most consistent
Product
And when you're doing things by weight
You need the most
Consistent end result
That when you said what's in your chicken salad
So I had
Just this one recipe right
Well as I am
Making this recipe
I thought you
Elizabeth down the street
We had a conversation about chicken salad and she loves fruit
And nuts
In hers
I'm going to make one for her
Now
Julia cross
Straight she loves spicy
I'm going to make one
And then if I'm going to have one with fruits and nuts a lot of people are allergic
A nuts
So
Just fruit
It's all of a sudden
I had different flavors
And
I started
Making recipes and I would
Package up little Tupperware containers
Of what I thought was a good recipe
And I would
Take these little Tupperware containers
Two people that I did business with in town
That you do business with
For what so
Hair Style
And in grocery stores
So anybody that I came across
You know that I would normally say
So I said would you please
Sample this and tell me what you think
And they would say
To dry
Too soupy
Too salty
Little Bland
An answer I received this
Feedback
Go back to the kitchen
Can't wait till we can't wait
And then one day
I handed
This
Recipe to somebody
I watched their reaction
Something I had not seen yet
And they close their eyes
And their head went back and they may just the strangest noise it was just old
Wow
It said that was a real reaction when that was
Impressive
So I took that recipe and continue to sample that recipe on neighbors and Friends
Anybody I came across and said tell me what you think of this
Until
I had a wide range of people that I have sampled this one recipe but they all had the same
So that told me that
This was the recipe
Citricide dresses of the time you
You separated from your husband
The time
You got
The recipe down ready to sell
Roughly how long is that
A few months
Say it was probably a few months
And why you were experimenting
Making chicken salad like
Was anybody any friends or what people cared about you
Cheapest price I hate you may want to just get a
Can't just get a day job at a really good at
This is not a sustainable
Way to make a living selling chicken salad door-to-door liked it anybody say that two or four people just
Quiet
Yes now my parents
They
Did not help back with that
Except
This is
Silly
You have got to go get a Dependable job
And support these kids
And I said please just
Just hang on
Let me give this
Scribe
Now I had friends that told me later
Did they were saying that they did not tell me to my face
They did say all good
Yeah good luck sounds good that you sent that from them
No
I was so determined
I was
Blind as a bat I was just going to make this way
See you are determined you don't Ruby Lee
Hair people think you're kind of
They're honestly there there probably were people
Call telling me that I was
Is crazy in a very soft
Southern way
Is it soft
Southern way like
A little bit
Polite but a little bit passive aggressive
Absolute
Absol it's an art
It is an art form
Imagine you
Making chicken stock
First of all you three kids
Two little kids did they demand a lot of attention
And you were trying to make chicken salad and sell it and so what are you doing this like at night like
What are you doing
So I would be with the kids
During the day and when I would put them to bed
Start cooking
And then we would get up in the morning
And I would
Start to panic because I had all this fresh product that I needed to sell
Quickly
And put kids in the car
And we would go knocking on doors they would sit in the car
And I would go knocking on a door with a basket and
Ask them if they would like to buy some chicken salad how much were you selling liquor
What's it like a quart of chicken
A pint is a pound again how much were you selling it for
It was $8
And
I really thought that I was
An aggressive salesperson and that I was ingenious and when I look back I think
They were thinking of here comes that poor pitiful woman
Here she comes pedaling that chicken salad lock the door and shut the blinds
But they've bought it
And then they play standing orders
And the word group
And
I needed
A name because I knew I was going to sell it door-to-door
And I thought the key to my sick
That
It's going to be
Car magnet
I thought the only way people are going to find out what I do for my
Home
Is to put a car magnet on my car
And as I drive around town
And I sit at red lights
People will be able to see what I do
So chicken salad
Has to be in the night
And I'm the chick
It's going to bring it to you
Chicken Salad Chick is catchy so.
Became the name of the business
And
At this point
I reach out to
Kevin Brown
Who had been
A family friend for
10 years
And
He was a computer software salesman
I knew
He
Was very business
And I didn't really know what I was doing
I come up with a good recipe
I had a name but I needed help
Understanding
Really the ins-and-outs
Of running an effective business from home
So I reached out to Kevin
The place come help me I don't know what I'm doing
And he agreed
To come and consult
With mate
So
Tell me about my name
Had him try the recipe he was over the moon about the rest
And
Kevin said you know if you're going to have different flavors
You really need to differentiate them somehow
Like I don't know give them like
Girly names are some
And not only am I going to name them after
Chick
I'm going to name them after
Real
Chicks chicks that have influenced who I am today
Best friend since kindergarten college roommate mother
Mother-in-law
Aunts friends Neighbors
They all eventually
Had named sex in days
Chicken salad came to life
So I was delivering
Fancy Nancy fruity Fran
Classic Carol
And Jazzy Julie
You're my flavor
What's delivering these around the neighborhood and I thought you know
The Gateway
2 communities
Are hair stylist
Anteater
If you can get a good product
In the mouth of hair stylist and teachers you will be connected to every family in town
So I went and put
A large bowl of classic Carol
And my children
School in the Teachers Lounge giant bowl of chicken salad
Yes
I'll put business cards out I put crackers around this giant Bowl
And the phone started ringing off the hook
Because everybody was like this
Perfect I can go home and make dinner
Or lunches for my kids is going to be ready made
Fresh chicken salad in the fridge made from scratch made from scratch and that turns into me cooking
Longer hours
And I find myself
Crying a little bit
It's starting to be overwhelming
And
As fate would have it the next phone call that came
Came from the health department
How do they find out about you
Well
I don't really know it was an anonymous caller
That called out
Apartment and said this person is doing what
They said this woman is
Cooking chicken salad out of her
Which was
Illegal
Is it for like food safety reasons
Yes because you have to
Conduct business out of a kitchen that is inspected by the health
Department
Right okay
So you got this call from from
Like an inspector at the
Alta from where you freaked out are you scared
Well
It was a little depressed
Because I worked my tail off it seem to be working
People were ordering this chicken salad do you know
And all of a sudden
I'm shutdown
I'm back to square one
I'm back to now
I've got to leave the kids and go get a nine-to-five because
Was doing was illegal
Yeah
So it was a dark time it was a dark day that
Wow this was working
This was really working and it's all over
And people like the chicken salad
Not so much
That they knew I had been shut down cuz I had to tell people no
And they would call anyway and they are go
Hey
I'm friends with Elizabeth
She said
If I told you
Baby you make me some chicken that I had to say all right everybody know I'm not bootlegging chicken
And salad I'm not doing this I'm not doing this I'm done
The bathtub gin version of chicken salad you could see me in the corner
Marvin Elementary School parking lot patch open Hawking chicken salad
And until you were finished
Your your business was done
It was
Done I was told
Shutdown immediate
When we come back
Highest AC 5e
Totally legal weight
Keep making chicken salad
And grow her business
Well beyond your neighborhood
Stay with this guy Roz and you're listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR and the following message come from luminary the only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah's a new pot
With his new show The Daily Show host challenges himself and his listeners to explore unfamiliar angles
And embrace differing viewpoints listen to Trevor Noah's new podcast along with other original shows only on low
Luminary visit luminary. Length / built
For your first
2 months of luminaries premium content for free cancel anytime
Terms apply
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Marcus
Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcasts Spotify Stitcher
SoundCloud
And Google Play and it gs.com podcast
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One Capital One is reimagining banking by offering account
With no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
It's 2007 and Stacy's homemade chicken salad operation has been shut down
By the health department
But
Just when she's about to give up
Her business partner Kevin
Comes up with an idea
He said you know you've gotten a lot of attention here in this neighborhood
I bet
That we could find you a little
Take out spot
Something small
And
Give this a go and it would pay your bills
And I'll help you do it
And we decided to partner on paper
That was 51% he was 49 and we were going to open up a little
Make-out spot
So there was a drive-thru window in this tiny little 800 square foot Shack
And
That was going to be it that was going to be Chicken Salad Chick how much was your wreck by the way
$800
Pretty good price for
A business
And what was Kevin's motivation
To help you and get a full-time job like
Do you really believe in the business
Yes
He was inspired by the
This crazy reaction that was happening
In town
Eminence
Exciting that start a business and
We have been family friends and whenever all the families got together
He and I always had a meeting of the minds of what was going to be the next
Greatest big thing
So we already had that connection
And then all of a sudden
We're going to start this little chicken salad business together
But now
This is
Right before
The huge recession
He's still selling software
And his job
It's eliminate
So he was pretty devastated with that
Because
He had
An ex-wife and a daughter too
Support
And he said you know not to worry
I'm going to really put all my effort
Into helping you start this chicken salad business
And then when I get
Open Office
It's fate I don't go get a real
Job
And I have never let him forget that he said that
So so
Just to paint the picture for me
You guys are working out of an 800 square-foot
Book stand
With a drive-thru window
And did you install an
A commercial oven in there and like her a commercial sinking
Did you have to do all that stuff
So
We are
Building the
This little thing from
Scratch and
Neither one of us
Had any money
We could not hire a contractor to come build this
So we were going to Home Depot
And we were buying flooring we're laying the flooring we work buying paint we're painting the walls we were
Hanging drywall
And thankfully I had wonderful parents and they would come from Rome Georgia and they would stay at my little place
And keep the kids
While Kevin and I built
This restaurant
Wow
And this was going to be such a tiny little thing we didn't need commercial equipment
We just need a residential cuz this is not that big a deal
So everything was absolutely Homespun
And we opened finally
January 7th of 2008
So
Recession is
Here is there yeah
And end
Did you submit this point your corporated you create an LLC like you've done all that stuff you are a bonus
Fideism
That you're legit
We're legit gear legit okay and then
County Health Inspectors are like it by eulogy
Can you open the doors
And on day one or you're
Former customers like a whining at the door waiting for chicken salad
So on day one
We
Cooked 40 lb of chicken salad
So you could have it as
A sandwich or you could buy a pound
You would choose your flavors of chicken salad
We would complement those with our maid
From scratch side salads
And then every lunch got the cookie
Because
My view is that you don't really know you're full
Until you have one little bites of sweet
It says you're done and happy
So that first day you make
40 lb of chicken salad
An
And we open up the doors
Our family and friends came to support us and
Please well-wishers and flowers and balloons and plants are being delivered and
The walls are lined with all family and friends
And you can say that in the middle of the room there's not a
Single custom
No one shows up
There's just such a
Deep
Since this
Heaviness
Is the elephant in the room
It just feel everyone's thoughts like
I mean how could she think this
What kind of work
It was so heavy and I thought what if I
Done what have I done after
Just put every
Penny to my name
Into a business that
Only
Serves lunch only serves take out and only sells chicken salad we could not have made it anymore
More difficult for you to be a gif
Cute head to fit into a very slim demographic to Be Our Guest
Yep
So I'm thinking
Stupid ass stupid
Doneness
And first guest walked in the door
And everybody in the room just
Her like she was the millionth customer you know that she
But she was the only customer
Play people does rennet or said hello how are you
We help you have
Come right this way right this way like
Like that kind of know it was like
It was just way too small.
And the people were
South everybody was hugging her and thank you
You just shut up
Chicken salad I know and guess what
She's never shown back LOL
Okay listening
Waze
Start that woman
Did she shows up for the chicken
For chicken salad
So she is
Stunned by all the attention that she's getting she orders
Her lunch
She leaves
And then
People
Start coming
And
A line forms
The lion guard
Out the door
Down the sidewalk and we sell out into our
What what do you attribute that to mean you you opened up and there were no customers and
In a couple hours
It just took lunch time
10 in the morning
Nobody wants chicken salad until noon
I just wanted people to be there
And
So
Kevin and I looked at each other and said well let's make some more
So we made 80 lb
The second day
And here
Was a surreal moment of realization
Every one of those faces
We saw
On the first day
Is there on the 2nd
And they brought a friend
And we sold out
In 2 hours again
With twice the amount
And very quickly
It turned into what always said look like the floor of the New York Stock Exchange
In that 800 square foot in an 800 square foot
Building
And
I'm thinking okay people are liking this
And they wanted everything we had to cook we could not make it fast enough we were running out of food but we were
Making a dime
My assumption would be the case for crushing at you making money hand-over-fist
And we weren't and you are at will why well we didn't know how much money we were spending on inven
Cantore we didn't know how to project
How much we needed to cook and our way Suite have waste of one item and then not enough of others
Yeah
So I remember very clearly this day
We were running out of food and
Kevin and I had busted out the backdoor we run down the production kitchen 2
Grab more broccoli salad more grape salad we're out we come back down
To the service kitchen and he turns around and barricades himself against the door he said Stacy
Stop
So what
He said this isn't working
We are not making any
Money
And nobody is going to work this hard we're working our tails off and we're not making any money it's not
Can work
Get out
That's the way I've got to feed these people
So he knew then
She's not going to give up
So he went in there
And he worked on our process
And every day he would say
Today we did this in six steps
Tomorrow we're going to do it in five
Today we didn't in 5 tomorrow we're going to do it in four
And he turned us into a well-oiled machine
And it didn't take him very long and the grand scheme of things
So
We open January 7th of 2008
And we were
Making
Money
About 2009
And we opened
Two more restaurants
In Auburn
To pull the chaos
Away from that one little Shack
But I have to imagine you were working like
Crazy
Like morning till night
So
You know
The reason that I wanted to do this
Was so that the children would have that stability
So it would not make sense
If I said
To heck with all that I'm going
To go open a restaurant that's going to have me working all hours
The night
And when we open the restaurant
We said we are going to run a restaurant
The restaurant is not going to run us
So
The first thing we did that was smart
We primarily serve lunch
So we're not going to be there at 4 in the morning
Preparing breakfast and we're not going to be there at 2 in the morning closing down a bar
And then Kevin made the commitment
He said I'll take the later hours you take the earlier hours so that you can be home with the kids
For the majority of the day
And he held true to that commitment
And
We got married
Bury the lede
During the time you were the two of you were both single parents and you were working together so
I guess you start to fall in love
I mean
Crisis bonding
We were in the fire
Yeah I guess you'd say we fell in love over chicken salad
In that first year you open up a
Business and you also
To each other
So in November of 2008 weekly
Lowe's
The restaurant
We hung a sign on the door that said the chicken the rooster have gone to get married
And we flew to Jamaica we got married we stay there for 4 days we came back
To the fire of the restaurants in a blended family
Sonographer
Kevin had a daughter Olivia
About 2 at that time and so we
Came back to
Free restaurants for children in the cat and the dog ran away
It was
My mother says it was a festive life
So
This business really started
Take off in Auburn right I mean
Who are the who is coming I mean
College students was it
Little lunchtime crowd was it just doesn't everybody
Well episode
When we open the restaurant I had no clue
But naming it Chicken Salad Chick might determine
And I found out
Once we open the restaurant
We became known as a chicky place
Yeah this was a place for women
I had no clue you know good foods good food right
So
Then it was
Really lots of fun to observe male behavior in the chicken salad
So I had
You know these names of the chicken salad
Sassy Scotty Fancy Nancy
Fruity friend nutty Nana
All these names
Well the men
Would come up to the
The counter and they would say
Give me the one with the fruits in the nut
And
I would say
What's Fancy Nancy
Is that the one that you would like Fancy Nancy
I said Don't make me say it
Names can't you just number them
Habit they came in the door
Oh they came in the door so the first time they would come in
They come in with a girlfriend or a wife
And I'd elbow her and I'd say you order
Because they didn't want to have
Say the name
And once they ate it
The girlfriends and wives didn't have to come anymore they were coming for the food and they didn't care about saying the names they were all
In
So as you as you grew in as you had more and more
Customers coming through the door how did you finance
The second third
Locations
Through
The revenue of the first restaurant so the cash flow is able to help you
Open up those other locations
Yes
And because
Believe me every Bank
Laugh
Us out
Of those office you could not get a loan
Tattoo open up now
Incredibly successful business in the bank said no way
Right they said you had to be in business for over 2 years
And I woulda
Steady income
To show
That this was a sustainable business
The banks
Would not give you any money
What does around a time where you started
I think about the idea of
Possibly franchising
So we were in this college town
And all of the students
Would come and they would bring their families to Chicken Salad Chick because it was a unique
Place to Auburn
In the moms and dads of these students would say
This is
Awesome what do I have to do to get one of these in Little Rock Arkansas
What do I have to do to get one of these in Virginia
Because we're running these three restaurants in
You know still in somewhat survival mode
We would say are you kidding
Like we can barely breathe franchise are you kidding
I mean I would joke around and say I'm put on an apron and help out in the kitchen because
I can't do anymore
But yeah we got tired of saying no
So
We said
Let's just put your name on a list
If we ever get to it
Will give you a call
And that list
Quickly grew to over a hundred people that wanted franchises
And
About mm
We were starting
Even write the documents to franchise tag
And then found ourselves in the position of
How are we going to rent
Franchise com
We have three restaurants
That it's taking every bit of every
Effort that we
Can muster
We need to partner
How did you
Start to look for partner
Well we wanted to partner
With people that had franchising experience
Because we had none
And
A couple
Husband and wife
Was introduced to us
Think this was
And the husband had franchising it
Experience with major brands
So that was very encouraging
But there was a little
Issue with how they wanted to partner
They wanted
51% of the biz
And
Kevin was
You're completely no
That's not going to happen
But
You know I rationalized it out by saying
We really didn't have
Plans of getting into the franchising business
And so our exit strategy is probably going to be to sell out to these people anyway one day
So what's the harm
And
Selling them 51%
Because they're going to take the lead on the franchising part of this anyway
And they were also probably going to
Put some passion
Oh yes
Which
For us was exciting that we had worked this hard and all of a sudden we were going to have a little realization of
Mia some success
So you took the deal
So we took the deal
And and
If you had sound effects that will go womp womp womp
Very quickly
It went downhill
They had a very different vision for the brand
Where it was going to go
And
We were not comfortable with that it was not a good working relationship and we knew
That if they took the lead on that it was going to be the end of the brand
So what did you do
So
We had a meeting with mr. and mrs. so-and-so
And Kevin said
We need to dissolve
This partnership because it's clearly not working
The husband said
Well kid
This is not a partnership
We own 51% of this business
And we can fire you
With just cause and take your shares anytime we want
Yeah wow
Felt like the blood left my body
We
Have been
Purchased by shark
Can't believe
How could we have been this wrong
And thankfully at that time we had a board of directors
And we took this
Situations are board of directors
And they said mr. and mrs. sew and sew you need to give the Browns the chance to buy you out because they're the founders of the biz
And I said okay will do that
And they said here's our price
Which was three times the amount that they had purchased four months earlier
Wow
And not only is this is our price but you have 30 days to get it to us
How much were they asking for
OnPoint
Wow 1.3 million
And keep in mind that at this point we didn't have a single franchise
Open
Kevin and I are determined to make this work we hit the ground running on what we called was ourselves
Eastern fundraising tour
He put together his best
Presentation
Best pitch and I
Packed up
Coolers full of chicken salad to hand out
Possible investors
And we pitched to anyone that would listen
Anybody that had a friend that could be interested please come and listen to us
So we traveled and held meetings in
Hotel conference rooms
Chamber of Commerce conference room
And every single meeting that we had
We heard
You want us to invest
This much
Money
For a minority share of a business
That does not have a single franchise open
Thanks but no thanks
Laughed out of the room
And this whole time that 30-day clock
Ticking away
So
With two days
Left
On that 30-day clock
Kevin
Is telling me we're sitting on the back porch
He said you have
Got
Ticket
Grip on reality
This Is the End
It was a good thing
But it
Is the end
And
We'll figure out something else
I was not willing to face that
But we go to work
Into our
Tension-filled office
And a lady in the office
Slid me
A piece of paper
And on that piece of paper
Were the names
5 people
And she said
Call these people
It's all I've got
But give him a try
Who was that lady in the office
Her name was Claudia Isaac and she
Was our receptionist
She said
Call these people
It might help
Yes
So
I called those gentlemen
And I begged
I begged with no shame
I said I know it sounds crazy but will you please just come listen to what we have to say
And they agreed
So we went to a conference room at the Chamber of Commerce in Auburn
Kevin gave them his
Best for our pitch
And we took them to lunch at Chicken Salad Chick
I packed them up full of course of chicken salad we put them in their cars and we said goodbye.
Charles Esten
And that was going to be it
And very quietly Kevin and I got in our car and we were driving back to the office knowing
That it was over
And Kevin's phone right
And one of the gentleman
In that meeting his name was
Erlin mcquarter
He said can you to come back to the restaurant and we said Shirley whipped the car around
We get back to the restaurant and we sit in the booth with this
Very kind gentleman
And he said
I believe in the two of you and this is a good thing and I don't want to see it die
And I will write you a check for every penny that you need well
And
I'm sure he thought I was having a stroke because I
Absolutely
Falling apart
Ears are blowing
And I'm stunned and Kevin is nodding and say
Yes sir yes sir and he became the most
Wonderful partner we ever could have asked
And he was just
I mean we'll see what was his professional was his background
So his background was in construction
He
Open
Instructed over
300 Lowes
Are you friendly with Leisure course
Yes
So he
Was a self-made man from the ground up
And he understood
That people had helped him in his career
And he
Appreciated that
And he was willing
To help us out
So you you're back on your feet
And at that point where you able to start
Selling franchises
Yes so eorlund infused Capital into the business
Wave
Got into
A great office building and we were able to
Higher
The most wonderful passionate people to build the infrastructure that could see
Port opening
Franchise
Effectively
Where was the first location
So the very first franchise location was Montgomery
And it has to do there
It's wonderful
They came at us like we were not prepared
So the expansion started in Alabama and and
Where did you go
The first location outside of
Well the Third location was
Was Columbus Georgia
See you guys were
I mean
This is like
A timer
But you're starting to you you can start to see where this is heading
Yes
Rattle exciting
Oh my gosh it was amazing and
As we're building our infrastructure
We are selling an opening more restaurants
Everybody
Is happy
Amazing and the story
I wish
No
Sitting in there
So after we had a number of owners
And we were on fire and
The line 2
Cell
Restaurants was long
Kevin said we need to have
Conference
We are legit we need to get all these owners together and celebrate make a plan for future grow
Growth we need to get together
So we held our first conference in Destin Florida
While we're there
In between putting on these
Segments annie's classes
Kevin what's this
Just not like him at all was having to lay down
In
Pain
And we thought he had a
Gallbladder problems
And he said I'm just going to go to the doctor when we get home but was get through this
Conference
We got through the conference
Goes to the doctor
And
And I'm so at age 38
Kevin was diagnosed
With
Stage 4
Colon cancer
And it had metastasized to his liver
So it was the beginning of another fight
I can't even imagine
I just can't
Imagine
I would like
Well
He was the toughest
Man
I have ever
Known in my life
And
It took him
About three days
Anna Todd that he got the news
To process
What was happening to him
And then
She came out with a new purpose
And a new mission
His purpose
Came
Helping other people
With this disease that could not fight for themselves
Because he was a
Fighter
And that was the beginning
Of the Chicken Salad Chick Foundation
And this became a new part of our mission
And
He went that full force
I had stage 4 colon cancer
He was taking
Chemotherapy
But he didn't miss a day of work
If he
Could stand up
He was at work
And he fought and fought
For this foundation and he said
We've got to make
An impact on Research
Fast
And he came up with the idea to hold
Concert
In
Jordan Hare Stadium which is our football stadium
Auburn's campus
And he said not only
Are we going to hold
Concert in jordan-hare
But we are going to have
Kenny Chesney
Headliner
Like one of the biggest
That's right
Biggest
Name in country music
The only person that could
Fill that Stadium would be Kenny Chesney
And
He got Kenny Chesney
And he got
Unfortunately
He passed away
Before
The concert
He passed away November 21st
And the concert was in April
But on that night
In April 50000 people
Walked
Jordan Hare Stadium
For Kenny Chesney concert and it was
The most amazing
Unbelievable night you could imagine
Amazing
He was just
Such a tremendous
Person and a tremendous presence
And
So now I have the honor
Picking up the fight in his name
In team
At the Legacy
The foundation
But the legacy of this business that's growing
Really really growing that you guys
How many locations does Chicken Salad Chick
Now have
So we have 85 locations now
What
What's
The trajectory does it is there a certain point where it stops growing or
Are you just
Planning on
Opening an opening opening opening
Well our goal is to be America's favorite
Place for chicken salad
So that gives us a lot of ground
To cover
So we can't wait
Say
How the rest
Set the country
Receives us
We're very excited
To bring the taste of
The South
To the entire country
I think that in 2017
Your company was like number 37 out of 5000 of
Fastest
Growing businesses the country quarantine core Fortuner for Bruno's magazines
Unbelievable insane
Crazy annie's chicken salad
And
Always tickled me when I would hear
People
Investor type
People say
Really just chicken salad you think that's going to work
The whole restaurant off of
I'm just chicken salad
Sounds like really
Pizza
You think a restaurant work off of Just Pizza
Herberger's you think that would work
What's the difference
Do you have a sense of how many
People are employed by Chicken Salad Chick today
I'm thinking us like 1200
And
I've seen reports of Revenue figures in 2016
Glad you guys
Are to talk about your Revenue at all is that private
We do I mean it's out there and
Whenever I speak at the University to classes
Are students you know her so
Attached to their phones and it's hard to get their heads up off of their phone or sometimes but
It's so funny the one thing that raises heads
Of the students are when
I say remember
About what you're capable of
When your
Passion is involved
Because this was a business
It only needed to make $500 a month to make ends meet is now making 75 million dollars a year
Wow
How much of this
Of the success of this
Enterprise do you think has to us
The skills that you and Kevin brought to it and how much of it
I don't know it's been too hard for me to say it was luck
We work really hard
That would that's hard to accept
Lucketts I don't think
It's luck
I think we have
Paid
Our dues I think
We were good Learners I think we also
New
That we weren't it
I know what I'm good at
And I know what I'm not so
Gradle
In every part of the business deserves
To have an expert in their field
For it to all
Work
100% on all cylinders
So
Kevin and I are very early had to understand what we were great at
And what we were not great at
You don't have to be a Rockette
Scientist
You don't have to have millions of dollars
You just
Have to have
Fashion
And drive in the will to get up and go
And when life knocks you down
You just keep getting up
Stacy Brown founder of Chicken Salad Chick
To this day Stacy has stuck by her motto that she runs the business
The business
Doesn't run her
So every Sunday all employees get the day off
To do whatever it is
They want to do
I keep thinking about how you
Boil the chicken just
Mind-blowing because I'd always
Roast
An entire chicken and then
Take all the meat out and then make some mayonnaise and
Dijon mustard some green onion celery there you go young salt I got my chicken salad
You blow my mind you just described another hole recipe
Probably perfect for you but you haven't tried mine yet
Please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
The first quick thanks to one of our sponsors TD Ameritrade
People who set defined financial goals are more likely to achieve them
And TD Ameritrade
Compucraft the planets aligned
Your specific objective
Tell TD Ameritrade about your goals
And then you can start building towards something beautiful together
Schedule a complimentary goal planning session
Is it tdameritrade.com
Podcast
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And today story starts with
Beer
Which if you've ever brewed at yourself you know it takes Just 4 ingredients
You got your hops which everyone knows about and you've got your yeast which is going to where the magic happens but Wednesday
Chris Rock Brothers on beer in college actually Grand play malted barley
You take water and you mix it in with the grand kind of like making a batch of oatmeal
And oatmeal is the key word here
Because when Dan and his friends were making their own beer they noticed all the leftover piles of wet bar
Smells kind of like breakfast
It smells like Brad is very fragrant but none of the Brewing books told us
What to do
What does grin
Put it in a dumpster all this is happening around 2009-2010
A few years later Dan was in the Bay Area
Where crack
Breweries
We started to notice that a lot of those breweries just like him we're turning out huge mounds of
Leftover spent grain
It smells like food it looked like food and so it was really pretty low-hanging fruit
To think okay well maybe we can make food products out of this
Get a friend named Jordan who would work in the food business
And totally cleaned up and called a bunch of small breweries in the Bay Area
And he starts to drive around with these big plastic tubs to
Pick up all of this used grain threw out my back a few times
Yeah it's heavy anyway they take those heavy tubs barley to Jordan's parents house
Ascend just experiment they took my mother-in-law's recipe for loose granola
Oats and flax honey
Cinnamon went back and forth with the recipe and eventually they decided to turn the granola
Into snack bars low sugar high fiber
With a great eating experiences not a much bar at can I eat like a rice crispy treat
Snack bars on friends and as farmers markets in. So great
The bars to be a bit dry and to be a bit Pokey weight
Hokey Pokey is
Stuck in people's teeth and one of the mouthfeel descriptors that we got pretty consistently was Ho Chi Sao 2
Eliminate the pokenest Dan Jordan decided to grind the beer grain into more
And then from there that really solve the texture issue so we did launch and I we have a great product that selling really well we going to
Another one on the way back bars are now on sale and Regional chains in many parts of the US and
They're not profitable but damn and Jordan have both quit their day jobs and they're paying themselves East
Small salary and I'm not buying a house anytime soon unless I take a down payment and then you know nutrition bars
Play nothing on it.
First do not taste like beer but they do have be renamed like chocolate coffee Stout
Honey cinnamon IPA
She want to find out more about regrained or hear previous episodes of our show
Head to our new podcast page how I built this.
Npr.org and course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to bills. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to
And thanks
So much for listening to the show this week
Subscribe to our program at Apple podcast or wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write us at HRBT at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet it's packed how I built this
A shows produced this week but run abdel-fattah with original music composed by Rammstein that are blue
Thanks also to Newark could see Santa's meshkinpour Neva Grant and Jeff Rogers
Our intern JC Howard
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
Running PR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates drag and drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com