Hey it's guy here and we got a great episode for you today from our archives it's on Burton Snowboards
But before that the show just a quick reminder that
Throughout the month
December
We're going to be asking you to make an end-of-the-year gift to your local public radio station
Because your support helps your local station
Keep bringing you the news and stories you depend on
Please
Take a moment to give back to your public radio Community just go to donate that npr.org bill
And thanks
Hello
Here's our episode
Burton
I mean I was like Willy Loman and I was a traveling salesman and I would
Load up my car it was a Volvo Wagon at the time but I remember once going out with
38 doors and I drove around New York State and visited dealers and I went out with 38 I came home with 40
40 snowboard because one guy had given me to back the boss said this is a joke
Brown NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movement they built
How did Jake Carpenter turned a childhood novelty toy
Biggest sports in the world from it Burton Snowboards
So imagine being on an airplane in 1977
You sit down you strike up a conversation with the guy sitting next to you you ask him what he does
Try something like
I make sleds for the snow except
You standing there
Skateboard
You have no idea what he was describing you couldn't have imagined it was in
What are years
Snowboarding would become a multibillion-dollar industry
And if that person next to you or Jake Burton Carpenter
There's no way you've predicted that one day
One out of every three snowboards sold worldwide
Would be a Burton Snowboard and not because he invented the sport he didn't
But there's probably no one on earth who did more to popularize it
And it didn't happen overnight
Ten Years After Jake founded Burton Snowboards
Fewer than 7% of ski resorts even allowed snowboarding
Today
It's hard to find one that doesn't
Anything about Burton Snowboards
Celtic culture around snowboarding
Culture
It was inspired in part by Family ski trips to Vermont
Glenn Jacobs
My dad sort of figured it might be something fun for a family to do
When I was around I guess
Seven or eight and he would take the whole family
I just always had this attachment to snow I mean I
Tomato with mint no school end
Still my favorite thing to do in life is go up to my kids rooms and
In those days are behind me but
Time to get up for school and then after they get up elements of snow day
Winter in 1966 there was a brief craze across parts of America for an hour
Novelty toy called the snurfer
As in snow + surf was basically a stand-up slide that
You could ride down a hill
A carpenter was one of the thousands of kids who bought one
For ten bucks
It was a 4 ft long piece of wood that was about six or seven inches wide
No edges
When you stood on it on this Earth
Staples it gave you traction and yet a rope attached to the nose
It was a little bit like you were riding a bucking bronco just getting down the hill
But it was fun
And I
Brunswick made them they sold 800000 or something like that
But it developed a sort of called
In a positive sense of the word
Nike friends and
We would do it together and we would modify them
For me
The surfer was the opportunity to serve who's basically surfing on snow
Surfing on snow
Not always Jake's childhood was
Free great even idyllic
But then when he was about 13
Things started to unravel
Jake's older brother George was
Killed in battle in Vietnam
And a few years later
His mother died as well
And for Jake
Hey what's up
Pretty tough time
Even ended up getting expelled from his boarding school
I mean I was a wiseass
And when I was young
To a fault
End
When I got kicked out of
Brooks was the school and I went up to see the Headmaster
It was a head master 1
My father was
And when my brother was there
It was brutal need my dad made me get in the car and go 5 hours see this guy you know for a 5-minute conversation
And then a long drive home and that is when I decided to turn my life around and start
Applying myself to whatever the hell I did
Did apply himself by figuring out how to take what he was good at
And make money out of
Jake's first Venture was a small Landscaping
And then after college
He went to work for an investor in Manhattan
In the back of his mind
Never forgot about the snurfer
In about its potential to be something much
Much bigger
Yai
Really from the very beginning of Surfing for me
I saw as
Something that could be developed
And I was sure that Brunswick was going to do it or somebody was
And nothing happened
But you know
In the back of my mind I always knew it could be a sport and I didn't have a business plan for a site but I did the math that
If I can make 50 snowboards a day I can make $100,000 a year
And that would be
Awesome
You thought I'm going to I can do something in the thing to do is
Makeup much better Surfer
Yeah make money on it
So I started the company in 77
Because you were living in Manhattan that the
The time right yes and I made my first
Prototypes in my apartment on the Upper East Side 80s
Shop in your apartment in like
Table saw and stuff in or I was just clueless then as you are now
I did not know how to do it I was a loser in shock last
School like my napkin holder was by far the ugliest or The Warriors
And so there I was with a saber saw
In my apartment making them
Like out of what
Yeah I would the very first
Skype with modifying some Surfers
First ever round and then
I said I got to move to Vermont
Why this company
We not going to start a snowboard company in Manhattan
So I left my job in New York City in
Like early
December at the winters here and I start a landscaping business
When will Spring start
Radiant Moissanite
I had a car station wagon a narrative in the family on
Fox garbage bags a couple of rake
That's what I started like landscape business with
Manufacturing is a lot tougher than mowing lawns
But I thought okay it's winter now the time start the company I almost missed the next one
Literally it took so long to develop a product
And if you finance
Get the money
Well my
Because my mother died
Young age when my grandmother died
She had some dough and instead of going to my mother came to
Me and my two sisters
And so I inherited almost $200,000
I spent a hundred and fifty of it
Developing Burton
So
Your middle name is Burton
Yes
Carpenter so why did you call the
Snowboards
I just always had this
Interest
And the guy was named after
John house Burton and I
Doctor
Burton was a
Cooler name
And I wanted to name it boards I mean boards was part of the name was Burton boards
And then I
Drove down to Montpelier Vermont and Incorporated went to the
We so cold that all the paperwork and everything was a big moment for me
Incorporation
Or
And maybe Burton Board they started it
Some form of
Trademark
Petite next to Android n
Yeah have anything official
So you okay see you you moved to Vermont and then to start this thing and then
What was your next step
Yeah so I went to this company called
Shushan Bentwood company and they made
Curved wood for people that made furniture out of solid Ash
Oh wow
So my first prototype was a piece of solid Ash that was just put in this thing to curve the nose
And then I
Just start writing
The money I was like literally made a hundred
But all those under prototypes they weren't all solid wood I got onto laminated wood vertically laminated and Horus
Zardoni laminated like
Plywood I went to a friend too
Live in California who had a surfboard company
And they would let me make
Boards in their Factory at night
And I would take a surfboard blank which is
Six or seven feet long and maybe three or four inches thick and by the morning I have whittled the pink down to us
And they were just these guys were so cool but they laughed at me when you went to these Factory you said I need you to
Give me this curved piece of water this piece of material
What is a 4 what would you
Tell them I'm in the store for there was some awareness
It has been around
So I was telling him that I was
Making a modern rendition of an
And I always feared that like the minute
Ski companies caught wind of this that
They were just jump on and I'll be out of business in no-till nobody care
Nobody cares
And it wasn't just you like
With this thing like
Messing around on Hills
Dude I was so alone yet
Giver come across people like what what is that
What are you doing
Yes it was
To the point
Literally if I was in a plane somewhere to ask me what I did I would make something up
Cuz I was just too
Embarrassing
Dai concept of snowboarding wasn't something that it would be like saying today
Yeah I ride cloud
Like that's my job I make state board for cloud skateboarding for sure
SuperSU at what point were you able
How to say I got it I've got this is the one I'm going to make
I hadn't thought about this in a long time but
I remember that specific moment on Mount Washington
In June
And you can hike up Mountain you know that you know would have been June of 78
And I'm hiking up there and Hellman's Highway was a trail and I had to board
Orwell just testing the final
Test and it was horizontally laminated
Rock Maple very much like Escape
What's better and more flexible
And I wrote
Now you know just hiking uploaded writers like okay
And then I've decided on the construction now so I go out and I
Rent this place that's going to be this little
Factory
And I hired to relatives
And a friend
To help me
Take these pieces of curved wood and
Shape them
Drill them paint them with fins on them but mad on them with bindings on them
It was a long process and we
As I said my original plan was to make 54 today that was always sort of my goal because you thought that they were just going to this is going to blow
Glow up
I majored in economics
Call Ajay
Classes with
Nobel Prize winners but I don't know if I really understood supply and demand
YouTuber shot
In Londonderry Vermont with Burton boards written on the front of it and big letters who are the kinds of people
Coming into your shop in Londonderry
Vermont
And sing out by 1
Yeah it wasn't
People
Out for a walk
Buying a snowboard in
We didn't sell any maybe a few t-shirts but
Are most people found out about us that would come there and
People we would advertise in the skateboard magazines in a little bit and ski magazine to spend some money there I mean I
Because there were these pockets
Around the country in Michigan and Arizona are these places were people
Hatsune
And like me and they sort of stuck with it and they got it they understood it
Cat first year
What kind of feedback are you getting from people
Who bought them do they love it they were day like this is going to change the world
Yeah it was
I mean I was
Like Willy Loman and I was a traveling salesman and I would
Load up my car
It was a Volvo Wagon at the time and I remember once going out with
38 Star Wars and I drove around New York State and visited dealers and I went out with 38 I came home with 40
40 snowboard because one guy has given me to back that he bought instead
No One Is Your Love
Pua would visit ski shops
Bicycle shops yeah that was my first
And then ultimately
You know some
Surf shops in
It was in the beginning skateboard shop surf shop ski shops nobody wanted any part of it and he did you have will udisc
Did you think maybe this is not going to work maybe I should
Just got paid
Yeah I had some I had a few days it was tough
Getting out of bed
Just motivating myself
Right I mean you are getting rejected all the
All day long
And you're all by yourself
Yeah
And I am like I'm an emotional guy and you know grabbing boss
People winning
Always happen
So I had to let go of
My chihuahua doesn't my friend very quickly
Olympic Games
Back to me
And you're too because we made enough boards
In that first winter I don't know what are we made of
We made an effort
3 years today just sitting here box but yeah they're pretty much done
So I had one high school kid helping me out
Part-time and now is it
Did you guys sell their first year
First year was $300 3/52 year was 700 I member one day and
That second winner of selling
Packing up to 700 forward and thinking
Wow that's
You know that's over doubling
So what happens
Net first unit second ear when you go from
302 700
Why why did you double
The number for was it just
Black
Who is just getting out there Word of Mouth
I'm in marketing
You know advertising placing ads in these
Ski Surfer skateboard mags
I mean I remember going to check the mailbox cuz dealers really weren't that interested
You know
Stores
And so we would send out these brochures right from your one we had brochures and
We would send them out with a little male or four minutes
And I would go to get the mail every day and I remember looking in the mailbox and would be like either
Nothing
Couple of envelopes or Sundays are be five or six envelopes
Then you open up the thing in it that is cruel order form and you can get it
You'd open up the envelope it'll be
It up two t-shirts or something
And then you'd open up an envelope would be like for snowboards for a family in Connecticut I mean
I can remember it so
Clearly and where could you actually use them
I'm assuming you couldn't
Take it to ski resort and just go down
Nobody was presented
I mean
Skiing at the time was 20 bucks a day
It was a lot of money so this was an opportunity to
Express yourself and have fun out and do with friends and
It was
A cheap way to have a lot of fun when it's snowing
You could not
Going to Resort
And to be honest
I didn't start as a resort
You didn't tear no it wasn't that wasn't it was like
A low-cost alternative to
Denny's kids
Who
Then I started to hiring more
Maybe your
Free to watch
To just help
Assemble these boards put them in boxes and get them out the door still doing all the assembly in that place in Vermont yes
And hand
Powerline
Yeah they were just help me get the boards out the door
This one Resort Brahma you could drive up to this Village that was
What are the way up the mountain
So we would buy one of the car drive up to the Village
Everybody would
If there are four of us one guy would stay in the car the other three with snowboard down the hill
And then we can meet at the bottom and do it again and again and then ultimately
Snowcat drivers would give us rides and
Bribe snowcat drivers with 6 pack or something you up to a point of the mountain
It was so challenging to ride those boards
People now they have these vintage races naked on
Also words and I for the life of me don't get it I mean it's you know
Hard but
It was just easy on rebellious I mean
What snowboarding and Burton did as we revolutionize
Winter life
Dandong
This was the beginning of it
When
Really start to take off
Well I mean in terms of the sport or my company I mean it was nothing
I think
Now in the context of starting a business people think of
Internet companies investing explode and they wanted there just was not
A defining moment in the context of
The sport blowing up I mean they were big Milestones along the way and
Timer
Calling at the worst new sport
Yeah that would have been
Early 80s
And part of that time
Sing the worst new sport was they said it was more about raging hormones and this was his rebellious young man
That were making it happen and then
Cool girls very courageous
Women got into it and started doing it
And I realized okay
We're not
Going to lose any more money
We might not make money but I can you know manage
Manage this financially
Play so
It just
Grew and grew and grew but at a manageable pace
Why didn't ski resort allow snowboarders
In the beginning
Well it was it was
Actually famous cases Stratton which was Resort when the First Choice let us know where this guy at Stratton
It's in southern Vermont
And that this guy
Broken his leg because of some
Sign or something skiing
Annies through the mountain and ID try to get
Definitely got a million dollars
So there was this liability
I'm there's this just
Paranoia about
Getting sued
That's all that was their fear but
They ultimately would give us a chance and we would lobby with them and their kids sometimes help than we would Lobby Resort
Shorts and then if a big Resort like that and then Bramalea to come along in Magic Mountain
It took years
But it was
There was no stopping at that point also I guess
Start identify people who are really good snowboarders and and
Sponsor them
Yeah we'll for a minute there these kids at work for me just happened to be
The best and then
There was a writer Great Khali who actually wrote for his company sends you started making snowboards after we did but they
Pretty well-known skateboard company and this guy Craig Kelly wrote for them but we were good friends that always.
Don't cry gif
You ever had the opportunity
We would love for him to ride for us and then Sims ultimately sold his company to Biggers
Skateboard company and so we got a deal anymore for me and I paid him $17,000 a year
And this guy was on Craig Kelly was a godson all Wheaties Birds
He was burned all over his
Yes
So having him
Represent Britain
That was my pre transformational
It was beyond Transformers
Cuz you're out all of a sudden not only
Give this advertisement
But you got the coolest
And the best guy
You can do all this
Cool Staffing
You got kids saying that's no lie
Well
I want to try this and I guess Burton's the way to go cuz this guy uses Burger
You know what that's
Pretty much it
Craig made the sport cool and the brand cool
When did snowboarding start to get bigger
The ski companies must have thought well
There's money to be made here right like
K2 in Ruston LA
Did they start to make snowboards
It's just so funny that this ski companies were so
Oblivious to what was going on in front of their eyes
I mean
Talk about
Close minded
You know
Rescue earlier destroyed
Rumors that some cucumbers going to start making in the neck
We went from being
Fly in the windshield
Straight through all of a sudden
We became a threat
In just a minute had Jake dealt with the competitors
I wanted a piece of the action stay with this guy Roz you listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
NPR
Gyros
Early days for Jake Carpenter
Building Burton and build the whole sport of snowboarding
Sometimes lonely
But because he stuck with it because the sport cut on
The biggest companies as you can imagine started to notice
And all of a sudden the market for snowboards so lonely anymore
Okay so when when the big ski company started to to make snowboards
What happened to you guys well by the time they started making a weird maybe on the 3rd of the resort
And then
They didn't want the sport to happen right I mean these
He companies did not want snowboarding succeed
So didn't like ski company
I mean people
Did perceive them as not being a real deal
And we didn't keep that a secret I mean we made it
Pretty damn clear that we were the real deal and
What day did
Have manufacturing ability and some of those French and Austrian companies were
Subsidized by the government
To keep their factories going
So, cost perspective they were lower-cost producer
For a minute there
But it was just they were too late
They missed the boat
Did you ever have
Is snowboarding really begin to take off in the
Did you ever face serious threats from
Competitors either big or small
Well it was always like in the early days was a rivalry between bird and Simsbury
We've doubled the number of snowboards sold
For the first 20 years I think of
The company so
Sims with red one point K2
Was somewhat of a thread
Got more aggressive earlier on
But now we've been
We've been the number one
Manufacturer
Snowboards
What's the day I
You know what I mean even though you
Addthis market share this little customer base
He's had a lot more money to work with
And you were
Your money was coming from sales
Yeah and ultimately we were borrowing money from Banks
I was very secure
And then
We would get bigger and bigger and obviously we're doubling our sale so we're doubling the money that we need from the bank and you need some money
Is the money for marketing and for what
We needed the money to make the snowboards because in this industry and skiing
We didn't start this
But you do shipping the stuff and whatever
August September
And then you don't get paid until
December January
So it was always working capital we've never needed long-term debt
But we've always had this need for working capital
And so we would work with these Vermont Banks and we'd get up to a certain levels have like three times
And then we get dresser level I sent you.
Maybe if I were going to bail
Never cuz we were late on a payment or
Young people money that we owe them
But they just sort of figured you know this has been a good ride we're going to
Bail and then we go to a bigger bank and then a bigger bag and then
We borrow we still borrow some working capital but it has become
Less and less
At any point did you think about
Going public doing IPO
Seeking venture-capital outside investors
Anything like that
Yeah interesting Lee
There was this one company called ride
And they started out
And then a guy that work for us what to work for that new sort of a mid-level manager wasn't was a competing snowboarding company
Convenience opening company you want to work for them and then they went public
Can they at a very low price
And the stock went up to
It's split and then we're up to
35 box was up to 70 on it
Non-solicit evaluation
Which was a millionaire all of a sudden and I felt this
Enormous
Amount of pressure
Like I taking care of my people and yeah I bet
And like
Just am I doing the right thing here and so I went and I met
With
A couple of big
New York
Investment Banking firms and I
Couldn't deal that the Bible I just was like this is nice
And then all of a sudden
Right stock
Which was it 35 bucks at
The time went down to
2 Box
Because they have these expectations
Is that
Like Wall Street just they take things and they
Project
Unrealistic
Expectation
So ultimately people have realized
Working for a privately held company
As many many advantages
I guess it was in like
98 snowboarding became an Olympic sport
You I know that you don't like to
Say this and you deny it but
You are widely credited as the guy who really made snowboarding what it is and
This is became an Olympic sport
What did you think when that happened like that must have been a pretty amazing moment
It was
Not
Cool moment at all
That was not the answer I was expecting what happened well
Best witches
International ski Federation
Swiss
You know whatever governmental body and they
I'm control the scene and then they started having snowboard competition
When they just said
Aside from the ski races and we were wondering what they were up to
And then they just arbitrarily decide okay so what's going to be the Olympics I mean they didn't even give me a phone call they never
How old is anything
I
Will take credit for pioneering
Miss Barton you would think
Then you might
Pick up the phone and tell that person what you're up to or
How do you think we should do this
None of that they just arbitrarily
It's like the baseball player that finds out he's traded when he reads in the newspaper
And then I go to the Olympics
We've got our team there and then I get to the venue and they got snowboarding misspelled
How to spell as well you spell it with a W snowboarding
But that as a no hyphen boarding is in Nagano Japan
Not a good sign
Right so
And then they proceeded to have the
The racing thing was
Heart conditions
And then
Decided it was a
Driving rainstorm
And they say okay we can have that
Monsanto we would never have this
Prestigious event in the rainstorm
But they can go they can get
Risk life and limb and not be wearing goggles
It's raining so hard
And so
But nonetheless
They've gotten
Better and they're doing it better and better job in the American armed it's a form of
Rob National associations
They care about this morning I've got some people to care about the sport they're trying to do better but
The last Olympics the venues for the freestyle stuff which is what
People care about
For the half pipe and slopestyle that the Bengals have been
Really sketchy
As your company grew
Describe the culture of the time
Was it I mean
I'm looking at you right now and I cannot imagine you ever wearing a suit and tie
And being like a boardroom boss
Schleich do you have your
Meetings with your top team instead of how do you
What are meetings you know you look at my office
It's
3 sofas and
Do chairs in a coffee table and there's no desk
Senior composite board meetings at cellphone
Put your feet up
Bring your dog to work and
132 registered dogs are between always heard of
Keep track of the number and
It's
Resembles snowboarding
Lifestyle
Edward tribe and we
Are so focused on the sport everybody in that cup you know damn near everybody in that company so bored
And cuz that's our source of energy that's where you recharge your battery
Jake I'm going to be in late today. Snowboarding
It's
Pretty much
The Dramamine if it snows over two feet it's an automatic
Day off at all company
And last year they were
3 of those days which is almost too nice I mean I like people to work to on that
It's
But people come in late and work late
You know people work hard there so that's
As long as people are giving us a solid effort I get it if they want to get up there and catch a few runs on a great day
You're a your wife.
She she actually at some point became
Took over as it as a Company CEO right
Yeah
What's the story there
Well she came
And went and then
She was even CFO for a while this is nearly days and then
When we had kids she backed off some she wasn't working as much then and then
When the financial crisis hit which was
Really right here Vine
The big one
Lehman Brothers All That
Hit you guys
Well
The bank
Charge this 4 million dollars to change one paragraph
Car loan agreement
Which was called a covenant when you're borrowing money
Your earnings had to represent a certain ratio compared to how much money or borrowing
And we
Slipped on that one
It was a very tough year
And we weren't losing money we were making money
But literally they said well you broke his coming in so
You're going to pay a $4000000 fee
And that
Boy I mean
With the lay people off
We weren't making the money that we had been I so we had snowboard
Is the recession
Yes exactly
But you know what it's
Always been a youth Rivermark and it's kids and I mean people would buy
Two or three snowboards a year
Can you look at
Italy or Spain to very big Market
It's for us
And the unemployment rate amongst people under 20 was 50%
It was a very tough
Stop time
And now
Through this process
Of this
Crisis and I think it's not unique to Burton
Art
Company culture kind of got
Destroy happen
Well I think a lot of people would
Blame other people
First things
Negative things
What's the weather happening in there would be finger pointing in
The culture of our company
Was messed up and at the same time
I felt
You're no women in our top manager
And that
Just felt wrong to me so
I got in there and I been Donna came along with me and
At that level we were running the company and I brought her and
Serta specifically that
Help with the culture and get
More women in leadership positions at Burton
When you see the culture I mean I'm just trying to get in through the
Innuendo
What's it like
Growish was it like
Male solo Macho was it like
I am what was the thing you want to change
Well
I mean you're not happy when
You're being managed by fear
Or
For you
Instill fear in yourself that you're going to lose your job or
It's just you need to make people
People have to understand
When and why
Stuff happen
Or you responsible for any of that
Friday event
Fear-based up
Well I think
IPod
Many of the people that were
In and around it and I think that
We were all responsible to a certain extent I mean I don't think that's ever been a
Tactic that I've used hopefully
But I certainly let it happen under my nose
Do you think that that you have a hard time
With criticism
And I said because you know
It it didn't really problematic right if you're unwilling to
I want to listen to somebody
It says listen I know you built this thing
But I'm trying to make it better listen to me
No that's
Couldn't be more true but less and less and less every year I mean I
Did every job that count
IMEI made
The first board
And for a while there I mean we might have had
50 employees and I was convinced
Not in that in a bragging way but I could do anybody's job
Better than
But that's not the case anymore you know we've been Engineers now that I don't even
Do you have a hard time having a conversation with him
I got better at it
And I had the sense to
Surround myself with people
Better
Red things
Then I am that I'm not good at it
That's been good enough learned
To delegate
That's not an easy thing to learn how to do specially when you're detail-oriented learn to let go like that
You have to trust
Beyond trusting you have to let him screw up
Young live with it and live through mistakes and if they repeat the mistakes and that's not
It sign
Burton's made every mistake in the book
But I don't think we've made too many
Twice
Why can I'm sure at certain points you were offered money to
I just didn't take those phone calls you could I mean
You could have sold this company
Open like a philanthropist and
I don't know a better life for sounds pretty cool it's like a pretty great life
Well I
For a long time if people ask me that question I would say well
I think I've become a couch potato and
Egyptian watch
SportsCenter
So you don't snowboard funny but
I mean it's the best job in the world why would I ever walk away from it that's
Selfishly admittedly
That's always
Ben
Part of it and I think they were doing a great job and we're humming along if if we were
Really struggling
Might be
More appropriate for me to look at that more
Seriously
Important is money to you
Is being rich to you
Well
To be brutally honest
I mean
Bye
Enjoy having
Eligibility financial aid
We're going surfing for a week in the Maldives next week my all family
And we're going to have a speedboat it's going to take us to the lineup
It's going to be epic and the stuff that cheap
So I love that and I would be a liar if I told you I didn't
But it's not the most important thing in life yeah
You're a really tough couple years
Your chest
Now
Internet recovery of it
Any surgery
I guess in 2015
And then
And then before that you had
Heart surgery
Right
And then you battled cancer
Testicular cancer
Yeah and I dealt with the whole process of chemotherapy which is
Dreadful
And in them
Tell lender that I was in a plane and I had a pulmonary embolism which
Really
Still
Affects me
And then I came down with that
Miller-fisher that form of gamma ray
Miller Fisher because
A lot of people know about this but
It's
I guess it's an autoimmune disease that can make you temporarily
Paralyzed
So
Like what was that what was going on like
Why did you even discover
What was going on
Well I'd gotten a knee replacement
And then I got home
And I was with the doctor
Next day in
I started seeing double and and
I told him that he's like
Check it out see if
I might just go away
The next day I was seeing double
And
I felt really lousy
And I wait till Donna went to work I didn't cheat
Through so much
With me and
And so I went to Dartmouth-Hitchcock and they
Barry
Quickly analyze what was going on and
Within 24 hours of meeting be in there they said if you have always take you out tomorrow you won't be able
Swallow
Open your eyes
Next day won't be able to breathe
And were they right
Yeah that's how it went down
That's what you get to the hospital and you are confined to the bed
Surprise you for 6
6 weeks
You couldn't move your body
Hours or days
And I was there for
Over 6 weeks
You're like a prisoner in your own body
Yeah
Very much so
I think it's like
ALS
Handstand do a couple of weeks
So first of all
How do you breed
Do a ventilator
And
The ventilator was
Behind me
Could hear it
Pregnancy
Did you have
Feeling in your body
Yeah
Yeah my wife would stretch me every night
Can I get Siri
Feel that
Repeating 2
Did you think your aunt died
For sure
For a minute
And then
You're my wife did
You know she told me I was getting better and
Eventually I would see these little
Improvement
What you start to notice
You know that I could open my eyes
And that I do.
I was showing the physical therapy right for me
And then I could do something a little better than
The day before
And once you get to that point then it's game on. It's up to you
Is that it
Experience change the way you
Live your life
And you interact
To the people you love
Well I sure as hell don't take my family for granted
Seymour in
I do live life
But the moment I mean
Much more than ever I mean I think
It happens through some
I don't know why or how
You're dead to me
Emma's put into perspective
All your success
And wealth in the thing
But you built like
Obviously that stuff matters but like in the context of your life
Nothing else
Really matter
Yeah yeah that stuff could have been further from my mind
I think it is now though now I'm like prepared to die
Really yeah I am much more so
I could
Die
Get hit by a bus walking out of your studio and I still think I'm
Luckiest
China world
Because of the life you had yes
Could you ever have imagined
When you were
And that first you need to fire your
Employees in
That you would have built something this big
I have no idea that what would happen over and I saw a sport
But I did not see
Shaun White on the cover of Rolling Stone twice or snowboarding be in the Olympics
The stuff that's happened
And it's been the athletes would have made it happen then we've facilitated it but it's been
Exceeded
I wouldn't even say dreams cuz I never dreamt anyting on the level that were on Now
Chapin Carpenter
By the way Burton just celebrated 40 years in business since Jake built that first snowboard in the barn
Londonderry Vermont back in 1977
And despite his health issues Jake still snowboards 100 days a year
Always winners fresh powder
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the
Things your building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsors Microsoft
Who wants you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family
Surface Pro 6
Has up to 13 and a half hours of battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Ever work takes
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that and today we're updating a story we ran
About a year ago so my name is Jana. I'm from Scarsdale New York
And
One day I was just so sick of opening my refrigerator and seen Brown guacamole Brown guacamole
We've all been there right
You scoop out the soft avocado flash imagines
Onion salt maybe some cilantro you stick it in the fridge and then a couple hours later
That bright green dip looks kind of gross
This is absolutely a problem that people have and I saved them would you like a container that prevents got your guacamole from turn
Turning brown
Oh my God so anyway about four years ago Jane started to experiment in her kitchen
She made a lot of guacamole
Start to observe that guacamole change color if I make some and put it in a bowl with
Saran wrap it turns brown
But if there was some way that I could eliminate
That
Air index
Space
Then maybe I could solve that age-old problem so Jane recruited her step-sister to help out
They found a designer and together they came up with a
Plastic container with
Cut up a little elevator underneath it
It pushes the guacamole to the very top
So there is no space between your guac
And the list
And then you simply
Close the tab to cover the air hole
Put it in the refrigerator
Forget about it literally forget about it I mean
A week however long you're going to eat your guacamole it will not
Turn brown okay so they had the right design
But for two years they ran into one problem after another
They were using the wrong
Cheerios or little elevator thing wasn't spinning properly
But finally
A couple years ago
They got out of the factory into the market
And they called it
The guac lock
You can lock anything up
So
Tuna fish egg salad you know chopped vegetables pesto hummus
In the more you can smash it and remove the air holes
The better it's been saved
Searching this is not my main problem with guacamole because
It was to lock your
Meaning of kids ask the guacamole Toledo before your desk up
That's a good idea that is a problem in my house that's our problem I get into the kitchen I just feel like green
Guacamole around the mouths of my children I feel your pain
Nationwide like a child exactly
What actually is very funny that you said that
Because a lot of people say I never have leftover guacamole why would I need this
I'm going to always say to them is
Now you can make in advance
Let's J knock
Co-founder of the guac lock
Last year she and her stepsister Sharon did close to $1000000 in sales
There most of the major stores now
And they're on track to do even better this year
Tucker partnering with Bradshaw Industries
Which is one of the biggest
Suppliers of
Kitchen gadgets
In the world
And if you want to learn more about the guac lock or here
Previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and course if you are
Tell us your story going to build
Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please do give us a review Jelsa right to us
HRBT at npr.org and do you want to send a tweet
How I built this and please be sure to check your podcast feed because we have two more new episodes from
How I built this Summit coming up
I live interviews with Lisa Price Carol's daughter and Katrina Lake Stitch fix
It was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by rum team Arab Louie
Thanks also to JC Howard North could see Neva Grant Michigan for Jeff Rogers
Our intern Disney event cat has been listening to how I built this NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com