Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign
An email marketing
Used by more than
In 250000 cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email
And customers
7 days away
Campaign
Weather.com
It just a quick thing before we start the show
Tickets for R2 upcoming live shows in New York
And LA
Went on
Sale last
Friday both of these shows are
Supported by America
Express
But tickets are moving fast so don't miss
Your chance
Head over to NPR presents
. org right now
To get yours
I used to hire an interview every person that walked in that brand
And then I didn't anymore and all of a sudden there were people working on my brand that I never met with
And then I might not have hired and you know it was a struggle and I tried to let go of the deep
Details
Then I realized the details what makes the company so special and so
I kept thinking I could fix it if we could just do this if I could get this it could be better
And it didn't get better
From NPR
Is how I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories
Lego
Artist named Bobby Brown
Dealt a billion dollar line of cosmetics by doing what
Making women look
Like a fart wearing
Any makeup
Why is a kid back in the 90
My older sister
Add a collection of those
Porcelain Mardi Gras masks on
Bedroom wall
Colorful faces
Is painted with
Blue eyeshadow and
Hebrews streaks
Across the cheek
The reddest lipstick no human good
Anything about those masks
They looks like models you see on the cover of fashion
Models didn't hide their makeup makeup
That was loud
Brash
The look
Was anything but net
This is the world that Bobby Brown
Kind of broke into
As a young makeup artist in the fashion in the
She loved everything about makeup
Except
The weight actually made people look
And so she was searching for a way to use it so that models look
Like they weren't really wearing it at all
So you know lipstick that was the
The color of
Actual lip sore
Blush.
Make you look like you were blushing
Eyeshadow that matches your skin tone
Spell particularly revolutionary
Today but
When Bobby Brown started to bash together off-the-shelf cosmetics
Come up with a new look
She was trying something
Totally different
She was
Trying to convince women that
Makeup
The bee well
Almost invisible
In summer fellow makeup artist
She-Devil zero left
Trying to sell that natural look
But of course today
Cosmetics is a brand that's been estimated to generate over a billion dollars of Revenue
Year a year
And Bobby never thought of herself as a businesswoman
She didn't set out to design a whole new line of cosmetics
Little girl in
Suburban Chicago
She remembers
How much you love watching her mom get ready to go out for the evening
My mother was
The most glamorous
Stunning woman she look
Like a young Jackie Kennedy
And I still watch her put her makeup on with her false eyelashes
Her eyeliner
The skinniest could be should be
Be standing there
With a cigarette hanging off of the counter
And I would just be sitting there watching her
And she I watched everything I watched her take her Brown
Pencil witch
Now we know is Led
And fill in your eyebrows
And with a toothpick put on false eyelashes
And bronzer on her cheek
Pale lip on
And go out you know with my dad Wednesday nights and Saturday nights
And I was in awe
You know I could never ever ever be that glamorous
And I was you know the shortest
I'm always
And you know not
The skinniest
But I was really lucky
Because the other side of that I had my grandmother and my aunt Alice
Who are more like me
Really simple
Comfortable shoes
You know people comfortable in their skin
And at the same time by the way
The beat the girls the models that were really popular
Where is Cheryl Tiegs
Oh yeah
And all these you know blond Barbie doll looking girls
Which I was not one of them
I you know
Thick eyebrows
Dark hair
You know I wasn't that
And then
The thing that changed my life
Was going to see the movie Love
Oh yes what's up with Ali MacGraw and I'll never forget I I I was somehow in middle I must
But in 7th grade
And I remember sitting there looking at this girl
Dark shiny hair
Parted down the middle
No apparent makeup
And literally
For the first time in my life I said
I could be pretty too
To change my life Ali MacGraw
Change your life
Change my self-esteem and my
You know
My my confidence and
Figuring out
Who I am
So when you don't have time for you to
Leave
Home and go to college what did you would you say
Well I I
Went to
You know with a lot of my friends are probably a dozen of us
That went freshman year of
Of college to University of Arizona in Tucson
And I was
Sober
That's cool you know because you would sit in it
It's a huge university
And you'd sit in these big giant halls with
500000 people and see this little teeny professor
At the end of lecture
With it on overhead projector
And I certainly it was not the way that I was
To learn so
And I went through the motions and the end of the year
I came home and I told my mom I wanted to drop out of school
Animal says you can't
And I said but why Mom it's so boring I don't want to go to college she says
I never graduated
College inches you have to
I said Mom I have no clue what I want to do
My mother said
Remember the two chairs we are sitting at
I was sitting cross-legged as I always do and she said
Okay forget what you want to do with your life
If today was your birthday you could do anything you want what would you want to do
I have no idea
And I remember as I always do quickly
Saying the first thing that popped into my head was
I want to go to Marshall Fields
And play with makeup
The big Marshall Fields
In downtown Chicago it actually in the suburbs cuz that's where I live but I wanted to go to the store and play with me
My mom said
Why don't
You
You know why don't you study makeup
Justin Rochester why don't you study makeup and I said Mom
I want to go to Beauty School
And she said no I'm sure there's a
College
Somewhere where you
You could study makeup
So I
Actually
My Dad's friend tell me about the school embossed
Skin called Emerson
That
Will let me study makeup
This is the summer after
For your first year of college
Right that was literally two weeks
Before I was supposed to go back to Arizona
And
My car was actually
Yuno packed when I made
The decision to go to m
So was it was like it was like days before
I follow up with my dad
Went to Emerson and and I asked
If they had to make a program they said no but we have something called
An interdisciplinary
Reprogram
And you can create your own major
Ensure you can study make
I said I'm in
I'm going
And honestly when I got to Emerson
I found my
It was a school
Full of kids like me
Creative diary
Entrepreneurial
And you're creating films and you're creating you know all different art projects
I remember even doing
Films and you know they pair you with someone
Instead of doing things a normal I would
Which is like oh what kind of film should we do
I remember thinking about what kind of makeup I wanted
What to do in writing the film around the make
What was it about
Makeup that you like to that spoke to
Well it wasn't even just
Makeup it was everything that goes along with
So I've always been someone
Dad knew how to use makeup
Differently than other people did so
And doing theatrical makeup making someone look older like
It character
Was amazing for me because in order to do makeup for play
For a film you have to read the script
Need to talk to the director
You have to create
What the
What the person is going to look like do they have a hard life
How do you make them look tired how do you make them look old
I have to go
Figure it out and understand it and then make the girls look like
So when you when you
Finished
At Emerson
Did you was your intention to do theater
Makeup yes
So I graduated
Emerson and 79 and a month before I graduated I was in my bedroom reading
Mademoiselle Magazine and there was an article about a freelance makeup artist in New York named Bonnie Maller
And I never heard of a freelance make
Makeup artist and she was doing all the fashion shows and doing makeup work
Work for Calvin Klein and Perry Ellis and I wrote to her
And I said can I come to New York and assist
She never wrote me back
No no no no
She didn't want me back but I looked her up in the phone book and I called her
On her answering machine.
She said hi Bonnie if I am not getting back to you I'm probably on-location call my agent Bryan Bantry to one
To blah blah blah
So I go to New York for a visit and I call Bryan Bantry and he said come up and talk to me
And he explained to me how
Freelance works
And I
Started just figuring it out
So I'm
You know I moved to New York
And I didn't know anyone
Arrowhead Bryan Bantry had a meeting with him
And he started to know slowly calling me
App to be an assistant
To some of his
People he didn't represent me but he let me be honest
So you
You get to New York and and you decide that you want to be
Makeup artists in that this was going to your life like
So how did you
How do you start a good job
Well I actually thought I would do fashion on the side until I broke into TV
So one of the things I did
There's another make of ours her name was Bobby
And she was the Mega bars for Saturday Night Live
I assisted her a few times
So you know that was cool and I remember doing a couple times you knows
The makeup artist on the Evening News couldn't make it I would do that so
You know it was a I started a freelance career
The only way
I paid my rent
At that time
Where's my dad
Gave me
$500 a month
To pay my rent
And in what
I got this time
In your life did you feel like
There were expectations that you aren't fulfilling I don't know I mean
Chart of middle-class home in Chicagoland
Your dad was a lawyer and and so
Do you ever thinking like
Oh man
And you know like my parents having sex
Locations of me in and I need to
I don't know I mean would you ever
I was thinking like that or worried about you
Can I tell you why one I have this
Really weird gif
You know you don't know what's a gift until you're you know of a certain age and look back
I am so naive
So I never think something's not going to work out and I never did
Dead so
I was not worried
Yes I was always anxious about how I was going to
Pay the rent or if I had enough money for this
And might I remember calling my dad one day and I said Dad
I just can't stick to this budget I had a credit card with a limit I think I had $250 a month limit
And I kept
She don't crying all these fees and I said that I can't stick to this and it's alright stop for me
Put it down
I said okay
He said stop trying to
To stick to a budget
Or create a budget
Why don't you figure out how you're going to make more money
I said
Okay
And I remember telling myself
Monday morning you get up
Can you fill your day book with
So I go see
She's as they call it so
I went I started make an appointment
And as long as I
Monday was my day to
Fill it and then I had the whole week to go see
People so I started calling
Magazines and I'd look on the Masthead and I would see the booking age
I booked with them
I am Bobby Brown I'm a freelance makeup artist
I love
To come in and show you my book
I had a you know a book I like faces that you know faces that I've done
Yes and you start to make
Relationships you come back and see
See people and I did that for a while
So here's my question
I mean what does it
The cow are you
Good like a better makeup artist than someone else
What is it that
You were able to offer
Well alright so let's go back to
The 70s and the 80s
The makeup
Back then
Was
Is the epitome of a natural
Foundation with pink
It stopped at the
At the jawline
It was Contour eyes were eyeshadow was
Yellow
Purple and blue
It was all of those
I was always doing
More of a now it's called a Bobby
Face and now it's called nude makeup but back then
It was just
I always made people look
Healthier
I wanted people to not look like they're wearing makeup and
I even had one
Very very famous makeup artists you know who I asked his opinion on stuff said
You will never work
Because
People don't want to look like that
Can I don't want to look like that people want to look
Made up and
Do you know I just
Couldn't do it so even when I was doing makeup
On TV
I had these really simple things I I looked for
I wanted to make the foundation
To actually be the color of the skin yeah
You know I had a mix and blend
Because most makeup on the market was bad
And you know having a giant
Kit I had everything
Thanks so I would
Can I get a smash a lot of it together
Then people started taking pictures of it
Look really good
So
Do
Are getting steady work
More magazine who was the first
Really big gig
That you can remember getting like a with a major fashion model
Probably
Two of my
Youjizz
Haha like back then was
When I had
Six or eight page spread in American Vogue
With
1 model Tatiana
Petites and it was literally
Full
Face full-bleed full face of makeup story
Only on you know different looks different makeup that was like
Put me on the map
And then the next map was
A cover of Vogue with Naomi Campbell
Wow when was that
Now we're into I think
88 or 89
When she was just starting to be a huge huge deal
So
You know you are doing makeup and that's your life at your career
I was at the top of my game and by the way
You do magazine work in editorial it's fantastic you
No matter how big it is
Do you still get a hundred
$50 a day so you really don't make a whole lot of money no but
When you do advertising
And catalog like catalog at the time was paying
Between 250 and 500 a day and that's when you do makeup
On a bunch of models for a Saks Fifth Avenue or a Macy's and then if it
It's a commercial you got a couple thousand
But everything you do you mean
People and youstina you tend to move in packs if a hairdresser gets
Look for something they book you and then
You know then you start doing advertising and that's
You know
Be up to 5000 a day
And by the way while I did those things I also had
A very very serious relationship
I got engaged
I moved out of the city
I had friends
I had a normal life
I started having kids
The same time
And I chose that
I chose that
I wanted to be
I wanted to go through that tunnel
Put my hair in a ponytail put my sneakers on
Be in the park with my dog
You know I'd rather be home with my
Husband in my baby then you know
State
I can understand why they wanted me to stay at a fashion shoot
Until 10:00
Just because they took a long time
Deciding thing
I'm out of here
Yeah
Show in 1990
I guess that was
Around the time with you
Started to kind of
Explain with your own makeup
Even happen
So
I was pregnant with my first baby
And I was on
A photoshoot for Mademoiselle magazine
Self mag
And it was called makeup shopping
At alternative places with makeup artist Bobbi Brown
And they took me to different places in one of the place
Is downtown I guess I took them
Did I took the crew 2 with kills Farm
Kiehl's at the time was this independently owned cool place
I brought everyone down the rear shooting there and while they were shooting
I was talking to the chemist
That was there and he had a little a couple lipsticks and on my Fork
Kiehl's
Chopshop Family Pharmacy last
Exactly
And it was a chemist on site
There was a chemist on site
And he had these lipsticks and I remember touching them
And I said wow these are really nice he's how I make those
And I said you make them
Yeah I said
Oh I thought I would love to
To be able to
To make a lips
He said I'll make it for
Are you I said
I said what I want
You can't buy it said I want something that doesn't smell
I wanted to be
Creamy but not greasy I want it to
Look like lips
I can't find a Lipstick Alley
Looks like lip color and he's like what do you mean
I said well and I pulled out my taupe
I pencil in my
Pinky blush and I said look at when you put this together
You put a little bit of bomb on it
And blotted on your lips he's like Alright give me those
Anyone home and he sent it to me
And I said oh my God I love this
I said I bet I could sell this
And he said all right
Why don't you sell it for
$15
He said I'll make it you sell it
You'll get 750 I'll get 7
Okay that's a deal
So I had a lipstick
That I called Brown
Cuz I thought it was brown base not cuz of my name
And then I said everyone's going to love that
And I said you know what not everyone has
The same color lips
And I started studying
People's lip color
And then I sat down and I thought about all the different lip colors
And then I said you know some people don't like lip color lipstick they like red
Orange
Someone likes a good beige
Pink
But I said
You don't need 15 different pinks in your makeup kit
Let me make the ideal pink
Let me make the ideal Orange
So I sat down and I thought of 10 different colors
I work for the chemist
He made these colors
And I thought all right let's put a number 1 to 10
Let me name them
I was going to name the way lipsticks are named
Do you know cherries in the snow and
I'm like why don't we call them
Beige
Pink
Orange
Red
So in a raisin
I named them what they look like
So you are doing like more understated
Yes I understand
And what was on the market
Wearable by the way
The word wearable
People could put them on and actually look good
How's that for a concept
You would take like
To to get the right color
What was the name of the
By the way
Steven Steven
Steven
The right color you would take like
I don't know
Paint or or different make ups and just like rubbing together like a
Petri dish recipe I would either mail it to him or I would say.
Do this and
Yeah you know back and forth back and forth
She made them for me and I did everything
And we said yeah make like how many
Like 5-10 sticks
I think you know he probably made
100 of each color
Yasso know once we agreed that we would be paw
Where is there was nothing in writing it was just while this could be interesting
Sting
It wasn't anything more than
And he had like a fabrication
Plantar visibility like
Make moldings around did I don't I think he did it in his home
You know it wasn't it was his side thing
Because he was a chemist
And what were you going to sell each to Calypso
Oregon $15 fifteen bucks
15 bucks
And
When I first started my plan was to
To sell them tomatoes
Editor's
And then one day I was having lunch with a girlfriend who was the beauty editor of Glamour magazine
At the time
It's a what's going on
You know we both had young babies and I talking about the kids and I said
You know I'm doing let me show you this thing
Oh my God
That's so cool she said can I write about
And you had the kind of a reputation in the industry
Because you were
Eye makeup artist
You get this article and Glamour and what
People started calling up an ordering lips
Wind
You know it wasn't like oh my God I'm going to be rich oh my God I could
Pay my mortgage
This month
It was just you know
Steady things coming in and we got a bunch offers
You know people wanted
Purchase lips
EXO
I don't even think
Cannot whistle
Finally sold a bunch of
Does not call Bobby Brown
Yes it was it was
Is it was called Bobby Brown I don't know what else
The calling you just put your name on the side yes
And that was really cool
And then I meet the lady at Bergdorf
And that's when things
Actually
Needed
Change you mean
Whoever.
I ended up going to a
Party in the city with some friends
And
Friends that actually eventually we're going to be our partners
In the company
And I met her friend Allison and I said thanks for inviting me on Bobby
She's a nice to meet you and I
Said what are you doing she said on the Cosmetics buyer at Bergdorf
Wow that's nice
But I never even shopped at Bergdorf Goodman
And I said wow
I'm doing this line of lipsticks
You know perhaps you want to look at them
And she said love to let me bring him in
So what happened you went you brought your look 6 to 2
To show her then a couple days later
She brought them in I mean I had no
Press release I had nothing
She called me back and she said they're really interested we love to take them
That's when
I realize
I hadn't really changed the way we were doing things
And you know I had to find a different way to scale up in the chemist because that was the only way he knew
So I parted ways with the chemist
And I had to find
A lab
To recreate the lipsticks
The way I want it
And we needed to find someone to
To do what I remember making all these calls
But then one day
I was in an elevator
And I said hi to the girl in the elevator and she said hi I think we're on the 11th floor so we had a few minutes elevator in your apart
At my apartment building in New York City and I said
The high
The high and I said what are you do
She said I work at at
I cosmetics
Lab
In Queens
And I said oh
Do you have a card
And
I
Had my lipsticks
I recreated there and they made my lipsticks
I met her in the elevator
Coming up more chance meetings for Bobby Brown and how they help her
Grow the company
Pallet Company got away from her
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this
NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did you come from wix.com
A web platform
Creating your own professional website
With wix
Whether it's your first time creating a website or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning Temple
Lights or start from scratch
With a dragon drop technology
And Powerful web
Joint over 125 million people
Already using Wix to create their own website
Go to Wis
X.com
To create yours today
So what will you cry
Support also comes from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
Their cloud-based plan
Poor man solution
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole come
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the work
They want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive
And engaged
Moret servicenow.com
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
It's the early 1990s
And Bobby Brown is come up with
10 new shades of lipstick
She's got a new Cosmetics lab to make them and a department store that wants
Bergdorf Goodman
We
Pretty much
Emptied our bank account which was I remember 5000 my husband remembers 10,000
Cousin I trust him more than I remember my memory and we actually partnered
With these friends of ours who won girl was in PR in the husband was in the Cosmetics industry
You know so
The four of us partner together or their names
The name of the Roz and Ken Landis
And why did you decide that you want to
To part with
Because my husband and I
Did not have the expertise
We had no idea
Yeah we were you know thirty-one-year-old
Kids
What's a new baby he was in law school he was a real estate developer
I was making fart
I knew how to make these make the lipsticks I knew what it should be
And we were friends
Couple that we are friends with he
I've been in the Cosmetics industry
And she was in PR
So it was you no a magical pairing
That's how we started the branch
And Bobby Brown is born as a
Product at Bergdorf Goodman
Yes and how does it do when it debuts there
Well we thought we would sell 100 lipstick
The first month
Which
You know that was the thought and we did a hundred the first day and were you in in the store we were we had.
On 5th Avenue and there was no room in the
Cosmetics Department
So they put us on a
Table
Outside of
The cosmetics
Department where I think they had you know handbags
And so you know he wasn't for any other reason
The people thought it was a brilliant genius idea that we marketed ourselves
Apart
From the noise of the cosmos
Floor
So you could Finance it with whatever cash you had
Write a review and then
And then you would sell product and then you
You will get paid by Bergdorf Goodman when they go to the next
App Store
While we were at Burgerville we we added pencils
And then we added eyeshadow like we did everything not
Lake strategic
But as they came up and we
We added them and we were pretty much with the
The same lab for most of the time
And then Bergdorf
You know one day we are doing so well at Bergdorf Goodman
They said you know where sister company of Neiman Marcus
Stay with love
To try you in for stores
So we open up for stores and Neiman's stores
Counter right counter yeah they call them doors actually
Play 3 open for doors for stores
Started adding you know products and I would visit the stores and do personal appearances
Usually with my husband and my baby or babies you know in toe cuz we always
You know I never liked to be apart from them and they always came
And I would travel to these Market
And I would be on their local TV I be on in their newspaper
So it was a full-on you know Preston
Did you ever get a by for people like
Who are you
I'm certain
You know an especially in Dallas you know where they would look
Look at me like
She's the Plain Jane type now cuz in Dallas that make up the hair the generator
You know it took a while to Geneva Marcus
Natural demons
Took awhile to be beloved by those women
But also at the same time
I was B
Becoming
Unknown
Beauty expert on The Today Show
Which
Was really a major launch
In the
The brand and The Business
So the story behind the
The Today Show was that I wrote my first book
About about
Cosmetics by makeup
Yeah and then I was having to be in Florida doing a personal appearance
It's for one of my
Makeup products and also for my first book and I'll never forget it was in you know the Inner Circle
Which were the fancy ladies at Neiman Marcus I finished my speech
And I said any question
And the little
Red headed lady in a grandma type
Raise your hand and I went back
You remember I put my hand on her shoulder she was so cute
And she said yes I have trouble keeping my lipstick on
How do I do it and I said well
And I gave her the answer
And she looked at me and she just thinking she said are you Jewish I said
Yes I am
And she said
I've seen you on the Today Show I've been on once I said thank you
And she said as a Jewish this is off microphone
She said you've done so much is there anything else you want to do
I said I don't know I said
I don't know maybe I'd love to be a regular on The Today Show
She said honey
Jeff zucker's my grandson
Deathstalker was executive producer of The Today Show at the time
Mike and
It was a Friday Monday I was on the Today show I was in my dress
You know my PR team at the time was beyond excited doing
How to put your makeup on something probably Katie was interviewing
Jeff came up and he said Grammy
You know wanted me to have you on I said that's awesome and he said
I hear you want to be irregular
I said I'd love to be irregular
Is okay your regular
I said when when can I come back
He said how about next month I said okay once a month is it okay fine
I was on The Today Show for about
12 years 15 years
And honestly being a beauty expert on The Today Show
Probably
Put me on the map
And you did this for free
I know I never never paid me a nickel
And I never ever push my brand they would say Bobby Brown from Bobby Brown cosmetics
And so it was an amazing thing.
Because it established me as a beauty expert not just someone
Who makes
Makeup it was really my expertise
So it's separated me the
Person
From the brand which was good but it also really
Helped the brand
Yuan in 1995
5 years after you first make those 10
Lipsticks you can offer
I guess you
Shirley on you guys are
Approached by
Big the big cosmetic
Who wanted to buy your
Brand and you guess you reject a couple offers
There was a lot of talks with shado
The Japanese company has a lot of meanings lot of talks
No official offer but a lot of me
And then there was a
A dallas-based
Company that tried to buy us a finance company that basically finally said
If you want sell to us we're just going to knock you off
With another makeup artist which they did
Which is fine I'm never afraid of that
Only creason knock-off brands
Well it was a different brand but yes a makeup artist
You know of a well-known makeup artist
The Creator
Products
It is still out there
Laura Mercier
You know it was a competitor I mean we were very we were always very
That was fun
And they wanted to kind of
Buy you out in
Who did they wanted to buy if we weren't for sale we didn't think they were the right people to buy it
We want for sale when
You know we got the call from Estee Lauder either
This is five years after you launch at Estee Lauder calls you
And you take the call
I kind of think it was for years but yes for years it was 4 years so I got a call from Frederic Fekkai
Who you know how to salon and was a well-known hairdresser and he said you know Leonard Lauder would like an introduction to
Can I do that
And I said sure
Sure
So we were invited have dinner
Leonard lauder's home my partner Roz and I
We're invited one night
To his home and
Tim and his wife at the time Evelyn we had a beautiful dinner
And you know fell madly in love
You know with him with her
And he basically said
You know I'm really interested in buying your company you've done
He said what he said to me says
You've done such an incredible job you are beating us
In the stores and we were beating Estee Lauder in Neiman Marcus
Set the time
You are feeding us
We can't beat you
So we thought we would buy you
You were open to hearing hearing offers
Moen Leonard said
You know that we can help you grow your business and you could do what you really love
Which is
Be creative and work on schuetz work
On the grand but not have to worry about the details
And we could help expand your business
And you can have complete autonomy
You know which means I could do what
I wanted with
The company and still being charged
And they were they were offering 100% they're going to buy out of a hundred percent
End
I guess we'll just burst about whether you did sell to them we get
We did it no one's ever gotten the number right and I'm not good at numbers and I can't even
And tell you what it is but it was like
More than I could ever have them it was a lot of cash
Yes negative course split
What's your partner's and then pay your taxes
Just be you were left with a
The more cash if you ever had
Yes
All right
Just paws
Looking back on that decision 1995
Two celled Estee Lauder
For whatever price average
Do some people say
74 million with a 50 ml
Was it the right decision to make
It was the right decision 100%
You couldn't have scaled Bobby Brown to what it is today without that
I don't know
But I didn't want
Because because I
Just wanted
To have
Fulfilling life with my family my friend
Am I kids
There's no question I have no regrets
Becoming a billionaire wasn't
Wasn't that
That was my goal
No millionaire is fine we don't need to go to
Alright so Leonard Lauder
Write you a big check
And Estee Lauder now owns Bobbi Brown what does that mean does that mean that you then become an employee of an employer
Yep they paid you a salary you weren't a boy with a 401k and all that stuff
At the beginning was it
Did you like it
I loved it it was fantastic I loved it for you know out of the 22 years I probably loved it
And so the idea was once Estee Lauder was running the business side
You not to worry about going to
Banks
Financing you don't have to worry about Supply change enough to worry about
Payroll accounting or
Not filing a letter with the office
Tax and Revenue
And you didn't want to do any of that
I didn't like the big corporate meetings and I would sit there and some meetings
And I know I used to drive people crazy
Because I didn't do things the Corporate Way
And I'm sure people either looked at me as
Brilliant
Or really difficult
Or
You know whatever
You know the thing is
Unfortunately
Men could be brilliant when women are considered
I can imagine
That would have been an easy transition
It wasn't easy and I'm sure it was harder for you know our partners at the time
They didn't stay very long
You know we we had a
Little bit of a tough
Relationship
You know for a while
Because you know you
Start a company with friends
You know things happen
And things get tough
And
It was a tough time
There was a bunch of years were think there was a struggle but
Between
You know Rosin Eye and then the four of us
You know after you know we sold the company they
Remove rods off the brand and
She ended up
Working for the company for a while and then she left and a stranger French
Oh really stranded
Do you think that it's a good idea
In general to avoid going to business
Best friends
Yes
It's not a good hundred percent and you know we
We're not friends for many years after we sold the company and we just recently got back together the path
Couple years
So
You know life isn't
You walked away
From Estee Lauder on 26th
At the right track
I don't even know what the right term
As it was it was a joint
And was that hard
Your name your company
You built it
And that you're out
Well
Play probably 2 to 5 years 5 years was
The last five years the last five years was
Struggle just because just because another it got so big the company got so big
The corporation gots
So big they bought so many other companies
It was growing it was huge
I am not a follow the leader
I am the leader okay I can't
And if I see things not working
What makes sense to me and wasting energy and time
I don't like it and I liked it
Do it different
You know and I like to try new things and invent new things
So yeah it was always
Always ask
And so then the last couple years were really tough
Mike what happened
Oh my god there was just
You know they starting I used to hire ever approve and hire an interview every person
And then I didn't any
And all of a sudden they were people
Working
On my brand that I never met
And then I might not have hired
And you know it was a struggle and I tried to let go of
The details
Then I realized the details what makes the company so
And so I kept thinking I could fix it
So I would walk in every day with
An imaginary you know
Taper on my arms thing
Okay let me fix
Let me see
Let me fix
I couldn't
And you know
It the last year was really tough
I'm sure they were not happy with me I was not happy with them
And it just was time for both of us
To move on
Was it tough in the sense like you dreaded going into the office in the morning
Yes wow now only dreaded going in in the morning
I was
Depleted
And spent
When I came home so
For two years my Aunt Alice who when I was 18 at the time
I would say to me
It's time
My husband say
Are you ready
Like my friends would say
Enough is enough
And I kept saying no cuz I think if we could just do this
If I could get this
You know it could be better
And it didn't
Get better
I feel like I'm imagining I'm walking down
Some Street New York
I passed you and I know it's Bobby Brown I like
Oh my God Bobby Brown I love your makeup
And you're on your way to work and you
You would say oh yeah
Thank you so much and I wouldn't know that you
You were miserable now
Walking to your powerful job at Bobby
Honestly if you really ask me why I left
I needed
To be the boss of
Yeah like when you're the boss and your case something doesn't work week
So yes
When I left Bobby it wasn't easy
The second it happened where I went down the elevator
And I knew that was that second it was done
I had a relief come over me
Like I can't tell you this first relief was
Oh my God
All these problems are lifted
All right
We had
Lots of
Founders of the company who sold
And then you know
Some
Some were angry with away was Ron and
And some of mixed feelings someday
But
You know Ben and Jerry for exam
Those guys
Bill Bill knock Ben & Jerry's now and again of the good-natured way but they will
Still there still the face of the brand and they're happy to kind of be the
Brett not happy but they are the brand ambassador
Did you ever think of doing that
No no no interest that you would have it was offered
Like the Bobby Brown I mean
Space of the
You didn't had no winter
No
I don't care how much money they offered me. Why
Why not
What I love I'm a man
I'd like
To to mold and shape
And being control
Apostle
Are so now I have
No I had no
You know honestly it's been awhile it's
I'm not going to say I walked out the door and it was
Was fine there was a lot of emotion the first
Month or two there was a lot of emotion
You know the first year now it's
Juno year-and-a-half
I literally
Could look
At what's happening there and I and I unfollowed everything so I don't see anything but when I do see it
It's like there's nothing there because it's not the company I
I found it and it's not the company that
That is not my company is there company
And yes I'm really proud
Of the products I'm proud of everything I did
But you know the world is changed and what they're the direction they're going is
It's fine is what they want to do
I mean you're still here
Young woman
Well if you consider 61 young Rd
People start businesses 1/6
By the way were you were you prevented are you prevented from your contractor Bobby Brown of starting a makeup line
Oh yes
Never be alone for the rest of your life
No that's not accurate
But I my name I sold my name
You can't you can't use the name Bobby Brown
But I would never
Yeah I wouldn't I would never put
Even if I could I would not put my name on a product anymore
Because I have to be the face of that product
I don't want to be responsible
You are everything
I did that already
To Bobby
With all this
The success you had in your career
How much of it do you think is because of your
Your intelligence your hard work and how much of it
Because of lack
I think that
My intelligence is mostly emotional intelligence which is do you know
Dealing with what's around me
I am
Credibly lucky and
You know
Fortuitous
And grateful and all those things
I'm not the only one that works hard I am not the only one that sees his upper
Opportunities
I
Don't know why
You know things I do are successful not everything I've done is successful but
Keep going
And I'm really good when I'm really good at and I hope there's other entrepreneurs out there that understand this
I am really good at hiring people that are good at things that I'm not
That's really
Cuz I'm not good at everything and I'm not I told my Aunt Alice I'm not really good at anything I'm just good at telling people what to do
I'm really good at telling people what to do
Bobbi Brown founder of Bobbi Brown cosmetics
Since leaving the company she started the health and wellness brand
Called evolution
She's also running a boutique hotel called the
The George Inn
Montclair New Jersey
And even though she sold the name Bobby Brown
She was able to start a new brand called just Bobby
Sell things like
Clothing and bags
Lucky for you to have such a cool name Bobby
I never liked my name growing up you hated it
When they decided what to name and I was named after my great-grandmother Bertha thank God that it
Berta
Not sure anyone would use lipstick called Berta brown or you could just that I could be your new
No you know what maybe maybe it's time
Berta I'm not sure that would work
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Microsoft Surface
Introducing the new Surface go
The smallest Microsoft Surface ever
Just over one pound as a
10 inch screen
The new Surface go has
Performance of a laptop
But with the portability
Tablet
Hey thanks for sticking around because
I know for how you built that
Is it a story starts about three years ago in Los Angeles
Guy names
Miles pepper I went to my local coffee shop to grab an iced latte
Before heading off to work
And as I was leaving the shop I
Put a plastic straw my drink as normal habit but as it happens just the night before
Miles Encina program about Plastics that are polluting the ocean
I had just seen the video of the sea turtle with a straw stuck up its nose and
I was thinking to myself that I already have a reusable water bottle
I already have
Reusable coffee cup
Why don't I have a reusable straw
Yeah a reusable strata not made out of plastic but maybe metal
A straw that could fold and collapse
Like a temple and a way to guarantee that it would always be
On me would be if it was a size of a
The car key
So I wanted a collapsible straw that was small enough to
To fit in case
The size of a car key
Unfortunately I didn't know the first thing about how to make a collapsible straw
So I started talking with friends I started talking with these designers that I have been working with
This mutual friend said hey you should call Emma do you remember to Emma miles did remember Emma
She was an acquaintance who also hated plastic straws
Even though a text talk about it
Straw suck
We become accustomed to living disposable lifestyles
Besan convenia
So a man died and jumped on the phone
Phone rings October 2017 and he says
Hey I've got this idea for a collapsible
Straw
And I just remember he first
Sounded really excited on the phone and it got me really excited
So anyway miles found in industrial designer in LA to help him develop a collapsible stainless steel
Steel straw and while they were working on the design I was working on creating a social media press
I have a love
Love memes and one of my favorite ones was filling a
Pack of cigarettes with straws and at the bottom it says break the habit
After about a month and a half
Emma Myles had a prototype of a straw that
Fold into
Sports
Fits into a little plastic case that you would carry on a keychain
Annexed
A Kickstarter campaign
And the pickle was 5,000 straws which would have been about $70,000
But we sold about 60 thousand straws
Closed a month later with 1.89 million dollars in the bank
Which sounds amazing right except discovered a really big problem
There's companies out there that are patrolling Kickstarter and looking to see
When people throw a successful campaign and as soon as they see that overnight success
Then they jump on it
And they use the measurements that are provided on the kickstarter to create an exact replica of that
And that
Is exactly what happened to Emma in miles
These random sharks basically hijacked their idea made some quick cheap knockoffs and started fulfilling
Orders before Eminem I could even get their straws out into the world
I mean it's shocking
The hardest part for her
Is the fact that
Most of these knock-offs are complete
Junk and so they're just ending up in the trash can and the entire purpose of our company
To reduce waste
And so I feel weirdly responsible you know no matter how many people tell me that it's not my fault
Like it's still
Feels like it is but I'm on miles are still moving head to apply for a patent and the color product
Final straw
And they say it'll be a lot better than the knock-offs
And that's something that people are going to love it was expecting to
Build the kickstarter orders sometime this November and she says this past year
Been a little like business school except on speed
No it's like going down a river in a
Tube like you just don't know what to expect and every moment is either like
Very Serene and calm or you're
Maybe going to die and I love it
Let's Emma Cohen lives
Whistler British Columbia
She's the co-founder of final straw along with Miles pepper
And if you want to find out more about
Final straw or hay
Previous episodes
Head to our podcast page how I built this.
Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're building
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why
Are there please
Give us a review
You can also write to us at HRBT at npr.org and if you want to send it
Tweets it's at
How I built this
I sure was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music composed by
20 naira blue
Thanks also to JC Howard could see leave a grandson has Michigan for and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Mia venkat
Gyros
And you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Don't this campaign mod
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
Drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week