This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox business insurance
Starts to Taylor intelligent Insurance Solutions to fit each businesses very specific needs get a quote at 8
H i s c o x.com
Hiscox business insurance experts
Pier 1 soap
If you ever try to get people to buy something
Going door-to-door
You know that this can be demoralizing can be utterly exhausting
But this is exactly how Angie Hicks
First tried to get their business off the ground back in 1995
And back then
She was lucky to get like
Two takers a day
But of course over the years
Angie's List grew to millions of members and hundreds of millions of dollars in Revenue
Company stories
Changed a little bit
He first ran this episode back in 2016 so we'll update you at the end but for now
Enjoy
People started calling you and you are the only person Manning the phone
I literally in like a hundred square foot Office Space
And so when we needed the second line we got a second phone so that I do remember times I feel like sitting on the floor in the off
Literally like toggling between two physical phones with no home button
From NPR
It's how I built this
Show about entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Raz
Angie's List Roofing 100 square foot office
To a massive Home Services referral program
So in the summer of 1995
Angie Hicks
Said just graduated from college in Indiana
Just where she's from
And like a lot of college graduates
She was looking for a job
Step the previous Summer She interned at a small Venture Capital firm
In Indianapolis
Airbus there was a man named Bill oesterle Bill was
Just a few years older than Andy but
He already had a lot of business 6th
Mentor to her
So they kept in touch
And with Angie job-hunting
Hampshire College bill was giving her advice about where to apply
Who is hiring
I was back in the day where you would literally send your resume and cover letter by mail so I sent out
Numerous letters and resumes
And then calls me up one day and says
Hey Angie I have an idea
At that point he had moved to do Columbus Ohio
He's like why don't you move to Columbus and we can
Start a business
Saul raise a little bit of money from your friends and enough to to get you through the first year
I want you to commit for a year
So what so what you think
It was a little out of the blue in any known I would never have defined myself
As an entrepreneur
A lot of times I thought of classical entrepreneurs I was
Like a they're risk-takers their big idea thinkers
That
Ring my hands about that decision and
Talk to my parents about it
Well you know you don't feel well you know he's not going to lead you astray
And then I talked to my grandfather and he was incredibly cancer
Depression just me
I'd like to pay cash for everything
He looked at me without even hesitating and
Looks like
You should do it in G I mean what's the difference between being
22 and looking for a job and being 23 in
I'm looking for a job
So
Literally like
Loaded up all of my worldly possessions in my Ford
Escort in office
So at that point did Bill actually have
A business in mind or was he just like hey come to Columbus and then we'll figure it out
We have a couple ideas
But then
Landed on what became Angie's List
When
Bill was trying to renovate his house in
It was a second house you don't
This house in Indianapolis is also a fixer-upper but in Indianapolis he was introduced to a little business called
Unified Neighbors
Cars that have been around
Since the early 70
A list of who was good and he wasn't in the city
For Home Improvement
So what do you move to Columbus he just kind of assumed there was something like that and everything
And there was a
And so
He's like really try to start our own
This is like
Like 95
That's right
So you get to Columbus
What did you do that like how did you start
We started just talking to people that we knew so you're the first stop on my tour was two bills next
Door neighbor
Did you say it was your pet
And it was like an okay we're starting this business
What we're going to do we're going to help people find
The best contractors in town
And Patty had lived in her house lived in her neighborhood for entire life
You know someone did not need what we were selling it was probably Patty
But Patty love the entrepreneurial Spirit of it
So she looked at me and she was like this is great
I'm going to take two member
One for me
And one for my son
Give me a list
If every service provider she'd ever used
And she also gave me her church directory
She told me that I had to call everybody in her church directory and tell them that
She said they should buy it
And how much was a membership at that time
$19 or $19 for the year that bought you
AR magazine in a Collins
So during the day call you could ask me for the name of the plumber and electrician and then the
In the evening I would go out door-to-door
And also ask for reviews
So you you did everything you you wrote everything I assembled them at I wrote the magazine
Like magazine is a very
Generous
Brochure issue Neighborhood News
How did you
How did you get more subscribers
I literally for the first three or four months I've basically went door-to-door every
What was that like
Introvert
Yeah it was probably one of the most miserable experiences you miserable because
You just weren't getting a traction like Hugo
Door-to-door people would just say
Slight buzz off for tonight in the mid-90s
I got now I like to look back on
Call it a character building
Experiencing
Yeah it was
Hard and
There was a moment in
The fall
And he was like you think about like I was 22 and I kind of realize that this is my life
Like this is my career really didn't need to go to college to do what I was
Doing
Did you know anybody in Columbus
Bill his wife
So you were just like
On your own in the city
Just work
Can all the time
Going towards or
As an introvert
You are totally miserable
So I called my loved one day and I appreciate the fact that you realized
But I was upset
Siri suggest that we meet like at the little Bakery down
Until we get there
Soon as I sit down I just start
It was going to be great
For probably 30 minutes
Everyone in the fake real looking at us like what is wrong
And I'm in he likes to tell the story that like at the end
All I could muster to say was that I was not going to quit
So what happened after that conversation is did you just go back out on the streets and start
Selling door-to-door
Yeah I got to tell you all the time like I used to measure
Success by
One or two memberships a day if I sold two memberships a day it was a banner
Fast forward a little bit more like okay
This is probably not the marketing plan this
Going to work so then we're like okay we're going to have to Market
Like Imogen raise insane amounts of money is like
$50,000 - $50,000
And so you know where can we Market that we can do it in an economical way that we won't burn through
$50,000 relief
We lucked out in Columbus Ohio has it that time have these little week
And so
So we put an ad in the back of the Weekly News
Newspaper and it was in your neighborhood by neighborhood
And
It was this little too by 3 ad that said tired of lousy service
So are we
So we decided to do something about
And the phone started ringing
And people started calling you
And you are the only person Manning the phones
I literally in like a hundred square foot office
The people in the other
Offices around me thought my parents rented
Good for me to do my homework
Where can I get a card table
Turn off phone system we had a phone
And so when we needed a second line we got a second
But I do remember times
You like sitting on the floor in the office
It's literally like toggling between two physical phones with no holds
And what people like your subscribers are
Just call up during the day and then say hey I need a plumber or
Like a roofer and you would say yeah yeah
Yeah it is like or if I didn't have an answer given the list
It was then I would go for
Figure it out I mean I remember one time
This woman called
She was new in town and wanted to
To sign her daughter up for ballet
I'm so
Songs like hang on
Luckily I remembered cuz I had signed up
Remember who is apart of the club
Ballet
So I call her up
Ballet lesson
I would just kind of try to make
You were you were looking at human however I cut you were a human Google
Yes you were the like the person like when you
Type it into Google you are the person the other side answering that question
And what was the company
Call by the way
Sure it was called Columbus neighbor
A simple knock off of the unified Neighbors
Yeah we debated names
One of the guys that was involved in Cubbies on the
Bored and he was like
Look up a list
And you know this pretty good name by the way
Maybe heart attack
And then Bill throws and it's like what we could just name it
Angie's List
Since
Angie's who you talk to and it does make a good story and
No matter what happens
I can always relate back to you know Angie was the first one that answered the phone
So you know
Probably not knowing what I was getting into
That was a decision we made
So when you ran these ads
And you started to see more subscribers
How long does it take before you start thinking
Is actually working the sexy generating some cash for
Signing up a thousand members in the first year
Azurite
This could be with this could be a go at it so then we started thinking like maybe we should go and see if we can acquire unified name
In Indianapolis
Right right
So
We ended up accomplishing it about a year after we started in
So then yeah I kind of wake up one day in July
I've got
Two offices so I had to
Start advertising to hire some
Some help
I'm 22 I don't know how to hire anyone
So I placed a little ad in our newsletter Tire
And I have this one woman that came in her name is May
Interviewed anyone before so I like asking questions
They finish up the interview and I'm like I'll get back to
A few days and I just remember she looks me in the eye and
If you're going to hire me
You need my phone
Like I was just like
That's exactly right
So the next day I hired man
You know Maggie is now this year celebrating her
20th
Anniversary Edition
So in those
The early years
He must have just been working like a
Because you had to deal with billing
Reading a magazine getting used
Subscribers
Expanded Indianapolis
Selling advertising like
Did you
Did you move to Indianapolis when you when you guys acquired unified Neighbors
No I didn't know actually I just drove back its heart that's been half my week
How long is a drive by the way
3 hours
Like what you sleeping
4 hours night
It was it was
It was a lot I mean you can find yourself you can just work work work
There's a lot of time in the day and you can work a lot of hours
All the time like
I couldn't have picked a better time in my life to do something
No family in your life or your kind of
Geared to do that
It's funny though
Because
You are so different
Every entrepreneur that we've interviewed in that
You are not
Incredibly optimistic about the
Success of this
Company early on
You are
Kind of thinking about maybe
Packing it in you were not a natural Hustler
But you were doing all of these things
Yeah I'm going to be
I think of you in retrospect when you think about
What makes an object
You are an entrepreneur
I honestly I think a lot of times it comes down to persevere
Yeah
And I think a lot of times
People can have the big idea
And they can have
You know kind of that
Initial kind of fall in love
With their IDF
Starting
But
They don't write it through the hard part
And they give it up
Yeah
So while I might not have had the big idea and while I might not have been the big risk taker
I had persevered
I think that
That is my aunt
Phone company
Gyros and you listening to how I built this
IPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities
Is can be a smart way to Head Market
Risk and earn guaranteed returns
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone tag
Lights with clear conditions and a direct
Mophie model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge
Which is not available in all states
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Market
It's Industries and the globally
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO Lance
The China's economic Outlook and much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
It's how I built this
Stream NPR
Gyros
Show about 3 years in
Angie's List
Expanded from two markets
24 Market
And so they decided to build a bigger management
Bill oesterle came to work
Guest full times
Yo
She says the crazy hours
The hard work of the earlier said
Really started to take a toll I was super burn
And so it was like
I know you
Stop periodically about business school why don't why do you think more seriously about
Not prepared to do that had to take the GMAT hadn't done anything but he basically decided in September that I would
Apply that
Wait for you
Your plan for business school in the fall of 98 like 3 years after you launch the
His company which is now really gaining Traction in and looks like it's going to
Become something
Like I guess you could argue that those three years were kind of like your business
Alright like why did you
Feel like
You wanted to go to Business School
You know for me if I hadn't kind of taking that time I probably wouldn't have
Kind of need for Speck
How do I learn to be a manager because I was forced to be a manager
Like I got through an acquisition
And I'd raise capital
Did I really understand everything that I was going through
Probably not
And so it was a great time for me to step away and kind of gain perspective
Applying to two
Scified
Kellogg
End to Harvard
Not getting into car
What was it like was it was it weird going there
It was weird at all
You know I was
I'd lived in Indiana or Ohio my entire life
This is one of those things where I was like
Like I was
So flattered
To actually have Jess
What's gotten into this
A girl
Middle class kid
My dad was a UPS driver my mama
First in immediate family to go to college
So for me it was kind of like wow this is kind of any two
Experience and I'm going to
Take it for what it's worth
But maybe I had a different perspective
When you are at business school and you would like run these models
How business is ran or how to be a leader
Will you like where the time for you to wait that's not how it works in the real world cuz I've been there
Yeah
Yeah I mean
It was fascinating
To watch you have these conversations of the companies to cut 20% from
From its bottom line New Jersey alternative people
People like what we should just cut 20% of staff
Have you fired someone before
Have you ever be actually
Done that because
That's really hard to do
Yeah sometimes you have to do it and sometimes that's the right to
Decision but
Let's make sure we really understand the context
Wow you were there were you
Involved with
Was it your intention to go back
Civility
How does the arrangement that like hate you should go in
Explore what there is
We're here but you should go see what
Weather is
Interview
I realize that sometimes you don't realize what you have until you
Yeah
So I decided I was going to go back
By that point Bill had hired a chief operating officer
Who had
Conservatively model the business
In such a way that after I agreed to
The Comeback Bill had to call me
And say
We may not be able
Able to afford
Wait what
But why was that because you would NBA that point
No he was just like he was literally like we
We now have too much overhead and I was like you don't feel are you just being you or is this
In here just like going to be like this is what this is what the model says and I'm like you know what
I'm coming back
Screw you
Haikou founded this company bill
Exactly needless to say
The guy that ran the model was incredibly conservative Auto
So we were all fine but it was is a funny moment
So when you got back what was your what was
How do I gave you
So the chief operating officer
Sister position was filled so I just decided to cheat more
This is kinda hard question for you to answer but it's just my observation that you must be
A person with Olmos
No yo
I am I right
Exactly right maybe I joke around like
I don't worry about titles I worry about getting
There's too much
Stuff to worry about
To worry about
Little Things
And maybe that's CI off
Remind myself yeah cuz people ask me is they come into
What's it like to work at like I like the last person to ask
I got tell people at orientation like I am really shy if you see me in the diner you need to come talk to
Okay okay so you come back to the company
After business school
Felicity early 2000s right
Yeah so we
So that's what we started opening markets
More frequent basis
We're opening one or two year
When did you go from being a
A newsletter like a
Physical newsletter to being
An online company
So we put our first website up
Play early 2000 or 1999
And basically literally we hired to college
Seville archives
It was just a basic like you know marketing informational website
Yeah I had to email
You couldn't check the list
I was just for marketing
So how's that website working one day
We realize was like you know half of our signups
For coming in over
Website in Silverlight
I guess I should actually build a website
So you know
It was like yeah
Is probably more interesting to
Read the reviews then
B&G read the reviews to you for getting people rather getting the mailing
Well they were just calling up the number
Right
Taking this online is it
It like a business
It is based on
Basically
Building a community
Trust
End
You have did this be
Before the airbnb's and the
The Ubers and that you know this or that
The sharing economy kind of
Took off
Right so
At the beginning were people
Skeptical of others
Yeah I think it was actually even an article written
Just probably
10 or 12 years ago about the fact
There was a Fascination as to why consumers were willing to share their opinions
Like you for information
That they are giving
Get right yeah
Of the article and it was a
There was something
Special about the
Service at first I thought it was like oh it's
Columbus because I know all the members are
Oh it's Indianapolis
There's almost there's there is a sense of belonging and obligation
It became a culture of
The service replicated
Self in city after
City
What are the values
We had it was the fact that we started when we did and we started pre-internet days
In many ways we looked at
Truly organic
Mimic
For our business model we looked at journalist
Every story has a
The Source right
Even
Occurred to us
That we should allow people to review an anema
Isn't that proved incredibly powerful
Why why do you think people were willing to write these reviews that
They're paying for
Because if they didn't
The next person
If you think about the kind of decisions are making around your home I mean these
Yeah I I call these like the high cost
The failure decisions
That's right I mean
You probably know the least about what you're buying
You're spending a lot of money
And if it goes wrong it could potentially ruin your largest ass
Yeah yeah
And there's bad information and like as not a great way I mean cuz a lot of these companies are small companies so how do I file
Weather
XYZ Plumbing is any good
There's lots of places to get information
But people are willing to pay for Quality information
As you guys started to expanded you
Did you go out
Raise money
We did you know that you know that was one of the things that
Bill having a venture-capital background
Was incredibly valuable
Cuz usually nrr raising money came around you know
Wanting to grow the marketing
Okay so what you're saying is you didn't need money to manufacture
The product you were primarily spending money on Market
We need to Market cuz effectively I mean
Business we are acquiring around for a long time
The marketing to acquire them
Once we were able to
Descale to National marketing
Erased open
So in about 18 months we open a hundred
What were some of the mistakes that you made
Why you were
In that in that sir. Expansion
So you know
We waited a number of years before we opened
Chicago
Cuz we were really uneasy about the cost of expanding into a city that
What we realized we open there was
No it just took off like crazy
Why did most companies start on the coast
Because there's that
That's where the population is
Absolute
And clearly that strategy
How many numbers do you have today
Over 3 million
Whatever you ever
I'm just about every city
DUI
Like when you see a
Incredibly positive review
And also incredibly negative review like
How do you know which one to believe
What I often find when I look at reviews
You know one
It's really important to actually read the
List of the reviews and
I learned this early
No matter how great you are the company you're going to
I honestly believe you learn more when you can see a company that has
A couple of
Complaints here in there
Then you do about a company that has all glowing roof
Yuan and part of that is like hey Ya
They might make a mistake
Can you really want to know how they're going to handle it when the chips
What's going to happen if that
You know what the countertop was wrongly
And now they have to redo
Because that's what music
You fear when the job doesn't
And you don't on the flip side new years ago
Pastor Leon in the business we allowed companies to start
Responding to reviews
Cuz they were like hey something I actually understand the
The consumer gets to get their opinion but don't we get
A chance
Sarc
Historic
And so we introduced that witch
Prince be incredibly valuable
Consumer
Because you do want to know how they're going to
Right
But I do spend a lot of time talking to service companies and kind of encouraging them not to
Respond on for
Cuz usually that's when they're angry no one likes negative feedback hours to Jessica to get a cup of coffee
Come back think about it
Before their rights
Because
What they say can be more powerful than 10 reviews
Might ever
Do you like
When you have to get something fixed in your house
Do the contractor to show up
Are they freaking out like are they
Super nervous
They're like oh my God Angie is going to sleep
Ruin me
You can ruin me
I'm okay my reviews start weight
The same as everyone
But yes
A lot of times my husband
Is the one that's home
When we have work done and
Fixes not my married name so
So that helps until they kind of
Look around the room and start
Sing
Pictures
And they were like oh wait
They're like holy crap it
Angie Hicks co-founder of Angie's List
The company now offers free membership in last year
Merged with one of its Chief competitor
HomeAdvisor
So NG new title
Chief customer officer at
Angi HomeServices
And by the way despite her best efforts to avoid the spotlight
Angie said she can't go to grocery stores or really anywhere without someone asking her advice about finding a contractor
I'm getting some bathroom probably done this is true story in Washington DC just off the top of your head
A good vacuum
And please do stick around because
Just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Smart Water
Taking inspiration from the
The clouds themselves
SmartWater 1 Epsom by adding electrolytes
It's for a clean crisp taste
It's the water you deserve
Smart Water
Vapor distilled
Purity
Electrolytes for taste
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that and today we're going to update a story we
Just over a year ago
And that story came to us
Joe Crites High guy Joel is from Cleveland
Cleveland sports fan
A few years ago he was at an Indian's game with his 16 year old son Cody it was a beautiful summer night
Baseball and Joel was loving it
He just wasn't into the action of the game he didn't really care about the outcome and you know it wasn't into the standings
Well yeah he just said this is boring let's go
And I said something to the effect of know I paid to be here tonight you're going to sit there and like it
Been in a similar situation
This is no fun for Kobe it's no fun for Joel
So in that moment
Joel suggested a game
He tried to Kobe and he said hey why don't you try to predict what the next
Batters going to do
Strikeout hit a homer walk whatever
And whoever predicts correctly
Windchase and fine and within the very next at-bat
We were laughing and high-fiving and I thought I had just struck gold
Pinchot actor that every time Joel went to see baseball he
Play the game with his other kids as well and he started to tell his friends about it especially friends with kids and
He realized a lot of fans were already doing the same thing people told me all I play this with my grandpa
Are we predicted that bats and we use
You know this and that to keep track of the score
And people in the bullpen hoverboard when they're watching a game evil do some version of its year later
He wondered whether he might
Turn this idea into a smartphone app
An app that you
You could play at home or in the stadium
Against other fans were all watching the live game in real time
But he needed to set up a wave
Scoring
How many points for a predicted strike or a home run or double play
Well fortunately in his day job
Chole
Is an accountant
I quickly got out my spreadsheets and started downloading statistics to figure out what should the difference
Predictions for Nat bat be worth based on their
Statistical likelihood
So there's ground out
Worth 2 points
Strikeout is
Three points
Single
Four Points
Anyway Joel eventually higher developer to build out a smartphone app
He put it out into the world I literally print it off flyers and I stood outside of Arlo
Local
Stadium
Just asking people to play and that's how I got it off the ground initially show search
Is one one thing you can have a huge baseball fan and I take my boys to a lot of games
Interesting beautiful and magical about being
In a stadium or andrena
And just watching the game and and having our devices off
I don't know I just Joy feel like I feel like you surrendered said nope this is the reality and I'm just
I was going to go with it in some ways I have but in the times we live in I mean the baseball
Average age of a viewer nowadays has gone from age 53 to 57 in the past decade
AIDS
You got to find a way to reach the kids in this is this is what I've come up with Joel's app is called micro fantasy and so far
He's licensed it to a
Few college level baseball team and he's made about $10,000 from that
But since we last spoke with him
He started to develop the app for other sports like tennis and basketball and he may even pitch the app to his
Cleveland Cavaliers
If you want to find out more about the micro fantasy app or hear previous episodes
Head to our podcast page
How I built this.
Npr.org and of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week
Describe Apple podcasts or wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there please do give us a review
Npr.org and if you want to send it to its at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by renting out of Louis thanks also to
Nor could see the grandson of meshkinpour and Jen Rogers AR intern is JC Howard
Listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
This campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com