Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign
An email marketing
Used by more than
In 200
50000 cups
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email
And customers
7 days away
Campaign
Weather.com
Support for the how I built this Summit comes from American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible Funding Solutions
Smart Savvy way to fund your business
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Business
Hey it's guy here and today we've got another episode from the how I built this Summit
That we held in San Francisco this past October
This week we're featuring
Katrina Lake
Founder
Stitch fix
Personal shopping service
For women and men
Original interview with
Katrina ran earlier this year
You haven't heard it you might want to give it a listen
Because Katrina story is
Pretty amazing
She's built a billion-dollar business
And is the youngest female
CEO ever
Company public
But she's also one of those Founders who
It really set out to
Katrina and I sat down together and
Turn of a live audience
Yerba buena Center
For the Arts
San Francisco
So what's what's the start with your self perception
As
You know as an entrepreneur you didn't
We talked about briefing
Who didn't go into too much detail on it was
You used to think of yourself as somebody
It was going to start a company and run a big organization and be a leader of all these people like
That wasn't
How you saw yourself
And that wasn't your intention
Any obviously you're doing it but
Why what why was that
Yeah it is it's funny I look back and it is one of the things that I am
Passionate about of how can how can we make
Entrepreneurship something that feels more accessible and more real to more people
Because I think I look back and
In my childhood like
Nobody
Thought I would be an entrepreneur would encourage me to be an auntie
Carpenter like my mom is a RC jets retired actually
She was a public school teacher my dad
The doctor in the public university system
I don't know that I was raised with that as even a possibility in my mind
And it's funny because sometimes people ask me like I know you went to Stanford that
Did that make you realize you wanted to be an auntie
In some strange ways that actually had the opposite effect of like the people who are the entrepreneur types
At Stanford were very different than
Kind of how I saw myself and so it took a really long time I think
Sing for me to realize that don't you
Partnership would be a good path
For me
And I think there's a lot of other people out there that would be pretty good at it
That maybe haven't had that exposure haven't had that push
I'm in Salinas definitely one of the things that I'm passionate about about you know making
Ensure that
This path is available
What did you think
An entrepreneur what was supposed to be like what did you think
It matters
What was that person like in your mind
I mean it's just it really is you know who you have exposure to
She was like you Mark Zuckerberg was around the Stanford campus when I was
And when I was
In school Google was created around the time that I was
School
Dealers you know kind of largely this
Like coder code in your garage
Likewear Adidas flip-flops
Kind of kind of personality that
That you know didn't feel all that accessible to me
Yeah as you as you mention the podcast in the early days you had to raise a lot of money cuz you needed a lot of money to get this thing off
You got to buy inventory is to build
All the technology rabbit you describe Stitch fix really is
The tech company
UC told me that mail VCU
And that you would ever most
Man that you were meeting with
We're not
Passionate about dressing women
How did you convince them
Or at least some of them
Otherwise
We actually didn't raise that much money we raise less than 50 million dollars.
This is now over a billion dollars and so you know I think are the amount of capital that we raised was
Very modest relative
To know where where we would end up
But in the early days yes we did need money
And so we raised I think 500,000 and a seed round and then we raised a couple of million and a round butt and we weren't
Raising these
You know crazy size Venture rounds
I'm a nail candidly like I wasn't able to
Like a fundraising was not the thing that I have the best in the world at
I hated it because I was bad at
I mean we raised
You can say that
Building a billion-dollar business on West
50 million is that something to be proud of like it's it's honestly the result that like fundraising is not my towering
It's just a
It's not the thing that helped me to be a good entrepreneur
I mean I probably wasn't very good at it then I don't know that I'm terribly good at it now
You know Capitol wasn't necessarily one of those things that helped us
And we should have
Some survey results from a survey that we we
Commission just to earlier today and it showed that women entrepreneurs who
Who responded some of them in the audience
You know they've reported bias against them as they try to grow their business
That's what I want to ask you at this very moment
Because
Because of what you represent the youngest
Female founder to take a company public
And
Yewtree this billion-dollar company
Do you like
Being seen that way
Is it irritating to you when people kind of
Say oh here's this
Great woman founder do you embrace it how do you feel about it
I mean
I am mostly positive but it sometimes mix
Like you know I think there are times when
Yeah it can be like oh that she's a great female CEO Mike
Just want to be great
I don't need the female part of it I
Just want to be a greaser
And I
That part can irritate me
Maybe cuz you know I think that this point like we have the credentials
The flipside I
I feel immensely
Proud and
Really responsible
To be able to show
People like me
And so I know I'm very proud
That I am
A woman and very proud that I don't look like all of the other
Public humping
D'nicio's out there and those are things that I think you know I feel like just by
Being on this stage I can have an A
Impact
I'm and I think is is really really important
Yeah do you mean
Do you feel like things are starting to change or turn a corner or
Do you think it's
More of the same
I am mean I think there just has to be
Positive change like you know I don't
I don't know that we're turning a corner but you know there are there are many morphe
Female CEOs out there
I'm when I was writing my business school essay like I remember I was like I had Google spreadsheets of like women executive
Passing how did they get there and
I mean either
Very few women for me to choose from when I was writing those essays and if I tried to write those essays
Now I
Anna 10 years later
There's many more options
The people that I could look to as role models
You know for that
10 years ago me
And so and I feel optimistic that changes happening
You know is it happening fast enough
That that part I think is is a real challenge
I want to ask you about building culture at
Stitchfix because
I wonder if even when you were just a tiny team or maybe it was just just
The few people
Did you even have the luxury of thinking of
Culture at the early stage or you just trying to grind through
I hate you I thought about culture really early on and I and I do wonder if some of it
Even I was thinking about starting this company like I was thinking about it in terms of like while I want to
Create
Like the retail model of the future but I also want to create
The company of the few
Future and related to that is like
I'm going to work at this cup
How many for 10 years 20 years whatever I'm now 7 years in like
In this day and age if you're going to work somewhere for
For 7 years like
It's a place you really love
And so you know I have this mind that when I was creating the company of like
What would be the company that I would want to join
7 years 10 years 20 years
You know I think the culture that we have I mean
People talk about diversity
Quite a bit and I think for us like
We have a very diverse
Steam we have a very diverse management team but I think it's also this idea of diversity of thought
And one of the epiphanies with Stitch fix was
That to be able to have two people in a room that had very different perspectives on how to solve a problem
Ended up with better outcomes than two people who thought the same
For example we have data scientist
Just sitting alongside
Side stylist
Like they look at the world images
They look at how do we serve clients better in a
Way and I think the the two working together is so much greater than us
Some of its parts
I wonder how
Crucial you think that is Imagine right people in this
Ennis audience is listening early-stage entrepreneurs
You know they got to think about
Everything from just
Getting a product out there and marketing and
You know competitors and
When all the things that you worried about
ETA mean
Could you argue that at the very early stages thinking about culture is an Indulgence or do you think it's absolutely
Critical and crucial the vet
Baked in from day one
I mean I think if you're going to have the best out
Come for your company at half
I mean there's a I think there's a couple of reasons for that I think one
And I think it is that the team that you have like all of
Pics of such a great example because there was a point in time where like I was in the room and we talked at every 6 then we style every
Obviously now I can't do that anymore and
It's all in the hands of
Achievement culture
And like eventually
If you're successful if you have more than 10
People who are
In a working for you like you are your company that
State of your company rest in the vineyard
And what is going to keep a team motivated it's not money
Actually it really is the culture
It's like what are they getting out of their day today
We all are lucky enough to have many choices
In terms of where we working are we spend our time
And they have to be choosing yours every day
And so you know I really believe that like if
If you aren't setting that up from day one
I'm you aren't realized
Using your full potential
You do something really interesting
You think of your job as a different thing every year I'd rather chew you described as you rehire yourself
Every year so what it what does that actually mean in
Yasso
Being a CEO is
I is fine with the very early days I remember I had a friend from high school who
I came to visit our
Tiny office
Set the time in
Do you like I feel like your job is kind of like
CEO / janitor
And it really was in those early days like some of the things were like I need to make sure the printer has toner I need to make sure that
When somebody starting that they would have
That's going to be
Computer
And so you know I think the recognition that like your job changes
And
You're to be able to have this
I guess processor just like this reflection of like
What is my new job today
What does that mean in terms of how I spend my time
And also like you know do I still like this job I think it's I think this is practical for me as CEO but I think it's also practice
For anybody who's employed at a company that's growing
Where are you know I think there are people who stay like I loved the early stages running out of toner and
Feel crazy running around
Like
Love that stage and don't love
The stages later and the reality is like the job
Changes in it
If you're not recognizing the ways in which
The job or changing or the wisdom
What you are changing
Then
You can get stuck in the stall Jack
And so for me what I think is super important for me to feel really energized and
Excited about what I'm
I'm doing is really like
Recognize
Latin saying like
This year like now or publicly traded company
Like now some of the new challenges for
For me are working with public market investors are creating a longer-term strategy around how people perceive the
Company from a financial
And really like those are interesting new challenges that I didn't have
Before and so I think
Yeah for me being able to be excited about the next chapter in the new challenges that come with that
I'm at leaving some of the old ones behind has just been like a really important practice
How how
Has your leadership style changed 5 years ago vs. now
I don't know that my style itself has changed I think you know I've
Developed in other ways but
I think the
Feeling this quote a little bit of just like I think this like idea of
Today's leaders need to be off
And that's just like it's such a great
Currency of like how do you build
Trust
And
I think I've been
Forced to just be that from the beginning because there aren't a lot of other examples of people I can try to be like and so
And so and I think that's been really can't
Interested in
True throughout my
Tenure as CEO
But you know I do feel just like
I don't know I feel more experience I feel a little bit more like I know what I'm doing maybe the thing that's evolved the most has actually less
What to do with the company's trajectory as much as it
Does for my family which is that like
Having a toddler home and expecting another baby just means like
You have to ruthlessly prioritize
And so you know there are things that I would get super excited about and spend all night doing or just eat a crazy things that I used
To do that way
I can't do anymore
And so I think that's probably been the biggest
Are remaining minute
If you were in this audience 10 years ago
And you're watching
A version of Katrina Lake hear what what do you wish you knew then that
Would have been helpful
All to you that that you now know
Firstly I think it's awesome that you guys are in the audience
To I'm really be
Be part of the entrepreneur
Community and really build. Network in the early days
I think that first and foremost you guys are
Are already doing better than
Then I was
I mean I think one of the things that I wish that I could have done better with a
Having
The ability to pull back
And I'm in
See
I don't know how do I split that's like
The as an entrepreneur I felt like my life was just as
Crazy up and down roller coaster where is like one day it was like today's The Best Day Ever and then the next day it was today's the worst
They ever and it just was this like
Crazy emotional rollercoaster
Sister and
You know if I pull back the lens I'm like
Generally looks kind of up and to the right and it just like things generally were better the day you know the one month later than they
They were the month before and
It was just really hard to get out of that day today
Craziness back then
And so whatever you can do whatever at my advice to me would be like whatever I could do to be able to get more of that
Perspective so that
I'm not on this emotional rollercoaster all the time I think would have been helpful
Katrina Lake
Founder of
Stitch fix
Katrina thank you
I spoke with Katrina Lake in October at the how I built this Summit
San Francisco
And we got one more of these seven episodes for you
Hang up
Thursday
My conversation with Lisa Price
Founder of
Carol's Daughter
And thanks for listening
Today Show
This by Rachel Falkner with music composed By REM kinara blue
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign mode
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign mod
Weather.com