I quit thanks to her
How I built this
Lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing radical easy
The big thinkers can focus on
Developing Big Ideas
Try for free at campaignmonitor com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and your business
Unforgettable
Pay really quickly before we start the show some of you have been asking about our Columbus Ohio show coming up on
February 8th
Supported by
American Express open
That show is with jeni Britton Bauer the founder of
Jeni's Splendid ice cream
The show
Sold out but good news really releasing a
A few more tickets
Get them
At NPR presents
. org
Alright. The show
Here I am supposed to be going to college. This thriving businesses
My dorm room I was buying computers and keeping them up
Capability and then reselling them so
I advertised I bid on state contracts
Remember how I figure that out but somehow figured it out
NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators
Entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements
College freshman turn to dorm rooms
Dell
What are the biggest computer makers in the world
Long before anyone heard of the tech wunderkind
Like Mark Zuckerberg
Spiegel
Katrina Lake
Back before it was fashionable to drop out of college to pursue your start-up even before people use the term
Start up
Back in the ancient days of the 1980s
The dorm room Miracle story you've heard of
Was Michael Dallas
Today the company
Is in Norman
Beyond Darkness worth
Billions of dollars
Dell has sold more than 650 million computers since Michael Dell founded in 1984
And what's amazing about this
Is the money it's not even the idea
What's amazing about
Michael Dell
Because he's not a
Back-slapping sales guy
Doesn't come across as
Particularly charismatic
He's actually on the quiet side maybe even a little shy
Michael grew up in Houston in the 1970s
Just as digital technology was taking off in that City with companies like Texas Instruments and then later
Compaq
His dad was a doctor his mom was
Financial Consultant
And guess what Michael would become a doctor
Like his dad
But even from a young age
Michael Dell felt pulled in a different direction
He was
The numbers
Remember
When I was a small child my dad had this adding machine
Is a Victor adding machine says before the electronic calculator
And I was just
Fascinated
Youku
Add up numbers
With this machine
And really big number
Should I make this like mesmerizing sound every time it did it
And it is I just kind of love that
And then I remember when I was about 7 or 8 years old
I bought a calculator it was it the first
Semiconductor base
Calculator
And I was fascinated that this small machine could do complicated math problem
So yeah I got I got very interested in this stuff
It also turned out that
About
Equidistant
Between my
Junior High School in our in our house
There was a RadioShack store
And so
When I was riding my bike home I could
Stop by the Radio Shack store in C
The
He don't early forms of the of the personal computer and hang out there until they kick me out of the
The store and what are you
It'll like kind of entrepreneurial as a kid
Yeah I I kind of like to business
I had all kinds of businesses
No selling baseball cards I had a Stamp Auction
I got a job
At 8
Gold
Coin and Jewelry store and I was to negotiate with people that were selling things and
Buy those things the lowest possible price
Because the owner gave me a
Percentage of the cut
And I rather you'll Sue
Worked for the local paper for for sometime
Yes oh I got this job
Working for the Houston Post newspaper
Doesn't exist anymore now they think they combined with user chronicling
My job
Along with
Hundreds of other
Mostly
Teenagers
Was
Call random people on the phone
And try to sell them
Subscription to the Houston Post newspaper
Harbor Freight
And I observed
Three things
The first thing I observed is that
If you sounded like the people you were talking to they were much more likely to buy the newspaper from you
Like like you
You put on a text like as heavy Texas accent
Yeah I'm not going to do it for you here but I think you can you can use your imagination
Okay so
Second thing I observed was that
People that were getting married
We're much more likely to buy the newspaper
And then the third thing I deserve is it people that we're moving into a new house or residence
We're also far more likely to buy the newspaper
How did you know who is getting married
And who is moving in
Will you talk to him
You strike up a conversation
You just call people and say and ask them about the
Themselves I guess this is like
At that time people were perfectly happy to help
Strangers personal details right
Yeah so I observe this and what I figured out is that
In Texas when you as a sister in many states
When you want to get a marriage license
You have to go to the county courthouse
It turns out this is public information
And among the information that you
Give to the county
Court
Is the address you want the license
Sent to
So
With this information I devised
A
Direct Mail
Program
Where I
Send letters to all of the people that had
Applied for marriage licenses
In a 16 County area
Surrounding Harris County
Which is where are used to text
And I hired a bunch of my
High School
Pals
To go out to Aldi's County courthouses and
Type the names
Into
Small
Apple 2 computers
And I sent
Massive Direct Mail campaign
To all those people that were applying to get
Marriage license
And
There were also at that time in Houston there was a building boom and there were these very large
Apartment and condominium complexes
They were going up and so I would go to these buildings under construction
And sort of figure out
Who was in charge
And
Say hey I'm from the Houston Post newspaper
You know we've got this great offer where
Your new residence
Get the paper free for two weeks
And all you do is fill out this will form
You are a high school student
Yes
How much money did you walk away with
I think about 17 years old and I made a little over $18,000
That year this is like freakishly precocious of a
Have a high school senior
But it's just weird that you would even know to think of doing those things don't you think
I didn't really think about it like that I just did just seem like
It seemed like a good idea I was pursuing it was working
I did tell you things it didn't work but
That worked so I kept doing it
$18,000
What did you do with that money that that must have more money than you'd ever seen in your life
I bought a BMW
I wanted I wanted to BMW
What did the other students
Think of you today what would did you have this reputation as I got the
Business Wizkid in in high school or or
Like what did they think about
You know I
I don't really know and I and I didn't really care
So I was sort of keeping to myself and I had a few friends but I wasn't
The most social of
Kids
But you must have been somewhat social because
Cuz you weren't going out at
And selling stuff
Strangers
Sure
Social app to make the sale
So you are on the one hand doing this entrepreneurial stuff and then I guess you were also
Just really into computers
Yeah
Are the original
Computer
That I
And I got my hands on
At home
Was the same one everybody else had one
Which is the Apple II
To ya
Yeah and one of the
Beautiful things about the Apple
Apple II was that
All of the circuits
In the Apple
Were discrete circuits that you could understand so
You could go in and start to
Don't play with those and modify them
And
Reprogram the BIOS and
Upgrade the system and
Take it apart put it back together
So
You know when you would take apart
The something happened
Cure
Around 19
IBM
Introduced
The IBM PC and that was sort of a very important moment because
If you dial back the clock
To the late 70s early 80s
In Addis company IBM had a leadership
Of the part of the economy referred to as
Information technology
Unlike any other company at any other time
History
They were by far the dominant company
Introduced the IBM PC
This to me seemed to be a very important moment so I
Try to understand everything was going on about that and so
When you took a part this IBM PC
That was selling for about $3,000
As far as I could tell it was about $600 worth of parts
What you bought one and you took it apart just to
Check the inside out
Sure yeah
What else would you
You got it you got to take it apart and understand if you don't take it apart
Philly most people buy computers to like
You know at that time again
To do basic
You know accounting and word processor
You bought it to take it apart
Well
What is understand
And you don't understand it you have to take a nap
And I remember in
1981 I was 16 years old I just gotten my driver's
And they had this
Thing called The National
Computer comp
In the Astrodome
Time in Houston
And I
You know soon as I got out of school
I would
Rush over there
And
They had
All of the computer companies
Of note in the world in the Astrodome and they were showing off their computer prevent amazing coincidence
That's because you went to that convention which happened to
Take place in Houston that year just happened that year and it just happened to occur like
A couple of months after I got my driver's
Yeah so
Yeah I mean there's there's there's definitely some luck involved
And that convention
Not only were you there
But Rod canion went there to who went on to start
Compaq and Dell
Came out of
Document
Yeah well in and I remember in my chemistry class
In high school
The guy sitting next to me
Was telling me that his dad
Had just
Left
Texas Instruments
To go
Start this new computer company
He was one of the early geyser
That compact
Amazing
Cu
Let me see you graduate high school
And then you go to T or C to to UT Austin
Yes it was a pre-med major and
You know some of this was the programming from my parents
Because
My father was a doctor my older brother was a doctor
In a lot of my cousins were doctors
End
I always thought
The doctor and hand
When I
Started going to school
You know my parents weren't
Around all the time
My ride cuz I'm I'm in Austin or Houston
You're pretty far away
She got a lot of free time on your hands
So I start
Exploring this whole computer thing further
And one of the things that I
Noticed
About the
Computer business was that it was very
It took a really long time for the Technologies
Did you get
From the people that made it to the people that were buying it
And it was
Actually rather
Expensive and
Slow to occur
And to me that was frustrating
So you are a yours
Student at UT
You're supposed to be doing pre-med
Training
Right and you
Start to think
TC market like there's an opportunity here is that
What you start to think
So
I was in this mode of
Buying computers and
Souping them up
Capability
And then
Reselling them
And it was just sort of a fun thing to do a way to make some money I loved
The computers
And
It was actually working out great
What would you do you would go and find like
Second hand
Computers and
Take them apart and
Rebuild them and then
Sell them to people
No no I was buying new computer again
And I would
Upgrade them with
More memory
And actually the main business
Became
Putting hard drive
In those machines so back then the original
IBM personal computers
Had no hard disk drive
So what I would do is
I would
Buy a couple of these describes
Buy a controller card
Write some software make some cables and make a
Hard disk drive system that you would put inside an IBM computer and then
Instead of
260 KR 320k floppy disk drives
It would have
A 10 GB hard drive height which is the time was something amazing
Sounds ridiculous today but 10 megabytes then was
That was like
Unbelievable
How long would it take you
To upgrade one computer
It didn't take that long
Pentagon
What you were doing
Maybe
30 minutes 45 minutes something like that so you could do a bunch
Computers ARROW
Osher
Yeah no problem in between classes
But you really weren't studying you weren't there's no way you were doing your score
I was I was definitely slacking off on the school work
During that time yes but who would you
How did you find customers it was oh Craigslist it was no
Avenue words
18 or 19 years old I guess who did you even know who to sell these two
I advertised
In the in the local newspaper
I bid on state contracts
And it's kind of funny the the state
Office
That was responsible for buying
Computer equipment and everything else
What's about three or four blocks for my dorm room
So I could just like walk over there
And they said they would give you all the
Dockets for all the
Things that the state
Wanted to buy how did you even know how to do
Do that you know I don't really remember how I figured that out but I somehow figured it out
And you know but Mike my biggest customers
We're
Universities in the area
Doctors lawyers
The architect
I think like that suit weren't really buying computers
Did the time end
Most of the students
That I knew
They weren't really interested in computers at the time that sounds
Like crazy right now but this is
Stacking
1983-1984
There weren't very many
People that had
Personal computers
I'm hoping that I don't sound like a broken record
Thinking Michael
Here you are
You are an eighteen-year-old kid I mean you probably look like a a baby and you were going around
Hawking computer soap
Like why would these Architects or business Banner lawyers
Have taken you seriously
Well I guess I figured I'd knew what I was talking about
Nobody ever
Said well I'm not going to
Buy from you because
You don't look
Departer something
Think so I think the early adopters of computers
We're
Sufficiently Technical and geeky that I was able to relate to them in a way that that resonated and so
I didn't have any problem
How much money
I was doing about
50 to $80,000 a month
In business
When I was in my dorm room
Wow
That's insane
Amount of money
I mean
Did you tell your parents that you were
But you're making this much money
No
Now I didn't now that they did eventually
Going back to
Late 83 now they became very upset with me and
Said you have to stop this and
Focus on your studies
So you got to get your priorities straight no what are you doing with your life and
All that
Stuff
And
You know I agree to do that
You know it was like going cold turkey
Or something it just
Alaska
Send about 10 days and
I actually realized that this was more than
A hobby were
A nice way to make some extra
For cash on the side while I was going to school but actually something is very passionate about
So during those 10 days I sort of
Mapped out the beginnings of
Kylie was going to
Finish up my freshman year
But then
Watch this is a real official business
And
You know I eventually made a deal with my parents that
I would do that and if it
Worked out it would continue and if it did not go back to
School
It's it I can just imagine how exciting it was
Your 18 +
You're selling your
Start a company basically without even realizing it I guess
What was it that was more exciting was it all this money that was coming in or was it just that
You were just selling a bunch of computers
Well it was probably a little bit of everything mean
The opportunity
Or and what became
Dell computer Corporation
Was more more apparent
And
Yeah why you couldn't
CL
Three or four years
See far enough out
That
Tell you keep going
So you were I guess for the first couple years or the
At least for the first
2 years you were just buying off
The Shelf computers and making them better
That's right
What we started
Upgrading
Other people's computers
And then we
Started making these
Hard disk drive upgrade kits that became the main
Business of the company selling
Hard disk drive subsystems
Add and memory kits to upgrade the computer when you say Michael and you say we who who were the Wii
You started this by yourself in your dorm room
And then
Who did you bring on to help you
Well I always say week is that makes
The salad is more of us
What I started it was just me
But I hired about one person a week
Every week you know for the first
You're so that it became more and more and
Number one time we had this customer
Who wanted to come visit us it was
Martin Marietta
Which is
Now part of
So much bigger company
And a guy wanted to buy like a hundred and fifty of these kits
Which was
Emma Frost pretty enormous order
And
He wanted to come to Austin and CR
Factory
Operation
So this was a little bit scary because
It sort of look like a massive dorm room
Was it wasn't the
Moe's
Put together place
Actual dorm room
Yeah
Yeah we we are growing quickly and so we
You know we tried to clean this space up and
Put on some
Semi respectable business attire
I'm at the hard drives and here's how we
Ensure the quality controls and
We're sure we can
Beecher demand for this order 450 units
And
He says what are those
I said well those are the computers that we have to format the hard drive
And by this time
We'd actually been
Assembling our own computers
Just to format the hard drive
Just became too expensive to buy them from other people
And
He said why don't you sell those
I was like
Oh
That's a great idea I should have thought
We were so busy
Making these hard disk drive kits that we hadn't really
Thought
Make your own computers
When we come back in just a moment
How that idea launch
Michael down a path
It would make Dell one of the biggest computer companies
In the world
Stay with us
I'm gyros near listening to
How I built this
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think of nobodies are too conservative
Too complex or only for retirees but annuities can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and
Earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that replaces fine print and phone tag
Clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life
5 / NPR
Gameboy
Which is not available in all states
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs for insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Marcus
Industries and the global economy listen to their podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape
The China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcasts Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com podcast
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Normally at this point in the show
Slow and steady growth of a business
Early struggles
And all the hard work that went into getting off the ground
But in the mid-1980s
Pretty soon after Michael hired
Is first Engineers to
To start making the first Dell computers
From scratch
They were selling so many
Computer so fast
Betley started to compete with the biggest name in Computing
IBM
IBM at the time had a
6 megahertz
286 computer
Did they sold
For $3,995
So
The Wii introduced
A 12 megahertz
286 bass computer
And we
Sold it for $1,995
So
Our computer was twice as fast
I was half the price
How did how are you able to do that
What we still made a decent margin
Selling them
And
I think one is we had some clever engineers
We had this
Great supply chain we created
It's okay
When we would sell let's say
200 computers in a day
We would
Give that signal back door suppliers
Who would
Everyday or every
Few hours deliver parts
To our Factory
Yeah and then we would
You know ship those computers out out to the customer so
We had a
Unbelievably efficient supply chain that we created out of necessity because we had no capital
That also meant that we had the freshest
Parts
At the best cost and is it cost
The materials were coming down
We
Benefit from that and we could get the latest technology
To the customer faster than anybody else and you didn't
Uur Direct
To Consumers
Company
Retail shops are not selling delcamp
You have to call Dale or
Foxtail in order computer
At the time that's right
Except
Most of our business wasn't to consumer
I was a business
It was the business
But that's
What you just said is that actually common misperception lot of people thought only consumers buy from delve yeah
That's actually not what was happening we were selling to
All sorts of
Companies and governments
Small
And medium-sized businesses
That was most of our business
Even from the beginning
That point
Like the late 80s
What did you have in mind for the future like what was
What were your ambitions
The company
Well
We had some pretty big operation
The first one was we said
We want to expand
Globally
It's pretty clear to us that
If you were only successful the United States
That would be good enough
II was
That we had to go after
Selling to big companies
Because
If you didn't sell to the really big companies and
The biggest governments in the world
Well you weren't going to
B
Irrelevant company
And then the third one was we said we had to differentiate
On the basis of service
And we created this thing called on-site service
And
Today would be a very common thing but
Back then if your computer broke
You had to put it in the trunk of your car take it back to the computer store
And then they were taken it off somewhere
You'd wait weeks and weeks and
Supposed to get it back and
So we came up with this program where
Calls on the phone
Before the internet
And
If you had a problem we help you resolve it on the phone and if we weren't able to resolve another phone we send
A
Technician
With parts
To your location to fix your computer on site
And we did that
All across the United States
And
And we thought
The minute we analysis our sales will double
You know because it was like so much better than what we were doing before
3D double instantly
But after about three months ago so
I want to listen to perspective because
Yeah we think about
Like really young
Entrepreneurs
And we think many people think Mark Zuckerberg or
The guys who made Instagram
Instagram
You are 21 years old
I mean
That time
Dell was already doing like Malta
Chipotle
10 20 30 million dollars in sales a year
I think we're 66 million
That year
I was I was 21
56 million dollars
Sprint Moment
An out-of-body
Experience Ramona
Don't invite you
But think about this
21 year old
Name Michael Dell who
Running a 66 million dollar
How many minutes is
Unbelievable right I mean it's it's
Almost
Possible to imagine that
The Happening
Yeah certainly
The song but I was more focused on the future and thinking about
How do we become
Three times larger 10 times larger
What new products
Are we going to launch into
Do we have the right Talent
How do we
Expand
And if
Get more sales people
What was your lifestyle like
Time I mean did it change where you still living like a
21 year old
All of a sudden
Did you start did you buy a giant mansion
How to change the way you lived
You know I
Wouldn't say
Massive changes
I did
Buy a nice
House
I wasn't
Wanting for things but I didn't really have a lot of time to
Consume things and
Was really focused on
I mean it
It sounds like you were so busy that you were
Get your full
Everything that you were doing
Jobing
And you didn't even have a personal life
Just working all the time
Yeah that's a that's a valid assumption I did
Couple years later
Take a little time off and
Managed to
Find
A fantastic partner
And get married and and
Have kids and all that and that's been
Amazing part of my life
I was actually motivated to do this
Impart
Bye
Steve Jobs and Bill Gates
Yeah and the reason I was motivated to do it because of them was because they were not married
And they were about 10 years older than I was
And
Having had the
Prince that I had
As a child
With my family
That's what I wanted
I wanted that family
I wanted that
Experience
And I didn't want to be
A single guy
In his 30s or Beyond
That didn't have that
What was
Stress you out at the
Because it seems like you're so
Even-keeled
That you don't actually sound like you get stressed out but I
Have to imagine there were things that would stress you out
We had plenty of stresses I mean
I remember one time
We got this letter from
Something called the
Federal Communications Commission
The FCC
And apparently
Computers fall under something called the
Federal Communications
Commission Class B device
Which means they have to be approved
By the FCC
So I did not know this
And
You know they basically said you have to stop making these things
Wow when was this
This was back like an 86 87
So
If we had
Follow their instructions
Yeah we wouldn't be on this podcast
Yesterday so if you had a business
Yasso
Fortunately I had some pretty smart
Guys who sort of said well what you need to do is
Call this lawyer in washing
He's going to help you fix
So I called up this guy and he been one of the
Prior commissioners of the FCC
He said he said okay here's what you need to do you need to go down to this test range
You test your
Computers
Immediately
I need to submit an application right away
And
Make sure they comply by
And so we did all that and then he went to the FCC and said hey you know these guys are
Honest forthright people they just didn't know
Now they filed their application and they want to do the right thing and
Here's what we're doing and
We're able to work through it
So yeah I mean the first
345 years
There were
Actually several
Things like that I remember
There was a thought at the time that oh wow IBM's going to
Take back this whole
Idea of the person
Computer and won't be an open ecosystem anymore
And
Bi-weekly
All be out of business
That didn't really
Materialize
So you guys
Decide to go public I guess in 1988 you do an IPO
And raise tons of money and
Why did you why did you decide to do that by the way
Because at that point
You like ice owned
The entire camp
Well we needed the capital we were
Growing at
Like eating
2% per year
And the company was only
4 years old and we were expanding into
All sorts of new countries we were expanding into new product lines
And we also
Wanted to be more of a
Appear with our customers
And
Being a public company someone enable us to do that because
Customers could look and see that we were
You know a real legitimate company yeah
You know that that was helpful.
Here's what I think it's harder to
Prefer lightskins wrap your head around which is
You were
Expanding by an order of magnitude
To every year
There was huge
Amount of Revenue coming in
But yet that wasn't enough
Cash
Capital for you guys
How to expand
Sure all the revenues not profit we weren't we weren't a software company
And so
We did need some Capital to finance the the growth of the business
Send
Hire more people open new offices open new factories
Fueled
It systems
We absolutely needed some cap
Am I getting that money were you able
How to say okay
Now we're going to
Bibl
Bigger than
Well
We definitely wanted to to to be the biggest
Hand
I would say
Changed a little bit in that time frame
You're competing with Compaq
And one of the things I think I learned along the way was that if you obsess
On the competitors
You could be making a really bad mistake
And I think that was definitely true
In the case of those two in the sense that
We had a better business model and if we were trying to
You don't just look at them
We would
Miss opportunities by
Not listening to our customers
And
How did we get
From a
A company that
Then started in a dorm room to having
Half a billion dollars in sales
Well we did it
Because we listen to yeah and we learn
I guess
Fight
The year 2000
In to mm
Dell
Computers
PCS
Because the number one
Brand bite by sales by market
Become number one more than combat more than IBM
Yes
What did
Do you remember
Finding that out
Yeah you know we sort of have this celebrate for a nanosecond
Sometimes a little longer but you know we were focused on
How do we keep growing how do we expand into
Servers and storage and services and software and
How do we solve the next unsolved problems and
You know 2000-2001
We would have been thinking a lot about China
Ian India
The Emerging Markets
Yeah so there wasn't a lot of
Dwelling on any particular success
So I mean
The company
The story of Dell
It's pretty remarkable week
Seems like
From the moment you started selling
PCS out of your dorm room until 2001
Success after
Just like there was no moment
Failure there was no
There was no real struggle is that true is that isn't right
No that's not right at all there were plenty of struggles and certainly if you go back and look at the history there
Are you fine
All kinds of
Missteps along the way and
Dead ends and
Mistakes
What was the dumbest mistake you did you make cuz it Doesn't
My Columbia
It doesn't sound like you made any mistakes it sounds like you were
Preternaturally gifted as a high school
Kitsune understand business
And then you understood computers and then you just started the successful company so
What was the
What was a mistake you made
Okay so 1989 we created something called Del units
Which was which was a software
Prior to the whole Linux
Wave and Unix
It was
Pay
Well used operating
System in mid-range
Computer sis
And
It turns out we were
Really
Early at that and that was a that was a really bad idea it was a kind of a horrible misadventure
It cost the company money did it
Sector stock price
Sure ya all that
Around the same time we also had a
Wildly ambitious
Engineering program
That
Artima cooked up
And
It was too big of a technical leap
Project failed it was a project
Call Olympic
We had
Problems with our inventory control early on
You know
We had
All kinds of mistakes
Fortunately none of them were fatal and
1 things I learned a long long time ago
You know when you find a problem fix it as fast as you find it
And look when your
Pioneering in a new area with a new business model
There's no Playbook there's no
You know you have to just
Learn by doing
And you have to into it
An experiment your way
Through the problem
I'm curious about
Step down as
Is the CEO of Dell
Leave the company
Is a virus a Fortune 500 company
Been already for more than a decade
Huge revenues did you just think okay I've made it on 39
Time to move on and start
A different phase my life
Not really you know I didn't really think about it as stepping down I had
This partner
In the company Kevin Rollins
Who was
The president
Running a company together
And we did everything
Together
And
I decided okay
Ubco
For a while I'll be chairman I'll still be very involved
And
After about two years
You know the industry started changing pretty rapidly and the board
Okay to being said
Yaje we think
You should go back to being
See ya
Yeah I mean
Happened during that time
Because
Accounts that I've read
There was a decline I mean
A 2004 Dell starts
Lose mark
Cher
And then a couple years later HP becomes number one PC seller
And then you come back in 2007 so what was going on in those three years
Well I think the market was changing
I think
There were new things starting to emerge
The cloud
What people call the cloud today and it was starting to show up
I think we weren't being aggressive enough
In
Changing the business
Given the ships that were happening
You know
It's a change or die businesses
Quicker dead business
And the board asked me to
Come back into the CEO role and I was happy to do it
That like around that time
The the quality in the service of
Abdel was
Was in Decline
But the company was getting a lot of heat
I'm sure you saw that criticism
So how did you do
How did you deal with it
Look I think I think you can
In any anecdote
Extrapolate
But there were definitely some areas where we could have been investing more in innovation
And
We
Change the focus of the company
Starting around 2007
Understand
And what we needed to do to be an unimportant relevant company in the future
And so look at my eye
Felt then and feel now deep sense of
Responsibility and commitment to the company and I'll care about the company after I'm dead
What is that meal care for the company after I'm dead
It means that
This is a lifelong Pursuit for me
In terms of
Helping the company reach its full potential and
Y'all certainly my dream is at the company persist well beyond
Mylifetime
Which
You know
I'm still pretty young guy so that I think that's a
Many years away
I wonder Michael how much
Which of
Your success has
To do with
You know your hard work and your brains and you know
Intuition and how much of it is luck
Good question
I don't really know
I'm sure there's some
Element of luck there is probably lucky
A lot
Yeah I feel like I was really lucky to be born in the United States
That's probably the biggest Stroke of Luck right there
Because I think
United States
You know you have an opportunity
Start a business and
When your
20 years old and you show up
And you want to sell something to somebody
You know they they don't look at you
Too funny
So I think that was my biggest Stroke of Luck
I was just being bored here in this country and having the opportunity in the freedoms that that's afforded me
That's Michael Dell
Unless you think of a Dell computer as the nerdy John Hodgman character in the DC versus
Mac commercials
Dell computers have actually been used by the good guys in the json
Bourne movies
Spider-Man Captain America even Mission Impossible
In fact in 2016
Del was the number one brand featured in movies
More than Sony more than Mercedes
Vans or Adidas and yes
More
Apple Mac
And please do stick around because in just a moment I hear from you about the thing
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our
Our sponsors Squarespace
Destiny is calling it says
You need a new website
Easily create a website by yourself with the help of
24/7 award-winning customer support
Header squarespace.com for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the Opera code build it
To save 10%
Your first purchase of a website or domain
Keep dreaming
But make it a reality
With the website
From Squarespace
Thanks so much for sticking around in the
Before we jump into this is
Installment of how you built that
Quick warning if you are a parent of small children you are about to hear about poop
Poop and barf
Because those two things are at the very heart of
Hannah England Fitness
She has two small children of her own
3 and 8 months and if you've ever wondered what happens inside one of those family changing room
Walk into the bathroom
And
There were two moms one was at the changing station and her baby
I just had a blowout like major like up the back all the way to the neck
And this is going to be a situation that every mom gets them so
Sounds into
And by the way every dad I mean
I've been there and kissing
Once you've cleaned up your kid
What do you supposed to do with all those soiled and disgusting clothes especially when you're not at home
I just cringe when you have to stick that in your diaper bag
And then when you have to open it after a full day
It is not pleasant
After the clothes have
Best ER in your diaper bag for a day
Is may become impossible to
To get the stains out
All the Scott Hannah think
I came up with this idea when I was putting my three-year-old
The bed and I came out to the living room
Just started describing to my
Sister-in-law and my husband
This bag that's soaking bag and I and I kept filling in the blanks what if we could
And what if it had this
And then they looked at me and they're like
Well it sounds like you just invented it and what Hannah and vision was a watertight plastic bag
That you could keep
In your diaper bag
It would have a soap pod in it
Kind of like the Pod that goes into your dishwasher so that when your kid pooped her
Barfed all over her clothes
You just throw it in the bag add water and well above clothes when soaked in soapy water
While you went about your day
And then I kind of just hit the ground running because
I thought I need this in my life
Ascentra bunch of samples of plastic bags and she and her husband began to test them
Immediately
Fill it with water and seal it and hang it upside down in our living room
And kitchen to look for drip
Then leaks because
We want these things to be able to hold up in a mom's diaper bag and that's like going to come back but it was really good
Nothing worth
The bags are breaker the zippers are come on down and waterwood
Everywhere
Chopin I kept calling around until she found one manufacturer in Wisconsin who seemed to know
Exactly
What she needed and he goes well I think we're going with this deal that's actually really aggressive for your utility
And I said exactly wanted to be aggressive
I feel so aggressive
But you would have to use scissors to
To get it open
And then Hannah found another manufacturer to make a very gentle soap pod
And finally
She designed the outside of the bags with
Classy black and white stripes
I wanted the design itself to not scream like okay this is a bag for
Soiled poop
Kickstarter campaign to raise about $12,000 and for a while it looked like she wasn't going to make her goal
But then, an amazing thing happened the accounting software company QuickBooks
Found out about her
QuickBooks has this program where is support small businesses until someone from QuickBooks enter a message
Buy a Kickstarter that basically said they were going to back you for the rest of the way it just showed up on our
Kickstarter thing
And my husband of course was going nope this is some weird fraud thing and I laughed at him and I'm like
What kind of fraud puts money into your bank account normally they take money out
Hannah was right it was not a fraud and just a few weeks ago she shipped her very first
5000 bags
To those Kickstarter backers
And if you want to find out more about
Hannah and her company wash it later
Check out our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build that npr.org we love
Caring what you are building and thanks for listening to our show this week if you want to find out
How I built this NPR. Org please also subscribe at Apple podcast or however you get your podcast
Detritus or email addresses HIV tea at npr.org
I put her address is at how I built this our shows produced this week but run. Del Ponte seen Arab Louis
Composed the music thanks also to neva grandson of meshkinpour Thomas Liu Diana
Rogers AR intern is newer could see I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email to
Templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com