Support for this in
NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from VSP individual Vision play
Entrepreneurs innovators and creators
Stop overpaying for eye exam
Sam's and Quality Glass
You can buy vision coverage on your own
Learn more at need VSP coverage.
Patriots guy here
You know I like to think that there's something
Special and
Unique about
Every single episode we do but
This one
This guy
Even though I interview them almost
A year ago I'm still kind of obsessed with the story because
It's about a guy who built
Huge business
Junk
This episode first ran in April Love
Enjoy it
I was learning much more running a business on the streets versus studying in school
I remember sitting down with my father who's a liver transplant surgeon but I remember having to sit down to him and just say Dad
Got some good news for you is good news cuz to me it was good news and I thought if I could
You getting excited he might agree with me and I told him I was leaving school he said you're dropping out of school to become a judge
From NPR
It's how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
I'm Gyros and old pickup truck and a simple
Idea inspired Brian scudamore to build the largest junk hauling service in the world
By this point if you've been listening to the show
You know all about the ins
Firing people who had an idea
And then ran with it
Whether it was Sara Blakely
Spanx
Tony hsieh
Zappos
They had a vision in the pursuit
But almost all of them
They had to go through a complicated process to get from idea to implementation
Which is why today story
Is such a contrast because
Well junk hauling not sound sexy
Brian scudamore's idea was comparatively elegant and simple
He didn't need a whole lot of money to start
He didn't need any outside investors
And he didn't need to hire any
At least at first
And to be clear Brian did not
Dream of a life hauling away other people
Trash
But he did dream of starting a business
Even as a kid
In Vancouver Canada
Etsy seventh grade
I remember in Vancouver
Starting a car wash one summer
I saw my neighbor across the street Eric and started this car wash
And he was charging
3 box of car
And I thought wow what a great way to make money I saw him washing cars and making money so I went and took a piece of plywood made my own song
And I decided to charge 2 Box how you undercut your
Libra Casa 3
I undercut my neighbor by a full dollar
And I thought
This is cool
And there I was learning about a price war and it was awesome because
Literally cars would show up on my side of the street I'd wash their cars
You get more cars we start competing on price
So the funny part is I got down to $0.65 you were a ruthless cruel
Heartless businessman in 7th grade
You know it's funny we've both made money we both had fun and we would do this
Several times throughout the summer
And weed weed up the marketing so I
Get some friends you know a couple of girls that were in my class and
I get them to go hold signs at the busier Street a block away to flag people over and
You start to learn about
Pricing and profit
And I was making so much money that I just I couldn't even believe it
Would you like a
Genius student like where you super
Go to school
Whatever the polar opposite of Genius student would be would be who I was
What would happen if things like reading night
I just that was one area I got stuck
I am so add that I
I couldn't focus on the words
My mind would go to other things and I
I would have a hard time with that
So I learned to read but I didn't learn to understand
And that became a challenge through school and
Andrea Lee
Serta help me back
From from learning through book
So
I
Failed
Many years throughout High School
I ultimately was one course short from finishing High School
So 12th grade
Didn't finish
Didn't graduate
But then I
It's all my friends every single one of them get accepted into colleges
And I said I don't want to be left out
So I went to one of the universities
And said I don't have
My high school graduation
I'm smart enough I can do this
I wrote them letters and I
Spent time
Any admissions office and finally they said
Okay
We're going to let you in
So you were
So you were about 18 I guess
At the time we were you working like
Your parents helping you out how did you even have money to go to school
My parents
When I approach them and ask
For some money for
For school they said you kidding me you didn't even finish High School why are we going to find your college education
Turns out they were probably smart but what it taught me is I had to get out there
Fund my own education
And what I did was I was in a McDonald's drive-thru
In Vancouver I saw this beat up old pickup truck plywood sides junk filled up in the truck
And had to sign on the box that said Mark salling
I was having trouble finding a job I didn't know what I was going to do to pay for college
And when I saw that truck
I immediately connected with that something I can do
I looked at the truck and I thought
I started those car washes as a
The kid
You can see how easy that was to get out there and advertising
Wash people's cars
And so to me this was
Buy truck and haul junk
Why should you be like rush out and go
Woodford Rye
Yeah grab the classified
Section of the paper
It started looking for trucks
And I found one that I
Google 5000 love with it but I certainly could afford
It's price tag of $700
Add $1,000 of my own money
And I spent $700 on a beat up truck of my own and it was this little
Blue Ford F100
And I got my
Girlfriend's father at the time to help me build plywood sides on there and
If I went I spray-painted 738 junk which was the phone number I was able to get from the phone company
Has my phone number and my company was called the rubbish boys
You know light bulb moment we are
Care about them but the reality is there.
Many lipomas usually
Long processing
Iterations and trying things and failing in life
This was a lightbulb moment that just
Happened to pass by you at that moment at the McDonald's
You would not have seen that truck and you may not have
I thought of that idea absolutely true but I would have found something else
It's in my DNA
How I think
And so sure
Found a junk truck
Hey I'm not passionate about junk I never will be but I love customers
Experience and I love building
Businesses I love building things
So I didn't see the junk truck I could have seen
Completely different I could have seen a carpet cleaning business and said hey
That's what I'm going out
So you two you go out you get the
And how did you even know what to do with
Even know what to charge
Or or or anything
DIYs I just started looking around in the classifieds
I started looking and going okay
There's other people
Doing what they called rubbish removal
And they say they charge by the truckload of the portion of a load
I called them up and find out how much they charge.
You call someone out and you say I've got a couch they're going to tell you
Anthony hundred box hundred fifty bucks dumping fees whatever it would be
And I would pay attention and
Make notes
And then I decided I started my my charge rate at
$80
Truckload
Which is pretty
Yeah it was pretty cheap but it was it was probably too cheap
Because
In the beginning I wasn't really making money I underpriced myself thinking
When you go out as a business specially as an 18 year old kid starting to company
How to be the cheapest
How are you getting the word out I mean
How did people know that you were even
Available to do this
So I painted my phone over on the side of my truck
738 junk it was just emblazoned on their was bigger than anything else you could possibly see
And I would park my truck
It at a high-traffic intersection
It so people would see this and then call
And I really quickly
I figured out that people tell I saw your your 78 junk truck parked at
Arbutus and 12th how much you guys charge
And so I I learned very quickly that that was my mobile billboard
And what would you do you go to a house and
Youku
Yourself no help
We are all the
The stuff that they wanted removed
Iwata
Just go into their attic to basement wherever the junk was in the garage and
You haul it away
But I realize there's a lot of things like refrigerators and deep freezers that were too heavy
For just myself Seattle
I need employees
And I recruited my best friend David snyderman
He became too connected to the junk I mean we're still best friends today but it was pretty funny because
He would just look through the junk and go
Look at that
Check this out you know the history behind the city would keep things and I'm like
She's not going to work out we need to work here
So how did you figure out
What do you do with John
Like because
Cuz you have to
Paof
BMC Metallica
Site like a landfill site where did you
Where'd you find
The best places
I called up the city the municipalities and they said
Where do I take a load of junk if I've got something
They gave me the addresses of all the different places and
I tried them all out somewhere we're closer than others somewhere cheaper but farther away
Experimented a bit but
Pretty easy stuff I made it really was a business of
Pick up someone's John
See the smile on their face
Take their stuff off to the dump or to be recycled
And repeat
So simple how how how long does it take before
Are you actually
You know you paid up
So within two weeks I've made enough money that a
Paid for the business
Adjusted my prices quickly I worked hard
And I made $1,700
Net profit
That summer 1989 roughly 1989
All I remember was that $1,700 was enough to pay for my school
And some leftover
And I would do this every summer
Until I finally
Have the Bold decision to drop out
I was learning much more
Running a business on the streets versus studying in school and I remember sitting down with my father who's a liver transplant surgeon
This guy's done more school than anybody I know and very successful very smart man
But I remember having to sit down to him and just say Dad
Got some good news for you and I presented it as is good news cuz to me it was good news and I thought if I could get him excited he might agree
Agree with me and I told him I was leaving school
Since you're dropping out of school to become a junk man I mean he was just
Destroyed
My oldest son is leaving school to become a junkman and then I said
On the glamour Spectrum I mean it couldn't be
Closer to the bottom
And I just said no Dad I'm learning so much more he said you know bright you got a year left in your University education
Just go finish it
I said Dad
My business opportunity might not be there
Forever
I said I guarantee the University of British Columbia will be there for years and years to come if I ever choose to go back
So we agreed to disagree and
I dropped out
At this point this became your your full-time
Get right look at this point
You and visit you in a partner overseas
Just you alone
So when I dropped out
I ended up having a
A guy went to school with me
John
And John Redal and I
We went from one truck
The three trucks
Right after I
Quit school
And whole thinking there was these mobile Billboards work
If I can add
Two or three mobile Billboards around town we're going to get that
Busier and things are going to grow when we're going to have this
Empire
You weren't even paying for advertising cuz you just had
We weren't paying for advertising and
My girlfriend at the time said
Why don't you call up the local press call the newspaper and tell them
Your story
So what story
And she said well that you guys have created your own job it's a tight summer
Labor market nobody can find work
You guys
Created your own job and I said okay
I picked up the phone
And I called up the Vancouver Province our biggest newspaper at the time
It must have been a slow news day because
I said I got a great story for you and they said what is it and I told them and they sent a reporter and they sent that a photographer
And the next day boom We are on the front page
Of the paper
We got a front page ad for free
With your phone number on it
Yeah and I remember the photographer saying
You guys are going to be busy tomorrow
And sure enough he was right we had bus drivers driving down the streets
Waving their newspapers with our picture on it
Out of the window going out to you
And that was pretty fun
By the way did you ever have to get a bank loan or or
Outside money
E225
I didn't I was lucky I
Built a business out of cash flow
And it was in your cost for lowrider
Was you and your partner and you were just hauling the stuff out
Yeah and I ultimately bought my partner out after about a year
And what I did is I just invested everything back into the business to grow it
But I never expanded beyond my means
Not in the early stages
What's the kind of stuff that died
U-Haul out of people's homes
We would haul away old furniture
Appliances
We're very much a
Keep up with the Joneses type world and I think
Unfortunately people renovate too much and always want new furniture and the latest and greatest
Some TVs and sell
We haul away their old stuff we try and recycle as much as
As we possibly can but
Furniture appliances yard debris when someone cleans up the yard
And it was a simple model but it was
It was fun because you would find weird things
I remember there was a woman who
Had Soup cans should a whole wall of Campbell Soup cans I made it look like a real life
Art piece
Write and edit remember you know looking at this and going
What are you doing in jail she just said well
If she was saving up for the next big war and then just wanted to have all this food stocked away and
Finally her kids to said like
And even if there was a war you couldn't eat that stuff it snow
50 years old so
We ended up cleaning out a whole wall OU Andy Warhol ish
Wallace
Campbell Soup cans
What were some of the challenges that you
Effaced
Were there any eat like
Regulations that you had to get around or
Competitors that tried to
You know shut you down or anything like that
The biggest
Challenge I faced in the early days five years and we are about a half a million in Revenue
And I realized I wasn't having fun any longer
I was avoiding spending time with my employees
Nigist
Have the wrong people and I realize that One Bad Apple spoils the whole bunch and
I had nine of my 11 staff were bad apples
I just decided to clean house and I
I got rid of everybody and I did it in one sitting
I took responsibility as their leader and said he had let you guys down and I'm sorry but
This isn't going to work out
What was the
Problem with him
They weren't clean-cut they weren't professional they didn't see what I saw and it was as simple as
I don't care about the cost
They were hauling away the junk
Taking it to the dump
They didn't have the sense of lips
Allow the customer to have that sense of relief
Their junk is gone that they
It got there space back
Let's chat them up a little bit and make them happy
And
They weren't aligned with
My vision
How are you able to
Like how he able to run the business the next day all the sudden
Fired your entire team
And presumably you had Jabs
To do the next day in
That was hard I went from five trucks down to
The ability to only run one at a time
And so I have my truck I had my cell phone I was the call center I did the booking the dispatch
The junk hauling I did everything
But what it taught me was
PE build a company that's all about people find the right people and treat people right so I got out from that day
To never make
The same mistake of course I've made hiring mistakes but
Relatively few
I really focused on finding people that I wanted to work with
When we come back out Brian scudamore pleaded with the state of Idaho to get the number one
1-800 got junk on gyros near listening to how I built this NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better
Their cloud-based platform and solutions deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive and engage
Moritz servicenow.
Thanks also tour 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
The campaign monitor
They took email marketing and made it radically easy
So the big thinkers to focus on what they do best
Developing Big Ideas
Choose from hundreds of
Professionally crafted templates
And turn key design
Create campaigns
Results
The best part
Are drag and drop editor gets the
The job done in
Record time
Try it for free
Campaign monitor
Take your emails and business
Unforgettable
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
A guy Roz
It's the mid-1990s
Brian has
Fired all of his employees
And after a rough
Few months
He begins to rebuild the team
But at this point
His company is
Still a small business
Running injuries
One city
When did you decide that you know it's going to be bigger than just like a
Junk Hauling Company in Vancouver
So you know what that this point 1997 we are actually two million dollars in revenue and I joined something called
Yeo the young entrepreneurs organization
I found myself surrounded by people who had some pretty cool businesses
Tech companies in
And growing ad agencies and just stuff that seemed a little sexier than junk removal
And so I think I found myself feeling sad because I was comparing myself to others
And I didn't feel good enough
So what I ended up doing was I
Went to my parents summer Cottage that this little cottage and I
I sat on their dock
I said okay this isn't who I am I'm an optimist
So I pulled out a pen and a sheet of paper
And I said okay what if I could just
Dream up possible
What could this business look feel and act like 5 years down the road
And I said we'll be in the top 30 metros in North America even though we were only in one
We would be the FedEx of junk removal clean shiny trucks friendly uniform driver
I just started to put these
Big hairy audacious goals down on paper that we would
Be like the McDonald's of of junk that we would you know just what Ray Kroc did where you got all these owners on board
We would do the same thing with a junk removal business
And I took Paul guy who was the
Operations manager of mine in Vancouver
And I said you're going back and forth
Toronto
Every couple of weeks to see your girlfriend
Why don't you move there why don't you take a truck
Why don't you start
The first franchise
How did you even notice structure
A franchise
You figure out how that would work
I looked at other franchises I looked at Subway I looked at businesses and thought
What kind of royalty are they charging
What what's the business model
I got out and talked to a bunch of experts so again being a guy that doesn't learn from school
Just picked up the phone and I called people I called
And I approached a bunch of expert
Person said this is what I'm thinking of doing what do you think
They gave me some feedback and advice on how to structure
Fees and royalties
I brought on a franchise lawyer who still with us today
And I remember this
He helped to give me a lot of the advice in the systems
He believed in us and knew that we don't something
Much bigger than where it was at the
The time
So you get your
First franchisee in
Toronto and
How old
How did it go
It was funny because I got a phone call from Paul guy so he
It took them I don't know week tickets
To Toronto you made a few stops
So he calls me up
Within the first couple of weeks
And he said
This isn't going to work here
Hello what are you talkin about Polly Sidwell
I found out that the city will haul away anything
For free
He said you can just put it out on the curb side that got special garbage collection days they'll take
Fridges stoves couches you name it it doesn't matter
I said Paul you've driven across the country trust me please just try it
Until he did
Any start to get business
And he started to hear from customers
That
You know someone was doing the renovation maybe they didn't get a city permit so they didn't want to call the city to haul away the junk or maybe the junk
What was in the garage or the basement
The city workers wouldn't come collect it from anywhere but the curbside
And Paul started to realize wow
Okay this is going to work
You did a million dollars in Revenue
In this first full calendar year
So at that point you're thinking okay we've got to expand we've got to move Beyond Vancouver and Toronto
And what was the next step was next place to go next place to go was in the United States
At the beginning is called the rubbish boys when did you come up
Did you become 1-800
Paul was in my office we were working and I said
We're going to go for this franchise model and build something
Across North America
I knew the word rubbish was going to be a problem
It was more of a Canadian British term
And the other problem we had was people would
Either think of the company is being the rubbish boys and some people thought of us a 7 3/8 junk so effectively they saw us at 2
New companies
So I remember sitting down with Paul and we were
We are brainstorm meaning
I said what if we did a 1-800 number
Something like 1-800 Flowers something that was more descriptive
So we started brainstorming in the whole got milk campaign that was running at the time
Inspired me to
1-800 got junk
And our phone number at a? In it and it would ask the question got junk
Of course I do then give us a call and so
And so I try to find who owned 1-800 got junk
It wasn't available
The phone company said they couldn't get me the number so
How to dig around
I ended up making about 60 phone calls I had people friends and family in the United States calling the number
It was only working in one state
And that was the state of Idaho
Kuna Idaho had this number
The Department of Transportation in Idaho own
This 1-800 got junk phone number
They didn't know it's spelled got Junk but they were using this phone number
And I thought okay I need this number so I called into their office
Called up there's main switchboard asked for the phone room and I got the sky Michael
Michael ends up
You know talking to me anyway
Does why do you want
The number and I just said it
Business ideas I really want it
That's why we're not really using it that much
It took three phone calls to him before he finally said
Okay here's the AT&T forums
Fax them over to me
The number is yours
I signed and we had
Ideal weight when he just gave you the
He gave you
The phone number for
I think he wanted to get rid of me I think he was sick and tired of me calling
But I mean you really needed that phone number in credibly Lucky break
It was a lucky break but you make your own luck I mean I could have given up after
Call number 54
455 I just kept going and
I've heard so many stories of going to Colonel Sanders knocking on 183 doors and then the hundred and 84th
The guy goes yeah I love the recipe
And so
Just can't give up
So how did you expand into the US
So we
Expanded through franchising
We found a lawyer
Started networking for a Canadian lawyer found a great attorney in the US we created our franchise documentation
You got approved by the FTC in
I said okay
Off you go
And then we just really started to aggressively go after the US press
The big turning point for us
But that the big media hit in the US with
Fortune Magazine
Why did you think it was so important to get
Press coverage
I saw that
When we were this little local businesses the rubbish boys
And we would get stories in the newspaper
People would repeat our stories back to us
Like wow
He dropped out of college and you're building this business and
What a great thing that you're doing a needle
It's an awesome story
So we just started telling the story
So okay so you get this
Article and then what
Like as a result
People are calling you saying hey you don't want to buy like I want to buy a franchise
Guess we ended up getting article Fortune Magazine and they saw one of our trucks in San Francisco
Adam lashinsky the writer called and said
Saw this truck heard about you guys
Seems like
The crazy business in Nigeria
You're building a brand in junk removal
Yahoo.
Yeah
And
Story came out
Hit the ground on a Thursday
And we ended up getting 506
Phone calls
From Thursday to Sunday
So that we
We were flooded
These are people who are interested in buying franchises
Yeah I mean 506 calls imagine listening to that
I'm trying to write them all down and calling everyone back we were overwhelmed
So
I got on the voicemail
I said due to an overwhelming response from Fortune Magazine we are unable to call people back
If you would like to learn more about our opportunity
Please call into this conference call at
At this time
What we did is we have like a hundred people show up on a conference call
And we would do a roll call
Of you know okay what city are you from in and we going to go through one by one all these different people
So everyone's like what I got all this competition I want to get in
And it drove the process quickly
And we ended up doing 53
French ideals that year
Which was just unheard of in the franchise space
And
Things to start at the hockey
Explode
I mean you are to adjust from running AC
Small business to
To a pretty big company like almost overnight rather than all of a sudden you had
Always new franchise Partners in a huge Channel
When the beginning it was
Great excitement
Things were just
Building all this great momentum and we
We raced
Pretty quickly to
A hundred million dollars in Revenue
What year what year
And so
It was exciting and it was as energy in this momentum
But what was interesting about that time is it 2006
I realized I had my
President of my company my cool
Cameron Herald
I was the best man in his wedding great friend we're still friends today
We Grew From together from 2 million to 106 million in a very short. Of time
But what started to break
Was that
You had to add
Fire Ready Aim types at the top of the company
Yeah and and that just doesn't work
We we started to make poor decisions together
Like what you do
We would overspending in areas where we would we would take some risks and we wouldn't really think
Through with any rigor and discipline
How would it affect our franchise partners
We had a truck roll out program where we said hey everybody needs more
Get more trucks out there and we
We put it in the franchise agreement that our franchise Partners had to increase their fleets by certain
Period of time
There's some Rebellion
I mean it and I don't blame them
It was too aggressive and
I realize that we were making mistakes and you can't have the two add types
Coffin
And I needed to find
A new leader and
Having to tell your best-friend that this is no longer going to workout is
A tough tough painful thing to go through for both of us
But we filled and moved on and and you know Cameron would tell anyone today Bryan made the right decision
So obviously I'm assuming you found
Something else to tell
Run the operations
I did so
One of the biggest mistakes I made was the second person I brought in as
The second president
And I brought in a next Starbucks
Cool
And this person had
Can a president of one of the US divisions of Starbucks
Done amazing things for that pill
30000 employees
Under this person
Report to your thinking this person
Sister slam dunk
They're going to do a great job for me
Oh yeah I'm just
Jackpot
Unbelievable
But
We almost bankrupted the company
Wow
After 20 years of growth
We went from
119 million in revenue is what we
We'd headed that peek at that time and we drop down to the 80s
What happened
For the recession-hit which didn't help but I don't buy for a second that that way
Was really
CSUB
Because what really happened was
My president's leadership
In my vision
Weren't aligned
I needed an Executor who could translate my vision and say
Here's the vision let's translated into a plan here's all the steps let's make these things happen I needed somebody that believed in me
And where I could also believe in them
So I
I got that person out of the business
How close to the company to falling apart
We couldn't have been closer
I mean I I would have given us another 90 days if we can continue down that path weed overspent so drastically
On big bats that didn't pay off
And Ida hunkerdown I had to lay off 52 people
I needed to elevate another team
The middle level managers up and I said
You know I know you might not agree with my decision
You probably think I'm crazy but I need your help and
What's the hardest. In my
Professional life
Well my middle level management team who is elevated continued to run the business
I scoured the country for
The Right leader
I interviewed 75 potential president / cos
I said I need to find someone
Whose strength
Talents
Wood
Take all the things I'm bad at
And make them happen
And I painted this little vision describing exactly who I was looking for
I got it up to my network
And three different people totally unrelated
Said the person you describe is Eric Church
Because you've only describe one person on the planet
And
I reached out Eric and I got connected
He was very happily employed he was president of a big Travel Tours and Company
And when the magic happened
It was just okay
We can see building this thing
Together we can see how we would eat
Contribute
Strength to the recipe
And we entered the
The partnership in the
It's been almost 6 years
And together we just
I mean we can
Bait
Discuss
And work together on the culture guy
And the vision guy he's the implementer of the rigor
He's the team building guy and it's
I mean it's
At what point did you stabilize they'll appoint were you able to say okay
Would totally passive
When Eric Church came in
The first thing he did is he had the goals that I had put in place
Lower them
He said listen Brian it's not that I don't believe
And you and that I don't believe in the goals
We're going to lower the bar
Because we're going to teach people
What it feels like to win again
We are going to make sure we win we are going to put the bar low enough
That there is no way in the world we're not going to win
And when people start
Feel and taste that winning Feeling Again
Confidence will build
Team will come back and so he thought about it a very strategic
Landfill
And we made money in the first year of this new
This new business
Really taking 1-800 got junk and restructuring honking country that week we made money
How many cities did you guys operate in now we are in every major Metro in
United States Canada and Australia
So you name the city where there
I talked to a lot of entrepreneurs
Michelle Wright
Some of them go the franchising route and then some of them decide not to do that
Why why did you
I think the answer ties
To the person I am and what motivates
I've never been a Money Motivated
I probably would have made more money in the long term
If I done a corporate model in an IPO and raise money
But what motivates me more than anything is
Taking someone who's got the American dream
Build your own business
But they don't know how
Giving them a recipe given them the cheerleading in the support and
And a team of other franchise owners who can come together
And so the franchise model to me was
Isb
You got skin in the game this
This is your business
And we could build something much bigger together
Versus what we could have ever done alone
NFL schedule
Who is Europe to go back to the eighteen-year-old Bryan
Like in that McDonald's drive-thru
And you could you're just there and you're like dude I know what's going to happen
To you over the course of your life
Listen to me
Would you say that
I would say Brian
Listen to your gut
Make the right decisions that you know with
All your heart are the the decisions that need to be made
Don't be afraid to make them in trust that everything's going to work out and I've learned that
You have storms in life
And
Just like any storm
In real life
They don't last forever
Yeah
One more question for you Brian which is
What is the weirdest
Thing that you ever hauled off
I the weirdest thing I probably hauled off was I had a
Entire truck load of escargot shells
So some company who imported escargot went bankrupt
And that we loaded the truck and it was very light
Kissing of the shells were all there
And the sky says to Migos
You can fit more in than that and I said
Beautiful chocolate syrup you can see the trucks full
So you came up with this idea on the customer's always right so we did it
He said
Go up into the Second Story the office
Jump into the back of your truck
Collapse all those
Shells
And set another load
So I we did it
Kind of fun you know screaming who is your jumping out the window into the back of the truck and we did we got another load in and
We had fun he was happy Brian scudamore founder of 1-800
Got junk
Last year the company and their franchise Partners made close to 8
Quarter of a billion dollars in Revenue
Calling off people's junk
Sometimes that truck is
In recent years
They've come across
A Bible that belong to
John Wayne
An old airport X-ray scanner
And an ATM machine
It still had $26,000 in cash
Inside
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the thing
Your building
But first I quit thanks to one of our sponsors Microsoft
A digital workspace for
Team skip
Create collaborate and communicate authentically
Bring together your chats meetings
Files and apps
All in one place
Office.com
Slash teams
To learn more
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
I never how you built that
And today I did a story we ran
About a year ago
I just want to start Swindon zamir was planning her wedding about
4 years ago near her hometown of Fair Lawn New Jersey
240 guests
20 tables
$7,000
Just for the flowers I know Seven Grand
And it was that frustrating feeling of I'm spending all this money on something that
You know why I want to have it I don't want to be spending this kind of money on
Quite frankly anything that you know it's going to be thrown out
Anthony was trying to figure out how to cut down on the car
She thought about a friend who is getting married the very next day
What I did was when I was talking to the florist I was asking them you know
Is it possible to you know maybe have her Reeves the flowers maybe we can do some sort of sharing
That was kind of that light bulb moment where I was like
The force of telling me that
Is can working
I know that I'll do it and I know that she'll do it
Okay so ultimately they need and her friend
Could not make it work it was
Too complicated
But she couldn't let go of this idea
So it didn't eat when I'm lying
And she start to search through wedding chat rooms and
Read through the thread
You have
Everyone just talking about you notes who's in the same area can we share this can we do that and that was
Another big moment of opening of customers you want to do this I'm not the only one
Who has had this thought I'd not the only one who's wanted to share my flowers
So the gears start turning her head
A few months later
Leaves her job at another startup
To start bloomerent
Fat Brides In the same city could log on to a website and then share flower arrangements with other couples getting married
On the very same weekend
Babies get a discount on their flowers
Bloom Redwood get a cut of the
The florist fee
In a florist would make out really well to exactly so you know for them they got to create those centerpieces one
And sell them twice
But Anthony started to put her website together and then reach out to florists in the New York metro area
She was surprised that a lot of them said
No
You know it was interesting literally everything the person that you know this is a really good idea and I love that you're reducing waste and I know them
Are you doing this
But I just want to do something new
And in so many ways that is both the most frustrating thing in the world
But it's also
Eating really motivating
And so did he just kept at it and her first paying client was a friend getting married in New Jersey
And then things just kind of
Grew from there it was pretty nice to kind of see that like domino effect of
You tell one person who uses it and another person uses it and they tell their friend who tells their friend so we are now in 14 cities
We're all over the tri-state area so
We have a lot of really exciting things happening this year
Destiny Tamir we first spoke to her about a year ago she and her business partner have been working on a new
You service called bundles
Which lets couples easily
Buy wedding flowers online
So instead of going back and forth
Coach
Florist
Couples can choose from one of three
3 bundles of flowers
Based on a budget
And that course they have the
The option to share those flowers
After the wedding on Boomerang
And like we mentioned all this started back when Denis
Was preparing for her wedding
And now
Denise is expecting her
First baby
Inmate
If you want to find out more about bloomerent and bundles check out our Facebook page
Of course if you want to tell us your story go to bills. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes
How I built this. Npr.org please also do subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcast
Or however you get your podcast you can also write us at HRBT at npr.org
Weed is too at how I built this or shows produced this week by Kacey Herman on teen Arab Louis, MO
Who's the music thanks also to neva grandson as Mexican for Thomas Liu and Jeff Rogers AR in
Turn is Narcoossee and Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com