This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this hiscox hiscox the business insurance
Experts who Taylor intelligent Insurance Solutions to fit each businesses very specific needs get a quote
At hiscox. Com
Hiscox business insurance experts
It really quick before we start the show I want to let you know that we got another life show
Coming up
It's on Wednesday August 1st
Boulder Colorado
I'll be interviewing Kim Jordan
The person who grew New Belgium Brewing Company ever
Basement in Fort Collins
Into one of the
Biggest craft Brewers in the
The show is sponsored by American
Express and
Roasting it
At the Boulder Theater on August 1st
Four tickets to NPR presenter
. org
And hope to see you in Boulder
People were just naked in front of the store
Welby showed up in their trench coats and you know we went out when we went with open the store I went out with my wife
Life and put my arm around her and then we we we said thanks for coming and everyone dropped their Trench
Running into the store
NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
I'm guy rosin on Today Show
Turned workout clothes
Into a fashion statement
And along the way
Delta breakout brand
Worth billions
So used to be that the clothes you wore
To the gym
We're like the absolute worst
Close you out
Heather radio t-shirt
Prius
Sweatpants
High School logo
Kind of short shorts.
Jay would have worn on the back
Basketball court
Anyway most of the superior was
Cotton Bass
Baggy
Look so great and honestly nobody really cared
Add one job to do
Which way is to sweat
At the gym
But at some point in
In the past ten or if
15 years
All of that
Change
Because simile
The clothes you wore to work out
We're also the clothes you could wear today
The grocery store or at a restaurant or
Even at work
Soap for better or worse
People were wearing their gym clothes
Outside of the gym on purpose
It was called athleisure
Chip Wilson
He was one of us
I am here
The brand he built out of his house in Vancouver
Is now worth more than
14 billion dollars
Now before I go on
Address
Elephant in the room
Chip
I said some things that are well
Rude and boorish
He's put his foot in his mouth on several occasions he's embarrassed the company
And you will hear about some of that later on in the show
But he's also an open book
An open to getting grilled all about his life
He's not a conscious Media training sound bites
Sky witches in park
What makes him interesting
Because that sort of power chip grew up
Without any pretension
Middle class kid in Calgary Canada
Chip was athletic he played hockey
Football
His dad taught phys-ed at the local high school
His mom
Weather
She live for it it's worth
Total passion was
She tried to make clothing for the kids but of course we didn't we never like what she made for us
Bedtime
You know if I want to spend time with my mom it had to be as her foot in the sewing room
So did you learn how to sew a like from an early age
Seahawks
I can definitely so
But more so I think it was working with the Butterick patterns and watching my mom
Lay them down on the
Fabric Indian
And then how she move them and twisted them in order to save fabric
I only see how important that is because
Once I got into big production and you'd lay fifty to a hundred layers of fabric down
When you can save even
567 in of fabric that can mean thousands of dollars
That before chip would go on to sew and design clothes for a living
He actually got his
First real job
Add an oil company
Working a
Ruling button
Credibly lucrative job
On the Alaska oil pipeline
Almost
2 years
How much should you walk away with so much gas
Well interesting in today's dollars probably about 600,000 and walking back then it was about a hundred
75000 American
You were just as cash and and that's
Simply cuz it was all of this money to work on the Alaska weather
Brighton
You know but I can tell you know I traded my life in for money I mean there was no girls there was you know nothing there
For you know you
You work so
I always wondering if everyone got that offer
Opportunity would they have made the same thing out of
But I didn't
Pretty good use your 18 or 19 or 20
What did you do what you do with the money
Will a turtle's head
Three goals in Alaska when I wasn't stolen my own house by the age of 20
I have to be in my own business by the age of 30 and retard Buy
By 40
Retirement meaning that I was doing exactly what I want
To do so
So I did I bought a house and then I finished up my degree and I work for an oil company
Removed
Right now I guess in like the late 70s
That's right I'm pretty much at
Around the time you graduate
Colleger
Start to make
Shorts
Baggy shorts for men
Yeah because I didn't you know how yet
Have to get what it was like at that time
Men wore very short shorts that were very very
Tight me know you only have
To look at
Movies from the header
Turn the lights to get that kind of
Picture and.
And they made a lot of sense to
Because
I had very big legs and I
I think because I was working out 3 times a day I was always in a constant sweat
And the idea of wearing shorts
All timers
Very appealing
Eventually
And these were like
Flower printed like
Loud Hawaiian like I'm up
Give me the Trader Joe's like those shirts like that's
What the shorts look like
Yeah exactly but you know we have to see it in a context that
There was nothing like that
Before everything else was
That are of
Brown rust off color okra
Yellow like solid colors it was
No brightness in the world at all that kind so that was a radical
Sorry I started
Because I couldn't get blouse
Flower prints in 2000 which is kind of what a person needs to go into business
I started doing what my mom did she quilt
Fabric so I would
Get masses of different types of patterns of fabric and then I would
I cut them into squares and then I would
Quilt them
And then in order to keep the stability of that I put up backing on it if black fabric
And then I realized I had
Reversible shorts only where they long and baggy in
Reversible
Really revolutionized
And then the skateboarder started taking them on because it kind of covers their knees
Seldom somewhere
Well I mean that's the invention of a vertical retailing because I
Made about 300 pairs of the shorts up in 1980 and I went to the big department stores here in Canada and the
They would have nothing to do with them so I had my first inventory problem
So I thought well what am I going to do so I basically set up a lemonade stand for the shorts and
Calgary in the downtown mall in Calgary
And I had a
Partner girlfriend at the time
And so we did that
Together and
In a week
You know we played all these shorts out and then a day would make like $1,000 a day selling the shorts and I was making like
$120 at the oil company so
Did wasn't tough to figure out
The master.
And what are these formats swimming shorts these are just like what like who would wear these shorts what would you be doing while wearing
Well these particular shorts you know I couldn't really
It was tough in the oil business of conservative Calgary
Four people wear Prada suits and
Cowboy boots to sell them on
Loud
Peggy
Shorts and socks
Originally
Call the barbecue
Two shorts because I needed to give
Men needed an excuse to wear them I knew they won
Underwear
But as you know a couple years went on that
Begin that's when the skateboarding Market
Took over from the surf mark
And the young boys me Noah
10 days
18 * 2
So this is
This is 1980
You've got barbecue shorts by the way the barbecue seasoning Calgary cast
Really short like a couple weeks
40 days you got 40 days to wear these shorts in Calgary
I mean not a brilliant
Marketing move but it worked
1980 and then
It's the same time you were still working for this oil company on the side or or you were doing this on a circuit board
And how long before you quit the oil cover
Well I had my goal of quitting at being in my own business by 30 so I worked through it all company for 5 years and
Quit on my birthday gift 30th birthday
Did you create a brand around around the barbecue shorts I called it Westby
Beach which at the time was
I think it's
Holly from being in San Diego and I was young and probably the
The incredible feeling I had from living on the beach
Everyday my total kit
Yeah when I was little
Keira Knightley
Being in Calgary tells 1 to get back to the beach I was going to get back to the West Coast
Wake us right field best so that was the brand I built up around it
And who an insult initially your customers were in Calgary but how did you get the word out around
Canada
Well I went to
Candy was pretty easy because you know that
I got into it almost a decade
Before anybody else I think
But in so I could slowly kind of move across like that we opened up a store in Toronto
But then I went to a trade show and signapore and then another one in Munich
And so you know
A person kind of comes out with something that's
So different like that
You know there's a lot of interest in
And then I had this sense looking 5 years in the
Future that
Skateboarding and surf markets were going to be
Huge
By the
Sort of that time the mid-to-late
80s what were you
Well
I mean the beautiful thing is I
When I formed a partnership with my
Two guys in Vancouver I moved to Vancouver
And then in sat
But starting in 83 in Calgary at started to do snowboarding and I could see snowboarding coming and Snowboard
He was going to be way bigger than
A surfer skate
And I didn't care about the
Boards and the boots in the bindings cuz for me that was low-margin hardgoods
Where I knew all the money we
HP made in
Clothing
Especially for us because it would take up the other eight months of the year which
We weren't really selling very much
And Snowboard clothing was
Or five times the price of
Surf & skate t-shirts and shorts
Who is designing
The apparel that West Beechwood selling
Well I was that was my thing and I
You know if I look back at it now I mean I never had any money
Free clothing when I was young I probably had
It's genetic
Desire for eating
Kind of ideas that I had
I think part of it was
You know my size and I think part of it was
I wanted athletic clothing that actually fit me so I think there was
Driven to both those
What were you making the stop by the way where's the closing theme
Well I'm making it in Calgary I found some Italian Couture designers that were
Just like my mother they were at home and
They weren't working and they were amazing
So we set up a factory
And so if you can imagine
Almost everybody else in the apparel industry I think everybody else
Beastly made clothing than wholesale
Did somebody El Wright
Not only was I doing my own manufacturing but I own my own store so I
Beasley taking the profit
Set of two middlemen out of the
But you know the big
Revenue part of the business was in wholesale
But my wholesale business was losing $1000000 a year and then I had these two retail stores that were making $1000000
Because you have these retail stores
And they were doing well but you
User wholesale business which was losing money
Well it was a quandary because I needed the volume from wholesale to get to economy of scale for duck
Action to bring my
Prices down
And because my prices were down my retail stores could make so much money
But I couldn't really make any money in
Wholesale because
Find me something
For $20 and I would have to sell it to Dick's Sporting Good
And then they would sell it
Wearing my own Realty all stories than I was
Wicked putting it in there for
And making $80
So there was a $60 profit
And so I kept thinking to myself how can I
Get to economy of scale production in that was the
You know that
The big Big Driver
And were you
I mean
What was your vision did you think this is going to work in at a con
Ruby the biggest snowboard apparel company in the world
Sure I mean in in a
Japan had just
Exploded so it's about 30% of all silver
And
The drive to grow in the grow fast knowing that
What I'd seen in Surf & skate wear
It started off
What three companies went to 500 and then went down to
3 again
I need the same thing was hacking to happen in snowball
Morning soap
When's the right time to get in
What's the right time to build with
What's the right time to invest in windy get out with Saul's in the back of my mind and sure enough
You know probably in 90s
6 or so the Japanese Yen store
Collapse
Starting to think that snowboarding was in
The cool thing to do anymore
And so the market was changing drastically and
We still weren't making any money be
Because we were just
Reinvesting
Just to keep on top of
The competition
So you decide to sell
Well yes
Wheaton result to a public company out of
Salem Oregon Morrow snowboards
And
You know we
Quite honestly could not make payroll on Friday and we sold Wednesday based on brand value only
Repair iWatch with a good
Johnny Cash
Well I had
Partners and I had Banks
And I had private equity in there at that time
So I walked away with a million and that
Tax 800000 and then
You got a
You know I had peed myself probably 30 to $40,000 after 18 years so I
No I needed
The car and I used to
Buy a house of some sort which was the best thing I ever did
Living in Vancouver
Okay so okay so here you are
Early forties and end
What were you going to do
Well actually my goal was
To be financially independent
840 so I failed in that goal
And
You know what
Thinking about what I wanted to do and
And then I
And I had this thing I have always bleeding this three times thinks when I see something three times and I
Moving they move really quickly
So it's Cena
I seen an article in the paper about yoga at cine poster
Telephone post with a little rip off about the yoga class and
Then I overheard a conversation in a coffee shop
About yoga and I went well
I went to this yoga class
Yeah I know
It went from about 6 to 30 people in 30 days I was the only guy in the class
And it's any
Jim and Heating
Course I'm always noticing
Athletic bodies and clothing and outfits I mean
I'm really a big data guy around you know I look at everybody talked to bottom and I have analyzed it and
At the time
The fashion of Jim's was to wear your very worst clothing
Mostly because Polly
90% of people in gyms were men and
And you you know you knew you were going to sweat in that you were going to get ugly in it and you just want to throw in the wash afterwards so nobody
Thought about
Athletic clothing being nice
Certificate inside your head hear you're in the Chevy class
And you are observing
What everyone's wearing
You must have been thinking already I have a business idea
When did you start to
Add two and two and say wait a minute
I can make this this type of clothing like
How do you go from one
Yoga class to that thought was an instant that it take a week to take a month
Well
I wasn't doing anything
And I think I was looking for what my life was going to be and so
What I saw in yoga was exactly the same thing I saw on surf skate snow plow
So like I said it went from 6 to 30
People
In 30 days and I extrapolated out
5 years away and I weigh
This is going to be
Substantial
No I didn't think it was going to be as big as surfskate or snowboarding and I had really no idea at the time
It would be a hundred times bigger
It's a big deal right this like your ear spotting a trend
Like really early
Until you probably can't fully explain why you were able to
See that trend
But it was just
Dislike intrinsic feeling you had you just
A part of you just knew that this was going to be a
Yep you can I was extrapolating
But
You also have to get as probably the only person in the world thinking about
Technical clothing outside of mountain Club
So
You know think the real question my mind is do I use this or do I
Just say
You know that I called
I called my 18 years at West Beach my 18 year MBA
And so
You know do I just leave all that information behind or do I say you know I've got something here and it's
It is worth using
After the break at Rick Wilson eventually use that 18 year MBA to graduate
2 an even
Tinker business a business that would
Change the Athletic Apparel industry
Forever
Gyros near listening to
How I built this from NPR
Support for this NPR Podcast in the following message come from the United States Postal Service everyday and
Beta companies are Reinventing the way business happens but none of that is possible without the right people
People who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery
Affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce the United States
Postal Service see why they deliver more e-commerce packages to homes than anyone in the country
USPS.com future
Support also comes from luminary
The only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah has a new podcast
With his new show
The Daily Show hosts the challenges himself and his listeners
Explore unfamiliar angles and embraced differing viewpoints
Listen to Trevor Noah has a new podcast along with other original shows only on luminair
Visit luminary. Link / built for your first two months of luminaries premium content for free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
Hey bucket back to how I built this from NPR
So after attending is
First yoga class
Vancouver in a late night
90s
Chip Wilson had this idea for his next
Clothing
But it took him a while before he acted on
Yeah I had to read an article in the paper one day that told me
That's 60% of the graduates at a university where women
In 1998
Then I went wow you know
Something really really big is going to come out at this and that is
We're going to end up with a market that's never occurred before and that is that
22.
35 year old
Single
Professional
Well-traveled stylish athletic women who owns her own condo and and
And that's okay
You know what I kind of put these things
Gather at end
I think that it just reinforced that this Market was there and ready for something big specially in athletic
Clothing diesel what did you what did you do did you
Did you run back from that yoga class
And I
Go back to your house or where we were living in start to sketch out ideas
Yeah there was a little bit of that and I talked to a quart
Puma staying Who was the
My yoga instructor
Can I dropped out of the New York Financial
World
To become a yoga instructor in Vancouver
And like I did answer skating snowboarding I started to use her as a
Sounding board in his ass
Creative
Source because
Unlike sir skating snowboarding where I was a boy and I could
You fit in the clothing I knew exactly what was going on
I obviously wasn't a woman
And I could see that
You'll get that time anyway with 99% women and
If I was going to do this and I was going to transfer my knowledge of what I'd learned in
Snowboarding Lycra stretch pants into yoga then I needed some advice
Icy Hot
Some money to play with
Sale of your other company
And you knew how to sew of course and you knew how to Source material so what was
Liquid your first move in starting the business
Well
One of my
Big issues in life is always been about rashing of clothing
And I could never really believe that
Apple Nike was at shoe company so I know they didn't really understand clothing either because
Even in their running shorts they had these open seams in between their legs
Run 5K and I totally rash
So for me it was like solving athletic problem
I went to Japan I'd heard about these machines that were $40,000
Peace which was
Shoot at the time
And I bought for the machine to do what
Paper
Flat seam so it's a
First time you could put two pieces of
The fabric together
And the Machine would
Flat seam fabric together and then cut off any excess fabric
So there was nothing flopping around on the inside
City idea was to
Basically make
Athletic wear that would eliminate rashes
Yes and
When I was running 10 K's or triathlons
The rationing was the thing that was always
18 point of what I call a high-level Athletics
Begin what I because I became a fabric scientist of sorts
I could bring in the wicking
If the moisture wicking I could bring in the anti stink I could make it thick enough where
It would smooth over a girl's body so chic
Feel comfortable wearing it
You're getting up in the morning putting it on at work and then you walking down to the yolk
Class and then walking home
Boise idea to just make
Pedicure yoga clothes or was it
To make
Fashionable
You know apparel
Well I think I was just you know the right person to be putting like I said the two together in my
My driving what differentiates Lululemon from everybody else's I came at it
Function and then put fashion into it
Heartless do a reality check here
It's 98
You don't have a lot of money
You took a pretty big bat like a
Pretty much bet everything you have
Right
Why why would you
Why were you so confident this was going to work
I think because when I started to do my first
Design meetings with these 10 groups of 10 women
And we had like
Five or six samples and they touched
Fabric
And they put it on it was the
The first time that
Really is synthetic fabric felt like caught
There was nothing like it any like it was just nothing like it
So I think that
Looking in the eyes of the consumer I could tell that this was something that was going to be
Unbelievable
Alright see you bet everything on this
And then you open a story
Yeah but it's at
You know what I can only get a store on the second floor in the right area on the right Street in Vancouver which
Probably got more athletic stores in any place in the world
Cuz if you know the type of environment we have
But I can't you know it's really hard to get p
People up to the top
Floor
So the only way I can I figure out how to do it is
This to combine my business with
Fiona staying my yoga teachers
And I had all my clothing on rolling racks and remove it all out
Decide and have
Yoga classes there early in the morning and then at night
That would bring women into
Yoga but also see weather
The clothing was and then it
Kind of moved from there
It's your first
Store was essentially a yoga studio
With a like a booty cancer
Crap
Because you have
Are you having this company which
What you decide to call
Lululemon
I probably get
Asus
Once a day
And soap
When I had Westby
Beach Ibotta
Skateboard brand called homeless
And with homeless I started to
I sell that to the Europeans and that Japanese
And it is certain to occur to me that the five big
Trading companies in
Pan
We're making
North American brand name clothing in other words they would come up with their own brand name and order to
Deliver that
The Japanese custom
But Japanese those big trading companies would never come up with a name with an L on it because it doesn't exist in the Japanese line
And so
But I got was that the young kids
Could see through that they went a name with an L in it is more authentic North American it's not like a
A Japanese knockoffs what had real value to
So
I started go all that's really a neat idea so I
Over the next couple years I just started doing alliterations in my mind and with l
But it was a pretty risky name at the time because lemon was really connected with a really bad cough
Call Detroit
Write a lemon yeah but I actually came up with about 20 names and it 20 logos
What were some of the other names
I'm bored the only one I can remember right now is called athletically hip
Also
Well that's what the girls thought too because I had
10 focus groups of 10 people and I had them vote on the names and the logos and they came up with the name blue
Lululemon
But the logo actually came from athletically hip
So it was a was a stylized a from the athletic
Here's a person a question
I'm curious I'm amazed you know
A man like you
And you you are selling
A product primarily to women
In a
Youth sport that yoga
Exercise
You weren't really an expert
And you are not like some
Yogi Guru you weren't
I'm your big guy you're looking
Football player type of guy
And yet you were
Trying to
Create a market
Send and sell a product
Toot toot toot young women
How did you do it did you
Set a step back and and
Have
Other women
Kind of sell the product
For you
Yeah I mean I had the
In between
West Beach and Lululemon I really decided that I only want to work
People I love to work
And so I was really determined to
Develop people
Train them to Mentor them and then get out of the way
And as I
Was running out of my money for my second time I had taken another $200,000 loan
Weight because of
The first time you ran out of money
You were
You're right
Brighton
I got
West Beach mold company moved back from
From Salem to Vancouver and they asked me to run
And it was like a gift out of Heaven because I have
We were really low on money we're I didn't want to advertise I wanted Word of Mouth.
Of the quality of our clothing to be The Branding Niche because I
I really did believe in the Tipping Point and it had to come from people that couldn't come from advertising
So
I was
Begin another
Probably like you thing I hired this woman who
With Shannon gray was her name
The first person I've ever seen that had a design portfolio
What's up with using stretch clothing
And it was in about 2 weeks I
After hiding her eyes
I left her in charge of Lululemon to seal for a year and I went back in
Beach and that's how you were able to
Some cash
That's how he's able to make more cash
Exactly
So you are and so we should foreshadows is a foreshadowing here that Shannon eventually
How's your wife
Do you salute lemon like really launches in in 98
In this neighborhood
Vancouver and does it take off right away is it was
Just like insane or was it a Slow Burn
He was very slow burn
And
And then
It was so slow that even when I left
To rent West Beach
We were running out of money
I had a lot of inventory B
Because I need to make at least five to six hundred of every of R6 Styles in order to get the price down
So I fell into the trap a wholesaler
Men soy
I made a big deal to wholesale to sporting goods company in
Vancouver and ice ship to them and they
Immediately went bankrupt
So that really took
The company to the very edge we had
No money to pay payroll again I was only a
Couple weeks away from the end of it
We had just decided to move across the street from our second floor into a
The store on the main floor on 4th Avenue at
$10 a square foot because it was an old
Beat up electronic store
And then
Another thing from Heaven came and it was they fired me
West Beach swell
Can I use that Loosely but
They combined with Sims skateboards in the co Sims Skateboards
CEO survey
He let me go with the 7c a $50,000 and if it wasn't for that $50,000 we never
Never would have been able to finish our store now
Just before Christmas time mm yogasan mm in even though we had this great
Yoga pants and tops.
Shannon had to decide this
Polar fleece bra
We got into the newspaper and brought everybody into the store and of course while they were there they
They mostly bought the yoga pants cuz they could Tina we're in a position then to educate
People on
The technical features of our patent once we had somebody in them they
They were customer for life
And if you were taking a yoga class in Vancouver that
Presumably you would have
Scene
The label cuz the label was like right on the outside
Of the waistband right
Yeah I put it there because I was
Very clear that I that I
I didn't want big low going
And I thought that somebody should look in the mirror
And not see any logos
And I definitely didn't like logos on the left
Breast because I looked at it as being
Kind of corporate low going you know it's always there on the left chest
So
I decided I wanted to logo small I wanted to be discreet and a place
I said nobody could see
So you
I guess around 2000
To you open your first store outside of end
Tourism Toronto
Martorano's
In Toronto
We had
You my second floor you know in Vancouver was a really a pop-up store in the you know where people had to relieve
Find it
We did the same thing in Toronto almost a year before we open the store there and it was
We got a way of developing the marketplace with
Team
A Lululemon business model so
We would go into every city in the future
Set up a store in
In the back alley or in a side street
And develop our Market invite yoga instructors in
Before we spent Dino 602 $1000000 on a store New York
Again created word-of-mouth which was you know my favorite type of marketing is break-even Market
Cuz I never had any money for Mark
You guys did some some stunts right like and when you opened your shop in Vancouver
You said the first 30 people who show up naked get her
Free outfit
Well that was worse than that I actually put my first at in as anyone that shows up gets a free outfit
And then I realized it's in Vancouver and I was going to get every person in the whole city would show up naked so I couldn't really do that
So I had to put another ad in a week later saying the first 30
And did you get that happen
Oh yeah and it created global
Got media everybody showed up
There was PV trucks all up and down the street and
Maybe make it in front of the store
Welby showed up it was a October morning it was
You probably never heard the Spot Vancouver it was
Overcast and drizzly
You know they all showed up in their trench coats and
And then
You know we went out when we went with open the store I went out with my wife and put my arm around her and then we
He said thanks for coming and everyone dropped their
Trench coats and went running into the store
And like no one even know he was arrested cuz like this
This is not normally allowed in most
Well specially in 2002 but I think it's it's part of the culture here and there's lots of nude beaches so I don't think
It was
I don't think it was out of the realm for
Vancouver very proud of our city and our police for
Frisky no stepping back in Dino just observing
Cement 2002 glulam really starts to grow like
2003 US Open
Your first store in the US and Santa Monica what should I do
Obviously you chose that because that was sort of
Write the center of the
Yoga culture in the US
Yeah I think probably the big thing that happened after we opened up Toronto and the
Second store in Vancouver is
You know I asked my lovely wife to marry me she said yes and so
He was April 20th
Saturday when we were to get married
Panda
I'm working in the store and really I became almost a traffic cop because that
The number of people come in the store was something they would never seen before I think it went from
At $10,000 Saturday to a $30,000 Saturday
So
Obviously
You've got a store in Toronto
You got one in Santa Monica and then I guess
Melbourne Australia you're growing fast
But you but you still alive
Did you Stitch an assumed you didn't have enough cash flow
To really scale the business
Well I only
After that we started making a lot of money and I don't
Just don't mean a little bit of money I mean a lot of money
I mean
You have to understand that
Again.
Nobody
In the world had
Was was owning manufacturing right to the retail
I mean I was taking
Triple the profit
At most people
It was 2005 that you
Went out and
And so
Outside investors
Who then
He's good at that point you don't 100% of the company so you sold
I guess about half of the company and then
Step down as a
Why did you do that what was that the only way you could
Expand and scale
Because I
Retail stores around the world that done Global manufacturing I mean
Honest to God I could have done it all
But I even though it was making so much money I've never taken any money out
My wife and I
Neither of us came from money and we were always scared
You know we were scared that
An earthquake Woodhead or
You don't like this seems really good but is it true is it happening that have to pinch ourselves every morning
And then and I wanted advisors I wanted people around me that could make sure that I wasn't
Going to run into roadblocks
Okay so you sold about half a company to private investor
A new CEO comes in
Are you staying on a chairman
And then and then I guess you become like
Chief Innovation officer
At this point right
Brighton
It allowed me to sit in the middle of the
Design Department
Which is my love is innovation and
Quality Inn
And Athletics
I mean that's where I really flourished
And I hadn't developed as a chairman I didn't understand public boards I didn't understand
How to act or bi mean I think people think oh you know I ended up with a lot of money on you know chip Wilson Seville
Businessman butt
Nothing really could have been further from the truth
The passionate product guy
So
Because
Even though you are still the biggest shareholder
You all of a sudden head outside investor
Who came in
And
Had their ideas
How this company
Should be run
So I have to match
Starting in 2005
Even though you're no longer CEO
There was some tension that be
Well
Yes
My my mistake happened when I was at West Beach and I brought in private equity
We had a board of directors but they had no vested interest they were there to help us out and they were wonderful
So I had this context of my mind that bring in private equity and having a group of like really great
Visors with me
Where we are all on the same page and moving in the same direction
Was going to be another Wonderful Life
But it was
Do you know that
It's my own fault I'm in the private-equity they're there to make money for their investors and
I had it very long term
Vision for Lululemon and
Bad credit short-term
Pink lemon
So we went to we ended up going
Public way too quickly
Right when you guys went public
I like in 2007 this was a hot stock
Yeah you actually
Chunk of stock pretty early on
Yeah you know again you know I had advised use that were just giving me advice that was good
For them and not necessarily for me
You know I really only want to sell 30% of the stock to the private-equity guys but end up selling 48 so I lost
Control of the board seats and I didn't know how to negotiate for them
So that
Is important because as we go public then
You know the advice I got was
Each of you should sell more of your shares in the market
Play Schism or shears are out there the more
The more the institutional investors will be able to get a good chunk of it and be able to hold it for a long time
But the reality of it is
All these were techniques to have
Kind of an owner founder
Dissipate and kind of move into the background and not have the
The power so to speak to control outboard
And that's really
Would I lost and ended
It's my own fault and but that's what I ended up with
But this company just like
Aquent took off
Right I mean
What is early 2000s into
Mm and then
It just it was on fire
Write a lemon was goes everywhere
Where in NY
Today but
I mean that
Despite
The challenges
The you face
It did
Exploding growth
If you got admit that
Oh it was unbelievable I mean you know okay so things happen to me big deal I mean definitely iPod
We have a
Long-term vision for my family and I had a long-term vision for Lululemon
You know those things never kind of work out perfectly but all in all I mean
You have to admit that what
And what has happened is
Made me incredibly happy and incredibly wealthy
In 2011
Lululemon are you land
On the list
Canada billionaire
Which I mean means you
Achieved your goal
Financial
Security and more
Was that like a a marker for you was an important
For you or did you
Think that you're not really care
But I could die really didn't care because I
Begin my dries
Poor family
And my my absolute
Fashion
Frat letter
The clothing
And I think my wife and I
Again we just always so scared of losing it all
You don't like
You still go to snooze
The store and only buy one tuba toothpaste
You know we couldn't like speaking see ourselves by
How to save time
I could do it my business but I couldn't do it at home
Alright so let's address the one elephant that everyone I say
Supposed to be on the show everyone says
That guy
Didn't he wants say in This Is Us
Let's just give the outlines of story
2013 Lululemon has to recall
Certain pants
Because they were concerned that they were too sheer that
Literacy through
And in an interview you gave offhand you said you know look some of these
Answers don't
Look good on all women's bodies
System
And this cause an enormous
Uproar like
Essentially
The interpretation of
Was that you were saying overweight women
Shouldn't wear
What happened
What's your take on what app
Well I think you have to go back into the end of 212 I mean I was
Quite frustrated with the
With the board I think that you know the board and I didn't see eye-to-eye on how the company was being run so
And then there was
Everything can I I said what happened it happened it was
Huge quality issue
So I went on this side
Program on
I think MSNBC Bloomberg
And
I did know
From working in the stores that there was definitely something happening to our
Clothing and I didn't know
What anyway that the question was a really about the
Pilling and I
Sidwell
The fabric pills
Right
What was you know you've done that
Interview with
Bleakley on Spanx
So suddenly
Women were coming into the store and not wanting
Lululemon for
Athletics
They were coming in looking
Ford the Sheep their body
But the
Sewing technique in the fabric wasn't meant
So
What they were doing is buying two to four sizes smaller
Then
What their size
In order to
Get out of the
Garment
Would it wasn't me
So
When you stretch anything to limit
A 10-minute
You sit on a
Wooden
Bench or something like that
Then
Cooling occurs
To a greater extent so
Anyway that but I didn't know that till afterwards ahead and lie but
Two two two together didn't realize what a big issue it was and
At the words that I said we're not
All women
Pick something Alwyn
Long and every pair of Lululemon said quite frankly some women's bodies just
Don't just actually don't work
Yeah oh yeah
Which is a lot different than what you said which is that allowed
I thought you said that
Overweight women shouldn't wear
Lululemon
Yeah I mean what you said is what I think people here
Which is a lot different than what I said just so
Did you want one
Did you get depressed
Yeah I'd have to say I was because you know didn't they
The board took me off a
Is Chairman bao
Because they felt like I wasn't the right front man for the
The company anymore and I was at liability to Lululemon
I mean this is he know after
30 years of doing you know
Thousands of
Public interviews and
You know I say one thing and then suddenly
I'm a liability
I mean so how did you kind of
Did you do you think about that any
I take your point that you
Feel like you were misunderstood and that that wasn't your intention but whatever happened
That's what came out and that was
How it wasn't
Interpreted and
Did you have some
Time to reflect on in the sink
Allison I'm just
Well it was a poor choice of words
It was absolutely devastating to me it was devastating to my family I mean people would
Come up to my wife and go how can you be with a man like that that would say that type of thing
But more so was the antithesis of everything I built to know with women and
For women for Lululemon it was the very opposite
Bedtime
Yes it was
It was
If I could take it back I certainly would
Is it is it strange to ask a question about the founders chip is is strange
To build a company put your blood sweat
Tears in something
People
Don't pay attention to for a long time and all of a sudden everyone jumps on it when it starts to take off
You know right
Success has a million
Our fathers in end
Failure isn't
So all of a sudden
Your company
This thing you built your idea the name
The product
And then you're no longer in control is that
Is that weird
Yeah
My vision for Lululemon and what I could have been there.
It's not everything that I think is
Canby Encino life is all about how you handle setbacks and I think Lululemon still on them
On the most informed cheerleader and I think it has you know it's a great future still
Give another give another business in you
Well what I learned is that
When I left Lululemon
You know what even though it was maybe two billion dollars in sales ad
What's the time I
My brain was on Lululemon being 78 billion dollar
And I
Work so hard
Building a company like
Play Brick by Brick that it was good
I don't think I can go back and
And be a starter of a company at the age 60
To anymore and
Probably got to get a life don't want to do that again
And
To make my absolute
Favorite thing I do is my 12 year olds
Twin boys and I'm coaching flag football
And nothing could be more fun
Nothing could be more
Chip
Event show before
How much of your
Success is because of your
Intelligence and work and how much of it is because you were really lucky
I think
I was
Pure passion
For athletic
Technical product
And I would have worked
18 hours a day for the rest of my life for no money
Now I think what happened
What is I got lucky
Because my
Drive and passion
Met a world that wanted what I wanted
And that was the lucky part
Chip Wilson
Is the founder of Lululemon
Wichita
Time of this recording
Has a market cap of more than 14
Billion dollars
Chip in the helping to run his wife and sons Athletic Apparel brands
Kit and Ace
And please
Please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear
From you about
The things your building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors synchrony
Synchrony has the payment tools Technologies and insights
To help people realize their own unique
Ambition
Synchrony
What are you working forward to
Hey thanks for sticking around because it
Time now for house
You built that
Is it a story starts about 8 years ago
A TV producer named Mike Sorrentino was out in the field
And using a smartphone to take pictures for his company's website
And what I found was when I would be in a place like
Louisiana after the BP oil spill I was constantly having to wipe smudges from my camera
Am I doing that is missing a lot of really good shots
Meanwhile
People were starting to worry about whether cameras in your phone could get hacked and I kept wondering why nobody
Solve these two things
Yeah well think about it
Forget you have a camera that you carry around all day everyday but it doesn't even have a lens cap
So Mike figured he would design an iPhone case where you just slide a switch of the top to cover up the camera
And on the inside of that lens cover
Is a fabric lining and it also wipes the lens
Of any smudges
So a pretty great and simple idea
Around four years ago when Mike first thought of that P said first thing
I got a patent
You know that's the most important part of getting a patent is having a good patent attorney
Attorneys really expensive
My wife gave you the great advice of
Do some side work
And find a way to finance your invention
So I started doing some video production
Decide to pay for a lawyer
Meanwhile you work with an engineer who helped take his paper sketches and make a prototype with a 3
3D printer
But at the same time
He was getting some pushback
Even close friends
Spore like this
Is a dumb idea why are you doing
Right people kept saying hey bike your TV producer why are you trying to break into the iPhone accessory business
Mike says they had a point
Yeah I'm not one of these
OtterBox
Stacker one of these major brand phone case companies who gets this
Spex in the designs of these phones
Before they come out so
I got to wait for the phone
To come onto the market
Then I've got to go to the Apple Store
And measure it
And then send it to the engineering
Lot of back and forth
But by the end of 2014
With the help of $20,000 that he raised on Kickstarter
Mike found a factory in China to make his first run of iPhone 5 and 5s cases with lens caps
And then
Somebody give him a tip
Somebody said to me
If your products already
In January
You have to go to the
Consumer electronics
You have to be a CEO
Yes so that's what my did
Federal Way to camp out in someone else's boo that
The Consumer Electronics Show in LA
Las Vegas
And there were
A lot of people that came up to me and said
I feel like they should be on the market already
But no Mike says he was actually the
First guy to come out with an iPhone case that has a lens cover and
Cleaner
Right and our logo is something I made up in Microsoft Paint a little
Phone case that looks like a little pirate
Can I attach that's why I came up the name iPad case
Because it covers up the cameras I
Since he launched the eyepatch case
Mike sold about 5,000 of them and he's making a profit
But he still splitting his time between iPhone cases and video production and
He says it's a pretty good combination
I work in an industry
That was all about ideas and content and things that you could not touch
Should I have a physical tangible product in my hand
So incredibly rewarding
If you want to find out more about the eyepatch case or here
Previous episode
Head to our new podcast page how I built this. Npr.org
And of course if you want to tell us your story go to build.
NPR
. org
And thanks so much for listening
The show this week
You can subscribe at Apple podcasts or wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there
Please give us a review
You can also write to us at HRBT at npr.org and if you want to send us a tweet it's at
How I built this
It was produced this week by Jhene West with original music composed by
Arab Louie
Thanks also to Newark could see sanaz meshkinpour Neva Grant
Jack Rogers
Intern
JC Howard
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsors snowflake the only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse start your journey