Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here you know a lot of you have started to tell us about your all-time favorite quotes and stories
From our interviews and this one definitely has a bunch of them
Spoil anything but telling you what you're about to hear
Just say you'll know them when you hear them
And this episode Ram
About a year ago
Troy Carter
And I hope you enjoy it
So what happened to the business
It was over and I didn't have the cash flow and the phone started ringing and it
Was the landlord of that building saying you know what rent hasn't been paid you know all of my vendors you know
Started calling me my house was under foreclosure and my wife
And my mother-in-law ended up pawning their wedding rings that you know that that's the save the house
You know I'm with me at you know I never could you know considered suicide but I know why people
Will do
From NPR how I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories
Lego
How Troy Carter went from the rough streets of West Philly to launching the career of one
One of the biggest pop stars in the world
Lady Gaga
Usually takes
Sev bit of instinct
Sim failure and a lot of luck to figure out what customers are going to want to buy
Seth Goldman
He figured a lot of people would want a
Barely sweetened iced tea
And with honesty
He turned out to be right
Herb Kelleher
I thought people wanted cheap flights with no frills
Well
We got Southwest
Preferred Troy Carter
It wasn't just that
He thought Lady Gaga would be huge
It's that he had no choice
Because
At the time he met her
This is just 10 years ago
He had lost
All of his money he was totally broke
But somehow over the next few years
Troy essentially built a company
Youku
Call it
Lady Gaga
A sprawling Empire of writers dancers choreographers costume artists Roadies music
Producers Engineers marketers publicist
You get the idea
And Troy-Bilt that without
Any family connections or money or
Formal training in fact
Much to his mother's disappointment
Troy dropped out of his high school in West Philadelphia in 1990
To pursue a dream
That dream was to become a rapper
We had this idea that we were going to be this rap
You know call to too many and it was me and two of my best friend
We called ourselves
2 to many because it was
We only had enough money for one of us
So it was always two too many of us
And my best friend said If We Ever Meet Will Smith Jazzy Jeff and Fresh Prince they're going to give us a record deal
So that we had the soul focus and Soul Purpose meeting Jazzy Jeff and Fresh Prince
Are the guys from Philadelphia
They were the only guys in Philadelphia they weren't they were from our neighborhood
They were successful they were like gods in Philly
And they were they were too way out
That was plant that was plan a b and c
So did you
Yes we we actually hop the
Train
And you know we don't have money so we just went in a wait for the
The train to pull up and jump over the turnstile and
The train down the Delaware Avenue
And we knew Jazzy Jeff had a record
Studio there and we just wait outside
Recording studio
Nothing we did that for almost
Six months and Jeff used to see us outside but would never let us end.
I think he thought we were like stalkers or something
And then one day we saw some friends
In the studio that let us in
Will Smith in
That just happened to be in a
Studio n
We walked in and
We played our demo
And he listened to it right then and there
He listened to
And
We actually went outside it was snowing
And we said well we want you to see how to dance to so we actually
He started dancing in the snow
I think
And we quickly found out we
Suck but you know
Well saw some potential in US
Antioch
He said look how you know how you guys
Getting home then
We said we don't know
And he
Drobots home at night
And basically told our parents
It's that you know
He had discovered we
We were going to be okay
And what was it was a track you play for
Did you remember how close
Oh my
God it was
Pretty terrible
You have to give it some of it
It was a song called where's the party at 1
I'm not telling you that actually I shouldn't even said the name because you're going to
Google Now
I know you are
Girls that so bad
We thought it was really good will thought I had some potential we put it out and it went doublewood
Cmake no money
We may 00 money
I probably still Will Smith money for that
That you establish a relationship with Will Smith which was kind of a big deal
Yes and you know what and will has a partner stilted
It is very day name
James Lassiter
You know he was in the studio that day we played the demo.
And
He was Jazzy Jeff
And fresh Prince's manager
He actually got the
The job is their manager because he was the only guy in our neighborhood with a
The car
And James had become
This sort of
Mogul in the industry
And
I wanted to be jeans
So in my soul
I wanted to be less
Fresh Prince
Amore Jean so I just kind of put myself under James
And James became a teacher
CCU
Basically move away from
Being a performer that
Appointment Etta James give you a job
Yes James gave me a job I had a few jobs with an account but I was James's assistant I was
Was Jazzy Jeff
Assistance
I ended up moving out to LA
And working with working with James at his production company what will how old are you by the way
I was in my late teens or early twenties done some sort of that transition.
Right
And
I was working at will and James
This production company
And I was having the time of my life and I'm very hard headed thought I knew everything
And I didn't have a car I thought it was going to be like Philly where you just can take the train everywhere
And in La everything so separated
And I was taking this car service
From the office
To visit this girl probably two or three times a week or whatever but I would
Pay
The bill at the every two weeks when I got my check
I would pay like the office managers they hate a Bills going to come in
I got you covered or whatever
And one time I think I pissed the office manager off over something
And she told James that I have been using this car service
The visit this girl
And James came in and fired me and sent me back the
The Philly on the spot that was it you were done
Done James basically you know he saw the route that I was going and I was taking a lot of shortcuts
And I was kind of living this La fastlife in sort of the stereotypical
Fake executive
You know I thought I thought I was much bigger than what I was at that particular time
He kicked me out of LA
Like you said go but you're going back home
So
Like you're in your early 20s
You lose your job and you go back to Philly
Yeah I went back I went back to Philly soda with my tail between my legs
Am I cousins in Philly
LeapPad started a small management company as sort of a
Production company
That they asked me to come in and run and wanted to clients with a girl that I met when she was 16.
Sushi and I known each other
And we started working together and and it was the rapper Eve
I had absolutely no clue
What I was doing
And you know it started off you don't even come to me and she
She said luck you know I need your help and you know it
I'm figuring this out
And at first I was kind of helping her find a manager
Finally she said look I want you to do it
And and of course I said yes and jumped at the Opera
Opportunity
And
I think initially the job was
Protecting my friend
So instinctively
The decisions that I was making was really about
How do I protect her and make sure that you know she has the best
Possible chance to make it
And everything else was you know learning as I was going along
And you know I remember the first
Tore that we went on with this cash money Ruff Ryders
Store
I got on the bus
This old bus driver
And you know scruffy beard and he said
You got the flu
I said I'll be right back
And I you know I got off the bus and I called one of my buddies who is done touring for a long time
Blessed dude
Float
And he said
The money that you
You give the bus driver for gas
Kohl's
Fuel you know everything else or whatever
So I got back on the bus and gave him the money and he knows
But here's the float
Anna and I sort of floated my way through the resta
For the next three years I got a float at my way through kind of figuring it out as I was
Was going along do you have to do
As a manager for
Book shows in Ensley how did you even know how to
How to do that or how to promote
Herbrand and had to get her out and
The world you know what the the way it works
Is
The manager sort of you know it's like the Hub
Of an artist
So you know I go out and I hired a booking agent
Who books the show
I hired a publicist who
Who who who does interviews and television
I bringing the record label
Beats the music
So sort of like you know
CEO of
You think of her of her business
And that
That became a pretty big business
Yes she she actually became
One of the biggest
Female hip-hop stars
Of all time
And you know I was lucky enough to have the The Fresh Prince bloopers
Breadsoda kind of understand
That a rapper could Duty
TV in a wrapper could do you know things outside of their Core Business
And Woody we ended up building you know a clothing line
A television show she
Calgon on the dude you know
Barbershop you-know-what with
Ice
Cuban and
Cedric the Entertainer
So we ended up building something
Really special in something unique for a female rapper at that
How did you know what
I mean negotiating is really really really hard
Work right
And you are so inexperienced
A time like
How did you know
What's a ghost
You know what I think a lot of it is you know
Is is West Philly Spidey
You know so when you have to
Negotiate for survival
And you have to know how to read runes
And you have to know who the bad guys in the rooms are who has the gun in their pocket
Who's jet who's just going to brandish it and who's going to who's going to actually pull the trigger
So I think that's just a natural instinct that comes with
Coming from where where I come from
So
Being able to take that tool into negotiations are on reading people and I'm reading rooms and reading Circle
Stances
I think it's
Very very important
And then also knowing
What's important for that person on the other side of the
Cable
And what's important for
The client
And a lot of time is not conflicting till so both sides can kind of get what they want out of
So I mean personally this point in your life you're still
Really young guy like you're thinking I'm set I am
This is all like
This is all
Unfolding exactly as I had hoped
Yeah you know I was
I was on cloud nine because you know this is everything that I've ever dreamed
That's all I ever wanted to do in my in my life with with music
And because I was a failed artist
I was actually able to help
Somebody account
Was their dream was you know definitely fulfilling
And then the trappings that came along with it as a young guy
I was I was loving it
Are you making money
I was making Hood money
So I was like I was ghetto Rich at that particular time
Have you had enough
The nicer house out of the 40 row homes on that side of the
Mistreat you were doing okay but by no means was I
Was I rich
You know
My goal was to make $1,000 a week
If I can make $1,000 a week.
Was it for me I was set that was my that was my goal
What was the name of your company by the way it was called Irving wondering what
And I and I did it out of Philly
For five years and then I sold that come
Company in an 2004
You sold it to another management company
Yes it was a big company in the UK called The Sanctuary group
And I'm so I sold it
To the sanctuary group and then move to LA to help them open
Why did you sell the your master
The real reason was
At that particular time it was
The largest liquidity event that I would have experienced it was a lot of money basic
Live in Czech
The check
You know walking around venues with you know a backpack full of cash from venue to venue
So you know it was an it was a complete lack of
Vacationing in the way we
Operated the business
And then
The guys from Sanctuary you know they were managing guns and roses and you know bunch of
Huge Rock axe
And it just done a deal with Matthew Knowles who was who's Beyonce's Dad
And bought his company
And he approached me and said luck this company can help you
To scale your business
They can help you
Grow your business you know in a way that you
You can't grow it internationally
And you know
You don't have to live check to check you have a young family
And he said look this is going to take you to the next level and I and I ended up doing
What is a pea
I can't tell you
NBA long expired I ever made
I'll tell you it was a it was a
Dad it was a 2 million dollar check
Actually
The actual number was to
2 million
Buy $275,000 with the actual number
Because I remember when the wire when a wire went through
I called and checked the automated bank machine
About 10 times to make sure that the money was
Still there
Because I never I never had $1000000 them in my in my bank account before I never had
Even close to it
And you know in in the bank at one time
And here it was now it's like okay you know what it's
This is this is very real
And I just
Yeah it was very real
What was it like working working for sanctuary
I hated
I hated it when you know it was it was fantastic at first
And
Because
I was so excited to let you know to get the check I can
Completely overlooked all of the red flags what were they
You know what it just was certain things and certain behaviors that showed up during that period
That I chose to ignore
Because I I I said I'm just going to take the check
And I'll and I'll deal with that and maybe he isn't such a bad guy
Maybe don't
Maybe they are ethical underneath some of the things that was happening
During the negotiations
So
Coming in
I just
Didn't do
The diligence on them that they were doing on me
So how long did you last there
You know what
Probably I remember waking up
And
Talking to my wife a couple times
About buying a
Because
I'm talking about you know me Growing Up Loving music worship and you know Berry Gordy
All of these guys in like this is my
Dream and I didn't
Have a plan B in this is all I wanted to do
And I was dreading getting up
In the morning going to the
Like I had knots in my
Going in and I were going to the office
And I will pull my shades
That we had glass off
It's down because I didn't want to work with
In about
2 years in a year-and-a-half
And you were managing you are still managing even
Yes I was managing the
Now when you lost Sanctuary Sanctuary you are still
Pretty much financial aid
Security
Yeah I thought I was
Invested
A lot of money back into the business into this new business
Did the new business that you started after you left Sanctuary after I left Sanctuary so
One of the things I realize was $2000000 isn't actually $2000000
You buy a house you paid
You know you paid taxes
You buy a couple new cars
And it's gone it's gone I invested in and I invested in this new business
Anna
He was going with me so I said you know what
I know exactly what we're doing
This is going to the next level
Did a build-out annie's beautiful offices
Design on Wilshire Boulevard
And and started this new this new business
What happened
Are you not even walked in one day you're not
Maybe I'll
Probably about
Your
Maybe a year or two into the into the new business
But she came into my office you know she sat down on the couch and she
She said I think I want to go
In another Direction
And I said what what do you mean
So well
I think I'm going to find
New manager
I said wow
Why
This is why I think
I want to go to the next level and
I want to go with a manager who I think
Could get me to the next level
That's it why are you thinking about anybody's
Specifically
She said yeah
Yeah I'm thinking about
This guy shot cam
Mentor and good friend
So
She ended up siding with one of my good friend
For management
And I mean she was like your
She was your ticket to making that new business
Successful so
But even even more she wasn't even she was my
Friend
And we know really close you know she was there through you know girlfriend and through my wedding
Little peanut birthday
Getting a Mac
Kids in
It was a heartbreak you know number number one
Tom in terms of how it how it ended up happening
You know and then the business what was Haile head
On that success what you know of her you know it was a single client business pretty much
So what happened to business
It was over
This was you know this kind of bleeds into a you know going into
Probably 2007
When
You know I didn't have the cash flow
And a phone started ringing and it was the
Landlord of that building saying you know at rent hasn't been paid no all of my vendors you know started calling me
And then it kind of spilled into home my
House
Was under foreclosure
And my wife and my mother-in-law
Ended up pawning their wedding rings
You know that that's the
To save the house
Uni
And even down there that you know the kids were in privates
School in
Having to to tell you no
That this had a school
Asking them to you know could you
You please
Keep the kids in
Score
You know and I'm going to pay tuition I just need a little bit of time
But you know scared that when I gave the waiter my credit card for a couple of bowls of oatmeal that it was going to be the
Decline
It also it was it was it was
And you know
Super humblin
Not not just as an entrepreneur but as a dad and you know in having a live through
That really
Dark dark dark.
And Hip-Hop is a very small community
And it will you know
We had a couple of buddies who were like you know real Executives in our business
Who committed suicide who are you don't have to
Successful careers
And everything else or whatever
And you know I'm with me at you know I never could you know considered suicide but I know why people do
Obviously you had
Already demonstrated some
Talent by managing
Eve and buy
All the promotional work
You died
But in your mind did you swear you able to save yourself okay I'm talented I'm going to pull out of this
Were the moments where you just.
I'm doomed
I am not
Going to get out of this
Now you know what it is
You can't fall off the
And I was on the floor no nowhere to go right
And
Mom mom
You know she was a single mom
We grew up
We're a lot of times we had the
Choose between
Weather we going to have a phone line in the house
Or electricity
And I remember us being on the bed with a penny Bank
And it was a bronze penny Bank shaped like a
A pig
And she was stick a butter knife
Into the slot
To get the coins to come out
And we would divide the
The coins up
To get that you know
So me and my brother
We have bus fare to get the
The school
So we grew up
My mom caught the bus everyday
To go to work and walk
Sometimes 4:30
Years straight
So my mom's work ethic
And spirit
In My DNA
And I was always working
I wanted that too
Make my mom and my grandmother proud
That was always a big thing for me
Are you know
I want to do that for my wife and family
And I and I think
Having somebody who has your back knowing you got somebody who has your back like that
The big deal
In the
In the midst of this
Microliter
.
What happened how did you
How did you turn the
Wow
A good buddy
Vincent Herbert
Who's like this
Very jubilant guy
This is like a character
But he's super talented
You know he was a child prodigy
He was like six
16 + 17
Producing record
Goodfellas
Celine Dion
You know Whitney Houston and
In
Toni
And we were the same age
And every time he was in LA he will pop by and just you know we would just
Talkin and
Ketchup
And he called me and said
You know
Carter I got this
This girl that I saw Myspace that I want you to check out
And any broader in
And she
Play dinner music at
Great
It was Lady Gaga
In the moment the story of how Troy Carter came back from Financial ruin
And help to build a superstar I'm gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
Look and much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast Spotify picture SoundCloud and Google
And it gs.com podcast
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to you
Your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Troy Carter is
Probably a few lowest
Point in his life
Houses in foreclosure
Is businesses
Falling apart and
But around this time
Introduced to a young singer and piano player who
Calls herself
Lady Gaga
Did you know
This is going to be huge
Yeah you know what you
The real answer is you don't know
You think
And you hope
But you don't know
Whip people see now
Is what she was you know except for his you know she was a brunette
Nnc
She didn't dance at that particular time you know she was behind the piano
Actually Ellie Reed
Dunya show
I just dropped from Def Jam
But you know what she in all fairness to LA
Cheat she was a piano singer
Yeah
And she going to West Virginia
Cried on her grandmother's couch afterwards because
Her dad gave her a year off from school and basically said you got one year
To figure this out or you need to go back to NYU
So she thought her dreams were shattered
I think it was that sort of thing you can't fall off the floor and so you know she had the spirit
And her that
You know when you feel that sort of pain
You never want to feel it again so she was a
Incredibly hard
Worker
So she just worked hard everyday to get better and better
So what did you guys start
To do I mean how did
When you are almost
Bankrupt basic
Financial your bankrupt
And she's like oh please can you manage mean you're like
Yeah sure okay
You know we made music
That that was the big thing like Vince Vince was incredibly talented at
You know helping her shape the sound
I knew
How to work with with female artist you know I knew about the fashion business from working with Eve
You know got signed to Interscope which was the same label that he was on
So I had a great rapport with the with the label already
So it was it was
Very it's all natural kind of navigating it
And we don't
I think we worked in a music for almost
9 or 10 months
And then we took it to
The record label in the record label said all those songs are great
Let's give this to the Pussycat Dolls let's give this to Britney Spears so she ended up becoming a great songwriter
And
A few of the songs we
We actually fought for it and we said we just not giving these records up
And we went out and we took those songs the radio
And it was a disaster
The radio wouldn't play it
It was the song Just Dance nobody would play that song
Nobody would play it
Build her career what did you do
We you know what it's
We ended up
This is as Facebook and
Twitter
And Myspace and YouTube all of those platforms were starting to
Just emerged as places where you can reach audience
What is directly
And we started using the platform they were free
Where we got lucky
Is that a lot of them were global
They were in markets outside of outside of the US
So we started reaching audiences and places where we we didn't travel Geographic
What you just liked post
Textra videos are like
Messages from Lady Gaga discover her
You know what is be sort of underground music communities that want it that want to find thing
Before other people
Pill finder
And I'm and I remember we came up with this concept called Gaga vision
And for you to
And it was like these 3-minute video clips of basic
Sickly
The art clips of her and her dancer
Her and you know but we will have the better music underneath and it was
Super artistic
And you know she was brilliant and in a one of them
First
Music voices who who really knew how to use and levirate social
And it really work so we started building you sort of underground followings throughout the world but it wasn't
Big it was
75 to a hundred people in clubs that we will play
But we we super serve that community
Because just a
Few years or year-and-a-half
Before that you're in a
High-rise office building in La glass office building
Living this life as a
Corporate executive at this management company
And you are now like going back to traveling in Vans and like
Sleeping in them and trying to get this artist into small clubs
Yep
Start started over and over
And also you know this was newt
For me because this was
Pop music
Totally different front from Hip Hop
It was it was it was a difference
Skillset and so-so really start starting over
How are you able to even
Fund
Like the videos
Heart or like
You didn't have any money
The time so how are you able to do it
Interscope Records
Ososo Interscope stepped up
Nna funded a bit
It sounds like they didn't think she was going to be as big as you thought
No you know what is it was a shoestring budget
We didn't need a lot though
You know I remember her
She know she didn't have outfits
So
She had this idea for this sort of mirror
Bra
Panty set
Or whatever that she couldn't afford
So she took a mirror
And she actually broke the mirror up with a hammer and crazy glued
Hp's Contour onto a bra and panties
You know we had this for all of the early Gaga fans you know from the from the early days
You know she had she had this latex costume
You know what these big shoulder pads
That she wore to every single show
Not multiple outfit
One outfit
That she wore
Every single show
So you know so we we've basically bootstrap this thing and every dime that she did make
She reinvested it back into her career
So I think when you married
Did you marry that with the perfect storm of
I don't have a plan B
She doesn't have a plan B
Vincent doesn't have a plan B
We we
Have to make due
Just had to work
Had to work
I'm getting anxious just listening to story cuz I'm thinking oh my God
Crazy it's crazy risk
Okcu
So you're trying to convince State radio station
Play her music
Keep building up a social media Network
But
What was the moment where
She just blew up
The moment that I knew like you know because it wasn't just
One moment right it just was like
Deathgrind over a one-year period
Forget it on the rain
And so I remember we were playing at
Theater
It was The Wiltern Theater in LA
And you know this is that things are
The feeling better
Yeah but I remember that we were so nervous about The Wiltern no
Because it's a thousand seats yeah
But we have sold out a couple of nightclubs
So we like maybe we can stretch it will keep the tickets at $20
So you know so it's super affordable or whatever and we can give away whatever we don't sell
We can give to the radio stations or you know
I'm kind of pad the venue right like 2008/2009 yeah right around that time
And I remembered
Driving down the street
That morning because I had to go downtown for something
And I drove down a path
The theater
And kids were sleep outside
To get tickets to that show
No they had already bought tickets to the show
And they just wanted to get in first and when I saw those kids sleeping outside I said we'd
Did it we did it because when you can get them to line up you got something special
You got something special that ride like you know what it was pretty incredible you know
We going to places that I never dreamed about
Met people you never thought you would me so not only did she go to an incredible
Level in her career it actually took me to a level in my career that you know I thought you know what I would do
WoodTV I thought I was at you know height but this height was you know your in your mouth
Everest did you guys
You and Emily guys you ever have moments
Where you just had a quiet moment and you just look at each other
How did it happen
Oh yeah
You don't meet me
Me Gaga invent somewhere like this trifecta
And we will always have those moments
Oh
My
Guy
Can you
Wow
You know you look out at
A crowd
Or you know I remember seeing her play stings
Ring Forest event in New York
Where you know Stinger bring out you know Legend after Legend Elton John Bono
Stevie Wonder
You know just all that great
And her being the only
Young artists
Is there playing with those guys
Seeing her hold their own with those guys and I'm just take her under a wing unit under their wings
So you know it just all of those moment so it just you know very very special Moana
Is it to drink during this time
Scissor like
2010's
You also start to
Like I said I'm going to Branch out right now
Yeah because
You started a company
Around that time
Atom Factory
Yeah I started atom Factory
Actually so I started Coalition Media Group
What was the original name of the
Things started
It was
Distorted energetic
Shift
With that within a company
And you know I not gone through
You know the terrible time.
I said you not
I want to change
The name of the company
I want to bring a new energy into it
And I said
I want it I want this company
Something small
But yet powerful
And just to be honest with you
The thing was
I just said I want to wake up everyday and do
That was
The mantra for me purse
And so whether that included management Oregon oh
Producing
Be your whatever I just wanted to do
Do you think that that inspired me
Yeah
So
Restart this company and
Lady Gaga's career
Doing great and
One day she walks in and says
I'm leaving
Yep just walked in and say I want to go in another Direction
Which is a story you had heard
Yasso
I can't say it felt any different than if that then it felt the first time
But you know what it is
It was a different
Experience
The first time I went in
To panic mode you know when that
When I happened to
This time you know I
I think I think I was able to
The sit in the middle of that storm
Anne and watched
The storm path
Want to part ways with you
Are you know what it's
I think it just it happen
I think I did differs in opinion you know on what happening and why have
But ultimately our
You know I respected
Took it on the chin
Are you guys still friends
I wouldn't say friends but cordial
Yeah cuz you was probably the closest person
You know that's the thing about
You know you
I can't do it without
Pouring my soul into
I can't do it without investing
2%
And internet released
So
I didn't go into
To the relation
Get wet
Gaga with my guards up
You know because
The thing happened
You know so it just doesn't work that way
It's just no gray for
For me and my mind all in or all out
Is it
Bittersweet to see her perform at the
What all do you know what is
Not not even better
Stewie I think it just
You know
Bet the songs that she
She sang at the
You know those old records that you know
I know the origin
I know the stories behind
You know we we were part of
I was part of getting those records
Super Bowl so it's a part of my life
That you know
Always going to be proud
Completely different side a
Of your career with
Which is arguably a much bigger part of your
Which is
Investing
You basically
At a certain point decided
I want to invest
Startups
Yeah that that
Sort of came about
Through
You know we were doing all of these
These things in technology
He's a startup
Liquid Gaga you know in order
Yeah just to promote the music
Yeah and the music industry and end
Just Hollywood in general
We're in litigation with most of the United Technology Company
So it was this sort of
This wall between technology
Quien Canta
And we embraced it and
Since I started building a ladder relation
Epson Silicon Valley
That
Introduced me to a lot of young entrepreneurs
Who started asking me you know can I buy
Starr companies github
Introduction
You know that I want to invest in their companies
And that that ended up turning into you know I think I've invested in close to a hundred early-stage technology
Yes I'm free
Pretty seems like
Uber Warby Parker Spotify write you an early industrial although
Yeah yeah Spotify
Warby
Uber Lyft
Dropbox
Slack
Really great company
Means that we're proud
So like
Looking back at that that
2 million
Dollar check that you got
20 years ago mean you are
Let's face it like your
Very rich guy
If you've done very very well do you feel
Secure now do you feel like you'll never get back to
That point
11 mm
6 worth
The banks are going after
Take back your house
Is itsfunneh tok talkin to like
People who grew up poor
You suffered Financial
PTSD
XOXO
Going through financial
PTSD
You always have that fear that thing just happen
Yeah you all you want you always have it
So
I'm just
I'm a simple guy
What I appreciate in life in the things that make me happy
Tend not to have
To do with with the money itself
More importantly
It's
Have an ability
Need to live a life
If that I can wake up every morning doing what I love
Nothing's more important
Timmy Turner
You never went to
College
You don't have an MBA you don't have
An advanced degree the
Being
I think to Harvard Business School case studies about you and Lady Gaga which isn't that great irony but
Geography like
You didn't belong
That you weren't
I don't know that like you are around
People who had credentials and
Made you feeling
Intimidated
Yeah
At time
He's right you know in
If I had a v
Grade teacher
Your name is more
And I was always the littlest guy in the class you know you take this
The school pictures are you get in line
The go to lunch in the hallway I was always first in line cuz I was
The smallest guy
But she used to call me the big guy
And she made me feel like I was six foot five
And like she get it was something that she
She did psychological
Did that like really really made me
I feel
Not only did I belong
But that I was special
So you know sometimes I'll go into rooms
Where
It's
This person has a lot more
Experience that me that much smarter
Denying
But I know what I know
And
I think I bring
A very bringing unique point of view to the
You know gif
With different
Experiences
And I'm
Confident in that in
That point of view
Elsa singing with the story you told about your mom earlier and
And she must be so amazed at
And how turned out
Can you meet you Dropout of school she was super disappointed
And
Look where you are today
United she she passed away
3 years ago
And yeah
She was 60
3 years old when she died
And she spent the last three years
With me and my family
But I remember
Man
We were at an award show they were giving me some award
Forney Chief Montano in the music industry
And
She she was sick
She was my date to the show
And we saw Berry Gordy
She said that's you
Do you like Oprah
Are you bring out the tears
Troy Carter founder of atom Factory
By the way Lady Gaga was not the only star they managed over the last several years the roster is included
John Legend Priyanka Chopra Meghan Trainor and John Mayer
Sing when he was a teenager it was probably a good one because too too many song where's the party the
Who played earlier it's been on YouTube for 10 years and it only has 13 thousand views
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
Thanks to one of our sponsors Stonyfield organic kids
Stonyfield organic yogurt snacks are perfect for on-the-go
Cups pouches smoothies and tubes
Ready for a delicious organic snack
Visit Stonyfield.com NPR
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that and today we're going to update a story we ran
Last year this comes from Robin Kerber who works for a bank in New York problem that has
Nothing to do with her day job gets super frustrated looking for parking
If I'm driving if I'm a passenger in a car annoying things
Car in a big city people fight with their spouses trying to find a parking space
Baden-Baden drive there fast enough so it's really a source of
Pension we about four years ago Robin noticed that her dad had come up with cut the low-tech solution
Gentoo the city's parking problem
Key devices system where he would put a piece of paper on his car window with a :-) if you
You were sleeping the next morning and drivers in his neighborhood began to look out for his car if they saw the :-)
Of course when Robin says I thought to myself there should be enough for this and how many
Very same thing but Robin actually did something she got a friend to help her do the coding and then she met
Need an app that allows drivers to share information about parking spaces we have a find a spot off
Option and Hostess pot option so if you are looking to find a spot you could click that button and it would search
Search for all the spots within your vicinity and it would show you the 20 closest spots
You want to snag you get the make and model of the car that the leaving and then you navigate to your face and they
We are actually tracking you on GPS so you know if the person is on time you could chat with them a nice person
You have to pay if it was successful or not course for the app to really work Robin needed hundreds actually
Visions of New York City drivers to download it and start sharing this basis soap to get the word out
The music video no I'm not trying to be rude but let me get that far from you I wish we had a bad way
Good spots go away
That's why I'm always okay so. Is my cousin Brad Meyer
And my whole family
Either staying in it or dance Bennett video did not exactly go viral but
Robin keeps pushing she put flyers on thousands of cars all over New York City
Chase after me when I'm handing them Flyers asking for more flyers to just her friends that live in neighborhood
They they love this and that enthusiasm is what keeps me
Pushing forward
Robin called her a par car that spelled
T a r k a r r
And since you launched in 2016 she signed up more than 16 in New York City
She's also hoping to launch Park are on a few college campuses this summer
It's still a side hustle though she's keeping her day job at the bank and if you want to tell us your stories go to build
Npr.org we love hearing from you of a things your building and thanks so much for listening to
The show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also subscribe to show at Apple podcasts or wherever you get your podcasts and why
Are you there give us a review you can also write us that HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send it to
Tweet at how I built this was produced this week that run teen Arab Louis who also composed the music
Thanks also to Newark could see immigrants and Mexican food and Jeff Rogers AR intern is JC Howard
A guy Roz even listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers with mobile-friendly email
Email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week