Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offers premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Just a quick note about this episode about a year ago does actually a
Free Tuff story to squeeze into a single
Podcast because
It's really
Two stories to Amazing Stories
And we didn't want to cut anything out so
Week
He didn't and we let it go a little longer than usual
Which I think
You will enjoy
We started out essentially designing this loaf game 4
Working things out of wood and painted soda look like plastic that was really would
Our idea was to take it to the Toy Show in New York
Amazing world we sold 0
Ramen
It's how I built this a show of activators entrepreneurs idealist stories behind them
Gyros
Hello in Bushnell took his love arcade game
Shape the childhood of millions of Americans
If you grew up in the US in the 1980s
Then you were probably playing a little bit of
Best when your birthday rolled around
Maybe you celebrated you know
Like this
Very iconic sound Chuck E cheese the pizza joint with
The games that
You distracted for hours
And an Atari video game which could
Frankly distract you for a lot longer
These bread
Incredible
Is it both of these childhood experiences
Who created by the same
Persaman scene guy by Nolan Bushnell
He found it at re Justice
Few years out of college and he started Chuck-E-Cheese just a few years after that
Inferno 1
Began when he was
The kid in Utah in the 1950s
A very simple lesson about business
The dinner one night Mom said boy we've got so many strawberries
We're not going to be able to eat them
Maybe we will give them away
I didn't think that much about it the next day I happened to go to the
Grocery store
And I saw that in the store in the grocery store
They were selling strawberries
50 Cent
The basket
I looked at
I said
That's what the market
So
Went home
Found all the
Xtrill basket
Were around
Went out picked a bunch
Strawberries and went up and down
Selling
The strawberries
For Discount offer
What the
Grocery store
And I sold
An hour I mean I don't even think I made it all the way to the end of the block
And all of a sudden I had more money
Then I would make an allowance
And mowing lawns 4-year nice
Young entrepreneur
And I read that like later on when you were in college
You worked at
That's correct
I started out
Actually on the Midway
Selling balls to knock down Milk Milk Bar
Man guessing
People's ages weights
Pandora
And jumping Kearney
Like like shouting at people like come on down
You got it then
And
I found out that I was kind of
Kind of good at it
How do you get into arcade games at start
The carnival
Yes
That was sort of
Where I
Got it.
Because you end up
What people don't realize how much
Coin-operated
It's actually quite surprising
And so
When you look at
Each of the coin operated games
It's a little bit
Typically you go into the
Joe's Cafe and say can I put my machine in your location
Then I'll split the income
These location
This would very often do 100 to 200.
Hours a week at that time
Pinball machines there were mechanical games
But yeah no video games
Then I was working
Summers at the amusement park Winters
Pursuing an engineering degree
At the University
And wow
One day I saw
Steve Russell spacewar
What's that
A guy named Steve Russell at
Am I
Program to this game called
Space War
And
I was mesmerized
More context
My brother says I got to show you something that will knock
Pieces
Meet me at 1 at the Merrill engineering
It's 1 in the afternoon on the snow
Show up during building
And there was space worm he handed me a box that had four buttons on the top
Rotate left rotate right fire and hyperspace
Those were the controls
And we played
Until literally
5 more
And I thought
Wow
If I could put this game in my arcade
It would make money
But then you divide a $0.25
Play into a
Half a million-dollar
Computer in the math.
But I did think to myself maybe someday
The cost will come down
And this would be cool
So you graduate college I get some
Like the late 60s
68-69
And and what did you do did you you're in Utah did you start a business or did you decide to
Where did you go
My wife's sister lived in Silicon Valley
And
I was a little bit of an anarchist
At that time
Call Mia
Lapsed Mormon or failed Mormon or whatever
And I kind of wanted to get out of Utah and see the world
And so California seems like
Cool place to
Go
So
That Thanksgiving we drove to California stayed with
My wife's sister
And I paper the street with Swiss my resume
And got a job at Ampex
Nmx was a
Teeth whitening
Electrical
They invented the video tape machine
And instant replay
I worked there for 2 years
But about
18 months in
I discovered
Aiken
Computer that looked like it was fast
To do a video
So you're thinking
Let me start something
It started out a little bit as a research project and then I said yeah
I'm going to start something and in fact it was almost prescient that when I was
Driving down the Sierras towards Silicon Valley I told my wife I said you know in 2 years I'm going
Start my own company
I just knew that was kind of on my trajectory I didn't know if that time
It's going to be a video game
I just thought I'd do it you know and in the back of my mind and I always kind of had this entrepreneurial
I think I've always had it since 8
Hardest computer company dislike game company
My office mate was a guy named Ted Dabney this was an Ampex and I said I'm just started company
Formal partnership we had this computer and the computer was
Mind-numbingly slow and
In order to make the economics work the computer cost like 5,000 operator games at the time
I needed to be less than $1,500 so the way I was going to do it as I was going to die
Timeshare
That one computer across three
Screams with three coin slots when I felt that I could get
$1,500 that way you were trying to design basically what would become an arcade machine like
A giant machine would be installed somewhere
People put in a quarter and they could play a game
Map of space war and where did you install this Arcadian where was it
We put it in a bar
Call the Dutch Goose it was in Menlo Park it was right next to Stanford University
The game was a Smash Hit at the Dutch Goose I license the game to a company
Call nutty Associates
And
Realize that it did really well on college campuses so
I mean it sold a couple of million dollars in
Units
Which was
Tumi
A big hit
But to the industry was kind of a mediocre
QWOP
But
I had a 5% royalty and so that was a
You know
$100,000
Massman
Put this in context
I came to work at Ampex for $825 a month is
Associate engineer
How did you fund
The company from the beginning what did you have to go to outside mess
Asking for money
No
This was also
At the time when venture capital
Was just getting started
And so
Ted put in $250 I put in $250
And that's all the money that went in
Wow 500 bucks
Start Atari
I'm in your first game was
Was a flop so how did you guys
How'd you guys go on to
To do the next thing
Well
Then came
Alicorn which was our
First
Technical employee
Cuz we were growing and we needed
Port Allen
And I gave him a
Simplest game
I could think of
Which was a ping pong table
When you think you're going to be in the video coin-operated video game
You write down every sport you can think of every constructs
In ping pong was one of them
And he went off
And he basically had
I think working at
More two weeks
It was
Really
Quick
And we are talking about what of course became pong
Which was just like two lines with a ball bouncing around a screen between those lives
Correct
And
It turned out
I thought it was going to be a throwaway
Yeah there was just a training
And it just
Turned out to be
Fun we were staying
After work.
Play the damn game
And then I get the idea
Maybe Valley wants this game
Ballyhoo who's also a big coin operated
Player
Out of Chicago
Getting the airplane fly to Chicago I have a little more cups that I can
Affordable yet
And I show it to them
And they don't like it
It's a two player game
And coin-operated world
Doesn't allow
For two player game if there's not a one player
At that time
That was sort of
Written in stone somewhere
Worlds
Kind of dejected
On my way to get on the airplane to come back California
I get a call from you
Who is the engine
And they had a service call
Cuz they had put a basic pong game in a cabinet
And put it in a bar
And the game
Became so popular that it filled up
The coin box lid couldn't take any more quarters
So I think myself
Maybe I don't want Valley to have them
Because the math were so outstanding
Little Machines could literally pay for themselves
I mean the game was earning
Almost $300 a week
Wow
And the total cost
That we had
Was about to
So you're thinking maybe we should just message me the machines and lens licensing Marcel
Exact
So is that what you did
So that's exactly what
Did I looked at all the cash we had
And we have enough cash to build
Like 12 units
You know the minute I got off the airplane
Submitted the
The order for the parts
And we were off to the race
I get on the phone
I have
Literally orders coming in
All over the nation
Of course I'm a week we think about pain today and it's 2
Basic
Yeah rudimentary
Revolutionary
Absolutely
Put it in context
People would come to me and say
How does the TV station know that I turn the knob
Nn
Clearly they're construct was it if there's something on the TV screen that came from Studio someone
And so that was kind of the
Constructs
We were dealing with
But
There's actually some very
Interesting psychology
Get back on it
And one of the reasons that I think Pawn
With such a massive success
Is the
Fed into the narrative
Of what was going on
Time
You know just after the summer of love the hippie movement
Women's Liberation was
Restarting to rear its head
And
Pain by its structure
Made it
Ladies choice
Because it
Team very acceptable for a woman to
Tampa guy
Sitting at the bar
On the shoulder and say I want to play Pong would you like to play All by
Who knew Palms ruffle in the history of women's Liberation exactly
Nolan worth more companies just calling you or
Calling you said we wanted machine
That was
And so
Our big problem then is we have no Factory we had no systems we had no procedures we have no employees
I mean we had there were four of us
And you guys are all in your like mid-to-late twenties
And in fact I think was 23 he just he just graduated from Berkeley
And we had a thousand square foot roll up which we thought was huge for the six
This is in what town is it
This was in Santa Clara California then we found out that we had a real problem
We could build these games literally into days like literally my hand with lutein nada.
But we had neglected to buy shipping cartons
We couldn't ship them on cam carrier
And so to solve that problem we bought an old furniture truck and started making
Deliveries without cartons to Los Angeles
But usually driving down the 101 or something
Yeah but
Slowly we were able to get procedures in place we were able to
Get systems
And how we Finance
The company was we would sell for cash
The machine
We had 30 day terms
Most of our parts we had 68 terms so we can get the cash
Literally 60 days before we had to pay for the parts
You how many of these
Arcade
Machines
Mm
Only if which
Atari only did about 35000
We got
Massively copy
But you couldn't you couldn't prevent these companies from basically stealing your idea and copying you
I didn't have patents yet it was on those days pants were just
Swoboda
China
So there was no so basically you could do nothing
Nothing
And copy
We knew we didn't have sufficient to manufacture
We knew we didn't have as much money
We knew we didn't have as good a relationship
With the distributor chain
That the competitors that have been dealing with them
For 20 years
And so
I felt
My only tool
Was innovation
An understanding of the technology cuz
Copying the technology Allen and creating the tick
Different
So you were still not really proper
Just kind of breaking even
Cash was always our limitation
And I tried to get
No investors but everybody thought
What kind of flaky
Who's going to pay for this thing
Exactly how did you
Even come up with the idea that maybe
We should sell this.
People and they could do it at home
One day we figured out
Is there was a new semiconductor
Technology called in Channel MOS and
These chips once they were designed you could buy him for five bucks
It occurred to us that we could put pong on a sink
Blue Chip
And hit a price point that would
Sell to the consumer
And how did you even begin to think of
Ways to discuss what you're talking about
Like
Building a cabinet for a
A giant
Jade system like how do you shrink that down into something else
Well once you had it on a single chip
Then it was just a matter of putting two knobs on a piece of
Plastic
We started out essentially designing this loaf
Game looking thing
Atwood
The painting it's a little look like plastic but it was really would
Our idea was to take it to the Toy Show in New York
Disappointed to a convention in like but 7475
And you show where people like this is amazing world
And it was a great demo and everything
But we didn't know
Is it the toy business at that point in time
Did not sell anything
That was more than 35.
And how much were you
You selling this
Atari console
Which in 1935
It was a lot
And so we thought
Spent all this money to get
Think developed
Our neighbors wanted
And they were happy to
Spend 70
Did you leave that Toy Show feeling
Dejectedly
Who's abject failure must have been pretty
Depressed Sceptre Pinellas money this thing
You don't
I'm not easily depressed
But I'm very easily challenge
And I said you know
There's something not right here
We just haven't found the right guy
What do you mean you haven't found
The right distribution Channel
So basically you're thinking these guys are wrong I know this is going to work at exactly
Exactly like I said these guys
Search for missing a wonderful opportunity
And so we were thinking
RadioShack of sinking
TV dealerships
I was thinking all kinds of stuff
And then
My head of sales
Thought about
Sears
Sporting Goods
And
The previous year
Sears Sporting Goods really focuses on
The inclement weather family room
And they sell pool tables
And ping pong tables
Things like that
The year before they had
Made
The consumer
Pinball machine
For $200
And they sold out
So
My sales guy said maybe these guy
Kaiser so he calls up the buyer at Sears for
It's a song that's kind of interesting
The next day
He was honored
And they were based in Chicago at the time
They were based in
Chicago Sears buyer comes to
Find out
Comes and says I want to see what
Your
Exactly
And that we actually had to scramble cuz we didn't realize he was coming he didn't say am showing up
They just showed up
And so we were in the conference room after that he says okay I think we're going to
Do that how many can you build
We didn't have a
Because we were
We're building coin-operated games
Where a big run with 5000
We kind of do a little mice
And so we did a huddle outside
I had my
It's so not wanting to be sole source
I said we can do about 7
You go back to the Sears guy and say we could do 75000 after your own guy tells you
Okay yeah
Okay
He give us an order 450
And
He want some delivery by Christmas fight you know october-november got basically 6 months to
How to build a factory
Train the personnel
To sort out the technology
None of which we done before so is anybody in Atari freaking out at this point
Everybody has
Ellen Bushnell founder of Atari when we come back
After the Freak Out
The real work begins plus a side hustle that track together pizza games Penndel
You're listening to how I built this NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace allows small businesses to design and build
Their own website
Using customizable Leo
Yes and features including e-commerce functionality and mobile added
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization to help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR guy Raz
It's 1975 Nolan and his Partners have gotten a huge order from Sears to make a
Consumer version of Pawn
Incident need to figure out how to build a manufacturing chain
Virtually
Overnight
We sit down
And we say okay if we were to build a hundred fifty
How would we do it
And then
The big question
How much money are we going to make
After we spend all this money on Factory and we realize
It's how I call it
The series Bayern say I ate do this to you
I'm going to
The price what was the price that he wanted
We were quoting
The retail price of 59 and we decided that we needed an extra twenty bucks per year
And he said
That's okay I can do that
Then I went through the math and there was no way
That I hadn't
Put in the conveyor belts to rent the ex
Sorry
Buy the parts and I calling them play Skillet
I really appreciate the order but I said I can't find this this is so don't worry
Only reduce you to seers bank
And so Sears Bank set up a Bonded Warehouse at the end of the conveyor line
So as soon as
Babe consumer pong dropped off the assembly line they would Advance us
80% of the contract price with Siri
Maybe Atari console that your building only play pain
And did you get it to them in time under 50000 consoles by Christmas
We did
In fact I think that year we sold almost a hundred eighty thousand they took them all
Wow
I mean at this point
Youku
I guess you guys aren't Benfica home
Computer game
Exactly
And then how did you go from
Making one console to play one game to 8
AKA balika home video game system
Well we realized at that time
When we were doing the
One game $70
That this was an unsustainable
Business
An end
Then
Magical thing app
A Semiconductor Company in Silicon Valley
We came up with the
Microprocessor
They were willing to sell a spray dollars and all of a sudden your eyes were opened
And we said
We can do
Vaughn women are
Picture program based put cartridges with ROMs in it
And we can have a program
That microchip allowed you guys to basic create a cartridge system that week
What's the steam turn out right exactly
You know it was just a magic
Time for technology
Silicon Valley
Time
You were as likely to learn about a new technology standing on the sidelines
Of your kids little league team
As you were
At any other time
In several times
I'd be talking about a technical problem we were having with
One of the other parents
Oh yeah
We had ship like that in
Development
Would you like a prototype it's not going to be really on the market for 6
6 months and I take
Yeah we we don't need production quantities for 6
You're not going to get that if you're
A technology
Company in in Oshkosh
Where I mean were there many companies
In Silicon Valley the time that we're focusing on
Entertainment
I can't think of another one
We kind of always felt like we were the sleazy
Company who
Focusing on fun instead of all this
How many more
Megabytes on a hard drive and it would help the serious companies were they
The devil they look down on you
We like
AR
Rebel status
And we were Rebel in several ways first of all we were all young
I was the youngest CEO in
People didn't know
What to think about a CEO in their twenties then we that was just off the radar
And I actually feel like I paved the way for Gates and jobs and some of the
Idea that you can be young and still a serious businessman
We
Got known as a real party culture because instead of bonuses since all our employees
Word in the early twenties
We'd have a beer bust on the back dock
And you get anal
$100 for the pizza into kegs and you had a party and that was totally under
And of course we have a game room we have ping pong tables stuff that Silicon Valley kind of thinks is
Do you record and necessary now yeah it was very very different and then
Have a dress code and we didn't have time clocks we had this attitude that everybody
What they needed to do and
They were adults they could wear what they want and they could come and go when they want and we weren't Big Brother
And so we try to make this meritocracy
In which outcome
Was the only thing we counted
Is a young CEO
I think you did a good job where you
You know where you
Are you a good manager of people at the time
So so
I think I was a good manager of people I think that
I always had a little bit of an inferiority
Plex in that
Because of my age
I felt a little bit like a
Poser
Which was okay with me on some level because of my Carnival background
But at the same time
I always felt
That I didn't know what the hell I was doing
And what I didn't realize has the most big companies don't know what the hell do you mean
I wasn't mature enough to understand that all companies are somewhat screwed up
Unnu clearly he like had an eye for you clearly had an eye for hiring instant people mean
And I think anyone knows a little of the story
Steve Jobs and Steve Wozniak
Work for you
Steve Jobs work for me and
He was a technician
In quality control
He was really good at
I can remember him coming insane
Only if you allow these kinds of solder joints you're going to have
Failures in the field
Did you already tell like that
Yeah we think of him as a sort Mercurial kind of
Impetuous leader was he like that even as a
20-something kid
He was opinionated but he was never wrong
In his opinion
You didn't have to worry if you empowered Steve
Do something
It happen
I mean Steve had one speed
It was
Full on
And so
He got the the Apple going and he came to me and says I want to start this company
And I'm going to be leaving
Do you want to be my first investor and I'll give you a third as a company
For $50,000 and you said of course
Yeah I did not say that
I've regretted it but you know anyway
It was fun times
Exotic matter
Definition of matter
It would have ruined my life would have made you
Totally insufferable
Yeah and I was already insufferable
So thank goodness you did not take that deal
Exactly so all right so you're running Atari
Doing really well
And then what do you decide to sell it like
I guess right
So I felt that we had to take the company public trays
15 million dollars
Racines pulp right now but that was all the money in the world to us
Time
And
The market Hiccup and they said there's just no way we're going to do it and I love 70's right
This was the summer summer of 76
And all the sudden we had Christmas coming and I knew I didn't have enough money
Even with Sears to be able to get this
New
Massive
Wonderful
Product into
The marketplace
This is that the Atari console with the
What cartridges right
Yes that's correct
So without
Inability to
Do that I said maybe it's time to get a corporate partner and so I started.
Driving for dollars from corporate partner Warner Communications showed up and said will not
Finally put up the money but we'd like to buy you and will pay you money and will put money into the
Company and you will get this big royalty stream and we understand creatives
We're going to link arms March into the sunset how much are they offering you 28 million
Which is why I was born boy from Utah
Music by a Learjet in those days for a million dollars
Took the money
And so what happened so so you continue to work for Atari at that point
That's a lie was not as rigorous
As I got
I started started taking care of my personal life
Instead of my business life
And I found that the word a lot of decisions that were being made that were really
Really pretty toxic
Decisions about where to take the company
Yeah and slowly we
Brought in a president of consumer
Who had all the hierarchy
No Reserve
Taxi places
Executive dining rooms and all the things
That were anathema to me
Yeah you're going from keg parties on your loading dock to an executive dining room
Yeah and I just thought that was so
Wrong on so many levels
I don't think you need that arbitrarily create an us-versus-them mentality in your company
You know and one of the things that happens when your own by New York company
They think that you're laid back Style
Is that you're not working so hard and they think the people that come in at 10 should be fired
And so the bottom of a sudden there was this Clash of cultures that got to be really ugly and old
They they got tired of me and I got tired of them and
Ike was fired wow how long does it take between time they bite you in the time that you were ousted how long was it
About 20 months
Wow that must have been a tough. For you
Actually not
I kind of you business
Little bit like the game of chess you play the game you play hard sometimes you win some
Can you set up the pieces and you blew it again and you don't have eggs oh my God
Watch the game of chess what am I going to do what was me and what that allows you to do
Is to view a little bit of sand outside or from yourself things that happened to you
So when something doesn't work out that well you can say G that was
Horrible but it was an interesting experience
Okay let me just stop you're beside because
This episode and here I would say okay that's Nolan Bushnell Visionary 5 of the tari
We are now
The second company you founded which is Chuck-E-Cheese
How did that happen how did how do you even come up with this concept
Well the math
Is very simple
Before I sold Warner
We were selling games these are coin-operated
We were selling them for about 1500.
During your life
I'm in coin drop
Play turn 30
So it didn't take rocket science
How to say I'm on the wrong side
I need to be
The operating
He seems to have been
But I didn't want to compete with the guys I was selling to
So I decided I had to create my own location
I thought to myself
When people going to come to this freestanding arcade
And I decided that
Adding food would be
A benefit B
Because in families could come
And that
Indicated pizza because there was wait time
And that would be good gameplay
When we was still mulling this whole concept
Ground
I went to Disneyland and went to the tiki room
Oh yeah and I said
Do this my guys can make these little
Creatures
Then I
Realized that I really
Wanted to have
The Branded mascot
And that I wanted it
B
The longer-form entertainment
I figured
Kids are going to be wanting to play the games parents are going to be bored the more I can entertain them unless they're getting you
Buggy the kids to leave so I said let's do some animated skits
The whole idea was to roll this out make it seamless not have labor costs just make it happen
So anyway I went to a amusement tradeshow bought a costume
Look up costume that they live like a human. Your guys are just
Turn into an animated robot exactly the famous Chuck-E-Cheese
Was a rat's right what restaurant is going to pick a rat as their mascot and think that's going to work
Will understand when I bought the costume I thought I was buying a Coyote Ugly
The code the code name was coyote Pizza in my guys I said how's the coyote coming in
What kind of costume I sent you
Oh you mean the rap so all of a sudden we had a problem so I said okay
Will be coyote pizza anymore it's going to be you regrets Pizza Rick rats Pizza that was going to be
Who was going to eat pizza place called Rick rats pizza that's exactly what
They said there's no way for snow that's the stupidest idea
They said we couldn't even know they'd be on the garden we wouldn't get our help license
And I said okay you name it I don't care but it has to be a happy name right and so they came back also
The next week they said we've got the name it's a three smile name
Chuck-E-Cheese
So hot so what happened you you opened up your first location in Silicon Valley
Yeah it was it was basically in San Jose
We took over
A old Dean Witter office and it was like
5000 squared
That was huge
Compared to Pizza
We knew the day we open
That we made
Huge mistake
Wow many was that popular
Massive
How many lines out the door
On a Monday when your customers little kids who who's coming
Everybody but then we sold the company and Warner didn't want to be in the restaurant business
You you sold at rue21 or Chuck-E-Cheese with was kind of hard because you
Who created why you're there so
For you to keep Chuck-E-Cheese you had to buy it back from them
Half a million dollars 500000 bucks to buy Chuck-E-Cheese
Open sports store was Cash 4 and 1/2 million dollars
They let me pay $100,000 for 5 years and that was maybe the deal of a lifetime
I had this business that was positive cash flow day 1
Well I was still chairman of Atari
And I I had a team of people that have been working on and I brought them on my payroll
And we immediately expanded to the second store this one was 25,000 worth
And I was having more fun
Chuck-E-Cheese
Then I was having Charlie Charlie was getting political
So when
We decided to part ways
Excited I could
Focus on my time on
Chuck-E-Cheese and I was going to happy about
Yeah I'm pretty liberating to work on this thing because you know you you were like synonym for excited about
You know sometimes
I feel that
Inadvertence
Shines on
Because
I had thought about French
Dykema
I want a franchise
Okay
And we started franchise
And so the franchise business was hugely
So how many Chuck-E-Cheese locations did you
Eventually
Franchise
I sold the company when we were about 280 stores
And 1/2 Warframe
It's time so we build battle
And franchise
What what
Opposite of mistakes do you think you made
That you learn from
ATS trucking
I think that I didn't understand
The nature
Entertain
Now that sounds funny
Amusement park and all that
But entertainment is
Fairy
Fragile
It's driven on
Novelty
And so
When we would first open
A unit
People would come
From all around because it was Mall
So there was sort of a half life
Shein
In which you say G you know this is St Louis looks to me like I need
Amor Chuck-E-Cheeses
When in fact what you were seeing is this novelty bonus
And that
People in normal life
Didn't really want to come to Chuck-E-Cheese
Three times a month
They wanted to come to Chuck-E-Cheese
Every other month
We got over bill because
We got another false positive
What was the first pasta
That you
Could pack the place
365 days a year
In a population
Which couldn't
It's it's amazing because
Did you
Built these two iconic companies
How many server many many people in America
Define The Contours of their childhood
And you can on 202 start
But at least a dozen other companies
Some of what you can speak
Killer failures and spectacular successes you've had
You have this amazing range of experiences on on both ends
I guess
I just wonder what I mean I'm sure the successes were were incredibly satisfying
Robbie's reasons but
In some ways you think the failures were
Or should have more interesting or
Kill time for you learned more about
Lifan about you in about
Business
There is no question
That
A good failure
Is good for your soul
There is nothing worse
Then feeling like
You are
Invincible and Reed
Cool
Entitled
Being entitled
Probably
Ugliest thing
A person can be
Because all of a sudden
It's not
What you do
It's who you are
And
People who rely on who they are
Opposed to what they
They do become
Very
Banal
How long does it take you to
To become Who You Are
To realize that
I hope that I'm not there yet
I want
To stay on the steep
Part of the learning curve
In fact I've even
Docker methodology
IAAI
Force myself
Do something totally outside my comfort zone if
Here
And I write down
11 things that I think I could accomplish in a year
That are
Outside my comfort zone
And then I
Myxoma put a number on them
Through paradise and I have to in that year
Do
What the dice tell me
And I discovered
Funny thing
Maybe it's just me but I think it's a generalized principal
But when you do different
Things you're happier
That this process of
Of expiration
And
Discovery
And of
Winnie wing
Out
The game and the medical
Is very satisfied
If you were
Able to go back to like I mean now you are a
Elder Statesman of the tech world you're in your seventies and
If you could go back to
To Nolan Bushnell in the Olay
70 years earlier
Ladies and say
Hey you know I want to give you some advice
What would you tell yourself
Well that's a real hard-on
Cuz
Some of the bad decisions I've made
I'm not sure that I would like my wife
To not have had
And I'm not sure
That
If
I were to give myself advice
And change that trajectory
I would end up
I am right
And I like
Tell me about what you're working on now
Well then I'll have to kill you
Nolan Bushnell
Is the founder of Atari and the Chuck-E-Cheese in exactly working on some pretty cool stuff right now
A company called brainrush would make software designed to help students learn School subjects
8 to 10 X Factor
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
The things your building
First Equity thanks to one of our sponsors swell investing
An impact investing platform that I
Identified high-growth companies solving today's
Biggest
Environmental and social challenge
Claim your $50 bonus
Swell investing.com
Built
Hey thanks so much for sticking around
I know for how you built that and say we're up to the story that we ran about a year ago this one is from
Paul Tucker who's worked in the beverage business in Southern California for over 20 years
And that entire time he's been making craft beer in his kitchen
5-minute homebrewer for
20 years and pretty quickly realized that the magic ingredient in craft beer is the Hops
Start a brew with hops in one day I had some left over and it just hit me that option
To be enjoyed on more occasions and how come it's only in craft beer
Bacon Maybe
But hops
Who knew it's a very subtle flavor wheezing and really pairs well with food and you know
The more I looked at it the more I said wow
This could be a whole new category but instead of coming up with another artisanal chocolate bar
Hops infused cheese
Pyside
What about a new drink
Maybe even a drink with no alcohol
As much as I love craft beer you can't drink it on all occasions
So yeah I started experimenting and probably about a year of research and
Many failures and trying different varieties came up with something that I thought was just
Phenomenal with Paul came up with has no barley no-yeast no fermentation of alcohol
And best of all
No calories
Paul basically made up Pops flavors
Sparkling water
And I think when people think of hops
They think of
Better but you know there are over a hundred varieties of hops
And lobster we use these Aroma hot
Add
Citrus scent Pine flavor is grapefruit it's really complex
And what I consider the
The spice for the magic ingredient
So Paul took his creation to a beer festival in San Francisco and
The first he was a little nervous about what
Beer drinkers would think
But when people came up and tasted it
People are like wow
Yeah this is
Legit the flavor is really interesting and refreshing and
That's what I knew that
It's not just me
Don't think about this for a moment
Sparkling water is super hot right now
Just ask the company that makes Lacroix and
It's no secret that craft beers huge
How to figure putting together
And he's managed to get his drink
Into a few small retailers in restaurants
That he's not making a profit yet but this year
He's expecting sales
And if I can get it to the point where
A big company would like to pick this up and distributed worldwide then you know I would feel
Fantastic about that
When we last spoke to Paul
He'd sold less than $100,000 worth of hot water but he says within the past year his sales
Went up 6 times and the company is still not profitable Paul is hiring his first employ
This year if you want to know more about Paul's company h2ops visit
Our Facebook page and if you want tell us your story about the things your building go to build. NPR
Oryx that's build with a d that npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week
If you want to find that Maureen good how I built this. Npr.org you can also write to us at HIV
BT at npr.org our shows produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis also composed the music
Thanks also to Diva Grant Michigan port and Jeff Rogers AR intern is nor could see
Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.