This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this kiss
Who understands every small business is uni
And tailors its policies to your business is very specific need
Get a quote or purchase a policy
At h i s c o x.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Hey it's guy here
So we've been hearing from a lot of you
Until we all found out the tragic news
About
Kate Spade
And her husband Andy
Kantar New York Studios last year and they sat down for what would become one of my
Favorite all-time episodes of How I built this
They were
Both so likeable and in every way they were self-effacing and also self-deprecating
The bird kind
Smart
And most importantly they were generous they were
Generous with
The reflections and generous with the lessons they learned
All along the way
So
Is a small tribute to Kate we decided to repost this interview
To her voice and her laughter and her warm
And get a sense
The kind of person
She was
We were still not making any money nobody was making a salary we were Andy was funding everything
I didn't leave you to shut it down I said it's
And in all of our savings at that point we still weren't seeing you know progression that was good
Next year in the near future so we thought we had a good run at it we think we've had it
From NPR how I built this
Show the innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they go
The person behind the brand is Kate Spade
Grew up as Kate Brosnahan
In Kansas City Missouri
Then she always loved fashion but
Never plan to work inside
She wanted to be a journalist
So in the early 1980s
She went off to study journalism
At Arizona State University
And that
Kate met her future husband
Andy Spade
We work together at a clothing store and I was on when inside he was on the men's side and
One day his car broke down and he asked me for a ride home then we really started off
Really great friends the car continue to break down so relationship along
And the rest of the story well 30 plus years later they're still together
Kate graduated from college first Andy was a few credits short so she decided to backpack around
Europe by yourself traveled around and came back to New York and
Brentwood temp agency because I desperately needed
Some some money
Arizona
To be with Andy but that's where my ticket
It started and ended in New York
Got enough money to get back so I needed a job in order to do that so I started at a temp
Place I was typing and I said I'm I don't think this is going to work out
And then she called the next day and said
Can you get ready right now caught in a skulls and they have a job in fashion Department
So they ended up hiring me they didn't want to because I couldn't type
My boss
That wasn't she's great and I don't need her striped lot
If we were doing fashion shoots and styling so
It wasn't is what were you doing
Well I started as an assistant so I was
Tying
Model shoes
On a photoshoot because they couldn't bend over their clothes
That are getting hair stylist
Snickers
I'm telling you whatever I irons
Carry bags
It was a lot of work
Say that
Did you were you were back
In Tempe at Arizona State University
I was back in Tempe I was struggling with a few required courses
I think I had more
Credits the necessary but there were a few that I couldn't get through
But I did start an advertising age
And see my senior year in college
And so I
I started
Trading ads for
Guarding food
Tie-dye go to a restaurant for example and I
I bring in the ad that they had running in the local paper
And I would show it to them and say I think I can do better if I come back and show you a
A better version of this
Will you either pay me in food or give me a few hundred dollars
I had like 10 takers
So I ended up with 10 accounts
How many things are going well
And Kate were you still planning to head
Back to Arizona
At that point yes
And I kept saying no I'm coming back
I will only stay here for
Woofers photos
Can I move to to sex
I said I have to be honest
I kind of like my job
I loved it and I love the pain of the past pay stub
New York and San Leandro
I loved it
Wish you got a job offer for $14,000 a year everything changed
Xi'an sting and that's what I say
I'm moving to New York
And you just figured
I'll find something
Yeah I figured I'd find something there I had a little portfolio
Of advertisements that I'd written and art directed
I thought I took that with me to New York and hopes
To finding a job
And what did you guys
Did you go out like move in together
We did
I I forwarded a little bit of money that I had
Advocate for security deposit on the cheap
Des Department chief
Defined
And
I remember arriving in
It's a call me from a pay phone on the corner
When you arrive
And all
Get out of the fire escape
So I called and I walk to 26 Renwick Street
And I looked up at
She was out of the fire escape she threw down a sock with a
Akita
It's easier to go down to the walk
I had
One warm coat
Suitcase
And a portfolio
Wow an integer but a KTM
I know you went to an all-girls
What high school does your parents of have
The problem with you living with Andy
They never really said much but
My mother
That's not please
She was not pleased with the doll bed
I mean I just kept saying it was a matter of Economics just being practical
Did you actually land a job in advertising
I did I was interviewing and a lot of programs like y&r in Oglebay anime there
But my portfolio didn't reflect the kinds of accounts that they're working on cars and IBM
What is walking to Grand Central Station and a young man in a suit pulled me over I was carrying my portfolio
He said you do
And I said well I'm looking for a job as a copywriter he said you have a minute
Is it true that I'd love to look at your portfolio and we stopped in Grand Central Station he wouldn't be my portfolio and
He said I think I might have something
Sing for your recruiter
Did you happen to see me walking to Grand Central Station
He went through what he said meet me in my office tomorrow
2 did any set me on three or four interviews
What which which was an agency named bozell Jacob Canyon and Echo
Latest opening for someone to work on the Army National Guard and Merrill Lynch
And
He said I know you haven't
Had any experience on these
Types of businesses but I like your hotspot
Oh. I didn't know what it meant until I called someone
What does it mean when they say I'll meet you after you took a chance starting own business at the positive
Until I got that job
So okay so you guys are on your early 20s
You're living a New York Life
Tate you're working at
At Kearney.
Right at Mademoiselle magazine
Amazon magazines
Actually it was amazing
I mean it by Mom
Framed
When they put my name in the
Mass that she still hasn't praying
What did you start to do that
But it was first assistance
For the senior fashion editor
And
Then I was promoted to associate editor
And I was in charge of all the accessories
And
I did that for a couple years and they promoted me the senior fashion editor
And if there's one thing I did learn was
How to be very resourceful
And it came in very handy
We started our business because
I mean
It was do not come back to me with
No
I mean you
Figure it out I mean it would be we have to go on a shoot in
2 days and we need 8 tickets
Bahamas in
Figure out how to get us all there
I mean if we're all on different airplanes I don't care but get us there
Make it happen
So I guess it was
Wizard of the early 90s like maybe maybe 1991 when you decided to leave
Mademoiselle magazine
What was going on why did you decide to go
It's funny you know Angie and I were talking one night
And I just said
I was looking ahead and
So the fashion director is
That would be your next
Jump from being
Senior fashion editor
And
I don't really see myself wanting that
That job
So and I were out honestly to Mexican restaurant and
He just said
What about a handbag
You just don't start a handbag company
Resupply. How hard can it be
Okay really
Progressives words
What white handbags
Well she was in accessories editor and she collected
Your handbags for fashion shoots that was one of her key responsibilities
So she'd have to
Handbags from
Vintage stores
For Beach shoot straw bag she had a
My Personal Collection that was amazing and then she knew every handbag company in the market
And I thought you understood it better than anyone
What's missing in the market
What was missing
At the time things for very
Baxter too complicated
And I really love very simple kind of architectural shape
And I would wear these
Very simple shapes
None of which were
Famous designers and their names
Someone hurt today
Whose is that I'd say I don't know I bought it at a vintage store or it's a straw bag I got in Mexico
Soaked and they were all very square in C
Simple I thought
Xiaomi why can't we find something
Just clean and simple and modern
Okay so about the time
Vet that you want to quit you were thinking
Like I'm done with fashion magazines
Yes
And he was like
You know bags you know like why don't you try to do this
Design your own
Absolutely it actually said it
Flyquest I kind of
Already had in the back of my mind and
I remember the very beginnings
Stay I could have
Made an income while I was working on that since someone said to me
The truth is you would never have done it had you stayed
Because I would have been a scrap yours I mean that it was kind of been out do or die so
I think if I'd still been working I would have been like
A little bit more lackadaisical about it words
When you don't have an income, then you are doing whatever you can to make it happen
So how did you even start to
Design hammock me you had no
Background InDesign you didn't even know what to do when like once
So things and
Put rivets in at all that stuff it's funny I did not know and I did start
Taipei
Big sheets of white
Paper
And I would cut out
Tape honestly
The shape that I wanted a knife
Look at it and make it shorter smaller cut it
And I went to a pattern maker that I found in the back of women's wear daily
She advertises she made patterns
So I contacted her she worked out of her apartments and she was
Patient as could be with me
Because I didn't know anything and I remember being really embarrassed about that
That
I wasn't there
Student
From Parsons to RISD or
Fit that I really didn't know what I was doing
And I honestly started with paper then we'd make a sample out of any kind of fabric Muslim
And then
I kind of got the shape down and I had to find a manufacturer so I called me mister daily they connected me to
Shoe department that they really said we don't do that but someone in the fashion Department said oh it's so hard I know someone
And he had left himself this
Production guide to start his own business
So was this guy that you found was he was he a designer manufacturer so he
Did the production
And so I brought in my samples and
He was like okay why want some money up front and he really was very nervous that I wasn't going to pay him and
He took our tiny little production honestly which would be
10 bags of time you know
And how how long after
Like you
Assertive start to sketch out designs was this was this like
A few weeks later a month later what what did you
Were you working on this idea for a long time in your apartment
At least a year and you were freelancing
Knight Inn
Certain days a week
As a stylist
And
After getting the
Patterns made
The next
Big Challenge was finding someone who would sell us
Fabric and
Because we didn't have any experience none of the fabric houses would sell us anything other than
A hundred yards for exam
Play shape so we only needed probably
40 yards
30 Yanni 25
So I called
I looked in the Yellow Pages
And I looked up
Potato sack
That's
Is willing to sell to
Annette three different
No weights
And I needed the heaviest weight so that
Substantial enough
Bram.
That was actually our first collection
Made out of burlap made out of burlap
So what is the bags look like they were imagine like brown burlap
Kind of rectangular little bag
Yes absolutely with Raffia Fringe
And
Webbing handle and I found a wedding company also
In the Yellow Pages
I see you get this
You get these samples and then what new
How do you get
Why do you start with the first thing you do
You go to these
Accessory shows
Treacherous
Trade shows and you get to get accepted
And we did and
The question is
You get the worst spot because all the famous people end up in
Citizen in New York
This is the first
Trade show you went to debut the Kate Spade
Burlap
Bag yes
We honest-to-god brought in our own tables
Round chairs
Tiffany lamps
Apartment apartment are both turned into our part
Basically for the week
What are you guys nervous I mean were you like I don't know where that what you worried that maybe somebody from
Cut be a little embarrassed or
Somebody was going to call you out and say what are you doing who you guys were you where you get asked me out
I was I
Because the editors come by as well as the buyers
To the trade shows
And I really didn't tell my parents
Or my family about it
Or anyone for that matter
Because I thought if it doesn't work
I will be so
Embarrassed
Because everyone kept saying
Why would you have quit your job
You had insurance but you know who do you think you are I just knew my family with just
Oh you got a little hot-headed big headed there in New York and
Think you can start this company
So I kept it on the down-low intentionally didn't
They talked about it much too
Family
Because I think secretly both thought it would fail
How did people respond to the bag
It well
I remember crying because when I came home we hadn't even sold enough to cover the cost of the booth
And I started crying and Andy said both who did you get and I said
What we got
Barney's
And he said
Okay and I said
Fred Segal in Los Angeles news
Brahe to the news
Migas
Katie
To the best stores in America
Why are you crying I said I think we should shut it down
I'm very conservative and I said I do I have no interest in losing money
I said and we feel we've already spent
$4,000 and that that's it for me I'm not a gambler
So that's fair and he was like that
Keep going
And also have to get a great deal of credit
To the editor
At the time we were
Selling a lot but the editors
We're putting this in the magazine
A lot what was it about your bags that appeal to them
Attention
I did because it wasn't anything anyone was doing and everyone there's a fabric show in Paris premiere
Busy on the all the designers go to
Sometimes you can end up with the same
Material
Mine came out of the Yellow Pages chances are going to run into any people that have the same material
So we were doing something different which was really to our advantage
Two editors for like
Beautiful burlap bags
They thought they were
Beautiful tiny they thought they were interested and we did we got a lot of credits than that
That's when my mother first found out
And she was embarrassed and she called and said that you didn't
Tell me and my friend had to tell me I said
I know I don't know I don't want to make a big deal of this and
It's okay it's one credit that's not a business
How did you come up
How did you start as land on the name
Well that was an
Because we weren't I was not Kate Spade I was
Kate Brosnahan and
I kept coming up with these names
Kate
Space because we were 50-50 partners
And
Finally I just said okay and I'm inside love it
Kate Spade New York and I remember telling
To your point about
My Catholic parents I told my mom
Honestly she burst
In Flames she was like
But you're not keep say that I said I know but she's a
Oh now you'll never be Kate Spade now you've been jinxed it and why would you name it Kate Spade and I said
What's my first name his last name is like
Dolce & Gabbana what the hell is that
And I said I said it'll work we hope
In just a minute
Why after three years of making no money
Kate and Andy almost walked away from their little handbag company
I got rides near listening to how I built this
NPR
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
When Kate and Andy debut the original Kate Spade bag
They got orders from Barneys and
Fred Segal
And it was a big deal in the world of fashion
Even with those orders
It didn't mean Kate and Andy were suddenly flush with cash or living large in New York
Wasn't going to guarantee that the
Company was going to be successful in fact
Andy
He kept his full-time job in advertising
Beijing
The overhead yeah I'm basically the rent in the other expenses right we'll keep freelancing that started the company
And I just thought we were both 29 30 years old and
It's time to do it we don't have children
Let's not quit even if we
Lose everything
Kate can always go back to Fashion job
You know I can continue to work in advertising
And you guys are running the company
Look at your apartment
We'd move to a loft in Tribeca because we were in a small apartment then we move to Lafayette boxes
Honestly guy everywhere
To the point where are Loft
Bad was up the stairs we crawl up
The entire apartment was just to see if
Brown boxes that sounds
We were doing very well but yeah
It really was we were still
You were shipping out
Things from the apartment
Oh yes for
At least
Two and a half years
I know you would take the train
The Brooklyn to the factory
Pick up the box
Just take the back on the subway
In trash bag
Walk them up a 5 floor walk-up
And she was shipping and
Packing bags and doing everything and taking orders on the fax machine remember they come through in the middle of the night
With your better around Wherever I Go
Excited but the orders would not be that big because it was hard to
The people that time to cut once they started selling then you get bigger order so it was really
Very gradual I mean it was at least
3 years before we paid ourselves
Baby 15000
And we're still working out of our apartment
It was our home office
Please enter shipping
Warehouse
Andar
Did you start to see
The first year 2
Women walking around New York with
I did most of him
We redditors who are getting them a very good discounts
Eventually we started to see it and I remember thinking
What I did
That was a big deal
And
You know I think it took people while even my family my sister was working
At Gucci and actually
Called me and said we're all pitching in
Mom
Father's Day
Get her Gucci bag and I thought
What
I never that
Because they really didn't think
It would be much
I still should be upset with him about that hopefully they're listening
Show all the while you're sleeping bags out you're getting orders in and you are still designing
Facts
Yes
So you're working like
Crazy
We are and
What we ended up doing
What speech took on
Two partners
For Sweat Equity only
It was at my friend Elise Aaron's
My best friend
Stars 80
Teen Olympian LaBelle
Someone that we just met
Two friends here in New York
So
The three of us were in cars going
Factories
I was really doing the design only but
Didn't I also.
Steaming the bags boxing packing
And how are you guys finding all
It means it was always you
Yeah I got a job offer to work for Saatchi & Saatchi in LA and I
I almost tripled my salary you're still funding the company ourselves
And we needed money
For fabric and we needed money
Trade shows
Until we both agreed that I would go to La you did move to LA
I thought I could go back and forth and at the time released
Pallet wood hold down the New York
Partner with you
FedEx in all my designs and materials and
I rented a little house that I called the house I never lived in
I never bought a piece of furniture and I just took the money and send it to me I'll put it back into the business
Did you ever get a point in the first two years
Where you thought this was going to collapse if this is going to fail
Yes and I remember calling back
Tulisan Pamela New York niacin
I didn't leave you two
Shut it down I said it's wow are you guys
Like in dad or
It was hard I mean it was we were still not making any money nobody was making a salary we were Andy was funding everything
And it at that point we were all kind of putting money in Pamela put into Emeli Sande
I just remember thinking of
We run to your 401K money
And in all of our savings at that point
We still weren't seeing
You know progression that was going to pass out in the next year in the near future
A good run at it
I think we called the partners who
We brought in as as
Equity Partners on a handshake without any salary and we said we think we've had it
Exhausted and they said
Left the start with you and we haven't even had to return the deals.
So we felt like you can't just walk out and I remember we spoken
It said all right
We're going to go back
I'm trying to make
9595 96-95 probably 95 and I did get another job in
New York a great job actually
But still the company was not making money
What was the what what happened
I would say the stores really
Started to buy more we were in sacks
The Neiman's and
When the
Large department stores started to buy
It
Kind of really took off and
We won
The cfda awards which is
The Council of fashion
Designers of America
And
There were photos from around the country not just
New York at the show that were saying
Who is this
So that really really help us a great deal I have
Nosey word
If smaller designers
Didn't win at the time it was usually a Ralph Lauren Calvin Klein Donna
Karen all this beef
And I remember Kate when we came back to New York and we were hoping something would happen then
Either Neiman's or Saks
They're buying for two or three stores and they said we're going to buy for all of our stores
Wow and that was 50 stores
More Than Words
And that quadruple are busy
But what you have to realize
When that happens although it's very good you also have to up
Front
Pay for the production they don't pay you for
30 to 6
Today so I remembered
Are we going to afford this but we
Never borrow a dime
Ever
Was there something that you guys did like a business
Decision that you
You made
That
That was the
Key to turning this around or was it just
More people started
Discovered in you just you just persevered through those rough years and then it's finally
Just kind of on its own
Youku
Got discovered
That's exactly what happened I mean it really was just
Kind of a little bit of a Snowball Effect
No just got a little bigger and a little bit bigger and
I think
At the point where the largest department store Square picking us up
I think that it will be realized
Which is very important
Table
And maybe you get a few
Basin shelves
Restore shop and Shop is what they call them where your name is above it really big
I got to see your
To walk into
I think it's more fun for my mom actually but it was a lot of fun I have to stay in the
Opening of stores do you know we'd open the store
And Soho tiny little 300 square-foot store the next day
You know we're opening a bigger Store New York and then we're opening in
Los Angeles
Austin Chicago
It was kind of at that point it became a little dizzy and
A bit of a whirlwind
State it was fun
Inside some point you guys sold
Part of the company
That was at the service scale up or
Like to make it even bigger
You know it was also a safety that quite honestly for us personally
And it wasn't even Marcus and we thought that would be somebody that would
Be in a position to help us
And they bought
Element more than 50
Percent of companies that they bought 56
And reportedly for more than 30 million dollars was that
Insane d.
That's what it was when they were I think our biggest
Client restore the time and
We're doing very well with them and they just started
Investing in other little
Little brands that they
They thought I had potential
And yeah they came to us we were
Completely
In shock
Exciting because
As we thought wow
Which everything goes goes away tomorrow
You know it will be able
Sustain the business
I mean it was really about not being able to have
A bit of an essay going forward
4 bus
I know what that mean when winning the Marcus by
More than half of the change
Kate Spade
We started going into work categories because they were
Encouraging that which a lot of the stores not
Mancino's Sac all of them
Really encouraging us
Categories
Stationary next twitch
That was right when the phones and emails and all that
Replacing people writing notes
Texas native Wars
Another category we didn't mean
You know I'd Online category
So I think what they were implying
Shoes they really wanted some
Real substantial
Second categories are third fourth
So then we started doing shoes and
It really just started
No I think it was just a good boost
I mean you guys probably had to go from you and Andy and your two partners II
Lots of employees quickly
We did but we have done that actually
In the process
Slowly slowly changing
Offices and we take a floor and then
We take another floor in the building
Who started the hiring people preparing our
Different departments in production people in
And then hiring people that
Have more experience
So I really had a lot of people around
And Andy did Andy really surrounded himself with the
Really
Greats
Art Department
And I really had great designers with me and
I think we really developed
Employees that were amazing
When did you start to see
Kate Spade bags
All over the
Huge iconic
And when did you first kind of realized
I'd say was about
It was still
Ferry New York so I must say
There a New York Los Angeles Chicago
I think it was about 98 or 94 UTM
Danny city that you went to
Counterfeit started
That was about to
Which Andy said that's actually a compass
You're doing something right when
They're on every blanket on every street and celebrated for a day and then the next day that was over
You guys sold the rest of your your share of
Walked away from it what why'd you decide to do that
So
We had a baby
And 2005 and I just wanted
It was a perfect opportunity
The point was it
Neiman Marcus
Set the time
Was selling
Themselves to
Pacific
Dan baldus
But then I must
Give them a lot of credit for that
But when we sold everything he know
Kind of like we have a
A boss
I want to leave on
On good terms if it's a
Perfect time to leave
I wanted to spend time with my daughter
It was
You've heard so many horror stories
About people who style and then they stay and then they fighting and they sue and
That's too ugly
Before me so
We left on great terms we stay because of turnover
For a year I think
For the transition to make sure all the employees who we loved had
Agreements to carry on
The end
Making sure you understood
What the process was
Instead
And
They were very gracious and I think we all handled it very well and
It was seamless
It was a very
Quiet exit
You guys obviously have this incredibly strong
Marriage meme email here college students you're still together you have a
You created this big amazing brand and how do you
How do you have a marriage and a business and
Make it work
Safe for my perspective I remember people saying how do you work together when I was thrilled
I said I'll wait up wait up and I'm not ready yet means
Let me tell you right now if you think that everyday
Good office together we can have lunch together
We actually were concept
Florist Parma that very reason because
Then he'd be on the phone and I take
Get off the phone
Something to tell you or ask you
And that
We had to really I had to
Myself
Boundaries in
We have to make a conscious effort not to talk about it 24/7 which is
As you can tell by how quickly I talk like tendency
And I also am very
Nervous person I worry a lot
And Andy could not be more different sleepless nights person
Always another
The sky is falling
Zico
It's fine and I think that because we
We kind of grew up together
Uniform Mart 20s
Up until now in are 50
And we actually have a lot in common which helps
You guys
Recently
Launch a new company
Together
What you call it by Frances Valentine
Yes in case you changed your name from Kate Spade
To Kate Valentine
I did but I added it I didn't change it I just added
Francis
Valentine into it so it's very
It's Katherine
No
Francis
Valentine
Brosnahan Spade
Elong
Did you do it in part because
Kate Spade and become
Its own thing and
Beyond a single person
Yes and I thought it was important to make sure that we weren't stepping on any toes and
That we distinguished
Our company
And I think that was important
For both of us
I mean people still call me Kate Spade I go buy it
Seitz eye
I get confused
Myself so you can call me Francis if you want
Tell me about Frances Valentine
We are doing
Shoes and Handbags
So we actually when we started
It was initially just
Shoes
Although we've only
Didn't visit
I'm not your just your little over a year
But we realize that
People expecting bad
And I mean now you're mean it sold a different right because
The hunger is
I'm sure it's still there but
It's not like a do-or-die thing
It must be that I don't know
Is it less stressful
We've air conditioning I think that's big that's a big difference right elevators and air conditioning
I would say there's
It's
Both I feel a little more confident
I think Andy feels the same because we've done it before
But on the same hand
You think that
People are expecting a great deal
So they're still there still a lot of pressure chest mean
Personal finance
See you again so
I'm not crazy that as I mentioned earlier losing any money
You know this thing go to work
Do you when you walk past
Kate Spade
Shop today or
RC bagged do you
Do you feel emotion emotional
Ashland to Aurora
Is it sort of like barely know that that's a
It's funny because I
I do look at it and I don't
People said oh do you have any regrets I've ever think you all I hope I don't
And I never have and I think they've done such a good job that luckily I don't have to have
And so we do walk by the stores and I have a funny story that we actually walked into the store
To buy my daughter something
Went to the cash register and teeth are you on our mailing list
And I said
So
And instead that I used to
Maiden name and ice
She surprised me
Send my daughter kind of kept nudging me choose died for me to say something and I didn't and then I've ever thinking you know
I'm not on your mailing list but I think I helped created
Kate and Andy spade and by the way if you've ever heard of Jack Spade bags for men
Kate and Andy were behind those two and no jack is not a real person just that cool
Cool name I mean honestly people constantly are same
And then I don't want to embarrass but I'll tell you he ain't heavy and then I felt
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250,000 customers
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.