Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Well I'm happy to replace the vacuum
In a bag with a psychic thing
Let me make some real money and they said okay
Electrolux
Brown NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements they built
Gyros
Reinventing the vacuum cleaner
Britain's most successful
Question
Who invented the light bulb
Thomas Edison right that is the name that usually comes to mind
Because Edison Diaz
Probably the most
Famous American inventors
History
He held the record for
The most
By a single person
Actually invent the light bulb
Took the existing design for a light bulb
What time the best light bulb would only work for a few hours
And Edison improved it he made a much
Much better life
That's basically what James Dyson
Dad with the vacuum cleaner
A product that had been around for almost
80 years any product
So Associates
1 brand
Betting match
The English-speaking world
They're still called Hoover's
So as you hear James Dyson much like Thomas Edison
Used a kind of trial and error design process
For that back
Prototype in a shed in his backyard
Tinkering
Making small changes
And then testing them
In fact he made over 5
Thousand Turtle types
Before perfect
Theisen's Journey as an inventor started a long time before he
Created his now famous vacuum
England
Right after the second World War
Moses brother and sister
His dad was a Classics teacher at a boarding school but
When James was about 9 years old
Is that
Died of cancer
My mother
Sword coming news happening we we didn't
It was more of a surprise to us
It was too high
She carried on
When trained as a teacher
Teaching
The school which is a school year
Page goat
The one where your dad
Boarding school
United States Navy health insurance
Being a little time
The school said where you can come as borders
App for free
We had a free education
Emigrate
Money and comfort
Kapoor family
Had a good education
She got to deliver this boarding school
Which is
Probably pretty harp music
As a kid
I want your dad
What do you remember about
I might have one thing that was it was quite difficult for me because I was at school in my father tortoise
There was a memorial service for him
Which of course the health school head coach
Pretend I didn't see the boys but if you want to
Set match lot to me but no NovoLog to the boys around me
And indeed I think getting away to boarding school
Just off to hit died from
I should have stayed at home
My brother and sister
I'm a mother
That was probably a pretty harsh thing to do to a nine-year-old
But this site are in England. Do not sending people away to boarding school toughen him up
Probably does.
So I had to remind myself and not anybody else
Determined
Very very determined to prove something
James wasn't quite sure how he would eventually prove himself and after you finish school
He managed to get a spot at the Royal College of Art
In London
And he decided to study Furniture Design and then architecture and Structural Engineering
Innisbrook job
College was for Fairly prominent British engineer and inventor named Jeremy fry
SF channel of an engineering company
Tok just got married
And he says well I'll give you a design Joel 2
And what was it about you that interested him and why would he offer
You a job light employing young people
What Bryson Pebble the right
Attitudes and ideas so he gave
Opportunity for young people
So I started designing one to two things
The sad thing I designed for him
What's this high-speed landing craft
This was a
Moonlight
Because his Maiden pissed
Was making valve actuators
Oil and gas pipeline
This was his iron in French
He had a side gig that was inventing
Boats
Well that just hit invented a boat
The theory was that
Flat bottom boats
Is the most efficient planing Hull
It's not very good in Heavy Seas
But because it's
Flats
Flashes in twice Robert custard
Movies when it's storming the beach of Normandy
Yes except
But that is not flat person
Oak that fish shaped house which is why you see the troops I mean to Wade through chest-high water in order to get to the beach
West we could land Straits on the
Patrick and ran the bait shop.
So he had this idea to build
This landing craft or transport craft that and he said to you hate
I guess idea
Can you
How to design something
That's exactly what you said
It was a simple as that
And it was as mad as that
Because
I've never designed a boat and I'd ever designed anything in fiberglass
And Abraham
I'm pretty have this wonderful attitude
You think
Think about doing something
You just do it
Any hated experts
Did he teach you how to make
Things because
How how does that work
But yes he did I mean we were taught how to make things
The college
But one thing we went well but we have to make a prototype
He supposed to say well. I saw that Caldwell
He said book don't try so I just went off and did it
Like you described a of a welding arc welding C'mon Man Welding courses
And save it for life
How to use engineering tools
By myself
So you have your prototype and and does fry say
Let's try some
Let's put this out on the market
A pretty much that
And I said I'd that I know nothing about selling
He says well
The time. Icculus you designed every square millimeter of it
Every nothing about you know everything about it Sagat and said it
Who's buying it was
What was it designed for the military initially has construction used oil companies
As a diving platform
As a bridge building
High tide many many uses
I'm within a couple years we was telling a hundred or more yeah
Very successful business
Fry was it was a very fortuitous meeting early
In your life that
She was older than
Oh yes yeah yeah
20 years old
Father
Probably
Mental
Told me everything I know
So I guess you worked with with Jeremy fry for a couple years and then at a certain point
You decide you don't want to come and see if I can start my own business
Yeah but for 5
What's happened yes
Anole
And he offered
Put the fun man I said that
I'm still mine
Sairento designed and made the bull barrel
Wheelbarrow
The pool inside of a wheel
New kind of wheelbarrow
What cuz I was fixing up the house
And I noticed
The deficiencies of metal wheel virus with narrow Wheels
This will advance table is binary legs
The Lexington
Agisoft ground wheel sinking
Soft ground
So as I used one
I sought it to redesign
And it was quite a good project
To do
As my first business
Because it was relatively simple
At least I thought it was
What was it what was
Well it had this big
Balloon Bowl
It was actually a plastic football
This 360-degree rotating ball
And it was more stable
And it was most stable it didn't sink into breaking ground
In your garden that didn't damage your lawn and it cuz it didn't sink on the building site
Why are wheelbarrows like that today
The difficult thing that's been sending it
Because
The traditional
Hardware stores is I wear then and a few garden centers
They didn't want to sell it
Very strange
So I used to sell it to Little Adventures Benson the newspaper
There's always next incontinence pencil the bulnes kiss
That would be the sad part 4
Four-wheel Paris train
Molten looking at you nicely to sign
I think real better
And I started to get quite a lot of business people sent checks see how this company the ballbarrow
And seems like it's going pretty well so well that never made mother
What happened
Does Name ID wheel bearings
Not many people buy wheel bearings
Types of very small Market
I will receive a cheat
No wheelbarrow manufacturer as a Salesman or a designer or an engineer
They just make the same thing they made
You're off to ya
I may have to explain why it's different the best
Yeah that was so fun I mean
50 Cent
But never made me money so I should have charged a lot more
My understanding is that you actually went when you took in investors
You kind of
Gave the patent over to the company is that right
I signed the passenger's a company
Which was possibly mistake
Yeah
Why'd you do that
Well it's quite normal to sign the passenger
What's a company
I thought you were
As I do not with
With all my
Then you put wall studs
Feather dress
Just came in
And
The thing was I didn't really own anything
In the company of puff My Shaz
And I-90 and about 30% of the business
That must have been pretty frustrating me here's your your idea comes out of your brain and you don't even own
On your own idea
No but
Sometimes one needs to go through
These Rites of Passage
To understand the importance of
The importance of a name
Having a majority share in your in company or even olish
Not charging enough for the product
Running a business doesn't make money
All these lessons of a very important lessons to learn
And feel viscerally
And I guess it was around the time when you are
I'm wanting to
Make new products right so what
What were you thinking
Well I've had the idea for the back
Is Carlos Beltran
Keep it very short
The frames for the wheelbarrow today
Instead of
Painting on wood
Wetpaint
That we had elected to use that thing called epoxy casing
But the way you get the epoxy on
The frames is the spray the powder
Electrostatic
I will back frame is REI open
It's a lot of the sprays going to miss the frame
And have to be sucked away
Well then have it go well
Play the factory
That you have a vagina
Vacuum cleaner
The back of a spray booth
Sucking away
Play Palace missed the frame
Michael is very inefficient
This kind of people who made this equipment
Smart people use
And I love that use John site claims
I've seen John cycling console Mills
For collecting
Find soda
So I went to call Pit one
But I saw an Electra Glide climbed over the wall at night and took some sublimation
Examined
I mean came back and gave it two weekends we made one that was about 34 High
How does a cyclone actually work
Cycling is littering outside on my butthole
You have to
Blow into the system or suck out of the cyst
But this is exactly why
I meant that
Spins around
Boy look
And the address I was sensitive
Military discount gets into the center cuz it's too busy spinning around the walls of a buffer
By centrifugal force
That's the basic principle of
In cycling for widely used in the industrial vacuum machines that were cleaning factories
It was widely used cement factories paint factors also two places that had nasty dust
That had to be sucked away by the central spec
Vim system
Assume that this is a very good example
But you see all the doctor
Sucking away from all the souls and everything
Socks at 2
On top of the roof by the EU say sike
Huge metal psycho
And how do you connect that to a vacuum
Well
Over the two weekends while I'm welding out this Thursday
Buford Highway
I realize
What's the point of this site
Which is that it collects dust all the time
Without ever blocking On Truckin
So when I saw house like fish
Like what I wanted
If you can make a small one and put it in a vacuum cleaner
So when I finish the welding I rushed home
I made a miniature Chihuahua
Call Bolton's
Scotch tape
I have connected it with a piece of hose
To my Hoover
And push it around the house
Listen Ram 1978-79
What just explain to me what was the problem with a regular vacuum cleaner in a bag
Are you frustrated by then did you hate vacuuming like what
Problem with vacuum cleaners that needs to be solved
Well I I
Just put my
Alright Heyman
Anthem
We had a vacuum cleaner
Dodge bolt what was
Bills
Custom bass popper
In the wild
Apus solo spaceship show
About to 1st and diamond
For the huge motor
Straight Talk
Anthem
I was using it one weekend
Professor
Sergeant
I couldn't find anything
So I took the bag out
Under the end
Contiprocontact salt into the
Garbage can
And put it back in the back
And I thought
Is it right to buy bags again
I just don't understand
I don't know that's a suction
Exact kids before I went to the bag it wasn't a full bag is completely empty
But I still have no suction
So I got in the car and went down.
Buy some new bag
Okay back I'm putting it and you back in
And I got good suction
So I thought to myself what's the difference between
The one I've ever
On the one I just bought
And I have to look
Lackawanna temperature
And you can see
It with my own eyes.
Poison
What blocked
So I suddenly realized
What's going on here
You don't replace the bags
Full
You replace the bags
Because that blog
Yeah
And I thought as a solution to
So at that time.
House for sale because you're still involved in that in the ballbarrow company which
Chad
Hey I got this this vacuum cleaner idea to look at what I suggested
Because vacuum cleaners bagless vacuum cleaner
They they didn't what they said was David so stupid if there was a passive vacuum cleaner Hoover Electrolux
Will someone else would have made it is a huge company
Play possibly compete with you Jai and vacuum companies
I thought
Say that these pictures
Improve the technology
Quite happy selling bags
I may be tiny and have no money and bad debts but
No idea my suggesting that we make a vacuum cleaner
Actually because I was unable to start I went back to my friend Jeremy fry
What is excellent
How far is 51%
How much did you tomorrow
Well it was about
40 of 50000
To get to start it did not have any of your
3 kids
So I started
Making price of Tide
X4
A site plan
Where did you do
In the shed behind my house
So you did this in your backyard
Yes and you borrow the money or the money
Lydia was Italy
You're so not all like start selling Lisa
Yes
Well that what what I thought
We thought rather well so it would get it to work
And then with licenses
Tell someone
C u r a
Trying to build this and you're doing this day and night day and night then
Yes
Nice booty
I'm doing in the shed like was it like trailer trailer was it
Italian Perico cuz this is before the days
Computer simulation
I was building one person type
The time making one change at a time
I knew what difference
What's that one change made
I'm so hype
Progress
The ricotta number problems to solve
The first lie
About time state-of-the-art was the site claims but only good at separating.
Songs about 20 microns
Cuz I have to get it down to half of my car
Cigarettes
Popsicles
That was the first pope
And the second thing
What's that I found it
Has
Sunflower
What goes straight through the side
A note B collect
And I built 5127 privatized
Before I got it right
Iterating and doing this in your backyard
How are you earning a living how are you paying your bills how are you
Providing for your family
Well the money that I borrow from the bank
And the money that
Dairy-free protein
What's essentially pay my Saturday
Plus a few costs
Black at the cost to a minimum
And once you got a prototype
Up and running
Did you go around and try to pitch the vacuum company's executive at Target
Vacuum cleaner companies and one or two other domestic plants come from and what do they say when I saw it
Butts
Getting ready to do anything I didn't want change
I wanted to Adam said that she rather like selling paperbacks it's like a
Jeanette's
Essentially they were curious but didn't want a license
How bad did your financial situation get
Echo pretty bad it's not nice
But at the one thing that my wife and I always said was that we both had skills
You could always teach off some attention did
Do something even cost lessons
And I could always send money making fun of something something like that we had practical
We could do it yes
They wanted to do but we had that back up
But with all of those companies
Mississippi companies telling you
Not really interested
Did you ever get nervous did you ever think about just packing it all in and then end and going getting a safe job as a design
Liner for become
12 Nation
Has the opposite effect on me
And I can see that they what time diamond
What is a good idea
Without good reason
I think it's a really good reason
What about your friends and family work
James Beard
Saying that he thinks is going to be a big deal
Obsessed mad
But the thing is never to take advice
It me is is amazing his even
Some of the most
Successful entrepreneurs have been on the show
I had sleepless nights they were they have anxiety about
About whatever.
Well I did I didn't I did
But I have a soda basic belief
I think partly from
But success
Of the bolt pattern
I'm from the
High-speed landing craft which I love you
Wooden pipe
Like a boat
Having having introduced two very strange looking very different.
Technology
You can make a successful
If it genuinely works best
Coming up the story of how James Dyson's design for a new vacuum
No one wanted to manufacture
Eventually became one of the best-selling vacuums
In the world
Gyros near listening to how I built this
NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and opened up free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
And presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
1985 companies to try and licenses
But none of them are interested
Return his phone calls but finally that year a small company called
Beck's decides to try making and selling Dyson's design
In Japan yes very small Japanese company that never made anything before in his life
To make it for them and they would send it
What does it look like
Compared to what we think about Dyson
Today
It looks much like
Upright machines accept his pink
And it has a lot of exposed hoses bit like the pompidou building in Paris
So you can see exactly what the address of cool
Respect
Quite similar to the
Aaliyah Prime machines we sold here
And how did the two out of the cell
I think considering it was $2,000 it did quite well and like today's dollars
It's a lot of Monday
It's a lot of money
Weston peick
Japanese people
What is the licensing agreement with
What's a Japanese company
Enough money
You pay off your debts
Well
Yes it's saved me from Bank
They put it that way
See you if you licensed it to this company and
They were kind of selling okay
What made you at a certain point
I should try and sell these myself
Well
Setting Sun
In Japan
That's a ridiculously high price
It didn't really satisfied
Because I wanted to sell the loss of a reasonable price
So I
Set Blackhawk me to go on like this licensing people
I want to make
But I can clean that I want to design that I can do
And I want to sell it in the way that I want to sell it
I decided to
Borrow some money
I was not completely on my own eyeballs out
Xiaomi find my
Mi Rancho.
Trying to borrow money to start my own business
But I thought I caught a good track record
Designed the new technology
Lycosa successful licensee in Japan
And I thought that I told Bill to raise money
The problem with
Adventure capitalist
Is that they all thought that because I was in engineering
I knew nothing about making him sending things and I could possibly make a success of it
Say they will tie me down
I'm actually trying to be grateful
I went to a clearing Bank Lloyds Bank
And by some miracle they agreed to lend me $600,000
But I also the bank manager off to us and he said well I sold it you would want a big lawsuit
I told that you had to termination there's a Little Caesars in America
With someone who copies
Oh so I buy this point somebody already copied your idea
Reminder to settle it very successful
Name something is this bank manager
He went home and asked his wife what you thought was that contain that didn't have bags
And she said wonderful
Exactly what I want
Determination
To win a lawsuit
I'm partly
That's his wife tonight bags in fact
And presumably you had to put some collateral damage
Like your house the house exact
My wife
And I had to sign the house over
I'm getting nervous for you thinking about that
So off I went do I have
That's a very small amount of money
To build
The tooling
And it cost the whole of the six
1000 lb is the internet
Detection Moe's inject the plastic into the makeover
Now one of the things about tuna
If you make any changes
That's where the tool making makes the least money
It's like a builder
Do you make changes to build a stockpiling on
Lacoste
I said to
My brother engineer
This is it I'm going in my money so this is it
Changes
We go out to dinner
And I put the tuning anoplasty
Plastic
Are there any reusing hallstatt fact
Nitrous acid can I use the other half
To assemble the back
And I said yes
So I had to
In a few people that dig message template
And through f4g
Myself
Time we had
One salesperson and
1 money person
Plastics Company
Made the pots and I paid them
At the end of 60 days
And so I have to go get some more.
How how did you sell who did you sell them
I'm too how did you know where to go
Well when I went everywhere
In those days the web mail order
Remember the Sears mail-order Charlotte
Well I wasn't splice a one or two people who had catalogs like that
Because
I spent a day with Abaya
Who was so curious about this funny man who done this
Yellow Taxi
I spent a David
Anthem
The end of the day he said
Why should I put
You're fat containing in my catalog
And take out the Hoover on Netflix
Anisotropic boarding
I just looked at a long time and then he said okay I'll give it a guy and he have to be the biggest
How much would you sell it for
199 lb
3 * what are the vacuum cleaners for sofas
Didn't any of these the catalog company say this is just too expensive is to
Your you're
Jurassic
Albany The Price Is concealed
Because you paid on the trip
You paid the same amount per week
Ice
Baseball print
Why would somebody take a risk on something that was untested that they'd Naughton ever seen before through
Catalog
Because it look different at his promise with no loss of suction
Identify bags
And everything goes into another
Catalog
Set my first
3045 Bond sales for today's Catholic people
And then I got into quite a famous joke
Call John Lewis
Department stores looking to compete with a big electrical multiples
And say
They wanted something different
For which they could charge more money
But it quickly became my best friend
And this was
Trey
99th Street
So how long
What's a before you wreck
I was in the black from the first month on
Iva pay my employees
When does making a profit
As my distribution started
And I I couldn't get into
Do the shops if I promised Drive
Verizon telephone
How did you do that Azure the money to do that
Well I didn't
So I said to
Fast retailing
Isopod look
If you order 10000
I'll put all the profit on this Viking
Listen to television
Which I did
I'm sorry my strapline the banding to say goodbye to the bag taken by the back
So I had this woman explained
The Dyson doesn't lose suction
Not this dude and then she said don't need these entwife a bag
Initial wax
It's Naples from that
I guess within 2 years
This vacuum
By 1995 this becomes the number one selling vacuum cleaner in the UK
Yes
Blown away over you for reasoning is yourself
You can't stop you just have to carry on
And then bring out of a new fashion of a kind of diversion
I'm even starting to export
How much were you making by the time you
For the number one best-selling back in the UK what was the annual revenue for Dyson
Turner's public hundred billion dollars
In 2 years
That's incredible
Guess I'm in at 8 sub
It's a very steep draw
And that doesn't happen
It's happened to coordinate techworld I mean this is a real
This is a real thing that people can buy and take home
And
See people buying the vacuum
Like
Commenting on the
It was tremendous that that was actually much more exciting
Tullahoma
And how did you get
Into the US market which is your by guess
Became your biggest Market in the world
Yes
The first year we didn't do any of the
But even getting
In master
Because
Everybody said I what you might have been successful in English
America
And then
Juniper
Best Buy
I took one off vacuum cleaners home
Couple of weeks
And said to her boss
Look
Is what it says it is
It works really well
And it doesn't do suction
Best Buy toolkit
And I'm
The first year we didn't do any effort
Seoul
Pretty well
It's like mm to mm
And then we
I started getting into bondage
So we decided to put all that money
I love you bestie
Into a television
And so it wasn't my suggestion
The summer set
But why didn't you do that
Explain what you did and why you did it
Just like you on TV on TV
Take it back
Container Park Shanghai talk bag
And then Chinese
Am I psychic
And you know that Americans are suckers for a
British Acts
Well I didn't know that
How that compared to work
Why does the suction
And why mine doesn't
Michelle sturgeon
My house
And it was a very successful
And that
We started selling very fast
Good
As you grew and grew and grew and grew I mean eventually
Began to sort of expand out to
A whole range of products
Text mean
Air filter
Bladeless fans
Anybody who's gone to a sports
Orem movie theater in the US the US and probably
Elsewhere has used Dyson hand dryer
Put your hands in and out of
Begin to expand other products
Well fast food
Define bladeless fan
Bring that to me
Yes yes
You accelerate the air out of an iris law
That draws another app
Event
Expand
Volume
But I've had that you're creating
Can you create
Negative pressure suction
Behind
So you pull it more
So you end up
Multiplying the ridge
Alaska flight 15 to 20 time
Knox
But that's the basic principle
I am not sure I entirely understand it but it is amazing
To see that thing worth is he was who
Blue
Delete powerful
Yeah
That is interesting
And of course you have no plates to clean
I'm curious about your the way you run a business because you really are an inventor and designer
And you don't strike me as somebody who's interested in
Administering a company you're doing the books or
Going to a bunch of meetings or maybe you are are you
How do you do those all those thing
Well I have to do all those things
At the beginning
But
As the company grew I did more and more the engineering
And now I spend it a night
85% of my time doing that
But I was the CEO for
The first 10 years
Ronald totally happy
Doing anything other than engineering
Do I still resent the time I'm doing that
I would much rather be with my engine is
I think I really love doing I'm doing what I think is the most important thing
Did you feel a sense of
Secretly a sense of
Schadenfreude that you
Or right and the people at the ballbarrow company were wrong and those
Other vacuum companies were wrong when they turned you down to you secretly think
No no I'm on to the next thing I'm going to
Everybody makes mistakes
Effective said what I do
Wrong actually that crazy
Mistakes great
How about charging enough for the bulb
Mistake mistake
I've never made the mistake of giving away equity
You own 100% of it you don't have to answer to shareholders
That's wonderful life
Pretty simple
You are
Two people understand that
Cuz you went from being deeply in debt
In your early 40s
Really having nothing no money and
Weekend
2 today reminder - 2 today you own
Jet a private yacht
I mean that's
Crazy to think that
Not that long ago
In middle age
You are nothing
Yes yes it is
Annies anyway that it's
I find it quite nice
He came much later.
I think it would be very different
Had to happen.
And you guys are so big wrists
Huge
Financial Risk
But I am able to do it and that's the Big Dipper
Hi I am able to take a long-term View
And invest large sums
Take big risks
Huge privilege to be in the
Position
How much of your success
Do you attribute to your scale your intelligence your hard work and how much of it to lock
Absolutely not my intelligence
Hardware
Yes
Perseverance
Yes and luck
Yes gif
I do believe
That you create your own blog
Because
Lucky Zara
Yeah I did long distance running a school
And you ain't E60 baidu
Huge amount
Training
And then
Having great stamina
Understanding that
Other people will say fitting Todd say
When you feel tired you should
Accelerate
That's when you start weaning
Yeah
Waze
Developing new technology
When you feel like giving up
Is precisely the point everybody else gets out
That point that you must put an extra effort
Are you do that
Success is literally just round
That's James Dyson actually Sir James Dyson he was nice
2006 Sir James will celebrate 50 years of marriage this year
The latest Forbes estimates put his net worth at 5.8 billion dollars
I like you still f****** your own house
But of course yourself you don't hire people to do it
I do some vacuuming
On my class
But I might like doing all those chores because I learned you know what works and what doesn't.
And stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you
Things your build
The first of quick thanks to one of our sponsors
The new Surface Pro 4 Microsoft
With a fast processor and all day battery life
This powerful laptop
Programs you need
When you're on the go
And it works with your iPhone
The new Surface Pro is the lightest
Powerful Surface Pro ever
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And we got a really nice product to talk about this week
Crime shows that detective walks into a murder scene and starts looking for clues in the blood
I'm just lying around
Real police have to be trained to do that and this kind of training has been going on for a long long
Time in forensic teams at police departments have used
Everything
Can make it realistic
Everything from Theron blood to animal blood sources to even corn syrup and water that classic
Fake blood movie you use to make your Halloween costume this is Teresa stotesbery she's a chemist
He says that if you're training a bunch of cops for like a day
You need blood that won't clot too fast that won't spread disease but it's still kind of acts like the real thing
And she learned all this when she worked at a crime lab in Ontario Canada
People were kind of
Grumbling in the friends of community that there were just wasn't a good enough
Fake blood product on the market
Teresa Connell
By the way that idea
Around the same time this is about 2010-2011
She's working in another lab on something
Totally unrelated
A better coating for steel
Tok keep it from corroding
So I was working with this
Clear colorless liquid that made a nice coating
It could make little spots
If you wanted to kind of spray it on things
And I thought to myself hey
This of course
What's her light bulb
I thought if you just put a little bit of
Coloring in this and just you just Tinker a little bit with its properties I bet you I can make a pretty good fake blood out of this
Until that's what Teresa did
In fact at the time she was in grad school and kind of different thesis
I'm fake blood I spent
Four years perfecting the materials
Got my PhD and then we decided to form a company where we would sell it
And she's not working with colleagues at Trent University in Ontario to sell it to police trainers around the world
The ingredients by the way are top secret
Are some water some
Polymers and coloring
The mixture has features that you find in real blood they call those little features
Tails or spines are scallops
And they can tell you a lot about how the blood got there so was it flying through the air was it
Just formed on a surface is a little creepy but that's the point right if you're learning to investigate a crime
Anyway Teresa's company impact scientific has made about $10,000 since it launched last
And one of the coolest perks of the job I do make a pretty mean Halloween costume
One year was I dress up like a zombie which was pretty
Intense
You can find out more about our Facebook page and tell us your story
Build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to the show this week if you want
More or your previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org please also down
Murder podcast in apple podcasts or however you get your podcasts you can also write us your feedback or
Or any pictures at HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send us a tweet act how I feel
I sure was produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to Geneva grandson of Mexican Port Jeff Rogers
Thomas Liu
Our intern is Newark Uso
And Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email template
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week