Support for how I built
And the following message come from Michigan economic developer
Corporation
Seewhy michigan
Is attracting
Top talent and top businesses
By searching Michigan pure oportun
Support for this podcast comes from American
Express
No matter what you do in business
I'm building a better mousetrap to building a better app
It's easier
Don't go It Alone
The powerful backing
American Express
Don't do business
Without it
Hate this guy here and today we've got a brand new live episode of How I built this
Featuring Emily Weiss
Glossier
The police have to show
A lot of people ask
How can we support
How I built this
And the best way to support what we do
Is by supporting your local public radio
Cured NPR we're launching our annual fundraising campaign starting
Tuesday November 27th which is
Is giving Tuesday but
You're listening to the show on Wednesday or Thursday or Friday it doesn't matter it's
Never too late
Pigeon
Really easy just go to donate. Npr.org
Slash built
Vets donate
Npr.org
Flash built
So we flew to LA and we drove
During rush hour all the way down to this Lake Middle of Nowhere place
Empty there's a stray dog like roaming through it like tumbleweeds blow I mean I was like why don't we just go
Call it this is most certainly not our guy but we went in and inside was this
64 jacked like Dad so excited
Women's skincare would not believe
Is how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
And the stories behind the movement
Built
Andre Rison
Beauty blog
A brand that now shaking up the entire cosmetics
Back in 2012
Facebook page
Billion dollars for Instagram
I remember we actually interview the Instagram founders
Back when we
First launched the show
What made Instagram
A valuable proposition
What is the time
Profitability
Instagram
Basically a
React
Posted the photos
But we did have with 20 million users
M Facebook
Saw in Instagram
Self years before
You build a customer base first
Figure out how to monetize
Business with those customers
This isn't
Easy way
Need to start a business you have to
Create something
Free that's compelling enough
People coming
After you introduce
Product
And this is sort of the story
Can I say sort of because
Emily Weiss started her fashion and Beauty Bar
Do it with the intention of one day creating her own cosmetics
But what happened was that blog
Into the gloss
It blew up
Hundreds of thousands of readers
Became obsessed with hearing about other women's
Skincare routine
And so as the Blog crew
Emily started to wonder
Could I actually create a cosmetic brand for my readers
In 2014
She found a single investor
She watched a small line of skincare and makeup
And today
Just four years later
Glossy a is valued at around
Four hundred million dollars
If her customer base of millennial women is the
Envy of the Cosmetics world
How did Emily Weiss
To disrupt
The first thing to know is
She didn't come out of nowhere
Emily's been walking lock since
Age 15
What you talked your way into an internship at Ralph Lauren
And then
Vogue where she ended up working
For several years
For quitting
Focus
Full-time
It's a Blog that inspires
Fierce passion among her readers and when I sat down with Emily for a live interview on
On stage
Skirball Center for
The Performing Arts
And York
You could hear that passion
Wow
Think you got a lot of fancy Emily
Amazing I wish I could do that everyday
I'm walking to your
Your living room and there's like a transaction
Alright so
This is really it is actually very serious question
Can we clear one thing up
Is it is it glossy a
Or glossier
Classy okay
Do people do people sometimes ask you that question
All the time in France
We just want to be friends
Is glossier and you're like no
Yeah
Let's start Lister when you are kid right you Google up in Fairfield County Connecticut starts you a couple hour and a half from
New York City
Tell me what you were like as a little girl I was really
I mean I'm still really weird I'm into a wide variety of
So
Love animals
I had almost every kind of pet
Like a turtle
Pair of blue capped cordon bleu finches
Ya like bread
Guppies fancy
Detail Guppies and tried to sell them to a fish store
Yeah
At the same time I was
Super into
I think
I think fundamentally storytelling
Like I was really interested always and I always have been in
The power of narrative
And storytelling and kind of imagining like complete worlds
Or like systems yeah I was definitely
You know very into makeup I used to make my own costumes like I was like so like butterfly costumes for Halloween
For sure
It's not even like
Action specifically or beauty specifically it's
Again that like power
Of
Creation like you can create yourself through fashion and beauty and you can create different looks and you can
Kind of
Use them as tools
So I've always been really interested in kind of products are like crayons you know or closer
Creative
So if if we were happen to a time machine and go back to high school
Your high school
Urine and I always saw you there what was
Would people have identified with the time as Echo there's Emily why she's really into fashion like it and you would see this
High school students order Pinterest
You know
Define
Yes it but it wasn't good
Like I wasn't I wasn't good at it
I was probably doing things way too young
Like I remember
Well I'll tell you one thing I did I went to my first day of middle school in a new
New school and new town
God bless my mommy
Clewiston Jessica
And I was
Really excited about wearing
Those outfit
And so I wore thigh-high stockings
First day of six
With high heel loafers
And like a fool
Kilt
And like a feather pen
In this like town where people were playing lacrosse
You know like so I never like who is
So
Like many teenagers you were a babysitter
And you happen to do
A babysitting gig
For a family that
Would eventually land you an internship
Ralph Lauren
How did that happen
Story
I mean that is you know people often ask me
What amount of your successes
Contributed to lock
I really believe in kind of grit
I mean I didn't make that up that's Angela Duckworth and her book
Grit
A very good book Buy
That actually just was luck
I mean that there was nothing pretty about babysitting for your neighbor
And he happened to work around 4
That the dad was Ralph Lauren
But you were like 15 and how did the conversation come up you were just like
Oh my God I love you was a very brief conversation
Remember standing in their kitchen and at some point I don't know how long I've been
You know how many times I babysat for them
And at some point I
I asked her he said
I work at Ralph Lauren in New York City and
Can I said
How can I work at Ralph Lauren in
New York City
Instead of
Beijinger kids
And they were lovely
They were really great and
He was a real sport to propose in 02
Ralph Lauren HR what did this is a long time ago I'm sure this was is illegal now given up his food
My interview with HR and I went through the process and I think they saw something there and I worked
But offer
For two summers and you were going to Ralph Lauren's
Headquarters on 650 Madison Avenue and was on Madison and 60th
There was a hot dog stand in front that I would
I was so excited about I'll never forget this I was so excited about getting these hot dogs and I was in New York City
This is what you do
They were like oh my God
What are you eating
Timati fat
I remember like
I didn't know
And what do you what do you remember about
Like what it what did you what did you do there maybe you were 15
Sixteen-year-old whatever whatever they had to take a photo.
I was I was so happy
You can give me anything
I was scanning I was
Running errands I was I was the happiest intern you've ever seen
Did you ever did you ever meet Ralph oh yes
So I know I remember I was in a room
You know I was ability note-taker so I was sitting in the room the back in the corner in like
You know everyone was
I don't know meeting and I was taking notes
And Ralph
Turned
Yeah I think I'd actually maybe she has had him at one point but
He has no man you know
And he goes and everyone just stops and you look Migos
What do you think
Hahaha
I don't know what I said I don't remember I just remember like the whole thing
Stop
Things they were talking about something
Yeah
So you did those two summers
As an intern at Ralph Lauren
And then
The temperature College you went here to NYU is
Studied
Studio art
Once you moved here
You got another internship
Vote Yes
Ativo
A Teen Vogue
I know I mean
A lot of us have have an impression of what it might be like to work and you know it like a Conde Nast Fashion Magazine from Devil Wears
Prada
The great film
It's a great feeling
Is there any truth to that
I mean
So I was really fortunate because I had a great boss
So I was actually
At 8 or Teen Vogue as an intern at Vogue which was
The job that had before building this company
Sure
And I was there I think it's all about it's kind of like anywhere all depends who your boss is
Like doesn't matter what company you're at it's like
Isn't there that
I just heard from someone that your personality is the result of the like three or five people who you spend the most time with
Do you know if you work with great smart talented people which I was very fortunate to do then you learn a lot
When you were
When you are an intern Teen Vogue and you got your purse
Chabot College
Adverb
Did you envision that your career would be as a fashion writer or a fashion editor is that what you thought of this is what I'm going to
I do with my life yes I mean you know my dream was to be an Editor in Chief
So at the time you don't like in my early twenties
That was you know I looked at
Someone like Anna Wintour and that was incredibly inspiring
How did you guess
At some point you were able to
Right
For Vogue you were able to write
An article
Which was about
So I didn't turned in
I was always working in fashion
And beauty is kind of like this
Ugly stepsister to Fashion in in magazines and in media it's really funny because all of the
Revenue rose a lot of income
Songs from Beauty and these magazines
You think about it like
Treating an issue of a fashion magazine
Beauty can sometimes at least
You know and years ago be like
Five or six
10 pages no there such little airtime
Dedicated to you know this
The topic that in many ways you're like
Forced to deal with on a more fundamental level everyday than even what you're wearing right it's like
Personal hygiene
So I never worked
Covered that's like I enjoyed talking about
People but
I'm not even someone who's wearing who's like
Fast with you teanaway if you Define obsessed as being you know wearing a ton of makeup
Or
I'm spending like lots of time I don't know
Getting facials like
Found out that was not me
But I was on a shoe
In Miami Florida
This is like 2010 this was 2010
And I was on the shooting Miami Florida with Doutzen
Krause I don't know if I'm saying her name right was them is the model
We were in a trailer
Which is often the case you're in this like you know RV in
At some point the model Doutzen she said
She start talking about
Amazing self tanner that she loved and I don't even think I've ever use a self-tanner and she was like all the other ones really crazy but when you
Use this when you exfoliate this way and then you put it on it's like air foam and doesn't smell it
You know all these things
Pittsburgh until 10 or 2 change my life
So I remembered it I got it from the CVS in my in Wilton where it where I was for the summer
It was great
I mean it was really a great experience this this self tanner
So
I wanted to write about
Like I was like someone else needs to know like I heard it because Doutzen told me which is a super crazy
Baby situation that no one else is going to be in
And I need like my civic duty is to like share this with the world
So I went to the
Beauty editor of Vogue
Who is the Fulton theater and I hadn't met her
Yoshida's Legend Sarah Brown
And
And I was like excuse me you know I
I have an article I'd like
If I can write for vogue.com but I think I would love to
Just admit it to you and if you like it you can publish it if you don't like whatever I just have to like
Calphalon
And she said yes and I and I wrote this article is like
Little
Little article about the self tanner and she published
And so that was where I actually caught the bug where I was like
I remember I had so much fun writing this post
I'm sure you can find in Google it it's what I don't even know it might be terrible but
I am such a cathartic moment
To have this conversation around a product
That I never really felt around like a shirt
I mean I want it's like we're cool shirt and look nice and
A picture but I didn't feel the urge to
To be like
Is anyone else out there wearing this shirt
Like can we talk about how great it is
It is a didn't get that buck and it was just a few weeks or months later when you actually
Decided Solange
Your block we should become famous into the gloss
Is that
Why you did it
I need to
To figure this out
To more of this
I mean your this was the era of
Personal style blogs it was like when all the like bloggers were starting and it was kind of this new thing
Not monetizing but like really individual
Like these early human beings and how they actually put
These things together
Supposed
Very tightly held images from fashion brands our campaigns it was like this is what's actually going on literally
On the street
With fashion
And I remember thinking we'll why does this exist for beauty
Like why is there no like in-depth exploration of people's Beauty
Identities in Lake Beauty stories and there's really no where to find me
Cheerleaders blogs that existed long before it's the glass around
Typically much more about kind of like what's new
Like it would be like
This new mascara from you know XYZ brand just hit the market
It's so great because of all of these things
Yet I off in Salt Lake
It's not necessarily what's new that I'm most interested in is what's that
And this idea of what's Best in Beauty
Because it's
There's no single what's best
Yeah like I might love a
Matte lipstick and say it's five out of five stars
But you might love
Shiny lipstick and be like this lipsticks dry
AF
I don't want it
0 out of 5
So how did you actually
How did you actually
Launch this
I mean did you was its source of as simple as like going to
Are WordPress or whatever blog in a hosting aside and then setting it up so I'm not very technical
So WordPress is
What hosted the first blog and I had a really amazing
Set of collaborators who I don't want
Interview I've said like 900 or 700 or like 8:50 but
Under a thousand thousand dollars
Solange
The website part was not expensive the money literally was just for the camera
To buy cameras you knew you were going to take photos Canon DSLR has great little camera
What was the what was the vision of it
Edit Eminem shirt evolve but when you when you went to like
Your parents are
Your friends you said
I want to start
What is blog
It's going to do what that's going to give a voice through Beauty give people a voice through Beauty
What was the first post about
Bruce post was a publicist you worked at a fashion PR firm called Nikki Dean and I thought
She had like really cool hair and great
Sort of like styling
Australian kind of
And I I just interviewed her and I took a picture I was asked her about like her hole
Hair beauty makeup the whole thing and
The very
Very short they progressively gotten much longer
And it was a pic
Picture of her and that was it and we were Off to the Races
Picture saying you are at that point
Emily Weiss
Young woman
In the world
You don't have a giant network of
People
You don't have a whole lot of money and access to
Media platform
Adding people even know about it
Yeah so I mean listen I definitely was in a great
Position to attract you know key
People to beef
Turn on the block now whether or not they said yes I want to take an hour out of my day to go be featured on
Unknown website
With unknown reporter
Was a different question but I was sitting on you know the floor photoshoots with like a fifteen-year-old Carly
Clocks like tying her shoes now she's like you know a supermodel whose
Instagram followers
We're all kind of place where time together be like hey can I like you know
Take a picture of my new blog and I had enough Goodwill in sort of that
A lot of people said no I mean literally like 80% of the people I would ask but I think once I turn featuring
If you have a couple people than different media sites start to email hyperlink
Ensayo today
There's a profile on you know Karlie Kloss on this blog called into the gloss
And you would basically feature a different person
And their regiment
Clear it was very clear and I think
I've always focused a lot on good design like my personal flask
Don't put things out into the world don't like make work that isn't really great
It should be time well spent
Don't don't waste people's look like
Fat content
So
The fascinating about into the loss of some of our most popular features like
They're not celebrity
You know like we're in this celebrity culture and we
We
Pure how much
You know influence influencers have
And yet like
If we all really take a moment to think about like
Who's the last person who told us where to eat or like
You like their outfit and
You know you sites like
They're probably not the biggest celebrities
Probably someone who
A friend from college
The following Instagram or
You know someone you work with
And I think that democratization of
Expertise and the democratization of influence
Just like the power of the
Individual to influence
Another individual
Is something
That's fascinating in part of the reason I think why into the gloss really resonated
You are doing this to put this in context
You eat a full-time job at Vogue
This is your side hustle you were like nights and weekends
4 a.m. to 8 a.m.
Uninstall Abbas like transcribing the or posting or editing
And then on the weekends I would do all the shoot so in the interviews
So I booked the interviews and shooting each one I mean I spend
I had I had your job
I love interview people so I would sit on people's floors and their bathrooms on there like closed toilet seat lids
You know with my tape recorder out
Yeah and it's amazing because
It's so hard for women to be the right level of Maine
If you're too low maintenance
Then you're lazy doing enough
And yet if you're wearing a lot of makeup or your like looks like you really care about you know beauty or appearance than your scene
Sort of frivolous or like not to be taken series
So
The kind of intricacies
Beauty as like a
Even just like a anthropological tool
Is really really really fascinating to to me
I'm wondering like at what point after you launch
The glass did you start
I realize that
It was more than just
You know
Some friends are a couple dozen people or couple thousand people but like
Enzo
Thousands
Pretty soon after lanzhou it it's
You know it was it was a slow build but within
Within the first
Year it was such that
You know
I I had gone to my first
Brandon had my first media partner with Lancome advertising is cash money
Letting was lanco
Yes it was what it was wrong, and was it enough money this
No no it was $5,000
And
You know this was more money than I'd ever
Had in my light like ever had in my bank account
I think it was two and a half years
Before
You know after you launched into the gloss you are
Still with Vogue for 1 year
When your 12 months because at that point you know we had enough
You know it's funny because people I say well how did you and this is one of the key questions for entrepreneurs right like when do you quit your day job
How did you know when to quit
VO2 gopher
Full-time hustle for personal decision based on a ton of different
Strap for any any entrepreneur
For me it was really just one decision to make
Which was
I have to pick one
This is taking too much time and there's too much momentum
It's impossible to continue to deliver the
Products that people want like people readers wanted
The point of a really
Big Community was really wanting
But I felt like I really
There was really no choice
It's not even just follow your God it's like
Follow something that is
Is really working is really delivering like
Ghettout changing things and once you knew that
You knew it was time
Time to throw everything into that
I would have thought that
That at that point
You know into the gloss was you were going to use her thinking about this as a media proper
Pretty right like
This is a Blog
Maybe you would spin it out into a podcast or a video show or something else like a deal with cable t
TV
But that's not what happened you did you decided to
Create a
A product
Was that
Again like was that
Something that just
Just kind of happened on its own or was it really
Deliberative
Hip hop through thing
Yasso the
It's a really good question and
Things to sing that has
Lead to every decision that I've made
It is this very Central thesis
That you can create conversations and connections through Beauty
Into the gloss was the first
Burden of
Like that was the first step it was a necessary
Beginning
That showed a certain behavioral shift
You know it was like encourage people to
Just be like oh okay I'm sharing now what goes on in my bathroom
You know that I used to do totally alone
And in doing your in and working on into the boss
The first year
I was exposed to all of you beauty
So I was working
She was long gone
I was working with Estee Lauder I was working with Cody I was working with you know every big conglomerate
Beauty is a
Huge industries
The 450 billion dollar Global Market
It's going to be 750 billion in 6 years
And why is that
Because of social media
Because of sharing because of the ability to have conversation that beauty is now something that is not just
Tightly held in the hands of
Sales people at you Noah counter
It was the last time any of you have like
Really relied on that
Yeah 50% of people who go into a Sephora
Take out their iPhone
You're Googling your texting your friend I'm in Sephora should I do what was that thing you told me about
You know
That's how things work and what's interesting is these companies
I was hearing in these interviews from from women as I was sitting on the you know on the bathroom floor
I was hearing this like disconnect
That would have been answered if you tea brands
Just listen
Like if the actual Beauty Brands were listening to
Well first off they knew who you were
Which they don't think
Because their client
What is the retailer
Judy Bradfield products
Can clients for the needs of you know Macy's end
Sephora and Ulta in
CVS in those are shelf space needs
Seasonality
Margin needs and
And all of these different needs
That have nothing to do with you
As a customer
So that results in this
Kind of subpar like product Experian the kind of brand relationship
There's not really this like personal like
You get me
Relationship
And that was what led to the creation of glassy-eyed
Because
All of every Beauty brand that I've ever known
Is been built top down
And the idea for glasses what would happen if you could build a beauty brand bottoms
You could ask a question like
Who makes your dream face wash and get a thousand responses
Who played your face watching a movie
And have them say Eddie Redmayne
Like
Yeah
So so that was where did you flossing came from was you know this is the next
FaZe
Like this is the next way that we can bring together this mission of of giving voice their beauty
Weren't you
Didn't anybody say to you
Do you really think you can take on yuno L'Oreal
Estee Lauder in
Revlon even know the name of the biggest
Huge
Enormous multinationals like
Did anybody say
You know
Despise not going to work
Oh yeah
For sure
I mean
Literally all the odds are against
Mosquito RR
You know a lot of it I mean for 1
You know
4% of venture capital
Deals last year went to female CEOs
So far out of a hundred deals when to win
So already
It's like well how am I going to find this
Because
Like
No one's going to give me money for this
You needed money Avi
Create
A product for sure yeah a number in your head of what you needed to start in fact I do
And it was based on precisely nothing
Hahaha
I was like it is going to take $1000000
That's what you said I was like I bet you
I need $1000000 to make this happen
Let me come back
Just a moment
How Emily got her million dollars
Found
Chemist in the middle of nowhere
And a new tribe of customers
Just about everywhere
Stay with us
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast comes from America
Pekin Express
Tracy Chapman
Is vice president of
Global
Experiential marketing
Team created
Amex business loan
Chaotic trade shows
Is Tracy on how the lounge's of adapted
V cast
Mermaids
When we first came up with the idea for
Business lounges we filled the lounge with laptops
And with printer
We found was the people weren't really turning on the laptops and they weren't using our printer
They were sitting down and they wanted up
Place to call their kids
That really helped us evolve what we were
We're doing
We need a lot
Airsoft seating we need
Quiet areas
Sound we were able to recognize these
People is more than just business owners
When customers are using our lounges we hope that they walk away understanding
What it means to be an American
Express customer
It means that everything that we do accounts for the human behind the job
Not just a job that you're there to do
To learn more about how America
Xpressga heavy
Your back
Business
American Express.
Cam
You business
Hey welcome back
How I built this
Text from NPR
So it's 2013
And Emily Weiss
Has decided
To make her own beauty products
If you think she'll need about a million dollars
Make it happen
How did you know how did you know where to start I mean
You're in the New York Fashion World obviously
Successful blog but like
A lot of that is Silicon Valley itself
Sea money is out there in that
Whole world
How did you
Nowhere start over so I was like what is Visa
T-Money
Like what is VC
Like what is it like a venture capital what is that
I mean let's not forget I went to Art School
I did not go to Business School
Did not I did not work at a
Tech company
And by the way a lot of founders
Fast growth venture-backed companies
Work
Astrocenter bags
Right
So as an outsider
Really hard to start
Very intimidating
Better get back to that Tower of
Grit
I just kind of plowed through on this
You know exploration like I think my
Personal superpower if there's like one thing that I think
Is I'm really good at I'm super curious
And so I I kind of made a list frankly it wasn't even just about raising money I remember
Having a whiteboard
Like what are all the steps
It's going to take
Did it to build this company
And I wrote you a fee seemed like raise money
Build website find chemist
You know
Make logo
You know she's like what are all the ingredients that is
Taken of course
You don't know until you find out
From one conversation what the other ingredient is you're missing in
Just you just have to
Start to start somewhere so
You know the money needing to get raise happen pretty early in
Process what was your like elevator pitch to BC's they
So you go in and they tell k
Next yeah
My pitch to feces in the beginning was
You know
We have this great community
We understand you know Beauty and people in stories we have this robust community
2 We Believe
Deserve a better
A better Brands like a brand that that really hears and understands them and
And there's a lot of room in the market because
The huge huge industry
Really ripe for disruption
There weren't very many Direct
Consumer brands
The time now you have you know
Colourpop and Kylie and
Kim Kardashian
Aldi's differ
That hadn't happened
I rather that you pitched a no 13 or 14
Vici
Companies
And mostly men
And only one
Eventually agreed
To give you that initial
Funding it was
The
DC was a woman Christian green
6% of venture capitalist
Are women
And hopefully that will go up
So
Listen we have incredible partners
I think
You know initially
So much of
Funding is around pattern recognition
And so you have
Venture Capital whose job it is to make smart bats on companies that are going to grow
Super super
Fasting and become the next
And so it's hard to I think look at like a female CEO who does not have business
Business school degree
And and sort of say we're going to take the bat and it felt
You know it's exhausting
And I think
I know a lot of entrepreneurs
I think it's hard for everyone
Is it was
It was exhausting to go and we would hand
RR Co and I we would hand our products you never little
LOL goodie bag
And end in bring them to different
Rooms full of
Guys and
Get the bag and say oh that's so nice thank you I'm going to give it to my wife and
You ask her what she say
And I would say to myself
If you don't some like Financial technology company came to me and pitched me I wouldn't be like
Ask my husband
Explain this to me
Yeah I would like learn about it I would like to like show me your product let me understand this let me put it on the back of
My hand
Can you tell me about like how people use it
This product
And the best people did do that and we have seen a handful of really amazing adventure capitalist we 254
Percent female board in our first investor
Kirsten
I spent a lot of time with
And she was the she was at
That one
She believed in this idea she wrote you that check
Do you know
Why
She decided to take the
Take the risk
It has a really
Got
And dated back to Knox
Identifying consumer product
She invested in Warby Parker she invested in bonobos
She invested most recently in a way so she she's got good in
She is really doing things the right way around
Around around what are people going to care about what they want to live with
You don't like what are they
What
People I mean this is a really emotional
Category
Beauty you know again there's no like single truth
Right
So it's really just about like opinion and preference and and so many
Other ingredients
Alright so you got this A Million by
Raised raised
Too well because you can't spend everything that you let you know
And so
How do you start a makeup
Company like where do you go like what do you call up and what do you say like
Can you make me this make up a little bit there's chemistry
Like how do you need
How do you make makeup I mean you know
Let me tell you how I built this
So okay
So my first hire
So first of all always higher
For your weaknesses
Write an end and surround yourself with
Just the most
Brilliant people you can ever convince
Succumb
Work on the shared Vision that you have
And my first tire was an incredible
Director product development who had over a decade of experience at MAC cosmetics
That was my first hire
Because I've never made
Make a product and I don't know how it works or vendors or how long things take like I've no idea
And
I remember she ended up getting a recommendation for a chemist
Best from someone who can use me beauty industry
Who was based outside of LA
So we flew to La we got our like Hertz rental car
And we drove during rush hour all the way down to this like
Middle of nowhere place
And we pulled into the parking lot the parking lot empty there's like
A stray dog like roaming through it like tumbleweeds blow I mean you know is very
It did not look like this was going to be Arquette
There's this little mirrored building
It was literally like mirrors
So you couldn't see entire mean
I was like why don't we just go this is most certainly not our guy
But we went in
And I am so glad we did because inside was this like
Six four
Jack
Like Dad
Like it like that
Who's like
Building game changing skin care products for some of like the biggest
Brands that you
You guys are literally sitting here wearing products
That he's created
Is so excited about women's skincare
Like you just
Would not believe
And and that became our kindness and he's actually developed like
I don't know almost all of our skin care products
This Centura want it like
How do you
Tell him what you want yeah it's it's really a huge collaboration I'm trying to think of like what I can do
Wait at you maybe like the relationship between you and liquor Ark
Like if you're building a house
It depends cuz there's lots of like each of us would have a different relation
It was an architect like one of us might go to them knowing
Exactly what we want with exactly the ingredients
Exact approach to
Inability and
Exact budget in like maybe
Super involved in other ones of us
Maybe like I kind of want like a white
House Tyrell
Nnc
Where we were is we were more in the
Former camp
And so
We came inside
We have these four products we want them to do these things
We want them to you know
Have these ingredients and not have these ingredients and we want the price to be this and so we have to figure out like how to
Find the most amazing you know ingredients
And it's really just a back-and-forth and we would spend
You know an average maybe like
Two or three months or four months
Just shipping samples back and forth to each other
But a lot of it was just nerding out in the lab
Yeah wait a little room
Full of ingredients like Rama.
Cereal is what they're called so
Literally like they'll be like a vat of like
Cubicle butter from like
You know the Amazonian rainforest
Just sitting there like that's like part one of the things you see listed on the back of your you know whatever will
In bulk
Sitting in a
Thanks
So he would say like
Undo a giardia
Elvis you know her
About a thing and put it on your hand and say sleeping in a Chef's Kitchen
And so it really is all about that personal relationship that you have in your ability to work with someone your ability like real
Each other
That is led to some of the most amazing innovation
It it seems like baked into
The business model from the beginning was this
Very
Deliberate idea that you were not going to
Add your product into CVS
Or Sephora or
At
Bloomingdale's or lordandtaylor wherever
Bet that this was going to be direct-to-consumer
Why
Why wouldn't you
You know
Make it available at
Other places
Because we can build better product by having a direct relation
Every person
We don't have to make
Decisions
For anyone other than the end-user
Play. So first of all that alleviates
The tan of
Things that don't
Things that don't matter to you holding something and enjoying it
It also enables us to like ask
Ask you questions
It enables us to like send you like questionnaires
Have you been happy with
Do you like what you got you know how would you improve it
What should we make later
It allows us to create platforms that connect
Our customers with each other to talk about in a shared experiences around UT so
You know we've put
A thousand of our top customers in a slack Channel who exchanged over 10,000 messages a week
Yeah I mean it's interesting because I was talking to
Disabled people about
And
Yo it's
Many people
Many women will go into us
Sephora and try stuff on and with
The question is how do you know what this is going to look like and
What's amazing is that you can
You can just go on YouTube and type in
You know
Classy a this exactly
And you will find
Dozens and dozens of videos
I'm from women with d
Skin tones and shades
And you can almost see what it
It looks absolutely it's almost like you
The most companies start with a brand and then build a customer base you had a customer base
And then you introduce your brand
Yeah although you know our customer base now is
Is much wider than your readers event
For sure but I think what you just described is again this kind of like shift of
And it's not about again
The influencer being this 2 million follower Freeman follower million follower thing it's the ability for your
Feedback on boy brow like that can be our customers video right like that
It's like this is how I
Use this in this is how it works for me and
You going to ours
What stores we have to
Flagship
It's one in New York in
101 in LA
That is what is happening in there
I mean
Women are waiting in line down the block
Meeting the person in front of them the person behind them talking about whether or not they use glassy before I like what they like what they don't like
Weather from
Do they need a roommate like suddenly they like work
Together like he doesn't like lifelong relationships that are being formed
And then you go upstairs and people are up there for like an hour and a half and they're talking to each other in the mirror saying what color is that in
They're barely even talking to the people who work
You know work
What about 4 for women who don't who don't have access to those stores in the makeup is so cheap
Personal thing
I mean most of your customers are buying
The products without trying them on first
So how did you know that
People were going to be willing to take that lie
Waking part of it is by having a product philosophy
Sofia approach
Two content that
Facilitate
Is that leap of faith
What do you mean well I mean if we had you know a super high coverage Foundation
Product
Then that would require us to make
You know 50 shades
Or something or 55 shades
Is there something like that
Which would be almost like impossible to sell online
I would have a really hard time like shade matching myself if there were Fifty Shades of
Something like I would not know how to do that
But we can do is create
You know a product like boy brow that's super intuitive
It's super easy to use that doesn't deposit too much that
You know is sheer enough that it can span a wide range of eyebrow hair colors
You know this is something that
Facilitates that
Participation
You launched this company
In 2014
4 years on crystal how many
Employees do not have
Oh we have some changes every week cuz we have like five people starting week even this Monday
Now we're I think a hundred and eighty-six employees
At 150 showroom editors I think since that
First million or two million
NC funding you've raced more than 80 million the company is now valued
Add more than 300 million Navy close to
400 million-dollar
4 years
That's crazy
I have to imagine
Set the big Cosmetics companies
The L'Oreal
Estee lauder's
Are really paying attention to what you're doing and really want to buy
By this company they really want to own this brand I mean
You know you can go down the list Bobby Brown and and
You know some of these other
Iconic brands at work
Purchased by the larger
Brands
What happens if and when they approach you maybe they already have
So
The company is that I'm most
Admire are companies that create
Conic
Products
That really stand the test
The time
The other thing that I think a lot about is our mission
So I think about
How else can we connect people through through Beauty how else can we help people sit up a little taller feel better
How to solve
True beauty
We have a really long way to go
In in terms of
Actualizing the vision
In fact I think about where we are today as
Truly just the beginning
Like being 4 years in for me
I wake up everyday I
Think it's day one
And
Typically when you sell to a larger conglomerate
It's because
You need more District
Fusion
Because
Is the benefit of having
You know being a Loreal and Estee Lauder company
Like that that they have this vast network of every dealers
Macy's
And you don't need that
We don't need that
We create you know our own channel
Through our digital
Platform through glossier.com
And one of the things that were most fascinated by right now
Is the fact that this beauty shopping experience the
This experience of walking into a store and yet wanting to be connected to someone who you pick and then wanting to find it
Information
Through a person that you relate to or that you are inspired by or choose
There's really nowhere to do that online
Like you can go on YouTube but it's really like look
Space
It's really about kind of like I want to do a cat eye or I want to do
A unicorn
Halloween makeup or something like that
But in terms of finding that individual story for beauty
It's really really tough Somme
We actually just hired
The person who
Built
Idioms and
Camera Instagram
And then we also made another higher of the guy who was Employee nine Instagram who's an amazing product designer digital product is
Desiigner because we're spending a lot of time thinking
About how to create that digital
Platform that channel
Because you've already built these tools right but like where is the
Place where people can come together
To talk about beauty
T22 to share what they
Learn from glossier and
All the other brands and products that you know they use and talk about how can they find each other like they could do it our at our flagship
I have to imagine with a big house medics
Companies are looking at your
Customer base
Very young
Multiracial
Super coveted
Demographic that you've got
Hard to recreate right cuz there's a
Antissa T2 what you do and there's a risk of inauthenticity when you try to manufacture
Are you watching your competitors as well do you keep an eye on what they're doing
Well it's interesting because
Beauty is not that
Competitive in my mind because
How many different brands are we all using everyday like how many different lip products do I have in my purse right now you don't want to know
From like all all different brands like a different
Lip balms and lip glosses and lipsticks
And I'm not interested in like consolidating that
That is like not a realistic
Expectation
Of any of us
Like no single Branch can make every in meet you know all of your needs and it comes to
The beauty at least in my mind
So for us it's just about how can we be a
Part of this of this conversation
How can you be a part of facilitate the conversation happened
When you when you think about an end
Actually answer this earlier but
When you think about the Arc of your career and your
Still so young and you have so much
To do ahead of you may build two or three more company
Who knows
How much of wood
What's happened to you and what you've accomplished
Do you attribute
Your
Persistence hard work grit and how much to
Two till two lucky breaks
I think
I definitely believe in luck
But I don't
Rely on luck
And I don't attribute lock to
Where I am today I really believe that it
Is
A combination of
This passion in this perseverance
And
Probably a little bit of
Having a very short memory
I think it's such a gift
I just keep going
I think when you fall or when
Someone says no or when
I'm something you try something and it doesn't work
The ability to just
Continue
Might just pick up
There's a resiliency right like there's that's really what I hear the regret that's what it says to me is there is a resiliency to just
To just brush shake it off right and then keep going
Just One Last Cry
Question for you
If you were sitting in this idea
10 years
And you're watching somebody like
IQ
And you had a dream or idea in your head
What what would you have wanted to know what are you
What
What do you now know that
You wish you knew when you were starting out
I don't know I would use the Phil Knight quote from Nike of like
Just do it
You know I mean it sounds
Be courageous
Like be curious and be courageous
Because the worst it's like my friend says about dates
It's either a good day
Or a good story
And I think that's really good advice try things it's going to help you grow and learn
You know learn something learn something about yourself
I really do believe that
Emily Weiss founder of glossier
I spoke with Emily on November 1st
At the skirball center for
Performing Arts at NYU in New York City
And just a few days after that
Classy opened its first permanent
Flagship store in New York
Bury Saint address
Company was founded
I need space
Painted glossy pink
And is ready for the camera which means if you
Couldn't be there
You may have seen it
On your Instagram feed
Are episode was produced this week by Rachel
Falkner
Music composer
20 mareblu
Thanks also to neva Grant Jeff Rogers
Howard
Santa's Michigan
Our intern
Is Mia venkat
And look out for another live interview coming your way this
Thursday
On Thursday November 29th check out our necks
Next bonus episode from
How I built this Summit in San Francisco
It's my conversation with John Zimmer founder of Lyft
Oh and one more quick thing
If you want it
Actually attend a life
Taping how I built this
Pictures release date
Few more tickets to our sold-out La show
December 5th
Theater at Ace Hotel
I'll be talking with Michael Dubin founder of Dollar Shave Club
And you can grab those
View remaining tickets
By visiting NPR presents
Dot or
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform
Form used by more than 250
1000 cup
With mobile-friendly email
It's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days ago
Campaign monitor.