Support for how I built
In the following
Come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is
Is the place to be
Learn
Why by searching
Michigan pure Roberts
Everyone you know one of the things that I love
About Lisa price story
Isn't she was almost
Blindsided by her own idea I mean
When she first started making skin care products
She was putting them in the
Baby food jars and just selling them to friends at church
She did not
Think about
Turning it into a huge business
But the story of how it happened
The story of how she ended up creating one of the biggest skin care products for women of color
Pretty amazing
Oh and by the way Lisa is also going to be a
Speaker at the how I built this Summit in October in San Francisco witch
She's being supported by America
Express
Anyways this episode
Great one
And I hope you enjoy it
You're bursting at the seams and you can tack on
Comedy people and your neighbors are starting to look at you like what's going on in there I mean we were actually
Watched at one point for suspicious activity
Because they're you know. Just ringing the bell and going inside and they come out with bags like what school
Been there
Running PR is how I built this
Show about entrepreneurs idealist at the stories behind the movement
Adult
Surprise switch Epsom homemade body butter in her Apartments
Sold it at a flea market
And then turned it into one of the biggest Beauty Brands
Women of color
If you log onto carolsdaughter.com
You'll see
This beautifully polished website with
Dozens of hair products
Body creams
Butters oils
Treatments
All for sale
And you'll see this incredibly
Diverse range of women's well
All types of
Skin tones and hues
Curly-haired
Straight hair
And if you scroll all the way down
You'll see in small type
A division of L'oreal L'oreal
If you don't already know happens
Just to be the worlds
Largest cosmetics
L'Oreal buy Carol's daughter in
2014 for an undisclosed amount of money but
You can safely bet that it was
Sapore a lot
Big multinational buying another company
Bonnie Wright
Is that Carol's Daughter literally started and Lisa prices
Kitchen
A one-bedroom apartment
In Brooklyn
And if you haven't already guessed
It started out as a pet
Because Lisa already
Pretty cool
In the 1980s
Cosby Show
Which
Time of course
Wasn't get tarnished
Because of Bill Cosby
It was the hottest
TV show
In America
I thought that I had found the career that I was going to do for the rest of my life because
It was amazing
Experience it was particularly incredible being you know what
An African American woman
And
What that show
Meant to me and my family
To see
African American
Did in
You know such a
Positive light so it was something that
For me to be standing in the Huxtable kitchen
The morning of my first table read as I'm listening to
Do the cast read the script
Why I could have just
Float it off I mean
Presumably
You know
I guess looking for the outside one would think
This is going to be a career
Like this is what you're going to do with your life but that is not what
No it's not I could have gone on to Venice script supervisor
Production coordinator associate producer
Perhaps on the on the
Operational side of things
And if that is what I thought
I was going to be happy
I was
Ecstatic is Wonder
And I think
Because I was
Very happy
At what I was doing with work
When I had my downtime
I'm and I was not at work
I didn't have that desperate feeling that you
You feel
When you're like oh God I'm finally not at work and I just want to relax
I just want to veg out you know
So I've became creative when I was at home
How did the idea to
Start making beauty products
Even occur to you
Well what
Initially happy
Happened was I'm a huge Prince fan and have been for many years
And I read an article about him and in that article
They talked about how he always smells very good and the reason for it was
He kept
An assortment of fragrances on his bureau
And it was also rumored that he put
Chanel Number 5 in his boots
So that whenever he took off his boots
He didn't have to worry about his feet not smelling good wow I could I could see
Princeton
So
I just love this idea of this blending of fragrances
In creating these unique fat but you weren't thinking about the
Business no not at all
Like just to do for me
And that's what I began to
To do I learned that the way that your fragrance last
On your body
Is you layer it
So you wash with it you
Moisturize with it then you Spritz it on
So then I said well I don't I don't have moisturizers that
It smell like this where am I going to get that
And
At first I started
Using lotions that I could get at the drugstore and I would put
Fragrances into them
And and blended it it didn't work
That that was a
You know balanced from a chemistry
Prospective so things would just separate and be kind of messy
And that led me into
Looking into
Possibly making my own
And one day I walked
Consider this like
New Age kind of
Bookstore
And there was a book
Are essential oils and the Art of perfumery
And in that book
War basic
Recipes
PS4
I massage oil or cream or balm
So then I thought this
This is great I can make my own lotion
And
You know the recipes were very like barebones than
You know they use things like paraffin and lanolin which I wasn't too
Crazy about you saying I
I wanted to use
Beeswax in I wanted to find
Cocoa butter
I used the the skeleton of the recipe with in the book
And then I just started adding
My own combinations and tweak it you know if something came out runny or too thick or
Too oily or too stiff
So you are like a
Literally melting down cocoa butter on your stovetop and I'm like
Mixing oils together and then
Sing what came out
Yes
That's how you make body butter right you start to melt a bunch of stuff and mix it together
Yeah I mean
Today you couldn't get old going
YouTube DIY videos and and get a good head start but
He just kind of had to figure it out
This was this was like what that the late 80s or the early 90s
That was the late 80s
I began selling
Because I had actually gotten something
That
You don't look
Good and work
And my mother encouraged me to sell at a church flea market
In May of 93 when she was she was saying
Lisa this stuff is pretty good like your
You should sell this people might buy it
That that is
Pretty much verbatim witch
There you go I did not say I said really mommy do you think people would pay for this
And she said yes she said your Butters are good that you know my skin looks great and she was using it on my little brother
Sisters and
You know she said I think you should try and I remember saying to my mom I said Mom what am I going to put them in because
Cuz I just would give it to friends and family so I put it in tupperware Rubbermaid you don't
Think about a jar
And she said well we could use recycled baby
Food jars
I'm cuz my mom had adopted my baby sister Torah
Very recently so she had lots of baby
Baby food jars well and we you know boil them on the stove like how used to sanitize bottles
Back in the day
I put the cream in the baby food jars and made my labels by hand and I took them out to that flea
Market and I sold out
Wow what did you what did you call them
I called the company Carol's daughter I did have
A name
And
I called it Carol's Daughter
Because that's literally who I was
Is my mom with Carol and I were
Was her daughter
And the products that I sold I called them fragrant moisture butter
At the time
So you show me the screen Market by the way you are still a writer's assistant on The Cosby Show
Dislike your weekend
Side Hustle
No by 93
Cosby had ended
And I
I thought I was a freelance
Person
But it was summer
Television typically in New York
Was very slow
In the summer months
Because you your season would end in May
And your new season wouldn't begin until
I'm so unless you were working on a pilot
You were probably off
During the summer
And that first summer
Of
Starting at that Flea Market at the end of May
I spent most of that summer
Making money
Selling at different craft fairs and Expos
Some things like that
And I went back
To work that
What did you
How much money did you have to put into
Like watch this
That very first
Flea market honestly was an investment of $100
Between you know whatever the table rental was in
The ingredients that I had
The purchase to fill the baby food jars that I had and
Maybe some flowers yunnan
How to decorate my table
And what I did
I just
Khepri invest
Because I didn't
Have
Money that I could say oh well I'm just going to go pull 10000 out of my savings
To start this business
So it was something that started in a very small way of very organic way
And I didn't
Do anything that I couldn't afford to do
So if someone told me about an expo
In Georgia
That's fantastic and the fee to get in it's only $5,000
I wasn't going there
But a table
You know in Park Slope for 35 bucks okay
What who is who who are you
Customers in that first summer
They were mostly African-American women that you know where in the different neighborhoods that I was in
And I did have some customers who weren't African-American but for the most part that's who would come to my table
I was not deliberately
Who sang this is for African-American women I was deliberately saying this is for dry skin and subsequently
When you have more melanin in your skin
That dry skin will show
You look dull you look it up
As people say
Ashy
And you cannot get away from that
That's how I probably at that time
Ended up
With that audience
Of people
Who were more Brown
Because they found something
That took away that Ash
So if you if you
If you are African American women in the early 1990s
Essentially there was very few options it is really
Few companies that were serving
Arawaks
Yes
Very few
There was definitely
A community that needed to be served
Who was not nest
Sara Lee being
King served
It was it was not something
That you could walk into a drugstore and
And say oh look at that
Is fantastic great
It wasn't there
It is now but it wasn't then
So that summer of 93 when you were like selling
Body butter in baby jars
Church flea markets
Did you think of this as you know azure
Your future
Just thinking this is a fun little side project hang out with people I know and
I'm having fun
At first
I thought about it as
And then
Of that summer
I was watching an episode of the Oprah win
Official and she was talking to
Two people who had started businesses
With little or no money
One person said well
You have to know that you're passionate
About what you do you
You can't start a business just because
You want to make
A bunch of money
Because it's going to take too long for you to make any money and if you're not passionate about it you will quit
Before you make any money
And I remember thinking
I'm really passionate about this stuff like I I like
I like doing this
And then somebody else said
She would Define passion as
If someone woke you up out of your bed in the middle of the night
Would you go and do this thing
And I honestly could answer yes to that question and I'm someone who is very fond of sleeping and
My love
A good you know lately we've been kind of thing and I realized yeah I would get up out of bed to do this because I really
You do enjoy it
And
I remember sitting on the edge of my bed and saying wait a minute
Maybe this is
This could be a business
And
That day was the day that I realized
This just
Doesn't have
To be a hobby this can be more
All right so that first summer ends and you go back to a job and
And what happens to to the business to Carol's Daughter
It continues to grow
People
Call
And say Hey you know that I bought a jar cream from you
You know what such a
Can such street
State Fair
And I'm running out how can I get some more and I would look at
Get my schedule and you know if I knew I was going to be
Be home on a
Saturday as well
If you want to come by my apartment on Saturday I'll be
Be home I'm working the rest of the week but I'll be home on Saturday what time would you like
To come by
And that was
The beginning
Of people coming and shopping
In my
Apartment
And and that
Continue to grow
To the point where sometimes I would
I would come home
Tenacity Massachusetts
Someone didn't know that it wasn't an actual store
You know they heard about it from a
My friend and you don't answer
At home
So at this point
How did you get the word out about Carol's Daughter be
Because initially you are
Flea markets in MA
Rights for talking but how did you
Get more people to know about it
You know my my husband calls this the sister girl net worth
It was literally one woman telling another woman
And somebody
Always brought a friend
With them
And if you brought a friend
Do you know get a free gift
Doritos
Tell something off
It was all of that grass
Type of stuff
And
If I was out
Selling somewhere and someone asked me
About something
If I didn't know how to make it I figured out how to make
So I learned how to make bath salts I learned how to make
Body scrubs
Different types of moisturizer
There is I figured out how to make shampoo how to make
Conditioner
And it was it was just experimenting the way
You would experiment cooking
And what did you decide to
Leave TV and just
Do this full-time
I left television in 1996
Because my son forest was due to be born April 5th
Of that year
And
I realize that
If I continue to work
I would
Basically just give my paycheck to a baby
Yeah so it just
Logically made sense
To let the job go
And see if
In being at home full-time while taking care of a baby
Could the business grow enough
We also at the same
Time
We were able to
To change
How and where we live
So my aunt and uncle were
Selling their home
They were selling it to someone else
And
I think there was
Three tries
Ice at the closing and it just didn't happen
And I finally worked up the nerve
To ask
Is there any way that we can
Could purchase your home
And we did it and
So forest with
Osborne
March 18th of 96
And May 22nd of 96 we moved into
The home that we live in today
And it enabled us to
You don't have the space that we needed with a baby but also have
Space for the business to grow
And that was
That was a big Turning Point
You know it was
Huge difference
So many people coming in on Saturdays to shop
You know there was a time where you would be like oh hi Diane hi Susie hi Charles
And that was like I don't know any of
I never met you
The voice mailbox would fill up every hour and a half
My husband and I would you no wait
When did you last check the photo I checked it at 2:30 oh my God it's five
You don't let me get me a pen and paper
And if you just
You just look at it and you and you can't
You can't believe it Lisa Price
In just a moment
How I mention from Oprah
Crashed her company's website
Gyros near listening to how I built this
ER
Sports
PR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
These to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely answer
Securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecure
Launch your crypto portfolio to
And open app free
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online press
Vince and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with
Features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR
Car for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase
Just have a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Definitely should have started to focus on Carol's Daughter
Full-time
Things started to take off
Pretty fast
What was the turning point when did you when did something happen
Where you sat
This is like
Bedtime
Well because I've been in business
For 24 years
And because
Turning Point
And
Success
You know those aha moments
Are very
Relative
Fluid there's been
Several of those
So you know there was there was
The moment when my second son Ennis was born
I was in the hospital
I'm after having given birth and my husband walks into the hospital with
Essence magazine
And I was in the November issue
And I actually had a half-page article with a picture
And my name
Which was a really big deal
How did they know about it
There there were Beauty editors that lived in the Brooklyn neighborhood where I live
So
They were always in search of something different
And then because I work in television production
For so long and then my husband
Continue to in
And still does
I would have access to
2 makeup artist
And hair stylist
And
If they
You know went on another production
They could reach out to me and I let you know I could send it to them
I remember hearing that
Edie Falco love demoisturizer of mine because
A makeup artist that I worked with on his show
Shared it with
Get out and I was like
Jackie Chan
I've never met Edie Falco to this day but she she loved one of my moisture
Wow so so bye
1999 you guys were able to open up like an actual ShopRite
Yes
The first store that was not in my house
Brick-and-mortar retail space
They said had windows and a door
And
The landlord
Wanted the space to be something
Elf
And I sent him a gift basket
For his wife
Ana Package
With a letter about the bread
To convince him
That
My shop would be great
And that location
And because
Of my letter
He decided that he was going to give me a shot and he wanted to meet with me to go over
What's terms
So I'm sitting in this meeting feeling so Victorious I've convinced this guy that
You know my business is what he wants
Put in here
He's so he said so
The terms of pretty basic I'm going to need
4 month deposit on the rent
And Baba and he's like talking other things and I'm quickly adding in my head
And I'm like that's 14
Okay that's 14000
It's $14,000
Yeah
I have no clue
Where are we going to get $14,000
And dumb
It worked out
We had some small account set up for our sons for their college
And we took it you know my my boys were very very young
You know we took
It up between their two accounts aye I don't know something like $3,500
Out of the bank
And then one of my aunts
Loaned me
Little bit more like another four or five thousand dollars
Yeah it worked out it was it was a little little dicey at first
But it worked out and I paid my aunt back
Before Christmas
Best of that year it's so incredible to hear how $3,500
Excruciating excruciating my money when
Of course
In a within a decade you were going to be doing it
A hundred million stars
In in sales but at that time it was scary must have felt really scary
It was it definitely was
They think that that made it
Palatable was
I knew I couldn't stay in the house
Like you know you're at your
Bursting at
It seems and you
You can't accommodate
People and your neighbors are starting to look at you like what's going on in there this oldies
People that come in and out everyday
I mean we were actually watched at one point
For suspicious activity
Because did you know I was just ringing the bell and going inside and it come out
With bags like what's going on in there
And and and
We found out later when
You know the police off
Officer came to shop
And she cheetah she was like I just want to let you know cuz you probably didn't know this
SEL
Somebody made a phone call and someone was nervous and they
You don't realize that everything was okay
And there was nothing untoward going on but yeah yeah
You just get to a point where
You have to
To grow up in and you have to take that leap of faith in
I didn't want to live in
Well what if I had gotten the store
What if I had
What if you digest
And I would rather have had
At the store
Fail
Then to have wondered what
What did your mom think about
That store that first dortmund
Her name was was in the Marquee
What you think what you walked in there
She she she loved it but it but I will I will tell you the moment that she was like
Really excited about
The business being
Carol's Daughter
I got to do the Oprah Winfrey show
In 2002
And so she got to
See that
You know to see her daughter
On Oprah
And
All of her friends got
To see that
And
The place where she went where she would get her blood work done on a regular basis with
This Medical Center in Brooklyn called The Hip Center
At what was she what she say
Yes
With an illness called polymyositis
So when she came to get her blood work done after that Oprah Winfrey show
Ole Miss Carol was so happy to see you here come right in. The so-and-so is waiting for you
And then I'm going to take you down to the lab as soon as you're done
She said she was in and out of there so fast
She told me she's
Said yeah girl
Keep going on television I could get you
How did how did Oprah find out about you
Through the magazines and and the attention you were getting there
Getting me on to the show came through
Douceurs
And the producers of
The show heard about me from another producer
Who was interviewing for a job
She went to Chicago to interview for
Position
They talked about what they were working on
One and one of the shows was
A show about women who it started business
Is in their home
And she said to them will have you spoken to
Lisa Price
And they reached out
They liked what they heard they interviewed me like
6 *
A week later I was in Chicago taping
Michelle
And I was sitting in the audience
And
She looked at the screen and she sees the name of the store and she said
Carol's Daughter
Counter I know Carol's Daughter your camels I know,
And I'm sitting here like oh my God Oprah Winfrey knows man I'm going to die
How did that affect business
When it when it was on Oprah
It affected it in an amazing way
We
Pad
Our website
Go from having
People in it
And within four minutes
A segment the audience
In the website went from
You know whatever it was 30 something people to 17000
Wow
The website actually
Crashed
I mean it was remarkable it was just remarkable
Not anything
Crazy like not what not what p
People think
That you know
One day you're on the show and all of a sudden you're a millionaire and money is just falling out of your hands
Not that but definitely ask
Significant
Lift and shift
In
Who knew about us
But it was something that was manager
We didn't implode under
Did the pressure
Basically
From the moment you open their first store for the next
Decade you guys were dressed
Thomas massive
Grocery
That you were just like
Growing and growing and growing every year and opening more stores right
Well we didn't open additional stores for a very long time
I'm I'm I mean I I
I wouldn't describe it as a massive growth
Factory
There was growth each year
But I wouldn't describe it as
As master
I didn't open up another store until 2000
And in 2004 I took on a business
His partner
And then in 2005
Took on invest
And you guys had some
Some big deal invest
Jay-Z was an investor right
Yes Jay-Z Will Smith
Jada Pinkett Smith
And the investment
Help desk
Open up the additional store
I'm but also helped us
To get into
Two places
Like Sephora at the
Time
And then subsequently Macy's
It helped to build a better infrastructure
You know that there's there's definite
Excitement
You know pride and everything
Sing when you're when you're small and your grass roots and your building
But they're there comes a point
You know when you start doing a million a million and a half two million two and a half million in
Sale where
You can't wing it
You know like things have to be
Cure
And and that's when investment was definitely needed
Because
There there was some winning
That was going on and you can only do that for but so long
At a certain point I mean you guys were
I'm your revenues were
You know
In the tens of millions of dollars when you saw
Those numbers at the end of the year
Was that Strange Fruit
Did you could you have imagined
That happening I I can definitely
He say for certain
That I never imagined that happen
And even to
This day
I still
Am amazed by it
It's still surreal
And that's not something that ever goes
Away
And I don't mind
That I feel that way because I I think it keeps me grounded
And it keeps me focused on the work that I do
Because that never change
Regardless of
You know
40 mm in
Sales in a year
Or
28 million in sales
Elf in a year
I'm still doing this
Same work
Your mom Carol passed away
More than a decade ago
But when she was alive
What sort of role did she play in
Because I mean she
Did actually get to witness
She she did she
She did get to see
A lot what Mommy
Always
Did for me was she always focused
On the
Positive
So if I was calling her
And saying to her
You know Mom I don't know how I'm going to get the
These orders filled by
Christmas
They all have to ship by this date there's just so much I just
Is can't figure out
How to get it all done
And she would say
Well actually that's the easy part
And I said what do you mean
The easy part I just said I don't know how to do it like it's it's really hard
And she said but what if
If you didn't have the orders
That seems to me like it would be the harder part
Define make
People be interested and make people purchase she says you have the orders
You have their credit card number
As soon as you get the stuff made you'll get the money
So the money is just sitting there waiting for you
You so dad seems like it's
Easy she said I think we just need to clear our heads
Figure out
How to get it all done
And then she would say something like go make yourself a couple
Petit I'm going to make myself a cup of
Booty call me back I'm going to figure this out
And I would be like
Is she crazy
I would go make
My cup of tea
And come back to
To the phone and we would talk and I'd sit there with pen and paper
And we would figure out
A plan
And
I never let that go
I know that in 2014 you sold the company to L'Oreal
Was that
Difficult for you to
Sell this thing that you
Built out of
Apartment in Brooklyn or
How did it feel like a weight was lifted up
Beholders I mean that
United
One of the biggest cosmetic companies in the world buying your company it was not a difficult thing for
For me to do
At at all except for the fact that the
Process to get there is death
So it wasn't
Oh my God I have
Sell my baby
I can't I can't I can't
That
Emotion had already happened
Because
In mm
Seven Carol's daughter took on Equity partners with Pegasus Capital Advisors
So once you take on an equity
My partner
Your goal is to
Celtics
Strategic partner and everyone exits Happy Tails
I'm so
Having someone like L'Oreal
Acquire the brand
With something that I knew would happen
I always had
L'Oreal at
The top of my list and it did work out
And I was
Thrilled
And proud and
Because for me it was the culmination
Of all of that work that I had
I do to fix the mistakes that I made
In my comfort
Not trusting my gut often enough
Not
Valuing
What I brought
Table and not valuing myself
As of business
This person and as a smart woman and I had to
Find my voice
Again
And
So I got it back
I felt strong I felt
Power
And I stood with everyone else shoulder to shoulder
And guided Carol's daughter to that place
For us to have that app
Position so
I was very very high
When when L'Oreal bought
Company some of your car
Customers were disappointed
Because
He knows pretty I mean you know they felt that well this was
Company owned by African American woman
Now it's somebody that's big
Multinational
How did you as you respond to that one when when you heard that
It didn't take me by surprise that there were
With some backlash
I think the only thing that took
Took me by surprise was that some of the backlash
Was very
Personal
And very
Acquainted and
Very cruel
And just speaking about me in
In ways that I was
Like how do you say this about somebody that you've never met
More wow
That was
Surprising
But
What I realized
Was
People didn't know
My story
I realize that as
A group of people within this world African-American people
Historically
We have left
Experience with generational wealth
Stream ABC
Successful in certain areas we may have
Become
Rich recently
But we don't really know what generational wealth
Is
And we haven't
Come up in families
That have owned and passed down busy
So they were just things that people didn't know
And they wrote a narrative for me
On what they felt was appropriate and what they felt
Was something to be proud of and I didn't follow the script
And and I apologize for how they felt
And
And that I didn't follow the script that they wrote
For me but I used the Opera
Opportunity and still use it
To educate asbestos
Is possible
Cuz it's going to take us
Time to build that generational wealth
And then perhaps
Be in the place
Will we have the luxury of
Not having to
Yeah because we were able to build it on our own or we were able to build it
With Mom and Dad
Help and we can stay privately owned but it's going to take time to get there
But it it was
It was difficult
Sometimes it still is difficult because people still will bring it up and it's it's almost as if
I've been asked
To apologize
For one of the greatest
Accomplishments of my life
And something that I'm very very proud of a little girl in
From Bed-Stuy in Brooklyn
You get pretty well yeah pretty well
I did I definitely did
Better
Then I would have had Ike
Continue to have a career in television and film production
And there's a
There's a a very deep respect
That one ends up having four
Where they are where they come from and what they have
When you go through something like that
Emma and I just I just have a very very profound respect
For what I've done
And I won't be that person who
Runs off and buys plane
Cars and things like that because I have too much respect for how hard it was
Together
There
Lisa Price founder of Carol's Daughter
Even though L'Oreal pot
The company Lisa is still the public face
Carol's Daughter
And despite becoming financially
Secure for life
Lisa still lives in that
Same house
In Brooklyn
She and her husband bought
Back in 1996
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
If you're ready to start your new business
Make it stand out with a new website from Squarespace
Visit squarespace.com
Build it
For a free trial
Then use offer code build it
To save 10%
Your first purchase
The website
Domain
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
Time now for how you built that and today we're not be the story we ran just over a year ago from Hayden emmolo
She lives in Jackson Wyoming with her husband Jesse and
They're two dots
The Husky is yazz named after the baseball player and the German Shepherd is Tuckerman
And all four of them spend a lot of time outside its Jackson Wyoming so skiing fly fishing
Trail running hiking
The dogs love it the humans love it
Except for a small problem Tuckerman I noticed a cloudiness in it
Signs when he was pretty young like only two years old
And then we noticed Yeah Yeah Yeahs
Was getting pretty visible sunburn after we spend long days on the water
The sun is really bright
And that's what happens a lot of dogs
Carsense
Today after overexposure their eyes swell up
Dark Cloud over
And some dogs can even lose their vision
Soap to find a solution
Eden's husband Jesse started
Digging through their old ski equipment
So he just started
Chopping up goggles and came up with these
Retrofitted goggles for the dogs which
Please thank you
Plastic visor that got from
The Dollar Store take
3 olds
Ski goggles I'll put together with a jumble of straps and hair ties
I think I probably laughed out loud when we first put them on it's like this is this is ridiculous but
I guess you know I'd better a silly looking dogs in a blind dog
Waylon Jessi
She kept refining
Until
People started to ask
Hey where can I get those for my dog
But they weren't sure there was an actual market for dog goggles
So
They decided to ask an expert
Their vet
So he put the Prototype down and looked across
Table Odyssey said well
You're probably going to need some capital
And I looked inside
Yeah yeah I think we will
And he's like well
I think that's our next conversation
2 Gap their vet actually gave them some money
Enough money for Aiden and Jessie to find a manufacturer in China
And then launched their very first line
The lenses range from neon pink
Neon green a lot of people love the the crazy lenses just because they make your dog look like some sort of
Superhero robot
They make him look pretty badass
Let me talk to Aiden at year ago they had sold $10,000 since them
They've nearly doubled that they've also released for new models
Goggles so they can fit a wide range of dog sizes
And
She and her husband have quit their day jobs to work full-time on the company
Empty love to tell people that yeah
Funny I was just that recently died
College reunions and you know everyone's going around. I haven't seen you Drake new what do you do what are you doing
By isao make dog goggles
And people say what
Really I make dog god
That's Aiden emmolo of Jackson Wyoming xi'an Jesse call their company
Rex specs
If you want to find out more about it or here
Previous episodes of our show head to our podcast page
How I built this
Npr.org and of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build
NPR
. org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe at Apple podcast or wherever you get your podcast on while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us at Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
Our show was produced this week by Rachel Falkner was original music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to North Quincy Neva Grant
Sanaz meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
JC Howard
Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days ago
Campaign monitor.