Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
What was the year was the first Wikipedia entry
The earliest article that anyone has found was an article on the letter q
And it was very sudden you just be the first person to say Africa is a continent and hit save
And what's not very good wrong and it start
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they don't
The story of Hope Jeanne whale started
Online encyclopedia as a side project to grow into one of the pillars
Internet
Okay I'm going to read you the list of the top five most
Viewed websites
In the world
So number one
Is
Google
Then comes YouTube
And then Facebook
And then why do witches
China
The biggest search engine
And finally coming in at number five
Wikipedia
Imagine for a moment
That you are the founder of one of these
Websites
How much are you worth
Forbes
Annual list
And
Larry Page founder of Google sits 50 billion dollars
Mark Zuckerberg ageism out with about 70 billion
Each of the founders of Baidu are worth around 15 billion and the founders of YouTube walked away
What's half a billion each when they sold a Google back in 2006 and the founder of Wikipedia
Jimmy Wales
V
Most visited websites in the world
His personal Fortune is estimated to be not much more than $1000000
He is quite possibly
The least Rich internet Titan in the world
But I like a lot of famous founders
Entrepreneurs Legacy is likely to live on for centuries because he is in some ways
Like a modern-day Johannes Gutenberg
It's like Gutenberg Press made it possible to spread knowledge Beyond The Village or account
Wikipedia made it possible for every single person on Earth with an internet connection
To gain access to
Probably the biggest collection of knowledge ever assembled
Like a lot of the entrepreneurs we interview on the show
Give me Well story starts with influential people and important events that happened
Early in life
Grew up in Huntsville Alabama weather
Uncle owned a shop
It sold early
Computers
It is too big Hobbies word
Greenwood computers
And reading reading just about
Anything he found interesting
Basically anything I get my hands on her including
Simple all the time reading the encyclopedia
You know you
Hear about something and you want to learn more and you going to have sex
Find the article and read that
It was it was a beloved
Wikipedia move it all use it
Did you buy in the store or did
Did somebody like come to your house in the house
Dora Dora when I was a baby
As the family Legend goes that somebody came to the
House and sold it
To my mother
Every year that was send out an annual update
Yeah
For example the article in the moon was updated when someone
Landed on the moon
And so they they were all these stickers and you would
Take the sticker out and you would go to look up
Moon you would find
The old article on the moon and you put in the sticker saying there's an update
My mom and I would do that
My first editing in a second
Jimmy eventually went to college in his home state of Alabama
And he was really good at complex mathematics
So good in fact that
He went on to do a PhD in finance
Jimmy decided that he'll really wasn't the place
Vim so
He left to take a job as an options Trader
Chicago
What I was doing is really just trading like buying and selling everyday Arbitrage
Modeling
Prices of different things to each other to look for opportunities to
Find imperfections in the market in pricing
So while you were in Chicago and the early 90s this was also around the time the internet starts to become
People like browsing the internet did you get into that I was I was really
But even when I was before I came to Chicago I was really getting into the internet
So what I was doing I had no life I was I just traded in the day and then we go home at night
I was working on my own web browser
You were making
Your own web browser like on the side like in your apartment
Just like sort of self-taught
Yeah I mean I'm very quantitative data analysis things like that
Lunch program
I was a bad programmer by I can cook
I just remember very clearly
The day that Netscape went public and was worth as I recall 4.3 billion dollars
On the first day of training
And I have the
I've been convinced refused time that the
Internet was going to be really big and really important and really kind of fundamentally changed the world
And this was the moment when I felt like okay look the market is validating that like other people are singing at people really
Investing money here
And so it was a bit of a transition. But it was really in 90
Essay about 98 is when I left Chicago
And I moved to San Diego and that was when I really
Decided I'm going to focus full-time on my internet ideas and
What's Jimmy settle down in San Diego
He founded a small internet search company
I called Bahamas
And because this was the late 1990s
During the.com Boom
Company for paying top rate
Advertise on the website
It's over the next few years those at dollars made it possible for Jimmy to pyra small staff
Programmers
And they have the money to just
Experiment
The idea was really at that time this is
Pre Google
Remember
The best web directory around was Yahoo
And Yahoo hired hundreds of people to go around in index manually by hand index
Topics and categories on the web
I said we'll look maybe the community can do that maybe other people can help out and you
If you could get
Thousands of people involved
It could be really bigger than
Yahoo's doing that was really the thought
So we allowed people to come in and build
An index
To any topic
If they were interested
We call it a web ring
I remember one of the first community members
Came in and built
Webring about
Jupiter
Put it in with like
Okay that's cool that's right now course
We doubled in all kinds of things we had
A few blogs
I remember my
Business partner
The time was talking about
Building what
To that I would say
His idea was sounded a lot like Facebook
But it was really more about
People reconnecting with people from their schools and universities with a classmates.com
Kind of idea
But I'm keep in mind that
This was also where we
We started
Nupedia
The predecessor to Wiki
Tell me about that because why you're at Bahamas
List
This thing new pediagrow
What what what what
I said at that promise we were always
Experimenting
Thinking of new ideas a new car
Possibly new things to do
I was looking at
The model of
Open source software
Seeing that that work
I was also looking at
You know I promise we had community members who were building indexes to content they were in
Interested in
So the idea of nupedia
What's the best clear up
Look at that disable let's build an insect
PDF
Volunteers contribute to it
And I just thought you know this this seems like
Low-hanging fruit actually I remember I was in a quite a panic when I had the idea to hurry up and get started because I thought it was so
Obvious
So when I
Started nupedia I really thought that other competitors going to be out there but after
2 years it was still no one really competing with us because it maybe wasn't as obvious as I thought
And the idea was basically did just put a
Make an online encyclopedia
At the time
Really understand
Wiki
The concept of a website anyone can add it
And also
We had
You know what's 7 stage review process
Skin anything published
So how to work you would
You write an article for
Eupedia and then went through
Like seven stages before we published
Seven stages what I mean some of the stages had to do with first yet
Posey article
Qualifications to write it
We had
Some stuff so Larry Sanger was the editor-in-chief
And he would
It was a whole process
Where about you could apply
Me to submit something and so forth and then
It would be copy editing
Reviewers much like
Academic review where you send it out to
Experts in the field 4 review
And actually one of the things that
Was really a lightbulb Mama to my mind was
One of the first few articles that
Got through that process and was published we had it up on the web for
A few days I would say and suddenly it came to our attention somebody said hey this is really plagiarized
Oh and we checked into an acai couch
So like somebody just copied the encyclopedia
But it was
It was not good
I realized
Even with all this process we built up to
Prevent this
It was still plagiarism and that was a huge problem in the fact the only thing that
Revealed it was
More people reading
People singing This is actually problem
And that
There's an old saying in the open source software world that
Given enough eyeballs all bugs are shallow
I want that means
Oftentimes when your programming there's some kind of bug in your coat and you just cannot find it and if you get
Another set of eyes on it
Sensitive eyes it becomes very obvious somebody will Spot It
And so
That concept does actually apply in Watts
Areas of life
If you get a lot of people looking at something
People can say hey there's actually problem here that maybe nobody else noticed and then sometimes a fruit
Oh yeah that's kind of obvious
So I read that within a year after launching eupedia
You the site produced a sum total of
21 article
Doesn't sound like it was
Churning burning that was not good and in fact as we proceeded through that year
And I was very frustrated with the slow
Pace of progress
I decided to write an entry myself
But I just need to go through this process myself to see what's wrong with it or how can we improve it
So I decided to write
An article about Robert Merton
Because
I'd read all of this
Option pricing Theory
Special
Back in Academia
South qualifier
Enough to write a basic biography
I found it
Very intimidating
Because I knew that they were going to take
My draft
And send it out to the most
Prestigious Finance
Professors they could find to agree to review it and I was going to get
Feedback
And it felt really a lot like rats
Yeah and that was really the moment when I said okay look this isn't going to work like this isn't Fun
We really have to make this a lot easier and a lot more open
I really crucial moment
The moment I tried to get something
Through the system
So when do you work
Working on new PDI and you were like sending these draft articles around
I guess probably
You like all over the country
How are you collaborating
Well I mean this was the thing one of the problems that nupedia had
Is that
The only real
Way to collaborate back then was
What's the email around a word doc
If you emailed around a word doc
Then
The typical cases nobody responds for the worst cases five people
Responding to both change the document
In different ways and now you got to figure out how to integrate that all
You know the the concept of a Wiki
Which is a website anyone can edit
Was actually invented by guy called Ward Cunningham
Lovely great
Programmer
Wiki Hawaiian word
Which means quick tan
Collaboration
Intellij idea is that
There's a document on the web but anybody can come along and edit it
And save it
We were the first to really say hey let's use that tool
Building encyclopedia
Sogeti it was you would
Eat you find out about this
Wiki soccer Anythink
Alex democratizes process
Writing articles throw it up and everyone
And the entire Community will
What kind of cross reference in check-in
Well I mean
Equal or more organically than that we had a good-sized community of people
Who are working on new PDF
And so these people were
All very eager people who love the concept of a free encyclopedia for everyone and their own language that was a
A really exciting
Concept
And so initially we thought we'll let's start this as a tool for that community so
It'll still be nupedia but we're going to use this Wiki
As a way for that Community to begin to work together little more efficiently
And I made the decision
To put it up
Domain name wikipedia.com rather than
Keep it on nupedia
Because we weren't really sure like
We have a lot of academics and although very serious people on the mailing list
And seemed a bit
Have a crazy idea and we thought they might find it offensive
And so we said okay let's just set up on a different domain and see what happens but of course
The history is that
Wikipedia very very quickly outstrip nupedia
In terms of the content created in the quality and everything else
I should know this
To me but I don't what was the
What's the first
Wikipedia entry
Unfortunately
There was no history kept of the very early days
The earliest history was lost
So don't really know that the earliest article that anyone has found
I was an article
On the letter
Q
And
I'm sure that was not the first article in Wikipedia I know the first words and we can
Wikipedia
They were hello world and I know because I typed
And then I started doing list of things
So I guess you laundry
Wikipedia in January of 2001
Nupedia still
In like two weeks you had more articles on Wikipedia the new pedia generated
Previous two years
That's right yeah yeah of course as you mention earlier that
Summit County warrants
It was a pretty minor achievement a month since but it wasn't a opener
It was like why we got this great community and
People just started right in
Making articles on various random things and
Other people editing them
And
Is lot of pent-up
Excitement about
Let's just get started building this isn't the the change
From really this
Huge very intimidating process
That was not very collaborative to being able to say
You know and it in those early days it was very sudden you just be the first person to say
Africa is a continent and hit save
And what's not very good
But it's not wrong and
It's a start. That was very thick
Vvid that you could actually
Chainsaw
This is all being run out of
We're like
Did you have an office in San Diego or was it your apartment or what
Small office with this was during the Obama stay so we had
A few programmers and
Cheap office in a warehouse
Space
This is the period of time when ad Revenue was good
So we were able to just
How some people get started
I guess you very quickly realize that Wikipedia is canopy
Can potentially be
You'd like it seemed clear like within the first
Months of year
Yeah it did it did I mean it
Remember looking at a list of the top websites at the time
And there was an encyclopedia reference kind of site at ranked at number 50 and I thought
See if we do a really good job we might be
Number 100 or maybe even in the top 50
But there was always this idea of like this could be a big thing
If we can figure out how to do it you can have a huge impact
In just a minute
When Jimmy Wales was faced with the question of how Wikipedia was going to make money he decided
And it wasn't
Play with us
I'm guy Raz
How I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor game
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees
But annuities can be a smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns game Bridge
Aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital Xperia
That replaces fine print and phone tag
Nike with clear conditions and a direct loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Game Boy
Is not available in Austin
States
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed from the tech IPO Lansky
Two China's economic Outlook and much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple Pie
Cast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
Gyros
In the early days
Jimmy Wales was able to get WIC
Wikipedia up and running
And he was funding it with money you from
His first internet startup
Thomas was run
Ads
The.com boom was in high gear but then of course kmvt.com crash
And all that add money
Get dried up pretty fast and vomits would eventually have to shut down completely
But at the same time Wikipedia was growing
And Jimmy had to figure out how to keep it growing without a lot of cash
There was no money really to support Wikipedia but it didn't cost a lot of money it was really community-driven
And so
One of the reasons that
Wikipedia
Became a huge success I would say
Ironically is
The lack of funds
Because
If I have had the money if I'd gone to Silicon Valley and convince somebody to
Give me millions of dollars to start this
Then your natural instinct if you have any problem on the site
Is this okay we just need to hire some
Moderators
And we're going to make decisions when I have stuff
Members who decide things
And instead it was no money we couldn't hire anybody so as a community working together we had to
Firearm Solutions
We had to say
You know what are the software Solutions we need to be able to control for vandalism and then
Imagine we have a really really tough editorial decision
Have to make how do we make those decisions
All of those things
Happened
Because there was no money to hire anyone
Our people
Prevented the rise of
Amor natural
Set of solutions
And who was managing it was
Is it just you
And Lori Singer
The two of you
Yeah I mean we had other employees who were helping out
And this and that
You know it's basically we had to think a lot about
How to glue the cleaning the right direction you know there were a lot of really complicated questions around
Okay when do we ban people
When do we block people from editing when I when do we think
They've gone too far and a lot of the editorial policy
You know you have questions like
To what extent do we allow peep
People to write essay
Commentary
Decor
Put jokes in article
Neutral
Point of view is like Ark
Core belief and so on
But all those decisions had to be made and they were made
In discussions with
Community in
You must have known to me at this point
And just wanted them to that
Wikipedia was growing supervisor
And it was going to be
Could potentially be
Huge
You decide a r I guess around 2000
Basically create a nonprofit organization
Wikipedia what was that
The thinking of
Why'd you do that
Set a review things going on there so
First of all
This was still the depth of the.com crash
There was no obvious business
Smaller
The community of volunteers very much wanted it to be in a non-profit when I thought that had to be
Taken
Consideration
And it finally for me it just made sense like it was
Aesthetically it just seemed like the right thing that Wikipedia my ambitions for week
Wikipedia
To become a really important
Moments in history in a really important cultural contribution
Really made a non-profit I'm a much more sensible option in India
You know I think if we'd gone in a different route
It would be very different
You can interview
2 /. What's it like. And you said
Imagine a world in which
Every single person on the planet
Is giving free
Access to the sum of all human knowledge
This amazing idea
But I wonder
Why you could not have done that same thing
And still
Cats on Wikipedia
Yeah I mean so here's the thing
If you think about the
DNA of any organization
It's very difficult to
Stop an organization
Shin from following the money
Wikipedia is a non-profit
And as a nonprofit We could run ads
No legal prohibition on nonprofit
Running ads is that as a means of support sure
Yet
Cuz the organization tend to follow the money then suddenly inside the organization people would start carrying a lot more
More about art
Traffic in
Highly developed
Advertising marketing
We would begin to care more about which
She does your reading
Because if you're reading about
Queen Victoria
Differently very little to sell to you and there's probably the ad rates are very poor
If you're reading about
Tesla cars or
Vacations in Las Vegas
We would have an incentive to start creating content
That would drive higher ed revenues which
Just really not
What we wanted to wear in a second
PDA we don't think about adding
Features that might drive
Pageviews
For traffic we just think about how do we make the encyclopedia better and how do we reach more people
Tickling the developing world
That's just like fundamental
What this is all about
So when you basically said rights nonprofit
We're not going to have any advertising
We're going to it's going to be use regenerate
Content how do you even
Fun
How we going to get the money to even funded the pain the servers and
Yeah well what happened was the main reason that
We went ahead
And set up the nonprofit was exactly thinking of that
For the future but I had no idea
Whether it was going to be
Set up a nonprofit in June and
At that time we were running on
Two or three servers
Bento
Then we had this
Disaster was a Christmas Day when
2/3 service
Crashed and I had to scramble to get the site running on one server
It was painfully slow and so forth
And it was clearly obvious.
Because the traffic kept doubling that we were going to have to buy a bunch of servers
And so that was the first time that
I decided to do
Fundraising
To ask people on the site to get money in
These days we call it crowdfunding and it
You know
Everybody knows it but back then it was not a normal way of doing things
I remember very clearly that I had hoped
To raise about $20,000
A month's time
But in about two weeks time we had raised nearly
Sofia the First
Fundraiser was
A huge success
Some people really
Said hey Will
This is great we really want to support this and so
Lot of small donors net
Of course today is the model
Wikipedia.
People
Who believe in Wikipedia who think it's useful in their lives
Site
Hey I should chip in
When did you soap soap Wikipedia really kind of started
Blow up in
Early 2000 when did you
When were you first sir cognizant of that when did you realize that
Wikipedia was
Becoming really big like part of the
National conversation
I think they were there a few moments but I think one of the most important ones
There's a guy John siegenthaler Junior who is a very esteemed journalist
Kia
Call me
Complain about it
Entry
When was this
And
He said hey there's a problem because
Wikipedia says that
I was briefly suspected of
Having something to do with the Kennedy assassination of this is a man who
Was one of the pallbearers at Robert Kennedy's funeral
If I remember the story correctly so big friend of the Kennedy family
And the store was absolutely untrue
And
Muncie
Called
About 10 minutes
To get that fix
Extend and change them we looked into how it happened and so forth
A problem resolved but then he wrote this scathing editorial in USA Today about the site
And it got a lot of attraction
That story so we had this
Really big thing in the night
They tracked me on CNN to yell at me and Sophie
Suddenly we're in all the Press everywhere
Are traffic
Really
Exploded
Because of all the news coverage so that was the
That was the upside but that's not the way you want it to explode
But in the end that was actually a mama.
Important for us how come why
Yeah so this this lad in the community to a real reflection on
Quality on sourcing this is when we
Came up with the biography of living
Persons policy and really started to say look if it's
A biography of a person
Then anything negative in the article really needs to have a good quality source
Because
That's just not acceptable to have
Negative things about people that
Aren't true
Became quite Vigilant about that I'm after intercourse is always
Possibility of
What is happening and so forth and it does happen
But the queen is very very
Vigilant about it
Keep anything like that out of
Is music is Wikipedia on a day-to-day basis everyone is I use everyone
Use it use it
I remember that time
John seigenthaler article
Umpr we were not allowed to use Wikipedia as a source and it wasn't
NPR news organization
Wikipedia is not considered a reliable
Sorts and it just shows you sort of
Yeah well I mean
Think that should
It still be your pillow
Wikipedia is
Quite good it is definitely not perfect then what all we say is
Wikipedia is the place to go to get the
Questions are the answers
It's the way to get yourself oriented in the contacts
And I always say
You want to talk page
Age of any article and see what are the wikipedians struggling with
If they're saying
GE you know this source is this and these sources say that in the
Has to be complicated that might be the most inches
Question you can ask
Let's get to the bottom of this
Is there conflicting information out there
And also you know
If you want it
Use
Wikipedia as a starting point then
You can always go to the footnotes and go to the actual source and that's why
What you should do
I just cannot imagine
Running
This volunteer
Organization with hundreds of thousands of Millions
To work voluntarily editing
Syttende
Did you ever just like get you so
Don't want to do it anymore
It's not really a nice thing is
I remember the very early days I would get up at night and check the site cuz I
Was convinced that somebody's going to come in and trash it overnight which never happened and then quickly I realized
Oh yes Vandal did show up at
3 a.m. my time last night but guess what somebody
It was an uncommon remember was up in Australia next week
Problem it so you can understand like communities do inherently scale I think
That is part of
What helps me not
We are one body
So we're now in this phase
The history of the internet
People fake news in like that term
Chinese reasons but with so much
Information
Looks real that's
Real human history
But now because there is so much information available
Sometimes difficult
Discern what's real and what's not and I
And I wonder whether
One of the challenges
Wikipedia is
Reasonable people are disagreeing about
Basic facts
How do you reconcile
Adam
Is Wikipedia a deal with that
The elements 01
When we think about the quality of sources
That's a really core
Sitting in Wikipedia and we have a lot of
Discussions and debates tonight I think a fairly sophisticated approach
The thing about the sources
I agree with you I don't like the term fake news but the original use of the term was really about
Clearly
Completely made up website
Look like news sites
With no concern for the truth with outrageous headlines and so on
Those kinds of sites have had almost zero impact
Wikipedia because
Wow
They might do well to share on Facebook
Something that comes from a publication called the Denver Guardian because
It looks like a new site and Denver everybody knows Denver's a city in America and
Guardian sounds like a newspaper so
Wikipedia's would take one look at it and say
I've never heard of that
Paper
That stuff doesn't really get into Wikipedia
A broader problem that I am concerned about is
Right now that the Trust in Media
In the US but also around the world
Really at an all-time low
Peanut butter
It's a tough problem and I think it's a societal problem to say
Look we really do need quality information most people are very passionate about
Wanting to be told the truth
Yeah you know that the best way to
Prepare people for
Authoritarian rule is not to indoctrinate them into an authoritarian philosophy
But you make them believe that there's no such thing as truth
And that's that's a trend that I'm not happy about
How many did you know how many weeks
Wikipedia pages that are today in English
Green apple
There's just over 5 million
So
So total probably
In all languages
40 million
Close to 50
+ 250
Do you know do you know how many people contribute to
Wikipedia
Around the world
It's something around 75000
People every month who make at least five edits
It's probably three to five thousand
The core community
People who are making
100 mm or at it
And so that's
Unwanted people but it's not as many people as some might think
Dark Horse
Making 5 edits
In a month
That's not a huge amount of participation but you're pretty you know you're around
A lot more people who just make one it a year
But in terms of a real Community it's probably that
75 South
Jimmy what
Motivates
People are few hundred thousand people to
Donate
Hundreds of hours of a Time
Every year
For free
To do this
Yeah I think it's two things
So
First you know the mission
Free encyclopedia
Everyone in the world
Is meaning
You could spend your
Hobbytime playing
Grand Theft Auto
Doing something else and the world wouldn't be any better off when you're done and
If you spend a few hours editing Wikipedia
You can go to sleep and think yeah it was productive
The world is a little bit better than it was
And someone somewhere will benefit
That's great
Evan also just fun
People you get to meet people are interested in the things you're interested in the motor house
School
Ethos of the community is to say
Look no personal attacks
We're here to discuss
Content
If you go on the discussion page for
A controversial
Protopic
You're not there to just debate that topic
Can do that lock the place on the internet what do you get a Wikipedia
A debate about
How do we improve this article
And that's just a refreshing kind of feeling
That's a lot of people really find it
Suits their personality
Do you do you know what the revenue
He is like angry at me for
Wikipedia from donations
Yeah Revenue I should know the number exactly off the top of my head but I don't but I think last year
Was around 85 million dollars
Just from donations
Primarily from small donors
That's important understand that
When the community gets together to debate something about what they want
Have Wikipedia say when a policy should be
There's never a question of will what will the Thunders
Yeah
Over the years we've really tried to run the organization in a very financially conservative way
Every year we try to build our Reserves
A lot of our donors one of the things that they really want
From Wikipedia is that
Wikipedia be safe
You can soak
That rises to say okay
They don't want us to run on
They don't want us to run
Nearly a break-even of nearly going broke every year we need to be stable
And that's been a real value
When you think about
This
Thing that you built
And your role in the house
History of
The internet
How much of of the success of
Wikipedia do you think it's because of
Your Brilliance in your hard work and how much
Do you think
Vlog
Huge amount
To the lock
Brilliance and heart
Work okay maybe not so much I do think a component
Of the successor
Wikipedia is that
I'm
Very friendly and nice person
I'm very laid-back and so therefore
I was able to work in a community environment where
People basically yell at you and you just have to kind of roll with it and
You're in some sense a leader but
You can't tell anyone what
Do the volunteers so you have to work with
I love and reason
Move people along in the interviews
So where do you think that
I am not
Irrelevant to the process
But I also think that
You know the community is amazing
And the luck
The timing
Really
Kidding that moment when
It was possible
Ulta Bill Wikipedia
Jimmy Hughes
Scene
The estimate
That
And that if we can pedia wore a for-profit
It
Could be worse
At least
5 billion dollars
Maybe more
Does it mean anything to you
No not really I mean it's
People
They love to write about Jimmy Wells is not a
Billionaire
And does it actually the articles without headlines
Exactly an infirmity that's all a bit odd because
You know my life is
Unbelievably interesting
I have the ability to meet almost anyone in the world who I want to meet
Wells founded Wikipedia
On the largest chain of car dealers
Across the southern part of America whatever like not that interesting
God I do I do think that
Remember me remember Wikipedia
And that's really really something I mean that's something that you can really hardly even get your mind around
Comparisons to the Gutenberg Press right this is the biggest of dissemination of knowledge in modern world history
Well yeah but I don't know it's been embarrassing to talk about it that way
Jimmy Wales founder of Wikipedia
Oh wait a few years ago Jimmy got grief for trying to change his own Wikipedia
A big No-No is entry showed he was born on August 8th 1966
Which is what his birth certificate also says
But it was a mistake because according to his mother Jimmy was actually born
Shortly before midnight on August 7th
Only to be confronted by Angry Wikipedia editors who demanded documentary evidence
Which of course he could not finish because
All he had to go on was his mother's version of when it happened
And please do stick around because in just
A moment we're going to hear from you
About the things
Your building
The first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Swell investing
Its impact investing platform that identifies high-growth companies solving today's
Biggest Environmental
Social Challenges
Claim your $50 bonus
Swell
Investing.
Cam
Built
Thanks so much for
Sticking around
You built that the story starts almost
20 years ago
When Florence Wonderwall was working in fashion
Helping to pay
Clothes that models wear
Which sounds like a pretty cool guy
But I was not happy with the work itself
I really was missing the creative
And the designing of things Florence was missing designing
Things because well she's a designer
She grew up in France
And then move to Atlanta where she did that fashion job
What you want
Start something
For herself
And I need to create a company you I need to do something that's going to come for me I was going to cut into some kind of a spy
And Florence was looking around for something to in
Spider her and as it happens
Her mom was working in
Peru at the time
And what her mom invited Florence
Send a friend to come visit
We had no idea
What we were going there for
But we exploring what the locals we're making into
Business that could be done with that
Susan were exploring the local markets
In Peru and they can't process
Finger puppets
You probably have seen them be little
Cute animals made out of yarn
People have been doing this for many years
And for some reason they're really like we just fell in love with him
Sofa Ronson Suzanne
And bought a bunch
Church of the puppets and they started to sell them in Atlanta
And they did pretty well
Cat thinking
I don't really want to sell someone else's work
I want to design my own thing
I was thinking what is it that children really want what is it that children like
Like when I was
A kid what is it that was confirming my more
Most vulnerable moment
And so he was really
This dog is little companion and I thought
I could really turn this thing into a doll
Seth Rollins design her own doll
And she took those designs
Back to Peru where she gave them to artisanal Knitters to get one for her the first.
You said it was too traditional in Alexander was narrow and then the arms and the different shape to it and I really want
Wanted to do something modern
Chapter three years
Of working with different Knitters
Peru
Florence and Susan
Finally had a doll
They were ready to sell this really cuddly
Squishy
Creature that's needed and so you get a sense that it could have been
Done by your grandmother however
The look of it is really modern the dolls are stitched
With these simple and
Clean lines
And they got these long arms and legs
Generic as a dog and a Frog bunny
In 2003
And Florence decided to name them
Bla bla dolls and it's just so playful
Really works for kids company and as soon as I said it's another that's it that's it
Grecian actually launched boutiques
Across the US
Became interested
End table dog even started to appear on
TV shows like Homeland and in Celebrity magazines
They became so popular they inspired copycat and wow blah blah is still relatively small
Lawrence and Susan say they are now considering bringing in an outside investor to help scale the brand
And they're in talks about doing a possible
TV show they have a life of their own that we
We confusing them it's so it's a really beautiful story
By the way
Totally coincidentally
During a recent slumber party at the
Arroz household
Several of the boys have been to bring along their favorite stuffed animals including at least
Three lovely dolls
You want to find out more about blah blah check out our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org
We love hearing about
Things your building and thanks so much for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or his previous
How I built this. Npr.org
Please also subscribe to our show at Apple podcast
Or however you get your podcast
You can also write us or email addresses HIV ta10
Npr.org
My Twitter address is at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman run teen Arab Louis
Compose the music
Thanks also to novigrad sanaz meshkinpour Thomas Liu and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is newer could see I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this from
NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email templates drag and drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week