Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
You come back to
New York
$300,000 worth of orders
How are you going
That was a big question I didn't know what I didn't know
I didn't have any Financial education
I didn't even have an accountant at the time
So I went to
All the banks I could and I got turned down by 27 of them
7 bags
Yeah
NPR
How I built this show about entrepreneurs idealist stories
Waiting tables at Red Lobster to buildings
What are the biggest hip-hop clothing brands ever created
Dress with any
There's some disagreement over what am I
Tell you but
By and large
Lots
Some people will say that hip hop
Was born in
The Bronx probably in 19
The center of Hip Hop
Foremost
The decade
By the early eighties
Hip hop center of gravity started to show
Queen
Physically a neighborhood in Queens
Call Hollis
Neighborhood
Who are some of the most influential
Hip hop grew up
Russell Simmons
Cool J and
And of course all
3 members of Run DMC
Remember their song Christmas
How is gyro
The favor
Acacia Hollis
Kind of crucial to understanding how Daymond John
Was able to build a global brand of hip-hop
A friend
Started from the trunk of his car
Because it's
Hip hop culture started TX
Explode
So too did demons little clothing label
Bull called boo boo
It's a brand that
To date
Has sold over 6
Billion dollars
Apparel note today
You might have Daemon as one of the sharks
Shark Tank
Confident
Smart
Trust
But you might not know about
Childhood in Hollis
Challenges he faced
Very early age
Right around my
About 11 years old at 12 years old my parents separated got a divorce and I would never see or speak to my father of ever again so
So you haven't seen your dad
I did not
And so it was just
You and your mama
Just me and my mom struggling trying to work it out
And how does she make a living
Obama is an executive assistant so she worked for Lehman Brothers
American Express
As you have her little side hustle she would probably
You know so close and try to sell them
Shugo and open up volume
You know maybe a little kiosk at a flea market and buy goods and resell them
So mama do a whole bunch of
Things such as that to make some extra hands me but you would also just
Mainly be a secretary or exact
You're growing up
Bncollege
Listen to late 70s
Pleiades
It was kind of a tough
Neighborhood
Did you feel
Paranormal
Childhood
I fell save it was a great time it was or what I think is the last of those old-school neighborhoods where everybody knew
Each other in
You know you know all the kids have to go inside before the lights came on on the
On the street lights I mean my mother used to always say I have to be either
Faster than the Concorde go faster than the
The lights on the Empire State Building in
And the reason was that
The Concorde Woodland
Approximately I think 7:50 or 7:30
You know during the night
At JFK so when we all the kids her the ground
Rumble
Because the Concorde Landing you had
Do you have to be
Be in the house by the time that rumbling
Stop
But during the winter months when you know it is still landing at late at night but yet it was getting dark at 5
As you say you need to be home by the time you see the lights come on on the Empire State Building
So it was very
Great Community you know a lot of barbecues and cookouts and and fun stuff like that but
That would all change around 86
I-87
Or we stop feeling safe when
Trackside is a devastating
You know our neighborhoods and we would start hearing of death
Send
And things are nation that maybe that's because I'm
At 16 or 18 years old and up
You know when I'm driving and I'm seeing more of the world but also crack was starting to devastate
Every neighborhood across
The country
So how are you living
In the neighborhood environment where
You got the crack epidemic
Friends who work
Getting caught up in
Selling drugs in
How are you able to
I do voices
I wasn't someone analytical and
I remember doing the math one day about you know if I would have work at McDonald's in about a sell drugs over the course of five years where
When I make more money and it look
Like I'll make my money
Because if you look at the drug dealer who
Has to pay for all the attorney fees and everything else every once in awhile to get
According to be out of five years if they had this
Just stay in jail
Two and a half
But three of those years in the wind and then you have to look over your shoulder and you end up dead
Maybe dad then how
And they have no medical how much really would they bringing home how much are they letting so I look for that nice a long
I'd rather working me down
Yuan
Dedicated to you
Dream about
The things that you
The kind of person
Early on in life I really dream that I wanted to be maybe a pilot
I really didn't know what else I wanted to be in life you know I had no idea
Until rap music really started coming around and I figured I wanted to be
Working and rap music and but I didn't know how to do that if I couldn't wrap Sam dancer
Reproduce I really do know how to do that I try what I could dance a little bit I actually did do some kind of dancing hope
Run DMC your
What LL Cool J Russell Simmons with discover me
At one point I did get an offer
To dance
For a group name Houdini
And my mother said no way in the world are you going on
It sounds like you were
A pretty good kid
But you didn't really
Ravel
No I
I think I may have one or two arguing
Maybe I'm a bit maybe now I'm 49
I've had three arguments with her and 49 glasses
Probably
Yeah probably
Two of them were
When I was in my
Did you
Was
Was College ever something
You
I did I did consider now but I'm dyslexic
And reading all week
Challenge science and math no problem I can do in my sleep
That was a challenge and I said to myself I'm going to take off one year
Neil getting out of
Are the school lights
Take off one year
And that one year became
5 years 10 years
So are you doing in that in that
And that time I was working here and there but I also was
Farting
Do you know dating as many girls as I could you know the normal
Kid thing you know
18 to
I turn around again I looked I said I don't have anything
And not only do I not have anything
I don't even have an education to fall back on
So
Again looking at all the friends I lost
And then talk about all this all the kids I thought we're not so bright but yet they were coming back from college and I was away
Waiter in Red Lobster serving them
And I said maybe I'm the idiot here
You are waiting at Red Lobster
I was a waiter yet
I was having a great time as a waiter but I was also learning from relapsing you know they will issue these Corley books on your nose
Are there pianos basically what was working what wasn't working I was
Do you know learning how to serve people reading their quarterly p&l
When you were later I mean
How many Waiters
Red Lobster any company
I don't know but that's not my problem I was reading it
So you are clearly
Thinking of
If you are waiting tables
And you're reading their quarterly reports in there
Piano Tiles like
You're doing this because you have a plan
Did you have a play
I didn't know what the plan is going to be but I neither just like working out every single day and just like anything else trying to educate my
Myself I had the
Ability to put
Various different things in my body or my mind you know drugs and rock and roll and rap music and drinking all the
How productive I was going to be later on or I can
Can put in
P&l statements in listen to Tony Robbins and listen to Jay Abraham and
Think and Grow Rich in the 7 highly effective habits of whatever no people
Tony Robinson reading
Stephen Covey
All day
All day everyday that's what I was going to
That's when I was 16
And it's not that it was easy it got darker and darker and ugly and all that I question myself and say that I am I doing
On the right thing am I on the right path cuz I bet of the day I saw that I just wanted to be
Someone who can take care of their family and have a decent house in
I wasn't sure what kind of business I was going to have if you was going to business be a business at all but I wanted to have a steady income I didn't have an address
You know just be roaming the streets
And how does this idea of making
Apparel
Google how does a
What's
Story
Well
Show
The funny story is that I will talk about that with my girlfriend at the
The time I was living with all
A little bit older than me she was 30 I think I was 20
Think she works
For America
Express in one of them
And very supportive but I would give her my ideas old timing
And I remember
She would laugh at some of them
And then one day I asked to borrow $800 and I asked her to borrow $500 i d i had call Fubu
And she said no
I would leave her after that of course
I left her after that
Remember maybe about
15 years ago or something she she's so my friend but she came to my office and she
She heard my secretary talk about my houses and all the type of stuff that
We have to take care of from a financial standpoint in the wire the money and she was like
You still want that $500 or Fubu
But that was a super a person
Okay so hot
How did you come up with the idea for Fubu
Show
You know we was I was spending so much money going out and buying clothes that
That that the Hip Hop Community love
To buy and they could be
Ski jackets Timberland boots whatever the case is and we start to hear rumors that you know
Clothing Cummins apparel, just didn't want rappers African-Americans inner-city kids whoever
They don't want people wearing their clothes
But what I saw to get fed up to hear about all these type of Brands and I want to create a brand that love them
I respected the people who loved and respected hip-hop and I called it fool
For us by us for us
And you so what it was the
The first
Barcode clothing
Well I didn't make anything at first be very honest when I first did I got a bunch of labels and I just went and bought a championship
I just put
My fubo on top of the champion cut labels printed that's a FUBU owner
And I just warm on top of my championships just because I wanted somebody to say I didn't want any weight even though it was mine
It was just one shirt
It's not like I can resell it to somebody cuz this is us $3
What the championship
Shirt for $30
I just tagged all the clothes I have
And then I I saw to see this hat that was on on a lot of these rappers and it didn't look like it was made by
Amazing clothing company and they look like a
A ski cap not with a ball on the top with a little tied like a string on the top
And I I knew how to make those my mother showed me how to make those
Because the first one I bought was about $20 and went all the time and had and I couldn't find it anywhere when I finally found if you had
The cast of tolls I pay $30 for this thing
And I showed my mother that had she said you know you can't afford to just
You pay that kind of money for something you can make for
$2
Anaheim
She told me to go to the store and get some fabric
I went to so I got $40 worth of Erica came back
Sore bunch of hats and now all of a sudden
I wasn't thinking from a commercial
Standpoint yeah
What about the same role of fabric so I have now this big roll of
Stripes fabric
And I made a tea hats
So I decide to go
Stand on the corner and sell them
So you brought this roll of fabric home
And what
You like cut-out patterns and
Still really easy you know about the pat it wasn't even bad it was just a straight square like the square you fold it over
Isa one side and then you
You flipping in now so and then you sold on the top and you tied a string on top
You're done
You just have to sew a straight line
It was one square with one straight line
And then you just
Ties on top and
There you go you had the same exact look
It was like making the bike taking a sleeve
Right and folding it in half and using the part you know and then putting on your head and the top is open
Can you just tile a string
Those just like
Those are really
Popular
Big Lots of
Play classic hip-hop artists whose kids were wearing those cuz hat
Yes and nobody and no major corporations making so there's no place to find them so where do you find them
With guys like me so I'm on the street corner
So I made 80 of them
It took me probably about
3 hours meat of them and I hit that I hit that street corner and I sold all of
Do you know a lot of people don't know a lot of people maybe listen to this and they may not live in a
Condensed area but trust me
Outside my house I went to the shopping area
Nassau coliseum Mall
What people actually going into shop
So I quit people are they walking in that mall and all of them
By standing on the corner
End
Did you do the hats have
Fubu
The food label on them at that point I did
I put the FUBU logo on on the front of a hat
And people buy them and how much
I saw of a 20 but if you didn't have 20 it would be 17 and F 17 to 15 minutes
2 $3
To $3 I don't think so cuz I bought
I bought $40 worth of very pretty 80s so that means you fifty cents
Seacomm home at night and you must be
That's something
Well I was on the way home I remember County I'm running I was so excited, nobody I just couldn't believe that I asked
Came up with the concept and I sold it and I was it was depending on whether I
I can sell it or not and then I just looked up
And bang I hit a car
Andeavor that guy getting out and it was a
Car and I remember him going kid now and I said man I don't have any insurance I'm sorry he said all right
How much cash you got on you I said I don't know $800
Is an argument I'll take it and he took the money and left
And just a moment and earn that $800 back
Dim sum and then some more
Play with us I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better
Their cloud-based platform and solution
Deliver digital workflow
Clothes that create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole come
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive and engage
Moret servicenow.
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated
Licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon jimenes mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
Haywood state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Play Welcome Back to how I built this
Stream NPR
1992 and David John has made and lost
$800 selling
Blue Hats
The word about us Brandy
Is spreading around town
Soap keeps
Making more hats
And then
He decides to
Branch out
The t-shirts as well
I study really you know refine the way I made the pass get better
Quality hats you know get better food with logos on them
And then start to put t-shirts there and then starts lky can't
Just hang out here in the mall
And sell these t-shirts so
Where can I get a booth out of where can I go to so I started to look at other places
Suzanne Outlets can I start a walking over the stores that were outside that mall saying hey
I'm usually outside this morning the weekends but if I can't be here
Can I put some shirts in your place or hats a new place on consignment
So I just thought I'd try to figure any and every way out that I can increase my sales
Lowe's and my exposure
Health Products
How did you find
Stop did you work
Just going to like shops and buy a
Yeah I was going to physical shops down on the Delancey Street area or people knew they can go and buy shirts and then I was
Starting to order as many catalogs
I could of people that way
Selling sweatshirts so like CCM the Jersey company wood
Sell CCM Jersey or blank or I will go to Boulder the boulder company in
Boulder Colorado they would sell sweatshirt so I would just talk to source as many places I could
My something of high quality
That was that had no name on it and they're using it for that purpose are premium come
The same company that would sell it to any
A large
Large, so you can play
Put your company name or logo
And you were
Literally
Showing the labels on
I was ripping old labels out I was sewing these labels in
I would then started going to screen printers and start putting screen printing on the shirts
Then the next step after that was to go to embroidery places
To start embroidering the shirt to get a high-quality I was out I kept improving the product
Improving the quality
And basically see the resistance or the acceptance of customers what level would they buy it at how much do they pay
Did they like extra large large red I wanted to just really start to understand the customer so I had to keep
Keep going back in time
Improving whatever I was doing
And I mean this is like
Free internet
That's so it's
But today you can just type up
Open Google
Screen printing
Silkscreen
Printers whatever how did you find them nice locate all these
Places
They were willing to
Do this for you
Yellow Pages cold-calling if you drive into New York City you'll see some sign on a bridge to say
New Jersey the embroidery capital of the
Embroidery capital of the world so what do I do I take a train to New Jersey I start walking around outside walking around saying
You know embroidery place so you know embroidery place I mean just not stopping getting up at 6 in the morning and just hitting the subway
All the while working at Red Lobster night
All the while working Red Lobster at night and sewing the hats and delivering the hats at the same time and trying the source the
The goods
Yeah I mean just but enjoying it when I was doing was kind of like this this new discovery this path that I was going down.
I was just so excited about
And to say that I also have to say that through 89 and 92 I close the business 3 times
Because I ran out of money
Cuz all these development course all the gas all this going on those trains and cars to go in his place
Places I would run out of money
But
I would I would only run out of like a $500 a thousand dollars and before you know it you know I walking on the Block somewhere
Say hey aren't you the little kid that sells food once again I need some more been looking for you
I need some more
And I will keep opening the business back up because the business started to call me instead of me calling the business
Did you ever
Get like were you ever in this
Situation where you were
Selling
Stephanie
Street corner and
City officials came up
Termidor or
Yeah I mean that had happened once or twice but the best permit ever when you're selling
Stuff on the streets is being able to run faster than them
The Great Pyramid
It's okay it's okay there's there's clearly a demand
On the street for your clothes at
When did you decide it was
Who sang take it to the next level
So when I finally got to the level of 1992 and my friend Jay Alexander came back and finding dead
Storm and he had had a
Couple dollars
She said I want to put in some money and I want you to take this thing serious
Am I playing at that time do the neighborhood was
The big black guys in the neighborhood
They had little
Options on
What they can have to be very stylish
So they had to go to Rochester Big & Tall
Or and get a big white shirt or a black shirt or
They had to pay a lot of money to get this tub custom made for
Play nobody was really making you some really tall or heavy
You're right
Right so what we did was we just found a place that made 4X 5x 6x
6X shirts and we made $20 shirts
Because
We mate with them cuz we knew that if we gave these guys t-shirts these guys are normally bodyguard
Not all of my cards right but the ones we did get where The Bodyguard they were in front of the clubs they will bouncers or something like that
I knew that they would not just wear it once and do something with some else like the more stylish kids who don't want to be seen in something
Twice we knew these guys who wear it
Forever wow
So that was our first plan of attack for the first 6 months get the same 20 shirts out to these guys and
That's what we did
And we just would do that and before you know it
These guys are walking Billboards and the artist started say
What am I chopped liver
Why you giving it to you know this guy over here and I can't get there like well I don't know we don't really make you decide you're not going to really we're not
Are you sure
Yeah I'm sure
Now that was out that was a strategy
When we first touch really launching
People I mean at that point
People like
Do they know if people still sing
What is a spoof
They started to know a little bit about it in the tight Community we're at and then I'm
This one thing they're just put me on the map was we would dress
D23 bodyguards at work for a guy in New York named Ralph
McDaniels
And Route me can you show video music box
Texas probably
I've been on longer than MTV I came out the same year
And Ralph is really known for breaking most
Of the music artist
From I would say 85 all the way to
298 date
All had to
Really really beg him to go on his show
And I'm we put on the bodyguards around Ralph and we found out
The Ralph is going to
To Teddy Riley
Concert with Teddy Riley had a weekend that he's throwing Virginia
So we said I wouldn't take the train down there
Because we know
He's not going to know as many people in Virginia
So where billy gets around easier and we got to Ralph and he said I'm only looking at yourself I know who you are I want to put you on my show
Wow
And dumb he did this interview with us and I was so sweet was so scared to death but he told everybody that you know
Who was the next best thing I think we had
I think we have 50 shirts
And I'll Ralph so much as being one of my mentors and somebody was a mental that the to the community that
If he really put us out there and after that all the rappers
All of them
We're ready to wear ice up because Ralph
Davis
Thumbs up
So I guess around the time
This is becoming bigger
You start to realize that
This has
Potential to become
More than just
Side project obviously
Yeah so what was your next move how did how are you able to
Garrett Morris
When I was about time for my game face on and it was about time to
Start looking at the numbers and being a real businessman even though I wasn't
So I started to
Put this plan together on how many retail stores would take my product how many we can ship and start taking out ads
Add session right on in Black Beat magazine and how can we start shipping these
Shirts across the country
And also how many
Street corners can we saw them on with the Inn in regards to flea markets the street corners and I started to do that
I saw to reduce my hours at Red Lobster and I saw to put in more hours here
And then I then I saw to bring in two and three other partners to help with the man hours that we need
Accept all that would require a lot of money
That would require a lot of money at first so of course you know like like many businesses I leverage my credit cards
You know up until I think my partners and I all of us leverage our credit cards are still be about $50,000
I'm with a very high interest rate which is not the smartest thing to do
And then it all culminated to when I
Decide to go out to the magic trade show in Las Vegas
Issa famous like industry
Betrayed show where
Apparel and stuff
Yeah so it's the magic trade show the magic stands for men's apparel
Guild in California is held in Nevada
I know I'm a little confused out of myself
But that's where all the stores go twice a year and they basically say you know that they'll go and see you
Ralph Lauren store Nikes your food was of the world no say okay this is what we want to come in for spring as well wind coming from
False
And as I go out to that show
My friends and I would
Scrape around money and we're all going buddy passes and stand by my mother having to work for American Airlines.
The time so
We all flew into Las Vegas California Nevada and took the bus is over because it was too busy to go into
Vegas being on standby
I only got a small hotel room a couple of miles away from the the
The trade show and we put our clothes on the corner of the hotel room stuff in the beds
Inanna
On the floor
And we will sneak into the magic trade show show
Now we didn't have a boo-boo didn't even have passes to go into those past that we probably had
You know
We probably each one of us had on us maybe $30
A piece about time we got there
So we sneak into the tray show
If you would just go so you
You didn't have a boost there but you would just go around and talk to
People
About your shirts
I would have the football on and I will see brands that I felt
We're like ours so if I was you Timberlin or whatever the case is
A stand aside their booth and say hey how you doing I would say
The forest by herself
You're here where are you
I want well instead of walking on my balls you want to hop in a cab or a bus cuz my booth is over the Mirage Hotel
Oh no no no
No no no not really in the room
It worked it out and you know we would write $300,000 in orders and that's what I would realize
How much capital I really needed
You walk away from that show without even a booth
$300,000
How are you going to find
That was a big question I didn't know what I didn't know
And I wasn't part of that time knowing all the things I know now I wasn't part of the Chamber of Commerce I didn't have an affair
Financial education
I didn't even have an accountant at the time
So I want to
All the banks I could and I got turned down my 27 of them you you said have that this business and and can I get a loan
Yeah I didn't know how to fill out a loan application I didn't know how to
You know much about reading pianos how can I write a p&l on a business that I never have grown past you know
2200 shirts at a time or 5,000 shows at a time right I don't know how to protect what
$300,000 would it would turn to
And I kicked in turned down by Banks
Entice
7 bags
Yeah
It was so bad long shots for turning me down
Because I'm happy I mean you were I guess in your
Mid 20s
Make it home with your mom and her looking at you you had no
Sort of History having a business of their thinking
Apus risk
Why would they take the risk I had I had no Financial intelligence I had no history in this business I had
You know
I had really Daikin collateralized the home I could I didn't do it at the time cuz my mother wasn't allowing me
To going to put that up and risk so
You know why I don't blame them I would have gave myself the money
And then my mother remember coming home and she came home she said
You know you've been working on this house as long as I have you put as much money as you put into this house and we have some equity in the
This house and we need to go out
And I wouldn't do this if you didn't have $300,000 in orders cuz it's all we have
Let's go out in the steak out as much Equity as we can in this house
I want you to sell the clothes you put the money right back and then you're going to hopefully you'll have a nice profit
So she goes out and she gets up
$100,000 loan on our house
So your mom
Really
Have a crazy risk that you took
Sheep sheep really believe
This is going to work
It was a really big risk
So
I don't know anything about manufacturing I mean stuff about you know putting an embroidery on a t-shirt stuff like that but as far as
Cuz I know I've only heard about manufacturing is over in China but
I'm not going to risk my money over in China show
What happens if my mother moves out
My friends all move in my house
So we start the early start all paying $75
A week for the room that they would rent out of my house so I have now 6
6 friends all living in my home
And
All the furniture I couldn't sell
I took on the backyard and we will chop it up and we burned it all
In the backyard because we wanted to make room in the house
For selling machines because we were going to trust a $100,000 around money
Overseas with somebody we don't know cuz we knew that we
We just weren't sharp in that area
Joey
Get all the sewing machines will get a Cutting Room we hired
We hire a bunch of seamstresses and we hire somebody to cut the fabrics and trim the fabrics and we create a factory in the middle
Animal Hollis Queens
You decide that you are
You are going to be the factory
Facilities disorder
My house is a big version of Airbnb meatzza Factory
How exactly
Did you have to work today
Just to fulfill those orders
It was hard I think we
We filled about
$75,000 worth of those orders until I turned around and I only had
$500 left in the bank
And I was about
4 months late on the mortgage
Again I didn't have Financial intelligence at the time and what was happening was I was paying for the setup of the machines
And bringing all the world Goods here so I had to pay for all that in advance
Then I was paying for the salaries of the people that will working there for me and that money was going out
The stores when they receive the goods they want to pay you for 15 30 60 90 days
And my lack of financial intelligence was starting to just underline how disc
Company was never going to go anywhere and now
I made $70,000 worth of the goods that I have a
The $300,000 order on in the stores are starting to say
You're not delivering to some time we're going to start canceling orders
So this is like
What like 95-96
Yeah this is right around 95
It sounds like you're
You're supposed to like
I'm both going bankrupt and losing the house
And losing all the orders that I had those stores are not going to trust me again because if they're waiting
Six months for something to come in the one they give you these orders
This is the order that they're not giving somebody else they could be turning other Goods
So now they're losing faith in me and
You got to be yellow
It was a really really dark time and I see this a lot now and entrepreneurs who don't realize what they don't know
So are you
Were you panicking
Yeah how I was panicking house value for sure how big I didn't know I didn't know how to get out of it and then my mother comes over to
Simon says I have a I have an idea
And I said
What she said
You need a strategic partner
And I said
What the hell is a strategic
And
She said it's OPM Damon you know
Opium don't have to be other people's money to be other people's manufacturing mine Powerman power
Marketing
I said alright well what do you mean
She said I need $2,000
So I don't have to download to go back to the Red Lobster and I work for a month
Can I come back on my give her $2,000 so what you going to do with the money
Cuz imma take a nap in the newspaper
And I said that's that could be the stupidest thing I've ever heard in my life
Like asking people if they want to
Fund York
Classified ads
And what is the ad say
Million dollars in orders need financing
What happened to
People start calling the number
Yasso 33 people call that ad
125% interest
I live in the Attic with collateral
Pictures of loved ones in case I got lost you know offer they can't refuse either loan sharks
Yeah but three of them were real and one is a
One with Samsung
Samsung like the Korean
200 billion dollar privately-held complaint Korean conglomerate
Somebody at Samsung saw that classified as
Samsung the head of Samsung's textile division
Because Samsung makes everything from nuclear reactors the cars the phones
And the text Oliver desorden said
Hey wanted to come in I like this opportunity here we we Finance textiles
And the deal with us was
That they would Finance the manufacturer in manufacturing and distribution of our product but we had to self buy milk
Billion dollars worth of clothes in 3 years to keep the deal
Wow invincible
You went there to meet with them and it was the person that you that was in New York
Yeah of course I was nervous I wanted presented you know I brought my mother with me
The later on you know my partner has a Samsung I would say you know
First man you ever had for a potential investment or whatever structure that somebody brings her mom like Iowa
Well miles pretty smart so I'm going to bring her with me
And you know I didn't think I was going to hit 5 million dollars worth of clothes in three years I barely even sold the first 300.
What the clothes
But I had known my customers so well because of all those things that I was doing that as we started to put the brand out there we
We did about 30 million dollars in 3 months
So Samsung of this huge
Textile manufacturer all of a sudden
Making your clothes and distributing it
What you're going from like
A tiny little
Mom Pasha to working with the biggest
Excel
Make her one of the biggest in the world
Yeah but I mean the work was still up to us who they were just financing that we still had the market even though they had to manufacture they manufacture
In a source of funding the manufacturer
And we have to find the
And we have to find the Factory The Factory have to be
Up to par and we dat's LK wire the money over here here so we're working with the
I mean all of it still
Landed on us the only area where I felt it obviously it was giving us the ability to scale is number one
The store's knew they were going to get their goods in time
How did you get
Entree into the big
Retailers Toy
To carry your product
Well that really wasn't hard at that point because we had already has six or seven years full of you know really Servicing
Specialty stores really well
And
A retailer is it actually we have to we have to stop the retails we have to not allowed
To purchase
Because some of the kids
Some of these big retail disabled NOW Foods not cool anymore
Because it's in these big retailers
I guess like
10 years
Before
Boo boo sucks really take off
Adidas
Struck out
Really famous Teen Wolf
The first time
Major company did a branding deal with
With with any music
Artist
I wonder if a lot of these big box stores like
Macy's or
Other companies that want to carry FUBU they trying to jump on that on the hip-hop and bandwagon did they see this as a
Hugely potential
Profitable Market that
They wanted it on
They did so they first of all late they were scared I actually did hear many stories say we don't want
You know a lot of those type of people in the store cuz they're going to have shootouts and or shoplift
I saw it
A large retailer did ask me to take the picture of myself and my my three other partners off the Hang tag cuz it said we look like a guy
Gang
So you got to understand the ignorance of some of them
Were you when you're running up against.
Kind of racism
And by us
People cannot judge you even before you walked
To the door
Do that do that
No not at all
I don't know where these people I don't know it was somebody's bias or something like that I don't know what they've been exposed to in their life
If you know maybe they weren't around certain other people and maybe they just need that one person or that other person their life too
Coming to the life the hopefully show them the difference of people are people
I also felt bad
I wouldn't be here if everybody knew what I knew
So if they all were that smarter than they would be no place for Daymond John
So I can't I can't spend my life being worried about what other people think or the ignorance or the challenge
They may have had grown-up they may just had the wrong
The wrong family members in their life
Who telling him the wrong things but
I know how I'm I'm listen to glass is half-full and I believe love doesn't come in a color or gender and we have a
With the summer beautiful people in this world that the people who don't understand that are suffering
16 and you get this
This
Delia steel Samsung
Within two years
Ubud
350 million dollars
And wrap you
I mean
That's insane
How do you what
What happened
I don't know what's all the fog
Sometimes
It always has rocket ship but it was having really great partners and mental is all around and
Being able to have these systems put in place where
We could start scaling but if you want to simplify it
You know if the men's division of what we were doing we were doing approximately say argument sake we were doing a hundred million dollars
By that time I 3 years what happens is after year one you get
You get a license
Comes aboard Jordache without first license and they came up when they started doing ladies clothes
So now we're doing a hundred say 150 million in mens they're doing a hundred million alone and ladies
Wow you start to put other licenses on
So bags
Shoes
Boots
Fragrance
Suits
Bedding
And he's one of those are doing 15 or 10 or 5 million a piece socks and things that nature and that's how this
Scalability
Dr350 but
You know 350 million dollars in the fashion business is great but it's it's not you no listen Under Armour doing three
3 billion or 12 billion you know this real numbers at that
That they're out there
Even though I'm extremely proud of what happened but that's how we started to scale
And who was buying
Who's buying
Who are custom
So many people show
In America primarily you know African-American and door people who love rap music
All colors I remember
You know we first NSYNC in one of our ads you know
We started getting so many calls from stores in Nebraska and Ohio like hate you know
It's not just a black thing
And then
When you start to have
Too many goods are overruns a good to then you sell it to the places such as Burlington and TJ Maxx
And those
Customers coming in their price-conscious customers they're just not looking for Brandy looking for some good old drawers that good old song
Socks good old jeans and they Brian and a lot of us
I see so many parents and grandparents with with myself on going I know this is Hulu until till I looked at the label I had
The food just has its own interpretation from various different people
Okay so you have this like
Several years of this incredible expansion and growth
At some point
Like a dozer play stupid with everywhere
Then I guess you
Something interesting
Mystic way
To describe this
Use in 2003 you semi-retired
At least
Place in the US was that
Because boobs
Overexposed or or what
Well what we did was we we do
Most of the distribution of it I mean we still obviously kept by categories but we would really narrow down
Apple stores just
Testa products
See I was going cuz we felt it it just need to cool down and more importantly we will reduce all the logos
As we could sell because people you know they already had 10 years of food boy in their closet they already thought that
You know it may not have been for them at the moment cuz we you know it goes through Cycles you know when a hot brand last five or maybe six
6 years
Maybe 7 years
I'm so tired of slow the brain down
And and were you I mean was FUBU did it seem at that point it was
Kind of time to
Wind it down
Is it wasn't
Money
I think it was you didn't want to force it on the consumer that's how I felt and I think that
You know if if the stores were like oh my God I have to have it
Then you know we needed to find something else to give to them and just put you no fool.
I want a back burner but kind of slow down till just really adjusting the way that the divisibility of product
You suck like a cup
Wheatley
Total
Change of
Career passing
In like
Blade 2000
2008's win
You became a
TD stock
I mean a lot of these other
Labels were run by
But people who work
Kind of well-known
Kennedy like
Like Russell Simmons
And puffy
And Jay-Z and you were, quiet I mean people didn't necessarily
No you was walking to the Brad Wright
All of a sudden
You become
A TV star by beak
A shotgun
How did that happen
Yeah so I wanted to start paying it forward and educating people on what I went through in trying to again show them
Somebody land mines were so I started writing books I read the first book called display a power and it talked about the fact that we all have the
The same engine underneath
I will heard but are you going to tap into what drives you and what can make you a rockstar make you proficient
Eminem bring you success and I I started going to
Stations like MSNBC Donny Deutsch CNBC talk about the book and Mark Burnett
You know Mark Burnett's you know crew saw me and he had show called dragons then there was already popular in Europe in
Japan coming over to America he said he wanted me to be a shark and I said
Yeah whatever why not let's try this understand like the show sucks doesn't matter but I'll I'll I'll go on right way
I went for an audition and they ended up using the the pilot as the first couple of
Episodes
Shark Tank and
For I know the show that I thought would never get anywhere and sucked with these few No 5 business people just talkin business all
All the time was that
Before I know you know going into I-10 theater
Do you ever when you're in the shower when you're in the shark
Yeah that's like
Go back to
To you
Try to pitch your company to
The Samsung Light
Think about how you felt
No
I don't because I remember I was so I was so unprepared
I don't even I give those people that walk in front of us way more respect than I kill myself when I was pitching B
Those people are night and day comparison to Daymond John so I value what they're doing and I do though
I I care for them because you know
I love to see the people up there that they put all the work in and they just need a little X
Stop and so
I value their their guts and I value their talking to a spirit
How much of your sick
Success do you think
Because of
Hard-working
Intelligence in
Skillet how much
Very hard I always contradict myself cuz I don't believe there is anything such as look up
Believe it's determination
And drive
Meets opportunity
But when I look back and I sit there and I and I
I say see who I am you don't want this National platform able to change lives
Father 3
And a Pisces
I said I myself wait a minute
You know something
God is about to bless me at a very different ways and that's why I work so hard
How to try to pay it forward to other
Other people
Because it's got to be some kind of lucky I don't know why I was chosen
I have no idea but a lot of it is determination dry but I think there is a bit of luck on what's going on in my life
Daymond John founder of FUBU a new book out called Rise & Grind
According to Business Insider Damon's grown his net worth
2 a quarter billion dollars since those days selling T-shirts on street corners
Hollis
And as for Shark Tank Daymond put about eight and a half million of his own.
Dollars in the companies featured on the show
And please do stick around because
Just a moment
Going to hear from you
Your building
The first
Thanks to one of our sponsor
Swell invest
Impact investing
Platform bed
Identifies high-growth companies solving
Today's biggest
Environmental
Seoul challenges
Claim your $50 bonus
Swell invest
Slash
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for Howie
You built that
The Story begins in
South Florida where Len Testa
And every year he and his family would pilot
And go to Disney World
And he loved it but
Like everyone else
He hated waiting in those long lines the summer before I went
Graduate school
I took a trip to Disney World with my twin sister
And we waited
For 2 hours in line for this ride called The Great Movie Ride
I was baking in the Florida Sun I thought to myself you know my God there's got to be a better way to
Do this and in fact there was a better way to do this and Len was the right guy to figure it out
Because he was going to graduate school to study
Computer science
And I went to my thesis advisors and they said I want to write a computer program
Let's solve this
Problem
And soul in decided to do his entire Master thesis on
Basically
The most efficient way to visit Disney
Yeah the first paper I ever wrote was in 1997 this is 10 years before the iPhone
I said you don't want that we're going to walk through a park and we're going to have these handheld devices
Can a GPS in something's going to be feeding it the wait time
The rise and it will optimize your route
As your wallpaper algorithm that would help people breathe through Disney based
Don how busy the rides were at any given moment
And when the iPhone eventually came along
Lantern debt program
Into an app
You tell the app
The ride you want to ride in the show you want to see
And the meals that you want to eat
And the Apple tell you the order in which
You should do those things to minimize your wait in line
When zap first came out
About seven years ago and since then
He's expanded its
Discover Universal Studios
And that's how I accidentally stumbled across it
When I was planning my own family
Trip to Harry Potter World
Okay so when
So I have to tell you I downloaded this
This thing and it
Where the meat we would have been stuck for like
Hours
Outside of some of these right if we didn't
Follow the app if we've
Go to Harry Potter World
Blindly it's good to hear
And is that pretty typical mean to I mean how much time can they can an average family save if they use
Use the app
So on a busy day
We can save you for hours in line
Pretty easily
I think it's your app works like Waze
It's right
I'm in a situation very often where I'm driving home
And then ways is like no quick make a right turn here and then I'm going to like the wind East Suburban
Read and like what I noticed they're like four cars behind me
Using Waze number
This is
This is the ways of vacation now driving so what happens when everybody at the park is using your app
Does it stop
Saving you time
Right so we have we thought about that early on and here's what we do we know
When were sending people to each ride and we know how many people each ride can handle in a given hour
What say you will send you a dumbbell with noon
And we know that it takes about 3 seconds for Dumbo to handle every person in line
Wishing you and your family of four
The Dumbo
We will add 12 seconds to the wait time
So that the next family gets whatever the wait time was + 12 seconds and we're constantly adjusting that tried today
By the way lens app is
Brie but the company makes money by charging AC
Description for all this other specialized data about when to visit the park
How to map out your trip
And he expects touring plans
Will make about 1 and 1/2 million dollars this year
I mean I tell people all the time I have the greatest job in the world
More about
Touring plans
Amazon.com
Facebook page
If you want tell us your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to
And thanks for listening to our show this week if you want to find out more or hear previous episodes go to how I built this
Npr.org please also subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcast or however
You get your podcasts
You can also write us that HIV tea at npr.org
You could tweet us at how I built this our shows produced this week by runty naira blue who also composed
Pause the music
Thanks also to need a grant
China's Michigan for Thomas Liu
Rogers
Our intern is Newark Uso
Gyros
And you're listening to
How I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor