Hey happy New Year everyone if you're listening to this podcast on December 31st is the last day of the
The annual public radio fundraiser soap
Please pitch in right now
When you give to your local public radio station you are showing yours
Support for our show
To go to donate
Got npr.org
Built
To get your contribution counted
And thanks
Okay now on today's show
If you happen to be planning a
Brand new project or launching a new idea in the new year
You might get some inspiration for my interview with Terry Chen
Kickstarter in 2009
A year later
I made it one of the best inventions
Xavier
This episode first ran in July of
Last year
Enjoy
But I think there's also like we could have tried
To go any faster there's just not that much was in our control we didn't have a lot of money we didn't have a lot of info
A lot of connections so we're moving as fast as we could and and that's kind of his that's as much as
You can do
From NPR how I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movement
How Perry Chad build Kickstarter and was it a culture of crowdfunding ideas
Might have never gotten off the ground
You know there's a kind of mythical narrative around
Startups especially if we're talking about tech startups and
It goes something like this
Founder has an idea
Ben founder recruit some friends than friends sit in a room and start writing code
And then they try to get the app or the website out to the world as fast as possible and then
It just explodes blows up
Millions of customers sign up and investors.
Beating down the door
But today
We have a somewhat different story
This is the story of Kickstarter and they did of course
Start with an idea
But it'll be years before that idea
Became a reality
The three co-founders did build a website but
None of them knew had a code
And he spent years refining the concept before anything even went live
And they were working with a very small amount of money
It's a path Less Traveled exam
Much less likely to 6
It's not how I would recommend anybody
Attempt to do this
This is Perry Chen what are the co-founders of
Kickstarter
Harry grew up in New York City
We went to college in New Orleans where he was really into the local music and art scene
And after he graduated he
Came back home
To me you are counting like a lot of college graduates
I didn't know what he wanted to do
But he knew one thing
He needed to find work
I came back to New York and at the time I've been DJing a bunch of New Orleans and I start to work on my music
I applied some record labels like you know
Send my resume
To whatever the worst job they have is where you like you're just stacking CDs on the Shelf
Yeah but you're opening box
Stacking City
And
Of course I never heard back
Answer that that didn't happen I don't think I had any idea and then I heard from somebody that they said that
A guy we know what school was looking for Warm Bodies
To do what
2 Above All Things
Day trade
Did you know anything about
Nothing
Nothing he just needed people to what to show up and do like
Click buttons
Yeah you know I think at this time in early 99
What's kind of the Wild
X yeah stock market
And
So I went down I talk to him
10 minutes
Kayla going to be like an office and then had no it was like a large room
You know it was like a open floor before dressing like jeans and t-shirt and you know mostly
Guys mostly under 40
And you know he talked to me and he's like okay fine you know he's like
You coming you know will trade you
For 5 days
Then you just go trade will put a small amount of money on your account you just trade nothing no clients not telling me anything
It's just this guy's money he's like if you
Do well you know you'll get
Some of that and if
If you don't
Just don't worry about it and then you know
That's it
Yeah they were like you got it was something
Play Modest like $2,500 a month you know
I mean listen it was you. Beggars can't be choosers I was like sure what happened
Was literally just get sat down in front of a computer and
Sitting there by yourself and you can buy or sell stuff you were basing your decisions on like
What I'm reading the Wall Street Journal or no not at all I mean you're buying and selling something and in a minute
Oahu or 5 minutes or holding it you don't
You might not necessarily know the name of the company
It was like a combination of
Mario Brothers
And surface which I've never done but looking out in the ocean I assume and I see a way of coming so you're like okay
It's simple it's a little distinction
And
I did it for maybe
Little less than two years or so did you walk away from it with some
Wilson cash
Yeah it was a little bit I mean nothing crazy but definitely decent for
Somebody in their 20s
But you know after while I mean I was kind of like
What am I doing you know I'm not doing anything I'm not helping any
Sing me the best what I'm doing is neutral let me know my selling somebody on it
I think so
The traitors like to think that there
Providing liquidity from great service but
You know it's it's
You're doing
Nothing you're shuffling some numbers from one computer to another
So
Yes I had to go back to normal and it's much cheaper than New York
My intent was to just kind of really focus on working on music to get better as a as a producer
And kind of
Pick up jobs here and there if I needed it
Did the idea of Kickstarter
Come to you
At that time
I think so I think it was
I was a late 2001 early 2002 because to be honest
You know I can't remember but
You know what New Orleans jazz festival is kind of bored of
The two big breaks the year that right now other than Mardi Gras
So I wanted to throw a show
Where I was going to bring in these this to
Electronic artists
From Austria
Critter endorf
See that you fly them
From
Vienna to New Orleans and have them do a gig
Sure I mean you know the hope is that though they would just happen to be in Mississippi
Yes I mean I was not an event promoter so this is all just kind of on the Fly
But
It didn't happen
And
It just kind of bother me
It why is it that
I would need to
Come up with the money and make this decision that this thing would
Have enough people,
I thought
What if the people that
Would want to come to the show could have a say in that
And if
Enough people
Could do that before a certain point then show can happen
And if not
Prince about
That was it that was the beginning and
And
What I remember most is that like
Are good ideas all the time and and you know but within a little thinking you're going to find the Fatal flaw
And so what struck me most about it was like
Confined
Edits so it stuck with
And so I kind of
Had this feeling I was like this is
This may be something
No after that feeling I was like okay
Cool
Impacts of regular life
Music
And
Being in New Orleans
Riding my bike
It's a good life like see your friends from high school or college
Coffin and start
Lake careers in
Laguna Clara Finance anything
Yeah yeah maybe I should go into a career
No I mean you know what I felt was
I'm living in New Orleans
I'm working on music
This is why people work for 35 years
Retire
So they can look through my New Orleans working music
So
Am I jealous of my friend who works
70 hours a week
No
All right so you are so you're in New Orleans
Your
Doing different things you had this idea that sort of comes and goes
And I guess around 2005 you move
Back to New York
Yes exactly in May of 2005
What was the reason why you moved back
I think it was a lot of things I mean I think that
Partially because I was
Moving
Away from music a little bit
I was kind of fighting with it
You know what
A lot of times we have an idea right and you can
How to put on the shelf of your brain
Some people say something at certain points in a remind you
Yes I think that's kind of what happened
As I was getting close to probably in the final year of new orleans's getting
Close to come back to New York maybe one year and a half
I think I came back anymore
I I knew that I was
Pepper soup
You knew that you were going to
Prestigious idea to educated come back to you
Yeah part of the reason being to is that in New Orleans it would have been pointless
You know I don't know of any
Tech Community
I was there
In the early 2000s it might have been
Certainly I wasn't
So yeah it was my plan A
When I bet went back to New York
Well
I got a job
Working at a restaurant in in Brooklyn that actually
Yeah you used to love you were a waiter there
And you know I'm at UNC after I've been at the restaurant for a little bit
Music of time
You would come in
We chatted a bit and we were like talking music and
Baseball in and then we just hung out a few times and end
Pretty early on we hung out maybe the second time or third time I kind of shared with him that I was working on this idea
His reaction when you told him you said so brilliant idea
What's funny that that was not the reaction
I mean it wasn't it wasn't the extreme opposite but he is like I'm not sure
So I don't know if my thought of time with that would be working together but I thought
If it worthwhile to
Talk to him
And as we started talking more and more about it and simultaneously becoming better and better friends
I think we
It just come naturally came together and started to work together
Holding orbit how to build a website or or anything like that
Well I certainly didn't throw any technical sense
I cannot code and I couldn't code
But I think I
How to send of
What a Feeling
I know what I like I know what I think feels good when I'm on a side
But
From the deep technical stuff
No
That was not my background at all Yancey probably have been closer but
Is not a color
So what did you start
To do at that point to meet you dope and head first
This idea and
And what were you doing during the day
Yeah it was head first
I mean I was reading blogs
On the internet
Bye
People who
Has started
Internet companies
I was reading about it
And maybe finding a friend or friend of a friend and you don't plan to give me telephone to talk to somebody
And I didn't
It was slow going
But you can learn a lot by just kind of
Google
HP Connected to two you have a third co-founder Charles Adler
We need
Somebody was a designer user experience person
I'm to help kind of
Mockup website
And
An old college roommate of mine from a friend freshman year
Call my friend Charles move to New York and he's do
Percentage
Charles my email to come over to my house and in Bed Stuy the next day
And
We
Work together kind of like almost everyday or every weekday
Couple months
Your hand drawing like what the said look like Man drawing or 12 go into Photoshop or illustrator in
Kind of like
You know just rough
Mock up stuff
You're getting into detail like
Here's a button
Here's a
A video
This is what happens when you click list
A real in-depth
I think at the end reproduce a document of Iran
Pages about how the sight words
0 code
What was it what were you doing who are you making this
What were you making this represent
Investors or we just
Which is something that you guys would have
This was to make
This was not for Annabeth
This was just
You know what we would use
When we
Had the money to
Higher
Developers to
To build it
But this is kritika
Call you know you got to know what
This is the
The blueprint
When did you guys get investors
For money
It was in 2006
Add friend of mine
And her cousin is David Cross
The comedian from Arrested Development mr. show
Great stuff
And so she connected us
And we went and had a drink at a bar tonight and I talked to him at the idea and a few months later he invested
A little bit of money and that was our first investor and you know
Two and a half more years for free of the lock the website
From your other early investors in 2006
I took a year-and-a-half so from that point probably from there too early 2008 we were maybe
$120,000 in a year and a half of the money you had
To basically pay for server space or whatever you need to do to find a developer code
All these people
I think you know
At first like the working title for years in my mind was critical
Because it was very much of the mechanism of life
When you reach a critical mass of
Support
Then I think.
Yeah but you know I think
Imessage using a lot of things
This Thursday
Bicycle organization in NJ
It's really good mechanical
In Owasso
I think you guys been together
Grueling process
Prezi what domain you can get
And yeah and then came out with this and
Was able to get the domain for pretty cheap
Tell me what the business model was from the
Are the idea was exactly as you today which is charged
Amalfi
If and only if the project was funded so
You know if a product and get funded the other new listing for you so
We would get nothing you would have this platform
People would put their projects up if it's funded
You guys get a cut what's up percentage cut
5%
Soak City tickets are we at 5% if it's not funded
You get nothing
Yeah
What's interesting about your story which is very different from a lot of other
Tech companies is
You didn't just like get to a minimally viable product like in 6 months
Have it up and running like this
At least 3 years
Yeah I mean to be a two-and-a-half 3 years but very different from
More classical stories were it's like a couple of friends who worked in the industry who
May have connections or they can build it themselves
I don't think any of us had a sense of
Where the end of the road was or where the goal was
Who went when the three of you like when you can see and Charles and you would would serve
Title the people in your life and you would say
I'm working on this and I'm trying to do this website and then you would see them again 6 months later
Come along do you think people were skeptical or or whatever
You learn what it feels like to be a documentary filmmaker
Or or a writer you know it's like you still working on the book I'm sure people thought that and I wouldn't blame them I'm a
It was long in the tooth for us certainly to
Aren't you getting stressed out that somebody else is going to
Beach just punch in and do the same thing
I think that's certainly comes to mind
But I think there's also like
We could have tried to go any faster there was just
Not that much was in our control
We didn't have a lot of money we didn't have a lot of influence
A lot of connections
We're moving as fast as we could and that's kind of his
That's as much as you can do
Why do you think you guys stuck with it
Intersecting
People wouldn't normally lose patience right
So was it just that connection between the three of you guys like each other was at the idea or was just like
You just stuck it out
I think it was the idea
You have so many things don't have access
There aren't Industries or investors whatever set up around fun things
Market Minot besides me
And then even the things the market might be sizeable enough to deal you have to make to do that
You might have to contort your idea and something
That starts enough
What your idea anymore
Yeah or you just happen to have money
Like this can't be the only way that
Ideas can get
I think we saw it
You know
Sometimes you just see it
I guess you're not always right
But just seeing it
Is really critical and so
And where was changing over these years
It only made us
See that what we're building made more sense
Not less than
That was Morenita
Did not last if you would
Engage with it more easily
With the rise of social media with the rise of YouTube
Not laugh
And so
And of course is luck involved that that was Rising as we were
Taking our sweet time
Getting it going when we come back
Opportunities Kickstarter had to grow into a much bigger company
NY Perry Chen decided not to pursue any of them
And I realize you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast
The following message come from Joyce Outlet
An original podcast
Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of toy salad
You'll hear a classic psychology experiments retold
William is an opera fan
Who enjoys visiting art museums on vacay
And is an average chest
Is it more like
That William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find
Schwab.com podcast
Or wherever you listen
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
To your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon Gemini's mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
State with state-of-the-art cyber security
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR guy Raz
So as Perry and his co-founders continue to make
Slow progress on Kickstarter
Competitors began to appear
In fact 18 months before Kickstarter went live Indiegogo another crowdfunding site
Was launched
I'm just wondering how you were able to
Withstand the uncertainty of it all day
Your recollection makes it sound like you were just sort of like yeah you know whatever will this is my thing and I have a plan B and
I want to do this but I mean
Most people I think wouldn't feel that way
Why they would feel
Anxiety
About the uncertainty of
Do you think that you're just wired differently
I mean I felt a tremendous
Gladiator
But it wasn't that excited with driving me
And
I think it normalized
Just a little bit over time
One of the things I noticed
Not just as weird
Triangle on butt after we had launched that
Those years were so trying
That I kind of had to learn to adjust a kind of like stay in the middle
Hey you're not to get too high or too low because I think that will happen like
Somebody might invest small amount of money and we be like super site
You know
Or
Hey we found a developer wants to work with us or whatever these little things like
Get super excited
Okay. Going to happen
And then something happens where that doesn't come and you look down and I think that
Happened so many times
Ups and downs
That I think it just kind of maybe my defense mechanism
Who's kicked in tonight
Force me to stay a bit more in the middle
Either way right what's the name of steamed amazing happened or what
Maybe sign that seemed IRL
I was about to occur
So what was the thing I mean it was almost three years in the time that you form a company to
The time of the website actually launch what was that
Who's at Rainbow and what enabled you to actually make this thing
Go live and become a reality
Well I think that
In some ways we made every mistake in the book
So kind of food that we did one laugh that way
Classic stuff like
People with experience telling us
You know you shouldn't do something
This way
And us being like well
We appreciate that but like you know
It'll be different for us and then of course
Like exactly what I said happened
More like duh
And so I think we had got a little experience after few years
Then there's just people you know we found amazing people
One of the people we met
Was Andy Baio
Who really helped us kind of
Figure out
What kind of Technology we should be using and help us interview the developers that we
Would hire and given to become a 1st CT
That was tremendously help
Because none of us could
Review the code that we were
The developers were on the right track
So that was that was really critical those things kind of
Coming together
When do you launch the day you launch
How did you get the word out of people even
Find
I think you're leading up to when we actually
Knew you were going to lunch or believe
Are we even talking to people about it
Telling people you know
Honestly we had to try to build up
Projects collage on the side as well so there would that Outreach leading up to the lodge
Thunder albums
Whatever their projects were
And I think we launched with Jenna maybe 5 or 10
Projects
The first week
Did you remember what were those projects for
I think the first one might have been
Drawing $4
Which may be raised
10 or $15
Do you just contributed a Kickstarter campaign to that person
Draw whatever
You know I can't recall whether it was that they were making a specific drawing but as part of a reward. You gay if I were $10
But they would also make one for you
But it was great
I mean it's amazing see anything
I backed that project
Launch go on with our friend Claudia
The first as well which is cool New York makes a book
Which was trying to get people to give $30
And everybody who did we get a book and page in the book just a minute
Whatever material they want to
Another page
And did Kickstarter make money
By the way like with a fees
Funny project
The first 6 months I think was free
You know people don't even know what this is you know how much can you ask them to
Pay money
Do people notice
Right away
Realize it was successful or was it still kind of underground in the shadows
What's the beginning
It was a very
Steady and I say that in the sense that it
Weird things on the internet
I think we sometimes have this feeling of
Oh my God one day just
Handling people
Study Island
It wasn't like
I know it was like the first
Wait there was 10 project in second week there was 20 in
The third week there was 30
You know what time does exponential thing but it was really nice and steady and
People got it
We have to go through a long. We're like
Like nobody guess this
We have to like change the whole bunch thing
But it wasn't also like oh my God we have to hire
20 people tomorrow
I think we're very fortunate
You know we're able to
Hire like one person a month
Maybe
Maybe even less than that
So we could kind of
Build a culture
Because it's not one that you come in
Which is
It's hard it's hard
To maintain something
So as you guys in that first year as you started to cut open up
And allow anybody to to raise
You know money for the project what kind of projects are you getting
I mean it's you know it's amazing depth of the human imagination you know like tattooing
As well
You know anything you can think of
School plays
Albums concert
People who
Wanting to fund their residencies
Books A lot of people doing projects to
Probably
Weren't doing projects
Had ideas in this was an outlet for them like a format for them a lot of really Whimsical stuff
Podcast it was amazing to say it was really heartwarming I just loved it I loved it
I guess after the launch went out and saw.
Money from Big names in the in the Venture Capital world like
Chris sacca and Ann in others
How did you what were the terms that you gave them was there was there any
Because once you do that you start to lose control and end
Those investors they want the other one exit strategy they want to know how quickly they're going to make money after
So how were you able to
Attract investors and avoid
That trap
I think going into it we knew that we weren't
Building this to sell this and we weren't trying to
Credit public company
And
When we went out for investment this was
You know one of the first things we discussed
First of all
With Chris sacca it was angelmon
It was their personal
And that was kind of
Purposeful
You know I think
That they can say hey
Cool you guys want to do your thing and you're not going to try to eat the world
And
We're done with that
Anzar on money and it's not that much
So it's very different I think than a lot of
Venture funding we did have one actual
Venture
Investor
Again not that much money
You need to raise money to
Presumably Tire people into expand pics
Yeah it's a
Can I actually just tell her that you in a modest even a tiny modest one
Getting a salary at all
No I thought you know I think that there was some sort of
Irregular
Redoubt
3000 bucks a month
Pure there for me and maybe me or Charles
But
Yeah we're getting ready to charge your money at the
Sports there's no guarantee of
That continuing
For very long in your first year after launch what
What was your salary
Either 60 or 6
Thousand dollars
Yeah
So at what point did Kickstarter
Become profitable
I think you know the first 6 months
Not at all no Revenue
I think we've been
A year after that
Spy within the first date
Regarding the block
And you were the CEO
I was
And how did you
I guess
You as
Kickstarter became more popular
A lot of
Companies that were making some gadgets and
Mustangs
We're using to Kickstarter as a way to cut
Prototype
There
They're saying that was out there some companies raising millions of dollars
I guess that at a certain point you guys just had enough
We're not doing this anymore and you
The quote that I read that you gave was we're not a store you kind of
Stopped allowing Kickstarter to be used as a platform for for these kinds of things right
Well it's
It's not different entirely accurate I mean basically what happened was that
We created
Additional
Process
Product design
Projects
And
They had more of a review process
And other project maybe more classical
Creative areas
Like an album
I didn't
And that was really because
You know we saw that
Do the danger of people
Kind of approaching
Kickstarter and things are being put up there
Like a new product as I'm buying this like I'm buying something on Amazon
I'm like I was going to come exactly the date that they're saying and
We felt that that needs to be understood
That Pixar is not a store
If you support a short film
You don't expect this
Short film to be the best short film you ever saw
Right I want you by like a gadget
People can have
More of a consumer expect
So we said hey
You need to show where your predator
You need to add
The risks and challenges of this project
In the checkout process we had
Pixar's not storing we link
Some of our policies to let people know
What did product need to do to get here what we might know and what we
Might not know
And
We want to let people be able to then make the Judgment of their own butt
With a little bit of context from
A company came to the kickstarter
And you know said hey you know what the
Cool product like
What headphones do something and
And we want to partner with Kickstarter to raise money
Kickstarter will do some promotion for us
Feature that the headphones in the homepage Drive traffic to it
And then an exchange you know we'll get Kickstarter
I think I like
Like 10%
Could you imagine
Something like that no I don't think so
Currently a game request like
In the past
Listen to site
Is open you log on your credit password You poster project
I picked a lot of big companies that want to do a partnership you want to sign a contract that's
Nowhere like listen if you want to go do it to go log on the side
If you want like some special stuff from us or
Whatever I mean that's just not we do it
It's a relatively open door but you're not
Any better than
Some young Creator who's
Working on their first idea this platform built
To do what you say you want to do so
You know
Go for it
How much money has
Internal itching
Charter projects
Braced
Recently
We passed the three billion dollar
Touchmark
Wow
So huge milestone
Yeah.
Excited about
The money that's gone to projects. Really had very little
Funding sources are really constrained funding sources are funding sources that would really
Forced the Creator to contort their projects in a way that they
Might not recognize it anymore
How to make compromises
A lot of crazy people have to do
But they're really hard
That's
Definitely what I'm
Most proud of
I've seen Kickstarter describers like that the People's National Endowment for the Arts and people it even
Who discovered as likely modern-day House of Medici
About the site that you created to you
Do you identify with those descriptions
Not really I mean
Listening
I'm proud
But
You know the medicis were giving up large amounts of money and it was a
Small group in a way we're trying to
Provide a clear alternative today
We know that
Whitman had funded some first edition
By having
Subscribers that he
Brother names in the first edition smaller amounts in Mozart
Angela Concerto in the same way
Statue of Liberty the base was funded
They actually the
They would some Miniatures for a dollar or larger ones for $5 I have the statute that funded the base
So
A lot of stuff that you see on the web is
Has maybe be existed
In another form nothing new Under the Sun
Pretty much it would Kickstarter
If I was telling a friend that I was working on an album and it was
Going to cost you somebody to go into a studio to make
Mixdown
They're not going to hand me $5
Write in a coffee shop
But if I put it up on Kickstarter and I'm trying to raise two grand to go to my next off my elbow
That same friend make it me $5
There was just this friction there was this social friction before that existed
And
The model has been able to eliminate that or even
Put in a way that's socially positive
So it's
The sentiment people have people want to help
Each other
Bring
Good
Interesting ideas to life
We have
Nothing to do with that
We are
Enabling
What we think is a good way to do
The idea of the model of Kickstarter is just
Seems like a no-brainer not really think about
Companies like Uber or Airbnb or
You coming to connect people with other people and in some ways Kickstarter does the same thing
And
You guys only take 5%
Which is a
Pretty small amount of money
You could take
Lots more money
Did you ever think about
Going down that path
I mean
If you're going to try to make a lot of money you know that's almost change the fee is probably not where people would talk about they would talk about
Raising hundreds of millions of dollars in Venture Capital quadrupling the size of the company
And a trap of a print
Doing major marketing campaigns or
Selling the company and
Making a ton of money
And one shot
But I think there's also like
There's got to be a way
But it doesn't have to become this kind of vehicle
Only four
Maximizing profit
You know
It was a quote I wish I could find
Leah tribution butt
We basically that
If a corporation was a person
It would be a sociopath
And
When you create something
If you wanted to
Cher
Your values
That's kind of why I ever since
The beginning we wanted to make sure to
Hold on to control
Hauser horses couldn't drive it that way
And then
Two years ago we became a public benefit Corporation
Would you still up for profit
Company but
It means that the
Obligations of the
Of the board and executive
And the company is to balance
The shareholder interest
With
Greater stakeholder
Including
The environment and
And you're
Various communities
And that's it that makes it again something more
A representation of
People
But really underneath the Mandate is
At the end of the day make the most money for shareholders
It's a really
It's not really a
A good fit for humans and I don't think it's
It portends very well for society
If it's what we accept
As the only way to
You are you are no longer the CEO right
No now I'm
Chair
And what was that did you just feel like a gay you know it's it's got to a place where I don't care I need to run it on a day-to-day basis setting
Yeah I mean I think that
Once we were out there
And
Things were working
I started to see that
Especially since we
Don't want to sell
Where's the Scuf
Things continued to
Then it just continues
That's what we wanted we wanted to just continue
But does that mean I do this
Till I can't do this send our I do this for 30 years and then I write a book on leadership and like this gives
Speaking circuit it's like you know
So I was like
And I also didn't have time to work on other ideas I have
In the Arts
Not two companies and so
I think we were just there when I just started the window I start to see
Hey you know a gust of wind is going to blow us down
We got a great team here
And so
This might be
A good moment
Did you ever I get to see career North dorfmeister after all
I've never I Have Nots I've never seen those guys I haven't heard much
I'm sure they're still out there making music that I haven't I haven't even caught up on my trip
Start that show.
The co-founder of Kickstarter Perry back in May of 2017 he was spending most
It was time for the studio in Brooklyn working on his own projects but later that year after his fellow
Co-founder and then CEO Yancey strickler announced he was stepping down Perry actually real
Turned to Kickstarter where today he is once again running the company as CEO
If you've listened to the segment at the end of our show how you built that
You probably noticed that more than a few of those companies got off the ground with money raised
On Kickstarter
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Hear from you
Things your build
But first
Quit thanks to one of our sponsors
Airtable
Whether you're building a product finding your very first customers or scaling your business
Airtable is
Is powerful enough
Keep your team on track
Get $50 credits today by
Signing up at airtable.com
Built
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And today we're updating story we ran
About a year ago
My name is Dustin Hoggard
We live here in Seabrook Texas it's Southeast Houston Texas up on a ranch and so he spent
And a lot of time Outdoors
Age of 10 or 11 his parents started to let him hike in the Woods by himself
Since I was a little kid I was obsessed with survival kits
When I would go to any store anywhere I would always go immediately to the survival kit section
Started to design some of his own survival gear and eventually
He got a job with the Texas state guard in the store that you hear all the time when you
Do these case studies of people who are in survival or emergency accidents as if they were never expecting to get into it
So you need some tools on you just in case something happens will there be a natural disaster
Or an emergency that happens while you're out doing outdoor activity
Need to have those things on you at all times
But most people just don't have those things on them at all times I mean most people do not want to carry a bow
Bulky survival kit around on a
Daily basis
They don't in the morning Keto
When they're going to work put on their survival kit it's awkward it's weird
And people don't like to think about that
So Dustin started to design a survival belt that you could wear everyday whether you were heading
Into the woods or you know just
Going out to walk the dog
So when you think about a belts you think it has to be comfortable and it has will still be fashionably appealing
So the number one goal is to make sure that everything
Fits comfortably
And does not weigh too much or doesn't look weird
Started to research how to make this belt
He found out that someone else was working on virtually the same thing and
That person lived about 15 minutes away
So Dustin contacted and he said hey if you know let's work together
It turns out that other guy was a former engineer at NASA
So they decided to partner up
They called a bunch of meals they found a military grade webbing for the belt
We have to figure out how to make
Survival tools small enough
To fit into it
We had to invent every single small part of most
So the foil is a custom foil the duct tape as a custom duct tape
The water containers a custom water container all of the the parts and pieces
Required us to go out and test the heck out of it Justin and his partner worked with almost 3090 facturas to
Custom Design every miniature Gadget that goes into the belt
The high quality
Button compass
Purification tablets and even with all of this gear on the Belt it's doesn't weigh a ton it's really
Hard to believe but if you put it on you with no you're wearing
A bunch of survival stuff
When we last heard from Dustin he and his partner
Or trying to fulfill orders from a
Kickstarter
Fathead raise / 8
Quarter of a million dollars
Turned out to be
Nightmare
They hit one problem after another in the manufacturing process
SSN
At the answer to thousands of angry customers who stopped they were getting scammed
But finally this past May
They managed to get all the pre-orders filled and Dustin says he feels relieved when people who had to wait
17 months for a survival belt leave a review that says worth the wait if you want to learn more
I'm at Dustin and his company why do survival gear or hear previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built
Npr.org
And of course you want to tell us your story
But still. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can sit
Describe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us review
You can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
How I built this
What show was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by REM teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to JC Howard North could see nieva Grant Santa's meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our internet is Mia venkat I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com