Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign
An email marketing
Used by more than
In 250000 cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email
And customers
7 days away
Campaign
Monitor.
Hey it's guy here and before we start the show I just want to let you know that we still have tickets
Available for our upcoming live show in La it's with Michael Dubin
He's a co-founder of Dollar Shave Club it's an amazing story of how we turn that into a billion dollar company
And if you haven't been to a live show they are so much fun at the chance to
Meet me and meet the
The team behind the show and also chance to meet your
Fellow HIV tea listener soap
If you want to take it
Go to NPR presents. Org
Metro
Supported by American Express
Hope to see you there
I had to go get another job besides Cisco
And we had only my income and we were
Mortgage the house to the hill which we might have lasted any particular time
And we had creditors up the Wazoo and I have people calling me at 2 in the morning complaining because
They didn't have their routers
Yeah it was very hand mouth
People who want to be entrepreneurs
Really don't understand
Robin PR it's how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements
They built
I'm guy Raz and I'm house Sandy Lerner help
What are the most successful companies in the world why she had to leave it
How she went on to remake herself
Again
That again
If you use the internet today or if you're listening to me right now through your
Smartphone
Computer there's a pretty good chance that that information
Flowing through a network that was developed by Cisco Systems
Cisco is the largest networking company in the world
Hardware servers routers and software touch almost
Every part of
Internet
Now the idea that
One computer can talk to another computer
Particularly Earthship
But in the early 80s
Pretty big challenge even it's Stanford University
Did you work tonight
Computer and say that
Engineering department
It couldn't talk to a computer in another part of the campus
We take for granted like
Email or instant messaging
Slack
There was no infrastructure to make these things work
On a big scale
But there was an informal group of graduate students
Stanford
I was trying to solve this very problem
Lerner happened to be
Part of that group
Other grad student Len bosack founded
Cisco Systems
Today it has a market cap of around 200 billion dollars
But that grows
It happened largely
After Sandy and Len left the company
After Sandy was
Pushed out
It was
Pretty devastating at the time and we'll get to some of that story but
After all of that
Sandy went on to build another
Successful an entirely different type of business a Cosmetics company called Urban Decay
And then she reinvented herself yet again
By starting an 800-acre sustainable Farm in Virginia where is she now lives
Annie's childhood almost sounds like a fairytale
Her mom and dad split up
When she was just four years old
Family
Sandy was sent off to live with one of her aunts
Which sounds like it could have been pretty traumatic
Except her aunt lived in Beverly Hills
Made Sandy
The center of her life
I thought
It was a
Wonderful thing to go and stay with my aunt she was very cool
She had a very elegant world
We would go to the merry company Tea Room
I'm sitting at gorgeous blue dining room I didn't think life got any better
So you
Your childhood was spent
Largely in living with his aunt in Beverly Hills until I'm six and then there came a day when
My aunt sister said if you come live with me
I'll give you a Coney
And my other Aunt Beverly Hills said what
If you live with me when you're 16 you can have a car
But you know when you're sick should think my God I might not even live that long
Maybe they won't be car so I took the pony weight
They were competing for you to live with them did I hit the jackpot or what
See you at age 6 move to where
Clipper Gap it's in the
Fire Sierra foothills of
Northeastern
Part of the state
California California and what what
What is a live with a ranch with a farm
It started out a hundred acres and they were farming Paris and my grandpa lived up there also
And erasing some cattle
And
I just
Download farming
To you
Yes
When it was time to go to college you
Stayed pretty close right
Left home at 15 and got a job working at the bank for year-and-a-half before I left College
Auburn
6 miles down the road it was it just a job
You're my uncle Jim for small town America with the Kiwanis
Put the bank manager and you know I think my uncle was kind of watching out for me and making sure that I had a
Safe place
It was a terrible job the bank owner made all of the tellers Neal
So he could check that our skirts were long enough
Any called assault Lewis
This isn't like 1970 1971 278 1971 1972
We were always because he knew Louise she been there awhile and we didn't really rate our own names and where you at
At that time
Get where you erase about that
Did you see the about that
You don't miss the first time I'd ever experienced any sort of sex is
Amy on the farm
I was a kid you know so you did the boy x you did the girl jobs you did you know I loaded the gas trucks
Summer
You just got on with it
The first time I hit sexism
Donut just
Completely
Rattled my world and I needed to get out
I just needed to get out
So I guess it was around that time that
You did decide to go to college and you went to
Sigma Chico State in in California what did you say what did you say there
My undergraduate degrees are in
International relations with an emphasis on comparative communist Theory and a minor in Marxist economics
That works for the Vietnam Nursery
Did you have a sense of what you wanted to do or absolutely I went to college in 2 years
And I wanted
2B I had it all mapped out I would have my PhD by the time I was 22 did your degree in 2 years
I mean obviously you're
I mean you're a highly intelligent person but were you just heard of
Did you feel unusual minutes that's very fast
Was a lot of work it was it was a tough two years but on the other hand
I was so convinced
I was never going back to that bank
Never
Yeah never
Never ever going back to that bank and having to put up with that
I ended up getting an absolutely
First rated
So how did you go from
Studying Marxist
Economics international relations 2
Sterling computers
Well
I went to Claremont Graduate School because I had a full scholarship
The first quarter I ended up being an advisor in the computer room
You know 1975 I was making 25 bucks an hour computer programming
You to me it was easy and it was
Something.
I thought would pave the way it is
Being able to enter the job market in a good place
So you are studying
You should have
Supposed to Computing at
Claremont
And then what what was your name at this point I still thought I wanted to be a
Academic
And so I
Picked up my
Little Sailfin
Applied to Stanford in because
Political science department there
Needed programmers because of course they were getting to the point where you couldn't publish anything if it didn't have some numbers in it
They let me in
I got in and immediately segwayed into the statistics and computer science department
1975-76
Stanford like
Now it's a legendary
Timer
It's like we're talking about
Beginnings the internet and all these
People influenced by jcr licklider and and
Steve Jobs going through Park Xerox
Meteora
That was amazing time so
You get to Stanford
In late 70
Is what is a computer look like
What were you were working with their brothers really like here Clermont we had a duct system 10
And that's what I learned program on and I learned a number the programming languages and did a little bit on
Assistance programming but when I got to Stanford
They also their dick Townsend
Which was great because it's a huge time sharing system
Would have 200 simultaneous users
And since I've been running the mouth
Statistical software on that timeshare Computing at Claremont
They had a
Watch volunteers it so I became a lot to volunteer a lot volunteer actually overloaded time sharing system
Got a little orange time showing system but just explain this to me in language that I can understand
When you say you were programming
These computers you were
Taking in raw data and helping them to
Creates the
Statistics from that that's right and this was just would come to you intuitively like you just
Kind of learned this
Biplane ride with it
Absolutely not I work my butt off
When I was in high school girls didn't get to take
Worth your Calculus when I was in high school girls should get to take
Physics
So I had to learn all that stuff in garage
You have to learn how to program
Oh absolutely what did you love about
2 things when the money
Don't to the Independence that it offered was which hugely attractive
You know not being tied to hours not being tied to a desk
You know I've always been kind of an anarchist
Down the idea that you could come and go in as long as you got the work done
Nobody cared about your day
When you got to stand for
What was your impression of the place was it was it like
Now I finally arrive to this amazing
Valhalla
Technology
Donut technology of smart
I wasn't freak anymore
They were very welcoming and I had great friends the computer
Computer science and
What's the time sharing system
And we would have two meals a day together and with who
This group of Engineers
All hang out around
Computer labs basically absolutely
We hear a lot about the and we know a lot about the gender gap in
In the tech world
What kind of the late 70s
You must have been like one of
One or two or three
Three women
Around all of these male
Gretchen silver very seriously I was the only
Graduate-level female
It was also a very
Welcoming group and
They didn't care real Hero3 for high grain and stink as long as you
As long as you have the technical chops and you kept up
And I could do that is a small group of people
You know they were probably about
8:10 or 12 if people would sort of ribs in a drift outfit remember we had two meals a day together
We spent the weekends
And watch the other I mean I would leave these people at 2 in the morning
Computer
Exit
Total programmers total when the people had written the first spell checker and typed in the entire dictionary incel
One of us
How to triple Major at Stanford and a master's degree in 4 years
And we will all
Computer addicts in love with this particular architecture
We built our own internet
We maintain our own internet with built-in printer and interfaces we built around computer terminals
It was just one of those times in life where what you
What you gave me
You got back
How did you meet
Len bosack
I'm at Len the first time when he was interviewing Stanford
And I mean that it was Stanford was not interviewing Glenn
When was interviews
Well he was thinking about getting master's degree
And he was kicking around thinking he needed something
To do
On that day I remember we went to Chinese food and remember these guys are all
Largely overweight and they're not the people were picked on the baseball team and
Girl sitting around in these guys are flaming themselves out with hot oil
On the Chinese food
I like all red in there like perspiring and everything
And when sat there
They were all like being very noisy and
You don't of questionable hygiene
And Wednesday out there in his clothes are ironed in his clothes match
Beautiful
White herons very soft voice
You can eat with a knife and fork
When they would get all done arguing with each other they would look Atlanta David's a well
You know basically essentially what is what is the answer
When didn't join in until they invited him and then he would tell them the answer and then they would
Arguing arguing then they would come back and stay woke
Glenwood is the answer to I was just absolutely Enchanted
I have never seen a more perfect human being in my entire life
Basically
You guys
Became partners
It was very
Quiet because the Dynamics of the group worth it
You know you
You weren't supposed to have favorites
That would have been very destructive to kind of
Ouija
Kind of group dynamics there and so it was
Really nobody even knew we were seeing each other until we decided that we wanted to get married
I'm trying to I'm trying to get a sense of
What
Some of the problems you are dealing with in
At Stanford in the
Early 80s basically Stanford
Right at the cusp of
You notice the bleeding edge of the technological Revolution
Lots of computers all over Stanford presumably
But
I guess they couldn't
Communicate with each other was that that was a problem
Well if used to be that
You either bought that computers you bought IBM where you bought hpu you bought data General you bought Wang or you bought whatever cuz those wood
The only ones that could communicate like
I didn't feel like a meeting with IBM
That is true but the reason was that it was so new
You entered into this Unholy alliance with
Put the vendor and they would help you
IC
To some departments had
IBM some head.
Some had doubts or whatever was around
Well whatever they felt match the researcher there
You know pedagogical requirements save
Were aligned to themselves and
But what they wanted which is typical University
Everybody wants autonomy
Do the 5000
Computers
Many more stamp
This is the late seventies and these computers could not talk to each other and Sprite
Animo Stanford against
Was actually trying to build it
Own computer network
Wasn't
Working so what in
In the meantime we don't want you are doing a shadow Network yourself
You land in this group of Engineers you guys are trying to figure plus all the people in the in the arpanet community
If you were working on parts of this
Ann Arbor dentist that precursor
By the government and that's what our power was for it was it was a network to
To Foster
The interaction and inter sharing of
Ideas and information
Among the different people who are taking taking our money
And that's what we were doing so
So
How are you doing this
Stanford aware of what you're doing
Officially
Absolutely not
We were definitely under the radar and we kept it under the radar and it wasn't until
One day
AR
Time sharing ethernet
Became the Stanford University Network
Wow just one day it just
You know that
Benediction winning in our Direction and then we were there we were the Stanford University Network
So you created
A system that would allow these computers to
Communicate what today we would just call it router
You build a network
At Stanford what was the thing that was motivating
Why did you want to do
Search for Stanford
I didn't do it for Stanford
I think there's a lot of
Misunderstanding about
Those early
RP years we did it because
It was the right thing to do
Giving money if it's all public
Public domain
Nobody had a financial motive
The thing that are paid that was so
Amazing even today
Was
Gave the right people the right money
It wasn't political it wasn't
There wasn't any religion involved in it it was just this collection of these incredibly smart
Dedicated people who made
I was really really lucky to get to be a part of
I mean everything that you could do everyday
And you can hook something you up for you get you know you could get a message someplace so you could
You could just use milestones and it was
I guess if you're a nerd it was just a
Terminus adrenaline rush
So
You are in your twenties this time
Sherpas government agency is
Funding all these cool projects that eventually would help
Create the internet
You are part of this team that
They create a network
It Stanford then adopts as its
Sparkle and an attack Point these 5000 computers
Are able to talk to each other
So what
At that point
Yuan when were you married at that point
Yeah we married 1980
We both graduated from Stanford same Department sting
Same platform
In June of 1981 with master's degrees
Beyond
Lynn had walked into a job is that
Computing systems for the Department of computer science and I got no job running
Pearson Business School
So we were looking at
Long happy
Nerdy careers in that environment
Wouldn't you want to do something with with a routing technology that that you'd worked on who absolutely but Stanford said
No you cannot licenses to
Technology
They would not entertain
Any any license
We have done our part and we taking the government's money this is all public domain
Weed invented all of these wonderful things but the office of Technology licensing didn't let anything out
And Stanford was not even letting us sell it to the university
So you and Landon
Are frustrated
Because you believe that this technology needs to get out into the world that there's
All kinds of music Arthur money this is United States money we don't have a right to
The stuff we didn't develop we did develop
We didn't invent it
It was a community
People
Very smart very committed in all of these different places and in Stanford all of these different departments there was a huge coming
India South Point
Stanford was saying
Just know
And you didn't care you weren't
Saying hey we're going to take the money for this
Know that the money would go to Stanford or or
Percent of it as long as you know they paid the bill for the parts we are good jobs
So was it at that point where you and lands are said
We thirsty
Ourselves
At that point I believe that lend you a whole lot more about business than I did and at some point he looked at me and he says well
We're just going to have to go in build this stuff
On our own money because we can't do it the university won't allow us to do it within the university so one day I drove up San Francisco
Give me the $5 bill and started company
$5 bill for $5 at that point to register with the California soccer
Tri-State furniture
And so you are
Trying to build a company that
Just in layman's terms
Would help
Computers communicate
Just we're trying to build terminal service and routers
And he called it
Well that came later Cisco is actually the
36 theme
We tried to get anything having to do with
Computers we couldn't have
Because it was taken by someone else to Cisco as in San Francisco
Yes and I design
It was my name and I came up because we were at that point two routers at Gateway
So I came up with logo the Golden Gate Bridge which is still the logo for Cisco
Going
So we just with tears on Rice basically said well I guess we've got to go do this
I had no idea what we were getting into
I think you had no interest in and leaving your job to Stanford
At that point
Leaking is comfortable life when you notice of servicing the computers
But this time this was 1980s
4 and they were starting
2B Creeks I mean I was paid
Half of what my predecessor made and I was paid
I was paid a third what my successor was paid
Wow
Found you know when
The Faculty would meet at
At the beginning of the year to plan the curriculum even though I was ahead of all of the Computing facilities
Both administrative and
Curriculum
Computing I went to have lunch with
The Faculty wives because where they had their annual meeting
This isn't this isn't 19
It was starting to
The creek and I was getting a little bit bored in
Dominican microcomputers were starting to come in
I really didn't have a lot of interest
And that
So I would say that
I was ready for something
Chanel spit
Yeah it's a complete
Misunderstanding of the times to think that
Len and I had huge dollar signs in her eyes and knew that this company was going to go public and make a decillion dollars
Whatever this is really where the story gets a little complicated
Pierce
Trying abbreviated
During that. You think
You you leave Stanford
And then Len also leaves
What you guys are doing with Cisco in the end
They claim that you've stolen their technology right in and they threatened to take legal action
So how did you deal with that situation
Well
When Lenin died left
When Les Stanford a great deal of the engineering team behind
The internet at Stanford left and so Stanford was left with a network it didn't
Having the ability to run and certainly
Nothing to maintain
So within that
Very fortunate Confluence of events for serendipitous Confluence of events
We actually did have some bargaining power and we ended up paying them I think a very fair royalty for
The first
Gosh I want to say $3000000 a product or something very fair royalty
And we had to fix the network for 3 years
So that's
Pretty good deal
You know what's what it's the deal they should have made video you know if they'd have said here pay us a modest royalty that you can handle
From Castle point of view
And maintain our Network where you going
Okay
And how are you bristle how are you funding your company I mean to build credit cards
Starhome friend of mine used to work for me at Stanford with synonym
Telephone and tell our vendors that the check was in the mail
How are you even getting customers you were just
Just
The internet new
Me and Len the internet knew about the routers the internet was the internet and everybody
Who was part of that wanted
What you were
By 1987
With no Salesforce we were booking a quarter million dollars
A month wow who are you
Our first customer
Was
Hewlett-Packard Laboratories
Second was Rutgers University third when was Boeing
And by that time the internet Community had matured
Found it was no longer just the bleeding edge that that were ordering these internet works which were Network subnet
So it did kind of moved into the keeping up with the Joneses in the sense that if you didn't have an internet
It was kind of
You are backwards so the style had changed and you can't rebuilding these
In a in our living room and Lenz parents soldering iron
Absolutely
Both job started in garage at least I living room
What is the actual
When when I'm trying to imagine you guys
Soldering and building these
Rappers
What would it look like was it was a giant thing that was at the size of this room
Redbox
So it wasn't that much
It was as of today
Well
Today's routers are that size
You don't question because I you and Len
Wer
Programmer
You're you guys could sit at terminal
And figure out
How to create
These programs that would then do things
That's what I that's what I want to know how did you
How did you know how to build the hardware is it something that you just kind of figured out nothing to do essentially with the hardware
Hardware engineer and that's how Cisco made its money
Because of Len
Annie's Hardware engineering Lynn also happens to be
Unparalleled
Systems programmer
Let's just really good were you stressed
Out about I understand that you were motivated
My money but you had to have money to
Absolutely
I had to go get another job besides Cisco
I work for Somerset computing
Computer aided systems laboratory running running their computers
And we had
Only my income and I didn't have a car
And with seven people that we're working we were mortgage the house to the hilt which we might have lost it any
Particular time
I'm and we had creditors up the Wazoo and I have people calling me at 2 in the morning
Complaining because
They didn't have their
Router or they're terminal server and yeah it was stress cuz you didn't have a factory you were making each one
We have the money to build the damn things we were having to buy parts on credit
Wow we had every credit card maxed out Kirk Lockheed was one of the founders gave us $10,000 length.
Give us $10,000
Robert Michael Salon is $10,000
He worked at HP
IHC Labs but everybody want to call these people want to buy them from you just could not make them
Fast and Furious have the money to make think about the University
The payment site
You know
Universities by the time they're budgeted
Write 90 days later
Yeah and
I mean literally
We would get the money
We had pretty good Martin semi we were we were doing a good business
We would get some money and we would pay off the the two months bills before but then if you had an order for another
Under 20 boxers
We had already mortgaged the house
You got it it's its
Just a few of you
Make me leave unless beginning
Trying to build this
You obviously have this thing that a lot of
Companies are interested in a lot of universities a lot of people are interested
Why didn't you just go and get
To put someone in the company
We went through about 70 radium 70 or 80
And the problem was that
You know this point the investor Community wishes
Fairchild
Semiconductor salesman
They didn't think that you could make any money out of public protocol because of course everybody would do it you know deck that was a proprietary
Protocol sna technology was in the public domain
You know anybody can do this right you you don't own this
Right everybody else was going to do it
What would make sense
Price accept it if everybody could do it why didn't they
So when you went to investors
Pitch them on the
They had no clue what I was talking about
First of all there was a woman found
They're all 60 or 70 they just didn't know how to relate to a woman
Investments yunnan
Any lettuce
A great guy but he's not normal
Meaning
Well the two of us are pretty abnormal I mean so I was basically a translator a lot of
You were the you were the face you would front man
Well armed woman not a lot of people can have a conversation with Lynn
And were you
Feeling
I don't know what are you feeling dejected or nervous or anxious I mean you you needed to build these you didn't
You have money
I think that I've never been in a war
But I think that we had all of us who are there are there probably about
10 or 12 of us at that time
Very much had a trench mentality
How are you paying everybody
We could get
Enough
Income fast enough to meet payroll
And we had a whole bunch of free labor
Lin's parents were building cables and
My aunts came down and did xeroxing for us and
I was managing the cash flow
But it was very hand mouth
In a way that I think that people who want to be entrepreneurs yesterday's
Really don't understand why was it exciting or was it
No
It was nerve-racking
If you can imagine being in a World War 1 trench in the mud
Been constantly shell
By the by the Germans and the mustard gas and
And no food and no relief and no sleep
I it was not exciting
When we come back
How Sandy and Len
Finally did get their funding
Cisco Systems
And why they both
Eventually walked out
Company
They built
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform
Form and solutions deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole company
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work
They wanted
Using technology
How to make people more productive and enjoy
Moritz servicenow.com
Thanks also chart
2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
A campaign monitor
They took email marketing and media
G-Eazy
So the big thinkers to focus on what they do best
Developing
Big Ideas
Choose from hundreds of
Specially crafted templates
Turn key design
Create campaigns
Results
The best part
Drag-and-drop editor gets
The job done in
Try it for free
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and business
Forgettable
Hey welcome back to how I built this from it
NPR
Cisco Systems
Was up
And running in Sandile and went through a
Bunch of different investors
Trying to get there
Refunded
Until finally
They found the guy they need it
I guess it's at that point where you
Come across
A guy who is
The following investment
Avicii World valentine
You
Come across them and this is the time where you are really desperate
Preferred cash and what is Don Valentine he's with Sequoia
Capital what is he
Don't told us that well you know taking 200 companies public you walk into his office and you know what your little cubes back there you got
Like always lucite cubes in business
Untenable mountain and he says you know you'll be part of the Don Valentine group of companies
Cons of company
Wow oh yeah
So the guy lost apple and Intel
Is comedian saying
Yes and telling us that
So don't worry about getting your own lawyer will let you know will pay for it
Let him I walked into a four-year vesting plan after funding the company
For three years clearly and mezzanine investment we're making we're booking quarter million dollars a month
Warrior fasting plan means
Your
We have four years
To put in to get our stock
And no employment con
And what did he get
40 give you what he got
She gave us 2.6 million dollars and
Linen I got about 30% but remember he was the chairman of the board of the company and he got stock from the out and all of his friends go
I think we're foreshadowing that this story does not end well
To watch
Tsotsobe
Don Valentine
Is NOW essential
CNN so
What did she say to you guys
I don't want you to run the company
Don't know he was done is much more clever than that
Don said well for the good of the company when you get you a
Professional CEO of the good of the company you know we need a professional CFO and Len and I were still kind of doing this
I think we wanted to believe
Yeah given our health or marriage everything for this company and here's this guy who's been wildly successful and
And we we truly
Didn't want to believe that that was for the best
And just next strategy
Disturbing someone in
Who is hasta
What's a CEO
Is a seasonal job mortgage
But I will swear the first thing he said to me was I hear you're everything that's wrong with Cisco
When the first time you
So
When John mortgage
Comes in to run the company
Tell me what he would have thought was wrong with
Well
Cisco by this time
How does Salesforce to Salesforce look like
Turn on time but younger
Salesman
Way into the
This current millennium are still having the parties with the naked girls jumping out of the cake
And all of the stuff that was a typo
The Caymans
So it sounds like
I like once
The the money came in from
Don Valentine
Sequoia
Lead like the kind of took over the culture that you guys have you heard this culture of
Passionate
Computer programmers and they brought in
Salespeople who
Different a different motivation
A different motivation they had a very different set of experiences
We have a very complicated product
Then we were people been talking to each other
Predicated right
I mean
If you think about it
20 years ago try explaining what a router did peep
We didn't
Normal things in the steel salesman
They would come in and they would start talking to
You gave me answer Lana Robert Michaels her
Uniqlo heater
Greg Sauter one of those people
The engineers for just like you staring at
They weren't staying the same language they had no clue and so I was trying a to translate
And be to take the flag from the sales pitch
Translate it right it up
And discuss it with the engineering PE
These guys were used to having a product that they frankly didn't understand but
To sell a Cisco box
I think I do understand some part of it
Because it's what made us different and
It's what's made us successful
At one point I was at dawn and I
Because he was arguing that
We didn't need more floor space
We literally didn't have a place to set
Boxes that we're making
Every company invest
Always wants more space and they always go out of business
Who said you don't understand on
This going to be a 1 billion dollar company
How do you know that
I said
Look at the people here
And then I said the most stupid thing I've ever said in my life
Which was
Leaving me out of it
These people are really really special
And I did it because I felt
I go for the grandma who said pretty is as pretty does and you don't say nice things about yourself
You know I was being modest
I was saying you know
Even if you don't like me
What you didn't see lowest me
Look at these other people there truly special I mean these were people
That came out of Stanford at the end of the 70s you don't know what you got here
How many women work
Well not very many although we had a couple that we're doing inside sales and we had
My friend who is still at that point running the purchasing department
I do remember that the executive meeting
The head of HR who was a former Miss California and I were the only women
That this is this is another
Part of the story words
A little complicated and they're obviously different versions of
What happened
Recently there was a lot of
Pension
At Cisco
It seems pretty clear that
There was somebody or some group of people who wanted
Who wants you out
That's right
Until I guess
One day the
Your CEO John my mortgage calls you
And
What do you remember about that day
Everything
What happened
Are sitting in my little office in the corner as I did every day he came in and he sat down in the chair without making an appointment
Mini setup
I think it's time you retire
That was it. You got all this money now you just
Time to retire
And I said well John I'm
Not even half vested yet and I've got a lot I still think I have I'm doing here and I started
Of course my practical way to tell me what I was doing and
I'm he practically told me to shut up
I mean basically I was fired
Wait but your
Sheriff
The company was going to fully vest
4 years
Does a two-year
Bingo
So
If you would walk out that point
I'll be walking out with half my net worth
I noticed they only fired me and not Lynn
And you could do nothing about that
You know at that point it was women don't get along they're not playing team players you know this was six months after the company IPO
So you fire one of the founders
And we're not getting along we did have an adjustment. Where it was
Very difficult marriage was
Was
Giving everything up for the company or health our marriage
You name it sounds like how you could have had a
All American
People handle stress in different ways and
They were simultaneously pandering to Lindsey go and I had no idea what had any go until then but
He got the board seat
I was literally chocolate
So they they very consciously tried to drive this wedge between us and
Chelsea was working
Well except for one thing and someone like Don Valentine has no way to
Really internalized
L'enfer
All of his things that can make him
Very unusual and sometimes very difficult
He is fundamentally
Fair and decent and it is in violet
And I went swimming at said
Len I don't know if you know you're on the board
Whether you've heard about this but mortgage just fired me
And I looked at me and his usual way of Sonos kind of goes up one side and says
I am sure
You are mistaken
Mysidewalk
I'm sure I'm not the words
You are fired leave the building
We're sad
And so when
I think you probably could have knocked over both Valentine and everybody else like little
Bowling pins when then walked up there and walked out
He walked out in solidarity with you
He absolutely did he walk up half of his
Potentially
We ended up getting it back
The only because it would have looked very bad for the stock 6 months after win
Both
Sounders walk out
And you can't turn feather the other one with
Girls don't know how to play on a TV
So you did manage to
Retain your 1/3 steak
With with our lawyer and
Threatening
To expose a list of six months after the IP
Speaks ^
Your
Intellectual partnership
Lynn
What's up with you
How much he
Respect
You agree with you and Lynn and I
You know we respect each other as
People and
We adore each other and we are each other's best friend
And I should say you're no longer
Married today right
That's right
But what's fundamentally hit with something that they could not have reckoned on and that is that there exists people in the world
Who fundamentally see black and white right and wrong
End
Lennox one of those
People
That has an unerring
Sense of
Did they
They must have panicked
When he walked out they did
That could have
Beckham son of the company
They were
Holy holy taking a bath they had no plan B
Sandy
Somebody
Who knows somebody who who's here in the story
And knows a little bit about it might ask you this question
Witches
When you in the land walk
It's been reported
You walked out with $170
Their argument Cisco's argue
You guys are now rich
Just go enjoy life
Enso
I mean you did have all that
Money
Was any part of you like yeah right I mean
I did my job here and
Okay I'll move on
You know it could have been that way had
The sequence of events been less brutal and less personal
They could have bought Lennon die out
We could have
Kept Noah
Facade of a relationship that could have been done
500 ways that would have been
Appositives was probably time for me to go
Probably time for them to go we're just not good people
In a collaborative environment
So you both leave the
And
How was your muscles
Arthur Rock
You know my entire adult working life was tied up and everything that had been done and sacrificed in
Built in that company
And
The people who stayed there were no longer not my friends
The people
For customers of them were no longer
No not my friends
And it was
It was a time that
You know any kind of
Tentacle our route that I had managed to put down was just
Forcibly ripped up
I was on my own I had
A comfortable amount of money remember that right after that linen I put 70% of the proceeds in the charitable vehicle
Message does not get distributed until both of you guys are long gone right
Well yeah and and weave
Paid out about
50 million dollars
And a private charity that that we've been spending since since that time so you know I had money but we're not talking about billions we're talkin
About
Attentive that you guys sold all your
We did
You're certainly people would say will you look you're crying all the way to the bank
How much money can you spend how much money do you really need I'm not somebody that you know I live in a log cabin
You know it
What they had taken for me was what they meant to take from me which was
Basically my whole working identity
The amazing thing is you are 35 years old
Barry
E335
You're ousted from the company that
You found it
You do have
Quite a bit of money at this point
So what did you do
You know I come from a family that believes very strongly in
The common good
I think it would great values with respect to work and
You know I decided that
Elmo's World was my first love
There were five animal shelters in the Bay Area that if your pet happened across the street it could end up in a in a shelter 16
Miles away
And they had no way
To tell where your pet was in a lot of times by the time you figured it was really missing it have been Houston
And I went across the street to the
Animal shelter Merced you know how I have this idea for Noah
And we can put all these animals
Dennis Davis
Be shared by all of these 5 networks that ring the day we could call it petnet
And
You know you guys could
Just sit there and
Your take picture the other one like typing
If she thinks about it
If people could sit at home and see if we're there animal was
So I just started
Working really really hard with
Rhiannon
On Peninsula and San Jose in the
Palo Alto in the Oakland
Oakland shelters building petnet
You
Spent a couple years
In the Bay Area after
To your Asha from Cisco
And then I get some 90s you started a cosmetics
Company Urban Decay
Which is completely like total did totally different direction right
How did that happen
My aunt whom I adored I was turning 40 and she said Hey kid it's time to lose the
T-shirts and jeans and by the way up
But you could use a little makeup
I adore her and I thought she loved me and so I
Took that to heart
And I thought jeans and t-shirts were not a negotiable item so I would concentrate on the makeup
And I went to go look at that and I went to the department store and it was all great if your Christie Brinkley
No I don't look like Christie Brinkley and I've always been kind of a
Shipping
Can Punk sort of person just cuz I don't fit in so I tend to grab
To toward those
Fashions
Belong to those people who
Joy not fitting in
You know it was all pink
Am I just go I can't do this for the rest of my life
This is not right why is your nails red well because it has to match lipstick why do you stand there and put your hands up
Fire face
No your nails should maybe it was how about that one
Rochester closed
So
Make a very easy thing you do 3 weeks we're on the Shelf in 3 months
Nodejs
Because at this point you were like I have never going to outside investor
Ever so you had the money
That's right because you could do that
You can make it happen quickly on your terms
What was the
What was Urban Decay naked
Well I just thought you know there's a whole market for people like me that
Really grew up in the time of
You know Vietnam War end
Hippies and punks and I was really heavy into the punxsy at that point
Are still delayed gratification
So
I just started making this really cool colors
Like beautiful Blues we had a
Kind of a light steel blue that was called uvd
We have plagued which was unkind of
Purple with a green tint
Broach which was an absolutely drop-dead gorgeous Brown and we had mildew which was nice
Screen
Steel color
Well
So you were making a colors
And giving them some interesting names
And I'm really really good ingredients the first place we were in
Nordstrom's and Neiman Marcus sell
We were
Using top-of-the-line ingredients and it was
Absolutely
We committed to no animal testing
End
Because
You put your money behind it was you you were able to get a cabbage to get Nordstrom to agree to the carrier
Because it was a really good
NBA I think it was good timing because
You know your type by the mid-90s enter your talk about Nirvana and you know the
The grunge wave in
Pearl Jam in that whole thing
I think Nordstrom rightly felt that they were missing a mark so it's coming it's really cool beat
Because you
Assertive headspin soap
Previous like two decades
Really
Understanding learning
Mastering
Here Technologies
And I have to assume that you
How to dive into cosmetics in the same way cuz I
I mean did you notice really easy
Eat at the base of the nail polish how much Michael you want to put in at the base for the
The color cosmetic eyeshadow what kind of my car using how much Mica how much pigment you're putting in it
Everybody uses the same stuff it's just
How they put it together and what they're willing to pay
So you say you would go to these
Factory make that make makeup for a hundred different companies and you would tell them exactly what you wanted and we would make it
You make it we would sit on the bench with the people and and make it and we had
Three weeks to get it out on the Shelf before
The same company with would knock it off for the other people on the street
I mean you were and you are such a highly respected
Technology pioneer
And
And you had all these friends in this community who did anybody ever say
Sandy Cosmetics that's interesting that's like a total departure
I wanted it to be a total departure because
And I was I was using my technical chops for pets
Service doing that and
Jamaica
Timmy was really
I was quite offended by
The makeup industry putting all the women in this paint box in our first our first ad for Urban Decay was just pink Nike
Puke
You know to me it was about choice
I guess you too jealous trait like how kind of pump
Urban Decay Vice
I've read that
Dennis Rodman
Play The Cure The Cure Houston X Gwen Stefani you stood I mean we had a we had
A whole lot of people
Who are using our makeup
So what why did you I mean it was like five years
After you launch Urban Decay that you sold it
Chewed lvmh
Copy that
Vintage Louis Vuitton
Why
For the simple reason that there's no intellectual property
You can't cut and color
Right
Like other companies
Cookie keep knocking you off she just
What you just figured
Clematis
Yeah
Was it worth the price was it worth selling
I'm funny bunny
But by the way I think is not owned by L'Oreal
LA right now
But still you know you started this company is
Probably cool to see this around me still rap solutely
To you
Have this entirely other part of your life which is
Arguably the biggest part of the Chalet food
Now which is a
A sustainable
Farm in Virginia
Complete left the West Coast
Build your
Life
In the Virginia Countryside
Were you raised
Rare
Breeds of
Cattle end
Pigs and chickens
And Turkish in Turkey
Tell me
Tell me about that had them start
I was raised on a farm and I believe in eating me I mean we got this pointy teeth right
That's why we survive the Ice Age
But you don't
The idea that you would factory farm to me was
Beyond horrifying
And I absolutely believe that we did not use that kind of farming when I grow up reformed
Play my grandfather knew how to farm which was
Seminar on the shield and you fed your cows good things in at the end of the time
You can't fit your neighbor I mean we would know more of poison dark house because we have poisoned our neighbors at that point
So I was convinced that I could find an economic model
Because I have the resources
To raise large livestock
Possibly
In a sustainable
OrganiCann cumin powder
And I am
Imagine
Like doing this kind of farming is hard
You know I'm one of those people that doesn't have I guess the Good Sense God gave it actor
To just
Not do something because it's going to take a whole lot of hard work from you is the hardest thing I've ever done
Much much higher than
Learning calculus is a graduate student in
Dinner
Physics and the rest of all of that stuff
It's it's it's much much much harder than anything I've done and it takes
More work
And more heartache and more aggravation than you can ever
Imagine
Something web
That is really striking to me is that you and you still have this partnership with land likely even though you haven't
Married since
Like the 90s
You still
Collaborate together
Clearly like you still value each other tremendously
Yeah and our foundation is called the Ampersand Foundation because it stands for Len and Sandy
Oh that's so cool
Can we both have put our money into matter what we do with our personalized the rest of our lives we are each other's legatee
Yeah
But you know that land and I found each other because we
Probably
We're more suited to each other than
Most everybody else in the planet
You know my parents
Thought when was A Space Alien
Until until they fix my uncle's chainsaw
Then he was like the Golden Boy
But my parents Allen's parents met each other for the first time I think they were each expecting sort of like ET and and why
You know because
Both of their children were so bizarre
You know it was it was a little a little touchy there for a while
I know you've been asked this before.
Hitachi questions I want to ask you anyway
You have been able to do
Anyting
He wanted to do
Giving away
So much of your wealth
Add yuan Len
App that stalk you
Would have been it would have been worth
Maybe more Billy
Jealous time I checked I think I would have been been worth 9 billion but it's
It's probably gone up since then
You know I think that
Nobody can see the future
And that Lennon died
Agreed to sell our stock
On a very joint basis and we did it because we fundamentally had no respect for people running the company
Don't it wasn't really that
We didn't believe in the
Company I mean I was the one who said that Cisco would be a billion dollar company and I knew that that was
As long as his people stay there even without me and Lynn
They had a technology Legacy
That they would be successful
It was because lenin i did not wish to live our lives
With those people having any more control
Over
RJ
It had nothing to do with
With financial
We made a pile of money and it really had nothing to do with you no Roi or not any rights and you know
What tech company was going to do it had to do with the quality of my life
And how we wanted to to look at the morning
How much of your of your success to you a tribute to
Your intelligence in your hard work and how much
YouTube YouTube
Yeah I've always said that it's a third being smarter third working hard on her third luck
No
Take that back
It's a half being smarter
Half working harder and 1/2
Sherlock because that adds up to more than one
And there were times
That Cisco could have just been
An asterisk
I mean there was so many times that company could have gone under and we were saved by circumstances
Out of our control
So there was huge luck in there
I still work harder than anybody I know
That's my great gift
And I love work
I'm I'm I'm besotted with work
You nobody already designed my Epitaph it has one word on it
What do you think it is
One word wow that's done word
I can't some your
I can't
Summarize your life into one words that
I don't know I have no idea
Bold
Sandy Lerner co-founder of
Cisco Systems and founder of Urban Decay makeup
By the way Sandy did guess right when she once predicted that Cisco was going to be a
Billion dollar company
It is now more like eight
Addition to running are sure farm and running as restaurant Sandy also started a library in the UK
The Chawton house Library
Which contains thousands of books written by female authors
Around the time of Jane Austen
Who said he says
In fact a few years ago
Sandy wrote a Pride and Prejudice sequel
Called
Second Impressions
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsor
Squarespace
If you're ready
To start your new business
Make it stand out with a new website from
Squarespace
Visit squarespace.com
Build it
For a free trial then use offer code build it
To save 10%
First purchase website order
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
Time now for how you built that and
Play Story begins
About
Seven years ago outside San Diego literally on a Manhunt
We were searching for an armed suspect
Mission was tough
The suspect was even tougher
The time and the people chasing that suspect in the
California desert it was incredibly hot 100 degrees is really hot if your in San Diego
And about 40 lbs of gear
And Justin kept thinking there has to be a better way to stay cool out here
No he didn't know much about design or engineering but
I got home he called up a friend
Who did oh yes JD is a management science and engineering major from Stanford
Back around a bunch of different ideas
And after a few years
They eventually designed a piece of
Clothing that could keep someone comfortable in hot
Or cold weather
It's just a
Compression base layer shirt that would look a lot like a Nike or an Under Armour shirt that somebody might buy at Dick's Sporting Goods
But it had unique Pockets that
Could hold Heating and Cooling elements
Haidian
Put it up on Kickstarter
30 weeks later the phone rang
It was actually the US Army
The Army has been looking for a way to keep soldiers cool and they said the Justin hate we love the shirt but
Can you make it stay cooler
For longer
One way that we we put it as we built a scalpel for athletes
And they asked us to build a sledgehammer for soldiers
But how were they going to build that sledgehammer
Well Justin and JD were stock for several weeks
And then
I was having drinks with a few friends that I just come home from Afghanistan
Remarks that are
That was on Kickstarter reminded them of how they try to stay cool overseas which was they freeze bottled water
And then they jamming in their body armor
And that is when I had the lightbulb moment of o
Justin's light bulb moment was maybe I could create a
Frozen water bottle that you could strap
Directly to your body like a
Flat plate of armor
Well
That's exactly what JD and Justin came up with
The way it works is You Phillip
With drinking water
Do you freeze it overnight
And then you wear it
And as your body heat melts the ice
You have cold water to drink
JT and Justin called it the ice plate
And it made it so we could stay cold for like
2 to 4 hours
It took it back to the Army to pitch it
But okay this is the Army right so
It turned out it was going to take years
The deal with all the military red tape before Justin and JD could actually get a contract
And we just
I knew that we were going to be able to go broke
So we took it to the commercial Market in August of 2016 but
They start to get some pushback
Negative pushback from the market
It'll never work that's a dumb idea there was every objection to some people just didn't get it right away
And we were just like oh my gosh that we just made the biggest mistake of our lives but just a few weeks
After they launch the ice place
Their luck
Completely changed
September 2016 we got a live chat
From a gentleman named Kevin Frye
Who work for Chick-fil-A at the time
Chick-fil-A happened to be looking for a better way to keep their outdoor employees
Cool on hot summer days
So Chick-fil-A now uses the ice plates at about 200 of their stores
So we we can busy
And since they launched their company two years ago
Justin and JD have sold
About 20000 units to law enforcement
Ted construction workers even to the Secret Service
This is the most fun I could have
Ever dreamed of having its nerdy engineering stuff it's helping the men and women who protect our country inn
Communities it is so much fun I could have designed a job this much fun if I try
Justin Lee's company is called
Performance it's based in
McLean Virginia and she want to find out more about it
Or here
Previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. NPR
Org
Of course if
If you want tell us your story
Going to build
Npr.org
And thank you so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why
You're there please do give us a review you can also write directly to us that's HIV tea at npr.org
As you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music composed
17 Arab Louis could seeing Eva Grant and Jeff Rogers
Are intern event cat
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag and drop email build
And customer support
7 days
Campaign monitor