Hey everyone just a reminder that we've got another live show coming up on February 8th
It's in Columbus Ohio and I'll be
We talkin with jeni Britton Bauer she
Who's the founder of Jeni's Splendid ice cream
Supported by American
Express open
There are still a few tickets available
NPR presents. Org if they're all gone
Checking back throughout the month
Releasing
Few more
The folks who've been operating as BC is on the board or kind of operating in the
Classic kind of heavy-handed way that a lot of BC's do
The way that I learned that I was no longer going to be a board member was that the financing paperwork showed up and that was just
What was in the financing paperwork was like okay you guys are just simply throwing me off the board but now I just
I feel like I'm a I'm an employee not a co-founder not a director
Bruise like look I have intense believe in myself I Believe I Can Go build something valuable right so
I'm scared to do that
Running PR it's how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movement they built
Read Hoffman turned his obsession with social networking into the billion-dollar
And how he went on to become one of the most
Powerful investors
Silicon Valley
Every actor is within six degrees of
Kevin Bacon actually check
Has a website called the
Oracle of
Beacon.org
Here let me show you
Try and connect
Kevin Bacon
With
Dwayne The Rock
Johnson
And what
Dwayne Johnson was in the game plan with Darrell Wooten who was in Black Mass with
Kevin Bacon that is just two degrees of separation
Silicon Valley was looking for its own Kevin Bacon
You could make a
Pretty strong case
Berbatov
Reed's buddies makeup The Who's Who of Internet Fame people like Marc Andreessen
Created Netscape
Jerry Yang of Yahoo
Elon Musk and Chad Hurley before anyone would take their calls
And what's amazing about his personal network is
How it's connected his thinking about networks in general about
Social interaction
And how these ideas work
Percolating and reads mind long before the internet
Became a thing
Probably best known for creating LinkedIn which
Was sold
Microsoft
Billion dollars
But he's also one of the most successful investors in Silicon Valley
And so is his college buddy Peter teal
Who you will hear a lot about during this interview
Peter
Probably the most famous
Conservative
Tech industry
He was a big supporter of Donald Trump and he spoke at the
The Republican convention in
In 2016
And well-read is a mainstream Democrat
He and Peter are still
Really close
Anyway more on that a little later
For now
What you need to know about Reed is that
He grew up mainly in Northern California
His parents divorced when he was a baby so
He's been a lot of
Is childhood bouncing around
Mom's dad
Grandparents
Which meant things were
Always Super Save
Both my parents are trying to figure out their lives and so they have
Yeah they be dating different people and
And I always have this kind of weird thing where I
Pretty quickly learned
But I didn't actually attach myself too much to whoever either of my parents were dating
Because you're here today
I don't know if you could be here next month
So nice to meet you
I didn't like no I don't want to develop a personal relationship with you
That part of it was probably a little weird but then
You know
What happened in a what what do kids experience the normal reading for me that was kind of the wild this is what
Does what growing up is like
But you remember any of that
Feeling unsettled
Well I think it's one of those things you know there's a compass classic
Phrase what doesn't kill you makes you stronger
And I was
Lucky and fortunate enough
But I think I Rose to it
Like you know one of the
Traits that I think defines be more as an adult is being very capable as a firefighter
I think that resilience comes from the
Instability uncertainty in child
Feel like a nut literally a firefighter but somebody puts out
Fires in the business
Yes exactly
Crisis solver
Okay so you got this
Kid with divorced parents
I'm someone
Unstable home life
Where does he go find Refuge
In which case
And this probably isn't too surprising
He found it in
Fantasy role-playing game
I would do the absolute minimum time on homework
And then I would spend all the rest of my time doing
Games GameStop
I learned that the game
Company chaosium was in Emeryville I was in Berkeley.
Until I got someone who knew them to invite me over
Pumpkin
Why are you here
Great movies are adults like
What's this
And so what I did
Was that publish something
And I went through it with a red pen and said like I change this I changes you made mistake here
I gave it to Steve Perrin who is
Editor the time
I remember Steve's first look at me with
Like
Punctual
Let me look through it and he was like huh
The prettiest thing
Is it look for work in another role-playing packet
Right now
Call Borderlands will you go take a look at that sun
Focus
Young kid has been nothing other than eat
Sleep lightly
And work on that came back 3 days later
With like just massive sets of revisions
Suggestions everything else it was my
Prince you give me a paycheck with my first-ever paycheck
Precocious like you singled out as is an unusually smart kid
I think people saw that I was
A smart
I was in tenth kid
Like you could engage me socially
But I was also tend to be very
I was self-directed and doing my own thing
Read when after boarding school in Vermont during High School
And then in 1986
Landed
At Stanford
You were there at at
Pretty incredible moment you were classmates with
Jerry Yang
Yahoo
In and of course famously Peter thiel
How did you guys meet
So Peter and I
Had heard about it
Each other he had heard that there was this
And I'll use the the youthful energetic language the time it was as Pinko commie
Cuz cuz I'm a progressive and a lefty
And I'd heard those guys right wing of the tail of the Hun
Cuz he's conservative
We heard about each other
We met because we took
A philosophy class together
We literally walk the picture of inside joke I heard about you
I've heard about you too
And so we arranged time to go talk and our first conversation was I think 8 hours long
Where we were literally just
Like
Ferociously arguing with each other
And so
We are
Is that even when we decided
So we're both going to
Run for
The Stanford student Senate
We basically conjoined our campaigns even though
I think totally different people
Mostly because then in the campaigning process we could go around talking to each other
What what did you like about
About Embassy
Have a troublemaker
Yo for sure
Among other things
Deeply original thinker
He is
Super smart
He cares action-packed pretty deeply about
What is the right outcome
For Humanity
For the world he has a different point of view
About how we get there
But like for example if you said
How do we get as much compassion in the world as possible
That's actually something he cares deeply about
He is a very different path for getting there then
I would
That's why we argue and talk
Incessantly
And you guys are still friends
Thermage
Amazing
Given what
How his life turned out
How your life
Did you guys ever talk about
Together in the future
Not really partially because
On the
A second
Conversation we had
We then said okay let's stop arguing this political position what do you want to do with your life
Was like a little second conversation
Peters
I'm going to a dance
The capitalism in the world
How did capitalism is the
Is the is the true discovery
What the meaning of life is and how Society should be organized and I'm going to dance the spirit of Kappa
That doesn't really strike me as something
Capitalism
The thing I forgot to say that capitalism is a great technology
Mediocre philosophy
And so you know I don't I think if you would gone back to us
As undergraduate said
You guys going to work together
I think we would have been very surprised
What did you want to be
So what are you still doing this a little bit or still kind of have is a background thread what I had decided as a nun
Undergraduate was that I wanted to be a public intellectual
Yes exactly
And so and I got a Marshall Scholarship and Oxford which is
Is probably the largest lhasa
Time in the world
With this kind of thought of
Okay I'll learn whether not being an academic flossers interesting to me
And I'm more or less
Learned within the first 3 to 6 months
Fat
I didn't really want to be a philosophy professor
I guess if this is really the demarcation
Point where read
Start to look at
Technology
Because he comes back to the US
After a couple years at Oxford
And try to figure out what to do next in all this friend from Stanford
Jumping into the internet
This was the beginning of the.com age
At that point
The
America online
Kaboom it happened
I was online there's online wasn't online is that okay I should go into that industry
America Online was based in DC
Oar Virginia
And
And CompuServe was in Ohio and so the thing that was local was the Apple computer uworld
And you're like the
The roommates of one of my good friends from Stanford is also friend of mine
Work there until I reached out to him and he said luck yet
You know you don't have a tradition
Skill set
The stockpot
We have a bunch of different
Kind of jobs
There are no skill set
Like there's no like oh You Higher One of these and so if you're willing to be a contract
Prison employee
You know we could just throw you the problems we can see if it works or not. I got totally fine I just want to start tackling these interesting problems
Yeah
And so I started it Apple computer
But you were all this was like a
Early baby social
Yes and well not social network
It was like America online
It was an online service and I right
There was a group of people cuz there was still a lot of
Apple
Fan people
Who
You know, said owner of this internet thing it's going to be huge we should be pivoting towards the internet we should take taking all the SeaWorld
Stop and we should make making you all internet
And so I started working on that
And then
Ultimately
I became clear that Apple computer was going to shut down SeaWorld
Didn't really have any plans on the internet
And so was like alright well
Going to starting internet things the right thing
And what I really needed
Product manager
So I went to
Fujitsu software corporation
Is there willing to hire me as a product manager that was obviously
Very helpful
But you have the career advice that I give people
Is the go to where they
Central
About the heat of the action is
In the Industries or the or the products or the services that you care about and then you just
Work your way up from there
Being at the center of the action in the Jitsu software corporation was a Japanese Darien in Silicon Valley
Yeah those don't tend to be in the center of the action
So how long did you last
Did you last there
I was at Fujitsu for about
About a year-and-a-half
When you left
Jiu-Jitsu to go
Glad to the world what was your
Planted you have an idea what you were going to do
Well when I left for Jitsu I had
Begin to formulate
A bassist
So some of my theories about
How the internet
The networked world was going to
Change
Could could evolve
Human exist
What kind of products
Be good for it
And so
I had an idea for starting a company called relationships
Which eventually
Social
And part of the reason it would it evolve is it started with a Wallace artist have a dating service like matched
Yeah, but we actually wanted to be a generalized platform
Blackwell
Relationship sounds only like romantically
Let's generalize it let's call it a social network
Blackoutsocial
It was It was supposed to be
What what what
Dating like me
Beat up
What's up
So the theory that was looking at this all is going well everyone's going to cyberspace it was really nervous what fibers
Everyone adopts
A username a pseudonym
But what really matters to them is their real life world
And the real life relationship
So
Let's build a platform
For how people build out those relationships one set of romantic relationships
Another one has roommates
And another one is
Is because it working Network
Another one special relationship
That was the one that we released well-formed
Everyone is oriented towards the dating stop because the dating stop already had viable going business
Match.com mackned
Yahoo classifieds
There was a bunch of stuff
People really really want that
So we were most focused on
That application but we were doing the platform across all of this
End
Who did you who did you
Starless
I started it with
Patrick Ferrell
Who is the
Founder of
Gamepro magazine and the E3 comp
MN Simeon Leifer
Who is an engineer
We got to know each other and work
Candy World
So we put a little bit of money in
Mostly
Patton die
Does money would save data from Apple
Yeah
And when we raise some Angel Money
And then
We knew we needed extra money we're going to shut down if we didn't get venture
And so
Part of the thing about being free
Entrepreneurs not having
Not understanding the
The dynamic Adventure mod
You tend to be able to raise money from
Capitalist if you view the current hot thing
Or
Something that's
Wildly different
So that
Somebody sees my dick all that's really in
I should take a
Different back
That tends to be how you should
Hbc's
And we were kind of going around going well we got a much better thing
Then
These kind of currently moderately interesting business
Scissor out there
Like that
And
That's not a very good
So basically the vast majority of these turn this down
And then Avicii and Saint Paul
Aldi's
Said he will give you a chance but we want you to change a business mod
Are we want you to partner with
Newspapers in
Television stations in magazine we think these guys need a
I kind of an online
A back-end new business model supplement what they're doing and we think
You guys to do that and he said that's the only offer money we have we're going to do that
Even though we'd really didn't have any good sense of what other
I working on
How much how much money
Social at all in raised about
Convert 40 million dollars in cash
And said yeah you actually have enough money to hire I mean edit
Tri-County
How many people were working there
This probably about 60
All in but you know part of the thing that happened is the
Is the VCS run happy with our progress
And so kind of is the model was back then I was like what we needed
Change the executive
And I said look I'll help you change the executive
Fatima help you hire a new phone
It's the right honorable thing to do but I actually don't believe
The model
That you guys are directed
So I'll help cuz I feel as my
Connor is a
Is the founder and as some of the you've invested into the
But I don't believe in your body
Why I don't believe in tomorrow after how many years
Probably about 2
Two years and you were basically like
I'm actually
I don't believe in my company anymore
Yeah and I had very quickly learned a we made a whole bunch of mistakes and watching this
I could literally the end of
At most every week or two
Tell you things I would have done differently
Earlier that week let alone earlier that year
But at that point I was like okay I think I'm going to
I'm going to go start another company been so I just helped you as much as possible but then go do that I didn't have a fixed timeline
Are you there
Rational about change
It just sounds like
You were like a counter wash my hands of this and then
Move on to get to see him so weird
Bet you smell the time on this project
And you had no emotional
Investment experience leaving like
Understand
Will let me god appoints the story which is
The folks who have been operating as BC is on the board
We're kind of operating in the class
Kind of heavy-handed way
That a lot of feces do not all
But they had
Decided that they needed to be running the show versus
Founders
And so for example
Amongst the things they did was only we're raising
The
Sirius C
Around
The way that I learned that I was no longer going to be a board member
Was that the finest sandpaper
Shut up
And that was just what was in the financing people
Hot bright lights
They had a conversation with me
I hadn't yet out kind of had this kind of degree of
Y'all wearing ass and discussion with them and Toes like okay you guys are just
Essentially throwing me off the board
Fine
Right
I honestly disagree with you
And so but now I just feel like I'm a I'm an employee not a
Co-founder not a director
And as some degree for me this was a sense of relief cuz I was like Wow but I don't believe where you want to go
It was like
You
Most were most likely to have failed because you were
So yummy you are
30 years old but it was a failure for
Yasso the
The failure was
Emotionally difficult
Challenging hard
I actually think that those kinds of failures are really good because you learn from them
Until you learn to keep a certain amount of humility you learn to keep a certain amount of activity
You realize that
You know that kind of the
I am Superman kind of mist
Sting doesn't really apply
Really to anybody
About to get out it's definitely a lot of emotional turmoil
Getting those
Simple balance statements
And I did feel very lucky that I had been
Able to
Get all this experience starting a company
And to be
Part of
A learning this is how the Futures being
Are being constructed and this is how to do it
But I was like look I have a intense believe in myself I Believe I Can Go build something valuable
Right so I'm going to do that and just a minute I read hop
Actually set out to build something valuable and how that new idea turned out to be very very valuable
Play with us & Gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor game Bridge
The Bold way to steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative to complex or only for retirees but annuities can
Envious smart way to hedge Market risk and earn guaranteed returns
Cambridge aims to change the game by offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital experience that
Places fine print and phone tag
With clear conditions and a direct
Loafy model
Learn more at gamebridge. Life / NPR
Cambridge is not available in all states
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online
Presents and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts along with features including e-commerce functionality
And mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So it's 1999 Hoffman is sidelined at the
Company he started social
And so
He's looking around for something new
Call Zack
Friends in the industry and
What's his old Buddies
I went and
Talk to my friend Peter thiel
And I was like
Yeah this isn't worked out
Computers that come join PayPal full-time
Surprise
Because
We've got a bunch of stuff to do and our model is interesting and different working in that wall they'll give you the right basis to go
Found another company later
And I was like okay great I'll do that and then he said alright can you start next week
Until I really accelerated got a whole bunch of stuff done
And then started at PayPal
My first title at PayPal
Cool
In
January
Mm
Yeah with PayPal like a hot start up in 2021 was everyone talking
When I joined it wasn't a hard start up when I joined it was kind of tough to be a little weird thing
It was a hot start up by about six months
I'm just curious
What's an important for you
Ff12
To make a lot of
Which was it
Like was that something that you
You thought you had to do to make your
So
I did want
Enough money to solve two problems
One problem was
That I wanted to be able to not
Be constrained by having a
So the way I put it was
My Ransom money
And her know you're allowed to say this on
And then I additionally would like
Have some more money to be able to fund projects
Be able to do the kinds of things in the world that I wanted to do
I've never
Kind of thought about it as a kind of a race
Like who's bank account
Is biggest
Cuz I just think that
Useless it's it's not a spiritual identity it's actually self destruct who do your own spiritual care
It's not the way you should think about it so I never got to run that kind of comparison.
What it was I wanted to have meaningful impact on the world I wanted to do things
They were creative I wanted to create new things I wanted to be
Innovative I want to do Inspire new things
To you you join PayPal as the CEO and you
What was your role what were you
Supposed to
To do
Well the
Primary the first conversation that Peter had with me
Was
We don't really have a functional business model
But we do have a really good way of attracting customers
So what we're like to do is try to sell the come
So what we need to do is we need to have
The company running with the
Strong
Organizational
Aronson
All the people working here none of us have had
Any executive or management experience about how to run
Like building startup team
Building management in building process
Cuz you get
You start to know process startup interview
You lightly built into it and go and we need that
To help package the company
Because what were the Prairie like to do is sell
I'm like literally the
But I'm a tie
Between
Agreed to join
December
And then join
Joint
Guardian
Conversation
Four different
Companies about buying
PayPal
At the same time
EBay China
Fresh PayPal
Yes eBay had bought a company called bill pay
Witcher down 200% off
And it locks on spot for many wanted everything to go to Bill Point nothing goes through PayPal
So you was a
David and Goliath
Where where we were David
Because the platform in the
Marketplace is owned by eBay
So it was a
Super difficult
Translate
Intensely competitive
And dangerous
Circumstance
True
And it provided really intense
Wartime and training for
For all of the people including myself at work.
Because you had to cuz I've heard you describe
Computer Asda
Describe you as a firefighter in Chief
At PayPal super you
Were you like the good cop
His Badcock
He has an aggressive
Reputation right and
Presumably you had to negotiate with lots of different people to make sure you weren't bear
Well I was more like
Pulp Fiction the wolf
Like I was more like that guy right sitting at the blood right
Yeah
EBay witch
Couldn't Crush you guys
PayPal
A billion dollars
Exactly
And you guys are you guys are all
Dunya me you all go your Separate Ways
Presumably at this point you could have
Just
Stop tour
Start a foundation or
Right well they got enough money to start a foundation
Identify
To tell my Ransom money I had enough money to
I do not need a salary
And I thought about
Kind of
Traveling
4 year
Like just got to taking time off
Taylor Swift 2002
And we were in the internet winter
I was like
Basically
DC is it concluded that
The internet came and played out
And I came to the recognition
Not uniquely but
Yo,
7 people that
That this internet when it was just the law of the internet was
Still going to be big
You're still going to be a variety of new
A powerful interesting companies
That we're going to merge
And that I should just action-packed not take the year off
Start Angel Investing and I realize I
Hartley 10
Is opposed to taking a year off I took three weeks off
To you
When you
Start LinkedIn what was the supposed
How to beat what how did you
Picture to be because I'm assuming you still have to raise money
Burlington
Well
What I had decided was the mistake around social net was was
Targeting a dating business versus
Doing the new category with
Is working at work impression I work I said
Book the way the world's going to change
Is everyone going to have a
Real name identity on the
On the web
Where that real name identity
Is going to be
In different categories
Racism is social identity
Professional identity
Social at that time was this big ramp
Friendster
This is well before Facebook
I need them for my space
Yeah I said look maybe Friendster is going to be the social
This is going to be the professional
And so obviously the
First application
Will be job hunting
Talent finda
But eventually will do go to
Everything from sales and
Business Partnership
Starting companies to
Finding information and staying
A expert 2 fighting
Skills learning like all of this would be belt
Obama's platform but this is the first application of a set of applications
And what people invested in
Kind of series 80 through series
D all the way through going public
Was essentially with the weary transforming
Date the world
Talent
Job searching and recruiting
But that they always knew that there was we could also build to being a lot more because that was from the very first pitch
But when you first started out
What's the IDF
Lincoln weather
Were the people who sing like
Yeah you know I don't notice things going to work
Yes Lots
Most smart people said this is got a dumb the and for different reasons
I was going to get all these really smart people are saying that to you
Why did you
Why did you doubt them
Will so the right way is entrepreneur to start
That is to say
You want to go to the smartest possible
Critics and refiners say what's wrong what's challenge but they did that was very helpful
To get the list of what are the key things that are going to be
Difficult riddles
Addressing modes
Immediately
But the facts
That a lot of people
Smart people thought it was dumb
Means that you have a Runway to start it that you're you're being contrary it now doesn't mean that you're going to be right or not
In order to get to the Judgment that you might be right and they might be wrong
You have to know things that they don't know
What are the kinds of things I knew was
I said well
Most people don't realize that the internet is going to switch to a real identity platform not to assume
Second thing is I had become an expert in virality
And I knew that one of the central ways for internet services
Spread was morality
And having that kind of expertise
Wasn't Factory Licor
In the third was that
I had a theory
Of human a daddy in a relationship so I said well
There's a reason we have a home
And we have an office in those two
Things are distinct or not
Lies are different identities are one of them to put on it
There's different spaces in which we operate in those we going to be
And I was right about all those things and so the question was then executing through them
To build it out the right way and that was the thing that
Took a number of years the bailout two and one of the things were Linked In was unusual thing is that usual
Things Are
You either hit the oil out and it goes to the moon
Or that never goes
LinkedIn was one of those ones that compounded year after year
Oh you never really quite got to the
To the oil well but we got to compounding an R
Relevance in our ecosystem
Until we
Finally you know got fairly big and then people would I call you at Lincoln's obvious now
Just a pause here
Prosecco
You at with the side thing going which was
You are an investor
Understatement
Another
Full-time job
And you were running LinkedIn at Asda
See all the same
Well so
So the first thing is I was doing Angel Investing why I was
Lucio
Of LinkedIn
Was possible because
And I'm kind of at the time
Oh well I still don't
Don't have any kids so
We don't have that start up so I could do
Kind of both the work thing
And also doing that
Tattletale like okay you have
That one full-time job and one intense part-time job
The part of my deal as an angel investor was
Which I will try to help you with
But I may be in any particular week or month
Super busy with LinkedIn and I might not be able to help you and so
That's how it work no it was an intense amount of work it was like
You know hundred plus hours a week
You're working all the time you're not taking vacations
And so that was the the pattern of running through it but it was a very intense
Okay so in 2016 LinkedIn Microsoft
26 billion dollars
Incredible
And in your no longer running a company right that's not involved
That's correct and I have been running LinkedIn for a while Jeff weiner
Co
Who took LinkedIn public until what time is good
Read I am
Africa
I kissed a bad
I do a lot of a lot of work at night
And so
I'm for the last couple weeks I've been reading a lot about
And I was like I had to take an eye to take a break I was exhaust
Did reading about your life because you write best sellers
You have breakfast lunch and dinner with somebody else you got a podcaster on Multi
Superbored Humana
Billions
Of dollars
Most people have a limited number of drawers in their head
In a limited number of
Apartments things that they can
Handle
I just
I don't know how you manage all those drawers in your head how do you
How do you do it how do you
You can stay on top of all those things in there
Well
Maybe the thing is I like feeling overwhelmed I like feeling like I'm in the deep end that I'm learning when making stuff happen
I do every time I get to Friday I'm
Like Friday night I'm totally exhaust
Write like
It's like
It's like I run a marathon that whole week
And then
Buy but Sunday afternoon I get back into the room
And so
You know part of that is it is exhausting but it's also rewarding
Write a minutes
You're learning a lot constantly cuz you're dealing with a lot of really smart people on your
In and you're part of
Like you're being a
Venture capitalist Greylock his people bring you the hardest problems
You know what
Keep my mind alive for a like how do I like
What kind of the teaching impulse how do I help teach
And I do the podcast with masters of scale and writing this book
But it is it is a
You're running pretty hard
You are just 50 years old
G-Eazy are you done starting businesses
Are you finished with that
I think so you know it's kind of this Never Say Never thing but
You know there's a wide variety of really important organizations
That I sit on the boards of Microsoft Office is one of them
Airbnb Convoy
There's a
Does the set of these different
You know kind of
Game-changing
Organizations
And
And they're all on my LinkedIn profile cuz
The horses Part Wilmington
And so I would have to
I'd have to seriously reduce a bunch of
If I were
If I rent a star company now
Maybe the right thing occurs to me it's the right thing for the world
What's the thing I should do
But I think it's very low probability
Okay so finally lead I have to ask you one last question
Pretty much everybody has a show
Which is
How much of what you accomplished
Because of
Your hard work and
Intelligence in
And how much of it is
The Privileges
What's up one of the funny things about these disease are false dichotomy questions cuz it's against is massively both
Of course
You know super lucky to be in Silicon Valley
To have the network of friends that I have here
To have
Participated in kind of the web 200
Our Revolution
And have all the skill set and learning
Kompromat
But also course thought about this very strategically
Deliberately took a learning mindset as a way of saying cost with you have to be constantly learning
And then and I'm constantly exchanging information with other people
I told this a bunch of hard-working that to which
Require skill in La Crosse planning and strategy
Until the answer is just massive quantities
Of both
Lock and
Reid Hoffman sound
LinkedIn partner at Greylock and host of the podcast masters of scale
Connection between bead and Peter teal well Peter can probably think read for helping him
Become a billionaire because back in 2004 read introduce Peter to a young entrepreneur
Just dropped out of Harvard Peter decided to give that Dropout $500,000 Angel Money
And of course you know where the story is going that investment was in Facebook and that's 500,000
Turn it to just over 1 billion dollars within 8 years
Hey thanks for sticking around because
My name is Danica La-Z I live in Germantown Wisconsin
15 years ago when I was in college she loves to knit scarves for friends
Start to say no more scars
Knit a hat I made it and I finished it I thought and it looked at it and there was a big
Big weird hole in it and I thought I made a mistake I tested on the ground really disappointed
Good thing that when she did that her dad happened to be in the room my dad salt laying there and you
After that
Some hair on top of Danica's head so just for fun she put her hair through the hole in the Hat
Ustedes remember kind of a collaboratively the room looking was like
That looks good
So I started so we're the hat with her ponytail or bun sticking out of it and wherever she went on
Apus are traveling around the country
People would say the same thing where to get your hat I like your hat without realizing it
Danica had solve a problem for people with long hair because
If you got a ponytail it's uncomfortable to pull a knit hat over it and it can look kind of silly to you
Weird balls on top of your head so after Danica got out of college and after she got a full-time job
Job in the chemical industry she continued to knit hats with the strategically-placed holes in them
I meant she would sell them online and that's where I thought that it might
Where I would keep my day job forever and I mean I was actually kind of thing going back and getting PhD
In chemistry
But that's not what happened
Like I get to work and I think I can maybe be making just about
What I'm making here if I made more hat
What is competition other people were making hats for ponytails so she intimated she made multi
Simple opening to accommodate different hairdos and she even figured out how to hide those openings so you could
Wear the hat like any other hats when he wanted to and all the knitting took a lot of time so
Danica started to get some help either getting a lot of emails from manufacturers in China what time it was
Website saying hey we can make these for you I thought I'm going to try that
So okay she found a few people in China who could have knit the hats there actually a lot of times made by
People in their homes but they were all turned out to be different sizes and a little bit different shape
And some of that was was just a major of handmade but it couldn't go on Realize
Grover business by knitting the hats by hand soap ever asking a lot of different Engineers she found
One guy in New Jersey to design her a knitting machine that would put holes in the Hat
I had every 18 minutes and I have to stop toilet about every 6 to 7 hours
And so I can get about 60 Pat and a day
And this year with her new machine
Danica plans to make about 20000 hats
Jokes to turn a profit to
You can learn more about Danica
Peekaboos ponytail hats at our Facebook page to build
Npr.org love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to the show this week
Hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also subscribe Apple podcast or however you get your podcast
You can write us that's HIV tea at npr.org you could tweet us at how I built this
I sure was produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis also composed the music
Thanks also to neva grab Michigan for Thomas Liu Diana mu stock and Jeff Rogers AR intern
Is newer coetzee
I'm guy Raz and you've been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com