Support for how I built
Send the following message
Come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is the place to me
Make it happen learn why
Why by searching Michigan pure Roberts
Hey it's guy here and we'll let you know that we still have a
Beauty gets left for upcoming live show in Los Angeles
On December 5th
I'll be sitting down with Michael Dubin he's the co-founder of Dollar Shave Club
What you turned into a billion dollar brand in just
5 years
Now if you haven't been to a live show there
Super fun it's a great chance to meet
Other listeners and Builders just like you
So if you're in the LA area on December 5th
Please come by and say hi
Our live show is supported by American Express
And to get your tickets
Go to NPR presents
. org
And I hope to see you there
I've been up all night I knew that I would have to deliver this amazing
Speech if I wanted betterment to be successful this is my baby I've been working on for the last 3 years
The bikery time stamps when you leave these notes and I woke up in the morning and I saw
Every 30 minutes all night long I had been awake and they writing down edits to my
Presentation is probably the most nerve-wracking day of my life
Ramen PR
How I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Raz
Had decided
Online Investment Company
A business that manages more than
10 billion dollars
Let's face it retirement planning
Is not simple there are 401 k s and Roth IRAs
SEP IRA CDs in ETFs and mutual funds individual
A million different ways to save and invest and of course lose your money
He understood this problem
And he became convinced that there was a potentially huge Market out there for service
They could help people save money easily and simply
Especially for people who didn't have
Tons of spare cash lying around
Inadvertently helped to create with an entirely new category in the tech sector
You may have heard the term fintech it's just an abbreviation of financial technology basically a way to use Tech
Technology like big data to make Finance more efficient and for consumers
A little bit cheaper
Betterment basically relies on mountains of data that
Beads in the computers
What's that make decisions based on a dynamic algorithm
Some people call them Robo advisors
By doing it this way
Betterment can charge a fraction of the fee that traditional Brokers charge
At today betterment manages more than 13 billion dollars
But John launched the company of what might be called the worst
Possible time just after the financial crash of 2008
Which year Messi had to convince investors that this thing was going to work
He was also pretty young and relatively inexperienced
Jean learn
Get to that point
Started with his parents and grandparents
John Grubb Dallas but some of his earliest memories actually come from his grandparents and their Furniture Company
In Upstate New York
And the community that they built around that company
Every Christmas we would be up there
At the Red House Inn in McConnelsville New York and
All of the community would come by
I heard they did they have everyone over for their New Year's party but even before that like every day there'd be a half a dozen people coming to the door
How to chat with them
To bring a gift
And they always have a gift to give in return like there's always
At your turkeys for every family at Thanksgiving and
High-end gifts for every family
Rasmussen
They built this real
Community and I appreciated that
Immensely
I also sign them a real appreciation think of it this deep investment in
Quality
And I just I always learned it was there because we have the finest craft
Because like we we build things that bass
Finest cherry
You know from our own land
I think I draw from examples and I dry eye drops from
Compare example that
Hey
They were able to do that since I think those are things that I
I learned from them
When you were kids like what were you into
Export-oriented
Comics or a like that
I was never good at any
When I would play soccer I would be the kid on the field watching
You know the airplanes go by overhead at the ball rolled past into the goal
And
I never was was big into that but I love scouting
Looking back on those experience
It says
I got a lot of
Confidence out of leading my patrol and leading the troop and leading I know these in a two-week Expeditions that
We do in New Mexico and Colorado
And
I became an eagle scout
Wow all the way up there
I still get called the Boy Scouts
And were you like
Into business or like selling stuff is
The kid or was that not even
Part of Your World
Well when I was
Freshman in high school I started getting interested in high school paper I started enjoying writing
And
I got
Super into it invited by my senior year I was
Editor of the
And
I
I interned at the the year before my senior year at one of the big Dallas papers the Mets
I wrote my college essay about that experience
And
Any published my college essay and it said my internship at the Met got me into
The headliner
Isner Style
Go to Harvard right so
What did you say
I studied economics was my major and I had a real interest in
Psychology is
I was taking human behavioral biology
Herbivore
He studied how people think
And taught me that
Despite our best intentions
We're highly likely to make mistake
Thanks we let our emotions get in the way
In fact we
We will not make rational decisions if left to our own devices
And I saw it
That
As
Just a really interesting puzzle
The song
Cotton problem
If people are so
Irrational
And yet
We can make the world better
If we help people make better decisions
How do I do that how do I reconcile
When I graduated
Still had no idea there wasn't a career in
Helping people make better decisions that wasn't
Thing one could do
But I liked
Theory of it
And I was swayed at the time by one of my
Icollege
Roommates
Dads who was it.
He's just talking about in his career he got to really understand
People and their problems and he was telling their stories
And then he was making them better and I thought that's that's it like that's the way that I'm going to
Going to help people in and feel good about victim impact that I'm having on on their lives and I'll be a doctor
Side I said I've got it I've got to pursue this and I did a post bacc pre-med year after I graduated
But
I just I couldn't stand it what was it about it that you
But you can stand
Blood for one day and I realized through
These types of experiences that
Really my my heart was was most likely in business if it took me awhile to find
My path I mean were you interested in finance at that point
Did you start to think about what you were going to do
I was never interested in finance if you can believe it had since I have a career in it I was interested
Economics I was interested in the science of how societies work
How economics is the science of studying civilization in its innocence and Anna
I was trying to put that together with the science of people and and decision-making
And finance was just like you know it's like helping rich people get richer that doesn't seem that exciting to me yeah
TTU graduate and then
What would you do next
Well I came to New York City in New York was there had the highest concentration of friends and I thought
I've got to get a job and I started looking around and I talked to enough friends I kind of got a sense for who is doing what
And my happiest friend the one who seemed to be doing the best woodworking at first Manhattan Consulting Group
He said I think you should come by and apply I think you would like it here and I did first Manhattan does consult
Voting for banks and financial services companies
I never thought I'd be in that
Data industry
But wow is getting access to CEOs and I was getting
Develop new products in
Really into
Problems
High-level travel all around the country on the world
But when people would ask what will you do I'd say my job is helping Banks make more money and you know of course
I was tongue in cheek about that and
Ultimately
Couldn't see myself doing that for my entire
Korea had to do something
More meaningful
Impactful
I see you're working there
And how long did you end up
At work and 1st Manhattan
I was there
454 in 5 years
Did you work while you were at
Consultant did you for sure thing
This is kind of like
Smoke and mirrors
Like this whole industry is like
I don't want to work but you know what I mean
I found many times that
We were
Working on projects
We could go 6 months on a product
Development and never talked to
Customer
That's that seem strange to me I mean we should be innovating Airways
Should be really thinking about what
The future of this industry not just
Perfecting transfer rate
Default rates in all these kinds of internal Med
What customers really want
I talked to a partner at
Got this
Netpartner said
John
Are there some industries that make money off of
People
And there's other Industries
Make money off
We make money off of
Money which was a way
Don't worry about it
That customer so much of course you know there's a lot of well-intentioned people in Banking and Financial Services who do
Care about their cuts
Customers in San Juan
But I didn't see enough of that I didn't see enough real Innovation coming out
Of the industry
When did you start to think about
I don't know
Leaving doing something on your own
I thought about it
Have from probably the
First or second weekend
I didn't seriously
Get the edge
Maybe forever
Couple years but I knew from from day one I felt like I was I'd been let into
Figure out how the
The industry work
And I was going to someday come back in and start a company
I and do something Innovative in differ
That was probably
3 years into my tenure at fmcg
It's like 2006 or so
Yeah exactly
But you were the kind of financial consulting you were doing was for like big
Companies
It's right like Institution
Correct
Were you pretty good at picking stocks and
Making investment yourself
Challenge really find many
People are really good at that
I was not
I had seven different brokerage accounts over the years I had made a bunch of different mutual funds that I bought at an ETrade account at TD
Scottrade account
And
Is that bad by the way they have all the stuff accounts
You know I open each of them because I wasn't satisfied with
With any of them
I found they would tell me
Whatever it was they wanted me to do
For them right sode
A broker just wanted me to trade and were showing me the signals around what I say
Straight around to give me more research and pushing me to the next trade
IND
Very few none of them really
Focused on what was right for me
Or how I might make the most of
My money did you make a lot of money
I broke
Even right I kept up with them
I get pretty good track of how is
And I made some great
Terrible investment
I bought Enron
I did I bought it at
$11
Fallen
70 + and I sold it
0 wow
In-N-Out
Great example of just
What was I thinking
In retrospect I bought it because
Must be there must be a market over reaction hair
Probably to playing on some
Behavioral
But I learned that I was subject to the
The same kind
And learned about it
College the things that my professors had told me to avoid I was
Is doing myself
And I realized that experienced it
If it was that hard for me
At someone who's
Had all the benefits
Business School
A degree in economics in
CFA in
All of these I can working in the industry
Wow it must be impossible
For the average person to time manage their money well
When did you start to think about
Actually
Creating
The business that
You would have been secretly
Was that a fully-formed idea
In 2006/2007
In your mind already
Yeah I wanted to help build
A new customer center
Service I wanted to
Build Financial Service
Around the cusp
I wasn't sure where to start
So I looked at a number
Again I had narrow down from like a my business could be anything to it'll be Financial Services right
And now is it payments
Or is it I want to build a better savings account or I Want to Build a Better investing app
Well others three let me tell you investing is the least
Mrs back in 2006
Is it a long time ago
In the savings Market
Online savings
I saw ING Direct
The company I had tremendous respect
Search for I thought wow what an amazing brand they've built
I can't do better than that my can't beat these
Dave Dave under
But then I looked at invest
And I had a Vanguard
Account and
Another company have tremendous respect for
Now you know
Like some great Vanguard mutual funds
But
The interface was
Terrible the experience was
Just not keeping up and it might initial idea was what if I just
Can I combine these two things
Great like he's of investing but with a better
User interface
Some of that
Yeah like get the ease of my online savings
Account through ing
Combined with the smart investing efficiency of
Vanguard
If I could just help
People
Get the best of both of those things
I made the world a better place and that was the initial pitch for betterment
Probably before we get to the actual pitch you I guess around 2017
You quit your job at first Manhattan Consulting
To go to the business school right
Dad I went to business school knowing that I wanted to start a bit
By the time I start a business school ad
Betterment
I knew it was going to be consumer-oriented
Because my passion
Was
People are my passion
Is consumerism
I think
Institutions and
Really wealthy
Are welser
There are so many
Smart people out there helping them
I think first
The average American
There's a retirement crisis
Because most people don't really understand the long-term and we're not evolved
To understand
We don't do well with thinking about
30 years from now
We've evolved from a time when we were more likely than not going to die before we had to worry about
Long-term problems
So just focus on survival
And so we have this now Retirement System in America where
Everyone is expected
Hip2Save
Non-retirement
Essential you were talking about people who have
Roughly how much do
We think of our Target cost
Someone who's
It's not make
Over a hundred thousand
That means there are
Professional
I would love to help
Literally
Everyone in America save and invest
The reality is
That
50% of America
Saving
About half of them
Don't have enough to really make a meeting
Nest
And I can't
Solve
Every process I would love to solve that problem
But we're focused on helping people who
Who are saving
And help them save and invest
Better
Sorry you
You get a business
You went to Columbia
And then you
You start to work on this and what you
3 * 2
Talk to people about it
I talked to everyone who is this
Send my poor classmate
Exactly how I put them through a lot
Show me people would say okay so I'll let's say I've got ten thousand bucks like what I just give it to you and
And you take care of it for me like why would I just go to Vanguard what would you
What are the challenges when you're really inventing something new
Is nobody wants it
Right
People say
Hey would you like a bank account
Orenda
Account or this new thing
But no one's going to want the news
Scary and
And takes a lot of time to build
Financial Services
Took time to get that
Message
And
The best way to die
Think about it
As we take all the best pract
Says that
Great investment advisor
Would put you work for you
If if you had one
And we make them smarter faster cheaper
For example
We give you personalized guide
About
What you should be invested in
And
What your goal should be and how which accounts to open
We tax-managed for you to save you more than you even pay us and fees
In Texas we give you net-positive returns
On your investment with us and I'd say that the
Concept has be
More and more sophisticated over time
And it's been
How do we
How do weed what's the First Slice
In the first place is
Make it really easy to answer the
The question what should I do with my money
One thing I found it was
Everyone
They were so bad
About the thing that they were doing everyone felt
Everyone felt like I know I'm not making
I know I'm not doing everything I should
I should be doing
I'd say aha there's an Insight here
This was just you you were good was going to be just you
Building a company
Hippie hats
Embarrassingly
I really thought I was going to build the whole thing myself so that summer that I was in business
I taught myself to code that you're going to build the
The site everything
And I did I built the first version of the site
I hate my roommate at the time Sean
Was an engineer at
Google +
He's one of the smartest people I've ever met
He kind of got me set up because Sean Owen
That's right and he was
What's amazing like they hurt
Roommate was a
Engineer Google
It was it was it was amazing
Fortunately Sean always pushed
Bored
Solve
The most immediate problem
Make it real quick
Please possible
The thing that I always tell people
For the day when they're
They make it realistic
Quick as you can
That comes from Shawn
Alright see you start to build a mock-up cuz obviously
Businesses there's a lot of regulatory
Challenges when you
Trader Financial
Services
It's not like just
Opening up an online shop like
Right you can't just
Pictures of shingles
Send your money and invest it for you
Believe me I tried went when I say I wanted to
Build a totally new kind of
Company
Around the customer I mean it I didn't want
KeyBank I didn't want to be
A broker I didn't want to be any of those
I think they all have
Bad reputation
It's for a reason they're manufacturing product and selling product I wanted to build around the
You don't have to be
A regulated entity at all
But everything pointed back
We do have to be reggae
Delight as well read
And I was
It was in my in 2008
I am I sexy
Your business school
In the early fall
That I
How to chat with
Eli broverman and who's who's Eli broverman
Eli bronfman is my
Co-founder
IMusic Securities lawyer
And I thought
I talked to him about
Not the problem that I was trying to solve and and he said yeah that's it
I can relate to that problem I'm trying to do something Smarter with my money and
Maybe let me help you out with this and I thought
This is it you know it's it's
It's better with a team and it said that the business plan started to grow so what was Eli
Weis job liquid he meant to figure out he was meant to figure out what entity should
Evolved into him being RC 00 and Amanda
Matching all of our broker-dealer operations overtime but he initially was there to figure out
The right there should be an investment advisor
Something else and we settled on investment advisor because an investment advisor
Is ultimately there a fiduciary and someone who's bound to do right by the customer which just felt right
Write to us it felt like they're the right kind of organization so you like Jo-Ann's by the way how are you finding this I'm in your
Try to build you know a website you got paper servers you got a I mean
How much money did you have in total remember it
I mean I had a good job as a consultant for several years and I'd saved quite a bit and I was able to live
Live off my savings for
A couple years
Hot hands at and so is Eli Eli had save money as well
The lawyer
And so we funded
The business out of our state
And it probably didn't cost you
That much
Yeah we were only paying ourselves
It's starting to cost more as we started to hire our first
But that was that was
So you have this this idea
Platinum
You launch this
And you it's you at this point is
It's just you and Eli
And and your and your roommate
Shawn Owen
And Sean
And at that time
Right after I grab
I hope we hired Anthony strout
To been one of my college
CG
Belts online banks for
At 4
For some major Nash
National companies
And had
This experience with
Customer
Yeah so he joined hazard
I had a prot
So what was your plan in in
In May of 2009 when you graduated from Business School
What was the plan to
Get this thing stood up
Really quickly
Yeah but one thing to remember is
September of 2008
Was the beginning
Exactly
And
At that time
I was talking
My professor
Most of them knew that I was working on
John are you sure this is the right time to start this company
It seems like the worst time to be
And
Tumi
Boy that that just
Drew me to it even more
Yeah because
Wow if
Keep lurking
Used
Frustrated with the existing Financial on
Institutions
I can see why
Adding a loss of trust for good reason here
And
Just seems like a gradle
I'm an opportunist
And to me
There's something about a really thorny
Harry ugly
No opportunities Everest don't don't touch that
Time is it
This is actually
Quite tractor
Because when everyone else is running the other way
Maybe something has been missed maybe there's a number
Opportunity
Really I credit
Starting at that time
I was a lot
I think it was lucky that
We got started
A couple other competitors that started at time
Still exist everyone who started since
Guys either really tiny or has been acquired or this or that
At 7
It was a good time
Happy starting
This business
And so you guys are planning on launching a
In the fall of 2009
So you had to get all of the regular time
Crazy stuff done
You at at the site stood up
You have to have like
Money people willing to invest
The money in this
And so did you make it by the fall of 2009
Is not that that timeline
Pushing out
I remember
Wow I was trying so hard to keep
ASAP Ferg
Now I should think it's really important that I be there I can
I can't I can't like that that I need any
Anytime slept
And what I realized we needed a forcing mechanism and I think Anthony said
Hey we could apply for TechCrunch
And I thought hey that's an interesting idea TechCrunch
2nd Century
Is like a text on a conference where you
You're pitching compete with other Tech startups
Yeah and Temperance was hosting their first-ever disrupt conference in New York City
The following spring may have
Mm mm
10 that's our launch date
And one of the rules for pitching at TechCrunch
Would you have to launch
On that day
And that's
What really helped us
Get up and get going
Alright so you
So you hear about this TechCrunch
And you decide alright
Week until May of 2010
To get this off the ground so what would you guys do
It was
Seriously stressed
Septic
The context leading up
Up to ten
The week before
We decided to start.
Pull out
Code
That had
Customer sharing information
About what
Their allocation
I had this whole I
India.
People would be interested in seeing how their friends
What are my friends words
Twitter my friends Alex
And if we started to user test and show it
Everyone said
Terrifying
I have no interest in seeing what what my friends are doing and you said it was going to be like Facebook for investing
Okay just put money into this Facebook was everything at the
Right in this whole idea of network effect
Clearly we're going to have some Network effects we got to build that into our products
People want to share all the stuff is like with the world
Yes I did
And I learned Anna from from user research thankfully
Only I want
To do that
So we were beer pulling that coat out
I'm in though in the week before we launched
We were testing the entire system in we've been testing at
4 month
And who are you testing it with
Our friends and
And they were putting real money
They were putting your money
That time you know we had to actually start to test the pipes right
And thank goodness we did because in that week before
We all Ben 10 Ben deposit
I've been putting money in
No one is taking money out and
Until the week before there was
Splash crash
And the assistant
Ave
Our partner Ryan
Was checking her account during the moment
The crack Shack
And she Paddock Sheaf
Freak out
Withdrew her money
And thank goodness she did
Because it showed us that
Withdrawals didn't work at all
We are going to work at all that she could not take her money out
Yeah if I get traded through but she couldn't actually get her money back LOL
So we had to go and
Fix withdrawals
And so it was a
A crazy
We can we were working there the entire way
And then
This is on the product side right so we've got two major things that were trying to get together on the product side
The regulatory sign
We got the
On the Friday
Before we were set to launch at
And of course the closer to the weekend so it's literally down to the where's the last day they
Could possibly have given us approval we got the final table
Not Friday the Friday before an attack runs on Monday
The temperature zone
Wow all of that on top of
Trying my best
Together a present
And Pitch this thing to the world
Of course I'm so excited about it
I mean I'm running through
Dispatch over and over again with anyone
Listen to me
I've written in script
The entire thing
Which I would never do again and would not recommend
Amanda never script
And I had it up until like the night before I had a Blackberry the time
And I was still like typing like ideas all night
And I woke up in the morning
The factory times
And I saw it every 30 minutes for more all night long I had been awake
And they writing down
Edits
To my present a
Of course I had not slept at all
Skip the next morning and
What happened
I was
So nervous
Terrified is probably the most
Nerve-wracking
I've been up all night
I knew that I would have to
Deliver this
Amazing
Speech if I wanted that are meant to be
Be successful this is my baby I've been working
4 years
And I've been telling all my family is going to be successful selling on my friends and business school and so I like this
This is my life for the last
3 years and now it's on stage and now
Get to see how how have I done
When we come back we'll find out exactly how John did at TechCrunch
Play with us
Gyros near listening
How I built this
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this mess
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
It makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
Is to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon Gemini's mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecure
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open up free account
Count at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated placed
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5 min
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR
So it's May of 2010
Small teen a better man about
2 pitch at TechCrunch
Years of work will come down to this one moment
And on the panel are some pretty big names
Marissa Mayer Who is at
I'm a big
Executive Google
And Chris sacca
A well-known Banker kappel
Increase a few and I had this amazing
Exchange
Where he says
This this thing is it's
It's just too simple
And people like
Financial Services
This is way too easy and I can't imagine
Michael Arrington
Who is the head of
The time and was a real booster for me and he was backstage
This is great like I love what you're doing
Credit Samford
Hisses
Support
And he comes at nieces
Chris will let me just interrupt you or are you saying
If they just made the interface
And if they actually
I made it harder to use this that you'd be more excited
That's that's what that's what I'm saying
And and of course
Is wrong people
Do value ease-of-use even in financial services
And I've talked to him about this Sensen and any
Easy laughed about it that I've been wrong you know is often side pain right so
If not that's not the first won't be the last
Remind people that
At that exact moment you are making this picture you were also launching
The company you're launching better man
Exactly right and it happened
And when I say
I really think we were unique and assuming we had
All of our team in the audience
The five of us right
They were out there watching a presentation
But also had headsets on
And we're answering emails
Mlife customer didn't monitoring the site traffic
Cuz they were the customer services near me customer service they were everything
We turned it on for the fur
First time
Write like an hour before I tie start
So how did you do
20000 people watched
That present
Temptation attack run
These are not all in the room
Is there 2000 people in the room
And out of those two thousand people in the room in 20000 people online
500 Crazy Ones sign
Right then and there
Within the week
C300 that day right like the 350 this is incredible
And they were small deposit it first or nobody put in more than in a 10K or so
But
All of a sudden
Buy it within a few days we had $1000000 under management we brought in 500 customers in that fur
First month
$2000000 now under management
$1000000 under management
On the betterment platform
We are thrilled this is incredible
Yan and then we started getting fewer cuss
What do you mean
No separate for those first you must remember we were not yet
It was
Stihl boot dryer
Bootstrap saving
The pretty quickly after TechCrunch for you
Will you produce by actual people who would you know who wanted to invest in your
At TechCrunch there's this
Blast of excitement
I mean we won best
Start up in New York and
You know there is
Aldi's
Investors there who wanted to talk to us and let's get meetings and yes yes yes and
Going to break at room and talk and I was like
Nervousing
So excited and telling them
Baton the wild things that we wanted to do and
Then at the end of the weekend at the end of the month
The phone stop ringing
So after the launch then I said okay now Priority One is getting funded and we don't have a lot of time to do this
We've got maybe like
3 months
Figure this out
And by the way in that time we're asking our employees to
Reduce their salaries and even
Contribute capital
To buy more Equity to pay themselves
So we were buying time is best we could until we could raise some capital
People who work for the company
To pay to work for the company
You bet I'm outside gratefully they they believed in
What we were building and they did it was still like
Six or seven of you guys it was it was it was five of us
I realized
We can't just stand here and wait for checks to come in
So I started to build a deck and actually think about who would be the right in the
Target them at the time we hired
Attorney and set up some meetings for us in the
The first meeting that he set up Waze with Bessemer Ventures
And we went out and we pitched Rob's Davis and it was love at first pitch we said we're building this
Company that is going to help people make the most of their money and and Rob said this is
2 years I've been looking for
A company that would answer the question what should I do with my money and it's the best one that I've seen
And he said how about rather than investing million dollars
You guys raised $3000000
And we said wow you were looking for a million dollars
You're looking for a million we ended up raising
And in terms of the kinds of
A customer's you want to go for the idea was
If you've got money to invest in your Rich your fine cuz you can go to one of these wealth management companies and
Dell
Esl like
Hop on the phone with you and they'll give you really good service but you got to give him 1% of your money and the really
Open the door for Youth of a million bucks
Yeah you're saying we're going to give you a similar
Service
Type service
That's right and so all these people decided to try us out
And if that time
Member
I just couldn't believe that anyone would trust us to manage their money
Because there's no fintech industry to speak of
I know online you know
Eden startup
Money manager
And who are we
So I was amazed that we got those first 500 and by the end of the
Of the year
Thousand customers
It took us a full
Year to get to 10 million dollars under management
We celebrated that wow that was a
The big number are they just
The trust that and Bayern $10 that's a lot of money right how are you making money
Off that
Money like you were charging
Percentage of the returns
We were charging
At that time 90 basis
Points and we sense lower the fee
90 basis points just underwear
Just under 1%
And what is it today
Today is 25 basis points or .25%
It's a fraction of what the you know that the traditional mutual fund charges or the traditional
Financial advisor charges
I and we
I would provide a
Really incredible amount of value for that
So okay so soon in year 1 you get 10 million
And then like
You cure growth is just crazy I think
Today you're managing like
13 billion dollars
Guelph
Yeah we expect to be in the ballpark of 18 to 20 billion by the end of 2018 amazing
The way that I look at it as it took us a year to get to
10 million
It took us another six months
To get to 20 million it took us another three months to get
30 million
It's just kept growing faster
Damn it was a billion dollars
Wow billion was a
Big number and it took us
5 years to get there and now we add a billion you know every every every month
We just keep growing faster and faster 10 million dollars is a bad day for it now that was our whole first year
And another slow day of net deposit today
I mean
Obviously you're growing and this is this is always a delicate question
Night when I ask a question but
As you
Started to grow let me know
Did you start
Like rethinking what with a split or the ownership
What is a mother found hers or what should be like was it
The tens with a complicated
Tough it's always tough
And there was a moment where
And I realized I'd done it wrong and in the early days
What how what did you do in your life
So
One thing that we did
Was in the early days we we created
Provisions around
Buyouts and and I'm so happy we did that when people ask
Advice I would tell them to do this
Because Sean remember was I was
Founder and was involved with us from from the very beginning and he decided to go to business school he went to business school and
London and we were working with him for a long time remotely like
Like that but it became very hard after
When the three of us were in the office and we were coming to
Decisions during the day and then we have a call scheduled
Shining
He would disagree in
You know we would
We now have to rehash the whole thing and
It just became too
Tough and ultimately Sean decided I just can't do this anymore
And initially
When I remember the day in my apartment I sat down with
Sean and
Eli and we talked
Debat how we going to split this thing often
I think they're just like
In a shot and I had had this sort of like
You know equal Partners view we're roommates and you know he's obviously got
Tremendous experience praying with
Atkins technical experience in
Eli comes in and picking oh my God that he's got to
Legal experiences can be so valuable I guess
I guess we're all just in it together we should have 3333 32 right yeah
And
I forget if it was you know
Weeks server month of me a couple months after that
I just felt like this isn't fair
I'm I'm clearly
I'm working so hard on this
Other guys aren't but
I've been thinking about this thing for years and until I think I'm back to them and say
I think we did this right here
And I was tough but you know ultimately they were
I bet they agreed that
The day should take smaller shares
I'm even hearing you talk about it now
You sound a little bit uncomfortable about it I understand why I would be to
It's an uncomfortable conversation
I don't think one of my strengths is negotiation
I think I'm okay at it but
I probably didn't negotiate the best deal for myself from that
From the get-go there
Sopra.
Desert Diamond
This is a very hard thing
Like we hear stories of
Co-founders are best friends co-founders who split up
It sounds like you still have a pretty strong relationship is
Is your co-founders
But like
The business figuring out like you know ownership and percentages like
That sucks this is not fun
I feel really lucky to have a great relationship with
Both my co-founders Eli's still on my board
Friend and
Sean is a great friend I just saw Sean
And London
Add a few weeks ago when I was there and
Remain very close so
Yeah
So I mean what do you say to people who ask you for advice when they're like
I like how I feel like
You know what working hard but it was my idea and and I have really been a
Engine behind this like
What do I do what do you say
I said those words exactly and and some others and set it just it just doesn't feel
Verdomme given all the years that I've
I put into thinking about this and all the time and doesn't school that I've put into thinking about it and
I'm
Here and I'm committed I know you guys are as well but
Ultimately like
I'm driving this thank you and and I'm the CEO and I feel like
I feel like we need to be fair
Did you did you have a feeling
Early on that this
This is going to be huge
I always
Hoped and I thought
If we're successful this is going to be a mess
Opportunity
I said when we launch it
TechCrunch
On stage
If we're successful
We're going to have
Summer camp
Everyone's going to be in this space because we're ultimately changing Financial Services were
Changing the way people
Do you see yourself as a competitor to
Talk to a Vanguard or two
Fidelity
Schwabe said companies that you know people can invest
Yes and I see SSS
Is Partners as well
Is a little bit of dislike
Club Venus in international services and so
I never liked
Really like that I thought there ought to be more competition
But there is the sense that even though you know a customer could choose between us and
Vanguard well
You know anyone who's invested with us is also getting
Some
Vanguard funds
So in a sense we're partners with them
Are we work with a lot of the other
At the other Financial Service
You know John I'm just
I'm just curious to understand
Whether there were any times where you
You kind of reflected on the
The world you got into which is a bad word
Corsair amazing wonderful kind people
Who are in your industry and in horrible rotten people sing with mines by the way
But whatever moments were you just kind of
Thought you know
The stuff
This world
Especially world that created the financial crisis
It doesn't reflect my values like I don't
Know if I really want to beat
But you didn't want to be a doctor cuz you were afraid of
Discussing it was a part of you like
Disgusted with some of the
I don't know the culture of the the financial world
Well I'm not
Attracted to
Finance and
I liked it
Remind folks that
In Dallas there's not
Really a financial industry there there wasn't when I was growing up
No internet in the 80s until when I was growing up
I didn't know anyone in Final
And a New York always felt like this kind of
Distance
Place where
In banking felt like a stinger people were
Cutthroat
We're like the wizard you know it in The Wizard of Oz that I just I really felt like
Make the people who do this are just Masters the universe they must be so smart
And when I
Got into the industry
Demystify the whole thing
Formats.
I can do this I can learn this I can figure this out
That was
I Really Got Confidence building for me
And I thought I can do it
Differently because they don't have this kind of
The sense of what it is and what it should be and I'm not here motivated primarily by
Buy money I'm motivated by something
And that allows me to have a
You are
A rich
Personality and your children will
Stand to inherit a lot of money
So it sort of this weird
Ana position that now you're and where
It sounds like you were
You didn't feel like it was fair that the ultra-rich were
Benefiting from Aldi
Rules in and the requirements of financial requirements that allowed them to enter this piece
Now you your
You know kind of gift
Whether or not you want to do you become
If if I become rich I think we still have a lot of work to do on paper we should be
Yes that's right that's right
And even then I have two daughters I want them to have a great life
They're two and four
The probably someday
Accuse me
I've run doing for saying this but
I don't want them to have
I don't want to set them up where they don't have to work cuz I think
Work is part of Happy
Do you feel
Like you're rich
Or is that just seemed like a
Paper thing I am living in the same
Apartment that I've lived in for the last
12 years
Before you had a kid a kid before I was married
The same apartment that Sean
Sean and I moved into that apartment
Together 12
Years ago
Do you like paying rent on an apartment
Pay rent on an apartment
Same place and now we've got both
Both daughters living there between his parents live three blocks away so we've got a pretty good setup
John how much of your success do you think
Is because
What's your
Really smart and you work really hard and and
How much
Do you think it's just
Just lock
Style of
This question and I I have to credit
A lot of My Success to
Lock
Timing
I
I have described myself as as opportunistic
I think that's a Common Thread throughout
All of my life I've been
Lucky to have
Amazing supportive parents I was lucky to go
So great
High School
With Incredible teachers and mentors that got me lucky to go to a great College I was lucky to end up in financial
Services which was a thing that had some real thorny problems that needed fixing to to me it's not about the things
Did I did I really believe it's about
About the opportunities that have been put it ahead of me
And it's so course I work hard
But I see myself is exceptionally
Lucky and if that feeling
That I've been so
Fortunate and life that makes me want
To help others I hate my grandfather sad
Of those
To whom much has been given much is expected
And I will be paying down the debt of luck that I've had for a long time to come
John Stein
Is the CEO
Founder
A betterment
Which at the time of this recording
Was valued at 800 million dollars
If you go to John's Twitter page
You can see an early warning sign of his career choice
He posted a Boy Scout merit badge from 1993
He was in troop 35 out of Dallas
In the badge
Isn't personal management
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first of quick message from one of our sponsors Microsoft
Who wants you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family
The Surface Pro 6
Has up to 13 and a half hours of battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Wherever work takes you
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now
For how you built that
Is it a story starts more than 20 years ago when Sherry stellenberg
Was a student at
At Virginia Tech
Where is Friendswood
Hangout app
The student center and there were pinball machines around the pool tables and all my friends while we were playing pool.
They take a break and go over and play Pinball and I thought they were just throwing money away
But one night
What are the strengths
Finally talked him into playing a game
One game of pinball
Begrudgingly I walked over
In Jesus must have been just a minute or two but had the time of my life and I
Kind of got hooked immediately and what it was that
It was kind of a physical game you could manipulate the flippers they keep the ball in play
But Jerry was a tech guy of
Computer engineer
Something about pinball that
Start the bug
While the ball is rolling around this painted piece of wood
It's not
Doing anything other than just rolling
Which by the way has been perfectly acceptable for the legions of pinball players who love the game for decades
Couldn't shake the feeling that the game could somehow be reimagined
And so in 2009
When touch screen tablets
I started to get popular
He got an idea
So I saw that technology and I wanted to figure out how to implement that in a pinball machine when we can take the physical pinball
Interacting with Graphics in the same way that your finger does on the tablet computer
Message are you set out to do just that I started with one friend who's a mechanical
And we connected with an audio engineer very popular audio
And after 3 years
Grace working nights
Weekend
Jerry and his friends
Build a pinball game where you could use physical buttons and flippers
Solange
Actual ball
Over an LCD display
Show that the ball while it's rolling towards the physical devices
Could interact with these
Virtual objects
What games they develop
What is called rocks which is a riff on the popular video game asteroid
Will you take the physical pinball and other trolling around the place he'll surface it's interacting with
Images of asteroids on the screen in mind you there still a physical component this game so the boss
Still rolling towards physical Target
But I we enhance aesthetic
As a prototype got better and better
Jerry and his team decided to show it off at a pinball Festival in
Frisco Texas
And so many people came to us and thought it was amazing people stay there and played it
4 hours
Surprising here is that up to this point
Cherry Bush really thinking about
Selling these machines
He and his friends have been mostly doing it for fun
But I was fortunate enough to have an aunt and uncle and saw the early prototype and they called me actually after the show
And they said hey if you want to try this
And we're willing to give you some money to get started
It was a very generous investment from uncle Gary and Aunt Diane
Jerry was able to quit his day job and tag
And pay a small team of Engineers to build the pinball machine
And a 2016 four years after that show in Texas
The company shipped out their first machine
To a handful of fans it doesn't need to be a billion dollar company to make me happy I'd be happy to selling a few hundred
Things that you're making it a lifestyle business
And giving people something new and different and exciting
Jerry's pinball machine is called the P3 the company is called multimorphic and it's based out of Austin Texas
As you might imagine
Jerry's also faced some skepticism
From pinball purist
And some of them see this new machine with this virtual interactions and they see it as an insult to what they love
And then they play it
And most of the time they walk away with a huge smile on their face making loud
That was really a lot of fun
She want to learn more about multimorphic or here
Previous episodes
Adore podcast page
How I built this.
Npr.org and of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build
NPR
. org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review you can also write to us
Hib tea at npr.org
If you want to send a tweet It's Pat how I built this was produced this week by Diva mohtasham with music
Music composed by run teen Arab Louis thanks also to JC Howard nor could see in the immigrants Anna's Mexican poor
Jeff Rogers
Are intern event cat
A guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign mode
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com