Hey it's guy here
You know that on November 13th
I'll be doing a live webinar with Gary Erickson
Clif Bar
I'll be talking about how to build a business in a business culture that
Reflects your personal values
The webinar is free it's
Supported by GoToMeeting and it's just one of the projects that grew out of our first
How I built this Summit in San Francisco
If you want to check it out go to Summit. Npr.org webinar
Pat Summitt
NPR
Org
Webinar
A1 mortgage
Little thing
This Thursday we're going to be running our first bonus episode from the seven
It's My Life conversation
Jennifer Hyman
The runway to be on the lookout for that in your podcast
Cute and now
Who is nadra scalable I mean all things
That we did we're not scalable we would take the orders as basically phone operators and
Would do the deliveries are salad and I remember graduating from business school and two days later
All my classmates were flying out on the Exotic vacations I was delivering
Thomas in my Honda
NPR how I built this a show of innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind
Show me the story of how a student named Tony xuan from delivering Thai food to dorm rooms
Building one of the biggest meal delivery services
In America
Rosen College it was a student
Pista roll a giant cooler
Corridors of the door
Chinese food
Get your Chinese food
Every Tuesday and Thursday night
This very enterprising kid
We go to a local Chinese takeout
Order up
A hundred bucks worth of chow mein fried rice
Beef and broccoli and egg rolls
Mark it up
By about 20%
And sell it to Hungry college students
10 or 11 p.m.
Only real delivery option
Pizza
Of course at a certain point
The novelty wore off
And the Chinese food man
Caljobs
That was at
Dorm room food delivery was
Scalable
Except that today
This very concept
Polls in an estimated
13 billion dollars in annual revenue
Which of the following situations
You want meatloaf or a burrito
Fried chicken or a burger
Binge watching some show
Let's face it you don't want to get off the couch
You want to leave your house
You click on GrubHub or ubereats
Postmates
Doordash
30 minutes later
Food is at your door
All of these Services got started to
Solve this exact
Problem
About 5 years ago
What's really thinking about
Eaters
He was thinking more about the rest
To get more of their food out
Into the world but
Didn't have an easy way to do this
Someone Tony was still a student in Business School
Handsome friends build a system that links
Local restaurants to Hungry customers
Drivers who were available to deliver the food
They started with a simple web page
Restaurants
Tempe Honda Accord
5 years later
Is valued at over
Billion dollars
And it's done over a hundred million deliveries
Across the country
But getting to that point
What is so simple
Tony didn't start out with lots of connections
In fact the only started to learn English as a boy
Tony was actually born in Nanjing China
And when he was 4
His father got into an engineering program at the University of Illinois
Urbana Champaign
His mom left behind her career in medicine
Started waiting tables
It is a kid
Tony got to work to
Trying to
Fit in
New
American School
There wasn't a lot of diversity at that time
Not in the late eighties and early nineties
And so I'd really two ways
To learn English
Russian an early learning lashai my own one was watching lots of TV
Nsic how you got my name
I am your name your name is no my Chinese name was
Shouxing
And
When I got to the US none of my classmates
Ignore my teachers Asian kid in school
Registration for Merced shoe Shank
And as I
Was learn English watching
Lots of TV to do it
I saw many episodes of who's The Boss starring Tony Danza
Pretty much at the age of 5 I walked
With my dad to the immigration office in
Legally change my name
Inspired by Tony Danza from who's the Boss
Absolutely
Did you did you do any like
I did have a couple of businesses so so I'm
We didn't really come with a lot of money and sold it in order for me to let you know
Buy Nintendo games or
I knew basketball I started working at a pretty young age I wash dishes inside my Mom's restaurant
The one that you
The one she worked for dishwasher I was a dishwasher I'm a very good dishwasher today
Emerald lawns
And I realize actually at a very young age
That
Walt because
The Lawns in Champaign or very large
Use Flash to make a business out of that
And I could actually charge
Money for different shapes or
We invested in a old lawn mower
And Oates go door-to-door and ask if I can cut people's grass
And I started realizing overtime actually if you cut grass a different heights
Can come up with different shapes
I'm in patterns
Look like a u.s. flag US flag into someone's lawn service at first use
You said first use the mower
To to make the stripes and I could cut him a different High
And then what I would do is a task
I can borrow one of their
Clippers as well
As
I am blanking my trimmers those are
And if actually make
Different shapes in the lawn
Carlisle giant American flag
Many hours
But when you really want a Nintendo
And you have no money in the bank
You do what it takes
Did you ever have any inkling as a kid that your parents
Struggling
I had a
Maybe when I went to middle school had had small observations of it
For example
The Weeknd
Ford lessons for me or sports uniforms
We lived in a fairly small apartment compared to some of my friends who had
Single family homes
I lived off of the
No free lunch program
Pretty much
Kindergarten through middle
I'm sorry I think it's small
Semblances of bad but I think
For most of my childhood
I didn't think too much about
Just just to be clear
Your mom was a doctor
China
She was a doctor and she effectively had to give up
Her credentials because when she immigrated to the US
No institution in the US would recognize her credentials
What's from China
And so as a result she
How to go backwards
So she worked as
A waitress inside of restaurant you worked as
A babysitter she works
A hospice
And and you know she did that for
Well
Yours
Before she could save up enough money to open up a mouse
And
Basically relive
Regain her life
And why your mom was doing all that stuff your dad
But since he became an engineer
And Agassi is first job was in
California see you guys move out there how old were you when you moved California
I was
So you guys move out to where where where do we move the San Jose
So you probably given where you move to all of a sudden risk-aware
People that were people who look like you where you felt right if you are now only occasionally almost
Play going back to China One of maybe three kids now write it and it in Illinois am I grade that
Asian and I moved to San Jose and like wow
Yeah this is it
This is a surprise
Yeah and my opening conversation with
The principal
That was one where he
And other Educators that says that I was like 2 years behind it
And it's mainly because I no idea how come
Additive
School system is here in the Bay Area
Hear it in the midwest especially where I grew up you were recognized for your athletic abilities
I definitely wasn't cool to be the smart kid
In class
I'm out here
Yeah there were math competitions there were
After school and I work my
Tell off I am
I was miserable in my first year it was just day and night
All I did
Was
Pretty much
Call First catch up because I actually was behind and then secondly
Do a lot better
And I remember looking the teachers in the eye and said
I'm going to graduate as valedictorian of your
Wow
You said that I said that
It was almost an instinctual response it looking back it was
Certainly
A bit presumptuous but but before years later that happen
You were the valedictorian High School
I was
Okay so you going to college
At UC Berkeley
Play and then it eventually you go to Stanford for business school
Yeah and
What are the things that you do in business school is you
Cool art projects
Yes I'm a witch
Spoiler alert
Beginnings what will eventually become doordash but
Tell me about
This project that
That you
Different for a class
What was it
Well this time it was work on a
Customer audience that you're passionate about
And try bunch of
That was really what my co-founders and I kind of gravitated towards my co-founders and I we all met
Really because of an inch
Sheridan
For local
Were they in a class with you
But they work so you all set around said
How can we help local businesses like
Scale largest
Make their
Their operations more efficient
We didn't even know what problems it was work on it
I was just that honest ever passion
And Annie reach each person
And their own personal
Connection
With a local businessman was clear with my mom
I've watched
In the world of local business for
20 + years growing up as a head
I've always been a fan
And we started by talking to a lot of businesses in the Bay Area
All sports
What were you asking them
Asking them about
It is there was a magic wand
And we could take away any problem for you this week what would it be so you would call up a restaurant say hey
Antonia Muggs tuna Stanford
And work on a project and if you do magic wand WhatsApp one problem you can solve that's what you got to do
What are they telling you what's their problem
What were there a few movie it with her diffuso in her challenges with Staffing winter challenges with
How do we know where customers find out about us
And enacted first idea that we had worked on was really an idea towards helping them better understand where their customers
It was more of a marketing solution
Amware
Put a tablet at the checkout and ask her simply when a customer was checking out
Or how did you hear about this
And I was actually the very first idea we weren't
Alright so we're that I Diego what happened to it
We realize that
While it's a
Helpful idea
I'm that it wouldn't be the
Fastest way to help small business so the maybe we can help until you where your customers are coming from and you can
Play more dollars into those marketing channels
Maybe we can just getting more costume
And and that was when we started
Gear shifting rr34 attention towards how do we do
So
How do you do it
Well we started hearing about
Challenges with delivery
And
Delivering like
From restaurants Florist some retail stores industry bizarre because
Deliveries been around
Forever forever
And
Yet
Outside in New York City
I'm just Vanowen does delivery
85% of restaurants in America
Don't deliver
See you were hearing from Room restaurant saying delivery delivery delivery and then
What to let me tell you that one customer said that this is a
A cake store owner
And her store is
5 Hertz router
Maybe the size of your studio
And she would say things
About turning down tender
15 Motors
This is material this is very very mushy when you're making cakes expensive
And is a member of how many orders my mom would use
To do in her restaurant in Illinois
10 of 15
She was turning them down why
Because she had no way to deliver them
She didn't want to do it herself K she in a shoe she was a one-person show many of the days
She cannot afford to hire cannot afford to hire
And an in when she did try to hire you know she had this challenge of wild
You know
Only sometimes with a driver's biz
Because you know when there was a spike in demand than the maybe the drivers very busy but the most days the drivers doing nothing
But she had to pay the driver obviously for for both the uptime in the downtime
She literally had copies
Love
Customers
Payment for
Formation and details
That she cannot fulfill
And so this is just crazy this is this is one America
Turn down all these effing credit cards
And so that was really
Turner eye towards
Is there an opportunity in delivery if so what
So at that point
You guys start to do some research
To find out who did research to figure out
Why is delivery not a thing
Outside in York City and the side thing we did was can we run a small pilot
You're at Stanford campus
To test our ideas on the 1st
We would do deliveries for
Services like dominoes
Or FedEx
And we would learn
How does deliveries actually work
What do you mean you would do delivery she would go and which is B drivers
Uou are you apply to Domino's real just be a driver you actually went to go
Work for Domino's
Yeah so you guys were
Your students
Stanford Graduate School of Business but you also add these like part-time gigs
Working as drivers for FedEx in Domino's just
Really to learn about how this works
We were just trying to figure out how delivery work
Has none of us had background
Analogous
And so we learned a couple of
Pretty interesting observations
Is it the first to us was
Is so hard as a single store
To know how many drivers to put in the
You know if there's for example a football game at Stanford
Wait times would Skyrocket sure you know we would we would we would know what to do if you know how to flex out the number of drivers
And this will happen at a florist to
If there's Valentine's day good luck
You know we're calling this the store owners are literally calling
All of their families
And relatives is Denver flower delivery
You can't Flex up okay but then think about you know
A normal day of the week
We're literally were folding pizza box
Set the drivers because
Isn't the volume until you have this
Very
Difficult and inefficient use
Of expensive labor
Nana and sewage consumption
Is becoming more last-minute isn't it strange that the way these goods are brought to us
Required dance
It is just this weird juxtaposition to us that says
Maybe there's something here
And and soul
We set
Let's just do something on Stanford
Campus something simple
Let's pick one thing to deliver instead of trying to deliver
Everything
Guichos restaurants
Because
What people eat 20 to 25 times a week
And we had research that 85% of them did not do their own deliveries in fact all the restaurants we have spoken to in the Bay Area
And so
When we saw that we said well
Okay is that because
Or is that because of something else and so that's what that was really the Crux of all we wanted to
Alright so you decide to
To test this Theory out
And how end
What did you do
But what were you or were you offering in but how did you do it
So on Saturday
Weave belts
A website
Palo Alto delivery. You guys all knew how to do this
Weed edible building website
Fairly straightforward
I'm and what we did was we put 8
PDF menus
I'm Palo Alto delivery.
And a mom
Local restaurant local restaurants
There was a Google Voice number that I sign up for that would ring cell phones of all of my classmates in NFL
And
And those at
So you end and did you partner with these restaurant you called me said hey
We do not do that did you ask your permission
Would you not eat dinner in the beginning that you just picked a restaurant State restaurants I'll be like today
There was Bangkok Cuisine which is a Thai restaurant there is Oren's Hummus which was a
How much do Middle Eastern hummus food
There was a Chinese restaurant
There was an Indian restaurant
I'm there was a salad bar
An end
People could call the number
And just order off the menu in and suit
How are you going to make money if the restaurants didn't know
Who is Eva
Goodnight hope that they tipped you like how's that going to work really making money so we were
I'm Soo
We would take the orders as
Basically
Phone operators and we would do the deliveries or south
Was a janky webpage
Can you call the number
Can you call the number say hello it's Tony from Palo Alto delivery may I help you yes and they would say sure I want
A big bucket of hummus
And some pita
And
You know some
Baba ghanouj music rate
And then how would you know how long it was
We will make it has to read it in the beginning would guess at least 45 minutes
And we drive to
The store call Oren's Hummus first Jose
On the way
And we would place the order
To pick it up on the half of the customer show up at the customer and use so I used to work at the square as well
Well so take a
Square card reader
And used Galaga in Telugu
Summer internship is square
Padme Scarlet Square card readers and with me
So I would plug into my phone and use that to
Received
Ascension meaning you were just being reimbursed for
For buying there food at the hummus bar yes we weren't we weren't losing money we just weren't making meme
And how quickly the time you put it out there
Until the time you're
Phones rang Tituba
Did you start getting orders
We got our first
Order
45 minutes after actually after lunch
And that was
Very pleasant surprise
The only way this customer could have found us was by typing in Palo Alto delivery into the browser
Drinking her and finding a
Yeah and and you know this customer
Places an order at a at a Thai restaurant
I'm cuckoo delivery
A microphone near me
And then when you showed up at his place
Did you say thank you so much for
Grad students at Stanford Business School doing this research
Or did you just say here's your food
We actually did the formal wear
Taped all the
Oh yeah she ever ask for permission in that end with my phone and ask them how you
What About Us
You know that and a few other questions
He was like okay thanks for the food he was really friendly who's actually visiting author
And he was a bit of
Tri-Rail spared himself
And an infuser supportive of avalor
So you
Decide that you're going to keep
Keep this going
Yes how are you if your Google
Voice phone was going to ring presumably
21st a day and the
You and your
Co-founders had to do all the deliveries
How did
And that works well as a bit of a limited term
Service so we should we only offer
Conservice when we were not in class in Dakota
Killer acid
Available
It in so this is this was certainly not
That is certainly
Not a venture but
So how long did you guys do this for we did this
We did this
5 month
And what were you doing
I mean every time you were doing a delivery
Will you recording like how long it took you would you like a
Book or like a spreadsheet they were putting numbers in
Yeah but they're few things are said that it is three
Major questions are mine.
Your number one was
Do people want
How much
Are people willing to pay
Payforit
Number two
We were interested in ER restaurants in certain working
So as we started getting orders we would talk to the restaurant and ask him it is this something that you know
Valuable
Is it either would you pay for the service AdWords
Instead of a customer paying a premium
Will the restaurant pay you guys yes
And in the final question was
As you mentioned we were in class
Set the timing so sometimes those diff
The cult I'm being in class and on a delivery at the same time and so we started trying to recruit
Drivers
So we're trying to figure out what
Can we do that
People be
The willing to use their own vehicles with people be willing to know how much
Do they need to be
Repay things like that
Those are the three areas that were really
At what point did you and your co-founder say
This is our business
Where can I
What what
What information did you get
Did you gather
I convinced you
This was going to be the same we're going to try to do
Yeah I thought there wasn't there wasn't that moment what we're doing such little volume we were we were delivering
I may be 5 to 10 orders add a half of them from our friends
ATS home
Shirley from the data it would have been to
Too far a jump
Around 2 to say there's a business year
But you know I think two things kept us going one was just enjoying working with one another right and then second was
We kept getting positive answers to the questions we were asked
You know is this something that consumers wanted is the something that restaurants were willing to pay
Or is this something that drivers
We're willing to
Partnered with
And so
It was more incremental
Then and there wasn't these you know step-function jumps per se
We are very small service dog
Did you strike a deal with any of these restaurants in that time too
Are you sure you didn't we did so some of them lecture will give you like a percentage of the sale all of them
But it's not what you were bringing them a whole lot of business
No the first check I remember cutting to a very popular store today
West Fort Wayne $1 and some change
Machine is not scalable
It was not very scalable I'm in Newton
All things that summer
That we did we're not scalable mean
I remember graduating
From Business School
And two days later while my classmates were
Define down under exotic vacations
I was delivering you
Hummus in my Honda
When we come back in just a moment
Italian shoe went from delivering a hummus in his Honda in Palo Alto
Delivering just about every food you can imagine
All across the country
I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message come from the Annie E Casey
Sea Foundation
Developing solutions to support strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf
. org
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable Lake
And features including e-commerce functionality
Leanne mobile attic
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
So it's
2013 Antoni Shoes company Palo Alto delivery
It's really growing a whole lot
And it's clear he and his Partners need more money to make this
Food delivery service then grow
They decide to apply to the Y combinator accelerator program
Aunt
Well
They get in
So that's like
Golden ticket
Right
I don't know if we've used it as a going to take it as much as just the next step on the way to
You know of our project because of some very small
At the time we were
You were high-fiving each other when we did 20 orders a day right this yeah I'm not a very large serve
So it was certainly not obvious that
Did that there would be this
So what does y combinator get you does it do they do they give you cuz I don't give you a whole lot of cash
They gave us $20,000
And then they get a small piece of ownership yes
And but you're in this thing which is very prestigious and of course all these
DC's are black vultures circling around y combinator looking for the next big
Sing
Then what was 20000 bucks I mean
Was it still a webpage with
PDF
Of menus it was still White Pages
It got a little more sophisticated we we we
We evolved from the PDF
Send an invoice
Two actual store Menu Pages for a customer can order it wasn't it was still all wet though
Nothing on your phone
So so at the end of Y combinator
It culminates into
What's called demo
Yes where you pitch an infant with there before tea companies in in our group
And all three companies
Pitch in on stage to a group
Ambassadors
What's an investor
I'm going to listen to this and I'm going to say
Tony
You're really smart and impressive guy
You present really well
I just don't understand what the big deal like how is this going to be different than
Is GrubHub in theirs
This and there's Daddy what are you offering
What did you say
Set the
Building link
6 pistols not a food delivery
And you know
Our goal is to
Not just do food
But we need to start somewhere
And we need to show value from day one
And this is the best way to serve businesses
So how
Much money did you guys were you able to raise out of those
Pictures
Should we raise
$2000000 a two-point
Pretty amazing
It was it was a bit of a harrowing experience because her bank account was doing the link quick laid to 10
Between 10 and $20,000
I had that you know from grad school as didn't my co-founders yet I had a wedding also
Upcoming my own wedding that I was struggling to pay for it so I had to take a loan
Well that's true
So alright so what was that $2000000 1 to get
You got what I mean
You what did you need to do with that money
We needed to prove that the service was viable in a
Indian market
Brighten and in one area
So we chose
San Jose
But you couldn't do that with webpage you had to at this point I'm assuming
Build an app
Yeah so so
After graduating y-combinator we launch harappans
First of the month after
What do you call Palo Alto delivery that pointer or doordash
Y combinator we launched as doordash come up with that name
So it was a bit of a nerdy experience but we
I feel fatter than I am
What would a few very simple criteria who wanted a name that is easy to spell
A name that was two syllables or less
Whose domain name is available
And there's a three criteria and we run a script across
I'm doing at the crawl Mia many third-party services that list websites to go daddy's of the world and found
So for $9 and ninety
$0.05 realtor
Purchase doordash.com
And who your driver
They're mainly ourselves
It was my co-founders and me and the early employees at doordash we did
All of the deliveries for the first
Almost
To run the business and you are delivering
Yes sound
So it was a
It wasn't exactly 24/7 but it was
Very close
And
What was it that you were
In that year
Trying to figure out triangle
Information where you trying to gather
We're realizing that the most difficult part of what we do with
Consumers Parkinson traps you
Three parties
Not just two
Is that
You have to put a lot of products
Consumers don't see
How do you get the order to the rest
How do you reconcile orders if they go wrong
What about
Payments how do you actually
Tide of the accounting
That restaurants are already doing
How do you know which door you should be entering
If your driver
Delivering cuz all these things save precious
Minutes
Which also saves money
Forget 4
Consumers because if we can save
Cost out of the system
We can get lower fees
So who was doing all of the
Coding and the
The data analysis and
Sucking all that stuff in an organizer
Michael Saunders LED engineering
And a lot of other early recruits we had an unfair advantage of friendship
We would happily hire a lot of friend
Most of the.
Initial early Insurance Murphy still at doordash today
I'm black but that was really the early crew that built the product
How did you get the word out
About him
An n
How did unions start
We employed a packet that that that that that work for free while at Stanford campus which was at the
Time we
Weird print out flyers
I would stuff take out bags at restaurant
Cheers that you're the challenge though
Printing is not free
And we
You know that that summer
When we were just testing this
Project out with printed out hundred thousand plus
Copies of
Fibro
Every single color printer
Campus and intensive into mystery right
School's Out
Yo no students are supposed to be on
Campus but yet all the color printers in the tunnels need to be replaced every day
I'm innocent when we launched San Jose we did something very similar
Printed out flyers and we
Are distributed them to the different restaurants in the restaurants got the word out
So will you on the phone all the times restaurant trying to
Explain what you did
Trying to get them to
Sign up with you or to partner with you
Absolutely I went door to door to door to sign up or first 50 restaurants
And and and later honey we we we we we evolved into phone calls and other
Other ways of reaching the rest
After the first year
In San Jose
When did you decide okay this going to work what's glucose Annex City
Hatsune
Lexus San Jose
Over a 3/4 matter of time is growing very very very fast
And
Once we discovered that
That's when we decided to
Raise our next round of financing to see if we can take the
Beyond the barrier
And you needed that money
Create new technology
The cranial technology by hiring people to hire salespeople
I'm when we launched into a city we have to make sure drivers on the road and so
Pay Dashers on the road
We have
To spend on marketing it was really
Top rated business we need at the Capitol
What's the time of this reminder because my understanding of doordash is
There's an app for the user like I have doordash on my phone
And then the restaurant has a different app
LS driver has a different
Yes that's a really expensive
Do all that back in technology it's even more complicated that we have to then build a lot
Figure out how long it's going to take
For this delivery
What's it going to be for deep dish pizza versus a salad
What is it coming in the same order
How do you even start will you get into the lowest level of detail
Tells you have to
So this is this is why
One of the best things that could have happened to our company
Every single person two deliveries
And customers
Every single day for
Actually we still do this today we do this again once a month instead of
Yo everyday
Every single person in the company
You become an expert
You learn about differences
You learn about the nuances of
How difficult is
Parking versus
If the food is in a different aisle from the drinks from a different aisle from the desserts you learn how to Kool-Aid
You learn how to build that into
The software
So that you can scale us across country
It is like Stitch fix
Witches yeah they sell fashion But ultimately
You're really dead
Yes what were many ways where to find math
Play we we we are at we are collecting lots of information which one is
Digitized
The physical world we're trying to understand
Where is every
Parking lot
Or try to understand where is every construction zone
Wears Valley
Where's every elevator inside of a mall
And how does it work is the delivery fee is how much
The delivery fee is a range from a dollar 99 to 5
So did there's two ways that time doordash makes money on doordash make money from the consumer
So delivery fee than doordash make money from
The restaurant
And so
It's really you know the combination
I'm the next model work
I'm serious like
When you
Think about
This
Disaggregated world we live in rice
Can
This industry
The logistics industry
Support
Doordash GrubHub ubereats
Postmates on and on and on do you think they can all coexist in that
What are do you think there's ultimately going to have to be one or two winners
So it is a very giant space as you mentioned
There are when we were doing our research trying to come
5 years ago there were 800
Plus companies just in third-party Logistics
I know we know about the FedEx's in the UPS is a horse in the Postal Service
There are
800 + companies just delivering parcels
That we research
And I'm sure around the country
The offline world is so much
Bigger and disaggregated to your point
You're the second thing I would say is when you look at the
Our current industry
The restaurant industry
It is not yet even online
95% of orders still happen through
A phone call or an in-person visit only 5%
Occurs through
An internet connection
I know we talked about a lot of these other
Services
But the fact of the matter is that we are in the very earliest endings baby gigantic industry
And we really remember started this all started because of a want and desire
Stop logo
It's also giving doordash
Clarity
To go and get all the detail
Even the ones that don't seem scalable
There's for example late Cheesecake Factory that we deliver from in San Francisco
It's on the 6th floor
Of them all of Mesa
Tamika in downtown
In Union Square in the shopping district it is very hard to make this delivery
And to make that one deliveries from that one store happen
With the find dedicated parking
That we negotiate with the mall
We have to find
Dedicated access to the mall elevator
That only employees and actress
Received that we have to figure out how to
Get Waters from different stations because that's where sold a large
So to make that one store
Happen I am losing sleep
Just thinking about
Trying to figure that out
There's just one problem
That's one of 242 Cheesecake Factory one of 200000
Tony I am really interested in
Just up
Pressure
You know like I'm or try to get into the
Movie in your head right you're your
Assertive like internal dialogue
You guys have raised enough money now
Different major investors wear your evaluation
Is 1.4
Billion dollars
If I'm you
I am like
I'm a nervous I mean of course you better
Project confidence
And you got to believe in this thing but
That's a lot of pressure
Does that feel like a lot
Usher
It's a lot of responsibility but it's one that I feel very very
Lucky
I mean
He think about it are you just wired to think of it that way even
Shield diamond
So I don't necessarily focus on
You have some of those men
We started this company again
Help
Businesses on the street
Why are we doing this
We're doing that because the business is on the streets
Even Silicon Valley
Produce 60% of the job
Inside every city and
Need help you need help more thrift stores we need to give them
Technology we need it offer them Logistics
I guess when my brain
Thinks about that
It stinks a bit less maybe about
You know did the company valuation
Or
How much
Pressure NASA
Sara Lee we're under I think more instead about
The future I think about how do we actually service that
How do we make the job
Easier for you know the Dashers how do we think about serving
Other types of businesses
That's where my bro
Where do you
Where do you see this
This in
Can you live if you if you are
You know if you're building yourself
Dream House Vision right
Like
You got your man
Magic wand
You asked these businesses early on
Hey your magic wand what's the problem
You want to solve you got the magic wand
Doordash is
What in 10 years is it
Is it the Netflix of
Of
Delivery is at the
Amazon what what is
Doordash
Is
Biggest
Infrastructure for a city that connects
Consumers Energy
We would be
Will be the first phone call if you wanted to start it
We can help you start that business
We can introduce you to customers on that business
We would want
To introduce all of the customers to
All of your use cases delivery being one of them but certainly I still Envision even in 10 years
People going into stores
We're still social creatures
We're still going to go hang out with her friends or coworkers are spouses and partners
I want to do that in the physical world
Doordash will help you figure out which businesses to do that with
And will be the best way to grow local business
When do you mean
I mean it's different serve different
Measurements butt
From what I understand
You don't have the biggest market share
Reign of the biggest chunk of market share yet
But I have to assume that the goal right to catch the greatest
Share market
Do you feel like you're
Heading in that direction
We've been the fastest growing service
In space for the past
Here and
Actually the biggest service in about 60% of the population in the u.s.
So
We have ground to cover as we were not the first service
Wishing very very good about the tractor
And we feel very good about the fact that
The ideas that we had come up with
A few years ago
Around servicing merchants in the best
Way I really prove
Proven that well
Can you even imagine
What you would do afterwards
Once a company goes public or
Is sold whatever happens you know once everybody cashes out
What do you think
I haven't given that a lot of thought
Yeah most of my days are
Pretty obsessed over
The people that we have
That was and
Plans for the future
I am
In the business we haven't given much thought about
When I
So we can I go back to
Maya
Life decision
Framework of
Where am I going to have the most fun in the least regret
And
That's
Women join today
How much of your success to trip
Scale and hard work
Intelligence and how much of what
What's happening
Do you think it's cuz of black
There's a lot of luck
Involved
I'm in in shaping a lot of circum
It is it's it's absolutely combination it's a short answer but but when I think back
In my life
I've come a long way on the shoulders of a lot of grapes
Cool I was going to meet in school
Things I studied in the past but somehow have magically made its way back into my life today
People in Silicon Valley who you know
Before even having a
NOAA Business Partnership with
With me or the company
More than
Volunteer the time to help me
I'm just been a lot of
Fortunate circumstances for me
On foot side of course there's a lot of hard work
And I think you know the hard work
And skill
Is is really not of one person
And I think that's the thing that
Sometimes people forget I think
We live in a world where it's
Easy to
Idolize this the Stars
To me the real heroes are
Are my teammates
And the people
Fuzhou
Collective hours skills
Hard work and drive
All right what has allowed me to be
Tony XU
Co-founder of doordash
Doordash is now delivered more than
100 million orders
Insidious
Cross the United States
And if you happen to live in the San Jose area
And use doordash on the right day of the month
You might get your noodles or breakfast or hummus delivered
By Tony himself
In his Honda Accord
It is the same Honda
What can I do
It's a 2001 Honda Accord
Too sweet Honda Accord it's an amazing Honda Accord great delivery vehicle
Today you're the CEO of a 4 billion dollar valuation company
And that you got a 2001 Honda Accord
It's a great car
Great you should be driving
I will do it for as long as it lasts
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
First a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Belching
It might sound like MailChimp only does email marketing but
They can do a lot more to help your business grow
With landing pages audience management and automation
MailChimp
More than mail
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
A Story begins
Few years ago in Miami
Ashlyn cook
Airdog
So my dog's name is Winston and he is a German Shorthaired Pointer he is liver colored away
Ashlyn was working in Miami in the fashion business and Schmidt a guy named Dean
Also had a pointer we started hanging out and running with our dogs taking the dogs to the beach and
Eventually it turned into more
Ashland and Dean and the dogs Winston
Eventually the humans in the story started dating
Things are going great
Then earlier this year Dean got a job offer in Boulder Colorado to Ashland decided
The assigns
Get out of Miami and head to the mountains
To the four of them
To humans to dogs
Relocated
Ashland pet cigarette what's
What to do next I really wanted to do something on my own I had had the entrepreneurial bug for over a year at that
Point and
I knew I wanted to do something with dogs but with a little twist
So we had bounce ideas off of each other for dog food
And honestly I just thought of a food truck for dogs just came out of my mouth
And we looked at each other like is that a thing
Well it turns out food trucks
For dogs work
Nothing
There were a few scattered across the country but nothing in Colorado
To Ashland and gene pool together their savings they
Get a loan from ashlyn's Dad and
They bought a
Custom built
Trailer that
Looks like one of those vintage models from the 1950s
They have that iconic
Paint job where half of the bottom is a different color
And it has that canned ham shape with the rounded edges
And after she ordered the trailer
Ashland got together with the local Chef to come up with a bunch of recipes for healthy.
With no salt no sugar no fillers
And Winston
Ashland pointer
He was a good taste
Tester for us because he is a picky dog of finding out like
Okay he really like this one
He didn't like this one I remember I tried to make a dried banana tree
But he would put in his mouth and spit it out so I realize okay
Winston does not like bananas
But Winston didn't like some of the other treats actually came up with
Pumpkin apple spice cookies zucchini squash biscuits and one of his favorites
Bison burger jerky it is made with just three ingredients
Ground bison which we do Source from a local bison Ranch
Cranberries and organic flaxseed
I know this stuff sounds like food you might order at one of those farm-to-table restaurants right but of course Ashley
What is Target demographic
Was just dogs
And the dog Centric nature of her business
Actually proved to be a problem
When she started to apply for the permit she needed
To launch the truck
The most challenging part was defining ourselves as a new category
A lot of the Cities would say what we only allow food trucks for humans
Other cities would say well no one's ever come to us with.
Type of business before we have no idea of how to define you guys
So we ended up going the route of Jessie
Full on getting all the permits of a
Keep human food truck
So finally this past June
Ashland started parking the truck at breweries dog parks in farmers markets
Salt lamp holder
And since then things been going pretty well
Treats are popular and a major sign of customer buying
A lot of the dogs are starting to recognize the truck oh absolutely stable
Literally jump up to the counter with their two front legs and
Stand up at the counter it is hysterical
The company is called Winnie Lu
Name for Ashland dog Winston and Dean's dog Louie
And in addition to that one food truck
Winnie lunow cells treat
It's online and it's
6 independent pet stores in Colorado so there are thousands of pet stores in the United
States and we would love to be
All of the independently owned smaller pet stores
.
We can
Find out more about Winnie Lu or here
Previous episode
Head to our podcast page
How I built this.
Npr.org and of course
If you want to tell us
What's your story
Put a build
Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts you can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And it's at this was produced this week by James delahoussaye
Music composed by Rammstein Arab Louie thanks also to JC Howard pussy
Jeff Rogers AR intern the event cat I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
And email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cussed
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week