Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Paint really quickly should let you know that we're building a brand new place for
For you to share ID
Madea's advice
Encouragement
About the things you are building
Pelicans
Speakeasy for entrepreneurs accepted
Online
Illegal
It's a Facebook group called how you built that
So if you're a fan of a show or someone
What's the Kinect
People like you
Around the world
Go to Facebook and search for how you built that
Oracle to n
.
PR
/ Builder
That's n
That PR
Flash Builder
We built the first prototype back in October 2009
It was not to be possible for it to be sensitive well that we code furiously for 2
Man's we launched his thing and then it's Off to the Races like from when we start working on it full-time when I publicly launched
With almost two years and so yeah going to be hard but it is actually possible
Ramen PR
How I built this
A show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement they built
A guy Rodger Andre show
Brothers from Ireland
Who wrote Seven Lions
Shooter code
Built it into a 9
Billion dollar business
The holy grail for a venture capitalist
Is the elusive
Unicorn
This is what
Hundreds or thousands of business school graduates working at Venture firms search for everyday
They said through pitch
Chapter pitch
PowerPoint after PowerPoint hoping that
Today
Will be the day that
One of these pictures will be the next
We worker Uber or Airbnb
An opportunity so rare soap
Coveted
It's like a unicorn
Well welcome to today's story because stripe
Is basically a unicorn with extra whipped cream and cherries on top
Choose a company that went from zero to a hundred million dollars in value in a matter of months
And today barely seven years after its founding
Stripe is valued at more than 9
Billion dollars
So now your next question
What is stripe
Stripe isn't
Thing you buy it
It's not like Under Armour shirts or Warby Parker
Glasses but
It is what allows you to
To buy those things online
If you use instacart
Floor lift
Kickstarter
Even if you shop online
Target
You're using stripe
It's basically the back-end technology that allows you to safely enter your credit card details and
Pay for what you want
There are two things that makes Sprite
Very different from its
Peddlers
The first
Is it Simplicity it was originally just
Seven Lions
And II
The ages of the two brothers who founded it
When stripe launched 7 years ago
Patrick
John Collison
21 years old
The Collison Brothers grew up in
In rural Ireland
County Tipperary where are their parents
Ramey's
Small hotel
Very small 12 bedrooms in Nevada
And
And we got a house. Milo to away
Until we grew up surrounded by
Farmland
If the options were to
Play in the garden
Dilaudid
I'm too
Play with Lego we did a lot of that and to read books
Signs
So your dad was running this hotel and where you guys involved
Electrocuted
Go out there on weekends in like
Change sheets
Yamato's hours
But remember
You know, I think before I was to
I'm so you're not the only
You know a two-year-old can only be so useful at in the operations of the
At the hotel
I think my favorite memory is the unit with the ballroom
Floor the highly polished surface
That was awesome as a
The kid for Africa
Getting a
But yet you know cover length game in terms of who can fly the farthest but
What channel is Howard like to imagine that we were extremely useful in
And running
Primarily
How did you guys get into coding
I bought a book
When I was 13
Reddit one Saturday and
Start running some web pages
I really was all said if I was all downhill from there
Saint Patrick get into coding
I think I will try that too
Yeah that's definitely an influence on and I think I have an experience
That a lot of people I know who learn to code hack which is
It's often an end result
The pools you alone
And you're making everything up as you go and you don't really understand you know you're copying things from a book
Griffin website
The computer
To get it to work
People often have
RI website
Or
Video game
Answer my case initial website is not very good
After I built it has Patrick taught me a lesson in
Insecurities in Arabic
I'll be fourteen at the time and I called together this website and they were vulnerabilities and issues and stuff that's Patrick
Then hackthissite
Teach me a lesson.
Officer Patrick
I Amendment
That's cuz you're not going to
In 2005 you won an award like that he's
The young scientist
Stella ward of iron
And
I'm assuming and maybe you weren't cognizant
People must have said oh there the Collison
Another those Tous really smart
Boys
What were you aware
That you guys were
Just really
Smart
Were you where the people were aware of
The two of you
When we were kids
I don't think they
Wer
Wendy Raquel
I think I should just this going to science contest
Who's winning the first time work
Anyone might have had even the slightest
Cause ya had to have
Kind of
Come across over or
Or heard of either of us
What would you do at what was your
Intention experiment of submission that when you young scientist
List of Ireland
Well let me touch then I got really into programming and
Become interesting this programming language called
Lesp
I was contacted by this because it's been invented that I 50
He's like really early into the history of tech
Technology
I
But I've been kind of Forgotten and ignored
The thing I worked on this Avenue version place
Update it making it really straightforward to build
So complicated what applications and things like that
And looking back and let that this little becomes clear and very early stage
I was interested in
Working on tools
Building things
That created leverage for other isn't that basically the whole point of working on this programming line
Which was to provide it to make it easier for others to build things
I didn't consciously think about it this way at the time you have
Stryper whatever
But basically all the things I've worked on Canada
Somewhat seriously having some ways and kind of tools
Recreation sex after Patrick one
Young scientist of the Year award
He decided to go to the US to MIT
College
And 2 years later
John Wooden
Follow his brother to Cambridge
To attend Harvard
But all the while the brothers were always working and cancer
Firing on Waze
To solve problems
Come across on the internet
For example why it seems so hard
To buy and sell second-hand things
In an efficient way
What afternoon while mulling over some ideas at
Local pub
Patrick and John came up with a potential solution
Backend technology
EBay user
Cheers to manage inventory
And they found two other guys were working on a similar problem
So did you end up with him
Move to San Francisco and call their company
Automatic
What automatic did was it made it really easy to have managed
Enter list items for sale
An existing life
Things like eBay or no other marketplaces for 4
Selling through these items
You could use automatic to
Track your inventory and to upload your items into manage the listing photos and so basically it was a tool for
People who work at selling
Significant events
To stop by like you no answer was software to help those people do that job better
Idid it was a kind of that could help us gain kind of one side of the mark
Play stupid overtime
We could come and then building a better user
So you guys build this
Who is the public face of automatic because
I mean obviously you colors
Super smart and talented but
You know you were really young right like 18 + 6
16 years old
So were you guys sort of staying in the background with the other
Founders
That the public face was really the website for the great light about her on the internet Nobody Knows the door.
I took full advantage of that
Pretty well right
I guess it's just over a year after
Had your original idea
It's sold for reportedly for
5 million dollars
What was a strange to all of a sudden
At that age
Aladdin to that kind of money and I know you
And yourself
Divided
Esopus Telluride
A couple hundred thousand bucks that was
Probably ever seen in your life
We certainly
More money than we'd ever seen
In our lives yeah
Was enough money to afford it a kind of freedom and really I think just kind of forced of a kind of reflection that you know had we being
Never had I being kind of understood
The treadmill has
Are you going to college
Gabriela Hearst job and so on such that
I can certainly imagines of a different version of you in my life or my career where I didn't do some of that thing
Until I get my shoulder so I guess this is the time you were at at Harvard
China and Patrick you eventually went back to
That's exactly right in the fall of 2009
And I should just practices within both of you with drop out and never return
But his head in the brief moment of time where which on your Harvard and Patrick you are at MIT
Is that really the Run 2009 is that where the early sort of idea
That would become stripe began
That's interesting questions on the one hand stripe has the most interesting idea we have come
Automatic in the
It was the single hardest thing
About developing in China
Was just the business side of it
It seems like a really important problem
And we thought there should be something really easy folk some developers in
Tattoo that people started
Starting accepting
The other hand
What we know right where that we're these two College
Yes no maybe the financial
System had it all figured out
And we were these these impetuous youngsters at with the wrong ideas
And so
You're trying to figure out in those early days of
Starting company
Clear starting a product
Are We Wrong
Or is the world wrong
Let me understand
Understand what
Take a picture 2019
I remember using
Amazon India no buying stuff from Amazon
For me as a customer it was
Seemed fairly free
Unless you know
I just hit
Bo clicked
Tempted by the night would be delivered like couple days later
That's exactly is and I think that's part of why
It didn't get solved
Is that as a customer
Everything seemed fine and then you talk
To anyone who have to run a business
In particular and internet
Business and they would talk your ear off
Remington
The stories they would tell you
Oftentimes to tell you
Is the single hardest thing about getting their business off the ground because that the providers that exist
The time is often true facts
They were the gate key
Hebrews they were the people that said yes you can
Can have it online
Or are no you can't
Answers much more important
Stop in in that regard I need to go to
Investors are Leone
They would say you know it seems pretty solid
2009 like at UIC
We have
This Internet payment thing down
And they would do some asking around I'm back
They got us right
So you sold so if you were starting a
Internet business
In 2009
Idea came to you
What I mean
Do you want to accept payments what's that you had a business selling
Oh I don't know
Yunobo me peanut by
That you would ship to me
I mean it was hard
It would have been really hard to set up a way to
To accept payments to your site
And it is it is hard to imagine that it could have been the case
Samsung easy to use
And we just weren't finding
If we came to realize that
Because was Financial
That that took technology companies were very hesitant to go in addresses
Why why would they be hesitant
Because you feel with Partnerships with financial institutions and Regulation and risk controls and making sure the things are so
Should have done compliantly and it becomes been very complicated figure out how to offer that service internationally and so the fact
I spend these multiple sectors and deal with all these kind of things
Constraints with with figure out a better way to do payment technology companies startups
Attended and Stilton Deming for understandable reasons
Highway from thing from problems that to do
React to solve a lot of hard problems
In multiple
And then you couple that with the fact that in PayPal existed and I think for a while back in the early days
It's a PayPal people thought that your PayPal was going to tell
Explain for mom as a PayPal
Because I have used PayPal not very often but
Locations where
Somebody asked me to PayPal limited PayPal them and it seemed pretty
Easy sew
What was the problem
To the basic issue with PayPal was that
Line for consumers. For businesses closing an app if you're building the website if you're building a new Marketplace
Something like this
People works okay for sending yo $20 from Joe Jane
Breadworks much less well is when you want to do this at scale you want us to build an automated integration to your website
Running a business with a
Those people just isn't designed for the business use case it was built
For eBay where can one off
Sending $100 in manually
From this person to that Yasin
I will rise when you're building a business online where your again integrating this into a website
Orion to Annapolis
You look quite different out of consideration
Saran how you do with it
Scale and PayPal has not been decided
Okay so
You guys were
Obviously super smart and very good
Coding
What made you think that you could
Solve these big enormous problems
Like regulation and dealing with banks a developing relationships
Credit card companies that
Yo Google and Apple
Clearly
Felt that they could not resolve
Enlarge person a healthy dose of the naivete of Youth
But I
You know
We didn't just leave it
We built the first prototype back in October 2009
I didn't replace Lee spent
Can a 8 or 10 months
Trying to Surf map out
Bob attacks be required to have this work
Sensitive
Near any material scale
What sort of people we have to hire which sort of entity we have to partner with and you know what that would look like
Until we realize while we need to hire a very senior and experience
Partnerships people to make sure that we can get today
First-year relationships in place with banks
And I really want a parent to a stick and I wouldn't be easy
Like I was not going to be possible if
For to be sensitive well
Naui
Code furiously
For two months we launched his thing and then it's Off to the Races like
From when we start working on it full-time
Do I publicly launched
With almost two years
That's how long it took us to
The kind of orchestrate all those details that severe described
Amber I guess we got to sense first of the doctor again that this kind of Investigation was
Yeah going to be hard
What is actually
So you guys had a couple hundred thousand bucks from the sale of optimatic and obviously you have the code
Loading
Chops in the technology chops but
You did not have
Any money
How are you able to
Get money to
You know fuel the Ambitions of this
One of the things that
Silicon Valley
As well
Is it probably has the hot
Patrick and I now travel to
Number of other places
Pinstripe has offices around the world in
Dublin London and Singapore in places like this
But I think Silicon Valley is probably the best place
In terms of the risk tolerance
Of the investment cap
That's available
If we could get people convinced of the opportunity
And if we could show
People that initial air leak
Customer traction
And how much it resonated
With the target market
They were actually wenzhou
Take a bath
Despite the fact
Certainty in every other
Aspect
Stop the execution
Between what path might be able to get
Visas for the meaning of United States
To work here
Ted would we be able to hire to help with the long-term
Financial partner
Docker things like that
People are willing to look past all of the things
To the opportunity
What I wonder is when you Amine
You had an advantage when you
When you start a meeting with investor
I'm assuming because you had already
Started and sold a business in the NM a lot of investor
Just love that they loved
To see that experience
What do they ask you where you ask
Tough questions Bible
Potential investors like for example
You know you guys are really young how are you going to manage people or you don't have any connections or Envy
Palm in the financial industry or backpack
Did you get questions like that
Surprisingly no
And people are used to that in Silicon Valley I mean by the time people become famous
Because because
The thing they worked on it
Succeeded
But I think the mental image we have
People who do successful things
It's like 10 to 20 years maybe even more
Older than the ages at which they tend to have actually done them
Right and VC's investors and I'm just people in general in Silicon Valley I think Arthur
Unusually to the iTunes this fact and recognize and realize it said hey
Really significant work
Not only can be done by people in their 20s
But is very commonly done
And so I think that's kind of 2/3 great credit and yeah we really benefited
Promise
Suggestive investors you know
Rush with enthusiasm to invest in stripe
Most investors had no
With the reason it was much more
Your reasons were much more because they just thought it was a bad idea
Are running the candidates
Well
You're a whole host of reasons it was going to be a developer oriented service rather than going instead of
Trying to
Run this big kind of expensive sales and marketing campaign is already many companies
Thousands of companies doing something like this
As you suggested there were a lot of
Partnerships we have to navigate and get in place and they are those
Don't tend to be have the Forte of a startup
And wasn't here to them back then
Viscerally
Just have a early the market kind of still alive
We were so starting stripe
In the wake of the financial
Surprised I said it's kind of hard to
I remember this or kind of
Internalize it
Now
The people Rocky fairly pessimistic about
Technology in some ways back then
Lowe's in part because
Us investors had really kind of thumb
Tilted fights Katakana vertical stripe
Partes para que son technology more broadly for well maybe we've already done all the stuff we're going to do
When we come back
John and Patrick's Day
Bullish
Stripe and how I finally got it off the ground
How I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
What's your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon jimenes mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open up free account at gemini.com built
Gemini the regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers licensed professional counselors who specialize in issues such as depression stress anxiety and
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment at your convenience get help at
Your own time and your own pace
Schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built
To learn more and get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
My offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
And Gyros
Patrick Hayes
Dropped out of MIT
John has dropped out of
Harvard
Their parents are not free
Freaking out about this by the way
The brothers are working
Full-time
Stripe
And they start to look around for invest
And a lot of investors are saying no
But finally John Patrick
Catch a lucky
E brake when they managed to get a meeting with a
Pretty big player in
In Silicon Valley
We had a meeting with Peter Thiel
Answer the phone that you're just having this conversation be set at
Told him structurally what we saw is being all the kind of major flaws in PayPal
Looking back on it I should have had you know how
Impolite
Augusta
So energetic Great Lengths
Belabor the point
Find about
How they've got a bad things wrong way
But Peter being as such as
You know
Inveterate contrarian
Was quite sympathetic to this case
And decided on the spot
Add to make
Material
Capital $200,000
Did Peter Chelsea and
Like what was it
Easy to use and it was
A software developer of omigod somebody
Finally figure this thing out
If any of the Developers
We're just
Really glad that someone was finally paying
Them a shawl now as it happened we paid
And we are really building for that audience
Put that bass line.
People were working with
Was very low
It was not compatible
I think about changed and wasp
We were
Fortunes be apart of
Was the fact that now
For internet businesses
Payments is actually part of the strategy that matters it's part of the product experience
And so basically I think this used to be a
Fairly tax
Toccoa vendor decision for the business
Prayer
It was just something that needs to be taken care of and
The only downside real you can make a bad choice but you couldn't make a great choice
Freezing now as we've seen with
Like Amazon like lift
Like insta
They can actually win based on their product experience
And that's new
200 caso4 people or not
Icon on Kodi
I look at myself
Explain how the
Basically
Your left
And I take a lift
Then I pay the driver I just
Clickpay in life
Are you guys I guess on my credit card
And so you
Have to communicate with my credit card company
Make sure that they are charging me
Acid in my bank account
Will be able to pay the credit card company later
Did you say you also have to pay that
Credit card company right like they're taking
Can cut of your money
That's exactly right so what's happening underneath the hood when you use any business card
My stripe is he know you probably type in your credit card you probably only type in one so that it saved
With your profile of any time using
In future that is security sense directly
Stripes odoo
Kissing at work
Extort on other servers
And then when a business wants to actually
Accept money and charge your credit card in the overtime it's now more than just credit cards is
Transfers
International payment method
Things like this but the business wants to charge
They say hey I'd like to
Two charges cards
$20
And we put money in their bank account
Captain we have
And everything that goes on
Between that instruction on the money writing
It's actually pretty complex what goes on under the hood
But again our aim is the
People did not start businesses
So they could deal with the minutiae of the
Because they have a vision of a product that they want to get out there and
And we want to
Get them back to doing that anything that does not get them jumping out of bed in the morning
Yeah we should be able to take off
So my understanding is it
It was basically Seven Lions
Zip code
I guess from a coding
What is very simple
Elegant and a developer
Lugz Adian
To the application or site they were developing
And then
That was it
That's weird lots of stories of people interpreting payments in an afternoon or anything
Anger and then launching their business the next day
Has a big break
Before
Once you
Started to gain momentum I guess you lost you launched
Publicly 2011 ride
That's right how did you convince
Companies to the trust this to work with you
Who's your first
Big
Mark Lyon
Well
Because we are serving high-potential companies and startups in fast-growing companies
We grew with our customers right there back in the early
And in the very earliest days
Yes those companies are pretty small
But some of them started to become pretty big
Like Lyft and Shopify and so I became customers of stripe
And of course list and Shop if I have now become you know
Every successful companies in
Does companies in India
Developed
Yes we should have got to know those people but I think more
Fundamentally an important Aid in Bosch
Enables product experiences that they wanted to have tow-in lift case for example
They want to not just charge of the customers what they wanted
Peter driver
And there was no product that able to really good driver pay my
Until
We've got a cool evolve with them
To enable the best
And you and your
Revenue stream was a percentage
Everett Transit
I was that that was going to end that is the way that
Get paid
Yeah we really wanted
Clarity in the alignment of interests
That's where we would only make more money
And the businesses be serviced
And is a guy's music 2.9%
Transaction fee
Be right back
Directions are right that's right did anybody try to stop you or make life
Difficult for Eubanks
Regulators cuz you're dealing with intricate Financial
Regulations in
I mean in big Banks presently have a big interest in this as could be a revenue stream for them like
Did the people who try to
Or was it just a
Once you started you just a momentum
The wind was behind
Police Department really tried
Tried to approach things differently. I think how technology companies often tend to
I
Technology computer think off an episode of go It Alone mentality will build it all in-house will do it all ourselves we can do things better than ever
From the outside world
Where's we thought the tribe would only be possible and it would only be possible to do it well
If we partnered closely with people who a deep expertise and experience and industries that we ourselves were less familiar
I live in the very beginning before we launched we partner Toshiba thanks and now we work with thanks and you too many different country
And I'm not just Banks because of other financial institutions
Besides
But we really wanted to build a stripe instead of in a multi
Decade thing
And if we're going to go and to do it that way we we really had to do it right so as you started to really
Juno launched in
Develop and get more more tension
Why didn't
The competitors come out from the woodwork white and like PayPal or
These other transaction
Square stuff say
What should I do with a do
Do they try
Well what we are doing doesn't look that important back that it wasn't the case instead of we immediately
Herbal what we're doing immediately
Looks like it was obviously working and obviously of major significance
We were
Back then in the eyes of others that are working with all these inconsequential little company
I end
Making their lives a bit easier but well was this mobile payment thing actually going to amount to much
In a curious world where they're actually that made developers that would be signed a successful companies me
Acana can I get back to this pessimism
Around technology that can exist
Silver Bells Ranch
Does a 9 mm tenants on that is one of the great fact about horrendous
Is it you cannot
Hearn
Money
Integrate products
As a kind of mechanical operation
If it were possible
There be many more great iPhone competitor
Facebook would have been long since he kept my MySpace or Yahoo or Google or
Good to use
The intricacies
I've good product of good design of good architecture
Those can't be triggered a replica
I mean I mean essentially your
Competitor that has was
Was you guys
I think it's
An amorphous
Combination for any of these products single stripe out
For any great product at some amorphous combination of set of
The ethos in the culture and the Pea
People
And
To the work Style
Kind of a fingertip sense
For the priorities
And all these things are just like very hard to copy I mean it
DeSilva Continuum at where
At one end to your
Your manufacturing steel
I'm at the other end your
Yeah you're manufacturing novels
And
In steel manufacturing sure you can turn Capital into a more better cheaper
4 steel and at the other end it's very hard to know how you how you turn the money into can a better writing
And software is is somewhere in between
And I think this is kind of
Consulate the challenge
For people looking to analyze and make predictions in the
The industry for again
Google should have beaten Facebook yeah Google it every advantage against Facebook they had
I am more people more money more distribution more brand recognition Morris can have any
Any of the obvious Imports
And yet somehow there was something this
What would you think of this number
Blast your nine points
2 billion dollars
Does that mean anything to you Amanda's abstract
Do you think
And I'm rich or are disabled
Cross your
Mighty mustard some level right
It's been my experience that people pay a huge amount of attention
To the headline numbers of of Silicon Valley come
Stripes a company that's being valued in
In fundraising
At night you and I
$2,000 are Apache
There is an assumption baked in
That striped
Continues to execute very strongly on the so
It would be very dangerous mode to slip into
Tired
Becoming rearward looking
I'm looking at everything that has happened
And today is because the most
Irrelevant fact
Is
Possibly release in 2018 hotly releasing 28:9
19 Stripes Global expansion looks like
Some things like that
You don't have a volleyball
Company
Unless the company
Execute
It's very Dynamic is a very careful way of saying I hate
What
How much of the success of his company do tribute to
Your skill and
Your
You know
Your intelligence how much to lock
I need the questions last about
How much can be attributed to
My
Skill and intelligence
And instead to
Fiscal intelligence of the
Hundreds of people who got in the Striped where it is
And I guess I would say
That's gilland
Intelligence and especially most importantly
Tents
Application and hard work
I think all the things are necessary
I think had they not being there had their
Not being so many people who just
Came up with
So many smart ways of doing things and
Amenities is toils
At such length
Does not chat
It's not a sliver of the chance that will be here
But I also think that the luck was required
The dirt again
Groups of people who are
Smarter and harder working at us
Who
It just didn't have the same gun
You are
Still both you guys are still
So young I mean
You know
You're at a
Everyday but
Everyday but little at a point in life where lots of
People are just starting out
Eating at the same age
So
When did you guys know
That this was
You know it was going from
This idea that you have in Cambridge Massachusetts
To raising 2 million to
Bengali
20 + 100
Billion and then today
How much is 10 billion. When did you
Did you have a moment
Julius a packing said
Wow
Rebuilt
Never really been time for that
I have
And there's nothing like a young company to
Every morning remind you that those
So much
Left to be done
That's not yet working the way it should be
I mean if it's really quite visceral
You wake up in the morning
Android 20 emails in your inbox
Somehow all related to
Two things that you're doing badly or wrongly
There's never a moment when I feel
Successful and
The quote that I
Kind of stop and think about it from Greg lemond saying
Did the first
It never gets easier you just go faster
And
Are you still going to
Cycle quite a bit and
There's a lot of Sudafed
Painful truth
That wear
As you cycle more you practice more zika
If it is you get faster is your form gets better
Sure
You start
Cycling faster your times get better
With the experience of being on the bike never gets easier
The pain that you feel on the first bike ride
That's the same pain that you're going to feel on your 500 bike ride
Just Begun much faster than 500
And I kind of feel like I can just start up for
Everyday now
The
Problems and challenges
And
Visceral pain is just as cute
Cuz when we were starting out
The problem we just have a different form
It's it's
Relentless
Process of
Trying to
Shift
But it is that
Exists and what
Collectively match
Create so far
Interpol
All set at
Creating the first
And we still quite a way to go there
Patrick and John Collison founders
Stripe
In 2017 John Collison
With the youngest self-made
Billionaire
On Earth
How do I get the brothers are also voracious readers Patrick recommends
Everything from the collected lectures of Richard
Find men to the collected works of Jorge Luis borja
And last year Patrick and John decided to launch in
In house
Intellectual Journal at stripes
It's called increments and it's meant to be
Online Gathering Place
Engineers
In the cut
A community
And stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first thanks to one of our sponsors Auburn
The brand new allbirds
Tree Runners are light
Breezy shoes made from
Sustainably sourced responsibly harvested
Tree fibers
Head to allbirds.com
How to find your perfect pair
Today
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
And the story comes to us from Selma Alabama
With Robert Armstrong
And his grandmother Anis of our family
Lifted the Great Depression even her accident was
Older Southern she would say
Bara
For butter and butter is the operative word here because Robert grandma
She used a lot of butter in her recipes especially in her family famous
Pecan chocolate chip cookies never tasted anything
Like the way my grandmother bacon
But they were small
Are Krispy and it was a
A good bit of butter in it so it
The Taste would linger
And I told her when I was in junior high school at
You know I make $1000000 off these cookies one day
Intellij idea kind of stayed with Robert
So
After we got our ecology thought today you know maybe I'll try this
Maybe I will bake and sell my grandma's cookies
But the problem
He had never baked a cookie in his life
Convince my grandmother to teach me how to bake them
And she got thought it was funny and that she had no idea that
Somebody would want to make a business out of it
She was all for it was just go absolutely so
Show step by step
In her kitchen
Chinese. Robert how to make her buttery pecan chocolate chip cookies
And then he tried making them himself very first day I begged about 3,000 cookies by hand it exist
Laughing like my grandmother told me and it rained that day and it was humid in the kitchen but I had no idea that that
That was going to affect the products open a all
Turn to Mush so I got to throw them all away and that's when Robert learned rule number one of cookie making
No humidity
Anyway he eventually figured it out he found a tiny kitchen in an abandoned restaurant in Selma
And he started placing his cookies in specialty shops
Around the city and around the state
For two years that was life
He was selling cookies in the afternoon and baking them early in the morning
I called it cookie present for a little while because it was just I was in there by myself for so many hours but
You sitting here baking cookies in your thinking there's got to be a better way
I'll think I'll make about $4 an hour at the time
Robert could not pay his bills
Soca 2011 he actually shut
The cookie business down and he tried a bunch of other jobs
T-shirt printing business I did it online so beef and pork to the military for a little while
Going from job to job
And this is for like 2 years GPS monitors
Robert kept thinking he should go back to what he really loved doing
Back to the cookies and thought you know
I proved the concept proof people would pay money for this thing
But this time around Robert knew that
If you wanted to make money on the cookies
He had to find a real Bakery to bake them in some serious Brokers to sell them
After months of calling around he finally found a bakery in Pennsylvania that says it's okay you know we'll give it a shot
So we work for
Domotz on the recipe taking it from you know cups in teaspoon family recipe to an industrial
Recipe that could
Be back on some industrial equipment
We took out a line of credit with a package with his grandma on the
Front
I called them
G Mama cookies G4 Danny which was her family nickname
She was me I would blush some that are facing her kind of her name is all over the place
But she was my number one cheerleader passed away
I got to see how G Mama's has grown since it relaunched
Cookies are now in stores all over the southeast and in some big stores to like Publix and Walmart
And last year
G momma's Revenue was nearly half a million dollars
You can find out more about G Mama cookies on our Facebook page and of course
If you want to tell us your story go to bills. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to
And thanks for listening to our show this week you want to find out more or hear previous episodes of How I built
Npr.org please also subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcasts or
However you get your podcast you can also write us at HRBT at npr.org completed
That's at how I built this our show is produced this week by Thomas Luke from Teen Arab Louis composed of
Music salsa to Newark could see leave a grandson has Michigan for and Chip Rogers
I'm listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com