Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Support for this podcast comes from American Express open
If you listen to how I built this you're curious about
Ideas and you probably have some ideas
Of your own
American Express open
Help you with money
Know how
You can turn those ideas
Action
Is it open. Com
Business done
It was the call that none of us could imagine ever wanted to get a pint of ice cream in Lincoln Nebraska
Is it positive for Listeria so we decided that we're going to recall everything
That 265 tons of ice cream in the world came back to us
And there we were did you think there's a possibility that you would shut down that your business could basic
I think at that point we realize that that was it and it was weird because
All the time just like I don't even have any ideas
York is how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind them
Movements
A special live episode College Dropout from Columbus makes hot pepper oil ended
Chocolate ice cream from that guilt Jenny's
Growing ice cream Empire was more than 30 stores
Cross America
Interesting little fact about
The Columbus Ohio area
It's actually one of the major food incubators in America
When do you start their sodas Bob Evans
Buffalo Wild Wings
Max & Erma's
Yes in Columbus
And what are the theories about why that is
Is because for a long time the population of Columbus was a
Pretty good proxy for the general population of the United
States
So if
People in
Columbus liked it
It was a good chance that the rest of America would two
If you know this
It kind of makes sense that ice cream flavors like
Juniper and lemon curd or
Osmanthus
Blackberry crackle whatever that is
Have also come out of Columbus
Because that
Is the city were jeni Britton Bauer
Fence
Tests
Oliver weird and
Wonderful ice cream
It's an ice cream brand that could only have come from the mind of a perfume maker which as you will hear
Was almost with Jenny became
I recently went to Columbus to meet Jenny and we chatted in front of a live audience
To be honest
It kind of felt like they all knew Jenny persols
Do right
It feels a little bit like you're like your your bar mitzvah
Is everyone who knows you
I know every single one of you
Let's start at the
You moved around a lot as a
A kid what is your
Parents do
That meant that you guys moved around a lot
I don't know they got bored
My mom could ask her
She got they got they we moved
And it wasn't very far
But we would move to a new school
Yeah so from the time I can remember we went to New School almost every year every couple of years
And
I don't know it didn't bother me
But even in Peoria Illinois where I started out we went
To several schools
There and I moved here when I was 12
What do you remember about
Like did you remember feeling unsettled you remember feeling that
Do you know
You didn't have stability as a kid
No I don't I don't feel I didn't feel that the funny thing is I'm a parent now and I wouldn't do that to my kids
I mean I was also very shy and fairly introverted
You know you think that that would be you know that would be horrible to have to go start in a new school and find new friends every year
Where to but
I don't really remember it being that way in fact when I moved to Dublin Ohio I moved from a small town
Call Dunlap Illinois I think the population was like 500
1985 I went to orientation
In summer before school started
And there were 40 other kids there in the whole grade came out to like
You know just to greet me and say
Welcome
To Dublin
But it turns out it was just a new kids
For 7th grade
In Dublin Ohio Ellen was going through a big boom then so you say you said you were interpreted as a
Kid how do you think
Someone would have described you I'm with
Is that how
Like a grown-up or describe you like our Jenny she's really quiet over there said
She's going to make it one
No they would have said
So kind and patient
Quiet
Rule follower all the things that I'm not
Really
And so I have read that like even as a kid
You were like already hustling like you were selling
Plastic straws filled with powdered Kool-Aid and sugar and selling them as Pixies
The true yeah one of my very successful businesses
I had three other people selling
M to in
We were selling them all over the school I went to a big school then
And did you go to high school here in Columbus
I didn't get my last couple of years at a Burlington High School
And so you must have been
Okay I'm pretty good cuz you got into Ohio State University right
By the time I got up early so I was very good at figuring out how exactly to get
Tracy's
Like
I knew exactly what I had to do cuz I always filled math
I threw it out
I just didn't even bother
Because then I would go to summer school and I can get an A
And they would merge the two grades
Together
And other things in the evening and that was great
So how did you get the
They were
Pretty sure that I wasn't going to get into college the guidance counselors because I also refuse to take the SAT I really
I thought that was horrible I still think that's horrible, it's horrible
You can't judge people by that kind of stuff it's just not right
So
They wanted me to do it but you know what that takes six weeks in a class that cost $350
And I have things to do
So we're going to Ohio State so of course I applied to Ohio State
And they said no thanks
But I wrote him a letter
I was just like what okay I know you like I get it but
Here's what I was doing
While I was not getting
Good rates
And the next thing I knew I got a letter in the study of I was accepted to a state fall quarter
Can you get too high
First aid and you
Video arcade
You get to the Ohio State
And you you decide to study art history
So yummy
I started in our because I always on her because my grandmother was not as my mom was very end.
I was I always hanging out in the art department at school
And then I was blown away by art history
Like not
Off my feet because
It was like a real
Like emotional look at what really happened versus history being with other people
Decided history would be
I would go to art history classes
And my brain felt like it was on a treadmill I wouldn't leave
Out of breath
I guess it was why you were a student that you started get into like making your own perfume
I did it was a creative time for me I was trying to figure out what I was going to become
Also
True that when you study art and art history
Mostly
I'm everybody in your life wants to know what you're really going to do
So you get bombarded with that question which isn't fair but
You know
So I was working at a pastry shop and I was thinking about maybe quitting school and going to pastry school I knew I would have a business one day.
You already knew that when you were a suit
Yeah
That was where I was headed
And then I got into perfume vials of sin
Like spearmint or one that kind of smell like
Tarragon or whatever
So then I got really into sex I'm late
I'm really into that and I was good at sent and I knew sent from my
Childhood
That got me really inappropriate I think I should be perfumer
And at the time
That didn't for me mean
So I should probably send it for some chemistry classes that wasn't what it meant for me what it meant for me was I need to go to the
The travel agency and see if I can get a one-way ticket to Grasse France
Perfect and hustle and figure out somebody to help me and then I'll learn all that stuff and
You know I'll be coming
Nose
And that would be great
Go to the travel agency and you get a ticket to grass in France right and
No I didn't do that okay I didn't do that again I didn't do that
So I'm so I'm doing that that's for that's okay so that's where I went when you're doing in my house
Building them
Yeah yeah as rain the most
I'm telling you I was giving away and I
I never couple years ago at a few books on there then
And then I have this one essential oil that was oil Cayenne that doesn't have a scent at all just has physical
Heat on your tongue so I was one of you got to cook with
Essential oils to Road
German pasta riverlink basil
Read me the news
Motion to some chocolate ice cream
Like from your freezer
Why was Botham I didn't have any
Oil into my
How can I stream
Does going to make a spicy
Frozen
And so I did that and it was
It was incredible so I took a bite and it
It was cold in the
Taste of the sugar in the chocolate in like a few seconds later
Heat
And it was a first video
Ice cream
Hot thing I thought it was like
Amazing so
Amelia me to rose petal ice cream with vanilla and started to think like
Ice cream is the perfect carrier
I've sent these oils right
This really quickly making different
Edible perfume in a way
Your ice cream you were buying like
Pint of Haagen-Dazs or whatever
And that she didn't
Experimenting
Yep and
How to make my eyes
Maybe
2 weeks later
Wow this is like
And did you know how to make ice cream in a bakery so you had some
Skills bug
Did you know
How to Star Wars start
I did not
Do Cuisinart canister ice cream machine that you have on me about it
For this
Project I am really like taking that much as a
And I should put that into some kind of because I like all desserts
So ice cream was just on the bottom
Right before cookies all cookies
I like ice I like ice cream I just didn't
Love ice cream
And how long before you were making decent ice cream cuz I have to assume like
You suck
Well now I would say it all was horrible
The first of all
The when I put the essential oils into the ice creams
Like I knew and I had one of those moments that
You read about
We're like the sky opened up
And I knew that I was going to make ice cream for the rest of my life
And I think that the reason it happened is because
Has I've been studying all the things that interested me and this is exactly where they all converge
I understood that butterfat meltable old body temperature because
I was working with other fast the perfumers off and use van
Emilio contractor skin
And so I knew that but if I was kind of a pet
And that ice cream with a perfect carrier of scent
Could tell stories because I've been thinking about that
From an art perspective
And then I knew a little bit about pastry because I've been working in pastry shop in the pastry kitchen and thinking about that so those things kind of crossed over
In ice cream
End
I didn't know what I need to do I thought I knew what I needed to do what I needed
I quit at school and go
Do it
I guess it was around 1996 when you did that you actually dropped out of
OU Ohio State
City University
What you do at an ice cream store which is kind of
Crazy
How was like a mentally that you took
How to say all right you know what time dropout
And
What was actually really easy because I was in a figure drawing class near three hours
I'm a model watching that I always had trouble drawing
And
She's like tall and beautiful and Andrew angular and so had and I couldn't get good work when I
Withdraw her
And so I was like I was just deflated
And
I sat there I just want to go home and make ice cream
So I did I just
Shut up
And left I left all it was portfolio week unless all of my art there that I had done I left all of my supplies there
Those are expensive if you know anybody is an artist or studies are at those works but you work hard to get those supplies
I mean at that point did you
Good enough
Add ice cream making
How did you
What was your next act like how did you even have the money
Open up a shop to
Make a business
What was it you had a friend and so she and I were were messing around with this together and
And she was able to get all of it from Paris
South County
So we are
So that was actually the easy part
For that one
And I started stalking the North Market we started going to North Park is an indoor Public Market
In Columbus
And you you went to them and said hey I want to get a contract with you to have a stall or
Yeah because the market had just moved into a brand new
Bigger space than what it had been in Advent in a quonset hut for many years
3 weeks are going there and you know they were just not into it they are just not into it all day or very they wanted
The market to be a grocery destination in Columbus
And I screamed it didn't fit at all
Without Vision that they have the market at all
Three-step going back
New casino
Really
There was a show on
Pedia is the Turning Point the show there was a show on PBS
About eyes are there another one about sandwiches they had a couple of different shows they put out
And they're really good and on the ice cream show
Showcase
A company called facets
At the Reading Terminal Market in Philadelphia
And the Heritage amazing ice cream company
And they started right there in the market needs to have a thriving business in the market
And I I had to call my grandfather to have him
Record this on the VCR
Haha
In Florida because apparently I didn't know anybody with VCR I don't know
But that was what I did
Anyway he recorded it and send it to us and that was how we got in the market because they watched
That and realize that a nice ring company can be a thriving part of a part with writing Market
To you go to the North Market
In Columbus
And what you set up a stand and you guys call it scream
Ice cream ice cream ice cream
Bring it in
An enso
And if I like was it already we are doing weird and unusual flavors was actually chocolate vanilla strawberry
Your first few flavors
David Carroll
Was was one of her sons of Wildberry lavender
Fly the flavors that we do now that courses hot chocolate one
And then I start using ingredients from the market
To send in flavored ice cream so we would have
Bye-bye
Basil or some herb from the farmer outside and then use that
Deep in the cream
And cream would absorb all of that sends when you lock it in there when it's frozen and then
Wizard of unfurling your palette
If we went back in time 20 years and try that ice cream would it taste exactly like it
They said it wouldn't it would it was
Some of the flavors would be similar Celtic Carol was was similar
But it was in the in the body and texture the ocean that I wasn't able to get right
So what do people make of you guys at
At this stop and you because you are a super young and kind of
Like
Alternative lights
Take care most the time and I were
Gucci outfits and
A lot of vintage stuff and
I thought it was cool I thought it was like
I thought it was like the artist making ice cream and it's funny looking back on that too because I like whenever you like I never got to the artist Park
Like I was studying art you know I mean I never even did that
You know
But I just thought that was cool that's like a cool business you you know
Did you something different everyday
And people will come in and be
Just so excited to see what you're doing that day
Not how we that's not like what a business assistant
How even I
Approach businesses
I mean did you get
Lots of great feedback I mean what was it was a lot of Buzz around a lot of Buzz around it
Maybe a little bit in the beginning
You know some people in the market you know when would come by and they liked our ice creams but you know we had $9 days
I think the worst day ever had a $3 day
Well that might have been
I mean one ice cream cone
Yep we barely got by but we did
I made $630 a month for the entire time we were open I took that home to live off of
For those 3 4 years
I'm into you say I mean cuz you're selling ice cream all day and you're making it all night there and that's
Stop making it all day selling it all day
It was great I mean it was great for for a long time it was really great I would wander the market
Talk to Merchants I got to learn about everything that they do I learn from the cheesy Isle about cheese the Wine Guy All About Wine a lot
Are the markets only busy when it's busy and it's not busy so I learned a lot I learned everything I know about food and learn.
What do you know about business and
People in
I'm all those days and I wouldn't sell it over the counter and learn how people reacted to
To it and did it
Feel to you like you were flailing or did it feel to you like it was
It was kind of working
The first years it felt like it was about to work
And then it started to feel like we were flailing
Yeah and then it started to feel like you know I don't know that this is ever going to work I don't know that my business partner is going to be really into this
Really wasn't your kind of gone the whole time she wasn't there
You know and I don't know that I have it in me to do this forever like
I guess it at around this time it's like between 2000-2002 you decided to take
And ice cream course at Penn State which is
A famous horse Ben & Jerry's that that's how they learn how to make ice cream
It did by correspondence
Why do that right before we close scream
Which doesn't make it a whole lot of sense
You got shut screen down
The same month I went to Penn State ice cream School
I mean you've been making asking for 4 years so why did you feel like you needed to take
But ice cream course
I felt like I wanted to know
How
It's everybody else does it
That's that that's where I got a lot of it I mean because I've been doing it for 4 years when I went to Penn State it was like all of these
This intuition that I had
Was suddenly
Knowledge that I now knew right
It was not just intuition I know had that
And so it was like I got it you know
And it was wonderful to because you know ice cream is all math
Math in chemistry and science
That is
Just not at all what I did when I was younger and that was really cool being in that environment and seeing
And these people put these things together and see ice cream the Lavin
Really close really what is your
Friends say what your mom said you was she like you know
Maybe you should you know I something else and where the people who were saying
Do you know this respondent
Great
But maybe she gets made before stable
That's pretty much what everybody said
In a minute
@jenny decided to completely ignore everyone's advice
And then resurrect her ice cream company
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Port for this NPR Podcast comes from American Express open
We know that listeners to how I built this our curious curious about how good ideas become great
Businesses
And chances are you have some good ideas of your own but as you know in business there can be a lot of Road
Roadblocks
American Express open knows how hard it can be to get things done and they want to help with money and
I know how so you can turn those ideas into action visit open.com to get business done
Hey welcome back to this
Special LIVE edition
How I built
Best from NPR
Harrah's
Okay so it's the year 2000
Scream ice cream
Is no more at the North Market
Jenny's out of work
But still she
Can't accept the idea of
Totally abandoning ice cream
Is it felt like a really long time for me but it's probably 6 months
Before I started writing another plan
To make ice cream
And when what was it was it just people saying waiting to get back to
Doing it
One of the things that really struck me when I was in that in-between time when I was really sort of
In limbo of where it what I was going to do
What was the moment that I was on a Saturday I'd saved like I had like $5 I had a Vogue magazine was going to a coffee shop
And I was really excited to get her Orange
And like that was in my whole Saturday
I went in there and I spent a long line I got to the front and I was like I don't have the orange scone and coffee
Redstone
They didn't care
And I just like kind of bandwidth line over the stove perfectly it back to East Moline
And like a line is still there and all these people are so excited or whatever and I wasn't anymore and I turn around I walk
Out with nothing to do but when I walk through the door
It like
Hit me
Like that is exactly what I was doing to all of my customers at scream
Because it's cream I would only have whatever I want to make every day and so yeah I knew that like
Everyone loves salted caramel but like I can't make it everyday
And so once I realized that
The thing that draws me back to a business
Every single time
Then I went to businesses is the thing that I had last time
But it's always
That changed everything for me
And once I once I swear I got that
I think
Everything in my life started changing I think I
I start raining this man nearly just knew we had to do you know I like
And then it started to kind of snapping a place like all the mistakes that I had made it scream really coming into Focus
You needed money
To start this business and you needed a location
So how did you
How did you do that
Of course I was hoping we get back in the North Market because
It would be difficult to imagine my company if the market
Didn't exist
I mean you can start up there pretty fairly inexpensively $34,000
And you've got too many people walking through every year like Pike's Place in Seattle
Reading Terminal in Philadelphia
That is how important or North Market is in Columbus
Yeah
Yeah and it's them it's in the middle of the city and everybody goes there and all the highways lead to the North Market
So I was hoping to to get back in the market
And I got a job in the market
And started hanging out in the market all the time
They're talking everybody the market
Get to know all the management
And just trying to change you know just said to change the way they were
And he let me in
Cuz I thought of you as I guess somebody who
Tried and failed monkey kid you know who
Maybe wasn't entrepreneur real real business person or whatever when you went back to them you said hey I want to open up an ice cream shop where they like yeah
Come back
Oh no not at all no
No
What they say
Piano
We're not we're not doing that again
It was a lot of nose
And and for how long
I don't know but at least a year I would think
Yeah
So how did you convince him how did you get
The market to
Accept your new iteration of
What started making ice cream
And
Imitate you're taking it
Market at that point Charlie had gotten me this machine Charlie was your boyfriend at
The time that your husband
He's on my husband's
And Charlie buy me this machine that I couldn't
Afford it was like a $1,200
Italian gelato machine
And and I was trying to say for it because I had these friends who I wanted to invest in the company
And they're really the only thing I do with money
So and I was their babysitter
And so I
But they were great they were just wonderful and I and I was very close to them and so I told him about the ice cream or whatever
And I wanted to get them ice cream soup
I'm so they can give me money
And I couldn't get the Sanchez couldn't save up or end they were going to move to
To Toronto
And so became urgent that I get this machines that I can show them what I'm doing so I can get the $40,000 in them
And I went home one day and Charlie had bought it
For me and
So then I'm back in business as much as I possibly can at home I get a little
Sears freezer whatever that can make him fill up
Getting it all over anyone I could tow it would take it back to the market I would put it on the desk
Upstairs
So
The restaurants that I've been working with where would find out about at 7 after the restaurant started
Carrying my sweet just making it at home
Making like
Oh's Memphis
What I have discovered
So the market knows that I'm doing that the people that Michael knew I was doing this and I was doing everything I could just to get everybody to have this ice cream
And then you would have plan and
And they've said yes
Well they did I don't remember what came first if we had to get the loan first
You need that money
Ensure that makes good money
YouTube
Did you get that
Well
Family the rights that I
Was babysitting for a nanny for
Pitch the idea to them they love the ice
We'd love to offer you the money
And I was like oh my goodness
And they're like butt
Don't take it
Because if you take it we will own
So much of your company right now
And
Just do everything you can for it'll be here for you were going to be in Toronto but it'll be here for you if you need it
Charlie Charlie like thought I was going to get the money that night
I don't know man I haven't like this they said yes but they said no and like
You know
What if we went to the bank together
Like maybe we can get this together like maybe we can get
A loan from the bank on the SBA
To you lunch as Jenny's
Was it called Jeni's Splendid ice cream
And you're back in business at the market
And what was the reaction
At that point
Well it was
Wonderful we opened on a Michigan game Saturday which around here is kind of a big deal
Means that nobody else has anywhere but you know watching the game and what
What changed about
Your hole
Approach
And in Jenny's versus Scream I mean did you
Did you look different as you dress different ways are different aesthetic
There were a lot of things that were different
First of all I I had
Two different dipping cake cases so that I had big signature flavors on one side and then I vowed like I'll never be a
Salted caramel again
And other flavors that were I knew people really love that I'd like hit that I was good at that were working
And another side that was just for ice creams of the Season or at my whim or
Whatever inspired by pop culture history whatever I wanted to do and then the other thing I did was I
Determined
If this was going to work I had seen failure and I didn't want to do it again
So I like cut my hair short I dyed it
Darker than my natural color which is not
Which is like dark blonde hair with light brown
And I had
Star sweatshirt
And jeans and like a starch apron everyday
Cub pharmacy Lakeville
Like got into character I get called a shopkeeper
Like
Wood
Was obsessed with old photographs I would buy them on eBay
I saw I love them like I just collect them like really old old photographs of Lights
People doing fun things in Victorian era or whatever
And
There's always there always has photographs of like a shopkeeper outside with a broom in there wearing like
That's what I'm doing from now on that
And in doing that what I did was and on purpose I knew it
Take all of them is actually off of me and put it on ice
And that was what was
Different
So is it when you had pink hair and you were wearing for
Thrift Shop clothes you think people judge the ice-cream differently
I always thought it was a whole package
It was
If I'm going there was a food critic in town that wasn't very real excited about scream
And I was like if I'm going to get him
Take me seriously
I need to be somebody that he would take Serious
And so
I dressed up
Part
And it works
I mean it totally works the same ice cream he hated before
So you are back in business back at the North Market in a starched white shirt
And did it take off
Yeah I mean from opening day we had a line that went down the market and and even out the like
Glassdoor
I mean it was pretty incredible
That first day when it was Michigan game Saturday and we knew that
This is it this is going to
Be better
And luckily to
Within that first
Year
Charlie's brother from Nashville moved up
To join the company
And that was wonderful so then it became kind of the three of us actually the two of us for a long time
Doing that so Tom quit his job moved up here to join our company which was really special and wonderful and
Incident at buganda
Former partnership
Apus Ramona nasty
About the actual
Ice cream because a lot of people think of
Premium ice cream as like
As a custard based ice cream
Mike French
Vanilla right witcha
Egg base
And your ice cream was an egg base you were
You're using cream and
And milk
Yeah and it was it was from that who I was
I was
Working with a dairy and I was using kind of a
I was because I was
Stabilizers in milk and cream and all the kids
Standardized format how to figure that part of it out yet understanding you so
What would differentiate dry skin where the was a
Really
Flavor
Yeah at that point was really the flavor is
What was your ambition at that point it's it's now 2002-2003
You're back in business it's a different look
Were you already thinking ten years ahead saying
I want this to be
Big I want this to be
The biggest ice cream in America or were you thinking
I was thinking the same thought that I had at that moment that I first aid ice cream back in 1996 which is exact same thought I have now which is that we
I want to set the standard for American ice cream the American ice cream can be so much better that it's
The best ice cream in the world when it's made
I don't know that I knew really how
Big or what
That was but I just knew that
That was a we're going to do
I guess you had a turning point in 2005 you get
A visit from
Estate regulator who says actually you're not supposed to be making ice cream hear you
You have a license
What what happened with this if you want to make ice cream sold over-the-counter your you're governed by your ETA to permit from your local
Health Partners
Ice cream and sell it to somebody else to resell you then or you then move to the state
Agricultural
Department
I didn't know that
So
We are making a Sims and they were selling a couple restaurants and so he came over
You're really not supposed to
Do that
So early okay
So now what the hell ya
Well he gave us to know all of the information that we needed to figure out what kind of a kitchen when you realize that we needed to
Open a brand new ice cream
Production facility cuz you were making all your ice cream at the market
See you at 2
Basically start making ice cream in another kitchen
How are you able to
Pay for that
It was actually pretty terrifying because
We knew pretty quickly that
The business we had said it wasn't going to be enough to pay for
Disney production kitchen
Facility
And so
We immediately started thinking about another location
Dallas pay for that and that was our Grandview location interior
Columbus integrate walkable neighborhood
So we went to the bank with both of those projects
We had some
Proof that we could do it
And they gave us the loan but it was a lot of money I mean it might have been $250,000
That was a frightening time because we open Grandview not knowing
Is anybody knew who you were if anybody would come and I've been sort of scared of having a
Door you know we're in the market and that is beautiful
Environment
So essentially this this Regulators visit to you is what resulted in your expansion
You had to open up
Absolutely we were three years old and
That wasn't on our radar at all
So it was really in the
Beginning it was you and Charlie husband your brother-in-law Tom
And you're growing right I mean sort of slow but steady
No one's getting rich at all at the
This point
I guess in 2009 you decided
You guys need to add
Someone with more business Acumen to
To join the company
Yeah
I I we've had conversations about it and I definitely knew that we needed a CEO that was our thing
And so we would use it with his friend John
Who is drink with a lot after
Long day of making ice cream
Who is our attorney friend but like in the beginning of his career in the beginning of what we were doing
And we got to know him very well and we know
So everything that I would start talk about who's the CEO of you like you know what it's like somebody exactly like John
But at that point John had moved on from being an attorney here in Columbus and he was now at GE and doing great
Just like his career sailing
And so Charlie's on the couch were at home and he like
Into message Johnny's like he John you know it we're trying to hire a CEO and
Like we want to pick your brain about that could be easily won her somebody just like you
But we're going to pick your brain
So that you can maybe help us figure out how to
I not person
And then John was like going on
But it was soon
There's some point within the next two weeks
He
Quit his job
GM
We got to be our CEO
Why would you take such a leaf
Of faith I mean
He's right over there you go
He was he had a pretty good job to use pie making
A lot of cash and he's going to a company that
Like first one
Did you offer him
Kind of money that he was making at the time
No
And
And actually his first job was to make his own salary
You know what I don't know I mean I think that one of the things that
Was just
Such
I guess luck for us for the three of us or Charlie and me and John is just that we knew each other
We spent too much time together and
We trusted each other
You know and there is something about
That
Was John
Was he sort of looking at other
Distribution that I was he looking at supermarkets and other places we were working with Dina.
Luka at we we we been in working with them for
Maybe a couple years
And I
And that was the beginning of our Star Grocery business
And so when John came and he kind of use that as a platform to them continues to really to begin growing that which helped pay for
Him
So that was really the beginning of that
Channel freaky thing they love finding like all the new
7UP
And great stuff out in the in America but you know that was just seen is Lucas so it was
Next year he should have took out and
Filled it up which is still happening
Ahsoka see you expand
Right you start to expand and
How many stores did you have after that first one and then how long does it take you
To get outside of Columbus and
Outside of Ohio
Guess who in 2006 we opened our first around the market in Grandview and then we quickly opened
The Short North
And then it was doubled in Bexley
Herein
Columbus
And then I did a book
And that was really great and I got some national a lot of national
Toradol that
And then we opened in Nashville
Two things seem to be going really well you guys are growing
Sustainable
And then 2015
Kits and you have
The biggest crisis
Ever
What happened
In 2015 we had
I'll set the stage just a little bit we had just opened la
And
I had just done a collection of ice creams inspired by colors
From Matisse
MN
Everybody wanted to write about those and it was like this
Incredible time
And we're just riding High
And then we get it and then one day we get this
Yes we're bomb dropped on us which was
That
A pint of ice cream in Lincoln Nebraska
Tested positive for Listeria
It was the call that none of us
Could imagine never wanted to get
John walked by my office
And I was like
Listen to Somebody talk about cardboard
It was actually company that we really liked but that was what we were doing we're talkin about cardboard
And I like
Saw his the expression on his face
And it was just like
I've never seen before and I know John really well so
I got up and left and
Learn learn that news
So
You stopped production
We did so we huddled up
All the team
We had to make a lot of decisions very quickly over a very short. Of time
We had to decide what we were going to do
And recall all that ice
So we decided that we're going to recall everything
We
Nobody was sick
Which is great
I mean that we knew of it
Yeah and we weren't sure
But we needed to prevent an hour
So we did we we file the paperwork we figured out how to do it
We we got approval from the FDA and we did a full recall Within
Yo hours
Which men
That 265 tons of ice cream
Betty been out in the world
Came back to us
And there we were
We don't have no ice cream
And stores that are closed and
No way to make ice cream because we still got to figure out where that was. Came from
So the clock starts ticking then at that point in
My 600 please
When I have nothing to do
Creamy
Actually
Did you
Did you think there's a possibility that you would
Shut down that your business
Good basic
I think at that point when we started to sort of look around we realized that that was
It.
There wasn't anything left
And it was weird because
I just have a journal the time and it's like
I don't even have any ideas
But I knew and I trusted
The John and our incredible team we're working very hard on
Getting to the bottom of it
I mean you look at it, like Chipotle which had
Taiwan food safety crisis
Arguably they still haven't recovered from that
Finally did you guys recover from that you're much bigger company three years later
What would you think explains it
I mean you you weather that storm
And you're much bigger today than you were then
Well we
We've learned so much I think we've been pretty
Open 2 about
Dad and I think that people
Relate to that
Kind of personality or that sort of openness I'm in the end
The listeria was coming out of a hairline crack over by the
Wall behind a piece of equipment and it's like we finally found it which we celebrated
The funny thing was
Not funny but
When we close our stores we had
These wonderful
People who would put Post-it notes of
At the stores and like
They were so beautiful
And we were just like you know what we're fighting for that like we're fighting for this community
And I think because we raised our company as a community with our community
There was a lot of trust built into that
That's what
Saved us
Mince pies anything about this little stall at the North Market
Today it's a company got 32 stores right
Doing more than 30 million dollars in annual sales
You could
Right now
Cash out you could sell your shares
I'm Jeni's kabita poppy Albert by like
Unilever orino Pillsbury like like Ben & Jerry's like Haagen-Dazs like
Like talenti
To be at every 7-Eleven
And Euclid
You wouldn't have to work anymore you'll be
Set for life
Super rich
I don't know what you want to do that
Great
I don't know why but
I don't know I mean I I like making ice cream and I want to make ice
What I do and how I
It's actually how I
I think
If I'm 44 years old I started my Harrison when I was 21 22 some more than half my entire life most
What I remember
Has been devoted to this so
For me it's
Hard to imagine doing something outside I really truly the puzzle that I still
And working on and so
And I will see
How how much of
The success of your company do you think is because of
All the hard work you put it and how much of it is
Because of of luck
I think about I think about
Luck sometimes
Yeah I think sometimes luck is like
You're getting a good wave
You know and you got to ride it as far as you possibly can we all have luck and I had
Soma
Me just being here
In the city
Black butt
But bad luck to I mean I had really really good like in really really bad like in my life
And I feel like both have made me
Who I am and then there's this like middle place be
Between those two that you get to make decisions
And
That's it
Jenny if you saw yourself
20 years ago you had a crystal ball and you said yourself, stage
Talking about this incredible success
Why you were toiling away at
Screaming and Jenny's
Would you have been
Surprise or would you say
I knew it all along
Everything I knew it
I have never doubted that
Vision from the first
Moment
I've never doubted it
They burned our thank you so much
Jeni Britton Bauer founder of Jeni's Splendid ice cream
We chatted in front of a live audience at the Fawcett Event Center
On the campus of the Ohio State University in Columbus
Jenny's
Favorite flavor is not
Brambleberry crisp
Or Riesling poached pear sorbet
Or even salty care about actually
Lemon buttermilk which I have
How to say I'm not supposed to indoors things
It's amazing
It tastes like
The most
Delicious
Lemon cheesecake
Every
Hey thanks so much for listening to the show this week if you want to hear previous episodes you go to how I built this
Npr.org
This week was produced by run teen Arab Louis
Also composed the music
Thanks also to novigrad
Channel is Michigan floor, SLU
Jeff Rogers
Interned is newer coetzee
I'm Gyros Newton listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor