This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
It's snowflake. Com NPR
Hey it's guy here
Pretty silly idea
Storing our stuff in the cloud right like
Files
Photos of music
Lives up there
Somewhere
But when Jennifer Hyman launched Rent the Runway
She essentially wanted our clothing to live in the Cloud 2
So she created a website
What does huge inventory of women's clothing that
You never had to own you would do
Rent it and send it back
Jen calls it a closet
In the cloud
Here's a story of how she and her
Your partner built Rent the Runway
Is episode first Grand
August
I sent you know we should really call Diane Von Furstenberg the famous fashion designer
Fast forward a few weeks and we're driving to the second meeting and her system calls and says Dad no longer wants to see
She's not interested in this idea and I said
Oh yeah
We're just around the corner like what will the strap by for a second
And add her sister very firmly said she doesn't want to see you what do you not
Understand and I said I saw for cutting off and I hung up and then I said down the
West Side Highway and we were
At her office and we just showed up
NPR how I built this
A show that innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories behind the movements
They felt
How to women who wanted High fashion but couldn't afford the price tag
Decided to make it possible
The Rent the Runway
So Rent the Runway is
Now we're the hottest fashion companies
Is in the US
Growing like crazy
Doing more than a hundred million dollars a year in Revenue
Hundred employees
Core product is
Designer dresses
Surprised to discover
But just 10 of its employees work in the fashion depart
Most of the rest
Well
They work for a technology company
Because that's actually what Rent the Runway is
The way it works is you go online or you go to the app
And well you better dress
Thousands of dollars to buy
Except you only pay a small fraction of that look fabulous for one night
And then in the morning covered
You mail it back
It's kind of like Zipcar means Netflix
Zappos
Hyman and Jennifer Fleiss
Came up with the idea when they met in Business School
As you will hear
The path to building their company was fraught with all kinds of challenges
Among them
Rampant sexism
And even harassment
Recently been opening up about that
Their Story begins just after she graduates College
And job working as a junior analyst
For the hotel company
Starwood
About a year into my time at Starwood when I was 22
I had this thesis that we had entered
The experience
Economy
And people were getting married later and starting to value
Experiences
Like travel
Over owning
And so I had an idea at the time
To Launch
The first honeymoon
History in the world
Where couples could register for
Their honeymoons and their friends and family could contribute by
You know paying for scuba diving or paying for a massage in Hotel night
As opposed to buying them pots and pans
So
As a 22 year old I
Was really passionate about this idea
I emailed the president of Starwood
And I pitched him on this idea
To start a wedding business
Starwood where the Cornerstone of it would be with the first honeymoon registry just ever so
R22
That's that's incredibly precocious but was there anybody around you who is like
Hey stay in your lane or you know was there anybody was trying to
Tell you to
Oh yeah
Several boxes of mine
We're telling me
To keep quiet and
One of
The experience is that really impacted me
Was
I
Had a female boss
And at the time I think she was like
35 or 36 so
Kind of about my age right now
And I would often
Raise my hand in meetings and speak and make points
And
I remember her
Grabbing me after a meeting one day and
She said you know Jen I really want to give you some feedback
It's really important for your career
And I said oh you know I'd love to hear what's your feedback
And she said
You really need to shut up wow
You're a girl
And
It would be much more becoming
If you acted
Sweet
In conversations
Because you know you're you're too confident you're too bold
And it's coming across the wrong way
Hand of course
I didn't really know how to take this I mean I don't even know how I would take the
22 year olds I started hysterically crying I was in the middle of like an open floor
Plan
And a more senior man
Sami
I literally credit this guy for my entire career
He took me aside
And because I
Didn't even understand office politics at the time and like what I should and shouldn't say I kind of just blurted out
Oh my God like
Just want to just told me X Y and Z and I repeated the entire conversation to him
And he said you know Jen
You keep doing what you're doing
Because that woman's going to be working for you one day
Wow
She innocence gave me permission
To just act like myself
End
Who I was as a 22 year old
The same person is who I am today it's the person who
How to creative idea about
The Experience economy and I wanted to share it
What are you doing with it with the idea you pitch this to the to the president of Starwood
Yeah
I think he thought I was so
Little bit crazy
For going in and pitching to him that his response was like yeah sure whatever
And I took that as a yes
Wait he said
He didn't say yes he just said yeah that's interesting in you
Went back to your
Your desk and you started to
Map out how this could happen
I started to work on it
I spent the next three years working on it
And
You know Starwood still participates in
The honeymoon registry
To this day
Has taken it to a whole other level since I left
But it was such a fun experience for me to a work on something that I loved and was passionate about
Indeed be part of the process of creation
So you are obviously on the fast track to like if you were still Starwood today you might be running the place and you were
Doing this at such a young age
Why did you
Decide to leave after after a couple years
I always thought
But I would go to Business School
Both my parents have gone to Business School
And so I thought that the track was you work for 4 years
Between college and then you go to business
Also when
I was at Starwood first
3 + years I applied to business
School and I got into Harvard
So here's a question for you about
Cuz we're going to get I want to ask you about of course what happens business coaches
The Incredibles 2
Rent the Runway but
The vast majority of the of the entrepreneurs that would have been on the show
Did not go to business
You had all this incredible experience and you were really ambitious and you were
Entrepreneurial already
Why did you think you needed
Take to go to Business School
Well first
I
Have always had Big Dreams for my career but I
Didn't exactly know what those dreams were
You know
Sara Blakely was
A guest on your program and
She's someone who
Has always been an inspiration to me I remember being a
Younger girl
And
Seeing her on Oprah
And she had this amazing business but she also like
Seem like a real person
Who cared about getting married and having kids and
Having friends and having a social life and
That was really important to me
I was still fearful
That you had to make a choice
Between having
An incredible career as a woman or having a family
And I've always wanted both
So incensed going to business school with a chance for you to really think those things through
To think it through to get that kind of extra
Potentially stamp of approval that I thought that I needed
I had lots of opportunities that I could go into
Different kinds of companies in different fields
But I really wanted the time to
To think about like
Where do I want to spend my time
Like what am I most passionate about
Yeah
You are why you were at at Harvard Business School you met the person who would become
The co-founder of Rent the Runway Jennifer Fleiss
Yes how did you know
So it's a really funny story my sister Becky
Prior to me going to business school put a Post-It note on my pillow one night
With
Jenny Fleiss has maiden name on it
Which was Jenny Carter
And
She said that you have to meet this girl when you go to Business School
Because a friend of a friend of hers new Jenny Carter
And my response to Becky
At the time was
Keto while meter if I meter
Needless to say
Jenny was one of the first people I met at Harvard
The school because we were placed in the same section
Because her name had been on a Post-It note for me I was like oh my God you'll never believe this like
My sister told me we need to be friends
And we became really fast friends and
You know the rest is history and at what point did you say
What's your business together when we leave this place
So we were friends
We actually
Through our birthdays together
I'm in September of
That second year of business
School and in November of the secondary business school I went home for Thanksgiving
And I was in Becky's apartment
And Becky had just gone to a store and bought a dress
That was higher cost than her rent
Azhar
Responsible older sister I was
Embarking how
She should probably wear
One of the dress
This isn't her closet again as opposed to being in credit card debt
And her response to me was
You know everything in my closet is dead to me
I've been photographed in it
The photographs are up on Facebook and I need something new
You know Becky was a 25 year old
Like normal girl who lived in New York she wasn't a celebrity
But she was talking about being photographed and not being able to wear something again
And I like it was a lightbulb moment
For me
Cuz I realized
I was having a conversation with my sister about the
Experience
Of wearing
An amazing dress up walking into a party
Feeling self-confident and feeling beautiful and that's
What she cared about
And she didn't care about the actual ownership of the items in
Her closet
The other things
She cared about was the
Photograph that would exist after the party
That she could post on
Facebook and kind of share with everyone she knew how awesome she felt and how,
But she felt it that way
Sweating with this idea happened on a Saturday night
I go back to school on Monday
I happen to have lunch that day with Jenny
We were talking about our weekend
Cuz I was like oh I had this idea like
What if we rent a dress
She responded on this sounds fun
You know that's like
Work on this idea together
Who do you think we should call
To figure out if it's a good idea
And
I said you know we should really call Diane Von Furstenberg
And like the famous fashion designer
Jennifer
Do you know Diane Von Furstenberg
And I said
Obviously I don't know Diane Von Furstenberg but we could probably figure out her email address
You could have this point figure out anyone's email address in the entire world
So Jenny and I wrote an email that afternoon
Too many different versions of Diane Von Furstenberg email address
And we basically said hey we're two women at Harvard Business School we have an idea
We'd love to come in and talk to you about it
This is where luck
Plays into
To the situation
Because
She or someone from her office
Open that email
She responded I'll see you tomorrow at 5 p.m. tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Yep and we
Drove down
To New York
That next day
Put on our dvf dresses
And walked into her office and introduced ourselves as the co-founders of Rent the Runway
You have a name
You came up with a name
Yeah we just
We did everything very quickly
Now we didn't really have a structured idea
So
You know we were kind of iterating the idea
Baidu
And
The initial idea actually a witch
You know we've never really told the initial idea was what if we could rent the dresses
That she is selling on her website so what if we powered rental
Her
Dvf.com
You know when we went
To chat with her
She
Was not too thrilled about
The idea of
Renting clothes in general and thought that it would
Cannibalize her
Retail sales and it would dilute
Herbrand +
She was ready to end the meeting with us after a few minutes and
I started asking her questions about what she disliked about the idea what was
She scared about end
By the end of what was
Almost a
You know hour-and-a-half conversation
We learned
That
A lot of her customers were in their fifties and sixties
And not
If we were to build a business that could
Make her relevant
To put
Her products
Into the hands
News of women
In their teens twenties thirties and forties
But that might be interesting to her and she might want to work with us
So what's next for you guys
Nervous I mean
Just that you said business school students mean
I can imagine like what that would feel like to walk into that room and and try to get them keep her attention in
Get her excited
What's a funny story so
At that first meeting I've always learned you know when you're in the first meeting schedule second meeting
So when we're in the first meeting we scheduled the conversation for a few weeks later with her
Fast forward a few weeks and we're driving to the meeting
And
And we got a call while we're in the car
From her system
And we're on the West Side Highway where about
40 blocks from her office
And her system calls and says Dad no longer wants to see you
And
I said oh you know well
We're on our way
We'll just come in and say hi
And persistence like
No
She really doesn't want to see you
She's not interested in this idea
Can I set
We're just around the corner like
What will the stop by for a second
And again her sister
Very firmly said she doesn't want to see you
What do you not understand
And I said we're cutting off or cutting off and I hung up
And then I
Dead down the West Side Highway and we were
At her office and we just showed up
Wait most people in that situation would have just been like
Crashed
Would have felt so dejected like I don't know what I would and would have just said well forget it forget dialysis move on
How did you not
Feel that how did you how are you able to just say
We're just going to do that for no walk in there
Well Jenny initially was actually started to cry and was a little bit upset about the situation which I polish them
People would yeah which I think is the much more natural reaction
And
I was like we're just going to do this what do we have to lose like
What's the worst thing in the world we show up and she doesn't meet us what if you walked in there and they were like security please a Scorpio
Flipping out
Great then we have a story that we could tell all of our friends
When we come back what actually happened when Jen and Jenny
Finally showed up at the house on 1st and Briggs Avenue
I'm grozny listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account at gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated placed
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from the United States Postal
Everyday
Innovative companies are Reinventing the way business app
But none of that is possible without the right people
People who get packages to over a hundred and fifty million delivery play
Affordably and on time with the latest technology and expertise
Who can help you deliver the future of Commerce
The United States Postal Service see why they deliver more e-commerce packages to home
Has been anyone in the country
USPS.com future
Hey welcome back to how I built this
From NPR
Before the break
Jen was talking about how she and her co-founder Jenny
Basically
Busted into Diane Von Furstenberg xoffice to have a second meeting
An amazingly
Diane agreed to meet with them
Pretty good advice
Actually that was the meeting where she told us you know I don't want you to do
Do this on my website
You are going to have to
You sell this idea
The other
Designers and get lots of people on board if I'm going to do this to
So in a sense in that meeting she gave us permission
To make it a consumer-facing business and to approach
The rest of the industry
Reroute your business plan right right there
Yeah
So did you walk out of her office would like names or contacts or did you just walk out of her office
This is this is clarified we now know
We're heading
Well we did ask her
Some introductions and I think that she introduced us to one or two people in the industry
We then would meet with those people and we'd ask them for introductions and so on and so forth
But we continue to just cold coffee
People so one of the next people that I cold called was
The
President of Neiman Marcus
Because
He was Botha HBS alarm so I had access to his
Is email address
And I thought that you know if this whole
Rent the Runway thing
Falls through like
Maybe I could work for Jim gold Neiman Marcus
What he say
He said yeah this is a really good idea women have been renting the runway from my stores for decades
It's called buying something keeping the tags on and then returning it to the store
Which probably cost them
Millions of dollars
Yes
Kind of the dirty secret of retail
That the return rate especially addresses
And special occasion
A tire is extremely high
Cash pot for second a-10s this question which is
I'm wearing the outfit I'm wearing today like I've worn this in the last
Few days
I have no shame about it and obviously there's a difference
Society has different standards for men and women
What is this about what does thing where where
Women
Do you like they can't wear the same dress
Two different function
I really think that
There's a value that women place on
Self-expression
And that clothes make
You feel a certain way about yourself
You put on an amazing outfit in the morning and
It makes you feel powerful or beautiful or sexy or relaxed or however you want to feel that day
There's just a general value in
Our society right now around individuality and self-expression
And so the way that you're going to achieve that
With fashion
Is Viva variety
So I had seen
At the time and it's even more true today
Set the way that women were accessing variety and individuality was
Through
Fast fashion
An off-price
Because the only place
That you could buy a quantity of items
Was at a place that was selling them for a very cheap
Forever 21 or
Exactly
So I think sit when you don't have to buy something
It allows you
To try
New things to constantly be playful to Experiment 2
Try things that are in colors or in
Trends were you know different kinds
The styles that you never would
Because they're irrational
So with Rent the Runway
It's like a Willy Wonka land of fashion
Then you can have whatever you want whenever you want it
Let's say you have a job in
Curfew you have
A party you have a wedding you're going to
You're saying I wanted to arrive at my home on
September 15th and I'm going to wear it and use it for a few days and then I'm going to run
And it's about 10% of the
Retail price
So how did you know for sure that
Are the women will be interested
In like
Doing this mean did you get any research
No we never did research in an academic sense we did real life research which was
We went
To Bloomingdale's
We bought about a hundred dresses
All In
Our own sizes
So that if this whole experiment didn't work out we would have an awesome new wardrobe
We spent a lot of our savings on this
We
Hosted a pop-up
At Harvard undergrad
And we invited different groups of Harvard undergrads to the pop-up and
Idea behind this was to learn a
Will women rent dresses
B what are they rent how much will they pay
What brands do they want
And most importantly
If they do run
What happened
Titties
Garments
Destroyed
Can you send them through the mail
How do you dry clean these items
And so on and so forth
This is like still like
Travis sing
Like a no-brainer but
Is what 2008/2009
This our first pop-up was in April 2009
At that time Netflix would like mailing
DVDs in the mail so that was going on
Zappos
You could get shoes need to mail them back but was still
It wasn't like when it is now then it was still new
It was and
It feels
Both so long ago and also yesterday
So you got the The Descent right away that
This that this could work because these these undergraduates useless women were like yeah I want to read this
I got the sense that it would work because I saw the emotional effect
So in this pop-up I saw girls
You know
Stripping down
Trying on
These amazing dresses and
Feeling
Beautiful
And you saw it
Their facial expression
They threw their shoulders back and they tussled their hair and they walked with a new sense of confidence
Tencent
You know I really thought wow
This could be a business that isn't just about offering her irrational or smart choice
But it also can be a business that is
Delivering something emotional to her making her feel
Beautiful every single day
Founders choose to do it on their own
Like me like Gary Erickson from Clif bar or even Sara Blakely
Thanks and she has a hundred percent of her company
But
You guys went for venture capital
Pretty quickly player Leon y
We had to
Raise money because we needed to invest hundreds of thousands of dollars in inventory
2 even
Launch a business or twists whether it was
A viable
Idea
And I don't come from a family that has hundreds of thousands of dollars
Savings
Especially
King of savings that they're going to invest in their daughters
Crazy idea
Until when you were pitching venture capitalist how much money were you looking to raise it in the first round
We raised 1.75 million dollars
What could you do is build a website right
You could buy initial inventory in
Various-sized runs with some depth
Because we knew we needed many
Different designers we needed a selection right you weren't going to come and start renting
If there were only
5 units of inventory on the site
We could hire some people
We could launch a website
That was about it and take photos of the dresses and put them on the web
Tell us another funny story until 2 weeks
Before the website launched we didn't realize that we would have to take photos at the end of
We thought of course in this industry
There's some centralized plant that takes photos of this how ridiculous is it that every retailer would have to photograph
This inventory over and over again
Needless
To say
We figure out like right before the website
Meant to launch that we have no photos
And we
Put together a impromptu photo shoot where we
Found a photographer on Craigslist
Who ended up working with Rent the Runway for
6 years
Bring our own shoes and our own accessories to this photoshoot and
Are you know initial team
Of
5 employees in many interns at the time kind of
Figure out how to do it
So once you
Watch how do you get the word out how do you how do you get people to even know what this says
Hustling
So was the hustle the hustle was we wanted to build
Alyssa
Of as many women as
Possible
You know the Sex in the City movie had come out that summer
And we would
Go to movie theaters with women who were attending that movie and we would get their email addresses we would
Convince friend
Just send us email addresses of other friends
They're so like we were really doing anything and everything
So what are the names that was on this list
That we had built it Rent the Runway had
A at newyorktimes.com
And
I was like wow like there's someone who works at the New York
What timezone is email address and I looked her up and I saw that she was a twenty-two-year-old technology
Reporter
Invite her in
Maybe she can write about Rent the Runway
So we met with her and we decided we were going to give her a story
And
I
Thought
That
If Jenny and I were photographed
For this article
Potentially we could be on the front page of the business
If it was a photo that
Two of you
Yes
Because it was a technology
Reporter and no women are ever covered in the Technologies
So
I
Say to this reporter oh maybe you know you should take maybe you could take a photograph of us
At the kuantan port warehouse
The dry cleaner
So we put on like these crazy dresses
And
We showed up when the
Photographer
I showed up to
To the dry cleaner
And we
Stewart on ladders
And we told the photographer to take a photo of us on ladders
In front of
Kind of the
Array of addresses
Does that we're on the kind of dry cleaning
Machine
And
Because the photo was so
Utterly absurd
It ended up on the front page of the business section and
The headline A1 photo on nytimes.com
So we had a hundred thousand people sign up for Rent the Runway off of that story wow
People making orders yes
Did you have the inventory to handle all the orders no
So what you do
We raised more money so because of of
Hustling
To get this story in the luck of ending up on the front page of the New York Times
We met our first year sales projections in 3 weeks
And we had a clamoring of
Venture Capital investors
We're kind of coming into our office pitching us on
Siri say so we got we have gone from
You know a very undesirable investment to
Black people
Showing up
At the elevator
In our building
To meet with us unannounced wow
Because they wanted to pounce on the deal
I mean both you and
Unfortunately
Still rare in in the startup world and they are your two women
Bleeding a huge company and end
The time when you were raising money
Did you ever get the sense from venture capitalist who presumably most
Leslie Mann
That I don't know they were like
I'm a bit dismissive or
Condescending or
You know
I know treat you differently
Yeah we had several different very condescending conversations one
In which a partner at a very
Prestigious firm took my hand into his and he said you know this is so adorable
You're going to get to wear such pretty dresses this must be so fun for you how did you react
We both froze a little bit
We were very polite
And we walked out and we said you know thanks for
The feedback no of course we never
Interacted with
This former this investor again we never pitched them on any subsequent round we were like kind of good riddance to these people
So there's an element of
You know we
Hydac
The capital
We had choices
Because the business was growing
And
That's a privilege
I read an article that you that one investor says feel like
About about this idea
Well that's something that we heard all the time
That wasn't one investor that was most
Let me talk to my wife
My daughter or my admin
Those were the three
You know
Target customers that we would hear and
Let me tell you why eat
Is problematic
Number one the wife of a venture capitalist
What is the billionaire
So the wife of a venture capitalist
Is not Mike Target
Write the daughter of a venture capitalist in most cases
This is about 12
Because most Venture capitalists are
When they're in the prime of their careers their kind of
45 to
So
You know their daughter is not a great Target
Either
And their admin admins who work
In the Venture Capital industry cuz it's such a prick
Prestigious job
Are often women who are in their 50s and 60s
Again
Not women who were in my target demo so
We would
Preempt
.
By showing videos
Inviting these investors
To some of our pop up show them who discussed
So that they really got a son
Thanks for who we were catering to
That there's been a lot of
A lot of attention recently to
Tula
Roguish culture of
Venture capital in Silicon Valley
The end
And how women are are finally in a publicly being able to come out and talk more about
Their experiences
Did you experience some of that
Culture in in this process
I through the process of building
Renttherunway was sexually harassed
I'm by one individual
And I'm happy to
Share that experience
However I will say that
I've had interactions with
Dozens and dozens of venture capitalist at
Dozens of firms and
This was
Just one individual
So
The
Far far far majority of my interaction
Have been
Incredibly positive but I was in a situation once where I was kind of
Proposition sent sexual text messages
Trying to raise my Rent the Runway
While I was building the company yes from someone in the investor Community sending you text messages like
Let's go on a date or whatever it was
God and things that are more explicit than that
Toot toot sissy to get those
I was
I thought that it was
Inappropriate and fairly bizarre given that it was happening over text message so there was
Evidence created
Now there was also
You know conversations that were happening in person
That
We're also threatening and
Very bizarre
Did you just
Ignore it was there anything you could have
Did you feel like you could really do anything about it except just ignore it
So I initially
Ignored it
And that was the plan
I was planning on ignoring it in
You know
Decided you know I was going to keep it silent
And then
This
Person
Decided to
To call one of my board members up on the phone
And so you know
John never responds to me
And I think that this is a real problem and
She's a really unresponsive CEO and she's probably she's doing this to me she's probably doing this other people and
He really challenged my behavior as a CEO
Actually that board member
Came into my office to give me
Feedback
And say I need to be more responsive
Which
Was
My instantaneous reaction was
Oh my God I can't believe
Fattest person
After being rejected by making me sexual advances is now trying to ruin my career
And just a minute
How Jen handled that very tricky situation
I'm guy Raz and you're listening to how I built this
NPR
This is Terry Gross the host of fresh air
We do long-form interviews with the people behind the best books pop culture journalism and more
So you can get to know the people whose work you love
You'll find Fresh Air on NPR one or wherever you get your podcasts
Peyton just one more thing before I get back to the show
We still have a few tickets left for our upcoming live show in LA on December 5th
Ace theater
It was Michael Dubin diesel
The co-founder of Dollar Shave Club and
It's an amazing story of how he turned that into a billion dollar company
And you haven't been to a live show they are so much
The team behind the show and also a chance to meet your fellow HIV to listeners
So if you want to get a ticket
Go to NPR presents
. org
The show is
Supported by America
Express and Ayo
Hope to see you there
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So in those early days if Rent the Runway
Jenn Hyman face the situation where one of our investors was
When she ignored his advances
Took it out on her he actually complained about her to a member of her board
She decided to be
Totally transparent about what was going on
I
I showed this board member the text messages
At that time
Basically
You know ask my board member
How how they like me to respond
What do board members
I mean the board member was shocked I bet
I proceeded to tell everyone else in my board
As well as some
Key Executives who
We're working with me at Rent the Runway at the time
The board was
Unbelievably supportive
And we decided that we were
Not going to do business anymore with this individual or his firm
So there's that form of sexual harassment and I think that that's a lot of what's been getting recent media cup
End
Hopefully by nature of a lot of very
Brave women
Speaking out right now
That sort of sexual harassment will
Stamped Out of the industry in one way that I think over time
That it needs to be stamped out as bi
Diversifying the sources of capital making sure that
50%
Investors are women but let's put that aside.
Just for a second
The second form of
Sexual
Harassment
Flash
Gender discrimination
Is way more subtle
And it's way more difficult
But for insta
Overall
I have seen mail founders
Receive
You know sometimes
More mentorship
Or
More
Chances
Is to be successful they get more
Strikes against them before their investors kind of pull the plugs
In a lot of cases
Women are only given
You know it's a one Striker you're out as this
CEO and founder
There are situations where
I've now come to understand that a lot of how deals get done
And how companies let they get acquired is
Someone is saying something like oh you should really meet the
This guy he's a Visionary he's incredible yet get to know him
And
I think across-the-board
More of those
Comments are being made about male entrepreneurs than they are about females
Vsac
Society
Feel uncomfortable
Using the words Visionary or brilliant
To describe women
That's not always in
Tensional I think it's
Ingrained in
People I would say in in in a lot of different instances
People have actually genuinely been trying to be helpful
To me like there was a time early in my career where
An investment firm
Beto sesame
OG and you know you should really meet
These other
Entrepreneurs are around your own age their brilliant you can learn a lot from them
They're building incredible companies they're going to change the world
Now all of those
Entrepreneurs were men and they were kind of
Breakfast is being Geniuses brilliant excetera
And
The same firm never introduced me in that same way to the same entrepreneurs even though we were at similar 10
On your end
Similar stages in our company
The irony is a lot of
Those guys their businesses
You know aren't around anymore
And
You know I'm the one who still chugging
I don't think that they were
Trying to be intentionally
Sexist
It's just that
There's a shade to which we
We all operate
That puts women at a bit of a
It's really amazing in you
It it it speaks to the this like
Perception of a power dynamic
It's so
Prevalent
In the end Adventure World
I think that those power dynamics
Exist in so many different in Des
3 up
I don't think that it's
Just a
Silicon Valley or technology problem
And that's why
I think that the more
Egregious
Sending you a text message in the middle of the night
Asking to
Sleep with you sort of
Sexual harassment
Hopefully
Can
Peace
Stamped Out via just
Being more vocal about it
I think so that the more subtle
Form of
Harassment
Slashed
Discrimination or just lack of opportunity
Is actually the
Harder problem to solve
This problem it's
The reason why
Only 4% of venture capital dollars are going
Towards women and
You know very very few investors are women
So
You know we need to fundamentally
Versify
Who has access to
The power of was Axl
What's the capital in order to get a diversity of ideas and
There is out there
Yeah
And obviously you have had incredible
Success despite the challenges
That you faced and women in in in Texas
As usual.
Begin to develop as a leader as a CEO
How did you how did you make that transition how did you figure out how to get to manage Lots
I think that
It is a continuous work in progress
I had never manage people across the diversity of functions that we have it Rent the Runway
Rent the Runway is primarily a technology & logistics company
If 1200 employees 10 employees are in my fashion Department
And
Hundreds are in my Logistics Department hundreds are in my engineering department
And these are areas
In which I had no experience
End
One thing that I've learned is that leadership
Evolved over time for small being a leader of a 1200 person company is different
Then being a leader of 100% company
And so I have to really evolve even though I've had the same title for 8 plus years like
There's so many things.
You know I've done wrong along the way
And
I think that the thing that has
Made me grow and develop is
The recognition
Of
Failure
And
Desire to
Improve in the desire to get better
I don't want people to have the impression that this was
Is all
You know you do
Freda From Success to success.
Easy never know
Low point
It's because I have been like with any company
And
And in 2000
You got some some tough press
About
Some people who left the company
They were quotes newspapers calling it a Amin culture and
And
And things like that
From some of these employees who left to that
Which would hurt by tweeting that
That stuff was sobibor
Criticizing you and and your and your management style leadership
It was
The most difficult experience
Of my life actually
It was such a difficult time
Because
As a woman
There's two things they could really call you as a woman
They could call you the B word
Or they could say you're in it
Never really had a
Had a fear of someone calling me an idiot
But I do value myself
For how I treat others
So to be called mean
+ 2
You know
Be quoted as having a Mean Girls culture at the company
Was so
Unsettling and sad and horrible to me
Cuz it's the thing that's the most important to me
Pino
What had been happening at
At the time
Was
The company was going through
Quite
Painful and difficult transition
From being a
You know
One phase of a startup to trying to develop some sense of entering our teen years are adolescent years
And I started to realize that I needed to
Make the tough calls
End
Fire some people
Was very unsettling to people
Because
We give men permission
As leaders and a CEOs
To make the tough choices you know with women
We don't give them as much permission
To make those tough decisions
And we often when when we do make those decisions
We're often labeled as
The B word
Etc so
It certainly was a low point
But
Lead to the biggest outpouring
Of support of ever had
It led to more
Courage around
My own decision making
Because
I led the company into the best place it's ever been
And
In a sense it makes the future less scary because that article or
Reversion of it
It will come out again
And the next time it comes out
It's just not going to have the same impact
On me
You mentioned earlier in the interview how
You always wanted to
Run a successful company
Start a successful company but also
Have a family and a kid and you did that Yoo-hoo
You have a child and a partner and
How have you
Figured out how to
To do in the way you wanted to
First of all let's backtrack
To being 28 and having the idea for run the runway and I just want to tell the real story here
I because I think that a lot of women to go through this and end
They don't talk about it
One of the major considerations that I had
In starting Rent the Runway
Was
Is this a smart idea for me
Because if Rent the Runway is successful
Will I ever be able to get married
I was always confident that I would
Turn Rent the Runway into a
Consumer behavior that millions of people did and that I would be able to
You know I still believe we're going to build a multi-billion-dollar company
But at the very very beginning when Rent the Runway launch
I had been dating someone
From Harvard Business School who I was very much in love with
The day that
Rent the Runway came out and we were on the front page of the New York Times
She broke up with me shortly thereafter
Auntie told me
That
He
Realized
That he didn't want to be with his equal
So that was really
Sad and disheartening cuz I was very in love with this
6%
And that's what led into the sphere
No
Sphere was completely
Unfounded and I had no issues
You know falling in love while building Rent the Runway I just think that
It
Paralyzed
The number one priority in my life
Has always been having a family and having kids
So
The amount of happiness that I have now
Having a daughter I just got back from maternity leave last week
I'm engaged to the love of my life
I can't even
Describe to you
The
Level of
Joy
But it brings into my life on a daily basis
To truly
Have all of my dreams
To come true
Plaster you guys
Pad Thai
Which I should point out
Exceedingly rare soap
And
I mean your
Revenues
Over a hundred million dollars
La Quinta
Public reports
Devaluation of companies I don't even know what it is
Do you know what it is
I do know what it is
Yeah but it's it's
Probably higher than you
Ever imagine
Even though it it it may still be on
Paper
This
Thing that you felt that you in NN Jenny built
Has made both of you rich
Show me you are even though babe
Spam paper you are rich your rich
You did not grow up that
Well being rich on paper is very different than being rich and reality so let's talk in the future
Because
I didn't grow up saying I want to found a company
I had this idea for renttherunway I saw that it was mission-driven I saw that it was driving self-confidence and making with
Women feel incredible about themselves and I knew that I had to commit my life to that
And I'm really proud
Got
We have
Had many
Different women
Leave Rent the Runway and then raise their own venture capital and start their own companies and go after their own dream
And
Jenny and I
2 years ago
Decided to start a foundation
Where we've raised
Millions of dollars to
Support other female entrepreneur
Scaling their companies and we've now helped
Thousands of women throughout the United
In scaling their organization
So
This mission
Of
Empowering women and making women feel confident is the actual thing that I care
Now if it happens to be
That Rent the Runway brings
With me
The ability to provide for my family and thank my parents that would be wonderful
But honestly if it amounts to nothing it is
The absolute best experience of my life and I would do it over a million times
Jenn Hyman founder of Rent the Runway
By the way her co-founder Jennifer Fleiss recently left
The company
It was amicable
Both Jen and Jennifer each own 13
Percent of the company
Put them on the Forbes list of the richest self-made women to watch
Renttherunway isn't just profitable
It's also become America's single largest dry cleaner
Dresses from 500 different designers
Including
So it took a while to convince her
Diane Von Furstenberg
Please do stick around because it just a moment to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors MailChimp
MailChimp is so much more than female
They've outgrown their name
With automation ad campaigns and audience management
MailChimp could help your business
Outgrow its name to
Not just mail MailChimp
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
I know for how you built that and today we're going to update the story we ran a while back with Monica
Huarache in San Diego California
And her story starts a few years ago when her daughter Leo was
Packing to go overseas on a gap year program
She was going to be traveling to 14 different countries
Which meant that she was going to be living out of a suitcase so we needed to find the system where she would be very organized
Tyson her travels to be able to survive out of a suitcase pretty much for the year
This for me or maybe even you you know we can just
Throw a bunch of clothes into a suitcase and forget about it but Monica
She is in
Probably organized
I was a mathematician College
And I was
What was daring to order like in math is one solution
Came to packing I just couldn't find the system we tried
With Ziploc bags we tried many other packing cubes
But you couldn't see your things
And I wanted to turn a suitcase into a set of drawers
And what Monica came up with was a modular set of
Clear squishy plastic cubes that you can stack inside a suitcase and pull out by a
Handle it when you open your suitcase you can see
Everything from your suitcase and eventually Monica ran into a friend at a barbecue who happened to work with
Factories in China so of course she showed him her plan
Then he says this looks really interesting
Then he took it to China
You made a prototype for me I told him I wanted to clear and Wanda piping I wanted to have a handle
And she made
The first prototype
Soon after that Marcus scrape together some money
And placed an order for 14
Thousand of these packing Cube
And a few months later
A truck driver pulled up
In front of her house
I thought I was getting maybe 60 boxes or something
We had a 20-foot Container full of boxes on a bike
Oh my God what
Did we do and that was the precise moment when Monica realized she'd forgotten one very crew
Crucial detail
She had not gotten the word out about the packing cubes no I didn't have a single client I haven't sold us
Singlecue
Fortunately her son Solomon had study business and marketing
In college
And so he stepped in and he said he said we are going to work really hard
We're going to put it online and we're going to sell it
So Solomon started to email Mommy bloggers about the cubes and one of them posted it on Pinterest
And sure enough he says
We just got you
Six or seven orders in like that was a big deal at the time that was like wow like this is working you know
And he actually liked the idea so much that Solomon bought the company you from his mom
And he called it easy packing
She still helps out with the accounting and her husband does the legal work
And other kids how about you but Solomon
How does the
Bulk of the work
You know what it's been an amazing honor
To work with my son I never thought I would work with my son
If it hadn't been for him I would not have been able to do it
That's Monica mizrachi
Easy packing
Today
Her son Solomon and his fiance
Company full time
Monica Still helps out
And since we first ran the story they've expanded to selling in Europe and have basically
Doubled their business selling over 10000 packing cubes in the past year alone
If you want to learn more about ezpacking or hear previous episodes add to our podcast page how I built this
Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write us directly at HRBT at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet It's Pat how I built this
A Show's producer Suite by run. Dale fukka with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to neva grandson as meshkinpour Lawrence Wu and Jeff Rodgers
Our intern
Mia venkat I'm Gyros and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsors snowfall
The only data warehouse built for the cloud
Unlock deep Data Insights with the instantly scalable Cloud build data warehouse start your Journey 2
Towards data-driven decision-making