Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is
When is Good Day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim style
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
Support for this podcast comes from American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible funding so
PetSmart Savi way to
Defend your business
Powerful backing of American
Express
Do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com business
Hey it's guy here
And today was
Brand new live episode for you it's
My conversation with Michael Dubin who founded Dollar Shave Club
And that conversation happened in La just a few
But before we start the show
Just one
Quick favor soap
For the past few weeks
I've been asking you to consider making a donation to your local public radio station all this month
You know ask for money but
It's
To ask for your support
Because public radio station
Does depend
On your contributions to Funk
It's how they can bring you the news programs you love in the
Cultural programs you Lovin
Even this show it's how they can broadcast
Star show on the radio
So if you can
Please
Consider donating
Go to donate
. npr.org
Flash built
To show your support
For our show
So our first investor was a company called science around Santa Monica they gave us
$100,000 check
I literally got to the bank and I was like yours my check for a hundred you to fill out the form
I filled out in the woman looks like
From NPR how I built this
Show us entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movement
How Michael Dubin turned 8 years of experience
Improv comedy and video marketing into the Billion Dollar Dollar Shave Club
Billion dollar companies
You said
Even exist
10 or 50
18 years ago
Companies like Airbnb or lift or SnapChat or Spotify or Hulu
Pretty incredible he's sick about it because
There's a pretty good chance that today
You use at least one if not all of the
EServices
And even if you don't like what
These companies offer
Can't deny that their innovative
That they all offer a new way to do something
Getaround
Find a place to crash or listen to music or watch TV
These are some of the sexiest startups
Years
But now imagine a complete
Wheatley opposite idea
A business that not only offers a boring product
Funny product that is dominated by one big
Company
I'm talking about men's razors
And just a decade ago Gillette
Owned
70%
The US
Shaving Market
But today
Gillette overall market share
Closer to 50%
And that
Partly due to a company called
Dollar Shave
It's a company
But decided to take off
Start by offering a better razor
But by offering
A better story
The story of how Dollar Shave Club went from a scrappy website
Billion dollar exit in just
5 years
Is more about Michael dubin's instinct
Fashion marketing job
Santa Isabel
Anything else
Because for almost 8 years
Before he launched Dollar Shave Club
Michael Dubin was doing two things that would help him figure out how to
Penetrable Market
What are those
Things was creating videos for corporate client
The other
Probably more important
Was taking
Improv classes
Night
Those two skills would help Michael
Create one of the most
Successful guerrilla marketing campaigns
In modern history
But long before any of that happened
Michael hadwin
Because a pretty normal childhood
Suburbs
Philadelphia
Dad was a lawyer and his mom was a
Teacher and then later work
Real estate
Earlier this month at the theater at Ace Hotel
Downtown LA
Shutdown cycle douban in front of a live audience
Find out why
On snowy days
His mom used to force him and his sister to stay inside
Unsolved math problems
Not right
Welcome Michael
Thanks for having me is that actually true that on snow days your mom would make you solve math problems or said apocryphal
You weren't allowed to
You know it was like you can have fun but
Before you have fun
You're going to
Be productive
I think we carry that with us wherever we go there's like
A little bit of guilt that we have whenever we have fun somewhere yeah you like I should be doing math problems
Yeah exactly is a good lesson to your work first have fun later
I might see you grew up mainly I guess in in
The suburbs of
I'm curious
And this is a little bit of foreshadowing
You're so don't get too ahead of ourselves here but
As a kid or is it
Teenager were you into
Theater or
Acting or school plays dramas did you do that kind of stuff I did I was always in the school play
I was in the I was the lead in the school play in
Fourth grade it was called Peace Child
NP child was all about
Preventing a nuclear Holocaust through song
And literally no truly there was a song that was called I want to live
I want to live in something like
I want to live the right to live my life I don't really like
I think you know why Messi
The theater cuz we'll get to that later
What about General academic
Text me
Did you feel like you were a good student
Did you become a good student I was not a good student I was not
A horrible student I was good at
At the subject
That I was
But if I wasn't interested in the subject matter it was really hard to get me to pay attention I'm also
I was probably one of these kids that went undiagnosed
Add to it but
Yeah I don't think I was much of a student I did okay
Good enough of you went to a
Pretty good school you went to Emory University
And you studied
3 they're right she started out as a poli-sci major
But I flunked poli-sci 100
Actually twice by fun in class twice
In back-to-back years which goes to show you what kind of student was my freshman and sophomore year
And then can do that anymore so I began history major
Because I always loved
History and I love reading about history and studying history so she did fairly well at that
I had a killer internship with a
With a company called Bright House
Now she got super into my internships at CNN
So I actually did more X
Security I think in college
And it got really into those things in that helped set me on my career
So you graduate college
And what did you what did you do
So I
Peking of page of the NBC page program like Kenneth
Correct the page program
Kenneth Rosenberg
So
So yeah it was a page program which for anybody knows of the page program as you get to
It's 50 kids that they take right out of college
And
You basically have the keys to the castle
You run around NBC Rockefeller Center
And the studios and you see the audience's for the shows you give tours of the studios and the trade-off is that they give you
Opportunity to take mini job
In different departments
And so does many jobs can be with Saturday Night Live or Nightly News or you know that's on the Rosie O'Donnell show
Still on the air
And you do those mini jobs
We're Simon's for 10 weeks each so I had some pretty cool
Assignments
And it was just I mean I've said this before but outside of this job at DSC
That was my
So
Was that your idea that you would stay in journalism or media like was that
Were you start to think
And this is what I do
Yeah I was super passionate about it and went to work at NBC and
Then went to work at MSNBC first as a PA and it's a writer and I
I thought that I would have
Career in the media
And maybe even in journalist
But I think it a certain point the 24-hour news cycle
You work all day to build a story and a narrative
And then it 5 p.m. right before your Show are there
They would know there would be some breaking news and all your work would get thrown out and
And then I also felt like
It was right around the time that I started thinking
Like I really want to be in marketing Robert
I mean how did you make that leap
Edu expose marketing and advertising or did you just think this could be interesting
What I had
I had I had this really performative internship in in Atlanta
And I got an opportunity to love
A friend of mine
Cousin who ran a small
Marketing
King firm in New York
City that was doing you know client service work for a couple minor league sports teams and the main project that I worked on was I
We're done early website print alarm company
And then I left with the one of the partners at that firm to go over to time Inc
Yeah and
Life magazine in the relaunch of
Life Magazine
2005's
And
I spent a couple years at life and then I spent a couple years ago
Sports Illustrated sportsillustrated.com and networking General was
I built a you know back in the day
People might remember the term microsite I build microsites for some of the Big Brand advertisers at life
And for Sports Illustrated
Yeah there's could have been for Gatorade or for Sega learning how to do this on the job
Build a micro website or
Make a video or something
For these Brands just figuring out what would be interesting to a user
How to present visual information with some copy in a way that's digestible
How would I layout
This website and you know I've always been a bit of a visual finger so it's fun it uxu eyes
Maze
For a puzzle
That's what great Architects do that's what great Zeus restaurant designers do when they lay out of spacer
Designer hotel lobby
What great product designers do ux UI designers do they create
These
Mazes
For people to go in and that's enormously satisfying when you can watch masses of people
Follow your
Read yeah
All of this
This is happening
I'm in New York or New York in the early 2000s and
You decide to
Take improv class
Almost 8 years have that
Startup
Was it just something you want to do for fun
July
I've always been passionate about comedy and
I'd heard when I worked at NBC that all of the great comedians that were on SNL
I trained and Improv
And a lot of them had trained at the Upright Citizens Brigade
Which of the time they only had one studio in the in the West Village
And
I was just
You know I said what up I want to do that you know just sign up just
Pay the fee a hundred bucks take the entry-level class and see how you do and it just stuck
I felt totally in love with it before too long I was taking sketch classes as well and you do this like weekly
Clear yeah you take a couple classes a week
It is sketch class you have some homework to do you have to write comedy sketches
If you going to practice improv at night with a bunch of people that you've never met before you I'll run some weird Studio space and you make
Jokes at 9 p.m. and it's
You know very bizarre
Experience
So you had you had this marketing job during the day
Making videos and
And then at night you were
Doing it
And I was also trying to start my
My first startup
Which is a social network for travelers so yes I was busy
Happen to the social
For travelers
So yeah
But I'm trying to stand I mean
There must have been something about improv like
I have to imagine in your mind you're thinking
Maybe I have a shot at being a comedian or being on SNL or was that
What you were thinking
I would never admit that but yes
Got it
Yeah that's right right because why would you take improv classes
4 years
Amelia Amelia
Is Brigade
Two three nights a week and just watch the most
Amazing comedian
People that have gone on to have amazing careers
People like Donald Glover
You know I went to go see Donald Glover win
He was doing these shows in the air in a basement in Chelsea under groceries
And
You watching six
210 people on a stage
Pull ideas out of thin air and weave them together into a
Story
That that makes you laugh and comedy is one of the hardest things to do.
There's a setup
And then there's
The equal sign
Right it's a plus b plus C equals
Hahaha
That takes magic that takes real talent and so it's addictive
And when you get it right and when you do it well
It's a high
And I also
It was such a great way to blow off steam in the evening as well because
You have these really hard long days at work where you're getting grinded by your boss at work
And you know you're trying to start this social networking
For travelers
In the margins
You know then it's like
You know you can go to the gym or you can go to
Wheatley blow your mind and do some Improv
Was there any
Part of you that thought
This can help me one day
If I want to start a business
This was that
Even a journal of a thought in your mind now
Cuz right now today you was saying okay
In your twenties do some improv learn marketing and that can help you
Sell razors on the internet
So you are in your 20s
You're in New York and I guess your by this point
Approaching your early 30s
And you decide to leave you decide to just
Go and move
Go to hear Los Angeles
Why I mean quit your job in marketing in New York improv troupe therein
Come here what yeah well I got laid off
So that I'd like a lot of
There's no hero story there
Sorry sometimes life happens on you
So yeah I got laid off
I was dating a girl at the time and in who lived in Los Angeles and
I always wanted to live in California at some point
So you know life
Happened on me
And I said Now's the Time like you know
I've got nothing to lose so no plan no job
You just came out here
No plan no job just came out here
And what did you
Did you start to do
So I
Through a friend I was able to get a job at a small
Video marketing agency
And what they were doing is they were
Helping brands
Develop and distribute
Videocon
I'm in this was probably 2000-2010
So simple customer.
Doing work for big Brands putting it online but
Doing it in his face that was you know
Pretty squarely in video
So I'm curious to finalize I guess
It's her
Somewhere near the end of 2010
This is a fateful moment for you because you meet somebody you are a holiday party
Sharon la
You meet a guy named Mark
Levine
At this party who is Mark Levine
What's that party what happen
So Mark Levine is my friend's father
The businessman has had a successful career
Intel Africa then came to the United States
You know and he use an importer he's like our family friend
Do you know which show up sometimes with like
You know a truck full of soccer balls were like a truck ride bikes and you'd be like
Do you want to bike or not
And cellulite
So
Yeah we've been trying to get connected for a while
Because
He had heard that I had worked in
You know where
In the internet
Inside the internet
And he wanted me because he had all this stuff in a warehouse
That he was looking to you know
Unload
Like when you say
Stop like he would just you just import whatever
Stop by the two things that he approached me about where
He was like I've got
Razors
I got my 250000 razors
Okay
He also had
A couple thousand cake slicer
Cake slicer
Yesterday no Warehouse slicers were called
Piece of cake
The slicer themselves was shaped like
A wedge
Piece of cake
Yeah so you know
Forget about the worry of having to slice twice
When you want a piece of cake
Now you lace to take your piece of cake
And you put it over the cage
Wow and outcomes the perfect slice of Cape I need to know why we are not talking about.
Cake Club
How how was that
How is that not the product that you said to Mark oh my God amazing the cake slicer yeah
I'm in
I just I knew that
You know gluten-free was going to be the next thing and
I just wasn't going to be a market for it
All right so you are at this party this holiday party and he's like yeah go Warehouse of 200,000 razors and
Thousands of cake slicers are you in is that what he said he was like he was like
You know yeah
What do you think and I was like
Let's give him a try and we'll see what we can do
So what happens if you go home and then you call him and say okay want to go check out these razor so I knew that I wanted
To the razors because
I'd always bristled at the price of razors and I had always
There was a time and I remember this specifically
When I was living in New York
I would walk right past Duane Reade on my way from Rockefeller Center
To the subway on the F train when I go downtown
And I would need razors and I just wouldn't want to go into the store to buy the Rays
Because the razor Fortress is always locked
You have to find the person with the key they're always doing something else yet and you actually feel like you're inconveniencing them
For piano helping you get a product of the only product it's like that or one of the only products it's like that in the store
And I didn't in 2006 save this is a problem that I'm going to go soft but at that party he said
The razors are grade what do you want to do with them I had the idea for dollars
All right so you go and you what you go check out this Warehouse to the razors are in a warehouse in San Bernardino
Bernardino or Rancho Cucamonga which is like an hour east of
And I get out there and
There's a guy there and I'm like
Hello I'm Mark Levine
You know partner and
I'm here for the razors and he's like oh
Jamaican inspired
Yes yes I am
You're like great you got to go to get me $700 or these Rays I'm about to throw these razors out
Tell the razors have been ever so long in the bill hasn't been paid like I'm sure that marketing
Rent storage space like I'm sure that he had almost forgotten about these
So I had to go get $700 sight unseen and give it to the guy
So that he didn't ride the razors and I could have asked
Sego nuc The Razor's Edge
And go and see the razor's I look at them and I
Mercedes look like razors that I would use
I take them home I shave with it and I knew that we
Well
She get home and and you call him and you say
Hey
I think I can sell these nieces great
Go deck yourself out
More or less yeah he was like what do you want to do with them and I was like
Well I mean I want to put them online and I think that the best way to do it is to
Create a subscription mechanism where people don't have to go to the store to get them they come automatically and
Yeah
How is it at that very moment
Cuz it sounds like that's what
What you're saying
You were thinking
This is the business I'm going to do
I'm going to drop everything I'm going to focus on
What
What was it about
$50 razors a warehouse in Rancho Cucamonga
That inspired you to
The thing like that
But because I knew there was a problem
And
I think that
A lot of an entrepreneur's will tell you that
You know they trust their gut and I trust my guy
And my gut told me that the problem that I had observed back in 2005-2006 when I had that feeling
About wanting to go into the store because the razors are overpriced in the buying experience
Super frustrating
If I had that feeling I knew there were other people like me that would
Have that that that were experiencing that same frustration
And I knew that there was an hour
Opportunity and
Like also like a lot of entrepreneurs
Once you become
Focus on an idea and you've identified a problem that need solving or thing you want to bring into the world
It's really hard to get that out of your head
I believe truly that there was a problem worth solving here
And I certainly didn't think that it was going to become what it has become but I knew that there was enough there to
Tell you no
Make a couple bucks
And and what about the name how did you
Was the name also part of the idea from
Within a few days of meeting mark
I wanted the
Function of the business
Come through in the name
And I think if you know where to plug somebody off
Street and say
What does a company called Dollar Shave Club do
You should probably be able to figure that when I got
So if I was
If I knew you then
Right and I
I probably would have said two-and-a-half to imagine other people
People said to you
Michael you're like a 30-something dude and
You weren't try to answer one of the most
Penetrable Market
Razors and shaving in America I mean
Gillette Schick
Did anybody in your family or anybody say to you
Razors
This is like
This Market is dominated by like
Two or three company
Yeah I I don't know that anybody
Flight phrases
Like that
Wisconsin
Tell ya I mean you're my family
You know but like
Don't listen your family
Because
For a lottery
I mean listen your family for a lottery
Don't listen your family for some things
I mean the way you laid it out is exactly right this is
Gillette the time
Had
Do you know it infected mengapa
Play on this particular consumer product
Business category
And you know for a nobody
To come in
With you know his
Rancho Cucamonga razors
And
And like
Change the way that people think about that category like
You know I would never have said it
That's what I was going to try to do
We come back
How Michael Dubin and his Rancho Cucamonga razors actually did end up changing the way Millions
The people would buy shaving products Gyros and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast comes from America
Express
Tracey schekman leads
Team of marketing
Bears who create event
Experiences
Introduce entrepreneur
To American
Express
What are team was asked to build a booth
Busy Tech trade show
They decided to go analog
A typical trade show is
Suicide how can we take it offline how come we let people talk to each other
I have some fun and we built off the buzz of the escape room trend
Where people are locked in a room and it was solve a series of clues in order to get
And we called it escape the office
The reason we created
Do we do
Is because relationships are at the heart of everything that we
We aim to build
Long-term enduring relationships
In a world
It's become increasingly short
Transactional
And in person
We hope that every experience
Our customers have with us will reinforce that given to
We want to be there for
Customers and make sure
For the traveling for
Trulia Supply
To learn more about how America
Express can have your back
Can life and business
Americanexpress.com
Do business
Hey welcome back to how I built this
NPR
Beginning of 2011 a Michael wants to see if
He can get any traction with Dollar Shave Club
Does new company that sells razors on the internet
Inter-fund it
He puts in some of his own savings he also gets an investment from Mark Levine
The guy who had that warehouse
Split razors that he needed to get rid of
Jermichael hires a few people to help him put together a
Beta website
So the goal of the beta site was really to test different pricing models test different forms of
And either the first brand that we launched was not what it is today it was really just you know what we have all come to know as
MVP
Minimum viable product
And let's just get something up
Let's see how it does and let's see what the
The feedback is
What was the best product
So what's the best assortment
What were people liking what did they want more of
And really just
You know can we
Can we move these razors and what
Yeah what do people want out of this
Type of a service
So I sew in that first year you were really kind of
Singing people would get to the sightseeing what
What they were buying
How did you even reach people
So early
They buy Google ad yeah like that yeah we did a Groupon
I went to a mom blog conference down in like San Diego or something
And
I mean you know this was real
Street Hustle
What's the time in like you know you by
You bite you do your own sem in your house
And I still remember our first customer was
Imran charnov Houston Texas
He just found you online
He just found Us online I remember where I was sitting when this first order came in
Which is the first stranger validation right cuz obviously
My mom had bought some in
Yeah you know like yeah
The other people my buddies had bought some and
Yeah.
The first real sale came in and like
That validation like
You know that first thrill
Of that first sale
Is like all the encouragement that you need is an entrepreneur to be like yes
Somebody gets
Yeah
Leslie at 8
And in this really comes to a head in March
The date was March
Your background
Video India
Your background Improv
Magically come together
Unplanned
When you release
A video what was the
Story about that video how does that come about
Yeah
So
I knew that
This was a fairly simple story
Razer overpriced
You're overpaying for the technology
And you can get a great shave from having to pay such a high price
And
I knew that if you just told that story flat
It would sound fly
So I wanted you to be a part of the brand
And I wanted to make a video
Oh and I knew how to write
And I'd sort of knew how to act
And I called up
A friend of mine Lucia Creator director of Broad City now while but she was met her at the at the end
I met her she
Directed
One of the shows that I was in
At one point
Community can you ask for help
I see she just moved to LA to and I said hey I'm starting this company
I want to do a
A video advertisement that tells a story it's going to go on the homepage
Like
You know I wrote a script will you meet me for coffee and end like giving those on the script and
And then help me film it till we met for coffee
She looked at the script
She says I really like it added a couple of jokes
Set the line are blades any good
No they're great
Used to be our blades any good no
And then some other bad joke and she gave me that line so I should know that
After that to Luchia
And we rented out the warehouse that we were fulfilling packages in out for the day
Background that you see Lemonade fulfill all kinds of
To use starting
With you behind the desk and attracts you
It follows you
Through this warehouse and we meet
Toddler shaving the head of a grown man
We see a bear of a nano SIM
One in the bear costume
You've got one of your
Warehouse
Employees in a Go-Kart with you
It's very very funny
You haven't seen it
25 million is
Think was the latest numbers amazing
You released it
On March 6 2012
Was there a reason why you pick that date or that time of year
To release the video
So we were ready to launch we just raised about a million dollars in in in venture capital
Raise that money went around and
To our first investor was a company called science around Santa Monica they gave us $100,000 check
Tyceno they gave us $100 check
By accident
And I got all the way to the bank
I literally I got to the bank and I was like yours my check for a hundred as I ask you to fill out the
The form that said
$100,000
I fill it out and the woman looks at me and she's like
But who were the Amin I have to assume they were some invest
Stars are made
This idea and said
I'm not going to get in
Into the razor
Honey
So what was the pitch that convinced those who
Agreed
To our road you know we said yeah she see money
Before You released
So that was
How you
We're able to convince those initial investors
Yep they were like
Well you want to do this
Spending a day with a person
All that stuff about you can do it
And I said they're like how you going to do it
I'm going to build a brand-new like yeah but what do you mean I was like twelve and I try to explain as I do know what
Just watch this
Usage
Just watch this video
Instantly many of them last I was funny and throws
Creative and I believe in you
All right
So you erase
Receive money
March 6th
Why was that date or that time of year
Significant
Side spend time in the media
I knew how the media
Would think about
Using a video like this
To tell the story of our fun
And so I wanted to make sure that we announced our funding at the same day that we launched the video
We also chose that day because
There's a nice low
Right before South by Southwest
People get really excited right before South by Southwest at least it did then
Do they look for a big
Text story
They hope something's going to break the way Twitter did in 2006 or whatever when you know and that was when Twitter kind of had a big moment
Was at South by
And it became a thing so there's a lot of answers
Dissipation in the air and people are looking for
Something exciting attack space so
I wanted to do it before the festival before that got nose you thought
There's not a whole lot of noise out there right now
Now and then maybe this will get some traction if I do it
In this window
Yes exactly
So you guys put out the
What hat what happens
You upload it to like YouTube or
Upload it to YouTube
Turn the sight on
Light the Night
Before and in
How do you get
All to know about
Click on the weather journalist at you
Targeted therapy
People that you went after we had done around a press
You know to Nassar million-dollar
C-Tran
And we talked about all The Usual Suspects
Techcrunch's of the world the Bloomberg's
Etc and
All the stories went live at the same time
And first the techie goes to
System pic
Annies video which
People found funny and engaging and also that it was promoting a real business
Was turn of the unique combination for people
Yeah I don't think there were too many examples at that
Time of
Direct-to-consumer business
That launched
With a video
That was funny
And good
And I think it's at
Tech Community
Surface it
And then from there it
It sort of caught while
And what happened
That day the sick
I mean were you
Surprise for you
A lot of people
Watch that video
Yeah I
You never build anything like that and think it's going to go viral anybody that tells you that they can build you a viral video or
Don't don't believe them
I did not have
Huge hopes
For this video
I just thought that this was a really compelling way to tell the story of what are busy
This was
And we launched
And I woke up at my normal time is 6:30
On March 6th
And I looked at the site
Insight wasn't there
And I was like
Oh my God what
What's wrong why is the site
Then I saw some text messages
Anderson my friends that were up on the East Coast earlier they were like
You know
Dude amazing video like
Put the site that I can order my razors and you're sitting there and I'm literally in bed and every on
Entrepreneurs Had A Moment Like This or a hundred moments like this
They look at their phone first thing in the morning and they're like
Oh
Whatever
And that was one of them so decided crashed
I had to go figure out how to get the side back up
Online
Eventually we did and then we sold out
And Vine
You cleared that warehouse
Yeah we had some other reason other razors as well we had we had some twin razor the first Racers worth
Then we had some for Blaze and we had some 6 by so and so
They sell out and
You know you're now you're like
What do I do
What do I do in this moment do I get no pull down the clothes shade and say sorry like we'll be back in
A couple months what must we can make more razors or do we keep selling put up a note that says hey you know
We're going to sell these razors to you
Eventually eventually will send you these razors
And people thankfully you know we're okay with that mean some people
Is the lady in the razors but
You know Dave they hung around because
Because the proposition was resume
And we actually had tapped into something we'd solve the problem
That many many people
Hat
And we did it in a way that resonated with them and they wanted to
Give us a chance at this point
Dollar Shave Club
Still you and
Anyone else
At that point it was so
Soap science was our first investor
We had
I was the only full-time in
Employee
But science had a studio of
Folk dancing designers
Dinner is a tech team that will third-party techshop that did all of our engineering
But I was the only full-time employee
And where were you sourcing your razors
Manufacturer in South Korea
You see these bags right
For Gillette or whatever
Razor it is and I
They talk about the sink
Technology as if it's like
You know something that NASA invented
If Gillette was selling
You know a 4-pack of Razor
Let's say 4
Four or five
Times the cost that you were offer
Which was a Dollar Plus
$2 for shipping and handle
I have to assume that
You were this is a last leader
That you were not going to make money off this for awhile
On that twin razor
On the other ones yet
And so
Explain why I mean we've talked to the guys who founded Warby Parker and they explain why
Frames
We're so excited
It was essentially Monopoly
And they said there's no reason why
Is it wasn't
Same with razors like why
Why were razors
Could buy it at a pharmacy
So much more expensive than the ones you were selling
Right well you know you think about
It's a very small community there not that many people in the world that make gravy
And you think about the science involved for such an old-school sort of
Product has been around for a long period of time there's an extraordinary amount of science
Stickers into
Taking
You know raw metal
Then finding it out
Then
Creating a blade Edge
Then then coating a blade Edge
You know that can actually slice
Hair after
And not skin off
There's a lot that goes into it
You can do it
People do it and so
But it's hard
And that's why there's not that many people that do it
How are you fulfilling those those orders in that after the video came out
What's it like you and I
Do people like
Packaging them up and
Yeah we had printers wait a couple printers hanging around the office and we know we were
Reading labels and you know it's so frustrating cuz you had thousands and thousands
The borders and its label printers like
So like the only answer is get more labor
Cell
Label printers and you know where we're fill out these roles of labels
And then we put them in these big trash bags
And we drive them down to the warehouse where we shot the video and there was doing our fulfillment center this is not an e-commerce
This is a place that like
On Monday they're feeling like
Windshield washer pellets in this
YouTube
On Tuesday they're putting vodka bottles in crates and on Wednesday they're filling order for Dollar Shave Club
And like
But if we have to go over there take the big bag of
Of labels
A big trash bag throw them over the fence
And hope that in the middle of the night nobody comes by and steals the big bag of
Which would be crazy if they did that but
But that's yeah that was how the operation work
So after
So I mean after you kind of
Be right broke through an end and start to get attention and start to get
Scribers
Did it become pretty easy for you to raise
Money at that point
Raising money has never been easy
For us and I think four
Unless you are
Snapchat Circa 2000 whatever
You know it's hard to raise money for any kind of company and end for all the reasons that you pointed out in the beginning
You know what
How do you think that you
Are going to have you know
Take on these Giants that have been doing this for
You know over 50 years and and are they going to squash you aren't they going to copy
It was never easy for us yes there was always
You can always raise some money for
I'm some portion of the people that you want to raise money from the smart money so to speak the smart money asks
The smart question
And they asked all the
She said that they should
And it was never easy
Steven you know into our series d
Yeah once you start to gain traction obviously
The competitors came in Harry's Razors for example
Do they make you nervous when when
You start to see other
People who are also using the subscription model
Yeah I mean I think
Of course anytime that you create something
And
You put it out there
And it's naive to think that people aren't going to copy your
Great idea and I think that for your first reaction is to be like
But
I think what you learned over time is that the presence of competition pushes you to Define yourself
More specifically
And focuses you on the things that you want to do
And
You know
Definitely makes you work a little bit harder so that you know
Most people when they first start a company and then they experience competition don't think that's a good thing
I think it's a wonderful
We've benefited from that in some ways
It's been validating in so many ways to
Did you have to do a whole lot of advertising over those viral videos cuz
Chris Moore
Was that really driving
The customers was that bringing in Newcastle
Yessir the virality wear off
For sure and then it was you no jump into the paid marketing game
End
Yeah we we shot our first
Television commercials
I believe in mm
13 we did another video for our one wipe Charlies which is are butt wipes for men
Weight for men
Do you want to talk about that
Well I mean sure
What is 2013 to diversify
Satisfyer first expansion was one wipe Charlies it's a butt wipe for men
It's a moist towelette that you use
Some people like to
Not before they sweep some people liked
Sweep before they mop
It's a better way to do it
And
You know anybody
Unless you're very flexible you know you're not spending any time back there
But other people that that care about you might
Might be
And so that might be a that might be a service that you provide not for yourself but for your loved one
A couple of things happened
To you guys at that are knots
Surprising because it happens to
Successful startups
The first is
The big players
Godzilla game
Description game the chillaxing and the other companies
They are
Much bigger that time certainly
Or much much bigger
In terms of the
The capital they have a
The cash the marketing dollars they had
Was there ever a concern when they got into the
Into that game that
They could actually
Crush you
Any smart on
Entrepreneur
Smart CEO business
In person
Should absolutely be afraid of
When something like that happens and you should be doing the chess on on how to make that not have
So yes of course when any competitor
Launches and many have
You have to
To think how are we going to be different how are we going to send this off
If you don't take competitive threats
Seriously
That's foolish so we absolutely took
Of course is that Gillette
Suju for patent infringement
I'm as your view began to take away market share from Gillette
It's still pending but
Did that lawsuit freak you out when that happened
Well yes or no I mean you know it was the first time
I think that we have gotten sued
And
You know your first
First time he get sued your like
What do you would how do you react to something
But I think it's at a certain point you
People have been telling us along the way to expect
Because that's a Playbook
That big competitors big incumbent
Competitors can do
Make you look unattractive
Give two
How to make you look on a tractor
If two potential
Acquirers
And show
For me you know like look you take everything very seriously as a CEO
But
You also say that
There was a business
Calculation to and also that made a lot of sense
From there
So
You put it all together
410 and rationalize it
So you guys
I think a certain
What movie was 20
15 by 20
15 or 26
You get about 3 million subscribers
Remember what percentage of this
Subscription Market
You guys have that point
Of the
Online razor subscription Market
I mean most most
I don't know the exact Market
The chair numbers off the top of my head
But I think that
You know as of now there's about
22 25% of
Of the men's
Non-disposable razor Market
That we have
Do you remember when he became prophet
No comment
We run by a very big company and we're not allowed to disclose your financial information right
Dollar Shave Club was it
Acquired by Unilever
Reportedly for a billion dollars
Okay
I mean it's a mind-boggling astounding amount of money
Were you looking to sell or did they come to you how did that happen
TriMet I met one of their Executives at a dinner in New York
And
We just started talking about where I wanted to take
The company
And he was telling me about some of the things that
Unilever was working on
And
That Men's Grooming was
Priority for them
Strategically
And the conversation really just started out as a hey how is there a way that we can
Potentially help each other
And the conversation you know
Took another step and then another
Then we ended up
Property acquisition I know that there was a lot that
Proceeded
You know
The founding of the company and there's let the wind into it and a lot of
Stress
And hard work but
You just put into perspective
5 year. From the time you found it
The time Unilever bought it
I mean
What do you think about that
Are you astounded at that are you I mean do you just think
5 years
And this is what
What we built it is pretty mind blowing
It is mind-boggling
It was a huge moment in the companies
Life
And history
And certainly a huge moment in my life
Incurrir No Doubt
But I knew that all the hard work
Was really yet
The acquisition in and of itself
Is a nice moment and an acknowledgement of the progress that we made
But there was still so much
To do
That you know I didn't spend a lot of time sitting around being like
Let you know
Popping a lot of champagne glass because there's just
It's just used to run the company or the CEO correct you work for Unilever
My Paychex
Is it yes my boss is Unilever
How
How does I understand that
You and and you'll ever really wanted you to stay at the helm because
It was your vision and your imprimatur has on it
Plenty of stories I mean Instagram is an example where you know the founders eventually left
But had a lot of autonomy for a long
On time
Has it
Let you know what when a big company like Unilever
Comes in as a
The parent company
In your experience has it changed
A lot
At Dollar Shave Club do you feel like it
The same exact place
No it's not the same exact place but not because of the actress
Yeah we've gone through an enormous transformation
Company over the last
Last two years
That we have had to
Change the way that our entire Tech
Technology stack is built
It the way that the consumer interacts with it
Packages that were selling people we went from
Selling razors once a month to selling everything that you need
A couple times a year
And and that's working out really well but just to get
To that point
Required
Transformation in advertising
And frankly transformation of
A Personnel I don't know the number off the top of my head but something like
You know
80% of
Avari
300 employees
Are new
That within the last 18 months
And that's what you have to do to you know
We had a great First Act and now we want to have a great second act
And so
It did the company is is actually quite different than it was
And that's the way that it should be
All the people here tonight who might be in your position in mm
Tanner 2011 he might be starting
Something up for
If you were in this audience then and you're watching somebody like you what do you wish
You knew then that you know now that
Would have been helpful
I think there's a lot of times when uses the starting a company and you're faced with
Certain death
Or near death
You have a near-death experience which will happen a lot
It's never as bad as you think it's also not as
As you hope it will be either
End
You know yes there are sometimes when the worst possible outcome happens
But it's really rare
And that you go through enough
Start of crises
And near-death experiences
When you come out on the other side
And you kind of like in your mind you said yourself
Okay I know what it's like to be chill on the other side of the crisis
I'm just going to put myself there
And know that like
8 out of 10 times
It'll be true and 2 out of 10 times it's not and it helps you I think get a little bit less scared because
Starting a business
Is is
Scary
Michael is a question that
I asked everybody come to the show and
And if you've heard the show you've heard me ask a question on curious
Premier Pineview how much of what happened to you
Do you think is because of like and how much do you think is because of
Your hard work and your intelligence and
Your skill
I think that anybody that so
Successful in
This has benefited
And
Anybody that tells you that
They haven't
Or don't
Is not being true
Luck plays a role in everything
Thing and I think that you continue to get lucky
Throughout your career
End end
Throughout our visit
Yeah we've gotten lucky in many ways
Some sometimes
Good luck
What is a manifestation of hard work
And sometimes luck is just luck
I like to think that
A lot of other people
Met Mark Levine at that party that night you know would not have done what I did with with it
We have all done with it because this is not a one-man show never has been but yeah
Lex luck is important Michael Dubin founder of Dollar Shave Club
I spoke with Michael Dubin in front of a live audience
In Los Angeles
At the theater
Ace Hotel
Never tells you that business school is the perfect
Path to becoming a successful entrepreneur
Well
20th Michael Dubin was actually rejected from business school because of his low college GPA
And today
That viral video that Michael made to launch Dollar Shave Club
Is actually used as a case study
The Columbia business school
So much for listening to this live episode of How I built this
Russia was produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by rub teen Arab Louis
I love team in Los Angeles includes Ali Prescott Jessica Goldstein Joetta Pulaski Isabella and
Baldassari
With recording engineers and huether and Josh Newell
Could see Jesse Howard and Jeff Rogers AR intern is Mia venkat
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of House
Built this campaign mode
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com