Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
Hate before we start the show I just want to remind you that
Tickets for the how I built this Summit are selling
Fast
We know have
Fewer than
50 tickets left
So don't miss your chance to learn from some of the world's most
Hiring entrepreneurs and also to meet hundreds of other innovators and builders
The Summit is on
October 16th
San Francisco
Had supported by America
Chicken Express
Go to NPR.
Org
Summit
Define. More
How to get your tickets
And I hope to see you there
We were sure that this was going to be
Andreessen Horowitz
A hundred million dollars in Revenue with this business and thereby be a billion dollar business and like
Just like you guys have no idea what you're doing you don't understand what it is to tell into companies you're going to need all of us experts
And they were they were like good luck
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists the stories behind the movement
Butterfield perfected the art of the pivot by turning a failed online game come
Messaging program now valued at over 5
Billion dollars
Remember story we did a while back
About Kevin Systrom and Mike Krieger
When they join forces to build a tech
They came up with something they called bourbon
It was a
Check-in app
That was going to take the World by storm
Take out your smartphone and declare hey I'm on Bourbon
Starbucks
Anyone there
Problem is there was no one no one use bourbon
At least not in the way it was intended
Kevin discovered was there small user base
Really love the photo-sharing
That was special
Was a failure but
That cool photo sharing teacher
Well they decided to make that
Effectiveness
Is better known today
Is instant
Imagine you're working to build a massive multi
Two player online game
A weird
Utopian fantasy world like
Burning man but in cyberspace
What was that was Stewart Butterfield's big idea this was going to be his life
Pursued his
Great achievement
Dwight and bows
He failed
But something else happened
Two entirely different
Entirely unintended products
Born from those failures
First one become Flickr
It was an early image hosting website where you can
Store in
Photos
The second one
If you work in an office and
Pretty sure you've heard of it or use it
It's called slack and if you
Don't know what it is
It's a messaging app design 14 collaboration
Black is one of the fastest-growing business apps ever and it was
Accident
We'll get to that story
What you need to know about Stewart Butterfield is that
Get kind of an unconventional childhood like
The grid back-to-the-land unconventional
Because his parents were counterculture hippies
Who decided to live in the remote Backwoods of British Columbia
Yep they had restored an Old Log Cabin that was built
Around the turn of the last century
Didn't have running water until I was
Read NIV electricity till I was four
Such a funny story of my mother's father
Who came from Poland to Montreal in between World War 1 and World War II
Coming to visit them
And they had a bathtub the front yard in the yard just like
Trying to eat
The food that they were growing and didn't have many possessions and he was black
I can't believe I
Escapist at all in Poland and send all of you to University
And then now you're back living in this
Stump oh my God
They look real live off the land
My name was Dharma
Your birth name was Dharma
Yeah that it Hindu and then later Buddhist concept
The pathway
And when I was 12 years old
Like most other as we wanted to be normal
So
Stewart
For some reason I had the impression that Stuart was the most normal name
No I regret it now cuz Dharma Butterfield
Stewart eventually went to study philosophy in college
Wellington School PS I got really interested in computers and on the side he taught himself to code
HTML
He started to make websites for local businesses
But his master plan his main goal would actually become a philosophy Professor until he real
Working in Tech
Might be a more stable job
Joey move to Vancouver and get a job at a tech startup called
Communicate. Calm cuz I have found it it had bought in 1990
All of these domains like Vietnam. Common brazil.com
Makeup.com in perfume
It was Brian Leo
It's unfortunately passed away since then
But I'm so this is like 98
99 Vietnam.
Wow yeah but also like
Dance.com intellect
Monica, you get hundreds of them really really valuable that was the guy
I didn't even know you could
Goodbye, in 93
Really really early
What at that time was
A gold mine
And the way that we fought back
We would
Develop one universal
E-commerce back end and it have all the domain names be the front end and the idea was that they were going to have
A bunch of websites
Mabel doll
Basically direct users to
This one Ecommerce site where you can get anything makeup or whatever it was
Oar tickets
Brazil or
Boxing paraphernalia or whatever the hell
But
No one had anything really to
No one knew exactly what we were doing
It's really early but, it seemed like this was incredibly valuable we're going to have a contest
Give away a BMW Z3 wasn't thinking that James Bond movies was like the hot car that time
So that we got people to sign up what are they signing up for I don't know but got divorced and worse and worse like day by day
Because no one knew exactly what they're supposed to be doing it in the management meetings turned into screaming matches
And so around the end of February
The year 2000 I quit I walked away I thought I was walking away from like 10 million dollars in equity
And I got bought out for
For $35,000 on my way up
And of course like
10 days later two weeks later was the first.com crash
And so in the end I got $35,000 more than I would have had I stayed out
What did you decide to do next
Convinced one of
But I do happen to sit next to me
Jason Clausen who was running a website on the side called grad finder who does that
102 classmates of this is how many years before
Facebook accepted then I convinced them to leave and I had my $35,000 in
We went down and raise the whole $50,000 money from other people and started it up to the real business
Yeah it is a way to find other people graduate from your college basically
Directory of high school race in each high school you can have a graduation year and people just sign up and
Message each other stuff like that
We worked on it for me
XXR 8 months and it got acquired
The dot-coms that had raised
Planet Money
$159
Gospel to the end of the year 2000
And
They not going bankrupt
A year later
So when you guys sold
Gray finder with
Acquired
Did you walk away with a bunch of cash yourself
Yeah I'm in a bunch of cash
Morton's
See what it was but it wasn't like
Millions
It was it was
December cash4you no gyno
The twenties
Yeah you know I took a lot of the next
Year off that did Consulting work but relatively low
What's wrong this time like 2,000 where you
Met someone didn't you got married
I did
In like 99
I started a web log
And there was a couple hundred people or so around the world who had blogs and we all knew each other
And one of the bloggers whose blogs I admired was a woman named Caterina fake
Call Katerina. Net and it still exists now 20
Plus years later
So
Around that time
We met
And
A year-and-a-half later
We got married
And
The.com era hype
And completely dissipated a lot of companies have
Imploded
But there's a lot of creativity in late 99
I started the competition called
The 5K which was to build the smallest
Are there any website or web page that
Be done in 5 kilobytes of data
And one of the people who entered the
Competition was
Mary Costello who lived
In time in St Louis
And
Spark up a friendship with him
But it's time Jason had come back
From
The grad finder acquisition and we all started working together on a project called game NeverEnding which was in
Contemptible the web-based
Massively multiplayer game
And it was a never-ending game presumably
Yep
This was
You and Katerina at your now wife
And
Jason Clausen who
Will you describe find
Yep and with this guy Eric Costello
You decide that you wanted
Create
A game
A massive multiplayer online
Yeah so there's that there's a type of Kami that existed before
Geographical games to cough
And it was a precursor for everything
World of Warcraft being the example that most people would know
But we weren't interested in fighting game
You're interested
In creativity and play is going to be pre-tax
Social interaction
So
This idea still has a lot of appeal to me it's a
Horrible idea commercial Hank like I said there's not enough people who are interested in it
But
A group
Who
To use the Prototype and we're very enthusiastic in the seeds of this incredible community
And we thought hey we got the Prototype people liked it we can make this into a real
Project the game
Look like
Would you be in front of screen looking at like
A Minecraft type interface
2002-2003 so the graphics weren't riding
Minecraft quality
There's the different objects in you can click on them to pick them up or
Cooking them to do stuff with them
I really rooted
So
We tried everything
Raise some money for this
And
There was Zero
The middle of 5 mm to
And
No one wanted to invest in anything that anything to do with you
How are you even going to make money off of
This was a business model
People would pay a month
Description
So
I put my money into it
Some of us working on it put our money into it we hired a couple people
We raised a couple hundred thousand dollars a friends-and-family money and when I say friends and family I mean like literally friends and family
And
By the middle of 2000
3 we know we have been working on that year it was clear
How come flag
Texas was going to be in
Would you like
We ready
And we were desperate for something
Else that time
That we could complete in a
Shorter man
And that thing ended up being flicker
And
I think when we started at the intention was going to build this
Someone will buy it
It for like a million dollars
What happened
You got this idea
To build this game very expensive
You just you just don't have enough money to do it right so then you decided
It needs you to starting up
Flickr
Would you like a photo sharing even happen
Well we had
At the time developed a whole bunch of really into
15 +
Relatively novel technology so we had a game that you could
And despite the fact
Is pretty rudimentary Graphics it was still
Protect logic
Totally
Fascinating a new
Yeah and the
Story sounds
Too good to be true and kind of hurt
Ridiculous butt
A group of lawyers had organized a
Law and virtual worlds in New York
And invited all the people in end
And I went
With Katarina
And on the plane on the way there
I got food
Got to JFK
Throw it up again.
The taxi pull over on the Van Wyck
The throw up all over the carpet
But I'm really sick I couldn't keep anything down, like fever dreams
And the part of town
Apocryphal
I swear it's true the whole idea for Flickr came to me.
Voted out on leg straps
The paper in the
Hotel room while I couldn't sleep 5 in the morning
Will you wrote At what
A way to take the interface that we had developed for the game
Black people chat
Change locations which let people
Manipulate these objects like a
Pull them into their inventory ADF with them
Instead of the
We'll just have photos
So you can upload a photo
And and you could do stuff
Stop I mean
People can draw a little rectangle in the photo and then make an annotation of that part of the photo
They can chat about them
I could send them to other people that could change the title and everything happened dynamically select
When I get something you would see what was happening on your computer
So
Again technologically for the time amazing
Mind blowing people were
Incredibly effusive
Then
Pause
Second to say
This was the first version of
How much we quickly changed in the reason we were successful is because you changed it
And I think a good point
Another character
I've got so many friends going here but
So one of the players of the
Was
Like early 20s
Hardcore just nerd
Who let the Tiny Village in England
And had a job in London he committed to London
I began to train for a couple of hours
And
She had developed a bunch of stuff
To illustrate the social networks inside the game plan if we didn't have any apis for him to use but
It turned out had hacked into our internal mailing list
Best when they're working on the game had been reading all of our messages
He was able to develop
When he was at like I'm just a person who
Play the game never ending
And
His name
Was Cal Henderson
Elvis such a
Geek like one of the nerdiest people I've ever met
My life is also a
Prodigy
Programmer
And so when I convinced him to start
To work with us on making flicker he was
You really into it and
On the train to London everyday 2 hours and 2 hours out
He wrote almost all of the gut
Lots of liquor
The way to upload the photos
Did the process them to store them display them
The original
Payment he got with me buying stuff off his Amazon wish list
So is like
Radiohead
Yuki's Alchemy of rare vinyl
Everyone's like focused on the
This game
The money's running out
How did you then convince everybody to
To Pivot
Did you say hey guys you know what let's just
Dump this gaming thing let's go all-in on a
Photo sharing
Did anybody say
What are you talking about
Oh yeah so I actually forgot about the
Couple years ago
I want has reminded of it
I could have laid out
And said the situation
Finish the game
I let everyone vote
You said to them you let them vote on whether it actually go through
Yeah whether to switch our efforts to
The flickering to really pursue that
Instead of the game
And then I lost
Why did you even think that was a good idea
Because it was something that we could complete
Actually get it
Out
Eric was the one person on the team who had kids so he's the one person who
We just weren't able to pay anyone
Yeah
So we had this phone I lost
Flickr lost in game 1
So they had to call Eric on the side
Doosan
What I imagine happens in the Senate to Penelec horse-trading
To convince him to change his vote
And I worked and
Decision was December 2003 and in February 2004
We watch foot
I'll put a San Diego
This conference
Super excited about when you launched
It was a pretty big deal when it launched him in that
Clovis community
Play Decade before the majority people got smartphones
Internet wasn't still perceived as a
It's kind of like weird creepy place like
If you saw the popular image of an
Internet user
It'll be like a really overweight guy and against man Simpsons
Exactly
Yeah
So you guys so it's like 2004
You put flicker out there and end
People who were on the internet
We're like cool
Place to
To put our photos up online
Yeah
So around that time
Google had bought blocker
How much is a little early blogging Pro
Programs
And they didn't have a way to host photos so they put
You know in there
Help materials
Online
How do I upload photos to use Flickr
You know it was like the one
Standout event
Time where the the world that kind of soured on the internet
Rose from the
The ashes of all
Destruction and became like a
A cool interesting thing that people can get involved in that was
In-N-Out hours
Flickr going to make money
Because all these people are coming onto it presumably good to buy like
Like server space which is a lot more expensive than before like
Cloud computing
How old how how did you do with it
We saw what we called Pro account
Which let you
I believe it was
You could see the whole history
If your photos were as if you didn't
Bipro cat you can only see 200 and
And
Better she went pretty well but you're right
The hardware that timer
Astronaut
These people's photos
Absolutely wenzhou every week we would
Put an order
Adele
UPS will deliver boxes from Dell and then every Friday night
I said I would go down to the
Where the servers wear and screwdriver
Put servers on to the RAC Center
Hurricane Ivan
But because the car was really taking off
So we we actually raise a little bit
Able to buy this
Growing releaf
People buying Pro account
You're not very many but we also didn't pay ourselves very much so we're covering the cost
True
Backhoe usage
And suddenly
Companies
I want to buy a
Like like
Which companies
We were talking to
Google Yahoo to
If I scored another six months or so now it's
Christmas
2004 that's about to turn into
And we also had a bunch of venture capitalist
At the same time Yahoo is getting really really serious
Search part of Yahoo
Make an offer to buy us
And then over that
Christmas New Years. 2004-2005 where to choose
Do I take this money from the investors
Can build this into something bigger
Or do we want to take the money now from Yahoo
And we got a great catch from them
And the promise was you
Come work at Yahoo by the company will get this money but we also give you all of these resources we have all of Yahoo's
Hundreds of millions of users and Oliver
Technology our servers and you can go listen to the
Is great and wonder
What were they offer
Who's around 20 mi
229 bucks wow you are
You are Rick guide overnight
So suddenly all the friends and family to invest in
Dumb game
Couple years prior
We're in a good position and everyone who work there it would
Deferred salary
Sacrificed along the way
What's in a good position
And
Hey look
You know this is Olivia a life-changing amount of money you'll be able to do what you want to do after
And who knows if this opportunity will stay wrapped
So you should just take the acquisition so smart move
Smart move for sure 100% of the time they would give you opposite
Singular thing
I'm in the internet
You guys you and Karen work till I kind of internet and after that acquisition
You landed on the cover of Newsweek
Yeah so I would say still a little bit internet
I was in New York
Fly back to the
Music
Issue came out
Well I'll tell you
I grabbed a stack of them at the newsstand inside of JFK
Spanish slapping down
And the woman who is checking me out
But you got to look up and she scanned why magazine and she flipped it over and scan the other one that she said
Honey you know all these are the same
Yep
Heaven
She looked up at me
MSU left out of the magazine she looked up at me again and she was
Really
Your eyes lit up shoes
So excited and then she read the cover of it
It said something like
Web 2.0
Open Flickr to Myspace
Something something
And she was just crestfallen Jesus like oh my God
I thought you're going to be someone
Important like your in a movie star or American Idol contestant
Or something like I cared about was like some Web 2.0
Amazing and she just scan the rest of magazines and check me out and that was it
Uso Yahoo
Pretty good deal now that we know now.
Honest this product
You walk away with
Probably good amount of cash probably not set for life
Spell right
Do not save her life and part of that
Apposition
What color now
Tell
It's conditional on the employees staying with Yahoo for a Time
How long did you to stay with Yahoo.
Flea bass
Scallion
3 years
Neulasta
Said how long
3 + 1/2
So you like it you babe are basically you made it
So how are those three years ago
I think
I would never in the arm
I'm 8 but I look back at that
I'm the way I would imagine some people look back at boot camp which was it was horrible at the time but like very real
Overworking the new machine and I learned a lot
Developed character
What was horrible about her
The timer has 9 people
So
9 people being acquired by what at the time it was like an eleven or twelve thousand person company
And suddenly everything that was just
Easy like we were just
Decide something and then it would be decided became this Mass
The process
Now we wanted to get more servers we had to go to the hardware Review Committee and you had to make an
You can get an appointment for like 5 weeks
Meanwhile
II fall over
And when we wanted to
Blogs
Something you know like making an ounce of public are at a future we would just do it
Before we required to you
It took a lot of getting used to
Almost all the energy things other than making
King's Liquor
It sounds like you
Do you really want to get out
I used to do cat mythology in the deliberate way I learned
Amazing amount
Some of it was negative lessons like me or don't do this
It's just really eye-opening
Certainly I learned a lot more than I ever would have learned many MBA program
Two pretty high-profile that access to all of the executives
She only decision that is involved in all these things I never would have been involved in otherwise
So when you left
Yahoo was it
Was it with a feeling of joy and possibility or was it a feeling of like
Okay
I don't know what I would do that
I thought you halfway between there was it wasn't
Overwhelmingly positive or
Cuz you I guess and this is the kind of personal thing but you
Your marriage is breaking up
Yep it was
We
I had only recently had a kid
And
We didn't work together that closely I Yahoo
But
It's some
Free challenging to
To work with your spouse especially the early days of a startup
When we first started working reflector like out of money
And such as the business's
Armani
We're out of money
And that that stress isn't like okay I can leave it at the office and go home to my family which is totally dependent
The other really
Interwoven
It was a difficult time and
By the time that we left
Yahoo like a pretty soon after that it was just
I guess you
You still have to work yourself to figure something out to
What did you do when when you walk
Avi what was your plan
There wasn't an immediate short-term planners Atlanta
Take some time off is that it
Benadryl whirlwinds
But it didn't take long
A lot of those same people who worked on Flickr and had worked on the previous game
Do you decide that we wanted to work on the game again
I'm going to go back to gaming
Yeah you didn't learn your lesson
The first time around
Yeah we apparently didn't even so the world look pretty different
Beginning of 2009
There was at least an order Maddie
Attitude more
People online Verizon 2002 the majority of people
Didn't have internet access at home now the majority did
Computers are Wayfair
Pastor all the hardware was way cheaper
Online games
Where some really popular
Cat fail
Like yeah
All of the conditions are
So we should do
When you say when you say
People who worked on the previous game with you all those guys
Yes it was me and three of the engineers including
Kyle Anderson
Another one
Next Ricky Martin
It in Vancouver
And what we
Glitch
Was completely different
Yes so in this game
It was a
Bizarre Fantastical world really
Try to encourage individual creativity and people can create stuff inside the world
But in the world.
Like milk butterflies and in order to
Butterfly milk and you could
Like eggs grow on trees and the look was kind of like
Dr. Seuss meets Monty Python meets like modern-day graphic novels
As you move around the world
It does look changed
Automatically
So you had a track record
Flickered like you already had reputations been on the cover of Newsweek youthworks
Yahoo
So when it came time to raise money
Was it pretty easy
Yeah absolutely
It was very easy
Started off with a
I can be a million-and-a-half dollars
Scramble to hire someone we were able to afford all the technology we wanted
And as we started developing the game we had a bunch of really positive early
The indications
Stop charge you money and they were
Vacate a lot
The average person who paid was paying $70 a year
And this is like what 2010-2011 some like that
Yeah
And people are already paying for it was that good
Well is that good for a very small population
So in fact it was really hard for us to get people even to
Go to the first few minutes of the game because he was just so different and so weird
Most people have tried it weird
Like what the hell is this
Peaced out in the first
3 minutes ago
Alright so you guys launches things
Early success to raise
Lots of cash
And then November of
You shut it down what what happened
Well
Been in business
Thickest occupancy of requires a lot of
Unnatural optimism
At some point
It's just that optimism is exhausting
We have
Called a leaky bucket
People would come in
Top of the funnel
And the funnel is going to
Describing Mike
First people hear about your thing then they go to the website then they sign up
Then they end up in our case play the game a little bit then they end up hating you on each of those stages
Some people fall out of the process of
I called the funnel
The Leaky bucket did you get people in the top
Next Fallout
Follow the process
Too early not enough of them make it all the way
And
Next game dynamically added
The next bit of customization
The next the next thing the next thing that I send
But I think continue to try those things
We just never
Found that magic formula that would
Make it work
Economical
It would have been
Define
People call lifestyle business
But it was never going to become the kind of business
That would justify
By 17 and 1/2 million dollars venture capital
At what point did you come to the decision to shut it down
Well so I was
I was losing a lot of snow
I was up really late one night
And I dislike
2 or 3 in the morning
Sinbad my
Haven't been sleeping for hours but I just realized
I don't believe that
I don't believe it
I realized
Right in that moment
There's a saying
If you're thinking about firing someone
A lot
You should just fire
Meaning that like that intuition
The cat keeps coming up
It's almost certainly correct and you wouldn't be thinking that all
All the time if there was a real
Shot at making a relationship work
Exactly the same thing with a
Business once I begin
Not have little doubt
A fundamental level
I was just like I don't think this is going to work
First thing that morning
I wrote to all the co-founders and then to our board of directors and just sad
It's over
And
That definitely was not at yunnan
Contention in an argument
Enormous amount of time
Millions of frames
Animation
Hundreds of hours of original music
So how did you break the news to
I mean they must have been
Excruciating
Yeah it was it was horrible
I say we can have an all-hands meeting
And everyone
You have files in a get-together people have
Coffee in the morning and a chit-chatting and
And finally like
I stand up
And the meeting starts
And
I start
Tell them that we're going to check out the game and before I could even get
First half of the sentence out I was
Almost everyone
My personally convinced
They should come work
It's company that they should
Except are stock options and they should believe in the project that they should believe in me
Humiliating is a real sense that I had failed all these people
I had an obligation to them
And I was Hadlock die as well
Is 1
Software engineer
Who had
Just three months
Before moved
Get a dependent from daughter
Baby 6 months
A year old
He was moving away from his in-laws were helping
Take care of the kid
Moving to a new city with his whole family
And now it's time to me didn't have a job anywhere when we come back
Has Stewart II failure to build an online game
Have a silver lining
And how the idea for Slack
What's hiding in plain sight
NPR
Sports
NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated license Exchange
That makes it easy
Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies
These to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely answer
Security on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art
Launch your crypto portfolio.
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Honda state of Mark
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to air podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics
Disgust from the tech IPO Lance
The China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Next available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Table come back to how I built this from NPR
November of 2012
Stewart Butterfield decided to shut down development
Is multiplayer online game
Any laid off almost
All of the employees
Are the time to really get to know what his next move was going to be but
He decided to do something
Kind of unusual
Which is the
How about the people he just fired
This is where
Ico
Why do we make the decision when we did because we still get raise all this money we still
Over 5 million dollars in the bank
It was late in the year when you're going to get T-Pain everyone for several months if they had a chance to find another job
We built a website called higher genius in everyone's life
Portfolio their name and endorsements we wrote reference letters we help people with the resumes we made introductions
Processed meat
Every single person who
Work there who's getting laid off and there is up
Like 37 of them I believe
Every single one of them got another job and in most cases they got a better job than the one
Bad
And I think making sure I got hired generated in enormous amount of Goodwill like in the community at large and
I think it was very helpful for us down the road
When we started talking more willing to give us a chance
Okay see you were left at the helm of this
Now
Rump of a
Company or non company and what
What was your next move
Well so
The interesting about
Klitch was while it wasn't successful as a
We were at
Extraordinary Libra.
And
There was a system for internal communication that we had to
That we didn't
I think about as a thing
What you didn't have a name we never talked about it it was just how we happened to communicate
And was all built around the
Weather Channel
And you got a channel
Creative writing
A project for a
Functional group
Atopica
Conversation
And a channel exists whether you remember or not
And it can continue to exist
After you leave
It's kind of an inversion of
The typical
Interoffice communication which is entirely based on email
An email
If you join a company
That has been around for
Thirty years that have been using email since
Inception
You got an empty inbox
Are completely cut off from the
History of what's happened before you got there
And almost all of them
Like 99.99
10% of it
Is going
Into individuals
Inbox
Is not visible
Anyone else
And you can be cc'd into something that was already going on or someone can forward you a conversation
But it's not accessible
Someone else has to give it to you
Whereas while we're working on the game glitch
We would hire someone new and
And they would have
The whole history of
All of the conversations
The customer support team it had before they got there
Do we have a whole history of
The topics of the designers are working on
Everything else that was going on was visible
My Samsung is that like
You weren't seeing ongoing intro chat system Revolution I like you were focused on
Glitch in this thing was kind of cool and it just made things kind of
Grease the skids
Am I Wrong were you did you actually wake up in the morning
Like everyday and say oh my God this thing is amazing
No I didn't you were right
We didn't even think about it I think it's someone asked me what do you do for intelligent I would have Shrugged my shoulders. I don't know if that's whatever
We didn't think about it at all and it was only
Once we had decided to shut down the game
That we realized I pay this
Systems actually pretty good
We would never work without assistance
It's so much better than before
Maybe other people would like
You decide
Let's see if we can't
Take this like Chat thing we bills and turn that into a business
We have these conversations and we have them in our internal
Indications that predated soccer
Pinterest timestamp
Memory is very different than the reality of my memory is it is it took us months to decide
In fact it took us like less than a week
The core was there like almost instantly
And so who is left to who how many people
State two
See if you can make this new thing work
So it was
Myself
And the other three co-founders of those four of us
Emitters for employees of a cat
One of him we had work with back in the clicker days is a back-end programmer
IOS mobile engineer are head of QA and one designer
So you decide hey let's see if we can take this this side thing that we've built
And see if we can turn that into our business
Where they passionate about the
Interesting to make a game of video
Navigation tool
I think we were
Go to the trauma with
A group of people and you really get
Bound to them
Makes you very close
I think we all wanted
Working together
Work with many more of the people that
Wake me up in have the opportunity to
Keep
Do happy stories being a pirate
Quite a few of the people who worked on the game
Including that one software engineer I mentioned to
I just convinced to move on Hangout he's been
Earliest I can play for a long time
They might sound completely different no one's enterprise software that has all this Fortune 100
Customers
Online game
Batumi
Fundamentalism
When is I just like making
And I like doing it with the other people they all like
Making software as well
And then on the other hand
Whereas
There were two massively multiplayer games and there's a massively multiplayer photo-sharing
Slack is most massively multiplayer Communications Network
So what did you tell your investors did you just like say
Hey you know we're just going to Shafter we're no longer going to do games that we're going to focus on this communication tool
Is that what you said
Yeah that's pretty much it and
You none of them wanted their money
And
For altruistic reasons but we already spent
Their options were
Like we can get back
Or
Taken by one more Lottery
And say
Keep the money
We'll keep our ownership in a company and see what you can do
Yeah little white movie
You have the best decision
Any of them had ever made
Alright so you
So at this
Point at the end of 2012
What's Slack
Scarlet Slack
Internal Communications
Yeah I was really wedded to the name and it was not really popular
Internally
And
They're going to be a regular English word
Wanted people to be able to
Ballot if we set it
We had to be able to get the trademark and have a look at the Domain
Pick a negative connotation
Slacker
You're slacking off
Pick up the slack with
Cut me some slack and I think that the negative connotations I felt like
Because it would beat this would be an
Did an unusual name it would
Be more likely to stick with people
He said that we spent
The next four months
Arguing about different names like dozens of different names
Put all of them in the end either ran into like we couldn't get the trademark or
We can get the domain name
And Slack
Speaking of.com
Registrations was registered by this guy in 1993 lives in
Somewhere in Wisconsin
Who is an electrical engineer and there's no more iconic internet thing this
He had his website with pictures of it
Slack.com you can go into the archives website with a domain name
So when you when you pivot
From glitched
To Slack
If the end of 2012 or later
Was it fully formed was it was it essentially
Ready to go
No there's two things that one was the internal Communications
That was
Just really trailer
But what was
As a blueprint for what we were
Wanted to build it was more like perfect
We had that
We started developing
Completely from scratch
Dial
December 2012 January 2013
Couple months later we had enough done that we could start using it
Couple months after that we had enough done that we could invite some
Two friends to try it and then suddenly realized
Here's a challenge
We have been working like this
Perfectly
Natural frosting
Advantages of
We're just obvious
Articulate
And we tried to convince her
Our friends and other
Companies that use at Neverland
Like why would we do that
Exactly
And the
Really hard part of
Unlike most
Software that you can't unilaterally.
Decide to use
With your colleagues
Everyone has to buy it
Yeah I can't send you a message unless you're also using it
So it has a real
Challenge
At the beginning
Especially when no one's heard of
No one knows anyone else who uses any
It's brand new software from this flaky company that just
Failed make it when massively multiplayer game so who knows how long they're going to be doing this why am I going to trust them
And
What we imagine would be really easy sell
How can we go and say
Hey just try this
Great work amazing for us
Was just received
The cold stares
By 6
7 * it would show them demo ism
Try to explain
It was great
We got much better at 10
Refining the pay
Catching explaining what the value of everything was
Can you save this to me in mm
I've got emails coming in
Phone calls
Text
Like Facebook
I don't need this other thing is this just going to be another time suck
And then you say
And then I would say
This will be like
Huge bun
Consolidate all the communication to tapping all these other channels
In critically ill build Hazard KY
The archive increases in value over
It's about the longer you use it the more you get out of it
You can find
The answers to questions
The people that had before it says resources shared across everyone
It's been a lot less energy and of course you would have Jack again and I went to
Yes I will go back and forth with
This rollout there's like
The first
Three or four external teams using it took us forever and then finally we convinced them
Comedy radio
To try
Funny people
Are you guys were at this point how many
Still the same
Working like
Yeah okay this is actually
Probably from the
Practice
We were sure that this was going to be
What's funny is we went back to our investors including Andreessen
Which is now like a really big successful Venture Capital firm
And group had a lot of experience
Enterprise software company
We went in there and told them
Andantino
Are Grand ambition
Which was
Hey we believe that there's
You know we can one day get to a hundred million dollars in Revenue with this business and thereby be a billion dollar business
And
Just like you guys have no idea what you're doing
You understand what it is to sell into companies
You're going to need all of this expert
You're up against
XYZ different now different companies are Technologies and they were they were like
Good luck with your stupid little thing
But did you
Think those investor
Where Ron eats it sounds like
Straight
Well so
By the time we officially launched
It was evident
That this was going to be something
The Leaky bucket problem I talked about in the context of the game was
Completely
We found that
Once people started using it
Hard as it was to get people to start
Once they started
It almost never stopped and
But we can see that they were getting utilities
They were
They were logging out at the end of the day and
And first thing in the morning they were right back in there
CU luncheon
February of 2014
Officially it goes down to
The app store or whatever and add to the world
Yep we also told other people who'd been using it for free like hey the grace
Yeah this business now we going to have to start paying
Will give you a nice
Healthy credit
To thank you for being one of our early testers
We found the conversion
Within
Maybe 2 weeks or 3 weeks of of launching that officially
We had sold a million bucks
By the way what does it cost
It cost $80
Per person per year that you would pay
You only pay for the people who are actually easy
If you have a 50-person company
And there's 20 people using it that you just pay for
20 people in the beginning it was like
67 bucks
Per user per month sound like
Exactly
So you launch it and within weeks you have a million dollars in Revenue
To be fair it took us many many more weeks to get the second million because I wasn't all the pent-up demand
You are Off to the Races unlike almost any enterprise software ever people would talk about it
They would be in line at the coffee shop and they would say oh my God you got to start using slices amazing to change
That they have to use it work now
Completely different.
This looks like a cat
By October of twenty
14 years after you shut down glitch in like have to break the news to all these people you raise
120 million bucks it's is a 1.2 billion dollar valuation
That's nuts that's totally insane yeah it was
Sweetly is Hayden and Nino at that same. We're still growing like
Somewhere between 5 and 10% a week how are you dealing with that. How are you hiring enough people
How are you getting
Getting through the day it was a pretty mad scramble you know and that year
We went from maybe 10 or 11 I can hide a couple people
At most all employees up to about 40 or 50
At 80 people and it was breaking up forgot to move offices and
We don't have enough desk people are sharing desks gradually we put some systems in place and we started hiring
Professional to manage different parts of the business and now it's amazing
So this has been called the fastest-growing business app
Ever if you went from
From launch in February 2014 to
The latest valuation is
5.1
Billion dollars that wasn't
September 2017m I probably is higher now
Did the numbers just staggering I mean for something that was just a side
Project that was never intended to be the business
Yeah
You know it's just feels like
All of the years of
Sweat and toil and sacrifice
All of the years
Pressing on with a game you know what kind of failure after failure
I've been
A more than reward
I can reward in
Dozens of times
Dover
All of the other
8%
Software development teams in the world videos this
And
That happened
Not that long after we launched
And now there's like
3-star Michelin restaurants
Norwegian Department of
Labor and Welfare
Ministration
The Hartford Connecticut
Police
NASA's jet propulsion lab
Aldi's in Norman
Companies there's all these small companies
We never thought it
Even in our grandest Ambitions it was like
A tenth of what it is today
Do you think it was a possibility that you would not have discovered
It's likely that this thing hiding right under your nose
You just
This should be our business was there possibly that could happen
Absolutely
Or that
Dimensions of the difficulty telling the team and independent what that felt like
It was hard not to let that
Crash because it is
Embarrassing make it so
Humiliating
But it's such a
Hard decision to make I think partly because
What you hear is
The never give up on your dreams
You know resilience
Critic
Keep going
Fight the slog
End
I think that generally true I think
Really important to persevere through things that are difficult
But there's also a point Beyond which you're just
Making a mistake
What what keeps you up at night now
Anything I mean
Potential
Editor's
Order are you like I'm sad
And you are you've got there many reasons for you to take a chill out and
Relax right now I'd I lose all kinds of
And this is where it gets really interesting
To me the most fascinating part of the journey so
Through a combination of
Inexperience and probably arrogance when we're smaller I thought
But my job is to be smarter
And to make all of the important
And if I make all the right decisions
Nothing
Set the story that we tell
Back around a lot of companies
But it was like a series of
Strategic decisions that made all the difference
But what I found is
What matters is
Apartments at the level of the organization
Is it to degree that everyone's pushing in the same direction you're able to achieve some
If people are pushing in opposite directions then you know you can put as much energy as you want in and and nothing happens
So you know
When were eight people
It's
Trivially easy for everyone to understand what
You get to a hundred people and that's
Tomato
2016 80 people to 3
23 doubled
Twice
Emmett Mencia we have an all-hands
I say hey put up your hands
You been here for less than a year
75% of the company puts up their heads
Really difficult when the average 10-year solo
I don't like that but like
There's two people
Or whatever on the Android engineering team
And then there were the other working their butts off
Developing yeah but they're also trying to hire the Third
Person in the third person starts
And have all these questions they don't know what they're doing and then
MIT trying to hire the fourth person
And if the internet
Black Chaos
Can you really difficult to connect
Hold it together
And
A lot of this is just
Kind of dawned on me over the
As a CEO
18 months behind where I should be
And
The challenges are starting to become clearer and clearer
But let me ask you about
1/2 questions
Personal life
So you mention that
When your marriage broke up with soda
Even building
Financial
Stress and you know you were worried about this and that
You are now
A billionaire I mean at least
Sandpaper
Does that eliminate
Stress in your life does that mean that
Everything set everything is taken care of
1 nominal correction we've been around for a long time
Company and I
Not even I'm not even a billionaire on
Okay I sure
Makes my life easier
There's all that research and I don't remember where we're at with
What's the latest version of this book
Like Beyond a certain amount of money doesn't make your life any better
I really like this kind of dish three levels
Wealth in the world
The first level is
I'm not stressed out about
People who are no longer worried about the
The credit card bills are student loans at level 1 of wealth
Level 2 is
I don't care what's up
I really want this thing but at $18
There's a level where it doesn't matter which
How much you spend
Ultimate level of wealth is vacation cost
How expensive hotel is where which flight we go on
Beyond that I really don't think it makes a difference to feel incredibly fortunate and it's great to have all these
I'm almost all of the way because
There's no happiness yeah and there's a lot of
Suffering in the world and
There's a lot of inequality
Both of your companies
Either you're well known companies
Were the product of pivots like
You
We're working on something
Completely different both happen to be games
And then when you realize it wasn't a work
You shifted
First I Flicker and then to Slack
I think you were able to
See that
Is easy to look back on it with hindsight say oh my gosh to a bar filled genius Workforce ID
Is that the deal
Do you think that's a fair assessment
Well
Remember where I read the
Visual
And that's
A billion blades
Grass
On this massive field
Imma keep on playing golf and every blade of grass is like I believe a golf ball is going to
Fall on me
It's only hit the golf ball and
Turn off it's falls on some Blades of grass
Msac
It was me all along
The ball is going to fall somewhere this is a kind of like
I was on the cover of Forbes Magazine with black really successful
If I didn't do this
What's it mean to just like okay well we won't publish a Martino cover
Someone was always going to be undercover someone was always going to be
And I try to remain very conscious of that fact like there's a
We work hard and we're clever and
Experience and I think we did a lot of things right
But there's a real increasing rate
Turn Dynamic like once you start to have some SSS
The rest of the sea
Becomes easier
Ultimate example of this
We were going
Really really quickly even before we launched
And because of that
The Press would write about it
And because of
Because investors were interested in wanting to invest
We probably raised all his money
And that God has more
And that got us more interest from great applicants he wanted to come work in the company
And the opposite is absolute
1 stumble
And you lose a couple of good employees and now investors are
Skeptical
You have to scale back your emissions
Now you're not doing anything interesting no one writes about you know and want to come work at your company investors are really not interested in you can you go to business
So
Noelle I am proud of all that we have
Accomplished
Enormous amount of hard work by a lot of people there is this real
Tailwind
That really just makes it all of that stuff a lot easier
Cocoa powder
CEO of Slack
Early days when interviewing job candidates for the company he would always ask
3 question first one
What's
3 * 17
Second one countries in Africa and a third question In which century was the
The French Revolution
Like you were disqualified if you got the answer
But it was just a way to start a conversation
People working for Slack
For curious
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the
Things your building
But first
Thanks to one of our sponsors
Squarespace
A dream is just
Great idea that doesn't have a website yet
Customize your website
Look and feel
Settings products and more with
Just a few clicks
Head to squarespace.com
Build it
For a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Is the offer code build it
To save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
The future is coming make it brighter
With Squarespace
Hey thanks so much
For sticking around because it
It's time now for how you built that
Enter a story starts
In Charlotte North Carolina
3 years ago
Abby kircher was a teenager
With a food Obsession I've always loved peanut butter flavored anything peanut butter
Cups peanut butter ice cream I love peanut butter and jelly sandwiches
But one day
A beaded something
Probably shouldn't do with a food you eat everyday
She looked at the label and I was just like oh my gosh this is
So much sugar
Tons of additives and preservatives
And so it just doesn't feel like it's almost
Peanut butter in any more you know it just feels kind of like a sugar spread
Baby decided to go cold turkey on
Peanut butter but of course she missed eating it
So I was like I might as well make my own there's no reason why I couldn't make my own so that's why I Just Whipped out
Add a food processor in just tried it out
This was by the way her mom's food processor into what she put some nuts
And coconut oil
And salt and eventually took forever it turned into a creamy texture is like wow this is so cool
I got very excited then I was like okay how do I want to flavor this or Sweeney
So I threw in some dates
Process. A little bit and it was
So good so good in fact that Abby started spreading the nut butter on everything
Apple sandwiches pancakes even salad
And she began sharing it with her family and friends and then
One night
I wanted to my room
And it was
Quite literally an aha moment and I just ran back
I can start a business and she was like
Oh right yeah absolutely
It's a good thing Abby's mom and dad were on Ford because remember
Abby was like 15 at the time
So she needed her parents help to track down jars and labels in a commercial kitchen to make the nut butter
But I'm still making a lot of the big decisions like early on she actually decided to forget about peanut
And the branch out into
Other types of nuts
I wanted something a little different and I I realize there weren't a lot of pecan and cashew butter is out there at the time
Time to Eddie came up with five recipes each with just a handful of ingredients
Flavors like date pecan
Strawberry cashew
Toffee almond
And Sheena Montana set up a stand at a big farmers market just outside Charlotte
Call people over they were all incredibly can you buy the story and how young I was they would always looked at my mom
Zombie like so
You started this
Anyway they kept
Selling out at the Farmers Market
And people kept asking for more
That was getting hard because they were still packing the jars of nut butter themselves and
How are they doing that
Spoons believe it or not
Many spoons mini mini hand
That was the worst
Part for sure it just took
So long so few months later they got a machine to do the jarring for them and soon
They were pitching their nut butter at local grocery store
For a young girl and her mom to walk in there excited about a product and it made them excited
I think that was a huge factor in our growth
Less than two years after a bee started making nut Butters
They were selling them like 300 grocery stores in the Charlotte area
In overtime it was just a b and her mom doing this for older brother join the business and her dad actually quit
His job to join them as well technically I'm the boss of my parents and brother yet
Which is
Definitely a learning experience trying to figure out okay what are our positions in the business regardless of our
You know what positions in the family that he's now been at this for
3 years and I'm Not Butter
Spread to nearly 1000 stores across
East coast and Midwest
Put in some pretty big chains like Wegmans and Lowe's
Now we're set to hit a billion dollars in Revenue by the end of this year
Which is pretty crazy because Abby kircher
Is still just
Her business is called Abby's better as in b
E t t e r
If you want to find out more about it or hear previous episodes
Silver Show
Edgewater podcast page how I built this NPR. Org and of course if you want to tell us what you're building
Go to build
Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe to it at Apple podcast or wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write us at HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet bitsat how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by runty never blue
Thanks also to door could see an evil grin
Santa's Michigan Ford and Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Is JC Howard a guy Roz and even listening to how I built this for NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor.