Support for how I built
Send the following message
Come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn
Why by searching Michigan pure Roberts
Support for the how I built this Summit comes from American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible funding
Smart Savvy way to fund your business
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Slash business
Hey it's guy here and today I bring you our second
That was held in San Francisco in
In October
Episode is for my live interview with
Eric Ryan and Adam Lowry there that co-founders of methadone
If you haven't heard that episode we did on methadone the podcast
You should definitely go back and give it a listen
It's the story of two guys in
Mid-twenties who took on Unilever and Procter & Gamble
Starting a company that makes
Green cleaning products
Adam and Eric Spencer
15 years
Building method
Together
Before they each moved on to found do companies so
I really wanted to dig into
Just how they made their partnership work so successfully
How they manage their relationship
Elf Rudolph
How they managed to stay friends
Thank you for for coming
I am imagining a lot of pee
People in this room maybe even in the bathrooms of the Yerba Buena Center for the Arts
They will find that iconic bottle
Of method hand soap
Tell me how you got the idea can you tell us how the idea
Can't you guys
Go for it
So Adam and I started this company at Pine and Gough
Here in San Francisco
Now referred to as lower Pacific
And arguably the dirtiest flat in San Francisco so this is not the Martha
Stuart Story by
By any means
And it'll
We took a different approach which is not necessarily trying to find a problem to solve or frustration
Cuz we are not known for our cleaning
Especially Eric
We saw a really big category which
With a sea of sameness
And we started looking at the category and start to see some up
Yeah Eric really kind of looked at it from a
From a brand for
Perspective initially it was his background
And I have very different background
Scientific Environmental
And
Start looking at it from that
Perspective and it just was one of those things just started to grow
I wouldn't really know what it was
At first but it grew into like mid-twenties at the time
How did you know that the other person was
Going to be the right
Partner when you
When you bet money start
Talking about this
I don't think
I don't I don't think we did
What I knew is that Eric
Thought in a way that was
Entirely different
From the way that I thought and I learned a lot
Whenever I spoke to him about business
I knew that that
Was a necessary element
Or any
And I'm just somebody that believes in
Trying lifelong learning
And so
I saw that is a huge ass
Yeah
We're so different in the way we think and what I
Skill sets are
In a typical business situation I don't think we would ever been
Brought together
What are the very lucky things for us is that we were friends and roommates
And
You as a Founder you off to look
To partner with businesses with people who are similar to you
But what you needed somebody to complete
Opposite of you to make a a
Yeah so tell me
Both of you
What skill sets
Did you bring to that partners
Relationship
You can spell and do math
I was 25 when we started the business so I did I can't claim that I had a lot of skill set
Balancing chemical engineering I'd been a climate scientist
You know I knew how to
Computer program I knew how to do
Certitech
Pickle stuff
And could figure out
Problems
At very simply Adams inside the bottle he understood that
The chemistry to chemical engineering
The sustainability behind it and I was outside of the bottle which was the design and The Branding of it
And one of you and you may not
May not know who one of them is an introvert and one Xanax
We need each other difference between an introverted engineer
Extroverted engineer
The extroverted engineer looks at your shoes
So
You guys obviously very different personalities
Totally different skill sets
How did you figure out who was going to do
I think I kind of came pretty naturally
There is no way you can trust me to do chemical engineering
Yeah I mean
The skill sets being so different we kind of had to spread out on the field but
Early on in startup you're doing everything right so Eric was
Didn't have any formal sales training for example but he was very much on the sales side of the business leading
Customer relationship development that sorta thing is it harder for you to do
You know
Yeah probably a little bit
It also required me to do things like learn Finance
I have no formal
Whatsoever
But yeah that's that's typical more comfortable being in the background and letting Eric
Kind of
Be the face of this to investors and partners and customers
Yeah
Part of that surround my internal motivation which is
I think I am oriented the way that I am introverted if you want to call it that
But also I'm much more and it says try to commentary on Herrick
How much more just sort of internally motivated about trying to learn new things and get better at something
Get a little bit better every day it's Friday night
So yeah but I think that that
You know the kind of bring that around that's actually really important in a business
Does that you have chef
Controls that you can
That you can play and it actually
It was very much to our benefit.
Some of our very early
Sales pictures that we
We talked about on the show where Eric was out in the front of the customer and I was
Kind of squirrel in a way trying to figure out
Stuff in the meantime and
Trying to get it all the
Come together
Arthritis
Yeah you know we had episodes
Where the founders co-founders split up
It's bad you know it it's
It's actually more common than not
Your case is almost unusual because you're still friends you see each other even though you've gone
Your separate ways we both have separate companies today which will
Adam must have been tension I mean that mean
They're still business decisions that have to be made there still
Processes
So
How did you
Yeah you're under extreme
Stress and pressure
And you do this as a partnership and I always tell people it's it's a lot like a marriage but it's
It's even harder cuz you can have makeup sex
There's so much I could say right now
But so much of the tension of the two of us of these very complementary skills and you can see that
Tension in art
Are Brandon great brands have
Attentions right so we had to find healthy ways in
And I think we understood each other well as friends
And it took a few years but when we really learn to understand each other well as
As business partners
And what are different work styles were like and we could respect it and understand it
And then we were able to support each other
An acre
Completely
Different level
I just been amazing
I would just add to that
Fought like cats and dogs we hated each other's guts
And you live together
That's good
In in we actually kind of had to intervene in it
The key for us was
Recognizing that it was way more important
For the business
That we have a constructive relationship
To get our own individual way
And the big learning was
Because we're so different learning that when Eric
Says something
Yeah what he really needs and when I
Say something he perceives it differently than what I'm trying
To say in example of that you are
I think you mentioned me I don't know if this ended up in the final version of podcasts you're very communicative your
Kind of an open book and and sometimes
You describe the way that Adam
Dealt with
Challenges are pressures with
Kind of
Internalized it'll stay quiet space that then get the energy to go attack the prophet you thought
He was angry with you
Yea or withdrawn
Blake Whiteley
You don't like the house is on fire and I was looking what he was doing and I didn't feel
He was having that same sense of urgency
Where he just needed to
Approach it from a very different way
Where when I'm under
Pressure under stress
I have to attack the problem head-on
And that's
Sperry classic introvert X
Did you ever get a coach or like a therapist or somebody else
Therapy together
I'm a big proponent of that because it's what helps you understand this like the situation that we do
You just talked about where
When things get stressful Eric talks-a-lot and Adam shuts up
Right and that's
Two different people
You responding in different ways that still need to work
Together in ways that are constructive even though they're stressful until
Having somebody to help you understand that
You know what Eric by talking a lot what he means you know not
You know trying to think my way through a problem that we kind of got to meet each other in the middle and use the best
Cast of each other's skill set
I'm just really fascinated how you
We're so
Kind of mature about this you were so young and your
Mid-twenties mean in your mid-twenties are going through lots of things in general like you were going to do with my life
Is this working out and yet
You both seem to just have this very single-minded focus on making this thing work
Yeah and I'm in a lot of that is driven by
What a lot of us are trying to do which is to create meaning for our work
Work right yeah we spent an awful lot of time working
And so if we can make it meaningful that's something
That
It has been a goal for our
For us all along and that means yeah putting putting yourself a little bit of side
Could you try to create something that's bigger than
You could ever be
Yeah
What what do you think the difference between good tension and bad tension is right because
Trust
Distressed
Why what's up
Yeah
Ndk conflict can be good right now usually is
Yeah yeah I mean
I say trust maybe that's obvious but
Conflict is a great thing because it's where you are able to build an idea into a bigger better idea
And
You're going to have differences of opinion
Trust is what allows you to evaluate that objectively as
Something that's
A better way of solving a problem that your business has or a better idea than the one that
Susie or Bobby came up with all by him or herself
Where there isn't trust that's when
You know things get weird
Do you know authorship
Becomes more important than
Quality Inn
All kinds of sea
Look for people in this audience for early-stage entrepreneurs and trying to build something and maybe thinking about a co-founder
Maybe they have
Cocoa powder there's a small team
What would you have wanted to know
You know
20 years ago
That would have been helpful for you as you've now grown and scaled your own business
I mean I always encourage people take a partner because
It's one thing to let yourself down
Really hard to let someone else
And that partner
You keep each other going when things get really hard wood
Which they always will
And then I was encouraged people to to find somebody who's just the
Sweet opposite
Of your skill-set
So between the two of you you can cover as much of of the
The business has
Yeah and go into it with an open mind because I think you'll learn
More about yourself
Then anything else
In terms of
What you're good at and what you're not good at how you're perceived and how ultimately you can be effect
Then how you can lead p
In a way that's not true and authentic
Take to type
I asked you earlier
Both of you how did you know
Set the other person was the right person and your answer was we didn't
So
Was it I mean was it just serendipitous that you just
I think yeah a little bit of luck and you know a startup is a journey
Any kind of figure out along the way
And if Adam it started
Method on its own it
Private eye look like
The Birkenstock
Smell
It smells like one
Edify start On My Own by look like Hello Kitty
And we've been toxic did work
And because of
Us coming together and bringing
These different points of view in the strengths we created I get with cats
Jennifer cuz we haven't found anybody who did it first but really the first Sikh Osheaga
Product
I design a deep sustainability
Which is really hard to do
And we are both insistent that it would have these
These qualities in and brought it's a lot of our personality coming together
A big part of it as well as making the commitment that hey I'm going to start this business right you start a business that's at least
Least a 10-year commitment
And
I'm going to do it with this person which
You know I mean we're using the marriage analogy a lot right you
It's something you've got to commit to not just
The way it starts but how you're going to develop it over time so that you can
Can make it work
Work to the benefit of the business
And then I think the key is always put the business
Before
Yourself and if you do that it'll bring you back around to that
When you know he said something that gets on your nerves or
You know there's a
This is breakthrough therapy
You you are both running your own business is now you useful method and you're no longer involved with the company
Eric you run Ali which is a
Vitamins and nutritional supplements pricing at Target and ripply pricing at all over the place Whole Foods as well it's a
Plant milk company
What do you most miss about
Not about not working with the other person
Eric's creative spelling
In all seriousness Eric is one of the best people I've ever met in
Just kind of coming up with
We're really building on ideas
Little nuggets that sort of get built into
More interesting and
And creative ideas
Yeah well I just missed her sense of humor
We always had a lot of fun together
In the office
I miss that pet healthy Panther like brothers from
Different mother
I love how Adam
Push these really hard initiatives around
Sustainability or
Chemical engineering
That would scare us all that we get behind it I think it was
Plastic was one of my more favorite ones as well.
Launch a line of products that were made
From
Plastic
Retreat from the ocean
And I miss being surrounded by his really
Kind of big are they
Thoughts on that everyday
Adam Lowry Eric Ryan the cofounders of method the founders of Ripple and Ali thank you
Eric Ryan and Adam Lowry
Co-founders
Adam Eric Journey live on stage at the how I built this
Which happened last month
Yerba buena Center for the Arts
San Francisco
Morley short bonus episodes from our Summit event will be coming out every Thursday of the next month
So check out your how I built this
Feed for new one
Next week
My interview with John Zimmer of Lyft
Thanks to Kacey Herman who produced this episode and routine Arab Louis wrote the music
I'm guy Raz even listening to this special bonus episode
How I built this
NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email to
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days
Campaign monitor