This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who tailors its policies to fit every business is very specific needs
Which may explain its 97%
Customer service
Get a quote or buy
Diane hiscox. Com
Hiscox
Business insurance
Hey it's guy here and I just want to let you know that we have a few tickets left for upcoming live show on December 5th
In Los Angeles
I guess we'll be Michael Dubin he's a co-founder of Dollar Shave Club and he has an amazing story
From nothing
To a billion dollar brand and just
5 years
If you haven't been to a live show they are so much fun it's a chance to meet me and
Behind how I built this and other HIV listener so
If you're in the LA area on December 5th
He will not
Want to miss this live show
Are shows supported by American Express
And to get your tickets
Go to nprpresents.org
And I hope to see you there
How did you raise the money to start this Venture at all
That's a really good question because I had to go back to all my basic same
People who invested with me in my other horse Ventures that failed right
That had failed gone broke so I had to convince them that even though we lost money in something that I knew a lot
What about that we were going to make money in something that I do nothing about
Ramen
Prp's how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
And the stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Raz and the most spectacular pivots ever from horse race
Racing 2 memory foam
And how we turned that gambled into one of the biggest mattress companies in the world
Don't sleep on a TempurPedic mattress
You may have tested one out at the
Store or see more of those commercials where the people are jumping up and down on the bed next to a glass of red wine that does not
Still
But either way you probably know that
Tempur-Pedic is why these squishy mattresses that feels strangely firm and soft
At the same time
What does memory foam that molds itself to your body
And today of course plenty of other
And pillows have memory foam
Russell first launched Tempur-Pedic in the US
It was a completely new idea a new sensation
Note to clear
Bobby did not invent memory foam in fact
When you discovered it on a trip to Sweden absolutely nothing about
Foam mattresses
Even making a living in an industry that
Couldn't be more different
Horse racing and horse breeding
Yes you heard that correctly
The guy who brought Tempur-Pedic to America
A two and a half
Billion dollar company today
What's a horse breeder
The time he discovered memory foam
He was also we shall we say
Desperately in need of a new gig
He did
Worcester CVS
Credible
Control in a new kind of mattress
Basically gambled everything to launch it in the US
Bobby Trussell grew up in Milwaukee
In the 1960
He's and was the oldest of seven kids
Sales and his mom is homemaker
And Bobby work
Odd jobs from the time he was a kid paper route some
Things like that
But when he was about 11 years old something happened that
Course
Erase entire life
When my dad was I think early forties
He went on a vacation with my uncle
And
They rode some horse
And he came back and
He sounds like I'm going to buy a riding horse I was 11
In any kid who
Here's that is
Totally music to his ears so I rode with my dad
Between the ages of 11 in
I went to college was 18
Pretty much
Every week
And
Horse racing became my favorite sport
We would get the issues of the Chicago Tribune and I would I would cut out the race results and keep them in a scrap
Apple can try and follow when it's been the same horse ran back
So that was I was totally enthralled in that
Eventually went to Marquette University but
Horse racing was always in the back of his mind
Pretty much yeah
I major in finance
But I would often be sitting
In the back row of a lecture
Reading the racing form I would get my
Marquette buddies and we would get in the car and we would drive it
90 minutes south to Chicago and go to the races at Arlington or
Hawthorne race track
And
We would have a ball but I know several times we were so broke on the way back we had to run the tolls
I didn't have the
Gates that you just Breeze right through my hope I didn't catch you
Africology
You are assuming you went to
Stop working with
With racehorses full-time
Yes the Thoroughbred to actually raised at the racetrack
And that's where my interest lies
So I
Who wrote letters
To the top
10 horse trainers
In the country
And
None of them
Didn't answer
And one of them
Was John Mayer rude
NTR UD
Who offer me two jobs
One at his farm in Ocala
And the other one
At the racetrack at Belmont Park
Which is the New York ride
In New York
And I never been on a plane before
So I went there
Here with my bag
Showed up at the front gate and told him I had a job with John a rude showed him the letter
And they said well missionary still in Florida he's not going to be here for two weeks
And I said oh no and they said well but his assistants here he's got 10 horses
Here you can go see him so they put me in inside the you track on the back
Stretch to call it where the Barnes are I went to meet the assistant trainer who was a
Yugoslavian guys book
You know very broken English
And I told him the story and he said
You have a college
Degree boy
And I said yeah he said
What you doing here boy
I said I want to work on the racetrack and he said you can stay over the bar
Only one problem is we have the mattress frames came up from Florida
Division but we don't have the
The actual mattresses yet
So
I said okay
That's fine
So anyway
I slept on the springs
For two weeks until the other horses in a mattress
Who came up with the word
And who would have thought 20 years later you would have been sleeping on a beautiful Tempur-Pedic mattress
Yeah in that amazing
Mid-seventies
You start working at Belmont and what was your job there
I started out at the hot Walker making $75 a week it's a Hot Wok
A hot Walker is guy who walks
Hots
Horses that come from their morning
I work out
And there
They're sweaty and hot and you need to walk him in a circle
For about 30 minutes and make sure any water them off slowly so he make sure that they don't
Drink too much water cause acne
And then cuz what I wanted to do was be
A groom
A groom a 225 a week
And they signed you three horses that were
Totally yours to take care of
Toothbrush and have clean brushing to clean their feet than to put bandages on him and
Feed them and take care of them to do all that for a while but
What's the thing you really want to do
Trainer
Trainers what I wanted to do
But I did leave
New York after 2 years
And went to Chicago
And my dad
Bought me
I really really really slow
Racehorse
Transfer like
1500 box
And so it got me my trainers license and I got in the game and
Ended up training my first winner
I was at Keeneland where it where is Keeneland
Keeneland is the racetrack in Lexington
In Kentucky
Lexington Kentucky
The great horses are
Are trained
It's the horse breeding capital of the world right now
Looks like
I guess you're assertive
Hitting up against the early eighties you're probably closed
30 years old at that time but we were you married at that point
No
You're single guy
Single guy
Focus on horses
Single-minded single guy
What is UCR in Lexington Kentucky and I guess
You should Korean horse racing
Right
Yeah
I got a job at gainesway Farm
And I had
Studied a degree
While I was
On my RaceTrac adventure and became something of an expert
And they needed that
And that was the best move I ever made in my young life because
Hi I was soon
Involved in racing at a very high level it said it was a horse that my dad bought me for $1,500
We were buying Kentucky Derby favorites for 10 million dollars a month before the race wait one horse for 10 million dollars
Yeah and
Can a horse of his name is crowd appeal and he eventually ran last in the derby
But it was quite an experience
And we also have
Significant interest in
In European racing we were just as interested in who
Was going to win the English Derby or the French derby are the Irish Derby as we wore the Kentucky Derby cuz
We are looking for stallion price
And so I spent a lot of time I went over
Boeing horses that we had made major investment
At what point because I guess I will support you through branched out of one on your own and started your own
White horse
Lending or insurance
Startup write that was in
So I was at gainesway from 79 to 86
And then
I decided to go out on my own with Tim Philpott he was the general counsel the in-house counsel for Gateway
And basically you would like the advising
Trainers online
Which horses to buy and sell things like that
Absolutely
So we started stallion Management Service
To do the same thing we do the Gaines way but do it remotely for Farms that couldn't afford to have that
Infrastructure
And then we also had a company called Thoroughbred Advisory Group which advised people
Another horse related transactions
And that was
Very good idea but very bad timing because the horse business started to go into recession
Is this is in the in the
The ladies
It was in the late 80s
Prices start going down
And essentially
Everybody
White Rock
Including you
Including me
Like how broke did you go
Well I was I felt like I was the brokest man in America
Because you know I did get married
When I was 34 in 1986
And so
I buy this time I fast-forwarding to
91 I had two little kids
And we moved
To a better location for kids than my
Downtown townhouse
But I couldn't sell
The
First house my two houses
Two kids
Into mortgages
And no job
Did you have to
Declare bankruptcy
No I never did I order everybody in town
But
Everybody else would everybody too so everybody knew that that
Suing isn't going to really helping
The big joke was it
If one guy could come up with
$10,000
He could pay $1000000
And that cuz
Personae would pay B&B with Casey and
We come all the way back around a person a
So how how
How badly in debt were you
House probably $1000000 in debt
So how did you
Pay your bills when your business goes bust
Two kids
House that you've a mortgage on another house that you are living in
How do you what do you do
Well
It wasn't easy because I would go to my
And my secretary say Bobby we don't pay the rent in a couple months in the landlord was down here
And then I got there Grand turn off the
Electricity and I would go home and my wife would tell me the
The same thing
Gas company called and
So I
Really didn't know what to do
I would
Get in the mail
I would get
Pre-approved credit cards
Going you're pre-approved for a $25,000
Line of credit
Piano
And I would say you're really stupid when I would
I would take them up on it cuz and we would charge groceries onto the credit card
Always figuring that you know things were going to turn around
But this was the period of my life where I
Fell back onto
My roots
Catholic Education in
I started going to Sunday
Mass with my wife when we got married
She really move me up quite a bit but you know I would
So kind of going through the motions
So I kind of rolled up my sleeves and and went to church
And started going to weekday masses
And
Literally just prayed that God would show me
What to do when I said
Doesn't have to be
In horses
I just decided okay
If people come to me with ideas
I'm just going to say yes
Am I French
Horse trainer
Alliance the Lord
He called me and he said one day
I know a
Swedish
Horse chiropractor
Who knew
A company in Sweden that makes
Air cleaner that can clean the horses stalls
Can air purifier negative ionizer with kind of
Zapya
What it was after
And so
My friend Alan said
This
Swedish horse chiropractor wants me to sell it in France and he said I'll go you one better I know someone will sell it for you in the states
So I started a company called Nayan
And it turned out to be the worst
Company
Because
The prospect
Over there
20 volt
Right over here at 1:10 so
Half as good here
Wait before you got them shipped over
Noel Miller age
My my
Market research was lacking
And then the retail price was
$500
Freddy's and there are products on the market that were similar
That were 4995
Who can make exact same claims right
Purify the air
Right Plus
The
Company was owned by a guy in Sweden who's probably the only guy in Sweden who doesn't speak one word of English
So
So he would send me faxes
In Swedish
And I would have to take them to University of Kentucky and get them translated
And when I talked to him on the phone I had to use an AT&T language line operator
I need to call call me
$300
It was like the worst company with the worst product over
10 times the price of should be
And so
This was going nowhere fast
But I had to go
Paris
In October of 91
Because I
Had horses over there and I was still kind of in the business
And the Swedish horse chiropractor said
Call mrs. Bobbie
You'll have to come to Sweden
Wire in Europe
I said why
He said there's another company
It's a matter
Chris Baba you have to come
See this matter
Crescendo
His name was CGI to CG
I don't want to hear it
Buy anymore of your Swedish crazy Swedish
Connections
But I still
Said okay I'm in yes mode
I went to Paris and I got on a plane and went Stockholm
And I met him and he introduced me to a guy by the name of Michael Magnuson
And that changed my life
Who is Michael
Michael magnusson
Is the guy he and his
Stepbrother. Landvik
On
The a manufacturing company which developed
The
First
Tempur-Pedic products
And
He told me that they had just
Launched it in Sweden the previous month
And that they wanted to go worldwide with
Launch what was it
Well it was a 3 inch overlay
The cast 3 inch mattress
Yeah exactly
It's temperature sensor
Distribute
Pressure over wider area so it was
Breakaway
You can put your hand on it would make a hand
You take your hand off and it would slowly come back
Did you ask him about it like where did it come from how did they invented I would have
What is this thing
Yeah it was originally invented by NASA
For the space program
To cushion the astronauts
I from G-Force
And since it was a
Public
Beijing US Government invention
US government and there wasn't a patent on it was freely
Alienable and my Swedish friend bought
A company in Denmark
Call Dan phone
And
They made it better
And reproducible
And War
Durable
And the idea was
Let's turn this into a mattress to sleep on was that their idea from the beginning
No
And that was the weird thing is they really didn't know what they had it would they had this squishy squishy phone was
Slow comeback
And
They had originally been interested in it for football
But
They made some 3-inch overlays and they put them in a nursing home
And coconut
And
They were thinking maybe it would be good for bedsore
And the reports I got back is at 8 yes indeed it help people
Who had bed sores
And
The other thing they heard though anecdotally was
Hey the people who had back pain said it helped her back
And so that's when they said hey
Looks like we got some
Like a mattress
Look for sleeping like out like a mattress
That's when they wanted in Sweden and that's when I met them
In Sweden you mean with this guy Michael Magnuson
And he's looking to take this mattress
Psalm worldwide
So how did you do how did you decide that you wanted in
So I stated house and slept on the mattress and I woke up and he said why you think I said this is the most amazing
I've ever encountered
And when I came home
After my first Swedish trip
I told Martha I said
Where in the mattress business
And what did she say
She said okay but can you change the baby
I mean it is remarkable right you do this overnight
Yuri open at Michael's house and
You sleep on this thing and you wake up and your thinking man that was amazing
Every single night
Yep and Enzo
Writing an essay that I want to work with you or you just said hey this is kind
We keep talking
Well given my
Position
In life
I was more forceful than that I said
I'm interested I want to get involved if it's any possible way he said
Well we want to go worldwide with it we have nobody in the states
So why don't you go back
And write me a marketing plan
And
I said
Okay
So I did so I went home and
Go to marketing planning ahead some help
With some
Old high school
Friends who eventually came on to work for us
And
We
Which is perhaps the worst marketing plan
Everett
And what was your plan like what you said
We're going to sell it here and distribute their like what did you what was your picture
We said we're going to sell this
In truck stops
Because
Because it's only 3 in a queef I would fit gradient
The back of the
Cabs of the semis alright they sleeping like that that
Elevated
Part of the cab right
We thought it would go perfect in there
And we are also going to put an ad in the
Chiropractor
Directory
So anyway that was it
And he came over Michael came over
Late 91
And we met him in Milwaukee
And he I negotiated that he would give me exclusive North American distribution rights
For his products
In exchange for in exchange for two things number one I had to finance it
Because he said we don't have money to finance
You have to raise your own money
How much did you have to raise
Well it was under fine but I was supposed to raise it what is needed so I raised about 500,000
$1
The other condition was we had to sell 10,000 mattresses
The first year in order to me
Maintain exclusivity
And so I said sure you know I can do both
Let me just let me just interrupt this for for a sec Bobby and I forgive me for this but
I understand trying to get into the head of Michael Magnuson
He is a a Swedish
Restarting a
Mattress company in Sweden and then he seems him
Success
End
He agrees to give you a horse trainer a guy whose entire life is in the horse business
The exclusive distribution rights
To sell
Memory foam in the US
Why would you ever have taken
A wrist like that like what
It is a seem so implausible
That's really
A good question
But
I spent three days with him and and horse chiropractor
And we hit it off
On a horse level
Cuz he was in the horse business in Sweden
And so he was like my
Swedish
Alter Ego he looks like Swedish spirit animal right yeah
And so
She got comfortable with me it's
The person I guess
And number two
He
Wanted to control
He didn't want
Have some company in the US
Dads
They're going to have their own ideas
He has certain idea in his head
Oh how he wanted this to play out
And he knew a figures anyway that he could
Control me
Which she couldn't so we had a collaboration we work together
They talked to him everyday
12 years
Did he didn't even do any due diligence like you could have been a mosquito you could have been an Axe Murderer like he didn't
Really know much about you like
You could have been
You know
Horrible person my teacher
Took this
Chance
He took a chance but his
Ace in the Hole was that I had to sell 10000 mattresses the first year
How did you raise the money
To start this Venture at all
Well that's another really good question
Because
Now I had to go back to
All my basic same people who had invested with me in these yearly partnership we raced in Europe
And my other
Horse Ventures
So I had to convince them that we even though we lost money in something that I knew a lot about
That we were going to make money in something that I do nothing about
Oh my God
Memory foam and I need your money and did any of them say
Are you out of your mind
Well my dad
You know he gave me
50g or something and my mom did too
Beijing
Did it cuz
I love you
Right
But the rest of them
I think they did it
Because a they were comfortable with me but d
When they encountered the product
They had the same emotional
Reaction that I did
When I first
Encountered it
This would include the first guy who invested Dave fog
How I met only a few months earlier
Told him the whole story that will bring me over the product
So I brought an overlay over to his house he was January
And it was freezing
And
One of the unique
Properties
Of the material is at it freezes as solid as a board at 50 degrees
That's the temperature
Your sensitivity sold the
The mattress
Frozen
On the way over to Dave's house
And so
I come in I'm carrying this overlay
And I noticed
Ella likely that had a fire going in the fireplace so I
I'll just step this over here
For 4
For a while
And we can chat
Annies okay and so
We talked about it and I'm kind of buying the mattress
To see your baby look like
Uncurling
Sony why it did fall out and he
I really liked it
And you wrote me out a check
So I think that's the answer to the question the product
Tampa Bay Lightning
Lights out
Michael Magnuson came over I told him I'm going to raise the money but can you help me so
So he came over we met him
In
Chicago
And we went over to my Uncle Bill's house
And we showed him the mattress
Told a story
He can see that you know Michael was really wasn't some you know
Fictitious guy cuz Uncle Billy lost a lot of money in my yearly in Partnerships
Uncle Bill
He goes into the back room he comes out
10 minutes later it has me a check for $50,000
So I'm just
Absolutely overjoyed
I said thank you so much
Michael and I left
I drop Michael off at O'Hare
He went back to Stockholm
I got in my car and drove back to Lexington
And on the way home I
Stop that
Fast food rest
The next morning was Saturday morning
And I get a call I'm dead asleep
9:30
Annie's Uncle Bill
And he said
He called me Rob and he's
Who's Rob
I got a phone call
From
Connie
At a Burger King
In Lebanon Indiana
Who said she found a check for $50,000 on the floor
And I said there's no
Possible way so I'm going through my
Fat pockets
Cold then I said oh my gosh and I thought Uncle Bill was going to say
You know maybe my money is not so safe with you after all
And then he said
Can I overnight you another
I said okay
Okay yeah
Wow
Uncle Bill
God bless him
Alright to you
Are now
You got some money you got that you guys sell ten thousand of these overlay mattresses how did you do
We're supposed to 10000 matches
The first year and we sold
So we missed the goal by 9930
When we come back in just a moment. Bobby Trussell
Managed to keep his company alive after selling just 70 mattresses and you listening to
How I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs on the state of Market
It's Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics
Disgust from the tech IPO landscape
Two China's economic Outlook
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com
Slash podcast
Thanks also to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this hiscox
Hiscox business
Insurance experts
To understand
Each business
Is as unique as a
Fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent Insurance Solutions
Every business is very
Pacific need
Explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business in
Insurance expert
This message comes from NPR sponsor Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
Early 1990s and Bobby Trussell has gone all-in on a
Business he knows next to nothing about memory foam mattress pads
A shipping them over to the US in
Containers from Europe
And he's come up with a marketing plan that mostly targets
But things
Are not going well
In a $500,000 raised from friends and family
A few months
We were spending the money on what product do you know the year that they containers were step
75 grand a piece we bought two or three and
We had
Sorry I wasn't taking a salary but I had two or three people
Working for me
And
We were just had a burn rate
And so when you were out
How did you continue
Operator
Well we had a container coming over it was $75,000 and
I called Michael
And I said
We have a problem and you said what's that
I said the container coming next Tuesday
I can't pay for
And he said
Oh
Okay
Let me call you back tomorrow I'll talk to
Doc
Is
And brother
So next day calls back and says
Okay here's what we'll do we will swap
That container
For 10% interest in your company
Tempur-Pedic
And I said
Okay
Because I wasn't
No position we weren't going to make the $10,000
A minimum
And I've got a money and he could easily just pulled the plug on us and said okay sorry didn't work we're going different way
But he said I'll swap dad for 10% interest in your
And I said Gray
Did you got into that position
Because the mattress pads weren't selling so
So why weren't they
Well
The chiropractor's
Who we were trying to
Market these overlays
Couldn't tell you
They would say
Bob
It's a pat
I said no it's a matter
Chinese would say what do you do with it
I said you put it on top of your old mattress
They said it's a pad and how much were they how much do they cost
You're like
$800
McQueen said it worksheet
They weren't
What the chiropractors kept saying
How to make a pillow
Is that what more in their comfort zone
Sewing pillows
They stole those anyway
And so they help me
Design
A pillow Along with Dan phone
And they came out with a pillow
Probably right around then right around July
Of 1992
So then I said okay now we add another product
And I ask the chiropractor we are working with
How would you go about selling it if it were you and they say well
Yeah it's really unique products you need to get in in people's
And
I said well teether
40000 chiroprac
In the US we don't have any
Rep for
Distribution
How am I going to get it in the hands
Of all these Chiropractic than I asked
One of them when I said
What if I just mailed them
And the guy says
Well I guess it could work
So
We mailed
500 pillows to 500 unsuspecting chiropractor you just found their names and like a chiropractor directory
Yeah and the pillow you just sent them a package with a Tempurpedic pillow and what did it say it's a year ago has it because of pillow for free
Yep you had a letter on top of the pillow and it's big box and it said
This is the Tempur Pedic Swedish neck pillow
You know the best thing since sliced bread yada yada yada it's yours free
If you order for
And if you don't like it all we ask is you let us pick it up in Ark
So
We got 25% of them to buy for pillows and that was the major
Breakthrough
That turned us out of the nose dive
And so all the sudden from that 500
A chiropractors weigh 225 of them Hulu
Bourbon four pills a month
We were selling it to the chiropractor
For $49
So we did about $300,000
Sales at first year all in the last four months of the year pretty much
And I always will have a fun place in my heart for chiropractors cuz they really
Got us going and we eventually
Solder have 10000 Power Practice which I believe you still do
Now selling the
Products in their practice
But of course
You know turning this business into a into a business that just distributor chiropractors was not
There's not going to be enough that was not how you were
Blood testing open
Right and we
Always wanted to course to get it in
In stores
And in November
M92
Kirk now we're still broke I got no salary
And we were
What up Cincinnati
To the mall up there and I will do some
Christmas shopping which is really more like Chris
Was browsing
Yeah I'm bored to tears
And my wife Martha
Sad bring your pillow
And
You can find a store that will sell it
You may like go walk like walk to the mall and find a store that
Would sell your pillow right
Walking through the mall
And she said oh there's brookstown
They sell pillows go show them your pillow
So I went there at 9
Show me the Formula 18 year old kid the pillow and he
He didn't know anything and he said well
I can give you the number of headquarters in New Hampshire
Great
So gave me the number of headquarters tonight
Call them the next week I got into
To the purchasing department
And he said all you need to talk to Steve Rich so
I left a message for Steve rich
And I sent him a pillow to
So I would call Steve
Everyday
4 weeks and weeks and weeks
And leave him
IMessage
And
Finally
I don't know
2 months later
My secretary comes in
Bobby
There's a Steve Rich from Brookstone online 2
And I said
And
Who's calling me
To tell him to stop calling him
He had a note on his desk
Everyday
Bob Goff
Audra Babcock
Tempur-Pedic
And
I said
Okay but all I ask
Is one thing make sure you took that pillow out of the box
Because you can't
Tell by looking at
He's all yeah it's very nice but we sell seven pillows and we don't need anymore and yours is what
Have to sell for a lot more than our other seven pillows
I said okay
So we hang up 10 minutes later
Is that Steve rich in Brookstone again
And he said you know
Maybe we'll take this down to research after all
Can pee and not taking it out the box
And when he did at Maya made him promise
He had the same reaction
Emotional reaction with a slow comeback
Back home so taking it down to research men showing his wife
His wife
Do I slept on it
She said
This is the best thing I've seen
So they called me back the next week and he says you okay you got me on your side now I have to pitch it to the purchasing board
And they called you back okay that
We're going to buy 500 pillows
You got a hundred stores we're going to buy for free store and you got to give me a hundred demos and
I said okay I'll hang up the phone and talk about
High-fiving me that was the
That was the seminal moment we have never sold anywhere near 500 pillows
And within two weeks we were the hottest selling new product in Brookstone
Brookstone was already selling a bunch of pillows this was probably
Far and Away more expensive than the other one
Right he said we're going to have to
The Celtics Bobby rap to sell this at $90
And
I said really cuz
Chiropractors is selling it for more like
70 in
He said yeah cuz it just to make the numbers work I said okay well whatever you want to do so
They sold it for 90 bucks and it would absolutely and I started selling
Do you think the fact that it was so expensive was there was like added cachet
That like some people go to a Brookstone and say
A $90 pillow man must be amazing by that
The answer is yes
I think
If you sold it for 30 it sell less
Yeah and that is what Michael Magnuson
Wanted that's why he chose me
Is because
His vision was this was not a product that will be discounted
And he was afraid any other company
What discounted
And would become just like everybody else
We have something no one else has so why should you discuss
It's high-end and it's
And actually
Perform
I would get letters
From strangers saying
Volume unit I had a sore neck for 30 years and now it's gone
That's when I knew
We were really onto something when I got these letters
And that's it what Michael
That was his vision is how to position the product
Italian
Connoisseur of pause and reflect on this for a moment you were
I mean you and Michael had only known each other for a couple of days when he agreed to give you this contract
But over the over the course of time as your business really
Started growing and you had to run this together
Which attention or did you actually
Continue get along great
There was a lot of
Tension
And stress
And we got along
I mean he was very
Exacting
And
He had his own ideas
Of how to market and sometimes I didn't
Agree
And we would kind of have it out
So there was some stormy days
But
We trusted each other
And one thing I learned about him
Is if you do what you say you're going to do
No matter how it turns out
You're going to be all right and same with
Me and him he would always do what he said
So we are very close
Working relationship
And yeah it was difficult we had a lot of
Ups and downs
Yeah
So they had they owned up significant chunk of the company your investors own a significant chunk of the company
How much were you able to retain
Well
10% interest that they swapped for that container
Of pillows
We had to do that for more time so they ended up going 45
Percent
A Viacom
So
Me and my us investors we owned
And what was your what was your Revenue in that in like 97 idea or you doing
2030 million-a-year sound like that my goal was always to get to a hundred million that seemed like it took us
Forever but
We did
300000 + 92 + 2.6 million + 6 + 1/2 + 13 + 28 + 40
And mainly mainly from pillows initially right
When initially but
The mattresses
Came in about 1994
Cuz what we were able to do is
Customized products for the US market
In other words we took that 3 inch overlay
And we
Laminated
To a 5 inch base of
Normal high density foam
So now we had a 8 in
Full mattress
Which almost double the price
So now we're selling a queen for like
1299 or 1399
But now we had something that could appeal to the US market
So since she was a mattress
Thick mattress you were able to
Kris at in his truck to sell it in
Right
How do people find out about them
How do they know about them again
To crack chiropractor
No the chiropractor's never did really get going with the mattresses they were kind of pillow
Pillow People
But we started selling in a store chain called relax
The back
Who had like 30 or 40 stores started in Texas
And I when we first started marketing it we marketed
The mattress
As hey if you have back pain
You got to have this
Similarly to the analogy I use is Volvo
When they started
If you were number one concern to safety
You got to have this
Exactly
We had this
Medical endorsement we have 10000 chiropractor
Selling it
Another
15000 Chiropractic selling it all for Europe
And so that was our core
And we use that as a springboard
And so
Okay we're in Brookstone we're going great guns
And I told Mike Anthony the CEO of Brookstone that I wanted to sell
One of them to sell the baymax is also now that we had the Americans
Fitness
And he said Bob
Our stores are tiny we can't fit mattress
210 there
Wear a men's gift shop
And I said okay
So I started selling to sharper image
Their archrival
Brookstone add an absolute cow
How about that
And they called me Mike Anthony called me and he said
Why we want you to
Not to sell to sharper image
Tooth going to hurt a business
And I said okay I'll pull out of Sharper Image if you sell the mattress
And he said
Okay
So we bought a twin size mattress in the by this time they've got 200 stores
And
They were selling one mattress per store every 6 weeks
And I was waiting for the call
From him
To say
Bobby
We tried
But he never
I never got that call
Cuz then it was one every 5 weeks
And then six months later with one every
4 or 3 weeks and ended up being like
2 a week
At the product got more and more
Momentum
And the reason
It got more momentum
Parallel to this
We had an open up another Channel
Call the direct response
And that's the other huge
Moments
When we were able to figure out
How to sell direct to the public
So I started advertising in the New Yorker magazine
M
My mango is to get our name out there
Install we were started selling in the Wall Street Journal and USA Today and then one day
I got a phone call from the New Yorker first two magazine
He said you know you guys have an 800 number
That means you're eligible for a direct response
Race
Okay how much is that
He said
6 lb
I said
I've been paying 25000 and I could be paying 6000
That changed my world
Cuz now I could
Advertise
Almost
Indiscriminately
I can be everywhere
And
It was at this time
That Brookstone was selling trying to sell mattresses and people became gradually more more aware
And they would walk into the store and say that's the one I read about in the
USA Today
And so that's what got us going with mattresses
Okay so let's get a sense of the landscape of mattresses in in the US like
It's at time like who dominated the mattress Market in the US and a TempurPedic was even like a
Drop in the ocean
Right it was dominated by the four S's
Sealy Simmons Serta and spring are
At the time and they
All were
Air Springs
And
They didn't even try to differentiate
Add a product it was a commodity
And they sold and prices
Terms
Hangouts
50% off and you never have to pay
That's how they they sold it so
We came along with our message and our magazine ads same
Hey
We have something that's a better wheel
We have something that can help you in the 1/3 of your life
That's your sleeping
And so it's a product that can have a big impact
It's okay so you have this
This growing business
And you know you went from
2 million to 6 million of 40
Are you making
Real money is it is the CEO of a company
As far as
My
Making money personally
I
Never was able to pay
Much of a salary because we weren't making
Any money until
We merged in 2000
50 the demerger in in 2000 was basically
Like all of these
Subsidiaries or selling temp
Orthopedic
Around the world
She became one big company right
Right because
From our standpoint
We just had a a
Distributor agreement with
The Swedish guy
And the day that they cancel that that agreement would be very sad day
Can we be out of business
Essentially they could have make it about any point
Just gone directly to Brookstone and said you are exclusive distributor
What would you have a contract but
Well that first year they sure could have
Probably the second
30 years to then we probably were hitting the
Yeah but still
A contract with a Swedish company what if they challenged it I mean it was
Very flimsy
But what I didn't realize is from their standpoint they had the same problem
We were 60 to 65% of their World Sales
So
Is there a company was
Only valuable
Pretty much because of that contract
So we both
I were very highly motivated to merge
The
Problem was
How do you value
Yeah cuz they had the manufacturing play
And they have the IP
During the 90s I couldn't draw much of a salary but I what I did do is sell little bits and pieces of equity
Friends family and stuff so I was able to
To keep going based upon selling it down so
Very many
People I talk to who at startups
Jose are never going to sell controlling interest and I got a controlling
Well
My Philosophy is the opposite is I'd rather have
5%
Of something really big
Then 51% of something
Small yeah
And so my advice
Stok you'd always like to control it but you don't have to
So okay so you merge
You end up with
Yapper certain percentage probably
L5r
About 5%
Yeah
And you are the CEO of this merch company
And I guess
Like in early early 2000
You guys took outside investment you took
A big chunk of of money from a private equity
Right right to private Equity companies came in and
Bought it
And weak
We retained our car 20% for our
Us group
315 million dollars
And in 2002 is that right
Well there was a
In early 2000s after weed emerge
My Swedish
Friends
Decided that they wanted
To sell a partial denture
Cuz they needed it
Good for their other come
This is only one of their
1015 form
But the investors
We're slightly worried about
I'm having a minority interest
With a private Swedish
Company
That they don't really know that much about
And so the sweet came back and they said well
We don't want to be minority so we'll sell the whole
So anyway that's what the 350 million was
The purpose of the transaction was to take the
The swedes out
Yeah not a ton of it
I went into the company actually
Soaps in 2003
This is no longer a Swedish company
2002 Act
And so you're not calling your not calling Michael everyday
Well they stayed on as a consultant
For a Michael did it for a couple years in but not as much no certainly not
And my boss is now was the board which was
To private equity
How did you deal with attitude
Like that
Difference
Because
There
Thing was they wanted to buy into companies that day
We're already growing already profitable and they were comfortable with mannequin
They didn't want to run it
So they pretty much
Let me do my thing
There was an equity kicker
Involved
That we hit certain numbers we will get another 50 million
Which they didn't really think we'd hit the weed
Blew the doors off and we hit it quite easily the next year
Yeah it turned out
To be
One of the all-time great private Equity deals for them
And then it took his public three months later so it was like
They didn't have their money up for a year
Anime like 10
Soapstone
Did you sell all of your your ownership as well and that deal
So little
I did get a little bit of a Payday but I got more options
I'm so now I'm now
Guy I'm CEO of a public company
New York stock
We're on ringing the bell
There when we went public
And so this is just
Tumi
The total answer to a prayer
* 100
So you are so that you're the CEO of this public company
You still at what percentage of the of the market did Tempur-Pedic
Control when you take a company public
We were
Probably
Then
About
L56
Percent
Of the US mattress Market
But we were
How much larger percentage
Of the $2,000 and up
Price point
Tempur-Pedic mattresses are very expensive compared to
Ordinary men
Right right we are definitely in the Hyatt
Luxury whatever you want to call it
We
Are able to operate
Exclusively there because
The practice just so good
It really is a breakthrough in sleep science
It adapts to your weight in your shape and your temperature
And so your mattress is adapting to you instead of forcing you to adapt
Yet
At what we always would say is he an innerspring
Pushes up against
Where is this breaks away from
You can see
That we have a better
Product and that's why we're able to charge more
Yeah
So okay so so Bobby I remember
There was a certain point
In my younger days
When I bought a memory foam mattress
Cuz I didn't buy Tempur-Pedic
I couldn't afford it I just
Ikea
And it seemed like there was a point in you know sort of the
Run 2006
What everyone got into this game cuz
Clearly
You there the other mattress companies
Just let you guys
Dominate the sector until they realized
They can step in and take away some of your market share
Write all those years back in the early and late 90s early 2000 I was expecting
Ticket
Call from
From industry
Player Mike Steele
To say hey we want to buy you out
Yeah and we would have said okay
But I never got the call
Because I believe
That they thought that we would go the way of the water bill
I just was a fad
That was one of the the main concerns of the investors is this real or is it a fad
And
We were able to convince them that it's real and
Convince the public market status
Israel
Because it is
Yuan you step down
I guess in 2006 as a CEO of a company
You just feel like you know what
Been there done that I want to Cana
Enjoy life a little bit and not works
That was part of it
And the other thing was I never really saw myself
As a CEO of a company
Talking to investors and end
There's guys who can do this better than me
Is what I knew from from the start
And I yeah I feel like I had been in a long another kind of wanted to cash in my chips
And and do something different
Yeah
Quite amazing about your story is that
Your entire identity Bobby was
About horses
From the time you were a kid like
You love horses you rode them you read the horse
Trades you read the horse racing you know
Newspaper
Section
You went to college intending to get via train or you wouldn't did this in
Till you were
40 this was your
Tire light your whole identity was around horses
And then you come
Completely switched mean you went to something that
You you had no natural interesting
You just like the product
Right eye I change horses in the middle of the stream you might say
Yeah
And I was in a situation where all all that I knew
Hey kind of dried up and going away horses
And when you're 40 years old and your resume says
Horse
Now I can go and get a job at a bank
Yeah
You really
Have to
Consider doing something.
Venereal
Which you were probably well equipped for cuz I can work your more equipped for that when you're forty than with them when your 20
You have to
Have
The
Ability though in the mindset to take risk
But when you don't have anything
It's not
So risky be think about it
Danielle
The thing is I think it's important to
Have the propensity to think big
And so
I always kind of
Had that
You know my
Feeling is you just got to keep trying
Got to keep saying yes
And
And you got to keep praying and things will break
That is a question of everyone who comes onto the show
And it is a simple question Bobby which is how much of your success
It is because of
Your intelligence naskila how much because of
Just lock
Well I think a lot of its luck
I think
It's the combination
Of
Perseverance
You know if I'm going to Pat myself on the back it's
I kept trying
Different thing
You know I had to ionizer business in the horse
You know
I'm definitely smarter than other people
I think I'm a risk-taker
And I got
Very fortuitously match
Stop
With a product
That was
Significantly better than what was out there and was something that no one else had
So I think
Perseverance combined with luck
Is what
Goddess
Where
We wanted to be
Bobby Trussell co-founder of Tempur-Pedic USA
By the way in 2012
Tempur-Pedic acquired its longtime rival Seeley
Making it one of the biggest wedding providers in the world
Company with a market cap of two and a half billion dollars
I'm just going to be frank with you for a moment
If you are a child
Like between you know 3 and 7
Tempur-Pedic mattresses suck cuz you can't bounce on them
Pictures if you're a kid you like you got to Tempurpedic
You're the one glasses Yuan
Jump on this thing
Yeah they're better for sleeping
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things your building
The first of quick message from one of our sponsors Microsoft
Who wants you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family the Surface Pro 6
As of just 13 and a half hours of battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Wherever work takes you
Hey thanks for sticking around because
It's time now for how you built that
And today story does not start in the typical way
A lot of people think of starting a company that
I think I know I got to wait for that
Lightning bolt moments just hit me like that amazing Insight that I was like oh my gosh I got to build a company around this
But that is not what happened to Chris Rena Forest
He did not have that lightning bolt moment
What he did have was morfa Restless which he had a friend Harrison were feeling bored at their 95
Five jobs Louisville Kentucky
And I really wanted to launch a business they just
I've no idea what the cell so we would actually walk up and down the halls of Walmart and say okay what
Bat toy and smashed it with that home object will we get and what if we took that thing in tweak that
Nothing what if we smashed this with that now with this
They wound up in the garden section
And they're pretty big selection of bird houses
Increase looked at those birdhouses but
Didn't think about birds instead he thought back to it how he and his dad used to build little houses
Literally a place for bats to hang out and sleep in the backyard
Which I know sounds kind of creepy
50% of people out there will think that's horrible scary
The other 50% will think
Bats
But whichever campuran Chris wants you to know that bats they get kind of a bum rap
The vast majority of them do not want to put you in do not
Carry rabies
In fact in many places bats are in trouble they're actually running out of habitats so
A nice little wooden house in the suburbs could be the perfect refuge and as a bonus
They will also eat your mosquitoes
A common bat
We have 2,000 mosquito sized insects in an hour
And that makes someone a Nature's greatest forms of natural Pest Control
Their idea they were going to sell wooden bat house
So now that we found this concept we started digging further into the Bathouse Market this is very neesham
Particular space Market was even a space at all but clearly
It was
And we started noticing that most bad houses on the market
They lack proper ventilation they're too small they don't have proper gripping for the animal to hang on or they just
Don't look at it so Chris Harrison design a prototype of a wooden bat house with grooves inside that the
That's could grab onto and then they launched its Indiegogo campaign and what kind of amazed what about 500 people
Signed up to buy bat houses
We asked them why did you buy this thing
And I think about
Two-thirds of them said like I hate mosquitoes but I don't want to buy pesticides I hate pesticides even more than
Hate mosquitoes till the two partners find a manufacturer in Missouri and they shipped out there first bat houses in jail
You should check out a picture of these things are made of red cedar they attach red for the roof of your house that hold
100 bats
And they look
Sort of like the Scandinavian furniture you're going to want to put it up on the side
Your house right in the middle of your yard and then when you have your friends over for a barbecue and they come over and they said what the heck is that
Nothing you can say my bat house smell like bad house what and you say like
Let me tell you about that
Chris and Harrison's company is called
Bat BNB
And since the beginning of the year the company has provided potential homes
2 / 100,000 bat
If you want to hear more about that B&B or hear previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this
Npr.org
Of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
NPR
Got to work
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there please
Do give us a review
You could also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
It was produced this week that runs abdel-fattah with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to JC Howard nor could see nieva grandson of meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our internet via venkat
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email 10
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week