I quit thanks to her
How I built this
Lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing radical easy
The big thinkers
Can focus
Developing Big Ideas
Try for free at campaignmonitor com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and your business
Unforgettable
Support for the how I built this Summit
Comes from American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible funding
Smart Savvy way to fund your business
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business
Without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Slash business
Hey it's got here and today I'm super excited because
Very first episode
From the how I built this Summit that happened last month in San Francisco
And we asked a few entrepreneurs who we already interviewed on the show to come back
And talk more about how to build a business
Masterclass from the people who've been in the trenches
Today's episode is with Jennifer Hyman co-founder of the fashion brand Rent the Runway
And if you haven't heard Jen's original episode on the show or the story of Rent the Runway
I definitely recommend listening to that first but
He can't wait here's a brief sketch
Came up with the idea for a company that would rent out designer clothes to women for special occasion
Back when she started out she had to convince designers to get on board including the iconic designer Diane
Von Furstenberg
Janitor co-founder hustled their way into a meeting with Diane Lee cool to the idea
Actually Diane Von Furstenberg and hundreds of other designers sign on
In today Rent the Runway there's a hundred million dollars in annual revenue
And what lessons Jenn Hyman learned along the way
How to introduce a disruptive idea
Is my conversation with Jenn Hyman in front of a live audience at the how I built this Summit
Francisco
All right
So
Something we didn't really get into the podcast episode was that you actually had a much bigger fully-formed idea cuz initially Rent the Runway
Play was
A place you could go in and rent a fancy dress for a Gala for a ball or some kind of fancy
The event and that's what it was the beginning but you actually had the idea of what it would be fully formed in your mind already
At the beginning race
You're so I had this vision
In 2008.
The closet would move into
The cloud because
People were valuing it
Experiences over ownership
And that there would be a time where a portion
Of what we wore every single day would be comprised of things that we don't own forever
So all rental meant to me is something that you didn't have to have a lifelong contract with
And that it could be a wardrobe on rotation
This Vision was Way Beyond
Where
Consumer Behavior was at the time and certainly where investor Behavior was
So I had to
Star
With a consumer value proposition that was more tangible
And that was easier to understand
Which was
Rent a dress for special occasion
Because every woman has that exact
Experience of opening up her closet
And seeing the closet filled with dead dresses
But she only wore one
Because she was a bridesmaid or because she
You was pregnant or because something went out of style or she had a last-minute date
It popped up
It was very easy for
For people to wrap their arms around at the time
Renting a dress
Because most investors are mad
They were able to compare it to
To something they did
So I'm starting with
The most digestible piece
Of the equation
Yeah I mean if you already had this idea in your mind you knew what the
The thing was going to be you had this vision
But you decide to take one small piece of it
And start
That way how did you know
When to start rolling out the other pieces
Number one is
It was informed by when the customer was ready
And
There were two aspects
Civ.
Number one is when
The world around us had changed enough
We're people would consider renting their everyday clothing
And
We've been
Able to
To grow not only because of the
The success of Rent the Runway
But also because of the sea
Success of Airbnb
And Uber
And we were
And classpath
The million of
You know the many sharing economies that have impacted and transformed
How we act in every aspect
The Our Lives
But we also at the point that we
Opened up a
Subscription to Fashion we had millions of customers
At that point
Who had rented the runway for
A wedding your first special occasion had a great
Experience
The behavior was more normalized at that point in time
And they were ready to try the neck
Stop
And in fact when we spoke to our customers
They were begging us
Offer them the ability to rent
To what they said was the most important occasion in their life and not occasion is work
We kept hearing from our customers
That the place where they want to feel the most self-confident the most empowered is when they walk into
The office every single day
They want to feel like a boss
They want to dress for the job they want
And there is this pink tax
It has existed
Forever on women
Where there's an expectation that you're going to have Variety in your professional wardrobe
That you're going to
Be spending a lot of money to look presentable even when you
You can't afford
To actually
Pay for those items
So that this was a real
Need that the customer had show me you you have this you knew that this was going to be the thing you were going to do
Do this what you waited for your customers to say we want this now we want to go and then you said okay we can go to face
Ways to now we can push this button
Yeah in fact it was always part of our early investor decks and presentations there's always the last
Page of like what are you going to do in the future
I think a lot of investors discount that because it's
The page where
The entrepreneur says we're going to take over the world
Where did I come to trillion dollar company
But I was convinced
That we can build
The closet in the cloud that puts that 80% of the closet on rotation
And gives you a better way
The other thing that was critical about breaking up the idea into
Two stages
Was that
To be a successful entrepreneur
You not only have to have a customer value proposition but you have to have an industry value prop
So remember
The thing that could have most likely shut me down
At the beginning of the company
Was
Retailers
Hating what we were doing sure
And calling the designers who we were buying inventory from
And sang don't work with
Renttherunway
And that was actually a very likely scenario you can imagine we were renting
Current
Season designer in
For 5 to 10% of the price at the exact same time that it was at Nordstrom
A Neiman Marcus
Shadowsocks
Netta Forte for sale
So the threat was
If Nordstrom wood
Call
The designers and say don't work with Jen
This is insane why would you put my clothing up for rent
So
We started with dresses
Because
After I called call Diane Von Furstenberg
The second person I called called
Was
The president of Neiman Marcus
And I decided that I would go straight into
Kind of the belly of the Beast
The person who is most likely to destroy me I called called him
And I shared the idea for Rent the Runway with him I said what do you think if I were to rent
You know designer inventory
For 5% of the price designer dresses
And he said
That's a great idea
Women have been renting the runway for my stores for decade
It's called buying address
Keeping the tags on
I'm returning it after you born it
Amazing
And I said
How often does that happen again this is
President of Neiman Marcus
He says
Percent
Of the time
I was like
If you know that why don't you stop at they're stealing from you you know their Steel
His response was I can't stop at the same customer who's renting the runway from the dress department is fine 10 pairs of shoes downstairs
It's my best
Who are exhibiting this Behavior
Fun fact
I proceeded to cold call the
CEOs of all of the major
So I met with Macy's in
Saxon Nordstrom
That's great
So don't the Rent the Runway rate at Macy's is only 35%
Whereas at Neiman Marcus at 70% proving once and for all the rich people steal more than poor people
Yes
Two important point which is
Do you think I mean
Given that you created this very disruptive
Brand
Do you think when when your idea is radical is
Is truly radical
Like like Rent the Runway is for the fashion industry
That it's better to face that idea in slowly
So there's two approaches there's the
Rent the Runway approach
And there's the
You would say the Uber approach
The Rent the Runway approaches
We're 9 years in right now
And the industry considers us to be their most important
Partner
They want us to be success
Then you have
A business like uber which of course is
Huge and unbelievably
Successful but kind of barreled its way in
Two Cities
And countries all over the world end
Sometimes when you borrow your way and you get
A huge amount of government resistance and
People deciding
On the ballot whether or not you should be there and you're you're starting to face the Reaper
Repercussions of that down the line so I would say that
We started off
In a weaker position with the industry now we're in a very strong position with the industry and it allows us to innovate
Very quickly
And as you've seen we've gone so quickly from being a business that just rent
Special occasion
Clothing
Two now renting
Everything that you might want to wear and our average subscriber is using us 120 days
The year my favorite said is you are the biggest dry cleaner in America
We believe it's in the world
That that's certainly a business that I never thought I would be in
Did you have a plan be like if this was
Going to fail
Did you
Eva
Something that you would pay that towards or did you not even think about that
I never even thought of it because honestly I didn't even have a plan A
I
We started working on Rent the Runway be
Because I had this idea and thought
But this sounded really fun and that this was something that would Empower women
Difeel
Their best
Before the moments that matter
And we started working on it and it was really fun
And 10 years later it's even more fun
And
I never thought oh I want to be an entrepreneur let me brainstorm an idea
It was just that I saw what was happening in the world around me
And I saw that there was an opportunity
When I had the confidence to say you know what
I'm going to pursue this
But if it doesn't work
I can just get another job
There are lots of early-stage entrepreneurs in this audience
What are you if you were sitting there and you were a painter 10 years ago and you're watching a version of you up here
What what
Do you wish you would have known then that you know now
I think that
Entrepreneur
And Founders are
Human
And we're not all geniuses
And we don't always have the solutions
And not
It's a very human thing to pursue a passion and pursue a dream and that
Really
Anyone and everyone can be a fantastic entrepreneur and founder if
Number one
You have this overwhelming passion
Add a knowledge.
If your idea is successful you're going to be dedicating the next several decades to building it
This is not some hay
Five years later like on to the next thing
Number two is if you have them
Humility
To learn
And to continuously
Transform yourself and make yourself into
Into a leader that is growing with the business
Just think of how quickly a startups
Scales
And
Before Rent the Runway I had
Managed all of 10 people
And now my company has
1500 people and will likely have
3000 people by the end of next year
So every year I have to double my leadership capability
And you can only do that by
Being really humble
By listening to others by accepting
Feedback
And by understanding that we are all in the process of
Cell transformation
Tell me
In the meantime we have your ambition
You mentioned to me backstage
What your vision is what you wanted to be how big you wanted to get
So I'm here to build a hundred billion dollar company
And
To change the way we get dressed
Every single day all over the world
And to democratize what I think is one of the most
Elite
Industries on Earth
And one of the most wasteful Industries on Earth
We have these
Storage facilities in our bedroom
Cold closets
That whether or not you care about fashion
Can you spend a lot of money on
And 80% of that stuff
Is worn three times or less and ends up in a landfill
It's in
Sane
And we can
Offer
A better way
To enable people also
To have freedom
Kids have the freedom to
To express yourself
However you want every single day
And to have that change
Who we are today is fundamentally
Going to be different
Then who we will be 5 years from now
And you should be able to not have that closet that hold you back that's the story of the past
But have your closet in the cloud which is the story of right now
Will you come back on the on the show when you're a hundred billion dollar company
100% hey Jennifer Hyman founder Rent the Runway
Jennifer Hyman join me live on stage of the how I built this Summit which happened last month
Yerba buena Center for the Arts
In San Francisco
Every be dropping many more bonus episodes from The Summit
Free Thursday right up to Christmas
So keep checking for update next week we've got Adam Lowry and Eric Ryan cofounders of method
Thanks to Rachel Faulkner who produced this episode
I got a rising even listening to a special bonus episode on how I built this NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support 7 days a week
Campaign monitor.