This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who tailors its policies to fit every business is very specific needs
Which may explain its 97%
Customer service
Get a quote or buy
Diane hiscox. Com
Hiscox
Business insurance
He just a quick update about our upcoming live show in
Columbus
Ohio
Yes
Tickets are
Sold out
For now
But keep your eyes on her
Twitter feed
I keep checking
NPR prison
Yes. Org because we hoped
You more tickets on sale over the neck
Few days
I treated myself to a facial
After an economics exam and I had saved 40 or $50 to go to this place that was suppose
Supposed to beat the be-all-and-end-all of facials and I remember walking into that place and the esthetician look through the lamp
At my skin what a pity
This is not a treat and I left feeling so horrendous and I remember to see my reflection in
My face is kind of raw and blotchy and thinking if I ever had a place like that I would know
Make my customer care
Bad about themselves
NPR
How I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
They don't
I'm guy Raz
18 year old named Marcia Kilgore
Small town in Canada to New York
With just three hundred bucks
Turn yourself into a Serial entrepreneur the founder of five companies
Bliss cosmetics
According to the small business administration
There's a 50% chance that your business will fail within the first 5 years
Took there some things that entrepreneurs do to maximize the chances that their businesses will succeed
Planet research the market
Play the way Arthur Blank and his partner Bernie Marcus did for nearly two years before they launched
The Home Depot
Or the way Jenn Hyman from Rent the Runway did tons of market research and proof of concept
Testing long before she went to investors all of this raise the odds
Past 5 years which brings us to Today Show because this is truly a story about someone
Never had a bigger plan Marcia Kilgore didn't set out to become an insanely successful
Serial entrepreneur
She never sat down and said hey I'm going to start a day spa in a line of skin care products
I want to start for more companies she was a personal trainer who had a side hustle getting facials
And what happened to her happened organically it just evolved into something bigger and
Bigger
Marcia actually grew up in Saskatoon Saskatchewan Canada on the map
Busy very cold place even by Canadian standards
Anyway the pretty middle-class home
Dad was a real estate agent mom took care of the house
Until age 11 when Marcia's dad died
After battling cancer
So her mom went back to work and Marcia well she started working too which is how she became
To become a bodybuilder
Pounds I can probably quiet 300
It was it was actually a skill and a
David translated self into you know what I could you later so
It would give us helpful
Well okay
So I think I've always loved a big challenge
French and when I was living in Saskatoon which was
A small City and there wasn't really much to
To do
Mysa
5 Middlesex
Started dating a guy whose brother owned
A gym
And he said hey you should come down to the gym and workout I used to run a lot
Okay well you know
Let me
Go down to the gym and check it out it's something to do
Because really
Hino Saskatoon
10 months of the year
Pretty cold and they're only two television channels back then so it was it was pretty dry
So I went down to the gym
And I remember them hooking me up with this
Sam
Female bodybuilder her name is Sherry something and she was missed
Canada bodybuilding at the time
And they gave me a couple of sessions with her
Learn how to do all sorts of
In a different weight lifting
Moves and routine
And she work me so hard it was a basement gym and I could not walk up the stairs to get out
And I just thought
You know
This is an interesting Hobby
I've got this free membership let me do it
You
This is like a
8 method
And apparently you became like a
Weight class
Bodybuilding champion
It's not a mess I went
Etsy
Southern Saskatchewan middleweight
I think I also want now
Don't laugh out loud
Miss Moose Jaw
I said don't laugh
But you know the it was great because I could also I mean by Todd aerobics when I was a teenager as well
Earn extra money I waitress
Start of Lent itself to many different things that
That were useful
And in what
What was the idea
Did you
Did you have jobs in
Did you earn money in part because
You
I don't know felt like there was some Financial NC
Security at home and that you
And it was a way for you to kind of have some control over your
Own financial situation
I think that I knew my mother was under a lot of
You know just just from being a single mother and trying to make ends meet and I didn't want to be
A drain
And if I could
Pay my own way in terms of at least not asking her for any money
And that was something that made me feel you know that it was it was
Relieving
Stressing from her
Certainly I never made enough to
Pay the rent
But I didn't have to ask
Schizophrenic
Because you're in high school
And your body
Aerobics
So you're already looking at like
The fitness type person as a teen
Then what was your
Plan after high school did you did you go to college
What when I was
17 my sister who is living in New York at the time so this was my
Oldest sister
Jody
She told me that if
I could get accepted to Columbia University and get
Pass
All the different entrance exams
Then she would pay my tuition
Wow how was she able to do that she was a model she was living in New York City and making decent cash decent cash
So
I came to New York I had $300 in my pocket
And I was supposed to go to Columbia and that year unfortunately my sisters
Financial situation was not as strong as she thought it was going to be
And so as a hat
Applied for a student loan
For a foreign student early enough
It's too late for me to get a loan
So I kind of was in New York
With my 300 bucks
And no school to go to and I had to figure it out
And this was
Like 1987
So you don't have money for school
No work
You know this is the interesting thing so I started
When I first arrived in New York
I got myself a gym membership
With the little money that I did have because of course once working out is part of your life you really happy
When you have to go
Pretty much every day for an hour Rescue start to
I kind of lose that endorphin
Dependency and so there's a really great Jim go better bodies
And I met a
Film director their name Douglas cave
We chatted in a while we were working out and at one point he said hey do you think
You could be my personal trainer cuz I want to look more like you
He was very tall and kind of lead and I was
Probably a little bit more muscular but not bulky
I said he wanted to have a physique like mine and so he was my very first
Personal training client
And then other people
Drew Cami inter
You just meet you and I started
My sister then
You realize that I was
Trainer and started to
Refer models and actresses and actors and stunt man and
We are all kinds of
People to miso
I ended up having you know
Quite a collection of interesting personalities
Personal training clients
And started to build up the money that I needed
Go to some part-time
Classes at NYU
So
Did you think
All right I'll do this I'll take some classes at NYU I'll be at
I'll trainer and then
But like long-term I'm going to do this
Store that did you was that
Even like part of the equation
I had no plan
I think I was in survival mode
I knew that
Doing personal training and getting up at 5 a.m. and sometimes having your last night at 9:30 at night and then
Sleeping maybe 5 and 1/2 hours and starting all over again and maybe going to a class somewhere during the day that was unsafe
Sustainable
And I used to fall asleep in my
Economics
Because I was so tired
And then I started to develop
Quiet
A bad case of acne and it was probably because New York can be so humid
I was running around all day
And you wanted to look decent to your put makeup on
And then go to peanuts
Personal training session with someone where you're sweating and then you put more makeup on cuz you didn't have time to go home and wash your face in between that climb
Find the next client so my skin got really bad
I want summer I treated myself
To a facial after an economics exam that I took at NYU but I had actually walked up
Town I had saved 40 or $50 to go to this place that was supposed to be the be-all-and-end-all facial
And I remember going in there and I had been under so much stress trying to write this exam studying really high
Hard working all the time you know paying for everything myself and I
This was supposed to be a real tree and I remember walking into that place laying down on the table
An esthetician booked through the lamp at my skin
And then she said what a pity
Okay this is not a treat she actually been proceeded to go out into the
Common area of that spot and bring in the spa manager
Who was a gentleman who came in and they both look through the lamp up my scanning and sort of Tifton Ono
What a disaster and I left feeling so horrendous and I remember taking the subway home
And as the subway pulled up in front of me you have to have the stainless steel side so you get your reflection and I remembered
See my reflection of my face is kind of raw and blotchy and thinking
If I ever had a place like that I would never make my customers feel bad about the
And
I remember
I decided
To take
The crash course
And skincare
And I took this
I think it was probably
Play 3 or 4 weeks
Crash course in
Skin carrying a base
6 skincare and how to do facials
And
I
Started to convince my personal training clients after I would take them jogging or
Giving me yoga
The classic
Whatever it was
To let me practice
Facials on them
An end
And likes
And you would have all the
You know I'm driving
Haven't had a facial.
Ever I'm sorry
Wechat
Like showing up in pee
People's Apartments
All the supplies you need to give a
Facial Impressions picture that you were you lugging around like potions and lotions and things like that
Oh yeah
I mean this was a huge bag of stuff first of all I care.
Steamer which is a very outdated piece of equipment I would never seen somebody's face now
Back then it was what everybody did and that was kind of the method that we learned and we thought
That was good for the skin
You know since then we've learned that it's not so good for the skin Tokay this steamer which was
We like a small
Coffee machine
And then I would have probably 20 tubes in jars
Cotton pads and
Towels and
You know it was certified
Like a giant bat
If you were going to go
Hike the end of the trail
You can go hike that
I was probably carrying around that
Because I would then also bring my personal training app
30 kilos
Wow
So you
So you had this life
Disservice
Sides and go and why you are also a personal trainer and
I mean it at what point Did you sort of
Start asking
People to pay you
Furfrou
I don't think that any of my personal training clients I don't think I ever charged them for
And then at one point
Kind of one of those beautiful organic things
Where
I was doing a lot of
Young model
I was their personal trainer
And there's an agency that used to send me all of the young models who were a little bit out of shape
To get them in shape
I'm at agency had
A couple of girls who were the boogers
And one of them had
Quite Baskin and started to come for facial
And then she started to send me all of the young models
Who had bad skin and I started to really
Gained a reputation for being able to
The clear up ads
At which point I got other people coming in who were not necessarily just
You know
Young new models but in fact
I'm more well-known individuals who happen to
Live downtown here about me through the grapevine and you know
Started coming in and paying for that service
Where where are you doing this at this point
What started at my apartment and then I rented a tiny little space probably
NSA
300 square feet
It was just a one-room Studio I had little closet where people could change
And a chair where they could wait
That was what I had in people to come in for their facials
So you would probably you were
Mira const
Currently working but it sounds like you were
When you were doing pretty well and you had money as a
Coming in Premiere Pro
Personal training good money it coming in
From the facials like that
Expenses but you
Like you were covering
Oh yeah I was covering my expenses I was at a very low maintenance person knows I lived in in the East Village in my
Studio arts
Isn't that sort of a
Kind of call it a one bedroom
And I had a futon
For a sofa
I had a
Tiny TV that one of my personal training clients have given me because they didn't want it anymore
It's sat on a crate
I had a
Vacuum cleaner
And you know it's a lamp in a radio.
So you know I was
I was
A minimalist
What's a client so mostly models at SFO
Yeah it was quite funny because
Only have one door right over the door
And people just sent us at the door knock and then I would open the door and
I remember from time to time opening the door
And the person standing there was so
Outstandingly beautiful male or female that I wouldn't be able to
Speak
Gasp and lose my breath and then I have to kind of
You know get my composure back and welcome them in and show them where to change and then
Give him a facial butt
That was when it really
Exploded and everybody started
Come in from
Uma Thurman I didn't
Kidman Demi Moore
Annie Leibovitz came in
How did you get all these Super Famous clients like
What was your
If I tell you I
I'm just really thorough
I think it's really important to be thorough and do you know
Do the best job you could doubt
Listen most facials
Would take an hour
Right.
Facial is generally an hour
I might be in there for two hours
With somebody if they really needed it for me time you know
If I have the time and I could
Could have somebody
Have there treatment for longer I would do it and I Bank
You get results when you put time in
So at what point did you think you know
This really could be
A business like I need to
Think about turning this into just something Beyond
This 300 square foot
In a little suit
Walk-in closet
2 something
I think I've
Realize that it could be
Viable
I guess career
When my appointment book
Started to be
People first
5 to 6
Thanks in advance
People would call and I couldn't necessarily get them in at the time that they requested I was working today
6 days a week
And still still trying to hang on to some of my earlier personal training clients
And realizing that it was just
So hard to be able to do both that I might have to
You know someday give that up
Also realize that I could train other people to do
The same thing
And that wasn't something that ever
Entered my mind before because
Cuz obviously you know when you think that you're
Early passes
You're going to go to university in your going to have a profession you're going to work
Professional never again no one in my family had ever
Have their own business or
Give me that example
You can run a business that you can employ people that you can
Grow an idea
So
I think probably after two years in that
That tiny little
Square foot space I hired someone
I'm who came in and started to learn how I was doing treatments
And then I found a bigger
Space that I could rent
Which was just
Two blocks away
And started to build out what was
Ben called let's face it
So when
How did you become Bliss how did that
Adeline name be
Become the name
Your company
So at let's face it
It started to become so busy that we were booked and they were
At that point probably 5S
Estheticians
Esthetician being a person who gives facials and we worked on different shifts
So somewhere part-time but we tried to make the most of the 12th
14 hours that we could be open in our building during during each day and we were also open on Saturday
And at one point
Probably after about
2 years
We were so busy that when people would call they wouldn't be able to get an appointment for
Anywhere between
You know 14
16 months
And supply
Yeah you know it was so amazing because people come in they would have their treatment they would leave it would be so hot
Happy and they would book
For that same time slot
For the next
12 or 18 months
I've never actually
Great story
Will you turn up the huge snowstorm of
In 1990
I-95 in New York where
Width of a snow piled up for 12 feet on the side of the road then
Yes okay
Every everything around us with closing
Crate Barrel close Dean & DeLuca close
Everybody clothes
Are phone that day
Was ringing off the hook
What people say
Has anyone cancelled
Can we get in
Because
They were hoping that a point would become available and it's somebody else would have cancelled their put and nobody cancel their appointments
Somehow
Despite the weather everybody still made it down there cuz gossip are they going to cancel their appointment
So it was amazing
So I guess it was like
Like 1996 when when you open an even larger
Storefront right in this is when you called it
Let's write
Yep
And it was
Much
Bigger
Area floorplate then we'd had at let's face it
We had 10 treatment rooms that we had a nap room
I'm and we opened in
The beginning of July of 1996
How did you have the money to do this I mean the Mustang you must have
Rent a space you have to
Play Take a 3-year lease you had to put lots of money down yet.
Convert the space I mean
Did you bring in outside investment
At the time
I was pretty scary
And I again peanut having not had the experience of anyone or you know really any
Business school experience I didn't really
Consider I didn't even think about outside in
What I knew was
That
If I gave facials myself
All day long everyday
And I can probably take Sunday off
And charged you know maybe it was 80
For a facial then
Then I could still pay that rent
By myself and I
How is a calculation that I made
I'm intensive of the build out of the spa
I took a little bit of a flyer on that one because at that time of course we were booked for
18 months in advance and I kind of did the calculation in terms of
What
You know
What we made
When we were full all day long
Everyday
That we were really lucky
The timing was great on this
About two months
Before we open bless and while we were still in the construction phases
American folk
Did a beautiful piece
With a beautiful Irving Penn portraits
A girl having milk poured over her head and talked about
Sweet cream
And one of them was a
I think one of them is creme de la mer
Which Pita Estee Lauder went on to buy and turned it into a big thing
And one of them was a Swiss oxygen cream that we saw and
When is
Article drop
Thousands
A people started to call to buy this with
Oxygen cream
And
It
Latin probably for four or five months
Buena Vista
Article having such an incredible effect on the sales of products
Out of our
The facial place
A lot of the construction
Cost for almost covered by that 1 hour
Incredible
You think about like renting a space in New York City today
In Manhattan
Insane like you have to be
Multi-millionaire
Are you have to put down tons of money and
Attentive
Applications in end
And you did this in 1996 which
Still kind of do that and not be a millionaire I think so I think it was probably one of the last
Periods of time that you could do that not be a millionaire they seem to be a little bit more
Rust in terms of hair
You know here's the kid I remember the landlord
Kind of looking at me thinking with his kid and she's obviously
Responsible and she's got this
Decent business already and you know let's give it a shot
Certainly I flinched
And it was terrifying filling out the paperwork
And it was
You're looking at it thinking of the responsibilities of that overhead
But for me
Cuz I never had anything
To lose everything
Was not a big deal
So here's what I'm
I'm trying to figure out they were at their worst
Spas
They're still there
But you come in and you
You have this
Baseball
Call it that
Somehow
Was just
Exploded
And I mean every articles and people are lining up in the key appointment
What was it about
That's what were you offering
That was different
From those other place
You know I've always
An instance then all the businesses that have started have been
Places I want to go
So I wanted to go
To get a facial or get a body treatment to get a pedicure in a non-judgmental place where people were having fun with them
Music was not about whales
Singing or
I hated that kind of music I loved
Your Jazz and really good sofa music so he's a mix of music myself
I wanted it to be different I wanted to be a place that I would like to go that I would feel comfortable
Where people will be at
Accepting of me
You no answer that's what we did for everybody else
And
I think
It was
Fantastic because it was
Very egalitarian
You would have those Superstars and their soap Madonna and whoever but then you would also have
Secretaries who had kids from NYU let you know terrible problems with their skin
Just wanted
Relief from it neighbor
Are going to school at the Block so it was easy for them to come to us
Yep really everybody and it was
It was
Wonderful because everyone
Was treated exactly the same way
I think I'd be nervous getting Madonna facial
She was very curious
She's one of those people with tons and tons of questions
What are you doing now what is this what is that supposed to do
But you don't screenshot with it really nervous
Giving anybody a facial
So much fun
There was so many characters
From the people who work at the front desk
The client
New New York
Bulova Mason character
It is like watching a television show
It didn't seem like work
In just a moment
Call Marcia sold Bliss
And then turn around and found it
A new company
And then another
Then another
And then
Another
Stay with us and gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
On the state of markets Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com
Slash podcast
Thanks also tour 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
To understand
Each business
Is as unique as a fingerprint or a barcode
Taylor's intelligent in every business has very
Specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase of policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance expert
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
My offering account with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So it's 1996 let's face it
Becomes Bliss and it opens as a day spa in New York Soho neighborhood and almost instantly
The phones are ringing off the hook
So in a very short. Of time Marcia decides to expand double the size of bliss
Chelsea gets married around this time to her boyfriend Terry
And he joins the business and the two of them decide to try new things like make a line of skin care products under
Under the name Bliss
And soon
They start talking about expanding to other cities
But just as things start to take off this is 3 years in the business
A huge multinational brand comes knocking
Lvmh
The conglomerate that owns Louis Vuitton and they want a piece of bliss
70% and they're offering Marcia
A lot of money
So the amount of money that's been reported
It was anywhere from
30 to 50 million dollars for that
That's 70% stake it which is a lot
But you guys were just hitting your stride so
Why did you sell it at
Pumpkin oat for about a year prior to 1999 if we actually had a lot it was a
Hot time for beauty companies
Retrospectively there were a lot of
Cool new companies starting and a lot of interest in those companies from the big Beauty conglomerates they were starting
To buy up smaller players rather than you trying to build their own
And of course both had such a reputation
That we we had more than one large large company come and try and get us
And I think the most exciting thing for me at that time was the idea of not having
All of the financial responsibility
For that business
I'm on my head we actually were we had expanded and Along Comes A large company
Start looking at books
Which was
Was also very funny because they had a
Account and I think based in Chicago who couldn't believe
But we were making this money without doing something illegal
They came in and made it a report and there were all these things in the report like
You know Bliss purports to have celebrity clients
Play reports to be doing facials in the what do you think we're doing in here
It was really it was quite funny to read I guess they just never seen anything like it before
But
It just
It seems like after so many years of
Being
Kind of flat broke
Or
You know on the edge
They would be nice just to have a little bit of money
In the bank
It is getting
Obviously Bliss
Really well but you guys were
Still living
Yeah I'll be okay so for anybody whose live their entire life worrying about money or you know just kind of
You're living very minimally
You do wonder if that's your motivation
And if your motivation and all this
Skills that you've developed will
Somehow profoundly changed when suddenly there are some zeros in your bank
So that was
The bit of Christ
This thinking will I be
Different if I'm not
Starving
But
It was just too good an offer
To refuse
They had flown me to Paris on the Concord
I had gone to pick Christian Dior Boutique they took me to Orleans weather Factory was where
They were you know manufacturing math
Skara and
I'll be there when you come back to me or actually I have to say I came back to New York
I flew back on the Concorde and I'm on the subway
America
In a Coca-Cola spilled all over the
Feed the garbage strewn everywhere and
Hanging on that subway car thinking Kind of Wonderful is the only person on the Concord this morning but then the subway
And it was just it was it was funny cuz I can happily do both
But you did realize that maybe after having worked my tail off
For 14 to 16 hours a day for the last however many years at that point I guess it would have been 11 years
Maybe it didn't have to be that hard anymore
Did it change your life like suddenly coming at all this money
You know I think
You get a few a few
Dollars in your bank account and I did have a laugh and we used to joke when it got wired you know we said the eagle has landed
Okay we laughed and then we went and got groceries in our regular shopping Brooklyn
Don't see money to you it just goes into
It's numbers on a
On a piece of paper and it lands and then yeah baby
You might
Fly business class
A maybe you might
Go and buy a few more clothes than you normally would maybe once
And then you realize
You know what you love is what you love and
I think it takes quite a long time to start
Living differently when when you
Live for so long with the same attitude
Okay see you guys in 1999 you sold
About 70% of the company to
To lvmh
You sold the rest
Your shares to another come
You walking
Tiredly away from Bliss
That's what was
Who is going on in your life
Lvmh after 2001
They started to divest of most of it Beauty businesses
And we were one of the first ones
To get snapped up by another business
So Starwood Hotels and Resorts
Because they wanted to have blue spots
And it was put those into W hotels and another hotel
And so
Yeah that was also very flattering so first I had you know one of the largest luxury groups in the world by
My business and then I had the largest hotel group in the world by my business so you know to two Good Hits
But they put somebody in charge of the business
Who was the young guy probably The Prodigy of the
The man who owns Starwood at the time
Really didn't understand customer service the way I understood it
And
I felt like I was spending most of my day
Trying to teach him but he was ready
And
For me
Do you know
Chip
Spend my time on
That when the person is not necessarily
Open Tuesday ideas
Just felt like banging my head of
It was very
Is it raining
So I decided to take a
And I didn't really know what I was going to do
But I just didn't want to do that
Anymore
So when when you left
Starwood
What did you do to chew Dino
Musa London
Like for a while did you just
Can I hang out
Controller not working for a while
But probably had a
About three months
Off
And
As soon as I
I had
A little bit of energy back I started to
Come up with a few new ideas for a new brands and and new things that I has a woman again
The hole in the market
Play Store
So I guess the
We should we should we should point out here that
It didn't take very long for
How to decide to start a new business
Which it which was soapandglory
And this is going to be like before tubal personal hygiene products
Yeah I'll be okay so I remembered you
You know scanning newspaper says scanning these
Journals
Every Sunday and
FEMA Zeitgeist really being one about collaboration
And you know Heist
Street prices all right you know
Really affordable pricing for designers
Stop an H&M was Leading The Way with that
And also
About waist
There was starting to be a lot of
A lot of
Interest in environmental concerns there was a story about David Beckham
Only wearing his underwear once
Throwing it out and how wasteful it was you know that
SOA
I started to think
You know people are really
Worried about the environment
People want more for them
And so how can I roll that all up and do
Fun little brand
That I can sell
And soap and Glory it was designer affordable
Cosmetic
And then of course I we also did Dre sample packaging that wouldn't be
You're too hard on the environment
Took all the Zeitgeist ideas
Bundle them up and
So we launched at Harvey Nichols
Really fun department store and then
Boots came knocking
Medusa's the big the big drug store
Britain
And so we rolled out into boots and it was
It was actually very small for the first couple of years we didn't do that much business but within
I'd say 767 years we were
Probably be telling about a hundred million
And you didn't and you did not take any outside investment for this cup
I know cuz you didn't need to you had you could use the money that you had from the sale of blessed to
Do lunch this next company organic growth
People think about these overnight successes and very rarely are they in overnight
My things do take years and they grow but then once they grow big enough they start to snowball
And though it started to snowball in it at one point
I remember
Istudent
Crazy Christmas bags
Is Chris inspectors stop
Full of Prada
And they were literally
But hundreds of thousands of them produced
Every Christmas and
The week before Christmas
That would be the special offer
We should go in and get
Soaking for a Christmas bag and if you walked around London
Every third person was
Carrying
Three or four of these on their arms
It was such a big
In the midst of of launching soap & Glory
A year later
You lunch to another company
In addition to that you lunch today
A company that makes
I like flip-flops
FitFlop
So how did that happened why would you like a second company whilst
Trying to a lunch
Second company why would you like to third company
But trying to get your second
You know
This is very interesting
White lights to kind of simultaneously
However I have just read this book called Originals
And this one chapter
In that book where it says
2 entrepreneurs always hedge their bets
Right you don't give up your day job because
You think that you are you know side hustle or whatever it is
Is going to actually pay off
You always do two things at the same time cuz one of them may not work and you want to make sure that you've got another one
And it's kind of like personal training
While I was doing facials
What's right and I guess I did that
Again where
With soap and Glory when I started it you know it was only a year later
But I also launched FitFlop and it was really based on
The idea for one shoe which was economically correct which would align your body while you watch
Because of my personal training days and trying to
Use my time more efficiently and having started this
This new business open Glory thinking that I'd have work-life balance and then finding that I had
No time at all actually
Or very little time to exercise
I was thinking to myself
What can I invent to make more out of this time that I
That I have when I am walking
How can I make walking really work for me in an optimal way
So I've been spent a lot of time on different trains in the UK going to different universities trying to find somebody
Who would be able to help me realize this idea and in fact
Eventually I found Doctor Dave Cook at the University
South Bank in London which was
Probably a mile away at the
So I eventually met with DACA
When I went in at security idea
Blah blah blah and he said I know how you can do that
So they told me they could make a prototype that they had a shoe design
Course going on within the University
I waited and waited waited about three months later I come in to see this prototype in it
Literally it looks like a lump of coal
With some breaks
Finance
Sell vested so ugly
No one will wear this outside no matter what it does for them
But we tested it right so we
We put it on
Some
Different
University students feet and
Put electrodes on them and we looked at their
Forces
You can see whether or not the technology is helping
To align
The force that goes through your heel
Your heel strike
When you walk
And
It worked right said this this lump of coal with the robes
It worked
So
I've been thought okay
What do I do now
About the shoe
It does what I wanted to do
I don't know how to make a shoe or where to go to get shoes made and then I felt like
To go to Nike or Puma or whatever and they thought no I can't cuz it going to steal my idea
Yeah and then in the recesses of my mind
Right I remember that I knew somebody who did Footwear
At the time they were called Peter black they've since been bought by a Chinese conglomerate
We called Peter black Footwear and we met with somebody who did sourcing for them
And then we had a mold made
Which again you know which one of these since you got to take a flyer it was probably
$40,000 to have the mold made
So you have to really hope this is going to go because $40,000 is not nothing
But at the time
I thought you know what I buy this shoe with the shoe was available so I'm sure other people will buy this shoe
And so would you run up we made a prototype
Ratably comfortable
Incredible
And
I remember sitting down so course I went to retailers that I knew
From my American days first and then and then also to Busan in the UK who is selling soap & Glory but about
A year before that I had met with Bath & Body Works
Explain the idea
And the buyer from Bath and Body Works
Looked at me and said
I'll take summer between 300000 and 500000 pairs of those in a year
Wow
I was shocked I remember walking away cuz they wanted to meet at claridge's so we went to claridge's you know and had tea and talked about it then
Walking out of claridge's tanking
Whole new level
I mean I couldn't get 300,000
Facials a year
It's incredible I mean if you if you think about it right so you
You sell blessed
You walk away from blessing
You then
Launch soap & Glory in
Run that business
Simultaneously launch
The economic shoe line
FitFlop in 2007
You sold soap & Glory To Boots
So I guess in
And then last year you launched
A brand new business
A subscription service
For high-end cosmetics
That are actually
Very little money
Adpi
How do you do that how do you
How do you
Create so many how do you say on top of so many different ideas and Company
You know guy today I don't feel like I'm quite so on top of it
But beauty pie the whole idea behind it was
Knowing
Peanut in the Cosmetics industry
Fun it is
To go to some of these third-party lab
And that you walk out of there with
Peanut bags
For a free cosmetic
And
Yeah you're you're walking
Through of cosmetic store with a bag that you just got from the third party lab.
It's probably
Got a $2,000 street value
And they were all free and thinking
Wow
You know what if I can bring every woman into the
Into the luxury cosmetic Factory with me and we can raid it together
Have fun with that babe
What a thrill is like being a kid in the candy store
And so that was the idea behind PewDiePie how do I
How do I give women the same feeling that I have to get the
Furnace parts
Of being able to work in cosmetics is Wendy's
Reebok
Stuff from the lab show up
And Pewdiepie is a little bit different if buy stuff at the factory
Drake Hospital
Is practically
Compared to what you pay for it at retail
What what's interesting is that you don't seem to be
Service sentimentally attached to your comfort
You lost them you create them you
Tournament
Incredibly successful companies
And and you sold at least
Two of them and
And you may
Sell others
Do you
Is there a certain point where you just say yeah I don't know
I just want to move on and in and start something new like is it
Is it almost like
When a business becomes
To bake or
Hey or are you just going to get bored of you
You want to
Start something new
You know I thought about this one a lot
I did get asked you and why
Why do you keep doing this
And I'm and I think about the
Thrill that is beauty pie right now which is really like I'm rubbing sticks together
And I think it's
What really drives me and what I really love
Have you ever heard the expression
Your first marriage is for love the second One for money and the third one
Companionship
I think some famous divorce
Say probably
They said that one
The companionship that
That
I get out of having a business where I can really
Interface with women and I'm making them happy
Answer Man of course we have
We have 4% men at the moment but do you want to make people feel that happy and
And have them communicate that to me is what
Give me the
Biggest Buzz I mean it's
It's
What do you think
That
That your your brain works that way that
That you just
R generating all these
Hainan and ideas that
That don't just going to
Flowed up in
In the space that ideas
You actually
Stop sit down and start
Really
They almost seem too obsessed
DC Legends
/ take everything
In your world like
Why do you think
That happened
How did I end up like this
It was sort of yeah
You know I have
But a lot about that cuz you have to psychoanalyze yourself and I
I also tell wannabe entrepreneurs right
I would tell them that
One of the tools that they should have is understanding of how the human brain works
Text right because if you can understand how your brain is fooling you
When you might be reacting
To something rather than making a sound
Decision or when you might be feeling insecure when you really shouldn't be a when you're jumping to a judgment
Nest doesn't have enough information to back it up
Now when you try to think those psychoanalyze yourself I would say well I must be extremely
Competitive because I will come up with these ideas and things
I can't do that and then I'll think
I have to do that and then I'll take
But if I don't do that fast somebody else is going to do it
And I don't know why I care
I need why do I care if somebody else goes and does it
There must be some competitive aspect to it and so I much
More comfortable
Where I feel like I'm building something
It's got to be genetic
Right cuz there's nothing else that would
Really
Blamed
How much of
Of your
Just teasing
Is because of
Of your intelligence
Hard-working how much how much do you think
Is because
Good luck
Okay
I'd say
I'm certainly above-average
And intelligent
I'm not a genius
I know a lot of people
People who are
Much more intellectual than I am actually much moisture
TJ
And
People always say that I'm very stressed
Teejet but I don't think of myself as such a strategic
Sick person Digest
Tend to think of things in very
Simple
Terms
Luck I've certainly had some
I mean
Moving to New York and having a sister who was
Really good looking at in a field where she could
Give people who could afford my services
You know if they
An introduction to me so that I can have clientele
And then more of those people
I would prefer more of those people that's certainly lucky
However if I wasn't good at what I was doing I don't think I would have any up
And if I didn't show up on time if I was
Pet friendly and
In a reliable I suppose
You get a bit of luck
I don't have to make something out of it
And
I find
When I see and I'm sure you see this is why you see people were so talented
Really genius at what they do but they're not
Ever really
Successful they're always struggling
And I always wonder
You know is it just a choice that you make where at one point you say you know what I am
I am worthy
I deserve this why not me
Because
You know why not you
And if you're willing to work that hard why shouldn't you then take the success that comes with it
And I think that's a very complex thing for many people
And somehow I've managed to
Over
Combat
It is amazing how many how many of these companies
Created
E-end
All the things you've done
Have you ever come up with the idea that that you thought was just going to
Amazingly well that you just
Didn't pursue because it wasn't actually quite right
I have one right now but I
Not that I'm not pursuing it
Not right
But I can't say what it is because we're patenting at the moment you are going to lunch something new
On top of all these other
Incredible a guy to you
Doesn't your brain want to explode
Marcia Kilgore is the founder of bliss Spas soap
Gloria skin care products
Fitflops airgonomics shoes
PewDiePie makeup and also a v brand we just ran out of time to talk about it
It's a line of environmentally friendly bath products called the super duper
Mercy has built so many companies that on the last episode of the Oprah Winfrey show
Oprah named her one of her
Personal inspiration
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about
Your building
The first of quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Starbucks
For the first time
43 years
Starbucks
Introducing a second espresso
Blonde espresso
It's smooth and supple
So whatever your drink is
Try it with Starbucks
Blond espresso
Hey thanks for sticking around
Tylenol for how you built that and the business were about to talk about goes
Back about
25 years
Before we all had cell phones and back then
The most
Portent handheld device
In our lives
Was probably
TV remote
I mean
TV a week and it's a device that we
Use everyday
This is Steve Crowell of Chicago
Steve worked at a big box
Electronic store
He discovered the many many ways that the
TV remote
Qingdao
The baby
Takes the remote and starts to
Banging
Destroys at the dog bite
Fix the remote
Control and a half
Text the
Numbers have the remote control really angry bird
I am surprised myself
About why people are missing
So many remotes
How to file this information away
In his head
And in 1992 when the electronics store where he worked
Went out of business
He and the other employees get a discount on the leftover merchandise
And while I was buying some of the
The used electronics one of the store managers
Big box of remote controls
And I asked my how much
Are those
I'll just give him
And Steve already figured that with lots of people probably have broken and
Smash remotes lying around
Take this box of
Perfectly usable remote
He'll sell them for a few bucks
A month later I started selling these at
Flea market and they were just
Flying off the
Michelle Phan
Like what
You know there wasn't a man
Not only were there a surprising number of people who needed remote
Steve found out there were actually boxes of
Orphan remotes
Floating around in the marketplace because
The TV companies usually made extras
To all he had
Do was become a middleman
And fortunately this coincided with the internet Revolution
The internet was
Push-up it wasn't for the
Internet I wouldn't be in this fix
Cuz I remember to this day I
Started selling on eBay March 3rd of 98
So you might be thinking yeah I get this year
He's no family with you know a crazy pet bird might need to replace the remote but he is this thing scale
Could Steve actually make money selling these things
In the answer
Productivity yes because he
He figured out how to sell wholesale like
He could sell a bunch of remotes to a budget hotel
Solder
TVs are quite old let's say from the mid-90s
Please I've got to update some
And they're trying to cut their cost
So they may buy a bunch of
TVs
From a refurbisher and they met
Knock it the remote controls
So then they contact me
So after years of doing this
Steve now knows how to source
TV remote
Different makes and models
Importers and manufacturers around the world
He charges anywhere from $0.50 to maybe twelve bucks a piece
Which may not sound like much but
Steve says he makes about half-a-million dollars in Revenue
And if you want to find out more about Steve
Honest Company Crowell Enterprises
Check out our Facebook
If you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org we love hearing
Seeing what you're up to
And thanks for listening to our show this week
If you want to find out more or hear previous episodes you can go to how I built this. Npr.org
Please also do so
Subscribe to our podcast at Apple podcast or however you get your podcast
You can also write us is Hib tea at npr.org
Between us two at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Falkner run teen there a Blue Beacon
Pause the music
Thanks also to neva grandson as Mexican Ford Thomas Lodi Animal Stak and Jeff Rogers
Are injuring his new recruits
I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week