This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who understands every small biz
Business is uni
Impaler's it's Palace
State your business is very specific
Get a quote or purchase of house
At h i s c o x
.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Support for this podcast comes from American
Express
No matter what
You do in business
I'm building a better mousetrap to building a better app
Easier
Don't go It Alone
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
People really quick
Before we start the shell
I have some
Good news to share
Two more live shows
Coming up
First
Talk with Emily Weiss
The founder of glossier
That one's happening on November 1st
New York City
On December 5th
In Los Angeles
I'll sit down with Michael Dubin co founder of Dollar Shave Club
Both shows are
Supported by
American Express
And tickets go on sale this Friday
September 14th
So just go to NPR presents. Org
To get your tickets and hope to see you in New York
Or LA or
Why not both
Early on I was putting together a plan
At the bank that we have been using personally and our Banker said
Know the way that you sort of dribbled this paperwork in makes me think that you know know
Nothing about running a business and I'm not even going to take your loan to the committee
From NPR how I built this
Show about entrepreneurs idealist at the stories behind the movement
Gyros
Turn her husband's basement homebrewery into New Belgium
One of the biggest craft beer makers in America
Founding stories of companies
Amazon
Apple or Google
You will find a version of the same story in that Story begins
Where else
Garage
Jeff bezos started in his garage
Larry and Sergey began in a garage
In Palo Alto and the two
Steve's
Jobs and Wozniak
Built the first
Apple computer
In a shared garage
And of course there are variations
Daymond John started
Fubu
Trunk of his car JK Rowling wrote the Harry Potter books at a cafe in Edinborough
You heard the stories
Some of them are apocryphal
Embellished a little bit years later tattoo
Add Mystique to
Founding narrative
But this story you're about to hear
Really did start at home
In the
Exact
In the basement
Just the office but it was
For all intents and purposes
The factory is well
In 1991 Tim Jordan
And her husband Jeff lettuce
We're newlyweds living in Fort Collins
Colorado was a really good amateur beer maker he was so good
Pet friends
Encourage him to sell his home brew
But Kim
Speakerplans
And even though
She thought she could turn their basement Brewery into a business
She never said it would become one of the biggest crap your makers
Company
It's been valued at anywhere from half
A billion to a billion dollars
How she got there
Welcome Jordan sat down with me
Tell her story
Front of a live audience
The Boulder Theater
Boulder Colorado
So welcome to the show
Thank you and thanks to all of you for coming
This is a is a pumped-up crowd
People are really proud of
Colorado maker
Right
Let's start at the
Beginning tell me a little bit about
You really
Grew up in Washington DC as it is a kid right
Yeah pretty much
My dad was involved in political Administration so we lived in Sacramento
He was
Pat Brown's press secretary this is Jerry's father
That gives you a sense of how old I am
And
Pat lost
To Ronald Reagan
And so we moved to Washington DC because Lyndon Johnson was
The president
And he was hiring Democrats
For his admit
Ministration
And I I read that as a child
He's very small child
You were taken to like
Pretty big rallies like even the MLK March on Washington what you must have been
Did you were you taken there as a kid
We didn't go to the MLK March I did March
With Cesar Chavez
In the
You know San Joaquin Valley
And then we
Did later marches on washing
So as a kid
Pretty
Solidly liberal
Yeah and also with a real bear
Community
Organizing activism you know we did go to March
And we did
My mom was a social worker
And she work
Chicken child protection
So occasionally we would have kids in our house that
Had no place
To go so
Yeah
And
As a kid growing up in a house that was
Really about policy and and and
Child protection of things like that did you talk about entrepreneurial stuff and it wasn't even
Looking glamorous
In your in your mind at all
No
.
I think it's good to set a tiny bit of context because I think
Business is different today than it might have been that I'm not sure of that
You know the profit motive was something to be a little bit
Suspicious cells
Business was not something
That our people did
You
You went to a quaker High School
Did that
Like to have
Any influence on you or was it just sort of you know the
Three four years and
Kind of moved on
I actually think it had a profound
Influence on Me George Fox
Who is the father of American quakerism
Had a saying that was on the wall of our
Of our cafeteria which is let your life speak
And so
You know that notion every day we had
Chores that we had to do an everyday we went to meeting and
And that notion of
Sort of
Attending to the collective
To the community
Really Randy panda
Little lot of sense to your DCU Washington DC graduate high school
How did you end up
In Colorado
What's the story
I graduated from high school when I was 16 and I lived
For a little while outside of DC with some roommates
And I had a friend who lived in Fort Collins and I thought well I had $100
I have $100 and I have a car
And I have a friend icon
Can stay with
And I
Packed up my Volvo 544 the turtle back one
And
I always knew
When I moved from Sacramento to DC
Did I was more of a western person and I wanted to move back to the West
So this will be like the late 70s
You go to
Takara move to Fort Collins
On July 10th
And
Soon after that enrolled
If University know I did that over several years
Later I went on the south
Paying
Plan I was raised to be really
Self-sufficient and competent than I just kind of decided I wanted to do that
So when you were when you got to college what did you think you you were going to do
With your life
Start a brewery
Yeah I know I didn't really know but my family were
Big Believers in a liberal arts education I'm a big believer
Labor in a liberal arts education I think it makes you a good thinker
And so it really didn't matter to me what I was going to do it matter to me
That I
Had that experience
So when you graduated what did you order
I started
Working as a social worker and a
Program for low-income single parents
In Fort,
In Fort Collins and a town close by
Did you like it
I did
Did I miss it
When I started in this
Not so much
It's a minute
It's
Tough workwear
But I would say that social work is a generalist
Degree so you learn a lot about a lot of working with
People and it's also systems theory
And those two things were the
Perfect setup
For the next
Tell me how you you're in Fort Collins
Cats right early 80s
When
And how did you meet
Jeff Levin
We met a few times through friends
And then we met at a party
He and we just sort of started like hey you want to go on a hike and
But you did that Bond over beer or any
Like that not the first time but the first sort of
Date we had
He brought us
Pack of beer
Oh nice very romantic
And what like what was Jeff doing up
Jeff
Is an electrical engineer
And he was doing bench
Top
Engineering I can give you sort of some bla bla bla words
But they mean almost nothing to me
Yeah
He was testing machines
And
So you guys started dating and
You hit it off
Obviously you liked him and
How long do you have between the time you met him in the time you guys
Decide to get married
Almost 2 years
Answer you I guess you're in your 20s
I was
31 ish
So you are
Doing social work
Jeff is
Testing machines out in a way we don't
Quite understand the story particular
I guess we're around the time you met him around the time you really started dating
He had just
Come back
From a trip to
Belgium is that
And he took
One of his mountain bikes
With him on that trip
And that's how fat tire github
Name he tried a beer
And he was a home Brewer and he'd started winning awards for his Homebrew
And
He started brewing a beer that was to emulate a beer that he had there
And he named It Fat Tire is a Homebrew which is kind of a common Homebrew thing
Try to give things clever names
When we started the brewery people say
Oh my God you cannot name that beer Fat Tire that is the worst name ever here like that
Take our chances with
This one
Explain explain to me when he
He comes back on a bike trip
And he starts to
Try and emulate this Belgian beer
What did he say to you what was your impression of it like what made it
Unique
But you have to remember again kind of take yourself back
Many of you probably weren't drinking beer then but it take yourself back to that time
Where beer was still really kind of
You know the drink of the knucklehead and it was there was not you didn't think about what glassware
Where do you want to put your beer in or what might you eat with the beer
It was
We would go to parties and we will bring some beer and people tell that's okay you know we have a keg of
Coors Light or something and
It was really kind of an uphill
To convince people
That beer with
Flavor
And you know
What do I want to say though because
The big to Brewers in this country make technically excellent
Beer
And I never want
To sort of discount that because
They're very
Skilled at it
But they're not
Craft Brewers
And they don't
Really have sort of that
Got feel for how you might
Start a movement
Where people are talking
Sing about what am I going to drink with that and
But I'm trying to understand how did Jeff
Convince you I mean
Clearly he knew about beer he was brewing it
But
How did you how are you convinced that this
Belgian beer he was making a special
The beer was good
We had not yet had they were going to start this Brewery conversation but that conversation
We were
Sort of right at the Crux of being
Married
And I just remember thinking
There is no way
That I'm going to stay to my brand new husband know you have to go to that bench top
Do that thing you do whatever it is because we have to have this paycheck it's like sure
Let's try this thing went to UNI said hey Kim
I want to brew this beer
And like
Sell it
I want to start a brewery
Yeah
And you said okay
Where
Right well that was so so we took a second mortgage out on our house
A big leap
Just saying sure let's take a second mortgage
With no
Like
Worried about you know I wasn't worried about it I always felt like we had these daytime gigs
And we could always go back
To those if we needed to
And this seemed like a really
Fun interesting challenging
The part that I maybe didn't
White Factory in is
The first few years of our marriage
Which would be totally mm
Absorbed in
Stainless steel and hops
Send mop plzen
You know I that part I did
Didn't yet have a fix on
So you decide to take a second mortgage what did you need the money to do cuz this was still going to fill this out
And your home is filled the basement and then the Builder base floors above it and Jeff designed all of our own
Initial equipment so that saved a lot of money we had a
Dairy manufacturer in Denver fabricated for us the door to the
The basement was too small when we got
The first equipment in so we had to cut the door out
So we could get the equipment in
And wizard Vision like did you just sit down and say okay we're going to Brutus fear of the basement
And make some money and then get bigger and bigger and bigger or was it just like yeah let's
Peruvian are basement to see what happens this is fundamental to our story before Jeff
F&I ever made a barrel of beer we went on a hike
Lake in Rocky Mountain National Park can we said we were going to be for thing
We were going to produce world-class belgian-style beers
We were going to be environmental stewards
We were going to promote beer culture
And we were going to have fun
And you'll notice there was nothing in there about co-workers and there was nothing in there about customers
Because at that point
We didn't have co-workers or customers
So it honestly didn't occur to me
Think about including them
So we get another
Pass through that cycle
Significant pieces
Mitchell hair
Explain
Both you and Jeff still had a job
Jeff did not I had a dragon
You and your day job
And
He was sort of like
Dealing with the beer brewing all day and then you would come home and
Start to
Deal with it at night
Bottle beer
I would work 4 days a week I had good insurance and
We had one kid
Trying to have a second kid and so I had good insurance and we needed the cash flow and so I would work 4 days a week
And on the fifth day
I would call all of our cuss
Stories in the morning
And say okay we have this beer in this beer in this beer what would you like
And it done in the afternoon
I would deliver all the beer
Who are your customers Hatton with a people who already kind of knew just reputation
They were both
Bars and restaurants
Sand in Colorado beer Wine and Spirits are sold in independent Liquors
Which stores which was key for us
That's because you could build a relation
And what would you do would you go door-to-door to the
These Bars and
With samples of the beer and say hey
Me and Jeff are making the spear and I'm can I
Pour you some
At the time that we started there was a brew pub in Fort Collins
And there was a brewery that made draft beer
And so we decided to focus
Unpackaged
It was a natural
Because there was really
Nothing
In the marketplace
In our part of the world
Like that
So it was not
Really hard
Tell I would
Call in the morning deliver beer in the afternoon go pick up my kid from school and he would poor kid new the
Down by the liquor store
For a while
I do not have any idea how to make beer
How are you were you like
Pouring beer
Two funnels in the bottles and capping the bottles one by one
Well we were camping them one by one I mean it was a very bootstrap situation we
Jeff actually designed
He built kind of
Frame to put for bottles
With a
Food grade
Rubber tubing with a parasol
So it would push the beer into the bottles and it and so
At night I would also bottle and label beers
Label each one and then you know pan cap
How similar is Fat Tire
Today to what Jeff
What's brewing in 1991
Which generally very similar one of the things that I always wrote want to remind people though is that
Beerus
Food and agricultural
Product
And so
You have
Changes in the characteristic of a hop or The Malt bill because
You know it was a wet year it was a dry year so it really is an art form
That takes both the ability to
I have a gut instinct and a scientific mind
In the first year
Presumably
There's a limit to how much beer you can make and sell right
Well we were so small
That there was a limit
How much we could make
But we could have sold a lot more I mean
In Telluride Telluride Liquors had a sign
In the store that said if you're going to
Fort Collins will pay for your gas
If you stop at New Belgium
And pick up 10
In cases how did they find out was it just Word of Mouth
Just you know you go to some festivals
What's you serve beer
Ativan
Send
So
In that in that first year 2
Did you ever have any anxiety over whether the
The thing wasn't going to work on it sounds like
Love the beer like
He was getting a lot of attention and
You know people are driving for miles around
Come and get it but
You know it's still tricky to run a business
That's right did you have any concern that
Maybe this thing might not work out
No my anxiety was more
If I had anxiety it was more keeping up with all the
Because there was just a lot
Do you know you start hiring
PeopleLink
In the beginning there walking
Through your living room later on WeMo
Move to a second location
I did get pregnant
With our second
Samsung
And the 1992 I think right 92
So
It's things like
We went to the Great American Beer Fest
In those days you served your own beer so
I served
Beer
On Thursday Friday and
And Saturday
I had Nick on Wednesday
And we moved into our second
Brewery on the following Monday
Wow
So
Amazing
Hi thank you
Look back and think those people must
Have been like oh my God don't let her give me any beer because she's
Going to explode here so yeah and
End
All of this was financed by
The second mortgage the money you guys
Well once we weren't sure we were going to make payroll so I called my parents and asked if we could borrow five
$5,000 and they loaned US money
We
Took out some credit card
And those days they sent you things it said you've been pre-approved for a line of credit especially for engineer
Let's go for social worker
Some credit cards American Express at here
We did not ask him to make that little joke but
This live event is
Sponsored by a certain credit card companies take a quick break
I hear a bit from them
And when we come back
Have you Belgium
Expanded out
Sims basement
To become
Craft beer Powerhouse
How Kim Jordan eventually sold
Tire Company to her employees
They were this guy Roz and listening to how I built this
ER
Support for this podcast comes from America
Can express
Tracey schekman leads at
Team marketers who
Create events and
Experiences
Introduce entrepreneurs to American Express
What are team was asked to build a booth at a
Busy Tech trade show
They decided to go analog
Typical trade show
So we said how come you take it offline how come we let people talk to each other
And have some fun
And we built off the buzz of the escape room trends
Where people are locked in a room and it was solve a series of clues in order to
We called it escape the office
The reason we created
Experiences that we do is because relationships are a part of everything that we do
We aim to build
Long-term enduring relationships
In a world has become increasingly short-term and transactional and impersonal
And we hope that every experience
Our customers have with us will reinforce that given take
We want to be there for our customers and make sure the traveling for business
Truly is a pleasure
To learn more about how American Express
Have your back in life
And business
Is it americanexpress.com
Do business
And before we get back to the show
Tell you about another podcast that I happen to host
It's called the TED Radio Hour
Every week we go on a
A journey through the
Biggest ideas
Emotions
And discoveries that fill our world with wondering
Check it out
Find it on
NPR one
Or wherever you get your pie
Welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Kim Jordan New Belgium from the basement
Into a new space and at that point
Kim finally quit her job as a social worker to focus on
Beer full-time and of course
They're doing all of this just as business partners
What is husband and wife
With two small children
What about like the dynamic of being parents
Raising children
And also running this business I mean
How did you navigate that
Was it a clock
I also really
You have kids I kind of can't believe you fell for that it was a lot of
At work I wanted to be a mom I volunteer I was a soccer coach I volunteered in my kids
School I worked
The good news is as a
Self-employed person you can flex your schedule
And then you I would go to Kinko's at night and work on
Yellow marketing thing
What would Jeff
And both you and Jeff were to the company I mean
Did you argue or was it pretty
This is not therapy right
I'm just checking to see if
You know I'm like live reliving my past
Sometimes we argued
And I would
Say like
That is really a bad idea you know we really need to
Try to
Have have these
Because there is a lot
You know
Personal quirks
Sure working styles
Financial
Pressure
Hiring more
People
Salat to do
Lot going on despite any attention I'm in the business
Was growing I mean you were
You guys are winning Awards year
Selling more beer
1995 you moved
A bigger current facility so
How by the way how are you
At this point financing the company all from
Revenue
A lot
From revenue but also Traditional Bank Finance
So you didn't take
Take any outside which is also a fundamental thing for us
You know I understand in some organizations
People really need
Disorder bringing outside advice
Investors
But for us I really wanted to kind of have our destiny
In our own control and a bank doesn't want
To run your business
They want you
As well
And pay them back hard to get a bank
Yeah
We failed a couple of times I early on I
Was putting
Together a plan
For the bank that we had been using personally
And they say well you know you also need to give us this so I would
Put that together and give that to them is
As well
And our Banker said you know the way that you sort of dribble this
Paperwork
Again
Makes me think that you know nothing about running a business and I'm not even going to take your loan to the
The committee
So
So how are you it's eventually you were able to convince Banks to give you loans
Based on the fact that you were growing right and you were your revenues
Who's growing
We did and we also built all of our own automation
Every single motherboard every solder every wire
Which was Jeff's
Strength
Back to that
Benchtop thing I don't know so much about
Really good at that
And
Because we had
How to cut
A couple of million dollars out of the total project
In order to
I feel comfortable
With the amount of money we were
We're borrowing you remember how much
That project
Well the building was about 10 million and then
The equipment was another 10 mil
What
Put this into context because
I guess around the mid-90s
The craft brewing
Phenomenon really just started to
Explode
Did it feel like there was a wave that you guys
We're riding
You know we were at the front of the wave and we were leaders in the industry I
Have been a part of the
Community of
What is a movement in a lot of ways a lot of my very close friend
Come from this industry
We go on vacation
Together and
We check in with one another
And that's unusual I think inbiz
And
We had what we felt like was a really solid
Management team we had a really great
Way of developing strategy
So you know 96 we were 5 years old
Well I guess and that was the year where
It became clear that Jeff
Probably
Wasn't the right person to
Continue as the brewmaster you guys went out
To the original Belgium to Old Belgium
Gavin Foundation
Brewmaster in
Vista Sky Peterborough card
Peter buchardt iPad
To the US
What how did that happen
We had sponsored some speakers at the crap
Brewers con
Inbox
To come talk to American craft Brewers About Belgium beers and Belgian styles
And we were having this dinner and Peter was sitting next to me and I thought life
I'm just going to see how this goes
So I said to him yeah you know
We're hiring
For a brewmaster and you know we talked about this and that and
Left it at that
And I came back to
Fort Collins
And
Was working at the brewery
And someone said this guy from Belgium is on the phone for you and I picked up the
The phone and it was Peter
He said my wife and I are in
Rhode Island
And we thought we would come
Drive to the brook in Fort Collins
You know it's a big
Country
So they drove all the way to Fort Collins
And was anybody really making
These kinds of beers
In a 1996 well we were the first
Brewery in the United
It stays to specialize
Listen belgian-style beers
The first three years that we took our beards
To the Great American Beer Festival
They didn't even judge RB
Because they had no category
Race for Belgian
Old Style Beer
Somebody took them home and had a great time and
But like we got we got these
The gabf gives you judges taste
Eating nuts and we got these notes back that we're like yeah we
Waiting
Chase them
We don't have categories
So once once Peter becomes
Your brewmaster
I'm sure the Tracy group but like what just in general was he
Bringing Emily
Coriander and orange peel and lemon peels and
What we were already doing that with
With some of our core beers but
One of the things that I can now see in retrospect
That just by naming ourselves
New Belgium Brewing Company
We gave ourselves
License
To do so many
Things because
You know we could use fruit
And coriander and crazy East Raines and
And things that
We're very new
Go to the America
The growing
2000-2001
Jeff
Leaves the company
You know I'm usually doing so well it was
A dream of his
Do you know why he left
I think he
Wanted to do other things
And
That sort of day today
Process was less interesting to him
Then that
Kind of
Early designing of
Should bury the lead but eventually your marriage and
And you still are very civil relationship you've got children that you raised together and
I guess you just
Even saw him recently
Was that period of time after he left
Was it easier for you was a
Challenging mean
Well
To go back to
Peter buchardt
For a moment
One of the things I've heard
Peter buchardt
Say is that I have never seen
One person grow so much
As you grew
In that time
As you grow
Meaning me
I just you know when all the sudden it's all yours
If there's no ambiguity Are You The Boss are you not the boss who's the Boss
And I don't think that leaders should discount that you know you're like all we're all equal and it doesn't really matter who
The boss has no in fact it does matter who the boss is
And there were a lot of things open book management
Employee ownership
We had wind power in a we were doing a lot of relief
Fun stuff both in beer and in business practice
And
I have been
Really transparent and honest and vulnerable
My co-workers were
Will tell you that I'm a sap and I cry easily I have stood up in front of
Have the men talk about getting a divorce
If you step in front of your divorce I've stood up in front of them
Ben said I'm looking at
How we're going to have this sort of succession planning and turn of the founders liquid
Quiddity wheel Landing
And here's what I see is the pros and cons and I have tried to really
Make
Nearly nothing off-limits and I've also I think been really human about it
And I think there are certainly people who might sort of poo poo
Do that within our organization
But I think there are a lot more pee
People who understand that I have tried to be really real
And human then
Care
We had done
We had Jim Cook
On the show
But you're not have to go in
And he said that a certain point as they became bigger
Beer snobs
Did not want to drink
Get anymore
You're not as big as Sam Adams but you're big and very big
Craft Brewery
Do you also have that
Issue where
You got
Yeah Fat Tire
You know they're too big
New Belgium is too big
Like I'm going to my local totally sure we do
I mean there is
We will put our wood age
In shower beers up against anyone
Yeah we're a bigger Brewery
But we. We do a lot of
You know from the silly to the sublime
We do a lot of really
Fun interesting things
And I don't want to be
Count it out
Where that's at
What what's your annual revenue now
E-40
We don't generally talk about that publicly but
When you get a job I'll be happy to talk to you about it
Burlington
200 to 250
I like to say quarter
Quarter billion
Do you remember ever
Ever Getting to a point where you just thought
Started this in
Basement and we're doing 10 million a year now
20 million a year like
Do you ever remember thinking
Thinking that are you just constantly working and just
No I to I totally have pinch me moments even like today
You know when I walk
Where it really hits me is when I walk out of the brewery and I watch all these
People
You know sitting in our Beer Garden
Playing Rollie Pollie or or just sitting on the front patio or playing with their kids on the lawn
I have this feeling like wow
Look at this
Sting look at this
Touching people's lives
Through something as great as beer
I'm still in awe
Pretty early on you guys
Decided that you would
Give
Ownership
Some ownership equity in the company to your employees
When was there serve
Was there a specific idea behind that did you think that's how we're going to attract good
People
Or
Or was there another reason why you decide to do that
The early days of New Belgium
It took all of us to work really hard and I really felt
This deep
Sense of wanting to acknowledge
That my co-workers were you know those were 14 16 hour days you can
Bottle a half a batch of beer
And they will pick that up tomorrow it's a live food product and you have to finish
If the machine breaks down
6 times or 20 times in between the beginning of the end you stay and you finish it
And it was important to me we had talked to people who were experts who said well you know it
What's really customary to give management ownership
But you really don't want to give him a forklift driver that's what your accounts were telling you or advisors
And I said no I am really want to give the forklift driver owner
Ownership because to me we were building this community we were all in this together
So we started off with a Phantom stock plan every 6 months we would
Allocate shares Pro rata to our co-workers and we would make them stand up in front of
All of the current owners seems bizarre now but and
And like speak to us about why they wanted to be an odor then convinced and we'd ask some question.
Chestnut just f---ing me but all of the owners so how long are you going to be here and
What kind of skill are you going to work on in the next six months and those kinds of things
And then
Eventually you decided to
Sell your entire stake to your employer you do not own any of New Belgium
Today right
Except as
An ESOP
Account holder within the ESOP Trust
Just as my other coworkers are I own
That portion
But other than that no
So a hundred
Percent of the company
Basically became an employee-owned company
What
Wishing
I wanted to see how do we
Test
This
Model
Where
People in America get
Own something where they build value
They're all in it together to
Do this thing
And it's this engine and you add love
And you had beer
Beer is great
And it's this engine that builds this palpable I mean I've had thousands of people say
I came to New Belgium for a tour and you can just tell
But these people are into it they they like
This thing
We spend a lot of time at this thing called work and it should feel
You good
It's I think it does that saying you are one of the few women leaders in the beer industry
What was it
Was it ever difficult that you ever faced
I mean you must have spent so many years going to conferences and trade
Meetings and you're one of the few
Few women
So I was and we had to trade associations for smaller Brewers
In the United
Midstates
And I was the only person that was on both
Bored
Any only one woman so like one woman on
To board so that's
30 men
One woman
Keyboards
Most craft Brewers are really
More enlightened
On the spectrum of
That kind of
Some of the things we read these days
Your kind of jaw-dropping
Honestly
But I do think
That gender bias
Is subtle in Purvis
And I think people who I love dearly
Sometimes
Just don't really even realize you no friends of mine in the industry
Occasionally I will think like
Wow
Did you just
Ask Dad or
Or
Mansplain right over the top of me your
And
I'm pretty opinionated and strong so I can hold my own
But
You kind of have to be opinionated and strong and hold your own
How much of
What has happened to you in this
Success
Of
Your company and your own success
Do you think it's because of your skill and intelligence and how much
Because of just
Lock
Yes
You know I think it is a combination of
Of those things
And you know there's that sort of old saw about luck is
How hard you work and timing
You know we worked really hard
We didn't say oh you know let's all take a week off and
If if there I like to win
If there is a competitive advantage to be had
We're likely to push to try to Prevail in that way
So it was all those things
That was simple stuff it was hard work
It was timing
That tire was a great name for a beer
So it's all that stuff
Put together
Tim Jordan
Founder
Of New Belgium
Thank you so much
Jordan step down as CEO
New Belgium back in 2015 but she still serves as a
Executive chair
408 in addition to that employee ownership plan
New Belgium has
Pretty cool perks for twerk
It's your one year anniversary you get a brand-new
Cruiser-style bike and some of the models have built-in bottle openers
And after 5 years of the company
You get an all-expense-paid trip
Belgium
We're of course you can make
A pilgrimage to be very bar in Bruges
We're jeff leathersich got the idea to make his own belgian-style beer
Hey thanks so much for listening to this live episode of How I built this
Recorded at
Boulder Theater
Boulder Colorado
It was produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by run teen Arab Louis
I liked even folder included Ali Prescott
Albanian
A recording engineer with
Accuser
Thanks also to Rachel Falkner Vendetta could see Benjamin Crump leave a grant
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Stacy Howard
Gyros even listening to how I built this
NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing
Form used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag and drop email build
And customer support
7 days
Campaign monitor