Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Hate really quick before we start the show
You may have heard of this but it's not
I want to tell you
Amazing
Exciting event that we're planning is our first ever
How I built this
Summit
All the Gathering
Innovators
An entrepreneur is sponsored by America
Express Sandra hosting it this
October 16th
San Francisco
Throughout the day I'll be doing live interviews Within
Credible entrepreneurs
Airbnb's Joe gebbia
Lisa price of Carol's Daughter Jenn Hyman of Rent the Runway John Zimmer of lift and
Katrina Lake
Stitch fix
We're also going to have workshops with
Experts and guides their to
To provide you with lots of
Vice
Plus you're going to eat hundreds of
People just like
You Builders who are taking their ideas
Next level
If you want to find out
How to get your tickets
Go to npr.org
/ 7
And this episode
We originally read it back
The fall of Troy
Hope you enjoy it
We went to a contract Manufacturing
Latrice Rafael on Assad
And told him I'll dream gave in the pitch
And said we need you to do like a test run for us
He's absolutely no reason
To do that
Because
99% of everyone that sits opposite me telling me this story does not
Succeed but for some crazy reason
I think you've got something interesting and I want to be in for the ride
Ramen PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories behind the movement
Lego
Glenn from doing facials for women that have
Beauty parlor in building one of the leading skin care companies in the world
Dermalogica
To the story about Jane wurwand
Really begins
About a month before she turned
Because that month
Her father passed
Jane
Barely remember
What she does remember
All of a sudden
Her mom had to
Get a job
There were four girls in the family
Two feed in
She now had to do it all on her own
This was Scotland in the 19
50s
James Bond
Happens to have a skill she was a qualified nurse
So even though she had
Worked for many many years
She was able to fly
Find a job
And also
Pass along an important lesson
The five wits
Change my life
With my mom sayings
Listen myself learn how to do
Learn how to do something
She was absolutely adamant that we each of us had to get a skill-set training
Set no matter what happen if we were somewhere anywhere in the world
We would have a skill set in our hands
The we could go to a
Immediately and earn money and keep food on the table
So when she was old enough
Jane wurwand decided on her skill
We become what we
Was called at the time
A beautician
And right after she got her qualification
At age 19
Cheap started looking for work I decided
Cuantas it's unsafe
Flipping out
It was freezing cold it was the winter of 1970
Gaston Wrecker
I'm reading the Sunday paper and I want to see Waze
The hottest place on Earth
Because I have to feel better about this
Freezing cold
Platinum living
So I look at the weather in the Sunday paper that said Johannesburg South Africa
Oh my God I wish I wasn't
Pics of Africa
How do I turn the page
She's like the universe sending me a sign
Does a quarter page adverts
Smoke from the South African government
Saying
If you meet
Our
Prerequisite qualifications
We will pay in assisted passage for you to emigrate to South Africa
As long as you agree to live after 2 years my soul
Good grief I could be in Johannesburg in a month
And they had a list of 10 careers
That they wanted to recruit
Kanye old vocational training
The number ones but shows number 2 is
Rotisseries
Said was a hairstylist in the fools with a beauty therapist in there I am six weeks later I was on the flight to Johannesburg
Until when you got there where were you actually able to find a job
Yeah
Want to go to Cape Town I sat in this
Immigration hotel and I
Picked up Yellow Pages
My literally started calling salons in the Yellow Pages
To see if they would hire me
I'm by 5:30 that evening I had a job
Was it was it weird
Deliver at the time of what was it like to be there
It was
Completely
Different to anything I've ever
Experience
You know I remember my first day going to work I was taking a bath
But it kept coming I kept putting up my arm and they wouldn't stop and I
Picture of what was going on because of the front of the bus it said seapoint and that's where I was going to work
Woman at the bus stop finally said to meet you and then I'm going to stop you because on the bus at the front
It said me Blanc
Garnet means non-white
Launch is it we have to wait for a bus
White
Anyway you said that was so what am I supposed introductions I I've never seen it obviously I know it's you.
Yeah must have been a must been strange
When you were there in South Africa where you more less doing the same thing that you've been doing in London
Gascan can manicures pedicures everything that I've been doing
I'm trying to do I'm in love with the industry and I'm feeling so happy that I had this training
Because literally
As old as it sounds I know I could walk have a
Michael Kelsey there today I'll have a job by tomorrow because
There is a such a demand for the work we do and if you skill.
You got any love it you're going to get work
So how how long did you end up
Living there I lived in South Africa for years
And is that where you where you at your house
Yeah I met him in South Africa he's from Cape Town
And
He was already in process
For green card for the United
I'm all we would dating his green card came through
An account even
Explain how exciting it is it's like
Getting the golden ticket
In a Willy Wonka chocolate bar it's it's
Wuhan
To emigrate
Legally and do it properly and he did and it went off he went and I was so excited for her
And
At the same time I had a job with an American company
And they were based in Los Angeles and within a few months that she got offered a training trip to Los Angeles
Until I met him when I came on that business trip and
Together we just said
We've got to do something
This is such an amazing country in
Such an amazing opportunity
I went back he's in my notice
I tried an immigration attorney and LAN
4 months later
I was on a flight
To Los Angeles
Secret telling this is like
Yeah it was January 1983
I was 24 and never been so excited in my life
Londi's in Los Angeles with a suitcase in one hand
And my beauty school diploma rolled up in tucked inside
Honda
Had no idea that there was an unemployment rate
10.4 pen in California
Point is it good not to know these things right I'm so my boyfriend to be looking for
Schedule for 6 months
Couldn't find any
Living in a one-bedroom apartment in Marina del Rey ready to take anything
And I'm a Londoner sdorica
I'm going to get Joven Hispano
So I'm going to stop cooling my trusty Yellow Pages
And the first thing that struck me was so hardly any advertisements
Skin care
They were mostly just like
Paris
Anyways then I quickly realized the ones I could find it was literally a handful
Roland Beverly Hills
I'm a very sort of
Elitist
Expensive
Sword of offering
So I went and interviewed at water-cooled go to job interview went to in
I want to go there
The people at the front desk will America
And yet
The people I was seeing in the white uniforms who were offering skin care treatments while we're paying
So when I have my interview
There's Johnny
Questions I do question why I just noticed all the people are American on the front desk and all the people in the treatment room
European
And the woman who owns
Who's French
Said to me was
It's really simple The Americans
Have horrible training they don't know how to get a
Skin treatment
And the Europeans call sound
So high in carbohydrates
I want away from the interviews and can't repeating what she just said to me in my head on my phone
I think we've just spotted the greatest opportunity in this industry
Straight and that is
Train America
How to do a task entry
Treatments
Ines
Combining with that retailing and 7
I'm surprised it's like skincare wasn't a big thing
Is in the us at the time what what was the normal skin care
Very limited because it was old
Big head big shoulders
Pods Dallas it was all makeup
I mean you can pick up magazines then VOC all this designer fashion magazine
Always articles on makeup
It was nothing
The dermatologist
How old saying oh you can use anything you need soap for multi
Remind you
But not only
Did the correct putter
What's what how can you go to result in this
Mourned
When you receive a treatment in a salon it's about human Connection in human time
Spiga happening in every salon
Then just the service receiving soap
I was absolutely convinced
There was a waiting audience
For the next
Iran
Instinct
So at that point
Like what are you do
I went back start with Raymond my partner
And he was her husband married and we was do we would just dating living together
So he was having the same experience because I'll be enough
The only job he'd managed to
Secure was
Selling skincare quiz
4 Japanese
Commission only
And we both come from the industry by spinning
So he can sell one piece of this Japanese
Equipment which was amazing
Equipment to do what
To do skincare to do steaming a foliation and it was brand new cutting-edge and he wasn't selling a p
Door-to-door to Salon de salon
Yeah
Until they were saying we are even understand what it is you selling
So we were having this
Epiphany to put it together because he was at how come they don't understand what I'm sending when this is
Absolutely sounded in Europe and the rest of the world and we sat down
And said
The opportunity is
Cute
We can teach
How to do correct skin care treatments
End
We can sell this equipment to the people that were teaching
Right then and there you decide to start building a plan to
Create a business
Yeah we actually cooked at up together on a drive back from San Diego to cos to nakul 2 hours
Nanette driveway completely to through a business
Rego Park can we wrote to Allen the kitchen table
On5
Pages of yellow legal pad
And the plant and the plan was fine was
To train the
Professional
Skin Therapy
Then cold
An esthetician
Are we going to take everyone who has lice
We were going to Bridget to the two-year training that we felt would bring them up to 11
Efficiency where they could be
Successful
The goal was really simple we're going to make
Skin therapist
More success
Unable to run their own business
And be financially independent
Spaghetti was that you guys would open up a school and yeah
Ravens going to still sell equipment he was going to stay on the road I was going to teach
I was going to use the equipment he was selling in the closet I was teaching
Sell the equipment off to the claw
Are we cooled at the international dermal Institute
Had you even have
Cash to start at the open up at
It was a helluva difficult together leaves
Cuz remember we were immigrants with no credit right
With no Bank references with nothing
So the only space we could find was an empty space that been empty for years
Next to the social
Security office
The Marina del Rey
And they found it very difficult to lease
This is like long lines of people waiting for the checks every day exactly
Sitting you know people waiting to assist countries
So we rented it
And then we got the equipment from the Japanese money
TripAdvisor
Then We're Off to the Races and now the challenge walls
Who will be going to train because we didn't know any better
Siglap
People have to know
Like who you are
Well so we knew that I'll target market would licensed esthetician so in other words they had to order to be like
Licensed
To work in the industry
So I called the State Board of Cosmetology in Sacramento Calif
On a cool demand I said do you have a list
Of everyone license
In the state of
California
Epiphone skin care
It was very short list was at 2300 names and they said
Yes we do
Am I said
Is that list
Available is it public record
And they said yes
Unless it can you sell me the list
And they said yes we can salute the last
$25
I would you like us
To print on Avery labels
Please
Something did
Wow and so we caught in the mail like the label of every person
Yes
So that was it and we sat in the library we go to phone book
Colors for the phone book
Are we plotted the zip codes within a 50-mile radius of Marina del Rey
Are we peeled off all the labels that fit the zip codes and we sent her a postcard
Saying this is who I am this is Mike Wallace
Location
I'm teaching a free one-day class
We mailed out
So we were hoping we can
My cat doesn't respond
We had 70 responses
Well within 24 hours
Free one-day class
To bring people in to get them
So people would know what you're
So we took 70 people rented Chaz took 70 people
Turn off to a couple of weeks to doing the free call to recharge $10
So now we had $700
In that one day and you were like
Teaching what
Cleansing double cleansing steaming
Exfoliation massage
And then I'm turning the moisturizer with very simple
I'm so by December of 1983
I was offering 8 differ
Coffee's you were teaching all of us everything
Yeah to every class did all the laundry to the laundromat night to a one-bedroom apartment
Fight in the garage laundromat
And I never slept
Never slapped works
Animo 16 hours a day
7 days a week
Fiji is
Fiat didn't take a salary xiamen
I'm rich by teaching classes
Gonna know we were actually earning enough
To pay the rent for the school
Uncover $300 a month for May
I was taking $300 a month half the business
To just sit with my underwear and pantyhose
Rey kept his job as a sales
And he was making enough money to pay our rent on our apartment
And a big night out was a burger on
Friday night that was
Xiaomi we
Saved everything
I'm for 3 years it was
Just asked a guy who emigrated he was a friend of ours
Who joined us and slept on the floor in a futon
And he was out pushing the cloth easy without services
Sales rep go to salons and say hey there
Free one first and then we'll
That's what they did
And where they fall classes
Yeah I'd full coffees with weightless
Yeah what people were flying from San Francisco they were flying for
Phoenix I'm coming from Nevada
They were meeting each other they were rooming together they were
They were forming friendships
The concert finish at 5
And we don't
You know Pete's Room box wine by 7:30
Burgers and pizza
Do you like kale salads in like lemon water
That we would know
Eating in a Twix and
Kit Kat
So short that time like
You know it
The first years of attending did you see yourself as an entrepreneur did you
Divisions maintenance
Huge thing or was it just something that you love doing that you were
It wasn't
Swell Festival
I didn't use the word entrepreneur sure I didn't knew that
Maybe I did
The hot sexy would like it is now
I just saw I'm going to leave the tribe we're going to change this industry
I'm so for 3 years the international Donuts she was already pissed
Very quickly I realized and Raymond Li both together said
What happened today using when they go back to the
I want I would all scan this they would say
They will European price
French German and
Italian
Why you don't use an American Pro
Invasive
Which one
And I realized it would know American made
Products in the salon industry. What time is it in the department store in in the drugstore there's nothing
It was like
A light bulb went off for both Raymond am I
Myself we both said
Okay
The Big O Fortuna
Is products
Unwasted to me
If you had to write down
The kind of product
Do you want to use
Do you believe you could write down the briefs for line unless absolutely
You should write down the breeze
Unless said about making a profit
When we come back in the moment
Will hear how Jane and Raymond invented that new line of skin products
And how they almost
Lost it before it even got off the ground
I got rise
And you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support also comes from Choy salad
An original podcast
Charles Schwab
On the latest episode of poison
You'll hear a classic psychology experiments retool
William is an opera fan who enjoys visiting art museums on vacation
And is an average chess player
Is it more likely that William is a professional violinist in a major Symphony Orchestra or a farmer
Listen to find out Edge schwab.com
Or wherever you listen
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence and run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layouts
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
It's how I built this from NPR
And Gyros
And Jane and Ray have decided to create a whole new line
Skin care
They wanted to be
Different
Anything else
Cinemark at I wanted cleanses
It would completely went soft
With water
I wanted to develop
An exfoliant that would be really really
Efficient and not cause irritation to the
I have an allergy to lanolin so I didn't want any lanolin in
The product I want to know mineral oil
No fragrance
No drawing out
DeWalt official
Color
Re-named the line.
We had the international dermal
Attitude so it's kind of fitting with that
And we wanted to know which line with a bridge between a pharmaceutical
Cool product
I'm asking
It Cosmetics
Cat sounds like
Amazing a lab should have
Yeah we start food with no drawers
Honey bottles and tubes
And we didn't have sort of pink drawers with gold
Thompson
Pink boxes we had grey and white package
A packaging looked Pharmaceutical
How many times people criticized in the early days of it was on
And we felt it was utilitarian and that was the image we wanted that was who we were
You been working with
Give the price for
Permission Cricket when you were still really young you were
Early twenties and late twenties
How did you know how to make
I've no idea
So
Icosapent took him is doing you and he said
Look at you looking for, so I can make the product
You want to use a lot of Botanicals and plumtex drive
Speak to the raw material for
Flies for the plant X
And ask them
Who in Los Angeles
Formulating product if anyone
Using a lot of plants
Cuz you need to work with someone that knows he's material
And that was what we did we
Contacted the raw material supplier in New Jersey often do you have any come smell like that using you material
And they gave us a list
And we started calling release
Honda out of the 70 names we had
5 would take a call
And of the five there was one that
Number one was willing to work with us the number to we felt
Could do it and this
Book houses in LA
Yeah he was in LA he's since passed away but he was in Los Angeles and
We couldn't pay him that was this
So we figured out Raymond figured out this amazing kind of
Way of paying him based on
The first two years
Manufactured products what percentage of
The product that we manufacture not a percentage of sales because
We wanted to make sure he was tied into the
The fact that we would actually able to ever make this
Not even going to get paid
He agreed
And and what did you decide to make what
Was a one product or two products 427 product
Because we needed to go in with a.
If we went in with one or two products
We couldn't
Capture
Skin therapist
Attention and say you need to use this exclusivity in your room and you need to sell this
Plies it would have been enough
Tula creams
3 cleanses to moisturizers
Three boosters
Two moths
Annoying makeup remover
And then we had
819 products that work
Professional only peels
Unprofessional mosques and things that would only be used in the treatment room
He was making
Office Pride
Yeah he was like Rumpelstiltskin is formulating them all you were going and testing them out a little bit or not
I briefed him
He came back 2 days later with a little cardboard box is sample size
Capacity of May
Any copyright I mean that's going to save on him both elephant
But they were both great
I mean an end
In 9 months
We had developed 27 formulas
And we named them in one afternoon
How are you like even funding that
You think about that today
Hundreds of thousands of dollars
Test it and just to get it into the tubes
We were buying tubes that nobody wanted we were buying 500 at a time that they were selling to us Vino
Feeling them yourselves
No but we went to a contract manufacturing Los angeles-- the Trees of the fellow nosodes
And told him I'll dream gave in the pitch
And said we need you to do like a test run for us
We can pay you like
$500
And his minimum monthly thousand
Without him we really wouldn't have to come because he looked to us
After we've been sort of like pitching
Breezily for an hour
He's absolutely no reason
To do that
Because
Sign of everyone that sits opposite me telling me this story does not say
But for some crazy reason
I think you've got something interesting and I want to be in for the ride
By the way had you how are you able to test them
The product I tested every
Everything approved every
And yourself
You are like your own
I was my own guinea pig and then
I took it to class
I like week the students like to ask them what they sow
I love that
And they were using it in the closet
It's just out of curiosity what does that have
How to go through like
Any kind of regulatory
Commissioned writing
Either we were very young
Company in
A lot of the rules I suppose we weren't even aware of
But Tom at the time and still we weren't using any ingredient
We would eliminated a lot of the irritate
Radiance
I'm so in the 9-month
That we were testing the product
Cuz we would develop
That we hadn't
Had any incidents
Reaction
Benzo allergies
Cancel that was a thing you just like
You just launched
Yeah
We launched in January of 1980
And the crazy thing was
The chemist to develop these formulas who we were
Going to pay off over to you.
Came to us in December
585 4 month
Before we would do to you
And said that he did not believe
In the product he didn't believe we could be success
For any new venture
What why did he say
Because he just seen so many stars have
Fail this is the visitor chemist
That's enough
This is the guy that you like
This is Rumplestiltskin he just said I don't think is going to work
Yeah I don't think it's kind of what I'd like you to pay me out for the
The formulas
Now
And we didn't have any money to buy the forest
Is it going to cost you I mean that he wanted something extraordinary and we whistle them down it came down to
You know Soda $14,000 probably was a lot of money for you and I
10 million
Why did the chemist not thing
It would work
How to get to believe enough
Using the formula I think he's only for two immigrants
These crazy immigrants
How did I know about starting a company
What do they know about
Funding a
Company contact
Don't stink
Company were you freaking out
Yes we were freaking out but we had to figure this out scramble put it together so
We
Borrowed money for family we put together everything we could from the school we put it together when we paid
Aren't you so nervous like if this is the key I sing to you this is not going to work
And you're likely better come up with a 14000 but we're going to be kind of screwed because this guy
We were worried that formulas he was giving us
Literally be exchanged on the table of a Coco's Diner
Que pasa manila envelope of formulas however we passed the money out of
And
We were worried that the phone is he giving us for not formulas that we approve but
We actually had
The guy who was going to manufacture the product
Look at formulas for us and he's another
This isn't that right
This the real deal
Just thinking about that that moment where a guy who was
Total expert
Same to you
Who's never manufactured
Skin care products
That
This isn't a work and yet you have to come up with
$14,000
Pay him
Did you have any doubt
No
You didn't think you didn't Maybe
No she couldn't be right wasn't possible because if he was right
We are about to launch into the biggest disaster of all life that may have been
The case may have a week to each other one with self repeated enthusiasm
Yuan Ray
Like you were a world like this is going to work
Isn't it I need one of us is having a modicum of doubt
Guarantee the other woman having a good day so on the days when I might be saying
We not crazy right rabies
This is going to be great and on the days when he was saying
I think it's a house
Cause maybe it'll going to collapse I'd be saying
I just closed it was so fantastic
Everybody's
This is going to work
You know what if it doesn't work
It's not the greatest disaster in the world we have nothing to lose by
And it was
What if it works
And we did the classic immigrant thing way
Uganda population
1% of the population
And to buy one product
How do you spell ready
Enormous bigger than it could ever be in the UK
So let's go for
Okay so
You had no investors and and you basically figured
Will sell the product that will fund the
Manufacturer of more of the product exactly
And most of your customers were who
My student
The first account be opened with in baking
Pittsfield California
And she was one of your students who had a salon there or
Becky Sinclair
She won't talk with the check and I said Becky I haven't even shown you the Prada
Then she said Jane if you and Raymond are in
I'm into
Am I said you are first account in the world
And that was at my student came out they came up with so we want and we want to be positive that
This was a California made skin care products
We were going to Take On The World
And you are not selling this in storage right
Who's only
Do you have to have a skin tag
Next episode
And why was that why wouldn't you just like sell it in Walgreen
No no because
Because I'm asking therapist we knew that this was an educated so it had to be people understood the
Skin
I don't sell these for the people that brought us
To the party
I my mom another piece of advice she gave me was you leave the party with the person you went with
We went with committee to
The Skin Therapy
Headed Dermalogica do
That first year
Did $1000000
That's insane
It was
So
Insane
You must you must have at that point
Like I had all these buyers who wanted to
To buy you out
And those people want you to lend us money and you didn't take any of it
Sales word
Funding the business
Yeah it was so excited
It was great I mean
That first year we were planning everything back into the business unit. We hide ourselves. We wanted people walking
Dermalogica
And so we will putting everything back into building the base
But how are you like
Teaching classes
And
Hiring staff
And like it
Building
An organization
We were working all tails up Victoria Day
I didn't hire another teacher until 1980
G7
Salvage rights in the Constitution
Maltese
I'm still doing the Loon
And Raymond
And a couple of other people while handling the product
When the class is finished
At 5
We would do the UPS holders
I was packing the boxes ceiling the boxes writing the label they were five of us in the
Company we did
Everything
We finished it
10 at 9:11
Pocket knife
Everyone came back to my house all flat. Bugatti
And then we were back at work
7:30 the next morning
When did Yuan
Andrade Services back and say
She might actually get really rich
I'm doing this thing that we never
New way to get rich
Last year
Lowry
No
We knew we had a tiger by the
The tile.
And we
New
That we had to
To spread
Hotels International we need eggs in Old basket so that
Is there was a recession in one place it wasn't going to take a business
And the international terminal
The Chew is now the number one provider
Advanced education in the industry worldwide we train a hundred thousand skin therapist every single yeah
And last year
A wholesale turnover was a little north of 250 million dollars
So you guys were
You basically
We ran the company
Promise 30 years
Yeah and
Decided to sell it
Last year sold
Unilever why did you decide to do that
Yeah we from the come
As what I
So they say was you never beneficial.
Dictatorship
We've always had a great team
We still have
But the decisions ultimately came down
Dongzhimen to myself
Product approval Advertiser everything the brand ID
And you know we realized
Much that we hate to think about it the death rate is holding steady a hundred
Ascenso
Ultimately we were going to have to make a plan
Of what we wanted to do with the company we have to do.
Does the 17 and twin
And neither of them wanted to come into the business and we didn't want them to we told them
Even what kind of before they were born we decided we have five children and not coming into Dermalogica
It's our dream and we believe it
It's a burden
Two kind of shoulder your children with that
Responsibility
And so we
Decided will hire a CEO
Are we going through a couple of CEOs
In the eight years before we decided to sell it we just wasn't working
When we realized
The problem probably wasn't the CEOs of problem was fully off
Because
We are the founders you don't we have this live
Passionate about
The ownership
And it's very hard to run a company when the founders room place kind of want to
I've lost what
I'm so we decided we should at least explore the idea of an ox
We've never taken a phone call from anyone that was interested in buying never even taking a cool cuz we said we don't even have
It's a distraction
Until we we could have lined up
Who we thought would be
The right partners
And then we we set about
Deciding which ones we wanted
Cool.
And Unilever
With very aligned with us
On that
Sustainable living plan
The very long with us on the volume
I'm so we decided to go forward
And I have to
With one year in and it's been a fantastic
The Kia summer so that Raymond and I kept
Smok centage of the company was still involved
It and that chemists the one who like bailed a month before The Logical launched he ever come back to you guys
And apologize
No never
He never did know he was like Rumpelstiltskin that flew out the window and never came by
It means amazing like looking back at your story
Because your mom was a widow with
For girls
And the cheetah racing around it
A little worried when you left
England for South Africa and the
The US
A little
What did she make of your
Of your success
I know I know that she was really proud she felt validated in the direction that she pushed us
She passed away in 2001
But she's so awesome
Success
And the lost of months of my mom's life s*** out
What time is
I'm not sure she remembered
Anything about gemologica
She remembered me and I sat on her bed when she was in hospice
Petaling
I was giving her money
I was right back to filing her nails and
Painting lemon
She was watching me
And she
I looked across that the woman who was in the chair next to her
And she said to her with a huge liquor price she said to
My daughter is a qualified manicurist you know
And am I smiled it's always doing it because I felt the
If she doesn't remember anything about
Accessories for cheese
Really proud
But I got that training and I'm going to be okay
Okay
Anawalt
Timberland founder
Dermalogica
Now spends most of her time on helping women around the world become entrepreneurs through her foundation
And of course we couldn't let Jane go without asking for her number one skincare tip
Soap Puritas
Single best thing you can do for your skin is keep it out of the Sun
So you wear sunblock you where you hunt I stop lying out in the sun
Get busy start your business
Got change the world
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first I quit thanks to one of our sponsors
Microsoft
A digital workspace for teams
Create collaborate and communicate authentic
Bring together your chats meetings
Files and apps
All-in-one
One place
Office.com
Penes
To learn more
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
And today we're going to update the story we ran about
A year ago this one comes from Winfield Pennsylvania my name is Nicholas Gilson
And I am one of the original founders of Gilson snowboards
Nick and his business partners fell into the snowboard business they were Middle School teachers in Nashville in
Data science project with a challenge their students to build a
Better snowboard I brought in the original prototype for an idea I had when I was my student age when I was
Middle School
Was basically to design a board which instead of being flat at the bottom
And they hope that it would make for a faster ride
And even though their first design totally failed
Eventually came up with one they love
With this board you can actually ride close to flat
And engage is really surfy drifty
Maneuvers that allow you to get through the trees way easier with way more surfing motion with barely any money
Nick and his partner
Switzer teaching jobs
And set up a snowboard shop
Inside
Stable in Pennsylvania
Who's inactive stable it was an active do they were donkeys and horses next time machine
Mike says they were able to make their boards
Even better
And we then started to travel the country starting a company much the way our grandparents would have we need to tangibly
Didn't physically share something with people
And so we went out and immerse ourselves in the community travel 17000 miles from coast to coast
And I started getting these people on the boards
The last spoke to Nick
His team has traveled 17000 more miles
The slopes and
Parks across the country
Letting people sample Gilson snowboards for free
The company is now
4 years old
They sold thousands of boards and they recently expanded
Huskies
You can find out more about Gilson
Snowboards on
Our Facebook page and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org
We love hearing about the things your building and thanks so much for listening to our show this week
If you want to find out more or hear previous episodes of Good how I built this. Npr.org please also
Subscribe to our podcast at Pebble podcast or however you get your podcast you can also write us at
HIV tea at mpr.org you can tweet us to at how I built this my Twitter address
At Gyros
Our show is produced this week that runs abdel-fattah
19 are gluey composed the music thanks also to novigrad Michigan for Thomas Luan
Jeff Rogers AR intern is newer coetzee
Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
Running PR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign Monitor and email marketing plan
Farm use by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email template
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com