Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is
When is Good Day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim style
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
To prove that this really was not tok
You drank it in London you know I love the British press is so skeptical
And she said is it in a safe enough to drink outside sure so we both took a shot at 12
What cleaner and then I immediately text Adam finally got back to me as i k
I'm going to be okay right
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists at the stories behind the movements
How to friends in their mid-20s mixed up some household ingredients to make soap and
And then took on and eventually outmaneuvered some of the
Biggest companies
In the world
If you were looking to start a business
In the late 1990s
You probably didn't have to spend a lot of time convincing friends and family that it was a
Good time to go into Tech
This was the height of the dotcom bubble and
It seemed like the future was
Literally
By companies like Google and Yahoo
EBay and Amazon
So they can be kind of hard to imagine why 220 something
Who lived
In San Francisco in the 1990s
Wood survey this
Promising Landscaping say
You know what the world really needs right now
Soap
Soap that will do a good job cleaning your kitchen counter or your toilet
But that
Won't destroy the planet in the process
And that is exactly what Adam Lowry and Eric Ryan set out to sell in mm
Barry year the.com bubble
And the company they founded method with its sleep bottles
Products smelling like cucumber or bamboo
Actually went on to compete with some of the biggest soap companies in the world but before they went into
Adam and Eric were actually childhood friends they met when they were kids maybe 12 or 13 years old
Because they were both super into sailing
And both of their families worked in the Auto industry which
Pretty much what everyone did where they grew up
Grosse Pointe Michigan
Almost everyone that I can remember
Their families were involved in a
I think arakur
Family
Great-grandfather dropped out of pharmacy school and move to Detroit to work for Henry for $5 a day
And then ultimately Henry Ford Ford stock that
Was bought when Henry was still running the company by my great-grandfather
Didn't I
Great-grandfather and grandfather together started machine and stamping
Giant presses that come down so they would make a lot of parts that went on
The automobiles
And so I kind of grew up
In the shadows of my great-grandfather and grandfather babies entrepreneurs who created something from nothing
Adam Merrick
Collagist was an early 90s Adam went to the West Coast he studied chemical engineering at Stanford
What's the East Coast
Business at the University of Rhode Island
Both of them were actually recruited by the university sailing team they were serious Sailors and to be clear
In college Adam and Eric didn't really keep in touch
Just whenever they were back in Michigan
So after graduating Adam stayed in the Bay Area to work for the Carnegie Institute of science he was doing research
Church on climate change
And Eric got a job in advertising
Eventually made his way out to San Francisco as well
And shortly after that
They both just happened to run into each other on a flight
I think it was Thanksgiving if I'm not mistaken 1-year Maybe 97-98
I walk on the plane I see Eric and I didn't know that
He was living in
You'd only move there
A couple weeks ago
And so there was an open seat I ended up sitting next to him on the plane we
For 5 hours got all caught up
It turned out we were living on the exact same block
Just out of
Pure
Coincidence
And
I was living in a flat
With
For other
Guys from
Stanford
And Eric was living lion
Himself in a one-bedroom
When one of those guys rotated out we
Invited Erica move into the apartment
And then we were roommates when you could actually live in San Fran
Cisco
For a reasonably
Low amount of rent
I paid $600 a month
Oh my God this is 1997-98 amazing
So you move into this group house
Doing what you doing on your early twenties or whatever and
In the house
Just like a six guys in a
Emily Natsu
Super clean
It was exactly as clean as you would
Expected to be
I mean
Either of you at that time
In your mind
Or either of you thinking
Business or you just kind of
Grinding away doing your day-to-day job
I mean for me personally I
I knew since the third grade I want to be.
You're annoying neighborhood
Kitty was constantly selling buttons or anything else I could so I just I always knew I wanted to start a company and I love
I fell in love with advertising and branding
But
I knew
It's pretty uncommon as an entrepreneur your first company will be successful
So I kind of wanted to build
A little bit of a safety net of a career but I was
Constantly noodling on ideas
For me personally just coming up with the right one that would eventually take Elite Four
Adam
For me it is the journey talk
Bernard ship was less predestined
My parents are both on
First they started their business
1980s
What would serve
It's an automotive sales rep
Business
Representing Parts suppliers in the automotive industry but
When I was 6 7 years old moms making
Chili for the week for myself and my older brother and my older sister and I watched them build
The business and do it in a way that was much higher
Then the risk that Eric and I
You are so young We Were Young we didn't have family
Mortgages and any of that so well Eric kind of always knew going entrepreneurs
As soon as I can for me I am motivated by
Creating some sort of good change in the world
And I'm a big believer in that you don't need to figure out
What you need to do with your life
You just need to figure out what you want to do now
What were you noticing
In 1999 that
Eventually you will
Would lead to
What was going on around me
I was working on a project
4 Colgate so spending a lot of time in the grocery store
And I just started looking at the
The cleaning aisle and saw that it was such a big category
But a sea of sameness
Everything looked and smelled the same
The brands were pretty dated
So that was kind of Clue
Dig here
But I mean you're 25 not get you working on an ad campaign
Colgate so that
Accessory starter kit
Exposure to that end
Like
It could have been anything I mean it could have been chewing gum like you could have
What was it that
That made you think
Cleaning supplies
Will it really I think with any ideas
Do you start off with
Absolute place of insecurity
But as much as my mom she's like
I've never seen you
You make it better you sure you're the right person.
Start a cleaning products business
So I hid the
The products underneath my bed
Because I didn't is pretty dorky I didn't want anybody to know I was even thinking about this category
And admire both back in Michigan
And we were driving up North early morning to go
Skiing and been close friends I felt like Adam with somebody I could
Share an idea with
Is the winter 99
I need to know there was skiing in Michigan but keep going
It is technically it's okay
Yes
And I
Mention that hey I think there may be an opportunity
Innespace
And I remember Adam
Looks over me as he's driving
Mangos
You know the degree in chemical engineering
And then we just it was sort of one thing leading to another that
And I said well you know not only these
Product really ugly butt
Did you know they're super toxic
Might as well
Right
And that was kind of
Where one idea gets added to another and it kind
Are you the one
Play remember us
We
Got to go skiing
And we went up the first chairlift
And
We did a couple runs has been more excited to go work on this idea that we were to keep skating
Tips to paint the picture for like
Cleaning supplies products in 99 like if I'm going into Safeway and I
I'm going to get 409 I'm going to get
Brighton release
Strong sense there's kind of like
If your eyes weren't watering it means it wasn't cleaned
Toxic category
Wait that was a thing that
She brought that really opened my eyes insight
You mean like you actually blue when you clean and use
Poison to make your home healthier
And this is like the winter of 1999 were you still working at the Carnegie Institute
I stepped down from
Carnegie
I did
There is an important detail here
I quit my job in
September
And in October was the Olympic trials
Olympics sale
And and I had been
With USA
Is on the US Sailing
7 years
We did not win the Olympic
3rd and
And so
That
Period of time for a couple of months there I
I just finished the Olympic trials
I was doing a bunch of interviews
Product design firms
Looking for a job
Engineering firms yeah
In the Bay Area
So so right
Then and there that moment you both
It was almost a perfect storm for you a time cuz you were
I have
Transition phase Eric you were were still working
The Ad Agency
Which actually
Was giving you this incredible experience
Open your eyes
This to this
It's her world that you had
Expose to the right
Yeah it really understanding like
Understanding consumerism
This was really kind of driven by so you go back to 1999 Ikea was just arriving in America
Home and Garden television was just taking off
So it was a time where people were starting to think more about their
Holmes azra
Reflection of themselves
Instead of thought was well what if we designed these
Products of the world
Like pieces of decor
And hey if a
Spray cleaner was beautiful enough to lead on the counter versus
Is hidden underneath the
The sink out of sight out of mind
You might actually use it more
And I've loved the phrase like there's no such thing as low entry
Categories
Just low-interest Brad's
So I thought was
How do we take boring cleaning
And not make it boring
So what happened after that
Christmas tree
To Michigan
You come back to San Francisco and
You do what
So
Yeah I was in the middle of it
And I said hey you know I'm going to
Look for some job
But I'm going to start doing
Researching
Trying to figure out these
Categories
Do some of the digging that Eric had a full-time job
Is adverb
Didn't have a ton of time to do and I said I'll start to do this
I actually at one point had a desk in Eric's bedroom
Where I would work on
Some of this stuff while I was gone
Kind of continuing my job search
We're writing the business
Plan
Together I was doing a lot of that research
Goodnight we kind of put the pieces together
So you already decide what's
Make a go at this
What was Israelites
You're the hardest thing with
Starting
He Is We are really insecure about this idea
25 and we're going to take on only some of the largest multinationals but the world's first multitask
The form of Proctor
Can you deliver
1250 year heads
Start
And it really you know own distribution
What was that your vision in 1999 make this and see who buys it
That we have a reset from the beginning like
Go big or go home
But I didn't feel very secure getting there so one of the first things we did was we trade what we called the concept book
And so we brought to life the idea
Give it to the 20 smartest people we knew
And ask them shoot holes in them
Nice for what professors
Friends family got everything from people who actually found some former Clorox employee
These lawyers of people going to finance background advertising just like
Tell us why it's going to fail
And nobody could come back with a reason other than if it's so good why is nobody done this before
Yeah where they'd say
The reason it's going to fail is because
They're begging you
You're small
Which we didn't
That's not a reason
This is still the
Before the.
Come
Crash against the.com right on top of it and April
I remember it well but this is a time when
Most people your age
At that time we're moving to this area get involved in
Text company
Trebeache
So what are you doing everybody said that
Add friends who are raising $40 on
40 page business plans and bragging about $1000000 per page for a raise or do these lavish launch parties which seems so
Ridiculous now to spend funds on a lunch party
But yeah this was San Francisco to turn of the century and money was being
Thrown around and Tech
And should we horse showing up pitching
Soap and idea that was hot a hundred twenty years ago
When do you actually
Mix
Stuff together get it get it was a dish soap was it cleaner
What was the first thing that you
Yes right around that time so the mid-2000s
It was mostly me mixing those things
Well
You can make cleaning products out of
Very
Standard things that you can buy in the grocery
Like whatever
Of course water vinegar baking soda
These are relative
Simple chemicals that don't require
Professional Lab in order to mix them together
And that's why I came home one day and Adam was
Mixing things in beer pictures which
What what what do you remember mixing
Well I think there's different
Soaps and different
Detergents
Yeah you can make soap from
Basically a base
And an oil soap
Boil and the bass you bring those together to make a soap
For solvency UK
Like vinegar
Some of the acids that are present in things like orange juice
Very
Common everyday
Mild
Chemicals that
You formulating differ
Current ways
To achieve a certain cleaning
Function and you mention dish soap
Hard surface
Cleaners that kind of thing
Were you awake I'm trying to mention where you would look in your
Room or in the kitchen of this group house like
With action pack it like pouring in Imagine sort of
16 oz jars maybe if plastic
Glass containers of
Orange oil
Baking soda and then I would just experiment I would try different formulations and I would make experiments the way
Way that a scientist does so that you
You know you can have a control and in an experiment and you
Yeah I was just a little bit of process to getting to something that work really well to Eric while Adam was
Looking into
Category and looking at
Ingredients of Fort Worth
What are you doing
So our plan was to create our first four products which were the surface cleaners
Get them in the local stores
So Adam was working on basically doing everything in the bottle and I was doing everything kind of around the bottle
And this joke was dialing something
Until what I started doing was we we didn't have a lot of
Money to do custom tooling
And so I started looking for stock bottles cuz I think I really like
Cytus
Camping water bottle
From Norway that I found just a really simple kind of bullet design with these nice elegant shoulder as he had his
Are utilitarian but the same time would look on the second base sitting in someone's home
So we use that as the basis for the first bottle and how are you paying for the
Okay We've ran the business out of pocket for about 2 years
How much money did you have at the beginning
How much money is YouTube
We'd put in $45,000
All the money
YouTube you had yeah my grandfather passed away
With that money
And so will I
We put it right in the method
And you split it 50-50
At the beginning
Yep put it down on paper and you called a method
At the time yeah we had something at the name by then
We wanted a name that represented a technique
A new approach
Do you make things
And I remember both brushing her teeth at the same time
Sounds very weird
Yeah basically one
How about method I like that's it
How did you come up with
I don't know I just thought of it
Is bottles that you really like
Were you just
Binders at the Shelf
Summer
Now we we did every design was so important
Big chunk of that the Dallas we had went into tooling we just going to forward that Expo design but to link
Find the bottle know we basically took inspiration from this bottle I found in Europe
And then had a supplier kind of do the engineering of it yeah and then build the bottle molds which
Ate up most of the investment
We had the bottles and we were making product home
Look like funnels paper towels
You were filling the bottles yourself you're bringing them to your apartment with a funnel in just pouring it in and closing it up
Okay and we wanted
We wanted to feel very different than everything else out there but also to really show it was you no say
Safe to be around you think about when most people clean they would put on that you know that old
Team building exercise sweatshirt from 1998 in the rubber gloves cuz you don't want to stop touching your skin
Cypress labels were very different they actually showed people on the front of it and put it in any money so we would go
Go to Home Depot and buy sink and photograph Adam holding the stink probably return the thing to get her money back
If you fast forward to late February of 2001 by now
Call Eric and I have product prototypes and
We were taking these prototypes around walking into grocery stores unannounced
And cornering the store manager and try and get them to buy a product
And so we got a grocer
Restore
February
To say yeah 2001
Yeah it was actually February 28th
So we had bothered the store manager enough
He said fine guys
I'm going to give you some
But you have to get the product
This was in Burlingame
In the mid peninsula
Of
San Francisco
Store called
Mollie Stone's
Yeah it's essentially what we need to do is get a proof-of-concept so we decided the first step was to try to get into
All the independent
Grocery stores in the Bay Area
These are the places with that manager can make the buying decision
Cigar shop at 6 a.m.
This guy is always really grumpy
And I think it's actually they just agree to take your product
Because they know you're going to
Keep coming back
Until they say yes will you going to the store Burlingame you went to Malta
Apple X
And in the first time you went there the manager was like I'm not interested
I mean imagine doing this
6 in the morning
With a with a store manager they are not in
At first Mall store manager
Just don't take sales calls right so that was
That's not how you get a product
Groceries
But it was the only way
How so
They weren't used to
I seen that
And
So there was a lot of
To the store in Burlingame
You got out the car
A&a products glass
Of the stores
Close your the back door
And we waited till they were open
Stocking the shelves still like all the trucks are coming in during the delivery and she's busy
Yeah it was the best training cuz we don't know how to sell
And you have 30 seconds
The pitch
And so it really helped you
Learn how to sell the product
And every time until that day at multiple stores
Osher doesn't
I mean after a full day of going round pitching this
Using a lot of emotional energy would you calm feeling like dejected
That and nobody depending on the day
What am I doing
A million
Write an essay for me
Personally like
The cold call
Was a hard thing to learn how to do
And yeah sometimes you know you get a bunch of rejections it's a little bit demoralize
Rising but you know we got it going before we got so demoralized it would quit
Let me come back how a Longshot email to a famous industrial designer and a big bed
Dish soap landed method on the shelves of Target stay with us
Listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated license texture
It makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrency
To your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon jimenes mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are in
Insured and protect
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open up free account
At gemini.com bill
Gemini
The regulated place to buy
Sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to
Design and build their own website
Using customizable Leo
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
So it's 2
2001 + Adam and Eric
Get the first method cleaning products into a grocery store in the Bay Area
Infrequently
They realize that they couldn't just make all the stuff in the
Kitchen
Weather San Francisco group house
They start to think about building a
Supply chain
Make more of a product
Funny wild and out
They're showing up at different stores
Trying to convince customers to try out method soap
One person at a time
We didn't have Market hours what would you do weird offer demos
So we did that
Of course we didn't do a demo so that would be
Would be me
He set up a table and I was wearing a lab coat which is comical to look back years later
And it's kind of funny I look at these photos I was standing in the wine aisle
I think I just realized that people shopping for wine were way more interesting
Talk to thin people shopping for cleaning products
But
We were really big Believers at the packaging would have to be the primary Mercury vehicle
And you would see it on shelf
Because the design
Buy it because of younique fragrances
To get home
Find out it works
Turn the bottle over
And realize it's good for you and go to the planet
And that would suck to create a following
And if you talk to most Americans at that time
They would say green doesn't
The only way we're going to make us work as we had to get the mainstream into a green product
And we thought a lot of it as it
The Trojan Horse for good
Where to put a green credentials
Is on the back of the
The bottle and I was kind of high.
So
After you got into
Mollie Stone's
What was the next step how did you get to the next
Or same process talk to the manager in
The first step was that I believe there were 10 Molly stones at
That time there
I think more than that now
None of her other similar chains
Premium high-end more Gourmet Focus
Grocery stores that we went to in the Bay Area but we did it
We built these 30 stores we called it our paper route so every morning we take turns
Driving to each store
Counting how many sold
Replenishing at writing up an invoice
And was a way for us to really understand the grocery business
A Big Moment of Truth came through when
Yeah we did have a customer service number so my cell phone was on the back of every bottle
And I never getting this first call
From this person who just wanted
Call to say how much they loved our cucumber bathroom cleaner
There was a friend of mine
But these calls started coming and we realized like we really struck a bit of an emotional
Chord
And a category that traditionally is so low interest and so boring
And it's just
24/7 us
Working
All the time
On this
Yeah me the challenges you know of any startup a particularly in the space momentum is
And that's a raise Capital you need to show momentum
So yeah I always felt this race against
The clock to grow as fast as
Is it possible
Pretty soon into this thing
Saying enter in 2001
It becomes
Clear that
You got a raise
You got to get
Because ninety thousand bucks
Is only take you so far
Patachou
What's the next step how did you get
The family
That was a saga
I mean we're constantly running
The cash and so we were getting
Five grand 10 grand here from every friend family
Person that would give us money
And
Did that
For about
Almost 2 years
To run the business and all told it was maybe
Couple hundred thousand dollars that we got that way
Before we were able to raise our first
Professional money
The people who believe in you more than a necessarily believe in
Your idea
And
I also found it so motivating cuz is one thing like for admire
Did I lose our own money or fail
But when you're taking money from people you really care about our roommates
Grandma Mae
Curdling parents
You don't want to let them down
And I was encouraged entrepreneurs to take money from family because I think it's the best motivation to ensure that no matter how
Hard things get
You going to find a
Path forward
So you know funding this
Anyway you can
At what point are you able to
At what point do you decide
Hey we got to go to like
People big money people in and get an infusion
Investment
We decided that really early on
But it took a long time
So it was probably I mean even by mid-2000
We knew we were going to need to get capital
Run the business but
Took another year at least
Before we were able to get a professional in
Bastard
Design on the bottom how much did the first round was $1000000
Is one firm
One investor
And we were scheduled to sign the timesheet on what turned out to be September 11th in so
In the months that followed we were stalled because of
Course nobody was doing
Deals with the uncertainty in the world particularly in a
Premium-priced cleaning products
And finally closed in November
And you always have a closing dinner when you raise capital and we went around the room to pay the bill
Afterwards in between Adam and I none of our credit cards work
Musically we knew the person who owned the restaurant that we had them if we can pay him next week after we closed
And yeah so all we had inventory and Order
All that was on credit cards
On the face that
We would ultimately get the
Investment
That was a scary time
What was your
What did you think convince them
To give you the money
A big part of our pitch was
Sherwin-Williams proven locally and regionally
And the argument that we were going to go get Target next
And that we needed Capital to be able to close Target and starts a scale National
Did you even even say that we talked into Target before you had
No not at all because
Because we wanted to
To be able to get the capital but we started doing it
With karim rashid
Who is very famous industrial designer
And
We wanted to
Create a line of products
Working with
Karen that would make a real statement of marketplace
Just supposed to take care of her she dislike
A huge industrial designer like
He's made products
Explorer
A certain design Pepsi bottles in
Iconic furniture
Perfume bottles like
You guys are
Mid-twenties like how did you connect with this guy and why would he even answer your call
We were huge believer in the power of design
And great industrial design to put a list together of the top industrial designers Karen with a stop at last
We just work down the list until we finally
Got somebody to work with us
And I shot Carrom
An email video
Shady Nook Oldham
Okay
NSAID acuzar pitch
We want to work with you to redesign the dish soap and object that sits across
Every sink in the landscape of America
Will you work with us
And he wrote back within 20 minutes and said he has
Well I do remember Sandy category first met us for the briefing he
Play 50 Cent Josh
Handy who we work with at the time he's like a new try to get some of the payment up front
Yeah we were able to
Convince him to do it for a lower fee cuz I really believe in the project but also with equi
And
Gave you no got enough skin in the game with us
So he agreed to do it
Take me to do it which was absolutely amazing and they the
The time Target was working with bleach dark
We knew that interesting
And working with Cara
And so what we did was working with caramel
We are able to use kind of Karam as a carrot
To get a meeting with Target marketing
Who invited the buying team
We did a big dog and pony show with Karen how to spend
Premature last dollars
Kind of went all in on this
It don't really know this company would have ever
When I do exist if it weren't for the risk we took on our dish soap
And Adam
Miracles
To get the first prototype of the dish soap
It arrived moments before the presentation actual soap
Add soap in the bottle
And that what was unique about this product
Did Karen had designed is that it was upside down
So the distal came out of the body
It was on this inside that everybody know you always turn it over it's a weird experience
Shout out of the bottom
Beautiful sort of
Sculptural
This is an important detail I was not actually at the meeting because as Eric mentioned
To leave literally the very last moment
We're
Putting together
The product I was in the factory
Doing that
24/7
4 weeks in preparation
So I was like sleeping on the factory floor
Doing that whole
Thing and then I Fed Ex this thing first overnight
To Eric
For the pit
Were you nervous I mean
This is like a make-or-break meeting
Oh it was
I mean I was trying to work in my business school application
Just as backup
Because
Yammy
You knew that
If we could not get
A national retailer behind it
The economics ranking to make sense
Wikipedia guess people who know they own their own plants they had a hundred fifty years to figure out efficiency
And we were charging initially that $5 a bottle to keep bringing the
The price down to make it
More competitive so you were losing money
Everybody lyrics
Do we need a scale
And we needed a fast
What happened at that meeting
God is able to a test
Marketing stood up at the end and said this is right for a guess it's
Design forward on Trend and so Target gave us a 90 store test
To basically prove ourselves
Giselle
Dish soap
And
And service
And do you remember how many units a bot
Oh they bought
Initially about
A lot of a lot of
Yeah yeah
Target
Not really because we knew if we fail that test we were out of business it was Mega break there was I mean
Triumphant like yeah we got this test which was great but I mean I remember
That moment vividly because my heart sank because you know I had to then make sure that we could get twin
25000 units made with perfect quality in all of this
Includes things like
Long lead times for making
Bottles
In all this type of stuff that
It never should have been able to be done in 8 weeks I still to this day don't exactly know how we got it done but we
Yeah there's a thing that always ran through our business that when you hit a roadblock
Yeah you get out
Paperclip in the chewing gum in the rubber band and you figure out another way around
And you know making 25000 units
Was just another sort of MacGyver moment
Do you know if you're going to build a business
It's hard
And you've got to be incredibly resourceful and for us that was very real because it was born from all of
These times where we went the past you were supposed to go
And a door got slammed in our face and we had to figure out another way
Soap mid-2000
To you are in 90 Target
And you've got a hit
A certain
Target
For them to
Spend out
Further
How'd you do that how did you
Create awareness around the product but we didn't hit that Target as it turns out
First thing we did was there the set date
And so we had to make sure we got on shop as fast fossil
Fox we start driving store to store go in if it's not set up you go to the bathroom
You pull it out yourself you take whatever's on shelf
Off you get your product on shelf
Quickly
But
We started out first week looking the numbers were missing the number
Innovative
Problem
Which was
The dish soap that we did which was the first ever inverted dispenser so it comes out of the bottom
Consumers would go to smell it cuz the
The fragrances were really unique at the
And it would
Olaf
Bottom in a way it wasn't supposed to really come off
So that didn't really go back on
And thinking we're great Merchants we put that on the top shelf
So weird walk in the stores
And there's just dish soap raining down already
Tire display
It's hard to sell a product when it's
Yeah
And it's really hard to clean up dish soap
India Love
What store
But how are you I mean
You had to hit this Target and you you didn't
So what happened why did Target
You caring
Ultimately it was
Why we weren't hitting the number of units of sell-through that
They gave us for a well-known brand on promotion
And all that
We're doing reasonably
Well unfortunately
A buyer at
Target
Realize
That it wasn't just a number of units
That we were selling
But the type of
People that were
Buying our products and the other types of products that they were buying in
Who were they
Yeah they were they were people that were sort of the millennial equivalent
What's the day right there were young they were
More Dynamic more slightly more urban
A higher-end audience these are
Exactly the types of shoppers
Target costumes
That they wanted to get in their store they knew that that was a highly valuable
Chopper for that dick that's a paradigm we really broke and I guess I'll take credit for it cuz we haven't found anybody who did it
Before I spot
Eco-chic
End
Traditionally
Green products Dental
Look beautiful
And beautiful products
Necessarily green
And I think a lot of it is
Just coming down our own dumb luck of atoms
Passion for sustainability
Mine for design
SI Target made so much sense because
We just needed a bigger platform to drive change
So
After Target
At that point did it become easier to get into other big
Box stores not retailers
I wouldn't call it easy
But what I would say is
Every next
Retailer every next
Financing
Get incrementally easier
And that's really
That's momentum right
If you build
It really at the end of the day I believe that business is about starting with a really small
That's a small
Success and building into a slightly larger one and if you do that a couple times whether it's going from direct-store-delivery at Paulista
Stones to some Regional Grocers to a test at Target
You only have to do that a number of times and you can build
A pretty big business
It's not easy
But the more you do it
It gets easier to get bigger and bigger
It's interesting that you started really with Target
Because we had John Mackey on the show was that other products that really started out at Whole Foods
They were not toxic and environmentally
Friendly
A hard time getting home
Is that true
Yeah I mean
You know I'd lie
They didn't like that we were already
In a mainstream retailer
And we were just very up front
Listen we think that we've got a product
That your shoppers
Really going to enjoy
Recent look like a green product
We don't wear the uniform of
Agreed we wanted to change that cuz we those weren't the people we want we want people to buy our product
Would never consider buying
It is important to note here like
I think it's totally pointless to make a green product
For green people
Right there
Only about 5% of
Products in the US market that are sold our
Green
Products
So if all you're doing is preaching to the converted
In the 5% like what are you do
We want to create a product that
Fairfield to everyone
And not just people that are only going to shop on their Environmental
At one point Erik Satie
Proves that this really was non-toxic
You actually drank it
But you drank what would you do
What did you drink which one did you drink
So is it in London
And
You know I love the British press are so skeptical
And I was talking about a product
Is that
There are not toxic
And Save
And
She said is it
I'm safe enough to drink outside
Sure
And it was a toilet bowl cleaner
And so we both took a shot the toilet bowl cleaner
And then I immediately
Text Adam is still you know he was still sleeping here and finally got back to me as i k
Citristrip the toilet bowl cleaner
I'm going to be okay
Right
He writes back what would have been my first
Choice
Ended up on Japanese television the number of time
Is drinking a lot of mess
How
Quickly
When did you actually
Become profitable wind went what's the news about 5 years in
Mm
5 week
In process after you're in Target
It's all over the country and
Still takes
Sometime
Before you turn
Play fast for a consumer product is
Seagal from nothing
Too profitable
About 5 years
Free quick how much money did you have to raise before
Stop raising money
I'm just fun because 25 mil
25 million
We felt we had to grow fast
Both
Keep
Startup competitors away but also all the Legacy brands
Restoring a copy of
I'm sure right cuz
Because you guys had this
People were like I love this product right they did try to
There were a number of brands that were launched
Bye
Large
Cpg Clorox
All of those
But what was interesting is it was so funny and in Eric predict
To his credit
He predicted that they wouldn't
Be able to get it right
And what they launched
Yeah
Invariably was sort of the same old like
Pistol grip bottle
With the finger grooves in it that happens to run down there lines already it was like a different label on it and then slap a fly
Flower on it
With some sort of like
Name
It just was like
Come on you know an invaded through a lot of money at that
Apple email
Really scary
Did it cut into your absolute disease in the short-term
It did
But because you know they weren't
Authentic products
They weren't
Interesting Prada
Text they were just sort of
You know people would try them once and
And they got promoted so they
Play Capture Shoppers that way
But then it just
The product
Didn't perform
The bay companies
So
I guess for a 2008 UD
Decide to Branch out into
2 personal care products
What was that name of the
Label
Block
And you say that in a very
Matter-of-fact way
This was
Shower gel in hair
Shampoo and stuff like that
The original idea was actually this really kind of beautiful organic
Shape
13 stand up
Shape of
Bottle ya almost imagine like a
Seed
We wanted so keep that kind of object
Approach and we ended up with square and then
Plane crash
It's not one thing that goes wrong it's like
Things that go wrong with exactly that we did there
From kind of walking away from our core vision of it
To not getting the tooling right and what it is we were always
A little bit more conservative
Here we believe in feel fast right
Do you get product out there limited number of retailers
Make sure it works
Just lunch and learn
And everybody love the design of it so we went really Broad
Everyone said this is going to
Everyone could have this in their bathtub
In the shower
Costco Love dead
Grocery to everybody got behind it
It is such that was nailed to the shop
It did not move
Expensive to launch a new product
It really expensive
The discontinued
Because when you see something on shelf that's being discounted for the store to get rid of it
The manufacturer's funding
Will you say you just got
All the stuff like what what happened to the excess
Stop
Actually just recycle
Playing a whole bunch of bottles that
Yeah you'll have some
We did hear some of it was sold to prison
Well so
How big of a hit did you get it
Take us back to domesa take
Yeah I don't remember exactly dollar term
But it was
You know Millions
Of you know any investment that
Basically the amount of money we lit on fire
But the bigger thing though is just
Product failures a reputational risk
And it's something that you need
Recover from
The customers meaning for us a customer was a retailer
Yeah they were they were
Not excited about that
Something that you have to dig yourself out of
So I'm curious because at this point you've had obviously had lots of success with
With method cleaning products
The company is profitable
And then you have this failure with block right
Was there any tension between the
The to be around that like
How was your relationship
Well marriage
Yeah it yeah it is
It's like a marriage I mean I think
Eric and I are
Super good friends
You know we obviously know each other incredibly well cuz we
Sleeping in the trenches
Kids together
There was a time
For a couple of years where we were at each other
Why
You know Erica I
Approach problems
From varied
And that is
ShoeDazzle
But it also can be
Huge
Rub
When
You know I see a problem from this Direct
Can you see the problem
From another direction and you can but heads
Not that
And
You know that what it requires is a requires a lot of oppa
Open mindedness
Requires a lot of selfie
Awareness
Requires a lot of listening
These are all
Skills that
I'd say that we've learned
But early on
I don't know a lot of
25 year olds that have that level of
Sort of experience and maturity to have those skills
Breakdown
It's unusual for
Partners
Create a company to scale it and then to stay friends after
And good friends
I mean how did you guys get through that
Those tense
What did we do
Overtime
You know we knew how to be friends but we didn't know how to be
Colics in pharmacy
And we started to learn each other's different styles professionally
-6 is to just
Engage run out of
Adam needs a little bit more space to kind of think it through
He's an extrovert I'm an inch
We really learned each other's working Styles and we were able to find a better Rhythm together
And
Very conscious effort to say like
Screech on the record like
We got to work on
That's right or this is going to end badly
And at the end of the day it was mostly about
Us
Doing it individually and working with one another to figure out
You know when Eric says XYZ and
I feel like it means this actually that's not what he means it means something else and I can
Separate
You guys sold this
Company
Method to ecobee
An 2013
Why did you decide to do that
He built this from
Ground up
Was it a point where you kind of had
Had to do this
Esl it
Gavin
We are approached by a private
Out of the UK
And they had owned
The recover brand
Which was really the Pioneers in the 70s
Spring cleaning
Enter the pitch to us wise was opportunity to really allow all of our investors have been it for a long time
To see a nice return
We're big Believers that you
You build businesses
I'm sort of for posterity
To endure
And businesses change ownership
Answer the question isn't
Willett
It's
If it does
Will a business be better after
And in this case of selling the business
Tui gewehr actually the greatest
Example of that as we were able to build
Was probably the most sustainable manufacturing facility in the whole world
In the inner city of Chicago immediately after we sold the business
So
There was an example of like deepening and enhancing the mission and building something
Can you help us grow the business much better
Rather than
What other people
Fear would have
See you both of you
Moved on a Draw 2
Yeah we're still still involved with the company
Satellite touch
But you have no ownership at all anymore of them
Struct
So I asked
A discussion of
Pretty much I want to come
Michelle
The star with you Adam
How much of
Successive method
You think has to do with
You know your intelligence in your skill and
And how much
Woodloch
I think there's other factors other than just those two
I think that it certainly isn't all because of me I'd like to think that I contributed
An amount
To a group of people working together to create something really awesome
I think perseverance was a
Huge huge key to the quote-unquote lock that
That method had
And yeah
You know what's there
20% luck in their absolute
I was saying on for Newark and never have an ego because lucky
Is always
A factor
And I agree with Adam with enough for sister
Since like always
Plex always shows up
Yammy
We made so many
Stupid mistakes and kind of had near-death moments that luckily the ball just passed the right way to Keep Us Alive
Just been a real pleasure
Is it strange to go into a Target or Whole Foods and see this bottle you design this
Coq design
This thing that you were making in a San Francisco
Group house called whatever you want
Enstilar
Emotional attachment
And everytime I see
You walk into a random restaurant bathroom and there's are are teardrop handwash sitting there and you see it and you can
Think of that kostoryz the creation of it at. So much a part of our identity like
Whether or not we own a couple of shares or not has nothing to do with it
It's still ours that's Adam Lowry
Eric Ryan the two co-founders a method by the way each of them has now launched their own
Pictures of a company called Ripple foods which makes plant milk and other dairy free products
Vegetable protein mostly from yellow peas and Ali
Nutritional supplements protein bars and smoothies and even though they're not professional Partners anymore
Adam and Eric and their families still hang out quite a bit around once a month
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you
Things your building
But first
Quick thanks to one of our sponsor
American Express
No matter what you do in business
From building a
Better mousetrap to building a better app
It's easier when you
You don't do it alone
Powerful backing of America
Express
Don't do business
Without it
Okay thanks so much for sticking around but
I know for how you built that
Play story comes from Marin County California
And she starts
120 years ago
Yeah my great-grandfather immigrated from Italy in 1897 and we have been farming and ranching here since the
That's Lauren Poncho from Tomales California
Where he runs stemple Creek cattle ranch
Oliver Ranch
We have a few with white faces are speckled faces but most of them are all black
All Black Angus beef cattle the same kind of parents raised
Lauren was growing up
Even though you love the ranch
She eventually moved to Sacramento to work in pharmaceutical sales
13 years ago Lauren realized
He wanted to get back to those cows
In Marin
I felt like
It's either now or never I'm 30
You know totally okay if we try
And fail
But if I don't even try
I'm not going to fulfill as a person
So Lauren talk about it with his wife Lisa
I mean I knew obviously since I met him
How passionate Lauren was about agriculture and
I was up for the adventure
Salisa quit a good-paying job at a law firm
And I moved back to Marin
To join Lauren's parents
On the ranch
But we were still ranching the way that my great-grandfather unrest at the time
And we need to change some things up and actually make it a profitable business otherwise we weren't going to be able to survive
And we essentially asked Lawrence parents
If we could take over
The running of the ranch
Thankfully they had the vision they were brave enough
To say okay so we can Lauren started to make some changes
For starters they no longer wanted to
To auction off their
Cattle to a
Feedlots
They want to raise them until they were slaughtered and then sell the beef directly to customer
Because they saw that more people were demanding healthier food
They decided to raise the cows organically
On grass
Instead of grain
But all of that
Took a lot of time and
A lot
We invested a lot of REO personal Assets in the business like we didn't have an investor we didn't have
You know seed money we were the seed I remember
Conversation with Lisa multiple times and Lisa think when are we actually going to
Pay ourselves
The do this
Both Lauren and Lisa kept day jobs
Paid the bills
While they certified the pasture and
There was many people in our lives that just thought we were completely insane because he had two children
During these years
And we were running around you know seven-days-a-week juggling all of these balls
It took them
3 years to fully convert to being an organic Ranch
And to build up a base of customers
First Farmers Market stand at local stores
Working on different ways to go easier on the
Environment
In fact they become one of the first farms in the US to actually measure their carbon levels
And now they're not only carbon neutral
There actually was known as
Carbon positive
Managing operations and the property the way that we do
Applying compost in rotational grazing
Or actually
Sequestering more carbon than permitting
It just
Incredible
Anyway a few years ago Lauren was able to
Quit his day job in sales to work full-time on the ranch
NOAA profit margin
In ranching
I slept
Their gross revenue this year is over 3 million dollars
Which comes from
Details Plus
Tours events and an Airbnb
All on the ranch
Started by his great-grandfather
I think my parents are like
Totally proud to see us
Back
And our business driving and they're always talking about I said they're always there are our biggest fans
The business is called stemple Creek Ranch
And if you want to find out more about it or hear previous episodes of this show
Add to our podcast page
How I built this
Npr.org and of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build
. NPR
Got to work
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there please
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us at HIV ta10
Npr.org
If you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
It was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music
Pose by ramtin Arab Louie
Thanks also to
Did Jay-Z Howard nor could see in the immigrants Anna's Mexican pork
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
SB event
I got Roz and you been listening to
How I built this
From NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign mode
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days a week