This message comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Who understands every small biz
Business is uni
Impaler's it's Palace
State your business is very specific
Get a quote or purchase of house
At h i s c o x
.com
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
He is guy here and in just a minute we've got a brand new episode of the show
For you today with Janice Bryant
Hemorrhoid of act 1
But before we start to show
Guess where am I
Taking minutes
To show your support for
PA programs
I contributing to NPR's year-end fundraising
Your local station
Depends
Support
The news
And the programming you love
Stations are the lifeblood of
Public Radio
So please
Consider donate
I going to donate
Npr.org
Slash built
Vets donate
. npr.org
Built
I'll tell you candidly and I'm not proud of it
There were times when I would get my intelligence to other members of my team and have them
Go in and make a presentation or them make the pitch so that the client wouldn't have to interact directly
Look with me as an African-American or as a female because you thought
They wouldn't want to in some instances I thought it in other instances I knew it
NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
Behind the movement
Andre Rison on the show today
Temporary gig is a secretary in
Spire Janice Bryant howroyd to build an employment agency
It turned into an Empire
Hyundai Genesis
First African American woman in history
Billion dollar business
Hiring employees is
One of the hardest things about running a business
If you listen to the show long enough you heard Founders talk about how
When their company started the
Descale
Hiring enough good people consume so much of their time
Because
Hiring requires patience in
Yes
Lock
Even the best applicants sometimes
Well after they start
And this was an inside
Janice Bryant howroyd
Came across early in her career after working as a secretary for
For her brother-in-law
It was the late 1970
And her brother-in-law
Needed an assistant for his growing role in billboard magazine
Hollywood
Janice notice that lots of other Executives in Hollywood needed
Clerical help too and they needed it
Fast
Setting up a time to find the right guy
People
So with all of her money
It was $1,500
Janice rented a small space in front of a rug shop in Beverly Hills
And she started an employment agency
At the time
Janis was a young African-American woman
Starting out in an industry
Dominated by
Older white man
Not today
Her company
Act-1 group does an estimated billion dollars a year in sales
At 1 handles hiring and recruiting for all kinds of Industries
It also provides a lot of back in service
Employee screening
Payroll
What began
It was just
One office
One phone
And Janis
Joe Pinette
First office
Listen to City she barely knew when she first arrived to LA
In her mid-20s
Janice has spent most of her life
In a very different place from Hollywood
She grew up in the 1950s and 60s
Big family
Small town
Carrboro North Carolina
I grew up on the other side of the tracks and that's literally the case because we did have a train that ran through
Bardstown we were a town that was
Incorporated in the 1700
So I train track in the middle of the town did indicate some level of price
Spirit
Now we were segregated make no make no mistake about that
But we had that Southern etiquette
Get that went along with it so there was a politeness
That occurred among
People
But we also were very aware of the injustice
How many brothers and sisters did you have growing up
By Brothers 5sis
Multi phase
So 11 kids in your house
Yeah you say that like that sounds so much to you
Yeah it does
She turned like a lot of kids
Oh my no you don't know my mom and dad if you thought there was chaos going on in the Bryant household
Matter of fact we had a system we are the older siblings would take care of the younger ones and when I
I say take care I mean they were
Responsible that we did chores appropriately we had personal grooming taking care of
They checked us for another you helped us with
And that homework was Donna so Sandy got me she was first born I was
Sports Bar
And when she went all the way off to Greensboro North Carolina which buy dry time
It's about
4 hours
It felt like the end of the world
At Hannaford
I ate everything just felt so empty to me yet there were still 12 people left in the house everyday if we had no
Guess,
Did your parents I mean was there ever a sense that
You know that they were struggling or did it always feel like you had everything you needed as a kid
Guy I remember sitting in a class and I had what Oprah later corned aha moment
And I remember
Sitting in class and thinking wow
We are poor
Had no concept
The Parvati growing up no idea
None at all we always had enough for us and some two
And that meant clothing fat men
Food and that also met emotional
When you were when you were little did you
Would you dream about
What you would
B
When you grew up poor
Did you order
Have big Ambitions as a kid or or were they kind of like biu Noel
I'll see what happen
Nautzi
Print media
Was really the thing that
Taught me so much and books
Sprint.
My mom bought encyclopedias and then she
He paid them off
Overtime
She also have periodic
That came to our house
There was a magazine called sip
There was ebony was popular
Jet Magazine was popular back
And so
I knew a lot about
The world and I knew a lot about
What black
People were doing in so I had role models who
Applefield
Thoughts about what I might do when I grew up
But as a very young child I remember admiring my mom so much I can change it to do to this
Date
She even then I could sense even though I
Could you put label to it
Was quite an efficient person and she ran our home like a
A business
My dad was a foreman
He was a poor man in a diaper
You know we're textile community in North Carolina
And dad was
Very integrated in our lives
EBay sure that we had on Thursday founded meetings Thursday was payday
And we all had to
To gather around and we discussed what we done what we would be doing
In business we say we discussed the gaps
And we brought war with the Solutions in my family dad just said let's see where we are and where we're going kids
That was always his open comment
Genesis when you were when you were a girl when your kid
Did you see entrepreneurs around you either in your community or or in your family
Retrospectively I saw them growing up I did not know that's what I was
Was looking at
I remember Grandma Dora walking around topper in high heel shoes coming over to our house
And they ran a Barbie
Accushot
And
They had a home that
Had a beautiful dining room in it
But their dining room was to serve their customers
Yeah and white people would come over to eat beer
Which was a big
Deal that they were coming over to have dinner with your lunch
But I didn't look at that is on
Then that's just what grandma did you know
I also saw her run
She said people to go bag
Common buy beer lunches or dinners at the back and she would charge based on who was working and who
Who was out of work
And she had that sense of justice in her mind about how to run her business and
I think it paid off because she did quite well
Such as I read that
When you are in high school
Your Mom and Dad decided to send you to a
And all white ice
You were going to be there
First
African-American students
At that school
What do you remember about
But your first day going in there
Well
Mom and dad
Didn't send me
We decided as a family
Event that would happen our community
She wanted to have our best and brightest
Go to the white school
To lessen any
Beer around with her and not the school with
Dilapidated anyway paillard
Attending it
And I was one of the first
And I remember my first day going into my English class
And I thought oh
English has always been one of my better subjects and I'm going to fail because I couldn't understand my English
She had a twang that
Sounded so
Different tubing from my side of Tarboro
Mind you were talking about a distance that I could
Walk to school from my home
But she sounded so
Different
The communities were truly divided in that way
Yeah
And
We had a teacher who stood up on the desk that day the first day I went into his history class
And explain so
Eloquently if you can even
See the paradox
Said that how
Blacks are so suited to slavery
Are never chilling so
Hard
God please don't let me cry
If you just let me get out of here without crying
I'll never come
That's how intimidated how fearful and how far am I
Felt in a US history
Did you want to stop going to that school I mean like to imagine being 16 year old
1516 old kitten
And feeling that level of hostility and then searing a teacher
Say that
Somebody with power
Just to say that
I absolutely do you want to stop going and I told my dad I didn't want to go back and dad gave me three options
He said
You can
Come back here and compete against
Other
Black kids who are going to need scholarships to go to school
He could go up and he could
Florida teacher
And seek retaliation
Or I could go back and I could understand and this is something that if you say too many black people they were
Finish this sentence
For you it's not what they call you
It's what you answer to
And that was my
First big lesson
From Dad
That I should not listen to what they called me
I could only be what I answer
Cu
Graduate high school
And then you went off
Unity College
North Carolina
A&T
Remember about that time
I'd love that
At campus and that's where my older sister
It was such a
Wonderful time to
To be at North Carolina
Everybody was
Full of promising
Ideas about what we
It 2
So much of my
Adult framing happened on that
That campus in
By the time I started my own business
I was able to reach back
On what I had learned in my home which is where I gave most of my business education
Set my home
And
The ability
T2
To meet new people and not a stranger
That I learned at 8
Tea that was sold
Wonderful
Yeah
What did you do
When you graduate
First I worked
In the National Academy of Sciences in Washington DC
DC
I worked here for about a year-and-a-half and I went home to visit
Mom and
Dad
And
I
Remember
One morning
My mom and dad
When we were kids early morning was always there time I told you that left her work really early
In the morning sun
Good date time
What's early morning
And they dated in the kitchen in the little bay window where she has a table there
To this day
And I got up to walk through the hall
And I saw them kissing and hugging just just like teenagers and I thought
You know I'm an adult by that right
That was the last time my mom saw my dad alive
And I
Many times since then
Have thought
If you have to say goodbye
What a wonderful way for her to know
That the last time you saw her alive
He held her in
After so richly and she him
Heart attack
My dad had taken too young man out
Auntie
Waters in North Carolina
Shrimp Boat Fishing
They want a shrimp boat
And a storm came up
My cat was taken in the storm
And so
I remember my mom took to her bed for a couple of weeks
I had booked
Ticket to come to
California to visit my sister Sandy
And
I remember I told my mom I'll stay here with you Mom
And help you my mom it been married since she was a teenager she's never had any other boys
Brandon
I knew there would be some heavy adjustment
And
She said
No
I'm going to have to learn to live on my own I better do it now
And then
She said the last thing dad would want
Is for me to stop you living your dream
Cuz we certainly
We certainly have lived hours
Cu
You leave North Carolina
I mean what
What a what a moment
In your life your mom's life in your family's life
Misses like
The late seventies and
You come to LA to visit your sister and it was It was supposed to be just a quick visit
Detect to see her a couple days or weeks or something like that
Had a couple weeks planned it was going to be a good visit two weeks by there was a long time still is
Yeah and you are
Just Academy you were in your mid-20s right there early twenties at that point
Although let me tell you what I got
La I didn't think so I mean
East Coast I thought I was all of that when I got to LA
And I saw the
These women who work
Without pantyhose on they carry purses
Is with somebody else
His name on it
And I was calling at Louis Vuitton
Adams
They were all all all the black people all the black women I saw
Work work work like
Fabulous
Gorgeous women and I felt like this little
Nappy Headed colored girl coming out of
North Carolina amongst all these fabulous
Does people know I didn't feel all hot and popping
What was your first impression of a valet at that time in this is like
The late seventies it was
Palm trees
Gorgeous gorgeous
Palm tree
You know you go up and
Drive all the way up and look out over the city and it was so
So beautiful
La was
Wide open
Truly was a very
Tell kind of exist
Just for me
And I want it in on it
He wanted to stay
Didn't at first
I needed to say
Chiang Mai stay financially cuz my sister
Stay
I'm the first family membership
She's got out
From home
To Sandy and and her husband Tommy
He worked at at
Billboard magazine
He did he had worked at Motown for
Gears and help move Motown out to LA
And then he
Went to billboard
You know his career have been in the music industry I remember seeing his name scroll the year he died at the
The Grammys
And Tommy invented what they called The Hot 100
Is chart of the Billboard Hot 100
To this day I
Keep leading people who just have such great memories of him and
Certainly I do
He was in
Credible incredible
First generation Irish
So you
Neglect la
Hate to see your sister and
Her husband your brother-in-law Tommy says
Hey you know I have some temp work for you at billboard and and and that's what you did you could have went to his off
Matheson
Workout works for him
Yeah
She and Tommy were going to animate conference in Italy
Lee and
When he came back I have reorganized things put things in form as I saw they should
B and he thought I at work magic I thought I did what I was supposed
52 and he said you know you don't you you really are good Janice you should not go back
Without proving you can make it on your own and
He was the one who seated the idea that I should hang my own shingle you are looking for work
And your brother-in-law
Essentially says
Hey Janice why don't you just
Open up a business
And you've got your job you got your own job
He absolutely did it was that simple
For him he later told me he saw so much Enterprise entrepreneur
Shipping
That I wasn't seeing in myself
So what was the business idea that
You guys started to talk about
I actually started as a full-time aide
Wit meaning what
We were finding I found people full-time jobs
You were like a headhunter
Yeah
At the admin
So what
Once you decided
That you were going to start
This company's agency to help
Place people in Ninjago
What was the first movie where did you get a novice how did you
How did you start it
I made a deal with a guy who owns the rug
Book Shop in
My setup office in
Front of the rug shop
Where was the Revenant filmed
Beautiful in Beverly Hills
In Beverly Hills location location location wanted a Beverly Hills address to say
I had a friend who
Hook me up with someone who had a Beverly Hills location
I was not looking at real estate that way
But it worked out
Perfect
Stars were lying
And what did you call it what you call the company
Act 1
As in act 1
When you're in a movie that kind of act 1
You know because it's located here in Los Angeles are yet many people thought that but
But for me it was
What's more around the biblical
Ants the book of Acts
So you get get this lot of space and what you put in a desk and a phone and
And there didn't have to it was there
And it worked out very well for me but I'll tell you something when I
I did get my own office but I remember the first
Date
I got a
Fax machine
Do you know who Judy Jetson Ensure
Of course I thought I was
Judy Jetson
Knology hit
Hard for me
Yes that was incredible for me
And it also taught me the power of
Of Technology
And I think that's why
Over the years my company has he
Baltimore Around how we build
Human friendly technology
Then anything else
When you
Started at 1
Did you need a lot of
A lot of startup money to get it going
Borrowed money from my
Mom and I had
Save 900 in Paris 600 from
But see you at $1,500 to start this business
Yep and that was going to get you the office
Sally's on the office
And I guess a phone
But here so I'm trying to understand you're so young and
You just
Reception just got there
So how did you even start how did you even find people
To recruit
To say hey you know what you looking for work I can help you
About finding people to place was not an issue during that time
Finding the jobs was
And the
Core of our business remains today as it was when I was one desk and that's understanding the power of the in
Understand I mean you
Talked with me for a few minutes now you know a lot about me and you know a lot of resource
Message to go to gain more information
And that's the way the interview work
Is well so the power of that interview enabled me to make sure that I understood the individual who was looking for work
I knew where they'd already worked
I knew if they were already employed that once they left there was going to be an opening fear
And because of the rich Network that I was able to achieve in the social side of how I lived with my
My brother and sister
I knew people who were looking for assist
Does people who are looking for people
Ulta hire
And built it on that
In the early days
I call it the womb word-of-mouth baby
I got
I got most of my league
To work opportunities to fill positions and most of the least or applicants
By Word of Mouth
So your business model was
You help companies
Fill these jobs
Mostly clerical jobs and
They would pay you a fee
And how are you able to guarantee that
The person you are offering was
Going to workout
Oh my goodness
Is there were so many different guarantees that were offered in her industry back then I have thought about this for years
But that's the risk you take on making sure that you're making a good place
And that's why I say we had to focus on the applicant
Because you
You offered people money back if they didn't work out
Then you know
You had
You had a reduction in that feed you got and you got you have to pay that money back if they didn't laugh
Nobody wanted to do that
Were you
Profitable
Pretty quickly or did it take some time
Actually
Thinking back on it
Hitting profitability in a year
Sings
Pretty good but living through it it didn't
But remember
I was in a
Very low overhead based
And I was in a business fat cat
Hi Transit
I was just
Good as my effort
Allow meat
Yeah
Early days as you do as you start to grow
Things rooting for like kind of
In the midst of this you like
You got married to write like in the early eighties
Well I met my husband as an industry conference
Bernie
I saw this guy and he was really handsome to me
He had this presence about himself
And he also spoke with this
English accent
But he liked me a lot more than I did
I noticed him I can't say I didn't notice
But he liked me a lot more than I like
Liked him and he
He chased me for a bit
And
I found out that
He was the founder
An apple one was a
Temporary employment agencies with apple one was Apple One was a
Really respected temporary employee and full-time placement agency
I doing business in California
So you married a sense of your competitor how did you keep
Like work and personal life separate
My husband and I love each other very much so definitely we
Have Rich and open cover
Versation so I think it would be the same as if we've had been
Positions
We are going to share a love of the industry and talk about it
And we're still competent capable people building a business
My husband is a white
European born man and
I have had a
Sissy's we are there have been differences in social settings not ever in business where people of old
You might you're so lucky you were married to him you must have learned so much from him
But
At the end of the
Today I think
Bernie and his
Best honest
Our conversation will tell you that he has rather learned a lot from me
And so when was it clear to you that
This wasn't just going to
Become sustainable but this could actually become
Billy Pig business was it
Was it
Within a year was it within 2 years
After that
No no no I would say it was about
I want to say six or seven years in
And I remember a lady named
Gwen Moore Gwen Moore
An elected
The facial congresswoman
Out of
California
And she had
Been very active in
Championing and I believe she was one of the original authors
Of legislation that
Required public utility
Tea companies in California
To have diversity spin
Because she said you're ratepayers
Adverse
So you should be doing business with them
And she contact
I still want to come see you
And she met with me
And she told me that I had an obligation to get certified
To do what
As a minority
Woman-owned company
And I didn't want to do
Do that I was doing very well thank you
And she said no it's not about you doing better
Although you will
She said it's about you creating the opportunity for other
Who won't get a shot
She said we need some
Strong businesses that are run by women
And run by minority
To certify
And go in and do business as such to open the door for others
And even when she was arguing the point as eloquent as
Clear as she is
I wasn't getting the
Bullet because
Initially I thought that certification
Was a strip search
I need it to open up my business to Total exposure to someone
2 in return have them come back and say yes you are a minority
Yes you are a woman and yes you are running this
And it just did not align with how I felt that I wanted to
Be measured
Let me come back
In just a moment
Agenus wound up changing your mind about that
And how she turned at 1
Into a billion dollar business
Stay with us
I'm guy Raz you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Sunder state of markets
Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics disk
From the tech IPO landscape to China's economic Outlook
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Support also
Comes from better out
Betterhelp offers license
Professional counselors who specialize
An issue such as depression stress
Anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment
At your convenience
Get help at your own time and your own pace
Schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built
To learn more and get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
So it's 1992 and Janice Bryant howroyd
L A based employment agent
React one is
Doing pretty well
She eventually decides to get certified
As a woman and minority-owned Enterprise
Becoming certified opened up many new client opportunities
He's for me because
Now companies could look at me as it look at my business as an offer
Opportunity to meet numbers and quotas that they had a round inclusion diverse
City and inclusion
And if it became a choice between me and another company who is not certified
I was going to get that off
Opportunity
I never known that existed
Before I get certified
And so that's when I started to expand into
Contract business before then
I was doing business on handshake Sauron
Service agreement but once I started to go after different types of business
I needed to do it in contracts and had to learn a lot about
Process
And one of the failures I've seen occur in my own business as in others
Is that we create
Great relationships with people and companies and definitely we should do that
But people are moving all of the
The time and the agreement you have with a person
It may not aligned
With the agreement you have in that contract and when that person is gone that contract is still
Spending
I saw you got to understand the difference
Between that and that was one of the biggest lessons I had
To learn
Once I started to expand my business
From focusing on
One-on-one transactions into
Contract
I just keep thinking and it seems like you were growing
Pretty fast
Your head has been spinning
Well let me tell you two things about that
One the
Big
Sing for me was not so much the X
Exponential growth as it was
The adoption of doing the
Temp work
And bringing temp into the fold
You're paying people longer for the
Hyatt Peju
And so there is another element of
Riskin
You're also the employer of that
Worker
And so you assumed
The employer
So you got
To Dynamic new
And very strong
Difference
Our Inn place
And you're competing against larger entities
Who are going in and Abel because of their scale
To offer a much
Better pricing
And
You are
Part for me and many companies like me woman-owned you were the minority company are you with Adam
Diverse company so you were getting one tip of that business
Against
1 larger than dirt
And I still had to meet the same pricing
As a larger cup
To do that efficiently
Need to do that sustainably
I need it to integrate
Biology in a different way and I didn't find any over
Shell technology
So that's when I started to hire people and we built our own technology
I guess we just mentioned here Jenna said that some of the solutions that you came up with
Charlie Davies
Became
Issued part of your business
Yashow our technology sweet is called deceleration
And it really was about that details reporting we were able to give to clients that they weren't getting any
Anywhere else
And so
I had a client up north who had a
Very bad experience with a publicly held
Company
Call me on a Friday morning
And asked if I would come up
So I actually ran over to
The airport with my brother
Another employee
And the three of us went up North
Add Northern California to
To the client
And we found out that they had an issue where this publicly held company was not negotiating well with them
Walked out
And they had several hundred temps who had to be paid
And we had to get all of that work together
Transition those people
And on Monday morning all of the work was done everyone was paid and they have reports on their desk
I got a call from the lady who was head of HR and sit my goodness Janice
How are you able to do this
And I explained that we used for her but we use in our own company technologies that enable us to do that
As she said we've been working with this company for 12 years
And they've never been able to give us a detailed of reporting that you have here
And they started to what
Conversations around how to buy my ticket
Pieology
And my brother called and said Janice
Best pause
Don't sell them to technology
She sell them for service
I said called him but he said no
Don't sell your technology
To them sell them the server
And we went up and had a
Conversation with
With them and they became out first acceleration custom
You miss your brother several members of your family actually work for
For the company for act 1
Absolutely
My sister Sandy was my first employee
And since then I went on to hire
7-Up a sibling sent to my
And they have just been incredible for all of those emotional and those are values
Support systems that you need in place
As you're growing a business up everyone needs that I needed that and I had that in Sibley
Now one of the things that I insisted for my family members
Before they could come into my company is that they either had to work for 3 years
In a larger company somewhere else
Or have three promotion
Before they could come to work for me
I wanted to make sure that they brought into my business some learning
Not just the ability
To sustain for
But the ability
Teach you how to learn and have
Grown within someone else's organ
The station
And then bring that value into mine
I guess at a certain point this is like 2007/2008
Your business
Worth well over half a billion dollars by that
And you decide to merge
With Bernard's business with your husband's business
Tell me why why did that happen dissenters was a Justice or the natural pointed going to bring your businesses together
When Bernie and I
We're leaving a conference
In San Diego
We
Decided to take the scenic route
Back to
La
And we were having a discussion about our
And
I remember
My brother has said
To be cross
Had said
You know Janice
Ewan Birney
Have something that nobody else in this industry has
And I asked him what he meant
He said will you guys work from completely different sets of
Strengths oftentimes
And if you were to combine that that could be
Dynamic in the industry
And I thought that was nice and I mentioned it to
To Boerne
And Bernie said that makes sense I said but it's not enough to to to merge our companies and we talked more
Or and then I said you know Bernie
I think the thing that would make it interesting
Kunming
Is that our son not have to decide which one of us he wants to work for
Because by then our son was looking at
Our industry as a future for himself
And he had worked in my company had worked in his dad's company as a kid
And I said Bernie I don't think he should have to make
The choice
And it is a lot better succession planning
For us to go ahead and do this now let's not have him have
Do it later
And that was the decision that was
Bought around how we will blend the companies
Just wondering
You're looking back
As a crew member for a long time you were
A minority within a minority you your small company
Be competitors
Your woman of color in an industry that was
I'm assuming dominated by
By white man
Did you run into circumstances a lot of circumstances where you
You are judged because of
Who you are or
Or where things were made
Much harder because of who you are
Very often
Very often I ran into that
I'll tell you candidly and I'm not proud of it
There were times when I would
Gift my intelligence 2
Other members of my team and have them go in and make a presentation or them make the pitch
So that the client wouldn't have to end interact directly with me as an African-American or as of
Female
Because you thought
They wouldn't want to
In some instances I thought it in other instances I knew it
Didn't they saw
An African American woman
Making the pitch
They
They wouldn't want to work with you
I think the
Questioning and the
Scrutiny would be different
There would be more
Question of
Can we then how will
Right
Whereas if I spent
Someone different on my
Tok questions around how are we going to do
This happened a lot quicker in the conversation
Are there women who will tell you to
They that still
How
How have you served grown as a leader
Over that time I mean for the things that you did
Earlier on that
Or mistakes that you learn from and you thought well
But that was not the way to go
Certainly I've made me
Estates the bigger of my mistakes
We're the mistakes I made we are
I have held myself back because of things that were
Latent from my childhood and sometimes burn
You know in businesses around the ism sweater that be racism or sexism or whatever
But those have been where I think my bigger errors have been made
When you use a when you held yourself back by
For example by not taking those meetings or by sending somebody else in here
Your place what what other
What are the ways to
Did you hold yourself back
Holding myself back from
Taking risk
Around expanding or investment
Bat
Work
Right in the core of what I'm doing
But I always
I always saw myself as
You know driving in my lane and under
The standing where my Lane
Dell
Sounds like
Even though you have has Incredibles
Success you
By Nature you're not
I serve a Kamikaze risked
Well I'm not going to be the bull in the china shop
If that's what you're saying
I'm not going to rush through and you know break things on the way to a higher goal
Perhaps the one decision I would change if
In my career
Would be that I would forgive myself for being smart and being female a lot sooner
Everything else I think
Has been
Integrated toward the good of a solid business that has a stye
Strong suit
Today at 1
Is
Either the largest or simile
One of the largest privately held
Women and minority-owned
Workforce management companies in the US your you and your family
On this company I believe 100% that right
Is a billion dollar business
I mean that
That's amazing
It's
Which think about that for a moment you came to LA
Break 2 or 3 weeks
Trip
And building
Billion dollar business
It's a blessing
This is what we feel
This is what
All of the people who really believed in me and trusted in me
Have built-in in our company we teach that there five things you can't teach people
You can't teach people experience
You can't teach
People
Common sense
You can't teach
Rich people confidence
You cannot teach people anything if they don't want to learn it and you can't teach him anything
If they know it all
And I think when I look at
Where you see the amazement and building a billion-dollar
Enterprise
I think it's because those things that you can't teach
I've learned
How much of
All that you've achieved to you
Sink is because of
The hard work you put in and
Your determination and your skill and and how much
Just because
Unlock
I don't think luck had anything to do
I do believe that I've been blessed
And I have
Receive those Blessings by honoring them with
All of the challenges
All of the
People
All of the clients and applicants
My life has been a colitis
Copic opportunity
I keep going back to that moment where your
Your mom
Good morning told you to leave
Told you to go
She did
But your dad would want you to
To pursue whatever it was
So you were going to pursue
And you didn't
Know what that was going to be
Right I mean
Imagine with your dad
Would make us dislike
His daughter
Running the largest
Women and minority-owned
Business
This kind in the world I mean
He would say or think
I absolutely can't imagine what Dad would say or what that would think
My dad is the one who
Who told us it was our attitude not aptitude
My dad was the one who told us education is freedom
My dad was the one who taught us that we wake up on purpose you know
Nnnn
I think about him so often
And you can't not think about him when you're with Mom
I was
Voted princess in high school
And I remember asking for new gown to wear on a float and dad said oh we can't afford it weave
You work so hard for you guys
And I remember my mom putting her hand on my DS Hannah said no Daddy they called each other mommy and daddy
She said no Daddy
Don't tell Janice we work hard for our kids
We work hard because of the decisions we made
And I kept that in my mind as I built my business and I've made
A point never to tell my children I don't work hard to give them what they want I work hard because of the
Decision I've made
You know
And for me
It's a choice
What's a joy to do
Baidu
That's Janice Bryant howroyd
Founder and CEO of
Act-1 group
Apis that you open in Beverly Hills with just 1,500 bucks
Now has an estimated net worth of 300
50 million dollars and she's also donated some of that money to education 10000000 to supports
Scholarships at USC and her adopted City of La
And another 10 million set aside for her much-loved alma mater
North Carolina A&T
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
North building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsors Microsoft
Do want you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family
Surface Pro 6
As if
13 1/2 hours of battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Wherever work takes you
Hey thanks so much
Sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
What's set the scene here it's 2013
Overwhelming and his wife Helene ER living in
Phoenix
And the feeling a little Restless
I think we dearly wanted
To do something different
But we will also
Completely broke
But they did have one daughter in college
They lost a ton of money in the housing crash
So it was not a good situation
They decided
Come up with a plan
And I said to myself
Find something that we love to do
And maybe we can sell to people and we almost have to do it anything they wound up doing
Yeah she grew out of offers love for music he would come home at night
And doodle on his acoustic
Guitar but as he was doing this
You thinking this is fine but
This experience
It could be a lot
Better yeah I want to have with the electric guitars Cup players have you know they get all the toys
Is on the gadget that can attach any sound that they want
Sikkens paint their music and anyway they want
Overthinking
I want to do that too I want to make my acoustic guitar sound more Dynamic more
Electric
But I want to do it in a really simple way
With no bulky amplifiers nothing to plug into a wall
So
He comes up with an idea
For a little box
Try to imagine dizzy it's the size of a big iPhone
Chilling imagine that you take this thing and you attach it to the
Back of your guitar
And then you give it some battery power
Building Electronics
Nintendo anything that you need to do is push one button and you start playing
Insanity from the body of the guitar you don't heal
Only you'll get down but you also hearing
Different kind of
To fix okay this is not much of a spoiler but this is a spoiler alert we are obviously listening to overs and
Mention as I speak
It's called the tonewood amp
That's pretty much how we envisioned it it's a battery powered box that
Attaches to the back of your couch
Guitar
And in the Box are a bunch of electronics that can make all kinds of
Cool effects
Reverb delay tremolo Overdrive
You can
Feel that you are inside Carnegie Hall
It's like if I couldn't seeing suddenly I could sing
And it sounds pretty impressive now but
Too ahead of ourselves
I mean the tonewood amp Injustice
Fall out of the sky fully-formed
Back in 2013 / was working on the very first prototype in his kitchen
Fellaini
What is he up to
In this case it was actually believe it or not the sponge that I went to Hobby Lobby and I bought
And it was electrician tape that's how held everything together and some electronic devices that I had to talk
Home that they basically put together
And gather first prototype was
Scott Janke looking
But over eventually got together with an electronic engineer to make the next
Version
By the summer of 2014
They were ready to show it off at a trade show in Nashville and the first really impressive musician that
At waughtown
Lean was Larry Mitchell who was the Grammy winner and I went up to my so would you like to
Try the tonewood amp
And he went with over to the whisperroom and when he came out he said to other musicians I don't even know how to
Planet you just
Goddess
Go try it
And that
Basically became heleni andover's marketing strategy
Did ask all these well-known musicians
The try the tonewood amp
And then get them to make videos of themselves
You know we're here in Phoenix Arizona and George Benson I heard about us
And then many artists introduced to artists like Travis toy from the Rascal Flatts
Peking and we went to her home
Janis Ian Joe Bonamassa
Vince Gill
The word kept on spreading and spreading in
You've got
Folks using it all over the world
And Laney and overtook
Some of these videos
Switch and use them to launch a Kickstarter campaign
They raised $120,000 enough to get
Two factories in Phoenix to start making the device
That was just four years ago and today
They sold close to
30000 units and they expect to gross more than $2000000 this year alone
Which means
They're no longer feeling as pinched for cash
As they were when they started
Moving from really being on the brink of being broke
To profitable that was a real blessing for us
And when your
Midlife and you don't really have savings and you don't really like what you're doing
You become
More hungry
So
This was like a really important
Adventure
Do you want to find out more about the weapons and Toad app or your
Previous episode
Head to our podcast page
How I built this. Npr.org
And of course if you want tells your story
CareerBuilder
Got NPR
. org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us
Hidta
Npr.org and you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
Please do be sure to check your podcast feed all this month because we've got some amazing episodes coming up
How I built this Summit
We got brand new live interviews with Lisa price of
Carol's Daughter Joe gebbia Airbnb
CLA cast
Stitch fix and more
Are shows produced this week by James delahoussaye with
Music composed By REM
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to GC Howard newer coetzee Neva grande size metric
Important
Rogers
Our intern
A garage
And you been listening to
To how I built this
ER
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing
Form used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email build
And customer support
7 days