Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is
When is Good Day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim style
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
Everyone
If you forgot tongue-tied when someone comes up to you and says
What do you do
Well if so
I'm going to talk to someone who has some advice about that very situation
Her name is Johanna blower she's a start of expert
Basically helps
People write their own mission statement
Joanna and I will be having a live conversation
Webinar
On Thursdays
September 13th
This webinar is free it's supported by GoToMeeting
And it's connected with her upcoming Summit in San Francisco
By the way
Summit is now sold out
But
If you sign up for the webinar
You will be eligible to win a free ticket to the summit
So
To register for the webinar
Go to Summit
Got npr.org webinar
That Summit
. NPR
. org
/ webinar
And one more thing before we start to show
If you've ever worked to that communal working space
They're like almost as common as cupcake shops
These days
Initially the founders of
Of wework
A really hard time selling that idea to the landlord who rented them their first space
And now today
The company has almost
300 locations worldwide
How they did it
Are you will love this story first ran in June of last year
Empty artist
So they showed it to us
I'm like wow look for me as coming from a design background like this is sick
Is as good as it gets
And I'm and they're basically okay here's the building what would you do with it
Sobieski I go home
And
Start thinking of
Concept
Of a name
I buy the domain
I build a website
I designed some
Floor plans really simple
Do like a quick like business model I stayed up all night
You did this in one night
Yeah basically because
We have been challenged was like what you going to do and we have no credibility right so my thought was
If I do all this stuff and come back tomorrow it'll seem like we were planning it for a weeks in advance right
From NPR how I built this
Show about entrepreneurs
And the stories behind the movements they go
I'm guy Raz how to friend
Real estate
7 years build a 17 billion dollar off of sharing company
Help me work
What's a back in 1985
Someone picked you on an idea to build a chain of stores that
Just sold copy
Or saying 2008
A friend asked you for some seed money to
To create a service that allows you to rent out a room in your home
2/8 total stranger
Orcas in 2010
Someone told you hey you know I want to open up a salon that only blow dries hair no cuts no color
Just blowouts
Thinking you're thinking
I would totally jump
But the reality is in the early days almost
No one side Starbucks
Airbnb or dry bar
We're going to work
Because who would need that one service right
Some people asked Adam Neumann and Miguel McKelvey
When they started to pitch a landlord
On the concept of leasing out unused
Parts of their buildings
For shared workspaces
But not just any work
A membership would include good
Coffee
Foosball tables
Wave lighting
Decor
Exposed brick
Comfy chairs
And looks
Aunt
Most importantly
A built-in community
And today that idea they had
Is called we work
It has buildings across
The US and in more than a dozen countries around the world
But before that happen
Long before the vision of a
Communal workspace
Even on the Gail mckelvey's radar
He was actually living in communal life
Miguel was raised in an all-women
Hippie Collective
And Eugene Oregon
There were five women who are all really good
Friends you know best friend
Referral
Bind it all
Pretty much decided to have children without the father's in
Picture I'm just
Because it was a time when they wanted to break free from normal sort of
Arrangements and configurations
And they all depended on each other for everything sort of like
If we were a family
The five women and their children some meatballs
For girls
And then 10 years later
My little brother
Shut up the bass leave those five women
Work ethic
What are the pants
Insulate like it any of them could
Be in charge
Exactly and we all had
You know all the holidays together from things
Giving to you start a Christmas like that was our family like
Everyone was
Pretty disconnected from
You know there are other
My
That was you that's why I grew up with and I consider them like
My mom's my aunts you know whatever you want to call it in my brothers
Did it feel different when you were a kid or was it
Is it just like that
Eugene Oregon
What kind of
There's like a V here
I mean there was a hippie Vibe amongst the smaller Community there and there was no kids
Kids with funny names you know like I remember a kid named wind you know and another there was Morning Star and evening star in
I'm so that made you feel not
2 weird
I think not until I was older and I realized that there was
People who kind of had money
That it became an issue like things that I
Didn't have an effect
But we always had
Crappy cars that were always breaking down in like billowing big
How to smoke
How to use more like the sort of lie
Being poorer than the lake
Being
Weird from a family
You know sort of
But at the same time
I wouldn't say I wanted to get out
But I did from a very young age have
A dream of something bigger
So
For some reason from the time I was a kid
When it would be like saying really
Boring summer day
I would be like you know your what do you want to do
What do you want to do I don't know what I want to go to New York
And for some reason I started saying that when I was a kid and I think it like
Became more and more of a thing the more I set it in the more it
Became real and it wasn't from lyca
I hate this place I've got to get out
Recent enough for something bigger
Wow
So you grew up in this environment
And you are one boy among
Lots of women
Yeah he's always all women pretty much basically
Four Sisters Inn
+ 5 moms
Yeah
And I mean looking back on it was weird
In the sense that like
Like I didn't have
Like I look at it now in terms of like say
My own Simon
The role that I played in his life and I realize things that I didn't have
At all
You know my mom
Did develops a allow for sports overtime but when I was younger she had no knowledge
And you love sports
Yeah I mean from a young age
I did but I didn't have much
What's guys Encino
An end which play
Why play basketball
But never I didn't play it seriously until I was really a nice
So you know I was like a kid just
Hanging out with
With a ball but not like I didn't have any
Scales and tails
And keep an eye exclamation
You are saying hi to me in the studio you are
6 foot
6 ft
Yeah
I can still dunk I'm proud of that I tried a couple of days ago.
What's a good time
Costco David this site
Okay so Miguel
He wasn't just any basketball player he was actually really good
He ended up making it
Team at the University of Oregon
So he was good
He wasn't
Diego
So he focused on his studies
And got a degree in
In architecture
After college Miguel spent a few years trying to build a startup
Pan
It was a company that helped connect
In the back of his mind
You still have this
Dream to live in New York
Maybe even work as an architect
Shogun 2004
He started applying for jobs
So first of all knowing there's something for everyone to learn
In my experience
Is that a New York no one's going to reply to you if your
Address on your resume
Is not a New York who cares like who wants to deal with it you know
So I learned that a friend who my friend's brother was living there and he was like
Like you can use my address and I change my address to his
Russian cream and immediately I got
Want to suggest that one
Switch
But I got to
Beijing three interviews
So I'm I flew out
And
I think it was a
A Wednesday
And
Timeout with one firm they were all
Super like
Shikari
It's acting like they're all black and like
Cool glasses in
Superslick office and all that noise like
Dino ID
Fit in there like
Stop for me
I mean the other one I went to
Was in dumbo in Brooklyn and it was just
Just two guys in the
Tiny little office
And they were in jeans and t-shirt
And you know they had like a really
Relaxed vibe
And you know I talked to him and basically this guy Jordan parnass who
Was the owner of the farm he was like
Okay great
We like you we need you were really busy can you start tomorrow
And I'm like
Cuz I said I lived in New York right
So literally I'm nothing with me I'm like well
Can I have a week
You know cuz I was trying to make up a lie on the spot it like why can't I stop
Tomorrowland
We negotiated musically let me start Monday instead of
Thursday so at least I went back to Portland I literally packed up my entire apartment
I called my mom and
Like Mom
Take all my stuff you know she packed it up and put it in her back of her car
And I moved to New York with a duffel bag on Sunday night I remember I landed and
And
Never look back
And you are young but you weren't like
Us30 size old
Another word for like
Somebody started
Trai
And the job was $10 an hour
So I mean I was in was like I'd Money in the Bank
They needed a
Certified for
Professional architect
Well I wasn't a certified professional architect right I was a junior level draftsman
Like I was the lowest on the totem pole that's what they were
I want to do one of the person they could pay little
Who do odds and ends jobs
Taking that risk it all
No because I think one it was
I get to move to New York
Which was the big
Your goal in that was
Do you know getting my
Foot in the door but
What did I have to lose
You know I mean I didn't
It's like I didn't have anything to my name
I didn't have any money I would
There's nowhere I could there's no way I was going down
The worst case scenario move back to my mom's house in Eugene for a while
Stuff out and what was it
So what happened there which was really cool is that
The Jordan parnassa grown up
With the attorney in March
So Dove is American Apparel
Founder
Exactly
So originally when I
First went there the project that they had was an American Apparel
And it was in lower Manhattan there was one that already done and then they're working on
You need to design a torta like
Yeah design it and managed the construction end and build-out
Yeah it was but also American Apparel this was their first reach out right so they were a wholesale company and they were just
Flooring could they do reach
And so it was great timing because one
Getting there at that time when American Apparel was just starting out was great but
To my background being in business actually was applicable to this new idea
Retail row map
And so what ended up happening was over the course of you starting out in more project manager
Control is like okay now we have to America
American Apparel
Now we have three now we have four now we have five
It turned from that which was actually managing
A project
2 now we've got in the office we have 10
Now we're doing 20 now we have 40 concurrent project how how fast
Explosive there growth what is firm in 2004 and like
Within just a few years
She's like 30 40 50
200 after 4 years or so
So mean
You got to this firm at just the right time
Like land of this really
Candyland
Clearly that
Exchange your life
Yeah I definitely had the attitude that
This feeling that
Every potential thing that's going to come up is something I'm going to use it
And so
American Apparel
Project Veritas
We're under like really tight time
Timeframes and Doug was like
Really intense
And you know there was times I remember a day
Black Friday is on
Obviously the Friday after that
Thanksgiving I remember him calling me and saying like
We have to have the store open there's a problem in Denver
We're not open I'm going to kill you
Something to that effect and he was like this is the most important
This is the most important moment of your life right now
You have to get on a plane
Right now to Denver and make sure the store opens
But it was like once you've been through that it's sort of like well
What's going to come up that will be worse what's more intense and having the
Person scream at you at the top of their lungs in until
Respond to it in like a positive way and say I'm going to take this
6 grand to know that I can
And learn from it and do something
So when you are
The Firm
Did you
Start my own firm
Start my own business
I can't keep doing this for a long time
So there was definitely an expiration for me in terms of
I think really
The learning curve when the learning curve expires
That's when I start looking for other
I think so
I think once we've done a whole bunch of American Apparel Project tonight
I've seen it before
I started thinking what what else am I going to do
And this is
Kind of starts the wework story is that
Why was working for the firm at a co-worker
Israeli guy named Gil
And I became friendly with him and we
You know where
Sexy I Was An Architect working on American Apparel projects in
We became friendly and I remember you know he invited me over to his
Apartment one weekend and
I went over there and
As we're walking into the building
I think in walks this other
Dude
And we get introduced in
Just Adam
It's a hot summer day in the US
We work
Adam Newman and he's got his
Shirt off I think which
Just to walk into a New York
You know Condo building rental building elevator with no shirt is one kind of statement
And then to
I remember ads were like
You know going up in the elevator
He's starting conversations with people who are on the elevator and then he's like holding the door as the person get off and then continuing the car
And I don't know Israelis at all so first of all I'm coming from Oregon I've never met an Israeli
Before so I don't even know this sort of abrasiveness
But I've come to love
But there's that and then there's Adam Hoosier
Just has like a really
You know
Exuberant sort of personality
Which is the guy who lived in the building
So he was girl's roommate
So what I didn't know that at the time though because I mean
I didn't understand like it wasn't like I've been pre introduced a new this
Situation or what I was coming into but sort of on that elevator ride it
It was all a
Explain to me along the way
So you and Adam just like hit it off right then and there
Yeah that sounds weird cuz it doesn't really make sense to me aside from the fact that we're both tall
We don't have that much in common
I mean we're totally
People for whatever reason we just connected we just
There was something between us that just sort of made sense
I'm so he had a couple of startups
One of them both of them I think we're baby clothing
Japanese and
He had sort of an idea for
Innovating a baby clothing by putting on knee pads
In baby's pants
Straight to protect
I'm with their called Crawlers
Did he have a baby at the
No no baby
I don't understand where the whole baby thing come from we have to
Ask him to remember but
Tell he was interested in succeeding in business
And he thought that was a good idea and until he was pursuing it
And that's actually the way we became closer friends was
He was looking for a new office for his baby clothing company
And he was looking at spaces in Manhattan and I was like look
You're going to get double spaced
For half the price
In dumbo what you know in my building where I am
In Brooklyn so
I may convince them to him to move there
So then he was just down the hall from you where I was working at that
I'm at The Firm on the America
NFL projects
Did you find
Kind of charisma
An atom that you
You felt you didn't
Yeah I think so I mean it's more like
Yeah it's a Christmas a good word for it it's also more of
A brashness which I think is
Is cool but which I don't
Like I can't
You don't like to be the center of
Well I like to be next to the center of a
That's the thing is that like I like the idea but I just don't want to be
But I really enjoy the energy
That sort of comes from that like I like that like seeing it
So what happened to he one day come up to and say
I have an idea and I want to do with you is a
Seamless or is it a little more complicated
So it's hard to say exactly
That moment like it's hard to remember but but yeah something to the effect of we're talkin about this building that were in
And we're looking at
The
Relationship between all of these tenants cool comfy
And then the level of service that they're getting from the landlord
And he had seen sort of the business model before I've liked office
Which I wasn't familiar with but he was like
I think if we make
You know these office suites we can we can make money we can make more money than the landlord
Currently charging
Hippie spice idea was to
Scream like a bunch of shared
Offices in cubicles invented
When can I
Exactly so I mean not nothing too complicated other than just like
Hey right now they lease you an empty space
With
You know 2000 square feet
Piedmont minimum
And you basically has a small business you have it in your own hands to figure that out
You know you have to
Build it out you got to buy all your own Furniture you got to
Sublease space if you can't fill it all up like you're facing all those challenges
And you're paying a good price with the time was you know 20 bucks a square foot or whatever would she knows a good deal
But it was just a very low level of
Service since I think
He
Brought to me that idea
I was like
I'm sounds great
The challenge was that neither of us really had a
Variance in real estate or anything
And so
He would go to the owners of
This building
DJ
Entei
Hey
We see there
Floors that are available here will you lease Michael Jackson
Well so they were like redeveloping the building over time they were kind of going floor-by-floor and trying to like
You know move people around 2 because they wanted to make my rent so they're kind of like
Improving cuz it was really crap
Bad shape
So they were trying to say they had enough
Thought to say hey let's read about this
Charge my money
And so I'm he started going to everything Lisa Soho floor and at the time I don't remember a floor plate there but it might have been you know 10.
1000 square feet
Square feet
America's Line
Who are you
You're like the baby clothing guy who
We can't even pay your rent on time
Yeah
Why would we rent to you it makes no sense that you don't know anything about it like we're the experts we owned 100 buildings
I may just kept saying no but credit to Adam in this
As part of his
You know
Innate ability to like
Continue to press even when people say no
He just kept going back and back and no nose every week for probably
I like the two of you sat down together to let Incorporated
You're saying he was trying to do this
Yeah we had no business plan we are not
It was a very simple idea of like
Hey could we break up
Space inside
No real
Plan it was just an
Simple prints
The owner of the building
So he's saying no no no no
For weeks on end and then one day apparently and I wasn't there at the time but he says
We are not going to give you a floor in
But I have this other building across the
I've been clearing out
You'll come take a look
Hey let's go look at this building
And it's
Beautiful
It's like perfect
Do you know Brooklyn
Warehouse building
Exposed brick
Timber no beams and columns big Windows views of the water
You literally like
You know ideal
Building 4
The cool like
No startup Brooklyn vibe
And I'm and they're basically okay here's the building what would you do with it
And
I'm like
What are we going to do
Adam's like I don't know I'm like okay I'll figure it out
Sobieski I go home
And
Start thinking of
A concept
Of a name
Come up with green desk
Which is
Owosso Speedway
Oriented towards
People who are environmentally responsible
I buy the domain
You know I build a website
I designed some
Floor plans really simple you like a quick like business model
Big Sky we remember I went
Kinkos in pack business cards made passing Little
National fires
Please put I stayed up all night
You did this in one night
Yeah basically because
We have been challenged with like what are you going to do when we have no credibility right so my thought was
If I do all this stuff and come back to
Tomorrow it'll seem like we we we were planning it for a weeks in advance
That's right
Only show up the next day with this
This whole thing and they're like
Kind of Blown Away like
Oh like
Whoa you actually
Have company you actually have something real here and that was really you know
Of course Adam
Sold
Presented this. But he's the one who
Piercing
No money
We have nothing
A moment to Adam and Miguel went
From BSN to building their first space
Literally by hand
Play with us
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
Bitcoin and other cryptocurrency
What's your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
An open-air free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini the regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also
Comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers a licensed professional
Solaris who specializes
Tissues such as depression stress and
Anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment
At your convenience
Get help at your own time and your own
Pace schedule secure
Video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built
To learn more and get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining banking
By offering accounts with
With no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in
5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
Gyros
So it's 2008
And miquelon Adam convince a Brooklyn landlord to give them one floor in a building
To start a company
And the idea is to create this really
Cool looking space wear
People can rent out opposite
In the company of this point is called Green.
Even before they finished
Preparing the space
They started to advertise
I remember the day when we first did it we
We put masking tape down on the floor to sort of show the layout of the works
And on we posted ads on Craigslist and people started calling
You know my cell phone and I would meet them into him to the building with just masking tape on
When people started signing up from just the master
That just showed how different it was one cuz it was cool
We had a list of all the things we're going to offer you never going to give you coffee we're going to cool events
This kind of stuff
And people needed that you would get
Permanent workspace
That would be yours or
Or what yeah so the the thing that was happening back then was there was
Their existing
Charter corporate office
And then there was coworker
What's the time
Co-working is primarily Tech
Focused it's a lot of like
You know engineers in a big open room
Headphones on your computer
And there was
Some of those wasn't like prevalent but you know there's some in Sanford
Just go if you in New York
And they were primarily like oriented towards a group of people who kind of all knew each other and then they're going to come together
There and then they all want to work together in
In the same room in the nearby Smothers
Adam and I didn't come from that all we were in this Brooklyn environment we weren't from Tech
And we were much more interested in this like diversity and all these
Cool different kinds of companies and what that energy is when they come to
That said
All those businesses are doing like
Real sales around the phone they're having meetings are talking to
So this idea of like a big open room just didn't work for us
It didn't make sense so I think when we first started it was more like
We're going to do small offices you could have like a small
Yeah 5 foot by 7 foot one person office
A two-person four-person
Person a person I think at the time maybe at 12 was the largest we did
And that was you know all glass parts
Distance are very open and Airy
And it was really like
You know hey
Join
A group of people working together but you're still in your own private
I think at the time we were probably starting at like
$300 for like the lowest end and you know whenever
Up to 50000 for a 4-person office ballpark
Was it expensive when you look at the overall net cost but also not cheap it wasn't like hey this is rock bottom prices
This is like
White before the financial crash
Yeah
You know that I think
Positive and negative in the sense that
One the world was changing very quickly and there was people who are thinking about things differently you know
Perhaps like working at Lehman Brothers or whatever is not
You know the
The best thing for your life where is
You could have been before
You either have some numbers like that or like how I used to be
For this company and now I want to do it on my own
So how many people did you sign up for that
First base
So I mean I think
Explore in that building was
A little under maybe I was 70.
People are so
So we had five floors
So I think that building was about 350 members
You know it filled up very fast and then we
Expanded back to 68j which was
Does the cool thing cuz we went back to the building they wouldn't let us have in the first place
And started building out more
Tempaper basic
You became the Arkansas
Yasso Gill was also our partner at the time so there were three of us and we work together again you know
Worked on who else
Help with that
And then I bet he was still working at American Apparel or with
The Firm that did that and then out of the store
The baby clothing company
Stylust beats to the operator
So I did
All the stuff to get the business going
And I really was
You know there
Whatever
18 hours a day putting the whole thing together and
I really running it
You know
As a very small business
So did you guys start to make money at this light
Very quickly
Yeah so the challenge there was
It was a good business definitely right off the bat
And we were profitable
But the problem is is that its capital intense
So we did the first building under R 50/50
Agreement
And we started thinking big we're like this
Amazing everyone loves it
Going to grow
And we started looking at Manhattan looking at
Cisco thinking of other locations
But they had a portfolio that they already own
I'm the owner of the building
So is in their interest to use all the real estate in their own parts
So they're showing us
Brooklyn
We're thinking about building a big brand and thinking this is like a worldwide phenomenon like we're going to change the world or doing something really cool
And they're thinking let's fill up a large
Custom buildings that have big
Then so as soon as we started talking about like
Other bigger things
It just showed this is not a partnership this
Going to work long-term so you laugh
Zoe Saldana
So he sold to them
They got a great business
Is there still operating
And we got some money to start over again so they own green
Leon green. Stay still operated and it's a nice little business what did you guys walk away
I wish I remember the details but I'm moving must have gotten like
Somewhere between half a million a million dollars each
I mean it was a good amount of money and I think it also presented
A challenge
In that
We had to ask ourselves like
Do we
Take this money and put it in the bank
Or do we view no sort of go forward and invested in the neck
Next thing I think
Bradham and I was
Clear like we're on the Sun
Something big here in
Let's roll with it and keep going
Anything for Gilly was a little bit different like you saw this money in
I was like hey I can move back to Israel and I've got a bunch of money in the bank and pay my life
I needed that so
No that was good for him in a good
Result for Adam and I was enough to say okay let's switch
Focus completely to this business
India to create a new name a new brand all the stuff
Yeah so I think one of things that we learned that green dots that was super important was
When the wind was really working what were
What school was the connection between people and
The things that you would hear
People say to each other in support of each other even though they're in
Completely different
Just eat a late at night there's
Across the hall people having these really cool conversations about life about business and then there's also
Accountability
Because one of the things about
Being a small business especially on
On your own or if your owner of a small company it's like
No one's watching you to see if you
You show up in the more I try
But one of the coolest things that happens is like
How people become accountable to each other even though they're not working for the same company so if you don't show up for a couple days
Someone actually asked you like hey where you been
So that's one of the cool things that happened
It's a sort of like
Play we're all working together even though we're separate
You know
Okay so obviously this point
You could not be greenedesk
Marceau
How did you start to come up with a new name
So
Problem that we had in trying to reinvent the business is like what do you call that you know what is the name for
A community oriented business
You know without it sounding too like
Hippy dippy
Like how do you come up with something to suggest the idea that we're all together and that we want to like
Be open and connected to each other but doesn't have these words in it that
Sort of sound
Like over the top in terms of you know
Hey let's all hold hands
We work
Yeah and I think it took a while to get there
What actually happened I think
Literally in the middle of the night Adams friend Andrew just
Literally came out with it and he said
It's wework it's we live it's we sleep that we eat at sweet
Like just flowed with this whole thing
And was a dialogue between
Months old that just
Happened in a moment for him
In the building haidian soon as we heard it
So where was your first stop where is
Did you go to find a
Your first place
So we looked
In Manhattan a lot
You did have a non-compete
With our green desperate
They're so we have limited number of areas week
We could go so we're looking in San Francisco and also a minute
And
It was tough and we had a lot of conversations with people who were like again who are you
You have no background in real estate
And also people looking for a big credit tenants I mean specially in that environment of
Of the
Financial crisis a lot of landlords have been burned even by credit tenant to you know broke their lease and
Went bankrupt or whatever
So very few people wanted to work with us and we looked at a tuna spaces in
Everyone just said
Why you know who are you
And so
Really what happened to me
It was a friend of a friend of a friend
Knew somebody in
And somehow
I'm connected
For this building I'm in SoHo
And
It was really a relationship sale
You know Adam again like
Redis persistence
And he was willing to go over and over and over to the owner and just
Convince him that
We were the right tenant for the
Does building
And and he know he he's good at making connections with people once that door is open like if he sees a crack in the
We can get in there then he's never going to stop until did you put the money
Did you guys have the money
Yes we had the money from the green.
Celso which was enough for the
Security deposit and you know it
So it's not like
This landlord has a
Carnival drops right here not like
Oh there's all kinds of companies
Clamoring to move in
Swing like a good place from a real estate perspective
Because we will take your whole building
And there's not that many other
What is the building look like
Ready to just
Rent out
The people or did you have to cut it and
Like
Not at all ready
Full. It was actually
In terrible condition so
Did it was it going to be
Required to renovate that build
Probably in the order of a few million dollars
Cuz because
You had a vision of what you wanted to be right like
Imagining life
You know
Hardwood floors
Distressed wood
Wood floors and
Beautiful
Appliances and
I mean yeah so we were more conservative back then in terms of our investment you know
We did a lot of the work herself and mutilate the actual labor
Yeah there was a limit to how much they would build versus us until we had some responsibility one of our responsibilities was it wiring
All the cabling
And so that we were out there getting bids for it wiring and remember we got
One for $100,000 and one for like 87,000
Hundred I remember getting those estimates to mean like
$100,000 is a pretty round number for
Wiring like
Cheniere like a more detailed calculation of how much that cost
So my little brother and I he's
Background in he was pretty mad and he's like kind of research scientist in his brain
And he had moved out to help us it was me Kyle and Adam at the time
And I'm like hey why don't we look into how this actually works in the way his brain works has been to break it down into like them
Micro Parts Peekskill
Every cable run how long is it
How many terminations you know how do you do termination
Then I mean I remember he asked me to
Going to cost us
$8,000 in materials and then you know whatever like 50 hours of Labor whatever the number was it was some
Crazy small number relative to this hundred.
And so are they
Well
It's not rocket science so we can do that are so
So we just did it ourselves
You wired
The building yourselves
Yeah you would like laying the wire dog
And all of it so we had to get like a hammer drill and like
I drill into the brick to hold like brackets to hold the wire we had to
I mean I was so much fun it was like it was crazy but it was also like we're really fully engage and we had to teach ourselves how to
The connect patch panels and program switches and you know so we put in that whole infrastructure
I remember one of the things we had to do was actually
This thing called soda blasting which is
If you want that cool like
Exposed brick has been painted you have to blast the the
This thing called soda blasting where you use baking soda to do that
And we have to buy
Baking soda by like the 50 lb bag and you need bags and bags and bag of the sermon we would like rent Zipcars
Play some New Jersey load up
The car would like to
Baking soda and we put so much in there that it would be like riding on the wheels on the tires so we would like driving back from New Jersey to the tunneling UPS
As the tires like
Running on the back of the
The wheel
But that was what we were doing was like every step
Was like we're going to
And we rented the equipment
The soda blasting equipment just to like do it herself at a compressor
On the streets of Manhattan just sitting out there like
Just like
The compressor is running out there in like
There's all this baking soda billowing out of the windows upstairs it was awesome
2 minute timer
So you sign the lease to when you
Open the first floor how long was it
A few months or 3 months probably a maybe a little less look pretty quick
Take me into that first floor that you
You opened up
Yeah so when you walk in you basically have you know an old wood floor which we refinished and had a lot of that cool character hundred
Your old work
Before you have it
Exposed brick
It's going to be soda blasted
Disorder bring back to that
Rustic sort of vibe we had iron columns that were
We're cool in High character and then what we sort of inserted into that was sort of a Sharp
Modern in a glass and aluminum system
Do you have this Play Between the old and the new
And another thing was like from the very beginning I didn't want to have an office evod that all again the seams
Not like a big deal now but back then we did
Batman 2010
How quickly things change I mean back then we did all
Incandescent lighting
To do that in a workspace at the time it just didn't exist you had like a cool Brooklyn restaurant in Old auto garage
You had you know other people say doing booty
Cheap hotels with that buy but in workspace no one did that at all
So it's totally unique there was nothing like it
How many
People joined up by the day you open
I think when we first open the first
Floor we are probably in the 70 to 80
Percent range
And then within the first couple of months the first two floors were were pretty much full
So once this building
Like most people started to join up in this thing
Start a tablet
Takeoff
Was Eydie immediately to go out
And get investors and
Like scale is make this
Huge
Okay so
Part of the story which we didn't talk about it
Before we even built the first location
Are we actually
Had an encounter with a potential investor who
In a room for one of these potential real estate
Also we are pitching a building we really wanted to get the school building down at Canal Street
And the owner of it was like
You know I'm not sure if I'll give you the building but I got this friend who might be interested
He's going to come over so this guy shows up to the meeting
Sit down doesn't release
These are like
Orthodox Jewish guys
During the black suit and stuff so it to me still has an Oregonian a little bit
I don't really know the world too well but Adam felt really comfortable with it by then
But he ends up calling I think the
That later that day or the next day after the meeting and saying hey
I don't think we're going to get that building but I want a partner
With you guys and we're like well we don't really need a partner we got money we're going to
Building your own thing here
Is it yeah but I what will it take
You know whatever it takes I want to
And so yeah we were like
Why not let's throw out a number
And
We'll make it outrageous
Is no chance I'll say yes but if he does then he were fighting like we did pretty well
And we had no building we had no signed lease even and we propose the 45 million dollar valuation
And
That's pretty high for
Sephora business.
Is unproven in
And until you said yes
And I said okay I want to be a third partner
Antelope
I'm coming to that
Which I think at the time was a little bit
Scary but at the same time it's like wow that's a real empowerment to say okay now we're going to have all this cash gave you all this cash
Shoe dress
So you didn't give us
But he committed to it
He gave us some of the
A little bit to start and then a little bit more of a
That's actually
A really great story in the sense that
He empowered us to think really big because we started out with this
About this
Valuation that sort of validated
Our picture of the future which was really big
So it was great and we're still good friends with him and everything is
Is awesome but
That was the first step in the first money that we took isn't
And then of course overtime you got more more investment
You
Expanded you build more and more these faces
Yeah and I think what we did
Was
We built fast
We built inexpensively
And we turned around deals really quick
And we were successful
You know we built up credibility because each location that we did
Worked and we did what we said we're going to do
You know we weren't like saved
A tech startup where it's like oh there's some
You know hockey stick
Growth and all of a sudden we're going to have
Millions of users or whatever
But we were really clear that we're going to
You know continue to grow
And the vibe in the building's was unique and it was super cool and when people came in they could tell it was something different
Just on walking in the door would be like
Like wow this is something I haven't
And that validation of both
You know the business is successful it really works
Fundamentals of the business are really good
And then we're like
You know we're cool guys and we have a good story and we're here at the right time and you know those things all added up
Yeah you know I mean
I wonder
And you must look at
Simmons company
Uber ride
Big Tex
Andy is coming we think of his
Giants Ridge
And you always have people to show people who started companies that
Don't exist
Like like humpback
And that was a fastest company in history
A billion dollars in Revenue
It doesn't exist
Read anything about it
Your company now
This is valuable
June 17th
Counting dollars
And it seems like you could be there forever but
I mean do you ever think that
Do you know all this
Collapse one day and
And not be there
You know it's a
Great question
One of the things that we're holding onto
Bratayley
Is the feeling that we're still figuring it out
That nothing we've done so far is the right answer
You still feeling
100%
Set up at the values irrelevant right to the business problem
Like who cares how much money your worth when you're facing
A business problem that is
Is always evolving and that
Your primary interest
Does in solving it in a better way it's or primary
Reason for existing is trying to help other people sick
So our problem is like
If they change WeChat
And it's sort of symbiotic
And that's why I think we don't really have a
The Finish Line it's not like a we're going to figure out some model
And then we roll it out across the globe it doesn't work that way for us at also
That challenge will never stop
Will have the learning curve forever which is what makes it awesome and Adam and I
When we talk about this
Is 100 year old child
It's not like he were building companies we can sell it and move on
We're doing this cuz we think this is the most
Interesting
Biggest challenge we can work on it until it's just
Keep on it forever
When you did your last round of Finance
The company was valued at 6
Billion dollars
Tell me that you started
In 2010
Which
Is
I see I mean do you ever did you ever give her stop and think
Patches
Knots
That's a good question I don't
It's interesting to think about the times at which
These things hate you
And
I would say I'll remember calling my friends when
We were first reaching
Billion dollar buyer
I can remember dinner with one of my best friends
When we were at 130
And he was like
Oh my God 130 like
Are you going to selling retired and I was
Like what
Like why would I do that like I'm just
This is so much fun you know no chance
We got you a billion I remember
Feeling pretty bashful about even saying the words like I remember almost feeling like
Like wow I don't want to send this in a text message cuz going to sound so Preposterous like I want to call and only say it verbally
But then you know once
You cross that threshold it sort of like the other ones going from there and
First of all I wouldn't complain about the fact that you
Used to live in Manhattan and I live in nice
And I'm living
You know I moved to an apartment with an awesome View and not so
Childhood dream to Lexi the New York
City skylines
Those threshold where I live a great life
That's awesome
But beyond that I don't have like some big MB
It's not really interesting to me it's more
Again like to be on a path where I feel like I get
Continue to engage in
Something that's what
It's really you think about like
These
Huge boom
Gold
Or oil
Ortega
And the company's really
We're sustainable the company that made money
The most money off of these ends
Tree Service
Levi's jeans
Surface the gold rush
And
Is company to service the oil
Riggs or
You know the
Become visible LaPlace
You guys are
Kind of doing the same thing I mean there's a
Just had boom
And a boom of
Amazon Chopra noodle spirit
And you
Kind of said what what services
Let's provide the service
Yeah that's a great way of looking at it I don't think I've heard it
It stated that way but I think it's really true and it's not just
Those things which any Tech boom is important
But it's also a shift in what people are looking for in their life and what their expectations are from work
Because
There's a
Major shift happening in terms of
Young people thinking about going to work everyday
And what do they want back
People don't want to punch the clock anymore and then have their life start when they leave the office they want their life
To be integrate
They want to feel like there
There's value in what they do everyday
And that's part of the environment that we create you know you can get that so you working at Google Facebook whatever super cool office you know maybe
Do you feel this vibe
But when you're a small company or so you're working for a bank or one of these places that isn't inherently as
School you may not get that
Azizi and what we're offering is something we're
You're an independent worker or you're a small company of
Two people
Warrior like
A division from a pharmaceutical company or a bank
We're giving you that super cool environment where like it doesn't feel like
You're going to work everyday it feels like you're going to
You know a cool spot to like meet people and connect and collaborate right and that's I think the trend that we're working alongside
Lexus
Specifically attack or less so than any other business permits more like a mindset
Yeah it is very interesting seeing you
Talk about this
With confidence in a
Barry
Shut up
Queer
Way and you
And I'm also seeing you as this
Kid in the
Is communism
In Oregon
And I'm trying to square that Circle
It's it's just
It seems so implausible
That
You know
Here you are, real estate deals
The price for square foot and
All this
And I'm not that is a bad thing
Rare it's just
Right I mean do you ever
I think that's
Just impossible
No primarily because
I've been doing all the hard work for the last
I mean literally
From 1990
Sex or whenever it was
95 when I started architecture
Pasquale and I committed to the work
Like
I work non-stop since
I don't mean like literally
I mean a lot of it was ours
But I mean it more like commitment
Like I've been committed to the work
An interested in engaged with the work since that Non-Stop
Anything that's part of the thing is that I found something that I love
To do and I
Felt with it
Feels like to love what you do
And I've never been willing to
To give that up
And I've been on that track
Ever since
Miguel McKelvey co-founder of wework
By the way among the six kids who grew up with
Miguel and the communist
2 RM
Employed by wework
And another Sadie Lincoln
Founded her own Empire
A national chain of exercise Studios called R3
And please do stick around because
Just a moment
I hear from you
The things your building
But first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Go to meeting
Easy to use collaboration platform with
All new
Features designed to keep your business moving
More winning
Less spinning
Learn more at gotomeeting.com
Hey thanks so much for sticking around
It's time now for how you built
And today we're going to update a story we ran a little over a year ago and when we first heard about this product
Our team actually got into a little bit of an argument because
The problem that is meant to solve
What was some people didn't even know this problem existed like if you have a comforter or a duvet
Then you know the extreme frustration of washing the cover
And then trying to stuff the duvet back into the duvet cover it says if you're taking it a bit
Big pillow and trying to fit it into its pillowcase but it's bigger than you are and you can
Jordan from San Diego
Properly and neatly and it's not all crumpled inside and if you ever had to do this
You know exactly what Chris was talking about has an enormous pain and it's something that she had to do when she was a kid
Anyway that's Crystal for self she's always looking for ways to save time
Until one day
Two years ago he died
I want to design something that makes it easier to put the duvet back into the cover it needed to be absolutely simp
That is Standalone you don't have to hook up any wires or
Any hooks
And doesn't require assembly or any of that
Crystal actually has a background in aerospace engineering
But when it came to designing something to help you make a bed
She didn't even know where to start cuz I had no idea how to invent something so I started toying with things I I read a book
On basically inventing things
And bought some stuff from Home Depot really basic stuff they're like
Ropes and clothespins and a kitchen sponge
Which he literally stapled together into a kind of
Clamping device
That was my ultimate first Raw
Prototype 2 just passed my theory of
Having this cushion underneath the mattress to work as an anchor
And then having Clips just hanging onto
The corners of the duvet and then
And what Crystal eventually came up with is a flexible clamp actually two of them
That you can use at the top two corners of the bed that clamps are kind of like liking it to the hands of
Somebody else there your helping hand the clamps are sheep
I'm like a spatula with his
Little plastic
Gate in the middle that can hold the duvet cover in place
As you pushed the duvet into it
And you can do this task alone in a few seconds with with very minimal pain
In time a few months after she's settled on her final prototype Crystal without a manufacturer in Turkey to
Make it what she calls
The duvets D UVA ID
There's nothing like it that exists we have no competition since we last spoke with Crystal
In a few thousand dollars selling the debate online
And she's in the final stages of negotiating to get it into a national chain and a few weeks ago
She got the duvet
He keeps the letter from the patent office in a drawer with her kids birth certificates because that she puts it
It's also something she gave birth to
If you want to find out more about duvet door here
Previous episode
Couture podcast page
How I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and
Why you're there please do give us a review you can also write to us HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to set a tweet it's packed how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rammstein Arab Louis also composed the music
Thanks also to Newark could see Eva Grant Santa's Michigan tour
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Casey Howard I'm kyroz and even listening to how I built this
NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
This campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week