Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Support for the how I built this Summit comes from
American Express
Offering eligible cardmembers flexible Funding Solutions
Smart Savvy way to fund your business
Powerful backing of American
Express don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Business
Hey everyone this guy here
Another bonus episode from the how I built this
Summit in San Francisco that happened back in October
It's for my live interview with John Zimmer that co-founder of Lyft
And my original conversation with John ran back in February
Of last year
I heard that you may want to check it out
Because in it
John tells the story of how he launched his first ride-sharing
Service in college
And happiness co-founder Logan green went on to build one of the biggest ride-hailing apps
In the world
They say one of the biggest court because 12
There's scoober
It's no secret that those two companies
They have been in a fierce competition pretty much since they launched
It's a rivalry that's up there with
You know
Coke and Pepsi are McDonald's and Burger King
And that competition
And how it's affected lift
Is one of the things I wanted to ask John about
We sat down to talk
At yerba buena Center for the Arts
In San Francisco
Are you doing
Yeah
Did you guys hear his episode
One of our earlier episodes
Really amazing story
Curiosity
Anthony a given day you might not be able to say the exact numbers but roughly
On a given day how many people use Lyft
So
Every month we do over 50 million
Wow
It's amazing
Missing
But what was his idea because when you started
This idea when you came up with the idea for lifted did you guys think of this as a simple idea
Innocence when this started we had a tagline that was your friend with a car
It was that it was that simple
There are
250 million vehicles in the United States
Aleve and they're used
Each car is used for percent of the time
96% of the time at the park
So the simple idea was
You know you know that time where you had a friend with a car
I got you where you needed to go what if we could utilize these cars more
We could offer new job opportunities
For those that needed it
Inflexibility
Think about a single parent
Who can't work a 9 to 5
Having
The timing flexibility
It was large and so that was the simple idea let's create your friend with a car
At a community level
And that's how it began
What is it and how much of it was driven by the sense of
We want to kind of
Recreate
Our relationship
With automobiles assertive
Idealistic
An ocean and and how much it was
We want to completely disrupt an industry
I never thought about disrupting an industry
We knew that was possible
We were aware of
Early days in San Francisco when we started I sat down with the general managers of the three major taxi companies
Because I wanted to understand their perspective
And I wanted to make sure that the work we're doing
Had enough
The positive benefit on society so
I'm heading disruption with something.
I became part of
The equation but wasn't the
Reason why we began alright let's talk about the competition
Pretty soon after your
After your lunch
Uber kind of step into your territory with
With Uber with a premium Black Car service
And once lift got traction Uber
Launch Uber X pretty pretty soon after.
And what's more about that because in some ways
The story of Lyft
Slightly early story of left is probably about your competition with Uber
Backwood when that happened
Cuz they were bigger than you and still are a little bit today
How are you are you about that
Optician
I will quite worried
We started knowing what we were entering into
So we knew we were The Underdogs from day one
We we we did that you know with their eyes open
We knew what we were taking on
Whether it was Uber
The taxi industry
A small company with
6 years ago
Maybe in five years ago we're about 30
How many people you know
I almost 5000
Five years ago you would 30 people you 5000 today
Say that we knew it we were we were getting into and indefinitely
That was concerning at 10
But I mean this became almost like a blood
Sport for some time right this competition between Uber and Lyft and it was really an Uber want to crush you guys
How did you how did you deal with that like how did you deal with that just for me
You know the stress level
It was very hard
I have amazing co-founder Logan green
Who's there
We don't know each other before you start working
There's a lot of stories are friends who start things together
That we started something together and became friends
I have a great wife
Who is very supportive but it was it was very difficult we woke up one day
It was about
For 5 years ago
An Uber has raised 3 billion dollars
And we had
$109 left in the bank which is
A lot of money
But only a few more months left
And now you have this crazy competitor who wants to
The kill you
. that was definitely definitely tough but I think we
We stayed focused on our values we
Stay focused on our
Our vision and our mission
And and just put our heads down and executed and tried our best not to
Got distracted
A lot of people here are building
AR building ideas
That will inevitably attract copycats inevitably attract competitors even even
Brutal competitors
What have you learned about your competition with Uber that might
Help someone
Figure out
How to deal with in with their own competitors
That's what you think back five
5 years ago everyone said we were
Right I mean if you look at the odds 3 billion dollars
A a strong competitor
Add Network effects as part of the business
But
But values do matter
Treating people well does matter
And having a mission that
You focus on and
Care about more deeply than someone else
In the end
Really matters
So I would just say
Focus on what you can control
And there aren't there are good forces at
And how did the dynamic between you you and Logan work like how did you win
It sounds like what you're saying is
He was kind of a steady
You know
Comforce and you are sort of
A little bit freaking out you would like to freak out person
I think in simplistic terms as reasonable
He's
I'm I'm more emotional
He's more logical
But I think it's fair to say there are moments where we both
Did you ever think that
I mean what you said people thought we were going to
We were going to be crushed really finished
Did a part of you ever worry that that might happen
Yeah I mean really like you thought
You have sleepless nights like this we might not be around
Yeah of course
Where's vultures circling around
I felt like it
You know you go to work everyday
And you want to rally the troops
And you talked to weathers reporters or investors
And in one of the big things people are saying was that like
Uber is so aggressive you guys are nice
It was like
Spotlight
Sorry
Word
We're trying to treat people well and we are aggressively pursuing
Our mission
But
You know we we entered as I said we knew what we were getting ourselves into and we took it on
Uber is a a good product
Lyft is a good product and they they they do things really well you guys do things really well I'm curious
How that competition is actually made lift
Better
Yeah it's a great point
The competition has
Absolutely created Mark urgency
Hot more Focus
More privatization
Yeah we started
Tipping for drivers we started rental cars that are completely flexible
On a weekly basis for drivers
We started this idea of treating drivers well
Which is that
Shocking that it's an idea
And not obvious and until I think in this case competition
Has been a good thing all right so this is it this is a tricky question but I'm going to
I'm asking this anyway which is
When you ran into so many problems
You know what those were many of course of their own making
Culminating in the resignation of
Of other founder
Was there some
I don't know some schadenfreude on your part did you guys kind of feel like
What did you mean Did you sort of feel like
Well you know
I guess I was disappointed
But we were
Very careful
About
How we
How we behave because it was a really critical moment
You know all eyes were on the industry were on us
I know a lot of people that were hurt by what happened
Anthony or internally a turkey
Competitor shirt externally
And so we told our team this is not a time to gloat and we mean that we meant that
You know why would we celebrate someone else's
Does pain
And
If our goal is to improve people's lives with world's best transportation and to serve our drivers and passengers
It doesn't affect us
Doing that
Sing about you or I mean not only
Is this a complex and regulated highly regulated
Industry but the technology is changing so fast right like
In 10 years we might not even even be driving cars at all
Maybe 20 years right
So how do you how do you think about your business model and how it might
How might evolve over time
So
There will be a portfolio of options that we are for you to say a
We want to offer you Transportation as a service
Instead of spending $9,000 a year to own and operate your vehicle
That we want to sell you maybe at
$500 a month
Subscription plan
Simatai you buy minutes you'll by a thousand miles
And
You'll get access to our by
Bikes and scooters you'll get access to Transit through the Partnerships we have with local governments
You'll get access to rides
That is what we're doing as technology changes as we had bikes and scooters it becomes part of that
As we look to autonomous vehicles
It's not the be-all end-all it's part of providing that trance
Asportation to Arco
In an earlier interview I asked Jenn Hyman about her business Rent the Runway
And she described how it was fully formed right at the beginning when she was in business school that she had this vision for
For a closet in the cloud but that
She just introduced a part of that company at the beginning that the high-end
Ball gown rental
Company
But ultimately she knew that she wanted to create a company where
You could buy you get all your clothes
Didn't it what you're talking about now where you're paying off a monthly
Subscription fee and you've accessed all these things and
Driverless cars were you thinking about that
No7 8 years ago or or
Or is Lyft with Lyft is today was that
Was that the vision
I need somewhere between
But when we started at
Again the vision is like
At the city level
You look outside
And walk around
You see cars you see pavement
DC parking spots that sucks
And nothing you see is people staring down at their phone
Or driving alone in their car
And and we don't like that
And so we're trying to solve what we think is a big part of the design problem
And so we did have that Vision to
Eventually get into other forms of transportation I remember thinking in College of some type of
Automated service
That would just be way more efficient and allow you to have less infrastructure
But there are parts of it that are definitely knew his way
I want to go back to the theme of scaling because of
It's 2018 now
And really four years ago
You are
Fraction of what you are today and we were a tiny company comparatively
April 24th 2014 on that one single day
You launched in 24 cities simultaneously
Huge
Insane launch how did you manage that
That gross and in that scale
Yes it's been a constant balance I think for us
About picking our areas of focus
That we chosen
To be careful about International launches
We've chosen not to go into food delivery
But we did think having
Coverage in the United States for
For every American is a critical
Doctor if we wanted to replace car ownership is the best way for you to get around
If we want to be you no have
Transit
Lyft bikes and scooters on one app
Having coverage first United States for a car that was as convenient as a car parked in your
Driveway
Coverage was important
If you hear the podcast you talk a lot about how
You're sort of commitment to
Environment and your interest in in the environment really kind of motivated this initially Desai
Tidy initially but
As with any new technology there unintended consequences
And even with lift there are even with Uber there alright you've seen studies that have shown that in some cities
There's an increase in traffic
Some people say you go to airports as an increase in traffic because of
Ride-sharing drivers
Is that something that you think about.
Do you ever think
That's not what we intended to do and n
Yeah we're definitely
Our goal is to get rid of traffic
So when there are cases that we are adding to it
That is not good and that's something that we do think a lot about is there a solution to it
Yeah
Congestion pricing
Is the best solution
Getting more investment in public transportation
Is another solution
And those two things can be
Directly tied together
So
We may be an unlikely
People might not expect it but you know I think will become more vocal about her advocacy for both of those
You can imagine
A future where the drive into a city at a certain time you have to
Toupee
Like in London need to pay a fee to go to the city
Yeah you need to have that
In order for there to be Equity you need to have a free option for those that can't afford it
We have that
In the Eastbay call the carpool lane
And we know how products like our shared ride service that can make it easier for people to connect and get into that car plane or just the car
Casual carpooling lines that exist
And have existed for many years that actually work
Quite well
So I do think ultimately
If we as a society want to get rid of traffic
We need to all
Create a new system
I know I want to shift for an inner final moments cuz I know a lot of
People think that when they launch a business
They really think of the what you know what is it that I'm trying to create
We've talked about this
Before and after I've heard you talk about the why
The wire that the why of what you're launching is much more important than the what
So what do you mean by that
Yeah so there's some revisionist history that I know like to say the Y and lift is
Because
The why behind our work
Is way more important than the what
The one that has always been true that the Y
Has been important
The reason is like
In today's society we can
There's so many things we can make
Technology
Incredible
We can have these computers in our hands
That everyone can have why
Why are we doing this
So I think there's too much focus on the next
In office
And Technology you have the the next phone release
And I think there needs to be a much
Much more push from all angles on people thinking about why are we doing
And if we all were to agree on
Like principles of what's important
Principals around enough for us Equity sustainability
Economic Mobility
Then
Then our what would be better inform
John and I love his question was asking people at your
At your point in your career the question if you were sitting in this audience 10 years ago
Watching
Somebody like you up here
What would you what do you wish you would have known
That would have been helpful to you as you are growing and creating your business
The first five years ago I very much could have been in the audience
5 years ago
Yasso
You can accomplish a lot in a short amount of time
And
You know the thing that's been cemented in our minds is just
Having a core set of values and a mission that drives you
Is
Is the thing that matters most
And so
Is that how you thought of an even 10 years ago
Yeah I think so I mean
I think in our society
You know in the United States for the most part
We're extremely fortunate that there are a lot of job
And if you do have a choice not everyone does
But if you have a choice
And you can do something you're passionate about
With the majority of your time
Or you can do something you don't like doing like
You know I got an if you're lucky and fortunate to have the choice then you should do what your passion
So it do you think people to be driving cars in 20 years
Just curious
In major Urban environments I do not think so
I think maybe we'll go to amusement parks to do that
Wow
In 20 years
Incredible
John Zimmer
Founder of Lyft John thank you so much thank you
John Zimmer join you live on stage at the how I built this Summit
Which happened last month
Yerba buena Center for the Arts
In San Francisco
Over the next month
We're going to be posting
Three more bonus interviews from The Summit
Next Thursday
My conversation with Joe gebbia
Airbnb
Oh and if you want to hear more from Summit speakers
Chicken a new video with Cheryl Conte CEO of do big things. Today
Cheryl talks about overcoming The Imposter syndrome and other anxieties that come with starting a business
Find that video
Are the how I built this Facebook
And thanks for listening to today's bonus episode
Produced by Rachel Falkner
Music composed by Ram teen Arab Louie
A guy Roz and you been listening to a bonus episode of How I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email templates a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week