Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
We put together this deck
Practice the presentation we go through this whole dog-and-pony talk about The Libertine and doing and what we were going to build
And he looks up and he says this is got to be the worst business plan ever seen
And and the air just got sucked out of the room
Ramen PR
How I built this
Show about innovators
Entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movement
They built
Inspire their business than not
The number one wedding planning site
Us
Right now I've got
3 wedding invitations
Hanging out my fridge
That's a kind of wonder about the
People behind those cards
6 people who are probably freaking out right now
Caterers the flowers
Bridesmaids
The groomsman the venue the hotel discount for guests are the make up the
Photographer
Because I'm starting to get stressed out and I'm already married
Play fun fact
The average wedding
Average
When in the US
$35,000
In the planning for it takes
Between 9 months and a
Tell my device
Elope
And if that's not an option
You will probably at some point make your way to the knot
Dot-com it's a multimedia platform that helps
Do you plan your wedding
And it's a big business the knot is this
Center of a Media Group
Now valued at more than
A billion dollars
Which is all the more remarkable because at one point during the.com bust
The knot stock price
Sense but
Look at that little later
When factors Carley Roney and David Liu start of the knot
In the late 1990s
It was more like a child it was a place people could
Pop into and type in all caps anyone else
Freaking out about their wedding planning
Well today
Can I test
It's used by 80% of
Of all couples planning a wedding
Which is also remarkable because
David and Carlos wedding
Double disaster
Briefly when they were both undergrads at NYU in the 1980s
Are both in the same film program but
What's exactly love at
Forsyth
Was David was a senior and I was a freshman
And we
Didn't really talk
During it because I saw
Does he look like kind of a super senior snob to me
Did you buy the David did you notice Carly
You did already
At the point
But nothing ever came of it
So after college
Carly and David
Went their separate ways
David got a job working at a startup in
In Philadelphia where he made video yearbooks
High School
ICarly was a script reader for a movie director
Your New York
50 years later in the early 90s
They both happened to be invited to a Christmas party by a former NYU professor
And I remember like looking at Cross
This group of people I'm thinking like
Ponytail why does he look so familiar
So you're like you're like twenties David at this point
Can I just show up at this
Party and
I remember the doorbell ringing
And hearing Carly's voice
And I Milly Rock remember.
Then she walked in and made a beeline for the
And went up to you and said
Hey handsome
It's funny as we ended up the project
We're like we should talk about
That's Amore
Maybe we could do some work on some
Together and
So we both left the party with the
Premise of being back in touch
Sweet but clearly there was
You eat it with interest be I mean bright
Super
Collaborate
Totally
Twitter first aid in February
We moved in together in June we're married in July
Jump through this story so far
You
You've gone from
From ponytail at the party
To Being Mary like
7 months later
Yeah
What was the irony that one of the starting irony is it
The story is that you know I have divorced parents I never thought it was
I didn't believe in marriage
I thought people just
Sort of like Jean-Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir I'll be better to just be in love with someone maybe but have your own home just
In case
And then I met this guy. Mike
Kind of
Amazing he's so amazing he lived in Philadelphia at the
I'm an I actually that moves right to
See you at that time to work on a project
Smithsonian
And so we started this like long distance
Romance
Philadelphia and
DC and I don't know if it was like
Something in the air or it was just like mad
True love
But
One time we were sitting there and we were talking about
Taking a trip
Hong Kong
And I said oh you want to get married in Hong Kong
Just like out of the blue I don't even know what I was thinking you said sure and I was like okay then
Let's get married
So you go to your parents
Carly music
You like a David
Yeah we're getting married
What what's funnier is like
I haven't told you about the
This guy David by the way we're getting married
You might want to meet him
Prior to the wedding and the end they say
This is crazy this is not going to work this is not how
Marriages last
Exactly what they said
When in fact
Turns out and I never knew this
They had sort of had a whirlwind Romance
Sanlitun beijing
Quickly and ended up divorced so this way
It was just like
Their biggest fear is playing out in front of them and let you know because you're
Yeah like young and spit in your like you just don't understand
So you
You guys get married
And
And how is the weather
What's the weather like
We were trying to
Look back it why was
That we
Picked a date
Of July
NGC
Which word where I am
It is 8
Horrendously
Oppressive time of the year July in washing
Tamil people
On a rooftop outside in July in Washington DC
She's going to be your wedding day
Annually how hard can it be you're literally throwing a party
Freddy people like
Like what we need we need
Like a location we really didn't have a place in mind we figured we could find once we sent with
Out the invitations which were invitations were Postcards From the National Zoo that had picked
Making a sound crazy
Will give you details when you arrive July 10th
Location TBD
But it was all in a kind of in the spirit of like we're just going to throw this on party and
Actually Community around us
All together and that was the fun
That my aunt to live near by relay
Like we're going to go get flowers
The Farmers Market
Another aunt
Mine was like I have a friend who lives who has a
There's a rooftop on the top of her building which is a block away from your home
And then there was this Peruvian restaurant near us that we knew kind of served
ESO
We want an ass
Ask them and maybe really just
Figured it out and over the course of three
And it sounded at this point I'm kind of loving
Sing it like it's like
First original DIY roof
Top
You know edgy wedding alternate wedding
And the only problem was that you know you still watch the news those days
To find the weather
And we should have turned on the news on the Wednesday Buffet
And saw the weather chart which included
Hundred
He was climbing it was going to be a hundred and 11° on our wedding day
111 degrees did the story
Just gets worse from there it's
Boiling hot I guess look like they're dying
We had
Me notebooks this venue the venue
Is air conditioning had broken from trying to get the place
Cool
And as we
He said it was like a beautiful Peruvian place in
Because you know we have
A flair for the dramatic I thought that the most
Incredible thing would be
If instead of serving the paella that we were serving behind the scenes
If they would bring out the paella when it walk it through the room
Play.
So
My my only horrifying part of my wedding day
Was turning looking up
And seeing
My grandmother's face
As they walked the steaming plate
Paella by her
I mean she was just
Horrified
Steaming fish
I mean
He was like oh my God this
Such a colossal
Lobster everyone is so completely uncomfortable there's no air conditioning
Snow cones
Inspector wants the hell out of there is what they want
And we walked away from that evening being like Oh my God
I never want to do anything related to wedding
Ever again what a crazy
History why isn't it
Easier
Why isn't there a place to find this
Information I just like
Yeah what it was exactly all the things we we
Thought would be horrible about planning a wedding were until we slam the door
And never want to think
So 1980s
Three you are married
Movie living together in washer
DC
What do you what are you guys doing at
You're still
Smithsonian Carly
We finish the project
We all move back to New York
Start grad school
Starcrest
So you start working on your
Ideas
Projects
So in the very first semester
I'm taking this class on interactive media and this new technology that was going to transform the world was
CD ROM
A word for a Transformer
And we
Started
Noodling on this idea that this
Project that Carly has been working on all summer was going to be the largest single largest
Collection of Smithsonian objects
Collective
All the different music
I was going to talk about American history
And we said that's such a shame that the American audience will never get to see those why don't we see if the Smithsonian will hire us
Mapreduce
D
Epic American history disc
Has the
Dizzy Gillespie
Trumpet in the ruby slippers in the Apollo Space Capsule and you know the words already done we can just
Didion and some animations music and we have CD ROM
How we pitch the Smithsonian
And they thought is awesome ID
We thought they had a budget
Basic crepes
You guys if you can find someone who pay for it you can do it
She's already farfetch
Two people who know nothing about anything
And we walked into the Egghead software store and started pulling CD-ROMs off the shelf and writing down the names
The publishers
Artifact
Proposals
And we have this one
Groupon Portland Oregon
Call this immediately said we're doing edutainment disc
This is right in the center of a bullseye in American history this week
Smithsonian brand
I flew out
Tookus to
Smith & Wollensky for big steak dinner
And after dinner the guy writes on a cocktail napkin
1 gold Master American history CD-ROM Smithsonian content
$100,000 budget
6 month delivery
Free date sign here
What
I have no experience
Half Baked
Yuan facts
Baked ideas
Blindly doable publishers
This one company by
Yeah and we we
Can we can we go to the bar area to do
Binding
What what happens
And we just said you know what whatever let's just go
If it's just sign it then we signed it and the guy
You know this is not a binding
Contract Masonry tsums
He said this is a test
This is just a test
If you guys had the hot spot
Taxi sign
And he said let's do it
Wow so you get this money
And when you start working on this project right away
Yes we like
Basically
Founded a business
Reviews of our Film School experience
Actually
Emmylou Harris all my class
Everyone
We're on board I mean we're Walton school for this and it's something to be able to create a commercial product with the Smithsonian brand
Was exciting
So you you deliver this
Smithsonian
And then they make this
CD-ROM available now
Anna shops
Well so the publisher
I was actually
Very aggressive
Says about getting the disk
And no one was really making any money
Pretty quickly we realized that this was not going to be the meeting that's going to change everything
But this publisher managed
To get the CD ROM
OEM bundle
With every one of the early I'm a
So if you bought the one of those iMac
Max you got Rd
And as a result
You know we got maybe a
I think it's like a dollar per disk
That was actually distribute
So
Kaman Twin Falls
Yeah I know some millions of bees dead
Crocheting
Discs of all time because it got bundled with such an easy win
Yeah
Turned out to be the sort of launch of our company so you walk
You work at a project
Like
Some cash
Play with enough cash
Keep the people
That we had hired
Around at least I think they like
I dropped out of grad school rank of sunlight realize what we have his company now we're going to work on the next project
Acton
We were at little
Digital media Studio
In the middle of this working on the
Project together
One of the four of the four of us
Friends Michael and Rob
They sort of said hey guys
I think we should be thinking about and we work well together to think we should be thinking about something doing something that isn't work-for-hire
You're somebody else
Like something that would
Was yours and you guys would own
Right
We started brainstorming what can we do
You know cuz our vision was Now to create this multi branded multi-platform content Studio
And we started looking at the different categories or seen you know sports news entertainment that's all.
Storming
The leader story makes it sound like
It was all lies
Dimension on her
After her horrible experience
Planning her wedding
The idea was first
And in reality what happened
And is
That
Michael
Actually like hey this guy friend of mine he wants to do so like this all my shopping thing it's slipping lately
Waited till like registry and
I think David and I look like
Extended goatee
Oh my God no way weddings know anything about them
Like completely disaggregated like the industry is old-fashioned
And then of course you have that moment your leg
Right
It's a disaster
And it would completely and fundamentally change
If you introduced
Technology to
You know there was not an MBA
Our research was going to the magazine store and pulling different categories
Bridal travel
Epicurean
And we look at these wedding
With a 400-page assessor understand like
You decide that you want to do something in contacts
And
Weddings was
Probably the way to go but what
What would it
Be like a minute this is like
96-97
I mean a website a message board
So what was it going to be like a way for p
List their services
We work on
People so we thought the best place to start
Pudding
Incredible like
Fresh
And the only way
Yes
And so the only way I would agreed
Do this the one who was suddenly I was looked at immediately like
You're the woman
You're going to be interested in wedding it sounds like the only way I am touching this
Is if we do something
Really really
Like the reason
Access any of the information that was out there when we were planning our wedding is cuz it was written for
People who work
Lately
A different world
I did not dream about my wedding everyday for my
When I was born
I did not I wasn't marrying in a traditional way I'm going to have like an Intercultural
Marriage with divorce pads
Every problem there could be
The wedding was in my way
And those magazines made you
You feel like crap
Yeah they wanted you to quit your job sit with your mommy having bonbons and dream of your big day
Calling it your big day today
My friends either were that way like all the women I know were like it was
At this point
The 90s
Your hip your
Are forward-looking
You care about
Fashion and there's like a whole like a
It's just had such a different movement among young people
And that wasn't reflected at all it would like the industry that have been left
Our whole overall attitude in the reason why we
They called it then.
What is it we wanted our brand to be very
Like alternative
Undifferentiated and not be
Yeah the kind of traditional cookie cutter
These are the rules wait
Plan a wedding
We wanted it to be like dare to do it
And if you looked at the Landscaping to Brides magazine the garage
Modern Brides 35
Martha Stewart's like a hot thing
After 10 years
We
Didn't know
Which way did
Eli's Bistro menu
But also Carly's in a belief in
The differentiation Orban
That we would be good because I'm waiting for the real world
And we Define that as
Interracial couple
Interdenominational couple
Same sex couple
Is your divorce
Second marriages
Is all the stuff that we knew that the traditional media companies couldn't touch in these are the marginal areas
And we're going to own event declare ownership of
We also had a really big sense of
We wanted to be to be a reverend
Because we thought that was sort of attitude only if you want to
You talk to
Brides and grooms
Not their mother
You needed a new
So I'm trying to understand
If you were to describe this to your grandmother who was
The part of the paella
Actual wedding would you say basically a magazine
But it's going to be
In the computer in the internet
Was is that a fair description of how you were thinking about it
There were
Yea to component
Which one it was like
The world's coolest wedding
Mixed
With a community
Remember this is on AOL
So we launched on AOL AOL heads like these
Message Board in the sky and like sites
You you partnered with AOL
Well they provided
This evening
How did you even get that
So
Exactly so Michael are Rainmaker co-founder
Had an In-N-Out
Managed to get OC
An audience with Ted Leo
Who is running between houses
And I remember we put together this deck
Practice the presentation Carly Michael Robert like the
Did the marketing
Presentation genius
Susan weed
Rental car drive down to Vienna Virginia
And we had
This audience
And we go through this whole dog-and-pony talk about The Libertine and doing and what we were going to build
And he looks up
And he says
This is got to be the worst business plan
Ever seen
Wow
And and
And if you just
They are just
Did you propose to make money
Well
We had gone to that
But he busy said he was like look
What's a lifetime about how long is an average engine
So your your average lifetime value of customers 9013
How do you ever plan on recouping
Energy marketing
Ism
But if your audience turns 100 /
Percent error
Every birth if you do your job right and they find the right person you will never have them as a customer again
To this day I credit our co-founder Rob who stood up in
Sad you know
We're going to sell advertise
And head looks at us and says
There's no advertising
Advertising on the internet
And Butthead
It was no app
Options allowed on AOL furniture
There's no idea either no banners it was Dino all face
Basically your subscription Disney
And 10 looks it is kind of funny and then he picks up the you know the brides magazine we brought as
Certified
And I still remember he picks it up brings it to his nose and flip through the pages goes
I don't know anything about this industry but I smell money because
Let's Ponder
Wow
Until we 90 seconds we went from the worst business idea ever heard to
You know what
When we come back
David Carly lunch the knife
Watch it
Value Skyrocket with the Dot com Boom
And then fall to Rock Bottom with the trash
Play with us
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Sportframe
NPR comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected with state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today
And open a free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place
To buy sell and store cryptocurrency
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses to design and build their own website
Using customizable layout
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Play Welcome Back to how I built this
From NPR
Gyros
In 1986
Explain Carley Roney and David Liu
Pitch their idea for the knot
The big wigs @aol wound up giving them
Pretty hefty amount of cash
Where you got RC financing by 1.6 million
I think it was our largest instrument that that time to in any contacts
Ironically though like
Is it really that much money if you have to buy computers for $7,000 each
Each desktop or you know there was no such thing as open source software so we are paying software licenses
You know there's no we work so hard to find an Office to rent in New York
What were you doing to build the site
We wanted to make sure that the audience came to our side would see something fresh and you everyday so we
Treated this like a daily publication like a newspaper
Ten con ten channels that had to be fresh content
And you know Distributors every single day
Planning
Fashion and bridesmaids
The Great Escape
So a lot of it was just
Producing a
And Publishing
Content consta
And who did you get to write the
I have this connection to
A group of fun really fun Young Writers they were
People who wrote for sassy magazine so really strong attitude
Men and women
I'll head
Great sense of humor
When we had that day
Edomite
My litmus test
Says if they would never ever ever write for a wedding magazine
Could right for me
The other key piece of that though was really understanding and this we didn't
We didn't know going into it but really realizing how important
Nanjing
Community
And building out the
Platform of
The different message boards and how to create connection
People
And that is where the certificate
Explosive what are the early concept
Like social network
Write how you catch
Crowdsource amazing information
And that's where AOL was the perfect training ground
Because
The
Assertive
The gravitational Center of all this stuff we're in their chat room
Wright Tire Anoka
These chat rooms you had to try to turn into these thriving continuous conversation
And
We all had to man the chat room
Sweetie we had aliases
Mine was Anya
And I would sit in this chat room waiting for people to show up and most people tend to just lurk they wanted to hear it and Whatley
Meet other people's conversations
And you had to try to figure out a way to get people engaged
And so I always have this one thing and I would rather
How to get people started outside
My fiance
Force me to buy a dress two sizes
Too small
And said if I can't fit in the dress on the day of the wedding to not show up
But you just make this up makeup
Spur conversation
And boy did was that the fire start the Roomba to explode
An explosion back away and that
Roomba just
Keep going for hours and hours
Mother-in-law always gets
Ram towing and
Misbehaving bridesmaid
It's just all about like putting this demons
Play do what it did was
It taught us
To listen
To audience
Yeah
It did was it was exciting
Making money
Pretty fast
Through another's AOL
Subscription dollars
No
Well if you think about the internet at the time
Which was
I mean mostly men
Even in AOL with probably the most women
Have any place on the internet
And still that was most
And then
People getting married since there are only two million of them
In America at any given
Time you're starting to like get down to very small set of
People who could even potentially br
But I think those first week I remember Ivar like monthly visitor account
$15
Riding with 7000
7000 out of 2 million Americans like we've got a long way to go
What we really had to do was go out why our first hire was a sale
You needed advertise
In fact one of our first advertisers
I think she may have been our first appetizer was Nicole Miller and she had this bridesmaid's dress line
That was cute and she wanted to be marketed as something that you wear again and
Nicole came to our office and I remember we were showing her the little pieces of art that we
Created that were essentially the first banners in a very little buttons
We'd sit on the side
And you know Robert explain to her hey you know
People can click on this
And she said well
What will my buttons do
And we realized
That she didn't have a website
And he said very quickly well the link to a catalog
Yeah we're basically selling
Links and buttons and clicks that were leading to other places that we had
Creeper the app
Which which the advertisement for the advertisers was this new shiny saying that they didn't understand and they were like
I got to assume that time work that high
Right they weren't they weren't
Paying that much money that time
They were
I think our first year total revenues were maybe 70000
Yeah $70,000 member like 71
1.6 million was that
Money was Bernie
It was almost gone
We were we are rapidly running out of money and
What's saved us
Was
We had
Down a amazing book AJ
And are you not remember our aspirations was always
Create these multiplan branded platform
And she actually managed
To get a
Getting War
Warframe multiple Publishers on a 3 book
Deal for the knot
And that money
Infusion of cash
We did we will lived off of bed and bath
Are three books
And so you put that back in the company
But you need to read books
Well, we just had our first
Baby until Carly literally came back
From maternity leave
All of maybe three weeks
And I still might the image I still have of her is like
Breastfeeding her daughter
Wild
Furiously typing rates
Computer because we had to deliver
The first mange
Listen to this my own story go to investors
Private-equity people are
Venture capitalist
Get some money
We we had
Thought about it
Yes
Where is trying to think of other ways
That would make money business
And we have this idea and we said you know
The thing that bride seem to be really vexed about
Is this whole registry
Isn't there a way to like
Completely reinvent
Create an online gift
You're not taking the internet
And we said
This is
Got to be the thing we do and that actually prompted us to go try to raise money to build the first online
Remember this is 1997
So when
Just like the website
Rio me act like it's
Super mind-blowing
To think of an online gift registry you have to remember that like
Nobody even really bought any
An end so how did you
What did you do that how are you going to make that a real
Yeah that's extremely clear because no one had online
Gift register
No way to do it we actually
Realize that
Do this
We would have to
Get the inventory arcel
At that time where
AR
Bride
Account or whatever we call it our member count
Was really growing
Hang in a very significant way
Word of mouth was
Our only way we were mark
We didn't spend any money I think was a lot about our brand and our at
Attitude like once you found us you wanted to tell anyone you knew who is getting married about
And so we were growing in that way like wild
People really
Very like loyal and excited about the brand
But it still wasn't so when you took the concept of the registry to
Potential investors what do they say
It was a really long slog
Economy news hard to raise money for anything that was female-centric
Image of space
And
It's a fact that large
Component of our business would now be predicated on e-commerce
On top of advertising
Pekin the first question people said was like they're not going to give you a credit card number
People too paranoid about that
They're not going to register
Sure they're not going to end and I think
We will probably wear marketing
For almost a year
Before we came across
Adventure capitalist on the West Coast
Said you know what this is
Really interesting and you know we're going to take a flyer on this
How much money do guys rate
3 million
We launched the registry
And was it on the night was like the knot.com registry
And we have a new tab
And
We certainly saw within I think 3 or 4 months
We had close 250000 couples Reg
In our registry
Put that in the context that's more than what Bloomingdale's
Wow
250 thousand people register
Within the first few months how do they even know about
About the righteous
This is actually the critical thing
Where Carly was the the secret weapon
Carly became the person
Cool
When we publish our first book
Suddenly appeared on The Today Show
And became sort of the wedding lifestyle kind of Guru
Meanwhile not telling the world
The word one about my actual wedding day remember the first time I was on TV a friend of mine was like
At your wedding
And all of a sudden you're a wedding Guru
Super youth
Profitable at that point where you still can
Gleaming how are you funding
The three million
We meet at last
But we were
We we essentially were
Looking to the raise another round and within a year we raised another
Also known in our office had Aeron chair
It's like everything was Ikea or hand me down or I mean we didn't
We sort of that that whole culture of the
The internet companies now
Does he know you were lucky if you got a
Pizza for you guys nervous at all
And you have
Tomorrow kid
You will not
Making any money
Because she pretty
Just funding is coming
You guys are probably
Learning nothing
If I remember correctly with seemed kind of unfair and exorbitant like
We shouldn't be taking his money and he did you ever have conversations
You know at night where you were like
Maybe it's just like
Go to law school or something like that you ever were you totally
Princess was going to workout
I don't think we felt we had enough
You know
We had BFA
Unemployable so we had to make this thing
Super this point you guys
You got the gift registry going
And things seem to be having a lot of gas and then
In in mm you decide to
To take the company public on the NASDAQ
I'm assuming this is to raise more cash
Yes so in 99 we actually had just raise money to build
Doubt in flush out the registry raise 15 million dollars and
Literally week later weird
Approached by Bank
Too sad
Are the windows going to close you need to go public
And and we were
Fresh money in the bank and I couldn't understand why there was such a
Are we took their advice
Fortunately and
Are we then I think 7 months of that meeting we were going public
December
Second
1999 Republic
The entire internet world collapses 4 months later
You're really lucky to have that additional 35 million dollars
So you ate when you went public
Erase 35 million more dollars
And then four months later the dotcom crash
Does that do anything to your
We never had the
Super spiky jump and we didn't have a super
Cataclysmic crash it just over the course of a year and a half
Went from $20
And settle down
So people lost
Stuffed shirts
Yeah presumably you guys had
A lot of shares to
We were not allowed to sell lemonade
We we were locked up in by the time the 6-month lock up with Head released
Honestly we're also
We were way too loyal and dedicated we did not want there to be any indication that the founders had lost faith in
And so we were going to hold on to the bloody
$20
26 Cents of a year-and-a-half
Must have
Ben
Rapha meaning must have been
Market analysts and people even in the industry were saying this this company make me laugh
OU's horrific but we had our competitors
Faxing or stock chart
To our advertisers saying look what's happening they're going out of business really want to give him now
And did that did that
In any way affect
You know how much money you had to spit
If you had to
To use like a Drifter
Did you just fire people just to lay people off
At that time or or we could you
Still kind of played along
We we never had layoffs we always we're able to downsize to attrition but we never formally had to leave
People often because we are always running relatively lean
And they were people who panicked and and
Basically
Should have got out
Jurassic the biggest challenge was controlling the like psychology of
Your team bet
Your advertisers did not do
Understand the distinction
Between
You're growing Revenue
And how they had nothing to do with your stuff
Play so between your young staff
Who also is looking like member those
Options are underwater by about $9 or
And RNN advertise
Kaiser said it was so much
Emotion control heading that way
Was the hardest part
Key people focus and it was exhausting and also you do go home at night and you were like
Remember when we were asked
Going to walk away from the
Disney
30 million dollars together and now we have
Electronic stores it doesn't seem worth it because it seemed where they were definitely a moment we feel like
Exhaust
The low point
It was the summer of 2001
Square
The stock drop below dollar for
Over 90 days
You get the listed
Are we going to go longer than you
Go down to the sea in bed now sector-3 considering the
And I still remember there's a little tribunal you make your case and then
This Old Gentleman looks over and says
I'm sorry you know we're still going to have to do list you but you have a great little business don't let it that
When you get delisted you you still you're still a stock right
You still start your trading in the bulletin boards but the key difference is now the major
Funds are no longer allowed to hold yourself you are listed you cannot so big fun tonight
Yeah the fidelities and unfortunately you know that's where a lot of volume in the sport comes
From Republic socks and so the moment we got Dlisted
2 million shares just
Automatically gets injected into the
We went down from like $0.90 to $0.26
You have to be above a dollar for certain number of months
To get realistic about $5
480 days
Without Institution
Once you're Dlisted it's almost impossible to
Get back on it cuz you'd have to
Convince people individuals to buy shares right
Exactly
Sew-in in the back
I spent the next
3 years
Going to
Dentist investor club meetings
If the back of the Red Lion Inn
Going to small-cap going to conferences
Drumming of retail support to try to get the stock
So you had to get individual investors
Buy shares
Yeah you need it to dentists in America
It was and I think
You know that's when you put on like 25 lb
I have this one meeting with a competitor and I think
It he said these fatal words that I've had sooner
Propel this thing forward
Baby saw this as an opportunity to acquire us and they said listen you have a broken IPO we should just put these companies
Together you know 7030 their way we will continue to repackage it and go public
This is an offer to buy you out
Yes and he said cuz
Your Dlisted
And giving relisted is like carrying a gorilla up 30 flights of stairs then pause
It's too hard
And I remember the day we got relisted in
Dying to send him a postcard with a big gorilla on it saying 30 flights delivered take that
So
4 years
You're awesome as.
It's a long time
I'm trying to figure out why you didn't just
Cut your losses
Didn't say
We're still young you know we can still kind of
Try something else out
This is knocking
It's not going to be the way that we're going to make
Sustainable life
I think
It was because we will never doing it for the money
Who did you hire kids you needed
Have somebody
Yeah but I think it was
I think it was the war
We were launching a TV show we were launching you know a national magazine there's so many really excite
Writing things that we were building you know the nest
The bump came last in the bump were like
The next iterations messed obvious
Play about
Is in your home
And the bump about baby
Yeah our audience have been begging us
That's four years to take
Take them beyond the wedding day and we
You know people on our staff who would like grown Beyond The Wedding phase and I'll head babies they all wanted to launch it so it's just him in crib
It'll be fun there was so much more to do
We always said to each other like
If it ever becomes
Super boring
We should get out
We were not particularly like
Planner people anyway wouldn't think about our
Future
We were just thinking
Exit wasn't part of a rectangular
You get relisted in in 05
You've been launched the nest
And the bump
I miss part of the
The hold to the media Empire you're working on a bunch of different projects
At what point
Were you
Did you guys feel like okay
We've turned a corner like we are
Where can I be okay not work anymore
I'm not sure there yet
Once we were like prophet
Butterball
Keep thinking you're ahead and then
Enjoy having your own back
Keep pushing again in 2006
Send 7 we wound up we we
Bought Wedding Channel
There is
Unbelievable so frothy expectations and what that acquisition was going to net us in
Stock hits $32 we have a billion dollar market cap and
Dino Dan precipitates
The next
You know minor nuclear winter wear the socks or declining down to do so you just can't live up to those expectations
And then
2008 Honda
The Great Recession stock price
I was talking to held up relatively well I think we're most media companies
Spore down 20% we grew 5%
You know we actually
Do that year because
A lot of the marketers realize that the only people
Who are going to continue to spend money during this Great Recession are our rights and rims
Weddings were truly recession
But what do you think it is about
About your personality essay
Work so well together because
You guys went through such
Intense emotional highs and lows building this business so
What do you think it was about
The other person there in a relation
This is where you declare your love of me and how amazing I have
Exactly
You know I think we were
Ultimately so different as people
I wouldn't say that
We necessarily work well together
But we were in
Credibly complimentary
Where there is no overlap there's
Less conflict in a time when there was overlap oh my God it was like
Like the two of us are both incredibly bullheaded
There are really distinct differences like David can kind of
Look up
Look ahead and think of something
Like really bold and
Teejet way down the road
I can grab that ball really
Quickly believe in it
Like I'm not a naysayer
Okay you want to do that
And then I figured out how to
When you think about
The fact that you both have
Bachelor's degree in Fine Arts
You met in a long time ago and
You probably will never going to
100% of traditional path never really going to
Make a whole lot of money
The fact that you built a country that's now I guess
Word collect
Half a billion dollars
Like weird now that you look back on it
Yeah okay
That makes sense
We we can do this
If it's
Cereal I mean at one point someone said
Do you realize 700 families are gainfully employed because of what you build
And then you know the
Sending kids to college and buy homes in next week
I thrive and there's a great sense of satisfaction
Company has always been good just lyrics
Extension of our family
There's a great deal of
Pride in having been able to build something that is sustainable in and continue to grow that way
We never really
Care that much about money
But I can tell you nothing worried about money
That is like that is what I'm so great
I spell panic
Yeah but that's like a personality
Disorder
Kill all the people
I think more than anybody else
Your business
Billy reflects the progression of your adult life and where I love that is
You you clearly did all these very imperfectly like your wedding was kind of a disaster and then
You know you kind of struggled with
Kids because you were busy or didn't probably
Do everything that all the perfect parents were doing and
All these companies that use Darden deflect all the things that you
Done in your life
And I think
Almost
Event you know
More to the point
Our whole set of Brands going to celebrate a damn perfect
I think what
Appeal the p
People is that
We're like there is no perfect there are some parents
Seducing perf
I'm not friends with any of them
And when I picked up
Carly from the house
Go with our daughter
I really don't watch it, it's there now go ahead
NR used Honda
Where are our friend I've come to help and we had
Abandon the little
Car seat in the back and as we're driving back from Mount Sinai
A friend asks
If we stopped at a stoplight and there's like a CVS or Duane Reade outside
Neighbors are like
Right diaper
Anythink
Oh my God I think it also made us could disappear
Because I think
We never walk around with a hubris
No and notion that we knew better
And that the process of Discovery in the process
Learning hat was
Constant
A team effort
Yeah and I think
You know we would never be in a position to help my God we know exactly how things are in wedding should be done or houses and pregnancy be done
When we learned it that you know by the seat of my pants and
We embrace the people who are courageous enough to do that as well I mean a lot of entrepreneurs
Have like
A spouse who will let you know.
Teach music lesson
Beside or
You know we'll be school teacher or a lawyer or have some kind of income coming in like
You guys did not have a plan B
Cuz you're both in this
Now this is the high wire
Yaldo I think back like
I would have hated to be married
An entrepreneur
One you're like
Never see
And they're just totally stressed out
And I think that it was
Super super stretch
Full
Like really
Dangerous
Painful and complicated and so many ways and it was the most
Romantic amazing exciting exhilarating thing on the other side and it was literally both
Like you're building something
From scratch and it was like
In the thick of it on your hiring these people or something
So exciting to be doing it together Carley Roney and David Liu founders
The knot
Since 2011 lyrics
Expanded their Lifestyles empires not called
The XO group
And it includes a site about
Pregnancy called the bump
What about home decor call the nest and a website called how he asked which is a marriage proposal planner
Hutu
In 2014 David and Carly both step down from the day-to-day running of EXO
Which means
What time do the kids
For hanging out with friends and never according to Carly
Ever
Serving paella
And please do stick around because in just
A moment
We're going to hear from you
About the things
Your building
The first
Thanks to one of our sponsors
Swell investing
An impact investing platform
That identifies
High-growth companies solving today's
Biggest Environmental
Social Challenges
Claim your
$50 bonus
Swell investing.
Cam
Tilt
Hey thanks so much
For sticking around because it's time now for how you built that
Turn up the volume on your device
For just a second
Play the sound for you it's sick
I know the subtle but I think you'll know what
Poke a needle scratching
Hang on vinyl which is a kind of a cool sound right full of romance and anticipation
Especially if
If you grew up with it and even
If you didn't
I started
Being really a student records when I was a kid I would go through my parents record collections and
Play Herb Alpert has Creedence Clearwater Revival
In the late 1980s when Mike Dixon was growing up.
In Wichita Falls TX
Then I just
Was always fascinated with the fact that you had to really interact
Music in a physical way to pull the record out of the sleeve put it on the turntable and play it
Is Michael older he started hanging out in clubs and recording some of his friends band
And a lot of them wanted to put their songs on vinyl because
As we've already established by those kind of cool
But to cut a vinyl record at a legitimate pressing class
Is expensive
Your general investment was about $2,000 and if you can sell
500 copies Euro
Definitely not going to break even
Last time Mike discovered that if you just want to do a really limited run of Records like say
A 20 or 30 you can learn to do it yourself
With something called a record lathe a record Lee it's basically looks like a large turntable and the needle is
Vibrating is the disc turns underneath it and the sound wave is etched into the disc
Old record labels in recording studios or radio stations in the 1940s and 50
And you can still find them usually in a Dusty Attic or of course
EBay
I got really obsessed with the machines
I've bought everyone that I could find and eventually I had so many machines I was having
Bands from out of town come over to my kitchen
And cut record straight to the Lay's in the other room
The drummer would be
Right next to the sink
The guitar player and bass player would be next to the refrigerator
And I would be
Getting the records while they play the song
Anyway this is all happening in Olympia Washington
And 2010-2011 and I should mention that in real life
Mike was teaching High School
But he's also got this vinyl record label going and eventually he moves out of the kitchen and into
To a studio and then into the world to small events and pop-up festivals where he
Uses his portable record lathe to Cut vinyl on the spot
And then in 2012 Mike and his partner got a phone call we got a call from
Converse about cutting records for Bank of the XX at their Coachella VIP party
What's a Coachella
Huge execs also pretty huge and family Mike and his partner Chris are at the big party
With to record lathe making vinyl dubs of Jamie XX for like 200
The attendees would go and listen to some samples and they say I want the song of the ace I want the song of the
B-side and then we would cut it for them right there
And then they walk away with
A disk they can take home and play and show their friends
Hate I want this in my party I need this my activation or at my Festival
Mobile vinyl recorders be quitting teaching job he moved to Tucson Arizona
And now he and Chris do about one event a month making vinyl record dubs festivals parties
People making about a quarter of a million dollars in Revenue doing quite possibly
Coolest job ever
It's something that I fell into and yeah I can't imagine having a cooler job either
You can find out more about mobile vinyl recorders
Facebook page
And of course
If you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org would love hearing what you're up to and thanks for listening to the show this week
If you want to find out more or hear previous episodes of How I built this. Npr.org
Please also subscribe to our show on Apple podcasts or however you get your podcast
You can also write us that's HIV tea at npr.org
Sweetest at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Faulkner from Teen Arab Louis composed the music
Thanks also to neva Grant
Sunrise Mexican for Tamiflu
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Newark
Gyros
How I built this
NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com