Support for this in
NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from VSP individual Vision play
Entrepreneurs innovators and creators
Stop overpaying for eye exam
Quality Glass
You can buy vision coverage on your own
Learn more at need VSP coverage.
So really quick before we start the show
I want to tell you about a live event we are about to do in
Portland Oregon
Thursday Mesa
XVI
I'll be talking with Seth Tibbott he's the founder and
CEO of
Tofurky
The show is supported by American
Express and our other Live Events
Sold out fast so
To get tickets
Go to NPR presents. Org and
See you in Portland
So there are no shortages
Dating apps
Ranging from free apps
The members only two ones that are based on quiz shows and pet preference
The Today Show
Is the story of to date
Tinder and bumble
And the woman who helped
Start the bus
He first ran this episode with Whitney Wolfe
October of 2017
Enjoy
I quite frankly thought I was at the very bottom of my Barrel I mean there were days where
I didn't want to live I mean the internet to find me the article called
The most ugly names in the world the people on Twitter saying the ugliest things but
But through all of this pain and struggle I still had an itch to create
And so I kind of sat down and said I can start something right now and I can change what I hate
That I see in the world
NPR
It's how I built this
A show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories
Behind the movement
They felt
I'm gay
How Whitney wolves
Exit from
Hinder
Aspire to build bumble
A Kinder gentler dating app
Where women
Make the first move
There was a time believe it or not
When internet dating men
You weren't
Awkward or both
It wasn't something you talked about openly
But today
It's the complete opposite
Because the Internet
And dating apps
So much easier and
More efficient to meet Lots
Lots of people
It's more less frictionless
Is no awkward phone calls or
Courtship rituals are
To face rejection
There's something almost
Transactional about the whole thing
And it's no exaggeration to say that
Even though they've only been around for
5 years or so
Dating apps have
Pretty much
Transform dating
And if you love them
You can thank Whitney Wolfe
Or you can blame her if you hate that because Whitney was part of the dating app Revolution
She was one of the founders who helped create
Tender which is now one of the biggest dating apps in the world
Whitney left
Tender under difficult circumstances
Sansa circumstances
Can't legally discuss but as you will hear
It was a time in her life where she came under intense online abuse
And that experience would Inspire her to build bumble
Which is a difference
Kind of dating app
And today
Just
3 years since
It's launch
Bumble is one of the top dating apps
In the US
But the story of how Whitney got into that world at all
Well
Like many of our stories it starts with
A little bit of luck
Right after she graduated from college at Southern Methodist University
In Dallas
I was just
Kind of going day by day
Flooring and and being okay with that right
I think
To my family I almost
Was
I don't think it was
Proud
My daughter went on to do a
It's right I was in this
Weird place
So I kind of moved in with my mom in California
And I went to LA one afternoon
To visit A girlfriend of mine
And ended up at a dinner
Where
I
Met a couple people
One of which
Went on to be the CEO of
Tinder
This was Sean rad
Yes
And he had told me how he was
Going to be the general manager of this
Incubator that would be launching all sorts of
Alternative
If an apps and they were looking
At the time they were focused on one app which was a consumer loyalty app
Call Cardiff I kind of like a digital punch card
For your favorite coffee shop for your favorite whatever it is and you told you about this
This dinner party yeah we were just having dinner or just a few of us and
I said well that sounds really interesting and when he asked what I was doing is that you don't really looking for a job I think I could
Probably help you Market your app
And he said why do you call me tomorrow and come in for an interview so I called him at 8 a.m. the next day I think he was alarmed and
Surprised that I actually called him
And I end up going in for an interview it worked out
Started working from home right away and then I moved to LA
For this
For this incubator
Yes for Cardiff I was the app
There been really no talk
Tender yet and my job is very much focused
Chordify so I started working full-time
And while we were getting kardify off the ground you know I spent a lot of time going door to door to door in LA to
Different
Restaurants and
Boutiques and so on and so forth and trying to sign them up and
I struggled with it because there's too many moving parts right and so
I mean you have to get the store on board
And then once the stores onboard you have to help
But the customer has the app
What were the stores interested when you came in but they like it
No
To be honest
A very few people were interested
I think it was really how you positioned it and I learned I learned a lot
True through that experience
Because
You know one pet could go one way and you say something a little different the next time I go in a completely different way
And so I really
Realize that it's not so much about
The what
It's the
The how or the
Why you should do this right like this is why you need this instead of
What you what you need right and so it was really interesting crash course in
In marketing and sales
But you are not
Attack Force
Necessarily you just really interested
Great
I wasn't even interested in Tech I was just interested in the
The the way it had reach
The way that Tech
Hood
Expand beyond the walls
Right
I went through college with no Instagram and so
Instagram really be
Became huge right as a graduated
And then you
Thoughts of four billion dollars and I think everyone kind of went
Well yeah and this was kind of like a
And I opening
Moment for my
My peers
And so
Didn't I mean
Did you put it like a sense of excitement.
Put on something big or did you know pretty soon after
Not going to work
No you know I think everyone was really excited and very hopeful and it was a beautiful app
I think everyone really wanted it to happen and I remember we're all sitting around like we're going to be the next big thing and
And then shortly thereafter I think we started getting excited about this side project Matchbox
Which
With what became tender but it
The time it was Matchbox
Which was supposed to be a dating app
Yeah it was like a flirting app
It was like connecting people to flirt right
And after we were really unable to get kardify to gain significant
Traction
I think we all know you know
The first
Few of us
Kind of like
Maybe we need to shift gears you know and I was
22 years old I just come out of college I was thinking very much like
College students
This will work and I think I was so excited about the fact that they're
What's something that I and my friends would use First
If I twitch
Something a person would have never used
And again it was not a
New idea you have to think about what existed already
Dozens of dating apps flirting apps
Connecting apps
I mean there was already the Behemoth which was match.com right
And we sat on the same floor as match
Nli
Sosa was
Was building tender
Blake Parvin idea to build like more of these
Dating type
Products are
So tender was not my idea I've never said it
Is My Idea ever I became a co-founder of Tanner via my marketing contributions in my early
Involvement in getting it launched and getting it out there
So
I've heard about 30 completing
Stories of
What the original idea was Andrew who really cares at this point
I mean it is what it is and it was to connect
People around you you know if you see
See someone that you want to talk to
2 across the room how do you
How do you talk to them
Without
You know
Feeling awkward I think
Where we went
In a very unique Direction was marketing at Millennials and I just don't think that had ever been done in a successful way
And what was the actual product
What was the app what it look like
It was very similar to what it looks like now is just a very early version of it so you just
Swipe left or right on people that actually
When I first saw that there was no swipe
It was like a tapping like a card game originally
And was it called Tender by that
No we played with so many different names I mean
Maybe going to be flirt and then it was maybe going to be
I mean there's so many different things
I was going to be and
Tender ended up sticking
So you're so you're thinking I like this thing has legs
And so what did you do how did you do
Yeah I remember thinking to myself that it would work at SMU
And I remember I
Took the guys into a meeting
And I gave them my little sorority fraternity
Roll out pitch
And said
I'm going to show up on Monday when I go to chapter meetings I'm going to run to the sororities
Eternity is going to get everybody on it
And then it's just going to take off at SMU
Yes at SMU
And so I got the green light
Go do this and we had
Very very very very minimal marketing materials I think I had three or four t-shirts
That we talk
That had tender on it and then I had to get really crappy so when I landed in SMU
Funny I was talking to my girlfriend about this the other day
My good girlfriend who now does the weather in La she was a year younger than me so she hadn't graduated yet
And I took a picture of her
And then I took a picture of one of my guy friends on campus
Drop them into the match screen like a
The tender screen
And I wrote a big thing on top of it saying find out who likes you
ICampus
And I save the file and I took it to the FedEx
Across the street from SMU and we printed
Copies
And I
Offered a bunch
People around campus $20 bills
Help me
Put them everywhere I mean
People's windshield
Under dorms
Everywhere everywhere everywhere and then
Monday night I rallied all of my friends that were still in school cuz again I just graduated a lot of friends
Younger
And we've made our round
We went to the sorority houses and gave a pitch
Got up on chairs and told all the girls
You know you have to download
Because
College is all about meeting people and right now you only have access to the
The people that you hang out with every weekend and it's a really
Close minded it for you no experience and you guys need to meet all the
Describe people on campus and there's all these really cute guys waiting for you on the app
We rushed and got all of these women to download the app
And then we ran as fast as we
Because to the
The Fraternity Row
And when
The Frat houses and said a different pitch and said
Hey guys
No other way to access
Casino hundreds of sorority girls right now
Download the app because they're all waiting for you they've all just downloaded this app and they're waiting for you to like them
And so
Yeah I know it's so ridiculous
But you have to picture you had to listen me how's it going to work
You were hustling this thing
Yes I think that would be an accurate
Representation
And so the next day I remember
You know we looked at the download numbers and hundreds of people had downloaded overnight and hundreds was bigger than the downloads
We got on chordify over months and so you know I'm looking at hundreds of downloads and I'm like we made it
Find the next Facebook right.
Just being
Super
You know a little disconnected from reality probably not that
Distances we would eventually discover so you go back to LA
Like What's Next Step
I can't remember if I went straight back to LA if I went straight to Utah because
I went and did the same thing at University of Utah
Which seems weirdly
That that one
Tenderete a new people there you know and it's funny I called this a long time ago I said to everyone on the
The team I said guys watch
BYU
Will be one of our biggest markets one day because
In the BYU at the LDS College in in Provo Utah
And they're all expected to get married by
By the end of college like that is the excitation
That's why I said I promise
I think BYU will be one of our biggest markets and I think
Half of Utah wind up getting married because
Tinder
Tinder became massive
In Utah BYU campus oh yeah
Wow
2013 you know
Wizard feeling like this is just
So amazing so exciting
Are you kidding yes
I mean
I lived
Breathe dreams
I was in golf
I mean my friends didn't want to talk to me anymore then I go cache
Contact. Tender again
No it was such an exciting time and
Again it's worth noting
Tinder was group app
Right it was not just me it was not just
One of the guys is not
Just one of the other guys
This was really
Teamwork
So
And go do something
We need that we don't often do in the show which is
I would you skip over a / 8
A few years went
Tinder was growing in
Dating app
Millions and millions of users
Because they're legal reasons
Why you can't talk about certain things
I'm just going to say I'm going to
Explain briefly
That you left
10 Durant way
Under pretty difficult circumstances you had been
In a relationship with one of the other co-founders
Where's that broke down
And so
Left
And it was a sexual harassment lawsuit and that
Settled in
Ask about that
But all the sudden you were you were all over the tech press
People
People caught wind of this lawsuit
Text messages that were sent
Q70
Republican flodgin
And all this time you were the public eye in and you were
I guess like twenty-four what 24
25 of the time
I was 24 I turn 25
A few days later
And you were the main target of of a lot of the attention
Surrounding
So real quick I'm going to jump in in
Just say I have absolutely no comment on anything
Lawsuit
And I have no comment on
You know any of the allegations or anything
But
The way
The people online
Spoke about me
The way
Both
Reporters
And complete
Strangers you know internet
Twitter
Comment section
It was
It it jolted me
In such a way it it completely robbed me of every last
Sounds of confidence
Ants that I may have ever had
Listen I was not
I was not
A famous person in my life
Salt Lake City
Parents
Quite frankly just
A normal professional right like that's just
Who I was
And to have
The New York Times calling
Extended relatives
And to have
The Daily Mail knocking on the back window at your apartment when you're not even there
And
To have
Your
Personal
Emotions
Being turned into caricatures on
Tech blogs and mainstream media
TMZ I mean
It was
Really truly
How did you display get through the day
I I quite frankly
Thought I was at the very bottom of my Barrel I mean there were days where
I didn't want to live
I didn't want to get out of bed
I felt
Like it was stamped across my forehead
And when I say it was stamped across my forehead
That was fifty different things
That was the article calling me the most ugly names in the world
That was
The people on Twitter
Saying ugly things
I mean the internet to find me
For a moment
Time and
I I wanted to die
Yet I had to
Make this bigger than myself
Right like this is bigger than me
Meaning
I have people in my life that I have
Be there for I have parents
If I have friends
I need to continue my career I'm 24th that's B25
I am not going to
Just
Call it a day at 25 I mean am I you know like there was a lot of that
And
After I was able to pay
Take myself off
The bath mat crying
I
I was able to
Through the fog
See the real problem
And the problem was not
Or the media or the story or what happened the problem was
The lack of online accountability
That
Human beings are exposed to every single day
And what it made me realize was
You know whatever I felt was going on online
This is what goes on a 13 year old phone all day everyday
And it scared me
Was it impossible to ignore that 7 could you have just shut that out
No
It was a possible
It just became this
Obsession and
It really messed
With my psyche I mean it and it made me
Really
Not right for a while I mean I didn't really socialize I
I kind of
Became a Hermit for
2 years and what I did during those two years was I work
My tail off I mean
I worked
So hard
And
What I
Had realized was you can't kill ambition
You can kill confidence but you
Can't kill Drive
Through all of this
Pain and struggle
I still had an itch
Inside of me too
Create
And I missed
The feeling of
Creating all day and
Building
And think something grow and
Engineering it to grow right you know marketing it
And so I kind of sat down and said
I can start something
Right now
And I can have an impact
And I can change what I hate
That I see in the world
When we come back
How Whitney took that idea
And turned it into bumble
I'm guy riding listening to how I built this
NPR
Support for NPR comes from Gemini presenting this message
Gemini is the regulated licensed Exchange
That makes it easy
To buy Bitcoin and other cryptocurrency
To your long-term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely on Geminis mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are insured and protected
With state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open up free account
Gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Support also
Comes from betterhelp
Betterhelp offers licensed professional counselors who specialize in
Tennis shoes such as depression stress and
Anxiety and more
Connect with your professional counselor and a safe and private online environment
At your convenience
Get help at your own time and your own pace
Schedule secure video or phone sessions plus chat and text with your therapist
Visit betterhelp.com built to learn more
And get 10% off your first month
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
Apps that can be open from anywhere in 5 min
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
By the time she was 24 years old
Whitney Wolfe had already helped launch what are the world
Biggest
Dating apps
Tinder
But after she left the company in everything that would with its up online bullying in
Severe depression
What do you want to
Get away from all that she wants
Get away from dating apps and build something new something
A little more kind
So I started working on this concept called Mercy
What was going to be was
Female only social network
Women only use compliment
They would no longer be able to
You know comment on appearance or hurt their
Hurt each other's feelings
Or use social media to bully right
It was the antidote to what I
I experienced online
And
I
Started working on this end
Had
You know my marketing plan mapped out and I
I was thinking about doing that and I was approached by
Minot business partner Andrey andreev
And he is
Incredible
Talented entrepreneur
Based out of London
He is built
So a lot of berries
Successful companies
Send
His current very successful company is called Badu and it is the world's largest dating platform
It is massive
Overseas
I mean we're talking
I think I have something
320 million red
I like they're part of that club of only LinkedIn and Facebook and Instagram like those
Big big big crazy numbers
And he said
Sorry to connect
The summer I know that's probably not the best time for you but I'd really love to hear what you're up to
And so
His initial
Intent was to hire me as their CMO their Chief marketing officer
Scrappy-Doo
And I said you know I'm flattered that's great however
I mean
Essentially not
Higher I'm supposed to start my own business and I want
But to be mission-driven and I don't want to work in dating like that's just not
Going to be my future
And he said okay so tell me about this vision of yours and what
What you going to do when
How you going to build this into a huge social platform and I told him I vision and
Yes and
He could hear and feel my passion for
This platform and he said you know what
You need to build this but you need to do it
And I
I decided I'm not doing and I said I don't think you understood me
I'm not going back into dating like that's not happen
And he said no no no this
This hat
What you're trying to do
Needs to be done in dating
And I thought to myself you want maybe maybe he's got a point maybe dating is broke
Right like maybe maybe connecting is broken Beyond just being a young woman talking to a young woman in junior high May
Maybe this is something that affects us at all ages
And so we kind of did a handshake deal instead of here we can build a company
And
We formed an incredible partnership where
I was founder and CEO I could build my own team my own Vision my own brand
But we would have access to his resources Beyond just money and that was
Something that was never going to happen
Twice
And you didn't know at this point you didn't know what
That was going to be
No
It's a really wasn't until a couple of weeks later when we brought on you know
I called
Crystals in skin ceramic who had worked with that Tinder there really
Really talented designers and you know in order to build a great
Brandon
And product you have to have a great
Define arson so
I brought them on board they had their own apt
Times that I wanted to come on as consultants and so
Once we were all kind of together I think there was like 10 of us in the room or something or
We're sitting outside in
Andre said okay so what is this
Product line
And I said
I think I have it
I always wanted
Text the guy first
To go after what I wanted
In terms of if I saw a cute guy in class I always wanted to talk to a guy but I was never allowed to
Because society and my friend said no
Pyside we're going to reverse-engineer this
And this is how the products going to work
You're going to mutually match with
Each other but
Women hats
They 24 hours to do it
Because it would give them you know
Kind of incentive
And if they don't the match
Pierce Brown
And
This will
Change the Dynamics of how we
This will put the ball in her Court
Freddy same-sex matches
You follow the same rules minus
Women making the first
Rights of two women match either woman can reach out if
Two men match either man can reach out however they do still have to follow that you go first in 24 hours and then you follow with
24 hours
Like completely different from from everything else it was was out there the time
Completely different
Dating apps
I think I imagined
Are most mostly guys are signing up
Well
My theory at that time was
They hadn't been built for women
Let's just look at this from from the basic
Men are raised
From very early age
To be the go-getter in a in a heterosexual relationship
Go get her
GoGo make the move right
And women on the flip side or trained
Play hard to get
So sure you're telling men
To be overly aggressive and hear your telling women
To be the inverse of that and so now you're at your training to human beings
To act in
Opposite directions
Each other
And so what you do when you do that is you
Set both
Up for failure
You set the man up to be constantly rejected
And you set the women up to be at risk of
Of aggression
Abuse
Right and so
Here we have this world
The behave this way now add another element
The profile write a digital
Shield
Where you can hide behind a username or profile photo and you don't have to be accountable
And so
When you when you put women in control you completely reverse the roles
Soaps she now
Has
The confidence
To go after what she's into
And the man on the other end
Doesn't feel rejected he feels flattered
And then all of a sudden you've balance
The behavior
So so so where did the name bumble
The name bubbles actually really funny so a woman who was a really actually a great
Mentor to me for the first
Couple of years a bumbler name
Michelle Kennedy
She named it on a whim one day because it was such a
Struggle I wanted Bumble to be mocked
The Moxie like you've got moxie
You've got courage right
Because you'd have Moxie made the first move
And unfortunately there is a really powerful company that exists somewhere in America
Trademark
Every format of the word
So we couldn't get that and then we were sitting there for weeks on my gosh it was a disaster we had probably a thousand words in the Run
And then one morning she said you know
I think she
Funny enough I think she called her husband a bumbling idiot she's got this really horrible British accent
She said what about Bumble
And I said
No way like ethics Bumble that the Bumble and Bumble the hair product I hate it
And then Andre was like bumble bumble I love Bumble and he checked the domain and we could get their domain
It was a miracle like in what world could we get Bumble but we couldn't get Moxie we couldn't get all these other words
And so after that I was talking to who she ended up becoming one of my shoes my third higher
Her her
Her family are really
Close friends of mine
I was talking to her mom in the kitchen with a k
About Bumble for a nap and she was like oh like be the queen bee of bumble
Find your honey on Bumble and she started throwing out all these really cute slogan I don't like it done
Perfect branding opportunity
Hives and bees and building your your hive and queen bee the women make the
The first move it was perfect.
So you
Andre
Contacts yuan July 2014
If I'm if I timing is right
You launched
Bumble by the end of that year
Cracked we worked really really hard when you when you first launched it
Were most people signing up man
Initially
No no no
Even even split how did you
How did you get people to sign up how did you get the word out about it cuz there's a lots of competition in this faces
Tons and tons of dating app how did you
How are you able to tell people that and get to know
What to do
Well I kind of had a little bit of a Playbook I may be done at 1
What's before so
I went right back to SMU
This time
Decked out in yellow and
I went back into all the sororities
And I I spoke from the heart listen
I have lived
Through
The pain point
Male-dominated
I have felt
I know what it feels like and guess what
Every Other Woman in that sorority house
Chances are she's healthy
So you know I'm speaking from the heart and I'm speaking to them about how they can be empowered and they make the first move and they go
After what they want
Me and my early team members I mean
There's the girls are at my office right now they're still with us
We went in there and we took pizza boxes with stickers on it and offered a piece of pizza to the fraternity boys that would get on at we
Wrapped cookies in Bumble stickers we took
All sorts of goodies and
We kind of growth hacked our way to
Success
Jump out of the story for a sec
Migas
I asked you about this idea that
That
Dating apps even even Bumble with
Your mission or purpose to empower women
Even an app like bumble
You know does it
Contributed
Culturehook
Well
So here's with interest
If the hookup is taking place and the woman is empowered and feels comfortable and confident in that
Then I say more power
To that
You know I don't care what you do on Bumble if you want to
You know
Spend the rest of your life with someone you meet on Bumble phenomenal if you want to hang out with him for only
A night
But you're going to wake up the next day and you're not going to feel terrible about yourself
That's what this is all about it's about reverse
Engineering
The Dynamics
How men and women
Peel and
Bumble is not just a hookup I mean
I can't tell you how many emails I get a day about
Bumble weddings Bumble babies Bumble engagements now we're launching bumble bizz
We have
Hundreds and hundreds of thousands if not in the millions of the
Is point of active
BSF user
Which are
You know young women matching with other young women kind of in that merci capacity I spoke about earlier they're finding roommates
They're going on trips together they're building Social Circles in new cities
It's really not a dating app anymore
I rather that that you guys have zero
There's zero tolerance for sexism
On Bumble but if
Two people are communicating on Bumble how do you police that how do you enforce
So that's a great question and it's actually a very tricky one
So
We have
Zero tolerance for bad
Behavior
But it requires a little bit of work from our user
Because
We also want to
Respect your privacy
Right
However if somebody is in a conversation and someone says something inappropriate
We have very easy reporting tools and once something is reported we do review it
And if there was bad behavior that user is banned
For life there are no Second Chances
We really take it seriously if you need us like
Work one click way
Do you ever
Rent any backlash from from you know people who
Who say
You know who are offended in some ways
The disempowers women that if it does it does it make
Some people angry
Yes
Bumble gets a lot of that you know just last week we
Became under attack
From this website called the
The daily Stormer a Neo Nazi site
And we had upwards of a hundred men standing up
Rats
We actually had a
Police that are off
That's all we got wow
They were emailing my employees
Calling my employees calling me
Leaving the most vulgar messages
Because you're you're self-proclaimed
Feminist organization
Female empowerment is not something that they
They believe in unfortunately
Fina we get this to that the bullying
Now I don't let that dozen
Hurt my feelings anymore cuz I know the
These people are just atrocious but
It fuels me the anger fuels me to
Try harder at work and try and
And you know change this misogynistic
Mainz Athletics
And so now we're putting such an emphasis to get all these people off of our app if there are any we're hoping there's not
We now have a whole new set of moderator is looking for
I hate symbols and Hate
Speech on our platform
We're really just trying our best
To build a clean Safe Community
It's been 2 and 1/2 years
You launched
Does company
Cracked you have how many active users now
20 million registration
That's I mean that's pretty amazing
20 million downloads of the app
Since you launched and when will you know that you have really
Created this
Hugely
Powerful
Thing when you got a hundred million
Billion
I'll never feel like we've made
We we got to just keep going I am mean
It's funny I used to say to myself
When we have 1 million we have 5 million when we have 10
And now we're here and I'm like you know what we always need to evolve and be better and try harder and
Have bigger reach-in better region
Once we have that reads when you start over and do it in a different vertical how much of of your you know of
Your story
Through Tinder and and Bumble now
Is lock and how much it would
You know luck is a funny word I don't
I don't know if I call any of those lucky
Feel
You know
I think
Luck is probably a certain element but if p
People think I just you know
Was at the right place at the right time and just
Stopped my fingers and twirled a couple times
Here's bumble
I mean they're really wrong this is been
We're talking all day everyday
Down
Highs lows and
And Laser
Focus
So you guys are still
Really young
Company
Do you
Do you like
Stay up at night
Worrying about a competitor or somebody else
Coming in and just
Yelp
Totally replacing you
We
Really truly aren't
Super worried about competition for 1 re
I really believe anybody can copy
Product anyone
I'm at the UT campus
Speaking to you right now I could go to the engineering school
Probably find five really talented young engineers and they can build bumble
With the right support
Somebody could rebuild any piece of
Technology
Engineering
However
You cannot just copy someone's brand and Beak
Become them
There has to be
Authenticity when you build a brand and there has to be true purpose
And so yes you're right
Anybody could go and build a
Competitor version of bumble
But where I don't think they can just come in and and
Sweep us off our feet is
I don't know if there's another group
People with the exact same
Story or the exact same
Mission and motive
And
That goes back
What I lived through that summer of 2014
What landed on my phone
Every morning
And it was
I almost
Built My
Remedy to
The the heart
Ship that I personally was going through end
Bumble safe
Text Whitney Wolfe founder of the dating app
Humble by the way Whitney now goes for the name Whitney Wolfe herd
Because she got married last
And that's how she met her husband through bumble
Bumble has not yet gone public but a few months ago after reports of a possible IPO
Bloomberg intelligence value the company has 1.1 billion dollars
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you
About the things
Your building
But first
A quick message
One of our sponsors
Smart Water
Inspired by fresh thinkers
Stories you're listening to
Smart water has more ways to hydrate
Smart Water alkaline 9 + pH
SmartWater antioxidant
Added selenium
Smart Water
Pretty smart
Hey thanks so much for
Sticking around
I know for how you built that and today we're updating a story from about a year ago
Turn up the volume for a second because
I got the sound that I want to play for you
Subtle butt
Think you'll notice
Poke a needle scratching
Which is a kind of a cool sound right full of romance and anticipation especially
If you grew up with it
And even
If you didn't I started being really interested in records when I was a kid I would go through my parents are Collections and
Play Herb Alpert
Creedence Clearwater Revival
When Mike Dixon was
Was growing up in Wichita Falls Texas was always fascinated with the fact that
You had to really interact with the music in a physical way
The pulled record out of the sleeve put it on the turntable and play it
Is Michael older he started hanging out in clubs and recording some of his friends bands
And a lot of them wanted to put their songs on vinyl because
As we've already established
Finals kind of cool
But to cut a vinyl record at alleged emit pressing plant is expensive
Your general investment was about $2,000
And if you can sell
500 copies you are definitely not going to break even
This time Mike discovered that if you just want to do a really limited run of Records likes
Say 20 or 30
You can learn to do it yourself
Was something called a record lathe
The record Lee it's basically looks like a large turntable
And the needle is vibrating as the disc turns underneath it and the sound wave is etched into the disc
And would have seen these old record lives in recording studios or radio stations in the 1940s and 50s
50s and you can still find them usually in a Dusty Attic or horse
On eBay I got really obsessed with the machines I bought everyone that I could find an
Eventually I had so many machines I was
Having bands
From out of town come over to my kitchen and cut record straight for the Lay's in the other room
The drummer would be
Right next to the sink
The guitar player and bass player would be next to the refrigerator
And I would be cutting the records while they play the song
Anyway this is all happening in Olympia Washington
And in 2010/2011 and I should mention that in real life
Mike was teaching High School
But he's also got the spinal record label going
And eventually he moves out of the kitchen
And into a studio and then
Into the world
His small events
Pop-up Fest
Staples Warehouse
He uses his portable record
CAD cut vinyl on the spot
And then in 2012
Mike and his partner
Got a phone call
We got a call from Converse
About cutting records for Bank on the XX at there
Coachella VIP party Coachella
Huge
The XX
Also pretty huge
Assembly Mike and his partner Chris are at the big party
With to record lathe
Making vinyl dubs of Jamie XX
For like
200 people the attendees would go and listen to some samples
And they say I want the song of the ace I want the song of the B-side and then we would cut it for them right there
And then they walk away with
I did ask if they can take home and
Play and show their friends
And after that event
We had a ton of people that said hey I want this in my party I need this it
My activation or at my Festival
After launching a company
With his teaching job
Tucson Arizona
And Chris have been making vinyl records and traveling around the world to places like Paris Canada and New York
Basically have the coolest job ever
It's something that I fell into and
Yeah I can't imagine having a cooler job either
Addiction is
Is the co-founder of mobile vinyl recorder
If you want to find out more about Mike or hear previous episodes
Hedgewar podcast
How I built this. Npr.org
And of course if you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org and thanks
Listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please do give us a review
You could also write to us at HRBT at npr.org
Did you want to send a tweet
How I built this
I sure was produced this week but Rachel Falkner with music
Pose by Rumpke mareblu
Thanks also to Julia
Kearny JC Howard
Alexa Grace Anna's Mexican Port Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Candice Lim
I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor.