Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
So really quick before we start the show
I want to tell you about a live event we are about to do in
Portland Oregon
Thursday May 6th
16th I'll be talking with Seth Tibbott he's the founder
CEO of toe
Tofurky
The show is supported by American
Express and our other Live Events have sold out fast so
To get tickets
Go to nprpresents.org
May 16th
Portland Oregon
You can also follow how I built this on
Twitter and Facebook to be the
First to know about our life shows
And out
To see you in Portland
I knew that something wasn't right and the next day they said that by you
They decided to replace me and George we put your furniture in
Storage and I remember thinking my furniture and my nick-nacks 40 years
Up stuff that I had accumulated and 50 cartons were put in storage
In the moment it felt like well damn if all these people who are my friend
Don't want me as their leader anymore then why do I want to be their leader
Grumman tr2 how I built this a show of activators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
Turn discounts into a multibillion-dollar Empire
Bitter battle that forced him
Chowking retail fashion
There are three main categories of customers
Obviously this is a slight oversimplification but
It goes a little like this
There are products for the top end of the market so think like a Birkin bag by Hermes
It costs around $20,000 in Arabic
It's only going to sell a small number of them a year
SL500 Birkin bags a year that's 10 million dollars in revenue and then there's the lower it
I'm so old lady for example a huge number of consumers can afford to buy their clothes and so they say
Sell a lot of stuff
T-shirts jeans button-downs for like 20 or 30 bucks a piece
There's a clear strategy with each approach
Store fashion brands can really hit the big time
Is in the middle range so imagine a Venn diagram of a person
Well now it again but also Target
That is a customer most fashion brands are hoping to attract the value shopper
White sound intuitive and obvious
That wasn't always the case if you wanted a suit for example in the 1960s or 70s
Settle for something that looked and felt
Well cheap inside George Zimmer had back in the early seventies when he was
The young suit salesman
Good suit was out of range for a lot of men and by the way George
Let's mention really hated shopping for clothes
And when they did they wanted to do it once maybe twice in a year so what
A place that solve this problem
A place where you could get a pretty solid suit at a good price but also a place that made it
Super easy to get in and out fast a place where while you were trying on your suit
The salesperson would come back to the dressing room with a stack of hand-picked button-down size socks
And shoes
To go with that suit
And the place that would do all the alterations on site
This was the idea behind Men's Wearhouse in what started out as a single shop in Houston
What eventually turn into a multi billion dollar clothing Empire with hundreds of stores across the U
George became the face of that Empire you probably remember those commercials of them back in the day
George would look at the camera and say
You'll like the way you look I guarantee it
But overtime is personality is charisma his vision
It created tension with the management and with the board and as you will hear
They threw them out
And they was ugly
But we'll get there
George Zimmer grew up in Scarsdale in New York
His dad worked for a discount men's clothing company called Robert Hall so obviously
Deadhead a huge influence
But it was his mom who really played an outsize role
Literally life
My mother
What is a
Truly remarkable
Woman
And she had both
Amazing
Strengths and qualities
That made us all proud
And then she had her own
Demon
Many of them connected to having been
An orphan which does carry
It's on baggage
But what she did for me
Which is
Something that
I didn't appreciate
When she was alive
But what she instilled in me
Was
This notion
That I was a
Special
Boy
And I would be able to
To do anything
I chose to do
In life and I must say
I've been a legend in my own mind
For decades
That's why I think we all know now
Confidence
Positive quality
I mean you say your mom and still this idea and you that you are special
Did you feel that when you were a kid that was assuming that because she said it you started to believe that
The truth is that I did not
But I think that
Because of her
Consistency in the way she
Handle this issue
That it did.
Enter my subconscious
And by the time I got the
The college
And shortly after college
I felt very confident
What about
Almost anything I tried
So you a 1966 ego off
College
The Washington University in St Louis
What do you remember about washing University
At the time I mean this is like
The height of
The Free Speech movement at Berkeley and student activism in the anti-war movement and what was
Sit like at Wash U
Well and it was fantastic
Often felt at the time that you spend in college
If you're fortunate enough
Can be the most
Positive
Years of your life
For me
I went to college
A sheltered
Young Jewish boy from New York
And
Because of what was going on in the streets
I became
Much more
Obey
Sophisticated
And politically aware
Person
Okay so you're at Wash U
Studying economics
Right and meantime back in Scarsdale
Your dad's business
Making clothing
How is it doing
Well when I went to college
His business
Wasn't it
Ascendancy
But he never really
Mastered
The art of making a
Prophet
In business
Although he did make
Small profit
You never really
In my opinion
Took advantage of what he might have been able to achieve what was your dad making clothes
Was he making inexpensive boys
Outerwear like what we called
Snorkel jacket
Out here they would be called
Ski jackets nylon
Shell
Yeah you also made more of an upscale
Boys raincoat
And when John John
Kennedy
Was standing at his father's funeral
And that
Famous boat owners
Salute
He's wearing my father's raincoat
Wow
Amazing I mean anyone listening can picture that image presumably he was manufacturing all
Call this in and around Scarsdale this is like the pre make your stuff in China era
Right well he ended up asking me in
Late 71
Since I had not gotten a job of any note I was substitute teaching
And my father and recognizing
His son was in danger of
Drifting away
Become a permanent hippie
Said to me
Why don't the two of us
Go to Asia
Because he wanted to look into manufacturing there instead of
The greater New York area
And when I came back to New York to make that trip
He informed me that
Something come up and eat couldn't do it
But he wanted me to go
In his stead which I did
Really that's
Beginning of Maya
Business
Experience
So 1971-d says Hey I want to think about making my stuff
In Asia can you go there
Where did you fly to
Why Pluto Osaka
My first stop
And we get to
What was known as Idlewild Airport
Alexandrite JFK right
It was called Idlewild
And
It was PanAm one
Flying from New York
Through Fairbanks Alaska
To Tokyo
And then I was switching
I'm flying down the wall soccer
Alright so you fly
From
New York
5 Fairbanks in Tokyo
Get to Osaka
What are you are you
Is 23 years old a tendon were you like a
Presentable
Were you
I was presentable
I told my father when he told me he wasn't
Making the trip that I didn't really
Understand is business well enough
To do this on my own
A Twitchy said
George they're going to love you in Asia
Because you're my
Elvis trial
Your number one son
And they're going to love the fact
That you're doing this
Because I can
So I would get up every morning
At about 5 in the morning
And start studying
Because I literally
Didn't know
Much about the manufacturing
Of clothing in
I would study from
Usually five to eight including
Going to the
Breakfast restaurant in the hotel
Which were
White glamorous
And
He was right
A lot of people
We're very
Excited
To talk to
The number one son
Who had made such a long trip because his father could make
And you were there on a fact-finding mission right you were looking for potential factories to work with
Yeah
My job
What's the fine
Factories
Give them samples
To make right
And then send them back to New York
And be sort of the middleman
Got any he was making
The decisions
Of course it was always about
Negotiating a price
The exact Fabric and I lived there for about 6 months old I ended up
Settling
In
Hong Kong
So did you find a factory that you decided this is the one that's going to work no I did not I found many
Factories that made samples
Which I dutifully sent back to New York
But
We didn't find
Any Factory that we could make a deal with
So after about six months
I came home and dog
When I got back to
New York
It was the 72 presidential
Election
And I actually got a job
In the McGovern campaign
Working in Chicago in the summer of 72
Charged up
What was called Grassroots fundraising
And I remember I moved to Texas on Election Day
Why
My father offered me a job
Dallas rapping is lying
Texas Oklahoma Louisiana
So you get back to the US
You work on the
McGovern campaign for a brief
Yeah
And then your dad sends you to Dallas
To represent
Him and his clothing company but why Dallas what
The
The rap He had there at
Quit so he had reps all over the country
And they were what that they would what would they do good
Department stores department stores
Specialty stores
By this time he had a
Thriving business
And
He was doing well
And I
Thought it was an opportunity to
Continue my
Carle careers
And I like living
In Dallas
It was fun
So you moved to Dallas in 72 and what
You start going to make an appointments and try to
We are making these raincoats and these jackets and you know
First 6 months
Okay I traveled the territory
Texas Oklahoma Louisiana
And the largest account
In my territory
Was in Houston
Which is where I ultimately started Men's Wearhouse is the account called Foley's
It was a Federated Department Store
And I went in and soul
Boys buyer
Sport coats
That were
I did my opinion
The correct workout you should have bought but I was too new on the job
To speak up
Let him make the order because it was in water sure
Then when they didn't sell
He told me
That he knew my father was the owner
Any like to return the coats
And I said well
We don't take anything back and he reminded me
That I could pick up the phone
Call my father
And get it done which I did
And we took back about 400
Or codes and you promised that you would give me a
Large order going forward and when I came in to get that order
A few months later informed me that they were dropping me
So I had about a 5-hour drive from Houston back to Dallas and
I decided that they didn't really understand
Not a retail apparel not only in Foley's but throughout my territory
I didn't think that they understood the idea of discounting which was really more
Northeast add to some degree in Chicago
But had not gotten into the South
I'm so what I decided to
Relocate from Dallas to Houston
And open the first Men's Wearhouse
Or maybe it was
I am truly
I mean you are
Your dad's rap
In Dallas
For 6 months or 6 months
And
You lose an account
And at some point you say
You know what I want to open up my own
Place
How did that happen how did that idea even come to you I'll tell you
Having been a
Student activists in college
Having been somebody that
Did not believe that capitalism
Was the end-all-be-all
What we needed
I did not like the idea
Having to execute
Nachos my father
But the sales managers
Vision
I always wanted to be able
Do have my own dreams
And the follow my own dreams
And so the reason I
The primary reason
I open Men's Wearhouse
Was
That
That it was a way for me
To become
My Own Boss
Create my own destiny
Follow my dreams
Okay so you are roughly 25
And what was her
A younger okay and before you even opened up Men's Wearhouse
What was your idea why did you think that suits
It was the right thing to get into
Well suits was what I knew
But how was it that you knew suits I mean was
Cuz I am understanding is that your dad's primary business was making clothing for boys
He'll expanded
So that is product assortment
We're
Outerwear like snorkel jacket
Lisa
Raincoats that have
Zip out linings that were
Fairly upscale
And then he started a line
Of Enix
Expensive
Suits and Sport
Right
And did you wear suit yourself
I almost never wore a suit
Until I went to Hong Kong
Why did you think the Houston was the place to go yeah
While I was living in Dallas
And going to Houston
Every month
And the way I explain this
Is that
Dallas was old money
Houston was new mama
So that
For a young upstart
Like myself
Trying to
Create a business
The chances were much greater in used
And in fact
Since I didn't really know anything about
The retail business when I open
Men's Wearhouse the only reason
That I was able to make it
Was Gus the city's growth
Was so extraordinary
That it
Coppertop for
What I didn't
Understand
Okay
So you decide
You are going to open up
A store that sells
Discount
Suits
In Houston in 1973
Did you start the company by yourself or did you do it with somebody else
Well noise
The way I'd I started it was
Harry Levy it been my
Fraternity brother
I know it was from Dallas
And I
Call them up and said
Would you like to move to Houston
And do this with me
And he said
What's in it for me
And I said well I give you a
Third of the company
43 Grant
Nice and how did you guys get the money to open up for store
So I got my inventory
From my father he became
My financial partner
The inventory wasn't suit slacks
And shirts better and jacket sets
And boy that worked was
That I had only $7,000
When this all began and that basically went
The first and last month
Rent
So there was really no money
As the company got ready to open
My father sent us
Several thousand
Suits
Sport coats
And slacks
As well as
Boss Steel
Rolling Rock
Which is what we use
Thrift Store Fixtures in the bible store
How big was that place
It was 6000 feet
So big place yes rent in Houston with a cheap
Well it was 3500 a month
Got it all right so
1973 Yuan Harry open the store Men's Wearhouse
Had to go well I remember
The first Saturday we were open
For business
We ran an ad
In the yard
Houston Chronicle
And in the Houston Post
We were selling sport coats for $25
Slacks for $10
And did not carry suits
Or shirts
Work by
We're up tailoring fact our first
Cash register
Was a mechanical
Old style NCR
That you would push the buttons
And it would come up in the window ya no sale
And that was how we started
And was it a hit right away
Well we did 3000 the first
Saturday and Monday we did $60
And so I would not say it was a success right away. Would you guys free
About that Monday no
Because my mother
Had always
Promise to me
That these things would work
So you are you guys are running this place and
Doesn't sound like it was
Throbbing decide when I first day it doesn't sound like you guys were really Breaking the Bank you know
Tune
Just crushing in those first two years
We weren't
We lost money in each of the first two years and then
We opened our second and a third store in Houston
Explain this to me you're losing money on the 1st store
But you go and you decide to open a second and
Third Store
Thinking that those will
Help you make more money
The marketing
In a major
Urban area
Are so high you can't really run
A single location
You need multiple locations when did you expand into jackets and ties and suits and
Belts and things like that
We started to get into
A broader product
Assortment
In the mid-to-late 70s
We first went right
Just suits
And we had a salesperson he was the
EVP
For our chapter in March
Based in Chicago that was what they were America's largest
Clothing manufacturer
And
He came to see us
And I said to him
They had the line Nino
Cerruti
And I said we'd like to buy that line
From you
And they said forget about it
Did I sell
Foley's iSell
And I said well let me tell you the whole story
We want to buy the line
Without the label
But we wanted 20%
Discount
Sobia white-labeled Men's Wearhouse
Nino cerruti suit but you would
Put your label on
Correct and he said
He said
Why would I do that
And I said you know Kenny
Why do we play a game
Nevada basketball
And if I can beat you
You'll give me that d off and if you beat me
I won't bother you again
The rest is history you beat him in the game
I beat him and we got
Nino cerruti suits
White label without a 20% purchase discount
Which enabled us to sell them moderately profitably at 1
199 when everybody else in America with showing them at 299
That was the acid
So I guess we'll wait for our chapter and marcher or any of the clothing manufacturers to sell more their suits
Play white label them
Even if they were selling to a lower price
Exactly
When did you first expand outside of Houston
In 1980 I came out
Did the Bay Area
On a vacation
And we were planning on opening up
In Dallas
Hazard
Next
Market
And I walk in New
Either Ruth Watkins or
Some other
Bay Area
Store department store
No it was a men's menstruacao
Clothing store
And it was not a
Regular price
100%
Wool
Suit
4 under
$300
We were selling
100% wool suit
For 199
So I
Went back to
Houston Inn
Gold my team that
We could pick up Dallas
Later
And we were going to go right to the Bay Area
Before things change
Where in the Bay Area
So we started
In the South Bay we opened in
Mountain View
San Jose
Fremont
And then we have one store
Opinion
Concord
So this is in the early 80s
Techboomers really
Java beginner
Presumably your customers were
That professional man yes
Mostly professional
And you opened up there and
What happened to people flock to it or or was it kind of again you know
Mixed results
I would say mixed results
We were not
Really success
Until
The mid-80s
In my opinion
What happens in the mid-80s
To make
Men's Wearhouse
Really successful
Well we were
Put under
Giraffes
Our bank
And not taxes
Call Tower Loan
And so we were putting
Difficult position they called you alone cuz they were getting worried about you
No it's
In the early 80s
There was a
General meltdown
All the banks
Mission Texas
And every Bank
Including our bank
Which was the largest bank down there
First City National
All of them
We required
Buy out of state bank
Right now
So we had to rethink our business mod
So I looked at all Redmond
And by then it was on
Computer
Printouts
And I noticed
That on about
Half of the inventory
There was a significant
Discrepancy
Between the
Ticketed price
And the selling
Meaning meaning what the selling price is much lower than what
The ticket price was
Yes because of
Promotional
Activity
In other words you have a sale
Correct
And you have regular sales
We did
So I made the decision
Change the model
And eliminate
Regular sales
You you decide
We need to stop holding sale
Lower our everyday prices
Basically send out the message that we just
That we offer
Low everyday price
Exactly
When you made the decision
Did you have a year of
Slow sales two years one year of slow sales
I mean it sounds like it was
You have a combination of a bank calling in your loan
Really low margins
Sounds like this change in strategy
Was kind of Hail Mary
Well I like the top is part of the
Was
Trying to
Suede people
That I knew what I was doing
Because they were questioning
Whether I knew what I was doing how did you know that you knew what you were doing I did
So did that degree
You could call it a Hail Mary
But I had been in the retail business
For a while by then
And I had a
Instinct
That this
Made sense
It made no sense to me
This constant
Garage
Abseil
It was though
Everybody in retail
Thought that the American Consumer
Was stupid
And actually
They're not as stupid
As those people thought when we come back
Just a moment by George Summers Hail Mary paid off in a big way
And the origins of that iconic slogan you're going to like the way you look I guarantee it
Stay with us and Gyros and you listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support also comes from fidelity
As a Fidelity wealth
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and
Protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations
Thanks for your full Finance
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Facts on the state of Market
Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs
You'll hear a range of topics
Disgust from the tech IPO landscape
Two China's economic Outlook
And much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
Cloud and Google Play and it gs.com podcast
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Capital One is reimagining banking
By offering accounts with no fees or minimum
That can be open from anywhere in 5 mins
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Welcome back to how I built this from NPR
It's 1986 and Men's Wearhouse is trying to pull out of an economic slump
George Zimmer
Just change the business model to focus on everyday low prices
Did get the message out
He decides to become the spokesperson
Are the commercials the Men's Wearhouse
You got all three
Service
Quality
And a good price George standing in front of what looks like a classroom
So what I did cuz we had training classes
Which I would give a presentation to
I found
I was very comfortable in those environment
Sure so I said
Set up a fake training class
And bringing three cameras
Filming from different angles
And we will just bring in random office employees
Ask me questions
I will answer them
And we will edit it into a good message saying what
Saying that we've got
Great suits and sportcoats
Here's why
And oh by the way
They're Priced Right
Clown
Why did you think that would be compelling I mean that sounds like the most
Boring real commercial ever come back
To my mother's
Words
It never occurred to me
And I could say this
About
Two dozen
Things in my life
That most people
Would say
Did it occur to you
That that might not work
I go
Quite frankly
Not really
So at what point did you order the
Very famous
Phrase
I think I ordered it in 86
And how did that happen it happened is an ad-lib
As I was at Living the commercial
I'm having an inner dialogue with myself while I'm
Speaking
Yeah I didn't have much
Time
Since I was in a
Live recording
And all I could think of was
I guarantee it
The beauty of I guarantee it was
Not so much
The words
Cuz the words are
As happy as you're going to find
Yeah but I when I started walking around
In my regular life
People were saying to me
Hey George
I guarantee it
And I knew a
That.
Was catching on
But I also have known something else
Which is
As long as people are calling me George
I think the companies
That I'm involved with
Will prosper
If they start to call me
Mr. Zimmer
I'll be worried so you essentially almost overnight become like the mascot
Men's Wearhouse
I did
And if the benefit is
That when you are
A spokesperson
For your own business
Of course you're doing it
To affect the external
World you want more business
But what happened
Is that and we were in
Retail business
With hundreds or
Thousands of employees
The workforce
Love the fact
That the boss
Is on TV
I know
I know George George
PennDOT
It was a great day
Part of the company culture
Soap by the late 80s you are still in Houston and the South Bay
We are Bob
15 stores in the Bay Area
Where in Seattle Portland
Dallas Sacramento
And what I'm still trying to figure out why didn't
A bigger company try an undercut you I mean
Clearly you got this
Thing going we are selling Nino cerruti suit people died Open Secret
That you were selling them for $100 less than a branded Nino cerruti suit without the label without the label but
If this is an Open Secret why wouldn't some other company come in and like Macy's or something company and try to do the same thing
Well I think that the answer is that many did
There were people that tried
The mimic what we did
But you know part of it is and I'm very
Proud of this I I did it
All the training originally in men's
And I used to say to our employees
Men look at going into a clothing store
Like going to the dentist office so their wife says to them
I made you a dental appointment
And it's like the worst thing that the man can imagine
So they put off coming in to a clothing store until they can know
No longer
Defer it any longer
And from that intuitive understanding we develop what we called
Shirts talking
So that when a man purchased a suit
While he was in the dressing room we would put together
Church ties belt shoes
Everything that would make
The outfit really jump then we presented to the customer
We were not in my mind
Pushy but we were
Not passive
Yeah sales people either
The result was
That our customers thought
We had great service
Because they perceive this
As service
And it drove a lot
Of Revenue
So basically man the thinking was Mendel want to spend a whole lot of time shopping
Jelly buying stuff
Have to
Karate going to go into going to try on the suit in the and the
Pants
But while they're in the dressing room where can I bring them
Like a pink shirt blue shirt and a white shirt were going to say
If you look right with a suit hear some great ties
And
And they would say thank you for making it easy for me I'm going to buy I'll take it all night walk out
Exactly
Wow
1992 you guys go public
The IPO brings in
A red light
13 million dollars
That's correct it doesn't sound like a whole lot for
Well I was never
Trying
To amass
The greatest Fortune
That I could
And
It turns out to have been
I think a very
Good decision because
Although we had an IPO that only raised
13 million
We Dine at 4:05 second.
Each secondary
Was that a higher
Value
Secondary stock offering
They're kind of like IPOs
I think the 1990s really was when he
Blow up ride run your riding a really strong economy
What else is going on why I mean cuz you now are going to cities all across the United States right
Right so what's going on that allows this expansion yr
Consumer habits
Changing
No I mean first of all
With the money that we got from the
IPO and secondary
We started opening
50 stores a year
Aura store every week
So if you can imagine each store Claus about a million dollars
In inventory
Insidious
All lacrosse
Write all 50 states
You hit I think a billion dollars in Revenue in 98
And then in the early 2000s the expansion
Continuous
1999 you start to rent out
Tuxedos
How did that happen What and why
So where we were at a training class
One of my regional managers at dinner with me inside
You know Georgia I went into a few
Tuxedo stores he was in Seattle
And you said
You know
This is exactly what we do
Fat people in clothing
Why don't we do this
And you said
I said let's try
And yeah.
12 stores up there
And I the first year
We did $1000000
Tuxedo rental shop Brazoria
Inside the store
Portneuf resection is light and it just said tuxedo rentals here exactly okay
Everybody in my organization
Hated the sight
Get why you doing tuxedo rentals We Gots every time you screw up a wedding
You lose
A customer
You know this is not a way to build a clothing business
So
We rolled it out into our stores
1/3
1/3 1/3 / 3 years
It took
5 years
Before the employees in the company
Stop complaining.
About being in this business
And I used to say to everybody
And it was it got to be
Redundant
Where I would say
A look
Dishes
Going to take a while
To develop but when it does
It's going to be amazing
And I guess there was a point
I read that something like one out of
5 suits in America was
Purchased at Men's Wearhouse
Correct that is astounding download
Particular chapter because this is going forward to 2011 you step down as CEO of Men's Wearhouse
House in
Doug ewert becomes the new CEO
And you picked
I did I I've been
Why did want to retire
And doggy been my
Siolo
And I've been doing a great job so I said to him you know Doug our offices were next door
I said I'm not retiring I'm going to come to work everyday yeah but you're running things day today
And I'd like you to get credit for that
You then become what chairman of the board Blackbird German executive chairman
Dedicate that I was still working
Just received a reality check
After you made that decision to step out away from being CEO did you really disengage
Company you found it in you started it did you really back away
I never told dog what to do
After he was made CEO
I said to him dog
You're the CEO
It's your decision
You make it the way you see it
Okay now
This is a moment where I guess
There begins to be considerable tension
Between you and the board
Yeah what started to happen
What kind of
Should have differences of opinion did you start to have with board member
I don't really know exactly what happened because
As it got closer to my
Termination
I was cut out a more and more
Of the discussions that the board
What's happening
But I give you a simple
Example
We on the division call K&G
Mkmg
Did 400 million
We had a hundred stores
It was a
Superstore in the sunset it was
25000 ft
And it was men's and women's
And the price points were below
Men's Wearhouse
And I said to the board
Can you dream provides a unique opportunity
For an offensive
And defensive strategy
And they didn't
Quite understand what that meant
And so what it means is
Men's Wearhouse
Stores
Were able to raise
The gross
Profit percentage
Buy a full 10%
Which is 1000 basis
Over a decade
Because
K&G
What's protecting
Our opening price point
And at the same time
Because K&G
Was a significant National
Presence
It prevented
Other stores
From realizing
That investing
And low price clothing
The way I had done in 70
3 gallon
Would make sense
So
Board and dog
Wanted to sell K&J
And I told him
That I would support them in selling it
But I did agree with it
Is hold with that type of decision
And the board represented it
In their public relations releases
As though I was unwilling
To cede Authority
And I never
Understood what they were talking about
Cuz I was
Totally explicit
And not
Explaining the dog
That he was the guy
All right June 19th
Yes
You're fired from Men's Wearhouse as the executive chairman
Yes or not the board
This is the company that you founded
In Houston in 1973
What do you remember about
Hearing that news
Well it wasn't that long ago so I remember everything
I remember that the lead director
Wyatt put in the position
6 ft 7
Stood up which made him quite intimidating
And said to me
You know George the board by unanimous consent
And went on to talk about getting rid of me but it when he said unanimous
I'm in a room of France and I'm going
Unanimous
Mean I have Deepak Chopra
As well as people that
You don't know
And I can't believe
That it is unanimous cuz I have done so many
Favors for all of these pizzas by unanimous consent were asking you to step down
Woodforest they said to me we'd like you to become chairman emeritus
And I said what is that may explain did
It was a figurehead position
I said when do you need to know they said by 10
The reason why was that we were meeting as a board in advance of a
You will share holder meeting
And so they wanted to get me off the
Perspectives as chairman of the board
And they said they could do it
If I notified them by 10 at night
So we were in a hotel
So I was just by myself in a hotel
I in Fremont
And
I remember
Being in my room and thinking
You know my lawyer was
Companies lawyer
Very few good friends
Outside of
The
Business
And nobody to really talk to wow
Deepak came up to my room at
And led me on a guided
Meditation
Because he was concerned
That I wasn't
Taking into account my legacy
You was right I wasn't valuing my legacy
And what I was valuing was
Do things out number one I said
Look
I know I
Told you that dog
Would be a good replacement
But after a couple of years
I was wrong
He's not qualified to run the company
That wasn't what Deepak wanted to hear
And so the next day they said that
You know
By unanimous consent Theory but
Decided to replace me in
They said to me
And George
We put your
Furniture in storage
And I remember thinking
You put my furniture in storage
I mean my furniture in my knick knacks
40 years
Of stuff that I had accumulated
1050 carton
We're put in storage
And in the moment it felt like
Well damn if all these people
Who are my friends
Don't want me as their leader anymore
Why do I want to be
Their leader
Obviously there's something not right here
Were you hurt
By your friends
Essentially rejecting you to do feel personally
Hurt
No I did not
It was not a complete surprise
There's been a phone call
About two weeks earlier
Where
The compensation committee chairman and said to me
We're going to leave you in your
Position for the time being
And I remember thinking to myself
Who the hell are you
Did tell me that
But I knew that there was
Something wasn't right
But you're in
Tire life
Your entire identity
Everything you knew
From the age of 23 24
Was Men's Wearhouse
Yeah how could you not have been hurt
By being
I was out in this may not be satisfactory in
But I don't get hurt
The way you mean it
I did not get depressed
I did not go into this
Poor me
Victim
I mean
I get it that you didn't feel sorry for yourself or that separate like
It's your identity
And then one day you've got it you got an office to go to their people you know they're people you see or George or I guarantee
And then the next day you don't have that
That's a big deal
Completely comfortable
In my skin
Almost all the time
People are interested in what I have to say
I feel I have a lot of respect
From
People I care about
I see what happened in men's
Has really an example
Capitalism run amok
Do you still keep in touch with any of those former board members
Not a one
So so soaked to say you didn't take it personally is not really true
Caldwell
I feel
That I'm a great friend
And so when you hurt me the only way I have to get it
Leaving is the with all my friendship
And say that's it
We're no longer friends and I no longer want to speak to you that's a normal human reaction
Yeah
Could be that
You know wonder some sort of
Therapy it would be
Discovered that I am really white
Hurt
But
I don't feel hurt
I got divorced after this happened
The second time
I have a great relationship with my children you know
Watching politics
In the evenings
But I don't feel
I don't know I think
Being hurt
Is
Very close
Feeling like a Vic
And I just
Reject
Okay so
After you left it
Clear the way for Men's Wearhouse to make a cake
Couple of
Significant decisions including acquiring Joseph A Bank for 1.8
Billion dollars
Turned out to be a bad decision
And the reason is
Because
Men's Wearhouse
Thought that the Joe Bank
Customer in the Men's Wearhouse
Customer word differ
Because
Shirts.
We were
More aggressive
In the selling price
When you walk in with Joseph Bank
They leave you alone
Dubrow
What I found was
That
You do a lot less business
With that strategy
Then if you have
A knowledgeable
Consultant
Who is
Genuinely
And helping the customer
And whatever the customers lifestyle
The company is
How would you describe the company today from the outside
Struggling do you own any
Chairs anymore
Appeal
And do you feel a sense of satisfaction that they are struggling since your departure
Yes and my new business
Is
Although we're a very small
Relative to them
We are compatible
So so I want to talk about your new business a sackbut
You leave Men's Wearhouse
You're rich
You can do whatever you want you can
Go to Hawaii you can
Hang out with your kids where it where you want to do
Did you think about that doing that for some time try for 4 months
I sat in my backyard
Impede my beautiful
Flowers
It was the summer
And
I thought
Treatises
Doll Emporium
My kids are in school
My wife got her own life
And I'm sitting in my backyard
Looking at the flowers
Didn't make sense
So I guess
Pretty soon after this you come up with an idea for
A new business which was an online tuxedo rental company called generation
Yes
And you launch this in
What September of 2015 right when the people from Men's Wearhouse found out about it
Oh my God this letter was like I guess I guess you didn't sign anything cuz
But you didn't pledge not to get by until you
You know what men's is Dawn men's is afraid of me is what it must be
Because after I was fired
The first thing I tried to do
What's by K&G
From which was that retail company that they are you try to buy it from them
490 million dollars okay
What verse
They wouldn't sell it to me at all
Then they said all right
If you give us a four-year non-solicitation and I said what do you mean by that
They said you can't fire or employer for 4 years
And I said are you kidding I'll give you two years but for years
Is an eternity deal never happened
Did this day
They still can't find anybody
That would offer him half of what I was going to pay out
That I had a relationship with Macy's
And we were going to provide Macy's
With the tailoring for there
Online business not their stores their online business
And as a lark
I asked my local guide
If they would have any interest
Doing a tuxedo rental thing with us
Yeah and within
A few months
My team and I were in New York
In Terraria
Lundgren's office
The CEO of Macy's
Making a deal
Tubidy tuxedo auxito
Rental
And we had the deal
It went to Legal review
And while it was in legal review
Men's Wearhouse stolen
Because I could not get Macy's
Do agreed with no-shop clause
So they shopped it around my girl how would happen
But the next thing I know
Terry called me and said
I'm very sorry George but we're not doing it by and I said
Who are you doing it with
And he said
Didn't want to tell me it first
The lady said Men's Wearhouse and I went
You gotta be kidding me yeah
And
It doesn't make me
Men's bowler
Revengeful it
It just makes me
More determined to do what I know how to do
What is the status of generation tux now
I mean you started 2015 it took you over our first year of
Profitability startled took a long time for Men's Wearhouse
How to get to Welches
Really gets a major problem
Much better
And
You go online and you
Get a tux and you just
Put your measurements in and it comes to you and then you wear and you send it back
Exactly
And we do things like
If you want any
Free home try-on
Will do not only one
To rearm dry on
We do free swatches
You know we do a lot of things that make our business
Strong and it's
Right now it's starting to really
Fire on all cylinders
George Gee you feel a sense of
I don't know vindication
That you were right
About Sterling Shirley were wrong about sending in 1/4 wrong over the course of their career
But I guess you were right
And in certain ways you did not want
Men's Wearhouse to acquire JOS A Bank in the like that model
They did
It hurt them
Does being right is that important to you
I think so
Why
Well I like to think that I'm right about
Manything
I'm wrong about a few things
But
Yeah I think that you know
That there is a real problem in America
I think that capitalism
Which clearly
Won the battle over communism
And even socialism
Is need in need
A modification
And I'm a capitalist
What the hell I've been my life making money
But there are a few adjustments
The capitalism
That would make it sustainable
Which on Fortune
I don't think it is sustainable
Would one of those adjustments be
Shifting the focus away from shareholders
Exactly
That's what it's about
It is always about short-term profit
Yeah
When you when you look over the course of your career
The ups and downs
How much of your success do you attribute to
Your hard work and your intelligence
And skill and how much do tribute
Black
Just being lucky riding a lucky wave
Well I think they go hand-in-hand
Another words
I think you need
Lock
But
You also need
The talent
And the
Intelligence
Know how to take advantage
Uplock
I think that what happens in life unfortunately
Is
A lot of people have the opportunity
To be lucky
But don't know how to take advantage of it
And you did
I did
That's George Zimmer
Founder and former CEO Men's Wearhouse George still runs
Generation tux
At some point I'm going to make you say it you know that right now. Right now you're going to like the way
Way you look I guarantee it to put that as my phone ringer when I was
At Men's Wearhouse I would go to
Charity auctions
And auction off doing that for $3,500 wow
I would do it for you for nothing by the way
Thank you very much
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
The things your building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsors wordpress.com
Powerful site building tools and thousands of themes to choose from
Users can launch
Site that's free to start
Room to grow
Get 15% off any new plan purchase
Wordpress.com
Built this
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that and today we're updating a story we first ran about a year ago
Begins around 1993 in Guinea West Africa
And one of the things he has a kid with the sweet ginger e pineapple juice
Call Ginger
Which is a really popular drink in that part of the world we know you go buy a snacks on the side of the road you often have we know what
Women that have a little cooler of ginger ale to a species like
Lemonade or iced tea or maybe milk to a lot of the kids early childhood in Guinea was
Pretty great but around the time I turned 15 the political situation in the country became unstable
Able and unsafe
Sara Haines parents sent him and his brother to the US
Raheem overstayed his visa and was eventually caught by immigration officials
And he ended up spending almost a year in detention
Odyssey looking back at it
It's now that I appreciate how difficult of a time you was
Young and
Too naive to understand how
How much trouble I was in when he was eventually able to get a green card
And then made enough money to go to Community College and then
To Michigan State University
The whole time he was missing home
His mom his friends and even that pineapple drink you loved as a kid
Yeah in Michigan when I'm playing sports
When I'm running around in them
Really hot
Summer that usually don't Pine for Coke
I think about Ginger
Can't find homemade pineapple ginger juice
Some African restaurants
But you can't just walk into a chain store and buy that the Shelf
Soul Train has Brothers.
Maybe we should start making it and selling it
And when they started doing research
I mean
Seemed perfect
You know what is that
The traditional
The Colts de Pepe
Dalida the carbonated artificially flavored
Brian
Market share
The point where
They have all started to buy a smaller companies that are developing
Fresh organic
Biotics queso a great opportunity for something like ginger but
As much as they love the stuff
They did not know how to make it
So
They caught up their mom and guinea
And ask for the recipe
Fresh ginger
Cold pressed pineapple
All fresh lemon juice
Vanilla
Play this is all happening around 2014 and
This point the two brothers are living in New York City
Start mixing up batches of gingin in Bahamas apartment
And Raheem Thursday give out samples to customers at the bar where he works
Dell Triton boat to find a ginger to be too spicy or some folks to find it to have a little too much lemon or too little
Lemon
Or the pineapple is not pronounced an hour for it is or later after trial and error
Muhammad
Guess the recipe exactly where they wanted
They decide to Launch
Xinjiang
At an African Festival in Harlem
He was one of those moment to realize that we really want something everyone that came by that world from West Hartford
Nudo products
Goodnight just buy one bottle you know it by
2 3 take a picture and send it to a friend
They sold out all of their bottles
And then a really big break
They wanted $25,000 the competition for budding entrepreneur so they moved into an industrial
Real kitchen and eventually
Play Pitch Ginger and Whole Foods and well
We're definitely not less in terms of
Sewing them
Because we knew Whole Foods wanted us to get a distributor and a distributor
Was interested in us because they know we talk in the whole food so we kind of played them against one another
And it worked out well
Since launching in
2015 New York City Long Island and Westchester
Raymond's brother are looking forward to opening their first Ginger Cafe in Harlem
If you want to find out more about rain Jello or your previous episodes head to our podcast page
How I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why your
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us as HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
Our ship was produced this week by Diva mohtasham with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Carney JC Howard nor could he leave a grant
Melissa Grace Anna's Michigan for Jeff Rodgers
Our concern is Candice Lim I'm Gyros and you've been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor. Com