Support for this in
NPR Podcast
Comes from Sierra Nevada Brewing
Family-owned
Operated
And argued over
Proud supporter of independent thought
Weather that's online
Over-the-air
In a bottle
More at Sierra Nevada.
Really quick before you start to show
I want to let you know that there are just a few
You tickets left for the
How I built
The Summit
Supported by America
Express it happening
October 22nd
23rd at the Yerba Buena Center in
In San Francisco
It is going to be in the
Edible event
You'll be able to hear from and
Probably even meet Founders from
Companies like away
Slack Instagram spank JetBlue Clif Bar Jeni's Splendid ice cream
And many many more
You can get your tickets
And learn more about the summit
Including how we can help
Grow your business
Or build your big ideas
At Summit. NPR
. org
I also want to let you know about
View how I built this
Live shows
What you got coming up
East Coast
This fall
Also supported by American Express
I'll be heading to New York on September 10th 12
Tina Tosi of Milk Bar
And then we'll be in Washington DC on September 12th
Tristan Walker Walker and cumber
You get tickets and find out more about our East Coast tour
NPR presents
. org
How are you doing as the CEO of the company
I'd not good I mean my team was very very patient with me
That was a lot to learn
Can you tell them what to do is keep doing it until you stop
My cousin has a very large learning curve
From NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists stories behind the movement
Snowboards on the internet
Platform Powers billions of dollars
E-commerce
Every month
So back in August of
And you might remember this
Kylie Jenner made the cover of Forbes
The issue was dedicated to
Female billionaires
And Kylie Jenner made her Fortune from a Cosmetics Empire called
Kylie cosmetics
I started to read the article I was struck by a few things in particular
Things that just weren't possible even 5 years ago
For starters Kylie's
Billion dollar company
Employees just seven full-time people
All of the products
Eggs are manufactured in
Send package by a private label Cosmetics producer in Oxnard California
Kylie's PR marketing team is her iPhone
From which you can reach 140 million Instagram followers
This is a thing that really blew me away
All the sales
Fulfillment
This is handled in
Hayirli by a software platform
Call Shopify
Why does all the stuff behind the scene
Make e-commerce work
When you click add to cart or buy make sure the transaction will happen seamlessly
You bought something online outside of Amazon or Ebay
There's a pretty good chance you bought it from a store powered by Shopify
It is now used by more than 800 thousand
E-commerce companies around the world
Within two years
Online sales will account for 13% of all retail transactions in the US
You can imagine this is a big business
Last year alone
Shopify processed more than 40 billion dollars
Salesforce customers
Company went public in 2015 and shopify's market cap is now just below General
And yet unless you're in tag or have an online shop there's a chance you have never heard of Shopify
Which
In a way it's the personality of the company's co-founder and CEO Toby Luka
He's the kind of guy who literally rode his bike to vcp
And even as recently as five years ago at a time Shopify had already raised well over a hundred
Million dollars in Venture Capital funding
Toby was still living in a
Spare room at his in-laws house
To save money
Before all that
Toby grew up in koblenz
In Germany
And as a kid it was
Preclude
Toby was bright but
He also struggled with learning
I mean I go Darkness positive learning disabilities and
Stay hot for me too
Perform well in the test
Sen salon
Anthem
I don't think I ended up getting a full diagnosis of fat but no
Dyslexic so you know just reading was hard
It was always a big question about what exactly was going on the Paisley I was bored
Back pain
The way the curriculum in Germany was Toddlers really basically he is always solution to my
Find useful later in life if they have a little time spent talking about a particular problem set fit both solutions would have
If I don't understand the problem I'm trying to solve it say hot for me to
Turn on a solution to a problem
So every finish the 10th grade tell me realize that school wasn't the right fit
So he left
Enjoy the German apprenticeship program to learn how to become a software engineer
And yes I'm starting as an apprentice on a small team at a subsidiary of the German manufacturing giant semen
I found this one team matches
Seem really fun
Basement has run by this wonderful Guy Star
Lexington tastic engineer
Prokarma
And he would always come on this like BMW motorcycle to work and we would have long hair and he was not
Being a suit like you were supposed to
And so it's like total crap
So good
No one could complain
You know I just like me to grab potato to him and his little
Group of rabbits
Better Brooklyn really interesting things have often prototyping new things for customers and so on
Until I wanted to be part of a group
And so
Starting roof 16 or 17 and year 2 of my apprenticeship I started getting paid
To program all day and that's all I did and he loved it
I loved it and I still love it as computer program
You can do you can forget all
Time around you you just can
Like I can turn everything off
If I'm Pokemon Ninja
Problem
Are the part of your life
I'm curious how you got into the snowboarding
Right you are snowboarder
Did you grow up snowboarding did you just
It comes out on your own
I mean my parents had a place in the
Add speed of growth
2 habits of 5-Hour Drive
Randy skeete
Fast forward a little bit
Took some friends
Spitalfields
Vacation
Initially started
Odoo United States
Button
Mexican donut was so low that you decide to go to
Can't wait to Catawissa
It's like 2000
Business around 2
Anthem
So this was the first time I said okay
I'm just going to snowboard I'm not going to take skis like this
Leticia spent all of our time there
That's really when I fell in love
The snowboarding and also on that same trip
Matt Monro wife
Fiona
Peter on the ski trip and what you say I'm going back to Germany but
Like I guess I'm here
Exactly I'm babysitting contact afterwards and
Should have said you know what I'm done with my bachelor's degree
Why don't I just come to Germany
Her parents must have thought you was nuts
You meet this guy is actually impressed by parents
The most wonderful people so she comes to Germany
You are working
Programming for to attack
She end up getting a job editing
Academic writing
Yeah baby we live together for 10 months and she said okay well.
I need to go back and some of us has program in Ottawa and she asked me if I want to come in
Because you could take what you know and do it anywhere
Where is my event is because
I grew up on American Media like everything Quin a word came from United States
That's where I want to end up I would like to move and then you know what your iPhone your figure out how
You know what the cat has America fought Europeans and breakfast
Used Cannondale ur22
You're like whatever let me try this
Who was the job that you did there
Netflix remote
Doomed to failure because you know
Email contact
What was the startup
It was an attempt at writing a different browser
But it's
I basically ran out the clock it was everyone benvenue if I wasn't going to do anything at that people best time to leave
We're talking like a raft of a.com
What's your 2223
This point was any part of you nervous like
I'm living with a swimmin like
I don't really you know know what I'm going to do with my life like where you feeling any anxieties are just like get something stable
Hey boss
I would be lying if I said I wasn't
I knew I had
Bebible
Pascal's I could always do more of a thing that I was doing recently or Western persimmons
I was just hoping I could have been
Read an indent in somewhere work4bk
Company yeah why
They look for Siemens Houston
Probably the most important things I've ever done in my life because they can't talk
Don't want
It was
In so many ways
Estranged
Company culture
In the wave at
If had exceptionally mistrusting of
You know fairly strict dress codes which is basically
A company saying have you don't trust
You guys to dress
And it is so much of that
Just fed wrong
20 year old Toby would not
You have a career path
And so
All the time I was
Stopping kadavy and autograph a cold place
Send the winter months of the year
But you can run a strategy of
Waiting for, you really have to
Do something before winter
Amiibos go to hell
And Snowboard Tanaka increasing interval
As I do I research everything I was about snowboarding wanted to know every option that existed and
Is pek spreadsheets of
Happy technology but you can use to build a snowboard
And
At some point.
Click10
Maybe using
My technical skills
How to start an internet business
Yes I did get a job offer from a fan small local company that
I was actually interested in looking for but then I went to the basically to sign the papers
Send that one of her top respect
They found out at this point that I needed a book from s2822 it to Eagle allowed to
Be there because I was on the process of getting a permanent residency
But my status didn't give me both of it and I talked with her friend of family in the
He said it's going to take you awhile to get this
You can stop business
Your only option option like I could try to vote remote
Hopefully again Fortune companies something like this oddly enough that's okay but I couldn't work for logging company
Doing this I use my technical skills I was thinking of setting up some online so soft
Because I think that would exist and then use that as a way to
Funny White snowboarding hopefully and
Have a good life
Alright so there's a guy that you met Scott Lake
If we go on to become your
Your co-founder
Who's got booked for Bad Company almost
Good height for a man to be kept talking and he was a friend of a family and
Exactly
You were living with where
The Fiona's parents
I mean you're like this German kid Dana daughter you're living in her house is weird
Mazelee
Supportive
End
Honestly
Kia cerato
I don't think I could live this
Anyone
But I can lift
The damn Bruce I made it incredibly
Baby by Justin Moore
Kind
Genuine
Endplate massive Road
Tell
Choose diplomat
Government
Is your mother
I got off of the office
Play time she did all the payroll and accounting and everything
Ascended up
Same company
So it sits entrepreneurship is Messi
Little Johnny video
But even if you make the choices have to embark
Kind of everyone around you is
Coming onto the trip
That's a lot of pee
People went up matter
Sangam
I clearly Was Naive about it I probably would never committed to my surrounding to Aspen
Craziness
Ended up the Journey of Shopify but
Type of shots
All right so you are
You're living with a parent
Yeah you give got the snowboard idea you meet this guy Scott who's working at this other company that does heat come to you and say
I told you I think
Going to work with you
Steven Universe saying hey you know
What I'm thinking and
I love Friday I'm a super supportive
Santa
It was really Scott.
Developing relationships
Deven Dorsett
Doing a lot of a business
Set up and always kind
Like I'm indecisive
Classical
Co-founder separation
I was looking out today technology and
Business site
And I guess your startup cost where not in
Incredibly insanely High
Why because you were doing all the code programming and
And you have to obviously invest
Money in and snowboards you had to keep some inventory or would you was the idea to wait until orders came in
What happened in that way
Replay watch the better brand
Inside you wanted to build something
Something but you hope would become big
What do you call it by the way
It was called snowed ever
Sotto voce
How are you going to get this out into the world
What's to like make sure peep
We're aware of it
So I mean
Step number one
Let's go find Tech
Ended up being a really really important
Mom and I didn't anticipate it because analogy to to like put it up on the internet to start it and then some
Start online first party because
It's cheaper
We didn't have a capital for signing a long-term lease
But we wanted to also have a physical
Anthem
IPad
Maybe a week
To get the one next to it
This was my expectation
You do in a week
Enzai
Trusses. Volume softer Alexander's 2040 top number
Thought so
I looked at some commercial software with most recording afforded
They're just got really confused because
Hi
2004 sitting in front of my computer absolutely
Stunned realizing
Betty Hutton
Figured out how to build
What's 1 x 1000
Books from Amazon
And so you needed a way to get
Photos of the snowboards up on the site
Either way for people to search
What
Snowboards for available
How to pay for the
Snowboards and then get a message
To you somehow that order came through at that you could
And that wasn't easy to find out the Shelf there's no software that would make the
This easy on Christmas Eve a credit card pot
He also hat I think novel at least modern ideas about what
Hubby wants both upset to look like we wanted to tell stories like every snowboard 50 so obviously
Took on the mountain
Animal Chronicle the way we spend
Universal thoughts of a time of emergence of blocking so they had in mind was something that rapped
Good storytelling around products that people are
Excited about trying to break away from the Sears catalog metaphor
Early
Curious win
When you and
And Scott
Exercise
Launch Daredevil
Like that you need but both of you need to put in money to start this and remember how much money you needed
Bigg Boss put money into the company at
20000 Canadian dollars
That's that's a capital P hat
Which was your savings for
Programming
All I have is
And one thing potatoes
Baggataway lacrosse
No
Rent snow
Various coffee shops
I tried to explore
My new city of Ottawa brightest
Taking random bosses and walking out to the van and coffee shop in Brooklyn from there
Yeah
Alright see you and Scott
Are working at a cafe
She posted about
20000 bucks
You start sourcing
Snowboards
But there's no official site
Actually so you decide
I'm going to write this
I'm going to do it
So exactly why I was like
There's only two ways forward
I like I compromised
My idea and do something that's a undifferentiated except for snowboards
Or
I'm going to fall back on my
Programming
Scouts
And I would build something bad
Hopefully we'll be able to pull this business
So what what did you
How did you start to build it and I guess it was a
I read about this
This sort of language that you found called Ruby on Rails
What was that and why was it so significant
So
I had this realization
But I probably got to be the only problem with avocados
So
I don't actually have to choose something that lots of people know I can actually choose
Just the best tool for the job
And so
Spinda spoken language called Ruby but I just have so much love to give us
People don't usually talk about programming languages like this but I find
Play I really really love the process of
Constructing something in your brain having this idea is it's a little bit also like
Painting if you have an idea for something
And then the programming language ends up being
Mechanism for translating the
Perfect picture you have your hat onto a canvas
And so you know if you have like an amazing landscape and I get your crayons
It possible to make a masterpiece of crayons
But if it'll be it'll always be a crayon painting so it's a lot of into a Java in August
I just didn't match the way my brain ended up constructing the relationships that make up software
Ruby was a
Thing is I sometimes later Japanese that's only Japanese
Equitation around this time for it
Elantra language calculator source code
Anthem
Source code is in
Latin characters
The instruction manual is in Japanese
Like I remember. Hey I have the power to choose
And so why don't I go and use Ruby because that would be way more fun
Using this
Coding language
This program
To build the infrastructure that would allow you how long does it take you to actually build the shop
Happy lunch
Snorted like a tuna half months later
So
It was really good technology
I mean I also admit I probably spend
$6 a day doing this
So a lot of
Coca-Cola and pizza and Faye and happy life
Style
It didn't feel like I was
Doing crazy hours for anything like this and I would never recommend anyone to do this
But like
There was literally nothing more in
Cheapest thing in the world
So was it pretty quick
From the time you launch the website to the time you got your first orders
It took
Let me let me just
Because
And I was looking for
Coffee shops
I had my first Auto and I usually remember
I got everything about that day
As is actually ended up being a really profound experience
Because some
I wrote the song
At some point
Doing writing software I actually had to type the email that
This outfit would send to me yet
And so
You know I've been to a coffee shop open my laptop
Anthem
It was a real order
From
Prudential in Pennsylvania no one I ever met
I really felt like
I think that's
The first time
You saw something
Her first time
Someone asks you for when the phone rings
Because I'm telling you just
Summit
Already great but like
It's that moment and it's something
But I meet Shopify customer
I often ask them where were you when you got that first order and everyone can remember
And you see your first order and you're thinking oh my got some kind of Pennsylvania's ordering from me
Eyeshadow
Walk home
To call Scott because I didn't have a cell phone
Auto and
LOL score today
People finding out about promotion
Flyers
But
Weight of 2012 front right light
Google AdWords
What's a new product
Birthdays at phone ads for click is $0.20 and
Minimum bets for almost every search for General voting on a $500 box
Google ads
And there were not that many online snowboard shops so how did Snow devil do
Is a business degree without my hat really good profit margins on them
LPS problem bookkeeping and entry and I'm getting inventory back and basically Autumn stock
But the
Bearden accents you guys recouped your investment pretty quickly
We had some good amount of savings from from Mass for the next phase
Scott or did you quickly have to grow and bringing other people to help you with inventory and shipping and fulfillment
Picture of awesome baby dad some Scott fans
Literally driving into the post office
Figured out a way to
Brown paper wrap snowboard
Shoulder
Exactly that's exactly what picture
It was fun
How do you say to your running
Snowboard business
It's going
Pay pretty well
Is making money and I mean
What happened
Guess what happened
Sesloc obviously in
Spring and the babysitter
Begin to conversations around
You not make it really sustainable year on business we need to unite what's a skateboard surfboard
Do something else
So you were considering
Hey it's a spring maybe we should do kiteboards and
Skateboards
Things that would have been
The natural thing to do to go year-round again
Scott and I said you wanted to start over
Location
Cantata
But I really
Doing bad development
I said I was no spending
Harvest Time
I got
Tweaking the self-guided not stop
The programming I was just
Okay now let me
Try things that may make it faster let me use different approaches
And so increasingly I got people sending me emails
And asked me if I would license no devil
I took them because they want to just said something similar people were saying hey can you
Just license if you built this
Can we use a Ferrari commercial
Right and exact because it was supposed to stiffen it wasn't it wasn't on the grid that was
I told stories of us
City Modern
Episode of Victorious
Anthem
Some people were saying I would love to dispute my business based on
Vets Foundation
Amazing it's it reminds me so much of the story of squares
Squarespace was essentially
Started because
The founder
He couldn't
Find a good way to do a Blog and website all in one
So he basically
Read his own way to build a website
Wright's Kidizoom selfie
It's similar store to here
Yeah but what I needed was
Something that helps me
Inbev
Journey of Entrepreneurship
From scratch
I'm not
That different
Like if I needed this at some point
That's going to be
At least
Couple thousand people watching
So it was like spring 2005 at some point score tonight
Set
Okay skateboards
Haybuster the office of Bishop.
So eventually I guess
Bring in the sky Daniel weinand
Who is he in
Why did you bring in the board
Yeah so I decided it's going to be software
I called Daniel.
Really good friend my best friend really from Joe was in Germany and said hey
Guess what I would like to do and I think I need another
Javier do business to want to spend the summer in Canada and we do this together and
I like if you could work together on BB fun
To yuan Daniel
Spend that summer
December 2015
You're trying to build this suffer together exactly what point do you stop selling snowboards
Around that time
How did you come up with a name Shopify for
Software
Wisconsin idea it was to be talked
About what it was he wanted it and
Print shop in simplified together
Was pretty straightforward
An event
I think
GoDaddy and fattest uber.com
I see you got Shopify
Building this thing
Really it sounds like from that
Moments from the beginning you're thinking
This is going to be our business we're going to build
The software that will enable
The open e-commerce site
Easily and simply
Yeah so much to building businesses so much complexity in
Lakers you can order how how does a bunny make it to you how to get ready to get shipping labels from how do you make a truck show up to actually
Except if I
Does office
Metal cigar
Because
You know that the moment
That matter described
I got my first sale be good office sale
From that point on
I can never get that again
But that was such a profound moment like what I want to spend my time on the side
Can I just have other people have attics.
That became said if a guiding principle of Habibi
And
Imagine that you got a
At some point Reyes somebody to
Pay for server space pay for
You know the kind of a
That cost
Associated with building this
Technology and then
Marketing it
When did you first
Start to think about
Bring in some money
So around that time.
Aspirin
Family for money
6 mm
Around 5
You Can't Beat Around
Like Fiona's parents anyone
My family I mean
You know I'm amazing.
People Trust
It was $200,000
Which is a
What do you need $20,000 for What would
She has to experience up to this point
This is
Valuable I know it's valuable because I would have needed it and then more people like me all these sort of like
People were still
Asking you for this and what were you saying to them were you saying hangover working on something just hold tight will get it to you
Captive a plug by I should have talked about my experience building it
I also had a landing page
Collecting emails
Shopify.com
And he is like a dam obits
Report of people snow devil to explain why we were doing this and
By the time you launched in 2000
Sex I think we had flow of 5000 emails so it's not
But that seems a lot
All right you've got the seed money
You've got
Small office
Techni basement office
SpaceX
Step off the
Coffee shop I got
Fslr
Play some desk
Santa hats
Buddy Welch
And it's time to Launch
You got 4000 emails or so
From the landing page
And did you just send like a
Last of email saying
Okay we're live we're here we're ready to go is that how you're not
I'm so just a blast email and what was the response
Some people signed up
Just try it out if it was really really exciting and
Cost of business running
On Shopify
Set that actually started on that day which
Remarkable
But it wasn't it was a lot I mean
Most of our customers
Right to that thing is not bad suddenly something goes wrong
Define responsibility
Free initially
It started out free
The first year
We decided against the motor booty affair
What's it cost in right now because it's going to be so hard to get people to trust us
That's
Making a cheaper would be more likely for people to give it a try and forevermore
Josh like 3 and 1/2 of 3.75 % for sale
It was a complete failure of a business model because but basically everyone who didn't expect to have sales
But it was amazing and people who
Effector cell.
That was way too much money so
We ended up
Switching at a year after launch the night before my wedding for a reason I will never figure out why I did that
For your wedding you switch to a subscription model
Said hey I promised my
Son so that I can use for free interlude cause Mario and so I got all these phone calls like doing my buddy
So you
In 2007 still living with your in-laws
Now but not married with your in-laws
How many
People at gym member like in those early
Days like the first year so actually
Sign up
For the service
I mean
A couple of thousand accounts that I would say like
Maybe a hundred active
And
India to
Interesting event I am in business
I think that Indianapolis
Team won the Superbowl around that time and if they actually had a
Local newspaper actually had a
Shopify store
Creative display started like 2 days before Super Bowl
I just was selling
T-shirts with the front page saying we won the Superbowl
Oh I like a front like a picture on the newspaper would look like if it actually happened to William
Nomadic meaning
And Sol
Tens of thousands and hundreds of thousands
Douglasville 450 shirts
On that day
And that was
Like a stunning
Experience fast because.
That was so
Fix someone just had a really good idea in an office and turned it into
Lake Alfred real economic
Yeah event
Buena Vista events that are regulating people Birkin
Experimenting with online retail Victor new businesses for starting instead of people coming up saying hey View
Reduce costs and switch to you
It says it was a slow burn though
It wasn't like an overwhelming Rush
She was like in
Incremental
But you're still
At this point you're still operating off of
Seed money raised and
Any Revenue you were generating
How is the money situation where you work was it just self-generating were you
No
Hike now
DHEC
Paying customers
Levi going 20120 fast
Like the eventually
Save Bandit
Basically
Run out of money around this time the
Luckily
Met an angel investor who ended up
Putting
I think $400,000 around 2017 that saved us is an individual by the name of John Phillips I think part of reason
Find messages because
His parents been autobahns
I think he wanted something else to do in town to have a nice day
I visited parents buy CO2 really like
Business
Becoming
Vesta and then basically meant 02
Is a very prescient investment
At that time the company was
Is valued at $3000000
Around this time 2008
Scott Lee
Besides
I want to move on
What do you remember about that decision
I mean it was
Hitherto the job of CEO I think he just realized
At some point.
Vasa Fitness reverse going as most of the people who
Vasilios Baxley
Highly technical
Parts of the founding teams
I think he also realized that
I will end up being the person with a care most about this company in the long run and so
You know that's okay we decided to part ways some more you worried about it cuz he was a CEO
I was cute avoid about us because
Like I was convinced that I should have a CO2
But
Someone gave me
Told me that if a great VC investment
They would have been that the Rope to find
The right kind of CEO
And so
I was like okay well
Maybe I really should talk to her
I travel to a second to talk about
PCS 2008 you decide
I better go to Silicon Valley
Find a venture investor
Who then can help me find a CEO
So you fly out there
A 2008 with a couple of appointments
Yeah a couple of appointments and then and just
Drinks with
Friends Central Avenue in Sacramento. Valley
Absolutely not my intention was
To build
20 people company that's what I want to do 20-person company super-efficient providing a sock for two people
A massive company you will be what you wanted to have
Just want a sustainable nice life
I didn't need the money because I didn't think this was Adventure I was building
And so I vent
Being too worried about the results I was more worried about the amount of money it would cost for me to fly to
Bacteria and accommodation since gone
Where did you stay
Say a little hostel
The internet
I actually bought that bicycle on on Craigslist
I was scheduled to be there for a week I ended up staying I think
True or false
When I should have maybe because
What happened pretty quickly if you know I would
Have my first meeting and again visit me biking
From the youth hostel
And showing up and they probably already five who is this
Cancel
I would have not
The first meeting and I had my notepads and they would ask me
Let's start at outside offensive explaining the business and
But then they would ask me some questions about
You know usage
Marketside we could have fangs
And some of us could answer
And then I would forget really interested
But the problem was that they quickly they ask me questions
Select favorites questions are on
Pek ratios and then end lifetime value and always going to think I would
Right on the Tums
I would rather
Look up
Usually I would get an equation
Abacus
Some advice but you supposed to apply to business
Kotor database
And get all the relevant data Tuckerman equation I would get
The numbers
So I had one more
Chrismukkah. Select meeting
And and so basically this is how I eventful these meetings I remember that
I mean I ended up getting
What kind of time sheets people actually
Franklin Graham
Call David feigenbaum has mostly Benchmark office
If someone eating free by the time I kind of figured out
Really worried there were some people were interested some people that interested but all the office for August
Conditioner
Conmovedor company II by
They all said woohoo
Will support you we going to move it
Yes
So I got two offers
I got some sheets
And some of them
Referred me to 10 to see yours I had
Bunch of late-night meetings of people who could take over as CEO because I wanted to play
I called you that was my dentist
So I said okay
Clearly
If you want to be snow and if I get good numbers you going to give me this late
I go back
Like I talk to her
My team think about this how many people are on your team
Is about
Define peep
Alright I had a customer support initially and then eventually rest of my team told me my English wasn't good enough
How are you paying peep
This was now have to be God's angel
I've said wasn't take a salary
Jobs your Runway was not very long
Now it's
Fidelis income
Time now Italy
It was still burning but it was
He got slower and slower
Income coming in from sub
Subscribers exactly
So I go back
And then
We're talkin mm
So
The demon drop
No
The bud was falling apart Lehman Brothers collapse
Market collapse
Rejected
And now you're about to face a global
Financial crisis
Around this time
Notice that
Toshiba no longer be honored because everyone needs type medicine so basically
When we come back after the break how the global recession actually turned out to be a huge opportunity
For Shopify learn to do the job of CEO
A job
Never wanted in the first place
It was this guy Roz and you listening to how I built this NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks
The two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast pasta
First
Does ZipRecruiter
Hiring you
Multiple job sites tax
Resume
Today
Hiring can be easy
Only have to go to one place to get it done
ZipRecruiter
ZipRecruiter since you're driving over 100
The web's leading job board
Ben ZipRecruiter scams
Thousands of resumes
Find people with
The right experience
Invite them to apply to your job
Try it for free
Ziprecruiter.com
Built
Thanks also to Capital One
The Capital One Savor card
You can earn 4% cash back
Dining in
Entertainment
That means 4%
Checking out that new
French restaurant
4%
Bowling with your friends
You'll also earn 2% cash back at grocery stores and one
2% on all other purchases
Now when you go out
Cashier
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Terms apply
I'm Shanker V.
Host of NPR's hidden brain
Think deeply
Gota tell you about our summer series
YouTube .0
Ideas and advice
About how you can respond to life
Kiosk
Just checked my phone real quick
With wisdom
Listen to Hidden brain
Every week
Global financial crisis
At this point Toby look good is the CEO of Shopify
The BCS who had been interested in investing
Quite so interested anymore
Shopify
The money was running out
Send something surprising
It turned out that lots of people who were newly laid off
Have lots of ideas about starting their own online stores
People who lost their jobs
Could reach for the own independence
A negation entrepreneurship
Shopify
And I said why don't I get physical
Like I'm going to
Tribus thing I was going
Try right and I'm going
I can teach you see start to see users and end subscribers start to take up
Yes
You size a measurable change in 2008 2009 would fall off a cliff and what they actually did it
Usually anticipated
A completely different outcome
Yes I was ready to think about
How to
Tell people that I copy payroll
Indian stats
Basically in 2009
The company now hit
First time for cash
No neutral like we can ride out whatever downtown this is
Stop
Thinking about long-term
And I spent like infrastructure projects
Okay mean time
You are the CEO
How are you doing as the CEO of the company
I'd Market
I mean my team was very very patient with me that was a lot to learn its at 7
Wonderful things about computer systems can you tell them what to do about
Keep doing it until you stop
Lottery
And
I would say 2009
To 2010 I truly had for company back from what I could have
And should have probably become
You held it
Engineering you know something's always have bottleneck
And then the moment you remove fat something else
Same goes for companies at this point
I intentionally slow down
The growth of a company a little bit just
Because I needed it to be mad before me
Wavering on Vermont
Important decision
Trust
Is fish a lifestyle business
Or it's
Is this actually Adventure
Is over $1000000 a year
Yeah right
But what sounds like a lot
Expenses you've got a growing staff
Yeah did you ever
Get the feeling like oh my
Programmers
And people are now like working for me and Adam
I don't know if this is going to work
Guys it's crushing
It's crushing me
Hospitality right like a
You responsible for everyone boisvert
Wright & Ellis
Blood blister
My family like
It's not a
Wealthy family
Like it said some in people gave me money that didn't really have like
Up to this point it was really just
The money from
John Phillips
For my family and Van
For the last
Yeah for my father-in-law forget me
Money for 4 to meet payroll
It's amazing that this works I mean I just couldn't believe
He was doing that because
He's like it was a broker. This was his saving
Basically
Divorce
Putting his life savings
Interview
Monday qualifier everyone was just unbelievably supportive because they
Somehow believed in this idea
Ethiopia
You know like
So one thing I found about Inferno Journey what is mine is
You busy lyrics it's in two different states
Best state of
Things are coming together
It diversity on Peterborough
And the state of
Complete threatened with that with that did that tonight
Handsome
I don't think I've actually ever been to way I still to this day have
The thing that changed as it used to be like
Months in one state to another
I meant to become a week and now they know it
This can happen
But I can stop by three times before breakfast
But at the bottom should I go to the barn so deep
End
Vape locations of what failure means
Is
It just means so much changes everyone's life story to a significant degree right
How did you manage that issue
Go for long runs.
Prozac.
Kayak
No I basically just
Program to actually often wasn't the best use of my time and
Did you talk to Fiona about it
Around this 2009.
Like really wavering on the
Decision right which is like you built
A stable
Lifestyle business
Split Shopify
Or do you try again for
For big money for VC money and make this thing
Huge
What happened
Cyborg look at my bank account
Just compare you know what it was last time
If it was going up
Basically is that okay
Should be investments in another team member or should we attempt
The marketing
So I finally said okay I'm going to save
And try
5 different ideas for Max
He said if any of
Boss meaning for the accelerator walgrove
Then I have to go fundraising again and actually go on the clock to what's an IPO or to eventual exit
Is the money really needed
For marketing
At this point in reverse
Held back by not engaging
F5 project
And what's your team you said
You guys come up with some ideas
Speed boat under DSP
Can I put things on
We tried them
And
Abby singers
Vivid adverbs
The Misfits took a little bit longer but we release a book on
The concept
I just tried to feel like I'm sponsored
Ashley I podcast
I do not like everyone of us
Bvtrack tennis like pizza
Directly mathematically trackable exit make money back in like
Type 6 month
Types of office.
And I'm like okay
Now you're not talking about fundraising anymore based on isn't it cool to be going out this Market
Talking about I have a formula and I need to plug bigger number than the Baphomet and so then
And pick up a phone called The Venture Capital Switzerland Kraftmaid
I have data you go back out to Silicon Valley
You convinced a few VC firms to invest erasing 7 million dollars
Evaluation was 25 25 million.
At this point once you to your begin $7000000
Those venture capitalist
Are also buying
On the Border
Developer Ford
You're now
Right and there you got a
Have regular calls them if they email you they're expecting you to get back to the
Stressful or overwhelming it was a helpful
I thought it was very helpful
I've always had a fantastic relationship with all the people invest
The company party because I told them
Straight up about
Li keqiang
I'm not going to play
Pretend I know things that
No and I
I really hope you're happy
Journey
Until
I think
Our relationship has always been bigger all on the same side
A hope
But anyways I'm fairly quick study
And so
Bit by bit
Hawaii running Shopify
A provider
It's all the kinds
Encinitas to to London
Did you have to remember this till 5 or 10
People with a still
People okay
And so all of you guys
Really doubling down mark
Getting getting word out
And what kind of businesses were being launched on
Indirect businesses
New businesses like
Sunglasses
Let's watch business
New ideas poster board
Looks like outfeed of all books
A great example of a kind of business Vector inverter coming out
And
10 months
After the series A
Jammin Java
Gentleman's hat
You are still mad
African strain
Buy money
How about
Instead of you spending a bunch of money
On fundraising
Buddhist
Quadruple the valuation of a company and
Mushroom
Because you can feel this way
Baby basically set
Liberty Safe me from
They said we see the potential here we're going to give you 15 million dollars more
Yeah yeah exactly
It was just so obvious
And this is why I said earlier that I had
Company back
Because
Anubis what
You knew it would happen but you said you would all this anxiety about all these p
People so if you knew it
What explains the
Freaking out
I think I was looking at what I had to do like the
Hrpro
Spell assistant I had to build
Everything make all the decisions
NFL if I also would be sitting on I
Perpetually
Exploding rocket ship right now on top of all that that's happening I could not the other
I need it
Take another year of Abreva
Before I could actually
Beautiful Sphinx
2012 I think you finally move out
From Fiona's
Parents place you have a kid at this point
Today you've got three
I want to say it must have been 2014 that they actually moved out
So it was a living
Actually raised a hundred million dollars in 2013
You're still nervous about I was making basically minimum wage so
Give me more money I would have probably given it back because I think I could use better than I did
So that's your lifestyle wasn't then require whole lot of money
As long as I have my laptop I was good
Alright so you guys are or balancing like raising kids
MS Companies
Really starting to take off like at end of 2013 you've got
80000 customers
Like 300 employees
But you're still under the radar like like no one knew who you were
Yeah I like better by Design
Company only Canadians could have failed because this ad
Our job is to make our Merchants look. Like this is why they exist
So he wouldn't put Shopify on the mix in stores like at this point
Peace and blessings be with me ask me
You know I'm looking at these numbers
It's a significant company how come I've never heard of you
You bought something with shop at 5 Los Javier
It wasn't like to experience it was
ISO
If it just doesn't stay so if I don't go to South Africa
Other people's lives it's been other people go to home on internet and so on
You didn't put that name Shopify the building of snow
You were in 2014 you were named the CEO of the Year by
Bicycle of male witches
Are these papers Canada so that was really one of the first times people even heard of device
Look at for you to recognize
You just moved out of your inlaws house
It was pretty surreal
It's not something
I love ass eating
A crappy CEO
4 years before that you're still struggling to like figure this out
Yeah that's exactly
Properly summarize mix.
There was a little bit of a surprise to me
What came out of it
But I love
I'm missing something
I am Daniel talked about
And Scott theology
Talked about this
In the early
Days of
Going for Pia after a week off
Programming
Is that
What
Happen if it's too distant book
Amethyst before investing
Thinking cap
Schlotzsky's kind of fishes
Heavyset
WK
Because you know what
No matter what we going to do now
This is going to be proud of all of our life
Chinese in all of us
Phantom
People be able for rest of our lives two things you couldn't do if you wouldn't back on the
Best no wave at the resident you learning office is not going to be
I can fall of us
You guys
Go public
In 2015
You went public
Because presumably
Your investor
Just wanted you wanted
It's a kind of give them return
This is
15 people
Started giving you money in
Mm
4 is that the reason why you went
He probably would have become the reason eventually but not at this
Point of time because
Ben basement only happened 5 years before that and
I took the Investments knowing that
I'm going to be racing the clock
To Idaho public office
Cancel it
Map us to Tuality of about coming by way of
This is true for Evie
A person who sells
The company
Just most people don't realize
What's happening
But I've been in
Into the Venture of a pretty clear about what it means
And so I really wanted
To set up a company to become an independent
Papa Company because
My private investors have all seen Shopify
Perform under-promise over-deliver
Month after month and vomiting after board meeting
All of them
40 trusses
The company and and fervor good performance was not fillet
Buying us in it
More than 800 thousand Shopify merchants
Will have
Purchase something on a site that's powered by Shopify
Does a very good shape since we talked about
That's
Decimals gratifying
Numbers relate to shop for and it's active now.
A B-52
2 seconds
Someone has that experience of getting up
For sale
The one that are described
And so many cases
Someone
Is going from being a builder
Turned out being an entrepreneur
That's so few things but you can do that actually change
Joe identity to a meeting for the great red
Anthem
Bus companies
Hardest really really thought process and trying to
Make this simpler
What's been so fascinating inside this initial idea
Behind snow devil the idea that being able to write
Computer software is like a specialized to Alana on a climbing trip
If I wouldn't have a specialist with me I would have had to turn around because someone's I just couldn't have
And then
What's up family is it's a selfie I wish it would have found ride like a text all these
Vertical balls and transform into insights like they're not it's not flat
Select still how to build a business
But at no point do you need exactly because of that significantly more
People succeed in building
Because
I just noticed
Discouraging experiences
Which make you give up even though you shouldn't have
And so
Body found at the best thing we can do for the pesos of Shopify
It's fine
Another one of us thinks which is
An incline and just flapping it
Best much as you can every single time you do it
More people succeed and more businesses
Kobe in 2004
You did not even have a war
5 years ago
You'd moved out of your in-laws
Place
Today
Easily the biggest employer in Ottawa aside from the federal government
You are
Wealthier than you can
If ever imagine and might be
Weird
To be a
Billionaire
I mean it's
Totally
Music
Is there any part of you that could have imagined
Honestly even know about Utah
Talk about assistance
Crazy to me I probably
Try to just don't think too much about it
It's
Hugely gratifying but it's also
I think the important thing is just that I
I remind myself how much
The most amazing work coming
Wonderful
Family hearing
Kinda
Time to support us along the way
Incredible timing
Off Wendy status
I'm like this is not a kind of company
The clippings.
Into yesterday
It needs beside right then and I need to be ready and good by the time
Opportunity around
Financial crisis came around
All these things been with you in public
End
La cosecha major component of
Entire Journey
Like why am I the person who ended up
You know winning the lottery five times in a row I don't know
You are like equations and number so
Eserve half answered my last question
But what percentage do you think
Of this journey is like and what
Incredible skill as a programmer on your talent
I think it's
I don't know if you know what I kind of modified it's it's a huge component
Luck
Basically all I can do is enjoy it and then
Be honest about what happened
Yeah and then
It's definitely the best idea I've ever had and I hope that I can run this to the end of my career because had a female
Amazing that's how we looked at founder and CEO of
Shopify since its launch the Shopify platform has been used for over a hundred billion dollars
E commerce sales worldwide
By the way Toby has his own little side hustle on Shopify
Do you like a secret
Shopify store like JK Rowling has like you know pseudonym Steve your own like secret shop
Yes of course you too
Sucks Mandy his birthday
What's this song called
That I look at you
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear for
View about the things
Your building
The first
A quick message from one of our sponsors
Squarespace
Design and build your own website
Features including mobile editing
Go to squarespace.com
NPR forum
Free trial
Venues offer code
NPR
10%
First purchase
Website or domain
Hey it's my Latino USA
Every week we bring you a mix-up reporting diverse voices
And coverage of current and emerging issues
That impact
Our Lives
Latino USA is one of a kind
Featuring stories
From the heart
Stories that make you think and maybe even inspire you to action
Listen And subscribe now
Hey thanks for sticking around
I know for how you built that
And today story starts about
4 years ago in Houston Texas
When was
Babysitting her granddaughter
It was quickly running out of things to do with her
I mean I wanted to take her to Gymboree and I wanted to
Take her to the park
But then I said but wait I can't really put her in the
The car seat in the car seat
Because she has arthritis in your thumb
And pushing the big red button to release the
Buckle
It's hard
Yes it's very hard if I mean it's just even people that can do it sort of hate it
Because they have to struggle and it hurts for safety reason
It actually takes about nine pounds of
Pressure to release that red button
How do you do that if you don't have enough
Strengthen your hand
Fortunately for Barb it
Turns out she had
The perfect set of skills to solve this problem I'm an occupational therapist
Which means her job is to help people with disabilities accomplish daily tasks
So using some pliable plastic that
She had lying around the house
Fart made a tool that could help her release the buckle on Eve's car seat
It's kind of a a c shape
Device
And the upper arm has a
Hague in the center
So can you take this
Complexity
You slide it under the car seat
Buckle you place the peg over the red button and then you push and you kind of pants and that
Will release the buckle
Super simple ideas
Actually work the first time Barb tried it
I was pretty excited and
Honestly just started using it and it was really Rebecca that said Mom
There's probably other people that would like this
Enter Barb's daughter Rebecca Rebecca is
And she also happens to have a
Background
In business
I think I said to her I said Mom
You know what if we what if we made this
Consoled
You know I've always had an entrepreneurship in the back of my mind but neither Rebecca nor bar of new if they were really
Rihanna something
Sowell Barb kept working on different prototypes
To get the clamp exactly right
Rebecca started a poke around a little too
Do some research
So I asked him learning about the ABC Kids Expo
One of the largest
Juvenile product trade shows in the country
And we ended up going it was kind of a last-minute decision truly travel to Las Vegas
Go to this big mansion
Oh my gosh it was
It was amazing it was one of the most
You know energizing experience as I can remember
People just thought I thought
Yes that is a need and that is
Solving a problem it's in the market
Game all the traditional milestones
Kickstarter campaign finding a man
Manufacturer and delivering the first orders
But then
A not-so-happy sign of
Success
Other vendors were starting to copy their device
Hey. It's kind of a gut punch
When you see it we just both went
It makes you feel just so defeated because
Yeah you know that they haven't gone through
The sweat in the
Alliterations in the bucket full of prototypes Rebecca and Barb did manage to get
Two patents for the product
They've been able to shut down some of the knockouts
Meanwhile Rebecca says that
By going into business with her mom
Chia seeds
Tirely new side of her
When it comes to this business I think my mom
You know it is such a go-getter and she's
Get on the phone and we'll call up retailers and yeah she's got the hustle and
It's really been that kind of a cool experience
Rebecca Davidson
Bob Hammons products
It's called unbuckleme online and it's a major chains like buybuybaby
And since they launched the business two years ago they made about $350,000 if you want to
More about their business or your previous episodes had to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org
Of course if you want to tell us your story going to build. Npr.org
Love during what
Your building
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week
Describe an apple podcast
Or wherever you get your podcasts
Why you're there please do give us review
You can also write to us at HRBT
Npr.org
And if you want to sell
Tweet
At how I built this
I'm at Gyros
Our shows produced this week by Kacey Herman with music
Decomposed by run teen Arab Louie
Thanks also to Julie carne Viva grandson has Michigan for
Jeff Rogers
Our intern David job
I got rise
And even listening
How I built this
This
Is NPR