Invited me to Ruth's Chris Steakhouse in Dallas and said this is going to work out here driving
Everybody is saying in this company and reach across the table and held my hands and I was crying and
Everybody even your even the people that your biggest supporter said I thought you had to go
Running PR
How I built this
Show that innovators
Entrepreneurs
Heelys
Stories
Airline travel
And again and again
To create one of the most
Innovative carriers
Us
JetBlue
So few days ago
I flew on a
Budget Airline
What's public radio guys
Anyway
Pictures of shorts
Flight so no big deal I know what to expect
Non-refundable tickets
Middle seat in the
Back of the plane
Iboard last
No recline no legroom no TV no snacks
Print my ticket out at home
It's fine that's a trade-off
As long as I get to where I need to go safely
I'm more or less fine
But once in awhile
The route I'm taking is one that JetBlue flies and the prices the same
And with that ticket
I get a seat that does recline
A snack
Beverage
Really nice flight attendants
TV
Which is why wouldn't JetBlue debuted in 2000
It made such
A big impact
It was a discount carrier that
Albertsstuff the most premium Airlines were already off
Or in some cases not offering
Customers noticed pretty fat
In less than a year
JetBlue flew more than a million passengers
And quickly built a super loyal following
And that was the vision of JetBlue's founder
David neeleman
To build a more Humane Airline
But the thing is
David's passion for a better flying experience
Actually came from his own background
His own face
David's family is Mormon in the Mormon faith emphasizes civility
Every practicing Mormon is encouraged to go on a mission when they're in their late
Teens or early twenties
Back in the 1950s
David's father was sent
A missionary trip
Brazil
He loved it so much
He went back as a journalist and started a family
Which is why David was born in Sao Paulo in 19
David's dad move the family back to Salt Lake City
Where was just going to baked in the everyday life
I was in a pretty conservative place I mean it was obviously a place that was
Was founded by
Brigham Young
And as they started the church they moved across
The Country Inn
My mom said the family were
We're Pioneers they came in covered wagons
My grandmother Seven Generations back
A lady by the name of Sally Hewlett
The family stories that she was giving a book of Mormon by Joseph Smith himself who's the founder of the
Heart urchin
And a lot of people have those stories Mei most everyone you
You mean it's all like has a story of somebody who either cross the plains across the ocean
You know how to grandmother died on the plane to his just kind of that
Part of our laurelville religion and end these Pioneer families
We're entrepreneurial in any way but did you lie
What cars are
What black dogs running like that
My grandfather had a few grocery stores
Small grocery stores you call the Miniature Market
We're like fast food
And we should make the sandwiches in the back and bring it fresh donuts
You're kind of a precursor to maybe a 7-Eleven but everything was done fresh
So when I was 9 years old I got a job there
Standing on a milk
Crate
Working the cash register checking out people you know counting money
So that was kind of my introduction to business in my
My grandfather was a really
That was so he was born in Salt Lake but his whole family came from Holland
And so you know he paid me $0.50 an hour which kind of made me mad cuz everyone else made a dollar an hour
He expected more out of me than the other kids and
He was really f*** son customer service if somebody
If there was something in the store that somebody wanted and we didn't have it he'd run out the back door and run over to Safeway and buy it and bring it back
Yeah he was
He never wanted to lose a customer
I look back on those years and I didn't get to participate as much
In high school in
Things of sports
Just maybe as I would have
Wanted to do but
You know I think it probably taught me alot
About a lot of things
What's Church
A Big Sur Center of life for you as a
Kids are going to
Going to services and going on Sunday
Things like that
Ya always was I mean it was 3 hours on a Sunday and
It's a cultural thing you know I think as much as a religious thing so you have both elements
I need to know your neighbors you
Document
Church on Sunday you have boundary areas
In our church where
If you lived in a certain geographical area and then you have to go at this church at this time
And when it was
My time to serve a mission there wasn't even a question
I'm going to go on a mission just like
My dad did
How are you as a student
Fargo
I was
You know it's not that for lack of
Not wanting to be I just
It was something I'd I discovered later in life
But I had a raging case of ADD and I know everyone likes to say they do today but
It was really something that
That was tough for me because I
Yeah I was
I was gregarious in and I could get my way through things but I couldn't read
It was really hard for me to read and
Yeah I would read a page in a book and I could tell you everything that I thought about why was reading that page except for
I was on that page you couldn't
Now he's really Harden
If you asked me today what was my favorite book I read Highschool I couldn't tell you cuz I don't recall even reading a single book in high
Yeah I got through it
Yeah with pretty decent grades but
Did horribly on the ACT I think I
I got like an 18 or something
And I think my reading was
Below 10
My counselor said I don't know how you got to score the slow had you just marked C on every answer you have gotten a higher score
Score
So he tried to get the lowest score possible
And this is what I learned about add afterwards
If it was something I was interested in I would devour
Play services something that I wasn't interested in ideas
Couldn't focus on
It was really hard
This is it this is life
The 70s
People weren't really diagnosing add it wasn't like a
The common saying
That people talk about
Now it wasn't and it wasn't until years later
When my little brother
Have a little brother that
Guitar
Is 18 years younger than I am I'm almost nineteen years
That he was diagnosed with it
And that my mom
To read this book called driven to distraction
By dr. Hallowell
And my mom sent me the book and she said you know marks has been diagnosed
With this
I think
You might have this
Hand
It was the night of course didn't read the book
But I did read there was there was 21
Characteristics of somebody
Who has ADD
And I read those 21 things and I just put
The book down and I just like got tears in my eyes and I all wow this is
Me
I guess you were you were 19 when you went on your
Commission for the church
Basically you are assigned
To a country
You go and and do Mission work right
Cracks and I was so fortunate
To be to be assigned to Brazil and I think part of the reason
Is because I was born there and I had a Brazilian fast
What's out
It was just
It just kind of
Random
He's put it in and
You receive your call and your call says you're going to be going to Brazil
What was your impression of it I mean what
What should I tell you when you got there
Yeah I've been there several times and I was
But my dad being a journalist and being a
Foreign cars
Responding and he knew all the Rich and Famous and so every time we would go visit Brazil
We were hanging up sports clubs or hang out at the beach we're going to the best restaurants in
Everything was just like wow Brazil is a cool place everything's so amazing
But you know what your missionary you don't hang out with those rich people
Divarty
Got their God do you know that it's their money or yellow or whatever they don't they're not helpful enough to
Change it's really the people that are really downtrodden really down on their luck
Does it have virtually nothing that listen to your message and so
I spent all my time with those people and end
Wow
It was an eye-opener for me
You obviously in in United States
We have disparity of income in classes but
At least you have an ability to move from one class to another
If you work hard and you're lucky I know you have some blocking you know you do
Certain things you have student loans and other things in Brazil it's virtually impossible to do that
And it made me very resentful
And you know I really
Ended up yeah I got tucked away in my mind
Did I win if I wanted to come back to Brazil
And I wanted to do something
How to help these people
At some point time in my life and kind of make my conch
Tribution
And did you cuz I'm just tryna remember my experiencing
Young young missionaries
What did you wear
A black tie in a white shirt and like around on a bike
Just like the guys in the play in New York City
We didn't have a bike but we had white shirts
Mens short sleeve white shirt
You're just a tide at DeSoto black tie and slacks
But I also I was very successful in
I'm kind of being a leader in the first time I had ever done that
And then
Also just learning disciplining and kind of overcoming my ADD
Being able to read scriptures in to learn a language in
When I came back from a mission
I was able to
Go back to the University Inn
Where I left getting seasoned he's I was home getting straight A's
Well
Yeah it made me I grew up a lot in it
They taught me discipline which is something that
I have learned in my
And my childhood because of my ADD
It might be kind of a stretch but
Means something like a weird way
It's almost as if
Your experience as a missionary
You are essentially pitching
Something to eat
If you're pitching and in this
Taste the word of God right
You're pitching
Your face
And you're trying to convince people
About
What it's done for you and how it's
Fulfilled your life
It's like business writing your pitching
Something you believe in
Yeah I mean it
There's a lot of companies that are in Provo Utah
Did you door-to-door sales of alarm systems
Pest control and whatever
And got to take all these
Please Kaiser come in Galveston from over missions
They're kind of fearless now
And then they said go sell alarm system ago sell Pest Control
Some people go out for the summer and make $50,000
I just
They are selling pest control or selling alarm systems door to door
So when you got back to
To the US
Were you were you single at the time
I was
And you got married right away and start having kids
Went to work when you were in college
Yeah
Yeah it's kind of
At what you do you know it's
The way it works at the church you get home and you're encouraged to get married and
We got married in December and our first child was born on November 1st so
Academy 11 months later
And it was just kind of Off to the Races from there
When you are on when you got back
Started up a college again
University of Utah
Rickettsias you start a business
As mobile
I did I was
Sitting in my accounting class
Sunday in
How is
Talking to someone who's sitting behind me and her name is Lily Rowe nags to remember
And
How she told me about this
Guy who who
This man who is a friend of her mother's
That own some timeshares
In Hawaii at this place called the Imperial Hawaii Resort
And he was having difficulty selling the timeshares
And so
I got this idea to go talk to him I said give me his name and I'll call him up in his name was a Libra and so
I called him up and I went down to meet with him and I said
Hey how about if I just rent your timeshares out cuz he was paying a weekly maintenance fee on all of them it was kind of drain
Let me let me feel him up and he said ok
So I under the resort accommodation section of the local newspaper
For the time
I would just run little one.
Say hey Hawaii condo for
$75 a night
Or whatever 50 bucks a night
Sleep
6 and so I start getting phone calls
Batman I booked them
And I
That pay him hundred thirty-five bucks I'd collect four hundred bucks an hour to keep the different suck it was
I was doing a couple of hours a day and next thing you know
I was making some pretty good money just filling up these
Condominiums in
And then I started getting other ones and one day I heard about an airline it was right after deregulation
It's like the early 80s 78 was deregulation so the airlines that was kind of sprouting up
So there was an airline call Pacific East
And I called the guy that was running it
In LA and I said hey
I'm not a travel agent anything but if I send you some money will you
Can you send me some airline tickets
Urso
I'm I would
Send you the money hit send me the tickets and then out
I would packaging with these hotels and then I would save
299 yuan
Fly to Hawaii but you got to drive to La Sophie
People tell I wheel of Hawaii
Yeah you tons of always love to why so they jump in the cars in the drive down to LA
Hop on this
Pacific East old dc-8 and fly over to Hawaii
You did this while you were a college student you just like
Create package holidays
Four people yeah that's how I did it then
I bet she dropped out of college
He's doing
6 million dollars a year
Yeah and it was
I had that all staff of people and we were
Sales people people to come in and sit down with your own brochures of different
Hotels that we had or different condo cuz then I would call it over to other places and say hey can I buy a block of rooms
For twenty bucks at night that's okay and so I just started packaging him
That was all working well until
There was
I have a new airline to started
And I was old enamored with this because it was Hawaii
Express and had a big pineapple on the tail and they flew 747
So I said why would I switch to these guys
So I started buying tickets from them
And then right before Christmas
It was 1982
Maybe 93
They called me up and said you know what they were ceasing operations tomorrow
Tomorrow they said well
We don't have any money and I said my prepaid all these people is right before Christmas
People pay for the hotels by no way of getting mobile all across all the airplane tickets were full I didn't have money to send everybody over there and so
It was
Kind of a disastrous time and I learned a huge lesson from that bit suited me well through the years but
It was obviously very difficult to go from
A point where I had this thriving business to for Monday the next I purchase it had nothing
Wait that
That white business out
It did because I had prepaid you know every single ticket
And it was about a half a million dollars
And
Yeah I probably had
Yeah couple hundred thousand that I have my own money in
And I should have at the time just called everybody I'm said like I can just give you half your money back
Of course you know you file for bankruptcy not personally but it was the business in
And then that you know their lawyers and get it getting most everything so
I was
Have the time I was
In my early twenties I name is 20
23 or 24 slide that I really didn't know anything about business or
How does zelle work
See you were like a living you were probably like
Like thinking
I'm sad like this is going to be
Yeah I was I went out and bought myself a BMW thought I was
See how things were great and I never I never bought another one again after that
I learned my lesson
Yeah you're young things are coming easy it's good the money I make imagine you your first condo
You sell you get mix Ram
50 bucks on it
Ask me for
2 weeks
Just that one cell that one phone call
So
It started up fast it
Was very successful and then boom
Collapse
So you are a College Dropout
With a failed business
And by that point you had at least one kid I guess
Two kids by the ndk
So
What did you what did you do what you do for work
Well my father-in-law had it drapery business
And I was kind of working the backroom kind of doing the county and stuff
So I went back to doing that
Am I grant my grandfather's grocery store I went back to work how many grandfathers doors
She started just like I did when I was 9 years old
Without the refrigerant nightstand dehydrated
No I didn't I lost the milk
Trey Teddy could stand up
The cash register
But yeah
Baby marijuana
Get out of bed do anything but yeah I just kind of like
Said I got to keep going and so
And then I got a call from
My my uncle Stan
Who just happened to be
The
State lawyer for
The Morris family
Ajuna Mitch Morris
And June ran over successful Travel Agency in Salt Lake City it was
Dealing with mainly corporate travel
At the time
So I called up and said June Morris
To talk to you
About doing some of the things that you were doing on your own for her company
She was older than me
Oh yeah
She's about the age of my parrot
And so we sat down
And she gave me a big smile and she said yeah right
If you come to work for me I'll make sure you get a piece of the company
You know you would we can do this together and
And I really liked what you did and so she convinced me
She convinced me to do that and so I
Kept the job at the store at night
I would go there during the day
And and
Call dipaulo's hotels and said hey
I'm back
I know I called up Hawaiian Airlines that I had this
Contract in my drawer
I'm at my Mio law office
It was a tie Charter contract to fly at
Hawaiian Airlines
Charter
From Hawaii to Salt Lake directly
Bypassing the drive to LA
And I just didn't have I was just getting together the bond my new the $250,000 Bond cuz was a public charter
And I was just trying to arrange that when the other Airline failed
So I went back to the drawer I got the contract out I went to June and I said if Mitch
Your husband can can help with this Bond
We can launch these flights
It's directly from Salt Lake City Hawaiian Airlines flight direct from Salt Lake
To Honolulu or wherever
Yeah it was a it was a what we call the reverse rotation that plane wood
On a Friday night would start in Honolulu and it fly nonstop to Salt Lake and then it would turn around Saturday morning and fly back
So that was the fly it's been
Yeah basically seven days six nights in Hawaii
And then
Play directing the whole package was 399
Cuz we were buying the charter flight until we started this company called Morris are Charters and that was kind of the Hallmark of our of our trip
Was this DCA that would it would make this trip
And so Hawaiian called me after one season and said hey Des Plaines going to be going back
In about 6 months
Can we come and face the plane in Salt Lake
Until you can fly straight to Hawaii and back but
For the other six days a week is there anything you want to do it this airplane
And I said yeah I want to fly to La you know there's a lots of lots of Mormons in LA and and lots of family interest between the
The to my grandparents were there and
Yeah I kind of spent
My whole life in the back seat in a back of a station wagon driving Death Valley
Between Salt Lake in LA and I thought
If I could sell those tickets for cheap and I had
Read up a lot on Southwest Airlines
You heard was my hotel who is my was my hero and I had read every
Annual report ever on those guys it was kind of my dream to to be like them so
I put lights on to Los Angeles for $69 using this old airplane
Fly in the Old West Imperial terminal
Parked in Salt Lake for 6 days a week
Is going to Honolulu once a week
Nintendo's and they said look you can
Listas from us
Do whatever you want with it for her for those are the days
Right
So I said let's fight a lie 3 days
And so we ran an ad in the newspaper
And the first day I didn't give me calls and then
I'm never coming in
The next day at work
And I heard verlo who is our receptionist sing
I have
24 Los Angeles
Calls on hold somebody please help me
I would rather go there and start answering the phones myself and booking people on piece of paper in
It was funny cuz there was a glitch in the system so we were basically overbooking every flight by a hundred people
Bucking everyone
We we lost we're getting money on that but
You know it was
It was a
It kind of a big success from the very get-go
Set up a travel agency
Which kind of focused on package tours
Chartering planes
But then you become you said you be coming
Airline did you and June to Dad's you ever sit down June is a hake
Let's become an airline or did it just isn't going to happen that way
Well it was about that time that Steve Harvey who's a well-known entrepreneur and the aircraft leasing business
He called up and said hey
My wife's from Utah you're my relatives come flying on you guys all the time you need to get legitimate
You know I have some I have some airplanes
I will miss you but I want you to get your own airplane seat
At this point this is what like a t
Mid 80s
Yeah I was probably late 80s
The Steve voorhis
Famous guy he's a
Made tons of money in
Aviation and funded.
When the air and space Museum outside Washington DC
He comes to you he says
Hey you should
Start your own airline with your own name on it
Right eye and he said I got a guy that can help
And there's a guy named Yusuf
And you still was at Old fa guy
I called you stow and he was living up in Idaho and he came down it so
Okay what's certified
You still live is any some hitting nineties this guy in
Call me a bracelet and said you got a little something for me to do I'm still here so
But he did
20 desertification and end
And June was really funny
She she wanted to compass rose on the tail cuz that was logo of her travel business
They put a compass rose and then she wanted it
To be magenta
That was her color
Until we made these planes are the Blue towel with the magenta comforter
It was called Morris air
Google Finance
Did did did June Morris and her husband finances did you get investors to
Cuz you're the
High Plains
At least them
Initially we were just making a cash flow we were just using that and you know you aren't buying airplanes you just
You agreed to pay them like a monthly rent payment on the airplane
With Leasing and then
They take
Can certain amount per hour in reserves for maintenance and then when the plane's going for maintenance so use that money to do it
Lights out
It doesn't require a lot of capital
From the very beginning and so we were we were just kind of bootstrapping it and that's why we got Mitch was really funny though cuz
During those years we were making money
Which was in a Marlin
Image was butcher
Yeah he was really a great guy one of the most
Amazing man I've ever met he was a great mentor
But it's okay to smoke weed and do guys
We're going to do 1/3 2/3 and 1/3
There's going to the government
Third Estate in the company
And a third is going to be Whiskey Drinking
Antar whiskey Drinkin by
So it's okay cuz I was our return for what we distributed so
So when one year I got my
I was in my
Maybe 26 or 27 and I got my
Whiskey Drinking money and it was enough for me to pay off my house
How do I win
The first thing I did is I went down to the bank
Where am I
Family had done business forever
And yeah we're this Banker was kind of
Knowing that my dad was always use always cover my dad's overdraft tracks of my grandpa's overdraft
Jack's
Kind of nudity Disneyland Mancino didn't have a lot of money
Since I walked in there with
I thought he was $165,000 check and I said I just want to pay off my house
Baumann
He said okay
Detective took the money
Until 8 by time I got back
To the office
June called me in and said hey
Your Banker called and said
That headed to inform you this but someone in your company is embezzling money
Oh she's got the biggest kick out of that so
I went back and closed my account and moved on to another
Bertha is
Could imagine that somebody that my age
Kind of an element
Hetalia always hard-working people but didn't have that kind of money
We could walk in and pay off their house when they were in their midst
And then just
A few years after you launch Morris air
Southwest
In 1993 buys the company for $130
I mean
What's been incredible
Tutu did the debate happen
What happened a couple of
You know I really care about things happening around that time
I idolise software
And yeah I kind of
I just like
Dairy I can't even tell you how I felt about that company
You know Kim and when I was still out with pattern everything we did after
Southwest
There was a few things that we did it more Sarah that Southwest wasn't doing one of them is that we invented e-ticket rap
I mean the first ticklish travel was done at
In the world
And it all came about because a guy who works at the timing Stewart Thatcher came into my office
Yeah you know I just went up to the
4th floor we have like 50 people up there
Printing tickets and stuffing them and mailing them out
Why don't we just come up with a computer-driven form that we can just
Go through it you know automatically
Gets that has a confirmation on Marana weed smell people that weigh weed
Six of their confirmation
Why don't we just give it to him over the phone and why do we have to mail a manything
Cuz well people will have some in their hands
Let's get a fax number we can still mail it to him
But we don't really need it at the airport
Rental cars don't have it and
Until we didn't have a repository for that information so I had to
A young guy that was back it up the computers and he kept telling me he could ride it to New reservation system
So I said
Why don't you
Redis reservation system
And he said
I don't know if I can do it and I said well
I'll give you $20,000
And you can buy yourself a Jeep
If you can do it
Until
He he went out and
And
Rought the system
And got it all done and we were we launched
The same as the first e ticket Airline
What's Southwest didn't know what a great thing they were buying that was really kind of the best thing that they were buying from that
They were
And have credit today in the Smithsonian is being the
First ticketless Airline
It was really our system that did it
But I'm going back to a bit so
Herb called me up and and you know said hey you know I hear you might be interested in selling and then
Tell her you're
Your Idol
Yeah I can believe it when he's on the phone I can still remember hearing his voice I like
Iherb
How would you like to come down me with this
And so I went down and out with them and
Smoke Filled Room with all these guys in there that I had idolized over all the years
And then I felt then I came home and then we found out that you had
I'm a very serious form of cancer
It was called inflammatory breast cancer
So I went in my office
And I was just sitting there staring at my phone and it rang and I pick it up
And it was a guy named Jim Weichert
And I was
He said how you doing I go
He is a guy with Charter planes from
My son is sick I just found out June has
Is terminal breast cancer
Inflammatory breast cancer know what
What I'm going to do
And he said
Gator on airplane now
And I said what do you mean
She scheduled for surgery no no don't let her have the surgery
We know this doctor blumenshine that
Is is
Is cavi amazing success with this
So I called up June I said June I just booked your ticket on American Airlines you need to get on there
So she raced out to the airport got on the airplane
Because when they
But they found his if you had the surgery do it spread the cancer through your body
And they needed to
Tezapp
And get rid of
The first cell
She got on the plane and he convinced her to go into the treatment and they just took her almost
You know Ted to dad let me borrow marrow transplant everything
And she lived
And she still like today and wow
She and I have a very special relationship
From this day
Because of that
That is it was a it was a miracle
And so
She was going through this treatment and Herb's there and so I'm sad
Simjang you want to sell this company she said yes I do
So you're like in early 30s
Do you believe God
December cash like
At least 20 million bucks and
All of a sudden you become a
4 year Southwest Airlines
Herb
Yeah he he always tells a story that I had my
My Book of Mormon
My Bible and my Southwest Airlines annual report
In my car no that was my scriptures
Not too far from the truth
So we were
Yo clothes and and he said look I want to put you on the executive planning committee
Which is our top
A steering committee
And I was just
Setting this meeting
And I would just
Watch these guys
And it would just go on and on and
Every time I would say something that look at me like
What's the weather right now
Lesion pancreas know anything he's ever been hearing
So I used to just
I see this right
Don't say a word don't say a word to keep that writing and I just blurt out something else
They asked me to take two years to integrate Maurice into Southwest
And within six months I had it all done
I basically
Joint fuel purchase joint ground handling
Yashow everything was all done and
Chapas had this had the steel where they were charging off-peak fares
On Saturdays and Sundays
And after like 8 p.m. at night
I went to message guys
My atmospheres are on Sunday and you just
Switch them all.
Pete I'm losing like millions of dollars every month because
You're charging off peak
Let me charge Peak on this flight
And so I sat down with keoki Taylor the time he was he head of Revenue management I showed him all the numbers and
And it was during that time they switch to know when starting charging Peak for Sundays and they
Your Southwest
Has made profit
43 years in a row or whatever
And
They were so successful you know they didn't really need to find and I was
Just absolutely paranoid all the time and I had to keep tweaking everything
Thing all the time
And so I was pressing all that stuff at them and finally
Herb invited me to Ruth's Chris
Steakhouse in Dallas and said
Get out here driving everybody insane in this company
I said well
You're paying more for long distance per minute than we are I'm just try to get him to
Take our contract instead of your Contracting
Herb I got that the peak fares that I got that thing integrated I got this
He said I know David but that
That's 5 mods
You should have taken you longer to do stuff and I said alright I was in tears it all but you were supposed
Stu
Stay in Southwest for at least 2 years
And we love our way he kind of led me to believe that if I just
Minding my p's and q's that I would be a success or what
You know that I care
You know I'm following his footsteps in
You know obviously there are other people that wanted that job and I was young and completely didn't fit into the
My ADD was just
Raging
So you were supposed to I mean this is going to be your employer and maybe you would have
Succeeded herb Kelleher is it
Harris Southwest and you were
We were fired up
Like 5 or 6 months
Yeah in May
So I started in December and they fired me in May
I can't imagine him like yelling at you and say
Get out of my office
Delete let you down gently
Oh yeah he wish across the table and held my hands and I was crying and
He just said you know it's just
Not going to work
I said everybody
Even your even the people that your biggest supporters say that you had to go
David neeleman may have been out of a job
When we come back
How he built the framework
That would become
JetBlue
Play with us
Gyros near list
How I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Facts on the state of Market
Industries and the globally kind
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman
You'll hear a range of topics
From the tech IPO
Landscape to China's economic Outlook
Look and much more
That's exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcasts
Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play
And it gs.com podcast
Support also comes from NPR
Answer game
The Bold way to
The steady growth
People often think annuities are too conservative
Too complex
Or only for retirees
But annuities
This can be a smart way to hedge Market
Risk and earn guaranteed return
Game Bridge aims to change the game
By offering simplified annuities in a Sleek digital Experian
That replaces fine-print
Phone tag
Nike with clear conditions
Nintendo Direct
Sophie Mudd
Learn more at gamebridge. Live
X / NPR
Game Bridge
If not available
What all states
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
And the old man was just fired from Southwest Airlines
Southwest
Company
Idolized
Not work for
Airlines for
5 years because of Southwest non-compete clause
So David
He went home
I went home and I spent a couple days at home and
I feel like I can't do this
I'm not going to I'm not going to retire
Until I went down tonight
I rental office instead of going to work everyday in Salt Lake and by this time Dave Evans who was my partner had been
Going back and forth
Dave Evans I'm guessing
You guys were together
Yeah and he came to me said look
Ticketmasters the future
Why don't we build a system in and sell it to all the airlines
So I said how much money he will take and he said
A million dollars so I said okay let's
Let's do it
Guinness hard remember but like even in the mid-90s when you're running the company
Like an airline ticket was a was like up a booklet with carbon copy
Pages
Like you would die
Bring this physical
Booklet
To get onto a plane
And Heaven help you if you lost
I know you were here in trouble if you lost the 85 big forms
Lost ticket forms and then they had these big auditing departments would look for him and
You. Keep coming back every 3 months
See if there
Did anyone ever claim your ticket and if not then you have maybe they would give you a refund at the end of
I'm so
It was a it was a real pain
What's the Circle K
You guys I guess you guys wanted to build
The reservation system that you could essentially then sell to the airlines
Why wouldn't
Xiamen airlines
To do it themselves
Well they didn't
Airlines had these big Mainframe computer systems they were using the time and everything was done are flat
So there was no relational databases
The actual the database was actually
So if you lost your ticket
And so it became a negotiable document
And they didn't have any other way of tracking
And then they would look at things
In the rearview mirror that happened 3 or 4 months ago
Dad no forward-looking ability
At the time
And so by us building the system we allowed people have real-time information all the reservations that were coming in
Yeah we can tell them
You know what the average fare was with the
But the love doctor wasn't he's fly all the
Stop that they never have before
It's always a huge it was a revolutionary change for the airline business
Set the time
And so did that during this period of the non-compete and
About halfway through the non-compete I called
A cup of coffee I made a year-and-a-half into it I called her man
I said hey herb
You know I've consulted
Aldea counseling
Kissing is not really
I mean I didn't get it consideration
He said David you're the last person I want to see the airline busy
I will fight you tooth and nail I do not want to see you in the airline biz
Alright fair enough and I signed it that's
I live by my word
You end up selling
Honest Company 2
New HP Hewlett-Packard
In 1998
And that's when you
Cat gets put your head down
Unless
The JetBlue idea but even before then
Understanding is that you actually started to
Think of
The JetBlue idea
Within a year after leaving
Southwest is that right
Yeah
I'm a new I had for years and I had the reservation system so I knew exactly what the reservation system would be
You know I just I just kind of biting my time
Understand this
Why
Did the graveyard of Airline like a failed Airlines is
Cute right like
Trump and liquor and
People movers what is called tw8ns
People Express
Like
What did you think the world needed like there were a bunch of Airlines
Southwest was
Thriving like
What was it that you
Thought
You could contribute to that
To that industry
Well I thought that
A couple things Southwest had a real book
That they didn't really violated the time
One of them did they never flew into
Kind of congested Airport
They didn't
Want because on-time percentage in
We are turning our plans in 10 minutes was just so important to them
That they didn't want
To go to near
Boston they weren't in Boston they want they were in Providence
The end
So they they they kind of skirted around airports they
Never went into SFO there were no clue
And so
They didn't really
Now go into these these East Coast
Congested airports in
You're Dumber who is the founder of people Express
Came to see me one time and I remember he was looking at starting an airline and you wanted to do in JFK
And he was saying
During the middle of the day you could run a bowling ball down the middle of
Of the runways at JFK throw me at night there's nothing in the day and there's a lot of people there
Search kind of file that away and and you know his
His airline didn't materialize
I so when it came time for me to
Profound
Your JetBlue I want it
To find a place that I could
Who starred in the NFL in the area where I knew there was a lot of people I studied
The New York travel Market
And so I thought well this the perfect place to put an airline
You thought you could do a discount Airline
Fly to places
The discount Airlines were not
Flying to
Yeah we're Southwest Airlines wasn't you remember that
The time to
Doll the carriers the Legacy carriers had accumulated so much
Stuff and pension programs in
Yeah that the customer service that time wasn't very good and yeah
We want to bring Humanity back to Eritrea
At yuan this is something that
I've kind of learned over the years
Number one is you don't just go star near line for the Sega starting you have to have
A reason for being but also
Just because
You're in a place where no one else
Flies or can fly
Doesn't mean
That
You know you can treat people poorly
So let's treat people awesome
Let's find a place that nobody else flies but fly fishing rods inside layering all this site say I was saying my team guys
Too much Overkill is Never Enough let's just keep lowering it on
Make it better and better and better
What did you want
Did you have a vision of what you wanted JetBlue to be
I mean
1990s
What that was rev I remember
Virgin Airlines
Flight in the 90s yellow TVs
Great food and it was just
It was very different
Felt completely different from any other Airline
Yeah and I know I was talking to earlier
Richard Branson early on
JetBlue was going to be called Virgin America
You're kind of funny story
Yeah I'm still
A little bit off the turnip truck coming from Utah you know
Richard invites me to fly over tonight
And I go to his house
And
Course he's there with his wife and speaking in the
Suave British accent
Completely enamored and then he
She looks go eat Indian food and I'd never eat Indian food buffet
For if you can believe that I love Indian food
It is a bus go watch a movie and he took me to his virgin theater in
And that
Please wife and I and we saw the full monty
Which was from Mormon guy was completely it a little off colour for me but
I came home got a chuckle about that move you better
Loving chicken curry which I had that night which I haven't been able to stop eating ever since so
But but Richard
At the time that he wanted a franchise fee and he wanted
To maybe change go to head gone to Washington and it convinced him that
Maybe he could change the laws on foreign ownership so he could control it
Where you may have answered launching JetBlue would have launched
Virgins us
Domestic Airline
Yeah I mean I thought that having a brand was important I flew on Virgin night
China's old TVs
Yeah I saw that whole service and I thought wow you know if I could create this this would be amazing
Soaps
5 year
Like. Of that like
Non-compete what ended I guess around 98
At that point like
Right when it ended is that when you announced that you were founding JetBlue did you
The units at Publix
Yeah I mean
I couldn't sell a ticket but I can do everything but
That's so
You know I had the reservation
System ready to go I had to
Could start working on it even before this night
Send it
Yammy we started flying in February of the year 2000 so
We were working hot and heavy we moved I moved the family to Connecticut
In July of 99
And we were funeral full Boar Head raised
135 million dollars
It's how we were all ready to go
Southwest
Revolutionize was they just peanut they never served
Food Rite Aid they was peanuts
Are pretzels and free drinks
Stand up
Very friendly service
And
And they also
Only flu and still do only flies
White 737 Boeing 7
So did you kind of look at that and say yep that's our best the model that we should go for Wii
You should get the same exact plan cuz I don't like to maintain one cup
Plain and not
Worried about food and all that
Yeah that was
I hired to be my CFO at JetBlue
Remember the name of John Owen and he was the treasurer at Southwest
And so he knew all the financial
About
Southwest know what they were buying airplanes from Boeing from and there by 7:30
Chris Evans
And we tried to go to Boeing we wanted the 737 we really wanted it
And we just said look how about giving us this price and they said
Too loud can't do that
Get ready to go see her bus and they said well go ahead so
Flew back to Washington DC weather North American officers were for air bison Armory coupon
Biking is a friend of mine today and he said
Cic of North America
Kefir are basset
The time he walks in and he says
Are you just here using us
Spoil
Are you really interested in buying airplane
And I said
I'm just here using you as foil but
Convince me you have a better plan
So he started selling us in
Kind of The Wider cabin the fly-by-wire
All the stuff the more seats
It's because we could we could go 262 seats on an airplane
And so I completely got
Convert it and bring it up
Upcoming below that number which I would have shaken with them on the first day
But we were willing with Airbus and we got to get the relationship
Airbus a320
Yeah so then that's their version
A320 is there there they competing
Planes you go with the Airbus
320s and
Put TVs in the back and
Free TV and
Nicesense
Fact I remember I've read I read somewhere
Quote of yours
You said
JetBlue is a customer service company
Describe it as a customer service company
It happens to fly airplanes
Which reminded me a lot of
Of Tony hsieh Zappos
Is he described
We were customer service company that happens
Esl shoes
Yeah
Is that is that how you thought I just
I just want to do everything and maybe it was because
I came up this whole notion of servant servant leadership
United maybe I learned that on my mission
Have serving others and
Firehouse Southwest that build their culture and
Yeah just about this thing at
Yeah we're going to go out
And we're going to take care of our people
And the people going to take care of our customers
It was funny cuz when I was talking to investors in New York they said
Hey dude your New York you're not going to find friendly people in New York
I said well I got a lot of life
Choose from so there's
Is 59 people after I'll find some nice people
And we sure did
You guys are
Profitable
Pretty quickly
And it is a difficult time after 9/11
One of the things that you did a lot
Do you fly the planes all the time YouTube making announcements
That you are the
The hair company and then you would sit on the planes and serve snacks and
How clean the planes
Without a sticker was a tree limb and what was that about
I just really want to stay in touch with her cousin
I really want to hear from them
You know not only what I get up and introduce myself but I would also
Jose Jimenez
Come by it's our snacks
But I also want to hear from your experience without company I want to know
What we did good what we did bad
You know what we can improve on
Any ideas you have for us
And then I had
Your other people in our company doing the same I just think
It's just incredible to stay in touch
With your
With your people and then
Yeah those working the flight
See that you care
Southwest
Their staff is unionized
And you did not have a union staff
Why did you feel like I don't want to deal with unions either that's going to
I just drag us down
What was her reason
You know I always thought if our people needs
Someone else
Become callous how to
Treat them
Then that would be
Pretty tragic
If I thought I didn't treat our people well enough
Did they needed somebody else
Then you know
That's how I can be I wanted to run
So
If I not being unionized and I could chip in and
Yeah pick up trash on the airplane and there wouldn't be a grievance file
Example her
And what one of the questions we ask in the interview process is
Now in your
Courier
Life can you give us some examples of where you left your area of responsibility and help somebody else out in another area
Because that was really something that we thought Avenue
It's amazing how many people couldn't come up with one single example
Have of how they could chip in and help out
Yeah we didn't hire a pilot that had
15000 hours and he was called me up screaming and I can't believe you would hire me I'm an experienced pilot
I went to the interviewers and they said well he couldn't come up with one single excuse if anything's ever done to help anyone other than himself
So
Yeah it was
It was a cultural thing in building the culture was important
David
One of the things about
Beerland
History is that it's a volatile right like
The price of oil is is huge Factor
Niigata recessions
Security scares 911
Traveled a lot less
-10 is it in general the margin
You know
Reliance is hugely profitable there generally
That the Martian
Fan right
Happy Camp
I mean it's a it's a business so you can make a lot of money and you can lose a lot of money
Yes it what is it that you guys
And how are you able to be profitable
So fast
For so long
Compared to
TIGER Airline
Well I think it was just a weird differentiator I mean people sauce and
Yeah we had to word-of-mouth and people love flying us but it's just
Building a better master
Trap and building a better company and and
Night I became enamored
At with this whole thing when I was running company
I read
This article call the constant customer
Some companies just grow quicker
The more successful
You know and they did a lot of research into what
What what it was about these companies that differentiated him from
From other companies
And there's actually United Airlines and Southwest in the article and it talked about the differences
Between the two and how they ran their business
And the three things they named was
You know number one is having people who work for you that are ambassadors for your brand
Adore your company
That feel valued in
And feel loved in a comfy
Number one number two was
Flawless X
Vacation on every single level you need to be completely flawless
And so
I web dashboards everyday what I can tell you everything's going on
At my company's Ein
On-time percentage when the last bag made it to the carousel on the most delayed flight
Everything about
That experience
She need to be Flawless and then
The third thing is you need to make it right with
The customer review
Make a mistake or you
Treat them imported whatever
You need to make them more loyal having had an issue with your company than if they had not had an issue in the
So JetBlue is like
Riding High
Profitable to Darling upholstery customers loved it
Then comes
Valentine's Day
The biggest ice storm in the Northeast in Lake decade
What happened
Well it wasn't just an ice storm it was
BFA had come out with this regulation
That it was only that year
Yeah it was only in 2007 where
They said if there is what they called ice pallets in the air
When you can't
That they reverse the next year they didn't have it anytime before that never had his head so is his what he's convergence of a
Where
Are planes
Got out to the runway to take off they called ice pellets
Planes worst planes are landing
I'ma Mendes
Storm moved and we had people stranded airplanes we couldn't get him back to the gate because
People say I
Actually Moore equine xi an hours
And so
It was a disaster and it was something that
And then you don't have to Dumpty was all over the place and it took us a long time to recover what happened what operation
National team failed Airline you know
It was just simply that simple I mean it was
You know they just didn't do a good job of handling the situation and
Your ass as I was
I was in the command center for
4 straight days
After you obviously got people off the airplane in
The octave
The first day but we had the whole
Play Swiss scramble then there was all kinds of bad publicity you know to the airline which is
You devastate for me
Person cuz we pride ourselves in running such great Airline
I think I set a record on that day
Where I started on the Today Show and I ended up on the Letterman show images of the you apologizing
Apologies explaining what happened
27 live interviews
All kinds of TV
But I came up with this
List of things that you know where we're going to do and then a Bill of Rights saying
This ever happens again this is how you become
But how did it
I mean how did it happen
I think
Their 1200 flights that were canceled
Over the next couple days ago
Why did it did this winter storm hit JetBlue harder than other airlines
Was it just a
A failure of management
What will ironically I think the others may have recovered better but Delta had planes out there
You know it's about the same amount of time if everybody was effect
It wasn't just us
Take us longer to recover
But also people expected more
I mean I think
Sometimes the media likes to build you up and then they like to
To tear you down
If you're flying too high
You know we're going to come after you if you if you're riding story we're going to tell about you but
You mess up even just this much
And then I was in a well on the way to fish
And making sure that it would never happen again when
And
Couple months
Later the board asked me if I would do
Just step up to be chairman In-N-Out
Kind of lettuce
Cielo at the time be the CEO
Here we go again and I wouldn't I was Herman this and but
It was different with this time obviously this was my baby I mean
I know it was I kill myself
His company
End
The Borg
Cuz you didn't it was a public company and now you work for the
Shareholders
They said
We don't want you to run it anyway
More
I can't imagine that wouldn't be deficit
Yeah it was it was
It was not steady but it was it was just absolutely the wrong decision
That was the worst
I mean if I
Maybe I was
My perception is better than what I actually my Persona is taking on a much bigger role.
We had a couple of
No guys on the board that were
Had developed this thing about founder syndrome and thought hey maybe it's better to turn over to someone
Take the kid I can run the company without the the passion and and just you know it's kind of like a regular
Business
They felt it that you had to be held accountable
Will Ferrell
For the
The blizzard
Absolutely I mean I had to be held accountable
And
Yeah and I was taking responsibility
I mean one of the board members kept saying to be quite apologize
Yeah we don't like you to apologize and said because
You're not you shows inside a week
Or whatever so we can blindsided by it
It's completely I mean it was a shocking thing that I couldn't believe it I mean
That was my office was just off the boardroom in the nr22 of the board members
MK management
Said you know this what we're going to do
And then they all got up and left
Got an airplane and flew away
Were you personally hurt
Oh yeah totally
Four years as I would land in JFK I would be hard even look over you know it JetBlue. Cuz it was hard to even see
CMI Airlines
I wrote a letter to
The crew members when I left
And I still had access to equity now so I set it out and I just said
Yeah I've always taught you that it's not really what happens to you is
It's how you do it
And so you know I've always had this lifetime dream to return to Brazil
And make a difference in the country of my birth
And
I'm going to do it
So I'm going to leave the board and you know I just want you to remember all those values and treat each other well
And I miss you
Terribly
Ain't nothing I'd like more to be back as your CEO but
You know that's not the way life is sometimes you don't get to make all the decisions and
Worst ever win the Bastion and I was gone
We can stop this park
Cast now and then
End of story you start another airline
You start a brand
New Airline
In 2008
Health Azul in Brazil by the way
Which one is blue
Was that
Will it delivered did you call Azul
Deliberately
Yeah
It was
I think it's obviously was have great affection for JetBlue and is always the closest thing in his old spino blue
Portuguese in Spanish so
I had made some trips down there in and you know it had this thing tucked away in the back of my head about
Going back to Brazil and making a difference
And
Did I had when I was a 19 year old boy
And one of the things that was amazing to me is how few people were traveling
I am Brazil
And I determined that there were two major reasons number one
The service just wasn't good
As far as Non-Stop
Twin Cities
25 largest cities in Brazil only had nonstops about
20% of the time but then they were like 50 cities that have no service that needed service that no one flew to these cities
And they're making people drive for hours makes airplanes the major aircraft manufacturer
Yeah they had they had during the military rule the military had done in tight traffic building Airport
But nobody flute to him
And then fairs were really high they were by double where they were the United States
So I thought
Well I'll go to Brazil I'll buy Brazilian made airplanes
What's your lowest smaller have a lower trip cost
And then I'll start flight all these cities that nobody flies to and it will be a bit
And it happened third largest
Airline in Brazil today
It's the number one airline in terms of daily departures
Number one Airline
And numbers of City surgery serve over a hundred cities
In Brazil
We have 800 flights a day we fly about 80000 people every single day wow
It's 10 years
Did you mean
You must have learned so many lessons along the way right at Southwest you are
Yeah they fired you for 5 months and you can do any better than and then you know
JetBlue office
Did the Borg
Decided they wanted somebody do there when you structured as well did you make sure
But that could not
Happened to you
Absolutely
I can't be fired it is privately owned
No it's probably it's on the New York Stock Exchange
But I have a voting control
Sensation picture that could not happen again fair enough
Absol
Penn kids
Yes
How were you able to
To all the
Stop like
Fly all over the place in
Could a board meetings and run these companies and also
Raz-Kids
How are you able to make
Time for the more you did did you
Fidget mix
Well I had a couple rules and number one is I always was home on weekend
I never
Since I don't golf
And I hate people who golf now
Have a joke I have but
No matter what was in the world I would make sure I was home
Yeah either Friday morning
Our Saturday morning and stay till either Sunday night or Monday night
So
That was
Really important to me I
Needed to be home I need to be recharged
Do with my kids and I need to be with them and you know
NFL
My daughters were dancing my sons were playing football or lacrosse I always tried to
Make sure I work my schedule around it so I would always be there for him if they need me and
And I tried to be the best father I could and we obviously
I wasn't there at 5 every night
To have dinner with them
But you know I had a lot of support from
You know my wife and and the kids
You know really
Helped each other I mean my
Oldest daughter was
Amazing and then the second daughter and then that their daughter and then
Finally got a signed number for until they helped
With each other and they and they chipped in and then when the first one got the driver's license they were
You helping all the kids around hit their lessons and so
It was really a family f
It's a great family and I know you didn't mention that I have
18 grandkids and three on the way
What is your sort of like dining
Principal as
A leader like now that you
Made mistakes and you
You know driven people crazy and kind of had time to reflect on
Kind of person you are you are what are you
What do you Aspire like how do you aspire to leave
What do you want people to say about you and I
Oh yeah David
He is
He made my life better
You know I
You know we have this
Thing at Isola where
I tell everyone I want this to be the best job you've ever had
I want you to look forward to come to work everyday until I walk around the company saying is this the best job you ever had is just the best job you had
If not why not
Cuz I think if you do that
Nephew matter
If your company matter
Then you're going to be more success
Yeah if you were plexing face the Earth
Primary Care
Yahoo wood-chopping memorial service
How many lives have you touched
Because I think the more people you touch in the more good that you do and then more people you serve
And the more lives that you change
The happy you are to
So all the things all worked
At 2223
Totally broke
I give you life
Dixie's
These Heights menu were broke
And then
Back to work in your grandfather store
And then all these amazing things happen
To you and your life
How much of that do you think
Is because you were
Really smart and hardworking and how much beef
Because of luck
Why I think obviously you have
Points of light
But I think you make
Your own life
Integrate
Add people
And I I tell people this that have ADD
Embrace it
It's you and it's who you are and take all the good for me
Might form of a TD has it have an ability to just look at a situation
That's very complex and simplify
And say what you do it this way
And
It drives my teams crazy cuz they're like no it's not that simple I'm so yes it is just go do this this and this
Json will have it solved
And so you know sometimes it's not that simple but
You know that's just who I am and that's how I'm wired I can look at a situation
And you know I can I can see
Solutions
And so
I'm brother if it was in the airline business or any other business I think I would have
Probably had that
Masculine
But you know certainly the airline business has been
My ticket to a lot of exciting times in my life and there's there's nothing like sitting in a cockpit landing and
Airplane in the NFL
4800 foot runway in Rio de Janeiro
To give you a trail and knowing that that's
You're planning your people and
Your happy customers on board
Its side
Aquinas real pets David neeleman
Founder
JetBlue
On top of building one of the most
Successful Airlines in Brazil
David that wants to watch another airline here in the US
It's still in the planning phase but the project has a name that
Oh and you probably noticed how Southwest founder herb Kelleher played a huge role in David's life
Poked her back she passed away soon after we recorded
This interview but
I was lucky enough
Years ago and
He told an amazing
Story
And you find that episode
On a podcast
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Going to hear from you about
The things your building
The first
Thanks to one of our sponsors
Smart Water
Your good taste let you to how I built this
Let your good taste lead you to
To the vapor distilled purity of a smart water
Yourself
Well thank you
Smart Water
Pretty smart
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Alfred how you built that
And today story starts
In May of 2008
18 in Queen Creek Arizona
Lisa Dalton was dating a software engineer name
Ryan
And Brian is
Is blind
And one day Lisa was at his house looking through his Pantry in making a shopping
He had 18 cans of refried beans and and didn't know it
So Lisa decided to reorganize
Also
A big mistake Kitty is memorization based system to organize what he had in the pantry
And
My man handling the goods I had completely messed them up but
Brian was
Forgiving
We said see it's okay you didn't know
It wasn't okay
Because Brian's personalized
Pantry
Something he relied on everyday
Was God and now
He had to reorganize and rememorize
Lisa
I felt awful
I felt like melting into the floor but y'all thought there has to be a better system
Time for Brian
He started
She found a few salute
Oceans like pudding
Braylon
Index card
And wrapping it around
Can with a rubber band
Wrong for a guy like Brian I just thought this is
Not the level of household his stylish dude I wouldn't want him
Have to do that ok something to know about Lisa
She actually sells customized and commemorative bricks
Using stamps
3D printer
Figure out how to solve
Problem like
Ryan Pantry she thought
What about using my printer to make a reusable labels
And so
She did
She came up with something that's
I like those Livestrong wristband
But with
Rail on the outside
Something you might
Slip around the container it's a rigid plastic it has a little bit of giving it for you can just slide it on
Anime Pop right off
That Lisa had kept all of the sassy
So when she gave Brian the label
He kind of cracked up in his face changed and he's like that's weird but that's really cool
And the next thing you said was hey you should really sell these
Tulisa started working on more Braille labels for
All sorts of
Cans and jars
And after a few months
Caterpillar
Pipes and a convention hosted by the national Federation of the blind
She didn't really have any
Expectations
Just wanted a little feedback
But instead
People kept
Coming to her booth
And then they come back with friends
And one woman
Asked Lisa
She would sell her a few of the Prototype
She had packed her husband's lunch
And grabbed the wrong container
2Pac in my beer
I mean I know
How mortifying that isn't
To know that you potentially made a job ending mistake
Over something so simple
It's got to be terrifying
She said that she didn't pack his lunch anymore
And that day
Talking to the people at the convention
It was a revelation
I got to the car that day and I totally cried
It was
Ridiculously moving the stories of how they've been trying to solve that problem
And how they wish that this event come out
20 years ago so Lisa went home and she
Build a website
He went live in
October of 2018 and now
She sells her Braille labels for
$2 each
Chelsa salesman starter pack
The name of the product
Well he comes to my kind of Mantra she had four years ago while she was
Recovering from a stroke she had when she was
He's just 30
There's a lot of things that I thought you know I can do that
I can do that to Lisa Dalton calls her products
Can do labels
I just thought
This would bring a lot of Independence to people who are also wanting to be able to do their own things I thought
These are yes can do things
And Lisa Belton
Business is
And doable
Busier she's planning to make it for full-time job if you want to find out more about Lisa or you're pretty
Previous episode tatuar podcast how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us
Your story go to build. Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can see
Subscribe wherever you get your podcasts
While you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us at beach by BTS
Npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
Aptoide
Our show is produced this week
Play James delahoussaye with music
Who's by routine Arab Louis
Thanks also to be a venkat JC Howard nor could see the Immigrant
The grace Anna's Mexican food
Jeff Rodger
Our intern
Is Candice Lin
I'm Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I be
Built this campaign mode
An email marketing
Platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week