So today story isn't just about
Clothing brands
Mattel huge influence
Fashion
Business of fashion
It's
Silly story about
Overcoming
Beers and
Personal insecurities
Biggest back in the early 80s
Eileen Fisher was
Extremely introverted
Ethan terrified at the idea of
Speaking to buyers and customers
About her clothes
How she overcame that
Rico Story is first ran in 2017
Hope you enjoy it
I was so freaked out the first day
I literally couldn't speak I just stood there people would ask me questions like how much
What's the style number and I like Frozen other people in my booth wood
Would help me out saying no tomorrow so I was like
Headlight
Robin PR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
Interior designer got over her stage fright
The launch Eileen Fisher
A multi-million-dollar clothing company
For women
So if you know a little bit about the clothing in this
The Giant
Especially for women's apparel
I Brands like Chanel and
Versace
Prada and
Of course H&M and Zara
Two given that Eileen Fisher does about 300 million dollars a year in Revenue
It's comparatively small
But in women's fashion
The brand is also incredibly influential
And not just for the designs but how Eileen Fisher started her company
To be precise with just
$350
She never took a dime from outside investor
And she still owns about 60% of her company
Her employees
On the rest
Now you seen the clothes you'll know that they're pretty spare and minimalist
Loki butt
Also elegant
Which is sort of how you might describe Eileen Fisher
Funny because lately I've been kind of calling my selfish IX
I think I don't know that I'm wired so much that way I just think that's something
I was kind of shut down when I was young
Classroom remember they were like 60
Kids in my Catholic school classroom and
Image it's always safer to
To hide and to be small and
Not speak
Ellen grew up in a middle-class family in Des Plaines Illinois in the
And 60s
Five Sisters
And a brother
Her dad worked
Accountant for a local company in her mom's
Spent her days at home doing laundry
Cleaning and making dinner for all nine of them
I think but I mostly remember is my mother
You know they're kind of unhappiness I think it was hard
Beijing seven children then
I think she felt it was her job to do all the hard work
Oh my dad felt you know his jobs to go to work and make the money in
Come home and be taken care of after that so
She would
Pretty much
We we Scott ranting and raving all day and then my dad would come home and just before my dad would come home she would
Get dressed
Academy already in
Sometimes you can put on lipstick
End
I just remember
I was about 16 and my mother had a breakdown
And my father said that the next day
You driving to work
And he had to pull over on the side of the road and he broke down crying realizing that
He had thought only a few days before that these are the happiest days of his life
But they were happy
Let me know there was a lot of Happy
Moments
Yeah we played the kids play you know we had the neighborhood
Suburbs and bicycles and
Reply
Canik 9mm a good humor truck came down the stairs
We got ice cream things like that so you know that's pretty much your tip
Typical Suburban experience
Aileen wuornos
The college at the
University of Illinois in the late 1960s without
Any real idea of what
What you wanted to do
Started out as a
The math major
But eventually
Decided on
Interior design
You know I just love fabric
Coloring
Playing with the shapes and
That's my mom for second I had sold with my mother when I was younger
So that was some of my
Happy memories with my mother
I used to have you
Pictures in my mind of clothes I wanted to wear
We would go shopping
I love being the fabric
My favorite place
In her early twenties Eileen moved to New York with a friend
But with no real plan
Felt this was 1972 when you
You could actually find an apartment in Manhattan for a hundred bucks a month
Search parent Eileen started doing some freelance graphic
She got a job working with a Japanese graphic designer named Laura
I was an assistant so I started to
Doing whatever needed to be done
And
We design logo
And we designed packages
Thanks for banks and
Let me get stuff for Japanese clients
Kirin beer and
Things like that
And
After a short while we were like working together and you know we ended up getting into a relationship
She was like
Oh no
And were you
Traveling to go to Japan
Right
Right so this is exactly where the clothing idea came from so
Ice that we started traveling
We took two trips
Together two
Japan
I'm just trying to match like this is the
I guess the
Mid-to-late
70s
1074 flying
From New York to do
Japanimation pretty glamorous writing that was a
Big deal
Yeah I guess
So
It was also kind of stressful you know I felt
Pressure and
You know I couldn't speak the language so
Tried hard to learn it
So there was glamour yes I guess
You know
But I'm not I don't I'm not so attracted to glamour I am always more uncomfortable with glamour by Sam.
Uncomfortable person that's why I had to make you comfortable glow
What struck you about
About design
That you came across in
Cheeto
Simple and beautiful
Things were
Temple released
And feel like you could
Really see like with a kimono for example
WinShape
You know for a thousands of years and
You know
They were just
Do you know use different Fabrics in different techniques to make it
Different every time and
And it was beautiful
Beautiful and
Yeah that inspired me
How long did you did you work
With a Sim Israel
About
4 years
And
I mean
Of course anytime there's a
Professional and personal relationships
Elsa always often causes
Some complications was that
Did that sort of begin to unravel your personal relationship begin to unravel your prefer
National relationship
God
Yes definitely it was all connected
We thought we could split up
And work continue to work together but that became quite
Clear Within
You want that was did not going to work
But yeah so I ended up
Separating getting my own little Loft eventually after about a year of bouncing around and
Hang a little space in a loft in
Tribeca and you lived and worked
Where I lived and worked
And I was stumbling around doing still in a few
You know some Japanese clients still and then some
Other
I work I was
Stumbling around and getting I don't even know how and if I look back
Cuz it was really
Day by day it was
Freelance like
Apartments I did a few apartments
Small office
Dentist office
Whatever I
Get
And trying to survive
Pay the rent and you know
Keep working as a designer and not go back to
Working as a waitress at with my one commitment I was going to end up
Waitressing again I hadn't done that in many years and I can let go back to that
And then I met him
People and that's when
I thought I had been kind of cooking on this idea
Of the
Now the clothing business and cooking on the side
Already in the early 80s
Oh yeah
It was it was in my mind for probably five years before the first garments appeared to make your own clothes
Find clothes that was in your mind
Right to try and design clothes where did that idea come from
I don't know I think some of it was at when I was trying to get dressed
Let me know the Japanese clients and you know the different I want it I need it too
Look like a designer and what does that mean
You know
Put together and no no
Clean and elegant and simple I wanted to reflect my own style of my own aesthetic
And I wore uniform when I was young
And
Let's go to Catholic school and so when I
Trying to get dressed as a designer
I kind of
I never really liked the uniform but I
Like the concert
Simple just shut up and
Have enough to think about you enough to worry about
Skip put the clothes on go and I'll
I wanted to make a
It's simple but I didn't want it to be so confined that it had to be exactly
Like you know the uniform
Or in one only one
Particular
Shape and I want to buy the same thing everyday and I just had this idea that I could make these simple clothes no one's really do
Doing it and
The images would come to me I would see this simple shapes
And the first one I remember was I called a box
Stop
White straight lines like a kimono sleeve and
It was about the way
Drape when you had it on
That was kind of the first picture that came to me and others were
You know the simple
Wide leg pants and you know there was a vast in a shell and the first few pieces of the star to come to me
I was talking to people cuz now I had artists
Best friends in Tribeca and
Other people who were designing clothes and jewelry and things like that
Which often happens when people have an idea
You were saying have this idea
To design these
Beautiful simple
Piece of clothing for women and and we're your friends think you should go for you
Definitely and you would have these conversations for
You know
For a long time with many people like
Over a period of 5 years
Obsessed
This is what I'm curious about
Because
This is the point at which
99.9
People
Do nothing
But they have a great idea
And
They do nothing either because they decide not to do something or
Just because of
Bad luck
What was that
That
Switch that idea into something
Actually tried
Okay that's good
So
I think
What happened is that I'm so I'm seeing these pictures and I'm trying to imagine Where do I
And how would I make this
Happened
And I couldn't picture myself you know
Like what if I made these clothes how would I do that and went and then I couldn't picture myself how would I sell them
You know what I go to stores other people telling me they were going to like
Henri Bendel and waiting in line for hours and by we go like nope
I don't like it if you did not have that was not you you were not a
You're not a hustler now
No I was a shy
Interpret the time
But I knew I couldn't have definitely not hustler and I could not have done that idea
What what what do you think it was the would have been the hardest
Part of that
Rejection semi saying no or
Trying to articulate
What what it was
Both
Both I think
Probably it was still rejected
The time in oh
But articulating
Was and still is
What kind of
Initial for me
To thinking today about trying to tell story
So you're thinking
Alright I
Try this but I
I cannot even imagine what I would do after
I would have liked a sample of this
Until what ended up happening is that a friend who took me to the boutique show
And
Famous show in the goat
It's at Rachel
Inn in York
Right
But it was a show Big Show that cater to the small boutiques around the country
And a lot of small designers and small companies would come there and show their things
And so I remember going to the show
Just out of curiosity kind of
Anti floating through and going like oh
I can do this
I see how to do this
I could just look at these different foods and saw how the designers were presenting their clothes
A little rack here a few things hanging
You know I know how to do a logo I could do they had I need a logo wouldn't I need to name you know
So I could picture
The whole story so it wasn't just like one garment
It was that I had to
People have to see it kind of ahold understand that it went together
And that it was a a little story somehow a 10in by going to the design
Show you
You thought well
I don't have to be Carnival Barker I can
Just stand here wait for people to come to me the people who liked it
Will come in
Write orders or you know
Give me feedback and the people who don't like it'll just walked by
Committed to
Small section just like a one
The same
For the next show
This is in like 1980
3 because I think
Or that I
At the show that I first introduced
You said I'm going to go there and
I want to go there and then I'm going to
Show my clothes right
I know fabric style that nothing you had designs pictures in my mind
How much time do you have
3 weeks
You would read weeks to come up with a
Clothing line of fashion line
No don't get carried away now it wasn't really a special line at the start out with for garments
But I had
So now you know as a kid so I knew
You know that wasn't that,
But I was lucky in that this is how it this is
Kind of weird how things
Happened but
You know again one of the friends I've been talking to said I have a friend
Cuz patternmaker she works in a
Clothing company
Maybe she can help you
So she came into work for me at night and on the weekends
The first three weeks this this woman
Volunteer
And she wouldn't will she said you can pay me I know you're going to your good for you can pay me
When you get paid
Did you draw bunch of
Designs and give them to her
Tissot
Or did you sell them well
I pretty much talked my way through it I scribbled them you know my little sketches and she said what
What's special about the Miley and I was like well it's special that they're simple
But I'll help you
And so first I had to find fabric
I was kind of the
Lange & sohne
She helped me
No figure out where I could go to get Fab
It was a linen and cotton blend
Yeah so what did you what did you end up making
I made the Box
Top
The little crop
Hand
Kind of based on the flood pants from Japan
And I made a little
Shell and that's the kind of went over
The
Top and then I made a little shelter
I could wear it just a shell with a simple pant oh my God these are like the pieces on my line today it's so amazing to just see the pictures
What color what colors were they
They were like a teal color and kind of
Burgundy
Nike white burgundy salmon need pinky right now
Ana ivory
So after 3 weeks you had
Piece of clothing
Samples
And that's what you were going to take to this trade show
I will email them into three colors
So I had 12 piece
And that's what I took
With my little logo
And I was I spent probably as much time obsessing about the graphics and the name because I didn't want to call it I'm in fish
White why not
Because I didn't see it as a personal
I thought it was something that
You know
People would make their own
That it would
I hope that it wasn't so personally me it was
Change
What's up what did you end up calling it
So I called cuz I couldn't think of anything else and I was working as Eileen Fisher the designer so
I already had my name registered as a business so I guess if I was going to take checks
Better having business name and so that
I worked for them
So like when they
Willie McGee the Eileen Fisher Story movie
Feature film one day and they have this scene in there
First trade show
Is this like this
Amazing moment with designers
Oh my gosh this is life
I've never seen anything like it is that what was going on no no no no no no
Absolutely not
I was so
Freaked out
The first
I literally couldn't
I just said
People would ask me questions like
How much does it cost
What's the style number
And I like
Frozen
Other people in my booth would help me out saying no
Tomorrow
I just want to give you a hug and say it's going to be okay I'll be okay
This is like
I was like
Deer in headlights
She said did you eventually get over the stage frightened and
Start selling
I did I did I saw it still 208 stores
I felt about a hundred pieces
So couple thousand bucks
Yep 3000
I was thrilled
And it was the right amount because anymore I would have never been able to deliver
I would have been able to get enough fabric I would have been able to figure it all out
Fast enough or get the money to make it happen
So that was a pretty good that was pretty good you walk away $3,000 and
These are boutiques around the country
Right
And
Fill those orders
You made most of them
Yourself
Cut everyone myself on the floor in my loft
Tribeca
And then carry them in garbage bags
Down my stairs on
Subway In-N-Out
The Queen's did you show your name Eileen Fisher in the
Act like a nut
Close the label I hadn't a label made that the source te
Tiny sewing company
Out in Queens
Seldom
So at this point this is like 1984
You got 3005
X-end
Are you like
Incorporated youku like do an LLC and all that
Stuff
Oh
I don't think I did that until
I got my neck
Around the Border
So how did that
Well I came up with
8 Style
And went back
The next Boutique show
And this time I had the
New fabric that I found it was a
Very textural
French terry bearing
Lush Fabric cotton
More like a
Elegant sweatshirts
And
Came back with
Read
Different colors
Peach mint and white
Remember
And
This time
People stood in line to write orders
Well I was like oh my God I knew
Something was happening
When we come back
Eileen Fisher took her clothes from tradeshow floors to department stores
Cross the country
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this
NPR Podcast
In the following message
Which come from wix.com
A web platform
Creating your own
Professional website
With Wix whether it's your first time creating a website
Or you're a longtime Pro
You can do it yourself
Choose from hundreds of stunning Temple
Lights or start from scratch
With the dragon Brock technology
And powerful weapon
Join Over 125 million people
Already using WIC
Text to create their own website
Gota wilx.com
To create yours today
So what will you cry
Support also comes from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
They're cloud-based Platt
Man solution
Deliver digital work
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
Ready for your hole
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
To make people more productive and engaged
Moret servicenow
Al.com
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
In the story
Eileen head
Just sold
$40,000 worth
Orders in her second trade show
And things seem to be looking up
Only problem was
Now I have to figure out how to put
Put together a real functioning business
But I was even for the back figuring out just how do I get the money
To buy the fabric
And
You know
You know how am I going to produce this you had
Either $40,000
Supporters but not $40,000 in cash
I just made the order
And you had to go and buy all of the material
You didn't have $40,000
Right well I would have needed about 20 to do the production
And
But I got some good advice actually while I was at the boutique show
But I deliver
Small order first so I did
White just for like them February delivery and then I did
The other colors for every couple months later so that let me
Spread out the delivery in
I could produce part of it while I was trying to turn the money
I did the orders on COD so then when they
Delivered
Boutiques with write a check and they had to pay right away to pay right away and
You know at the show when they were standing line was kind of easy to ask him to do code while because I have
How to play with them I'm a small designer need
Pcod and I were
Accommodated me
But did you want to try to get a loan at a bank
I tried and
You know I went to the bank I remember and I with my stack of orders then they were like well how long he been in business
They just looked at you and they're like you have no tracker
How do you get a job you do that then
Right place at the first thing that person of the banks of witches
Greatest
How do you know the reason real orders
I know this check credit on that order
Okay now I'm done that
That's a good idea what it what does that mean how do I do that
We stressed out about this or were you cuz you don't sound stressed out about it now you sound like a very chilled out and
Your I take your demeanor your you just seem very calm and know it was you were nervous
Yeah yeah
Well
Was I nervous even during the days when I was trying to make this come together no
No no I wasn't nervous then I was nervous at the show I was never wanted to present myself
But it was never nervous
You know trying to sell the problem I love Tom the problem
How to get the money I'm going to do this
You know
Who's going to help me how am I going to ask what what do I need here
You know and I
Shows my on my Loft and I are friends, they brought friends and I bought orders when
Another paid me up front and I could deliver
Things like that anything you had to do
Puzzle making kind of fun
That was fun
And just figuring it all out I like I like I guess I'm a math major somewhere in my soul in my like
Solving puzzles and problems and
No tryna make things right
To you would
Make some
Get the cash
And then to use cash to buy more material and then just continue to come
Right right
Grambling day-by-day
You know how to make this working
No it didn't go to the next show and sell $80,000 of the orders and then it's like oh my God here we go
You know what
Did you
Did you actually
Say I've this is real
I just going to trade shows
This is a company I need to hire somebody
Well
I hired my first official employee that was Siggy who still works for the company today
And I don't remember thinking I'm a real business or anything
I just remember thinking I need help I really need some
Stable
Help and
Did you start to go to department stores and and do the thing that you were mortified
To do earlier in your hand
Design career no I never did that but eventually opened
Store Madison Avenue
And
Byers
From the Department Stores would come
So you open this
The store on Madison Avenue in
And how to do
Really well
Again similar
Variants to that
Boutique shower
You know people just
Ben leinbach clothes and stacks of closing
It was so delighted to find a store
I remember that's when he was a buyer somebody from Bloomingdale's came in because I've been looking at the line.
And they would say things like you know great clothes but you know they're just going to get lost
Bloomingdale's
And
Simple
Simple you know
But I knew that was the idea that
Anyway so when they came into the store they knew
They didn't understand it but they knew something was happening
And so they wanted to
Open the shop smoke shop
Yes it was a kind of I think that
Catapulted us to another face
Who are your customers were they
What was a certain type of woman was it a certain age was it a certain
Profession
Yeah that really pays out
Describe the most
Artist
Therapist and teacher
And
Seems like they were people who
You know I used to say they
They help people find themselves something like that you know
That are that they could figure out how to
Make your own style with these
Clothes and they
They operate in the in or not in such a
Corporate world they can have two dresses
Certain kind of way
Were you able to finance
The stores
And
The production just threw
Existing sales
Yes and know how we found we were able to get a line of credit
Cuz we we bought Fabric in bulk even though we were small because we I was very dead
Educated to a certain Fabrics sewing
Built around 1 Fabric and then I
I had my brother-in-law can was helping me and he got me a small light line of credit
$50,000 line of credit
Then I got a new accountant 2
You know help me to happen to the banks and how you had to put business plans
Gathering
It was a combination of credit lines and loans and
UNICEF funding because it was growing and it was
It was always profitable
From there were you
I mean what's the cross
Just
Off the charts
Who's that
What's happening
You know it was
Come strong and steady and I know it was
Not exactly off the charts
But it was exciting and sometimes it felt like you know like
Horses and a carrot like an out-of-control Hilton Hotel you know like he was pulling me somehow
No
Mosto
It wasn't
2 out of control
You know it was mostly organic there was never like an attempt to make it ever bigger than it was
It was more like okay
It's working so that's open to more stores or it's working so it's open for more store
You know or now you know
No other department stores want to buy the line
Saks and Nordstrom's and you know
That kind of thing
What was your Revenue with that
Oh
Different moments in time how much
I can't remember I remember my dad came to visit me one time in the early days any
Set back in the chair he was in the county of going over some of my books you want to make sure I was
Campaign things are working out okay without adorable
And he sat back in the cherries
Do you know how much money you made last
Here
And I said no I had
You said $200,000
Gross sales of course and are plenty of expenses
But you know
Was still
Pretty
Pretty shocking
How did you I mean as the company was growing in the 1990s
How did you
Deal with
Being a CEO did you
Did you like that no no no no no
No I think
CEO is
A word that I've always
I am always been sort of uncomfortable
I'm not actually
Helmet I'll used to call myself Chief creative officer that was sort of the closest
I could come but I did know that sort of the Buck stop with me
Yeah sometimes I had to make important decisions
How much work would have been would be hard
But I always kind of help
Business Insider leadership standpoint pretty
Pretty loosely
And so I like the designers
Being with it and making it
You know
Their own and working together and you know in the end of sort of collective way
And I feel that way about the leadership and even today were leadership team is pretty complicated
Then we're really working to streamline it and we're getting better we're getting a lot better
Period of time when you really mean
Really just start
Exploding
Yeah
Did you find yourself in a position
That you were reluctant to be in
Yeah
I saw myself more than designer artist rather than a business person even though I wasn't bad at it
In terms of
Maybe not so much the managing people
I guess I never liked
Telling people what to do
I
I ate and I never liked working
For other people
Oh you know when they would try to tell you what to do it didn't
I didn't like being told I like give me the problem and let me do it my way kind of thing
Ellen DeGeneres
I mean I know that
In the 90s
It was a
Incredibly
Active time
For Eileen Fisher
Continue and also personally me you were
You been married
Two children in a in a
4 year
Period of time to young kids you are trying to run this company and
Your marriage was
I'm falling
Part 2
How did you
You manage the personal on the
I would say that wasn't the hardest
Hardest ever and if I look back
Man if I could do anything differently that be now I'm not not going into regret by
That was incredibly hard
God I think about all the women out there trying to start businesses and work in the business world and
How hard it is to manage families
So I really had to rely on
People
In company
I tried to again no sort of lead Loosely in just
But I struggled a lot with
Being in two different places and wanting to be at work when I was at home or worrying about work
You know I'm reading reports and try to understand us working or not what's working and what's going wrong
And at the same time worrying about my kids when I was at work and just
You know I guess the
Nothing I say to myself now is that
If I look back I would
I would have just worked harder and being where I was
Doing what I was doing in the moment
Stop tryna
B2 place
And stop taking the work home and do the best
Canon
You going to be the best
Mom you could be
And also run the company
Anna
You
MSI mean it it it it
Kind of sounds about like
What your mama
Overwhelmed
Right I mean she was
Everyday was his hamster wheel
Yeah
I did the best I could I I had to let go a lot of had to
Trust a lot of people
Which Wich work
And didn't
Do you know it worked in places
And then they were moments that I felt
You know sad about her let go too much over here when
I know
Going to a store and see pieces I didn't recognize or feel like
The line didn't look where I adore
I couldn't find the clothes I wanted to wear or wasn't really
The concept was gone where was the stall of this company and you know what happened and
Yeah
You know
Once I got divorced it was
The kids were four and eight and I said I am
I'm going to stop working on Wednesday Thursday Friday
I worked in my home a lot and I would
And I'll let the people keep working at
Close the door and go in and out and be with my kids
And
You know my husband will have the kids on Mondays and Tuesdays
Share the weekend things like that
So actually
Work better for me I don't think it worked so well for them they didn't really like the going back and forth stuff and then
I guess kids never like divorce
Yeah
But I think that I know overtime I sorted it out and
Things got better I got I got stronger I I started
Doing things like yoga and meditating I had some time to myself
My mother never had you know
I can have to have a breakdown actually it's a
To get a hold of myself
Eileen where you
Cuz your business was
I just bought are huge like you were
Successful
Beyond Your Wildest Dreams the late 90s
Today and
Did you ever think maybe I should just
Cash it in and sells company of somebody into
Wash my hands of it
Oh my God no I never never thought that never thought never crossed your mind that would be like selling
My first born child is this really felt like that
You did have that security like
You could have done that
Alright was never about the money no
I mean
Probably in the very beginning when I didn't know how to price the clothes wasn't about the money by
It was personal I guess I wanted it to be how I wanted it to be and I think it's still true
And actually what I did do was sell part of the business of employees
So we are 40% an ESOP employee owned
And I always wanted that
Collective idea wanted
I wanted to people who are a part of it too
Paid and feel like owners and be owners
I think Eileen Fisher has
Like
55 and Pregnant You by Eileen Fisher
Your company
Has like
About 60 stores around the world
Bowser ring rights
The right rough
Yes and thousands of employees
1200 direct employees
But many
Probably ten thousand
People work daily on are making our clothes and
Became
More corporate
Moka bros
Add more people
A big company
Plus million dollars a year
Answered
Of course much more today but
Was that
Will weird for you maybe you're the you're the person who
Want to work for other people
All of a sudden you are your name is a
Oh man
Santa weird
It is weird
Yeah it was weird it still weird
Write a book called how I became Island
Southern like
It's just strange
I keep singing
I like I keep thinking of your dad
Coming to visit you in New York
Senior liaison saying
And I like looking through your books and saying
You guys made 200
$1,000 last year just being so
Blown Away by that
Eileen Fisher does
Hundreds of millions of dollars in Revenue
A year
I mean
Is it strange
To you that
You
Became Rich even though you'd never wanted to or tribe that wasn't your intention
Oh yes
I feel very uncomfortable with that that's something that I have to adjust my working therapy on
Because you grew up with like
7 children your house
This matter
Middle-class oh yeah I put myself through college no my father said no
I don't need to go to school so he and I like that your parents ever see
This level of success
Yeah my mother did
My father was utterly totally impressed by 2 and $1,000 instantly Spanish
But my mother did I don't know that she understood
Did it quiet
You know my sister is at work in the store out in the Midwest and so should go in there
She's so adorable she would go in and
Even as the company got really big and cheap
Damages we have a section of Damages that would sell in the back of
Duarte
And she'd go to the back of store and pick out those damn today
Take them take them home and 66th
Put on the main rack
But I think to her you know
How it could have been 200,000 would have been nobody
Hitman
How much to her
You know
It sounds like you are
And in a pretty good place in life
Personally
Assertive
You don't have to do this
Logistical operational stuff of the company you have
Can I have like fission and
Big picture stuff and
You seem like
You're really happy
Yeah well
You know
Not everyday not all the time
But I
I know how to work with it
Now watch my mother she was depressed
And you know
I remember having this inside even before I started the business
When I went through a kind of a dark moment in my late twenties
I remember going you know having this Revelation that
I can make a different choice
I don't have to be depressed
Just because my mother was
I might have to be overwhelmed because my mother was overwhelmed but I don't have to be the prince
I didn't I didn't understand the full impact of the different choices they had to make but I realized
That I could choose
And it doesn't mean it doesn't get the better of me some days but
I also know it doesn't last long
So I would say
Happy I'm happy I'm also really sad sometimes I'm also really
You know scared like before I came in here today I'm really anxious I'm really
Excited I'm really
More feelings than probably ever in my life
I love that
You
Is everybody listening to this
Going to say
Eileen Fisher
Future successful
Creatives amazing company and brand
Has
You know made it beyond our wildest dreams and yet
She has bad days she gets out
Absolutely absolutely I think what's different
Is now I know that
And I can
I can look at it and I can just
Be with that
So if I'm anxious I can just say I'm anxious
And it's okay
You know I don't have to try to
Pretend I'm not
I can just
Be who I am
That's okay
Eileen Fisher the founder of
Eileen Fisher
By the way Eileen still oversees all of the designs
The company and in recent years
She launched a program called
Green Eileen
The goal is to eventually you reuse or recycle almost
All of the clothing the company sells
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you are building
The first
Quit message from one of our sponsors
Mercedes-Benz
Featuring the new a class with
Mbux
Mercedes-Benz
User experience
Able to learn the way you
Speak and drive
Respond with
Suggestions
Learn more about the 8th Class
MB
USA
Dot-com
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
I know for how you built
And today were
Updating a story we ran over a year ago my name is Glen
And I'm in Minneapolis Minnesota
And I've created a nice mug
In the idea for nice mug came about
Totally by accident
It was on one of those freezing winter Mornings in Minnesota
Outside
Backyard
And pick up a jug of water that had frozen over night nature freezes water in a jug from the house
Outside in and from the bottom up
So you get kind of a hockey puck
Type freeze at the bottom but there's this really interesting cavity that freezes last
And that's an iconic shape
And that shape was a glass like a
What kind of glass you would put on your dinner table perfectly formed
Made of clear ice
Sobini
Resourceful people that we hire with a beer in our hand we poured a beer in a nice mug was born
I mean can you say USA any more clearly than a
Cold beer in a glass made of ice
Anyway the first thing Glen did naturally was to take the ice mug into his backyard sauna
It held up
Pretty well until you know it melted
So then I started messing around with different molds and different ways that we could freeze ice
So I experimented Glenn came up with a plastic mold
Seemed to do the trick
But it was a massive challenge for me
To make clear ice
And without clear ice you get leaks and leaks are no fun
The leaks actually come from air bubbles in the ice and
Concord 4 years
To come up with a mold that
Would make a mug without the bubbles
And finally he mailed it but never leaks and I'm really proud of that
The way Glenn mold works is pretty simple fill it with water freeze it overnight then
How about your own ice mug
He's no selling molds all over the country
And just a couple years ago
Some Executives at Coca-Cola in Egypt
Actually called them up and said
Hate we want to use nice mugs in one of our ads
Yeah it's quite a rush you know the biggest Beverage Company in the world
Make it nice mugs putting Coca-Cola in there we just had a great time
Business has
Tripled since we last spoke with Glenn
But nice mug is still a side Hustle
And he still assembling and shipping the molds from home
Eventually
The cutest a job as a
Salesman
Just not yet
Do you know if we could send a kid through college
With the proceeds for nice mug while I couldn't be happier
And if you're wondering how long the ice mug actually last in your hands before it melts
We can have nice mugs that last like 30 minutes 45 minutes
I mean I suppose
The one thing that's cool about nice mug is when your ice is melted you're done drinking
It's Glen Orbach of Minneapolis
The founder
Nice Bach and if you want to learn more about nice mother here previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built
List. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build that npr.org
Love hearing what you're up to and thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe where
Wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review you can also write to us at Hy-Vee
Npr.org
If you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
It was produced this week by run. Delta CHI with music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis thanks also to me event
Cat Julia Kearney JC Howard Norco to leave Grant Melissa Gray size meshkinpour and Jeff Rodger
Our intern is canvas Lim
A guy Roz and even listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign mode
An email marketing flag
Form used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com