Hey everyone it's got here so
2 years ago
Edible Aspen or her name is Macy
And may arrive
In the US
Basically not
Knowing a soul
20 years later
She wound up sitting next to President Barack Obama at the White House
Advising him on how to create jobs in America
Because creating jobs
Was exactly what nation was doing
With the
Candle Company
She don't
From the ground up
This episode first aired in March of 2017 it's a
Super amazing story and
Hope you enjoy it
We registered for the New York gift show which is the Holy Grail
I'll trade shows and we thought that this is going to be the ticket to Our Success
But you were wrong it was a complete disaster
Ron NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movements they built
Gyros in the story of how he left China for America
Use Campbell's Soup cans to make candles
Turn that into a multibillion-dollar company
So almost
Everything about the way Macy's life
Turned out
Is improbable
The fact that she started a business
That she makes candles that
She even lives in America
None of this was supposed to happen
And she describes it
Growing up in China in the 1970s
This was
I like living in a movie without
Color
When we grow up there was absolutely nothing everyone wear the same thing everyone would
Eating the same food everyone had
The same small apartment life was very happy in a sense that you don't have to be jealous of each
Each other you don't have to be wanting things you cannot have in the 1970s
China was still a black box
Closed off too much of the world
Actually the government realized
He needed better diplomats
People who spoke foreign languages well
Sail around the time a turn
This is 1979
The government decided to open up some boarding schools
Praying that next generation of diplomats
Animation
Was one of the lucky
If you who got it
So
We learned
Western culture American studies
Renaissance art all in English
And I knew more about Smithsonian and the locations of each art
The many Americans
And this was the thing about
Learning a language a language is really living it
I remember it was very funny that I was watching Godfather at 14
Which has a lot of violence a lot of sacks in a lot of murders
Enjoying it we we thought it was
You know something that
Everyone in the United States to honor every given day it was a pretty Charmed Life
Especially compared to other Chinese kid
May was on the fast track to becoming a diplomat
That was one problem
In the spring of 1989
Chinese students started to organize demonstrations
Going for more reforms
But we now know as the Tiananmen Square protests
After 6 weeks
The Chinese government
Crackdown
Help me she wasn't an activist at the time but that didn't matter
The government decided that educated young people like her
Wharf rat
So they were sent
Out of Beijing
They assign me
R2a Northern City
Very cold
Not even the city a suburb
My job
For the whole year is going to
I'm watching a warehouse
Four minerals that are going to be for Oxbow
So I have a clipboard
I have 2 highlights of a day
When the truck comes to pick up one load I put a check
And then it came again in the afternoon I check
That'll be the day
Follow you
You must have been miserable
I was beyond miserable
At that time I was already dating my
First husband
His name is David
So we were very close and being
Far away was obviously not a good
Arrangement on top of that
What I worried most
Is that for 10 years
I was practicing
And speaking English
And language is very easily forgotten
And I barely speak
Chinese animal in English
Because my boss does not like to talk
He's a man with few words he smoke most
What time
And that's my life for
Samain
She decided to quit
What to do
He was a trained geophysicist and
She spoke English
It decided to apply for temporary visas to come to the US
And after 2 years of waiting
They got them
So I flew to Washington DC
When we arrive at Dulles Airport I was very slow
Sleepy because up to jet lag and I saw to size
American
Citizen and the other is aliens
It's just as you arrive at immigration
Edward alien
Was
Kind of confusing to me because I remember aliens from Star Wars solo from you know
Go science
He said I was so excited I said wow
They actually have a
Section 4 alien
And
So I got very excited I said let me see
I'm certainly not American citizen so I guess I'm
Going to have to go to the ATM part and that's
Great cuz I can see them
I never knew that the word idiom means the nun American on Green
I guess they realize that too they changed
Do something a little bit more human
What was it like to adjust to the US and you had that serve embrace yourself in American culture urine
Entire childhood
When you finally arrived here
Did it surprise you to disappoint you was it
Lonely
Well I don't find it particularly difficult to adapt
What I find interesting is that in Washington DC
People
Kind of avoid
That's something I stood
I think was my first impression of the city
I was riding the subway
And I found a very interesting that as quickly as I look at someone they merely change the eyes
And they try to focus on reading
And I said to myself I said wow this is a beauty
Deep
City because everybody's always reading
David Icke volume
Apus where you able to
To find a job
Yes so I found a job in New York
It was a job for
American
Medical device companies to export equipment
To Chinese Hospital
And was it
Interesting work if you enjoy it was boring I have to be honest with you it was a lot of paperwork pushing a lot of
Import export documentation working with
You know different factories about
A SKU numbers and
Pushing a line of credit
Through the banks
But what's interesting out of
The party's not so interesting thing is that
They put me in a hotel
Next
Bloomingdale's
Why was that answer
Well imagine a bird out of cage I
I've always been interested in fashion
Many people wonder you know if you grow up in a country without any fashion how can you really have an eye for it
When I was
You growing up in the foreign language Middle School
China at that time already started exporting
Fashion and they would have those rejected fashion
And they put them on sale
Near the bus station
So we would be jumping from one
Place to another looking for
Cheap fashion you know
So that was always something I'm
Very interesting
And when you're put next to a
Bloomingdale
That was the best thing that can possibly happen
So what you would just go in
Everyday I would go starting
I found the first floor which
You Don't Own Me
South ladies that they spray
Fragrances and everybody hate them not me I love him since spray on me
I like
Being
Sort of in the middle of
Something that launching and be able to tell what's in in the fragrance that I like and dislike
And then look at the packaging packages always fascinating to me because I grew up in the country with
No touching at all
But what interests me the most is a fashion floor and it's usually the second floor
And just
Being amazed
And I love the women in New York the way they are so confidence and they dress
Centos colors in those shapes and they look
And then I would always end in the home Department
And it would always
Give me a lot of question because
It look like it's in the 1920s
What's the weather look like
Furnitures will very ornate it has a lot of
Dairy
Gilded finish
And then the place I like
Laura Ashley Princeton a very small Grandma's
Wallpaper
Floral
And I'm just
Wandering the person who is so confident walking on the street will go home to
Sheepish
It's so disconnected
So I keep saying that to
David
When we talk on the phone
He hear me with Loathing in in DC
Bmdc I was in New York and I would get up
At 5 on Monday and took the first train
And I'll get home at 9 on Friday so it's not really
A very good quality of life and I was
Calling him about what I discovered was very exciting and then
I continually
Bring up how disconnected
The fashion and home
Apartments
Finally he said may you seem to be really upset about this commute
He said
Maybe we should start something
Cu
Seaquest and you
And then then what was the plan but what was the business you guys were going to do so we knew if it's going to be home because we know where is home
Home Goods because the fashion business is dominant
By Brent
And we feel
The home business is left without bread
And that's what we see.
Opportunity
It's close the gap between home
So that's how I do it we don't know what product
We just quit
At the same time will you just like started brainstorming in your in your apartment or your house of the time I try to figure out what
What to do
Not only without each other but we reach out to her friends
So we brainstormed with our friends
And as a result of that
When we started the business
In the middle of
I would quickly got a lot of feedback
People send me samples me
Pictures
And we
Zoning on
About four categories
The first UBC
Surprises silk flowers I don't know
Fake flowers that never die
The second category is accessories for your car so
Seat cushions something to make you feel comfortable when you drive for a long distance
Add a third category because I know this American Doll was so popular
Is a kind of doll that
Can rotate with music
And the last
Something that I did
Even think it's interesting but I
I think it might have an opportunity
Candle candles
Every category mentioned
It's a huge business in this country there
Getting some dollars
That are in each of those Cam Newton have access to massive
No Ben Because the Internet wasn't available
It wasn't and I don't really know
What difference we will make
Other than
You know making it cuz I'm better but I didn't even know how hard it is
Is that actually good that you don't know everything
That you don't know how hard it is that you just have
I got that something can be
Down to make it better
There's no amount of research
That can prove
And idea
But there's one thing you can always do which is to take your product to the market
So that's what we did
How did you get the products by the way
Date they sampled us
Dave send by FedEx or DHL from China
We haven't imported them with
December 8th December
DHL FedEx
Text whatever it is said that
What time is available silk flower seat cushion flowers I think David brought some of those back by up breaking his back also
The suitcase
And by that time it was September 1994
All the major wholesale trade shows take place twice a year
In January when people replenish their goods
After holiday
Adding summer when they're buying more
For Christmas
But it was September so the only show we can possibly go to
Is sing Charlotte North Carolina
Why what happened
90% of a business
Came from the candles
And and what
Did the candles look like where they just
Candles
Fair
That you don't see them anymore they're called glow candles that round
And they look like stained glass
And when you burn them they are glowing
From within
So people came up your booth and they were not interested in anything else is up flowers of the car seats it was
It was at that stained glass
Looking cattle because holiday and it was gift-giving season
And it's a great gift
Pakistan after the show eating disorders
How did you do how did you deliver them how did you get them to customers
We rent a very inexpensive Warehouse with office in the front
I was kind of Ford many people four times we just have one part-time
To help us
End
We were able to use our savings and our family and friends
Helped us
To the first container was a 20-foot container not even a 44
What container
And then we ship them
Very fast we got reorders
Yes
So what was the candle
Retailing for
$15 the most
We probably will take
50%
Margin on them
So it was
Almost half a million dollars a business redid
In 4 months
Insane
I mean where you David just like
Shocks by the candle thing we were taken surprised by the
That we would not
Expected to do so well for the first
4 months of our business
And we were shipping everyday I'm
I was a sales manager
I was assistant
I was accounting
I was
Taking product out of the
Icontainers I was everything
Okay so you shut this container from China and then you deliver all the stuff to your client
And then what did you guys do after like what was what was the next move for the company
The second year I decided since the trade show it's so important
We registered for the New York gift show which is the
The Holy Grail
I'll trade shows
So we went to the New York Gift Show
And we thought that this is going to be the ticket to R6S
But the show which is
10 times bigger with an international audience told us that we were wrong
It was a complete disaster
You
Are trying to sell kidney sink handles that you're importing
China and
Fennel salad
End
I was devastated
Because it's a very expensive trade show I'm assuming at this point I mean
You must have
Certified senior mind that maybe this candle business
It was a fluke maybe the fact that we did so well that first
4 months
Just had to do with Christmas
Exactly
That was the thought
But I wasn't giving up
I was always more International minded
I was already scheduled to go to visit
Frankfurt
Germany
Because every year in February there's a big
Home Products show caught on Beyonce
An Ender
Imai very depressed
Moments
I need it to go there to see what
Potentially be the next thing
Because what I envisioned
For home
Is already there
The design is very streamlined
Sandals
Everything from home furniture
2 lighting and table top
The colors are very bold
They have oranges
Lavenders
And they have those
Beautiful contrast with white
And
I was so happy that I went there because it's confirmed
That
Home and fashion could be in sync
Soap soap doesn't change your trajectory Avenue still
Have a candle business where you bringing these like stained glass window candles
King from China
Yuan Frankfort you see these beautiful streamline designs
And you think
What
So I could use that
Design elements in Kendo
That you would design your own candles that was always my thoughts even
Is a diplomat I think not many people end up doing what they're trained to do but that's training is very helpful
Because I was exposed to a lot of
Art education when I was very young kid
So I started
From the very high level of Art
And that it trickles down to
The fashion
It finally goes to home
Portrait Johanna change your approach to two
What you were doing
So I came back
Very refreshed from and invigorate
From what I see and really I was determined
That I'm going to really start to do something
And
Another thing I discovered by
Starting to pay more attention now to candles
Is that my competitor in the US
Vapcell candles
In the Millions
And probably billions
And I ask myself
Why do they buy it all year round
It's not because they have
Patton it's because
The power of fragrance has been written
Men and women over the years
Happy wearing fragrances for many reasons
But for home it takes on a very new meaning
So that was that you you basically decided to
That point to start making
Scented candles
Yes
At that time we were for the first time joined by a permanent
Employee which is
A friend of David
His name is Richard
And he and I went to visit
One of the fragrance vendors in New Jersey to learn how to make candy
So he and I went in his speed up
Hunchback and
For 4 hours we learn everything
The one need to learn
About making face and candles
So many people think about candles and they say how hot can it be I can make it
With my eyes closed
Jose that you just pour some wax and then you put and then it's going to be a candle
But if you want to make it a business and you want to make sure it doesn't burn someone's house down
She actually have to study how to make it because
A candle is both
A piece of art
And a lot of science
Five things that are interacting with each other
Is the fragrance
It's the base which is the wax
Is the color pigment
Is the WIC
And finally
Is the vassal
Which is the glass or a container
And if you don't do all those five things perfectly would like what was the wrong
Well have you ever seen candles that has a lot of black soot
That's because the wick is too big
Or you could have
A candle
That simply tunnel burn into the middle
And you don't smell anything
That's because
The formula
And the witch
Optimize
So happy that you visit there and
What you drive back to Maryland you start
Experiment we were bursting out of excitement we sell wow we're going to start making freaking candles for
The first time and
We decided to
Experiment what we learned
We didn't have the most when we went home
So instead
We will always
Eating a lot of Campbell Soup
Campbell Soup Campbell soup noodle soup
So we said these are great sizes
Siletz used
For molds for mode so we started mixing in our kitchen
With our regular pods
Oils with wax
With colors
One thing we forgot in our excitement is a chemical that blend the oil really well with a wax
So that when you
Take it out of the modes it looks very smooth
We forgot that camera
What happened is a random Hobby
Because
When we took the candle out of the mode
The candle look fossil
Fossil
Because of the oil not blending very well
So can I have this aged look around if it has a snowflake
Endnote
Candles I like
What is snowflake would be on different part of a candle
Everything looks
Handmade
And on top of that
I blended fragrance different
I put vanilla with
Lavender
I put
Watermelon with mint
Where many people just have
Best rate
Vanilla or straight watermelon
Is that the secret sauce of the the fragrance
Yes and many people say
The reason why they burn favors
Is the finishing touch
Cleaning at home
When they want
Finish
And since that
Home is ready for that
You know friends and family to come
For entertaining or
When their husband and children come back
Tom
You want to put something
Tomorrow
It's a clean house
So they put a candle
It smells like a cookie it smells like a
Fresh cotton
And that's why people continually by the can
Because they need to pray for
As You Are
Really kind of honing in on what what this product is is going to be is that when you came up with the name
Yes
So think about those colors
Beautiful cobalt blue
With a lavender with a honeydew bring not home to Greenwich everybody use
Sunflower yellow white
Think about
What it means it means energy
It means fresh
And this is where we give the name
Because we were living Annapolis
Annapolis Maryland Annapolis Maryland
And many times
I would take my dog for a walk
I like how Annapolis
Bitties
Still today is to very quiet
Is not the Hampton store
Any other
Yuno sushi place. Very down-to-earth
It's very real
Christina sent that to me
Coming from China
It is very untouched
And
It stand for natural
And I want
Communicate that because our
Candles are not touched by lava chemical
Natural finish on AR
Texture
So we just called it Chesapeake Bay candle
When we come back how many Cy.
Making an enemy out of the one person she needed to get her candles into Target
And eventually she recovered stay with us it's how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First ZipRecruiter
What if you had your own personal recruiter to help you find a better job
Now
ZipRecruiter technology can do that for you
Just download the ZipRecruiter app let it know what kind of jobs are interested in
And it puts your profile in front of employers
If an employer likes your profile
ZipRecruiter
Let you know
So if you're interested in the job
You can apply
Download
Free ZipRecruiter job search app today
And let the power of Technology
Work for you
Thanks also to E-Trade
Investing your money shouldn't require Moving Mountains
No matter how much or how little experience you have
E-Trade makes
Investing simple
Along with great value they provide the
Tools and support you need
Navigate to Market
How to help your money work
Hard for you
Good morning formation visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC member
Sitc
When you're paying for college on your own there's a lot to balance
Help you get through it all and scares life can't talk to the real expert
Student
Finding a side hustle that works for you and works for your schedule is usually beneficial
Find life gets new guide on how to pay for college in apple podcast
Or npr.org
Flashlight kit
It's how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Pixel experiment in her basement with Campbell's Soup cans
Macy
Stumbled across a new kind of candle with
Bold colors mixed
Fragrances
And now
She just needs
To convince someone
Dubai
So I called blooming
And I was
Working with the secretaries
Begging and pleading that
I have a great product
So finally she gave me the name of the buyer
The fire is really important they are the eyes and ears for any company and particularly for Bloomingdale's
You can imagine that
That the standards really high
When I describe two candles
What's the texture of the fragrances
And the colors she was very intrigued
So I got it
Appointment right away
And
You know when I went there
Didn't even sit down
They started
Taking a candles and show
Everybody around in the office
And you New York Gotham
So I take it Bloomingdale's maiden maiden order
They loved it
They just showed it to their
Bosses and we got it
First order
To ship to
The store said I have been
Going so many times
How did you
Produce enough candles to
Kill that order
So here comes the best
I was frustrated
Because
At that time China did not have a home fragrance industry
To produce that kind of oil
You need a chemical compound
Facility
And they were not used to that
They used to
Delta cinnamon send their Jasmine's overseas
The French and the US will then
Turn them into
Oils for fine fragrances
Call for Food flavors
But they don't have industry themselves
Sister Chinese word
Making fragrances like this head like
How are you able to even start that
So I talked to a few factories in China
They look at me like a
You know
That's a problem because
They certainly wouldn't take on a project
Like that
I was frustrated I told my sister about this
And she too
Was very determined to help me
So she said I'm going to quit
And she said I'm going to start a factory
In 1995
So that was the year
When we started have our own Factory which changed
Everything to me
Perfect look is it you can do that you can just
Build a factory is already 95 so you can put
Ceccoli in that part of China
Is very entrepreneurial
There are Villages that make nothing but buttons or Village that make nothing but candles
So
Having a factory is possible
But we have borrowed very heavily from friends and family
To build that
From scratch your sister builds his Factory and starts manufacturing the candles and
Would you working like crazy where you always working
I'm always thinking
Because I'm
I was always thinking about the next color
The next fragrance that can mix order next
Packaging that we can put together
So
I was always doing a lot of things at the same time
What were the things at that time that
Kept you up at night what were the
That certain guys you have
I was never have time to worry I'm a very optimistic
Sick person but I was always wondering who is our next
Customer so we stole
To Nordstrom right after Bloomingdale they're very similar companies
But in 1995 and 96
My eye started
Search for
Who is this
Company that's
Trending
Dave
Represents some demographic change
Stop
Shopping list
Yeah and I I started to focus
Why Target
Base ten for style and Design
Versus Walmart which stands for value
And it really inspired me
Because I really said
Describe two design
Fall
That philosophy because I came from a country with a
A lot of people
Without a very poor
And
I know a lot of teachers of mine
Who has
Great taste
Who would never be able to buy things
Instead of so expensive
Tibet Bloomington
So
How can I make it more fertile
How can we make it so we can sell it for
$20 purses
$80
So
I knew it's going to be the
Growth for us if we can get in
Because it's already 700
50 stores
National
And they have two dedicated Isles
With 48
Feet of
Candles
So who do you who do you call there
So it was pretty straightforward
You can find the name of the buyer there was a telephone
Extension
End
You can leave message
And you
Call Epperson
So this is the time when I always say you
You cannot give up even if you call for a whole year which I did a whole year every month at the same time
I called and left message
And you said what
I said hi
Same thing I did with Nordstrom and same thing I did with that I have a great candle
And now I can't even say it
It's sold at romanatwood
Juicery
Target buyers
Listen in and they say wow they already at those stores we want to be those two
Or so they would usually return your
Your phone but not
The buyer
And nothing silent Asylum
So how did you
Had you finally break through with so I have to say this
Probably one of my biggest failure is that I started to get frustrated and I said
To the receptionist she's not returning my call
So she said I think you could
Call her boss
And makeup
Which I did I basically say well you're one of your buyers have not met
Any return phone calls
2 minutes later to buy a call
And she said this is so and so
And just so you know this is not a way to start a relationship
And she hang out and she hung up on you
Wow so you were
Finish the time.
Every time I call again if it's her voice I didn't even leave
My voice message kept calling even though I kept calling
I can't call that you were shut out at that point I basically
So I waited until the next year in April
And it was a very different voice
It was a very cheerful voice
It was a new buyer it was a new buyer
And I like my message and I got it back in 2 days
Finally
Come
Because as you can imagine every new buyer wants to make a difference
I want to make that
Denmark
And she hurt me
So she said why don't you come
And I did
Where's our headquarters
Pepe's Minneapolis
Right around
So I flew there
And she was very young she was probably in her
Late twenties and she coming
And she was sitting down listening to my pitch but
Halfway through she has to get up
And smell the candles from the bottom
Candle buyers
You should want to smell the candles from the bottom
That's when the oil settle into the bottom
And you smell the most
SpongeBob
And so what you saying chief
Did she put an order in
Basically in a big store
It's a lot process
Dubai
Play Asia
Capability questions pricing questions
Cherry pick what they want
So I didn't expect
Anything to happen
Josh Smith
If I put it in my store how soon can you ship
That was the moment when I froze
Because I said what do you mean
Are you going to test because I heard they test a lot
That do testing 50 stores
100 stores
She said no me I wanted
Put it in 750 stores
And I said
Oh in that case and I started
To calculate in my head
How fast
My sister's company can produce
With 700
Beast Wars
And I said
6 months
I just have perfect that would land Us in October and you can ship it so it arrives
In December
And that's when we set for spring
An end how big was ever
That order end up being
Over $1000000
And the forecast for the year
End up being over 3 minutes
How did Jamie soap so basically it mean when you call your sister and you said
We have a sword from Target we have to make how many can't even remember how many candles you had to make it's probably
Half a million candles
How many candles
What was
Factoryville
Mapreduce
That was going to stretch them
They were going to have three ships
Everyday of the week
Just like 24/7
Yes
We'll have to hire people
To work 7 days a week
And the thing about the the target
Shipment is that is really daunting
When you think about people scamming that business
That's one of the things people
Overstock
Think about is financed how to finance a big order
I mean it.
The second female ask is legit
Physically how do you turn over 20 containers
Oh candles
In two days
And we don't even have to
The physical space
Ways to turn 20 containers
In 2 days right
So we rented
A very big empty Warehouse in Laurel
In Laurel Maryland Maryland where are
Other warehouses
But there's no electricity
So we parked up
Two cars
Used to headlight
To light up the warehouse in the evening
And we literally
Packed and unpacked
Using aqua love you you
David Richard
And two or three of our warehouse workers
Five of us
All together
Witch Hunt over 20 container was five people in the US have the time
5 to 6
Fulton paper
And we went into holiday season some somewhat absent-minded
Waiting to see when the product will show up on the shelves
I showing up right after Christmas
R Prada
That's what they're but it was radio silence there was nothing coming from the buyer from Target
Until when
Hunter 2 weeks after it was set
And I get panic order
Call from the buyer
Some a word
Big trouble
Oh no they didn't get all the
Products or
You're not moving at all
No
We are under forecast
We could have sold 8 million dollars off your candles this year
And you need to go back to China and build a bigger factory
And we need to catch up because I don't want to be empty shop
In April or March
So is that what you did
Guess what we did
And we found a much bigger facility
And we all fit it
So that
By March
We started shipping out of the new facility how many factors do you have
So we have one in
Hangzhou China
As the first factory
Now we have whining High phone
In Vietnam
And now in Glen Burnie Maryland
Clouseau
It's a lot more expensive to
To manufacture candles in the US
Why are you doing it
I came to this country
And I'm a citizen for many many years
Always want to find product that said meaning
USA when I go back to China
And I couldn't find them
Everything is always made in China
Made in Indonesia Made in India
I think mating USA stand for something
We may have not real
People believe that
There's integrity
Andeavor cell
Cool fact
With product says made in US
And we haven't
Strada
Did you think you had a competitive advantage
In part because you are an immigrant and in part because
Everything in America was new to you and your kind of
Knife
I think that's
Precisely
I think immigrants
A self-selected
They are self-selected group that is
Dairy Pig
Taking risks
In some ways they have
The same Trace
Panniers already
Instead of taking what's easy
What's already
Familiar
They choose
Unfamiliar
Unchartered
Because they have more confidence
And they have more curiosity
So in selecting themselves as
Immigrants there already
Facing big risks
From a company that you started
Is it is an afterthought with
Silk flowers and car seat covers
To accompany that
I seen does
Reportedly
Like 60 to 70 million dollars a year in Revenue
It's a
Pretty amazing
We could you have imagined that when you came to the US
A temporary Visa that
That you would be running a company that
It's so big
So remember the alien story
Yeah remember I thought I was
You know going to meet an alien and discovered that I was
Actually the alien
How cool is it that an alien
Next president of United State
And talk about
How to create job
In America
That was me
In 2012
I was creating jobs in the United States
Cuz I'm a factory and
The president's office
Took note
And he invited 13 of the biggest manufacturers such a
Ford
Intel
And I was invited because I was a small business
And
I was giving advice
As to why it makes sense to revitalize
Manufacturing in this country
Hawaii
That we have not done enough
For those company
Sprint jobs
So I feel very fortunate not only
Was I accepted not
Just as a florna you know I was able to giving a path
To realize what I want to do a more
Macy founder of Chesapeake Bay candle
Let me hear after we spoke in the fall of 2017
They actually decided to sell the company
Chihuahua making a
How do you get deal with Newell Brands it's a New Jersey based business that also owns Yankee Candle
The purchase price
75 million dollars
As for me
This year she started a new venture
A website macy.com tells stories of women entrepreneurs all across the country
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the
The things your building
But first a quick message from one of our 2019 lead sponsors of how I built this hiscox
Understand every small business is unique
Taylors
Policies that your business is very
Pacific need
Get a quote or purchase a policy at hiscox cam
Hiscox
Business
Insurance
Hey it's Peter Sagal so you're listening to this NPR Podcast because you want to be informed you want to learn something
You want to be a better citizen Great Wall for that
I should listen to more podcasts myself it
What if you need a little break
What's that little voice in the back of your head stop saying do this it's good for you and starts
Whispering for jokes and rude noises
Well then you want to check out wait wait don't tell me the NPR news quiz
It's the show that lets here lizard brain enjoy yourself for 1
You can't be serious again later
New episodes drop Saturday
Listen and tell your friend
Hey thanks so much for
Sticking around because
Time now for how you built that
And today
We're updating the story that we ran about a year ago and it has to do with beer which if
Yourself you know it takes just four ingredients water
But everyone knows about and you've got your yeast which is kind of where the magic happens but Wednesday
Jean-Pierre in college important ingredient is actually Grand Masti malted barley and you take
Can you mix it in with the grand kind of like making a batch of oatmeal and oatmeal is the key word here
Because when Dan and his friends were making their own beer they noticed it all the leftover piles of wet barley
Smells kind of like breakfast food smells like bread very fragrant but none
That Brewing books told us
What to do
With this grin
Deleted put it in a dumpster this is happening around 2009-2010 and a few years later
Dan was in the Bay Area where craft breweries were Brewing
We started to notice that a lot of those breweries
Just like him we're turning out huge mounds of leftovers spent grain that smells like food
It looks like food and so it was really pretty low-hanging fruit to think okay well maybe we can make food products out of this
Luckily for Dad
Your friend named Jordan who would work in the food business
Ginga and called a bunch of small breweries in the Bay Area
And he starts to drive around with these big plastic tubs to
Hiccup all of this used grain I threw out my back a few times
Yeah it's heavy
So anyway they take those heavy tubs of barley to Jordan's parents house and
Just experiment by took my mother-in-law's recipe for loose granola
Oats and flax honey cinnamon
And eventually they decided to turn the granola into snack bars low sugar high fiber
With a great eating experiences not a much bar at can I eat like a rice crispy treat
Did the snack bars on friends and at farmers markets in. So great
Found the bars to be a bit dry
And to be a bit Hokey Pokey
Until we get bit stuck in people's teeth and one of the mouthfeel descriptors that we got pretty consistently was Poke
So to eliminate the Pokedex Dan Jordan decided to grind the beer grain into
Two more of a flower and then from there that really solve the texture issue that we did launch and I would have a great product that selling
Really well we got another one on the way and the snack bars are now on sale in many parts of the
The US and on Amazon since we last spoke with Dan
Ian Jordan has managed to get there bars in the Whole Foods in eight different states and when we first met
Friendly story both Dan and Jordan had just quit their day job to run the company now more than a year later
They're finally able to pay themselves a salary and I'm not buying a house anytime soon unless it take
Take it down payment and then nutrition bars
Is called regrained and Beltway reclaims networks do not taste like beer but they do have
Aerie names like chocolate coffee Stout in the honey cinnamon IPA
You want to find out more about regrained or here
Previous episodes of our show head to our new podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and
Of course if you want to tell us your story go to bills. Npr.org we love hearing what you're up to
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe to our program at Apple podcast
Or wherever you get your podcasts then why you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write us at HRBT at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
At how I built this
Our show is produced this week that run. Dale fatter with original music composed By REM teen Arab Louis the two of them have left
Start their own podcast
Thanks also to Julia Carney sanaz meshkinpour need a grant
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Is David jot
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR