Support for this NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from betterhelp
Online counseling by license
Professional count
Specialized
Issues including the
Depression stress
And anxiety
Visit betterhelp.com
Slash built to learn more
And get 10% off your
Your first month
So before we start the show I want to tell you about a
You how I built this
Live shows
Attend on the E
East Coast
This fall
Supported by America
Express
First I'll be heading to New York
Christina Tosi of Milk Bar
Town Hall
And then
I'll head to Washington DC on some
Tristan Walker of Walker & Co
Lincoln Theater
Get your tickets and find out more about our live events in
Including a third East Coast show
That will be announcing very soon
NPR presents
. org
And I hoped
See you there
I also want let you know that tickets are almost in
Tirely sold out for NPR's how I built this Summit
Happening this October
In San Francisco
It's also supported by Americans
Express
It will be a bunch of it
Shredabull Founders Day
Companies
Spanx Instagram slack JetBlue and many many
You can find out more information and get your tickets before they're gone
Summit
NPR
. org
And what are the other factors that will be there is Marcia Kilgore
You don't
Some of us are lucky enough to have one really good idea
Lettsworth building into a business
Marcia Kilgore
She had five
5 ideas
Call different
All of which turned into incredibly successful companies
This is
Unbelievable story
And I can't wait to talk to him more about it
At The Summit in sand
San Francisco
We first ran this episode
January of last
If you haven't heard
So
Crazy if you have heard it is
Totally worth
Rehearing it one more time
Curtis
I treated myself to a facial
After an economics exam and I had saved 40 or $50 to go to this place that was
Supposed to beat the be-all-and-end-all of facials and I remember walking into that place and the esthetician look through the lamp
At my skin what a pity
This is not a treat and I left feeling so horrendous and I remember to see my reflection
My face is kind of raw and blotchy and thinking if I ever had a place like that I would know
Never make my customers
Feel bad about themselves
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
They go
I'm guy Raz
Teen year old named Marcia Kilgore moved from a small town in Canada to New York
Which is three hundred bucks
Turn yourself into a Serial entrepreneur the founder of five companies
Bliss cosmetics
Fitflops
According to the small business administration
There's a 50% chance that your business will fail within the first 5 years
Took there something to maximize the chances that their businesses will succeed
Planet research the market
The way Arthur Blank and his partner Bernie Marcus did for nearly two years before they launched the home
Depot or the way Jenn Hyman from Rent the Runway did tons of market research and proof of
Concept testing long before she went to investors all of this raise the odds that these companies
Make it past 5 years which brings us to Today Show because this is truly a story about
Someone never had a bigger plan Marcia Kilgore didn't set out to be
Successful serial entrepreneur
She never sat down and said hey I'm going to start a line of skin care products called Bliss and then
I want to start for more companies she was a personal trainer who had a side hustle getting facials
And what happened to her happened organically it just evolved into something bigger and
Bigger
Marcia actually grew up
In Saskatoon Saskatchewan Canada go ahead find it on the map
Busy very cold place even by Canadian standards anyway pretty middle-class home
Dad was a real estate agent mom took care of the house
Until age 11 when Marcia's dad died after battling cancer
So her mom went back to work and Marcia well she started working too
Aerobics instructor
To become a bodybuilder
Yeah I mean I could probably bench-press 185 lb I can probably quiet
It was it was actually a skill and a
Mojave that pilate itself into
You know what I could you later so
It would give us helpful
Well okay
So I think I've always loved a big challenge
Lunch and when I was living in Saskatoon which was
Small City and there was a
Really much too
To do
My middle sister started dating a guy whose brother owned
A gym
And he said hey you should come down to the gym and workout I used to run a lot
I thought okay well you
Let me
Go down to the gym and
Check it out it's something to
To do
Because really
You know Saskatoon
10 months of the year
Pretty cold and there are only two television channels back then so it was
It was pretty dry
So I went down to the gym
And I remember them hooking me up with this
Female bodybuilder her name is Sherry something and she was Miss
Canada bodybuilding at the time
And they gave me a couple of sessions with her
Learn how to do all sorts of
In a different weight lifting
Moves and routines
And she work me so hard it was a basement gym and I could not walk up the
Just got out of the gym
And I just thought
You know
This is a
Interesting Hobby
I've got this free membership let me do it
You
If this is like a tape meth or not but apparently you became like a
Weight class
Bodybuilding champion
It's not a myth I win
Etsy
Southern Saskatchewan middleweight
I think I also want
Don't laugh
Miss Moose Jaw
Got moose
I said don't laugh
But you know the it was great because I could also I mean by taught aerobics when I was a teenager as well just to earn extra money
Waitress
Start of Lent itself to many different things that
That were useful
Is in was was
Was the idea
Did you
Did you have jobs in
Did you earn money in part because
Was you
I don't know felt like there was some Financial insecurity at home and that you
And it was a way for you to kind of have some control over your
Own financial situation
I think that I knew my mother was under a lot of stress
You know just just from being a single mother and trying to make ends meet and I didn't want to be
A drain
And if I could pay my own way in terms of at least not asking her for any money
Even that was something that made me feel you know that it was it was
Relieving
Stressed from her
Hitman never made enough
Pay the rent
But I didn't have to ask
Schizophrenic
Because you're in high school
And bring a bunch of jobs at your bodybuilder
Robux
The fitness type person as a teen and then what was your
Plan After High School to Jutsu
Did you go to college
What when I was
17 my sister who is living in New York at the time so this was my
My oldest sister Jody
She told me that if
I could get accepted to Columbia University and get
Pass
All the different entrance exams
Then she would pay my tuition
How was she able to do that she was a model she was living in New York City and making
Decent cash decent cash
So I came to New York I had $300 in my pocket
And I was supposed to go to Columbia and that year unfortunately my sisters
Financial situation was not as strong as she thought it
It was going to be
And so as a had applied for a student loan
Foreign student early enough
It's too late for me to get a loan
So I kind of was in New York
With my 300 bucks
And no school to go to and I had to figure it out
And this was like
So you don't have money for school
No work
You know this is the interesting thing so I started
When I first arrived in New York
I got myself a gym membership
With the little money that I did have because of course once working out is part of your life you really have
Citgo Antioch
To go pretty much every day for an hour rescue starts
To kind of lose that endorphin
Dependency and so there's a really great gym
Call Better Bodies
And i met a film director there named douglas keeve
We chatted in a while we were working out and at one point he said hey do you think you could be my personal trainer cuz I want to look more like you
He was very tall and kind of lead and I will
Was probably a little bit more muscular but not bulky
I said he wanted to have a busy like mine and so he was my very first personal training client
And then other people
Brewhemia
You just meet you and I started
My sister been
You realize that I was a purse
Personal trainer and started to
Refer models and actresses and actors and stunt man and
We are all kinds of
People to miso
I ended up having you know
Quite a collection of interesting personalities
Personal training clients
And started to build up the money that I needed
Let's go to some part-time
Classes at NYU
So
What did you think
All right I'll do this I'll take some
Classes at NYU olbia
Your personal trainer and then
But like long-term I'm going to do this or that
Did you was that
Even like part of the equation
I had no plan
I think I was in survival mode I knew that
Doing personal training getting up at 5 a.m. and sometimes having your last night at 9:30 at night and then sleeping
Maybe 5 and 1/2 hours and starting all over again and maybe going to a class somewhere during the day that was under
Sustainable
And I used to fall asleep in my
Economics
Because I was so tired and then I started to develop quiet
A bad case of acne and it was probably because New York can be so humid
I was running around all day
And you wanted to look decent so you could put makeup on
And then go to
A personal training session with someone where you're sweating and then you put more makeup on that you didn't have time to go home and wash your face in between
That client the next client so my skin got really bad
I want summer I treated myself
To a facial after an economics exam that I took at NYU but I had actually walked up
Town I had saved for your $50 to go to this place that was supposed to be the be-all-and-end-all a facial
And I remember going in there and I had been under so much stress trying to write this exam studying really hard
Working all the time no paying for everything myself and this was supposed to be a real treat and I remember walking
Into that place laying down on the table
An esthetician booked through the lamp at my skin
And then she said what a pity
Okay this is not a treat she actually then proceeded to go out into the
Let me know common area of that spot and bring in this file manager
Who was a gentleman who came in and they both looked through the lamp at my scanning and sort of piston oh no
What a disaster and I left feeling so horrendous and I remember taking the subway home
A nasty
Subway pulled up in front of me you have to have the stainless steel side so you get your reflection and remember to see my reflection of my
Basic kind of raw and blotchy and thinking if I ever had a place like that I would never
Make my customers feel bad about
And
Remember
I decided
To take
The crash course
And skincare
And I took this I think it was probably
Three or four weeks
Crash course in
Skin carrying a base
6 skincare and how to do facials
And I
Started to convince my personal training client after I would take them jogging or
Give them a yoga
Classic
Whatever it was
To let me pray
Facials on them
An end
And likes
And you would have all the
You know I'm driving
Haven't had a facial.
Ever
Like showing up in
People's apartments with
All the supplies you need to give a
Facial Impressions picture that you were you lugging around like potions and lotions and things like that
Oh yeah
I mean this was a huge bag of stuff first of all I care.
Steamer which is a very outdated piece of equipment I would never seen somebody's face now
Back then it was what everybody did and that was kind of the method that we learned and we thought
That was good for the skin
You know since then we've learned that it's not so good for the skin Tokay this steamer which was
We like a small
Coffee machine
And then I would have probably 20 tubes in jars
Cotton pads and
Towels and
You know it was sort of
Like a giant bat
If you were going to go
Hike the you know the trail
You can go hike that I was probably carrying around that
Because I would then also bring my personal training app
Play mat with piano
30 kilos
Wow
So you
So you had this life
Disservice
Sides and go and why you were also a personal trainer and
I mean it at what point Did you sort of start asking
People to pay you
Furfrou
Think that any of my personal training clients I don't think I ever charged them for
And then at one point and it was
Kind of one of those beautiful organic things
Where
I was doing a lot of
Young models
I was their personal trainer
And there was an agency that used to send me all of the young models who were a little bit out of shape
To get them in shape
I'm at agency
Cihad
A couple of girls who were the boogers
And one of them had
Quite Baskin and started to come for facial
And then she started to send me all of the young models
Who had bad skin and I started to really
Gained a reputation for being able to
The clear up at
At which point I got other people coming in who were not necessarily just you know
Young new models but in fact
I'm more well-known individuals who happen to
Live downtown here about me through the grapevine and you know
Started coming in and paying for that service
Where where are you doing this at this point what started at my apartment and then I rented a tiny little space
Probably
NSA
300 square feet
It was just a one-room Studio I had a little closet where people could change
And a chair where they could wait
That was what I had in people becoming for the facials
So you would probably you will be work on
Currently working but it sounds like you were
When you were doing pretty well and you had money as a purse
Coming in from Europe
Personal training good money at coming in
The facials like that
Olivia mean you you had expenses but you were his hands
You are covering
Oh yeah I was covering my expenses
I was at a very low maintenance person though so I lived in in the East Village in my
Studio art
What's it like sort of a
You could kind of call it a one bedroom
And I had a futon
Leather sofa
I had a
Tiny TV that one of my personal training clients have given me because they didn't want it anymore
It's sat on a crate I had a
Vacuum cleaner
And you know it's a lamp in a radio
So you know I was
Apus
A minimalist
Let's say we're clients are mostly models at SFO
Yeah it was quite funny because
Only had one door right over the door and people just sent us at the door knock and then I would open the door and
I remember from time to time opening the door
And the person standing I was so
Outstandingly beautiful male or female that I wouldn't be able to
Speak
Kroger open the door
Gas
And lose my breath and I have to kind of
You know get my composure back and welcome them in and show them where to change and then give him a facial but
That was when it really
Exploded and everybody started
To come in from
Uma Thurman I didn't
Kidman Demi Moore
Annie Leibovitz came in
How did you get all these Super Famous clients like
What was your
If I tell you I
I just really thorough
I think it's really important to be thorough and do you know just
Do the best job you cut down
Listen most facials
Would take an hour
Facial is generally an hour
I might be in there for two hours
With somebody if they really needed it for me time you know
If I have the time and I could
Could have somebody
Have there treatment for longer I would do it and I Bank
You get results when you put time in
So at what point did you think
This really could be
A business like I need to
Think about turning this into just something Beyond
This 300 square foot
Being a little
Walk-in closet
2 something
I think I've
Realize that it could be
Viable
I guess career
When my appointment book
Started to be full for
5 to 6
Six weeks in advance
People would call and I couldn't necessarily get them in at the time that they requested I was working today
6 days a week
And still
Still trying to hang on to some of my earlier personal training clients
And realizing that it was just
So hard to be able to do both that I might have to
You know someday give that up
Also realize that I could train other people to do
The same thing
And that wasn't something that ever entered my mind before because I'll be
DC you know when you think that you're
Early passes
You're going to go to university and you're going to have a profession you're going to work as a
Professional never again no one in my family had ever
Have their own business or
Give me that example that you can run a business that you can employ people that you can
Can grow an idea
So
I think I'm probably after 2 years in that
That tiny little 300
Square foot space I hired someone
I'm who came in and started to learn how I was doing treatment
And then I found a bigger
Space that I could rent
Which was just
Two blocks away
And started to build out what was
Ben called let's face it
So when
How did you become Bliss how did that
Adeline name be
Become the name
Company
So at let's face it it started to become so busy that we were books and they were at that point probably
5 estheticians
Esthetician being a person gives facials and we worked on different shift
So somewhere part-time but we tried to make the most of the 12th
The 14 hours that we could be open in our building during during each day and we were also open on Saturday
And at one point
Probably after about 2 years
We were so busy that when people would call they wouldn't be able to get an appointment for
Anywhere between
16 months
Ansible
Yeah you know it was so amazing because people come in they would have their treatment they would leave it would be so high
Happy and they would book
For that same time slot
For the next 12 or 18 months
I've never actually
Great story
A huge snowstorm
In 1990
I-95 in New York where
Width of a snow piled up for 12 feet on the side of the road then
Okay
Every everything around us with closing
Crate Barrel close Dean & DeLuca close everybody close
Are phone that day
What's a ringing off the hook
What people say
Has anyone cancelled
Can we get in
Because
They were hoping that a point would become available and that somebody else would have cancelled their put and nobody cancel their appointments
Somehow despite the weather everybody still made it down there cuz gossip are they going to cancel their appointment
So it was amazing
So I guess it was like
Like 1996 when when you open an even larger
Storefront right in this is when you called it
Let's write
Yep
And it was
Much
Bigger
Area floor plate than we'd had at let's face
We had 10 treatment rooms and we had a nap room
I'm and we opened in
Beginning of July
Of 1996
How did you have the money to do this I mean the most to you must have
Rent a space you have to
How to take a 3-year lease you had to put lots of money down yet
To convert the space I mean
Did you bring in outside investment
At the time
I was pretty scary
And
I again having not had the experience of anyone or you know really any business school likes
Experience I didn't really
Consider I didn't even think about outside
What I knew was
That if I gay facials myself
All day long everyday
And I can probably take Sunday off
And charged you know maybe it was
Is 84 a facial then
That I could still pay that rent by myself and that was a calculation that I made
I'm intensive of the build-out of the
Spa
I took a little bit of a flyer on that one because
At that time of course we were booked for
18 months in advance and I kind of did the calculation in terms of
What you know
What we made
When we were full all day long
Everyday
That we were really lucky
The timing was great on this
About two months
Before
We open blessing while we were still in the construction phases
American folk
Did a beautiful piece
With a beautiful Irving Penn portraits
A girl having milk poured over her head and talked about
We cream
And one of them
Was
I think one of them is creme de la mer
Which Estee Lauder went on to buy and turned it into a big thing
And one of them was a Swiss oxygen cream that we saw and
When is
Article drop
Thousands of people started
Call to buy biswas
Oxygen cream
And
It
Latin
Probably for four or five months
Buena Vista
Article having such an incredible effect on the sales of products
Out of our
The facial place
A lot of the construction
Cost
We're almost covered by that 1 hour
Incredible
So I mean you think about like renting a space in New York City today
In Manhattan today that's insane like you have to be
Multi-million
Are you have to put down tons of money and
Attentive
Applications in end
And you did this in 1996 which
Still kind of do that and not be a millionaire I think so I think it was probably one of the last
Periods of time that you could do that not be a millionaire they seem to be a little bit more
Trust in terms of his
You know here's the kid I remember the landlord
Kind of looking at me thinking with your sick kid and she's obviously
Responsible and she's got this
Decent business already and you know let's give it a shot
Certainly I flinched and it was terrifying filling out the paperwork
And it was
You're looking at it thinking of the responsibilities of that overhead
But for me
Cuz I never had anything
To lose everything
Was not a big deal
I'm trying to figure out they were there worse
Spas
They're still there in the
But you come in and
You have this
Baseballism
Call it that
Somehow
Was just
Exploded
Articles and people are lining up
What was it
About blessed what were you offering
That was different
From those other play
You know I've always
And and since then all the businesses that have started have been places
I want to go
So I wanted to go
To get a facial or get a body treatment to get a pedicure in a non-judgmental place where people were having fun with them
Music was not about whales
Singing or
I hated that kind of music I loved
Are Jazz and really good
Soulful music so he's a mix of music myself
I wanted it to be different I wanted to be a
Place that I would like to go that I would feel comfortable
Books where people would be accepting of me
You no answer that's what we did for everybody else
And
I think
It was
Fantastic because it was
Very egalitarian
You would have those superstars in their soap McDonald whoever but then you would also have
Secretariat
Kids from NYU let you know terrible problems with their skin and
Just wanted
Relief from it neighbor
Are going to school up the block so it was easy for them to come
Yep really everybody and it was
It was
Wonderful because everyone was treated exactly the same way
I think I'd be nervous getting Madonna facial
She was very curious
She's one of those people with tons and tons of questions
What are you doing now what is this what is that supposed to do
But you don't screenshot it wasn't really nervous giving anybody a facial
It was so much fun there was so many characters
From the people who work at the front desk
To the client and I'm New York
Is so full of amazing character
It is like watching a television show right
It didn't seem like work
In just a moment
Call Marcia sold Bliss
And then turn around and found it
A new company
And then another
Then another
And then
Another
Stay with us and gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Everyone just a quick thanks
The two of our sponsor
Help make this podcast pause
First
Capital One
With the Capital One Venture Card you earn unlimited double miles
Every purchase
Everyday
And you can use those miles towards
Travel expenses like
Lights
Hotels rental cars and more
Just book and pay for your travel using your Venture Card
Redeem your miles
Ortho cost
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Credit approval required
Capital One Bank USA
Thanks also to fundrise
Fundrise innovated the way people can invest
In real estate
They are the first online investment platform designed to give
People the opportunity to own a portfolio of high-quality real estate
Affordably
Thanks to their
Cutting-edge low-cost model
Access private Market real estate projects for
High-rises
DC
The multifamily apartments in LA
To get started
Fundrise
Sec.com
/ bill
To have your first sick
Six months of advisory fees waived
There's a multivitamin that
Alive
Instantly better
Or we need to get its benefits
It's just step outside
Nature and
Parks and Greenery
Helps us be our better selves
The miracle of vitamin n
The latest app
Notify you 2.0 series
On hidden brain
From NPR
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
I'm kyroz
So it's 1996 let's face it
Becomes
Bliss and it opens as a day spa in New York Soho neighborhood and almost instantly the phone
Are ringing off the hook
Took a very short period of time Marcia decides to expand
Double the size of bliss
Chelsea gets married around this time to her boyfriend Terry
He joins the business and the two of them decided
Try new things like make a line of skin care products under the name Bliss in soon
They start talking about expanding to other cities
But just as things start to take off this is 3 years in the business a huge multinational brand
Comes knocking lvmh
The conglomerate that owns Louis Vuitton and they want a piece of bliss
70% and they're offering Marcia a lot
Money
So the amount of money that's been reported
It was anywhere from
30 to 50 million dollars for that that 70% stake it which is a lot
But you guys were just hitting your strides
Why did you sell it that
About a year prior to 1999 if we actually had a lot it was a
Hot time for beauty companies
Retrospectively there were a lot of
Cool new companies starting and a lot of interest in those companies from the big Beauty conglomerates they were starting
To buy up smaller players rather than into trying to build their own
And of course both had such a reputation
That we we had more than one large large company come and try and get us
And I think the most exciting thing for me at that time was the idea of not having
All of the financial responsibility
For that business
I'm on my head we actually were we had expanded and Along Comes A large company
Set looking at Redbox
Which was
Was also very funny because they had a account and I think based in Chicago who couldn't believe
But we were making this money without doing something illegal
They came in and they did a report and there were all these things in the report
You know Bliss purports to have celebrity clients
Play reports to be doing facials and what do you think we're doing in here
It was really it was quite funny to read I guess they just never seen anything like it before
It just
It seems like after so many years of
Being
Kind of flat broke
Or
You know
On the edge
They would be nice
Just have
A little bit of money
In the bank
Obviously Bliss
Switching really well but you
You guys were
Still living
Yeah I'll be okay so
For anybody who's live their entire life worrying about money or you know just kind of
Young Living very minimally
You do wonder if that's your motivation
And if your motivation and all this
Skills that you've developed well
Somehow profoundly changed when suddenly there are some zeros in your bank
So that was a bit of a crisis thinking will I be
Different if I'm not
Starving
But
It was just too good an offer
To refuse
They had flown me to Paris on the
Concord
I had gone to the Christian Dior Boutique they took me to Orleans where the factory was where
They were you know manufacturing math
Skara and
I'll be there when you come back to me or actually I have to say I came back to New York I flew back on the Concorde and I'm on the subway
In a Coca-Cola spilled all over this
Steven garbage strewn everywhere and
Hanging on that subway car thanking God I wonder if I was the only person on the Concorde this morning between the subway
And it was just it was it was funny cuz I can happily do both
But you did realize that maybe after having work my tail off
For 14 to 16 hours a day for the last however many years at that point I guess it would have been 11 years
Maybe it didn't have to be that hard anymore
Did it change your liquor like suddenly coming at all this money
You get a few a few
Dollars in your bank account and I did have a laugh and we used to joke when it got wired you know we said the eagle has landed
And we laughed and then we went and got groceries in our regular shopping Brooklyn you don't see money to you it just goes into
Do its numbers on a
On a piece of paper and it lands and then
Yeah baby
You might fly business class
A maybe you might
Go and buy a few more clothes than you normally would maybe once
And then you realize
You know what you love is what you love and
I think it takes quite a long time to start
Living differently when when you
Live for so long with the same attitude
Okay see you guys in 1999 you sold about 70% of the company to
To lvmh
You sold the rest
Your shares to another come
You walked entirely away from Bliss
That's what was
What's going on in your life that
Lvmh after 2001
They started to divest of most of it beauty biz
And we were one of the first ones
To get snapped up by another
Business so Starwood Hotels and Resorts
But ice
Because they wanted to have blue spots
And it was put those
N2w hotels in another hotel
And so
Yeah that was also very flattering so first I had you know one of the largest luxury groups in the world by
My business and then I had the largest hotel group in the world by my business so
Two Good Hits
But they put somebody in charge of the business
Who was the young guy probably The Prodigy of the
The man who owns Starwood at the time
Who really didn't understand customer service the way I understood it
And
I felt like I was spending most of my day
Trying to teach him but he was reticent
And
For me
Do you know
Chip
Spend my time on
That when the
The person is not necessarily
Open to the ideas
Just felt like banging my head against
It was very draining
So I decided to
To take a break from it
And I didn't really know what I was going to do
But I just didn't want to do that
Anymore
So when
When you left
Starwood
What did you do to shoot I know
That you
Musa London
Fort for a while did you just kind of hang out
Choi not working for a while
But probably had a
About three months
Off
And as soon as I
I had
A little bit of energy back I started to
Come up with a
You new ideas for a new brands and a new things that I had
As a woman again
The hole in the marketplace
Play Store
So I guess the
We should we should we should point out here that
It didn't take very long
How to decide to start a new business
Which was soapandglory
And this is going to be like before double personal hygiene
Skin products
Yeah I'll be okay so I remember just
You know scanning newspapers
Toscanini's
Journals every Sunday and
Same as that guy's really being one about collaboration
And you know High Street prices or you know
Really affordable pricing for designers
Our stuff and H&M was Leading The Way with
With that
And also
About waist
There was starting to be a lot of
A lot of
Interest in environmental concerns there was a story about David Beckham only wearing his underwear once
Throwing it out and how wasteful it was you know
SOA
I started to think you know people are really
Worried about the environment
People want more for their money
And so how can I roll that all out and do
Fun little brand that I can sell
And soap and Glory it was designer affordable
Cosmetic
And then of course I we also did Dre sample packaging that wouldn't be
You're too hard on the environment
Took all the Zeitgeist ideas in
Bundle them up and
So we launched at Harvey Nichols
Really fun department store and then
Boots came knocking
Who's has the big the big drug stores
Britain
And so we rolled out into boots and it was
It was actually very small for the first couple of years we didn't do that much business but within essays
767 years we were probably be telling about a hundred million
And you did not take any outside investment for this company
I know cuz you didn't need to you had you could use the money that you had from the sale of blisstool
The snacks company organic growth you
People think about this overnight successes inferi
Rarely are they in overnight
My things do take years and they grow but then once they grow big enough they start to snowball
And so it started to snowball in it at one point
I remember
Istudent
Like crazy Christmas bag
Where are these Christmas pictures
Full of products
And there are literally hundreds
Thousands of them produce
List every Christmas and
The week before Christmas there would be this special offer we could go in and
Looking for a Christmas bag and if
If you walked around London
Every third person was
Carrying
Three or four of these on their arms
It was such a big deal.
In the midst of of launching soap & Glory
A year later
You lunch to another company
In addition to that you lunch today
A company that makes
I like flip-flops
Is called
Call the FitFlop
So how did that happen why would you like a second company whilst
Trying to a lunch
The first company Earth II company why would you want a third company
But trying to get your second
You know
This is very interesting
White lights to kind of
Simultaneously
However I have just read this book called Originals
And this one chapter
In that book where it says
2 entrepreneurs always hedge their bets
Right you don't give up your day job because you think that you're you know side has told her whatever it is
Is going to actually pay off
If you always do two things at the same time cuz one of them may not work and you want to make sure that you've got another one
And it's kind of like personal training
While I was doing facials
What's right and I guess I
Did that
Again where
With soap and Glory when I started it you know it was only a year later
But I also launched FitFlop and it was really based on
The idea for one shoe which was economically correct which would align your body while you watch and
Because of my personal training days and trying to
Use my time more efficiently and having started this
This new business open Glory thinking that I'd have work-life balance and then finding that I had
No time at all actually
Or very little time to exercise
I was thinking to myself
What can I invent to make more out of this time that I
That I have when I am walking
How can I make walking really work for me in an optimal way
So I've been spent a lot of time on different trains in the UK going to different universities trying to find somebody
Who would be able to help me realize
This idea and in fact
Eventually
Found
Dr. Dave Cook at the University of South Bank in London which was
Probably a mile away at
The crow flew
So I eventually met with DACA
When I went in at security idea
Blah blah blah and he said oh I know how you can do that
So they told me they can make a prototype test
They had a shoe design
Course going on within the University
I waited and waited and waited about three months later
I come in to see this prototype init
Literally it looks like a lump of coal
With some ropes
Finance
We can't sell this this so ugly
No one will wear this outside no matter what it does for them
But we tested it right so we
We put it on
Some
Different
University students
Speed and we put electrodes on them and we looked at their
Forces
You can see whether or not the technology is helping
To align
The force that goes through your heel
Is your heel strike
When you walk
And
It worked
Rights of this this lump of coal with the robes
So
I've been thought okay
What do I do now
About the shoe
It does what I wanted to do
I don't know how to make a shoe or where to go to get shoes made and then I thought well I
I could go to Nike or Puma or whatever and they thought no I can't cuz they're going to steal my ID
Yeah and then in the recesses of my mind
Night I remember that I knew somebody who did Footwear
At the time they were called Peter black they've since been bought by a Chinese conglomerate
We called Peter back but we're and we met with somebody who did sourcing for them
And then we had a mold made
Which again you know which one of these since you got to take a flyer it was probably
$40,000 to have the mold made
So you have to really hope this is going to go because $40,000 is not nothing
But at the time I thought you know what I'd buy this issue with this she was available so I'm sure other people will buy this shoe
And so would you run up we made a prototype
Frantically comfortable
Incredible
And
I remember sitting down so course I went to retailers that I knew
From my American days first and then and then also to Busan in the UK who is selling soap & Glory
But about a year before that I had met with Bath & Body Works
Explain the idea
And the buyer from Bath and Body Works
Looked at me and said
I'll take somewhere between 300000 and 500000 pairs of autism
A year wow
I'm shocked I remember walking away cuz they wanted to meet at claridge's so we went to Claire just you know and had tea and talked about it then
Walking out of Clarence just thinking
Wow
Whole new level
I mean I couldn't get 300,000 facials a year
It's incredible I mean if you if you think about it right so you
You sell blessed
You walk away from Bliss
You then
Launch soap & Glory in
Run that business
Simultaneously launch
The economic shoe line
FitFlop in 2007
You sold soap & Glory to boots I guess and
And then last year you launched
A brand new business
8 Hayes
A subscription service
For high-end cosmetics
That are asked
Salem
Adpi
How do you do that how do you
How do you
Create so many how do you say on top of so many different ideas and Company
You know guy today I don't feel like I'm quite so on top of it
But beauty pie the whole idea behind it was
Knowing
Cosmetic dentist
Treehouse fun it is
To go to some of these third-party lab
And that you walk out of there with
Yeah bags
Full of free cosmetic
You're walking
Through of cosmetic store with a bag that you just got from the third party lab
That's probably
Got a $2,000 street value
And they were all free and thinking
Wow
You know what if I can bring every woman into the
Into the luxury cosmetics
Factory with me and we can ride it together how fun would that be
What are Thrills of being a kid in the candy store
And so that was the idea behind PewDiePie how do I
How do I give women the same feeling
That I have to get the
Furnace parts
Of being able to work in cosmetics is Wendy's
Free boxes of stuff
From the lab show up
MPD pies a little bit different you buy stuff at the factory cost but
Is practically
Compared to what you pay for it at retail
What what's interesting is that you don't seem to be
Sentimentally attached to your company's
Is you
You launch them
Create them
Tournament
Incredibly successful companies
And you sold at least two of them and
And you may
Sell others
Do you
Is there a certain point where you just say I don't know
I just want to move on and in and start something new like is it
Is it almost like
When a business becomes too big or
Or are you just bored
You want to
Start something new
You know I thought about this one a lot
I did get asked
DIY
Why do you keep doing this
And I'm and I think about the
Thrill that is beauty pie right now
Really like I'm rubbing sticks together
And I think it's
What really drives me and what I really love
Have you ever heard the expression
Your first marriage is for love the second one's for money and the third one's for companionship
I think some famous divorce
Say probably
That that one
The companionship that
That
I get out of having a business where I can really
Interface with women and I'm making them happy
Answer Man of course we have with 4% man at the moment but
Do you want to make people feel that happy and
And have them communicate that to me is what
Give me the
The biggest Buzz
I mean it's it's
What do you think
That
That your your brain works that way that
That you just
R generating all these
Cytosol
Time and ideas that
That don't
Flowed up in
In the space that ideas
You actually
Stop sit down
Start to really
They almost seem to obsess you
DC Legends
/ take everything
In your world like
Why do you think
That happened
How did I end up like this
It was sort of yeah
I
You know I have
But a lot about that cuz you have to psychoanalyze yourself and I
I also tell want to be on top
Respite
I would tell them that
One of the tools that they should have is understanding of how the human brain works
That's right because if you can understand how your brain is fooling you
When you might be reacting
To something rather than making a sound
Decision or when you might be feeling insecure when you really shouldn't be a when you're jumping to a judgment
He doesn't have enough information
Back it up
Now when you try to vanco psychoanalyze yourself I would say well I must be extremely
Competitive because I will come up with these ideas and thank
I can't do that and then I'll think
I have to do that and then
But if I don't do that fast somebody else is going to do it
And I don't know why I care
I need why do I care if somebody else goes and does it
There must be some competitive aspect to it and so I much
More comfortable
Where I feel like I'm building something
It's got to be genetic right cuz there's nothing else that would
Really
Explain that
How much of
Of your
Trust you think
Because of of your intelligence and hard work and how much how much do you think
Is because
It's a lock
Okay
I'd say
I'm certainly above-average
In IntelliJ
I'm not a genius
I know a lot of people who are
Much more intellectual than I am actually much moisture
Strategic
And
People always say that I'm very stiff
Teach it but I don't think of myself as such a
Strategic person Digest
Tend to think of things in very
Simple
Champs
Luck I've certainly had some
I mean
Moving to New York and having a sister who was
Really good-looking and in
Field where she could
Give people who could afford my services
FB
An introduction to me so that I can have
Clientele
And then more of those people
Would refer more of those people that's certainly lucky
However if I wasn't good at what I was doing I don't think I would happen
And if I didn't show up on time if I wasn't friendly and
In a reliable I suppose
You get a bit of luck
I don't have to make something out of it
And
I find
When I
The end
I'm sure you see this as well you see people were so talented
Buy Morita really genius at what they do
But I'm not
Ever really
Successful they're always struggling
And I always wonder
You know is it just a choice that you make where at one point you say you know what I am
I am worthy
I deserve this why not me
Because
You know why not you
And if you're willing to work that hard why shouldn't you then take the success that comes with it
And I think that's a very complex thing for many people
And somehow I've managed to
Over combat
It is amazing how many how many of these companies that use
Needed
E-end
All the things you've done
Have you ever come up with the idea that that you thought was just going to
Amazingly well that you just
Didn't pursue because it wasn't actually quite right
I have one right now but I
Not that I'm not pursuing it
Right
But I can't say what it is because we're patenting at the moment
Right now you are going to lunch something new on top of
Things that you do incredible a guy how do you turn your brain want to explode if I've had too many
Marcia Kilgore who's the founder of bliss Spas soap & Glory skincare products
Ergonomic shoes
PewDiePie makeup and also a v brand we just ran out of time to talk about it
What's a line of environmentally friendly bath products called the super duper
Mercy has built so many companies that on the last episode of the Oprah Winfrey show
Oprah named her one of her
Personal inspiration
And please do stick around because in chest
The moment we're going to hear from you about
The things your building
But first a quick message from one of our 2019 lead sponsors of how I built this
Hiscox
Understand every small business is unique
Tailors its policies that your business is very specific needs
Get a quote or purchase a policy
H i s c o x
Dot-com
Hiscox
Business
Insurance
The US has the highest incarceration rate in the world
With 2.3 million
People behind bars
This week on through line
How we got
The history of mass incarceration
In American culture
Through line from NPR
The podcast where we go back in time
The understanding
Hey thanks for sticking around
It's time now for how you built that
And updating a story today that ran
About a year ago
It starts in 2015 in Los Angeles
With a guy named Miles pepper
I went to my local coffee shop to grab an iced latte before heading off to work
And as I was leaving the shop I put a plastic straw my drink as normal habit
But that's what happened
Just the night before
Cena program about
Plastics that are polluting the ocean I had just seen the video of the sea turtle with a straw stuck up its nose
I was thinking to myself that
I already have a reusable water bottle
I already have
Reusable coffee cup
Why don't I have a reusable straw
Yeah a reusable straw.
Made out of plastic
Maybe metal
A straw that could fold and collapse
Like a temple
A way to
Guarantee that it would always be
On me would be if it was a size of a car key
So I wanted a collapsible straw that was small enough to fit in a case
The size of a car
But unfortunately I didn't know the first thing about how to make a collapsible straw
So I started talking with friends I started talking with these designers that I have been working with
This mutual friend said hey you should call Emma do you remember Emma and in fact miles did remember Emma
She was an acquaintance who also hated plastic straws she even done a tedx talk about it
Straws suck
We become accustomed to living disposable lifestyles
Based on convenience
So MN ident jumped on the phone the phone rings October 2017
And he says
Hey I've got this idea for a collapsible straw
And I just remember he first
Sounded really excited on the phone and it got me really excited
So anyway miles found in industrial designer in LA to help him develop a collapsible stainless
Steel straw and while they were working on the design I was
Working on
Creating a social media presence
I have a love of means and one of my favorite ones was filling a pack of cigarettes
With straws and at the bottom it says break the habit
After about a month-and-a-half and my miles had a prototype of a straw that folds into Force
Fits into a little plastic case that you could carry on a keychain
Annexed
Kickstarter campaign
And the pickle was
5000 straws which would have been about $70,000
But we sold about 60,000 straws and closed a month later with 1.89
$3 in the bank which sounds amazing right it's a big problem
There's companies out there that are patrolling Kickstarter and looking to see
When people throw a success
Spell campaign and as soon as they see that overnight success
Then they jump on it and they
Use the measurements that are provided on the kickstarter
To create an exact replica of that item in that
Is exactly what happened to Emma in Miles these random sharks basically hijacked their idea
Need some quick
Cheap knock-offs
And started fulfilling orders before Emma miles could even get their straws out into the world I mean it's
Talking the hardest part for her is the fact that
Most of these knock-offs are complete junk
And so
They're just ending up in the trash can
And the entire purpose of our company was to reduce waste
And so I feel weirdly responsible and you know no matter how many people tell me that it's not my fault
All like it's still feels like it is
Emma started filling Kickstarter orders in November of 2018 and she says this past year
It's been like business school on speed
I don't know it's like
Going down a river in a
Too but you just don't know what to expect and every moment is he there like
Very Serene and calm or you're maybe going to die
And I love it
That's Emma Cohen the co-founder of
Final straw
Issue date
I sold about 5 million dollars worth of collapsible metal straws
Emma is not working on their necks
Reusable products
Final Four
If you want to find out more about final straw
Podcast page how I built this.
Npr.org ofcourse
If you want to tell us your story go to
To build.
Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening
The show this week
Unsubscribe wherever you get your podcasts
Tiger there please
You give us a review
You can also write to us at HIV.
Npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
How I built this
Or at Gyros
Our ship was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music
Opposed
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Carney leave a grandson as meshkinpour in
Jeff Rogers
Intern
David job
Daraz
And you been listening to how I feel
This
NPR