Support for this in
NPR Podcast
In the following message
Did come from VSP individual Vision play
Entrepreneurs innovators and creators
Stop overpaying for eye exam
Sam's and Quality Glass
You can buy vision coverage on your own
Learn more at need VSP coverage.
Just before we start the show a bit of news
Last year
After a year of doing live shows
We decided we more than
Deeper
Experience with you with our community
So we decided to Launch
Full day how I built this Summit
It was so amazing and fun that we're doing it again this year
This time we're doing it over
Today's
It's happening
October 22nd
The 23rd in San Francisco
With support from American
Express
And this year we are doubling down on our main stage speakers
Able to hear from and
Probably even meet some of the greatest living Founders and entrepreneurs in the world
Including Sara Blakely Spanx
Stewart Butterfield
Slack Kevin Systrom and Mike Krieger of Instagram Tariq
Breed of Edible Arrangements
David neeleman of JetBlue Troy Carter who managed lady
Lady Gaga
Marcia Kilgore of bliss Jen Rubio of away and many others including special surprises
And on top of that
Will have dozens
Website session
Experts
Special guests of everything from the nuts and bolts of starting and scaling your business
Two ways
Thinking of more Innovative and creative way
The food is great the coffee is great the party is super fun
How does the Sun is one of the best investments
You can make in your own professional and personal development
You will meet people who will become lifelong friends and contacts so
Please join us in San Francisco October 22nd to 23rd
At yerba buena Center for the Arts
To find out more tickets including early bird pricing available for
Just a few more weeks
Go to Summit. Npr.org
But I got that $60,000
Loan within 6 months I went back and asked them for 500
And they said there's five hundred thousand bucks no they said no
Well they didn't say no they said no not without equity and we were like
We've got nothing
Running PR it's how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Dealer stories behind the movements they built
Horizon house Stacey Madison turn Dale
Pita bread into a new snack
Stacy's Pita Chips
The world's biggest food company
Order of a
Billion dollar
So there are sub startup stories
Place where most of us are
Probably thinking
I couldn't do that
Squarespace
If you heard that episode
You remember that Anthony casalena was and
Use a gifted computer program
He had a highly specialized skill
Literally designed and then fashioned
Shoes from leather
And sold them
But then there are the stories were most of us
Chile imagine doing that thing ourselves
Like Brian scudamore
Bought an old tracking Africa Holloway people
Trash
That's how we started 1-800 got junk
Lisa Price
Tinkered with homemade lotions in our kitchen
She went on to sell her brand Carol's Daughter
L'Oreal
Well today story is of the second variety
Stories
Anyone can relate to
Because it is such a simple
Elegant
Idea
Take pita bread
I didn't
Bacon parmesan orzo
Seasoning on it
And Wallah
You got Stacy's Pita Chips
Even though the snack today
Today is a 6
Six billion dollar juggernaut
BC medicine did not have a grand master plan 2
Disrupt snack foods in the late 1990s
At that time
Cheater boyfriend rule literally selling pita wrap sandwiches from a sandwich cart
Downtown Boston
The pita chips were an afterthought
A way to use up those extra
Peter's at the end of the day
Pita chips were never supposed to make Stacy rich
Eventually
Frito-Lay would come knocking with a fist
Full of dollars
Long before that long before Stacy even sold her first sandwich
She was on an entirely different path
Grew up in the suburbs near Boston
After college
Stacy went out to California to get a master
In social work
She thought about becoming us
Psychologist
Your dad
He wasn't so enthusiastic about
He thought I should always
Become a social worker
Rather than go on
How to get my pH
Sambia psychologist
He was like oh that's no profession for a woman
That's
One thing that he said was smile and look pretty and you will find a
You know I don't want to make him sound like a
Jerk
Caring loving man that put his family
First
But he was also a product of the fifth
Sure
So once you get your master's degree
You actually
Move to Washington DC to
To do what
Social work
Yes
I worked
In a group home for
Homeless
Pregnant drug-addicted
Women
And
I have to tell you I mean I loved the job it was very
Rewarding
But at the time I think I made
$22,000 a year
And
It was really
Paycheck-to-paycheck and very hard to survive on
That kind of
An income
So I decided to go and get license
And
Be able to private
Which eventually I did go on to do
But I found it very isolating
Now I've got a
Go and I
Unlock the door and
And I do
Marriage counseling in
Send my
Evening is overripe
Being five or six patients and
I closed the door behind me and I go home and
I put a lot of effort into getting those degrees and licenses and
Realize that It ultimately it probably just was not
For me
I guess roughly 30 years old at this time at and by the way you were engaged
22 Gannon Rec right
No
That ended
Images
Mutual
I think ultimately it was just
Not the right thing I think wechat
Agreed
We had had the
Place picked out that we were going to get married
And it was kind of a bizarre story but
I went and I had a massage
I know sounds like I'm going off on a tangent here but it'll come back I had a massage
And the woman told me
To take off all my jewelry and Bubba Bubba Bubba they took it off I put it in the dish
Got my massage and I got up and I went to get dressed and I was like oh my God all my jewelry is
Is gone
Including my ring
My engagement ring and I was just
You know it was from his family it was like I was just so upset
And
The girl was gone she had
Like never to return I think she took off to Florida or somewhere she never came back to work she just kind of took off
All my stuff but
With Rick and I it was kind of like the ring wasn't replaced immediately even and I don't
Don't care about the ring
Even if it's just a cigar brand or something like that but it kind of took so long replacing the ring
That it's for both of us to look at should we really be doing this maybe this was a sign or
Or something and ultimately yeah we just decided
Maybe we shouldn't get married
So you so you guys split up
Xiamen time
There was this guy Mark Andres who you had met through your brother a few years before he was a friend
Did you guys start dating or would you just kind of
So he was
Still a friend and I talk to him all the
The time about
My disengagement and all of that
He was super supportive and eventually
Our friendship led to dating
And
He was
Getting his PhD so he was doing an internship in Hawaii
And
Fayetteville lunch come out to Hawaii
And what did you do in Hawaii
So
Hawaii was an amazing experience
We lived in
Just this tiny box
And there was no kitchen or anything and they've been there was no bedroom it was basically a cot
And we bought an electric Wok
And we used to
Cook
In the walkways wash it in the bathtub and
Eventually we found a roommate and she had a nicer apartment and we worked out a deal where
We would
Take her second
Bedroom and
In exchange
For a lower rent we would cook for her
End
Well I was out there I worked at a restaurant
And I got a job at it as an assistant manager and the restaurant was going to open up a surf
Theme
I need another location of surf team
Restaurant and
They said you want to be part of that opening and I said yeah that's great
Which
Thinking back I'm like wow that was
Great experience I got the kind of experience
Learning Center
Start a business
Yeah
We
Had this big opening with
Are all the Surfers the local Surfers in Hawaii and
Even Retired Surfers they came in the owners of the restaurant were like if we could pull this off you know you guys are going to
And get a big bonus and Bubba
And we did I mean we were money was coming in left and right
The point that we have to stop it and beer boxes and
Bring the cash down to the two
The basement
Because they couldn't fit it all in the register
It was just crazy so
Successful opening of the restaurant
Couple weeks later I sat down with my
General manager and said
How about
The bonuses they were talking about you know my name
Coming in
And he's like let me meet with the owners and
Get back to you
Wait another couple of weeks
Sat down with them again
And he said well I spoke to the owners
And they've decided that we need to let you go
And
Wow I was
I never
Lost a job
In my life
And then I remember speaking to my aunt who was in the restaurant business
Since you saying are you kidding me don't be so naive they always hire people to get restaurants open and then they let him go
Ultimately I circled back and said well if I can work this hard
For someone else
Then why can't I do it for
Myself
End
It's a kind of funny because
At that point
Mark was still in his internship and
We were in these high-rise buildings in
Downtown Honolulu and
We were cooking meals
Our roommate anyway
We figured why not just put a sign in the bottom of the building
When people got home they could
It was at the time of fax machine
They could fax over and over
And we would just have their dinner ready
What you would
Yuan Mark
Is Mike was a trained psychologist writing that that's what his work was
You guys were also just like pretty good
Home cook
Yeah we loved cooking I mean
Mark was a total Foodie in
We marketed
To our building in the surrounding buildings
That if
Anybody else wanted us to cook them dinner that
We would do that to me call deconda cuisine
And what are you offering like was it just like in tonight's dinner is or you could order from a menu
It's just more of a you know you had a choice between
Two or three items
Your we had seared tuna with
Pineapple salsa
Things like that
Needless
To say we're cooking in our apartment
Got very quickly shut down
Like some guy you don't call or knock on the door I was like
You can't do this
Cathay pacific Health Department
It's like you don't have a license
That didn't last long. That was like yeah yeah
Are not doing this if you want to do this you have to get into a commercial kitchen and you have to write
Etcetera etcetera
So that dream that dream died
And how how long by the way did it last
Before you were shut down
A couple months 3 or 4 months
Man that clearly like that experience kind of
Set into motion this idea that it maybe we could
Duke some kind of business
Yes
Definitely
And it kind of
Pick me back up onto my feet after
Losing that other job
End
Mark even though he's
Getting his Doctorate at this point
He always wanted to be a chef
He came from a family of doctors and it was kind of just that's what you're going to be but it
It also meant that he
Was
Setting aside his dream of becoming
So
It was a really
Crazy decision but we decided when we got back
To Massachusetts
We would try something
In the food business
Wow it's okay Mark
Has a PHD in Clinical Psychology
You are a social worker by training
You always knew that you were going to go back to boss
Both of you guys
Or I guess
From
Yeah New England
And
He was going to become a psychologist but I guess your plan was hey before you do that let's just Contest out
This food business idea for short
Going into this and then you got a call so keep in mind
The reality of the fact that
He's got $100,000 in student loans
I don't have a penny to my name
Remove back to Boston 1996
What did you guys decide to do
So
We decided to buy a food cart
Cuz we couldn't afford
Anything else
I think it was
$5,000
And
I worked with my sister who she owned a catering company in downtown Boston
She was a huge help and
Yeah I laid out the menu and and she would look at the menu and tell me you know
You have too many items on here are you have too big of an inventory you have to
Streamline this to have it like she kind of
Always
Gave us that
Reality check on on what when that business
Sense
And at the same time
As because now we learned you have to be in
Facility
All of our menu we prep
And made out of
Her
Catering
Place in Boston
So what kind of food were you
Make it I mean this is like I'm acting like a hot dog push cart with like
You know a water bin that's
Hot and warm and like
Another band that keep buns
Like steaming hot was that with a food cart look like oh my God
The food cart yes was a
A cart with
That was a hot dog cart
And we used to go out at night
After the bars close
And we did the sausage scene
Cooking up and we were just trying to get money
Any way that we could
So that we could revamp
The cart
And once we collected enough money
Then we put the cart in
To a shop and
You know I designed it you know made it pretty Frontenac
Beautiful green awning
And we hallowed the whole thing out and made it almost into a deli counter
And we served healthy sandwiches rolled in pita bread off of
The food cart
And then we made everything to order
So these were like I mean
Rap
Kind of became a big saying in the
2000's the late 90s
And remember this like pita pita bread sandwiches started said just like pop up all over the place
Yeah but just to clarify that it was basically a
Chicken Caesar
Roles in a piece of pita bread
They were very few options
But we made
Worm yet we had goat cheese
We had
Turkey and havarti and we had
More
Upscale
Choices
So we prepared we sliced all the meat we put everything in a giant cooler
And then we went to downtown Boston
We were literally roll the cart up the
The street
And put it on the corner of Chauncey and Summer Street
And
We getting ice delivery to the corner
And we throw the ice in the bottom and then we put out all of
The ingredients
And then we roll it up in the pita bread and then we had this big white
Piece of paper
And we've all the sandwich in the white piece of paper and we twist the bottom so people were walking around with almonds
Like they had this big white club and and so it was really good cuz they've walked away and other people that they knew that looks good what you get
And what was the name of the
Did you have a name for the pushcart
Daisy's Delights
Stacy's Delights that it apostrophe l i t e f e l i t e s
What did Elie
Flight status
90s I love that
How did the dude was it a hit did you guys get custom like lots of customers right away
Yes it was a hit
But we were not the only food cart down there you have to remember that you know up
Don't go 50 yards away is the pretzel cart and then there's the burrito guy in the
You know so
Was that a time when in the food cart
World I mean now food card is more HIPAA
Trendy and there's a food truck inviting it's more of a food
Truck but at the time of food cart had the connotation of dirtying
Stop saying yeah but the way that the cart was designed and that it was presented and that it looked and we had fresh tomatoes
Mountain of them out front and it was
It broke the
Traditional mold of what is a food card
Yeah yeah everyday we ordered fresh bread
Where would you get the bread from
Just a local bakery
End
It was always over order the bread because
You can run out of alfalfa sprouts you can run out at 2
Tomatoes
And it's not going to be a big deal but in this business if you run out of bread
Your clothes
Yeah so I guess you were just going to you you've all this extra bread and you thinking
What do we do with this extra bread
And we didn't want to use it the second day because it's not as
Viable to roll the pita sandwiches so when we got back to the kitchen we would cut them up
And bake them into different flavor chips
And the idea was that you would
You would do what with a pita chips you would give them away you would sell them like what initially what we going to do with them
So initially it was just a way
Retain our customer base
And to keep people happy as they were waiting in line cuz it was a long wait you had every pita sandwich made to order
Yes and people would
Yeah we hired a college student
She was a cashier but in between should go up and down with a basket of pita chips and just give them for free
People standing in line while they waited and pee
Loved it because it was kind of like a happy hour
And
Your we gave them away for free but people started saying that they did want to buy them
So initially we would just put some in a little baggie with a gold ribbon and and keep a basket of them out on the food
As well and you could buy it for like
Fifty cents are in a dollar
Tara buck
And just just out of curiosity like
Did you guys experiment with a baking gazyva
Pita bread contain like
Burn pretty quickly
Write like
I have to assume that you had to
Experiment would like the right temperature and
The right flavors and stuff like that
That came
Later
Initially we just bake the cinnamon sugar in the parmesan garlic
Everybody thinks Simply Naked with our first flavor
It wasn't
It was
B
Parmesan and
The cinnamon sugar
We were baking them in a four rack oven
I mean literally for maybe eight
Tres res
Is a tract of enso
We could
Spread out the pita chips on a tray we could bake eight of them at a time
You know you
Really we were making toast
Yeah you were making thin slices of toast
Really good toast
And it wasn't until later as the company started
Growing
That
There was a huge jump
Between
I'm going to make toast in my oven
And I'm going to
Sleeping in mind I mean Mark suffering is loans and his lungs
Yeah he's not at this point he's like
Full on
In the food business and you are too he's not using his PhD in Clinical Psychology
Clinical social worker he's got his PhD in Psychology
And we're on a street corner selling sandwich
And so at that point
Yeah we are
All In
We are going to do something
We could not
Put our tail between our legs and go
Running home
When we come back
Has Stacey and Mark make a full pivot to pita chips
And shake off the warnings of an industry expert
Who says they will never grow their business
Stay with us
Gyros and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First
Wix.com
How I built this tells inspiring stories about the founders and how their businesses found
Success
With wix
You can create a professional website for your own business
Choose a template design for your industry
Customize it to match your brand
With Ascend by wix
You can connect with your site visitors capture leads and manager
Customer relations from one place
Get started by going to wix.com Hib t
10% off
Support also comes from Gemini
Presenting this message
Gemini
Is the regulated licensed exchange that makes it easy to add Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies to your lungs
Long term investing strategy
You can buy crypto safely and securely
Leon Gemini's mobile app or website
Knowing Investments are protected
Hey with oversight and state-of-the-art cybersecurity
Launch your crypto portfolio today and open a free account
At gemini.com built
Gemini
The regulated place to buy sell and store cryptocurrency
Mitch McConnell
Become a champion for conservatives
But back in the day he wants got support from groups like
Market down as one of the worst things I've done in my life
So you thought about it
30 years
Mitch McConnell
New series from embedded
Right now
Oh and really quickly before we get back to the show if you love how I built this
You'll probably love another podcast I just launched
It's called wisdom from the top
It's available on a new podcast platform called luminary
It's a show about the
Latest leaders in the world in the how they learn to become leaders
You can find wisdom from the top in addition to
Several other
Great new shows
Go to luminary. Lynx guy
Grey free
3-month trousers
Description
Hey welcome back to how I built
Best from NPR
And Stacy and Mark have
Side hustle out of a side Hustle
Selling pita chips from the little sandwich card they started in Boston
The chips are doing so well that they decide to make more of them
But they're using an oven that can only make a tracks of them
At a time
But then
They find a way
Bastilla
We met a very nice woman when we were doing the food cart Who Sold pretzels
It was Boston pretzel Bakery
And
She said oh I have a 40 rack oven
Why don't you come try to make them over there
So we went over to Boston pretzel
And we mixed up are the pita chips and we were able to make a rack of 40 of them at a time
I'm instead of instead of eight trays we can make 40 trays
She had backup rack
Sowell 40 we're in the oven we could load up another 40 trays
40 came out in 40 went in and
We're like okay well this is this kind of makes
More sense
What I'm trying to say is look at what
Point running this car
Did yuan Mark say
Actually
The business we really should focus on is the pita chips
And not the pita sandwiches
So I think
The coming about of that whole thing was the struggle of getting in
Inside location
And
Come winter it's really rough
Being out there in the cold
Yeah and we
Started working with a realtor and the realtor qunar lasted us and said
If you want a tiny little indoor
Location near where you are X want to keep our following of people
You and your food cart can stand online behind
Oban pan Dunkin Donuts
At the time Starbucks was coming into the world you know everybody wants his little spaces
We realize we had to make a
And we decided to go for the
The pita chips
Because
In the winter I was working on the pita chips and and the bag and
The design and the lights
I'm saying and all that I needed to do in order to get that off the ground
So with the pita chips
We could get bigger faster
Yeah and I took a bag and we had put them in almost like a coffee bag
Like one little window
Oh yeah plus
LaPlace
Check bag inside of the paper bag
A lot of Labor went into it but you know what
I took the bag and I
I walked into bread and circus and downtown Boston and I said
Hi I'm Stacy
These are my chips and I'd love for you to give him a try you just walked into a
Bread & circus
Stop at Whole Foods and you asked to ask for the manager
Yeah okay and what did the manager say
He's a good
Yeah. Forget them and
Now we have one store
There was like 6 or 8 of these bread and circus
Stores and he showed them to corporate there was nothing in them they were all natural
It was the time of the beginning of the natural food Revolution and that's just what we were
Innately doing
And obviously you guys
Personal you chose the name Stacy
Pita chips just cuz that's what it was called Stacy's Delight when you are food car
We chose it because we thought that
Female name on
Snack food brand with
Sell more than a male name
Yeah the woman in the kitchen kind of things I hate to say it
That's really
That was the thought behind it was that it sounded better than Denmark
Let's just pause for a moment and talk about
Money because
Even though you are getting some stores
Willing to pay
Pick up the chips and
To sell them
I can't imagine your business could
Operated
Tyler Lyon like
The sale of pita chips how did you have
Money tok to run this thing
Yeah I mean we had
A lot of
That
Between the two of us
We ran up our credit cards
We applied
For it so I was I started working with the neighborhood Development Center and they help me write a busy
Display on
There was a really networked with everybody I
I can possibly
Draw information
Nation from the neighborhood
Send her there was
I think
Jewish vocational services
Was in downtown Boston and there was this one girl that used to eat at the cart and she
She said to me
How do you know if you have enough bread
Add
She asked for these weird
Questions
And then one day I said why you asking me these weird questions
She said why teach a business plan boot camp
And
I use your cart is an example all the time
Wow
I said really I might
Can I take that class
She's like yeah you want to take you come on over
And I went and I took an 8-week business
Plan boot camp
So between all of these agencies that I kind of worked with cuz remember I didn't have a business
The grey I didn't know
I didn't know what a business plan was
Yeah so after that 8 weeks
I realized that I didn't just need $25,000 for the packaging machine but I also needed
$20,000 to buy bags
Yeah the run on the machine
And then I needed $20,000 for this thing that people kept calling working capital
So that was all new to me
So I swear I thought I only needed 25
$1,000 with 60
I needed 60 yeah right
How did you get $60,000
So the neighborhood Development Center in Jamaica Plain help me
Spruce up my business plan a little bit and
Put me in touch with a bank that they used
That
Worked with the SBA
So we had to put down
20% of the 60,000
And that's where our family
Kicked in
You need to prep 12 thousand bucks
Collateral base
Oh yeah
And that was a $60,000 loan from a small business administration back
Bank in Boston
She got $60,000
Which gave you how much
Runway how long could you
Could you
Function of $60,000 cuz you see you're talking about
Need to buy a machine to seal the bags
To buy the bags and then you're not left of the whole lot
$60,000
It was not going to go very far because yes we bought the machine we bought the bags
But the one thing that we did have
We had customer
Both the consumer
And the retailers that loved our chaps
And kept reordering
And when I got that sack
$60,000 loan
Within six months
I went back and asked them for 500
Wow
And they and they said
Here you're sure here's 500000
No
No they said no
Well they didn't say no they said no
Not without equi
And we were like equity
Equity in what we've got nothing
Yeah at this point
So they said no to 500
Over a couple of months
We were able to scale it back and they did say yes to 350
Wow
So you got a
$350,000 loan
From the bank
Yeah but how did you get the word out
About the pita chips I get it that you were
Your cat pounding the pavement and you were
Asking for managers
At at at local
You know
Markets in asking
Talk with them
How did people find out about the chips
Entirely word-of-mouth amenaces pre-internet priest social media pre and he didn't have a dollars
We would go everywhere we could
Two sample
So we would go into the store and we would set up a table and we would just give away chips for free just like
We did on the cart and people would try them and they would buy them and that
That's how we built our customer base
We had three words
Simple simple simple
Did you at this point have a vision
Or how big this could be were you and Mark saying
Cuz I have to assume you were still doing a lot of the legwork you were still maybe even baking
The chips and maybe hiring people to help you but
Did you think this is going to be huge just going to be a national brand or was it was that your ambition at this point or not quite
Know our goal was to be
Original brand more like
Cape Cod potato chips and we were
We were going to keep things manageable and in the Northeast
But what happened was with the growth of the natural food into
History
There were these
Pockets like
Colorado
And
Atlanta
In California and then we don't belittle
Pocket square
The Natural Food business was really
Booming
And the whole
Creation of Whole Foods and and then buying up all of these smaller stores we were in all those smaller
Stores
So we were in the bread and circus and Wild Harvest and then they all became
Whole Foods witch
Grew tremendously so are
Initial
Plan to be a
Small Regional
Brand
We had to rethink that and I think that's
One of the things that Mark and I were really good at was
Not being
So locked in
A straight
Half
That
We were able to see when other Opera
Opportunities came along
So for example the pita chips over
Food cart or
You know rather than selling a small Gourmet
Food stores
We're going to go into the natural
Food you know we're like what we could sell to these
10 stores or this one chain has a hundred
But that the business was still you and Mark right it was you were the only permanent employees at the
The point
So
It was Mark and I for the first two years and then my brother who at this point
Had his
PhD also
And we said
Into him
You want to sell some chips
You know and hahaha we were all joking around about it and then
He came back like couple weeks later and said
You know what
If I don't try this
Now
He's married they don't have kids
If I don't try this now when am I going to try it again he's like
Sure
Does his wife she was an accountant she had a steady income
So
He said you can just pay me minimum wage and then
We'll give it a try and after the first of the year
You can just kind of start
Paying me back as we start
Generating a little bit of money
And that's what really really important
Is that in the beginning we
Surrounded ourselves with
Two psychologists
Can a social worker
Running a pita chip business right like how implausible
Is that like what like nobody would say I want to start my business I need to psychologist and a social worker
But somehow like
You're you guys have brought the skill sets
To this
To this day
I was street smart and those guys were both street smart and book smart
And said we all work together on trying to figure out how we're going to do this
And I'll tell you that one point
We had
Paid $1,500
And we flew a consultant up from Frito
That he was a retired
Frito
Guy
And
Heat Washington
How we were running things
And he was just like
These are very good and they taste good
But
This cannot be
This is a home-baked
Type
Product
And it's fine but you won't be able to scale this big
Wait why did he say that was
Would you literally like hand cutting the pita
Pita bread
Mark's right bicep
Was like
Three times the size of his left
Because he was literally using a knife
So when
This guy walked in and he saw you know
Marcotte hand cutting bread and
We're handbagging everything and
Each
Batch took a certain amount of time and then we have to like
Scrape off the trays and clean everything in
He was just like
Yeah you'll never be able to
Bring this
Product to
Market on any kind of scale
So for us that was
A really hard blow
I bet but
We
Also still found it
Hard
To believe
Like
If we can take 40 racks
40 trays of pita chips
And we can make that
Why can't we just
Line up a whole bunch of these ovens
And
Be able to make
So many rats at a time
And then with that led to was us realizing
We needed a conveyorized
Oven you needed a conveyor belt oven where you could do
Throw the pizza on there and it would just go to the conveyor belt and then
Come out the end in j
52a just a big barrel the pita chips are made
Yeah and the endgame we ended up having
To purchase a
Custom built
Oven
Is the size of a 52-foot like an 18-wheeler truck wow
But you are still at me nor Mark was still hand slicing the pita into the right shape
You can't scale that like one or two or ten people can't do that
So how did you solve
That problem
You're right on target here we broke it down into each stage of making a pita
And
That
Piece of it what we did was we would go and we would tour other Factory
So we went down to Cape Cod potato chips and we went on that tour that everybody in Cape Cod goes on that tour
When is Taurus
We went as far as we look through that window and we saw
They were
Cutting potatoes
With this machine and we asked him well
How does that machine
Cut the potatoes
And
They gave us the name of the machine and then we went out and we contacted
That company
NSAID
This is what we're trying to do and we had this guy who worked for us
Who
Continue her with anything
And so what we ended up buying was a machine that used to cut carrots
Campbell Soup
So you know how they cut those
Tiny little
Square shirt
Well
What he did
Is he took those blades
And space them further apart
And when he first
Face these blades and all of us are kind of gathered around the opposite end of the machine holding up bucket where the
These are tempted chips are going to come out until he feeds the bread into the machine he starts
Tossing you know a piece of bread a piece of bread
And we're standing out at the other
And we're like
Holy
BHS it's a chip but you know
The very last day that marks
Spread
You must eventually got married right to your business partners and then you got
Mary cuz you were together right
Yes we have been together for a long time
And eventually we just
Got married
I in in 97
And
Always good
All right 1999
You get your
Production method down get the machines you need
The revenues growing
I have to imagine that there are big chip companies looking at you guys even though you're this
Tiny little new england-based pita chip company and thinking
Pita chips that's the new craze let's make pita chips and crushed
These guys
Not really because so at this point in time in the company as we just started to grow
It was also during the time of the
No carb face
It was a close
No carb low carb diet
Oh yeah
And we were like here we are
Once again we're making toast
And
We thought oh my God
That's going to put us out of business like all these silent all these things along the way you think I'm I got this
Put us out of business oh my God that's going to put us out of business but
Ultimately people love
Chips
It was something people
Ate all the time and it was becoming a staple in
Their cabinet
It wasn't just a one-time purchase
Alright so you guys are
Can operating under the radar but growing
Steadily
Give me the first year you actually turned a profit like a significant profit was it
Was it in 1999 or in 2000
People say it takes three years I would say it take
So it took some time
Yeah but I guess you guys hit a million dollars and Revenue
Iran 2001
Which sounds super impressive did that mean that you guys were
All making lots of money
No
We really paid our self very little and if anything really weren't making anything cuz everything went back into
Do you know if we needed another oven well you know you don't buy this you don't die that you don't do this because
You need another oven
Yeah
Do you guys
You starting to become
Horse stable in the production process
Five years after the two of you get married
Umic divorce
You decide
To get a divorce that year
Yeah
But then you stay honest is 50
T50 business partners at this is normally how the story unfolding normally
This is a very messy and traumatic and difficult
Doesn't sound like
Yeah
Like I'm not going to say we didn't argue
I mean certainly we argue
Over a lot of things mean there's a lot of tension
And
The employees had to put up with us like
Baba baba baba
Leave the room and
And then eventually everybody would come back to their test command
And that's okay
But
We had a common
Gall
And
I would have to say I think
He probably agree
That during the time that we were married for the most part it was a
Successful marriage but we also had a successful divorce
It was clean and it was clear
And
We shared the company like it was our child
Everything that we did was in the best interest of the company
So we went to court
Gather
And we went before the judge and we said we want to get a divorce and
We're splitting this 50/50 and we really had no assets
Yeah everything we had
Was the company and we agreed we built this together
And we were splitting the
And we were both going to stay on and the judge was like wow this was
It is
I think it's surprising at least for me I think
Play for a lot of people
Listening
Because
It seems to me that it takes eight
Remarkably like
Clear headed people
To come to this agreement to say
Hey you know like we're not going to be romantic
Partners anymore but
We're really good business partner
And we got the script thing going
And let's keep it going that when I when I hear that I'm thinking of
Of course you would say that that makes total sense
Rightmost
People don't say
So
The greatest gift
That Mark
Gave me
During this period
Was his honesty
Cuz it
One point he said
I don't know
When or if
I want to have children
And I was in my mid-30s already
So
He said that to me and it was really in meaning it was that night that
I left
I went to the factory I had
You know I brought my dog to the fact
Play all the time
So I really I went to the fact when I slept in the dog bed that night
But
You know now that I look back on it
Spring Valley
Could you imagine if we would have stayed together and we might have ended up having a kid that he wasn't
Anti having kids
Could have been that road that's so many people go down and it ends up being a mess
Yeah but I did decide to start a family and he was
Very supportive of that
I think this is like 2 years
Later a2003 you have birthday to your twins
Yep I was 39 years old I gave birth to my twins
I mean I went to Boston IVF
And
That's how I had the kids and I and I
Have always spoken openly
About that
That I was financially and emotionally ready to start a family and I do
I just need a little help.
So
At this point when your girls
In mm
With Stacy's Pita Chips with with a trajectory
Like was it clear that it was going to be
A much bigger brand or or does it still feel like
It was a you know
More successful Regional
So at this point
The company was growing like crazy
It was successful enough that we could each be taking
A decent salary
Pull that much out of the business but
You know it was enough so that we could each
You know by a car and
Yeah we can teach by our own place
Or whatever so it was successful enough to do that but we
Really
We decided how much we going to pay each other
And
Then everything else just
What companies coming to eat to you guys at this point saying hey we want Stacy's Pita Chips in our
In our store
Yeah
So I think it was
When we
Got into the
Club accounts
Like Costco and Sam's Club and all of those so we started manufacturing for them
And then we got into Trader Joe's and we just
And it was a perfect demographic
For us
And
Trader Joe's was an amazing
Company to do business
They paid
On time or early
And because of that
We were able to not take on
Equity
Wow and
At that point you everything just went back into the business
But we were just about to give up give up a piece of the company
We never ended up actually doing that because we got Trader Joe's and they were ordering by the truckload
And when we were selling them
Truck is really
Amazing
When
Trucks are lined up
We're selling a you know what
$2 item
We're not selling computers
You're when we're when we get to the point that we're doing you know 30 40 50 million dollars
Those are
$2 sales are $1 sales
That looks like just truckloads
And
At this point we were we had
Move to the Sealy Mattress fact
Drake where we bought the building and
It was
Two or three hundred thousand square feet something like that was basically four acres inside
And we converted
The Sealy mattress factory
Into a giant
Pita chip
Factory I think it's like
Buy 2005-2006
You're selling like
More than 50 million dollars
With a piece chips a year which is e v I think
65 thank you
Pepsi announces that they were acquiring
Stacy's
How did that happen today approached you like a year before do they say hey we're really interested in
Buying a company is is that what happened or are you looking to sell it
A couple months before we saw them at a trade show and and they were like others look up product and
In order for them to even look at you you have to be at least 50 million in sales and Bubba
And we were nowhere near there at the time and
And that was the only contact we ever had with
Then
You know a year later
At the trade show again
There was this one month window where we got
Phone calls
From
Of
The biggest
Food companies in the world
And
We were alike
We better start looking at this
And this at this time I had
Two little kids
Hey there two years old
Single mom
So we we really
Said you know what we should
We should wear we never considered selling
Yeah we should maybe
Think about that
Sexy you decide
In middle of working on a deal
But actually this ship
Fire in the
Yeah there was a big big
Fire and
We had already signed the SBA was the stock purchase agreement we already signed that
But it hadn't closed we agreed on a price and all of this
And then we had a fire there was 9 million dollars in Damages and 25% of the factory was burnt down
And that's a really hard phone call when they call you you don't have to kind of say
And basically the way that it ended up
Working out as you know we still ultimately
Had a brand
That was worse
Value
End
We were like
We will get it back up and running
And
The way we did it was we built the wall
Across half of the plant
So we were still able to manufacture on the side that wasn't burnt down
And then the other side we called in
Every
Person over the last decade that had helped us with anything and then
People were working electrician they brought in like with the one guy
Turned into 6 guys
Overnight Round the Clock
Who's supposed to close in December
And
Bye
January
12th
They inspected the plant and they said
Don't believe it
They're back up and running place looks great
Could you go
Sending the check
Exactly send them to check
Which it would have been nice to see a check
But nowadays it's a trance
So we all sat in front of the computer just looking
Waiting for the number to change
It is a bear
Is it there is it there is it
I meant it was like you know that the money transferred in and
And we did
Obviously
Close the deal
I've asked you know other entrepreneurs
About
The sale of their business and their different answers I asked co-founders of Reddit
Why they agreed to sell their company of the time they did in the answer was
Cuz it was more money than I've ever
Had my life I didn't grow up with a lot of money and it was
Life-changing money which I think is a fair answer
I have to assume that
Was it
Factories not be factor in your decision
It was life-changing money
But
It had also become
You know where we love this business
And we loved running it
At a point
The tables turn
And the business starts to run you
So I think
It was
The perfect
Timing
Yeah I was working crazy hours I was lucky if I got home on time before my kids went to
To sleep
So for me it was the right time for Mark I think it was the right time he was burnt out
That means
Sad
After it's sold
There is this major
Like
This was my
Whole life
Best Miami kids and
What am I going to do now
So what
What did you do in
How long
Do you stay with Stacy's after
Soda Pepsi
One very disaster
First year
It was so hard I was
Contracted
To stay but I really only had to work 20 days a year
But I didn't know what else to do so I would really go in every day
And I think I was more in the way
And I thought that I was going to be
Like a buffer
Between the no the new leadership team and the employees
End
I think I probably just
Created
More confusion
So it was eight months of
Yeah
I can emit like you don't sound
Like a person who is different from the person who you were in
High school or college of course we all change
Equivalent of all that like
You you sound like a very down-to-earth person
But I'm all of a sudden you were you had
Des welfare
I have to assume you weren't
You had no experience with
How did it change
The way you live your life or anything else
I think it
Even
Today
Sometimes when I go
Do something
You think twice how can I do that
How can I buy that
Coconut you know and
Initially
I went out
And I bought
A castle
Right
Was like I'm going to buy a big house
Beautiful neighborhood and get us
Sports car and do all that
But
Then I realized
My kids
Ride their bike and they go on the bus and and there's only
5 kids on the bus cuz everybody else is going to private school and
Yeah and I was like
We're done
Amethyst House
Put the house on the market
And I bought a
Smaller house in a
Neighborhood where
Our neighbors are
Right next
Store
And you could
You know borrow a can opener
And the kids can ride their bike and
Yeah that's how
I wanted to raise
My family
Just curious mean
You Are Young You Are
In your early 40s
Having accomplished
This incredible
Zayn Malik growing this business and
The whole rest of your life ahead of you
I mean
Huge part of that uncredible exciting like I know
Black people
Listening would say I would love to have that
But at the same time you had to figure out
I guess
What you were going to do with the rest of your life
Right people are people look at you like
You can do anything but at the same time you look at yourself and your like will now what am I going to do with my life
Of course I'm on my mom and I'm parenting and that's person
Foremost
What else am I
Yeah
And it's a very hard position 3 hard place to be
And the past for 5 years
I've had
Some
Big
Medical
Challenges
I had breast cancer I had an autoimmune disease I had a full knee replacement
Knocked down for
Why were years
And
When you're in that position you really feel
Like the money at that point
Doesn't matter
You know if
There's a day
Will you think
You may die
All of a sudden there's this
Mortality
Yeah you have to think of your
Kids it's a most awful thing
Think about
What's going to happen
With my children
Who's going to give them a hug
Who's going to
You know
Take an obviously you know what I mean I've got family that
That would step in and take care of him but but
It's the little things
It's the day-to-day things
That you mentally go through
That makes it really hard
How's your
How's your health now
Now I'm
I had double mastectomy
I don't identify myself
As a cancer survivor I just look at it as
This was a time in my life
And now it's over
All of that
Getting past the medical issues
Selling the company
All of that adds up
Taking control
And that's my sense of bold
So you kind of cut it now you got your mind in a new space
Amazing
Station you think about the trajectory of your
Life in your career end
The incredible success you had to do you think that it's because of
The skills that you brought in the hard work that you brought her do you think that
Pluck
Played a bigger role
And that
You know a lot of people say oh she got lucky
That really pisses me off
Cuz you're yeah maybe the Stars aligned and maybe the timing was right for a lot of
Bangs
Each and every one of the challenges
And the hurdles
That you overcome
Others might not have gotten there
And we did
I could have very easily
Followed
The path
Dad
My father
Laid out for me
Probably could have just
Stating that
Comfort zone
But
Yo yes by moving to this place and moving to that place and taking on additional challenges
I think you develop the skill
Someone of us survival
That's what
Goddesswear
We were in
When we sold
Yeah maybe there was some luck in there but there was a lot of skill
That's involved
In Crossing that
Finish Line
Ted Stacy Madison
Pita chips
Still in the food business
A few years ago she opened Stacy's juice bar Needham Massachusetts
And along with her brother Dave
She's just launched a new energy stack
Call diebold bars
But even with those who Ventures
Daisy still gets excited every time she's at the grocery store
And see someone putting a bag over pita chips
There was a time I was in the grocery store and this woman picked up two or three bags and she
Put them in her car and I just couldn't resist I'm like you know what I'm just going to go tell her and I did I went up and I said
Those are my chips and she looks at me and she goes
No they're not they're my chips
Oh my God
And please do stick around because in just
The moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
But first a quick message from one of our 2019 lead sponsors of how I built this hiscox
His doctor Taylor's its policies to fit every businesses
Very specific needs
Which may explain its 97% customer service rate
Get a quote or buy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business
Insurance
After James reeb was murdered in nineteen
55 National Elk
The back of the scene of the crime in Selma Alabama
Many people responded differ
What happened
And what did Justice look like all these years later
NPR's new podcast
White Lies is Seeking a
Listen And subscribe now
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Timeout for how you built that and the Story begins about
5 years ago
Country ratchathani was a pre-med student at UC Berkeley
Taking organic chemistry what do you want to get a hydroxyl group onto a tertiary Carbon on an alkane
Well then you can use a sn1 reaction
During this is going to stress some of you out
An alkyne which is a double bond into a sink I hear something you should know which is that
Foremost
Pre-med students organic chemistry
Sucks their people who will cry the night before the final there are people who would just lose it
Just because it's so difficult
Because it's about the essential building blocks of life every molecule in your body is an organic chemistry Mall
And those molecules are reacting with other molecules all the time
And so you need to know these compounds pretty well and you need to know how they interact with one another
You start with molecule a and you have to figure out how to make
Molecule B
And maybe it's kind of obvious by now that
Prereq was one of those rare pre-med students who really liked organic chemistry
Intimate friends with a fellow student Dalal who felt the same way
We both very much site like a game
And then by the time we graduated we finally were like oh my God we actually have time now we're both plan to medical school
Let's try to do this thing like let's try to actually create a game and see if we can
Demystify this
Daunting obstacle that still many pre-med students face all recruited a few other organic chemistry
Start to develop a board game that
You could play in the classroom
And then we literally met once a week at UC Berkeley and one of their classrooms and
Started brainstorming
How is this going to work
What do we want to have this game how exactly do we want to convey why we love organic chemistry and why other people should
Lot of to eventually came up with a game where you get this card with a simple
Carbon chain on it
And the goal is to manipulate that carbon chain into a more complex molecule
And you do that by drawing more cards
With all kinds of reactions and substrates and reagents on them
I have no idea what any of that means
What is the person with the most
Complex molecule at the end of the game
So the earliest version of the game was literally a kid you not me and my dad printing this out on
Normal printer paper
Eight and a half by 11
Like 6 cards per sheet
Cutting it out with scissors in my downstairs living room
Play that first version of game
But it went on
Forever I couldn't even finish it
Cuz it was still really complicated Ardex for like three hundred cards each
And again they're on in 1/2 by 11 piece of paper card for everywhere there was a mess
But it wouldn't work
So over the next few months prereq in his team simplified the game
They eliminated some of the molecules and made
Card each chemical element
Cartoon figure instead of thinking about all these chemicals
Scary chemicals they actually look really fun like our bromine is a is a bro it has a nice hat on it and it
Looks like a browse Anyway by the spring of 2017
Shrek and his friends went on the kickstarter and it reads $15,000 from 18 different countries
And the thing that I think really made us all proud was I think people love the idea was not doing any of the
This on a full-time basis
While the kickstarter campaign was going on he was getting ready to go to med school which he started in the summer of
2017 this is a side gig for all of us
I'm in med school I should take care of patients full-time and yet I still have this other thing that I really want to get done today
The game is pretty much done it's called react
With an! A company in China is making it there's a website where you can order it
So far they've only sold about 400 games but the market is going to grow I want
React to be the supplement for all organic chemistry classes across the not even the nation even the world
And even something they can play before they take the class to really be like okay so this is what I'm getting myself into it's not death it's not cray
Is basic science
Directions
Creator of react
The board game about organic chemistry
Nonprofit their back-up plan is to become doctors if you want to find out more about reactor here
Your previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want
Tell us your story go to build. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us at HRBT
Npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
How I built this
It was produced this week by JC Howard music composed by routine Arab Louis
Thanks also to Candice and Jeff Rogers AR intern
David jaw
And I Rise And even listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign mode
An email marketing plan
Used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com