Hey everyone just
Quit notice episode first ran back in October of 2017
Hope you enjoy it
When I walked into Ross Perot xoffice I felt like I was at
Like I had tried everything I had tried to access everyone and I knew either
He supports this or I just really don't know where else to turn so I I literally told myself
I won't leave his office I'm going to glue myself to the chair in his office and I'm not going to
Until he commits
From NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories behind the movements
Convince graduates
Some of the top universities
To forget Wall Street
Forget Law School
Forget big money
Become a teacher
Sotomayor
Different from
Other episodes
For starters you will not discover
Because she didn't
Money was never the point
Wendy's
Still a really successful Builder
You can say what are the most successful non-profit Founders Andresen
X
Our story is
Textbook case study
For how to start a business
Probably why there's an
Actual case study about her
At Harvard Business School
Because Wendy built teacher America
From an idea in her head
Operation with a budget in the hundreds of millions of dollars
It's a program that sends thousands of
College
December the most neglected Public Schools
Across the US
Each and every year
TFA isn't without its critics and you hear about that
But is also a program that's
Change lives
And schools
Wendy during her time as a student
Princeton
Even though she didn't really have any experience working with underserved students
In fact Corona bringing in Dallas
Was practically
Another world
And honestly I grew up
In a community in Dallas Texas that
Referred to itself as the bubble
You know it's kind of lack of diversity and disadvantage me my parents had
Really made it a point to
Bias
Place in this community so that we could go to the unit, notably strong public schools there
And
Somehow I managed to grow up really without understanding
The extreme disparity
Praising our country and
The fact that where you're born really does so much to determine whether you have access to an excellent education
And I
You can never become aware of that really in its full extent at Princeton but
On NE campus and inferencing included you can see
You know evidence of that that
Reminder freshman year roommate had gone to public schools in in the Bronx
And
We honestly love the most driven brilliant people
To make it to Princeton but still threw her and and threw her friends made from work kind of other first-generation college
Into Princeton
I realized how differently prepared they were to do well so
Many things that turn me on to
Viscous
Fact that our country that
Claims to be in really aspires to be a place of equal opportunity really isn't one
And what are you
Just thinking about this tougher or did you
Did you start to do something
Well
Actually I had organized the conference alongside some other
Students
Princeton about
Improving our education system
And it was at that conference where we had
Pulled together students from all of it
The country and they were some of the
Most
Incredible student leaders and they were saying
We had no idea there was a need
For teachers in in urban and rural areas we would teach
And it was really sitting there that I thought of this idea like
Why aren't we channel in his pee
People energy and
And
What struck me was this idea that we would
Essentially build a movement among
The rising generation of leaders
To channel their energy
The teach in urban and rural Public Schools
Knowing that that would have really important immediate impact in in classrooms and schools and in the life kids
So I became obsessed in the minute I thought of it I just thought this would change our country
Can we change the consciousness of our country and it became the answer to everything
I need to propose in my senior thesis
So you decided
Turn this idea into
Is your thesis your like your research project
Yeah I mean I do know I looked at different things I looked at
Other models again
Looked at the Peace Corps and
There was a federal teacher Corps in the six
And this time and I really went back
I analyze the policy
Context do you know what this actually work could we get these folks into classrooms
And also the mood on college campuses having it all the factors and ended up in this thesis
Proposing the creation
Andava national team
Heater core ideas
That
They were all of these
Talented
College graduates every year who
Or willing and and could
Contribute
Set a few years to teaching kids in
Chicken in low-income areas I mean that that resources
Being underutilized
I mean I felt like
You don't when I was
Thinking about my own self and all of my
Piers at Princeton you know
Since we're really searching for
What do we want to do and not a whole lot of people knew exactly what they wanted to do so they were
Doing was in
Front of them
The time is late 80s so
All the recruiters were
Literally investment Banks management consulting firms
Send a couple of brand manager
Friends
I was at Princeton liberal arts majors at Princeton I mean those for the
Companies that were banging down our doors
And so
My thought was you know how different would it be in our country if we had many of the most
Promising
Future Leaders instead of
And working in Worcester
For two years right out of college teaching for 2 years in
Urban and rural areas
And how was the
Desus receive like when you are advisor
I called you in to give you feedback what they say
Well
He called me in and said can you come into my office and I was thinking hoops
I guess this didn't go over
But he loved it you know he did he said
About this
Brilliant
Wow so he was like let's let's make this happen for real
In the last week of writing a thesis I decided I'm just going to say in the thesis that I'm going to go do this
He liked the idea but he thought it was really crazy to think that I was really going to try to go do this so I had this plan
And one of the things I had looked at the origin of the
Peace Corps and there's this incredible paper and
The paper was this beautiful analysis that
Concluded that it had to start with 500
Core members that that was the smallest possible number that would seem nationally
Important
But that it was a workable number anything bigger would be unmanageable so that became my number
Like okay we've got to recruit
500 people saw the whole plan was to inspire
Thousands of people to apply in the first year unselecting training place no fewer than five hundred of them in
You know five or six communities across the country
And I had a budget saying this was going to cost two and a half million dollars in the first year
And my thesis advisor became really obsessed with that number like how are you going to raise 2 and 1/2 million dollars
He said you know do you know how hard it is to raise $2,500
And he sent me down he said I'll tell you what I'm going to link you up with the head of development Princeton is going to explain
How hard it is to raise $2,500 and this is 1989
Yeah
And so tilted that happened that you'd sit down with the help of development
You said hey I've got this idea
Una Familia box
Yes
He was very nice
He he did explain how hard it would be
But meanwhile
I had take
Look back at this and I too wonder
What
Possessed me
Blessed with the advantage of
You don't know you have at 8
And I was
Really obsessed with
Society I mean I just thought an end really it was an idea whose time has come
Tom I mean I would
Tell people this idea and they would just a dozen this already exists in fact they spent most of
The thesis writing just looking for I wish you
Vince someone must be trying to start this because there really was a mood on College
People really were searching for something
That would enable them to make a real difference
And
You don't the fall of my freshman year of my senior year
There was a front-page article in Fortune Magazine
Saying Corporate America takes on edge
Education reform
And so I
I thought
These people will fund this
So I wrote letters
To everyone quoted in the article
And a few others by the way I would pick out
Like you know Delta Airlines and write to the CEO of unless you know the advantage of an expiry
The believe it or not I got
7 meanings of those letter
It's not with the CEOs but with people who they would pass the letters down to and
One was the head of the Business Roundtable
Who is the CEO of Union Carbide
And you know the Business Roundtable was the group that it said we're going to take on education reform
And they had no plan
So
You know
I think my timing was just perfect and he said I'll tell you what I'll
But you use our office in Manhattan
And I'll introduce you to some other folks
And I met another executive at mobile
Who was just
I love the idea
And said you know
What do you need
To try to make it work
I said I need a $26,000
Developed a budget saying that's what I needed to do to you don't need it
Spend three months like flying all over the country and really trying to put it together
And he said okay I'll tell you what I'll do it if you can get Princeton to be the conduit
Funds
So I called the head of development and literally I mean this is amazing I now realize but
In two hours he got the president to sign off on being the conduit of funds what was the condo Define
What does that mean like they could write the check
The Princeton
And then Princeton would just give it to
Even though we didn't have our tax exempt
Stop
Hawaii
Was that important to him
Well
Have no credibility in and you can't give him another Foundation you can't give
Funds to an individual like me
So young other ngos can
Can figure out how to be a conduit to Startup
Spec
You know you have to jump through hoops to be able to
Do that so you got person to agree to
Listen to launder this money to help
Help you launch Teach for America
Right off the bat you thought I've got to just go to
The corporation
To get funding for
Well I had to find
Yeah I had to find some funding before I graduate it's what I had to
Something to live on
And that was my biggest thing was her you know that was very stressful day April
I'm thinking I've got two months to get some money
You know a lot of
A lot of students right
College
Reese's right like mine was on gladstonian liberalism that was a last time
I
Expose myself to gladstonian liberalism two decades ago
But you can we are
You know
Your thesis is been your life's work
What do you think it was that compel you to
This idea did you go out and graduate and say I'm going to pursue this
What is a relay
Is good idea right like one of those ideas
Is that if I hadn't
Pursued it
Someone would have figured it out in the in the
Couple years after I'm really cool
Commence to that I mean it's just one of those ideas it's so foundational with so many other things
You know somehow I just landed on
On a good idea
Okay so you got
$26,000 in NC money
And then
You got this office space in the Business Roundtable
And are you guys at this point already calling yourselves
Teach for America
Well we we had named ourselves
America and then we found out that that was
Name of a medical supply company so we played.
3 months trying to think of an alternative until one night at midnight
Subway I just bought for
Teach for America
Thank heaven
Great cuz Teach for America is such a better name
You keep saying we so I'm assuming that you and Emma I guess a couple of friends
Guy came up with it
With a plan to launch this thing
Yes well our plan was
Let's
Show people
So I mean that was
Pretty much
Cuz we were hearing
No one was going to do anything the school districts were telling us if you get these people from these colleges we had a list of 100 College
And they would look at the list I would remember meeting the head of Human Resources in Los Angeles and I mean it had its legs kick back
Back on the desk and he started laughing when he looked at the list of a hundred
Intelligence
Okay I'll tell you what
You get 500 people from these colleges to want to teach in my schools and I'll hire all five
Is the LA Unified School District
So you went
To meet with
Seattle hiring there and said I have this plan
Great costumes do you want them and he said if you can do it sure I'll take them
And and he would have to pay any of them because you were going to get the funding for this
Will know he was going to hire them at regular teacher salary so I had gone through and just
Was really testing the feasibility will the district
Tire them in
And I was hearing yes
If you can actually get them in the
Funders I would need these potential funders and they would say well
It's a good idea but you know it's not going to work
Does the college student
So the whole
Plan became let's just show people that the college students want to do it
So what we did was to
Decide okay we're going to find
Two students at each of 100
We're going to find one and tell them to go fi
Find someone who represents a difference
You know what sort of diversity on that
And then those two
People are going to
Essentially put flyers under doors and try to inspire people
So you you said hey
If you want to teach in a low-income
It's cool we can train you and then place you in a school
And then
Can you put that out there and did application start
Yeah I mean the pitch was even it was like
If you want to be part of the movement
Improve education in America
And ensure that we live up to our nation
Promise to be a place of
Equal opportunity then
Apply today
And you'll teach for two years and then you'll be part of a
Group of leaders who work
For the rest of their lives to
To change
And
One of the first people we found
Was a guy
At Yale actually who
Drafted this flyer
And he was really the first one he put it under doors
And within one weekend
He had 170
Voicemail messages on his answering machine
Saying hey I want to play yes and and there was a man has some of your listeners
Remember Fred hechinger
Who is a columnist at the New York
X who
You know I'd met him along the way and he just couldn't believe he know where is this out
Preen of idealist
Coming from the
Visions of you told that story
In an article in The Faults probably October
And so one thing would lead to another people start realizing wow I mean this generation does want to do that so
The donors who were
Not
You know making a decision decided some of them okay we'll get behind this the school district started
Taking it more seriously
So everything was coming together
The only massive
Problem was
That we were nowhere near present
Million-dollar
You
Are going out
Basically advertising
Tencent
Hunter College
Apply for the
But like you didn't really have a guarantee
Ironclad guarantee that that you could actually
Place them in any job
He was really just kind of
And you were kind of
Hoping it would work out
Yeah well
That is as I look back
Like you that maybe how it looks mean at the time it didn't
Seem soap
Precariously
There were real
Teacher shortages in these
Districts
Talk to
FedEx in many of these districts and realize that they really
Wanted
To hire these folks
And so
It didn't seem as precarious as it sounds now
So how many
Applications did you get
We had 2500
People apply
How many spots
Could you
You were aiming for 500
So
Wow I mean how many of you were now
Running this organization like
Four five
Well
You know it just kept holding on
South Bend
We had all these applique
Patience we had underestimated
Everything
What to do
Do with 2500 go through 5
Yes
That's a very good question
But we hadn't thought through
But one thing we did was say okay we're going to send teams of 2 out in
You don't actually
I got the head of
Hurts to donate Rent-A-Car so we had
Five rent-a-cars and we were going to send to people I need to them
Off to interview these
So they would eat steak
Parts of the country and they would drive from campus to campus and would do these interviews and we had
Created a day-long application process that you know
Start with an essay application and then they do the sample teaching session and
And interviewing we have had someone go out and develop this kind of
Selection process
And by the way this is about when I mean you know we have these teams out on the road
And there
Spoke and
I'm thinking
We don't have it
Money
When we come back
The Scramble for money
A mutiny in the ranks
The struggle
Just stay alive
Play with us
Gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First ZipRecruiter
Hiring is important
Especially when you're looking for
Trustworthy insurance age
That's why Allstate turn to ZipRecruiter to help thousands
Agency owners hire
Talented professionals
Cross the US
In fact was ZipRecruiter
Allstate was able to find quality candidates and decrease their cost per hire
By double digits
If you're hiring for a ZipRecruiter for free
Ziprecruiter.com built
Thanks also to wetransfer
Wetransfer surveyed over 10000 of their users in nearly a hundred and fifty countries
Found out
People get their biggest most creative ideas
Step away from the screen
That's why everything we transfer designs makes the most
Your time
Their tools are simple and beautiful ways to bring ideas to life
Get you back to yours
Find out more at leave. By wetransfer
Dot-com
Next time on rough translation
The feeling you get when you quit your job
Try to start
Something new
You're a loser
Are you you're worthless
An entrepreneur from Mexico
Faces down that taboo and accidentally launches a global community that
Celebrate stories
Failure mistakes I was making was part of my journey
Travel with rough translation from NPR
Listen answer
Scrap
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros so it's the spring of 1990
And Wendy is about to train pfas very first class of teachers
The only problem is
She's short on money like two and a half a million dollar short
Kind of a Hail Mary move
When he decides to contact Ross Perot who at the time was one of the richest businessmen in Tech
Texas and you might have heard of him because he ran for president in the early 1990s
He's from Dallas and I'm from Dallas and and he's really into education reform and when I was growing up Ross Perot as a busy
Just leader in Texas was no really fighting for all this legislation to improve the school so I had never
Never met him but I just had in my head he was going to fund this
And and Ross Perot doesn't doesn't think I wrote him 11 letters before he agreed to see me but
We have different memories he called me up
I actually thought it was a friend of mine cuz everyone knew I was trying to get to Ross Perot and someone yells down
The hall
Ross Perot is on the line and I pick up
The phone and say yep I thinking
This is one of my
My friends
Pulling a prank
And I hear his voice on the other end you know which is very recognizable in like oh my God and I said to him I'm coming.
Dallas I'm going to be there
Next week can I come see you and he agreed and
What happened when you went down there
Well when I walked into Ross Perot's office
I felt like I was at the end
Like I had tried
Everything I had tried to access everyone and I knew
Either
He supports this or
I just really don't know where else
Turn
So I I literally told myself
And I've often
Wished I could be as
I won't leave his office
Seminole
Glue myself
To the chairman
His office and I'm not going to leave
Until he
You say to him
This my thing is my program and what did you ask him
For how much
Well I asked him for $1000000
I needed you know another 2 million
Basically
And
Keyspan I mean I was in there for
Probably 2 hours
And
He spent the whole time thinking about his friends who would do this to me really loved the idea
And he kept saying I think Sam Walton would do this and
I kept thinking oh now I know where all this leads like no
Like you are the one I know you're the one who care about education
Haitian you you're an entrepreneur you understand this
And he finally I actually think he decided I wasn't going to leave
And he said I'll tell you what
I will give you $500,000
If you can raise the other 1.5 L
And that was the moment I knew it's done like I knew that his
His credibility
And that
Can Leverage
I could just go back to everyone else in that they would all
You can go back to our house to say Ross Perot has committed $500,000
I need your money
Yep in order to Leverage
Yeah
All right so so did you I'm assuming you raise the money after arrest
Yep
The one year after I graduated I was
Literally looking out an auditorium full of 489
Recent grads who are all in the auditorium at us
Hereafter
Keep right when you have to
You got it you got these
College graduates in this room
Ready for 45 weeks
Train from DIA tweaks to go to the LA Unified School District
Net well they were during the summer they were but then they would go to the one at 6
Places where we had decided to Cluster them and where the school district
Agreed to hire them
The word a New York City in the NL a New Orleans Baton Rouge in Southern Louisiana
Cannon to World sites in in World Middle Georgia and
Eastern North Carolina
And they had to make a two-year commitment
So I mean
Ifi'm remember correctly you were not a teacher you did not study
Did not have a teaching credential
Like how did you know how to train
I didn't know an end
You know that's why we found
This
Experience teacher Educators in an experience
Teachers who had a specialty in
You know preparing and supporting
Teachers in urban and rural areas and we really just turns the whole thing over to them to her that first summer go of
It was terrifying
You know I mean
It was the first year we had 489 people cooped up in dorms for 8 week
A diverse group not as diverse as you know we would all hoping his
Teach for America is achieved at this point but
And we had a
Max
The folks who had never been in
An environment like this and we're never
Many of them who had
Been working in
Urban rural communities so there was just a lot
Of tension and a lot of issues to sort through and it was
It was very
And I was exhausted
YouTube
Start teaching and you see the microcosm
Of the world
Playing out in your car
You know you see kids
Are facing all the challenges
Poverty and lack of adequate
Healthcare nutritionist
Racial discrimination the whole bed
And
It's very overwhelming
So the pioneering Force
Four members
Hi-Tech
Find their way to solution
You don't often from other teachers in their schools and
Ultimately we're learning from them
Once that first class of teachers went
Are schools in
Start to teach
Did you just have to get right back on the fundraising
Hamster wheel
I mean this and an on the recruitment
Sidon you know it gets it's a cycle rate like every year and
So yeah the fundraising never stop
Kind of an ongoing underlying
Casella's were all of your Revenue was going
Come from
Different fundraising right
It's a non-profit
Search for different from
SSS mention the other companies
Switch on the show
But it does you were running a business
I mean you were a Christian
In the hardest pieces you say was about recruiting selecting training supporting them but then
There was how do you manage them
I had no idea what I was doing
I mean I hadn't really
Really idealistic Notions you know we should all make the same salary and there shouldn't be any hierarchy and all sorts of things
Which now I might think
Maybe this path to some of that
But at the time
Chaos
And and then ultimately
Most importantly me there also
The political earnings you know how do you navigate the politics
Pics of education but probably most
Fundamentally
Can't do anything
Without resource
How are weaknesses
Stainless things
Financially because none of those donors
Thought they were going to stick with it
Yeah
And we were losing donors in
In like half a million a million
Docker chunks
And
Sweetly convert the
The funny bass essentially
And that kind of
Threw us into
What I think of as the dark years of
Teach for America you know what like
Every paycheck
Every payroll
You know there's a question about whether we were going
Meet at
Was there something
That happened during
That. That was
Particularly difficult
If there was so much
Probably the most
Excruciating moment
Was
When President Clinton
Launched
Americorps
List national service initiative
Teach for America was one of those
First partners
Americorps and said that Federal funding really gave us
But the second year
There was
2 question actually about our
Financial viability
And so
The defects were operating Americorps
Wooden
Approved
I granth
To Teach for America
And
This is about
June
And we have five
Teachers
Think that they're going
Going to training but we didn't have
The money to even
Buy them there
And so I felt like
This is at
Either we get the governmental approval
Or
We shut it down
And we were ready I mean we were ready
To FedEx
Letters to all five
People saying
We can't make it
You're not going to be able to come
And
We could not get
Anyone in the government
You know I'm still in
20 is 20 whatever we still had
Only so much credibility and we're dealing with these governmental
Official
And you know we were taking ourselves a lot more seriously than they were taking us let's just say but
Ultimately at about
One minute
Before we would have
Posh Salon
You know
Plan B after shutting it down they finally came through but that was
One of many many examples of
The extreme stress
Sarah I mean what how much money did you need
Toot It To Me payroll
Watch MTV
Well
I mean I think that Grant
The big one you know is probably one and a half million
Frost
When and why did it come in at the last
I mean we were calling every
Sing
Person
Lever
Possibly
Come up with
And ultimately I guess we wore them down
But you know these things happen
Like this is what happens in Vegas
Bureaucracies and it's what happens to social entrepreneurs you know I mean ultimately it all works out
Appreciate the ecosystem
The
And that's why
Teach for America Ulta
Smelly
Thrived but I think it's kind of the definition of social entrepreneurship
There aren't natural funding sources so you you almost have to
Create them in Alton
What we buy your existing
It's helped shape them in
Until that happened it's the
Just excruciatingly
I need to make it
Wendy I guess at a certain point maybe maybe it was about five years
Teach for America
The staff
I'd like they've they've revolted a rebelde all friend request what was going on
Oh gosh that was even earlier I mean
I think it was our second year actually we were all at our training in
Institute and
I was still I had this notion of no hierarchy
Which was a genuine notion I just thought
If we're all on the same
You know we're on the same Mission why do we need a hierarchical self-direct
But people decided this was because I wanted to control everything and
They just decided unless we can make all Decisions by vote we're all walking out the door how many people said that
Well it was everyone
Sitting in a room
People are 15 people
Suicide
If we can't vote on every decision by democratic
And so would you do
Well disappointed
To know what to do I was honestly still remembers like midnight I'm so exhausted
And one of our
Staff members who turned into my husband later much later
Raises hand and said Wendy
I mean I was making no sense and wasn't being response
So what I'm hearing you say
Is that we're not going to make all Decisions by vote
Is that right
And even then I had like I should have said yes
But now if so we all left
And the next morning I sent out
Note saying
You know we're not going to make decisions by vote and you know what no one left
Any truth in what they were saying like were you autocrat
Jamaican in your style
Let's just say
I wasn't autocratic in Maya
Concussion
You know I really did have this thought that everyone should just
Do the right thing
You know it was just not
In itself out as in
And it's so I'm sure that there was some truth
On all sides
When you are
24 or whatever
25 however old you are
The time in
The whole team is like hey we want to
Vote of no confidence
Even even if it wasn't but it
What kind of Lies
Did you did it
Shaky
Did you sleep feel like
Did it
Exacerbating self-doubt
Oh yes
It did
But I didn't know what
I mean part of what
Was leading me
Stay in it was just
Ascent of response
Disability like
I couldn't figure out how to get out of it
I mean honestly if someone had a
Appeared
So I felt like
Get us out of this
And get us to
Point of stability or some
I think I would have just turn the whole thing over to the
There's no doubt about that I mean I was
In fact I was
Looking for
I couldn't seem to find the answer other than to keep put my head down and key
Keep going at it
Until we could get out of
Once you get out of bed
You know
Became more financially stable
Were you able to
To start seeing the impact
Teach for America
Well I think
I mean we were seeing even your five we were
Starting to see real evidence of
Beyond the immediate impact of Art
Teachers of what some of our alumni were starting
To do
Like we were starting to see
The big idea play itself out these people aren't leaving their dedicating themselves
Sylvester becoming the pioneering leaders we thought they could be so
That's what kept us going through these dark years like realizing that
This really
Is Agatha chilling it really is working
Because we were seeing enough evidence in classrooms
And enough Avenue
Even a whole school's that actually
When you meet kids
Who are facing a lot of challenges and have a lot of assets but
You don't with high expectations Amex
Support they need they'll Excel
An absolute
Scale soap
That
Recognition is what
Really inspired us to say okay how do we take this to the next level
Azteca America really starts
Takeoff and
And grow and grow and get more and more
Attention
You also
With more visibility
Thomas More criticism
And I just
Trying to sing me you were
Still pretty young
You had no teaching experience and there were
Professional Educators who are kind of going after you
Criticizing Teach for America everything from
This is your wife
Eternalism of middle-class wealthy kids
Going into
Poor neighborhoods
Color to
You know there's not enough
Training to
You know they're only there for two years is too sexy
Disruptive
Did that
Did the curse of hurt you did it
Digital
Keep you up at night
You know we were
Working
Very hard to get better you know when the criticism actually started
Pretty early on I mean it
You don't this wasn't
Constant
Fred
During
First decade actually but
In a way we were our own harshest critic
When we were
Tearing ourselves
Funny weed
Felt that we needed
Do things a lot
Better
So
I guess our assessment was
The world isn't going to be better
If we shut down
Teach for America
So there's really only one option
What does de get better
So you just it didn't it didn't faze you
Well
It's not that it didn't I mean the fact is it made the work so much
More difficult
It's easy now
Justify a decision to
Go off
To work for the consulting firm
I'm 40 years to don't even Teach for America really good
Thing like there's enough
Question out there
They're in the
Blogosphere you know and then so it definitely made the work more.
Call but
You know it was the criticism became probably at its most extreme
We were seeing incredible
In communities
I mean when we started placing teachers in Washington DC it was the lowest-performing of all the major Urban District
Kids for 2 years behind the kids in Harlem
And
You don't now it's graduation rates
Enrollment rates everything moving in the right direction
And the fact is if you talk the teachforamerica people out of that City not just the teachers during the two years right but the
Teachers who are still in the system and the
The school principals and the last two schools chancellors who presided over the system for a decade and one of them
Save an alarm of
And that's one city
I mean name a city I could tell you the stats like it's really they become such a leadership Forest
For changing the city so
You know you can critique it all you want
But
I guess my view is
Proposed the Alternatives write like we have here
Deeply entrenched
And
Systemic
Issue
It cannot be solved from within classrooms
Write this is
No amount of teaching is going to solve that we need incredible teachers
But we also need
Some of those people who understand what you understand
Teaching
And decide I'm not go
Costco prints
Schools and some who say I'm going to work
System one summer's day I'm going to run for office cuz we got to change the policy contact
I'm going to start something that proves the child welfare system
Is that
Until we do that we will never solve
This problem
And that's what Teach for America is trying to do so
I know that and I know that we need to stay the course because I have yet to see another thing that's made of
Bigger difference in really tackling
The systemic challenges
It's full complexity
And the critics
You know I wish they dive in and help us
Do better
Essentially
What's Teach for America
Budget today
It's about 300 million
Cute
It's gone from Two and a half million
300 million
Funny
Teachers does it
They're about
You know
7 to 8000
Teachers at any given
+ 50000 alumni
Most of whom I will say are still in the work
Wendy train
I think anybody hearing this
Conclude that you could have been a
Start up business
A for-profit company
And
Probably
Metronome
Do you have
Talent
Vince Gill
To do that and
And I wonder whether
You could have gone on a
And on that and let's say you had three hundred million dollars now you could have just been a huge philanthropist
Given 300 million dollars to
Education
Projects in your name would be everywhere to be the Wendy Kopp building for Education reform and people showing up to you would have
Who knows but it's
Just not
There's really not
A bone in my body I feel like I don't even know how I would
Do that like
You know what everyone's cut out for
Things in NY
Shape Barrel
Experiences
Of course but
I don't even I have not one insta
Do that right like I'm
So to this day I'm I've never been more energized
Like 27 or however many years in
You know like this is really all I've ever won
Yuan to do
That's Wendy Kopp founder of Teach for America
In 2013 she stepped down
Yelp also co-founded teach for all
Which partners with organizations all over the world
Recruit teachers to work
NDT schools today that network has more than 14000
Teachers in 50 countries
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Going to hear from you about
Things your building
The first a quick message
Are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox
Hiscox understands every small business is unique
Taylor's its policies
Your business is very specific needs
Get a quote for purchase a policy
H i s
Cox
Dot-com
Hiscox
Business
Insurance X
This is Terry Gross The Host
The fresh air
From WHYY and NPR
We do long-form interviews
With journalists breaking the big news stories
I'm with the authors filmmakers and musicians behind
The best in pop culture
So listen And subscribe
Hey thanks so much
Sticking around because it
Timeout for how you built that
A story that we were about a year ago in 2015 Abby kircher
There was a teenager with a food obsession
Cups peanut butter ice cream I love peanut butter and jelly sandwiches
But one day a beaded something that you probably shouldn't do with a food you eat everyday
She looked at the label and I was just like oh my gosh this is so much sugar tons of additives in
Preservatives and so it just doesn't feel like it's almost peanut butter in anymore you know it just feels kind of like a sugar
Spread to go cold turkey on Peanut Butter but of course she missed eating it
So I was like I might as well make my own there's no reason why I couldn't make my own so that's why I Just Whipped out of
Food processor and just tried it out this was by the way her mom's food processor into what she put
Some nuts
And coconut oil and salt and eventually took
Forever it turned into a creamy texture I was like wow this is so cool
I got very excited then I was like okay how do I want to flavor this or Sweeney
So I threw in some dates
Process. A little bit and it was
So good
So good in fact that Abby started
Spreading peanut butter on everything
Apple sandwiches pancakes even salad
And she began sharing it with her family and friends
And then
One night
I went into my room and it was
Quite literally an aha moment
I can start a business and she was like
Alright yeah absolutely it's a good thing Abby's mom and dad were on board because remember
Abby was like
15 at the time
So she needed her parents help to
Track down jars and labels in a commercial kitchen to make the nut butter
I'm still making a lot of the big decision
Like early on she actually decided to forget about peanuts
And the branch out into other types of nuts
I wanted something a little different and I I realize there weren't a lot of pecan and cashew butter is out there at the time
Abby came up with five recipes
Each with just a handful of ingredients
Flavors like bait Baccano
Strawberry cashew
Copy almond
And Sheena Montana set up a standard
Big farmers market just outside Charlotte
Call people over
They were all incredibly
Story and how young I was they would always look at my mom be like so
You started this and she'd be like nope
Anyway they kept selling out at the Farmers Market
And people kept asking for more
It was getting hard because they were still packing the jars of nut butter themselves and
How are they doing that
Spoons believe it or not many spoons many many 1/2
That was the worst
Part for sure it just took so long so few months later they got a machine to do the jarring for
They were pitching their nut butter at local grocery stores
For a young girl and her mom to walk in there excited about a product and it made them excited
And I think that was
A huge factor in our growth
Less than two years after a bee started making nut Butters
They were selling them like 300 grocery stores in the Charlotte area
In overtime and it wasn't just Abby and her mom doing this
Older brother join the business and her dad actually quit his job to join them as well
Play I'm the boss of my parents and brother yes
Which is definitely a learning experience trying to figure out okay what are our positions in the business
This regardless of our positions in the family
4 years now
And her nut Butters of spread to nearly 1,000 stores across the east coast and the Midwest
I'm putting some pretty big chain
Like Wegmans and Lowe's
Abby's nut butter is expected to pull in 1.6 million dollars is
You're pretty amazing for a CEO who is now just 19 years old
Young entrepreneur and starting at such a young age
You know I didn't think that I can't do it I just thought I could
It's such an incredible opportunity in a blessing
The business
It's called Abby's better than
Tter and if you want to find out more about it or your previous episodes head to our podcast page
Npr.org of course if you want to tell us your story go to build.
Co.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe an apple podcasts or what
Wherever you get your podcast then while you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us at the HRBT at end
Npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
How I built this
I sure was produced this week by run. Don't fight with music composed by Rammstein are blue
Thanks also to Juliet
Cardene immigrants
And Jeff Rodger
Or intern
Stable job
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR