Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
How are you able to come a stay optimistic or you just looking at projections and saying
Stay optimistic what makes you think that I was optimistic I was
I was defiant in the face of a terrifying reality
Companies don't die because the companies fail they die cuz the entrepreneur gives up and that was the approach just
Keep the lights on keep growing and that's what we did
Is how I built this show about innovators entrepreneurs idea
Ulysses and the stories behind the movement they built
How to build a multimillion-dollar men's fashion brand
Bonobos
Okay so before we start to show
Talk about a serious issue in men's fashion
The Khaki diaper butt
You know you see men all the time with
Pants that might fit perfectly in the waist but
Show me some little baggie in certain other areas it in this is really common because you
Your other option
Is wearing pants that are really tight in the waistband
If every man is wearing
Khaki diaper butt pants
What does it even matter
Except
Andy Dunn and his co-founder Brian's family were in grad school in the mid-2000s
They had a hunch that there could be another option
A best-of-both-worlds type of
Browser
With a curved waistband
Fits really well
Eliminates that
Diaper look
Delete turn this idea into Aiden Cheyenne
Company bonobos
Which in 2017
Sold to Walmart for a reported
310 million dollars
The story is a little more complicated than that because
As you were here
Andy done made a lot of mistakes along the way
Thor x wenzhou bows
Calendar
Including a very messy Fallout with a co-founder
We'll get to that little later
Here's what you need to know
Anytime grew up in the suburbs of Chicago
Family was squarely middle class
That was a high school teacher born and raised
In Chicago
Is Mom an immigrant
India
What's an x-ray technician
Grew up in a bicultural house
Even though as he tells it
Identify that way for a long time
I didn't know I was different
It all
Until
I think it was in high school
This kid
Ed
Invented a nickname for me which is Windu
Which I guess stands for white Hindu
And I was totally it became a thing and you know how
Teenagers are
Yellow became like a good
Derogatory nickname and of course those can catch on like wildfire and
You know depending on
How you feel about it it can be a little bit
Setting Army for upsetting so I came home and I told my parents
Expecting empathy and instead they both started laughing
And that was the only
Time in
In terms of awareness that I started to think like okay wait a second I'm not
I'm not just among mostly white people I'm I'm not
Just
You know I'm halfway
Half Indian which is a little bit different
I think I did a bad job of connecting deeply with the Indian side because of the dominant white culture that we have
Engagement culturally with through my mom but I didn't really own it
Until I went to India in 1997
I went over this
Setting freshman or sophomore in college
And that really connected me
And that that helped me kind of shatter the bubble that I think
Lightways I grew up in the suburbs of Chicago you know all the way through
Your college he went to Northwestern
For college and effort
Studying for the MCAT
He decided to switch gears and going to business Consulting
And private-equity eventually
Enrolling at Stanford Business School
It was amazing just creep people
The filter for empathy and self-awareness I think
And then there's no
Great disclosure to employers
So they remove the competitive Dynamic of how you do in your classes
A minute smaller it's 350 275
People which is I guess twice the Dunbar number
Which is the number of people that
Existed in hunter-gatherer Villages and supposedly has the number of people where you can know every member of the tribe cheer
So you kind of her
Friends with everyone or one hop away
And you put all those ingredients and you mix them together and it's a magical place
Alright so you go to Stanford in the fall of 2005
And
You become friends with with
Somebody was going to factor in into your life tell me tell me about meeting Brian
We became housemate.
Sleep so
Once we both got into school we had a,
My friend kind of jazz
And I called up Jeff Lewis
It was an alumni of Stanford and I said Hey how do I think about getting a
A roommate for Schwab which is the building where
A lot of first-years live and he's like all you got
You got to live with this guy Brian's Bailey
Until I invited them to come out one night
And
Divers terrific
Funny and fun and
Super smart and so we became roommates
So you and Brian can roommates
And you're doing your own thing your take
Classes and I guess when your business school
Will you personally you're constantly like
Bouncing ideas off other students right because
ZZ ideas that they might be somebody you could build something with
Exactly yeah I kind of thought about it as
Entrepreneur-in-residence opportunity
Do you like your
Amongst all these brilliant people and you can
Learn from them and figure out
Hey what do they think of
A different ideas in
I had a bunch of dumb ideas and most
Time people told me
But what were your dumb ideas
So
Taking different things I'd seen when I travel
Investing in new ideas
To create those products in the US there was a South African beef jerky called biltong that didn't exist in the US
I'm a vegetarian now but I used to love this at
It's very different than American beef jerky a taste almost like dried filet mignon with salt pepper and coriander
And I couldn't believe this didn't exist in such a carnivorous country like America
And we got to the end of the project and the guy who is the professor overseeding in it
A guy named Joel Peterson you would factor in
Meaningfully into bonobos
So I think this is a bad idea
To you and Brian
Bailey r
Roommates
You got a bunch of weird ideas and and he had no idea as well right
Well he had one good idea which is he was obsessed with the idea that pants don't fit
And so he did a project
Summer than what I did on biltong where he really dope deep on the idea he got cancer customer feedback
He went out to a bunch of guys in our class and ask them
Yeah what what are they think about their parents and everyone said the same thing we are pants don't fit so we wear jeans number one
Number to we don't like shopping for him so it's not worth the time to figure out what fits
J.Crew and like you could get
Pants with butt but he felt that that men's pants just
Didn't sit well
Yeah he felt that if the pants fit around your thighs
They tended to be too big in the waist
And if they
And so they would cinch under your belt and if it had the right fit in the waist it would be too tight through the thighs so you're either like
Like super uncomfortable or wearing something that was really foxy
That was his inside which was brilliant
Bet that men's pants just didn't hot or not cut well exactly and what he did that most guys were
Wouldn't do as he would take pants that fit his thighs to a Taylor and have the waistband Taylor then and now is this genius
Is inside the actually the way to do this is to make pants with a curved waistband
Which would bring
In
The pant around your waist in a way where the overall shape looks looks Gray
And I hadn't really been done
In a meaningful way
In men's pants before
So how did Brian turn this like this project into
Into the next
What was he mean you have this idea and embroider paper on it
And then what so yeah I'll I'll never forget that it was spring break of our second year I was
Is going to Kenya and Uganda on a service-learning trip
Ryan was going to head down to Brazil for a wedding one of our classmates in
He said what should I do should I go to Brazil for this wedding or should I
Stay here and fight and I'm heading to LA
To buy fabric and make pants
And I was like this is a no-brainer you got to go to the wedding and Brazil when are you going to have a chance to do that again with
You know a couple dozen of our classmates
Until I flew off to Kenya and Uganda and had an amazing trip there
When I came back I said how is Brazil and Brian said I didn't go
And in our house
There was like
Rolls of fabric
The Brian had bought in the Garment District of LA
Because he
Decided he was going to make
The pants that
But he thought men would like
Exactly he thought he was going to make
Pantherfit by taking and he took a pair of pants
They had been tailored the way that she liked
Chapati maker in San Francisco
San Francisco pattern maker that made an original pattern
Based on what
What the overall fit should be with the curved waistband
Kid bought all this great fabric
Really cool like turquoise corduroy
Really fun eye-catching stuff
And then he found I think one of the last
Factories in
The Bay Area actually in San Francisco not far from where the Giants play baseball
Which may be had five or six Cut & Sew
Women working there
And they started making pants
There and said
8 *
Open padlock with with what money with
Like with the idea of just sell it to who
He
Was a great pre business school moneymaker and safer so he had
Kid made some money from the company he worked at
So he he funded bonobos in those early days
And then he turned the
The pants that he was making into sales by selling them to our classmate
He was just like
Taking a fabric that you bought in LA
And making orders with this
Small Factory in the Bay Area
And he would like walk around and Hawk them
Mike self into
Other
Students
Literally
He had he loved Trader Joe's he had to Trader Joe's bags the red ones back at the
The time filled with pants
And he would walk around telling
People about him
And they would be like dropping pants behind parked cars and trees like trying them on
And people love the pants
Set the time they called him Staley pants and
I think he was charging a hundred bucks a pop
One day
We had a pants party at our house
And I think we sold $16,000 worth
And that day
Now is when I kind of looked at him I was just pitching in helping you know taking some pictures for the
Website
We kind of looked at each other and we're like
Wow this is
Becoming something
So
When did you formally get involved
I can remember sitting in class one day and on a Post-It note I was sitting next to Brian we had a different ideas for
He had ideas for what to call the parents and one of the
Ideas said
Bonobos bonobos I said what's a bonomo it's like many people I couldn't pronounce it and he
Oh it's a it's a peaceful
Chimpanzee that makes Love Not War
I was like what do you know about that
He's like I don't know you
Read about it somewhere
Intel
We kind of talked about
Bonobo should be the name he was making all the decisions at this point
Cuz it was his Hobby and
Then there was this weird thing where he had taken a job
To go into private equity
And I said hey you what you're doing is awesome selling pants on the internet like maybe I can make that a thing
Like this was his side hustle as a
Exactly he didn't think that this necessarily have legs
Pun intended I think that
I don't know why but he
I think felt like I could do it
At that stage
Into once I express interest
I became the co-founder and the CEO
And the deal was that if it really did well that
He would come back
What were people
They may say like
Are you are you sure you want to do this
I had a summer
Road trip that I took my parents after graduation
And I sat down with them and I said I have this offer from a venture capital firm
Which was the firm up in Seattle called maveron
And I said but I don't think I'm going to take it
Because I'm going to sell pants on the internet
Oh my God Hindi
You know
You sure and I said I was sure and they said okay
So in this is Ann and I guess the Summer of Love 2007
You stay
In Palo Alto
Wanting to turn this into something bigger
How did you
Pitch this to
Is presumably you needed my now in the making
Clothing manufacturing clothing have a lot of capital
Did you have any of your own money at that point
I had nothing I had I've spent all my money
Traveling in
At school I think I had about $160,000 in debt
Until I had one asset which was a 401k which I think if you cash in early you poop you pay a penalty so I did that
And I had a couple thousand dollars in the bank so we definitely need some money Brian had funded it with
50 or $60,000 of his savings and it was time back
Get some outside capital and what was your pitch I mean
And they were companies making men's pants and they were doing just fine there was J.Crew there's Banana Republic
And so
How are you pitching this to people who you needed to
Assembly raise money from
It's an awesome question because the
You know the inside of bonobos
Other than the better fitting pants part was just the role that the internet was going to play in the future of retail
No retail isn't just physical
Products it's a bundle of physical products and customer service and those two things together create the experience
The drives customer enthusiasm
And I believe well if you could make a big brand
Using a catalog
It stands to reason that you can make
Even bigger Brands using the internet given the
The power of the web
And that's when we decided okay
We're going to build this brand online rather than through brick and mortar
And that was the pitch
What is this isn't just Ralph Lauren
This is Ralph Lauren plus apus
So who did you put it you go to Deb
Ask for money
So my first meeting was heading like at 7 in the morning meeting
Rachel Peterson and Joel had been the guy
Who had presided over the biltong experiment professor at
At the business school yeah he was a lecturer at Stanford and then
The rest of this time you spent still doing investing
Until I kind of pitch them on the idea
And he said nothing home eating he just nodded silently
And I thought oh my God he hates this
And then we got to the very end you know 40 minutes in and he said this
This reminds me my first meeting with David neeleman from JetBlue wow which is we're going to go into a stagnant category
Not focus on customer centricity we're going to build a much more customer
Centric offering
And disrupt the whole industry he said I'd like to invest
And I couldn't believe
I couldn't believe it how much did he give you
Well at the time
He he said I said how much are you raising I said $300,000
He said what I said at what price I said will sell 10% of the company and you said okay that's about a 3 million dollar value a
He said at at 3 will take a hundred thousand but if you dropped it down to 2 will take
All around
If you drop the valuation to 2 million
He would give you $300,000
End
You were thinking that's great that's
Let's do let's do it
No I was thinking let's stay at school 3 million
Well then I went to see the other Professor from school who is amazing business person in Andy rachleff one of the
The co-founders of benchmark
And he also offered to invest
And he was willing to
To do it at the $3000000 price and I said okay we'll have the two of them co-invest
At 3 and then we'll figure out the rest
Just I just want to I just want to pause for a sec and ask you
Energy went when you met with
Your first to Angel Investors
It seems like you were able to convince them pretty quickly that
This thing
You know
Battle shots
And remember a couple episodes
Ago on our show
Retrinal Akon
Stitchfix also want to stay
Business school also created a
An online clothing retailer
Oh she had a problem
Initially
Raising money
In part because you said a lot of the a lot of the investor sheet
Talk with which they will let me ask my wife what she say
Thanks let me ask my secretary what she thinks about this
It's just surprising that
These guys
Instantly were like yeah
Asustor sounds good
I'll
Tread carefully here cuz I don't want to imply this is about
Joel and Andy
But I think
I've seen this experience my wife's an entrepreneur
My sisters and I
I think there is a lot of gender issues
I want to come stai entrepreneurship in fundraising
No worries
9% of all species are women
And a lot of the
The consumer spending in our world is controlled by women I think the numbers
Somewhere between 2/3 and 80% so we have a mismatch
We're men who don't understand
Women are hot women shop
Are trying to decide how to make investments and only 9% of feces are women
So it's a fundamentally
Misogynist
Dickly wired system
Thought I was fortunate
That these two amazing
Investors were willing to put money in in
I think that's
That's one part of the story but I think the other part of the story was I had had experiences with them where they knew me when
Joel it was the biltong project
With Andy I had written him
I love letter basically I wrote him a four-page letter when one of our class has ended
I spent two pages saying your
One of the best teachers I've ever had and here's why
And then I spent two pages saying
I hear the things I think you could improve from having spent
A lot of time around a great teacher which is my dad
And
Andy later years later told me that when he cut that letter he cried
CNN he's not the kind of person where that way
Seemed like something that could happen but he said that it had validated a career move that he had made
Talib
Venture capital in to become a teacher and when he saw that he had that much impact on someone it really it really moved him so
I had a relationship
With the two professors who invested that I think was
Why they invested I don't think if I had just cold
Pitch them
Even if I could have gotten the meeting at NASA
Surely would have been the same thing
See you raise the first
Seed money
What was your next step
Southern food in New York
Food in New York with a duffel bag full of pants and we called on a friend who
Graduated before us who had a job and a Michael spirito and we did a little
Trunk show at his apartment
And I think I had
20 pairs of pants in the duffle bag and send them out on a table and
He invited some friends through to
Try on these you know
Allegedly better fitting men's pants
And who I mean who was the god like
Who are you targeting like
Who came to that truck show it wasn't the fashionistas it wasn't the people that have a really
Strong understanding of hey here's exactly where I go for this part of my wardrobe
It was kind of the next
Tear of guys who
Want to look good but didn't necessarily confess the time in it or didn't know how to do it
So is New York professional senior guys in advertising or startups or Finance
Two were in Michaels Network who came to this event
And I'll never forget this seven guys
Bought three pairs of pants six guys but two pairs of pants only one guy didn't buy anything
It was at that moment that
I decided we need to build this company in the ark
So you moved to New York
I guess in the summer or the fall of
And did you like get an office was it
It's just you like we're
What did what did you do
The guy who helped me build the website for
What was then called bonobos pants. Com over the summer I can remember he drove me to the airport
With two
Suitcases one one was
Personal clothes in the other one was
We're bonobos pants
And I flew
To Chicago for a friend's wedding when I made these bright blue corduroy pants
Tube for the wedding of a friend
Inspired by Cubs baseball on I thought I'm going to sell all these
Like one pair because the color was so weird
And then food in New York and I can remember kind of coming down
2nd Avenue in
Heading to an apartment that a classmate of mine had rented and I just agreed to live there I've never seen it
Moved into
Department put
A couple hundred pairs of pants up on shelves on the walls of the apartment
Like in the room where I slept
And we were off the races
End
Like
At that point you have this
$300,000
And
What was your next move I mean
You had to
Your website
And pants and then and then what did you think what do you do with that boy
Will 300 wasn't enough money
And so what happened was
I started to
Sell as many pants as I could in person
Two guys in New York through referrals
So there was sort of a direct sales operation with
Trunk shows
And sales in person
And then there was attempting to get some
Coverage and so what happened was our first press hit
Came from urbandaddy
I remember I was sitting at the Heartland Brewery and Cafe in Union Square and I got a call from
Our first employee
He said Andy
We're getting too many orders should I turn off the site
Endanger like how to Pedal people know about this
Yeah Urban daddy wrote an article
Called Monkey Business
Which is half right cuz bonobos are Apes not monkeys but let's set that aside basically telling a story of this brand
With great fitting men's pants
And
To this day
I'm not sure how they found out
Literally imagine you were like going you were just calling anybody you knew and said hey can you host book a
Like a pants party like like like a Tupperware party
For me but with pants and and dies
Is at your apartment exactly and then the pants had these kind of signature pocket Liners in the back where you could see a difference
Fabric usually with a floral or geo print
And today attracted a little bit of attention
Cuz they're
There was a little bit of flair and Verve to it
And
That also created a bit of a reality you know the name was interesting the story of these non fashion guy so
We properly launched bonobos pants. Common October of 07
And we did 10 grand that month
Then in November we did 20
December we did 30
Came back from
The holiday break in January and we didn't know sales for the first five days and I thought oh my God this was just a
A fluke
And then all of a sudden January February March she went 30-60-90
So
At what point
I'm after you move to New York in 2007
Do things look
Pretty good enough for you could actually get in office
Oh that was when we got
Kicked out of your apartment
Yeah cuz they're starting to be
I guess complaints about all the packages stacked up outside the door
In the landlord
That was me in
Started yelling at me and said I had to move out because I was
Violating
If you can't run a business out of an apartment
Until I said that I totally understand and
We found a little a little
Lofted space on 16th Street and 6th Avenue and we moved
So I have read that
Like within the first 6 months you guys
What were projecting to do like $1000000
That year
Answer that I guess I was a player Brian
Comes back to the company that dislike 2008
Exactly yeah this was March of 08
There somewhere right in there
He was awesome
Because Brian was able to jump in and take on all the clothing
Work the sourcing that production in the design the merchandising
Which freed me up
To work on the marketing
The technology making sure the fundraise was coming along
The Limited hiring that we were doing
Customer service
And we were just jamming it was an incredible time
So
I mean end of story
Blake Fairy Tail ending
Right I mean
That's amazing boy here's the thing
Which is having 2 L
Two Founders in there I think
If it's hard to get more complicated as we grow
And Annette
That then became the challenge of
Who makes the decision
More complicated between you and Brian
Exactly
What was going on
So I remember this
Debate about what to do after pants I think we've spent
At some point maybe a year-and-a-half just focus on pants we started thinking about the next product category
And Brian was excited about swimsuits
And
I was excited about shirts
And there was really good rationale behind both
Until Weaver
We are in conflict over business decisions like that and then on a
Personal level what I realize is once you get into a Business Partnership
With a friend
The Friendship gets totally sublimated
The Business Partnership
So a lot of the stuff that you used to talk about or do
You don't have time to do cuz you got to work on this little growing baby
Company
And so it went from what was really fun
And kind of the
Laissez-faire world of friendship where you talk
About the things you want to talk about it and do whatever is fun
And support each other when things are difficult and it actually flipped that it takes away all the fun
The support that you need your no longer going to get
From that person
Except for very fortunate friends and business partners where can
And all the magic
Can come together
And then press it just became talking about big decisions at the company in
Frequently not seeing
Not seeing eye-to-eye and so it really it Unwound how you resolved that conflict cuz we were 50/50 Park
Partners
You know I have the title of CEO but Brian
Had a ton of business acumen
And so it really was a partnership of equals and it becomes difficult to figure out who makes the call
And
And how are you personally, though it was it was it like waiting on you or did you fly
Like sleepless nights I got depressed
So it turns out I have a propensity clinically for depression and so I got to the place
Swear I kind of had to fake it at work that I was doing okay but drag myself out of bed and come to the office
And kind of put on a show yeah it was super tough to navigate that cuz you're you're definitely on
Display in a small company so what was the office
Environment like like where their days were you and Brian were just
Not speaking or was it just like clipped conversation or what
I thought we were doing a pretty good job of talking in private and then
Presenting a unified front right out of the way you talk about you know parents and kids and then
Then I got a call from one of our investors and he said I heard that you and Brian are fighting Ally from your
Wow how did that happen
He said that's really bad
And I said you know what do I do and he said
You got to come and get to the bottom of what's causing that and it'll get to a place where
Where you can work together and
Now is the beginning of a process of figuring out your how do you resolve it
I cannot imagine
That because you have this
Business that
Rolling in the
It's exciting and you can start to see where this might be headed
But
The whole thing could I also unravel like
There was a
You must have thought in your mind
Maybe this
Crash and Burn
He was a little
Different than that
In that I thought you know bonobos is going to make it and it's got to make it it was more
Should I leave
Worship Brian Lee
Because I thought the company was going to do
Fine it was just
If we needed at Clear CEO
But you had come to this conclusion in your mind or maybe Brian had to that
You were not going to be able to
To do this together
Yeah I didn't have the ability to do it just based on the
Depression in
Someone said Hey Siri I see a therapist
11 Lisa and I I had some
Shame or embarrassment around that
At that time and I finally said I got to go do it so you did
I did
And you probably were so busy like you had to pry car about that time as well
Yeah I used to take a taxi
Uptown
Random part of the Upper West Side
And do work calls on the way there and then went saw this therapist and we were a few sessions in and she said handy
Are you in touch with anger
And I said anger
What's anger
And
And that was the beginning of this realization like hey if you're if you actually are
Or you have an emotion
You've got to express it
Because if it's sublimated she goes you know sublimated anger
Can become depressed
And so that was when I realized actually gosh I'm angry about a lot of these Dynamics
And
And we've got to figure something out
2 going through this antenna
Trying to work through
Your depression and also
Related to that depression obviously was was
What was clearly a
The beginning of a breakup
With
Your co-founder
Friend
What happened how did you
Solve this
So
It was a very
Bad way to do it
Probably speaking to the challenges I had with difficult conversations in Candor in person but I wrote Brian a longing
Right basically said luck I think one of us should become the chairman the other be the CEO
And I'll take either side of the trade
And the CEO can run the day today and run the company and the chairman can focus on external work
That was how the conversation started was through that
Open it up
And then one day
We are in the office I'm supposed to work on Saturdays and just get stuff done at the office and
One day I just asked him I said hey
Would you be willing to step aside
You don't give in
Giving everything is going on in
He got a little teary and he looked at me and he said
Yeah
It which was so weird cuz I had envisioned that conversation so many times and was so terrified to have it
And he was just
Unbelievably
Dignified
About the whole thing
And that was when I learned you learn a lot about a person
By the way they leave something that they love
Yeah I mean it
It speaks to
His
Ampersand
Kiki is that he
Had the foresight to know that
One of you
Had to go
And
He was willing to be the one
It was
An unbelievable GIF time and he gifted
The company
Did he had originally
Conceived of
Tumi
To this day
The Loyalty that I feel to him for having done that
An end then the fact that afterwards it
It's difficult
Write that friendship is
Has been eviscerated by that business issues
And
It took many years
Before we could
Sit down in
Have dinner and
Go to Cubs games together and see you've reconciled to bed by this point you reckon
Yeah I think so
If you could do it all over again
With Brian
Did you think
You guys
Could have worked
Through those things
I don't think
Unless I
Could have been more enlightened
At the time about how to
How to do it
I think we were both
Zoe
Young and in some ways insecure and trying to prove ourselves in
You know in some regards I think
Arrogant I I think that it was going to be hard at that stage of both of our Lives to figure it out
But I would I wouldn't do it any other way
You know the way that it we did it was how it had to be done
You know Brian went out and built another company called Trunk Club and did an amazing job with that
And he's got to
Amazing Stories
And so I'm so grateful to him that he enabled bonobos Thrive and gave me the opportunity to continue to build it
To Sabrina leaves
This is 2009 and your
Your laugh I guess is that is a CEO is a top decision maker
2008 was the
Was the co-founder
Separation
Thought that would
And all this
Depression I thought that would be the worst year of my life
2009 was far worse
Because I couldn't I could no longer blame anything on Brian
Had to blame it on myself
When we come back in just a moment so Andy capp's bonobos alive despite
Mistake after mistake after mistake
How I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
To design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts
And features including e-commerce functionality
The and mobile app
Squarespace also offer
Chris built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this
Best from NPR
So it
It's the beginning of 2009
Andy just went through the
Hardest year of his life
Co-founder Brian spaly left the company
An enemy is now a loan
Top
It's not
Too dramatic to say that
Company
Was in a bit of a
Prices
It was a scary year I thought I was good hiring in a bunch of people I'd hired didn't workout
I thought that I was good at fundraising and we were running out of money like how close were you to
Insolvency
I flew to
Silicon Valley one day from New York
Because
Are then had to finance told me that we weren't going to make payroll we had enough cash in the bank I thought
Make payroll but then we had a guest promises supplier through a letter of credit
And we were about
8 days away from that make
Payroll which is not an inspiring moment for your employees
And I went to
Hertz Rent-A-Car in San Francisco
To rent a car and I swiped the card and it was due
Decline
Yeah
Swipe my personal credit card which which was
Somehow still solvent spite of all the debt that I had and I
Drove to a Starbucks and sat down with
With
Someone who knew about the company in
Explain to him our growth and said we definitely need some more money I didn't I didn't
Say where we needed the next week and he offered to invest $300,000 in the business
And then I had another 90 conversations like that over the course of an ex
Couple months and piece together another round and you know we ended up raising
Our first eight million from you know over
Over a hundred and twenty investors
So we just pieces
Together
Cuz you had a meal
The trajectory looked good on you were still
Presumably growing every month but I have to imagine that
Sales were not able to fund the business
It was not properly
Yeah we we did 2 million in that first year and
Kind of full operations in a way
And then for
In 09
And then
We were heading towards
7 or so
I think we made one of the Cardinal errors that an entrepreneur makes which is the second Angel round that we raise we re
Race at too high of a price
And actually Joe was
Pretty upset about this
I actually think I wrote the email to
Control that
Was a condescending email on summerguard around supporting the company in
It was the dumbest email I've ever written
And Joel then said he wanted to sell his shares
Created a whole issue for ourselves
And then ultimately
Ultimately figure out a way to get the round done in
And Joel didn't invest
So you bet mean
Your Patron
Like the guy who
Was your first
Investor
He's out he's out of that next round
He was out
Wow that's a big deal cuz he was like a mentor to you
It was a terrible
It was
Was really really bad and so I flew out to apologize to him and I said I really screwed this up
I said what what you consider
Now that we have this discussion with you
You consider ever invest me again and he said look not right now but maybe
Let's talk later
Infer
The next round that I raised
I went out and saw me I said look up
I've learned so much from you I learned a ton from you and terms
How badly I handled that
Situation
You actually tell me the truth and hold me to account would you consider coming on to our board
Not only investing but coming under the board and he said yes
Well
Aside from raising money
We're still
Running a company
It was both a
Men's fashion company any technology
E-commerce
This is not
Brick-and-mortar stuff
So how is the technology side
Bonobos
How is that working
It was a huge challenge
Cuz at the time the New York
Tech ecosystem was pretty small or lease it felt small to me
And
At the same time it was really hard to attract talented
You know software engineer
They were all in in the Bay Area
They were in the Bay Area or you know they wanted to work at a company where the core Enterprises technology versus a pan
Yeah
It was really a a rift
Between the folks who worked on
Technology in the folks who worked
On the rest of the business it wasn't
There was a
Battle over the soul of the company
You know was it a technology company or was it a
Menswear company
But it was both
Which is the challenge I mean
If I had been a better leader maybe I could have figured out how to do that you don't we open an office
In Palo Alto and it turned out to be a catastrophic error
Because all of a sudden now you got your New York office and then the technology people were in
Exactly and if you think tribalism and human nature is still alive within one off
When you have people in different places with different ideas about what the saw the company is and you
Increase the expense and by the way you're now competing to hire software Engineers with
Facebook and Netflix and the pay is higher you know all those ingredients came together and it was clear
Clear after about a year that we had hired the people but it wasn't working
It deepens the divide between let's just call it tek in retail and
It's hard enough to be a good CEO when you've got five days a week in the same office
All of a sudden you're two days a week in each office
You were flying back and forth
Between New York and Palo Alto
Yeah
And you then you're letting people down on both sides
In so I'm I'm trying to imagine you as a CEO
Going back and forth and trying to kind of
I guess keep everybody
Be happy
But the tech
The tech folks write the engineers like they have knowledge that
You just didn't have your not a
Attack guide
It's not your
Like skill set
Did you feel like you couldn't just
Tell them what to do
I don't think you can tell anyone in this life what to do
I mean I think you can try
But human beings are a gallon species we don't
Authority
Until what you want to do is inspire people yeah
And you want to set a common Vision in contacts
Shared values and then
There are times where you have to step in intervene
And make important difficult calls
But
What it was was it was clear to me
Oh my God
Did the organizational Harmony at the company was being destroyed
Baidu
Cross Coastal
Conflict
And so
In some regard it became pretty straight
Forwarding
I brought to the board and they couldn't believe that we were going to pull the plug your in you went to the board and you said
I want to pull the plug on this West Coast office
I said this isn't working
And they said what
How do you know in a year
Yeah when we give it two or three
And I said look this is becoming more costly this is becoming Harder by the day
The culture is deteriorating
This is just wrong
In spending more time is going to only make it
More expensive
More doubling down on a sunk cost
Let's
Lots of Jessica lesbian Electronics here and let's adjust course
How could you do that I mean
Your core bit of your business depended on these Engineers like
You are work
Are a technology company to I mean
How do you just say let's pull the plug on it and we'll figure it out me that's
It seems like
A lot of stuff in this afternoon at world
Pull the plug on the whole division
I was really scared
But what I've learned
In 11 years of doing this is
Sometimes when you're the most afraid
Is when you're making
One of the
Most important decisions
Right like if it's not scary
It's not hard
And I think ultimately what we
We need to Value more in this life for everyone not just Hunters is courage
The courage to look at yourself honestly
Look at the decisions you're making honestly
And save yourself you know what
That was my fault
I got that wrong I'm not going to blame anyone else
I'm going to take responsibility for it and I'm going to fix it
It's 2013
Clos DES office on West Coast you have
Almost no
Engineering staff left
You got no
Chief technology officer I'm assuming at this point either right
No so what did you do
We we got
You have two engineers in the state of scientist to relocate
Literally I remember sitting in a
At a coffee shop in Palo Alto
Just back
I mean literally begging
Being like will you please come to New York at least for 1 to 2 years
And so it really didn't work out and I'm not I don't even want to think about running that play in retrospect
You know without those two came
So once you kind of
Recover from that account
Pek
In a mini
Disaster or more than a disaster
And things started to stabilize first
What is the company
Profitable was it making money in 2013/2014
Not yet
But we were we were massively turning the corner towards break even
I would be free
Freaking out like I mean
How do you how are you able to come to stay optimistic and were you just looking at projections and saying
Stay optimistic what makes you think
Did I was optimistic I was
I was
Defiant in the face of
A terrifying reality
And ultimately you just
Got to Believe
It's almost religious it is religious
It's faith
And there's a really good saying I don't want to say this is true cuz I've been lucky
But that
Companies don't die
Because the companies fail they die cuz the entrepreneur gives up
And that was the approach just keep the lights on
Keep growing
Keep learning
And that's what we did so what was the thing that
That enabled you to turn the corner just more customers more awareness
More what
I think was actually more Focus so what what really changed the company
Was the move from single channel to molt
Meaning
The build-out of the relationship with Nordstrom in the reinvention of the retail store with the guy shot model
Can this was an incredible paradox
Cuz everyone was betting on e-commerce
Venture capital is flowing into econ
Countless companies were rising and falling
And the irony of our business was after years of being told
It wholesalers going away
And IT department stores were dying
Are most profitable business became Nordstrom
And our second most profitable where are retail stores
And those two businesses profits were funding losses from e-commerce
The wonderful paradox
To the way that we can see for the company
Yes I guess I guess we could we should
Explain this for people who have not been the shop cuz I've been doing guide shop in general you don't go in and then walk out with a pair of trousers
Right you go in and get
Did it
And then the trousers are sent to
Exactly it's
It's a bit to ship concept
So when you think about our
This was another really fun board mean
Was
This debate around is this an e-commerce company or is this a menswear
Experience company
And I need the case and this is the people that funded the company with a view of e-commerce
Being at the core that our company was actually not an e-commerce company it was about serving this customer
If we could invent way to deliver the same level of fit and service in person
Then that would actually be consistent in a deepening of who we are getting us closer to go to Who We Are
2R torsoless a business versus getting away from it
What's the question was why you do that with physical inventory if the whole model of bonobos
Is offering a lot more sizing
And a lot more fits in a lot more colors
If you look at are chinos business
We got 36 waist and inseam combinations
Four different it silhouettes
And we might be running 15 to 20 colors
Ticketmaster
4 to 5000.
How do you possibly stock that so that the incredible Insight was
You don't
You don't stock it you create a clothing store that has no clothing
And that was the inside
Which is the customer doesn't need it right away in that flew in the face of
Everything everyone in retail told me
From the traditional industry
Instant gratification
It turns out for a busy customer that's just not true
If they get great service which is what you can put out
If you ripped it inventory out
You put the service in
It actually is a much more magical combination in terms of dollars per square foot productivity
And customer
Delight you know as measured by net promoter score
Yeah
As you can as you start
To turn a corner
I guess you also
All star tattoo
Attract more and more investors
And more and more capital
Fuel the growth
What does it mean for for your own state
Did you quit will you just getting more more diluted and
Did you care was that important to you
Oh wow this is a fun question what it would it leads to
You know I think a lot of times as a Founder you're thinking I'm going to go do this for 2 years and see if it works and then I'm going to do it
Four five
Which country lies is it takes a decade to build a real
And so what happens is
After four years here you fully vested
And then you got a debate which is
Stay where you are
Take on more Capital get diluted
What's happened to all the other shareholders
Or ask for more equity
One day I woke up and said you know what
I'm going to ask for more I want to get my steak back
How to more meaningful Evelyn and I had this really unusual
A zero-sum Game standoff
To the board and said I want more equity
Seems like a fair request and what do they say
They said no
Pittsburgh
And you know
Said hey like you need to work
You need to work for the sheriff so you've got
And then you know ultimately
I just
Warm down and I got some alternative perspectives
From people in the venture capital.
Company space and said hey this is this feels right to me
Was there a mean in a weave interview lots of entrepreneurs to move take on capitalism
Don't to bootstrap in then
No sell it for hundreds of millions of dollars
What as you saw the value of the company go up
But you're
Part of it
You know
Going down
Did you
Did you care or did you say you know there's a certain point I mean
A certain number
Is just a number and
That's great
You know
If this works
A little bit of money
Oh my God I thought
I'll be so lucky
Tav
Have any of this
And I think it's warped to live in a world where
Let's say
You're going to make
$29
Difference between 20 million dollars in $109
It's not clear
Yeah
Right
Enough for me
The only things that excess Capital are good for
Is getting money
The family
And loved ones
Who were part of Ginyu to where you were my case you know an immigrant mom
In high school history teacher dad
That's number one number two is
Investing in other entrepreneurs and companies number three is making political contributions if you want to influence the future in our forest being phone
Don't drop it
Now I'd love throwing some nice seats
The Cubs game 2
But the idea that you're trying to optimize for making
And more than yeah yeah it's just
I don't get it I think you get Warped cuz you start to heal about hear about what other Founders are making in
You hear about
You start today
Is the human problem I restart a circle with people wear
You sure to live in these bubbles
Where people have so much money
Yeah and then I would just cut back to hey when I graduated business school I have $3,000 in the bank and $160,000
Mars attack
And I started the company with that balance sheet that was scary
End
So
I tried to stay true to that and think instead about how do I make sure everyone else thinks
How do I make sure that our shareholders from every round
You know that we're dropping to the right on the post-money valuation and ultimately going to make people money how do I make sure the management
Tina's enough stock
Employees have stock
And I'm going to be fine
Yeah
Speaking out of two sides my mouth is on the one hand that's what my philosophy is on the other hand I did say look look I want to be inside
I do feel like at the end of the day
You know owning two or 3% of the company is probably not commensurate with the work put in
And bolts word of is my fault that we had to raise so much capital
It also is
The price of innovation
If you're the first mover in the degenerative brand space and you're going to invent that model
I can't go back in time and undo this company on 20 to 30 million
If it's what I think it is
Would take knowing what I now know
Wow did we get to have fun learning everything we did and why was it gratifying to be
To be the Pioneer in the category in a freezing lot of capital is the price of that
Northern that's what the price of it was
So you guys
You know you finally turned a corner
And you're growing
And this brand is out in the world
And then what
Seem to hit the rest of the
Piano
What team is the rest of us fall into
It's like a lightning was
In 2017 you sold to Walmart
How did that happen today
Did they approach you guys do they say Hey you know we want to buy you did you go to them where you did you
Get to a point where you side okay
We got to find a buyer because I'm going to pay these investors
I was at a wedding
And I was talking to you
Friend
And
He knew one of our Angel Investors
And that angel investor said you know bonobos is great but I wonder if I'll ever
Paid
And I think at that point he'd invested
Eight or nine years ago in the very first round
And that wasn't the only reason but once you got Venture investors who been in
For 7 years and Angel Investors who've been in for 10
It just would be wrong
Chin. Make other people money
So
I felt like we were at that stage where the company that get ready for the next stage we had
Discovered our soul as a consumer retail company
And we needed to learn from people that we're good at taking some retail companies public
That's the point ride and then
At the eleventh hour
I got a phone call to do a reference
And I get the reference and then the individual who's calling me
Said how are things going
This is someone that I have a colleague from
From way back and I said look we're in the middle of this process and
Hey why don't you come talk to us
He worked at jet.com
And I was like a new
Genderbent acquired by Walmart
Denmark lorry for years
And every time I saw him we are game-changing for me a game-changing conversation
Founder of jet prank to probably the best third-party e-commerce entrepreneur
On East Coast
I said you know what I know Mark II can't understand how
How would Walmart
And bonobos be a fit
Doesn't make sense
I just talked to him and I thought you know what every time I've talked to Mark I found him to be a bit of a Jedi
And we sat down and it was amazing I didn't think Mark cared about Brands and then we had this incredible mind meld
Did the future of e-commerce was going to look a little bit like
History of Netflix
Set a
I formed it with streaming other people's content
Distributing other people's content would vertically integrate and start to develop their own
Proprietary
Right and Mark and I might melt it that was going to happen Commerce and that
Bonobos was going to be
The brand
EE.
And that we would go and
Lo and behold that long
Set long dreamed of multi-brand vision
Was going to come to fruition in the least expected way I could have ever imagined
Which is with the power of Walmart and Walmart's balance sheet behind it
How long does it take
Before
You close a deal
Yeah
It took months
And it was made Tricky by the fact
That the deal leaked
In the middle of the process
And because Walmart
The public company
World's largest and revenues I couldn't sing
Do you have to walk
Go to the office and show up like nothing was going on
Well that's out that wasn't the approach Alton
Because people you know the quote on quote
Water cooler talk was
Channing and then there were messages on slack saying
This is
This is a
Catastrophe for the brand
With no
Walmart acquiring bonobos
I got it
Like I wouldn't
Didn't have the
Understanding of the strategy in the way that Walmart and jet.com
Transforming
E-commerce for the company
It wouldn't make sense and so I had to call a very strange meeting
This is before you close a deal this
Tweaking out in
Italy
I was out of the office
I was actually working on the deal elsewhere
I rushed back to the office and
I got everyone together
And I said we're going to have a very unusual meeting
Here's what I can tell you
I love this company at least as much as you do
You know me
I would never guide us to doing anything that wasn't
In our self-interest is Brandon is a company and its shareholders and employees of the bran
What has been published is not
A fact
It's not
An announcement
It's speculation
We have not
Decided our path
In our process
And when we have news
Versus rumors
Of course you'll be the first to know
When we have news
And in the meanwhile please
Get back to work
It was the weirdest man ever at everyone just got up
I went back to work and I'm sure the conversation continue
But it just the energy change by directly addressing it
It felt like
Wow that
That turns out that just killing people
Like it is the truth
In the trees was we had decided at that moment
And then it I think it was another couple months before we actually could announce
There's a big difference in going to Walmart and buying a pair of jeans and going and buying
The premium brand right like
There were people who said wait a minute now I own Walmart closet full of Walmart close
You know why I can't blame people for reacting that way
No not at all so we anticipated
Meaningful blowback and if you go back and look at what I wrote at the time
I was pretty direct the day of
The day of the announcement around the future of an oboes
And I said look I think a lot of people are going to be
By this
In
It was fasting for 72 hours there's a really big
Reaction in an availability bias of the most vocal people
And then
In a business return to normal the vast majority of people
Don't think about the stuff that much everyday
And for me
But I couldn't say to them is
Hey been almost gets to continue to exist
Write like
Because we get home you know how hard that is actually like
Security outcome
Walmart
Reportedly
Paide 310 million dollars
Griffin elbows which is
Impressive mean it's a lot of money
How did you respond to that number does it
Didn't mean anything to you where you
Proud that you got to that point
Or
Was it just a
Signature at the bottom of a sheep
I'm so proud it's so hard to do that
So hard to build a company that
Ends up being worth something
Really meaningful
It was just a staggering number
And I was so grateful that we got that done and got a chance to let you know there very few things in this life you can look at and say we did that
In selling a company is one of those moments
I'm so I'm so proud
We got the chalk that one up in the baguette
We get to keep going
And I really safe home
You know people ask why are we doing this
And part of it is hey I'm excited about the strategy but part of it is
We get to exist now
If we do our jobs well
For a long time
Maybe maybe 50 years or more
Maybe a hundred years bonobos will be around
And not
That's rare
And I always ask
What's the question
Most offensive
Question
AB to the people interview with just how much of
What
Happened to you and and the creation of bonobos in it
Success was because of
You and your talent and
What was the decision you made and how much of it was because of
Black
Luck is a concept that
I thought of in a straightforward way
For a while
And then when I converted to Judaism last February I became acquainted with this concept of
Kismet
Which is
I am pronouncing right probably but it's kind of the intersection of luck and serendipity
And maybe even
Some measure of Destiny I don't want to go that far
Cuz I still don't know why really bad things happen to good people
So
I think you got to be open in life
To the way that the universe is trying to help you
The people who love you quotes you just listen to them
And cultivate relationships with
People who are direct will tell you what you
Need to hear
If it's not what you want to hear
The same thing that accompany the people on the way
Your board your investors your employees
Kuno as a collective
What to do
More so than you but in combination
You can unlock
So I think if you bring self-awareness and you bring empathy and you bring
Positivity and you bring intellectual honesty and courage
Ultimately try to make
I think you can influence a lot
But I would have tribute
I would attribute
This outcome in this company
At the end of the day to three things
To the quality of the
People
Around me on all fronts
To the hard work of those people who really believed in this and made this happen
The team
And then a healthy healthy dose of
Self-awareness in the pursuit of
Qismat
So you're not a believer
I am
I am I think that the two
That you're
The two
Really big things that influence your life
The family that you're born into
And
I don't know what to call it that your DNA the genetic stock who you know who
How you show up as
Is a creature as a human being
You have no control over those two things
Until I feel like in life I was dealt if we call it luck
You know I don't want to say pocket aces cuz I don't know what
How to think about my genetic makeup
But I was born into the most incredible family ever and I was given the best
Of all opportunities wanting for nothing
Occasionally experientially
The best mom the best dad the best sister and I've got the best wife so with all that and all the amazed
Using groups of people I've been around I owe it to everyone
To do something
And at the end of the day the credit goes to them
In so many ways
Eddie Dunn co founder of bonobos and he now runs the company as an employee
Walmart Children's Apparel company started with a sister Monica is called Monica and an
Andy Andy and Brian story is now used as a case study at Stanford Business School
Including the email and he's sent to Brian that
Eventually led to Brian leaving the company
It's a sort of what to do and what not to do guide for new students
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the thing
Your building
The first
A quick thanks to one of our sponsors
Airtable
A cottontail
Cattle tracker fabric sourcing system product roadmap
Post production pipeline
All built
What are table
Get $50
Credits today
By signing up at airtable.com built
Hey thanks so much for sticking around me
Timeout for how you built that and today story starts
Skin Seattle
Where Amy and Brady King run a construction
Company together he's a general contractor so he builds the buildings and then
I manage all the business side of things
And a few years ago they were looking for new ways to expand
We were we chatting about new businesses in inventing and coming up with new ideas and
What are the things that
Your other people feel like man
Everything has been invented
You know everything's been developed you know at times and that's that someone when you go that's
I can't possibly be true
It's already began thinking on his days as a firefighter
He's seen a lot of really bad housing options for people who were displaced by those fires
Is there floods or other natural disasters we talked about Katrina I think which is probably the
The most obvious example of Disaster Response and kind of failure of housing PA
People in those moments
The start of the spark an idea Amy and Brady wondered how they could design a better shelter something
Prefabricated
Portable secure
And private
Shelters
The cat house one family
Idealistic
Drop these in the neighborhoods after a tornado goes through like dropping into your neighborhoods in all the neighbors can
Live in them for the first
However many
Your weeks or months and rebuild
Bear neighborhood together
And heal each other so what are background in construction
Amy and Brady started building a prototype
Which basically looks like a small white square said it had Windows electricity and
Laws that allowed for light
To come in its eno8 feet
Wide 8 feet long and about 10 feet tall
It pops up in about 20 minutes no tools required
And all of the panels are manufactured here and
Made out of the material that's mold mildew and rot resistant so once I hit a working model Amy and Brady went to a tree
Rachel where they met
Get first client
Our very first customer was the city of Tacoma and actually
The group that purchased from us was
Their Emergency Management Department in the spring of 2017 and Tacoma Washington
Adjust declared a state of emergency around the homeless crisis in their City
And even though Amy and Brady design their shelters for natural disasters
Their own employees help them realize why these shelters could have an entirely new purpose that's because
Lots of the people in their construction crew
I spent time in jail and I've been homeless in the past
And they were saying you know when we were homeless there's the option to go to a shelter but
Family can't stay together and I thought if we were homeless and they said okay your husband has to go over here and you and your
Your daughters are going to go over here I'd say
No way I'm not doing that we're keeping our family together
So now Indian Brady's construction business
It not only employees those who were previously incarcerated or homeless their product directly serve that
Same population we know we haven't
Specific Mission and that mission is to create jobs for people who are traditionally marginalized in the employment
World and our Focus population is primarily people who are transitioning out of incarceration or who have criminal justice involved
Women in their past
As well as people coming off the streets out of homelessness
Today Amy and Bradys clients are mainly cities looking to provide housing for the homeless there's a Humanity
Indeed out there
And if we can provide a solution to fill it
Then we should at least
See if it's something that we can do
Any Brady Kings product
It's called the pallet shelter if you want to find out more about the palace shelter or hear previous episodes that you are
Marcus Paige how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Got npr.org we love hearing what you're up to and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
If you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this our shows produced this week but Rachel Falkner with music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
It's also to be a venkat JC Howard nor could see nieva grandson has Michigan for Jeff Rogers
Our intern
I'm guy Raz and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
This campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com