Quickly before we start to show
We got another live show coming to Washington DC on some
September 12th
The Lincoln Theater
I'll be talking with Tristan Walker founder of Walker & Company brands
Best beauty products
Devil
Forum what's going to be announcing two more live shows on the East Coast
Soon
And don't forget we still have a few tickets available for the how I built this Summit in San Francisco in
October
The Summit
Supported by America
Express at The Summit
You'll be able to hear and probably even meet some of the world
Greatest entrepreneurs Founders Beyond companies
Instagram / JetBlue away Jeni's Ice Cream
And many many more
The Summit is a man
Incredible opportunity to connect with
Other builders and hear from experts on how
Grow and scale your business
You can get tickets for both the DC live show and the Summit AT NPR presents
. org
And helped
To see you there
So the meeting that we went to with the new buyer
The first meeting tonight with the first meeting I think I was nursing I remember being in that room having a baby
Baby and just presenting this woman was I don't know in her late twenties and
She was not responding to anything that we are saying in a positive manner
So it was a hard meeting
And without them we were sunk
Running PR
How I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist and the stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Rising on the show today
Tell chance with a black panther inspired Susan Griffin black loyals
And then grow that idea
EO products
What are the most successful independently owned Natural Body Care
A word that gets thrown out a lot by Venture capitalists and Rich folks
Invest in startups
Is scale
If you've ever tried to raise money for a business
Probably found yourself seated across the table from someone who asks
Taking a scale this thing
Really asking was
How to get a girl your company into a
Billion dollar Venture so I can get a hundred X return on my money
Scale
Big profits for investor
Engrossed
Only goal that really matter
I'm more interested in a
Slow sustainable growth model
Which is why they avoid venture capital
Binky Barnes fanart of Patagonia
Or Seth Thibodeaux
Tofurky or Kim Jordan of New Belgium Brewery
All of those companies are independently owned
Beholden to neither shareholders nor venture capitalist
Same thing with a company whose story you are about to
Because EO products is in a way
The opposite of scale
Brad and Susan Griffin black have never taken any Venture money
And I never had much money of Their Own
So the story of EO products is a story of a Slow Burn
Nearly 30 years of building up a brand one product at a time
Fighting for every store and eventually and sustainably
Growing into one of the most recognized natural body
Are brands in the US
The company does about 50 million dollars in Revenue a year for 30 years ago
What you started the company
Susan Griffin black was a single mom raising her son in San Francisco
But that's not the most amazing thing about the story the company itself was barely scraping by
Buy Ford's first 15 years
And once it actually started to take off
Unraveled because the co-founders split up
Their marriage
Collapsed
Will get there
For now
What started the years before Brad and Susan Matt
In the late 1980s
They were both living in San Francisco
Brad just moved there from the East Coast
After leaving a job in computer sale
My initial motivation was to move to Australia yet this is
Pre-internet and I didn't know anyone in Australia so I had a couple friends in San Francisco
And you know I sold everything
I guess I had
Two or three thousand dollars in the bank account
And moved in with one of them who was on Haight Street
And what did you do
We started a clothing company
Called
Maniac
And Maniac is spelled as in the state of Maine right Maine - IAC end
You know we
Hell
The space of
I like rock
Climbing and mountain biking
This was a time 88 it late 80s
Where the whole
Activewear thing came alive
Stussy
Mossimo
And so
It's activewear and then that tied into our lifestyle
So then we would mountain bike and we would rock climb
During the day and run the business
And then we would go out and party at night
All the time wearing our clothes which
Like who doesn't want to show off what they do
And if you make your own clothes and we made our own clothes and
We would sell our own clothes
I mean much of it
Via ignorance
And Blake
How is the business doing
The business was kind of secondary
2 lifestyle
We were living at Large
Entrepreneurs in San Francisco and
This is before the.
Cam internet
Sing head and it was very vibrant a little
Gritty
Yet
Artistic
And
We could really own it and
You know we would peddle our Wares and we sold to
Nordstrom
And we sold to the
Hardcore rock climbing
Shops yet we didn't really ever make money and when we had the Opera
Trinity to make money
We just never
I don't know if we were mature enough were that we
Saw the opportunity that was
In front of us yet
We didn't make money
Around this time I guess
You also had a
The clothing store in in San Francisco
Yeah
It was a great little store
End
We got written up in the chronicle
Probably within the first couple of weeks and so that gave us a great start and
You know
The part of the local design community and
It was a really
Vibrant time
That time of your married to
Lawyer
Yeah you know we were I think we were in an apartment by that time in the marina
Passes the bar and goes to work for a big Law Firm
And
Things were more much cushier
Eventually
We went from the marina to a very nice building in Pacific Heights
He was working really hard I had a store on Sutter Street
Mike was born my son was born in 1986
And
All looked very good it didn't feel very good to me but it looked
Why does it feel good
I don't know I
I guess I had fallen into what was considered at the time
The Yuppie life
I'm a free spirit and I really liked the whole heart scene which I wasn't really doing much of anymore and
All of sudden it was like waking up one day and
Feeling like I was at the wrong party
Like I didn't really
No more
Play relate to the people who are there and
I had this like a doorman
A kid
And a French
Nanny
And
It all look good and it just
Started to feel
Fragmented
My conversations our conversations were
Pretty stilted and got very tense because I really felt like
Bill had sold out and he was hurt on the wrong side of things
I just felt like
It just wasn't my life
And I couldn't make it my life
So
When Mark was
Two and a half
Have we split
Yuan Bill split
So you left behind
The Nanny the doorman in Pacific Heights the
Fancy apartment in and
You left behind
He had much to my mother's dismay
Imagine
So so what about your business I mean
Did you
Continue to run your business
I did for a short amount of time and then I sold that to my
Partner at the time for $12,000
So you're now a single mom
And what it was your plan what did you say
Think you wanted to
Well I wasn't
Stressed financially
I took a job
Because I could see that I would get stressed financially
So
I ended up
Doing some Consulting
True friends in the clothing business and helped a few friends start
Beer companies
Andam
In 90
Hi
Took a job at asprey working for the late Doug Tompkins
Oh yeah it's a no I mean a legendary guy I think he was at one of the founders of
The North Face
Yes and originally he was an asprey was it was a huge grin definitely in the eighties nineties and still
Yeah
Alright so this is like
The early nineties
Both of you Brad answers both of you are in San Francisco
Both of you are working Kennedy apparel business
At one point Susan you having to go into
I can do any bread store in
Is that worth for the two of you
Yeah it was their warehouse actually and all of the products were there
And I remember
Brandeis shokan
He was cute
He was smart I like them right away
But you like seem like a good guy
It was really resonance right off the bat
And after
Susan left I got her business card and this was
Is June of 1988
I wrote her
Dear Susan
You know thank you for your time
We just
Connected
And
We kind of stayed in touch
She would help us a little bit or I would help her
Really
Struggling entrepreneurs and
Were able early on to engage with each other like
Shelly Scott me
And I always
Got her and
And even now you know I mean it's like
In 30 years and
She can start a sentence almost and I can see
But it really started that way
Respect
You guys right away were attracted to each other
Yeah
But you guys were not dating at that point
The richest
Hanging out with a friend we are friends already so you guys
Start meeting app Susan you are working at asprey
This company that really was just like
I remember every
When wearing a binder of Benetton sweatshirt or innisfree sweatshirt
Oh yes
And
Also at the time you know during that time
Doug was very interested in
Transforming the company into a more sustainable Environmental
Company and looking at all the processes that were involved in manufacturing and
At that time there were just so many incredible people coming through whether it was
You know David Brower the environmentalist
Or
Yvonne chenard or Anita Roddick from The Body Shop
I mean it was a portal for me
Into really
Thinking about and looking at
Sustainability
And so
I had met Anita Roddick from the body shop and she was opening
Franchises
In Northern California and
And I loved her but I wasn't totally
Crazy about
Products
I've always been a product person
I feel like I'm you know I've been ahead of it and trust my instincts I think
Eventually anyway
So when I see something
That I like even if it's like a little bit off
As soon as people learn about it and understand it they'll like it too
Pegasus all couldn't begins
To come together
For you when
When asprey sent you the London
To go buy something like a buying trip
Is that
Is it right
Well yes you know we would go to trade shows you know fabric trade shows it was the way to
Certified interpret Street fashion in
And up-and-coming trends
Yeah
And so
I was in London on a buying
And I was sort of running through the Covent Garden area
And I
Ran into this little store and ice
Was just
Taken
I want it smelled like
Moussy store
Neal's yard remedies
Yeah right next to Neal's yard Dairy yeah yeah
So
Stairs
You can see an herbalist or an acupuncturist
Homeopath
And then
You would come downstairs and get your prescriptions filled in this little apostle
And so the reason that it smelled the way it
Smelled
Was
Because of
The essential oil
And the herbs
That they stock
So I picked up this little bottle of
Lavender essential oil
And I inhaled and everything check
Like I
I knew what I wanted to do with my
My life you know the body shop Sardis
Help me pay attention to that segment of
Product in the market and then
This was like oh no this is
Wow
This must have been like totally mind-blowing right is essential oil still kind of hippy dippy right it's not
Not mainstream
No no it was very hippy-dippy
Yeah and you go in there and this was like nothing you would seen before you hadn't known about essential oils
You know around that time they were all those awful
You know candle stores and
All sorts of stores that you would go in and it would
Have a really synthetic coin smell
As did a lot of perfume most perfume right someone would get on that elevator and be like oh
Lord you know this was like
Being in
Beautiful garden you know I mean it reminded me of great parts of my childhood just like
Being in my at my grandma's
Watering tomatoes
Smell of lilacs
It was real
And it was very different in that store and what you're there and you're thinking
Cigarette do something with this like this is what I want to do
Yeah you know I had to sort of live that lifestyle
So I think them you know I was searching really
For what made sense and what was real and what had heart and meaning for me
And so that just opened up
A New Path
And something new to learn and I was very passionate about
Social like what did you do
Do that put additional I contact the founder and say
Hey I want to I want to work with you or like
Beer distributor or likes Elvis
In the US
Is that what happened
Yes and
She wouldn't talk to me until I worked in the store so it worked in the store for three days
Motioning
Romy Frazier
And she said you can work in the store
Before we talk
She said if you're interested
You know I mean the retail is the heart of what we're doing yell
I was you know mixing herbal tinctures and in the back room and
Doing all sorts of things and I loved it and
Amy met after and
Basically the idea was to open retail store
Bat in the US
And and you said around me I want to be your person doing this in the US
Yes
But let me just I just hate driving
Obviously you are super talented super smart and driven
Good like
You have no money
You had no
Access to it like
Immediate Capital you know track record
Selling essential oils in the US
Why would you even consider working with you
How you know she also was a small company they I think at the time they had a couple of
She could see how sincere and interested I was
And also you know from being in the clothing business I did have relationships
Swift
Buyers in
Cheeto
Merchandise managers
Owners of
Specialty store
Torso
I had some access to
Understanding distribution
So what did she say to you she said yeah go back to the US and let's
Do that song
But
Well essentially I tried to put a plan together for retail stores
And
I could see that that would never work
Because you needed people who were very well-versed in all of these alternative modalities in aromatherapy and
Homeopathy
And I was running out of money
So I thought
Best to wholesale
And
See who's interested who wants it and then
I could have them pay for half of the order I could import the product
Which I didn't
My garage in Potrero Hill
And then
Have the retailers who wanted it
Pay half up front
Then I deliver it and get the rest of the money to let
That's what I did
Alright so you go you're back in San Francisco
And by this time like
A 1992
You got a five year old
Kitten
Are you and Brad dating yet or not yet
We weren't really dating I think we were still good friends I think Brad had a girlfriend
And we would spend more time together because he was
I was in the neighborhood
And I was working out of my garage
And then he would
Brightest bike
Open the garage door and I have a little teeny office in there he would help with business plan and we would commiserate about
He was he was still in the clothing
And you were essentially trying to make this
Import
Business of essential oils work in Brad you remember like what
What did you think about this idea did you think all this is a no-brainer or you just like that one help don't help
Cuz I like her
It didn't happen that
Quickly
You know Susan had no money and I had left
What really I think sustained the relationship and made it
Exciting is
That
It was never a no-brainer and it still isn't after
30 years
But I was full-on in my clothing company and
We wanted to help out each other
And how did it work with rummy
Frasier
And you'll see our did you have to
Pay her up front and then she would ship you the oils or
Was it like a partnership or she just shipped it to you and didn't charge you
Place the bad like how does that work
We had Net 30 Terms
3 days
Yeah
I think maybe in the beginning it was 60
So she was basically selling you
The oils at that cost a little bit above cost
You were then marking it up a little bit and
And that was it was really was like a distributor
Relationship you weren't you weren't like
Equity partner
No
It was it was a separate entity and
Finances where
Completely separate
So how are you
Keeping us afloat meaning
You have to pay
Neal's yard in 30 days
How are you making out
Well I am
I raised a little bit of money
Come friends and family
So we'd have a little bit of a
Cushion
And also
Be able to increase
Inventory and AR accountant
Eventually had to get a space
In the same building where Brad's company was
Yes and so you running out of there and bread were you helping her with it
What kind of what was happening it on my side of things is that we
Decided to
Shut the business down Maniac Mania
And then that
Opened up
A pocket for me while you know what am I going to do and
Where we dating at that time
Probably yes
And
I had
Two or three opportunities
One was
I was going to open up a bungee jumping site in downtown San Francisco
And right and another opportunity was working for a
Sock company out of
Japan
And the third was working with Susan and and so our relationship started to develop
And
There just were opportunities
And we were good
Together and so that's
How
Our relation
Yeah we were selling Neal's yard and we had that we were making a few products
Neal's yard
Because it was
We wanted to learn how to make stuff
Right so we would make bath salts and
Anything that you could cold Max and then poor you were making it in a garage in San Francisco or you were
Place organisms well in the warehouse that we rented we have a small lab there and we are making
Do you think you and other people or will you by yourself
I had to employee
And a part-time book
Cuz we had
Several accounts by then and
Tell her
So we were learning how to make things
By hand
And I knew
Someone introduced me to the marketing person at Birkenstock
And she said why don't we do a little foot care kit like gift with
Purchase of like a little foot
Put salt and little foot soak
Until we did a prototype
And she gave us an order for $32,000
It was
320 for each gift box
Which meant
I had to
And then Brad came down the hall and I'm like how are we going to do 10th
You was like such the I Love Lucy show when you walked into her
Warehouse and
You know of course I saw the numbers
As well and I didn't know anything about it
Natural oils really I like how they smell
I know how to really make anything yet I can
How to figure out the most
Thanks you know with Maniac we
Made our own
Products and so I learn how to sew and
Learning these things from a Mechanicals aspect
Was pretty straightforward for me in terms of like okay well this is Jay
Just what you do
But just put them together
Let's make these 10000 kit
Yeah
He said
If we're not going to Phillies by hand we're going to you know jerry-rig this
Way to gravity feed and then will
Zelda bottles that way and
He had made gravity feed
Describe
What did what did that look like was it like a giant funnel that you just pour the salt in
You know really what we did is
We started from hand pouring
Into bottles
2 adding equipment
And
You know gravity feed is one of the ways but yeah it's really taking it from the funnel
And moving it to a machine
And then instead of one a minute
You have the ability to do a 10 minute or 10 minutes
And that was presumably game changer
For you
We never would have been able to
To fill that order now
Just like sprinkling it with little shovel I guess
Scoop
It wouldn't work because low
That wouldn't work now
Just a dressy me today if you want to figure out how to make
You know bath salts
What was it that you just go online right in like 1993
How do you figure out how to make this stuff like you just buy a bunch of salt and add essential oils to it
But we did learn a lot
From Neal's yard cuz they were small
Picture so
We could
Suss out the processes
I was very
Interested in studying aromatherapy with a bunch of different people
So I understood the
Properties of essential oils in the blending of essential oils
TheCHIVE
I understood how to do that
If you go online right now you can
See where the at home person can
Create sort of the easier
Thanks and that's what we stopped
Too so we make bath salts we made lip balms
We made massage oil
How are you getting the oils in 1995 where were you where were you
Well through
Various Distributors that we had started working with we learned a lot about essential oils and distribution
Also from Neal's yard in from taking aromatherapy classes
And then you would ask around
You know and then
Play I don't have a lavender
This person has a Labrador or hey I need an orange
Where is Orange grown
Alright it's grown in Florida so then you would you know go through the Yellow Pages
Threatened
Essential oils actually aren't oil
They're called essential oils cuz the it's heavier
Then water
So
Any talk about lavender lavender grows
Many places but the best lavender
Is from France and
You know there's a certain taste level just like with food and wine
How about you know what smells best what's the best quality
Can you source that can you
Make that a consistent part of a formulation
Because essential oils are finicky you know the reason that people stopped using them and went to synthetic
Pregnancy no
Was because it was way less expensive sure and it was consistent
And was like being delivered to your little I don't know where house
That you guys are running like in 10 drums or in like the last charger and red giant bags of
Wright glass and
Aluminum
Bottle
And there were some local distributors
It is well
That even though they charged
A lot
We had access
Choose your beer basically running this little
Company that is
Trying to make a go at it with essential oils
I'm out how are you guys doing financially for you
Is it sustainable
Yes or no
I mean
Sustainable as in
Raise a little money we could pay the rent
But you weren't making a ton of money
Oh no no no
They are scraping
Ride along with that stress
Was
The question of
What else would I be doing
Got me now there was always like
Yes you're stressed
Stan okay what do you want to do about it you want to get a job
No
Do you want to do something else
And then it would sort of just settle into this is
What we're doing
You are because you are basically
The distributor
For Neal's yard right
Yes and doing that alone
Was not going to be enough just selling Neal's yard
You know it wasn't and it was
Because you know we were
Importing so we were basically
Slapping glass bottles halfway around the world and then
Reshipping them
Two other stores
And we got it up to a certain level of sales at
I think it was half a million in the US
But we could still see how we could do it
Ourselves
And do it for
Less money because
You know all of that shipping
And do it our own way
So we
Gave them six months to find a different distributor and gave Neal's yard 6 months
You figured
We got a
Do this on our road now
Yes
Well I think one of the early on indicator
It's Rusty around that
Time
Essential oils
And higher-end
Personal Care bath care products started
Take off in the gift
And
Susan head created
An access point
To a lot of
Retailers or folks that wanted us to make
Make the products for them
And
There was some demand
Cuz it just weren't that many companies that made essential oil based and more natural
Body care products
So who just accuracy who was buying
Essential oils
At the time the early 90s
Mid-90s
People would put it I guess you could rub it behind your neck or
You could use it as aromatherapy or use it in in a bath
Like what who are your customers
So
In 1995
Bloomingdale's card
And said will you
You make us
For essential oil blends
4r
Holiday Cash
That's a big deal
I know you said sure
And we had to think of a name for the company then
And
These were very small bottle
So
And we didn't have a lot of room on the label
And aromatherapy just seemed like way too long of a word
So he just came up with
The initials EO
And then we did for Blends for Bloomingdales and that
Started
Company
Okay so 1995
You guys decide to launch own company you call Danny O products
Which stands for
Essential oil
Millions of dollar
Dollars
It was I think of $15,000
Yeah
Butter
We still had to
Salata bottles
In a relatively short amount of time and come up with the formulation
And then it was sort of like okay now what
Again 1995
It is so easy now you can just get Shopify to put your web store online you can
Easily find a company online that will make labels for you they will even do fulfillment and shipping
However example did you
Play Closer to slap labels on these
A little bottles and it had to look nice cuz it's Bloomingdale's you cannot mess around how did you do that
For example
You know we're very good at
Doing
We would just
Figure it out in our Pace levels
Have always been
Hi
And I
When you look down at products in
More natural products and natural food stores everything had a leaf on a flower
You know really bad type and not very nice colors
So we just
Went very minimal
And
Chose a beautiful typeface
Which was
Dido which is similar type paste in Vogue actually
In the products had to smell
Exceptional
And then they also had
Form which was
A little bit of a hurdle
And
Our idea was it for using these expensive very beautiful
Essential oils we're not going to ruin it
With
Harsh
Chemicals and so there was a high bar
That we set
Right off the bat
And I guess
So at this point Brad you are
Working with Susan you are
To feed an
After a couple years of dating and working closely you you really are in love
And you guys get married in 1995 in the middle into the midst of all this
That's right
Oh yeah we were gravity feeding and
By the way out of the Abyss like a line of
Essential oil sale at Bloomingdales
Do they sell out
It crushed it but
But crushing it from the other side I think they ordered once
And that was it
Yeah
However it was a springboard
To add something here
Suzanne you had a ten-year-old you guys were married
And you just had another baby you guys had your first child together
Lucy
So you're a ten-year-old a newborn baby
You're launching a business
To get together
Was that crazy was it just like
Insane
Yes
Yeah it was
And
The financial pressure was in there was a lot of Finance
Because just
You weren't
Selling as much as you
He wanted to sell
You know we did not have
We didn't have money really
For the first
15 to 18 years
Come up alot in this conversation yet
It didn't really come up
Much other than
You know I want to swear a little bit
Airgas why won't yeah
It was a struggle in so
We
We love what we were doing yeah and we're very Scrappy
Yeah and we just made
Work and that was that was really the reality of it all
Were you guys interested in becoming rich I mean was that important to you to make a lot of money
I got make a lot of money
Here's something
That I kind of learned from my
Early thirties when I lived in Pacific
Height is that
Money is not
The thing
And I know a lot of
Really rich unhappy
And I know that money in and of itself
Army wasn't
The key motivator
And I already knew that that was not like my
Path to happiness however paying our rent was important in our bills and survive
Driving a little bit past survival was important because otherwise it was a lot of prey
Pressure so the question wasn't when we going to get rich the question was when
When are we going to make payroll
When we come back in just a moment
Susan and Brad navigate the spress
Growing a business and how that stress to the toll
On their marriage
Stay with us
I'm Gyros and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First door how I built this 2019 lead
Sponsor hiscox
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Do understand that each business is
As unique
Fingerprint or barcode
Tailors in
Halogen Insurance Solutions to fit every business has very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote or purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance expert
Thanks also to First Republic Bank
Traveling should be an enjoyable experience
Whether business or pleasure First Republic ATM rebate checking is the ultimate travel companion
Enjoy unlimited ATM withdrawals with no access fees
Virtually all ATMs worldwide
The best part
First Republic rebate
ATM access fees charged by other institutions
Make your next trip easier
Learn more at firstrepublic.com
First Republic Bank
Member FDIC
If your child plays video games for hours on end perhaps you consider that answer
Be social but these days Walling yourself off from The Real World could be the center of your social life
Today's games offer more avatars and experiences that reflect
Real life
I'm Joshua Johnson
Subscribe to 1A on NPR as we
Explore the social side of Gaming
One more thing if you love how I built this
Check out my new podcast
Wisdom from the top
It's a show about how some of the greatest leaders
Business and politics manager
Some of the biggest corporate and professional crisis you can ever imagine
You can find wisdom
Exclusively on luminary
It's a new app that allows you to listen to all your favorite podcasts plus a bunch of amazing exclusive shows
Just for subscribers
Shows from people like Lena Dunham Trevor Noah Russell Brand
The creator of Slow Burn and many many others
Download the luminary app at your app store
Go to luminary. Link
Slash guy
Free free no strings attached
Trap
Welcome back to how I built this
NPR
Gyros
It's 1996
And your products is
To say the least
Having some problems
But around the time they get a lucky break
A big order from a West Coast department store called Mervyn's
That order is enough to help them keep the lights on
And also take on a new challenge
Try and get their products
Into Whole Foods
We went to our local
Whole Foods in Mill Valley and they turned us down
And then we
Did some guerrilla marketing we would like all Whole Foods and say
Hi do you have to
You'll be like no
Relyco you should carry it at
It probably would just call up and just the two of you do this
Hora local Friendswood going to the Whole Foods at Whole Foods
Asking for
What did that just sounds like a totally like
Transparently obvious campaign like didn't they know
That you guys were doing this
Well you know we have a lot of friends are kids were in school and then we had people who wrote notes on the community
Bulletin board you know asking do you have EO products
Yeah or what why aren't you carrying your product and they finally
He finally started carrying
Hair products
And then
When Whole Foods led to the next
So
I think maybe the buyer changed it Whole Foods and you know it was very sort of
Biocentric
If they liked you and they wanted to carry you that was their decision
And I tell Whole Foods Rand yeah
Alright song 1997
You can add Whole Foods kind of a big deal
Seems like you guys are really turning a corner
By guess
Like later that year or around that time
Like your biggest account
Mervyn's
They kind of look like
We always think we're going to
Stop buying from you
What was that is that
True that happen
What a nightmare that was
Butter
The buyer changed so the buyer that knew us and loved us
Left
And there was a new buyer
Who didn't really like aromatherapy and didn't really like essential oils
Susan tell guy about that meeting
Went to with loose
So the meeting that we went to with the new buyer
The first meeting
Fright with the first meeting I think I was nursing
Boosie I remember being in that room presenting
Having a baby
This woman was
I don't know in your late twenties and
She was not responding
To anything that we are saying
In a positive manner
And without them we were sunk
So it was a hard meeting
I mean when you say you were sunk
You lose mervin's you lose this account
What does that mean how close were you to the business just like
You know that's not such a big deal because you know we were on the brink of crumbling for many years
Well you know that device Inc
That this was a
This was a
This was
Should I get a job
Should one of us get a job
To just smooth out whatever was coming
You know
Minar account was like
He did he did advise us to
Baby folding
Get a job
Cute you're counted after this Mervyn's thing said maybe you guys should just like
Call it a day
Yeah that's when your account is telling you that the person knows your finances better than anyone else
That's really bad
It was bad
Butter
We didn't think about
Wedding we just thought about how are we ever going to get through this
To get to the other side
And was there anything that happened that
Kind of throw you a lifeline
Yes
You got a $65,000 order from
TJ Maxx
Bam
Just out of the blue
Well
They came to our place of business and
At that time
We had a 3000 square foot to
Space
And they came to visit and they just couldn't really believe that we are manufacturing everything there cuz it was you know
Square feet right yeah
And they still gave us an order
All right so you kind of get a Lifeline from TJ Maxx
Thank you TJ Maxx
Thank you TJ Maxx forever and you're in Whole Foods
Yeah if you were to walk into a hole
Foods in two
And you saw a couple of EO products
Available
People walking the grocery store Stacey like a product available at most people assume all that's a big company or
You know the people involved in that company must be doing really well
In in 1999-2000
Were you guys able to pay yourselves really good salaries
No
But we were able to buy a
Small private label manufacturer like a factory
Yeah they had
Thousand gallon tank and a couple of other tanks and
Fort Clifton
Everything you know
Was set up and ready to go
This is a private label that was making soaps and Beauty Supplies
Yes for other company but not organic necessarily
No and it was pretty run down
And and how much did you guys pay for it
We didn't
But
There was a very Progressive small Bank
Our accountant knew those guys
And they ended up
Lending us the money
So at this point have a factory
How many products around 2,000 how many products different products were you making
Chris 835
So like soaps in hand soaps and shower gels and shampoos and when what else
In conditioner bubble bath
Lotion
Baby lip balm
So that's a big product line
You guys just working like crazy was it like all the time
Yeah
So the way that it was working for I don't know maybe it was years is that I would get up at
The crack of dawn and get to work
Between 5 and 6 +
Susan with
Take care of the kids in the home in the morning and she would come in
9 or 10 and then I would
Pick up
You know what three or four and Susan wood
Stay until 6 or 7 and that's
Really what the routine was
Since you are still super pretty small right now
I think I'm like 2,000 2002-2003 for like
You're probably doing what a million dollars $2000000 in gross sales
2 baby
Yes
Are you never really raised
Massive amounts of money you always
You always kind of
A hundred thousand two three four hundred thousand there
$1000000 at one point but you never one for like
Series a series B series C
No
First of all
Either we had companies on the show
That you know that have gone to BC
And I
Because they think they want to scale fast and they want to be first out the gate and they send you the money to really grow fast
And I have to assume then and maybe even now you could
Pretty easily get that money
I was your reason why
Yes because everything I saw and that we saw
Companies that took
Private Equity money and especially if they sell the majority
They didn't have control anymore and I we always joked that the first thing they would do is take that rose essential
Cuz $850 a kilo that we use you know very very sparingly but very beautifully
And they would take that out right away
Getaways watch the consolidation in Personal Care in a natural Personal Care over the years
And that's
Been a consistent
Sing of
Changing the product slightly or not really taken care of the brand and its original intention
And there were a lot of unhappy people and not a lot of
Success
All right so you guys have this really cool business
You started together
You're raising two
Kids
Growing up 30
Byproducts yeah you still small but
You can see where this is heading
And how did you guys do as a couple how are you how is your relationship going
Yeah it was very tough
He married raising kids being under Financial
Pressure
That takes a lot and it's
We sort of we lost our way
We lost our way but
And
We really cared about
Did you go
To Kaplan
Sure
And
It was helpful
At times
And I think
It was definitely helpful long-term
Because we can still refer back to
How to work things out and how to smooth out our differences
We also I think
Individually did a lot of personal work
And
You don't got to a place where
We couldn't make it work
And so we separated and then divorced
Thank you for hearing that
Can I just be shocked
You guys are sitting there
Together
Talking so wonderful
Finally about each other
And your divorce
2007 Yukon
Divorce
Yeah
I've never heard of a story like this my life
Not only are you
Business but you eat I guess so you
You divorce
And you guys decide what you say
You know this business is going well it's a
Keep it going is that
Is that what happened
I think we decided
There's no reason to like you know
Take down the house
Jelly Bean
Personal relationship
Wasn't thriving our business
Is
Our kids are
So what is
The best way
You know
And
We we understood our options we could have
So we could have
But each other how we could you know we had options
So I mean this was a very conscious Choice adult
Immature decision
Like it speaks to the kind people both of you are just wondering like
What is the people in in the office feel like I what was the atmosphere was intense
What people like
This is weird I got out of that employers respond
Well the first two years were
We're tough
And certainly you know the first 6 months were the hardest
And absolutely they said that
And yet
For me it just never got
That bad like there was a lot of Demand on me to make it that bad.
Family or culture
You know what have you oh my gosh you got divorced yeah it's this is the path
Did you go down yet
If all you're doing is you're looking
To get through this day as
Best you can
It does shifted perspective a little bit
The other thing I
I think that's important is that there was no
No other person involved
So we didn't have to navigate that tour divide Trail
So
I think that
Because we were parents that
Didn't alter
Life
Daily life
That much
If you're officially divorced
And
Reasonably that it's still not
Easy
But the business really starts
Take off I guess around this time
Walgreens
CVS
Walmart start to express interest in carrying your products and
Like what what explains that
The timing
I think that the timing really
Was on our side we were kind of met because we were always ahead of the Curve
Yeah we were on
You know sort of the parallel path
With
All the natural food stores Whole Foods was growing
Had a really Hefty clip
That was such a natural venue for us
Because
People were
Buying into the same beliefs
About health and wellbeing
When you started to get into places like Walgreens
Walmart
Target
What is that
Infor
I'm just like
You meet the demand of in the world
Even with your small little place
Well that that really didn't happen in it in a big way until
We launched our second brand
Everyone
And that was an
That was sort of a consumer
Less expensive
Everyday products like shampoo and Ryan
George Allen
Yeah it was a larger format
Product and
I send in a band in the Band came home and
They had all these
Really awful products
In the bathroom when I went in
And I was like have we taught you nothing like you know what are these products and
They be like Eros too expensive and you need
Indian Peaks open
And then at the same time Brad was hearing from
A lot of Whole Foods buyers that we
You know
We needed a large size value sort
Proposition
So we we started a second line called everyone
And that really
Took off and how are you making it less
Expensive
Ingredients of how are you able
How to make a more budget-friendly Prada
We use many of the same ingredients however instead of using a rose
Essential oils we may keep it to Citrus
Or instead of putting in a lot of extracts
Text which are expensive as well
We would you know Duo
Much smaller amounts will be simplified
Formulas in addition our margin is less
Twin over the years you've raised very little money so you most of the company
You guys are
Right
Yes
I have to imagine
Last year
You been approached
Buy all kinds of big
Beer companies who want to buy you
Yeah and
You said
Right now
Is there a reason why you wouldn't
Want to do that
You know
The idea wasn't to cash out
The idea was to
Building Company that we wanted to work
It provided
Opportunity
For as many people as pause
You know the other part of this
Is
The business is part of our life
But it never was
Separate and so
You can look at the success of the business
And you can also look at the success of
Our relation
Our family so
It really has enabled
The best
To live
To our Highest Potential right
Like life is pretty good
To do both of you or both of you in
New relationship
What's today
I am and have been for the past 5 years
No Bradley still looking
And and end with like
It sounds like you still consider yourselves to be
Really close maybe like almost best friends
We are
Yeah it's it almost it almost takes things
Two whole different level you know you have really special relationships with
Your siblings Brothers
Sisters and
You also have some close friends and
I think that we've kind of taking some of those Concepts and put them on steroids a little bit I mean imagine
Choosing to engage on a daily basis
Is with the person you divorced
Knowing all of the good things and all of the bad
Thanks and it's still choosing
To be together it's a wonderful
Xperia
Yeah
And we just mean we get along all the time
So it's not that we don't get in a fight but we do tend to get out of fights
I'm going to ask you some questions Susan first you
What do you think it is about
Brad that enabled
The store
Like
What is about Hamlet that allowed you guys
To stay friends and business partners and
To work through the
Painting stuff like
He has a brilliant capacity
To be
Irreverent
And kind
And
Open
And dumb and stubborn
With all of these qualities
We always come out aligned on
What's most important
Bratz but what is it about Susan that allowed for this to happen
Her perspective
Her capacity
To have compassion and
There was a there was a
A guy that came into our office
The other day and
Are there was someone sick in his family and
The way that she
I dressed him
And engage
With him he was met
It was it was beautiful
And
To be able to be this close with someone and not be
Involved romantically
He gives me
Such a great opportunity to be a better
What do you what do you attribute your success to success of this business at 2
All the hard work you put into it in the Blood Sweat and Tears or or
Your intelligence or just
Warlock
Well Susan you're going to laugh
We're not such great business people will really great not going out of business people
We haven't had the luxury to go out of business
What not to make
Work
There's never been a choice
Not to be
Successful not to make it
Work
Susan about you
We've been
Really privileged
To be able to
Live our lives
And meet that in our work
With shared values
Exceptional
And it's a beacon
To show that it's very possible
If we can do it
You can do it
At Susan Griffin black
Brad black
Founders and CEOs of
EO products
The company now employs more than a hundred and forty people at their headquarters in San Rafael California
Which by the way used to be a special effects Studio owned by George Lucas
Even found a few scenes for Star Wars inside
Play the company turns out more than 50 products
Including their signature lavender oil
Susan recommends a few drops of it in the bath
Before bedtime
Restful sleep
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about
Things your building
The first
A quick message from one of our sponsors MailChimp
So you want to call your business
Now what
MailChimp all in one marketing platform that's what
It is all the marketing stuff
You need to grow
All in one place
Learn more
Mailchimp.com
Building a good relationship with your doctor can be really hard
Especially when it feels like you
I don't know what it is about walking into the doctor's office but it's incredibly easy to forget half of what you wanted to tell the
The doctor check out in purlife kids new guy on navigating doctor-patient
Or subscribe to like it all guys
For Oliver episodes all in one place
Hey thanks for sticking around
Time now for how you built that and today our story starts in the cold Northern Waters
Juneau Alaska are surrounded by the ocean on one side
And then on the other side were surrounded by Ice fields and
Which mountains
This is Leah Heifetz and for years she and her partner Matt would get into an aluminum skiff and gopher
Fishing out
In the Pacific we be trolling for salmon or maybe we'd be fishing for halibut and the fish were
Biting that day and
Rather than go home empty-handed
He was stopped at a kelp bed a bed of bull kelp to be exact
Twisty brown seaweed that looks like a bullwhip a 5 gallon bucket full of
And
Be able to bring some Bounty home
Because it is totally edible by then do it raw and it has the consistency of a bell pepper
It's salty and crunchy
And Heather deep
Umami taste flavor are Savory bass flavor that makes everything in it tastes
More like itself that's what your mommy does
And it turns out full kelp can also be pickled or cooked into salsa
So what I really am at right now
One of those 5 gallon buckets home
Call up some friends to grab some other ingredients so we would sometimes make a green salsa
That had tomatillos
Made a variety of other sauces that
Add tomatoes and onions along with the couch
Emollient that discovered a few years ago is that kelp was actually getting some attention among Foodies
National scale
There's a lot of Whispers in 2016 about helping the new kale
Pull up nutrition into all kinds of things like pasta and jerky even butter
Open Juno
Leanne that started to sell their bull kelp salsa and pickles at farmer's markets and people kind of took
Selling it locally for the huge
Jump the consumers in Alaska
A lot of them are familiar with it as a food
Slowly try to expand their products House of Alaska has taken
Some more education and
A lot of demoing so people have the opportunity to try it and it makes sense to
You salsa is kind of a gateway to get more people to eat kelp
Martina try the salsa and they say it tastes pretty good
The slight aftertaste of the ocean
Anyway soon after they launched Liam at 1:40 thousand dollars in a startup competition and use that money
I need to get their products into some Regional grocery stores on the west coast but doing all of this from Juneau Alaska
It's
Treetop we're not on the road system
We are surrounded by the ocean and mountains
And that requires some
Real Innovation when it comes to Logistics
Which means when they want to get their salsa and pickles out of Juneau usually involves
A barge
I'm sometimes a fairy and then
Talking once it hits the road system or are afraid
Slapping a pretty
Immense challenge but since they went into business three years ago
Tiamat and their other partner have been able to steadily grow the business
There now harvesting canning and cooking bull kelp full-time
They sell it online and in about 150 stores and guess what
Last year they made $350,000 in Revenue
Selling bull kelp sometimes I think I'm sick of it
But once I cracked one of those jars open and eat it which is almost daily it tastes so good
So no I'm not sick of Celtic
That's Leah Heifetz she and her two partners Mad Max are the founders of Barnacle Foods
More about the company or here previous episode of podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you
Do you want to tell us your story go to build npr.org and thanks for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe it Apple podcasts or whatever you get your podcast while you're there please do give us a review
HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet you can reach us
How I built this horad
Gyros
It was produced this week by JC Howard with original music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Our show is edited
I need a grant
Thanks also to Julia Connie Sanchez Mexican floor and Jeff Rodgers
Our intern
Is David jaw
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR