Support for NPR comes from investor.gov
Presenting this mess
When it comes to investing
We all have Quest
And investor.gov has answers
If you're free resource
Tools tips and information about investing
Before you invest
Investor.gov
Is guy here
With a very exciting announcement
This coming October
Could be coming back to the Yerba Buena Center for the Arts in San Francisco
For our second how I built this Summit
Supported by American
Express
Over the course of 2 days
I'll have conversations with some of our most remarkable founders
From the show
Including David neeleman
JetBlue
Marcia Kilgore of bliss
Kevin Systrom and Mike Krieger of Instagram Stewart Butterfield to slack Jen Rubio away
And many many more
The summit Disney
Incredible opportunity
Connect with other entrepreneurs and Builders just like you
Come around the world
Last year's Summit sold out early so to find out
How to get tickets
Visit Summit
Npr.org
And I hope to see you in San Francisco
I had never had a wild strawberry
Intensely flavored
Picture of cream on the side and a bowl of sugar if you needed
And I couldn't have enough of them and I wondered where they came from
And they told me you have to go out in the woods and pick up
NPR how I built this
Show that animators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movement they built
I'm guy rosin on the show today at the farm
To table movement from her California restaurant and sparked a global revolution in the food industry
So if you open up the latest edition of the famous Michelin Guide to the San Francisco Bay Area
You will find 57 restaurant
In and around San Francisco
It happened granted 1 2 or 3 Stars by the notoriously fussy Michelin reviewers
Getting a Michelin star can turn a sleepy little Bistro
Find a restaurant that takes reservations 6 months out
The kind of place that is essentially impossible to get into
These are considered to be the most
Innovative and inspiring
Palaces of food
In the world
But one restaurant perhaps one of the most
Famous in America
It does not appear on michelins list
Is located in a converted old house
Berkeley California
Call Chez Panisse
And today
It's the kind of place well-to-do Berkeley parents might take their
Children during a visit
What kind of restaurant food tourists will seek out
Mainly because of its contribution to modern cooking
He's a great restaurant
You're not going to find saved Frozen orbs of aged balsamic vinegar suspended in Yuzu July
Your plate
What you will get
Is extremely fresh
Really local farm-to-table food
Perfectly ripe Peach with a
Scoop of creme fraiche or a roasted Quail with some blackberry jam made with just picked black
Berries grown a few miles away
The person behind that restaurant
Alice Waters
Notable for cooking
She's probably much better now
3 impact she's had on American Cuisine because Alice Waters was really one of the first American chef
Promote the idea that food should be local fresh and seasonal
Today almost every good restaurant in America pays homage
Farm to Table cooking
They tell you the name of the farm where the chicken came from and to
Ethan the farmer who grew the crops
And Alice Waters
Is largely the reason why
But when she opened Chez Panisse in 1971 in that old run-down Berkley house she wasn't necessarily true
Trying to start a movement
I really just wanted a nice cozy
Any place where she could invite friends to share a meal
Grow up intending to be a chef
Is a kid in New Jersey
She ate a pretty typical American diet of that era
Her mom wasn't exactly the greatest
Cook and she focused instead
Unfancy
She wanted something healthy for us but you didn't
Know how to do that
She knew
You know
Meat potatoes vegetable
Salad fruit cup
Producer
The most
Bus from a can
Or Frozen
She
Funny brown bread
Semi sandwiches
Very try and
Spread with peanut butter and bananas
I didn't
I like food very much.
Was a very picky eater
And this was a time of a food revolution in a sense of the way we think about it today but the food revolution of the
Late forties and fifties was
And and Frozen and then eventually
Microwavable ready to eat
Meals
I remember when that frozen meal
Came
In
Prepared
You just stuck it in the oven and
People saw that is as wonderful
Innovation nobody thought
This is processed food right beside it is amazing what we can actually
We actually more time now
Thought we were a country that
Didn't have
Deep Roots
In agriculture
Growing
Food
Foretaste
We always screw it
For quantity and ship ability
But never
Flavor
And we
We never had
Strong
Sense of the table
A place
Of
Conversation
Pleasure it was
Much more of that sort of puritanical
Just
We're here to eat
And she will up
I'm so when the fast food industry came in
It just
Hold us up by the rest
Sure gif
Cul-de-sac
Yeah and we went with it
Went with the ideas at
What's easier
To do this it was fast cheap and easy
And
Even my parents who had a
How to garden in the backyard
Stop
Applesauce
Yeah
So you I guess
By the time you hit your teens you
The Family movie
I love that right you moved
To the Midwest and then to California was this for your dad's job yes
Give us
He was transferred to Chicago
And then he was further transferred to Los Angeles
So you went to so you decided
When you graduate high school you went to the University of California
In Santa Barbara
And this isn't the early 60s
And what about
What was your impression of the place
Mount Davis party placement
Right by the water on the beach
And
I decided
To transfer to UC Berkeley
And the fall of 19th
64 to the fall 1964 you end up at UC Berkeley
A junior college or a sophomore in college
And that really imagine you're getting there at the time when this is like right as that the
The Berkeley
Free Speech movement
Is starting out
Starting up and were you I mean you get to Berkeley what are you in anyway politicize at that time or were you totally like
Not even
You know was it not part of your world
And I was really shocked
What was going on
Yeah
And my friends forever
Citic in the same place
We all
Bortron it
Enough
Be outside of the demonstrations
Listening
Curious 10
Inspired
Ultimate do you remember seeing
Any of those leaders
Oh yes Mario Savio
Sports
Touch me in it
Very deep
He talked
About to change the world
How we have to work together
Stop
Dr. gears put yourself
On the line
Demonstrate
I mean be willing to take a risk
Opposite
To take a risk
When you had grown up in this very sore cloistered secluded
50s
World
And now you were in the middle of
1960s
Berkeley I mean the service center of college radicalism
Charlene the United States
It was the war that was the Free Speech movement the sexual Revolution
Drugs I mean all these things right
Batman exciting times
It parts I mean it really was
I think I must have had some of my mother's jeans
Cuz when I think back I mean
At the end of her life she said to me
You're living the life
I always wanted
Well
2 in in 1965 you
First Student
And you have I guess opportunity to study abroad and you went to France
What
What struck you about France when you got there what did you discover that you didn't
Quite realize until you got there
Well I never
Daenerys the country
Show
A revelation on
Off
Two fries in Paris
Beautiful
Beautiful city
I don't know if we see every part
I've got experience it just whistling Awakening for me
It was
Really and Wendy remember thinking there's something different about
Food in the connection to food here that I have never experienced
Before was it almost instantly after you arrived
It was almost instantly because
We student line
To get a hot pack
And then you got it
It was more
Race back to work to the rooming house and if we had some apricot chair
Better
We ate at on the hot breath and
I wanted to eat it every morning like that I wanted to bowl
Cafe Au Lait
IPhone it
To see what was inside of these little restaurants
That we're all over
Paris at that time
They were very small and had
Paper claws
Antique candle lighting
Unique poses
Food sitting up
On the tables as you walked in
Beast
I just really fell for it
Did you start to
Did you start to explore the
Food markets
Send
Well I went
True one of those markets the really old Market Street
On my way to school
Was it just like
Shockingly different to what you have seen in the US
They different
Because it was kind of
Bus was the supermarket
Yeah and this
Was
You know life
Intervene a lot
Beautiful beautiful
Vegetables
That
Just said look at me
Buy me
I didn't call them farmers markets was just the part they was too smart
And all the food
Was
Really
Had area in and around Paris
Would you would you watch the markets in Paris and see produce
That you had never seen before
Oh indeed
You know I had never had
A wild strawberry
Not talk about that
As being the moment
When I said
In what was defended to eat
Paper tiny
So intensely flavor
And to who
Preserved hepatitis A
A little picture of cream on the side
And a bowl of sugar if you need to
And I couldn't
Have enough of that
And I wondered where that came from
And they told me you have to go out in the woods and picks up
I didn't know
That I was being imprinted in that way in terms of
Seasonality
Because you
You went around with your French friends and things
Picky about
What restaurant
And you aren't used to that and I was hungry and they would not allow
Wants to go into the place until they had examined the various menus
To see who had the food that was the tastiest
They have those clamps where did they come from but it wasn't just about food
The discourse at the table we would sit there maybe two hours
Talking politics talkin talkin about life and
I was fascinated with that conversation. To table
So you so that year obviously
Was going to be a turning point in your life what you didn't yet
Probably no
Didn't did that year
Change what you thought you wanted
Do with your life did you think you know I want to
I want to be a chef I want to be a cook I want to study cooking or or did you go back to Berkeley and just
Think all right
Did my year in France and I'm
Chris Moore I did my hair
France and now I'm back
The time
I was cooking
I wanted to eat like
That pushed me
To explore the markets and try and find
The taste
I couldn't find
You know
I wanted to eat in French restaurant
In the city
I saved all my money so I could eat in the fancy French restaurant
But it didn't taste like
Csr2 finished up
At 8 at UC Berkeley at your your cooking is French food at home and
Hoosier Hoosier Planet what were you
Going to do with your life
Depends who is teaching Montessori School
And
She told me all about Montessori
Plus
Of teaching
And I
Said oh my goodness she
Is really sinking
About the world in the same way I am
The idea of opening your senses
Because those are the pathways
Into our minds that you're touching
Hastings
You smell like
You're listening
You're seeing
And that's what
Happened to me in France
I had Awakening of my senses
And I slept well
Maybe
I could teach
I Montessori school and there happened to be one
Right down the street
In Berkeley in Berkeley
So you say you
Got a job there is a is a preschool teacher or
End end
You can open did you must have
Enjoyed it at mine was that did you think
Lithium versus maybe what what I'll do
It was like that although I was very challenged
Bye
326 year old children
I've never been around them
For did you ever at a certain point so you know I'm
I think I want to take
Cooking classes I want it I want to
Surfboard learn how to do this
No
Intimidated by that
I thought it was
You know complicated and that I would be exposed for my
Ignorance in the way that Julia Child felt
At the beginning of her cooking
But I wasn't
As determined as she was to
Chop
A pile of Funyuns properly
So that I could excel at
Claps
Funny to experiment
At home
And just do
But I
Thought I could do well
So it's a late sixties you're teaching at a preschool
And enjoying cooking at home
How did you start to show
Under this idea that maybe
You want to open a restaurant
Well I was cooking
For a lot of my fence at
Our house
I was living with a printer
And he was very political
And
Invite friends over for dinner and
A group was producing a magazine called the San Francisco
Express-Times
And so they would gather at the table
And I started cooking for them all
In fact so much so that they said that they liked it and ice
Started doing a little cooking column
Colt Alice's Restaurant
And in total
Waited 30 of those but broke buying the in
Maybe
I could open a little place
And then my parents would pay
To come and eat there
And I had the encouragement
Other extraordinary friend gift with Tom Luddy
Running that Telegraph Repertory Cinema
And it parties for all of his filmmaker friend
John Licata and Francis Coppola and you were just cooking for them
They were dinner parties and they were crazy so I'm trying to
Recreate this moment and oftentimes in the on the show we get to this moment you know there's a business plan
And there's a you know very methodical kind of process if it isn't it just like yellow
Do this do this because Tom is pretty extraordinary person
And he saw that I had that inclination he took let's just go
I need to know that little French restaurants in restaurants in San Francisco so we could get an idea
Of what it is that you're looking for and we had gone
To a very special restaurant out in Bolinas that was in a house
I was very struck by that maybe it could be a restaurant in the house
Because then I could feel like I was cooking at home
And then I saw this place
In Northbrook
This is where Chez Panisse is today on Shattuck Avenue in Berkeley
What what what was that
Play wasn't that a house for rent
It was a it was a plumbing shop
It was in the house
And all the pipes in over at
Front
Insert at the Courtyard in front
And it was so
Very plain stucco house
2 floors
I love the location and it was commercially
You were broke
Because you were spending all your money
Denny's dinner parties
Just a business question from I mean it
Did you
How did you even have
The money to sign a lease or to make a commitment or
To refurbish the place did you have to go and ask
Friends to absolutely
And my parents
Mortgage their house
Well they had please believe me they believed it all
Their kids
I guess we should acknowledge that you also did borrow money from other sources
A story that you got some money from like
Pot dealers in Berkeley
It's true
Okay so see you get get this lease and remember how much money you had to raise from
Family and drug dealers over like
You have the confidence to like
Sign this this lease agreement
I don't remember exactly
People who gave me some money is still on the board of directors Shay pennies
And he was a friend of Tom lettuce
He found the people that had
The confidence
That I didn't have any says I think you need to get connected with Paul erito
Because he has cooking skills and he's got all these copper pots
He knows how to make a risotto
I'm sure he could be a part for you were these people who were investing in
Yuan restaurant did they think that they were investing in that they were going to get a return on their investment or what
Was it just like hey this is a cool idea Alice like this is Ruby let's play some
This was the seventh
The early 70s
And
Ashamed
If I had been looking to make money
Nobody
Who is involved with this project
Expect
Make money
Hooked
But we didn't expect
It was celebra flops
And
Weaver
Doing it
In this
Fairy
Non-professional way if he will
I thought I had a little bit of a
Experience because I had waited on tables
In a couple of places to make money in high school
So when you when you really kind of start to ramp up to open up the restaurant
Are you never run arrest
Is a really challenging business most restaurants
Eventually fail
Where you at anyway intimidated or nervous about all of those people who are putting their faith in this thing
Working
Or not
I know
Was really good
The people would come
I knew that
Absolutely I neuter
But I was too intimidated
How to cook at
Beginning
Victoria Cross was the first
Cook at the restaurant
We practice at home
And me
Really deeply read about it
And so
We
But we could do
One menu a day
So this was not
Ambitious
We didn't
When were you able to actually open the rest
August 28th 1971 and this was a French
Traditional sort of traditional French
Restaurant
And what what is the inside of the restaurant
Look like what did you have a an idea what how you wanted it to be
From my French friend
Mighty
And she was an artist
She had lots of ideas
About
How we could find things
Flea market
Alameda
So I would go with her
Find silverware mismatched silverware
Flea market in Alameda
And we had
Red and white checkered
The tablecloth
Flowers on the table
When did the Kindle
And Martin design
Very first poster
That we had for the restaurant to be put in a frame and put out
Front
That night
I greeted people at the door
And what would you serve in that first meal
That first night
We served
Pate en croute
Cornichons on the side
And then we had duck
With olives
And I think that was Victoria
She felt really confident
Putting the
Trays of ducks in the oven
Stuck fat everywhere I remember
And with olives
And with some sort of
Celery root
Jurassic
And Lindsey the pastry chef made a thumbtack and how much was that
But Samuel I think it was 395
Let me come back in just a moment 4 dollar meal turned into one of America's best restaurants
Eventually
Tired of revolution in the restaurant industry
I don't this
Support for this podcast and the following message come from The Economic Development Authority of Fairfax County Virginia
Located near DC
And home to 8900 technology companies
And 144000 Technology jobs
Details at Fairfax County Eda
. org
Support also comes from luminary
The only place where you can listen to Trevor Noah's a new podcast
With his new show The Daily Show host challenges himself and his listener
Explore unfamiliar angles
And embrace differing View
Listen to Trevor Noah's new podcast
Along with other original shows only on luminary
Visit luminary. Links build
For your first two months of luminaries premium content for free
Cancel anytime
Terms apply
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering account
With no fees or
Animals that can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built
Text from NPR
Hits 1971
And Alice Waters has
Just opened up
Chez Panisse
She's trying to capture some of the magic
She felt eating at restaurants
Paris
And pretty soon the tables are starting to fill up
Analysis
She has to figure out how to run a company
I was out in the dining room
Trying to make it work
I know that
Everybody who works there
Was
Passionate about
I decided that we couldn't
Run the restaurant without these people
Uber critical
Taste to the
With place looked
Waves at the cafe run
Miss running at Subway
Reformed
A corporation
We had people
Brett money
Stock
That helped us to run the restaurant
I also
Cape shares
People
That were instrumental
And we had this group
People
That
Believe in the project and infested
Inner
Were you I mean it sounds like you are getting your own business education
As this way
What's happening right because you
You haven't got a business school and you
As you say you didn't
You didn't go into this
Thinking you wanted to make money in fact
That was anathema to you in some ways but
You still had to run a business cuz they were people whose livelihoods were depending on the sand part
Is that what was happening where you kind of
Learning as you went along about
Shares Nevada Corporation about
Structure these things
Absolutely
Learning by doing the Chesapeake Montessori idea
That actually
Doing that works
So you heard anything about
It's value
And what is critical
What it really means
Clean up the restaurant
After hours
What those people needed
To be paid
What are dishwashers
Should be paid
Remember I got a fairy
Powerful lesson
About garbage
One of
With the guy who
Who brought fish to the restaurant
Really early on the sky political friend of mine from way back
Who
Collected muscles
Along the coast
He would bring them in
The restaurant
And he said
Give me one day
I want you to come out
And see the dumpster
And I want to have me pulled it open
Didn't smell very good needs
I want you to get in the.
I want you to know
What it feels like
B
Not careful
About
The way you put garbage
In this container
And it was a big wake-up call for me
You were the center of this
Hub-and-spoke and still are
But at that time I mean it it's
It it strikes me that and I hope I'm not the sort of extrapolating but you
Wanted to do this because you loved
To do it and you wanted to be around people you liked and he wanted
People to be happy but a business and inevitably you're going to run into
Challenges with birth with person out with people who just are
Not working out did you
Those early days
Do you know what if you want to fire people was it
Was it hard for you what if you had to discipline people did you just avoid that
I try to avoid that
I did but I eated it
Different way
Try to hire friends
That
Really help me to self
When you're working in the business
And you're working
15 hours a day but I figured
To be with people I liked
And that I shared the value Swift
So I was willing
To take the risk of it not working out
Unfortunately
There were very few times
We're at that became an issue
What
What was it that was
Riving you at that time that was really motivating me because you weren't making money and you weren't going to make any money for a long
Long time
I'm in and it seems like
Money wasn't
Really
A source of tension
Right I mean is that
Is that was at the secret at least at the beginning because
Everyone says don't hire your friends don't work with your friend
But if I get some money is not really
This thing that everyone is chasing that there's no
There's no condom
Because money is really the center of conflicts in business
Yes it is
And I wanted
Chase and
Chase
That I
Wanted to be in
And that it was constantly
Growing and changing
And
That happened
When different people
Brought ideas into
I think what
Really
Has
Created the smelling life
For the rest
Is the fact
That
We don't have
One person
Who is
The main chef
The restaurant
We have two people
And they share their job
They work three days
And then they're paid for 5
And
It allows us to
Time to recover and have ideas
This business was your baby at that point I have to imagine that
You're working like
Crazy
I was working all 7 days a week
Just about seven days a week. Closed on Sunday
I just
Threw myself into it What was
What was the thing that just kept
Kept was it that means some people describe the fear of failure some people describe
You know the the bottom line some people describe
This sort of intangible passion like what
But what's up
You showing up for 15 hours a day 7 days a week
Only one menu
It's different every day
You have to find
Those ingredients
You have to put them together differently
People have to
Want to come
There
And taste that
Maybe I was pushed more
Quickly
Into
Finding ingredients and I really believe that that
Sort of
Search
Let me to the doorsteps
The local organic
Farmers Branch
But it was that the game
I kind of
And challenge
To the restaurant
I guess it was maybe 73 or 74
Ivy most famous food critic in the United States
The time James Beard
For Whom the
Famous award is named after
Key to the restaurant
And a couple days or weeks later says this is one of the
The four best restaurants
In the United States
What what happened after that came out
Cuz you were like this
Collective
Communal
The all of a sudden this guy says one of the four best restaurants in
Annapolis
Socratic
In one way
But
Play it made the restaurant
Incredibly busy
Assertive
Almost to overwhelmingly so
That we were
Prepared for that clientele this is probably ultra-wealthy people flying to the bear
Area for the weekend and eat at your restaurant right
I think probably some of them were coming
And that way
Ultimately it led to my conclusion that
My friends couldn't afford to eat there
And couldn't get in
Maybe
Think about it
Really seriously
I think again at Tom's ID surgeon
Did I get back to my wrists
That I really loved
Simple food
And it was a trip
Italy
Actually when I
Saw a pizza oven in about 1978
That I said
We need to
Kate
Caffe Bistro
Upstairs
That is more affordable
We
Don't worry about
Money so much
Because
Pasta isn't too expensive to me again
Baby Pizzas aren't 10
That would be a place
Four friends together
As as restaurant to get more attention especially after James Beard and more
Media attention you started to become a celebrity you started to become a famous
Person Acheson Berkeley but nationally-known was that strange for you or I mean did you even
Absorb assimilate that idea or were you just
What kind of doing your thing
I mean you can't help but be impressed friend
Newsweek magazine wants to put you out to cover and I never
Expected that kind of attention
What I thought was
A pretty simple local
Community restaurant in Berkeley California
I mean what was
Clear to me then
And is very very clear to me now
Is
That
Weaver
Doing something
Against the fast-food culture of
This country
That we were created
Emil
That
Was supporting
Slow food movement
That was
Actually
Buying its food
Directly from the people
Who took care of the land
No Middleman
Giving them all the money
Then they brought their values
Into the restaurant
And that
It changed us
And we became
Really political
We started writing their names
On the cafe clips
The disc came from Popcaan arts for
If this came from Del Porto's Ranch
That this
What's Mas masumoto speech
Identifying the people
Growing and raising the food
We became in a way
Co-producers
Did people come to you and say Alice
You know we got a
We don't make Chez Panisse cafes and Chez Panisse expresses and you know you got to
Branch on an open open them all over the country in the world in and we can
Get investors and Venture money and we can
Do a whole Alice Waters line at Target in and Kmart and
I mean that must have happened right
Earth tattoo Tappan
And
A few times
August
Almost tempted by the money
What happened why didn't any of that happen
It didn't happen because I really
Feels like
It's important
That
You fine people
That share your values
When they do
There's a run
Breathe life into it
And should make some money from it
I just couldn't imagine knowing have franchises work
If that there would ever be away
To do it to do in the way that
That align with your own values
Yes
Feels like selling out
I had to use that term to put
It feels like
I'm doing it
Just to make the money
I just cannot
Think about it
That way
But it's
More than that I
I can't ever imagine
Flying around the world to visit
Thai restaurants
What I like
About being
I restaurant
Trees
Know the people who works there
And it's the pleasure of my everyday life I
I'm friends with them
I know the customers who come in
I love
That aspect of it this was
Maybe we could if we stopped that the story here it would be impressive and Chez Panisse was this really cool restaurant but
That's really not me that's plays for the beginning of the story because
What's interesting about
About Chez Panisse is that
There's a virtual consensus among
Shops in the United States that
What we consider farm to table you know which every restaurant does now or talking describing
The source of of produce like
They all agree that started at Chez Panisse in the late seventies that
This was the restaurant that really
Creative
The farm-to-table movement
How did that happen to me
You were a French restaurant
And
You are serving great food but
Was there was it just the kind of a Natural Evolution or did you reserve point where you thought
Look one California this is like the breadbasket of North America
You know we can actually
Source all the stuff locally and until people are come from
It happened sort of
Naturally I'm not
Not really consciously trying to do that
It became
California
Without us
Really
Identifying that right away
In California meant
Local seafood in cooked in a toaster oven
You know I'm fast way right for me
For sure a very simple
Kind of cooking
And we are really at the beginning it
In this country
Discovering
The ingredients that we have to
And I
Have always been
On
The organic
Spectre
Really insistent
And how the animals are
Cared for
And what they are fed
Sleepzy I wanted
To be about
Purity
We need to be
Thinking
About
All these different aspects
For the survival of the planet
And for our nourishment
When you start to focus on
Local food
Farm to Table
Which I guess you didn't really call it farm-to-table
Did you
Think that you were building
A movement that you think that this was going to become
Something really big or did you just
Do it because you thought that was the right thing to do
Well at the beginning
I thought it was the right thing to do
But I
Felts
Potato and in the late 70s to early 80s
Especially
When the caffe
Became so successful
That
We had this audience
And that we need to talk about
Taking care of the land
For the future
And it really
Became into my Consciousness when
My daughter was born
And I felt like Japanese
Could not be an island unto itself
That we were
Upstream and around the world
And I became very conscious of that and it's
Started
To actively
Talk about it
Every way I could
Every article that was written about the restaurant
From that point on
Was
Really
Talking about how dependent and
How easy it is to
A relationship
The farmer
And how was talk to that person on the phone or to see
Farm
Aunt and talk about the planting and
Grow your own
Back to the land movement
It's something that I hope happens again and soon
Because
Is that
Is what
Is going to bring us a real economy
When we can
Find a way to bring culture to agriculture
When we can bring security
To the farmers who take care of the mat
When we can buy directly from them
They will
Want to take care of nature
And I know men
Are doing that young people around
The country and I'm thrilled by
When you think about organic
Today it's everywhere so it's actually
A huge
Value-add for businesses to use that term organic when they can
Cuz they can charge more money
It's everywhere
You can go to Costco and Walmart
And Target and buy
Organic gummy bears in organic salads
Inorganic
Candy and organic
Apple juice and whatever everything's organic
Are you a part of that is connected to farm-to-table because that's been active option for people
Or or
You know you go to any any fast food place and it will say farm fresh eggs will every egg comes
Ultimately from afar
The question is what is that farm
When you see like
You know
But when you see that everything is organic 2
Everything is
Describe is farm-to-table or
Is Parkview
Happy about that I'm proud of that
I'm troubled
But I'm very troubled about
The labeling
Unpack
What
How people are
Taking
The values of our movement
And
Greenwashing
There
Industrial
Products
And we have to learn
And the educated
About what those words
It's really me
Is it
Certified organic
And who is certifying
Where's it coming
Are the practices
Optispark
Humane
Are they taking care of their farm work
Are they paying them
A decent wage
What about the packaging
Is it all plastic
What does
Fresh me
For some places
Could be 2 weeks old
Who do you trust
Palace when you are
A public figure
You are associated with
I really important
Movement
Inevitably you will be criticized
There will be somebody who criticizes you
And you receive your fair share of its Ms Posse don't you know this is
What you talking about only apply
Affluent people if people can afford to restaurants and
People of the money for organic food
Do you
Do you internalize that criticism do you think about it does it change how you think about what you do
Do you ignore it
I don't believe
In the Sun
I don't believe in the Mist
A fast food culture
Food is precious
It can be affordable
It can't be an expense
If
You know how to cook
I mean I say
That I can buy now
Organic chicken
And I can make at least three meals out of it
For a family of four
Jose Andres says he can make six
That's it for
I know
That we can make school lunch
They can even fit into the minuscule budget of the USDA reimbursement
If we know how to cook
And we do not
Fast food
If we buy
Food
From
People who are doing
A bright
Enteric
This
Ideas that I'm talking about
Delicious
This is not hard to do
This is about sitting with your friends and family
Eating together and even cooking together
Mississippi
Human values that we forgot about this is
Addressing the issue of loneliness
This is addressing the issue of meaningless work
We are
Cooking
Something that makes other people happy
We are falling in love with nature
We are
Seeing the trees turn color we are
We're having an everyday pleasure of that
Where
Engaging in the Beauty and the biodiversity
Shane 10 colors of carrots
It's kind of Sterling I cooked a purple and orange carrots last night
Marvel Titan and that's
That's what is
Going to make the revolution
If you will
I call it a delicious Revolution but it's it's a pallet
Winning people over
Stop by overthrowing
Stop by separating we need the biodiversity of people
Just like we need the biodiversity in nature
To survive
You you won the James Beard award think it was in 1990
To your name the best chef in America
Which is
Interesting because you are
It in some ways you're not best known as a chef I mean obviously you're known as a chef what you're best known as
The person behind a movement
Do you
Do you feel
More proud of one than the other do you see yourself as a chef primarily or do you see yourself as a man
My service is really good cook
And I see myself as a great critic
And taster
I'm not
Is chocolate a discectomy
Stop saying that
Because you are a chef
Befriend a kitchen
And if you find a kitchen
You're a chef
But for me chef
Goes into that
You know it's raining
Like Julia Child did
You know when she
Cook every single thing on her book and she brought such
Wonderful instructions
That's
Not ever been
Something that I've aspired to two
When you when you think about the success of Chez Panisse
You know weather
And it's and it's interesting how we define success cuz it's not
It's not a silly financials
Success of course people
Done well in the band Live comfortable lives but
It if it's not you know
Billion dollar Corporation about the success of Japanese and then the the movement
Which we didn't really talk a lot about that all of the shafts to kind of
Came out of that world
2 and created their own
World
How much of your own personal success do you attribute to
Just luck and Circumstance and how much do a tribute to
Your skill and hard work and your determination
Are you know
I really consider
Said it was good luck
That I went to
France
When is Westphalia slow Food Nation
That I had to help
Tuesday at a young age
Understand
That I had a passion
Events
I didn't know
How that would reveal itself I didn't reflect on it
At the time
But
I just
Absorbed
What I
Cool
Human values
At that time
Pinotage
Picture
Eating together
How people have done that since the beginning of time
How's a four ways taking care of the laugh because that's where the food came
I've always thought of food is precious
So
To you
The biggest factors luck
I guess there has been something termination
People have asked me
For one word that describes me
I said determined
Some people have said I'm compromised
I'm not quite that
I'm very
Determined
To make something happen
And usually
One night
Feel this way
It happens
Alice Waters
Founder and owner of Chez Panisse
1995 Palace found an organization called the edible schoolyard project
Which sets up organic Gardens in schools and teaches children to care for cook
And enjoy fresh produce today the original edible schoolyard in Berkeley
Also offers training programs for parents and teachers to replicate the project throughout the US
Please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
But first a quick thanks to our 2019 how I built this
Lead sponsor
Hiscox
Hiscox tailoring its insurance policies
Every business has berries
Specific needs
May explain its 97%
Customer service rating
Get a quote
Arbeit hiscox.com
Hiscox
Encourage
Courage
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
I know for how you built that
Intraday story starts in Dallas
In 2003 when Pearson games was a teenager
And wanted to make a change I played soccer throughout my life
I always wore my hair and braids
And then when I was going into Highschool I decided that I wanted to wear my hair straight take my braids out and wear my hair straight
Not like many African American women
Kirsten has highly textured hair
But her hair is also very fine
Straightened it would curl up as soon as I sweat
Took a shower and never had it before
So she went to a stylist and got the treatment and it first
Her hair looks
Great
But then I was in geometry class and there was a guy behind me who said Pearson
All of your hair is on my desk
Yeah it was bad it was really bad
Kirsten lost her hair all of it and it took a long time to grow back
Now this happened again a few years later
Which is why Pearson was
Wary of new salon but in 2016 when she moved to Boston to go to Harvard Business School
She really needed someone to do her hair
One of my friends said that she was going to a girl at Drybar
It is an Express Salon Service they only do blowouts
You know I never seen anyone who would my type of hair walk out of there
I was scared but I was like I don't really have an option right now but it turns out the stylist knew exactly what you were
Who's doing the experience was just amazing I would honestly like an hour-and-a-half which had never happened to me in all the time
Times have been going to the salon since I was a kid and her hair looked amazing so she was hooked
Kirsten booked a weekly standing appointment but
It didn't last
She left is she like she moved out of state so Pearson got just one month of Salon Bliss
That didn't seem fair but what it did seem like
What's an opportunity for a demographic of women who spend so much time and money
How much time you spend nine times more than any other group of people in our hair
But the service is just
Are subpar. What is there could be a chain of salon
All over the country for people with highly textured hair weather was big or coarse or fine or
Haley curl
Salon where they could get it styled into hours and they would leave looking great I really believe
I didn't do this somebody else is going to do this it was just so obvious so glaringly obvious but
Needed to be sure so Pearson pull together a few hundred dollars from her student loans
Organized a one-day pop-up Salon in Boston she found three hairdressers to do the blowouts
And to get the word out she emailed Black and Hispanic groups of local colleges the promo material that is not a zip file
Finally a blow-dry experience for you and it had a picture of girl with light curly hair and Pierson also decided
To serve green juice so her first client a little pampered I thought it was going to be pulling people's teeth
To try this and it's sold out it's sold out now each blowout was just $10
Colors and Pierson wondered if
It was just a fluke
To find out she needed to do more pop ups
Soap she went to Atlanta
And she got into an incubator there one that was geared toward women of color
Ever next test she raised her price
$50 a blowout
And she said something other than green juice in Atlanta
About the experience and the mimosas and those pop-ups were booked
Solid
Not only did Kirsten make a profit
Joseline clients asking what's the next one can I reserve a spot right now
And at that moment pierce the new
She was really onto something if we stay doing the number that we do not these pop-up will be making
1.6 million in blow out the loan this year Pierceton is back in Dallas
What she's hosting pop ups every other week and scouting locations for her first blowout salon
And who does her hair now our Master stylist and educator she is my stylist name is India this
Lucian whisper me a Creative Solutions that I went to a new city
I could Google somebody and know someone do my hair this was literally for me
That's Kirsten Gaines she's the founder of pressed Roots if you want to find out more about Pearson or here
Previous episodes of podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us
Your story go to build. Npr.org thanks so much for listening to the show
This week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please do give us review
You can also write to us at Hy-Vee tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
Our shows produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Carney JC Howard nor could see the Immigrant Melissa gray Santa's meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Candice Lim
I'm guy Raz
Listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customers
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
Alexa drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week