Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Somewhere along the way I get like a call on my cell
Hey guys like hey its course it's okay so I called the date
Hey can you reboot the server and it doesn't come back and it wasn't coming back
And I was like I got to go to New York right now and I just drive to New York and I'm having a panic attack to hold out come and get screwed I lost all day
That little experiment over
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movement
Anthony casso has dorm room coding project turned into Squarespace
Is it
Business schools that teach a bunch of ideas about entrepreneurship
The one that is the clearest path to creating something unique
Is this
Find a problem that lots of people have and solve it
Example how can I get from this exact point I'm standing on to another specific
2.2 miles away in a relatively fast and cheap way
Swellinfo cities in America Uber and Lyft have solved that problem
Cheap pair of cool prescription glasses that's the question the guys behind Warby Parker wanted to answer
Answer website
Today that is not a problem but not that long ago
You either needed to know how to code or know someone else who knew how to code and charged you money to make that
List of course was the problem that Anthony casalena wanted to solve
Belt before I go on
Acknowledge the elephant in the room here because yes in the past Squarespace has sponsored this podcast
And so of other companies that do similar things
And I promise you
That fact will never influence which company's we profile on the show we look for great stories and
The story of Squarespace
As you will hear
Pretty great Anthony casalena literally created his product in a dorm room at the University of Mary
Maryland in 2003 21 a self-taught coder
I'm looking for a way to combine a Blog and a website go figure
And out of that small problem he wanted to solve
Squarespace
It's a company with now value that around 1.7 billion dollars
Anthony grew up outside Baltimore in
Early nineties
Just as the internet was becoming a mainstream thing
His dad worked in sales for companies like HP and Cisco so Anthony was exposed to a lot
Type of computer hardware
From a young age
My my dad always High computers around so
I would break those and incur the wrath of my parents and
Eventually I got to a point where
They were sick of me breaking their computers and
And Amy are getting one that I could break myself
Which I hate you know
Learn how to load games onto and learned a little bit of basic and stuff like that and
And this is like the area of like
286 is 386 is
Dos Windows 3.1
Windows 95 that kind of era but I was always really really into that
Cute you started to
Tell her how to program
Is a kid I like how old are you
Probably 1314
Because when I was 5th
Teen I work for an internet company
In in Maryland in Baltimore
Actually they were trying to actually work
Croup my dad and
You know my dad was like I'm busy and I
Employed excetera butt
You know
My sons are good programa you shouldn't you should talk to him
Just to put this in
The right time for talking about the mid to late night
I think you're talkin about the midnight
Give me the web was really new
It wasn't like
Common thing
And I kind of gravitate towards this thing called
Internet relay chat so it's like this like
Global chat room UK
Can kind of go into and
It was like a wild west of the internet like you were connected to this that is not work and
Yeah I remember
Earliest programming I did
Was programming scripts to go into the fire
Find that would control it and give it new functionality and things like that and I also
Was around people who new windows program
And I was obsessed with user interfaces and
I learned a lot of Windows programming because I just wanted to know how it how it all worked I mean
It's really cool I don't know why I was so fascinated by all that
But I was definitely into it
So you I guess
You decide one must have to go to college
You went to the University of Maryland
Yeah
And you are
Studying computer science
And
Time Life
People
On the Block
The websites and
You wanted to do one
Be yourself
Yeah this was like
Mm
And in 2003 I wanted to make a website
Myselfin
I'll take two things about doing that one at the time you had all these different software programs
We have to put together to make what you would
Normally think of is a website right now right do you have blocking software but that's up with them page building software right like that was like
Dreamweaver and FrontPage and all that
Sheppard software that would like tell you who's visiting the website to be like statcounter or something like that
Upload that somewhere and host that somewhere that was an old hosting services that you would
Use an
I just didn't I didn't want I didn't want this mishmash of thanks and the other thing that
I was really into is I was just always into the way it look the way the interface work than I knew the
Give me the finest is going to be like
Create a blog and a website
Remember but
Even in 2003 right not really
No I think that
There was livejournal but that that wasn't a very nice I would like a professional right until you didn't put your professional set
Was blogger at the time which again very personal in nature
I wanted I wanted more of a more of a website it is soon as you start to do that
Yeah that's blocking Services didn't let you do that until you thought right well I gotta make this stuff let me try to figure this out
And so I started making it for myself and I show people it right I mean
Logging software
Make a website with it too is not cool and I remember my friends being like
Are you two hundred bucks for that
And I'm like okay
Maybe other people could use this
And so I started turning it into like a multi-user surface where people go when they could sign up and you know
Service and they could go and create their own site and things like that and and you know it
Pretty quickly evolved
Into this could be a business idea from the beginning
Easy
To build a website was that was that what you were thinking when you were creating the software
So
It was always about
Publishing
I wasn't going to be able to come
Compete
With
FrontPage Microsoft
Dreamweaver
Macromedia later Adobe
When blogging
I see it as a kind of beginning of this DIY
Do it yourself
Wave
Where people who have otherwise been a little intimidated
Yeah it was just kind of like so I can do this to
But then giving them something more power
Sing
Lucky you can publish The Blacklist you can publish your page
You can publish if you can do all of these
The block was the anchor but it was always about doing more with it
So I take me into your arms at your dorm room like are you seeing from
Computer just
Theaters at The Keys just like let's get in there yeah yeah yeah
20 toilets
University of Maryland
In Sky of the dorm is called
South Campus
And I was in a
How many bedrooms
Four four bedroom
You know it's
Single bed end
Does my little desk
In front of it and I have
M20 computers have two monitors which is like a huge deal at the
Like CRT monitors right that he's like giant like heavy like Neymar with televisions used to be like
How do you say particular
What's thanks
So you were
In your dorm room
Just yeah
And how long did it take you to actually build this architect
So
The original version of it
I start a program in 2003
April 2000
A little bit before that
And it took me until
November December I was
It's kind of like done and ready to launch at so
What's a 8 months
And and did you did you have
Annie
Any money any
Small amount of capital to actually
Try and launches into a business
So
Back then
I didn't
And I did everything I could have possibly done with the
Whatever skills I had or whatever I thought I could fake right and so you know
I know how to program a thing I can write the homepage and do the right the marketing copy I can make the interface now
There's a couple things I couldn't do
Right I couldn't invent servers to run it out of nowhere so I needed to buy some
And
I need the money for the service so I went to my event to my
Who
I know how to calculate but I need a 30
And $3,000
To get 30000
To get this off
I needed I needed the servers I need
The two of them right because
Crashes that
Yeah text nice quiet I know that using scratch
Dad friend
And it was a fight I remember
Parking of the University of Maryland
I was in that that's stupid parking lot outside of the door
And I remember being on my phone
NN yeah it was like why do you need to why can't you have one
Why doesn't
Yeah that would be half like I mean it was It was a
It was a fight
And
Yo they eventually
I eventually won that fight and ended
The first semester
Did you call it
Squarespace already like
Did you already pick that name
Yeah
Exactly when I picked it but
I needed to get to the.com
The. Net
The. Org domain
Dad-to-be open
Rights I need to be able
Negotiate for them
Because I got in having mites o
I remember
Googling it
At the time and there was Zero Google results for
And I was like okay
We're starting from zero here
And
For some reason just thought like
Okay
Squarespace
Like
Monitors were more
Square that the time they were in his rectangular like
It's not your space online I guess that works and
You know I can probably draw the logo for the
But
Yeah I mean that's kind of that's kind of where it started
So if I ran into junior year of college
What's going on
Is business now is it what what's the business what would
Dakota publishing
I said you know what's a way to make websites and blogs
And I probably would lean more into to blogging back then cuz it was more topical and people were like what's that
DIY Thing 1
Possible
Yeah this is why when you launched it in 2004 like you just don't know
Play button and then and then it just like here it is or Squarespace
So I won the fight with my parents
On the thirty Grand and
Cerberus right
And so
They were on the floor of my dorm room for a while
And you're most vulnerable to Data Center these are not like
Normal
They're like really flat really long
And really really loud and so
They're so loud that I have to keep him off cuz otherwise
Terrible back of the time I read
A lot about software development blogs I read
Was this guy
Joel spolsky and his blog was hosted
In New York by a company called Pier 1
And so I was like okay well when I do a Datacenter
Hear what sounds good they like Joe and say hello
I visited New York as a kid and
There's just something about it
That I I just knew
I just knew I wanted to be there
Eventually them up
A my car
Put everything in
And turn them on check that I can remotely connect to them and tell when like at dinner New York and then
So when do you when you launched
Squarespace
Spike from the perspective of a customer
Yeah it was just a website
People would
Book find
Right so
I turned it on and I was like what how am I going to get people shot like
I guess you can do advertising
And so I bought a bunch of Google AdWords what now
Watch about like 200 bucks
Google AdWords
Underlight
Website make a blog like all these
Different things and
A couple people came to
Like I'm even talking like
Not a lot
Sore like
To sign up
Squarespace inc
So
Loon facts
Actually for the
First gear
Did have a
Free plan
You could actually use it for
Afraid we always had a free trial
But then I actually had a
Free plan
Any idea
Yeah there are plenty of examples of
People giving away software for free and no sings growing up
I like your Hover was free millions of account
Myspace whatever it like
People going to give away for free and that people cannot
And so in the first year
I realize that
There were a lot of people who are going to use this thing
For free that were
Never ever ever
And again I'm running this like
I don't like
Other money
So I need to keep this thing running so I don't want
The people who are free
Who are never going to upgrade
Using up all the service beso and it was really not the point of the thing it was
But I was out there trying to make an ex livejournal
Blogger I wanted the
Let me focus on the people that want to pay for this
Africa
Between 5 and 2
15 bucks a month
They Don't Really inexpensive
Soapdish
A man in that in 2004 that first year
I mean you are still a student and running this thing and what did that
What is your life look like in that plane
It was interesting how it evolved because the end of the year
I'm making 50 Grand a year my parents will I breaking a job after college it's a nice little side project but word
Your job and I really started to see at the end of that year if I double to Triple that like
They stay around right like they make a website for not leaving
Going to try and grow this until I actually stayed on the graduating in 4 years I waited in The Graduate
Fit in 5
And kind of took some like
I just a pretty light workload classes on that app
I was buying myself time right I was buying myself out of like my parents really getting on my case
About getting a job cuz I got to pass them in school I mean I think that they were the inklings of how it would later impact my life
But I don't think it really it hit me that stuff coming like I I just wanted these events along the way
One of the early once was
This is my friend and we're taking a road trip
To Miami
17 hour drive somewhere
Along the way
Call myself
And
Hi guys like hey it's course it's okay and I'm like
I don't know
Take me to an internet cafe
This is ridiculous
This is mm
This is a different world of internet and I like log on and I can remotely log into the servers and like reboot
Put something that comes back in the
And it was like my first taste of this like
Responsibility
End
Foreshadowing
What would that
App simulator
In your arms
You graduated from
College Inn
And by the time
You graduated college
I've heard that you guys had like
About 10000
Townsend
He knows it's starting to look pretty good
Would you were the only
Person right you were the engineer designer and support rapping
Can see you
Yeah I was I was kind of everything I mean so in the first year
I think we will like a run rate of like 50 Grand
And in the second year I think we were at a run rate of like
200 Grand
Then it was like a million bucks every night
But it
In your to I was able to convince my parents
Instead
I'm going to do this and
I started looking for apartments
In New York
I knew I wanted
In New York I put the service there
It was like the scene of
These like really happy moments in my life but also he's like
Readily traumatic moments
Where
There was nothing to happen maybe
A year in
Where
I didn't have a lot of space
And so
I have my redundant one but it was
And so at some point this happen again
Thanks black.
Somebody say hates down okay I try and login to account login
So I called the date
I'm hating you reboot
The server
And it doesn't come back
Bluegrass
And it wasn't coming
And I was in Maryland
Evansville
Yeah my girlfriend
And I was like I got to go to New York right now
As of 50 minutes
I just got the car
But server the backseat
And I just drive to New York
Anime
Can I get screwed I lost all the data
That little experiment over like I should have the other thing
There is replicated all the stuff in
I had levels of redundancy
He just not that much
And so I remember going up there and
Thing like IHOP's works
And taking baths
Are the computers and taking all the drives at Awana
Sliding them into the other
And turning the thing back on
And
Turned on
Africology
You decided to move to New York
God is it closer to the server
Just want to live there too
Yeah place
So I went to Craigslist
Yeah I didn't know anyone in the city inside it
Want to live alone there's no reason
Incur that expense and like
I moved in with four other complete strangers off of Craigslist
And is a 5 bedroom apartment
4th floor walkup and I remember I had to Old BMW
Black 3 Series I
Packed everything Ike
Could into this car I remember driving
Up to New York alone
And
The first thing I did is made like an illegal turn over 23rd Street and got a ticket
And then the second thing that happened to me was
I park in front of my place tonight I guess I
Park like this but I'm going to be running out of my car and carrying all my stuff up
Literally alone at the end of the last trip I was just sitting out on my phone my
4 and I was getting a little bit tired
Take a minute
Exhausting and
I go down my car is towed
So it's like I'm just piled
Tickets and no car and
I remember going back up to my room
And realizing like
I have a light in this room New York crap like
Go to like the tow yard or whatever on the west side
Get my car and call up one of my best friend
Live in Philadelphia
And so I went back to fix the next day bought myself a lamp upon myself a pet
And I went on from there
This is 2006 and I think Square Face was still just
Yeah so I had at some point along the way a part-time
For the editors somebody who's doing part-time customer support and then I had contracted out
I'm somebody to do helping me with a template designs but they would know no full-time employee
And was your office your room in your apartment it was
And the time like
Were they just internet thing
It's like the New York right and it's New York
10 years against not like Silicon Valley
What do you do you make websites whatever
Anyway
Philly startup they're like oh you're unemployed interesting that's cool
So what's an 2006
Speaking about
Tu250
And read something like that which would sounds like a lot of money
Before
A guy in his
Early or mid-twenties
Will you making a lot of money with a lot of profit or is it
Just
We are expenses I would put it 100% back in
As much as I can
If I
May twenty bucks an AdWords I put twenty bucks back in
I made a thousand bucks and out of it that's in a thousand more
Device payment
Yeah I keep a little bit of a balance in case I needed it for something but
I would just put
Almost all of it back in
And
Yeah I mean I didn't have a problem
Pay my rent
Yeah I was going out with other
People my age so it wasn't like
Yet you won't go to Michelin 3-star restaurants
No no I couldn't even find someone to go with me if I wanted to
And
At some point
Forgot exactly why
But I ended up being like okay I should
I should have an offer
Just a split up
Workday
And not work day and so I remember being the okay well let's see and took a course
Craigslist
And I rented a desk
Architects
Down in
West Broadway in
So it's like
Tribeca but you were still doing most
Everything
Like you were the
CTO the CEO you were
Designing stuff for a while and and how did you cope with that was it was exciting was amazing
Are you stressed out or what
I think it took me years
To fully appreciate
What the stress was really doing to me
You know at some
Point in this
Two things happen
One I stopped making progress I would set
These minor goals myself like the simple things like okay I want this feature out in a month and then you know
I just
Ryan Edwards I pay my taxes and like you no answer, so I didn't actually get anywhere until I started
This is Millwork into
Yeah but they packed
And I didn't know what that was or where that's from or I'd never experienced that in my life before like like heart palp
Applications engineer
Yeah yeah Hearts racing
Gets rights closing up you can't breathe a busy cuz you're having a heart attack or what you think in your mind to be a heart attack
Here's the funny thing and it's why I said that I didn't really appreciate what it was doing to me it was
Almost nothing would regret you just be kind of there and he start to get your
Your head start to focus on it start to get stressed and you know it was stressful in the moments where the server would cry
Something in my heart would be racing but
But that's not a panic attack panic attacks like
You just sitting there at like
2 p.m.
In your room
Hanging out
And your heart's racing
They don't know why but was stressing you out
What do you remember what
The things that would stress you out
Yeah I think that
Try to do it alone for a while
The infrastructure side is so I can't really like
Explain to you
How stressful this was because eventually after
Then crashed a bunch
You set up monitoring
The monitoring
Check City
And if it
Crashes
So there's a performance
Problem or whatever
They would send a message
Where's my phone
And so it would happen in the middle of the night it would happen
If I'm out to dinner and you never know what's wrong with it
It's always like the psychological
Are you go figure out if your wife broke
Like and there's no one else who can save you
Cuz no one else knows
Don't think so
Go for it
It was like in a way I was really free because I was in New York and I had control over my schedule at and all those Miami
Plays in the self-service thing any other hand I'm completely and totally trapped
When we come back in just a moment how Anthony started to
Bring other people on board to help out and then realize that letting go of control
Is a lot harder than he thought
Steak and Gyros and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Score Fitness podcast in the following message come from fidelity
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor to help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact
Taxes and make
Clear recommendations for your
Full Financial picture
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
This message comes from NPR sponsor squares
Squarespace allow small businesses to
Design and build their own website
Using customizable Leo
And features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
Squarespace also offers
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online press
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
This from NPR
Around 2006
Things are going
Pretty well for Anthony casalena
Middle East business
Personally
It's not so great
He's running Squarespace
Hayirli by himself
Annie's really stressed out
Squarespace
Totally consumed in his life
Even refuses to travel by plane because he's afraid the server bike crash while he's in the air
It's a one-day
Someone suggested Anthony
She got some business advice
Converse lot of customers over chat with Verizon support and stuff like that
And it was a point where
I was having a lot of castles
Swann customer and
Hey I'll introduce you to somebody who is business guy and will help you
They were talking to this guy for a while
And it was like Hey you know you're really good
Anthony at
Engineering design all these things that you
I have done up to this point you know in an end or somewhat successful at right I mean this is not
Christmas is a good store
Why not you know not a bad way
But you haven't been rated hiring
Yeah you haven't hired any
Are any of that business
Yeah well I mean some parts of
Business I would say cuz I mean distance
What time and it's like this was a really successful project
This was not a really successful
Company even though it really look like
Right and he said okay you know let's join up
And I'll be the CEO
And
You is founder everything else it'll be great
And you know I'm going to bring over one of my friends
An engineer and looks are hiring people
Bonsai Janus
Which specialty
Who was
Damn look what was his background what how did he
Convince you to
Well I mean
He was somebody who had
Get started a couple companies in New York I'm kind of
I'm blanking on some of them but he was a guy who old older than you
Yeah
Maybe like
1215 years older than me
Something like that
Right so what's up more Experian
Answer the brain
Yeah yeah
How
How are you going to
Hey I was there enough Revenue coming in Where You Are
Pay you a salary
Yeah totally
Squarespace always had enough money to
Yeah
Salary is that kind of wasn't an issue
So he came aboard as your CEO and
Scholastic
Gross
Yeah and I eat
For me at the time
I didn't know what it meant
Have a certain title or not have a certain title I was just like look this is fluid easy okay cool
I'm still running the show here like I you know
I'll just take this risk
And over the next
Couple of years we moved into an office
On Center Street in SoHo
And yeah we started adding people of the car
And frankly some
A lot actually join very organically
Play we had
Some people join in
Creative rolls who were
Customers actually some moves
15 New York
Yeah we had a guy join and help
Yes
Do people help with the infrastructure and
Did that instantly
Free you up
Did that take some of the pressure off
Honestly
More people there
So I am at least not like alone and in my head
And that really needs some stress but I
I think it probably
Created more stress for me
Then I realized
Because I didn't fully appreciate
What I was doing what
I'm 20 what
Four five six
I never heard a single person
Entire life
And I'd say that you're through this process site
I learned a lot about myself
I learned a lot about
11 people in a company
And I learned a lot of lessons
Really the hard way by literally making icing
Pretty much every possible
Steak
One can make
You start this thing in your dorm room
It's you
You're the engineer you're the CEO your the marketing guy
Team up with somebody who has business
Experience
Who has a plan
We need to start hiring people lie to expand which is exciting
Camp butt
You would have to give up
Rollover
The day-to-day running of
Can imagine was probably not easy
Yeah and it didn't work for me
Was there friction between you and Dan
Oh yeah
Which is very normal and it happens
All the time
In startups
Write this is a story we've heard on the show before
He was there for five years
Ukiki Lefton
Start his own company but during that five-year. Was it
Really difficult for you to
Align
What your Visions were did you
Kind of
Plow through that five-year period or or was it actually okay
There wasn't really okay
I think
You look I was young
Bright and I think
The people had
A good intent
Send N I didn't know what I was getting into
I need to know what a good manager that look like I didn't know how much stress I was supposed to have or not have
I didn't know what kind of dialogue
We're good or bad at like what the
Dysfunction look like what
Yeah I didn't know that
And so I was in this motorbike
Keep it all together.
Is keep it together
Don't let it fall apart
Don't go back to zero
Keep it together
And try and find a way through this
And that was a lot of what I was
What's the temperature
Actual
Website publishing status
Intersect
Cuz I mean Danes there's
Scrolling
Is like
The delay mm
Let's see what's happening on the
On the product side
So
The product
Add squares
This is always
Ben one of the
Primary growth drivers
And
A lot of good things happened
The time I mean we
Suspender advertising channels
Adding more
People method
I wasn't in this mode anymore where I was sort of
Just constantly like not hitting any goals and so
Around
So
We launched
Squarespace 5
Which was
A huge huge update to the platform mean
Deers like
07 wait something like that
Animations and things on a website and web apps
Like we're entering into a different era
And
Launching Squarespace 5 was either one of the things that helped Propel us forward and I would say that
It was a total disaster
We flipped it on for everyone at once
It had these
Really hard to track down bugs
We're literally working
24/7 overnight
Every single person
Cuz it was just crashing and crashing and we couldn't roll it back
And
You know I think that we finally got
Through it and
We kept growing up
And at the time
Yeah we had a couple
People in mark
We had more people in product view more people engineering we had
Weather South 10 million-dollar run-rate
And at some point
We were approached
Just to sell the car
And
Yeah so we got approached by Getty and
Yo Gotti sells
Stock photo stock photo stock video stock audio Etc
I want other ideas as well a lot of these
Images end up going with websites why don't we
We sell stock websites to
Yeah this is little company in New York
15th Virginia
Job so
Banded up
Coming and talking
With me
And
You know I don't come from
Like
Money or anything like that
And I had never started
Squarespace 2
Sell it like
I was having a good time. We were making impact on the web
And some dishes are not insignificant
Offer to buy the company
And that would have been a really
I really I struggled with it
So what you do
Brown the same time I was also approached I don't even know how they like caught windows
Spotlight
What's meant Pastor saying hey you don't have to
To do that you don't have to sell it all
If you want some liquidity why don't you accept an investment from us
School put some money into the
The company you can sell some of your shares to us
You can keep running it will put a board and play as well help you recruit Executives and all that
And I am
I like that and if if the other shows did anything it did cause me to go down that track
And realize
I want to keep
I want to keep running it
I want to
South of my shares in the company
What a real board in place
I want
Different kinds of kind of a different kind
So we closed
An investment from indexing
Cell
In July of 20
10 * 2
Forums index
Dentures and Accel partners and
Think I read
38 million dollars
Yep 38.5
And I think that
That was the one of the catalysts
Stormy kind of kicking off
That era of
After this investment
We started looking at the product
And I remember this moment with
Dinner with one of my main
Prada people and we were looking at the site survey
Cradle cap form
I'm a businessman
Texarkana
But
Not growing as well as you know we had
We're starting to tap out on a couple different
Add channels where you reach kind of exhaustion
Spending
Not hit appointment
But
I'm in the web is changing there were
Did the iPhone
NN so people were
More used to saying okay the web
Experience on my phone while different
Needs to be very high fidelity
And The Sting the sting that we had
Add Squarespace five
Yeah it wasn't going to
It was going to do it I mean it too
These look like outside bars
Leaving work on phones what is it
And so
Me and a couple people
Started to rewrite all squares
Like the whole thing
Wow this is an
Hits in 2011
Until we start to work on Squarespace
Escorts basics
Don't look if anyone knows what it sounds like when I'm like I will
Just rewrite the thing
Like that's probably the worst
You never want to be in a situation where you're rewriting core platform
It always takes three times longer than a week
Expect another people who Ridge
And it's usually disaster
But
Yeah I want
To take another shot at
Does that was the point of the investment
The point of the investment was
We're not done
We know we can
Make something better
It's over 2 years
A small group of people
Made Squarespace
Which
Really division was
And we want to be able to create any kind of website
You resumed
The role of CEO after Dan laughing around 2011 that right and the 2010
And you are leading the re-architect like a complete re architecture
Encoding how are you coding
And also try to like be a CEO to where you
Cuz you're good coder obviously were you able to also be a good CEO I think
I was in a mode where
I knew I didn't have the right kind of support around me
I think during this time
I started realizing
What a horrible manager was
You know after this invest
It was a year after
And I ended up meeting are our first
VP of engineering
John Coulton is
Great
And I was trying to code running
Nearing team ahead
Weird relationships in like
He just like immediately
Took
Such a massive amount of stress away
With respect to
How to be a manager
How to remove Roblox from people
You like I just learned so much and I've never worked anywhere else really it sounds Anthony like you
You
Grilling
I mean you were a kid you know
Premature like you eat a weed overall
Different versions of ourselves
Fox as we get older than me at 30
NBA 20 are very different from who I am today
And it sounds like
You
You started to kind of
Realize this
What are you okay with criticism and feedback or did you when you get defensive
What are things that happened a long time ago in Squarespace when
Doing a lot of customers
Support and doing it all alone
It's like
What do you like
The feedback or not you're about to get a lot of it
Right I mean people cursing me out saying idiot
ATS equipment manager on the line even though I'm the only person the compass
Like
Then then literally leaving and being like I'm
Done with you
This product sucks and so over the years I think I I develop some amount of
Realization that
I need to create a
Find where I hear feedback
I always have
To agree with it
But to create event we don't
Here it is
Is really the scariest
Sting for me
Because I think that
If you remain closed off to it
Vulnerable
Is big like
Seismic shifts where
Ignored something
The point where things really going to break
So I'm worried about
China listen to what's there and
Figure out what I can
Can figure out from it
Because look
At the end of the day I've made so many mistakes it would be so silly
For me to sit there and think that I'm not
Making any now
Have to be
Help him just more to intuitive
Chaster resolving
What what
And it sounds like a turning point was when
This new team started the
Cam you start
To rewrite the software but
Divisibility of squares
Space Also change like you guys
A pretty interesting
Strategy which was to advertise on
Podcast
Seattle disclosure
And then people weren't really doing that in mm
Yes so we did it even before 2010
I mean podcast
Yeah I remember
Yeah we were going to we're going to maybe try podcast
The first pocketed it was This Week in Tech
And
I'm sure it cost like
Xiaomi like 30 grand
That's our whole AdWords budget
Like the whole month
And how many podcast reads and what's the audience in are you sure like I don't know but you know what at the end of the day
And it immediately worked for us
Yuasa traction right away
Right away
You could do this is really authentic thing around like you are supporting a show host that show host
Has a connection with their audience
You are supporting the creation of that
Content and you never hide the fact that it's sponsored but you know
People genuinely like okay I'm bored with this I love podcast I love this show thank you Squarespace for doing this
And I think that
It was a it was a really great thing for us like every podcast was sponsored by
We tried
We really tried
I'm later on
It was a joke
When we first did I Super Bowl ad
Somebody was tweeting they were like I didn't know the Super Bowl to the podcast
So yeah I mean we went in his face and it yeah it was great because I mean it's something we related to what we did right Square
Play supports lots and lots and lots of independent creators make a lot of podcast series
We're independent
Creators and they had you know voices in and show Concepts that otherwise wouldn't have
Will you know existed if it wasn't for that Medium so it's really amazing to be able to support it
The way we get
As you serve began to turn a corner did the growth just come from in a combination of
More outside capital and the ability to Market your brand more is that was that the game changer
For you
The outside capital
Is not it main driver for it
Was
Squarespace 6
Launching
And that changed every
Lacrosse
This is Mike 2012 July
Is version 6 is Squarespace
Version 6 of squares
This is the one that you know
Small team couple years after the
This investment
Came together
The rewrite
You can use today
Yeah this is the one that's online today
It's technically seven but it's not a big
Diversion difference
And it changed over metrics
You know you had all these
Crazy Beautiful sites you could do
It portfolio sites
The fullscreen images you could use those for businesses
The sites were
If some of the first sites that
Work perfectly on mobile phones without any adjustment
That's right and so that was a bee
Big deal
Without that product squares
I'm curious how did you I mean you started this in 2000
3 write in a dorm room and it was really nothing
Like it out there
Today
There's a lot of competition
This much more complex
World that was
20 shifts
When you first had Squarespace
Lights out in the world
Yeah
Yes it was funny
It's almost love
Last Dragon
And you know I don't know if you
You could grow this
AdWords
The same way I did
15 years ago cutting people look they look for the brand
It's definitely a different landscape and also
When you got companies like us that have had such
Investment
For such a long period of time
In the space it's really
As we've grown
The ambition of the company is scale
It started with
Can you make a website for
From South to
Yeah can we make blogs in these other kinds
To you know the kind of sites
Kraton scores
6 in
Converse platform medicine
Can you sell on Squarespace
A lot of people selling on Squarespace
And yeah we're just really centered around entrepreneurial success
Can you put the site online
We help you be successful in marketing yourself and
Starting a business
That's really the core with Squarespace is about
You now have this
Huge
It means that with that comes like
Responsibilities that you probably never even imagined power
You probably never even imagined or wanted
Charlie Wilson
Controversy I think last year where some like white supremacists are using
Squarespace and
You know you're going to face these things all the time
Yep how do you delay each
Each situation
You know what would you do
You try and have rules around it and so
Thing that's great about Squarespace frankly versus other
Situations other providers are in
Is the
Is a paid service
So we have to avoid the worst of
That Sprite very rarely as somebody like
I'm supposed to punch bad stuff online. Here's my credit card and here's my address and I'm going to post you know what I mean like
We're very lucky
So
Are Stan's like everyone else
The stats has to evolve Wellness as
As time goes on because
Yeah we are business
We're not
The government and we're not you know trying to protect every possible
Viewpoint on the planet
And so
Yeah we need to make sure that
And I we're doing business with the right
You know the kind of people we need to do business with
I think at the end of 2017 Squarespace raise
$200
Funding
Valuing the company at 1.7 billion might be valued higher now
A lot of money and you were
You know your attack
Success
These conferences
But
You are also does it also make it challenging
To you know to make new friends and to meet new people because you never know if people just want to be around you for that reason
Yeah I'm really lucky in life that I've always been the kind of person that I've made good friends that have
Kind of gone
Through a lot with me and I know kind of what that
But that looks like when it's
Nanjing
Superficial and
Yeah I still have a lot of friends from
Like from that that original apartment in New York
I think that's been a really positive part of my life actually have we stay in touch in
You got older and
Contact
So it is harder it becomes harder than
Wilshire any when you're when you're 23 24 and you got your reading roommates and you
Have a bunch of time and you have your school friends whatever like yeah people are more up and now more people are
And kind of Family Medicine everything
You want to do that
Have family
It's a great Quest
I've really put Austin
So much has changed my life so rapidly
It's really been focused on all of that
I'm not ruling it out I just
It's not front and center right now
But you know
The things are friends and reminded 25 and 35
Different
Your mom
When are you going to go
They do that they do that though don't don't don't worry that voice
Anthony obviously you're
You see how you were like
Super talented
Coder programmer
From young age
And I have a lot of talent
How much how much of your success
Because of that talent and your skill and your
Intelligence how much of it
Do you think it's because you
You just got lucky
Oh man I've been lucky so many times in my life
My parents had a computer around me
Yeah I'm lucky that they didn't get deleted their Alita but all these scenarios I mean
Yeah we're words even scratching the surface of the other crazy things that have happened that mean
I'd say the
There
Qualities I probably have the
Have helped
Me stay here around you know perseverance and pain tolerance in
And make us some level of adaptability
My best moment some kind of self-awareness but
No I think that anyone who possibly claims that
They didn't get Lucky's crazy that's Anthony casalena
Founder of Squarespace last year there was speculation Anthony would take the company public
But for now
Squarespace has decided
Stay private
Meanwhile Anthony still keeps a vast collection of magic
The Gathering cards that he bought when he was a kid
He says he's got hundreds of them sitting in binders in a storage space
Including the rare Black Lotus car
Said to be worth more than $20,000
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first
Equipment store how I built this 2019 lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing platform
Mobile-friendly email templates
Drag-and-drop email Builder
Customer support 7 days a week
More
Campaignmonitor.com
Make your emails
Unforgettable
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that
What's a story starts in mm
Right outside of Boston with K Westervelt waddling around Target
Waddling around Target because
She just been released from the hospital where she given birth to a 9 and 1/2 pound baby boy
So Kate was sore
And she had stitches and
She was really up for a Target run
Now the thing you should know about Kate is that she's kind of a planner so she's already fully stocked her Nursery
Free with everything she thought the baby would need
Diapers and wipes and
Clothing
But she didn't really give much thought to the things that she might need
After her baby was born
The nurses walked in with things like mash underwear and
Ginormous pad
Plus ice packs and
Squeeze bottle to help keep her stitches
Clean
Old stuff she needed for her recovery
What stuff Kate didn't have at home
On the way home from the hospital while her husband and new baby waited in the car
She went shopping
And
Chevelle
Kind of Clueless
I got
A bunch of different
Breastfeeding AIDS you know organic pads synthetic pads whatever I could get my hands on because I was
I was just desperate and in dire need of any help and I'll help and I knew I wouldn't be able to get to the store again in the next
Couple days
Kate left the store
Totally overwhelmed but
She also left
With an idea
We live in a convenience economy we get razors delivered groceries delivered everything is delivered
How are we not providing this convenience for new moms
You need it the most
And as soon as she got back in the car Kate. I'm going to go build this thing
And by this thing
Cement a box
Build with products
A new mom would need
A box delivered right to your door
She kept thinking about this idea during her leave
Choked after she went back to her nine-to-five job
Kate decided to start working on it
At night
After her baby went to sleep
I would order various products then I would test them all
Maternity pads creams protein bars herbal supplements
He tried more than 400 products over the course of a year
And eventually she settled I set of
And items
To go into her first boxes
She said the friends and family and she asking for feedback
And the one products are test mom's really like
Ice pack
At the hospital they give you the
Bags of ice and stick them in your underwear and say good luck
So Kate found the perfect ice pack size and shape
Some new moms could walk around
But there was some women to told her you know this ice pack
Rate
I ended up with a C-section
And what I really needed was a heating pad to play some
Belly
Or
Some sort of oil for my scar in my incision line
Shiki decided maybe I should
Curator C-section recovery box
She went on to put up a website and build a social media following on Facebook and Instagram
Really viral 60% of moms
Momsource across the internet
So Mom started to talk about this box
And in January of 2018 nearly two years after her frustrating Target run
Kate sold her first box
It was designed to look just like a present
Pink and glossy and I thought you know let's put a handle on this box because it makes it feel like a
Special arrival like a special trunk
Filled with self care items
Kate decided to jump
Bully into this Venture so she quit her job launch the company and in her first year she sold almost
500 boxes all assembled and packed in a room above her garage kit Westerville the business is called
Call Mom box and if you want to find out more about it or hear previous episode head to our podcast page
I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story please visit build NPR
Cr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're
Are there please do give us a review
Go straight to us at HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet it's at how I built this
It was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Carney JC Howard Norco scene Eva Grant
Jeff Rogers AR intern is Candice Lim
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
From NPR
Conspiracy theories seem to be everywhere
But they're far from the modern problem
Through line
We'll explore how conspiracy theories led to the founding of the United States
And how they became the currency of political opportunist
Long before the intern
Through line
The podcast where we go back in time
To understand the Press
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
This campaign money
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week