Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is
When is Good Day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim style
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
So before we start to show
I just call you know that we
Just released a bunch more tickets
Live show in Portland
On Thursday May 16th
I'll be trying to live on stage
Tibbetts
Creator of tofurky
So if you haven't gotten
Still a chance to grab some
Live show with Seth
Supported by America
Express
How to get tickets
MPR presents
. org
And out
To see you informal
There were days when I thought nothing could stop us that
This is going to work and that this is going to be the most brilliant thing ever and there were other days that were
Really really dark and I just would hold my head and my hands
And say wow this is never going to work
From NPR how I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealist stories behind the movements they built
Alex Kidd in California watch the PC Revolution unfold in front of them
Is Fortune with computer table
So what's your regular list
You know
How much I love
The gold rush
Because there's a simple Elegance to it
All those people going to mine for gold
Heated tents
Pickaxes
Shoveled
Take me to the food supply
Transportation
Entire industries were built around the rush
And people who had nothing to do with gold
Made a lot of money
Which can sometimes be
The smartest way to think about a business
Especially
Chet Pipkin
Yes
You've never heard of Chet Pipkin
He doesn't do a whole lot of interviews
Generally keeps a low profile
But there is a good chance you've heard of it
The company
NPR computer or
Smartphone
You very likely use a Belkin product
Because Belkin makes
Accessories
Naturetek devices work
Things like tables
Surge protectors
Keyboard
Networking device
It's a company that was built around the PC boom
And then later
The smart phone bill
Now if you think a lodging business
Is a marathon
Where the starting line is the idea
Finish Line
Is a successful company
I think we can all agree that everyone starts that race in the same position
Name some of the founders we've talked to hit clearly you start out with certain advantages maybe they've got money in the
Bancorp they know people who have lots of money because they went to a top business school or they just start with
Valuable experience in a certain industry
But in his case
Chet launch Falcon he was just 21 years old
He didn't have any money
Kid dropped out of college and he certainly didn't have a clear idea of how business even worked
But he did have one really important advantage
A good childhood in a stable family life
His parents were both blue collar workers who moved to Hawthorne California
Farms in the Midwest
The second world war brought them both west
My mom doing work in support of the war effort my dad
Also
And that eventually he was drafted
Into the Army Air corps
And they both settled in Southern California
After that
Will you parents
Educated Beyond
Very little formal education so I think my dad made it
A little bit past the eighth grade
And the same was true
For my mom
I think partially because my mom didn't have the benefit of a lot of formal education it was really key to her
She was definitely a lifelong learner
She's the best speller
That I've ever met in my whole life
How she got there with head limited education I don't know
My dad was a machinist
He worked on a lot of defense and Aerospace work
What he could create out of metal with the his hands was
Really inspiring
Yeah they both had bearberry
Little formal logic
Besides having a great family
The other day
That hat was
The time
The place you grew up
Time because he finished high school in the late 1970s
On personal computers
Just starting to become a saint
And the place
Because Hawthorne was a hub
Aerospace and defense contractor
Anyway After High School
Chad Stark
Classes at you
UCLA
Still living with us
And working out
Few different jobs for money
But he didn't even make it through a year of
College because instead
He was spending all this time just
Hang out all these different
Computer shops close to his house
A lot of these Engineers had set up these shops they were
Hobby shops or small
Mom and Pop
Style stores
Selling
These are early models of
PCS and printers and modems
And yeah
More of them did not wear
Hawthorne Boulevard
So it was a very rich place to I be able to go from shop to shop and just kind of walk in
Ask a bunch of questions observe and them that's precisely what I did
But were you into computers was that I mean were you like
Trying to program computers and take them apart
Or was it something different
Most definitely
Interested in how things work
So part of it is I did
As a kid was I took things apart just
The kind of see how they worked in
Every so often I was able to
To unsuccessfully put them back together
And I had a lot of ideas about
How to make
Who sings better
I imagine
Creating a different kind of
Shower head
That would maintain a constant
Temperature
I thought about putting a little
Metal strips in the road to a be able to
To allow cars to cannot drive themselves down the road and
Different kinds of things
Turn into anything about
Computers per se
That
It look
Like it was going to be
This next
Huge
Generation
Transformational change
Ferrum how people might live
And I wanted to learn as much as I could
So you
You are
A student
UCLA
Hanging out around these like
Early p
PC
Suzy ass
Shops
Did you eventually be like try to get a job at one of these places
So there was a bunch of things going on for me all at once I was
Working at the YMCA as a day camp counselor
Most of these kids were kids that it had negative
Encounters with
Society or
People of the law or something
I was also working for an electronic
Components
Manufacturer
Remember I was
Counting some of these things and ask them when I go what do they do
When the person says
Doesn't matter what they do for you just count them
And the heck I just sort of smiled and got a catalog and figured out what it is day I did do it
Yeah
I was going to class I should have been doing my homework and I was learning as much as I could about pcso
So instead of spending time on my studies and my homework
I finally just said
Why don't I just
Give it a go and then it's either going to work
Or I'll get it out of my system and then I will take it from there but
This is just something that I had to go do
And what what what was it I mean what was I mean did you have an idea what that thing was going to be or you just start
I'm going to do something in computers
Yashow the early thought was
Understand this and it's going to be inevitable
That they're going to be gaps they're two they're going to be things that people want
To do that the other people are not thinking about
I didn't know exactly what that was but I knew the kinds of things that I was looking for
And then as I began to hang out in the stores
Most of the folks seem to enjoy having me around
I just watched
And
What are the things that
Was impossible situation to miss almost from day one was these folks
Goodbye
This PC and a printer
And then that they would say
How do I make this work
Well you just plug it in okay well can I have the thing to plug it in with
And because these computers were being made by all these different manufacturers they had different
Connectors on them and the printers had different connectors on them
And it's not like the way that it works today that there's a relatively small number of them
Interfaces to a good things to a work together it was almost unlimited
In that day and age
It was an absolute nightmare for folks who were just trying to get the stuff to work for them
Early days of the railroad like they had
Different gauges on the rail line so like what's the other one
It wouldn't connect cuz they were different sizes that's exactly right and there was no reason for things to
I work across these platforms
Until there I was and yeah
Remind me of trying to sync my Google Calendar with my Outlook
Calendar
Impossible
In some ways things have really evolved into gotten better and in other ways when exactly the same
Spot aren't we
Take me into one of these
PC shop
In 19
Anyone
R82
What does it look like inside look like
Shelves
Stocktwits
All kinds of different accessories
Different kinds of computers or was it more like a
Like a Soviet supermarket in 1985
So they all look very similar
The
Proprietor was almost always doing it on a
Part-time basis
That would be people walking in saying
Hey I've heard
That I can do word
Processing
That I do not need to use my typewriter
Anymore
Can you help me
With that
So
This was unbelievably
Explosive
It was so exciting it was so much fun
Transformational change
Of course it was changing so so quickly
So walking into these places and
Talking to folks was one of the primary ways that people were able to learn and
To be aware of things
Are you say you are
This young guy and you're watching
Explosion
All these different small companies
Try to get into this
PC thing
Is a clearly see where this is heading
Word processing in
Spreadsheet stuff now but it's going to be something much much bigger
What I wonder is
Why is that point in juicing
I want to be a PC maker I want to get into the PC thing is for making personal computers did you even
Think about that it definitely crossed my mind
But it was pretty quickly dismissed
The amount of capital that it would have taken
To do that and have any meaningful way would have been more than I could have imagined being able to kind of musty
And the Dew and secondly
There seems to be a lot of people going after that
Space
And the void I saw
Looked even more compelling and more exciting to a May than making the other Hardware
Connect with the boy that you said was
Peebles
Yeah I mean there is no
No missing it
That wow the big void here
Is
Providing
This elegant
Tool to folks to make the stuff
Work together the way that it should be able to
So the path we took
Overwhelmingly on
It sounds like
You saw the PC Revolution happening
That was the Gold Rush
That was where all the
People rushing into and your thinking
I'm going to sell pickaxes and shovels
Yeah I think that's a really good way to phrase it
What time we hadn't have the capital to do the stake in the in the mine itself
But there were definitely things that people needed that was
Fix it for us
I'm trying to figure this out
You're like
20/20
You realize that
Connectors
Cables that was not
Opportunity
I like where do you get the wires where do you get the
The plastic
To cover the cables where to get there
Pin connector thingies
So I've been taking the stuff
Apart and putting it back together
I've been wiring up things on my own kind of like
Cannibalizing
Some of the things for other things
So I had hands on
Experience from tinkering and
And building
And yeah just kind of dive in and
Do it so
I went often and bought some cable and bought the wires and bought the connectors and
And then I started putting them all together
I think you are still living with you
Parrots
That is right and I am
I've been in the same house my entire life
So this first started to happen
On my parents dining room tables where I was building the stuff at
Night
And after a couple of day does Maya mom goes
Chat I love you very very much
You're going to get the stuff
Office
It's our first big move was from there to the
Garage
And
We were there until we moved again so
And you say we
Was it was her we or was it just you
Yeah it was just me
It's just really hard for me to use and I or and me
Infant picture this
You had like a
Soldering iron and you know what's that metal that you used
Why can't I used to do as a kid solder
The very first things that I made I use my dad's tools
And then he was very
Curious she was very supportive
He was never in my hair but it wasn't far away and Abby would watch
Xiaomi work
And then he would actually machine other little tools and things saying
Hey do you want to give this
A try I think that this might be
Helpful
He didn't understand anything about the electronics
But boy that guy was really good at making stuff
What's that expensive your bunch of wires cables and and then
Different connectors and then just soldering them together
Did they look like a Homespun like Frankenstein
Wires did they actually look
Professional probate the factory the first stuff we are made was really bad
So it was really Frank
Anstine stop
And it function
Computer shops where you been
Can I hang it out and then do the owners probably use you say Hey I'm
Make me cables do you want to sell them to your customers like
Was that your pet
And that is exactly right
I said hey I can build these for you would you like for me to and
Do that and the answer was almost always yes
And then the next
Question from them would be how much do you want for them
And I
Don't know what do you usually pay
And then in those early days
The cost that I was
Paying for the component
Wasn't competitive
Some of the times I was buying it a place like a
RadioShack or an electronic store or something
But my labor was
You know
Free
And there was no doubt in my mind that I didn't have to worry about that
I just start to make it work and just get a little bit of scale
And that I'd figure out
How to get
The cost right
Alright so you
Started to make
These cables Frankenstein
Just like what
Around then
And did you think
This is it this is my business this is what I'm going to do I'm going to incorporate a business
Make a go of it
Yes I first started getting going
If I would have been around 1980s
Sure or so
And then in October of 1982 it was either go back to school
I get another job or dive into Belkin
A full-time basis and I chose the latter
Alright your name is
Chet Pipkin
And the company is called Belk
What's
The story
Yes I didn't want to use Pipkin because
I didn't want people to see that the ham shut
Pipkin of the name of the company is Pipkin. Just
Same to us Mall
And again at this time end in my life there's alot going on
And a friend of mine
He and I were going to start a different business
That's not Belkin but them something else
And because he and I were I going to do that
I had bought letterhead and business card
Words that it said
Belkin
The his last name began with b e l
And so then when we went to begin Belkin I called him up he was doing other stuff then
I said hey do you care if I
Use the letterhead and business cards that them say valken and he said no go right ahead
Yeah that's how we going to start
And was it still just you and I 1982
Yeah so I drafted my brother who was working for me for
Free
My dad was helping out like making the tools and being able to make things easier
My friends would just kind of come by to see me cuz I didn't have a lot of time for printing
Social time then
So they would come hang out with me
Make things with me while they were there and then they would leave they would go off and do
Other things so
And then hired the first person on a full-time basis
And then hired the second hired the Third
We all worked around this big table I had built it was a 4 by 8 piece of
Plywood
That I put a piece of laminate on the table and make tables
Direct
Yeah that I would I would go out and sell it so that I got
Our own separate phone line that we put up in the garage
Still in the garage we had cables long links of cable literally going up
Up and down the sidewalk neighbors would come out and say what are you guys doing we would explain it in the truck
Trucker cap or something and then
As more and more was taking place there you know bigger and bigger trucks where I come in the house delivering goods and
There is simply just too much going on for the garage to hold us
So then we moved our first building over the holiday
We've always called her official start date January one of
1983 baidu
The actual work started
A couple years prior
How did you how are you
Growing
You started out by just selling it
The shops on Hawthorne
Boulevard
Were you driving
All over LA and going to
Shops or we're different shops finding out
What about the cave
Grapevine
Yeah in the earliest days it it was all out
And almost immediately our constraint was a more ability to make the stuff
Quickly enough
So we actually did have any trouble
Getting orders
We had trouble keeping up
And then as we increased our
Capacity
Then I would had a couple more
Places
And then I think we ran our first ad and computer dealer magazine
And we got an order
For a hundred pieces
There's one of our bigger
Biggest hoarders ever
For cables that went for the parallel port from an IBM PC 2A
Turn Epson
Printer
And about a hundred of these things it was the student store
From Carnegie Mellon University
Oh wow
Why wouldn't a
A computer company
Like IBM
Apple at the time
Have just made their own
Tables
Connect to their own products or
Another product
And just said
You can't
Make these we are going to patent this
Technology and nobody else could do this
Yes I think that there are a lot of reasons that it didn't
When was IBM had their hands full just making enough
PCS
I bet it feels like
It was probably years there were just not enough of them getting built
And
They
Have no idea
What printer
Any given small business or consumer
Was going to choose
And
Most of those printers had different connectors on them so they wouldn't even know
Which one thing to make there really wouldn't be such a thing
So I think
A little bit too small
And too much work for them and for us
Perfect size and just the right amount of work
Year one official year was 1980
You hit $180,000 in sales
That year
Who suggested like
Four or five people making
Everytable
Yeah let me think about the number of people
At the end of 1983 we probably
We must have been a like in the 25 ranger Power something yeah
Shut in 1983
That's right you were 23 years old
You got 25 employees
180000 in sales
You are running a business
I mean you know what to pay people
Know how to manage people out of do the accounting like did you eat what were you overwhelmed with all those things
Yeah so that's a really good question I remember saying to my dad
SS was just getting up at the house I go that I don't know anything about accounting
I don't know anything about like
Being able to run a
Run a business I got off licenses all that stuff exactly and he looked at me
Me straight in the eye
They said
You don't worry about that one bit you're going to figure all that stuff out
You just stay focused on creating things that people want and if you get that part right
The rest of it's all going to work
But there's a
Funny
Funny things
Along the way from me not knowing
And then there were MoMA
When when things happen
There's a bunch of those so
October of 82 I was actually 21 I was almost 22 years old so I was 21 when I
I embarked
So I knew very very little
When we moved in for that building
I didn't realize we had to turn the electricity on
Nonso it's a mad power
But then the guy came to turn the power off.
Because it was from the
China
Apps
We are literally in there working this
Sky shows up
From Southern California Edison
He walks to the back of the building in and he turned our power off
Right
And
So
I look out the back door and I go are you going to turn the power
Back
Hey basically says hey you an idiot you have to call in and actually establish
Service
And then somebody came from the city and said hey you have a business
License
How do you spell what is that how do you get one
And
So you know there must have been
50 of these moment
Where I just did not
No
And
Somebody eventually ask Torquay Mom calling and then you know we just took care of it then but
United know how to do the book
Yeah where you like collecting
You don't billing people in in
Accounts receivable and payable
Pictures of papers all over the place
Shuffle
Yeah so you know we created a
Purchase order form to kind of buy things off of but it didn't have a purchase order numbers we just went like 1 2 3
Free piano
Really really crude stop
We don't have a lot of money always the cash flow was very very tight so if it was a bill offended
Stuck it in a desk drawer
And just said
You know I'll deal with it later
My girlfriend at the time she's now my wife Jan
Worked in a family business in Northern California
And she knew how to do all this stuff and so then she would come down for the weekend
He would dig out all of these old bills and get them taken care of and
Kind of show me how to do the books and
It took a little while for me to get that damn concept but
She was a really really big help
So she actually saved your butt and your early days
She did
Yeah and then after we got married she came to work at Falcon
And
I remember I got a call from a guy he worked it up
Place called Computer Stop one of our bigger accounts
He said
Hey this new collections person um have is an absolute and I won't use the word but it
It was not a very
Polite word and I said oh you you've met my wife Jan
Yeah so everything everything worked much much better
And she was
Unbelievably brilliant and awesome
So the quality went up
The production efficiency went up
Our receivables went down
I was not always really Pleasant to work
Well she was very patient with me though
But I mean
Did you feel any stress about all of those
Those things I mean
I'm coming in the mail in the letters from the IRS or whatever might be did did ever
Stress you out
It was a nightmare there were days
When I thought nothing could stop
Bus that
After this is going to work and that this is going to be the most brilliant thing ever
And there were other days that were really
Really dark
And
I just would hold my head and my hands and and say wow this is never
We had a customer file for
Chapter 11
And we didn't have the money to cover the money that we weren't going to get from them
And
I went to a my dad to I borrow money and my mom and dad didn't have a lot of
And he took a loan out on the house.
Fairy house the Bell kind of got in it
Songs.
Beginning days and yeah
How much money do they take out
I think I first got
7000 and then I think it was 20 some odd thousand
Yeah that was a lot of money for them and I remember my mom
Looking really really scared and saying you know what if you don't pay me back
I will when we come back in just a moment
His parents
Belkin grew into a company worth hundreds of millions of dollars
Gyros in you listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone just quick things to do
Two of our sponsor
Who helped make this podcast possum
First SimpliSafe Home Security
If your friends are
Family have their place broken into
What would you do
When the friends of a
Electrical engineer Chad Lorenz had
He decided to build a whole new type of security
SimpliSafe
SimpliSafe 24 hour protection for your home
No contracts or hidden fees
Antedate SimpliSafe protects over
3 million people
Learn more
Simplisafe.com built
Thanks also to Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
Design build your own website
Using customizable layouts
Features
Putting e-commerce functionality in Mobile editing
Squarespace also offers built-in search engine
Translation
You develop an online presence
Squarespace.com
NPR for a
Free trial
Ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10%
The first purchase of website or domain
Nineteen
A darkened Street Corner in Selma Alabama
I do podcast
Exposes the lies that
Kept this murderer from
An Explorer's memory myth and
Accountability
For a crime
Hark the song
From NPR
White Lies
Listen
Oh and really quickly before we get back to the show
If you love how I built this
Probably love another podcast.
Just launched
It's called wisdom from the top
It's available on a new podcast
Best platform called luminary
It's a show about
Weight as leaders in the world in the how they learn to become leaders
You can find wisdom from the top in addition to
Several other
Great new shows
Go to luminary. Links
Slash guy
Free 3-month trial
Description
Welcome back to how I built this
Br
Especially because the entire operation was self-financed
A few years business by 1985
Looking pretty good company into a bigger building and at this point
50 employees
And they were still making all of their own products but realized
They wanted to scale-up they would have to start doing things a little differently
There was a moment
I think around 1985
When the person who was working in reception came and said there's somebody here to see you
And
The person
Was coming to see us
Manufacturing
Company in Taiwan
And it was the first product
We saw
That was being built
In Asia
And
It looked pretty good
Football
It was a parallel printer cable
To go from the IBM PC to a parallel printer
And I asked him
What it would cost to buy
And the price he quoted
Was less expensive
Then what
Cost us two
Bill.
Same item ourselves
So that moment was a pretty scary movie
Scary because
Precious
Exactly right
And it appeared to me just instantly in that moment
That we were going to have to start thinking more globally about how we would
Manufacture things
And
I didn't know if I had
Permission to do that
It's hard growing up in this household
That them had appreciated things being made in the US
That's why I went to see my dad
I brought this
Cable
Just sort of explain to him what we just talked about
And I just got it paused
They said
Yeah you need to explore it and if it makes sense
You've got to do it
Why why did you think you needed his
Commissioned it sounds like
What was it that you needed his sort of approval that you were
Going to make it outside the US
Permission of me with your company
Yeah
Yasso
It would be an emotional or spiritual permission that
I wasn't violating
Anything that
My mom or he had stood for and then it was just going to be okay with them and stand up
Approval to say it's okay I did
I did
I certainly wanted it was certainly easier with
Remember this is as a kid it's hard to believe now but like
Made in Taiwan
Mandisa mean it was cheap
Taiwan Japan Korea very very high quality
And of course it's happening with China and
Not another country
Asia
Like did you fly to Taiwan and find a factory worker
Yes I think the phenomenon you speak of happened you know very very rapidly I'm at least from you
Grass perspective I mean all that
Is part of what we were living in real a Time
And yeah
I did exactly what it is you said I just
Hopped on a plane so
I went to three places
2 Explorer
What might be taking place in the developing world
So I went to Taiwan
I went to China
And I went to India
And would
Set alarm so we were still manufacturing most of our things in the US it was very
Critical to us that we
Maintain all of our Innovation or invention our design so
So the bulk of what it is we do is still done in the us but we began to
Learn about extending some of our Global Manufacturing
In China
And yeah I
I literally physically
Help to set up some of our initial manufacturing lines
So what does that mean
For I mean
Did that
Decision
Result
Explosive growth
For Belkin
It put us in a really enviable place
By that
Point
We were still doing the bulk of the manufacturing in the US and that gave us very rapid Turner
Around
But now we could also do high volume
A Tesla cost
Anyone else was doing
Anywhere
So
Because we
We were a little bit early there was
An advantage that
That everybody else
Didn't have and those were very very good craft beers for us
So
By 1990
Yumove Falcon headquarters
To Compton
California this is
Sr the lack of height of the gang wars
Compton was
Popularized
Hip Hop
Unwrapping
A year later you've got
The LA riot
In South Central mainly in South Central LA
Tell me why you had decided in 91
To move
Bedquarters
Yeah there were a few motivating factor
When was we were moving to
Bigger and bigger buildings
And there simply weren't that many of them available
To real estate was less expensive
I had
Spent
And continue to spend a lot of time doing community
Service work
And that was mostly with youth and it was mostly
With at-risk youth
Chinese very
Comfortable in these communities
In addition to being comfortable
Felt a reward
From being able to invest in these areas
And that worked out very well
When you have the
Peebles
End
The anger
Connected to the verdict of a Rodney
Hanging
Results of Lotto
Fingering
ABC violence
What do you remember
About that time were you
Real work that day were you in Compton
Yeah I have so many memories of that day
I remember
As the civil unrest
Started to accelerate
I was at work
And on the drive home
From the freeway we could see
They are fires across south of LA
And then the next day
There was a little bit of
Thought and discussion about
Whether or not we should be open and to go to work and and we chose to be open
We're in very close contact with
Little Compton police
Department saying hey we think it's important for us to be here and
Adjust remote
Normalcy
And we'd call in to the police department every hour and now we can start to see fires out the back door of
Falcon
And
First the feedback was hey it's all fine you don't have anything to worry about
Hey it's getting pretty active around here
Hey you guys should think about what you're doing to the left
Call we made
I think the quote
From the
Compton police official picked up the phone was
Get the hell out of Dodge
And I think that was Private 2 in the afternoon or something like that so we worked with all of our people and
Safest ways to get home
And that night I'm at home I'm watching the news and more and more buildings are burning and if
I feel this overwhelming desire to go to work
The things are okay
My wife
Convince me that that was probably not a smart thing to I do
So yeah
You know it was really scary time I
Had a lot of mixed emotions I can
Really feel
For people that
Felt that they were being marginalized and didn't feel
A part of the system and not being
Heard
And
The very next day or the day after that
What time is it
What are the branches of the LA YMCA in
Very active
Wesley Theory why
Volunteer staff
Person in a board member and
Right in the heart of that community at Weingartz
That we just immediately started leaning and and
Reinvesting in and doing everything we could to
Start building bridges again
Did you ever
Have any
Invincible
To come to work with
With your dog in because
You know because Contin
Canada reputation is as
Tough place
It's a dangerous place
So I was always super comfortable there
Anybody that was working there I think was
Comfortable there
I start to get an increasing amount of feedback from the organization that
When we are
Recruiting people some of the people of got
Simon concerned about
Well they be able to get
To and from work
Safely and are the amenities around there
I'm safe and my early attitude was
You know
All of this work
The more that were
Completely integrated in every way that
Requiem can imagine the better off all of us are I'm going to be
We did eventually choose
Remove
We're in a very established Tech hub
At the Western end of town of LA mayor at the
Time there also was a part of getting us the movie witch
Just trying to get us in into la
But the
There's a big big
Pisa made that
Message being there
I think he has moved out of Compton in 2000
For quite a while
We were
So just respect
Then a bit
Ever think that
First-time Belkin took outside financing
Up until that point
It was entirely self financed
But started it in the garage and
You know you never took any money
Except for the loan from your mom and dad when Williams
Thunder
Why did you take
Outside financing
At that point.
When did you need it to grow into scale
Yeah so we were beginning to see around that time that while
At that time
We were extremely well capitalized.
Balance sheet was great
We could start to see a time in the future
To get to a bigger scale
That
We would absolutely need outside capital
So we made a conscious choice
On that day because we didn't need it
But we figured that the day would come that we
What needed
Man died that that would be a great time to Kanab
Kind of start to learn
At this point like by the time we hit the turn of the Millennium Falcon
You know you guys start
Of course you moved out of just cables you move into
Huge product line of mouses keyboard laptop
Case of surge protector
Power supplies all kinds of USB products going over your website today
Tons and tons and tons
How how are you able to
How to stay ahead of
Editor's because I can go on Amazon today and buy the same table made by Amazon
100 different companies are offering very similar cables
How are you guys able to stay ahead of
Those
Competitors
Yasso
We're really fortunate in that
Our reason for being
Just as we were first
Imagining what this organization and this brand could be
Is almost exactly the same as our reason for being now
So it's doing the
Hard
Complicated
Innovation and Engineering work
That allows these
Interfaces to a work together with
One another
For thirty some odd years
More often than not
We've been able to do that
In a little bit better or more elegant way than other folks
And
As long as we're able
To keep doing it
We're going to do okay
But we are only as good as as how well we are doing things this morning so
There's a lot of positive
Apresurado
Because the moment we are not best as is the day that the
We will be at greater risk
So I guess in the past year in 2018
Dell Consulting
Subsidiary
The fox tan
Play called a fight
Reportedly more than 800 million dollar
I think you were the primary owner and
Shareholder of Belkin
Was a part of your reluctant
Do that because
I have to assume that
That would mean the end of your time at Belk and which was your in
Higher identity
Why would you have a role in a cup
Play today
Yap so
I'm still
Running Belkin
And the folks said fit you've been kind and gracious enough to allow me
A2im have an expanded role inside of f i d
Combination of v and Belkin has created a company doing
4 + 1/2
Billion dollars
Revenue a year
So
This is nothing about
Ending any kind of
Chapter but rather
Azzam Oliver chapters has been
What are the actions we take what do we do to put us in the best possible place
To do our best work going forward
That is what this is all about this is
This is an enabler
Conversation I had with
Haim Saban
A couple
Beers ago and I asked him about
Well then I said was it important
To you
Early on
To become
Wealthy and his answer was interesting
Was but not because of the
Actual money but
The money was a marker
Success form
Make so I wanted to make more
Because to me that was a marker
Very poor
What was earning money
A lot of money
Important
Do you is a marker in that way especially given how you grew up
Yeah I I can really relate to that
So definitely an important thing that
That what it is we're doing matters
But another measurement of success has how many people want this and
And so yeah Financial results out of an organization is is one way to sort of measure what
Whether or not you're being successful
I think also for me as a kid
I doubt this experience with my parents that I
Wasn't sure if they had a lot kind of set aside to give them a little bit of wiggle room when
And things got a little leaner so I think I did set out to make sure that
That was less likely to be the case for me but
That particular issue probably got solved
A little while ago
Your mom and dad
Lived
I no longer live
Both of them
They did live long enough to see
You
Successful very successful in fact
Obviously you paid their loan back
What do they make of it
Did they ever talk to you about it reflect on it with you
They really felt I think a lot of
Ownership
Because they were able to park
Participate in various ways in those early days my mom is making
You know breakfast lunch or dinner for everybody that was
Working there they lent money to the business
My dad helped
To build so much of the tooling am hung out there
And so yeah I think that they fell
A lot of pride
But they off
They are always worried
So I would hear feedback
From my friends
And people that worked at belcan
We're both my mom and my dad would pull people often
I didn't say
Hey
Is Chet doing okay
And it said yeah yeah I think he's doing okay
So they felt a lot of pride a lot of reward but
But I think they I'm always worried and
And maybe that's just a little bit of what Mom and Dad to do
How much of your
Success to you tribute to lock
And how much do tribute to
Your intelligence and skill and
I attributed to
Mostly other people
There's nothing
That I could have accomplished
With them out a bunch of other people making great things happen if it wasn't for my teachers
Wouldn't be here
If it wasn't for my mom and dad
I wouldn't be here my brother I don't think I'd be here a thousand people
Belkin thousand two people inside of fit it's each and every one of them you know
Making things happen every day and you know more than anything else it's because of of the work
Other people that I have been able to do what little that I've done
That's Champion founder of Falcon the official name of the company is Belkin International
Incorporated that also sells networking products under the Linksys brand Witchduck in the choir.
Play we didn't get into this during our interview but the first really successful product red hat
1983 was a connector called the Belkin Hamlet he was protecting the Apple II
To see computer to different types of printers and the name Hamlet
Your joke about the cable car.
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Going to hear from you
Things your building
The first a quick message from our 2019 Leeds
Sponsor of how I built this
Hiscox understands every small business is unique
Tailors its policies that your business is very
Specific needs
Get a quote or purchase a policy
Hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance
Hey thanks for sticking around
How you built that
And this is a story about something we
Almost never think about
Until It Breaks
The common everyday zipper the moment of oh my God my backpack just split open
Turn on me and I'm on a trip and Central America play McCabe and he's kind of an expert
Broken zippers because he's got hundreds of stories I have a musician that was getting ready for show and his
Zippered blown-out on his pants you known he was
I mean who wants to go play a show in front of thousands of people with your pants unzipped
Window zippers break
Throw the item away in the trash
Even if it's your favorite pair of jeans or the backpack that's been everywhere with you
But this is not the way clay was raised
When was a kid in McCall Idaho his dad had a repair shopping
He would fix everything
Everyday there is somebody could come into the shop
And have a broken zipper
Keep fix it in about 5 minutes and actually Clay's dad built us
Give me the
Kit for people
So they could repair their zippers at home so it's just kind of a fool
Do-it-yourself kit that had
Handful of different Sliders in them
Which is it that's the little metal piece that you grab onto a slider is the thing that can break or fall off a zipper
It was like a little bag that had a bunch of different types of the slider
And it also have these little Stapley things for attaching the slider back to the zipper teeth
Anyway all this is happening back in the early 1990s
Clay's dad put the repair kits on a very basic website and started to sell them in a few chain stores
So that was kind of like
Supporting our whole family
Pretty pretty much you noses it was a meager living but it was enough to get a spy
Things got harder after
Clay's dad died
Is mom took over the business but she had a hard time keeping it up
Show about 5 years ago
Why you decided to take it over
Cuz it didn't feel finish to me
You know it felt like there was a lot more potential and what he had started then what was
Currently there
But in order to tap into that potential
Play decided the whole look and feel of the business
Had to change
The old website was like
It was straight out of the 90s
You know it's almost got this
Important words like so retro is cool again
A complete rebranding of his dad zipper rescue
Updated the website design logo and then he started to
Gladden shake the trees a little you know things started happening immediately it was like okay I landed us a new account here
Aaron started to Cana
Get a handle on what was going on with Amazon and how you know how it all worked
Actually once you get the kid on Amazon
Clay had to deal with a wave of knock-offs
Says one thing he offers
The other guys don't
Customer service in fact he takes a lot of the calls himself
And helping other people repair their own zippers
It's become one of his favorite parts of the job
It becomes so meaningful when you're helping somebody fix something that's just
Literally Irreplaceable
You know it kind of gets me through my days like if I'm having a hard day and I get that called some cute old lady
He knows how to Southern lady be like you walk on water who is so happy
To have this little thing working again in their lives
3 Mile Clee it's pretty happy that the money side of the business is looking good to you.
Getting to the point where like a six-figure profit margin is like insight
You know it's pretty exciting
Play Makeba Portland Oregon
Company
Zipper rescue
You want to find out more about clay or your previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org
And of course if you want to tell us your story go to build npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to
Show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and why you are there please do give us a review
HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
Are shows produced this week by
Herman with music
Decomposed by
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Candice Lim
Julia Kearney indoor could see neither grandson as meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
Gyros
Is anyone listening
How I built this
This
Is NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign mode
An email marketing flag
Used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days ago