Weren't any of the investor saying you don't have a tag team you don't have a chief technology
Yeah it makes perfect sense to have how many people do you think you pitched over that
Yes two months. In San Francisco
Directions
Ramen PR
How I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories
I'm guy Raz and I
Iowa college student named Melanie
Turn her passion for making better yearbooks into the design platform
Now value
At over a billion dollars
So there's a story that I think a lot of
People have tails
Make a difference
It's basically a version of this
What time
You are a very clever business
He was an idea for a super useful product or a service that would make your life
Play Easier mine was actually one cup coffee maker I swear that was my idea but
Like most people
I didn't do it and if you're like me
You didn't have time to work on it or the money or maybe it just seemed too overwhelming to get started
The way the story always ends is that a couple of months later maybe a couple of years later
You're shopping in a store or you're surfing the web and there it is I can remember the very day I
I saw the one cup coffee maker at Target
Someone took my exact idea and made it happen
Because every business starts out as an idea
Put a turn an idea into a reality you have to get started even if it means starting out small
Plant the seeds for a business to grow before someone else does
Melanie Perkins here she did have a big idea
She wanted to transform the entire desktop
19 years old but instead of feeling
Overwhelmed by the scale of Rydia Melody
Focusing first
One little piece of the idea that she thought she could make work
Which happened to be an online tool to design and publish
I grew up in Perth in Western Australia
Her mom was a teacher and her dad was an engineer
Mid 2010 graphic design program
Adobe InDesign or Microsoft Publisher and she was frustrated at the program
So difficult to learn
Completely silly that you take so many instruction manuals and so many steps through the Myspace
Basic of things
She just wouldn't take a host messages go anywhere the buttons well and how to design
It seems very apparent that
Leasehold
Desktop pricing would be
Completely okay cannot dated in the feet
Feature
Very oversized Asian fit taking on all of these different Industries
Post office
Locksmith
Rubber Industries is okay
I thought Robin people using things like clipart
They should be able to have access
Beautiful templates like design history
But at that point in time I've
Is 19 and I had no business experience
And so
Robin trying to take honey
High road is as I know he's really big companies
Expose take on school yearbooks in Australia you keep saying
When you say weekly
My boyfriend Tenkai sounded clay
And you're still together later
You decided to start
Like a web-based
People design
Upon the idea of
Of your books
Weihai
The decision for all
For taking on the entire world design
But you will seem to be like a really pressing need because school teachers and get starting today the same that had no design experience
I might see my mom put together School yearbook for hair school
People with no design experience respect
Did you say something
Look professional
And I realize that it be a really easy thing to do
Because it's such a strong locket made for these people to Crate
Gearbox
So how do you go from having that idea
Chili
Like what was your next step cuz it was you and clever
He was also 19 live 2020
Fusion Bowl
Fusion books
Right if you guys lie
Coders or software engineers
Find an interview every software development company info
And white people told us
We're completely mad but how did you even have the money
To pay them
I got a 50 Grand line from friends and family
Which was awesome and then we got 5 grand back
So that was a mock
You went around your friends and family
I have this amazing idea
We want to develop
Of a web-based
Software
Solution for pi
People designing your book
That's exactly right
Are Clif have a little bit of cash
Can you go round two
Software developers in Perth
Could you eventually
I'm does it's amazing company code in depth
And
I I would even if I have 80 page description of exactly what we wanted to do it like I had wireframes bruise off
Like you sketched out pictures
To the house what every single button was going to do a how it's going to whack
Like these projects we ended up being bike
5 times bigger than I anticipated but they were very kind to just like we've had a fixed-price contract and what was going to make this
Better than anything else
Available at the time I think there's just nothing much available all over these desktop base program
Sir Robin have everything having to send the e-mails back and forth and collect all those files I wanted is to be collaborative and
Online and really simple
Cuz at that time if you want to make a yearbook page you would just
Microsoft
Worder door like yeah Mac software to publisher
And then also it wasn't just that pot you didn't have to go get you your stock photo easel stuck illustrations
Sexy make it look really good
And sorry to be so many different things you haven't pieced together the Cradle by Mike really really happy
Email that page to somebody and say hey what do you think they say it but you wanted something
Everybody could kind of jump in and make changes
That's correct
So you go to the software company in Perth and how long did it take
For them to
To build up the sock
Because about 6 months
Before we had a fancy duration and then immediately started a second iteration
And and
Remember what year this was that with a 2008
2008 so you
Just put it up there on the one-handed yearbook seem like a really nice Market
Right because it's
Yeah one time of year
On the other hand
Actually
It's a surprising that there was nothing really
Out there
To make it easy
Yeah absolutely and on the plus side as well
Because a yearbook actually has to get printed that was however to monetize
Give the software away for free and then actually sell the physical yearbooks
So the idea would be that
Somebody would go on their design their yearbook
Hit submit and then you guys would
Take that
And then print it
And you would make money off of
From the actual printing
Yeah
So what happened
I've got 16 schools knotfest yard which were very excited about
And then
We ended up getting printing presses in my mom's living room
How did you how did you
Put a how did you get printing
68006 Hadley
Really cool deal where they said that they give us
The print afraid we paid for the inkan touched it and I kind of believed
We had like a
A newspaper article empath and they
Everything sore that article about you guys yet and they saw it
Have I felt that that help Adam would become a big Printing Press Company one day
Why so they gave us a printer
A couple of Xanax
Actually and say we would have a printing press
Going for 24 hours
For three months a year
Atrophy printing out AZ
Yearbooks and then we drive you to a binding he's not actually do this
The finishing in The Binding
Did any of the schools know that
You guys were like 1920
Easel
I don't imagine so
Within your first year do you remember like what kind of Revenue you did
The first year Revenue would have been very modest but it was enough to be able to afford to do marketing next year so we just ran
Investor profits every year into the next year
And very fortunately I guess we had become profitable quick Lakes of us would have no company immediately so the
First you had 16 School II you had 50 schools next year we had a hundred schools and then it was like
There was growing that quite rapidly did you start to think about building listen to
Something bigger by 2010
I can imagine
You can start to see this thing has legs Yes actually the original idea of taking on
How well do design and make it easy for a brown was actually planted right from the start and then we narrowed it down to you
But we can't look around people be like we used to design a Canteen menu than a newsletters and a school fire
Tires actually there must be more technology available now that does that
Honestly wasn't
But then in 2010
I meant do Thai who is this
Silicon Valley investor
I'm here and
He was just talkin about all these companies and startups
Like when I first had him steak
It sounded like a windows were holding you out
You met him
What was he doing there
I'm who is speaking at a conference
Listen to that
Yeah so
Even though like we should have
A company with that we've been calling but the only thing that we knew at that point in time is over a small business that really struggled to get away from the
Didn't have a credit history and those whole well to start up so we're taking on big Industries
Throwing up to him after a station
Someone there
Kylie shisui and said he's going to cool company
And
He said yes if I went
Scrapy happy to me
And you said oh okay great
Ticket number
Yeah
That's exactly right
Answer
As soon as I met him I realized that was the next level
And that if I could do anything we possibly could to get there
Cjis email
Can we talk
Well yeah I kind of was like hey I'm going to be in Silicon Valley just going to be in the area
Did you really have plans that point are you just thoughtful
If I just say that I'm going to be there and he says the guy who made out with another guy
And sorry
Could not have been more than I actually even responded to my message
Yeah
I was just completely dumbfounded
So you
Ticket to San Francisco and how long was
Were you planning on going out for coming out for
I plan on coming out for 2 weeks
My brother was living here
And I thought I'd come and visit him about going to this meeting that I was absolutely
Afraid of his understatement
Answer in between the time that he said that he would meet with me and coming here
I put together
My
Business plan
The future of publishing with what I tied it and it had a picture of us beating Microsoft Office
And a whole bunch of other companies
Say we met on University Ave
And I'm at a cafe
Table card for lunch
Say I brought my
I physically printed my pitch deck
Which I also didn't realize was put on Coldplay
A computer right that
I totally didn't notice the time
Netflix stapled I was sitting there like I had my paper pitch deck hands like Jeff and iPad
No I was like trying to sleep two pages in my deck and
Explain about the
Future publishing in Harrogate to take a noise
Companies
And try to eat my lunch and
And he was there wrapped
Like engaged know he was on his phone the whole time it was
Sorry okay I felt like the biggest flop
And
But very forcefully when I went Jaime I had an email from him and he said if I
If I detect him he'd be happy to invest
Yes I hate actually they need
Messaging a lot of dick
People
I'm an HTC
Me to them while during the meeting so he was actually the phone messaging
Yes I
The next meeting I had was with last recipe
Listen he co-founded Google Maps
And meeting him
Completely blew my mind because
I really didn't know
It sounds like
Desire but I had no idea that people that made
Big world changing companies with
Regular niacin
Hard-working normal people
I'm and meeting laws
Completely changed by
Deception about was possible
When he met you he said
Either something here
Yeah we enjoy having an incredible conversation
4 hours
We both had a really similar view of what the fit
Feature of communication and Publishing should be like
So does a fee philosophies one of them was that over time
Industries with converge
So rather than having the printed sleeping over here
Haven't used it
Prince of educated website and differ
Self-medicated presentation in different self-educate marketing materials
And some of these things being online it's on Dominguez.
That all these industries would
Come together and be in one page and then discuss for 12
Same crazy that you'd have to use so many different tools and
Gon learn today
Thanks for everything you wanted
To create
See you need to Sky Lars
You say to him hate
Bill says he's going to back me
If I find a tick
Maxine
Can you help me is that
What uses a large yeah that's exactly right and love said
If you have you given Pfizer
What are enzymes
Entailing was
Cambridge acting everyone for a full year
Why did Lars have
To prove it
Was that bills
Condition or yeah that was Joe condition
He said old white wrestlers
Is Lars
Is a thumbs up your Tech tmall fund
That's exactly right
So you are in San Francisco
For the next
3 months
Until my Visa expired
Okay to she's a great Christian sees a tourist visa
And wherever you like
Working at a what are you that I was sleeping on my brothers had a one-bedroom apartment a sleeping in his living room floor
And I was working in at Nordstrom the shopping center
Westfield Shopping Center in San Francisco
Say okay and say I would go there and out of whack
In between valugard every single conference that I could
Anything anyway
Teaching people how to tame
Are you just naturally kind of
Gregariousness
Outgoing was it easy for you to just show up like
You just talk to you is that what you do
Say I'm actually not actually really introverted
But when I have a go live
Do everything I can to get there
And say yeah I'll be getting off inside
If people let me do a 1-minute picture to conference I would get off and I'll be doing that one minute pitch and color your Beating racing
Completely completely terrified but I just keep on pushing my
What's I wanted this
Iran
Your partner in
Boyfriend cliff
He was still at work
Is presently for those three months he was working on infusion the yearbook
Yeah
And how is it doing
It was very well it was growing age
Like he moved out from your mom's house
Central Fest office
Yeah it was it was
Interesting time because we knew that though this big amazing opportunity over here
But it was really hard to make progress with
Heaven on the other side
Procedure that was a Shore thing growing every month every year
It felt like I've been over in Silicon Valley
Batavian
Wild-like
I'd left him with old Hardware
Pretty much summed it up
So
3 months
Your cheer for 3 months
Was it exciting or you
Encourage did you feel like
This is moving forward
I think every day I felt like I'd make a little progress
By the end of the three months I didn't have a tag team and I left feeling like
Biggest failure
Because
I had not lie detector
Which meant that I had landed investors which meant that alright done
In my view at that point in time was like
Nothing
I left a lot but I hadn't actually
When I was going back to pass I'm on the Fly I write a list of the things that I did
2 Chainz and one of them is like
Staying Alive
Which of the little group body with but then
Then move the company from Perth to Sydney
I meant came back around 2
Coming up in just a moment by Melanie's next step in our search for investors
Was learning
Kitesurf
Gyros
And you listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for NPR in the following message
Come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better for
Their cloud-based platter
Man solution
Deliver digital work
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
Ready for your hole
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the work
They want
Using technology
To make people more productive
And engaged
Moret servicenow
Al.com
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Snowflake
We only dated Warehouse
House built for the claw
Today organizations need the agility
Buddy that rapid Data Insights bring
To stay a step ahead of the
With snowflake
You can instantly and infinitely scale your data warehouse with the touch of a button
Delivering deep insights at any time for all user
Start your job
Towards data-driven decision
Snowflake.
Tom
NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining Bank
I offering a count
With no fees or minimum
That can be opened from anywhere in
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Nna
Welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Something you should know before we get back in the Melanie story is that deal time
The VC investor Melanie met with at the Palo Alto coffee shop
Kitesurfing
Bills taken these two things better capitalism
And kind of combined them into a conference
Capitan called Mai Tai
Is that one building that was Melanie
Basically told her hey Tiff
If you like I can invite you to this event
Is there about your idea
Cuz I made it seem like I was really interested in kitesurfing and sorry he said that if I
Kaiser
Please conference where a lot of a Saison I'm invested with a
Say I went to Kaiser and felt like I was going to be
My life is really frightening and what does he do
Talks like during the morning and then everyone kites Us in the afternoon people there
A hundred and
Hotel in
Maui
And kitesurfing by day
And then
Mingling at night
You went to both you and Chloe we both win
And you guys are must be thinking
Sza weight
Thunders yester's that's exactly right so what did you do
Were you say we went schedule to talk or anything but one and one of the events
We just said I can we talk tomorrow can we do a pitch
I'm at this is like it
10:00 at night
And eventually he said yes
Say we end up like to stay up until 6 a.m.
Prokaryote picture
The picture of life
And eventually got off in The Wiz
Sorry incredibly nervous in front of everyone but
Apparently didn't do so bad
AXA of Shutterfly came up and said he would be
Peking twin bed
And a number of other people said that they think about the injuries or
It would be came to invest as well
What does that mean does that mean like I winch I'm ready to write you a check now or does that mean
I'm interested in further tok
In talking more about
Feather talking more about this
You say who else is going to reinvest before we invest is Buzz the general feeling
If you had to get enough people who are interested to invest
You did not leave now
Stack of checks
Snotty nose
Is there a
Okay so the next
Super Mario you went back to San Francisco
And what did you do over the next
Six or eight weeks like that you was at
Did you start a pitch potential investors out
Is that what you're doing
Yeah pitching everyone includes
It worse to pitching out of fur
Other engineers at this stage we student have an engineer
Repitching
Any venture capital
List or angel investor that would take a meeting
Weren't any of the investor say
Hey this is a really cool idea
You know Fusion seems cool but
You don't have a
Chief technology officer
Yeah it makes perfect sense to have how many people do
I guess 2 months.
I don't know you.
Between this like the first year
And
That year. It would
A400
People more
I didn't count the time I was going through my rejections the other day I was looking at some of the emails and
What was it
They catch you going when you were just getting rejection after rejection
I think he does know the game you're playing
And
You know we wanted to build the future publishing and
We knew that this would like in my head this is just absolutely the feature there's no way that things
Baby desktop-based anymore everything was very evidently movie online
Is no way that things are going to be fragments Jack Russell eating
It was going to be easier for people
I'm sorry
I really wanted to create that even though it was frustrating
It was a say I knew it was a pretty important thing today to get people to see the same
Featured ideas
Yeah but I think it was really beneficial because we got so many different
Questions
Now I'm coming soon
People not liking what we're doing at all
M&W really had to know what we're doing and really her final strategy say every single day would go back and revise up
Pitch deck
Every time we got a really high Quest
That was very right in front of
To the hardest question to answer
At the front
Robbing people sitting
I'm going through the entire pitch and then like all but you're the same as some ran
Got nothing to do with us
Waiting for the side not Pitch that quick
Should the Gap in the market
And all the other companies
Beyblade
Peach cobbler
I'm a lot of people would say that he knew nothing about design
They don't know anything about industry in
That was a reason to not invest
So we made it
One of the first pages I pitch that keeps paying the industry and where we believe this huge gap
This was in 2000
Okay so what say I'm one of these investors
The berry I would say
This looks cool but has a lot of questions for you
First of all
Tech team we're detecting
He would say what
So we've already due to company with Fusion books you demonstrated that we can make a profitable company that's made out of gravelord
Internationally and
We're just going to take it onto the beach
I can totally understand why nobody wanted to invest
And then I would say and I was like why
Microsoft
Google can they see what you guys do with
The crush you because LG
Just put something else out
Way bigger and and
I mean you just kidding
Right away
You sound totally like one of those invest and what would you say
Wade say
There is a
Is Hugh Jackman
Because it's
It's kind of up to actually create the
Music industry the future publishing
You would have to completely cannibalize horrendous
And if you look at the years of publishing over the years
Beside roof with metal plates that we moved into the tot setting and paste up his ex became the second sliding up his check
We then moved into the desktop
Ciara and then we are now moving into the
Near which people is going to be online
And what you see
Darren vest
Is it noisy industry fire has actually ever been able to go from one industry to the next and actually still maintain being the market leader
And say we every single time there was a new era I need my cat later a mess
And so we believe that muckalady can be up
And then I would say okay but I Know It looks interesting but you guys are
Play Australia like why would you guys consider
Replicating here making it
Moving your team here
Say it depends weight when you lost his quest
At a certain point in time we end up fighting an amazing co-founder Cameron.
3 headband I'm at Google
And so he was going to basic
Australia
And we will submit another amazing guy from Google
Eli said
Best whoever whacked with side 800
I'm so sexy
Cheap stuff to buy
And Dave Dave had white in the US that he was
Australian he's going to be in Australia
And sorry
It's sort of status
Swing the pendulum towards Australia and the government in Australia had these matching funding thing where they would match it
Every dollar that we got from investor
To stay to stay in Australia
To Dave Haunted Mansion he what he ends up becoming your
Your Chief technology officer right
He was really talented engineer working Google
I'm sure he's very well paid at the time
Instead
Well he sucks the time on Google
Design pitch deck
I can probably claim the number 1
I went on to Dave and Dave
When Psych
Interested in what we're doing here
So he was a little bit concerned about joining say what I did
Was I went to his Facebook page and I took
2 page and I put together a
Pitch deck
And said Riordan
Amazing adventure to come and join in 3 trailer
Peachtree publishing and taste the face of the internet
Using storylines from this Friday so I take it from him
Indication
I think that definitely moved it in the right direction I think they realize we have a lot of passion and we're going to do whatever it took to
Okay so now you've convinced a few
High-profile
Join you
Only play together
Build the
You're still
Pitching investors getting
Projections right
When did that change
We had enough people that was somewhat interested it hadn't reject
Strategy
We're rather than asking if he wanted to invest
We ask people
Advice
And you can go back and you can
Say hey he's going to give me some advice I'd love to show you my penis back and then I'd give us some advice
That means I didn't Thanos cost at this point in time due to give you feedback
I like how you going to meet us another month
And look who's on the things that we said we're going to die
And once he had done that enough time
I realize that you actually do the thing
You say you going to do
Kind of had enough people at that point
The kind of interested we kind of in demonstrating that we could do what we said we were going today
And then
At the tight end because we had
We are all the sudden
How much did you
Percy Brown
So we
Winterize 1.5 I think we left
Saint Francis
This game we're a 750
But then over the coming months and not feeling at that roundabout
One point
6 I think it got to
First time you ever subscribed
And then the Australian government gave us
She got three million bucks
This is what
Early 2003
Yeah 2012
Tofu year of development
Between lending investing
Actually launching the product
Peanut Thai recipe
Like what the hell is she
I like it a long time so I like
The Lean Startup with a big deal back then
Amend
Launch and eat right and you do something to the weekend and see if people like it
Yeah but the whole point
Was it really called
Things to make simple MN great Fairground accessible
I mean say that took a lot more
What times in a week
And so you spend that you're developing this thing and then spend a lot of time like
User-testing making sure that people actually understood that people are scared of Designing cuz
People condition for their whole life thinking that I'm not creative account design things
Millions of these things. Challenges that I'd come in there
Change the color of a circle and put a hat in the monkey know these little silly challenges that built up people's confidence with a design abilities
So that we took a while
And and
Why you were
Building building out this
Technology
To write how many people did you have to iron that first year
Before you launched
I think we had about
15 days so you had
Sounds exciting
I just the flip side of this all of a sudden you got
$3000000
Other people
You've
You've convinced he's really talented Engineers to join you
You got
Other people who've like giving up their jobs to
Come and work for you
That's scary
That's a lot of
Responsibility
Yeah Def
I actually went up at laws and
Started to think about his whole world bench
Capital and taking people's money
I realize that I had to make
Decision at that point
Time to defrost going to Petit Spa
I would have to be
At least
Partially okay with the idea of it no backing out
And why that
It was something that was important enzyme
Really know someone that
Likes to give up ever on it
Thank you but yeah it's only with water pressure
Bereghost
So incredibly happy for it to have gone from something
Make where everything was external so trying to convince
People to join my team
It was entitled like a cocoon
Work really hard to make sure that this is an amazing product
And I like
Microphone
So you guys launched
I guess in August
13 in
And you're ready with us online graphic design and
Publishing tools
Single out
Website goes live
What happened
Do people come to it right away
Fortunate that be
Because we had
So high Free Falling
Vested in that first round
When we
Land that says running backs
We might we announced it
Pick up some TechCrunch coverage we're pretty certain about that and we end up with
Fifty thousand
People before we launched
Lisa Boucher was like Viagra
Occasionally initially
Stokes. Out that wasn't saying what we're doing
Then yeah we we launching August 2013
We spent a lot of time prior to that engineering its
If he would have an amazing
Is there an end to share it with others
And that certainly happened inside
Within the first
Every month
The biggest and best ever
And what
Explain what the business model was it is like you it's free to use right like you can just go and design anything
Description
Play one of those philosophies right from the start with what we wanted designed to be accessible to everyone we want to be free
Completely Freddy's and then you can purchase images $4
And so it would mean like if you're in a putting together your school assignment are you or you just a really small business
Crate get your social media off the ground you can afford to pay some
Mindful Gray
And then we also you have
I paid off
Springfield
If you would like to save your brand colors and fonts and logos
Amenakin
I'm going to
Penny offering
Subscription
Design like
A yearbook page right
I can go and design it
I want to actually download
Do I have to pay
Nights at Freddy's
That's free
We wanted we wanted to ensure of a free product with a complete value late like you can go and get your thing completely free
Do you guys have ads at all
So how
You need it
Pretty significant percentage of your
Users
To buy images
Because
Building this technology is expensive
Yes if the concept was that we'd give away the sofa for free
But then you could purchase images you could touch response
Ticket purchase
Potentially layouts
But we're currently giving them away for free
But the idea is that you would always be able to have that bass product
Free for everyone
Amend
We're actually profitable
Designs in 40 countries I can have it delivered to your door
How many people do you have working
314 Alaska, but we're growing really rapidly.
I'm sorry 300
50 year in Sydney
I'm in the we have a team in the Philippines as well I mean I'm really surprised about and I'm LOL
Actually is that it sounds like you just
Didn't make any mistakes after you washed it it just sounds like you
You put this
Great product out there and there were no bugs
And everybody's happy with it is that
Is it true I mean
I am I'm like waiting for the disaster story where are you know you launched it and then like
Crash for 4 days or something
All right I'll give you I'll give you a tidbit
I'd certainly hasn't been smooth sailing but I guess I'm always is focused on the neck
Mountain to climb
Safe example
Play we had
I just told you the entire back
Story of only of the effort that has gone into getting it
Launch
Sorry I was back in San Francisco are you sleeping
Probably the apartment he was actually away
I'm sorry to say about myself
Before I told my dad to go to sleep and someone breaks and bodyguard
Breaking bargo's at your best
About to
An article came out
And they that they are out of
We had a
Not very good products
And that
We had cheesy photography and said it wasn't very easy to use
And
I filled you that point in time like
The last
6 years of my life was Crush
Very
Fortunately that
It was a bit of a
Everyone else
Vicodin
And get what we're doing
So
As you scale and grow and hire more people
300 +
People
You are the CEO you're the boss
The company
I'm your self-described
Introvert
You're sitting here you
Seem like
Just ate
Kind
Andrea Lee
Delightful person
And
Sometimes you have to
Beetalk
The clu
Decision
The fire people you have to
Review
People you have to have difficult conversations with people
Have you
How to learn how
Do that or
Does that come naturally to you or do you
Avoid doing that
Think everything every single day
Bright from the start is Dana Landing Cove
Has been people that haven't worked out over the years
We try to just have the nicest conversation try to actually
Listen to understand that why it wasn't working out try to
Curse them to actually make them better
Is every dead every single stage the same things to learn
And I don't think that
Yeah some things never get easier
But you just have to figure out
What is the best thing that you possibly can do and when is he died
I think that's one thing that I'm pretty good at he's just in time letting
End of the Earth
It's only been a lot of things to learn
You you guys
Get a valuation of a billion dollars
Sunrise at Australian R Us.
Us
Fitness test this year
Yeah given that you are like one of the
First Australian uniqlo
Does that
Increase the pressure on yuan
Super proud of it and you know
Carry on
I mean do you feel
Any of that weight
I think the ironic thing is like
Since I was doing my Simonton you to avoid water pressure on myself and for that same price. Testifies today
Like if courses different at different magnitude
But I think I've just always feel a lot of pressure on myself have always wanted to do
The best I possibly can
I'm and now yes I feel I would responsibility for the livelihoods of a lot of Asti members
But I think
That
Yeah that same pressure of just like trying to do my absolute best every single day it's his that's kind of been continuous
I'm just curious like hundreds of thousands of designs that then created
Tatted up until this point with his tool that you brought into the world like
Jimmy favor
To me the stories that really touch
Watch me are like 20000 nonprofits
And this is everything from
People trying to end poverty to cure cancer
I seen the stories
They're pretty damn cool like
We had a lady found her best mother who she created appraiser uncover
I'm posted on Facebook
Found a best mother
Who sings so many people post their resume that landed them a job
Or are they just like
So many stories every single day I like
Look for Twitter and I say so many tattoos
Stories of
That one philosophy of design should be accessible to everyone is actually being put into practice
Cuz I'm having real welding
How much of
Of all of this
This amazing story.
B2
Your skill your intelligence your hard work and how much
I think it's a really interesting
Question because I think that
If you zoom out of lock
He say where were you born
Paleo parents
Hey what was the education
You're heading good health
It is so many lies of Locke
So if you look at all the voice thing
Be luckier
On the other side of it
I feel like we planted enough say instead of eventually one of those
Grace
And so that's kind of another version of like he's like
Maybe a thousand Saints and what are they saying screw
And so you could come back to me that day the local hardware for planning a thousand Sage
I'd say a little column a little column B
How how old are you
Amazing Amy you're so young but
You're a veteran I mean you've been
In the startup world
You are 19
Like you started your first
Real company
So you you a lot of experience mean you got
12 years of
Experience
Doing this
Raising money
Starting a business
Creating a brand
Marketing
What do you
No now.
You wish you knew when you were
I think one of the wonderful things
About these hoes
Experiences that I didn't know a lot going
Intuit
I think that learning
Every single day as Hikari
Has actually been one of them
Is critical pods
Because I think if I need all the lessons that I had to learn over the last 12 years
I would have been incredibly intimidated
How do I listen to
Statistics
Example and thought that that was something that I should
Be afraid
That probably would have dissuaded me
Every single day getting spending the day Fenton
But at the same time I love
Taking on the theme to The Impossible from the outside
I don't know
When you don't know
What you doing tonight
Then you can't really be afraid of it
Is Melanie Perkins co-founder of Canada
According to company statistics from mid 2018
Online designer polishing tool is now used by over 10 million people across the world
The new designs are created on the site
Iterative
20 per second
And by the way
Kelly says she does not kitesurf
Anymore
But I did it for five years and I can now officially hot tub spray
But I felt for 5 years like I was kind of repeat my last I'm retired
Take risk
Seeing things that are kind of calculated inside my risk loss ratio
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
But the things you're built
But first a quick thanks to one of our sponsors
TD Ameritrade
Offering
Free education for invest
Choose from articles videos webcast
In person event
Take your trading knowledge
Next level
Visit tdameritrade.com
Education
Member sipa
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now
For how you built that
3 story comes to us
Tristan corriveau
Portland Maine
2 years ago
Tristan was staying at a hotel in Boston
When he did what
Many of the Stewart Hotel
He went to the bathroom
Open up the box of soap
I'm washing my hands
Bar of soap that he's about to toss aside and
To think this must happen a lot everyday in hotels
I was really curious about it I decided to just look it up and he discovered that most hotels
Throw away their used soap
More research
Found a nonprofit that
Does take old bars of soap
And recycled
Tristan.
Great butt
What if we could turn that soap
Into liquid soap
Make it available in bulk
Cut down on plastic waste
You buy soap dispenser plastic
You put an extra saying you had it for a few weeks maybe months and then you go get another one
And you multiply that by
Million people
Washing the hands everyday and all the sudden there's a lot of plastic bottles out in the world
Calling hotels
In Portland Maine
And a lot of them
I'm were sending their soap to the nonprofit
But
They had to pay a membership fee
And the cost of shipping
And some of the smaller hotels couldn't afford that so
There soap just
Went into the trash
And one of those places
The Press Hotel
Really hated doing this
So Tristan got in touch with manager
And he said hey
I can help recycle your soap
For free
She was just like this is amazing like
We've been trying to figure out something to do with our soap for so long
We would love to work with you we'd love to give it to you like
Let's do this let's go
Yes yes let's go
Sex
What do I do now
Tristan has found his idea all the way through
A week later the Press Hotel happily gave him nearly
50 pounds of old soap
And
Kind of gross
There's dirt on it
You can end up on the floor
It picks up little
Pieces of like paper and dirt and show step one
Clean it up
That's just a really tedious job
Set over
Venom soap and scrape everything off of it into another bin in 5 hours
Scraping later
He was on to step two
Which was
To liquefy
Cyst inside a DIY Community online
Really into making their own liquid soap from new bars of soap
Dave grind it up and
Boil it down and turn it into liquid hand soap for their
Are you sat home
So I thought this is really easy
But
Old recycle tow
That was hard
Tristan knew that
Some people would worry about
Soap
Return to step 3
The experts
He consulted with the biology Department
The University of Southern Maine and they suggested using
Autoclave
It's like a steam sterilization
Process and it's very common in dentist office
Sin tattoo studios
Is a way for them to
Sterilize their tools
Put in autoclave cost
$4,000
Money Tristan did not have
What he did have was
Used soap supplier
Press Hotel
And proof that the autoclave process
And that was enough
Secure a local business
To buy an autoclave
And so armed with a new autoclave
Tristan move to step 4
Actual product
I put the guy that first batch and
Great
Perfect self I'll go sell it
Until we started by contacting
A friend who owns several Portland restaurant
In a friend electrician hang a few wall display
In the bathroom
Everything was looking
Wait
Then
3 or 4 Weeks Later
I get an email that's like hey that's the soap is separating
Pretty much all that's coming out as water
This
To put it mildly
What's a minor disaster
240 year Tristan searched for an ingredient that would
Stabilized
But one that was also a
Eco-friendly
Cornstarch
Flower
Even recycled wood
Key ingredient
Turned out to be
Baking soda how did I miss that
Finally by the
Fall of 2018
After two years of troubleshooting
Tristan had a marketable recycle liquid soap
He sells it by the gallon
An enlarged
Refillable glass bottles
Speaking to his mission
Cutting back on single-use Plastics
The Press Hotel
They're using his soap in their Lobby bathroom
And they're also
Still supplying him with
Pounds and pounds of used bar soap
Deven
Times when I felt really overwhelmed by the amount of soap that I'm getting
And I've asked them hey can we put collection on pause and
They always refuse
Now if you got to keep Collective
Let's keep going
Extra
Qorvo
Portland Maine
Is business a called the one gallon soap come
He's got five people on his team and in the next few weeks
Tristan will become the
First full-time employee
Decided to leave his
Current job in sales
To focus
Growing
If you want to find out more about
Tristan chord
The one gallon Soap Company or hear previous episodes
Edward podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build at npr.org thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please
Did you give us a review
Get us a right to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this our shows produced this week by Kacey Herman
Music composed by runty mareblu
Thanks also to be a venkat JC Howard or could see immigrant Melissa gray Santa's Michigan for
Jeff Rogers
Sprintern is Candice Lim on Gyros and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign
An email marketing plan
Used by more than
250000 custom
With mobile friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign
Monitor.com