This message comes from
NPR sponsor
The only data warehouse
Built for the cloud
Unlock.
Data insight
Lights with the instantly scalable
Cloudbuilt data warehouse
Start your journey towards data-driven decision
Snowflake.
1 / NPR
I'll never forget the first time I took my parents they came to the studio my
My dad looked around and my mom sort of open doors and antique under desk and my dad looks around he says to me no show
Who is going to come here
This is not a battle worth fighting
NPR
It's how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
Behind the movement
Two women with no background
Fitness
Set up stationary bikes
Dim the lights
Boosted the music
Delta multimillion-dollar business
Cold Souls
Okay so imagine going to an elektronik dance the music throbbing
Lights are flashing DJ is twisting
Computer
Everyone is moving to the music turning
Oh yeah you are doing all of this
A stationary bicycle that
Basically is SoulCycle
Indoor cycling business That Grew From one little studio in New York in 2006
10 yearly 90 today
I sold to a large company
Ten Years After it started
The founders walked away with 90 million dollars
Each
If you haven't heard SoulCycle
Goldwell
One of those Fitness companies
People get super excited about
If you have a friend who happens to be a devotee
Be careful because once they get started
They can go on and on about the
Celebrity stylist
Instructors
Handelsman
Studio The Purge
The music
In that sense of loyalty of New York
Bible devotion
Is kind of what the founders of
SoulCycle envisioned when they set out the building
Julie rice and Elizabeth Cutler met in New York
In 2005
The time Julie was working is it
Talent agent
And Elizabeth was doing acupuncture and realist
On the side
They were both in their thirties and both of them
Married with young children at home
But they were
I'm so hungry to start something new in their lives
Here's Elizabeth
After our second daughter was
Osborne
I started to really have the strong at entrepreneurial urge
And I really wanted to dig into some
Something and I
I kept on thinking about
Let the struggles that I've gone through and having the kids and how much weight a hurricane and how difficult it was for me to lose it and
And I joined Jim's I went everywhere I beg friends of mine who belong to other gyms to take me as their gas so I could try to
Classes I really want to find my class
I couldn't find it was what was wrong with it
From me
What was going on in there it just wasn't inspiring
People play the same playlist over and over they would phone it in it was
Boring
It was I remember somebody yelling at me
Pretend there's an 800 pound gorilla on her chest
My father myself are you really kidding me right now has no last my music system cells in the mirror oh my God
What is yeah you know
Bright lights
Bad smells and
People walking in and out of class
Exactly
I guess you kind of found yourself in
And kind of a similar
Situations you'd move to New York from
From California
I guess an in 2002 what was
Going on in your life at the
The time when you guys met
Well I really missed
What I had had in Los Angeles in terms of an exercise
Community
Exercise for me it was social
It was a huge part of the way that I connected with people it was a big part of the way that I spend my time bonding with my friends we would go
Hiking I can think about some of
The most important moments that we had together having really deep talks
Going up the mountain and then solving problems coming down the other side of that mountain
And I got to New York
And
All I can really find were gym class
Glasses in boot camp
I swear you are definitely going to burn some calories
But not get much more out of it than that
Actually when you
When you were calogen
At this time
For you blonde before you meet Elizabeth
Do you remember starting to sing
I think I'm lost
Business
I definitely didn't think so I want to start a business
But what I did
Tsinghua
In Los Angeles
There was
Boutique Fitness that was starting to happen in New York nothing like that existed
And I had them I had taken some indoor cycling classes in Los Angeles
And I had been
I really actually loved it and I had
I found a community in a small Studio there
And because I had been in business wear
You know I build businesses out of people
I kept thinking about how this could be different
And how can this can be marketed differ
Currently in position differently and what would make this unique and it could be about empowerment rather than about
Putting pressure on yourself
And so it wasn't that I just had this need to start a business
I had a need for a very
It was really more about a need for a product than it was
Oh I just want to be an entrepreneur
People have ideas
I've walked into like kombucha shops inside
Do a better kombucha shop than this
I'm going to talk to a friend
Want to do
But then I just move on I keep doing my shows
What did you start to say to people
I'm really intrigued about
Do they have these in LA and I think
I want to do one
Which is that would happen if you start to talk
People
I did I started to
Say it first to my husband who told me I was insane
I meant to my parents and told me that I had good health insurance
And then to a couple of friends
Who told me that you know they love the gym that they belong to and why would anybody ever do something
But it was one of those things that just would not go away from me it was one of those things especially because exercise with such
Daily ritual of mine
But everyday I would wake up and try some sort of exercise
Leave feeling unfulfilled
And go back to thinking
About this ID again
And remember what made it one
You know one notch even more difficult
Was that
I was talking about charging p
People
To pay per class for this where is Jim's already offered cycling classes they were on the buffet
They were included in membership zactly they were plenty of them
Around
I got my cycling class
Exactly
Elizabeth Eaton parallel
The parallel universe you're living and also New York City
Not knowing Julie
Were you thinking hey
We could
Do a cycling Studio or was it much more soda
Abstract
No I was
I was thinking that I wanted to start indoor cycling Studio
Because what I felt like I could find on that bike wasn't out there
And I started researching what it would take to open one and I started talking to
Took a couple of friends
And one of my friends said you know I really don't have the heart to
Tell you this but you know spending is over
Over
October 2005
Over it was over
It had it had been
Really popular in the 1990s rap for cyclists butthead.
And had mainstreamed in gems for sure
But that trended kind of falling off and
He just said they're Gill never make anything
Sing happen out of this
We're either because like I don't know
A little bit embarrassed when when you talk about in people kind of throws
Dad that concept just doesn't make sense.
I was not embarrass I was
For sure doing this
This was a calling this was definitely happening
My husband told me I was going to ruin my life
And I was going to work 24/7 and I said
I'm going to handle it
It's going to be fine
I was I was also not embarrassed I had such conviction in this idea
This was something that was definitely going to work
My husband was definitely embarrassed and I can remember several times
Before we went out to dinner who would say
Please don't talk to my
Friends that don't talk about this weird yet but I think
For me
You know it was meeting Elizabeth
That really
Allowed me to take the leap
You're not I'm not I'm not
Quite I'm not quite as convinced that if I had just been on my own that I wouldn't have been you know like he with the kombucha
But but
Two of you
MTG how did that happen how did you even
Get connected
I have been taking This Woman's class and indoor cycling class out in East Hampton
And I tried to find one in the city
And eventually I ended up
As a guest at a class at
At one of the clubs Uptown in New York switch
Churches near Julie's
Apartment and I met this teacher that I like tonight
Talk to her after class
It's a listen I'm thinking about trying indoor cycling Studio
It's really funny
There's another woman who takes my class on Saturday and she's been talking me about
Same thing YouTube we should go to lunch
That was so she said you should contact her and what happened like
She gave you
Her number
We went to lunch all three of us
A my husband so the four of us had lunch
Yep and Julie and I started talking and we just
Like what you like about her
We
We you know we very quickly
Babies that were the same age and we made some small talk and then
I think we quickly got to a conversation that was that was even more philosophical than just what we wanted
The open I think that we fundamentally saw two different
I think we both felt that exercise did not have to be torture
They could be joyful
And that by creating a place that
What was she going that way
Aspirational
And turning our instructors into more like spiritual gurus and being drill camp
Sargent's
We felt that we could really create something that people would value
And then
At the same time we could create a new product and there was no mark
A place in New York at the time there was no
Opportunity
To take pay per class Fitness at the time we're talking about 2005
There were some yoga studios but other than that
You know the model for Jim's and this is a lot of what we
What about we talk about how
Traditional gym model was
Take your credit card
Charging for monthly membership
Hope that you don't show up
So that then you can you know add more people's memberships you know
Trying to understand what the utilization rate of your gym was
We said you know what we're so confident
That we can make people feel good
That we are going to challenge ourselves every time
Every time you come you'll have a great experience because you'll have to
Pay all over again to come back
An end
And what you say
Hey let's do it you just like leave the laundry like let's do this
Yes that's exactly right
So we leave so we leave the lunch
And
You know I leave I get in the cab my cell phone rings
And Elizabeth says to me okay here was here's what's going to happen
I'm going to look for real estate and you research towels
I'm going to call you on Thursday
Intruder word Thursday the phone rang
And she said I found something on Craigslist
It's on West 72nd Street you should meet me there tomorrow
And on Thursday we met at the
The studio at what would become our first SoulCycle
Go studio
It was an old dance studio
That they were subletting for 5 years we could
Dick sublease on it
The entire thing was about 1200 square
Are feet
And we walk through and we looked at each other and we said it's
You signed
Five-year lease like
Pretty soon after
Yes
Within three weeks. I had the least sign
Kayla just passed
Cuz I want to break this.
Did you do formal partnership agreement that you do all that stuff it was still pretty much handshake like
You and me are partners and we're just going to figure it out
So at lunch that day
The woman that introduced us
VI resorts
Fitness instructor our third partner and I were friends
And so we decided at the end of the lunch that
We each bought a really particular skill set to
The business and she was going to be
The fitness instructor and she was going to help us to find other
Are teachers and help us create
The program cuz neither of us had ever created anything in
Fitness before
And Elizabeth was going to work on all of our design
And all of our business and all of our technology
We're going to work on The Branding together Elizabeth and I since we had
Such a similar vision
And I was going to work on the people
How soon do the PRI was going to train the studio staff
And so that's the way that we were going to divide
And Julie did you have any
Money at that time did you have like
Welfare
Personal you know it's like a huge stash of cash
So ironically
I had actually milk
What am I
Very close girl friends had just gotten married and she had one of the Great
Blaster glass rate rent control Apartments left in New York City
It was the first floor walk-up
Over Harry's Burrito on the corner of West 71st Street and Columbus Avenue
And she was nice enough to
To say you know what forget for as long as we can
Police why don't you take
The sublet
And so it was nine hundred and something dollars a month
And that apartment
Really allowed
Need to take that kind of risk
Sweet a 5 month old baby at the time
Can you quit your job
Well I worked I worked while we plan seoul
Cycle we met we met in January and we open SoulCycle
Ome
An integer husband really die
Continue to have a job at the time
It was actually perfect
What time it gets heated just got a new job he just figured out a way to
We have this $900 a month Apartments
And I remember at the time
Once we made the decision
SoulCycle
We got a bar credit
And on every Sunday night
Spencer would have me an envelope
What's $200 in cash
And he would say here's your money for the week
And so I know I remember
How is my baby
Folding up the
But the stroller and taking it on the crosstown bus and
You know Starbucks wasn't really an option I drink a lot of coffee at home and
All of those things it's
It's amazing
It's it's it's amazing how quickly $200 can go in New York City when you're walking down the street
Everyday but but we did it we really
We we we did it because it was something that
We really had
Well I really had
Convection oven
And he's always been real
It is okay so Julie you
For a weekend
Elizabeth did you did you guys have
Any money
I had had I had bought a little studio apartment and I had recently sold at
I had about a hundred thousand dollars
And then Allen
My husband had a great job working at this Investment Bank
Cod Lehman Brothers
And so
I said am I said I really want to start this business
And he said I did I get it
If you want to do it I'll let you know
Let's we can do it
So we took $250,000 and
And started and started SoulCycle with that
And we built the studio out inexpensively
We built a website in a reasonably inexpensively I feel like we got a lot done for 250
$2,000
And the worst thing that could happen was that in five years Julie and I could look at each other and say you know what we tried it and it
Didn't work
Yeah we would give it we would we would commit
To that.
So in that way didn't really feel like a huge rest
Yeah that's when you sign a five-year lease
What do you what do they want from you, do they look like
Six months rent
I think we gave them three months security
And the rent on the on the studio is $5,000 a month
Oh so that's
Upper West Side New York
Well it was hidden in the rear Lobby
Former Mortuary so
A very fancy location
You sending them what like how
Menu at the start of
Get the bicycles and
Get furniture in like
That must have taken
Sometime right
It took a little time but it really didn't take that much time there wasn't a huge bill.
Today which one is it
One of the things that we liked about the
Space
And our front desk original front desk had no access to it so you either had to climb over it to get behind the front desk
Or vice versa
Or you had to walk through the studio to get behind the front desk it was it was very
We don't we don't for maitreya
United and we had a we had a huge mural on the back wall that was referred
Vicodin the mirror that was a road probably Texas like one of those roads
It just goes straight into the horizon
And we thought that that was like a metaphor for the Journey of getting on the bus
Oh and we planted some bamboo outside the window so then
In the press release we could write that we had exam guard
OIC
I forgot about the bamboo
And how did you come up with a name SoulCycle
It was matter of us
We have been thinking for a long time he has a lot of really bad names
See
They were not good
They were not going to
And I cannot
Tina my husband eye Willy
I kept on describing that the
The feeling that I wanted to have when I was on the bike and when I got off the bike
And he got out of shower one day
What about Saul
What about SoulCycle
Yes yes it was like that you could have paid branding company under thousands of dollars he was just like shaving in the mirror
That's what happened
Or do you even open the door
Liking this. Of time where you're like between when you sign the lease
And when you're building it out and building Ikea furniture and
Did the three of you like surround say
Cute we are going to French to ask me all over the
The country it's going to be massive like was that your ambition or was your ambition to just
Make this one studio and see what happens
All three of us were ambitious I don't think
Vicious but
When Elizabeth and I first saw the space we went across the street
Starbucks in the business plan
In our business plan with it if we
We can see between 75 and 100. Julius always been a hundred
100 people
You know we brought them back of this afternoon which Elizabeth
Has rained in Harrah
Is it true that if if we can see a hundred Riders a day
You know that we would have enough money to
You know pay our rent
To pay the minimal staff that we had to keep the lights on and have a little bit of money left over to pay for you know
People that were helping us raise our children
And that was really our goal
To explain something to me because
Core SoulCycle
First
Spin cycle Studio
In the world that they existed not not
Quite like that
Do today but
What what was it that was going to make it
Different
You talk about community and
And I get that but
Specifically like
Was the music going to be different
What is the lights going to be different what is the
The design the
Spirit house experience going to be
So different
Fat people with half
To go to SoulCycle
I just need
Well the first thing was that we were going to have to
Technology so that people could
It was 2006
So the sounds crazy to talk about now but there were
Very few booking apps
We found that in order to become part of someone's life
We had to help them plan their weeks
So we worked on this booking app you get on your computer at noon on Monday and you could sign up
For your class
Search for the week and then that way you would know what you had to look
Forward to
The second part was the people who worked
At the front desk
Square trains to
Remember your name to ask about your vacation to remember if you liked your water or room temperature
Cold
We wanted people to cross the
The threshold of
Studio
And feel like they had gone from
The crazy in a world of hustle that is New York City
And that they had walked into a place that
Was fine that was a sanctuary and that was
The place that welcomed everyone
Before you even opened up
How how did you determine what you
Wood chart
Did you look at like
Did you look at like how many people you needed per day and rent in like how did you come up with the number and then what would initially were you
Are you charging
We started at $27 a class
We thought about it as
To cocktails or inexpensive personal training
Because we
We thought it was actually important
For people to pay for the
The class
Because people value what they pay for
And if they pay for something then when they walk in the front door
And they participate they are going to bring something different than if they aren't paying
Forest and Julie what was the idea that there's like
Open the doors and put some balloons out and hope people come in or or Gigi how did you get even
Get people to know that this was
Going to be there
So
We did a few things we we may postcards and we went door-to-door I remember pushing my baby carriage around the upper west
Sidon
You know making friends
The doorman hoping they would let me in and put
Flyers in mail rooms in
Asking other business owners if we'll be okay if I left some postcards near their counters
Then we had one other plan
Which was when we were all done building
The front desk and weed
Saved enough money so that we had enough of a run rate for a year
Elizabeth looked at me and said okay we have $2,500 left over what do you want to do for Market
We decided that we were going to make a t-shirt
The time people were just starting to come around to the concept of
Swag
Only printed this yellow camouflage T-shirt with the logo of the wheel on it
Spider-Man said SoulCycle over it now remember
Taking the first t-shirt at about that bass and I looked at a lizard
I said you know one day is not even to need to stay Soho
SoulCycle it's just going to be like the Nike Swoosh people just going to know what it stands for
Can we were like yeah yeah that's definitely
We decided that we would make 202
And we would try to get in
250 you know coolest people in New York City to wear them so that there could become some sort of brand recognition
Looking back on it it's kind of funny to think that 250 of Anythink
Make an impact
And so we put on cute outfits and we thought I told great today is the day that we're going to deliver the package
To the editor of Glamour
Thinking somebody is going to let us upstairs
Trey little little do we know that we would now spend the next
Two weeks in car is getting
You know rerooted from
Confront nail desk
The back Alleyway is where you're allowed to ask
Drop off
Packages that may or may not ever make it up
Did you get guess you you're finally
Get ready.
That's right April 26th 2006
And
I'll never forget the first time I took my parents
They came to the studio my my dad looked around and my mom sort of
Open doors in
Antique under desks and my dad looks around he says to me no showers
Who is going to come here
I live in this is not a battle worth fighting
When we come back
Patchouli rice
And Elizabeth Cutler drew that no shower bike Studio into a big business
Why they sold it
And what it was like
Stay with us
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
This message comes from NPR
Capital One
Is reimagining bad
I offering account
With no fees or mini
They can be open from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Welcome back to how I built this
Stuntman PR
So it's 2006
And Elizabeth Cutler and Julie rice
Just open their first
SoulCycle studio in New York
And I'm freezing a problem that many brick-and-mortar businesses face
Getting people on the street to actually take notice
Come in
Soda
Julie Elizabeth
They had to get
Creative
Elizabeth auto rickshaw
On eBay
And she spray-painted the Rickshaw yellow and silver
And we will assign on it
It said SoulCycle with an arrow point
To the front door be
Because you put this on the on the sidewalk
On the sidewalk because you know we didn't have a sign and so is death if you know starting a business
New York City
Without the ability to use the density of the passer Byers on the street is sort of a disadvantage
And you did not have a sign because why
Because we had signed our lease
We had sort of our landlord had pulled a bait-and-switch when he told us he had a sign he meant it would be on an interior door
In the rear
Exterior side of the building because the building would not allow
Correct with Landmark so we had no exterior signage and so you took a rickshaw and
SoulCycle this way and you can park it on the
China Wok
So we changed it up to a parking meter
We didn't and unfortunately the community board did not really like
The Rickshaw in the middle of every night so we would get a ticket for $65 a day for each day that the Rickshaw was chained up
Parking meter
But what we what we could we did was we we study the traffic
Batteries outside
Because $65 a day was actually a lot to us you know some of your classes have nobody in them and some of them had two people that could be
You know the whole price of the earnings of what we made on on running a whole class and so
We learned that you know Saturday is it might make sense to put the Rickshaw out there because
They'll be a lot of traffic
Walking by foot traffic
Pek tune from Central Park
But maybe Wednesdays around lunch time on the upper west side not so busy not worth
$65
And so we would put out our marketing vehicle on days that we thought the returns would be
And
So this is a slow burn people are coming in
And I don't know what's like Julie was your husband like
You know
I'm nervous
Department
Stop making that much and
I know you quit your job like
Are you sure about this daddy
Ever say that
Infairness
It was a Slow Burn
But the truth is in a note in business years
We started
Cashflow pretty quickly
Like how fast
Restart Cashland buy V
So we're positive cash flow
And we stay lean and you know we do we did all the jobs ourselves and we certainly weren't out there do you know
Buy expensive dinners but we definitely began to make money
And we also like keeping it lean because it allowed us to learn every job
So we put ourselves in the position of understanding how the website works
Do you know what could work better there how the what was the
Functionality of somebody checking in
How was it for something what works cleanliness standards like how would have the bathroom.
Look like
Are we just had to make sure we started doing checklist
To make sure that when there was downtime of
People are always doing things
Because we're always do
So you are cash flow positive
5 months
IMS amazing
2 after
You know you start to see
People coming to classes in the classes filling up
It becomes apparent you got to open up a second
Studio so what you do
Well we weren't quite ready to open up a second Studio but Julie had the idea to open a studio up in the Hamptons in the summer which way
Does a great idea at the tip of Long Island we were concerned about the summer
Though studios located in a residential area and we
Does you listen to your customers you hear them talking about what their summer plans are
We realized
A lot of people are going to be leaving
And we wanted to
Captivate
Keep them captivated with the brand we don't want them to get distracted and get interested in something else
In New York City
A lot of people do my
22 East Ave
Summer and
Simultaneously Elizabeth got a phone call
I'm from friends of ours
Who had said that they had heard
That there was this old barn
Butthead house an exercise Studio Buffet
Foreigners coming up for rent at summer
I was a legendary was body bark
People have gone there for 20 years and then somebody was doing pole dancing there one summer and that didn't really work on it was going to be available
And Elizabeth and I looked
Said you know what
This is a three-dimensional Market
Experiment
You know we had to rent houses out in out in the Hamptons to house our instructors in our staff we had
But on top of our rent
For the for the actual fitnessstudio to operate this thing
With our New York City organization and its
Steak houses in rent cars
And I will live delete okay
The second floor for the first
So we didn't get the car and the houses until the 2nd
We were happy we were having employees in the upstairs or very Scrappy
SoulCycle Studio
In the Upper West Side you decide
Next summer summer 2017 open up in the Hamptons like
Did both of you just like constantly go back in
Enforcing back and forth
We made a decision that the Elizabeth would spend a little bit more time out and run the studio out in in
Bridgehampton
And I was going to come back and forth
We were actually talking today about how
I'm our retail operation actually exploded that summer and we had this
This older gentleman on the upper west side who basically printed you know
Buffet at a friend's birthday party and you want to print 10 t-shirts that said you know
Happy birthday that's the kind of printing he did but somehow we made him our printer because our quantities were very small in the beginning
And then slowly but surely people start
Fanatical about the soul cycle clothing and so we would Design One collection a month in
I remember I was going to Harvey's office on East on West 83rd Street had a cat that sat on his desk
Now it's a harvey you know I know that I only needed 50 but now I need 250 can you get them to me by you know Friday
And every couple weeks I would go back to quantities would increase and I would load up my car on Friday nights and bring them out
To the barn Bridgehampton with all the new merch
And we would we'd stay up late on Friday nights and we'd set up the merchandise and I would stay for the weekend
And then during the week Elizabeth would run the Hamptons studio and I would run New York and then we get back together on the weekends
I need to take a break from his interview just cuz I'm exhausted by the descriptions of the head
The studio New York the studio in the Hamptons you were making a line of clothing by the way who is designing
Lakeshirts
It's just shirts Orlando
T-shirts and sweat
T-shirts and sweatshirts and hats and tote bags
When the leggings don't forget about the leg Incorrect and then we we branded leggings
And then we went to two sports bras and then after sports bras we went to athletic shirts and
I would say by the time the collections really got into full swing witch
Probably about
34 years into
The business we were designing
65 to 125 SKU Zaman
Unbelievable
Essentially people are
Hang you money
To advertise
I always say that the the merchandise at SoulCycle is almost like
Like having to buy the t-shirt from the best vacation that you've just been on
My mom still calls me when
She's somebody missile cyclist
I don't have the heart
Explain to her the tens of thousands of
People come to SoulCycle day
But yes my mother still calls me
Thumbelina full cycle shirt
And so we went to when you opened up in Bridgehampton the summer of two
Was it also a slow-burner world two people know about it
What happened
Game changer
There wasn't much to do out in the Hamptons
And people thinking of all the kids are at camp and then people come out as if people are on vacation and
The adults needed something to do besides drink
And
So people would do what they did all day but in the morning everybody was
SoulCycle it started at 7:30 in the morning and it had ended at 2 in the afternoon and on the hour everybody was there
And that was
Profitable probably from day one
Day one and then after that we came back from that summer and
We had gone from being a neighborhood
Business to being a
Full Citywide location
People were taking Subways up from downtown several times a week
People were really coming across the park
If we were like what what is going on and then
We would walk out because our studio was in the rear Lobby we would walk out and we would see the Town Cars and SUVs why
Signed up for
Back-to-back-to-back-to-back and this is
Uber so no
Fancy people would have there that have their cars and drivers and all the cars and drivers were lined up
In front of SoulCycle in the neighbors are wondering what was going on
And
Everybody was there rioting and it was
So fun
A certain point I don't know if it was at this point but at a certain point
The original third partner Ruth
Leaves
Why
Why did she go
There's not much we can really say about it but what I can say about Partnerships is that
It's just really important that everybody has the same vision in the same work ethic
And
If you have those two things you fight a lot of battles and then
You know your struggle is not internal your struggle is more external and that's really where
You know that the focus
Needs to be
And universe amazing teacher and she can hit as he tries for years and
Was that was that a heart was it hard for the two of you when when when I have my mink Julie she was your friend was it
Difficult at all
I think it was it was it was very early on in the business it was we don't need it only been open for
About a year
So it didn't it didn't feel so dramatic
The time business was very small and also she she stayed on for several years and continued
Teach
Another really interesting thing is that you know after that happened Elizabeth and I kind of decided that we were going to
To really invest in our partnership
Because we had
We had seen partnership not work
Doubt and I think that we
Really felt
Like
The success of SoulCycle with a real combination of the two of us and so
Elizabeth found us
A business therapist coach
And I remember she called me one morning I didn't even know her that well we've been busy
Together for a little over a year and she said
You know I
I Googled in the middle of the night last night and I googled NYC life coach and I found somebody
We're going to start seeing
Panda
Chuseok I'm not going to see anybody that you meant on the met on the internet
Let me explain to you I am
A very relaxed person and at 11:50
85 on a Sunday night I'm having
Fault
I get some help so I'm going to talk to her I'll let me see how it goes
If she's good maybe you'll be up for meeting her
And so and so that started us down this journey of
We have an amazing coach that we still work with
Today and
The person that we met on the internet first night we met on the internet
Wow and it was amazing was you know we really made a commitment at that
Time to saying
You know there are going to be moments in this business when
You see it one way and I
I see it another way or you know you want to grow another five Studios and I don't want to or whatever it's whatever it is
But we are going to make those decisions together we're going to really communicate about them and
I think that
That was
Ultimately one of
One of the things that I think made the business most successful with our dedication to our partnership
Okay so it eats I guess round 2008
And
You guys decide to open up another Studio New York in in Tribeca
I need this was 2008 this is the start of the recession so
Where did you get that money
Yeah it was it was
Timing so a couple things happened one
I checked the bank account after Lehman collapse and I was
Fleming Island
Shenzhen
I was so proud of him cuz he had
He had sold
Then I went stuff invested he had sold it and so I was
Oh my God there's money in the bank account it's so awesome because
Julie and I
Need some cash to open Tribeca
And I want to borrow $600,000 and he was
I'm having the worst month of my life
Are you kidding me
I said no I'm super not getting you offering to pay you
Huge interest rate and you are going to let me that money
I tried to be honest with you I tried to get money from other places I had a friend that I grew up with it ran a private bank at one of the big
Big banks in New York
And it was after the collapse in the feds are funding these Banks and I said I need a credit line of $3000000
I can start with Millie but I need three
And they looked at me and they said okay well if you put up
For collateral
Your apartment
And equities that equal the same value as the amount of the credit line then we will lend it to
I was so Furious
How dare you do that
A my taxes are funding you right now
I am not asking for that much money we are running 10 million dollars
Farm
Aren't all of our transactions through your bank and that you that is your message to me
And they said that is our mess
Once you have 60 million dollars of Revenue we can help you
I said by the time we have 60 million dollars of Revenue I will not need you I got up and left the room
It was a really stressful I was so mad
But that's what I that's actually when I called Alan and said
Hey
I checked the bank account and I realized you have some cash in there and then we can probably do it for that but it was tight I mean we
When we open Tribeca we almost didn't make payroll we didn't have might we
Somebody called up to the office
Jason said
Oh my gosh
Elizabeth do you know we need to buy some toilet paper and
Credit cards aren't working
How much toilet paper do I have
Well we got about 20 rolls I'm like that's great will you better wait till tomorrow
But we never miss payroll and we always had toilet paper and
That part that part really were
Worked out well
Alright so you guys
In Spanish open up a couple
Locations of New York
You're doing well
Run 2010
Competitors tried to come
Including one
Called
Flywheel
And this was started by
Your former partner Ruth
You shocked by this to do to make you nervous to upset you
That
Well when flywheel opened and they were going to become
Competitor in the
Fitness space
I think rather than sort of freaked out about it which
Of course we did for you know the first year or so kind of monitoring the scene and what was going
Yunnan
And there were some new bikes that were coming out there's a bunch of stuff coming out
Yeah it wasn't just that the time I think that you know
Milkweed we started of
Boutique Fitness Market Place in a lot of things were now coming into the market
People had
Going to be on just flywheel peep
Other choices that they could
Hindu Purp
Paper class so
We were no longer the only option in that
Marketplace
But we really we really took the opportunity
We talk to our coach
Only really took the opportunity to say to each other you know
Who do we want to be
You know let's not react
You know we always did things that
Many times
People thought we were nuts
To do that
But we always made the choices that felt good for us and I think we really just tried to keep our heads
Yeah I'm really curious about
The relationship between the two of you
China Grove businesses
The fraud and filled with tension and
But it strikes me that
That getting a coach
Like a kind of like a therapist
That you forced yourself to go and talk to together
Was kind of a key that that
That that really
Help you guys
Develop your leg
There's no question that it did I mean I think that
We also lived by this this one saying we only said to each other High Road Longview
Hi Road Longview we would never allow ourselves
Get down in the mud and get dirty we would
We went we would do that if something needed
Was broken and needed
To be fixed
But once we did that
We really kept our eye on what was most important so
I think that that that's it that's
Cheese fat
You know both of us decided matter
You have to remember
You know we actually weren't even the stars of this business we haven't really talked about our instructors yet
Who were the face of the company
So we were sort of we sort of thought let's build the stadium
Let's put these rock stars on the stage
Let's let them sort of the phases of and bask in the glory of and change these people's lives
That was really what we were doing we're building a
Brand we weren't in a we weren't in it for either of our egos
What's the point where
We really turned other people into
The faces of the brand
So I think it was around 2011
Pretty big steak to Equinox
Status
Future of high-end Fitness Company
Why
Real thing going you were running it
Did you leave
The further scale business
Yeah we felt like
To have someone to have a strategics
Play book
Would be really valuable
We wanted to expand to the West Coast
And we felt that by being able to work with these guys that it would
It would allow us to do that and so we we did do a partnership with them in 2011
Let's just be frank at this point
Both of you are rich you know that you are going to have money and
Truly for you you didn't have
A whole lot of money was it
That must have been amazing to to know that you were going to be financially secure
Yeah that that first part of our sale
Equinox was really
That that was life
Obviously for me and for
My family in
In a bit beyond what we could have ever imagined tonight
I remember thinking you know the day that we actually got that wire to come through
My kids are good and I ll remember
Did the time that I was able to put them each in their own bedrooms and then each child having a bedroom in New York
York City is a monumental
It's a Monumental task
Sure
And so yeah it was it was truly life
How many SoulCycle
Studios are there
Today 88
Couldn't have happened without
Unsend messages
It gave us the confidence to
To do it
The truth is
Looking back
Yes we could
Yes we could have done it
But it really gave us
The confidence to do it and sometimes that's what you need I mean I think that
Listen people always say
Entrepreneurs are
They're such good Risk Takers and
And the truth is sometimes you do take a rest but Allah
A lot of times it's really terrifying
And we had a lot on the line
SoulCycle did it
Expand
But there
I guess it was some tension after Equinox
Took over
And eventually you both
Divested you you left
The company
Today
Neither
Neither of you are owners of
SoulCycle
Correct
You are not a piece of
That's right that's
Is it weird
Tok to walk
Down the street SimCity and see a soul cycling
I don't know that
For me at every time I see a SoulCycle I still feel like
It's a love child and I feel proud of
I feel proud of the
Of the energy that I know is contained in those rooms and what it what it does for the people who opt into that
Experience
I will say
That
There are those who said to me when we were getting ready to
To do our original deal in 2011
You know selling a business is not like selling a child
I mean
Do you have children this is your business
In a very detached
And I will say that that is
Supernatural I obviously didn't know back checking
As to whether or not the person who said that
It's me or the people who said that to me it ever started a bit
Because it is a child
In fact
When we were
Funny story We Were
People at 70 was coming to an early out in the distance and you should franchise
And I looked at you in
Are we already have
For children between us how many children
So we just
Kind of felt like
SoulCycle each one of the studios was like a child and
And I'm when we left
Sweet and we left a few
Days of our heart there because
That's what you do
I think Elizabeth's right look
I think that
Somebody should write a book
44 founders
About what it is like
To sell their businesses you know it
I think that there is
Yeah there's there's definitely a morning.
There's definitely
There's definitely you know. Where you spend some money
And then there's definitely. Where you begin to think about you know what am I going to do next
For me
I'm it still is a really
Significant part of my day in my life meaning
Moore's I was a customer than it is as somebody who founded the business
I'm able to go there and sort of
Enjoy the product.
We created for ourselves
I'm curious cuz a lot of
A lot of
Very experienced and entrepreneurs listen to the show famous entrepreneurs but most people who listen are
Starting out you know or there
In the middle of
The chi grinding away
And
Curious if you had to go back
2 mm
And you had a crystal ball what you said
Let's try to just do this on our own and not bringing any
Investors let's let's keep bootstrap
I mean if there were two alternate universes I would certainly play that out
But on the other hand
You know we never forget why we started the business and
Like we said we we really started the business to
Create an environment for people that was like the secular sanctuary
People could feel safe coming in there and they could
Berner cheesecake from the night before or the tap into some
Something tribal on that bike and that was why we did it we never ever ever forgot why
We did that
Sure would have been
Interstate Econo play that out but
The thing is on the other hand
The way that it did work out we
We still got it
To do all those things
Baby must be weird to go from
Dislike fast-paced like
Really
No special your co-ceos you to staff your people around you play Everyday
Second day was scheduled
It was a teen that was energy and then like one that you wake up
Xiamen airlines
Having coffee with
Kitchen in your life
Play cuz it wasn't like that
Well we're busy still I mean you know we tried
Catch our breath of Denton
We we actually remember Saint Elizabeth
Set them on the day that we made the decision to
I said okay but you have to make sure that we get an office
Together
So at least I know that we're going to have two computers and sticky notes and we can have a place to meet in the morning and I can do this
As long as we know that
Somewhere there's an office where we have to desk
Twitter side by side we did it we took an office
And there was definitely something psychological
About sort of knowing that there was a
Place where would that we could touch base with which with each other every
And I think I think we're kind of just coming up for air right now
I think it helps
But for the first time it's like the two of us can look at each other and
Kind of
You know it's like you're at your eyes adjust to the light a little bit differently weird
Coming conversation this morning about how much the world has changed
What what do you think the world needs now
Is you know I asked this question
Everyone come to the show and I want somebody truly
How much of what happened
With your cycle do you think is because of
Your intelligence in your skill and how much
Because you
Just got lucky
It's interesting you know and thinking about the neck
Time around now that you know so much it turns out that
The lesson that I would help
People live in ignorance is actually Bliss right
We made so many decisions we made so many mistakes but we just kept
Keep going because we didn't know any better
Now you know how to look at all those Excel spreadsheets and p&l and all that stuff and you can make yourself crazy but I think it's
Time
You know what we didn't know helped us
And weed
Trust in our God and we went
And I don't think anything about it was lucky I think the only lucky thing with Elizabeth and I bumped into each other
Elizabeth
I mean how do you
Outback
David on top
I think it was lucky that I got time that we got to meet each other at I got to meet Julie and then she got to meet me I think it was lucky that we got
Houses in
Incredible writers who inspired us every day and get to work with people that we loved and
It was extremely high touch
We always had our office
Is attached to Studio we never
Using the product then
I meant I think
You know that kind of effort
That we would that we brought to it created
I guess you could call it like a certain kind of
Cumulative magic that happened over the years that everybody participated in and created
Elizabeth Cutler and Julie rice
Co-founders of SoulCycle
A mother no longer part of
Company
Julie Elizabeth have kept up their partnership
What to do investing firm
Call Mike shop
By the way
Elizabeth says that her husband said give her a hard time about opening a cycling Studio
Even the SoulCycle really started to take off
He still had his doubts I could tell he was getting mocked at work because one day he comes home and he's like
If you guys ever make
10 million dollars
I will run naked
Through the streets
East Hampton New York on a Saturday
In July
Vicki lucky you didn't make the bed
He made the bat what we never being that we never made him
Make good on the bed
You never made him do it now
Okay let's do it next Summer Palace
We're going to have him run naked
It's going to be a video podcast you're such a Visionary guy like this
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
Things your building
The first
A quick message
One of our sponsors Microsoft
Who wants you to know that the newest member of the Microsoft Surface family
Surface Pro 6
As of 2/3
13 1/2 hours of battery life
8th gen Intel Core processor
You can work for as long as you want to
Forever work
XU
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you go back
And today story starts
About 7 years ago
Columbia South Carolina
Gabby Goodwin was
About 5
And everyday
She went through the same routine
Mama will put Pigtails in my hair
And for every pigtail that was in my hair
There was plastic barrettes on every single one of them
I think you know Gabby talking about and usually
She had one of these plastic barrettes in
10 / pigtails
But me when I was little I will be running around at school and my mom would pick me up and my hair will be
I would say in what happened to your bones like what were you doing
Pep Boys in courses Gabby's mom Rosalyn
Really
Set up that her daughter's Brett's kept coming over hair
One day
Roslyn
Actually went on Twitter to complain about it just to blow off
Christine I didn't think anybody would respond I got off Twitter came back on and probably about an hour and had all of these respond
Bosses from Mom
Who felt the same way all these mom saying yes our daughters barrettes are falling out to
Emma wasting tons of money replacing them
The Roslyn wasn't necessarily looking to solve this
This problem she was working full-time as a healthcare Lobby
Austin
She has no interest in
Starting a business
But
A couple weeks later as I was
Styling Gabriel's Hair I mumbled under my breath
Somebody needs to make a bowl and she jumped out of the seat and said Mommy
Are we going to make a bow until every single day after that
Gabby would ask Rosalind
Same question
When my phones coming when I'm at those coming when are we going to make a bowl
So trifling figured okay since Gabby is so into it maybe we can just do this as a kind of
Work on a design for a buret and see if we can make
Chest
One just one threat
The first aid Reddit design
Two-Face
So you could see a pretty decoration no matter which way the buret was turned
In each case
Has teeth
Annie's critters
To trap and gather the hair
So you're basically creating this
Sandwiching mechanism
To make sure the hair
It doesn't slip out of hair
Tourism looks at this design and she's thinking
This isn't half bad maybe
Maybe we can make a prototype so she gets the number of a couple of Engineers
End
She calls him up
You can just kind of hear them sigh like oh God
Can I sit me up listen you got 15 minutes
Is it good to meet with these guys in North Carolina and it first
Things do not go well
The engineers are looking at the sign of a hair clipping not getting it
And I said well you know what
I'm going to run to my car and I'm going to go
In my backseat
Promise you there's a standard burette that is falling off Gabrielle's Hair
And sure enough
@doug in the backseat of my car
Founder Standardbred
Brought that back in at that point Roslyn use the mannequin to demonstrate how easy
Standardbred just fall out of your hair
And how her and Gabby's design works a lot better
As soon as I did that
A light bulb went off
Playset ma'am
You think you're onto something
So these two engineers
Weed to help her make the Prototype
It had a manufacturer in China
They made an initial run
500 Bose
And in early 2014
Roslyn and Gabby put them up for sale on their website
And in like
20 minutes
They get their first order we can offer sale and we're like
This is actually happening like
Oh my God we're business
And they sold out all 500 barrettes
Pretty quick
Aliso Rosslyn and her husband took out a few loans to fulfill more orders
In last year
They became profitable for the first time
With over $100,000 in Revenue
Gabby is not 12 years old and is the CEO of Gabby bows
And even goes around the country sometimes giving talks
About how to be a kidpreneur
Anybody can be a computer as long as you
Have the courage to run a business
You can be 4 years old and have a visit
Let's Gabrielle Goodwin and her mom Roslyn
Founders
Gabby's bows
If you want to learn more about the company or here
Episode head to our podcast page
How I built this
Npr.org
And of course
If you want to tell us
Your story
Build
Npr.org
We love love love hearing what you're up to
Thanks so much for listening
The show this week
Tribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review you can also write to us at 8
IBT at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet is at how I built this was produced
Sweet by James delahoussaye
Music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis thanks also to be a vet cat JC Howard Norco
Santa's Mexican for Jeff Rogers and Gyros and you been listening to how I built this
NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign mode
An email marketing flag
Used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Bill
And customer support
Seven days
Campaignmonitor.com