Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Before Christmas got a lot of press cell
But we found out when we placed our order that there was no way that our bag would be ready be
I don't know why it was so surprising to us we're like what do you mean like we have this time
And it said that if we ordered the bags by August would have them for the holidays
Someone had said that we had to stop doing that
NPR how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movement they built
I got a broken suitcase inspired
Rubio to design a better one disrupt the multibillion-dollar luggage
Instagrammable suitcase
Away
Standing at the baggage carousel at
At the airport
Waiting for your bag to come around
The never-ending parade of black suitcases going by
And every now and then the person next to you rushes to grab one of those bags only to realize
It's not actually hers
Who's a pretty common scenario
Because a lot of people
Suitcases
Just the thing you shovel your stuff into when you go on a trip
450 bucks at TJ Maxx or on Amazon
And most of the time
You shove into a closet or under your bed
Between trips
Probably only last
A few years before the zipper breaks
The handle falls off
And most of us have always accepted that that's
Just the way it is right
Well Jen Rubio
And back in 2015 she had a hunch that other people might
Needed help mid-range suitcases were designed they
Boring and uninspired
She wanted something that would last
A long time and
Create a bag
That would be I catching something
You want to show off at the airport
Approached a friend named Steph Curry
Who worked with her at Warby Parker
And the result of that partnership is away
It's a line of sleek suitcases that come in tons of colors like rose gold or violet or
Sky blue
Perks like a built-in phone charger
Kind of bag you want to Instagram poll you travel the world
Indians own story of traveling the world it started when she was a kid in the Philippines
Your mom was a dentist and her dad was a business professor there
Until one day when Jen found out that their lives
We're about to change
Remember when I was 7 years old
My parents told me that me and my brother and my mom were moving to
To the US
And we've never been and we are so excited
And they told us stories about how in the US it's
And we went to
It is giant mall in Manila
And bought snowsuits
Had a penguin and my little brother had a blue one
And a reward them on the plane since May 1st
Big big fight with my mom my dad stayed behind cuz he didn't have a Visa yet and we were snowsuit
Remember to speak very sweaty on the plane
And this was like
I don't know
Late September on the plane to to the USB insisted
Found it
And we land at Newark Airport in Lake September
Sweltering was super hot and that was the first time I'd ever
Really experienced true disappointment
Why did you guys
Would you do know what the reason was it was it just like new opportunities her or what
Yeah that's a good question I mean read a great life
In the Philippines
As far as I remember
But
It was presented to us a very
Exciting
Opportunity that not a lot of people got we had
A couple of aunts and uncles who already lived
On the east coast and we were going to join them and
We never even met these ants
We are super excited about
Obviously looking back now is just
For my parents to
To continue to grow and have more opportunities to develop their careers and
And give a better life
10 to us
Jen's dad was able to join the family
New Jersey
Her mom opened up a dentist office
And her dad
Started to settle into a new life
In America
Did you put the kid that you like or you immersed in Filipino culture or
I think
Interlock two different experiences of immigrants
Kids and they're the ones who embrace it and they're the ones like me who are
Immensely embarrassed of of these
Periods and I think it had a lot to do with
You know the other kids
School or like wanting to fit in
Orbitz
No I I only spoke English I would like
Get mad at my parents when they would cook Filipino food because it would make like
My school jacket
I smell like food
And I was just
I don't know I was like as a kid and I just so embarrassed of the whole thing
It'll come to terms of that until you're
Like cold early 20
When you start to kind of realize
Is that it's a hugely Rich part of
Yeah and it's so valuable and and it's so important and I just
I advise that you know play the first
10 years
In the USA just like being embarrassed
Abby Filipino
That was a pretty good student to high school
Despite that she says being more interested in being cool
I'm doing well in her classes
What time do the college
He chose Penn State
It was like TV College
Public College in the movies
Nerf football game and there are
Hunza people
Colors
Like a qua. I know that's normal and every
Best but it was just like all of the
College things you saw in movie
And I was like this is amazing
And I
Pics of major
Cold Supply Chain
It was like
Begin the orientation day it said
You know they're one of
A handful of schools in the US offering supply chain as a major and I was like
Cool
Exclusive
I chose not to study
So you're doing like
You're in college
And
I guess you decided that you just at a certain point
You
Opportunity
I meant that you didn't
Go back
Call it's like what what happened
Yes so I was on
I think a bunch of classes
In a business school and they had at Penn State was called a co-op program which is you take a semester off
And you work for six month
At a company
And I was hating school and I was hating going to classes
Taking the test
Actually having to apply
Myself
So I read about this program
And I was like
Kulyuk
You got credit so you don't have to go to school
And I decide
To do it and I was place
Stat
Johnson & Johnson in
Show me New Jersey
And I remember getting there on the first day
And
It's on
Huge company and this is their headquarters
And
They told us something
Mind blowing on the 1st
140000 people work here
And I just couldn't
Wrap my head around that number
I can remember I kept trying to relate it back
It's like the Penn State football stadium
And how many people could
Fit in there
And I was I was just enamored with the whole thing I like I got a cubicle
And I got an ID badge
And I had my own desk in my own phone number and my own email and an email signature
And just the idea of
Work and being
Like a business lady
Was so exciting to
Me and I just never wanted
But I had to sew it it ended
I had to go back
I first semester and I was
So miserable I had
I had felt like
And you what was out there
I knew it was like to work
This whole like
Corporate world existed and it was like
Thrilling to me and I wanted to be a part of it
So after a semester baggage
High School
I got another Co-op
And this time I got placed at Neutrogena
Which is also owned by Johnson
Datsun in LA
And I asked them to extend it
Summer internship and then I asked
Extend it into another thing I just
Back to style
Fathoms
Going back to school
And
I don't know how I did it but they
They let me stay
And they made me
I promised that I would take the rest of my credits
Online
And that I would finish and get my degree
And I never did
And they offered you a job
Yeah and I and I base it was just like
The intern who never laugh
And I was invited to walk at graduation but I think I'm so
So you you're insecure
Technically a College Dropout
Yacht Technic
Yeah I think I think people are like oh cool your College Dropout might not like drop out of college so I can
So I could work in a cubicle
2007 year in early 20s living in LA
You're working for a Neutrogena and that that was your plan
Yeah so I was working at a church and one woman that I really admired and that
I have never spoken to her personally but
I just remember recalling like every time she sent an email like everyone would open it and everyone would
Read her analyst reports all the time and every time she spoke with people with people with listen and she ran marketing
And I was talking to kind of my mentor about her and I was like okay how do I get a job
It marketing So This Woman's like
Oh well to work in marketing care uni
Need to get an MBA
And me being me
Think to myself oh I should finish and get my
My undergrad degree so I can go get an MBA I would like there must be some way around that
But now exist
It opened up the
This whole new world to me
Of being able to work in marketing which to me at the time meant that you could control how
How people
Found out about your product
And how you could take everything that people were saying about it and maybe change the products and I just thought it was so cool
And I knew I really wanted to do it
And that if I couldn't do it there I would find
Somewhere else that would let me do it
So I quit
And did you have a job or did you did you think okay I'm going to figure this out I'm going to
Try and do marketing for
People and
Just
Figure it out
Yeah
I need to do marketing I quit
And I didn't have a job
And I don't have a degree
And I didn't have that much money
But I had
That platform Tumblr
Yeah Usher
So Tumblr
I guess maybe just started and I was like one of the early people on it
And it wouldn't make it off I would do in my spare time I would like to write on my Tumblr blog
And I had met a few
People in LA on Tumblr
One of the guys I met
You know did social media
Add
YouTube social media
Other job like I had my space eye Tumblr
I had Twitter and I
I didn't know that you could
Do that and also that it was part of marketing
But he would do
He would use social media for some of like the OG food truck
In LA
He would like to eat like
Control their Twitter or whatever Facebook with whatever was around at that
So it's so wild it was literally Twitter and
Doing social media for food truck MetLife
You would just tweet where the truck was going to be
Which sounds so crazy now. That was some of the job but I remember like following the Twitter account
Finding out that the truck was going to be like
On the corner of these streets in La driving over there
There be hundreds of
Well there
And I don't know why but it just
Blew my mind
You can just tell me where you are
My people will come
And that's
But those are business
Otherwise like the truck would have just sat somewhere and you had to maybe drive
Buy it
And I think it was like this is marketing
Like this is how you get paid to do marketing and do social media and these are all things I was interested in
I got this I'm figuring this out so
I started being like a freelancing filter
Set the social media
You just put your like you to sleep hung shingle out to like how did you get people
Tire you how did you know where to go
Honesty
So much of it is like it was a really a lot of the right place
Right time I was living in La it was when
I'm in food trucks for a big thing
And I kind of just spread the word
I would go to small business
Kisses and two food trucks
And my first client was the caffe
On my street
Not around anymore but
You're just a little cafe on Beverly Boulevard and I would
But he's sitting at Cafe all day
And sweet things like
There's a password of the day and if you say the password at the register you get like
Caffe Espresso
So.
With such a mature our butt
There was also nobody doing
So
I found myself in this
Kitchenware
I am getting paid
To do something
I don't know that much about it
But also at the same time everyone saw me
And it was
One of the wildest
Years of my life because
My first
Client was
Was Buzz Coffee
And I don't even know if they paid me like I think they paid me
Coffee
And then all the sudden I was doing it
For a food truck in a restaurant and then all the sudden like they introduce me to someone and I was doing it for
A new hotel that was open
And then all the sudden I realized I
Just spent a year being immersed in digital and social media and realizing how
How people could
Could use that in a really powerful way
Like I also it wasn't making a ton of money but I was
Size also doing like personal assistant stuff so I was a personal assistant to
The wife
As one of the heads of like one of the very big studios in LA
And then she had asked me to help her with her blog
And her social media and her website
They start helping her with that
She told her husband I was doing a great job
And all the sudden I find myself like
Driving up to the lot everyday like checking in with my ID and
Meeting with these film Executives talking about how they could Market their films
Like your social media and this was like
This is a time when it's just starting to explode right into primarily this is like Facebook and Twitter at that
Adam Wainwright
Yeah I was just Facebook
But I like my space with tapering off
I mean
You were just sort of
Doing it right like you weren't even set up a business or a company or
You didn't sort of show the company's how the their social media impacted the world right you weren't like producing
You were just out there doing the social media
Stop and
Hoping that they were happy with it
Yeah exactly because there are no metrics the red-nosed analytics of any sort at this time
And
Artistic look what I tweeted look at all these people that responded look at these people who showed up and end for me it was
That was actually great because it wasn't reported look real tangible stuff it was like
People showing up and saying some
We're doing something or spending money
At the business
I'm in that was really exciting
Skip ahead
Prefer sex
Because I guess eventually you were you were able to get a job at
Like a legit
Ad Agency New York and then and then you started
Do this
What type of stuff like marketing
Real
And then in 2011 you got recruited by Warby Parker how did that happen
So I have Tumblr to think for this one again so
My friend Rich who worked a Tumblr
Would like
You could meet with these guys are starting this
Glasses
Company
Online and they just want to talk to someone about social media
Remember meeting this guy who works at Warby Parker
And we met at at Union Square Park
And
I remember realize I kind of halfway through our conversation that it was a job interview
I thought that
I just like coming in there to like chat with them about the startup and
They would like take my brain and there was something like really open to
And I like being like I think I just interview to be the social media manager at Warby Parker
And that's how I got started in the startup world
Damn
To the cofounders have been on
The show
Before and them
In the social media yet
Really came up do they have
800 social media strategy when when you got there
It's still
This is the like the Stone Age is just a social media compare
Compared to today but today
Do they have like
Accounts for all the different social media Staffing
Sickly for
No customer service and
And the guy who interviewed me Brian
You're his whole job is like
Replying to everyone on Twitter which I became my job
Fidget spinners
10 hours a day
Plaintiff
People even if even people
Be like I love Warby Parker I would reply like
Thanks
Like hundreds of times a day
Xian Facebook
On Twitter
Are there on Tumblr
And
Instagram login
Right when I started
Are the guys there's a school platform
I think we should go on it and they're like the pic or whatever
And what did you what did you do for the money
Like what
Did you start to use like me like Instagram to
Tepexpan
Their brand
Just so I think
I started thinking about
The content strategy would look like how do we
How do we take
This is amazing thing that we're building this kind of weird which is selling glasses online
All of my friends thought I was crazy for doing this
I like how do we how do we like translate that experience
It's like a social media community and we would do things like
Like Warby Parker had that like home try-on program to Tryon
5 pairs of glasses
And we would do it so that like people would post their 5 and like weed repost at or Tambo
And then like our community would like help them pack
There's like a big thing on on Tumblr
Facebook like
We're basically crowdsource
What brands people should buy
A new disturbance
Really loyal really engaged community and its
Kept growing and growing and I think
It was embarrassing to kind of like
Look back at
Your work
Especially in those early days but I really was just like
I really could feel how
Social media was having a
Impact on
How much people love the brand that was released
When you why you're at
Warby Parker did it ever cross your mind that
Like I want to start my own business one day or was that
Not even
On your radar at all
No I never wanted
Start my own business I never wanted to be an entrepreneur
I think it was just so grateful to have found
Work into something that I really enjoyed and for me that was a social media and marketing
Eventually
Brand development
That because those opportunities
Seems so Limitless
And that I never felt like I could learn everything there was to know
About what I was doing that it never occurred to me to do to start my own thing
So I guess you you should have
Plasti Dip Warby Parker for
I'm about to
Plus years
And you were
Recruiter ruu
You got a job with
AllSaints which is that the
The fashion brand
Basement UK
Global head of innovation you would like
26 27 years old
Happy that happen when I join Warby Parker there where
8015 p
People there
By the time I left there were a couple hundred
So
It was still growing really quickly I still left like
Pretty early days but my my father passed away while I was working at Warby Parker and it kind of
It like I kind of
Slow down a little bit after that and I start thinking a lot about what I wanted to be doing and coincidentally like this head
Headhunter called me at the same time as kind of going through that
And moving to London
I
Seems like
The most exciting things I could do and I was so drawn to the opportunity
Thing to do with anything
I'd ever done
Before so I became
The global director of innovation at all
And this is when they were there trying to turn the company around they had new owners and new CEO
Yo
Has 26 or 27 and I had a seat at the table
With all these like very seasoned Executives from
I'm selfridges and Harrods and
Engagement from Warby Parker and they wanted some of that magic
For their brand freezing Italy
Basically the new CEO
At All Saints
I think I just
Wanted someone from Warby Parker it was like
Great job great title like I got to live in London
I didn't realize until after the fact that what was missing is that might our career had revolved around the idea that
There's a Brad
And that
Someone in the middle does something
And then
Does
A customer at the other end Who falls in love with it
And I don't mind her career around like
That middle
Like being in the gap
Between
The customer and the brat
Building a relationship making people fall in love with the company
And because all of my projects at All Saints
Turned out to be internal facing and more like internal innovation
I realize that was the part
But I really miss
A bike wasn't wise enough to realize that at the time
I bet I can get space
So what
What happened what did you mean
We just kind of
Waiting tip
To figure it out
Yeah I was waiting to figure it out
I've always promised myself that I would
Only
Work on things it
Made me happy especially after my dad passed away was like really poor
For me to
To spend my time doing things that I was really passionate about and I knew that I had kind of
Dried up for me and this opportunity
Since I left
I left all Saints
And I was still living in London
Kind of
For finite amount of time
Because my Visa was going to expire so I started interviewing for jobs
I
Interviewed for like
VP of marketing like CMO.
Sat companies of all different sizes
And during this I completely just on a tear around the world
Splitting my time between
Interviewing and like going on vacation
So I'm in Zurich Airport
And
My back break
And it was this
Old dog that I'd had
Texas College I guess
No name
Like black ballistic nylon bag
Super Mario saying like I didn't realize it broke
I didn't realize a zipper broke so I'm leaving a trail of like
My underwear behind me as I'm as I'm running through the airport
And
I get home and
I
Go on Facebook
And I told her about this embarrassing story about my back breaking and I asked
People if they have any record
4 News
Just trying to shop
This is like this is like 2015 this isn't thought that long
At that point I've travelled
Hundreds of thousands of miles in my life with this one bag
And I was super annoyed and I was just like okay I'm just going to buy a really nice bag
But I love and this won't happen again for a while
What time
So
I asked a bunch of
People in every single person is like
I don't know or
I have this but don't get it it's awful or or I would specifically ask a friend
That and you traveled a lot
And here she would be like
You know what what brand a table with and I think
So crazy to me that
All of these people including myself
Who love to travel who did it all the time who packed a suitcase every time they travel
Really had
No connection to
This thing that they brought with them
Get on every single flight on every
Most people
Bogota like
Target r
TJ Maxx or something or
Marshalls in just like
Go to CK sorry and get a suitcase
Yeah and I didn't want to do that which is why I asked them
And then if I found out that like
No one really had luggage that they
There is
One girl
Really loved her
And it was like 4000
Even though they make $4,000 luggage
So what I thought to myself was
I have to find the spread
There has to be a great luggage
Yeah like I didn't I didn't
Start my toes just like we're not looking for
Just be clear
You weren't looking for the category start a business in
No not at all not at all know I was like
I wanted to go shopping
I wanted to buy the right thing so that this wouldn't happen
I was I was crowdsourcing for answers
I didn't get it
And these are people
Who I have liked
Emmaus
A network of friends over time
MC2
Whose taste I really trust Whose advice
I take and
No one had
Any advice from
Iran is like good luck
So I started to think
Why doesn't this luggage brand exist
That's like how come buying luggage
Is so awful
I like how come you have to go
It's like the basement of a department store or
I'm your New York there's all these like
Crazy luggage stores in Midtown
There are massive and
And you go in and there's a
The $500 bag
Text a $50 bag and they look exactly the same
And I
I like the luggage sales man is like whispering in your ear like
I can give you 30% off
If you buy it right now
Why is it so horrible
So
That's when
I maybe thought
That I could
Start something like at this point
Because interviewing for jobs and in my head I was like I can start a little luggage business
On the side
I like make it like
Some cool brand
And maybe sell it at
Like at liberty or on Netta Forte or like this cool places that I like to shop
And that's when I caught up with
Stuff
Parker
I met Steph Curry and we started on the same day
And we became fast friends and we're friends
All throughout my time at Warby Parker
Sharon supply chain there
So she's in charge of how
The glasses where me is like
The factories that we got him from like how they got
To the states to be shipped to customers
Stuff that
I actually
Technically went to school for but really didn't know much about
Kind of went through this like
Hypocrisy growth of Warby Parker together
And we stayed friends and we like Loosely kept in touch we check in
Every few months
So just has this like
Is little baby idea
Of making luggage that my friends would love
Was brewing in my head
I I reach out to staff and
Facebook message
And I said hey there
Something I've been thinking about would love to catch
With you
And
She was
Chisholm business school at the time so should we will be Parker
Yeah she left her B Parker to go to business school at Columbia
And I
She just always been my son
Sounding board
So I called her catch up
And I was mostly complaining
I was like
Good luggage brand doesn't exist like
I have a bunch of ideas like I think
I think I could make like a cool one
Also how annoying have to go interview
Other job
I was just catching up
And this was supposed to be a 10-minute
Call and
3 hours later
First on the phone
And
Basically she was in business school and she had been looking
And she was the one who was like
What we did at Warby Parker
We can do it like
Wow BC got off the phone and she realize like
All the same things that we saw
With I where we were seeing would like
Like
Crazy markups in the end
Like no brands that people really love
Just like a really awful shopping
So she was coming out at
In this whole life
Lek supply chain disruption angle
And she's
I guess she was sitting there and business school like looking for her category and I be so he called her with my little baby
Maybe idea start a luggage brand
And she's like this is at
Like this is what we have to do
When we come back in just a minute how Jennings death turn this baby idea into a reality
And have a copy table book save their business day with this guy Roz and you listening to How I
Built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobiledit
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR
To save 10% off your first purchase
Is have a website or domain
Support also comes from servicenow
Making the world of work work better for me
Their cloud-based platform
Form and solutions deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees
And unlock productivity
For your whole come
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have
So they can do the work
They wanted
Using technology
How to make people more productive and enjoy
Moret servicenow.com
People come back to how I built this
NPR
Okay so it's 2015
And Jen Rubio and steph korey
We have this idea for
Better luggage
But to start working on it
Take a leap of faith
Because at the time
Both of them work interviewing
Other jobs
So I still living in London and I was in
Pretty late
Stages
To be VP of marketing at this fashion
Stuff is in business school and talking to a few startups about
Being like their VP of supply chain
And I
And I was
I was actually being flown into New York
Or like one of my final interviews
And I realize I was doing the interview that I was like
I don't want to do this
I want to do the luggage
I don't remember how wet but I got the job offer
And I really didn't want to take it
Because I had been
So excited
About
About this idea
4 luggage brand
That I actually wrote
I wrote stuff in email
About how
I never wanted to be an entrepreneur before but like
Was really passionate about this a to ya
And I thought that we were the two perfect people to do it
Animate a whole list of everything I wanted a co-founder and then explain how she embodied
All of those things like I wanted someone
Crye-Leike
Complimentary
Skillset and like had other lucrative opportunities that they were turning down to do this which is like
Weird qualifier but was really important to me
And it wasn't until
I wrote that email
Like asking her to be my co-founder
And asking her to do this with me
That
That was the point of kind of realize
I wanted to be
Did you did you come up with the name already at that point
I was looking for
It's a wild story about how he came up with it but
As I was doing my research I was like
Try to stay organized
I made like a folder on my computer
Peter
And it was like
TBD luggage brand and one day I like open my computer
And I just typed in a way
As a placeholder like it just came
And I always had it in my head
There's no way we can use it away as
Brand name
Just simple like four letter word
Sick extremely common
And then it stopped
She spent a lot of time like brainstorming new names but we just never came up
With anything
As good
And she found like
Some trademark lawyers
And ask them
If we could trade market and they basically laughed in her face
I just like
Cilic insisted that they looked into it and then a week later they called us and they said
You have been given a gift in the marketing gods
Because
This trademark is available in your category in a lot of different
Countries
Alright so you have a name and
What's the first step like how do you
Luggage made like where do you where you going to start
Yashow kind of like
Our first steps made sense to us because
We R Who We R I had this
Branding background should the supply
And I was like
Okay we need to get a brand new
Like we need someone
To do that it was still like we didn't have a product
Pretty middle how to make it
But I was like I'm going to start working on the brand
I need to design
Light design
The suitcases are going to look like
Oh yeah I didn't
Think about that
I'd like I can sell any
I was like we have two brand it like what are you branding like the company
Budget
Chicano Batman
So I think that's where my head was at and
SF is like okay well we have to like come up with a product
It's also how did you find
Like I mean how did you
Begin the day cuz I have assumed
Suitcases are probably mainly made in China
In terms of
Finding a place to make them and
Designers and
Like what was the
What did you do that how did you
What to do
Yeah so we
At Warby Parker
Except easily learn
How to make things
An object Industries are different but she had
A bunch of contacts in China
Kushiyaki
Intros to like in the luggage space
Yuri Casas y that we realize that
There are
Lots of different factories
Like a varying degrees of
Being good at what they do
And like varying degrees of working conditions and like
An end product and all of that
That we couldn't really make a decision
Until we had decided
And
In the first few weeks were just like really intense
Like our intense version of like market research
Wish shopping
Every single day
Logic every department store
We went to every luggage store
Am I compared all the experiences and all the prices like at very meticulous notes
On what was out there
Mainly cuz we couldn't afford to pay for the industry reports the real like we'll just figure this out ourselves
So
We start shopping for luggage
And we're like
Getting a better sense of like what was being offered it still wasn't super clear to us
So we decided that
To really create the perfect luggage we need to actually figure out what people wanted
So over the course of a few months
800 people
And we would just talk to them about travel and we would ask them things like
Not even about luggage but about their biggest pain points
When they travel and we discovered things like
People get hotel rooms and they would like
Steel laundry bags from hotels because like they didn't have their own
Or that you know everybody like wanted a bag that they could
Fit a ton of stuff in but also have it be
Flexible but also really durable and like really lightweight
And then something we heard what time it was
My biggest pain Point like one of my biggest pain points when I travel is like my phone always dies
I'm at the airport so we were basically armed with
I would not a list of features but but story is that kept coming up
And that's how
We figure it out all of the things we needed to make like
R1 perfect suitcase
So as the the design process
Began what look like how did that work
What did you
Yeah so basically you know second I had this list and
Then I knew what I wanted it
To look like
And I
You know we're basically up
Like 20 hours a day
Because
Ivar dustrial designers rent Tampa
Yes, we had factories that we were talking to in China
I'm busily II
One of them
Rodi send email
Like we would make sure to write back or pass it on so there would be no delays
Because also in all of this
A night to this day don't know where
Came from
You know this way
A January 6th February of 2015
And we had it in our heads
That we wanted to launch my
So in less than a year we wanted to have like
What product out into the world
Luckily like we really didn't have anything else
To do so we just like immerse ourselves fully in this
And we're just obsessed
Everything
So I guess it's amazing is by
This idea really begins
In 2015 like
January February 2015
By November of that year
You guys managed to raise
Like two and a half million dollars from
From
DC company is yeah
Was it was it hard to get I mean it was hard to make
Make the case cuz it sounds like
G-Eazy I mean
Pretty quickly after that you had the idea
Yeso
In March
Like when this was
Barely an idea I like we still
Didn't have a Time directions what we were doing
A friend of mine in San Francisco
Introduce me to Eureka him
He's a partner at Forerunner
And
Forerunner is the
The VC firm that invested in Warby Parker and everlane
And Dollar Shave Club in jet.com
And they just had like
Amazing portfolio and he's amazing wins
And we had heard about them Odyssey when we worked at werribee but didn't really interact
To them
And my friend was like I'll introduce you to one of the partners
Me like I just had like
The audacity to
Schedule a meeting with her even though
We literally had
At this point we still got away with the place
It was just like an idea to create this thing and we were busy just like in the throes of
Doing research
Verizon San Francisco and I met with Yuri and I kind of like
It was busy just like a meeting of me being excited
About what we're doing
In my head it wasn't
Me pitching her
But because of that
But because of that early meeting and because of like her wanting to stay in touch
And excited about the agnc how excited we were about the idea
We stayed in touch
Which meant that when we actually went out to raise
RC drowned in the summer
We already had like a
Like a foot in the door with one of the firms that we wanted to partner with
I meant we pitched a lot of
Because a lot of VC is like a
Crazy process really super diligent we had
Is crazy spreadsheet of every single Venture Capital firm who'd ever invested in a direct-to-consumer brand
Who the partner wasn't
Each permit did it
If we had any like Mutual connections on LinkedIn like how we would get to them we had this like
Crazy master plan for for fundraising really thought this through
You really did your homework
Yeah I mean I think
I think part of it was at like
That deadline to Launch
In 2015
Came from nobody but us
We really wanted to do it I don't even know where that timeline came
And you want us to do in time for Christmas
Merry Christmas ya
We're like this would be like a great way to law to get a ton of press
So we had the self-imposed deadline looming above our heads but like
Once you're down
We stuck to it and that meant being super methodical and everything we were doing whether it was designing the product
Or fundraising or just like
Literally anything that we were doing
Sissy drowned in the summer and we talked a lot of investors and
And Yuri Kim at Forerunner ended up kohli-dang
RC Drone
And she actually brought in the other Kool-Aid which was
Brian O'Malley from
Sell at a time
So you guys I mean by that summer you get your
Picture of million-dollar
2 million
So what was
Plan in the summer of 2015
The plan was
To launch before Christmas and we had known from
Previous experience at the
It was like a very
Behr lucrative time
2 to launch something
All the media does guess guys
There's also like
A lot of demand for human interest stories and things like that's what all these angles
What's that we wanted to hit
The PC the plan was
To launch the suitcases and get a lot of press cuz when you
From Warby Parker that
Depressive debate
A part of
Forgot to self write they have disliked article in GQ or Vogue or something
Petition definition
July August of 2015 like the big magazines are already
30 making decisions about their Christmas issues
At this point the gift giving guide
Yeah so we didn't do that
At the time
We're like
We are whole thing was
Watch Before Christmas got a lot of press
Solana tequila
But we found out when we placed our order in August
That because of the way we designed the bags and we use like all these like top-of-the-line components and we had
Looked at like every single supplier and wanted all the best thing to mulch suppliers
That there was no way that our back would be ready before Christmas
Wow
Which
I don't know why it was so surprising to us were like
What do you mean like we have this
Timeline in the spreadsheet and it says
The spreadsheet that we meet up
And it said that if we ordered the bags by August we would have them
And it's so weird that this whole world did not adhere to our timeline
And it was as if like someone had said like we had to stop doing the
Company it was a self-imposed deadline
At this point
We actually started
Like we didn't even have a suitcase set and we've already started talking
Two editors intellect potential PR agencies about what we were do
And he'd gotten some really good feedback so
But didn't they want to see
Suitcase or did you where you say men like
Photos of it
We were sending them like
What's 3D rendering
And we're mostly just like
Selling them on
On this idea that
Don't like
Before us
Amazing affordable luggage did not exist
And
Beyond that there's like
Is whole brand that was a
Successful travel the way that they were
And that we were created
Secured is excited about that
And when we found out the bags were going to be ready we're like
So what are we going to Lodge like
Quit we can't watch suits
So
Obviously our options are like don't launch or push it back
Wasn't on the table
Price for whatever
Or we could lunch with the pre-order
Which I think is just like
The most boring thing you can do when you're launching a brand like
No one wants
Put their credit card down for something that they like merriment
Not yet
So we came up with this idea
And the idea was
That
We would come up with something before Christmas that people would want to buy
That would show them that we were like this amazing Utah
So they're due to write a book
Or a single suitcases come off the Factory The Factory
I said I'm just like I was
I usually get this freak with all these crazy ideas and stuff and be like okay okay we can make this work like
We were just total enabler this is going to be a book of your flight photos of your luggage
No so basically I was like 4 like
We have to show people that that were an exciting you travel Brad
And that that they're going to love us
So the book was we were going to find 40 tastemakers like not celebrities but people who had really
A strong Community like people who he wanted to vouch for us Anjali and my friend who would like a freelancer
40 magazine envogue and into the gloss she was going to interview these people about like
Your favorite place to travel to
And to write the little blurb
And we realize it like we would need
Photos in the book Ruby really boring so she would also ask them for their vacation photos and we came up with this list
Of a people that she would interview
And the whole plan was to write this book
+ 2
Yeah we had to do was just us into designers at the time
And we got them to agree to design the book
So we're like we're going make a coffee table book and then inside the coffee table book
We're going to put a gif
Card
The people can redeem
For the log
Wait let me just
Yuan raised to 1/2 million dollars from
PCS who wanted you to make
Luggage
Uni using that money to come up with a coffee table book of people
Vacations
I just I just would like that anybody say hey what are you guys doing or or do they not really no
What's actually funny because when we were trying
How to choose our and
A lot of the feedback that we got really
Oh you're kind of Warby Parker for luggage
Great will invest
Another Super
The other feedback was like
Yeah we show them a picture of the leg
I get like a rendering of the luggage and they'd be like
I don't get it
It's just like it's like what's different about it we're like
Well here's all the great things about the
The product but also
And then I would go on and on about
Brand that we rebuild
I knew that I would like a ramble about the band and I was like
Like we make luggage but we're travel bran it's really going to connect
People and that's the whole idea for away is that
People
Didn't emotionally connect with
Samsonite or Tumi or any of these other brands
And basically the feces that we ended up going with we're the ones
Who got
That brand
With this tangible thing that we could make uniquely ours and that's what would said
So every time
And even not like everytime you come up here like some
Crazy idea like this they're like
Okay must be for the brand so no one questioned what we did
Where we going to sell the book
So we're going to that was like the book
But the thing that we were going to sell
Also we had set up this whole website
To sell luggage
That wasn't going to be ready so then we change the website
To sell the book
Wait so if you were on the away website in November of 2015 you could only buy
The away coffee table book you could not buy suitcase
Yeah I mean I guess
I guess I could different way of looking at it would be like you would
Is this a pre-order for the suitcase that you would get the book
And the reason we did that was because
We wanted people to be able to like give
People things for the holidays like something tangible
So yes if you want on the website
November 2015
You buy the coffee table book
And the book would come
Put a gift card for the suitcase but you'd have to go back on the website in February
Turning the gift card and it was like
Crazy likely sufficient
Idea
On paper and even now as I'm telling you
But stuff like
You know what I think this could really work and we made
2000's books
And I'm I remember like the books got delivered the Haley's food boxes and I think Stephen I looked at each other
This is either a great idea or we're going to have these books
MS Office like
Fraternity around we had
We had lined up
A bunch of progress we invested a ton of time and
And meeting with editors like getting into foam up with with us and the idea and the product that would eventually launch
And a November 9th 2015 we woke up and there's a big feature on
Boat.com all about the travel brand
And that was our lunch and we had the book on the website and we basically spent the whole day like
Profession Google analytics refreshing are like a dashboard for the platform that you were selling on
And people just started buying the book
How much does it cost
Well you have to basically you had to buy the book for $225
Which is the price
Of the First suitcase
And we sold hundreds on the first day Thursday
On the first day I'm a bunch of other outlets picked it up all of the people in The Bookworm
Like really excited about it like a big dinner everyone's posting about it
And the next day like a hundred more sold and then and then more the next day and by the end of a couple of
We had sold out
Of all of the books and each book represented
One suitcase that we ordered so it's sold out of our first order
Is it still did not have a single suitcase like in stock in the US
Ivory suitcase
That would come in February with a
Show February of 2000
16 suitcases were going to arrive
My prom dress
And how and where do they live
Steps to becoming like a giant
Shipping container
To look up
Warehouse in New
Yasso
So that should be it because
Soda like the holidays happened
We sold the Box
But like our minds were blow and we were like
Look at the appetite for
For the spread like all the stuff
We told you she is real
And we actually weren't sure if it would be
That felt great
But then we're like
Okay we actually have two
To get the light
Over here
So right after Christmas we flew to our fact
And we actually spent days like
In the factory on the production line
Doing like
Quality control
Checking every suitcase
Like Steph and I were like
We're standing there with all the factory workers like we inspected every bag off of the line
They got packaged
In their boxes
Were you happy with them to do they look do they look the way you wanted them to
Yeah it was it was a dream come true
Because we basically spent
An entire year.
Just imagining
I'm in designing it and like
And putting in the work
And I had never been a part of that process before of
I like coming up with in designing something from scratch
Annunciating
The end result
I'm through a lot of Tears
It was a very emotional time but we were on the factory floor like crying
Like hugging this
Fiesta. Was January like they put them on a boat
They made their way over and
We sold our first
Physical suit
In February of 2006
That year
I think
In your first
The first year you actually had the
SE cases
UE wenzhou upselling 55
1000 suitcases which is amazing
How did people
Find out about
I mean
I think what we saw
Pretty quickly is that
Our timing was perfect
We were in this time and social media where travel is
Status symbol everyone wanted to post about
Not just
Their trips and like nauseous about the beach that they're on or like the mountain that
Just getting on but by how they got there
And people taking photos at airports or or even when they were pocket
And stuff and I realize it would be hard to be a part of this
And we had to be the bag
In all those photos that people are posting as they were talking or as they were
At the airport
So we basically found I mean in the beginning
NBA news a lot of press and then it was a lot of
Basically anyone we knew on social media that had a lot of followers like asking them to post about the bag
During that kind of like pre-trip
And we made it so that
Anytime you open Instagram and then someone was like getting ready for a trip
They would be posting a photo with their waste
How did you I mean
Pretty I guess
Pretty soon you were
Even celebrities were
Starting to use the bags
Like Rashida Jones and
Karlie Kloss and I mean did you did you deliberately seek them out and say
Hey check out our bags
I think what happened was
We give it a couple celebrities and I can't remember who but
PS celebrities
Get their photo taken by Paparazzi when they leave the airport
So
The bag would start showing up
Like in all these magazines
As
As celebrities were leaving Airport
So I think they did a lot for
Growing our customer base
And also other celebrities seeing it
But I think what's been amazing is that like
Celebrities were so drawn
To the brand
Every celebrity collaboration we've ever done has been because
That's the lad has been
It was crazy like I don't I don't know how.
I like when we first launched the book and we were like looking at the orders come in
Elliot see the names of every single person
Who ordered
Yeah and I'm ever be like oh I know that person from college like they must have seen on Facebook or
Like I used to work with that person
And it'd be like names of people being you and then maybe like
Name the people we didn't know
But then once in awhile like
Marching orders come in one day
Laura Jean Witherspoon
Order.
Assassins
Dusted out loud
I like that's Reese Witherspoon that's her real name
You know that
Alex she had heard about it from like one of these articles are one of these influencers
And she ordered a box of Jackson has one of our
Like original books
Send the bag
You started this company
To view
How many employees do you have now
Because a 200
15 points wow
It is pretty unbelievable
You
It is unbelievable that you start this company in 25
Game
Today
You know
3 + years later
You know you're doing
The last I've seen is
50 million Revenue probably higher today
So we've sold over 1 million
I mean
It gets
It's pretty amazing how quickly that's happened but at the same time like
You really
Mercy wings and staff
Can do this with
A lot of experience
An experience a really kind of
Set you up
To succeed in
And this Venture like this was
Thank you
The time to
Turn the ropes and
It's it's not surprising that it's
Succeeded so quickly
Does it surprise you
I think that
Things have been moving so quickly that
Like I don't think we stopping us like
I think about
What happened
What we've done
I think a lot of it has to do with the fact that
We're so dead
Different and
Basically like any strength
The staff has is like my weakness and and vice versa so that might like from the beginning we had
All bases covered
So I feel like
Even if this wasn't a runaway success we would have done things like twice as quickly or
Are twice as good as anyone else
Like from the beginning operated is like one brain
I mean I don't know I think it's like
I never set out to do this I never set out to
Toronto company with the hundreds of people and I think
What's asked of you when when you have
Couple dozen employees and maybe like a couple million Revenue
Is so different then
And what is being asked for us now before us like
Well externally
It definitely has been successful in real exciting and said they were really proud of
Where where does like we're constantly like behind the scenes like trying to fix things or trying to
Trying to keep up with that
Yeah
Investor meetings
They'll sit there look at you
To see if you have what it takes or if you have the idea that can turn into
A 1 billion dollar company
El Sol Dante
How to create a billion dollar company
And now the kinds of investors that we meet with her that we're getting to know for the next phase of the business will say things
Games like yeah we really
You're really just evaluating to
See if this can be like
5 or 10 billion
Which which is mine blower
You are
Like at the time of this recording your only 32
You've got
Oh my God like your entire career
Where do you see this company going
I mean do you what what do you what do you imagine a wavy
Becoming a
Beyond
Company that
Sells hookah
Emily 31 sorry
I'm sorry
I mean I saw a thing for us
It's funny because the future Away really goes back to what we were saying in those first investor mean
We're building this travel brand
And I think we talked about it a lot but we didn't really know what it meant
When you were going to travel Brad and we're going to start by selling
Luggage
But
We became so obsessed
We just every part of the cow
Experience
So I think you know in the short-term like our goal right now is
The way you would go to like
Turn Nike
If you're if you're playing sports and you kind of get
You can get everything from like 1
Sportswear brand and they make all the difference
Things like we want to do that
Asia travel
When someone's going on a trip
We want to make everything they need to go on that
You must lie
I think in the long-term like what we've done
Or what we're trying to do is really set this foundation for
How do we create a brand
That people love and Trust enough so that we can solve every single part of the problem
How much do you think of
How much you think
Luck played a part in in your success and how much do you think it was
Hard working skills
Allen
I think it's on
It's probably
50/50 I mean I think for me personally luck and timing
That's so much to do with
With everything I've done at every single step
Sometimes it like the way we time thing
For the people that we met
Or even just the fact that like he was really lucky that I called staff
When I did
And that we didn't take the job that we were supposed to
But I think
We
We work our tails off
Especially
In that procedure
Obsessing over everything
I mean I don't know I think it's like
Every time
I saw something that is
Excited me
I would find a way to do it
Like I never thought oh I need to
Get a degree to do that or any test certain Works. To do that I would just find a way to do it and I think I'm just
A very curious person that's of something I learned from my dad actually and
I just followed all of my Curiosities
Rubio of a way the company has expanded its product line Abyss
Ebags Emma Factory floor in addition to their signature hard shell suitcases and now sells duffle bag
Backpacks
And the brand continues to gain more and more celebrity fan
Including most recently
Duchess Meghan Markle
Quarterly gifted away suitcases as party favors at a baby shower
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Hear from you about
That stings your building
But first
A quick message
One of our sponsors
Smart Water
Inspired by fresh
Thinkers who
Stories you're listening to
Smart water has more ways to hydrate
Smart Water alkaline 9 + pH
SmartWater antioxidant
Added selenium
Smart Water
Retard
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because
Timeout for how you got that
Is it a story comes to us from John moroney
Who lives just outside Grand Rapids in Michigan
Way back in November of 2015 the Snows came early to the east side of Lake Michigan
And what happened then
John decided to take the kids
Something fun and grab a few slides and go find a hill
And then spent hours
And as John watched his kids slide down the hill he said hey
I want to get in on the action because
Sledding is awesome
But John is also a fully grown middle-aged man and as he sat on that sled
Waiting to
Why down the hill
You realize that
Always agree with grown ups
Many pounds--in years later on our bodies
Sweating isn't quite as exciting as it used to be
You know when you're 8 10 12 years old
Which did John didn't seem fair or right
Sledding should be fun for everyone in besides
This seems like a problem waiting to be solved
Which worked out great because John happens to be a professor of product design
So that afternoon he decided to
He got his notepad and take some notes we noticed that a lot of kids like to run and jump onto their
Their sleds
Trying to get a little bit more speed and in a lot of them would do it running and then kneeling on their sled as they go down and hitting
Jumpsuit things like that while that was terribly uncomfortable for us as adults
That kind of got the wheels turning a little bit
The wheels started turning and Sean got in touch with a group of friends who also love to solve design problem
He shared his notes with the team and he has to figure out a way to make sledding more comfortable
And more fun
Pictures for kids but for grown-ups to one of the team members said was hey I think we could really make this
A little bit more exciting
If we created two independent sleds and strapped into our legs
Two sleds
Strapped to your legs
I like the pads a hockey goalie might wear but instead of pads
Baby sleds so John and his buddies decided to pursue this idea
They pulled together about $20,000 each and got to work the first prototype was actually
Kind of like a foam-filled sled that was cut in half
And duct tape to somebody's legs just to see if it were possible to have two independent
Legs
With something underneath thumb track and stay straight down a hill
Possible but
Not that simple so for the next model John made a hard plastic shell to fit over the
Lower legs screwed some straps to it and then
Cut up some yoga mats and stuck dots on the inside just to get a little bit of cushion
Yeah you laugh but when you're my age that matters
Dispersion did move better on the snow but
Now John needed to make the sleds more comfortable without losing that agility the phone was kind of the key
The ingredients all this
There's an impact
Energy absorbing foam that goes into it that sort of raises your feet up in the back and really makes it possible
To go down the hill and pick up some Speed without totally dragging your feet the whole way at this point John needed feedback
Design so he got his friends his kids and his neighbor's kid
Did try them out
You know we heard really straightforward things like I really like how I can run in
And slide on them it helps me go faster
I like how I can walk up the hill and I have to carry my sled up by the next winter 2016
Team was ready to sell their product
The use of their money for advertising and they ended up selling 800 units
It was time to celebrate
But
About two days after that big shipment
We hit this local ski hill all the founders put on a pair jump went down the hill
And half of them broke
I'm the very first run
Thank God for the beer because that probably made it a little bit more tolerable we discovered what the problem was but
Man it sure didn't feel good at all the problem was the straps they weren't properly attached
2 Team grab the beer and left the hill and spent an entire night troubleshooting and after a few days
They sent customers of follow-up shipment
You had better Fasteners and instructions on how to attach them
And they also started gearing up for the next winter
The Tweet the sled design and the added a smaller size for little kids
So when the 2017 season rolls around
We sold 8000 units we actually sold out
Jabroni
Team are the founders of a sled legs next year they're planning to
Cells legs in stores if you want to find out more about John or your previous episodes
I guess page how I built this. Npr.org and of course you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please do give
Review
You can also write to us at Hib tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music
Composed
Teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Carney JC Howard Miller could see the Immigrant
Melissa Grace Anna's Michigan for
And Jeff Rogers
Our internet
And it slipped
I'm guy Raz and been listening to how I built this
This
NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cuss
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com