Support for how I built this and the following message come from America
Express
You want to build your business
Can help building
Your business with financing Solutions
Eligible business customer
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Business
20 years 20 years of losing money
How are you paying your employees how are you I was the question that might
Tax guy always ask me every year when he died
How much money do you lose this year and how are you still in business
NPR
How I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movements
Lego house
Build a bridge
Bird out of tofu then grew his company into a multimillion-dollar business
One of the best names ever
Tofurky
If you're a vegetarian or vegan
You may already be well aware that meatless meat
Is kind of having a moment
Restaurants that built their entire business model
I'm feeding a Roundup animal flesh
Are experimenting with legitimate
Plant-based burgers
Even KFC is experimenting with a new product
BFC
What does a bucket of vegan Fried Chicken coated with the kernels
Secret blend of 12 herbs and spices
Too ahead of ourselves
I should mention that humans are consuming more animals
Than ever before
The percentage of vegetarians and vegans in the US has been substantially increased
Since 2000 but there is a growing segment of the population that
Is cutting back on meat vegetarian flexitarian
I just say this is a guilty flexitarian myself
Eating meat is really bad for us
Planet rice
Livestock production produces more
Carbon emissions than all Global transportation
While a lot of innovative entrepreneurs believe there is serious money to be made in plant-based protein
Just last month Ethan Browns company beyond meat and one of the most successful IPOs of the year
It's now valued at over 5 billion dollars
And another company
Impossible burger just raised a bunch of money at a 2 billion dollar valuation
What are people who indigenous
At least hope for really hard that all of this would happen
Receptivity
Back in the early 1980s Seth was a committed vegetarian living in Oregon
Making and marketing a food that hardly anyone had heard of at the time
And for years Seth barely scraped by
Do you even live in a treehouse to save money
But everything changed when he started selling a frozen holiday roast called tofurky twitch
Turkey substitute made as you
Probably guessed from tofu
Superheat quickly became a symbol of vegetarian pride and
The butt of many many late-night jokes
And all that
Help raise its profile as more people became
Ariana vegan
Seth was eventually able to grow tofurky into the roughly 40 million dollar your company it is today
The company now makes all kinds of plant-based protein in Hood River Oregon
How far from Portland
I sat down with Seth and Ferb alive audio
Dance last month in Portland to hear more about
How he did it
I was a scrawny little kid and I was a very picky eater I subsisted on
Brown sugar and butter sandwiches and
Little baby puppies that my mom would shock
Can she leave me the baby peas raw baby peas which actually is
It's probably one of them
Better Foods you could eat
But you know I grew up and I actually kind of hated Thanksgiving to be honest because
I would go down to my aunt
Glenn and Uncle Ned
Farm in rural Virginia Palmyra Virginia
And
I didn't like turkey I didn't like mash
I don't like any of those
Cranberry nut
And my mom would
And be slipping me like
Peanut butter and jelly sandwiches under the table
I was a picky eater
And and what like what how would you describe yourself as a kid where you
Studious review academic or you
I was maybe a b student ya growing up
Not really I'm the man was more sports-minded followed the local
Gold sports teams
And like to play baseball my
Career goal was second base for the Washington Senators baseball team didn't happen but not yet I'm still here
If this could happen it working on it got to get those Senators back
All right
1969 Malibu 1969
Go to college in Ohio I think
You went to two different
Colleges one was
Wittenberg Bergen wenzhou Antioch and and what did you
Study you in college
Well
The first disorder General courses and then I
When it came time to declare a major I
Like kids so I
Study Elementary education
Until I started taking these classes and found out they were pretty boring
And
Yeah so I dropped out of
School's Out
Ended up in Annie
So this is like the height of the Vietnam War like
Outpost Summer of Love early 70s right this is
Just just an invisible force shutting but like
Do you have any
Since that you were going to do a business and what did you think about
People who had businesses
What was your mindset about
Oh I left
The business made
Me and my
Friends we
Did not
You know Union Carbide DuPont
Yeah those are business General Motors General Electric they were they enemies it wasn't the hotbed of social
Change so
We really I don't I never took a business-class
In college
And never
Aspirations to be a business no
No not at all
So after I dropped out of school I became a naturalist actually a teacher Nacho
Lost it
Glen Helen Outdoor Center which was run by Antioch College
And it was there that I really
Discovered a love
Of doing things positive in the outdoors with kids
And
I was like this is what I want to do I want to
Teach kids but I want to be on the other side of the
Classroom on the outside
So
Learn that trade and then I came West and I got a job right here
In the Portland area in Washington County teaching Outdoor School
Around this
Time you're in your early 20s
You
Come across this book
Diet for small
Which lake has a huge effect on you what is the book for people don't know it and what what did you
Learn from that but
Well this was a book by Frances Moore lappe and she was the first person to point out to the
The American public and to me personally
That
The
There was no sense of
Feeding all of these grains
Through animals you know you take 15 pounds of grains and put it in
To an animal you get maybe a tosser
Pound
Mead
As opposed to a few feet
Grand Rex
People
You know you saved
Show maps
Grain and resources and land and everything and
It made sense to me as a naturalist because
I was really concerned about habitat loss and I thought
Well if
There is a sufficient way of producing protein
People that
That would be a lot less habitat
Loss and that inspired you to become a vegetarian like right away
Well that and a meal from a beautiful young woman my floral McAllen
Cooked a recipe of lentils rice and onions and
I just
Talked about
Not needing to eat animals and
I thought boy this would be great
To be a vegetarian diet mainly consist of
Vanilla wafers
Yum candy bars
It wasn't so good still
Mainstream right so there wasn't any
There really wasn't a lot of knowledge about
Nesb
Effect of vegetarian diet
Appoint
In the summer of maybe was like
Visiting a hippie commune in
Tennessee
Call the farm
Crack where you first discover this incredible thing
What was that what was that
Visit what was going on there
How'd you end up there
Well they were
Pure vegetarian
And they took a vow of poverty the only eight
Beans and fruits and vegetables
They had soy dairies all over the world Sri Lanka Guatemala
And when the
Hurricanes
And tornadoes would go through Tennessee that go out there and they build houses for people
And
They do really good they were a great force for good
In the world and it wasn't
Just sit around and
Get high it was yeah you know
And although they smoked a lot of marijuana
Vegan food
Marijuana I'm really surprised that a hippie commune
In the seventies
Marijuana
So is this
This is the first time you are introduced to this like
Thing called Tempe what do you remember when
It was
Like heaven
It was so good we had all week
I remember making it
In that
Hot Tennessee
Summer which is a middle
It's like Indonesia
Indonesia
If you haven't been there like about 88° which is a perfect
Tempe incubating temperature right now
Tennessee was the same way and so I
Weather all the
Staff was sitting around on a weekend and I was making the Tempe
And I
Put the beans
The inoculated beans out into it
Field just in a stainless steel pan
And the next day
I went over there and I
Pulled up the lid of
The
Tin foil and there was this beautiful
White cake of mold growing all over the beans
And it had little droplets of water on it and I was just like
This looks great and everybody on the staff was like
We're going to probably die
Penis is crazy guy
Seth I know that we are in Portland and so everyone in his audience can tell me everything about Tempe
Pictures of Everly
People who are listening who don't know where it is
Can you just tell me what temperature it is
Yeah absolutely so Tempe is an Indonesian protein
Food from Indonesia
Soybean and the way you make it is you take the hall off witch
Makes the beam splitter
Two pieces
Two cotyledons you cook the beans
And you dry the beans and inoculate them with
Rhizopus oligosporus which is a mold member the mole
Family
And you incubated for 24 hours or so at
88° in
It binds the beans together into the stick cake about the
Texture of like a
Paperback book almost nuke
You can slice it
So good
Alright so you're you're thinking all right this is actually pretty good
You I guess
End up going back to Oregon after the summer in Tennessee
And you kept making tempeh right
Right
So I was started making tempeh
Friends and family and
There were Retreat group so it come out so
They wanted
Some tempeh and I got an old refrigerator and I strung Christmas tree lights
Open side-by-side refrigerator refrigerator as a heat source
Back then not the LED lights these were the big old big
Flights
And then you're like a warm refrigerator to
Burn the house down with your Christmas tree lights
A little apartment in
We were living in
A teepee in the summer in
Barn in the winter
This is the most NPR me
Portland conversation I've ever had my life up
Johari
So
And how are you how are you cooking the Tempe just like what was your
Just cutting it up and
Frying it up like
Like bacon or what well I was giving it to the cooks at the retreat center who would
Hookers and reelers are very talented cook
So the retreat groups loved it
And
It was little income
My pocket
5 lb
The Tempe and I would bring in
$7
Yes when did you when did you get this idea to turn us into a business like
How did that
Idea come to my
Well
My girlfriend Kim and I moved into a house in Manning Oregon which is on the way to the coast on Highway
Which one is cigarette right down the street was this restaurant called the
The Java restaurant
And I was right in Manning
Which is a town of about 50 people
It's was the only Indonesian restaurant
A hundred yards from my house and I was this is a sign and so I got to go down and meet him
So I met this woman
Ina
And she was the
Proprietor of it
And I said
It doesn't look like you have tempeh on the menu
And she goes
You know how to make tempeh you know about Tempe and I said yeah I can make you some
She said
Really and so she ordered 2 lb
And I and she said but it's got to be good
And if it is I'll order more and I'll sell it to all my friends
So I went there and
I made that tempeh I brought it back she liked it and she ordered 10 more pounds
And because of that I felt like you know this is a good sign so I went to the local cow
Co-op Forest Grove
And
I asked if they would rent me their kitchen
At night and they said yeah
We can run it out to you for
$25 a month
So it was like grape soda
December 1 1980
I sent you an my stamped envelope to the state of Oregon and register
Turtle Island soy Dairy as a business as a business
Imagine light
99.9% of people you came across your life
What's tempeh
Does what
Will you having to
Explain this
Over and over and over again people
And not only with her
Are people saying what is tempeh but
People are telling me this is a pretty bad idea
Yeah
Like I was at the school
And in Forest Grove substitute teaching that make some money and I went into the last day of teaching
Announce to the
Lunchroom
Teachers that you know I'm going to
Start making
Tempe
And I was just like
Oh my God silence
What and then I was like yeah it's moldy soybean
And they were like
That tastes like a paperback binding
I didn't mention that
Shut up but they
And then finally
One of the teacher said
Well
You can always fall back on teaching
Always one of a fallback I always say that to entrepreneurs
Right you always wanted to know if
Tempe
All right and you were doing this all by yourself
I was doing it by myself and I was driving
In my 3 door
Beat up
Somebody damaged Datsun station wagon
And
Then it was really the co-op's that
Kind of embraced it
Nurse staffers
And who was buying
Tempe in 1981
What's it's like
Really kind of
Hippies and just for the record you know this
I love him
I make my own tempeh bacon
All right I'm just going to clear by then
Full disclosure
Who was buying tempeh in 1981
It was the early adopter
Right
In marketing terms starting to get
You know it's really starting to ramp up production
Contacts cuz you're not really making any money
But you had to find a bigger space I guess in 1981 in jail
Who's to Houston well yasso in April
1981a distributor called Applegate Natural Foods
Out here in Tigard called up and said
We need you to make a
1000 lb of Tempe a week wow and I was making like
The hundred pounds of night on a good night
And a lot of it was coming out bad and I was
Composting in my garden much to the
The light of the local rufous-sided Towhee population yeah
Find a way to do that so I needed a bigger space now
We were grossing like
$1,300 a month at that point and so I started looking outside the Portland metropolitan area and I went
Map to qusome which is about 70 miles from
Here is the fear of small little town
And
I looked in
The window of a school building there was an old vacant School building out there
And I looked in
The window and there was this perfect
Tempe kitchen I was like
It was a commercial kitchen
And it had
Two big huge
Stainless steel sinks that had stainless steel
Pool tables Hood
And if even had to store rooms that were just the right size for a tempeh incubator
It was just sitting there and it was a for sale sign on it and so I called up
The superintendent
And
He was
Saying yes we really want to sell this but as we spoke he was thinking
We haven't had anybody
Offering on it so maybe we would rent it
Uso
I said could you put me on the docket for the school board
Meeting and so he was nice enough to do that and so
My brother Bob came out and we cooked up some tempeh
Wow horde the local school board
And will they think
Oh well
Yeah
This is 1981 yeah and people even the earliest they weren't the early adopter
They were
Skeptical but
Open to the presentation and I made tempeh salad and I
Topsham Tempe
For the strips and I
Better to them and then the conversation turned to
Well how
How much could you afford for rent
If we did rather show you which was the conversation I was
West Reading
Divided
Have much money
So
I said how about
$150 a month
It was just like
Silence
Yeah I know buddy
Said anything for a minute and then
This one woman who was
Kind of like really enjoying the Tempe
Chico's
I say we take it
What do we have to lose
So you get
Amazing
She get this commercial space
Abandoned School
450 bucks am I
You got to make a thousand pounds of Tempe week by the way
What you know about running a business
So I know nothing
Are you like Alexa
Don't like
I never felt like I you know
The businessman
Yeah I heard I never opened up and he said you are a businessman
Did you keep any All or nothing like that
You know I've always felt like a little misfit
Yeah business world so still doing a lot of
So just to be clear you were making tempeh
It's like 1983
You are not making money
You are not enough
I'm your living kind of
Pretty modestly I think it is a certain point that year
You couldn't afford your rent
What did you do
Well
There was a couple of
Strategies but one was
The postmaster of the Town had given me a
Apartment to rent
Free she said we just need somebody to live there yeah
And so I was living rent-free
And I was thinking how am I going to make money and turn this thing around
And I said
I've got three classrooms
That I can rent out
And so
One classroom I rented out to my friends with a graphic
Art business
And they were good pairs
I had
The other classroom I rented out to a mom-and-pop wooden fruit basket company that were making fruit box
Okay and then I had this one more classroom and I'm like what am I going to do with her class but couldn't find a rental you know this is
Poor part of foot
Sac County
And one day I'm sitting there in my office and I look outside and here comes the
Does purple
And it's got a Yellow Umbrella
And it pulls up
These two guys get out
And they come in and they go
My name is
Space and this is space
And we're clowns
And I'm like okay
And they said
And we
Tune pianos when the
The clown businesses song
Okay
And we need a space
For our clown business to build prop
And I was like I think I can provide you that space yeah
And they were people are like
You're going to run to these clowns I'm like
You had me an ace in Spanish
So
But you're living rent-free
But eventually you got what you got
Kicked out of your apartment will have the rent Market
Got a little better and so now there were people that would really pay for that
That apartment so you got
Kicked out yeah
So I don't have a place to live
And
One of my employees Ambria zacateca
Piece of land right outside husum and
She offered to
Rent me for trees
For $25 a month for $25 a month
And then I could build a treehouse you could build a treehouse
$25 a month
Which you did
Seven years why did
Running water electricity phone
What did you have in there
Well it had a wood stove so it was insulated and you know it's very warm and cozy in the winter
It had three levels it had a
11 foot by 16 foot
Ground floor and then a sleeping Loft above that and a little cupola
Yeah up on the top
And was kind of the first tiny house
And the tree house was on a Frisbee Golf Course
So I'm living on a golf course
American Dream
Pretty amazing right you are going to the school every day making tempeh
But you know your sort of approach your late thirties and
You're really here
Not making any money in your living treehouse
Cool but
You know I was for the Wii U
Stressed out like we're sitting pretty like I got to figure another figure something else I need a new strategy because
I don't know this is going to
Be sustainable
Yeah
The thought came up
And actually in 1986
I had an offer to sell
The Tempe business to a local tofu company
They offered me $25,000
Or the business
Which would have been life-changing money flow
And then I could go work for them for $1,000
A month
And
I thought about it long and hard it took me about 9 months to decide
You know whether I'm going to take this or not and
Went through a lot of those questions at that time and
The end of
The lion I just said
I like
I'm growing and I'm going to stick with this so
I kept the business I turned down the big money yeah
When we come back to just a moment
Acceptable eventually starts
Is pounding money
Humble holiday roast
8 of tofu
Play with us
Gyros and you listening to how I built this from NPR
Support for this podcast come from American Express
Director of global sales strategy Chase Hines
Explains how American Express works
With their customers
Define the right Financial solution
Their business
It's a lot like solving a puzzle
Each customer is different each business is different
We really want understand what your goals are for the year
For three years
And what would extra financing do
To help you achieve no.
One of my customers is a long-standing family-run restaurant
And Sons dream was to open up a second location
Finances are a little bit tough as they were just running the business
We are able to partner with him
Understand
Exactly what he needed and help him open up that second location and now they're onto the Earth
The weather is Anita
To open a second location or
Until a big New Order
We want to make sure that we're there for you along that Journey
American Express wants to help you move your business forward
Flexible financing Solutions
Chat with him today
See if you're eligible
Work is it American
Express.com business
Learn more
Gem Supply
There are
So many different labels on food these
Organic
Non-GMO
Fair trade
Cage-free hand gathered it's overwhelming
I sometimes jokingly refer to it as been a scarring of our
Life it has a new episode making
Sense of food plate
Find it
And War by Sir
Life kit all guide
Can apple podcast
And for about 10 years and
It is very safe to say the business is not making him a rich man
This amazing there's a period of 8 years
The Treehouse years
Where
You're in
Higher take-home pay over a period of 8 years
$1000 31
Nobody could live on 30000
$31,000 / 8
Year.
Did you I mean
What are you
Were you ever like gun
I don't know did you ever heard of anxiety over
I don't know what I'm doing my life for
Yeah I was
I had some existential nausea
Yeah how about that you know I did feel like a failure in the business sense
But I felt
Like the mission sense you know seeing this
Tempe business grow and seeing people
Eating more and more of a
The product
It was satisfying and I was involved in local
Activism in the
Ecoworld I had a very fulfilling life I'd I never I mean
There was
A. Towards the end of that where I was really
Starting to wonder whether it was ever
Going to take off and I was looking for
Ways out
I guess run around
The next movie 9u
You were dating somebody
Who would become your wife Sue
Did she move into the treehouse with you or
I don't know what it's like how does that work
You know it's funny because right now people asked Sue they go
Does he make you sign a prenup
And she goes
Prenup
What was the one that needed the prenup he lived in a tree
I have the house
So she said that you got the move in with her
So yeah she got a house on the ground
And so yeah
Eventually I guess I guess around 92 you made your way to Hood River
Here in Oregon
I know your plant is still today
Why did you move from
Washington State
To that to that location was going on
Well towards the end of the Houston run the
School District had sold
The building 2
A guy who turned out to be a crook in the jail time but then it fell
Into the
Local Firehouse
Also the it's now the firehouse a few items
What's a great deal on the you had to find and I had to find a new space and
There was an oil
Tortilla Factory
In Hood River
Which is 10 miles from Houston
And we rent it out
5000 square feet of this 26000 squared
Building
And I borrow the hundred and
$60,000 from Bob your brother my brother just financed a retrofit
Always
In the early days
Funduro
Your brother
Like business
Well yeah
Anybody had a bigger heart than a business sense
And he was always
Loaning me money and I would be paying it back
Not always on time
You paid it back
So I'm curious I mean because
It's really is the
Sort of story pivot
This is where
Add something totally unexpected
Expected happen
I guess there's like these vendors that work with you they want to
Catering business
Just couple the Robles
And there they were like a
Vegetarian catering business
Buying tempeh from you correct
And
They
They're making like
Tofu roast that you drug kind of, crossword
What what
Yashow Hans and Rhonda wrobel run
The higher taste which is a
Great Sandwich Company and it's been in business since the early 1980s
And
Hans especially
Anything he touches turns to Gold he's like one of the best
Shafts that I've ever met
And he was in 1994 I was delivering Tempe to him and he was making us around Thanksgiving
These stuff
Tofu roast
He had been working on
And he was selling them
About 2:25 or
Ear and
They were
A dome of tofu with stuffing
In the middle and I was
Always looking for something to eat at Thanksgiving
And we had tried all these
Stop pumpkins that kind of collapsed in the oven
Gluten Rose the word
Too tough to cut with a chainsaw
So we were failing and then I saw it with Hans this is
Something this is kind of
And so
And
Suet been working on
Burger at that point
That we had rejected cuz it tasted like Thanksgiving
And
We thought I wonder if we make these into not Burger shapes but drumettes
And so we made them into Tempe drumettes you may Tempe drumettes
We made drumettes right
How to Tempe right you said what you said can we maybe
So that first year we bought the the tofurky to Market here and this
City
With
Hans and his team
It was it was a frozen tofu loaf stuffed with
So it was like
Whole wheat bread crumb and cranberry stuffy nose really delicious
And what else came of the box
And then there was a top of gravy that once again haunted created of nutritional yeast gravy
And
That never sleeps 8 Tempe Drummond
Vegetarian sitting around leg
Isn't that an eight legged turkey
No
But we didn't know it till 4 cuz look like in the wild
But we knew they had a leg
Wow
I'm just curious looks okay this is important
This name is super important
They are making the disliked stuffed tofu Dome
It's around Thanksgiving time
How do you name a you come up with a name for it
Okay so I didn't invent the name Topher
Right in 1981 when I was delivering
Tempe around Portland
There was a tofurky
Sandwich
Gofur k
Eey
And it was being made by King Harvey
Local sandwich
Liquor here in Portland over slices of tofu or deal with slices of tofu
Sort of Turkish
Rights-based
And
I thought I would buy those when I
I really liked
But I always love
The name
Tofurky
A lot of people were
Against the name
But at that point
I was ready to change
Something cuz I had been trying to play it straight
As a businessman and make it look like a hippie didn't get within ten feet of this food
Then
Tofurky I mean was more
Whimsical and fun
And
And I just thought it was more me
I wasn't getting anywhere by pretending to be a businessman so why not
So tofurky riding tofurky
Collaborate you you decide
Cell
The first batch of
Tofurky
I guess you
Freezer section Frozen
Frozen and you sold them
$30
Each in 1995
That is super expensive
Did you get pushback from retailers who were like $30 in the
Freezer section by this
Yeah we did you know but the once again it was the coops that rally
To embrace the concept and
And people loved it
We put self-addressed stamped postcards in every tofurky that year we sold 818
Postcards work for feedback
It was for feedback from the customer people said
Oh my god I've been waiting 20 years for this product
And it was just so heartening to
Right away feel like
Finally
I can see my way through this and Thanksgiving
Thanksgiving saying I mean PCC up in Seattle was another one that embraced that they put in a tofurky
The hotline
They were getting so many orders and they're going crazy for it
I think about
Straight year after making a first-half rookies you you wouldn't Robles
What kind of winter separate ways you you actually know the second year
We were making we went to a tofu maker and Hunt setup
Baked tofu which baked out some of the
Sponginess out of the tofu
And
It's it didn't look
So pretty plated so
It was still a problem
But
That was the year that we actually
Went online and sold
Three hundred of these online you know that tofurky was one of the first Frozen products
Text ever to be sold
On the internet wow
The first thing that was ever sold online was
A pepperoni pizza
The first food
Was sold online this is 1996
Tofurky
And and when did you
I'm a certain point you have to change the recipe right because
Tribal loan was not going to cut it
Presumably
Come make it into a
Things you could slice
Jason really was
It wasn't to be spongy
So what did you do
So
The third year in 1997
A friend of mine who had
Had a failed safety
Damn company called me tough weed
Came to me and he said
Meet
Yeah
He had figured out how to
Strew these roast in
Have stuffing in the middle and they would have
Seitan
I'm on the outside
And we tried it and we thought
It's good but
I wonder what it would be like if we had a tofu to it
And so we
Add tofu and I mix the seitan and the tofu yes
And it became
Tofurky and that's essentially what is today
It's essentially the same thing we ended up
Actually
Buying the recipe from
The amazing thing and I guess it's not that amazing
When you think about it because it was called tofurky
You got all this
Attention span
Today Show
And comedians were joking about it
And it when you work you did not have an advertising
When you saw comedians joking about in people mocking it
Were you were you sad that you feel humiliated a real like yeah right on keep doing that
It was more like the right on
Cuz you know up until that point
Our marketing and then
All of an app
Natural food marketing wasn't very Whimsical or funny
Your farnan this was like
Fun but
It was also in the early days
People kind of took offense to it a little bit cuz you were taking on and iconic
Turk amerikan
Bill and holiday and everything and
Bringing
A tofurky to a dinner was always come
Controversial and yeah
Even in into the late 90s
You really pivoting now
How to tofurky
Your business is not yet
Profitable
Start this a 1981 rack you are not yet
Cash flow positive
How are you
Keeping the lights on how are you keeping things going
Do you know where a lot of it was
What they call a paper loss
But it was still a lot we weren't really
Making money but we were paying the light bills
State employee
Facebook
The end of the day in
And we were
Borrowing money where needed
And it was but most of the money that was being borrowed was for investment into equipment
And things like that did you were you able
Two in the late nineties start to see a light at the end of the tunnel because
I mean were you thinking
I've been doing this
20 years we are
Still not profitable or were you at that point and you know what I actually can
See where this thing might be
Oh yeah
Just from the first
Response to the tofurky
Felt so different
Different than anything I had felt
Before
Marketing Tempe that
I really felt like
This is going to
Really
Turn around at some
And it really did and you're right that a lot of the
Media exposure from
The Wall Street Journal to the New Year
Your times
At one point I have had two
Put the Washington Post on hold to talk to the New York Times it was crazy
Code for episode
That was like
Are bully pulpit
China Village
It really then Thanksgiving rolled around
Trees with turn golden brown and
He would come the tofurky and he would come the media to us until we had Millions
You're 20 years in
I mean how was your business Acumen at that
Little better
Sue Helm yeah did you have more
Yesu was
Doing the books at that point.
Good
So we had books yet accounting good yeah
No it was improving
And
I was becoming less stupid every month
When we return
Prophet
2000-2001
Right about then it became really
Profitable because
We brought the production of the tofurky into
In the house we were buying it from a manufacturer Komander
And then we brought it in house and we started making
Sausage Deli slices
And we went to the same buyers and said
Hey would you like Deli slices and we found it
Play tofurky in this new recipe sliced really well you can leave recipe
Right bicep slightly different
Right and smoking and we we smoked it in a real Smokehouse and created the smoke
Hickory smoked so when did the slices
First timeout
Those came out in 1998
And and then the sausage is followed and the sausage followed
Prayers later
Did they become popular pretty much right away they really did they really took the industry by
Storm and we became
Happening comfy
So when did you actually I don't know if you remember the point where you
I know you woke up and you were like
We're making a lot of money
This is a
This is not me
Treehouse
Turn up temp at a bathtub
Like we're actually
Eat a lot of money
What's an odd feeling
Do you remember cuz I was pretty good at losing money yeah
Would you remember when that happened
Well you know when we
Baidu
At the end of the year you know
Having enough money
Give some nice bonuses and
Pay off a lot of debt
Was that what 2004-2005 yeah right in there you know it was really a
A new world for me
And people that
Wouldn't talk to us about Tempe or now
Clamoring for
Puerto perky
It took us tofurky took us from being a Regional West Coast
Distribution to us
National
Distribution
I think today you could have stayed the ark
Factory today
Hood River
It's a leed-certified building you've got
200 employees
Think I mean your your your revenues
Somewhere between 40 and 60 million dollars a year wishes
Unbelievable
I'm everywhere right you're not just a like
Whole Foods in
Co-ops and Trader Joe's your life
Walmart Target
What we're seeing right now is the mainstreaming of plant-based foods and
We're in
27000 + stores worldwide
It's really
A friendly world for plant-based Foods now at
Yeah we love to see all great tasting vegan companies succeed
Partly because we're Alturas and we're mission-driven company and we want to see plant-based Foods
Grow
All over the world
But it's there's a business reason to which is that it's easier for us to place products
In a category list
So here's the thing right
You are
Entirely
Family-owned
100%
You your brother or maybe some other family members own
Tofurky
I have to imagine
Over the years certainly over the last few years
You been approached by
Private Equity by big companies
Who have offered you a lot of money.
To buy you out
Yeah that would be correct
Why not cash in when I when I take the money in and you know you you work for you to lose our tree house for 7 years made 30,000
I mean right now
Only at this point in your life
Are you actually
Sing real money
And you could
You could be
Rich beyond your
Wildest dreams
And for the next 6 Generations
When I take it
I feel like I'm rich
Beyond my wildest dreams right now to be honest
I mean to have
To be in this business has been you know how to get joy and
Great
Feeling of my life and it's
Taking me places that
I'm still I'm able to travel around the world I'm able to work with nonprofit
Groups like fig annulare that are
Just getting going over here
I can't think of a better
Dream at this point in my life I just feel like
Like the luckiest guy in the world
So this is
Is important because
I've been reading
That you actually cannot produce enough of your products
For the demand
It seems like
The answer to that
Challenges
A cash infusion
To build another production line
Right we've we have just borrowed
Some money
Investor
We really
But it's a loan it's not it
We haven't sold at
Korea in a week
Like to
Keep
Are equities so that we can keep the mission
At the center of our
Lives and so that nobody can tell us what we can do or can't do
Yeah and
Giuseppe Rossi what percentage of your sales now
Dentist Tempe
Account for
Tempe is roughly
10215 /
Obssales but it's really
Outpacing
Some of our other products in growth
Now so we're just
Scroll saw blade
Yeah I just looked this morning at the new incubators
Which were building
Dubl-r Tempe
Capacity so
We're pretty excited about
I just may have been about four decades early on the island by thing
I have to assume that you're not using Christmas lights to make tempeh anymore
Soaz
Cuz you know Seth has as many of you know I
Almost always in my interviews with one final question. Just curious if you're a people answer it you know and we get it
How much of this
Story and in the success of the
This company do you think
This is because of your heart working
Your work ethic and your skill in your intelligence
How much of the story do you think is to
Just luck
Timing
That's a good question
Certainly luck
End timing come into play
I was lucky enough to
Jump on this jet stream
Natural foods that was just starting up in the 1980s and
90s and then
Helping blazed a trail for other meat alternative companies
The come on now
But a lot of it you know is just persistence and
Hard-working
Trying to be less stupid
Yeah
To get strategy
September
Thank you so much
Bed September founder of tofu
Turkey in 2014 Seth stepson
Took over duties as CEO of tofurky
Last year
Company announced it had sold over 5 million tofurky roast
Oh and you know what Seth and Jamie and others at the company called real life turkeys
Baked over keys
Thanks so much for listening to this live episode of How I built this
Are shows produced this week by James delahoussaye with original music
Louis
Thanks for Live Events team Ellie Prescott
Call Schaller and John Isabella
Xotic ac hermann rachel falkner jc
Howard Julia Carney can Aslam
Grant
Jeff Rogers
I'm guy Raz and even listening
How I built this
This
Is NPR