Really quickly before we start the show I watch you know about another live show coming to Washington DC
September 12th
I'll be talking with Tristan Walker
Walker & Co
Company brands
What makes beauty
Babylon
Forum
Ruskin announced two more live shows in the east coast soon so stay tuned for those
And don't forget
We still have a few
You tickets available for the how I built this Summit
In San Francisco in
October
The Summit is
Supported by American
Express and you'll be able to hear and probably even meet some of the world
Greatest founders
People who founded companies like
Instagram slack away JetBlue Jeni's Ice Cream Edible Arrangements
Bliss and many many more
The Summit is
Edible opportunity to connect
Other builders
And hear from experts on how to grow your business
You can get tickets for both the DC live show and the summit
Add NPR presents. Org
Hope to see you there
Okay Auntie this week show and this one got a
Ton of amazing feedback when we
First granite
Back in February of last
Your dad is
How to replace the vacuum
A bag with a psychic thing I suggested
Let me make some real money and they said okay
From NPR how I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories behind the movement
Now that persistence and turn them into one of Britain's most successful
Entrepreneurs
Just a question
Who invented
The light bulb
Thomas Edison right that is the name that
Usually comes to mind
Because Edison is
Probably the most
Famous American inventor in history
He held the record for the
The most patents by a single person
Actually invent the light bulb
Took the existing design for a light bulb
Best light bulbs
Only work for a few hours
In Edison
He made a much
Much better life
That's basically what James Dyson
Bed with the vacuum
A product that had been around for almost 80 years any product so associated with
1 brand
Betty much
The English-speaking world
They're still called Hoover's
So as you're here
James Dyson
Much like Thomas Edison
Used a kind of trial and error design process
For that vacuum
A prototype in a shed in his backyard
Tinkering
Making small changes and then testing
In fact he made over 5000 prototypes
Before perfect
Journey as a
Adventure started a long time before he
Created his now famous vacuum
England right after the second world war with
His brother and sister
His dad was a classic teacher
Boarding school but one chance was about 9 years old
Is Dad
Died of cancer
My mother
Saurik coming news
Then we we didn't
It was more of a
What's the price to Austin it was too high
Very private Kyrie.
When trained as a teacher and
Teaching
The school which is the school
We have to pay to go to the one with your dad
Boarding school
United States Navy had insurance
Being a little time
So the school said where you can come
Us borders
App for free
We had a free education
Atlanta Craigslist
R35
Money and comfortable family as yet had a good education
She got to deliver this boarding school which is
Probably pretty harp music
Is a kid
Lost your dad
What do you remember about it
I might have one thing that was it was quite difficult because I was at school in my father tortured
School
There was a memorial service for him much
Which of course
Old school hat
Pretend I didn't see the boys but if you want it
Decatur
Set match lot to me but no Norful.
The boys around me
And indeed I think getting away to boarding school
Just office
It died
Got should have stayed at home
Amen my brother and sister
And my mother
That was probably a pretty harsh thing to do to a nine-year-old
But this side are in England. Do not sending people away to boarding school
Will toughen them up
Probably does.
So I had to remind myself unless anybody else
And I think it makes you very determined
Very very determined to prove something
The teams wasn't quite sure how he would eventually prove himself and after you finish school
He managed to get a spot
The Royal College of Art in London
And he decided to study Furniture Design
And then architecture and structural engineering and his first job out of college was for Fairly promise
British engineer and inventor named Jeremy fry
I just got married
And he says well I'll give you a design Joel 2
And what was it about the you that interested him and why would he offer
Utah light employing young people
What Bryson pedal the right attitudes and ideas so he gave
Opportunity for young people
So I started designing one to two things
The third thing I designed for him
What's this high-speed landing craft
This was a
A Moonlighting
Java TV
Because his main business
Was making valve actuator
Oil and gas pipeline
This was his iron
Invention
He had a side gig that was
Inventing
Boats
Well that just hit invented a boat
The theory was that flat bottom boat
Is the most efficient
Planing Hull
It's not very good in Heavy Seas be on this year
But because it's
I'm flat
Why is Robert custard
In those World War II movies when it's storming the beach of Normandy
Yes except
That those are not flat.
Oak that fish shaped house which is why you see the troops I mean to Wade through chest-high water in order to get to the
West we could land Streisand
So he had this idea to build
This landing craft
Car transport craft
That and he said that you hate
I got this idea can you
How to design
And that's exactly what you said
It was a simple as that
Because
I've never designed a boat
And I'd ever designed anything in fiberglass
And a butthead.
I'm free this wonderful attitude
You think
Think about doing something you just do it
Any hated experts
Did he teach you how to make things because of her designer
How how does that work
But yes he did I mean we've taught how to make things at college
But about one thing we went to his house of wealth and we have to make a prototype
He's supposed to weld atossa. Caldwell
He said book gun try
So I just went off and did it
Like you described a of a welding autodidactic welding Iron Man Welding courses
I saved a life
How to use engineering tools
By myself
So you have your prototype end and does fry say
Let's try Sally let's put this out on the market
A pretty much that
And I said I'd that I know nothing about selling he's as well be ridiculous you designed every Square minute
Tomato head every Nuts and Bolts
You know everything about it Sagat and sell it
Which is what I'm
And who's buying it was it
Was it designed for the military initially
Well minute for use construction use oil companies
As a diving platform
As a brick building
So it had many many uses
And
I mean within a couple years we were selling a hundred or more yeah
Very successful business
Why was it was a very fortuitous meeting early in your life that
She was older than me
Oh yes yeah yeah some 20 years old
The Father prayer
Mental
Taught me everything I know
So I guess you worked with
With Jeremy fry for a couple years and then at a certain point
You decide
You don't want to come see if I can start my own business
High for 7 years
It all
And he offered
The fun man I said that
Sorrento designs
Anime
Bull barrel
Pictures of wheelbarrow
The ball inside of a wheel can come up with an idea to design a
New kind of wheelbarrow
Well because I was fixing up the house
Doing a garden
And I noticed
The deficiencies
Metal wheelbarrow Wheels
That's why they unstable is binary legs
The Lexington to soft ground will sink into salt
So as I used one
I started to redesign
And it was quite a good project
To do
As my first business
It's because it is relatively simple
At least I thought it was some
What was it what was different.
Well it had this big
Balloon
What was that
It was actually a plastic football
It's quite interesting past
Buy some purple rain
This 360° rotating ball and it would it was more stable
And it was most stable it didn't sink into breaking ground in your garden that didn't damage your loan and it cuz it didn't sink on
Why are wheelbarrows like that today
The difficult thing that's been sending
Because
The traditional
Hardware stores is I wear then and a few garden centers
They didn't want to sell it
So I used to sell it to Little Adventures Benson the newspaper
There's always next incontinence
Cancellable miss Kiss
They would be the sad part 4
The wilbury strange molten looking at you nicely designed I think real better
And I started to get checks
See how this company the ballbarrow and seems like it's going pretty well so well that never made Monday
What happened there's no money in real virus
A very good lesson to learn
Not many people buy wheelbarrows
Types of very small Market
I will bear spray cheap
No wheel bearing
Manufacturer has a Salesman or designer or an engineer
They just make the same thing they made
Yeah with the yeah
And we have to explain why it's different than Besa
That was so fun I mean
Pictures sent to the market
But never made me money
Should I should have charged a lot more understanding is that you actually went when you took in investors
You kind of gave the patent over.
The company is that right
I signed the passengers that company
Which was possibly mistake
Yeah why why'd you do that
Well it's quite normal to sign the past
Tow company
That you work for
As I do not know
Wake up with all my
Jennifer Walls
Feathered vest
Just came in
And
The thing was that I didn't really own anything
In the company of puffins
And I know I need about 50 Cent's the business
That must have been frustrating and here's your your idea comes out of your brain and you don't even own your own ID
No but
Sometimes one needs to go through
These Rites of Passage
To understand the importance of
The importance of a name
Having a majority share in your in company or even olish as
Not charging enough for the product
Running a business doesn't make money
All these lessons of a very important lessons to learn
And feel this Saturday
I guess it was around the time of You Are
Wanting to
Make new products right to what
What were you thinking of
Well I've had the idea for the vacuum
It's a long story Beltran
Keep it very short
The frames for the wheelbarrow
Instead of
Painting them with
Wetpaint
That we had elected to use a thing called epoxy KC
But the way you get the epoxy on
The frames is the spray the powder
Electrostatic
I will back frame is REI open
Thanks a lot of the surprise going to miss the frame
And have to be sucked away
Robinhood it go whenever the factory
Say you have a job
The back of a spray booth
Sucking away
Vape out of this mr. Frank
Michael is very inefficient
Kind of people who made this
Equipment
Smart people used
And I love that use John site times
I've seen John Sykes
Samsung Sol Mills
Eclectic
Find soda
So I'm going to cop it one of those
But I saw like Fullmetal I climbed over the wall at night and took some soda measurements
Examined
I mean came back and gave it two weekends we made one that was about 34 High
How does a cyclone actually work
Cycling is littering outside online
You have to blow into the system
The most out of the system
But it is exactly why in Buffalo
I meant that spins around the world
Are the actors off of centos
Military discount gets into the center
Because it's too busy spinning around the walls of a buffalo
By centrifugal force
That's the basic principle
And cycling for widely used in the industrial vacuum machines at work
Cleaning factories
It was widely used
Cement factories
Paint factors oil filter places that had lost it.
That had to be sucked away by the central vacuum system
Assume that this is a very good example
But you seal the ducting
Sucking away from all the souls never
Set to on the roof by the 8th you say a site plan
Huge metal cycling
How do you connect that to a
Well
Over the two weekends while I'm welding out this 34 Highway
I realize the point of this song
Which is that it collects dust all the time
Without blocking o clock
I wondered
If you can make a small bottle and put it in a vacuum cleaner
So when I finish the welding I rushed home
I made a miniature one
Call Boden
Scotch tape
And connected it with a piece of hose
To my Hoover
And bushes around the house
Anticipates work
What just explain to me what was the
Problem with a regular vacuum cleaner in a bag of me that you were you frustrated by then did you hate vacuuming like
He was It was a
Problem with vacuum cleaners at these
Is basalt
Well
Just put my retirement and time
We had a vacuum cleaner
. board what was
Bills
Is the most powerful
In the wild
Episode of spaceship shape
About to fussen diameter
For the huge motor
PayPal
Anthem
I was using it one weekend to the suction MS
Professor
Thai massage nearby
I couldn't find any
So I took the back out
Under the end
Contiprocontact salt into the
Garbage can
And put it back in the vacuum
Michael
This is great
How to get rid of eye bags
I just don't
I don't know better suction
6 divided into the bag at Wilson duffle bag is
Completely empty
I still have no socks
Buy some new bags
Okay back I'm putting it and you back in
And I got good socks
So I thought to myself what's the difference between
The one I've emptied
I'm the one I just bought
And I look
Lackawanna
And you can see
In my mind I
Is the poison
In the back what blocked
Respond.
So I suddenly realized
What was going on here
You replace the bags because they blocked
Yeah
And I thought there must be a better solution
So at that time.
House for sale because you're still involved in that in the ballbarrow company which had
Investors Jeff goes Batman say
Hey I got this this vacuum cleaner idea to look at what I suggested
The idea to the other tractors let's make this vacuum cleaners
They they didn't what they said was that was a stupid if there was a passive vacuum cleaner Hoover
Will someone else would have made it is a huge comfort
Because
I thought
Improve the technology
Yeah quite happy salad bags
I think my suggestion that we make a vacuum cleaner the final straw they kick me out
Phone company
I was unable to start developing I went back to my friend Jeremy fry until
Are there for vacuum Finney voters
Excellent so he put up
49% the capital of borrowed 51% from the bank how much to get tomorrow
Well it was about forty or fifty.
You did not have any of your
A big mortgage
3 kids
So I started making prices
Lights.
Recycling
Where did you do this
In the shed behind my house
So you
Did this in your backyard
Yes and you borrow the money for the money
Lydia was little
Like start selling these things
Yes but what I thought
We thought rather was that we'd get it to work and then with licenses
Adele someone like
C URL
Trying to build this and you're doing this day and night
Yes
Nice butt
I would like was it like trailer trailer was it
Exactly that it was empirical in Thailand Perico cuz this is before the days of
Computer simulation
Iris building 1 prototype
That's what I'm making one change it
Time
I need what if
That one change made
I'm Sorry by progress
The requested number problems to solve
Firstly
About time state-of-the-art
Was the cycling
Only good at separating dust. About 20
Because I had to get it down to Hoffa
Cigarette smoke
That was the first problem
And the second thing was that
I found it
Has
I'm fly
But got straight through the sights
Not be collected
And I built 5127 privatized
Before I got it right
Iterating and doing this in your backyard
How are you earning a living how are you paying your bills how are you
Providing for your family
Well the money that I borrow from the bank
And the money that
Dairy-free protein was essentially paying my salary
Plus a few costs
Can I get the cost to a minimum
And once you got a prototype
Up and running
Did you go around and try to pitch the vacuum company's executive at Target
Container companies in one or two other domestic plants company
But
Beijing really want to do anything they didn't want to change
I wanted to Adam said that she rather like selling paperbacks it's like a
Essentially they were curious but didn't want to license
How bad did your financial situation get pretty bad
What's up we both had skills I'm she's an autistic
And she could always teach awesome
Which country did I do something even cost lessons
And I could always on money maker
We had practical
But we had that back up
But with all of those companies
UCSB companies telling you
Not really interested
Did you ever get nervous did you ever think about your
Packing it all in and then end in going getting a safe job as a designer for big company
Think like react
Has the office
Suspect
And I can see that they what time.
What is a good idea
Without good reason
I think it's a really good reason then I would have gone there
What about your friends and family work when using teak oil full size mattress
Weird thing that he thinks it's going to be a big deal
Obsessed mad
But the thing is never to take advice is amazing
Even
Some of the most
Successful entrepreneurs that have been on the show
I had sleepless nights they were
Bad anxiety about
About what
Well I did I didn't I did
Thoughts
I haven't sold a basic belief
I think partly from
Success
Apropos
I'm from
They
High-speed landing craft which a lot of people wouldn't buy it because it didn't look like a baby
Having having introduced to very strange looking very different
You technology
You can make a successful
If it genuinely works pyside
Coming up the story of how James Dyson's design for a new vacuum
No one wanted to manufacture
Eventually became one of the best-selling vacuums
In the world
Gyros near listening to how I built this
NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to
The two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First to eTrade
With all the jargon
Best think and feel like a foreign language
E-Trade makes investing simple by
By providing
Personalized support
Guidance terms you can understand
They let you get started in the market with as little as $500 and then help you learn as you go
You don't need to be a pro to invest in E-Trade more information visit etrade.com NPR
E-Trade Securities LLC member sipc
Thanks also to wix.com how I built this tells inspiring stories about the founders and how their
Businesses without success with Wix you can create a professional website for your own business
Play design for your industry
Customize it to match your brand
With Ascend by Wix you can connect with your site visitors capture leads
Manager customer relations from one place
Get started by going to wix.com Hib
Get 10% off
I hope and expect this to be the only time that I will speak to you in this matter
I would not provide information Beyond
That which is already published
In any appearance
Before Congress
Special counsel Robert Mueller isn't getting his wish
He sets
To testify about his investigation into Russian interference
And possible obstruction of justice by present
Trump
Afterwards the NPR politics podcast is going to be there to break down everything you need to know about what
He says
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
1985 companies to try and licenses new vacuum
None of them are interested and most don't even return his phone calls but finally
That year a small company called Apex decides to try making and selling Dyson's design
In Japan
Yes
Very small Japanese company
Never made anything before in his life
To make it for them
And they were to sell it
What does it look like compared to what
We think about Dyson
Cleaner today
It looks much like
Upright machine
James accept his pink
And it has a lot of exposed hoses
Bit like the pompidou building in Paris
So you can see exactly what the school
Quite similar to the early Alpine machines we sold here
Tattletale
Well I think considering it was $2,000 it did quite well
Rick isn't like today's dollars is like six thousand bucks
It's a lot of Monday it's a lot of money I unfortunately there was some quite rich Japanese people.
What is the licensing agreement with the chapel
Enough money to pay
Well yes it save me from Bank
They put it that way
See you if you license to to this company and they were kind of selling okay
What made you at a certain point
I should try and sell these myself
Well I was sending some
That's a ridiculous high price
It didn't really satisfy me because
I wanted to sell a loss of a reasonable
So I
Set Blackhawk Credit go on like this license
People that suck
I want to make
But I can say that I want to design that I can do I want
And I want to sell it in the way that I want to sell it
So I decided to
Barcelona
I was not completely on my own eyeballs house
Germany flag
My partner and I went well. Able to try and borrow money to start my own business
I thought I caught a good track record
Designed the new technology
Lycosa successful licensee in Japan
And I thought that I oatmeal to raise money
The problem with
Adventure capitalist
Is that they all thought that because I was in engineering design.
I knew nothing about making and selling
Things that I could possibly make
So they will tie me down
But which I mention eternally grateful because I'd have to get an equity I went to a clearing Bank
And by some miracle they agreed to lend me $600,000
But I also the bank manager off to us and he said
Well I would want a big lawsuit
I saw that you had two termination there's a lawsuit in America
With someone who copies
Oh so I buy this point
Somebody already copied your idea
Yes my photo of five-year lawsuit
Reminders to settle it very successful
Name something is this bank manager. He lost his wife what you thought of the fact that didn't have back
And she said one.
Exactly what I want
Determination
To win a lawsuit
That's his wife.
Light bags infection
And presumably you had to put some collateral down like your house
The house exactly
My wife and I had to sign the house over to the bank getting nervous for you
Thinking about that
Enza
Off Highway until I had
That's a very small amount of money
To build the tooling
And it cost the whole of the six
1000 pounds sterling is the
Plastic into the makeover component okay
Now one of the things about tuning is it you
If you make any changes
That's where the tool make and makes all his money
It's like a builder
She make changes to build
Stockpiling
I said to my
Feather engineer
This is it I'm going to my money so this is it
It changes
We goes out tooling
And I put the tuning in a plastic
Plastic
Are there any reusing hallstatt Factory
I said can I use the other half
To assemble the vacuum cleaner
And I said yes
So I had
In a few people that dig this assembly and Thrift
Foraged
Myself
Rihanna
One salesperson
And1 money person
6 company
Make the pots and I paid them
At the end of 60 days
And so I had to go and get some motorcycles some orders
How how did you sell who did you sell them
How did you know where to go
Well when I went everywhere
Nobody would take it but
In those days the web mail order catalog
Remember the Sears mail-order.
Well I will
What's Black Sails but in England one or two people who have catalogs like
That is because
I spent a day with Abaya
Who was so curious about this funny man
Instead of yellow and silver
I spent a David
Anthem
The end of the day he said
Why should I put your vacuum cleaner
An isotope because you're boring
I just looked at a long time and then you said okay I'll give it a guy and he have to be the biggest metal
How much are you selling it for
199 lb
3 * what are those
Vacuum cleaner for sofa
Didn't any of these these catalog company say this is just too expensive is to
Jurassic
I will know the price is concealed because you paid on the drip
You paid the same amount per week
So they did not show the
The full price all you could have
Baseball print
But why would somebody take a risk on something that was untested that they did not
Ever seen before through
Catalog
Because it it look different at his promise with no loss of suction
Identify bags
And everything goes into another
Catalog
Set my first
3045 Bond sales for today's Catholic
And then I got into quite a famous job coach John Lewis department stores
Looking to compete with a big Alexa
4 multiples
They wanted something different
For which they could charge more money
But it's very quick
And this was
Trey
Not tonight stream
So how long
WhatsApp before you wreck
I was in the black
From the first month
On
I was going to pay my employees
And let making a profit
As my distributions.
And I I could any get into the shops if I promise to advertise on television
How did you do that as of the money to do that
Well I did
So I said to
The first retailer
I said good luck
If you order 10000
I'll put all the profit on
Isn't the television
Which I did
I'm sorry my strapline the banding to say goodbye to
The bag say goodbye the back so I have this woman explaining
The Dachshund
Police auction
Another stood and then she said don't need these entwife a bag
Ndk wax
Ritz Naples
From that
I guess within 2 years
This vacuum cleaner
By 1995 this becomes the number one selling vacuum cleaner in the UK
Yes
Were you just blown away or you or we just think of yourself
You just have to carry on
Rialto
A new fashion lots of a canister version
I'm really starting to export
How much revenue
Were you making by the time you or the number one best selling back in the UK what was he had no Revenue
Hundred billion dollars
In 2 years
That's incredible
Guess I mean it it's up
It's a very steep draw
And that doesn't happen
It's happened of course in the tech world that mean this is a real
This is a real thing that people can buy and take home
We're making real money
Answer
See people buying the vacuum
And liking it
Commenting
It was tremendous that that was actually much more exciting
And how did you get into the US market which is your
I guess became your biggest Market in the world
Yes
The first year we didn't do any effort
But even getting in with different
Because everybody said I what you might have been successful
America's height difference
And then
Junior buyer
At Best Buy
I took mine off at
For couple of weeks
I'm said to her boss
Look is that she is what it says it is
It works really well and it doesn't
Police auction
Best Buy
Took it
End
The first year we didn't do any appetite
Sold
Pretty well
This is like 2002-2003
Exactly
And then we started getting into bondage
Let's say we decided to put all that money
I love you bestie
Intuitive
And so it wasn't my suggestion
The summer set
But why didn't you do that
Explain what you did and why you did it
Just like you on TV
Mets on TV
Taking a vacuum cleaner apart Shanghai TalkBack
And then chain
Am I psychic
And you know that Americans are suckers
S4a
British accent
Well I didn't know that
How about you
Why does it suction
And why mine doesn't
There is a spider by simple approach
Michelle sturgeon
My house
And it was a very successful
We started selling very fast
Good
As you grew and grew and grew and grew I mean eventually
You began to sort of expand out to
A whole range of products mean
Air filter
Bladeless
Fan
Anybody was gone to a sports arena
Orem movie theater in the US or Sterling the US and probably
Elsewhere
Has use the Dyson hand dryer that you
You just put your hands in and out of
Begin to expand other products
Well fast meet at the fan
Bladeless fan
Explain that to me
Yes yes
You accelerate the Iran
That draws another
Event
Expand
Volume
That you're creating a new create a negative pressure
Suck from behind
So you pull it more
So you end up
Multiplying the original AR-15
20 *
Are simplified
But that's the basic Prince
I am not sure I entirely understand it but it is amazing
To see that thing works
Participants who
Blow
Really powerful
Yeah
And of course you have no blades
I'm curious about your the way you learn business because you really are an inventor
And designer
And you don't strike me as somebody who's interested in
Administering a company you're doing the book
Sore bunch of meetings or maybe you are are you how do you do those all those things
Well I have to do all those things
Beginning
Better
As the company grew I
Did more and more the engineering
And now I spend it at 95% of my time doing that
But I was the CEO for the past 10 years
Absolutely happy
Doing anything other than engineering
I will do those other things if they need to
Do I still resent the time I'm doing that
I wish I could be with my engineers
I think I really love doing I'm doing what I think is the most important thing
Did you feel a sense of
Secretly a sense of
Schadenfreude that you
Or right and the people at the ballbarrow company were wrong and those
Other vacuum companies were wrong when they turned you down do you secretly think
No no I'm on to the next thing I'm going to
Everybody makes mistakes
50% what I do is
Wrong
Actually that great
Mistakes great
Cast of The Bold Mariner
Namaste
I've never made the mistake of giving away equity
You own 100% of it you don't have to answer to shareholders
Venture capital
That's wonderful
Pretty simple
You are
Just two people understand
Cuz you went from being deeply in debt
In your early 40s really having nothing
No money and
Weekend
Today today you own
Jet
Private yacht
I mean that's
Crazy 8
To think that not that long ago
In middle age
Yuan
Yes yes it is
Anyway that it's
I find it quite nicely
Much later in life
I think it would be very different
Had to happen.
And you guys are still big wrist protector
Developing electric car
That's a huge fun
But I am able to do it and that's the big difference
Hi I am able to
Take a long time for you
And invest large sums of money
And take big risks
Huge privilege to be in that
Position
How much of your success
Do you tribute to your scale your intelligence your hard work and how much you have it
Tulloch
Absolutely mental intelligence
Hardware yes perseverance
Yes and luck
Yes yes
I do believe that you create your own
Because
Lucky's around
You know I'm on the long distance running a school
And you ain't
Succeed by doing huge amount
Training
And then having great stamina
Understanding that
Other people say finna
Tots
When you feel tied you
Accelerate
That's when you start weaning
Yeah
Waze
Developing new technology that
When you feel like giving up
Is precisely the point everybody else gets up
That you missed PartyNextDoor
Are you do this and then
Success is literally just around the corner
That's James Dyson actually searching
They said he was knighted in 2006 the latest Forbes estimate puts his net worth at 5
24 billion dollars
And last year
Sir James and his wife Deirdre
Celebrated
The years of marriage
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things your build
But first I quit thanks to her
2019 how I built this
Lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing radical Yeezy
So the big thinkers can focus on
Developing Big Ideas
Try for free at campaign monitor. Com
Campaign monitor
Your emails and your business
Unforgettable
Bitcoin music
Huge amount of electricity to power to impeach
And that is created some very unique money making opportunities in different parts of the world it is also
Causing some government Tucson listen And subscribe to the indicator from NPR
Hey thanks so much for sticking around
Time now for how you built that and today we're going up to the story that begins with a TV producer named Mike's
Sorrentino
As part of his job Michael be out in the field using his smartphone to take pictures for his company's website
I would be in a place like Louisiana after the
BP oil spill
I was constantly having to wipe smudges from my camera lens
I really good shots meanwhile people were starting to worry about whether cameras in your phone could get hacked and
I kept wondering things
Do you have a camera that you carry around all day everyday but it doesn't even have a lens cap
So Mike figured he would design an iPhone case where you just slide a switch of the top
Cover up the camera lens and on the inside of that lens cover is a fabric lining in it also wipes the lens clean
How many smudges
Show a pretty great and simple idea
Around four years ago when Mike first thought of that be said
First thing
I got a patent this good that attorneys really expensive
My wife gave me the great advice of
Do some side work
And find a way to finance your invention
Meanwhile he worked with an engineer who helped take his paper sketches and make a
Prototype with a 3D printer but at the same time
He was getting some pushback
Even close friends were like this is a dumb idea
Why are you doing
Right people keep saying hey bike your TV producer why are you trying to break into the iPhone accessory business
The mic says they
Kind of had a point
Yeah I'm not one of these
OtterBox or Speck or one of these major brand phone case companies who gets the specs in the designs of these phones
Before they come out so I got to wait for the phone to come onto the market
Then I've got to go to the Apple Store and measure it and then send it to the engineering that it's a lot of back
By the end of 2014 with the help of
$20,000 that you raised on Kickstarter
I found a factory in China to make his first run of iPhone 5 and 5s cases with lens caps
MN
Somebody give him a tip
Somebody said to me if your products already in January you have to go to the Consumer Electronics Show you how
Have to be at CES
So that's what my did he got away the camp out in someone else's booth at the Consumer Electronics Show in
In Las Vegas there were a lot of people that came up to me and said
I feel like they should be on the market already
Text know Mike says he was actually the first guy to come out with an iPhone case that has a lens cover and
Either right
And our logo is something I made up in Microsoft Paint a little
Phone case that looks like a little pirate got an eyepatch that's why I came up with the name
IPad case because it covers up the
Cameras eye since you launched the eyepatch case for years ago Mike's been doing a pretty modest business
Sold about 7,000 so far but he's trying to profit and he's about to release for new models
And he says
It's great doing this business as a side hustle to video production
I work in an industry that was all about ideas and content and things that you could not touch
Should I have a physical tangible product in my hand was so incredibly rewarding
Do I find out more about the company or he
Episodes of podcast page
How I built this
Npr.org
Of course if you want to
Your story go to build. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe at Apple podcasts or wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there give us a review
You can also write to us at Hy-Vee tea at npr.org and if you want to send us a tweet it's at how I built this
Our shows produced this week by Kacey Herman with original music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to Santa's meshkinpour Neva Grant and
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
David cha
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this
Forum NPR
This
Is NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from the Kauffman found
Working together with communities and Edge
Education and Entrepreneurship
To create uncommon Solutions and Empower peep
People to shape their lives
And be more successful
More online at Kaufman.