Support for this podcast
In the following manner
Message come from mizzenandmain
Creators of
Moisture Wick
Wrinkle resistant
Thin dress shirts that
Require no ironing or dry
Head to mizzen & Main.
And use code NPR at checkout
To receive $10 off your dress shirt
So before we start the show I want to share some exciting news with you
I'm coming back to New York City for a live show
Thursday April 11
That was you haven't been to a live taping of how I built this they are super fun super energetic
And it's a chance to meet other listeners
The podcast
I'll be talking with John Foley the founder and CEO of
Peloton
The show is
Supported by America
Express
And you can get your tickets
Nprpresents.org
And I hope to see you there
I met a lot of shady people who wanted to manage me I didn't feel like I was a priority it was a bunch of guys who knew
You everything you were telling me you got to have a girl record you got to head Hard Rock Breakfast Club you got this
I like telling me what to do and I sat down with a young man who had just as much experience as I do
I did and was prepared to risk everything to attain his dream and he
He needed me needed me as much as I needed him and I was like
Yellow man
NPR
How I built this
Show of activators
Entrepreneurs
Stories behind the movement
Rapper
Spiral Music Manager with no experience
Top the Billboard charts
And build a multi-million-dollar business
2 years ago
Turn on a pop music station
You could not get away
From this song
I feel like I'm out of my mind
I don't know if you don't know this track
What listening to the title of song is one eight hundred two seven three
It's also happens to be the phone number for the American National Suicide Prevention lifeline
The song blew up on the billboard
It was nominated for a Grammy and it
Actually turned logic
The rapper behind the track
Do Superstar
The song as
You can imagine
Is
Pain
Pain of loneliness
Depression
Two subjects that
Aren't always friends
And Center in the world of Hip Hop
Nothing about this song is
When logic performs at live
People in the audience
Break down and cry
So many people connect with it and a
And personal way
Almost like
He's rapping about their eggs
Exact experience
Who is actually born Sir Robert Bryson Hall II
Second
Was writing something that
Authentically describes his own
About growing up around violence
Benediction
Without a stable home life
Life and sometimes
Without anywhere to live
And the chances that
One day be performing in front of
Tens of thousands of
People with so
Totally remote
Could do was
Write music
And rap
For the most part
That's what he was doing 10 years ago
In and around the DC metro area
Around the same time
Chris cerulli
Psychology
Struggling to find work
In the music
In fact
He couldn't even get an internship
Any of the big record labels when he
First came across logic
Will get there
Because the story of how logic
Grand logic is as much about his talent as a musician
Is it is about Chris Ruth Talent as a marketer
And today's episode is about what happens
Totally different people with totally different skill sets
Happened to me
And you'll hear from Chris cerulli a little bit later forced to logic who as I mentioned
Osborne Sir Robert Bryson Hall II
My dad likes to tell me now that we have a better relationship that he's the one who gave me that but I know it was my mommy
Because
She's like of English descent if you go far back enough and she's an eccentric woman
And she decided to name me
Serta first and my father's name is Robert Bryson Hall
And so she made me Sir Robert Bryson Hall II
Where in Technic
Because she added the sir I'm actually the
The first which is really funny
Whenever I have a boil named him the third but he'll be the second
So I'm
Your parents and I guess you were the only child of their
Marriage of their time together Willie Marriott
They were never married I was born out of wedlock
My mom like the nitty-gritty of it is
She's just a
Deep deep deep deep down
Good woman
You're not a young age was
Molested
We've been raped growing up she got into the all kind of drugs
Running around with drug dealers in
My father
Was never really in the picture because he was addicted to crack cocaine
So when you were little
It was just
It was
You
Never knew that you just need your mom
Yahoo I knew my dad you know but I knew him as a
Drug addict
Hey witches
Messed up
Reno
But he would yeah it was like he'd go away for a few years and I need to come back
He leave and he come back
I can but they were never together
Whether that's the one thing is like they
It's really weird I've seen my mom go back to a lot of man she never win
I never had that moment
Liftware felux
So you're
Your mom and dad basically
They had a
Brief relationship you were
You're the price of that relationship your dad
Is African-American and your mom is Caucasian she's white
And tell me about
Like where you corrupted you
Did you grow up in a in a house or an apartment
Yeah we grew up in Section 8 housing so food stamps welfare
Had a few hundred dollars a month from the government to live off
Jr Vaughn
Yeah just me and my mom she's been a lot of that
In different times on you no alcohol
Cigarettes and I
Liam remember X where
We have
Three and a half dollars that could have bought us some rice and some
Some powdered eggs in NYC by a pack of cigarette
I grew up with her
Saying the craziest things like
I was just a kid you know I was a hyper kid and then
If I pissed her off she'd say things like you deserve to feel pain or she called me
Are any of these crazy things because of the systemic racism that was deep down inside her with
Which is insane but mind you it's like she was troubled so I feel bad for her it's not like I'm like all my mom's screw her
Terrible woman it's just like
Wish you a good mom know which human being who had a terrible past and took that out on me and her other kids yes
And that's the reason she's not my life
So you grew up with your mom
Mainly and we would see your dad from time to time and was he
We serve go in and out of
That smells or was he
Constantly
Using drugs
Yeah he was
You've pretty much constantly using drugs
A lot of my childhood
Was in AA meeting
Like you know you know
Just kind of reciting the prayer at the end of it and
Listening to all these people talk about all the things they go through which is so hard and it's so
Difficult
Insane people
Just kind of
Using again and then getting clean in this and that my dad was like that one of my earliest childhood memories
About 5
And my dad I don't know why I was with him but I was with him for I think the weekend and my dad
Take me to Southeast
DC
And left me in a car
Back of the car for 5 hours while him and some woman I didn't know
I went to go
Smoke crack
In this in this house which was insane crazy
How how did you avoid like getting into drugs and and alcohol
It just really really really scared me you know I ran around and I've done a lot of stuff I shotguns at Rob people
I've done a bunch of stupid things because I was around other stupid people because I felt that they were
Where my family you know it's why a lot of young men and women join actual real
Gangs it's because they have nothing at home and here's a family who will protect them and it's kind of sick and twisted
Did because it's like okay we're going to hurt other people but these people won't hurt me so we'll hurt others together
And then at least that way I'm safe but there was that voice deep down that was like
Yo like this isn't right and for me when I got in the music for real
And I was
18 and I was like I'm not going to let anything hold of my father is an incredible musician singer percussion is
Explain cocoa and Chocolate City
DC I mean amazing and I saw
What cocaine did to him and
And I was like
Can't let this happen
Enemy so that's why I steer
So sticky
With music for
Forsaken being exposed to it
I guess it is a teenager you
You started meet some people who
Can I take an interest in you
Musically who were they
What kind of even when it comes to music I had a friend named Josh
And he was
Who would eventually going to be like my Godmother's
Sun
And I her name was Mary Jo and I love her and she
She's sweetest woman in the world
Any kind of saw that I had an itch for
Raps I just freestyle
You know on the block with all the all my friends and had fun and so he was he was a person that
I was there in
A gentleman named Solomon Taylor who was my mentor
Who Solomon
To Solomon was this guy that I met when I was volunteering in our fellowship
The right fit Rockville Football League
Just to get extra credit to be able to pass 8th grade and so I was 13 he was 19 at the time
He's a hustler
So basically you have it all these football I would set up the football field and you have like kiwi in
You know these kids in middle school and stop playing football and what he would do
Show up and how he built this whole kind of businesses
Huge film
The kids games
And then duplicate to tape create highlights and then sell those
Did the parents
Which is really amazing and then so we became friends and then I eventually kind of work for him at his booth and he paid me nothing and it taught me a lot
A lot about a lot in the winter in the freezing cold in the snow standing at a booth outside
And this dude was there for me he keep the introduced me to you know so many
Incredible MCS he he brought me
They sold things called how to be an MC CDs
Which is basically like a bunch of instrumentals famous instrumentals of the 2000s
Maybe like rap on these and I would literally rap on every single song and if he gives me ten Caesars like
80 beats rap on those and he was cool I was great
I read that I read that
When the movie Kill Bill came out
You got you got the soundtrack to
To that
To that film which was
Which is produced in n
5 Libras
Wu-Tang Clan
And that
Was like a huge
Translate for you heard this new like
What is this
Yeah man
That movie like
Just something about it
You're probably also the fact that my mom was like
Can't watch this
It's too bloody and then you want to go do it when I heard that
I soundtrack I was like who the hell is
And like
This was like back in the childlike where was like
Pop Lock and Drop it and do that laffy taffy it was like that like the whole South like fun turn up
Music I wanted something a little
Don't have to wait for my location
Outkast
UGK like yours a story
Choke after being
Introduced to the rez I found Wu-Tang Clan
How did you evolve
Wu-Tang Clan shirt but I'm on the 14 year old kid like I don't really know is that I'm learning
And I listen to Wu-Tang I'm listening Wu-Tang album and then I discovered
Raekwon only Built 4 Cuban Linx and then I discover Nas
And then I discovered the beef between Nas and Jay-Z like truly
If it wasn't for Kill Bill if it wasn't for the Risen if it wasn't for Tarantino dude like we wouldn't even be talking
So when when you were like are a teenager will you just
We just rap
Translate just mess around and just like
Try Rhymes or just try to imitate your favorite
Artists or did that come later yeah I know
No no that was yeah for sure like we always do freestyles but
I took it seriously
When I was 15 and and and I was introduced to how to record myself through you know
The BS microphone into a computer like
I took it
Serious
And I learn to emulate
All my favorites
How does POC rap like this how does Jay do this how does Kanye do that
I want to rap over this boom-bap 90s beat this Run DMC be okay now I want to rap over super mainstream hit song
I want to sing like Drake I want to do this like that I wanted I wanted to do it all
So take me back to 2007 year 17
You leave home you stop looking at your mom and your working jobs
But you're also making music
Jamaican music
Did you buy
Microphone and lights
Cuter and like what we're doing that
I was on a Yahoo messaging
Chat about Music & Hip Hop in
Some some person introduced me to
A program for recording a lot of people use it in radio called Adobe Audition
Sure and I was at the house I don't know what that is
This small file
Took probably about 9 hours the person actually
We sat with me for 9 hours on my computer
So they were somewhere in Alaska I don't remember
And they transfer the file onto my computer is an illegal download
And so I learned kind of had to use that and by the time I was 18 years old and living
It would Mary Jo and had two jobs Solomon had provided me with a PC very strong PC at the time
Add a million
Tormented album
I mean from Jay Z R Kelly I was rapping on
Brian McKnight beats like I did whatever it didn't matter what it was you would just take you to take like Beats
And like samples from other records and then just like mess around rap over those
Yeah and I was just like Loop them
I would like the end of the B and I had to be eaten
I did that with a $80 microphone in a jerry-rig
Closet with a
Pillows around it
And just would just
I would just go and go and go
Every song ever
Wow
But you thought
You were going to NE you were like
Working Jiffy Lube or whatever jobs
We could get but like you really thought
I am going to make a career out of
Being a performer
Like this is what I'm going to do like you really thought that
That moment
Came 2 years later
I was 20 years old and it's before I put on my
First mixtape ever called young broke and infamous
Stella public on the
Hosting site DatPiff
But you just put
Put your mixtape out there of your own music
And anybody could put
Put the music on the site
Yeah anybody can put their music on the side I think you're the pay like 50
Is there something to upload it but that was the time that was
The moment
Is actually a song on there
Call youngster.
What you been inspired
The series so then my following me stay with him tonight read than young Sinatra want you
And that's when I said I'm working at a supermarket
Quit
And I was like
This
Is it
She's everything I'm just going to do it now is the time I'm young it's okay to fail
It's okay to fall down cuz I don't want to look back in my 50s like
With Rick
Can you imagine being yappy 60 70 years old filled with
Rat
There was that
Voice in my head
Like nah man you can do this
That's when I went to go live with with Lenny and his bae
And I College Park
So you live in a basement with a friend in college Park's run 2010 2009-2010 trying to understand me
You decide I'm going to make I'm going to make a go at this
Like you're putting out mixtapes
And I guess your
Performing locally you like going to open mics
But you have no money you are still bouncing you're so pretty broke and I was so broke that I was
Steal quarters from Lenny's little life
Like collection that he had so I could go buy food and he actually like
Screamed at me was like
Just ask
Van Dyke
It's all good I get you
I didn't have a job I was supposed to get a job
It was unspoken and
And I kind of just sat down with him and was like
Can you just
Give me year
Like can you just give me one yeah I know this is
Insane but it seems like every week
Something new and exciting is happening and now is the moment
Could you just give me just
1 year
And this was 2011 so I was 20
I was just turn 21
And any and yet he gave it for a year
I
Did everything I could and you just put out music on the internet you weren't selling
Yeah I know it was all free
All right we're going to come back to logic
Just couple minutes
Because
Wow
At this point his life he was crashing and his friends basement
Is future manager
Chris Ruth
Is going to college in New York
This point they do not know each other in fact
A career in music isn't even on Chris's radar
Because at that point in his life
He was a laser focus
I'm soccer
I
Thought I was going to be a professional athlete
I played soccer
Very competitively
Growing up all the way through
Peru High School in
.
An opportunity played
Vision one which
Which I thought was the first step
Up to
You know completing that go all right
Will you playing by the way
II my freshman year I played for
Canisius College in Buffalo
And you know I thought that was the best opportunity for me at the time
They're very competitive team
Soon after that I think after my sophomore year
I transferred in
In between men
Explain a different School
I realize that I do
You know I wasn't good enough I was I was very good but I was in
I wasn't good enough
Play at the Harlem trying to figure out how you
Like me to transition into music
Did you stink
I'm not going to do Sports I'm going to get into the music business
Yeah
I was 20 or 19 probably at the time when I
Started trying to figure it out
I knew when I stopped playing I wanted to do something I love them as passion about I think that's all I knew
So I ask myself
What else
Do I love as much as
That's sport in the only thing that I can answer with
Was music
That's what I'm going to do
I didn't know where I start I didn't know anybody that didn't have any relationships
Barnes & Noble in
Kind of read books
On on the music business
I'm trying to figure it out
And I chose management
Because I thought it would be
The least power to end
And I was like okay if I find Talent
And start working with them that would be my way
Into the
But you didn't think like when it goes like
See if I get a job working for like what
Please big
Record labels or management
Companies in
Experience like that wasn't where what you thought you should do it first
I tried
Oh I definitely tried that route
Started with internship
I didn't graduate college
Yes I didn't
Really apply for jobs but
I don't want every major
Record label I apply for inter
Internships in
You know I kept getting turned down
When I actually got one interview that they actually had me come in for an interview
And I thought it went great and ultimately
Did you know they said
You know sorry this
Is it going to work
And I just remember I emailed a woman denied a site
Do you still have the email I asked
Why
Isn't isn't this going to work
And then she told me I didn't have enough
Experience
Which I just thought
Was really funny cuz I went out for an internship in the funny part about in the reason why I said
Not I have a team actually printed out reason
I'm getting it
Frame for the office
It was deaf
Which is ultimately where we're at
Logix logic signed to
Probably a year a little bit over a year
I see you're living
I'm an island
Parents
And
Getting all these rejections for internship so so what like you decide
Maybe I'll just
Do this without an internship like maybe I'll do
Just figure this out
Yeah and then to be honest I didn't have another choice
I didn't I couldn't get into
Friendship I didn't have any relationships or
You know friends or family that work in the business.
To give me an opportunity so
Yeah I didn't I didn't have a choice that was that was the only
Pat that I had
So what did you just did you decide to like start
A business or did you
First decide
I mean, scour the internet
I can find someone
You think that
Starting a business came a little bit later I was just like you know what let me
Let me find some Talent Let me let me reach out to them and
Just kind of start a dialogue and try to build a relationship with some of them
You know convince them to let me manage
How did you come across
Patrick Star
Yeah it was it was it was
It was kind of by by chance
You know
Yeah I use the word
Serendipity
I was
Managing
An artist a rapper
Add a Philly at the time
And this was
2011 so is very early days of
Twitter
You know what I probably at the time.
2530p
People
And I was sitting
From my computer
Is DJ
That the rappers DJ that imagine Philly
Tweeted out a a YouTube
Right there was no description in there was no
Anything else in in the tweeters
Is the Winking eye and I clicked it
It was a
Acapella video of logic rapping
Todd University of Maryland
Campus and it was
Super super low-budget in poorly done
There was there was wind in the microphone he actually is
Add the microphone like tucked in his hoodie
There was just something about it that
That stood out to me and I thought it was really special
And I kind of dog in a little deeper to try and find out
Who he was and
And reach out to
What did you say like I'm Chris and Emma
I manager
Yellow manager
On the phone
I probably asked if he had managed
Cuz I don't want to step on anybody's toes
You have to understand it
You know I'm a kid
Try to get another kid to trust me
Winter Soldier I had no idea
No experience no resume
I think I pointed
To some of or one of the other artists I was working
Without the time is it hey
Don't work with this artist we had built this so far
You know check it out
And I've loved
Chihuahua
To be involved
China Versailles Chris
Like you were
20 years old
And you're emailing
Like different potential artists including logic
That well-known
And you were saying or manager what did you not like what did that means you like how would you
Even know what to do like dude what are books that said here's how to be a
The manager of a recording artist like
How to negotiate contracts in five venues and
Do any of that
I I didn't
To be honest
You know a lot of
What I was doing was
Was learning as I went
Looking back now I am very grateful
Glad that I did learn that way cuz I
The best way to learn a lot of
Management a lot of
The music
Business
This is very difficult
I don't think
Q10
Learning
Yeah
And you call and I should mention you called your
Your company Visionary music group
Yeah
Which is a great name it sounds it makes
You got a big building in Hollywood
Visionary music group
Yeah it was I remember I made
I got the time
You having to come up with a company name it was more just
Ducati
You know I formed an LLC
See when I started to make money cuz I had
Paid in full
I had a little I remember in Microsoft Word
Document with
Some names and I ended up landing on
On the word Visionary I thought it was
At the time fitting
I think that's how logic and I
You know looked at ourselves I think we are doing something
Very different
That I thought
And then we thought we
Was vision
Alright Chris
We've been leaving logic and lurcher cuz you are sitting right next to each other
Logic what are you
What do you remember about Chris like you were his 21 guys named Chris
I'm going to meet you
What was your first impression of
Actually we met in New York City it was my
First time ever in New York and it was just kind of happened by chance that I was going to go there to shoot a music video
And I wanted to do something that was different and it's like a low-budget right live video game even like yeah there's low budget
Anime
And that's what we had
The camera
And your point and shoot as we call it
And so yeah I go to Newark and
Chris had like a friend who had a rooftop and we're like rooftop
You know that's
That's content right there
Can we go there
That the music videos called Mind of logic
And
Like skeleton me rapping it like a hundred twenty pounds
After
The shoot through the camera to buy you lunch and I'm not
Reboot less I'm ready I'm like
And so
We're coming near Times Square
Everybody tried group for a man like this is great let's go somewhere and he said okay
Ruby Tuesday or something like that I might let's go now about to get a free chicken
Sandwich or something
How do you know
Yeah I'm used Taurus stuff you need any you want to go somewhere else and like what I didn't realize is
Looking back I'm talking to you a broke college student with maybe $150 in his account like if that
Just got to last in the next 6 years of his life
And we talked and he was like I want to manage you
And it was honest with me was I hey look like I'm just getting into this to he's like but I made some connections I know some people and you and you
You know you met some people at blogs
Different blogs on online and ndk music
Spaces were
Young people were excited
And word-of-mouth
Via the Internet was a big deal
And I was like
All right well I was unable to sign in
That was a big
We're going to do this
And he wasn't
Pushing to sign anything either
And that's a really
Amazing thing
Because he
Key
Allowed
He was like yeah I'm going to walk the walk
Like I'm going to show you
That I'm going to do this
And that's what we did for about the first 6 months
Engineer design you would like to try this out committing to you
Yeah I remember
We released the music video and like overnight
It had 20000 views
But you gotta understand
20000 views in 2011
I was going from a hundred
Views and it was all people I knew I liked that
To the point where we actually sat
Chris down all of us
And
Intervention and I was like
Yo what's up man you pay him for views or what cuz there's like back then we're like people it was a big deal because
Fake it till you make it people would pay
Airbnb FAQ is a not really like I can prove it to you I can show you and
And Maddie it was legit but even before you get that point like
I'm trying to I'm trying to figure out like
You're like eating at Ruby Tuesday or whatever and Chris is like hey give me a give me a give me a chance
And
You don't have anyone managing you at that point and I guess you're
Still not
Kind of an unknown
Artist
But what made you
You think yeah
I trust this guy with stroller experience
Who's like my Asics
Cuz obviously
We know how the story is going to end
In 2011 you did not
And neither of you knew how this is going to end you both could have just like
Fizzled out but
What was it about him that you thought
Yeah I'm going to try this
I met a lot of Shady
People who wanted man
You know
Older dudes who were once kind of in the industry you know different people who were musicians themselves
I didn't feel like I was a priority it was a bunch of guys who knew everything they were telling me
Got to have a girl record
You got to head hard regular
Breakfast Club
You got this out of that and I like telling me what
And I sat down
With a young man
Who had just as much experience as I did
And I was looking in a mirror
I was looking at
A green kid
When no idea what he was doing
It was prepared
The risk
Everything
To attain his dream
And he needed me
Needed me
As much as I needed him
And I was like
Cat look like
Yellow
That's what it was
Tok Chris
Pelagic anchors
Forgive me for kind of characterizing this way but
A sentence like
Like logic you were
You were the brand
What the business is
Was being built around
You and your brand and your talent and you
It's like you're the product that
You putting out to the world
But Chris
Like when I do interviews with other entrepreneurs it's at this point when they go out to VC's and raise money
The product end of the world
How are you funding this how are you
How are you having lunch
Record music and cos
I think at this time
You were just releasing all of his music
I'm putting it on the internet and letting anybody
Take it right
Yeah and in
What we were doing like you said we were building the brand
I viewed that
Putting out free music as as in
Vesting
In the brand right as we were
Building an audience in a fanbase
That was becoming more and more invested
And what that means is
They would
Later down the road whenever we asked
For it
Spend the money meaning
How we're going to put out our first
Gto project for sale
Oar hey we're going to put up a tour for the first time
We spent $12
To come see me in San Diego
Hey we're selling T-shirts for $20
So I
That's how I view
We were essentially monetizing free music
So how did you guys make a living
Different White
2011-2012
You were putting out and maybe between
13 like you were just
Putting out free music
How are you like
How are you guys paying your rent how she's buying food
My parents were
Very very
Very good about allow me to deliver Target out of still in school
I didn't have to I didn't have to worry about that
Logic was still at
Lenny's apartment so you know we
Didn't have too many expenses at the time in
Advise you not to interrupt but like
I was in college park sleep Inn Atlanta
Couch
And you know we were we were still shopping ourselves like we wanted a deal that was like the goal and you know there was even in
Independent companies
That put
Contract for 1.5 million dollars in our hands front of you
When front of us and Chris had and I remember you said something really cool
And then I was like I don't know either
Well tell me things worth 1.5 million and 1.5 million.
Lot of money right now
Young kid
Inso
Long story short
Yeah we turn it down like it was nothing
Why
Because
They wanted me first of all we were getting screwed over on points on royalties on longevity they also wanted us they were going to
Take a lot of control
And we were like now we always have to be in
Because we know
What we want
I just want to kind of pause for a second just ask about music
For Mama because
What will what do you think it is and it was
About your music that
Cats with people like
It's rabbits Hip Hop
But generally like
You know you're described as having positive messages
Is and
And you know
Talking about things in an open way about your own emotions
And about
Injustice in about anxiety and
Depression all these things
Do you think that's what was connecting with
With people even from the beginning
Yeah I think I was the Everyman
Or every kid or every person or every whatever it was like
People were watching me grow up
Like a child star
United me like they were
They listen to this and they hear me say
I can't wait to make it I can't wait to have
Fans
I can't wait to be the man with the master plan I can't wait like
Daddy. And then
Like me to like I can't wait to
Graduate college I can't wait to
You know raise my children I can't wait to
Follow my dreams I'm going to do that and I'm like follow your dreams like no matter what
Haters Gonna Hate
Even today like on a mainstream level like
I called us so much
Things I talk about openly from anxiety depression
All the
Who said Injustice the things going on
One I'm scared to talk about
Car was scared
At a point cuz I was scared that
How people would perceive me or this it at
But to it's like
Now it's become a
Trend
You know you got you got you got rappers hardcore rappers and
People talking about
Depression
And mental health
And I ain't the first
I think it's just
Time
Place
Yellow a bit image
Just
I'm doing this nerdy
Young kid that
Other people felt they could relate to
So how soon after Chrissy start working with logic did you say all right let's we got to go on tour
And did you go on tour
Yeah I'm not sure exactly how soon but it was it was an intuition
Nothing right because there was no
There's no metrics at the time or data that we
We had that said how you can sell out
30 shows across the country it was something that we both felt
Hey I think it is
Feels right and
I think we could probably go go on a tour now and
How we did that
Because that's an expense
Sipping right there's a lot of startup capital
That you need to fund a tour
We ultimately sign
A record deal
The phone doctor
Could we needed the money
I think we could have waited longer if
We had some money but
You know if we didn't have
Opportunity
NFL right I mean this is 2012 the record deal you signed is
Def Jam 2012
You know I D comes to you you know legendary producer who's you know new executive at Def Jam
And definite General like Def Jam records
Most iconic hip-hop rap
Label is willing to sign you give you great money give you creative control it was kind of like
If there is a time like Now's the Time and
Yeah but I'll tell you this it was very difficult
You know looking at a check
And seeing you know lower six figures very lower
Just six figures
In advance which is still great
And then literally going okay well
Yo after XYZ takes a percentage is on my team management lawyer at that time
I have to put all of this
And do a tour and the end that was that was a hard thing
But it was I just had that young man was like the way I just got the check and I got to let it all go but it was worth it right
This is your Sweat Equity in in in the brain
They suggested like you got some kind of
Put all that soap
You could have
Gone to the tour and been broken and we might have to be
I can today
When I was a pasta with a very real possibility
The odds were
In that favor
That it wasn't going to happen
When we come back in
At the moment lol chicken Chris hit the road but there will be speedbumps ahead
With money and mental health all on the line stay with us
Gyros and you're listening to how I built this from NPR
This message comes from NPR spawn
Answer Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Facts on the state of Market
It's Industries and the global econ
Listen to their podcast
Exchanges at Goldman
You hear a range of topics
From the tech IPO landscape
Two China's economic Outlook
And much
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs
Available on Apple podcast
Spotify Stitcher SoundCloud and Google Play and it gs.com
Thanks also tour 2019
How I built this hiscox
Hiscox
What's the business
Insurance experts
To understand
Each business
Is as unique as a
Fingerprint
Barcode
Taylor's intelligent
Every business is very
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox business
Insurance expert
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
When is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimum
I can be open from anywhere
In 5
Capital One
What's in Uruguay
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
So it's 2012
Logic and his manager Chris Subaru have signed a record deal
Def Jam
Hardly glamorous
They still haven't cut an album and the money they got from signing that deal
They had to put most of it towards their first tour we toured the country and in a minute
Nissan Altima right eye I rented from Enterprise Rent-A-Car and I remember filling out the paper
Working it specifically said that the cars the vehicles could not leave New York State and we were literally touring the country
And the way it was routed we are going to California and back. You know they'll never know we left
And then I ended up getting you know million and one tickets for fruit going through tolls and
All over the country but
No it was not first class into 5-star accommodations worth
Logging garbage bags and we were you know selling merge aftershows I'd run in cell
Emerge after shows logical come over to merge booth and meats
Before we try to figure it out and I had my right
Mantidae my
He was 18 years old
Only employee
At the time
And I said to him I said Hey cuz I realized very quickly that I couldn't
Be on the road full time and trying
Sustained and run the business was very difficult
I think I did the first
Two weeks of it
And I remember saying I was
Hey dude you know
Would you like to tour manage
And he was
Sure and I threw them on the road
Again
We had no idea we're doing IUI
RR accounting my accounting
System
Was manila envelope
So
Before tour I kind of wrote out every show so yeah
Denver Colorado
And we'd settle all the shows in cash
At the time that tour was actually
No guarantee
T torso
The rest
Chris Massey
Tell him real very quick
Cuz it's something I want to say
Tell him about what happened
Trust
Again it was meant
Manila envelope not settle in
Tina put the cash in envelope and seal it
We ended up finishing the tour
So I have these
He was 30 shows at 30 different envelopes
Looking back we just did so
I kept the back
Back on the tour
All of the envelope with all the cash
And we carry it around and we were just
Leave it in a green room and walk away
Took that back back that was the entire income from the from the whole Court
Serena getting back and I died later put everything into
You don't Excel spreadsheet and in trying you know log everything so
I would take out the cash and I would you know count it and put it on top of the manila envelope I was at my house the time Harrison
I was helping me I had I was working still and Harrison's like you I got it don't worry about it I'll finish
I said cool
I ran off to work and I came back
By the way
I worked at a cold rule it was it was
Like an Abercrombie & Fitch
You know
Retail store
An actor going on tour with logic managing logic tour you were back at the mall working retail
Yeah and I came and I came back
And
Envelopes
Gone
There was just 30 piles of cash
That I had no idea
What belong to what and I called Harrison and and
Nikki ended up
Trying to clean up
So he took the envelope and rip them up and threw them out
So I had no I had not your Christmas so we had all this cash we didn't know where it was really know how to divvy it
But I say all this to say
That Harrison went from fumbling 20 grand or whatever we had
The juggling multiple multiple millions and millions of dollars in this company with Chris
And it just goes to show that some nineteen-year-old 18 19 year old kid
Is now this young 30 under 30
Boss and I just I just had to show some love
So you basically are your your accounting system is driving it on the back of a manila envelope and then later on
Insert into
Excel but you walk away from that tour in the bike you but you made some cash
Everlywell
How do you emphasize a super awkward question for both of you
But I always asks if a Partnerships because it is
Part of business like
How do you figure out
Who gets paid what I mean obviously logic
You're you're out there you're the face of this
Organization like you represent all of the people now
To work
For Visionary music group and and the other people involved in so
Chrisley how did you know
How to
Divide that up
Dares
Write a typical commission is how
Work right
15 to 20% is
Is the traditional Commission
Fort for manager
I've learned
To love the commission model the more that I've grown
It's because you
You don't eat
Unless everybody
There's not one person
You're at the table that has a full plate when you're starving it's it's
That's why I've learnt to to love
And things are crazy now
You know that mean 30-plus million-dollar deals here and they're doing this doing that
But you just got out
You got to look in the mirror and say like what does this person deserve it
Truly like yes or no take your ego out of it take
Take one in at 1 an extra meal here there in a deal that
If they had a lower percentage of
But the truth is man like
He earned every penny because he provides
That
With me
I don't feel cheated I never felt that things were unfair or this or that and we
Always so open we have conversations by we have talked about it
And also to be fair
When you get to my level there are
There's there's a bunch of different people in your pocket
But they're all there to make you money
But I am always the majority
And I think that that is
Fair and where you find yourself with artists who are being like
Taken 4
70%
I mean that is
As insane as a collective
And and that's where the music industry is really horrible violin
Chew you up and spit you out but
This is my friend and my brother and
But I think that's
The
Secret
Element that has
Enabled us to be
Successful for so long is
It just did
Really simple
Genuinely
Caring
About that person's well-being
And what I mean by that
You know going back to
When we had a 1.5 million dollar offer
I knew
In my God
It wasn't the right
Opportunity they were not the right partner
It was not a good deal
But if I had
Just
A suggested or advised him that
We take this deal because I didn't really care
What happened to him I wanted to get my commission
And get my check in
You know I'm out
But I didn't
So this is 2012
It's still going to be like another two years before you guys release your first studio record
But between that point
And and the releases to be record you still are releasing mixtape were you guys selling
Again still kind of building the brand
Releasing the music for free
We are still putting out for free
That tour was
A massive eye-opener for us it was
What logic and I had
Thought we were building it approved to us and I think everybody else that it was
It was something very real
Bringing out
Three four hundred kids
Cities across the country from putting out
Free albums in free mixtapes
Been selling a lot of merch
It was very became very real at that time and we wanted
To keep that going
Because if we were building leveraging is
In building his brand soap
Our thing was we wanted to make a splash what it was
Is time for debut album
We wanted to have a really big first
Week sales
Obsolete we decided to can
Continue
Building a putting out free product
I figured as happy as you get the word out like we've done we've done interviews with like the
The founder of glossier
David the Cosmetics Brandon
She started with a beauty blog in overtime she just finished built a following and then she introduced
The brand of
The products the product line and then
We've we've done episode 1
Like founders of Instagram and how that way
What kind of a
A slow build like how did you how did people discover logic
You can't put out the internet
I hope people will find it
Dog was it was it was
Much more thoughtful and there is
The strategy behind everything I think
What I did a lot as I watch
Wright III
Would watch the way other artists would break
And I would try and reverse-engineer that
And in figure out
Okay this is really interesting
YouTube is
An amazing tool at the time
For being discovered because the way their algorithm work
Anderson
Suggested video
Algorithm if you remember right and it's still there
Today
Much different now on the right hand side
If you be watching a certain video music video it's
Suggest another artist
That's something that we do
Took advantage of
I sat down with logic we would go through the project and I said okay let's identify
Four five song
That we think are singles
And we shoot
No budget low budget
Point and shoot
Music videos for those
Because that was that was a way for us to to get more attention to those
Songs
A social media started to come out paying attention
Nevada remember
The very early days of Snapchat
What's something that we took advantage of
Logic was on there and building
You know a big audience on on that platform and then Instagram
Play the role and we try to be
First-mover zombie
Platforms quicklogic to the great job
You know speaking directly to his audience
It's always about sorry to cut you off in like
Taking
Something that's already been done and making it better
You know I've come recently come out with this thing called freestyle Fridays on my Instagram
Were you essentially create a perfect Loop of a song
And it it seems like it's a never-ending
Music video that doesn't stop
And I don't necessarily know of anybody who's done that at least not on a mainstream platform
But it's like finding ways
With something that already exists
Put your own stamp on it and make people
Wanted it all that Freestyle Friday thing is that's it just crowdsourcing
Logic and I were just having a conversation
We came up with the idea
Now we we get to go and look at 15000 comments
And see what their opinion is on the song before we put it out and we can decide
Hey is that something we want to put out you that make the album or not
It sounds like you had
A
She had to slow build from Thrift mm
Before you logic
From 2009 but
Once you enter
Peter Criss
Through the first two years were sounds like they were they were focused on building up
Keynote the brand awareness like
Who is
Making sure people knew who logic was so by the time
You put out your first
Studio record
I'm in in 2014 under pressure
Deborah Kerr
But I think it debuted or one right to number four on the
Billboard
Which is like
Were you guys surprised by the hell you shocked or did you think
Yep this is exactly as you planned it
We were devastated
Actually
I know I I mean
Legitimately devastated
Wait for us it was a number one album
Or bust
And
Wait that was a number for record of the Billboard charts
You were devastated it wasn't number one
Devastator
Because in that was where
Again looking back
I could have done a better job probably
At educating
The record company
And and making them feel a little bit more involved in the early days as we were building
Still very much independently
Like we are putting out.
Free albums
Entering the country
At that point I think he had gone on I think you did a great job you did an amazing job
And we were working with people who aren't that company anymore cuz it's like musical chairs who didn't believe in your
Are you talking about like
By communicating bro you did
A fantastic job and
Say what Chris won't date under ship has
They didn't believe it in a so much that they under ship my album and you had all these other Hughes artist
Within a 400000 plus
CDs in stores
And I had fans
Going to Best Buy
Having
You have the workers there go to the back
Take it out of the box be
Because the entire label didn't believe in us enough
Steven by shelf space
Not just new release
Shelf space
Michelle Smith I just have to say
Your man bro and you did your job
I mean I mean
The blind person perspective
I mean
Thousands of records that are released
Every single week around the world
Like number four on the US Billboard charts
Fractional
A fraction of a fraction
Percentage of albums
Ever get that high
That's a huge achievement I mean that
Like even if I believe you that you were sad it wasn't number one but
It it sounds like you spent the first two years
Building up the awareness and by the time that album came out
It was
Can I play was going to sell a record sold a half a million
Copies I guess
Eventually
Yeah I think it was the first time
That we
Prove to not only ourselves cuz I didn't think we
We needed to I think we understood it and
We believed in and knew what we were building
Prove to the business and end
Really the world that
What we had built I think a lot of people viewed it as almost like building it in a vac
I remember having the conversation to be incredibly frustrated
You know what the head of sales at the time at Def Jam
He didn't understand cuz he's like how you have
You never sold a song
In history
Of your career
Accurate
We had sold
An X number of dollars in merch
So that's going to translate
The expanse who are invested in
Right at the first time we're asked
Not even asking we're putting on music
For sale
If they're coming to shows
And selling out
Rooms across the country
Kramer selling out shows all over Europe
They're going to buy
In album
47909 to me it was
That was the next logical step is like
Okay just the natural progression of his career
Now he's a major label artist
And we're going to sell music
Black Wii U
When you perform right
Are you
Do you feel like you're the same person do you feel like you're sort of a heightened version of yourself
Do you feel like you're almost
Embodiment
Character when your arm stay
Oh man what a
Yeah I think I'm be at my purest form in a way
Like
Be the best version of you
It will not even I think the most vulnerable
I used to be so
Nervous if I would mess up a line or flub here or do this or do that
Then you got to realize it's like
Xiaomi lyrics are in my mind like right now
One breath
Get data later I'll hit you with a permit to get better stay down straight shots in a playground living how I'm living with the life that I'm giving anybody is riding with me I'm riding with him
The enemy enemy enemy second a bit of my getting hit with the ventilator need to attend ever do it I knew it already been through what I do it for the streets
Preparing for life anybody that's gang related
Like you have any times I haven't met up to to be able to do it like that
But it's like I was I was
Kicking myself it wasn't
Good enough I was
I was Michael Jackson and after the show I was Joe Jackson
Looking in the mirror like
Could you do this
And then I kind of started to realize like you wouldn't that
Like I said it was because I thought I was at a time when I needed it
Everything had to be perfect but
Play one wrong key bro
It ain't that deep you know I kiss you have
Sold-out Arena
At the Garden
People who
If you make a mistake if anything it makes them
Steel
A further connection to you because
Is totaling state
Cuz we are
So it's definitely a heightened version
But a more vulnerable
You guys released on the 2nd
Studio release was the incredible true story that debuted
Number three
Charge your third album everybody
If you say number one and a
I think I should train plan terms of like your mainstream
Popularity
Maybe
Expenses superstardom
What's the song one eight hundred two seven three eight
They came out in 2017
How did that song come about
Oh man it's so crazy so earlier
With the second album
We did a tour
Where you know we paid
Six figures for a tour bus
For fans to go to their homes and so
Surprise them and play them the second album before it was even out
Add
Yeah we ate dinner with these people on meth
Their families and friends and I heard about their hopes and dreams and
Hard times and happy times in a row
The biggest thing
That I heard
You know when they would talk about my music I like yeah dude I love your music like it's
It goes without saying like
Make great music and I'm like wow well thank you
But they're like
That's not it
The reason I love
You like
Logic and your brand and what you represent
Is because of the message
You know there's people who are like
You know you've saved my life your music has saved my life
And I after that
What about it for a long time I was at you I didn't even
Try to do that
And actually have the
How are you do that
Could you imagine
What that would be like in end and so when I
What I wrote it
I knew it had to be simple-minded
Had to be and it just came it just was we were just in the studio and
I
I had to hook
And iiii
Sang it
Then I get the verse
And then I knew in my heart I was like
Pac-Man
I need other people on this
And I need other young influential people
You know that can can help get this message out mind you I'm not in the studio light yo this song about killing yourself
I was about to be a banging number one like no
Like no way
I know but I don't care
Nobody saw
Like nobody
Saw that
And a ninja was Chris
Who had the idea
To make it one eight hundred two seven five
Let you know in in really give it the
The whole
Number B
Then we could reach people and give them
That platform
I never had a place
Call Ma
And that number
The name of the song when it hurt to seven three eight two five five.
Telephone number for the National Suicide Prevention
Hotline
I mean wow like you could have called that song
I want to be alive or something else and
You by giving it that
Title of the
Phone number looks like
Suzhou super
Powerful
Did you know that
You know hindsight's 20/20
We could sit here now and be like all of course it could have been but like
No like
What was on the radio I mean it's glorification and
We knew it was a great song and it's funny cuz in the song comes out and you got people like it's going to do well because in his life
Get out of here man
We are not we had no clue
Did you
I understand that you are singing on that record from different
Perspective
Inviting different voices
But I'm
Did you feel that way to Huber
Were you ever suicidal in your life
Here's a crazy
Thing I've never thought I thought about killing myself
I've seen I thought about
Punch a cash register
These are intrusive thoughts that
Just happened where human
Like they happened in there
It wasn't until I was
Experience
True depression
And didn't even know I was
Depressed
While I was touring
And working that
That song
Because everywhere I was going it's suicide suicide suicide talk about killing yourself
So Def def definitely can you imagine
Solid gear
A talking about killing yourself even if you aren't
Like talk about killing yourself
Golf in particular as the artist singing the song but it's like
Yo and that is
Is crazy and in going from like I given up on trying
And I remember telling Chris before that album I was like I'm done I don't want to do it I was always like in the studio trying to make hits
It doesn't mean I wasn't trying to make
The heart beside man I wanted to be Drake and Rick Ross and this I wanted to be that popular guy to
And when I gave up I ended up making the song that did it and
Then
I kind of was like
Hello man
Like I love this I love
Being in the spotlight and being in the spotlight for a pause
Get a message but I just
Work dating
Grinded and did it so much while I was waking up every day and
I wasn't happy going on
And I guess at the end of that
Turn towards the end of that
Just long starts a tourism
Answer the fall 2017
YouTube breakdown icon
What is in Pittsburgh
What happened yeah it's
Crazy Matt so I'm backstage throwing up before I'm going on malnourished
Chameleon healthy
You know when nervous
So bored no I wasn't nervous
Which know I was like
Panic attack feel like you're out of your body
But you you feel like
Like a little person in your brain kind of like you take a swig of water and you're like wait did I actually drink that water
All right now and it would have come to realize I think it's at home
A hyper analyzation of the world around you in real time
And in and that was really hard so I'm going through all this and
You know won't really get too much into it but obviously I was dealing with like relationship issues and
I'm trying to manage up
Accompany
My business
Make albums go on tours in it
And if there was a time where I was even like like I love Chrissy my partner and I want to like quit not quit rap
I just want to run away but I can't cuz we got
Multi million dollar deals on the table
And if I don't do this then it's all going to crumble and he said
Sacrificed his life
For me I'm up here it's all the weight on my shoulders I can't I can't I can't do this I can't do that to him
I start realizing
My future family and I have to stack this money for my children and I'd come from
They like me now but then they might not later I go on Instagram and if you sucking your terrible and you're going bald and your Wyatt Earp
You Can't Rap hip-hop and what is his 1-800 I like you better when you're at like this until
Going crazy and you step on stage and you don't want to be there
They're after nine months I mean think about 9 months on the road
9 months of hotels 9 months of
Of Dark Places
Behind the scenes in this
And I'm sure I'm a human being and that's something that a lot of people don't understand Fame be like
Famous crazy
And and that's what that was
And I didn't go home and
Shoot guns in Rob this and do and just like to know I went home
And I said I'm going to go see my therapist do I see regularly
I'm going to drink a lot of water
I'm going to workout
I'm going to eat better
And I realize that my goals have
Have changed
You know it's like
It's not about money anymore
It's about it's about
That's why I go do a show
Just cuz it's going to make me $500,000 in
An hour onstage like that's
Great
But if I'm not there I should
Want to be honest
Now I do not want to be on
Cuz I taken
Chris how did you
How did you
Deal with
With logic
Anxiety in and exhaustion and and you know that
What happened in Pittsburgh like that that wasn't
I mean obviously that was an expression of
Things that were probably building up over a long time
How did you cope with it
What did you do
I mean I immediately
You kind of put on
The
Friend hat
Right because
That's
What makes this relationship
Specials at
Again yui
You generally care about him so
For me I was a lot of questions about hey
How how can I make
You feel better and what can I exchange
What can we do differently
To make sure something like this doesn't happen
Again and we learned a lot from it I think both him and I
On how to
The move forward in nn
Conduct the business
And operate on a daily basis even
It is a kind of change
A lot of the
Things we did from this daily
Communication
To what we say yes to to what we say no to
And I think we're
Better for it
He'll say the same
Thanks and I think we're going to be
Much more successful
Moving forward and end
It's because
We got through that and it allowed us to
To grow
When I think about
The business that you guys
Created
I'm curious about where it goes
From here like I think about
To write and
Can I go to Jay-Z
Or to Kanye West like I could buy their company outright and Jay-Z could leave the picture
Cuz they're still like
An investment
Our man there's a label and there's other things that
At this point you don't necessarily need Jay-Z the business can thrive
Right now you have a business around your brand whether it's
Performing or selling merchandise for the tour or reading books or acting all those are
Are great but they all require you to
Constantly stay on
Hamster wheel
Did you get to ever
Both of you think about
How do we
Build something
To the Future that
May not require both of
That can just be a business
Is even bigger than
Will what I think Chris is already done that
Envision tees group and and the partners
Ships that he has why won't speak for you let you say that but
I even said I have a record label and we're both
Equal Partners on that that that we run together
Call Delizia
With artist that I've signed
That we believe in that will go out and essentially
Make us money
Those businesses
And I think that mind-state
You like I have a production company and I've really disgusting too much but it's called Bobby boy and these these are things I'm doing my films through in
And yeah it exactly and so imagine like
If I this production company and I write a script and somebody else
Takes the wheel so
I am looking at the future
Through still being creative but more so behind the scenes
Because I have a
Fan base that wants
Any product
I am willing to give them as long as they are familiar with where it is coming from
So how about you
I mean the brand logic there's a lot of equity in that
Young girl my business and and
Have have use my experience and I think some of the relationships in
What's important than knowledge and experience
But I've
Wild
Building logic
Career right next to him
I recently took on a handful more clients of a 5/7 management client right now I just
I just did
Did a joint venture
A label with Sony music with a very very excited about
So yeah there there's there's a lot of things
Look forward to in
But one thing I will say though is we kind of did
I just question and the question was
What what do we have at we so kind of cuz we have these artists you have these artists we have insurance
They're doing things for us
I can't speak for Chris I like to think I can when I say this
He said you know that
Always on the hamster wheel is always going the truth is my brain isn't
What does not
Stop
And that's how I live so I have to be involved somewhere if I'm not in yet
I trust no one with my money with my company with my visit with my dad if I'm not involved like I trust Chris with my life but
I'm not just going to be like just go take it not because I don't trust him but because I don't work that
I need to know
How you cook the fries at McDonald's
Who sweeps the floors who flip the burgers the exact time to flip the burgers this this that that even if I'm sitting all the way
Play on the
57th floor in the CEO chair I need
So this is a question that I asked everybody
To come to the show and
Of course I'm going to ask
The both of you
First Eucharist when you think about the journey that you've taken
Are 20 year old no experience like
Catching this guy logic
To where you are now
How much about you tribute to
Really hard working
An intelligence
Skill
And how much of that do tribute
Probably somewhere in the middle
Between the ball
When I look back
Yeah my at my life and I
I think being
You know raised by my parents
Play played a large role in
Who I am as a person today and
Instilling confidence in me
How
Serendipity
Played such a role in me
Discovering
Logic what I told the story
If I hadn't been sitting at my computer at that very moment
To click that
YouTube link and see the video of logic I don't think
I think we'd be sitting here today
But there's a lot
Large portion of that wear
You know it it's a
Just takes in in
Almost unimaginable amount of hard work
And perseverance
Because of every roadblock
Door that's
Closed
To figure out a way to
Get through it
I think
If it lives somewhere in the middle I think my journey
I would I would probably have one foot in
Hard work and intelligence in
Grind and hustle
And one foot in
Pure and simple lock
Logic
Yeah I mean I think it's in the beginning it's a
A lot of luck
Reykjavik
Without that lucky wouldn't even be blessed enough to
To be a nurse positions in those situations
You know what's really funny I can't speak for other
Famous people celebrities musicians
Whatever but I can tell you like
No one knows how hard I
And until you how are we can work
IPR over $1000000 in
Salary to to my employees
Year
This is a real
Real company
Hard work
You work hard every mother F day
Play we work on everyone
I work hard every mother
That's logic AKA Bobby turn
Tito AKA young Sinatra AKA Sir Robert
Bryson Hall II and Chris ceru founder of visionary music group just spiked
The success of logic music
Both Chris and logic are relying on
Old business strategy to keep the business relevant that would be the strategy of diversification
In addition to working on a new record Logix writing a book and
They film script
Bruce Park
Chris has taken on several new artists to manage
Cleaning up and comers like Jon Bellion
Chelsea Cutler
AOK mentioned earlier Chris is launching a joint venture with Sony to build
Brand new label
Called what else
Dictionary record
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Going to hear from you about
The things your building
But first a quick message from one of our sponsors
Discover
Discover alerts you if they find your social security number on any one of thousands of risky websites
Alerts are free for Card members
Just sign up online
More
Discover.com
Free alerts
Limitations apply
Hey thanks so much for sticking around beak
I know for how you built that and today were updating us
2 years ago
I'm a woman in Stateline Nevada my name is Cassie Burnside and I'm the owner and founder of fatco
Backhoe
And why would
Anyone want to put the word fat
Into the name of their startup
Well
You have to go back a bit because of about 7 years ago
Cassie
Starting to notice
Thing that kind of bugged her
I would go shopping and I would look at labels and look at ingredient panels
And not be able to read or pronounce anything
I had no idea what these ingredients were
Especially bothered by products that go directly onto your skin
Deodorant
Lotions and creams but then she thought maybe I can make some of those things
Used to Know
Old fashioned ingredients
Those were ingredients that we used a lot in soap making Orbeez the Latin candle making
And I started wondering like why don't we use them anymore why did those things go away
And here is where
Fat comes in
Because Cassie realize that animal fat
If used to be a main ingredient in things like
Soap and lotion
And so she decided that make skin products with
Beef tallow
The fat from a cow chop it up and you cook it low and slow
And rendered Tallow is the liquid fat
It rips off of that
Hard factoring that rendering process
Just to be clear
Cassie does not do this at home she gets her towel from a company in Colorado that specializes in red
Rendered fat
And then she mixes the fat with other oils
Fragrances to make things like body butter and lotion
They're nursing their nutrient dense
They're very concentrated and a little goes a long way
Cassie said she took a
Big risk five years ago when she
Quit her engineering job
To start.
Petco
3 years
She's made
$600,000
Each year
And last year
January 2018
Target started selling fatco products
As for all the friends and family who told her this would never work
They are not saying that anymore
Even my mom told me I was a little crazy but now she's our biggest fan she will go to her grave saying she was customer one for
Backhoe
Taxi company is called
Are launching five new products this month
Do you want to find out more about it or your previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. NPR
Dr. Org and of course if you want to tell us your story go to build
Npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcast
While you're there
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us at hi BT at
Npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
Wechat how I built
Are shows produced this week
A James delahoussaye
Music composed by
Teen Arab Louie
Thanks also to
The Julia Carr DJs
C Howard Nora coetzee
The grand Bliss
Grace Anna's Michigan for
Jeff Rogers
Our internet
Anti-slip
Gyros and been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Campaign monitor
An email marketing flag
Form used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Bill
Builder and customer support
7 days away