Support for how I built this and the following message come from America
Express
You want to build your business
Can help building
With financing
Solutions for
Eligible business
Customers
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Business
So really quick before we start the show
I want to tell you about a live event we are about to do in
Portland Oregon
Thursday Mesa
XVI
I'll be talking with Seth Tibbott he's the founder and
CEO of
Tofurky
The show is supported by Americans
Express and our other Live Events
Sold out fast so
Ticket ticket
Go to nprpresents.org
In Portland
I was a nobody from Key Largo
And here are named venture capitalist I mean I don't want to call him out by name but think of 20
Venture capitalist you further name I'm sitting there and they're saying No this is dumb no thank you and you're like
Who am I to think that this named person at this name shop is wrong
NPR
How I built this
Innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories
How man who knew almost nothing
Fitness Media or technology
Delta brand that does all three
Peloton
Home Fitness Company value
More than four
Billion dollars
Account for all the money generated by the Fitness in
History in the US but
If you factor in gym memberships alone
It's around 30 billion dollars a year
And that number is
Is growing
Because
People are becoming more
Health-conscious
A lot of that growth is
Being driven by what
Call the
Fitness category
Things like bar yoga
Spin Studios
A smaller gyms that do one thing
Really well
All of these options is that
Post Park
You need to book a slot
Which is fine if you're super organized
Not so great
You forget
Which is where John Foley was
Back in 2011
You realize
A spinning class
Can only accommodate the
20 years
30 people in the room
Basically the class couldn't be scaled beyond the number of spin bikes available
But what if you could scale
What if that very same class
Reach a thousand people or
People or an unlimited number
You didn't even need to make reservation
Heidi has started this
Swirl around
John Foley
Shake it
There were a few problems for starters
John knew nothing about the fitness industry second he didn't know much about technology least things like
How to make software
Was in his forties with kids
The mortgage and they're pretty safe job
And finally this is a common situation
Didn't have any money to launch it
And yet just years later
John Foley isbill Peloton
I'm into a business that's been valued at more than
4 billion dollars
How did he get there
Well we invited John to tell a story
In front of a live audience
In New York City
John actually grew up
A small town in the Florida Keys
His dad was an airline pilot and his mom stayed at home to help run the household
John's first shots order in fast food impact in the 1980s
He would work at McDonald's Wendy's
And Domino's Pizza
But by the time you got to college
John moved on
Candy
When I was 19 years old I got a co-op job in Waco Texas at a manufacturing plant making Skittles
Starburst Snickers and Twix
It was modern-day Willy Wonka we meet 6 million snicker bars a day
Wow just for North America
Wild stuff
I wore a hairnet
Hard hat steel toe shoes in a uniform
Working midnight shift
For five years to pay my way through college
Idaho
I don't recommend it
Don't have your kids do it
Cuz you you studied industrial engineering
And so
The Mars job was really kind of the
Through school or was that
Potentially going to be a career
Yeah it was good was both it was going to get my foot in the door so you can get a job when you grabbed
And so when you were at at Mars
You are mainly doing like
You are on the production line for all those six years
Exactly yes
Candy
Chocolate M&M Skittles
Skittles and Starburst manufacturer North America
Managing 200 people
While I was 20 years
2 years old
Had a great experience in and it felt like
A good job that pays well and they treated me well and I
I saw myself spending the rest of my life in Waco
Yeah
Can you eat Skittles today
I don't
No
They're great
There they are good
She get your
Feel of Starburst
Skittles
And then you
I guess you're the first, maybe grown-up job was
With a tech company
In your early 20s yeah there was a little Bridge there where
I went out to LA for kalkan
Pedigree Whiskas Sheba pet food
Which is a division of Mars
So 25 years old I said hey
I realized I didn't want to spend the rest of my life
And I requested a transfer within Mars to La where I start making pet food and Vernon which is
Is the Meatpacking
Talk about lights pretty
Pretty Grim scene on itself
But that was that what's got me to La and then I made the jump over to
And what was that company
So it was it was a 1996
And you guys all followed it like I do or know that in 96
The.com was exploding the internet was a thing
And there's come pick out citysearch.com a lot of you might remember
I went over and you guys appreciate this now it's
You guys know this
Dot-com startups
What are super fun super dynamic
There's interesting people it was
Quite a contrast to the manufacturing World in Waco Texas where it's people who are going to
How to punch in the clock literally literally punch the clock
And so was a totally different person and I just fell in love
With the idea that you can work with great people the challenge you to motivate you that they're your age and they're
Also ready to take over the world it was it was I found my people over
But you decide after
What are your two in La at citysearch to go to Business School
Let's go to the Harvard Business School
That's right and coming from you
The Florida Keys and going to Georgia Tech resin engineer and then beating Waco I just didn't know the world and I wasn't very exposed I wasn't very sad
Fabian wasn't very confident
And all these hot shot people at citysearch bro
Way over educated and they all wanted these fancy schools and I was very intimidated by him they work
Internships at Goldman and Mackenzie and there were this and that
And so I just didn't know that whether I can hang with them
And my brother-in-law encouraged me to apply to Harvard
Stanford in Columbia I said you're going to go to physical try to go to the one of the best
I got the rejection from Sanford
But luckily I got it I got an HPS
Sand
And I was very excited it did
Many ways changed my trajectory
Because it gave me the confidence to know that no one is that much smarter than the next person and
Everyone's trying to figure it out and
And so it was it was a transformative
Opportunity. There you didn't feel like
You got there and thought you know what actually
That they're not that him
Any more impressive than anyone else
For sure
After 2 years I got there and was incredibly intimidated
The Vinewood you talk when you know when you're when you grow up in New York City and your parents work at Goldman Sachs
Your talk I don't know what investment banker
Dove TI be the bank of the keys
And I was
That's where you got your check cashed at the bank to me
So I didn't know anything about much
Xiamen
And so it was it was
Alright so you get out of HBS
And
You got all these options what do you where to go
Itsfunneh I got a job at BMG music which was the
Being always be with my dream to work in the music and
And it was in 2001 it was a recession and so I accepted the job and six months later when I was set to start
I was going to go away to Italy for
Are weak
And I called the HR Director and I said hey I'm going to be out of the country for the next week if you need to reach me who's there
And she's like oh my gosh
No one's called you
And I said why you need to talk to someone so
Turns out because of the Napster
Disruption was right around that time where music industry is being decimated
My job is going away my old apartment at going away
Wow and so I was sitting there
Coming out of HBS in this recession with no job and I had to sign a lease in New York City in
I spent four months trying to get a job calling back people there like of you trying to sound screw you
So what we're doing.
So I went back to to what was then IAC Ticketmaster City search the people that I work with prior
Truth be told my brother-in-law who is this
The CEO of Ticketmaster
Pick me up
Up and dusted me off
And giving up
Opportunity
A kind of force
A roll because he
Cared about me and him and it was
It was a moment that
But I need it
So take it to your Ticketmaster Ticketmaster owned by IAC which is a
Bigger so it was still the same people that I had left they just bought this tiny
Company called evite.com
The interesting that you appreciate this a lot of
Budding entrepreneur is listening this
David Ford I believe 45 million dollars into building Evite
And I think we bought it for $3000000
Because it was
2001 and everything in Crash
And so it had one point 120 people
I got it down to six
Sour like running a startup within a bigger
Organization
That's right
And this is a tiny tiny business
Effectively meant nothing and so
There was a lot of pressure but we were The Little Engine That Could we saw it becoming something massive and so
We put pressure on ourselves that a lot of fun trying to
Pull a rabbit out of the Hat
We grew it in a substantially from
Call the million dollars top-line 225 million top-line and profitable so
You know in in relative terms successful but still meant nothing to anyone that I say
So you are
I guess still in your maybe late twenties or early thirties by that point
La that's right
And were you married
I was not right around that time I think it's 32 I was meeting my wife Jill who was living in
Who's who's right around
Take me back to
Is it to your mindset at that time were you
Were you entrepreneurial and the way you thought about the world did you think you know
I think I want to run a business or will you really focused on the kind of
Security in the stability of working in a big organization
Right around that time I was
Starting to become off parole in mine cuz I was surrounded by these type of people in your seeing people take risks and get the reward and I
I'm starting to become I have more belief in myself
There was enough of that conversation on the water cooler that was starting to get that bug
To go to
And I guess
Assertive towards the end of the first decade of the 2000s you jump
To Barnes & Noble
That's right
So my
Buddy Ganem William Lynch
Became the CEO Barnes & Noble
And everyone knows that Barnes and Noble 2010 was challenged Visa V Amazon
But
Do any of you read Barbarians at the gate
Birthday
I'll probably come he's attacking something and try to take it private
Taking a company private sounded like a pretty fun
Pirate type Nino take the ship exciting challenge Nicole
That was so cool
But we weren't able to do it
I mean you were involved with a digital side of ours until we know what's going on with the details
Surviving free fall
So what was going on with with a part of company you were running
Imagine it was
Play losing all my exactly trying to compete with Amazon
15 years late
I mean you don't wish on your worst enemy
Competing at Amazon in their in their core category right
So it was pretty rough and yes yes we were losing money
So what are you starting to
At that point
2010/2011 starting to think
All right I got to come up with an X thing
Yeah I mean at this point I'm anxious immuno 40
I wanted to
Be in a bag
And I'm just kind of spinning my wheels and
Haven't found anywhere to anywhere to go
Sorry
Coming
But you said you wanted to be
Big what do you mean by that what it would that actually mean
I don't know I'm a competitive guy and I study I study
Everything I read every Business book I've listened to every how I built this
I really am a student of business and and
After
Years and years and years of this
I say I think I'm as good as that for that person I just heard
You know some of my think I'm better
Until we know what about me I think I can do it they give me a chance
And so I was
I'm starting to become pretty anxious and wanted to approve my
2011 you're still at Barnes & Noble
And
You
Get an idea for a company that would become the one that you not run out
So
Like a lot of New Yorkers I'm guessing a lot of you here Boutique Fitness was exploding in New York City
SoulCycle flywheel Barry's Bootcamp yoga been around for a long time I done spend
Back in the 90s in LA
And I hit I clearly felt that the boutique
Instructor-led group fitness high-energy programmed experience was better than
Then going to the gym
It was more fun than going for a 6 mile run by yourself
It was more fun than going to the old big box gym and trying to throw around the way to get on a treadmill and get yourself excited
And so I had tasted this content
And I said this is
This is good people want this I want
But it was at a different location at somebody else's time going to pay a lot of money to get that experience
And interesting Lee my wife who
Is
Probably works out two or three times more week then I do she's
The poster child
For the stuff
She premeditated workouts for the week
And she'll say okay next Thursday morning to wake up at 6 and go to this class until the Beast schedule and reserved my bike
And I just didn't do that I didn't don't have that Gene
Thinking at 10 at night before I go to bed, am I going to set the alarm tomorrow
Right
And that's how I think it's effectively because the good locations in the good instructors are sold out so quick
But I wasn't able to go to that why was box out of it
And I said if these classes sell out these 50 bikes sell out
And 30 seconds
Would there be 500 people up if it was infinite room would there be 500 people that wanted in with me
Pier two thousand people in New York that would want that great time and a great instructor
If you could
Skillet globally would there be 50,000 people in 5 million people that would want that great instructor at great time
And so I said it did it just started to scream distributed technology play
And obviously I knew enough about technology that
Yeah I got me excited
Do you talk to your wife right away dude
This amazing idea or was it more of a Slow Burn
I think it was an amazing idea
It was
You're with your words your words not mine
They were it was
I think it came to me and I said I think you can digitize that experience
And build a hardware and software platforms
Consuming Fitness.
So the light bulb went off what was the description you gave us
Google take me back to 2011 I'm at your house and you like a guy
I have this great idea
What are you what are you telling me
Yeah it's it's effectively Peloton bike it was yours a big screen
And
Here is a bike that talks to the screen so you have metrics
Competition motivation
UEFA leaderboard
You have great
Instructors
I knew enough about
The content in the celebrity that you could
If you had the global scale
You could pay for the best
Constructors
And in all these things a content is King
Has a lot of you guys are connoisseurs of the category you know that
And sometimes you're
Say yoga
Your yoga instructor
Is more important than the yoga studio
If your yoga instructor went to a different Studio you might follow him or her
And so the content really
Is is important I said we could get the best people
And so I explained the whole thing and I did go home and talk to my wife about it
She knew the categories you knew me
And she's nodding and luckily she was behind it very early because
You know I think something for the rest of this
Podcast rent talk about the bone-crushing next 7 years
Thanks thankfully she believed in in the idea
Who's the first serious person you called
How to say
Can one tell you about this
Cuz
You needed to
Presumably
Do this with somebody else
Yeah there were there were three phone calls I made my mentor John Pleasants he and I he just started job at Disney
And so he dragged me on a Disney cruise
And what wait we pulled out to spin bikes and I was pretending the coach him through as I say there's a screen e r a
And I was on the bike
Coaching him through I would like
Stand up
And if any
So I cycle right now work on Yahtzee and turn it off and I work and true for
10 minutes of
The pho class
He said I get it
That was better than I would have done myself until the light bulb went off in his head so
He was an early investor so I got him
Then I called to my co-founder
Mitsubishi
I'm using to store general counsel in one of my best friends and he knew how to start a cup
Your pregnant with starting the company and have a backer
What you do then what do you write for parade in Delaware
So he was instrumental and he was a very smart guy and so he advanced
That you know you wasn't just the legal guy who sent you
Couponer never sent
And then a third co-founder Tom cortezi
Who is just
It worked with you at IAC before and he's never start another company with
He's just so can do and
Positive and so I sat with him
IPic remember there was a bottle of wine and some
Sushi takeout
And at the end of it he's like a man
So with you get a little bit of momentum of getting some other people on board and Things become more real
When there's other people that jump in the Box
So it was that easy to convince those guys to
Presumably leave their jobs
Or
Do a side hustle with you on this by the way you are still at Barnes & Noble at that
I was but truth be told by his so it was about
2 years before he left his job
So he was Moonlighting so he didn't have to take the risk
And Tom was out of work
Wasn't
You always want to go to somebody's out of work.
Play trying to find a co-founder right is the best type of co-founder
Alright so you got these
You got these friends and you got to start
Coming up with a concept but
From what I understand what are the first steps
You did was
To go out in
Just raised him
Amend
People you knew or people in your network of people that those guys knew the seed round was Route was relatively easy
It was $400,000
That a 1.6 million pre-money valuation
Pinto 2 million post
Any raises from like
Hungry people
I know this was this was from I think eight people
Alarm and it was
People who just knew me and trusted me and log me in and worked with me in the past
So it was my best friend's dad who
I had some money not a lot of money but enough that he was going to give me 50000 which was the big check
And then my brother-in-law who
I've made a couple million dollars in his life so it was
One of the richest people I knew
And he was going to give her number at the text
I said we are you in 425 and he said you send me a picture of 50 Cent he's like no I'm in 450
He's either very excited he's a very excitable guy
So you were like raising 25000 50000 here and there and the valuation was 1.6 million.
So initially Rydia was let's just buy off the shelf
Stop
The Shelf bike and let's
Getting off the shelf
Tablet and let's try to do it
Yeah that's right I'm in it for all of you biting on spinners
Software is he is easiest to appear software company is easiest to do
And it's easiest to raise money
Every venture capitalist is looking for the next Instagram
Were you put
$250,000 in an 18 months later it sells for a billion dollars
So we were trying to think can we be software
Only
I'm started to look at the but we started to do deep research on the on the bikes in the category
And
As you probably know
Fitness equipment categories in
Incredibly Dope
Noatak
No design
I just didn't feel like it was a bike that met the bar of
The call if call you if you wanted
So then we start thinking guy let's make it bike
And let's have a dongle
To plug in your iPad
Everybody's got an iPad and I kept coming back in my mind to the clock radio
When your Holiday Inn
It has the iPhone 4 dongle
And I said I don't want to be that company that looks so dumb cuz your product is
May be relevant based on some of other companies Hardware Cycles
And so I said I think you got to make the tablet
Height by the way this wasn't me this was
Channing Tatum we were coming
Us together but
These are the decisions we make
You got some seed money you get some office space I think in
In Manhattan
And even before you started
Think about the actual bike right you went to
Flywheel you went to SoulCycle you said hey
Do you want to partner with me on this is that
That's right we went to SoulCycle
Have instructors you guys
Jeff Studios you guys wanted this is what you guys do
We're technologist
We're going to build a Hardware in soccerplatform what about we come together
Seems very obvious that would be good for us and good for them
So I can joint venture
Yeah exactly
And we got we got
A couple weeks into a term sheet with flywheel and then they backed away they just got through financing around and it didn't make sense with her
New investor
SoulCycle
He was tricky though the only there was enough human chemistry
But the team they were
Very big
We were nobodies so the conversation was kind of
One sided
Write in a way that I thought it would be
Conversation equals
But they they were doing so well
I'm getting so much
Affirmation from their community
That it wasn't a conversation of equal so it didn't
So it didn't work out
And
You decide are we going to build this bike by the way
You still were going to
It's like SoulCycle classes in flywheel classes
I'll give you like going to the class
I did yes
And what were you laughing
Well you have all of us very quickly got kicked out of flywheel and tolls
You're saying that you are not
A class and somebody
Yes
They like monitors there like they're like oh there's John Foley he's going to be our competitors to what what happened
The very territorial category
Especially New York
The flywheel and SoulCycle and you had to join Elizabeth
On the show right now
Friendly with
But that because
Because
Give me the roots Aukerman
Defection duration started with them when they separated
And she she's amazing woman I love her
She went to start flywheel and so
There was a lot of vitriol between the two
And I understand I made it wasn't
It wasn't personal it was its
Competitive
Alright so you got
Some seed money
And you've got to
Build a bicycle now
How do you even
Start like
What are you
Like what are you going to go to find out how to build egg
Stationary
Spin cycle
Yeah we went to Taiwan to trade shows
Superfund by the weather
Incredible to go to Tie Fighter by Eva Air to Taipei and go to one of the trade shows your mind is made
Really opened up with so much
Manufacturing and
Schoology
Most interesting stuff ever
The Wii
What's first two years of
Pulling the thread through the technology and doing prototypes and
Testing and
Taking the dog food and getting people on the prototypes at
It was so fun
The tough thing was those years we just didn't have any money so we were always about to run out of money and when you
When you have a vision and you have people and you you need
Capital to build a business and when it's not there it's very scary and very stressful so
Yeah mon Ramen when you went to
Manufacture of spin bike is really
Expensive
So
Did you start to go to VC firms and ask them for money
I would bet a pitch three times a day for 4 years
Between thousands of angels that ended up giving the first we have a hundred angels
2 / 10 million
But in order to get a hundred Angels at my success rate
I probably pissed
3000 people
Wow
And then the 4th at the 400 institutions that all said no all of them
All of them
I'm so it was a hundred angels
They gave its 4:10 million and then finally after
Almost three year tiger global
Which of the New York city-based venture capitalist thankfully
Because the valley
Sandhill Road the valley
Didn't see what was happening
In New York City with the
Did the guy go out there they would say there
Two types of biking out here John mountain bike
Viking road bike
Straight
And that they just didn't see what was happening and it was it was a blind spot for them so luckily there while you're there were some venture capitalist and Lee fix
Television area
Tiger global
Saw it at
And maybe they were the
Over that three-year period from 2011 to 2013-14 when you are pitching and pitching and pitching relentlessly
Pitching and also you know
Run a business
That must have
Should have been difficult I mean I can't imagine there
Maybe not but I can assure you wouldn't have had some self-doubt
Sure there were there was there was there were
Quarters in years where there was a
Incredibles
It had to be a man
I was a nobody from Key Largo and here are
Named venture capitalist
Assuming I don't want
Calling out my name but think of
Venture capitalist you've heard their name
I'm sitting there and they're saying
No this is Dom no thank you
And you're like who am I to think that this named person at the
Disney shop
Is wrong
Yeah
Supercomp
Located
Expensive to
There's no Market data about it
And so
What did you what would you respond
That was a frustrating thing is that no Market data because
We created a category of
And I thought when the venture capitalist heard that they would say wow this is
Does truvision
This is true disruption
Absolutely let me in
And they were saying
No there's no research
Search there's no that they look
What's called pattern recognition
And it wasn't a pattern and what we were doing
And so
You know it was it was frustrating cuz I saw it clear as day
Are are early members
Customers
Thought they were saying oh my gosh
Who sings change my life
They're going
Crazy for you
And still the investors weren't there
You had
Two kids
Edward mid-40s OS you're not 21 or 22
2 year olds
Ajisen Ramen
Yep
The stakes are high
Take some very high and it's a one point I told my wife alright we're going to sell her 401K cuz we need we need the money
Doesn't sound very smart but your desk
Yeah and in the early days when we had engineers and we have very little money
And you have to pay Engineers a lot of money to get great engineers
And give them a lot of equity obviously
I cleaned the bathrooms and I vacuumed every day for 3 years in this little
What's the place we had and it will have to clean because
We could afford a cleaning office
I said I didn't want anyone else distracted with
Cleaning so you know I was that guy but then I turned into the the fundraiser
And we made it work obviously we're sitting here but it was very very dark days
When we come back
Capella time is actually made enough money for John to stop
Cleaning the bathrooms
Add a company van went on to become a major Force
World of fitness
Play with us
I'm guy Raz listening to
How I built this
Support for this podcast come from American Express
Director of global sales strategy Chase Hyatt
Explains how American
Expressworks
With their customers
Define the right
Financial solution
Their business
It's a lot like solving a puzzle
Each customer's different each business is different
We really want understand what your goals are for the year
For three years
And what would extra financing do
To help you achieve
One of my customers is a long-standing family-run restaurant
And Sons dream was to open up a second look
Finances are a little bit tough as they were just running the business and
We were able to partner with him understand
Exactly what he needed and help him open up that second location and now they're onto their third
So whether it's a need to open a second location or
Safilo fig New Order
We want to make sure that we're there for you all along that you're
American Express wants to help you move your business forward
With flexible financing
Chat with him today to see you
You're eligible
Americanexpress.com business
Learn more
Terms apply
Before we get back to the show
I want to tell you about another podcast
Do you think that
Fortune 100
CEOs have
Sleepless night
Four star generals get anxiety or the
Big City Mayors gets
Scared
Greatest leaders
In the world navigate
Crisis
And setbacks
To become leader
Find out my new podcast
Wisdom from the top
It's available
Exclusively on
Luminary
New podcast app.
Lets you hear your favorite shows
Who's the one
Trevor Noah
Lena Dunham
I'm gay
You can download the luminary app to your
Your smartphone or
Check out luminary podcast
Dot-com
Sign up to listen
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Die Rise
Soca 2013
Sean Foley
Is out trying to raise money
Peloton afloat
Meanwhile his co-founders of Designing a bike
Who's the author of high-tech alternative
Typical home workout
But
When the first
Prototype pariah
It was a big problem
So you know the spinal tap where I was 18 in 18 ft
But there was a little scale problem
Where the first the first prototype was about
40% too big
It was like we looked at it really that's a big
Indoor cycling bike
So
Funny we have a good friend of ours
Lawrence allamanda who is a tall
Beautiful woman
And we we needed some marketing
511 or something
Harry said
Can you come model this bike so that the proportions look a little bit more normal
Trick photography
So that was the first intravasation we had to do with that with that one of those
One of the first
Predators in was the bike as great as you had hoped it to be I mean aside from the
Giant scale the next prototype that we got that we got
Skil raised we were much closer to Launch
And we were much more anxious
What's with the next fight the game off
The crate from Taiwan
And we got on that we're excited to look greater threat scale
And I will put the tablet on and I think my wife got on it to ride it cuz she was off in our Muse
Tube
To test things out and
The whole thing started wobbling
I will... Screen she couldn't
Watch the instructor cuz the screen was wobbling so much and we tightened everything downtown everything down still wobbles like crazy
We realized there was just fundamental design flaws with entire body
But you around that time
You have to do a kick-start like you guys decide to launch Kickstarter that's right
Kickstarter's require a video that's right
So you got a wobbly bike and a giant bike so so what are you video
Well we fake it till you make it
Or it fell. We say you got to rob a few gas stations on the way the perfect crime
And so what you do is you ask the model and the kickstarter video 2
Not really ride it
Mature enough to be very delicate so and we can
Who doesn't shake
And we know that we got a little more time to work The Kinks out and drip trying
You know I'm problem solve the the Wobble
When you guys did the kickstarter was that actually
To raise
Necessary money or was it
It was both but we were very excited about the raising money piece of it
And
It turns out it was a flop it was incredibly disappointing we thought here's a video is a 4 minute video tells you everything you need to know about
Peloton
And
200 people
I guess we were stranded.
Some 200 people bought
And 100 of them were invest
So
It was you know
Rihanna back to the drawing board
Do we have a business
How we going to sell this thing it was it was
It was a moment
At that point you are
Building bikes
I think you the kickstarter you sold them for 1500
Were people
Investors in and maybe others kept
Can I push it back in saying
Too expensive no one's going to buy that
One interesting thing
A couple months after the kickstarter thing we launched
A website and we started pricing it at $1,200
Because
It was just over $1,200 was our costume I like let's price it at Cost because we have the subscription digital content business model
Comes afterwards so we don't need to make any money
And we were selling at 1200
And someone told me
That a $1,200
It seems
Sheep sounds cheap
And so we said
Increase the price and we increase the price
And
Impossible to truly tell
But it seems like the velocity of sales in
So you have
A piece of hardware
You're building a software
Oh and by the way you have to be a TV production company
YouTube build a broadcast-quality studio
And by the way how big was your off
In terms of square footage
Probably
2000 square feet
And yet how many people are working in there
That point is probably 20
5 people
You guys know about
TV production
What would you do like what your first step
Wood
On Wikipedia research
Okay television production camera
And you'd see here's the real expensive one here's the
Media morning Mo a fun thing is we were our office was right by B&H Photo
So you go over to B&H Photo and you talked to somebody and say this is what we want to do
And they help you I mean this is the learning this is the fun stuff about nursing we love these
And what was that what did that first Production Studio actually look like was it a professional
I know Studio has no it was it was basically the back of our office we hung a curtain and put for stationary bikes
And put a camera
And static camera
Set a camera against the wall some lights and studio lights
I think we are
RCT oyouni as a fake instructor
You know it's kind of feet do the first class before because it's his way before we could convince any instructor to Joy
Moving hearts
Is the bike there's a software there's getting instructors DirecTV production so how do you get
Instructors mean
I have to assume most of the great instructors are already working at Firewheel SoulCycle or other places
Yeah sure so we are I put I put an ad on social
Cuz you can't afford relied so you just posting things on social
And it was not what I was looking for the 10 best instructors in the world
And just ridiculous bombastic I get it but it was we were
Until it
Cu cu bites
And so I remember when the first
At the first instructor that we hired was a woman at Jenn Sherman
Who was a big deal
Got to love Jen
She said look no further I have the email she has the email with it with the moment and her personality was captured in it
And she's such a
Fun charismatic believes in herself
Cheeky everything about a personality came out this email and she's like
You found your person
And we did and then quickly Robin took a risk
That was awesome Hannah
Cody the not-too-distant
There was there was an energy
And we tell him what we're doing and
I think they they
Enough of me saw it
And we didn't have a studio at that point we didn't have stores they didn't know how we're going
To sell these things
How to get the word out about this and what was your distribution model having to sell them
Yasso office in Manhattan streaming videos that's right
Time we had this product that we thought was awesome and
The website was up and no one was coming to the website
Start doing some Facebook ads in
You know trickle of sales came in but not nearly fast enough to build a business
So we
We thought about having a pop up in Grand Central reach
Commuters
I'm couldn't get the right spot but I think it was either Tom Cortes of your ryannangle this young young guy on a team
At the idea of going out to Short Hills Mall
And finding out whether they had
Stop application
Short Hills because it's the trendsetting capital of America
Well what you want cuz I don't really days
To your point if you have a $2,000 product you you do think that the lowest hanging fruit is going to be awful in neighborhood that's an athlete
Incredibly awful and I've never been there never heard of it
I ended up not going because I was still in the in the deep dark days of fundraising
Somebody else watch the retail and I was a combination of a right angle and Thomas
But we did run the math and we said we need to sell one bike a day
In order to make
This work
And how did the do-over was Aaliyah
Curiosity
Three shopping malls are
Right on the decline were there
If you aren't fewer there's there's less most foot traffic in shopping malls
So that was kind of a rest
But what is
What happened to people
Check it out yeah it was it looking back it's it's it's amazing to me it's still a miracle V
Did this happen
But you think about who's going to come in walk by a store in the mall they've never heard of
Come in and check out a bike
And get
$2,000 in the credit card out and say I want one
Once a day
Everyday somebody going to come in to buy Peloton bike
Very quickly
We were selling 5x a day
Well and it was just
Mind-boggling that's just
People never heard of this and I will tell you the interesting guy
The main objection back then wasn't the price it was
What it what happens to this bike when you guys go bankrupt
Write write 95 percent of startups
Go bankrupt I have no idea but it said it took material
Majority
And I had a good answer which was
If you're paying the subscription
We can keep an Amazon web services server going
And park the content up there
And stream to the bikes because that economics will be
I will still work for the business over in bankruptcy whoever gets this asset of the annuity of the
I had it I had a story at work
Sometimes
And how much content I mean if you are an early adopter if you were buying
The Short Hills Mall
How much content was available at the time
10 glasses
Time they weren't filmed in that back room
They were alive.
So it was
See I was five months before we had our studio in Chelsea open so
You were still selling a dream but I will tell U Visa vie
I mean even one Jenn Sherman class
In a Cheesy Unifour bike studio in the back of her office
Her personality came out
And you get on it and you put your headphones on you like
I can take this anytime I want and by the way then click over and gets take a robin class and
Enough was there that you like I get it
And you're going to add classes every week
Sure reading class every week
And they got excited and if you like Fitness and you likes
Take me to risk taking it was it was fun
So at what point are you able to go back to some of those investors they look I have this model now
I can show you the you know where where this is heading
When when did you start to get
A better reception
So the frustrating thing guy on that Vector is
A lot of people would say I'm going to wait to see if there's bikes
I'm going to wait to see if people want this property
I go back to those same people and they're like
So you're selling bikes
But this is acid
Subscription digital content business model
They might buy the bike and they might turn after a year
Come back after you have more coworx data after a year or two on the churn of the Civ
Description
As I go out come on
I can't get two years down the road if I don't have more money were you surprised at how risk-averse a lot of these VC
Incredibly
So yeah absolutely I was
Jardins de more lies and you think venture capitalist
History of War
How to have a vision and end
And take risks
You have the right guy they minimize risk going to end you get it if they're shepherding your Capital they want minimal risk but
It didn't didn't make sense to me at the time
Still have to
Secret pop-up shop
Presentable your online
Where are 2014
I mean February that
Pop-up shop
Closes
So now are you selling the bike
No we were able to renew the lease on short
And we said wow this is working
Let's go get a couple more
Allocations
Give me four locations in when we started selling bikes and then shopping malls
Only child
So is it was it something that
You guys felt
Customers or potential customers had to try
But if they just saw it online it wasn't
It wasn't really going to be enough cuz it's a big ask
What you're asking people to
Shell out
A considerable amount of money
And no matter how you make the argument look over
Timer going to save money on gym membership
It's still too
Big one time cost at that time
Did you feel like
We got to get this in front of people people to sit on it and try it
That that was exactly right. It was
You and your wife would walk up and I
Profile
Cuz she's probably sold
Cyclist probably are
Outdoor cyclist do whatever in
There is there are some gender bias in in
10 Fitness
One of you would get on the bike
Within two minutes of me talking to you and say going to try come on please
And I'd be adjusting to seed and minimizing the friction so you get on
How to get Yuan
Pikachu on the paddles put then I was a hand over the headphones to you
And I'd know what class to start with you what
What instructor you might like what instructor she might like I'd know what
What class and I'll be honest
It was a fun game for me to try and get the hook in your mouth
Right away as quickly as possible I get you peddling so the endorphins start moving body start to giving you reaction
Headphones on loud music
And you would look over your wife
And you'd say
This is amazing
Right right screaming in the mall
Because the tide make the music too loud and generally if I could get somebody on a bike on a stick
God I got to a point where is 50-50 chance that you're going to buy the bike even though you've heard of it
Because it is something that once you experience it
And get on it and see it and it
Clicks
You want it
Cheer raising money or going to shopping malls your
Sales guy always sings
Curious mean you still got children
Presumably want to spend time with them I mean how did that
Impact your personal life
He was it was tough again the fact that my wife believed in it meant a lot again either at work or
Marriage wouldn't work if if she hadn't been you know a believer in that it was it was very dark days and it was
I was
You know a shell of a human being
For several years
To two years in particular
She would say I'm feeling disconnected your not present you're not here
And can we have a date night and I would say I will have a date night
If we talk about
What happens when we on white.
If that's the conversation
How we're going to move in with your parents what's going to walk me through
Walk me through the unwinding of this
So that I don't
Yeah something bad doesn't happen
So you act like
The significant anxiety
I was masquerading as
Running app
Great company and we are trying to put on a happy face and
You know sell to the team and sell to the investors
And if the truth be told first
Two or three years we were about to
The collapse and we didn't have the money
And if it was
It was stressful I mean I mean a lot of fun
I'm not the first alternative.
But it was it was first time I've gone through it was very tough
So when did you start to see
To see like a light like what did you start to turn a corner was it when you started to open up those shopping mall
Locations and when did you start
Really see
Sales kind of pickup
I start seeing the light on Peloton about
6 months
Okay
It was hard for a long long time
But the traction
Yeah we started opening more stores
But then it's like you're selling 4000 bikes and you have this massive burn and you have great shoulder expectations you're still running
Money
Hugo do pitting on 100 pitches you get a hundred knows ya even though your Sultan bikes and you have some happy customers
You're still in the grind
Meantime you have to like
The company has to produce
Tons of content
Is there more bikes or selling the more
Demand there is
So
How did you how did you guys kind of
Do that
So
Tibet there was that we wanted to have a studio that was
Content production
Facility basically television
And in the early days it was I I say that it was a
Spin studio
With a television
Bright
Now it is a television production facility
Filming fit
Enes Kanter
And we have I mean
Some of the best
Production people
And some of the best on air Talent I'll be sleeping in our celebrity
Instructors
But we've become a pretty hardcore Media Company
But in the early days it was
How do you rig up a camera
And get the lights on the instructor so that the
Countenance captured
So I know you said that is
Yeah you just started to get
Comfortable less less anxious six months ago but but I mean
You guys
For profitable relatively early and you have it wasn't you.
But you were profitable by
Yeah I would say we were we were probably cuz we could we could see profitability and in six months I would say we were effectively prop
Truly turned
The prophet book
We would
Be Scrappy enough that the margin in the bike and the proceeds from the
Subscription wood
Started we could see that it was going to pay or overhead
But then we would quickly want to Triple down on
A new product or a new market a new marketing and more higher growth or more stores
And so
We've always needed money
Undergrowth when did the Industrial
You've raised
Billion dollars
When did that turn
The series eat
Date was 2 years ago effectively
When investors started to really see it
And we actually turned down at me for the first five races
We took every dollar we could
From anybody
And that creates a cap table of 300 people
Yes to do Shenzhen individuals
And you know some of them
Are my best friends but I've seen 95%
We are friends but five
Percent of them
4 people you wouldn't want to take money from
But when you don't have an option
Me and are you going to go bankrupt you take money from literally anyone who will give it to you
It's public knowledge
Which store has been publicly discuss that
There's talk of Peloton
Doing an IPO maybe this year and Ikes
Could value it as high as 8 billion maybe more
What do you mean
What what is the vision of where this
Company
Is headed what are you imagine
It'd be coming in 10 years from now
So yeah we we were very excited about the category wheel of fitness
We love
Technology and we love media
But there's a metaphor that Henry ellenbogen at T Rowe Price I put on my radar a couple years ago I thought
Well that's that's good
I had thought of it
But the metaphor was in the 80s you would go to the arcade
And today arcades are gone
Because you have better experiences in your home
Interconnected with the world
Especially now with things like fortnite
We're your friends are in it
So it's social
It's sticky
It's a better location and it's better value
Cuz you're not paying $0.25 every time you die in Galaga
Dating myself
But
So we see a world where few have better Hardware
The best bike of the best treadmill
In a
The best location which is your home and you have great software and your the global community of supportive people
And it's time shifted to a twin you want it
In a why would you travel to an inferior experience with of inferior piece of fitness equipment with somebody else's
Sweat all over it
So we see a world where
Content will evolve
And the programming will evolve
And the software will evolved
The hardware
That you pedal is is a
What
I mean
The company's got this
Huge valuation
It's just
Charging forward has gotten a lot of attention
Does anything keep you up at night anymore are you do you are you feeling like okay thumbs up you know mission accomplished
Now we're not hot. At all
No I honestly believe we're just getting started we we have massive Global ambitions
I think if we do it well
This will be one of the special companies of Our Generation
Answer your question guy what keeps me up at night is
How do we scale our culture
How do you go from two thousand people to 50,000 people in the in the neck
Next five or six years
And still have
The fun.com energy
The that the trough
What's the transparency
Having a fantastic culture where you're able to
Kroot and retain
The best people in the world
Is what
Keeps me up at night how many stores do you now have we have seventy globally
And how many bikes have you sold
Close to half-a-million
Familian pipe
So you've got
Hundred
Thousands of Subs
Scribers around the world
That's right
You said that just a
Few years ago you were like winding down your 401k or thinking about it and
You know kind of freaking out a little bit about
Money cuz he had two kids and
Right you know you're in your mid-forties at that time
Do you feel
More comfortable now you can you kind of feel like all right
I'm going to be you know I'm going to be just fine me a rich guy
I do I do feel more comfortable I'm not comfortable yet
I will tell you my wife gets frustrated with me I spend money as fast as we get it and
I bought my parents at a house they didn't have any money
Thousand we just recently bought my in-laws house
And so I am you know
We don't we don't have much money in the bank account still because I'm
Every time we get any any money we're trying to
Impact the lives of people that have been there for us
So I asked a question and I know that folks
Listen to show I have heard me ask
Gemini I love
This question because I love the different answers
Sandwiches
When you think about all of the things that happen in all of the
Ups and downs cuz it was a grind
Right where you are today and where you might even be in in in fiber
For 10 years from now
How much of this do you think was because of your intelligence in your hard work and how much you think it was
Because it was
Good luck
So yeah
Floodplains of Life part in everybody's life I was lucky to have
Two parents
That Built Me Up and gave me confidence and love me that that is
You hit the lottery when you have
Credit cards
But but I do think like most entrepreneurial Ventures you hear that 1% inspiration 99
10% perspiration
We check our egos at the door
Everyone brings their best self to work
And I think that's how we
Concord a lot of
Okay one last question
3 John 4
If you were sitting in a society
Watching you
You know
10 years ago
What is it that you wish you knew then that you now know
That would have helped
So I was thinking
You're probably looking up here saying I hope I'm not on her 48 years old
My buddy Amar lalvani who's the CEO of standard as old saying
Risk is the Tariff paid to leave the shores of predictable misery
And
One thing I did in the early days it was I just started telling everybody that I was starting this
Everyone would listen I told him starting
4 months
Looking back
I realize that
I have been had to deliver because I would come to ego-driven I wouldn't
You know I couldn't look you in the eye cuz he was like wait a second you said you're going to do that yeah
So I think putting the energy out there
And telling other people get to look gets the momentum going and ends hold you accountable
And I thought that was a that was an important thing for me having the courage which is basically
I just had I had to deliver on my promises
John Foley co-founder Peloton
I spoke with John on April 11th at the BMCC Tribeca Performing Arts Center
York City
And I realize there may be another reason why Peloton is
Caught on so well
No one's going to bother you
Which might
Explain why Peloton has
Army of celebrity Riders
Jackman
Jenna ezarik
Richard Branson
Even Usain Bolt
Hey thanks so much for listening to this
Live episode of How I built this
Our shows produced this week but James delahoussaye with original music
Who's Byron
Bluey
Thanks to our Live Events team in New York Ellie Prescott old Schaller and John Isabella with recording engineer
Isaac Rodriguez
Casey Herman
Energy
Howard Julia Kearney, slim Katie Monteleone or could she needs Grant
Jack Rogers
I'm guy Raz even listening
This
Is NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Built this campaign mode
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email 10
A drag-and-drop email
And customer support
7 days a week