Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is
When is Good Day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim style
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
Before we get to the show
Just a favor
We like to better understand
Who is listening
How we're using podcast
So you can help us out please complete a short Anonymous survey
Npr.org
Podcast
One word
It takes less than 10 minutes and it really helps
Support the show
That's npr.org
Slash
Podcast
I decided to invest in some fundamental research and I wanted ask myself
One question did any retailer in America believe the trampolines were dangerous
So dangerous that was Costco the CEO of Costco
Who was the manager of Senegal and Jim said I will not sell trampolines and
So I made it my mission to try sell Costco trampoline
From NPR how I built this
Show innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements
Elin Professor with
Canadian businessman who believed his potential
Safest
Backyard trampoline
A while back we didn't
Interview with James Dyson and facing a course is the inventor of the Dyson vacuum cleaner
Came up with his vacuum you working
Backyard shed. Prototype
Prototype
Testing
Perfecting his invention
That's a familiar story right
Finding a problem
Tinkering until
Finally
A solution
James Dyson manufactured the vacuum cleaners
Scaled his business and then
Became one of the wealthiest
People in the UK
That's not exactly the typical inventor story because for a lot of inventors the end goal
That someone else will by and take the market
Because a lot of times inventors don't have the
More resources or ability to go into business themselves so we're going to do something
2 stories
Story of one man Keith Alexander who invented a safer trampoline maybe even this
Safest trampoline ever the story of
Steve Holmes the man who took that invention and made it into a commercial success
Because even though Stephen Keith arndt
Technically business partners
Springfree Trampoline couldn't have been a success without one or the other
Keith Alexander grew up in New Zealand
His dad was an engineer
Keith was really sure what
Wanted to do this life
So he joined New Zealand's version of the Peace Corp and fruit
He worked as a grade school teacher
But then
You decided to go back
City university
Canterbury
Christchurch
I found that actually really enjoyed engineering
Yes I started doing my engineering degree at entry
And
Suddenly realized
That was what I
I wish somebody told me many years before that I was an excellent engineer
I found I could
To get iced tea
Quite easily
So I did a masters
And then did a
PhD
I am over you like wait we the kind of engineer who just
Just always love to
I like where you always
10 Greenway
I was always
Can crayfish eat through a PhD
A table like a
Eventually
Tools and
That's right of Beach
Put up a bench somewhere if it wasn't there I had these two wrecks
So I made with all the tools on and I can take them off the wall pick them up text
Well I made all sorts of things did not exhibition
I made a 6
Mousetrap for that
Exhibition a collapsing chair
I made walk on water shoes
Defended myself through my Ph.D by winning
Walk on water pump
Wait sorry
Let's break this down
What's what's walk on water
Walk on water shoes radio Maven which was
The radio in
In Christchurch
The time
Put up this competition I walk on water competition thousand-dollar prize
Sorry
Bay City
Weber competition if you can figure out a walk on water weave
$80,000
That's about it
That's about it okay
At that time my father had
Developing simple car motor
I'm here and I've been playing around with it cuz we had a dinghy
Weeping fig
I have to do this
So that's a tinkering in the garage
You need some flotation
The competition put limits
On how big these
Flotation
Could be so it ended up being
You will not have anything longer than one meter
Didn't take
I need you need to work out how big
Piece of polystyrene at the beach
Okay see you you were coming up with
Some kind of flotation
And you could answer of walk on water
With that device it was balanced that would allow you to kind of
Hover on the surface of the water
Is that the big stick
And
The solution is put your feet on the bottom
You got a hole in it
Can you put the plywood on the bottom
Topeka right through the bottom and then
It stays
The police sirens around rank
And you invented this
Yes my father and I invented this we had to make it fit
The competition
I flew back from Oakland
Got to stay with my parents
And I built these shoes
Competing this
Competition
And I'm headed to win the competition
To using Rock
I didn't want to feed one adult internet help fund my PhD
Because you got a thousand bucks
But it's more like $5,000 wow
So what were some of those things to you
You bet
Willfully at exhibition
Q-Zar
Enduring experiences with having a hiccup
Doing my PhD at University and
Young Tootsie lady was giving me the haircut and she said you realize you're standing on top
It was really embarrassing
So I thought
That would be a good thing for young guys to have because you can never see the top of your head so I made this
Bald patch inspector
Move to leave us NF
It would reflect the other mirror and I could show you the top of your head exact you could see with your going bald
What you do once you finish your PhD
At first I thought
If I want to come back to academic life I really need some engineering
Beard Products Inc, valid
Teacher of engineering Elizabeth
Engineering experience
So with a PhD
You decide I've got to go out
Into the world again
Experience
Before I can come by
Absolutely that's right
So I moved back to Oakland
And
Got a job in engineering
Consultancy
What kind of work did you do
Set it off at the value of a 1 of the value of that I knew nothing about
But valuation was
OK Google looking at a piece of machinery and and working out how much cost
And after two weeks I was getting pretty good at it after 2 weeks I found I could do other things as well
Waiting for consultancy gota variety
Was quite a bit of insurance with the West
Air crash investigation
Fort Worth
As well so it was quite a broad range of
I wasn't particularly happy with
Because it'll comes out of the money in the end it so how much
Have you been up an invoice this week
And I really like spending
Time on things
Put more time into it thinking it through
Just like I guess the
The Miz
1980s
You are
Late 30s early 40s
Jeffrey Berry
I got married
So it was while I was at the engineering
Consultant Seattle
And
Pretty soon after
Yes
Two and a half years later
Your first house
How many kids do you have
Guthrie
So
Amazon
As You Are
Doing consulting
We got a young family
And
This is probably a pretty steady
Lifestyle
Yeah so when you would come over
Your consultancy
Consulting job
Would you come home and then go into your
The workbench area and
Tinker
Match to the grace of my wife is
She took her awhile
Get used to it
So you would like the mad scientist in the back of
Garden working on
Crazy ideas not all the time
Not all the time
Are you really once was
I'm magnetic
Fly machine
Which was supposed to use the Earth's magnetic field to fly but
I was very proud of what I did but it didn't work
Do the laws of physics actually support that idea
Idiots in NBA one of the best ideas would be to go to the South magnetic pole and put a big
Ring of conducting material around the magnetic fields and put a huge current through it and it wouldn't actually flies
Spice
But it's not a very good place for spiced pork
Trying to solve problems like is that right
Exactly how you would
That's pretty good if other people haven't been able to solve it I want to solve it it's a real charge me that's something
Excites me no one else has done that's all I want to do this because no one else has done it
What was it eventually
When I was a kid I'd love to trampoline I just love the idea of being in the airport
You couldn't buy a trampoline in those days
Elizabeth a gymnastics trampoline I wish we had one of the school and then the gym class
To get city kids there and we had to get on jump three three bouncy seat drop get off next bus that was
Is it that was my jumping and I love this
Yeah and that really frustrated me
So when I start to become available in the shops
And I had a young child
Going to get one of these
Young and I'll be able to bounce on at 2 and so I said to my wife to get a trampoline
The Katy
She said
No I take it a place in town they don't have it trampoline place either they just too dangerous
Does it snow today
And she said trampolines not safe I think I'll just
Look at the research
See what I can find
So I looked at the research
Sure enough
Even in New Zealand that being some research
Fishtown on the increase
Injuries from trampoline
And I thought well I really
Maybe I can do something about it I'm an engineer should be able to do something about
And that's that's when it started
So you look as research
And you
You realize your wife is right
Things were not
My wife is right dammit
But you wanted a trampoline and you wanted one for your daughter
Scientifical way around that
So what you do
South Hill Rite boat
If I can design
Joshua trampoline
It's pretty simple
Shirley Arkansas fair catch the engineering
And I love designing things like this.
So we are going to do it
Let's design one that she likes it
And maybe you can even sell it
I don't know
To take me back to that
You're thinking
I want to see if I can
Top with a
Trampoline
Where do you start
I mean to you
What's the time
Easily available
Why did you even start to
Think about
How you do this
Right so going to come up with the trampoline what what are the issues here that we have to solve
Annnd
Traditional trampoline is God steel bar around the outside agent
Springs
What decided and then the math is Jump On In The Middle
And I can see that it's dangerous cuz the exit right to going off on his
Pretty obvious
You give this nice bouncy things
The kids and I know about celebrity knocked loose
Ctrl + f4 on the bottle that fell down the hole between the spray
So are they fall off
When I pull up
But the thing that probably hit first is distilled out on the edge
That's the thing that impressed me most I thought that still bad it's not fair
Let's see if we can get rid of that steel Bob that's that's a good step
So I'm thinking about
Inflatable things are soft
Why do we replace
The steel frame with an inflatable ring
Just like a big inner tube and it's stretched
The trampoline
Mets roster
Would that work
OIC like a giant
Heavy duty dinnerware
2 Tire
And then you would have like a
Canvas
Inside of it in
In this spring apart would come from the inner tube
At first I thought Rockwell put Springs on
American foot rope around a to hold this
Spring so we could talk
I have the Met
Connected to the Springs at so I sketched this up and I got to Kansas
I need to make a map
Full mean I got some
Trampoline springs in summer
A bar
The coolest Seabiscuit a big inflatable
Like a zodiac book circular
From the tennis company actually
At that time
My son was at 2 and 1/2 years old
He bounced thought he could bounce a little life was only about the height of it
Cheer
Selfie kid
Fell off they didn't have far to go and the edge was
Inflatable on salt lamp
You actually literally made this you stretched canvas over the giant rubber tire
Thingy thing
And I and you had your kids Jump On It.
First one has built one
So the one that we
Only made a couple thousand dollars for
Just had the Met
Selling into that
Top page of this big ring
And that was good for the kids at the time
And your wife was happy with that shoot
Is totally comfortable with us he was really happy with that this is something the kids could actually
Pick up and cut around the backyard and this is like how big was it that was about 8 feet across
The Mets score
Five feet because it was on the top of it
The big
Problem with it well several big problems that number one the material cost for that was about $800
The back of that time just the material cost to put is no Manufacturing in that it
Always late there's always someone supposed to be
Didn't matter how many times I put in a pot inside to find a leak there's a problem to problems there a problem
It just wasn't I mean I couldn't get any height on this did not bring you back to your school
Days we had those three jobs
Fly
3 is all you don't want to jump into hot
So it was great is great for the kids to have it
It wasn't what I wanted
You start to realize that the same as just knocking
This is not
Going to be the saying that
Makeup be fun for a while for the kids but
Stipulated
Can jump very high
And anyway you can Market
So what are you do you go back
To you or to the garage
Start again
Well around about that time I
I sat down on
Summarize all the skates
Cuz I got no lie ideas I got
This is not down
They all got to come up with other ways of doing
I went through a whole range of ideas
And came up with
Civil court
Complicated ways of using
So I just stages
Working at the University kind of job
Christchurch
Entrust your teaching mechanical engineering I'm assuming
I had a contract on you contract it wasn't a full-time job so I didn't have tenure
But I had a job there
And that meant that I could for educational paper
Just give students projects
Yeah the final year of engineering
The students get individual project
How did we go to Hold Ya
So I put that up as a
Project he's an idea for making a trampoline
Completely differently woodspring some
Why what can you do as a
16 but can you come up with
Suggested just to get a sense of Oneness is were talking about
Mid-1990s
Like 95-96 more and then
I start at University in 96
I ran a couple of University projects
96-97
And
I getting pretty close guidelines cuz it's a lot of thought into it he's away I think we could do it
Could you build one
How could you do the analysis on us
And at that
Time
I had the
I did in my mind and I found it very difficult to measure never seen anything like it was a bit like a boss
It with the
These at these are things I like fishing rods
Obviously if you
Go to fish on the envy
Fishing with a fishing rod
It'll keep sensational
Maybe I can make one like that
What is an out of that material
Something like five
Fiberglass Rocket fishing rod
Material and I thought well if you stuck at a fishing rod on the ground of Italy on your stuff another one over here and you're tied something
Between them you get the tension but then that's sticking out these things
The sticking straight up but if you are on a trampoline on
On the top of you fell on it
Because the vertical if you fell right on the edge you can pause your cell phone
So what if we laid them over
So that that 45 degrees
Then if you landed on them
So that was the idea
Suggestive pictures my mine
Yes it was
Could you get some kind of a tree looks
Let's go fishing rod
Lakeshore Drive
Yeah
At an angle of 45° in a circle
And stretch canvas over that
And essentially
That would be the tree
Bounce on the canvas
That was laid over these
Tangled
Rods that
That were bendy
That that's a pretty good description of
So yuan
Students working on a prototype of the snood
Trampoline design
Diamond full size vans 8-foot diameter
How to work using using those like
Fiberglass
Fishing rods the fiberglass rod
That's why I was sitting it was more bouncy than the inflatable one so it's going in the right direction
Exactly there yet
Yes you're right I was thinking I need to get a commercial pissing involved at this stage
I don't know whether it's going to be commercial no idea let's contact someone
I want to ask you about
I would imagine was like obligation which is at this point
Yuan
Keith Alexander
Backyard speaker you are also Keys Alexander
Professor at this University
What that mean about all the work you do
University
It's their property
Mighty you are
Stanford Harvard or whatever
That's exactly what I'm supposed to be doing is
Publishing paper
They did have this
New policy that just came in
Couple months after I started they said if you come up with an idea that's commercialized
Got until this new commercialization office
It would just developed
Now that you've done it
Because it belongs to University
100%
Or am I thought while I haven't already thought of this
I'll be doing this at home for a while
And now got a job with University
Well icon
I got to do that
They say then I had to do it
So now every idea you have
They are which is not uncommon
It's not uncommon
So I went along with it
I'll let them have it
If I can commercial Isaac
So I took it to them
Show them listed all that's fine
Kids toy
See what we can do
Which but in the meantime they
They were just like you do whatever you want
They were not paying attention
Dental painting
And that what they wanted this summer
I was going to make
Millions of dollars
Really want a child
They want like a
Biotech
Something
Trampoline World
These guys working on
Nanotech
So I looked in the Yellow Pages
I found the biggest trampoline manufacturer in New Zealand
He was selling 400 trampolines
I bring them up
And he said yeah I'm interested send me some photos
I'll be in Christ you still coming over look
3 time
And I had them all day from
He jumped on them
He said well the inflatable one
I like that
But not as a trampoline
I like
It's a great pool toy
The one with the ROTC
Compromise
To live
It's got to be hot going to be dangerous
Make the kids think it's
That's going to be bigger Saatchi small-cell want something is 10
And it's go to
Take down so it can be shipped
So you have to be able to pull apart and assembly
And it's
It's got to be able to be assembled by a solid matter with no Tools in half an hour
On Christmas Eve after
She's at a glass of wine
Because I always get people ring me open Christmas Eve saying how do I say move my trampoline
So if you can sort out those problems I'll be in
And you thought
I don't like it is a challenge
And we got company now disinterested
And I'll pay one of these students who've was happy to work out a summit to build this 10-foot version and see what we can do
So that's what we did over the next year we had this
Waking why he built up the 10-foot trampoline that was high
Make a test that we can put on a pot
Put together again
Put it on two boxes
We couldn't assemble it in half an hour
It was another company in in New Zealand it was
Pain specialist in completely fiberglass
Used as a spring Springs
So we started forming a relationship with then
They formed a relationship with him
Andis company in food making 450 into you
Had we started to
Build
The prototypes for customer files
But for the typo customer trial
And had it turned off
I was pretty pleased with what we were going to Market at this stage because I had a commercial person
By products of potassium
And the guys from the commercial arm of the University came out and have a look because it was a bit of material going on
They look at it and they said
Unicellular
Thousand hundred thousand dollars to make it ready
And then I went away
The university said
Yeah
So what
Does that mean
Well
I thought that was the end of it
Really I thought
I can't get a hug
The $50,000 I thought it was market-ready
I was very depressed
And you needed the universities
Permission B
Because they owned it
They only I bet they owned it
I didn't have to do any more I was doing all this work
Supervising this
How to get the money to
To support
Making these customer trial
So the dream
Dice
Well I thought so
But
I always
Do you like challenges
And my mother-in-law
Tearing up
To talk to my wife and when she
Get me on the phone should say
Auntie's house that trampoline going
I hope you still working on
So
This was an idea I really wanted
This is a problem in the world that needed to be solved
Hilltop glass safe
I've got to do something about this I'll just have to keep going
Around this time the commercial out of the University hide another person and he died
And he had a look around New Zealand trying to find is there any business in New Zealand or interested and
Canada found someone in Canada case we got someone to Canada
Cinema photos
And we'll see where we go from here when we come back
Almost 15 years after he started tinkering on a new safer kind of trampoline
He gets to see his invention finally come to Market with us
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this
Running PR
Support also comes from Choy salad
An original podcast
Charles Schwab
On the latest episode
Boise allergy
You'll hear a classic psychology
Experiments retool
William is an opera
Who enjoys visiting art museums on vacay
And is an average chest
Is it more likely
That William is a professional violinist
In a major Symphony Orchestra
Or a farmer
Listen to find
Schwab.com
Or wherever you listen
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
To design and build their own website
Using customizable leg
And features including e-commerce functionality
3 + mobile app
Squarespace also offers
Chris built and search engine optimization
To help you develop an online price
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off you
Your first purchase of a website or domain
Welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
It's early two thousands and
East University find an investor who's interested in the trampoline
Steve Holt
At this point
Steve's in his mid-30s he's living in Toronto
He's already been involved in a couple of successful small business
Help Steve know some investors
And he's got access to a little capital in eventually Steven teeth
To start discussing the details
A piece of mention the end of the phone call I remember saying okay Keith can you mail it to me can you send it
Shipley the trampoline
Just shoot me the Tramp
Pause
The money was an issue right now, going to ship the traffic keeps Private Ryan figure I said I'll send you ten
$1,000 will you shoot me the
What do you remember about that call it was is similar like you were on the phone with Steve and you just kind of explained
This invention to it
I find it pretty hard to remember I was breathing
It's about anything like that
Fitbit cool would have made me
But a freak me out
Yeah and
Shipping something overseas
I didn't even know that you have to dial 0 0 1 2
Comerica theater
What are things that didn't like
Calibration David Steve says I'm sending
Antenna you got $10,000 so you can
Do what
Needs to be done to get me in
Information that I need and get me a trampoline
And I didn't have that for the money
When someone says please ship it to the other side of the world has a big deal
And when someone says I'll give you a $10,000 that was a big deal
So are you so so how long does
To take
Fort arrive
What's 6 weeks in shipping I can't remember if we are afraid or not but we at the time had a backyard
We really didn't have any grass that was a problem we had patio and so
When I got it
It was a little overwhelming so I assembled it it probably took me a boat
3 hours
And
Several bruises
End
My kids interesting that is deaf
The time of 1614 and
12 and so my 12 year old.
Jump time
And she loved it
Alright so so so she
She's jumping up and down this thing
And you realize
From that
Maybe there's something to this
You know
When it comes to good ideas I believe you measure it by the reaction of the people you hope to sell
And it wasn't a kid in the neighborhood who didn't want to jump on
Everybody came to your backyard
Well anybody that we let in
And so you get caught up in the enthusiasm of your kids
When did diapers switch coffee
Your mind were you
You thought okay
I meant
I need to pursue this because at this point
You sent $10,000
You did not have a business
The university didn't
You own this patent nothing you just had
One really great trampoline your backyard
Yep
You had a prisoner a lot
To consider before you invest the money and buy this
YouTube
Find out
How much wood ash
Foxy costume
Manufacturer
Is you have to model this out where this was going to be a viable business
Did you do that
We did
October 2002 we had
Secure the paint
Effectively a letter-of-intent agreement-in-principle we had locked up some
Some period of time
And first thing we did
Was we went to the Super Show
In Las Vegas Nevada which is like a toy know it was used to be the Sporting Goods manufacturing association
This is a 2000 January of 2000
I went to see what the reaction
Built wanted
Can you display that there we built one
We took a prominent
Spotted
The show we hired some dancers from Siegfried and Roy 2BR jumpers along with my daughters
My youngest daughter and her three friends and we just said
Like this is go big or go home
Did you
How big
What is the trampoline
Market
Well I would have said it was pretty small I think that we had measured that we thought the
But the trampoline Market
That maybe it was a five to six
600 million-dollar trampoline
Tea Market globally
So you were looking for
Bite out of
5 / 600
Diamond ever been greedy
A small business can be a good boy
I guess we took a philosophy internally which was to think big
But start small
And so we try
What was it what was the reaction at the show Awkward people say to
What was really quite amazing actually we had lots of different react
When's the first we had was from a retailer who came up and said will you can't sell this in America you don't have an enclosure
And I said will hold out an enclosure is in bed
Try this again but no retailer will sell a trampoline without an enclosure
I had somebody come up to me and said you know I have
Patent
On the enclosure and you'll never sell this product in America
Ever quote on the enclosure
And then I had the at the time the CEO from what was
Very large Sporting Goods retailer come up to me and said you know this may be the most Innovative product we seen
The show in years
Seawalker that show and what are you thinking so I decided to in
Invest in some fundamental research and I wanted ask myself one question did any retailer in America
Believe the trampolines were dangerous
But they wouldn't answer.
The CEO of Costco was a man of Jim sinegal and Jim said I will not sell trampolines
Wow
End
So
I made it my mission to try and sell Costco Tramp
Okay but before we get to Costco
So
At what point did you say alright I'm going in
We're going to get this we're going to buy the
Traffic we are finished
I was advancing all of this
Very quickly I think contractually was all locked up I probably met of Oats
And what did it cost you
To be honest guy I wouldn't even remember the number
More than billion dollars
Yes
More than willing.
Buy everything when everything was all said and done all the settlements
What is a Keith
You are a professor at the University
You come up with an invention they sell the patent
To Steve and
You get a check for
Yes the arrangement with the universe
Was stuck
What do you eat pine wood
Facebook three wise
That was huge
I'm curious at this point did you
When did you have to deal with the fact that
Answer right
Lights are sold to someone else in and now like
Detestable
Naked
That's right
That was
A very sobering
And I thought
Yeah
Okay I guess that's the way it is
I guess I can let it go now
I don't feel like it but I guess that's the way it goes
Do the chick coming in
I've got to think about this
Alan Steve Steve
I'm going to need a
A bit of a helping hand cuz I don't have any
Trampoline engineer
Do you mind giving me a hand with this
Give me some technical input
Yeah yeah
Fine okay
Yeah and
And that came in fairness you know what Keith and I had a conversation once about risk and reward
So I asked
What level of risk are you willing to take
Versus the
Economic rewards you expect
And he said
I have
I don't want any rest
Yeah I want I don't want any red
We reached an agreement at that point as to what his role would be and how he would
Be compensated
So it was good
Pizza Steve you are
Running a business
Canada and Keith you are
Still in New Zealand
Consulting on the
What was the next step
Well Keith Knight created the
Springfree enclosure
We kept looking at all of the principles of art design and said
Better be soft
It can't be hard and everybody had produced enclosures with steel poles
We kept looking at this American Peyton and say we can't infringe this
So we didn't sell any products we didn't make any products we just spent a year building an enclosure for the spread for bread
Left that convention Las Vegas determine that you had to solve this problem
But if you were going to make this thing
As safe as possible
It had to be enclosed
That's it
And we decided that we would give ourselves a deadline
The deadline would be the January Super Show
Bealls in Orlando Florida in January of 04
2004 Super Show
What made the enclosure different how are you able to create this thing that
So Steve said now that a relation
Skip to the people that make people treated fiberglass
You've got to make the towels out of the
Sign material
I'll see what they need to be strong enough to hold this meeting
We can try
Had a post-grad student needed some money so he's working in our backyard we got these 12 of these
Around the trampoline fitted on and tie the top of them together with with some cold let's see
See what happens first grade student
Local fishermen people around the place you can get some Nation after that for days he come back with some fish
The last all day at the top of the bottom said it was Wallace like that
Enclosure and innocence different than the ones directly but it was this really flexible thing
So then when I came home from University and the kids was still on it that were bouncing off the walls
Running into it and bouncing off and I'm thinking hey this is really something we didn't expect
Can you play Sofia the other trampolines. Have we might a rubber room now this is white
It's not just the safety day this is another places
So you got the enclosed
Trampoline you're ready to introduce us to the world
2004 go to the Super Show in Orlando Florida
They had a competition there which was called the product of the Year basically
And if you got to a finalist or the top 10 you would be displayed in a specific area of
Super Show independent of your booth
So we made all the applications necessary and
We became final
This was the unveiling
Springfree
This was it
And how did you do how many
What did you get the orders
Well
We got One Import
Buy Costco Canada
Wow
Excited okay if we do it in Canada that doesn't seems not as litigious they're all really nice people there they don't seem to sue each other maybe we'll
Try it again
And they put a test in for an Essence it worked out that we put in a test
Let's try selling
400 unit
The first word was 400 pieces on a trial
And you see Rugby's first 400 units we made August 480 or 400
Nadia think something like that in New Zealand
With one container
One container load was the retail price for
Drug that time the retail price we put it out to kannur was 999
Just to just to
Clarify something
This was at that time going to be one of the most
Expensive trampolines right so it was a big risk
And you had to make the case that this was
Worth the cost
Yeah I mean our value proposition
We had that very first product
Orlando is the same as what is to
Which is that we provide the world's safest trampoline we producing out of the highest quality materials we give the longest
Warranty
10 year warranty on everything
It's still that today and that was what we kept selling on the retailer side
But you are selling them
99 bucks
Aston Martin
Fly costume
It was more than that
We were losing money on every Pro
We had to do that to find out if we
Create a marker
All right so they roll them out and Costco
And how did they do
Move very fast very very fast
Jodi Duplantis second-order
Well because we've put it on a test and that was the spring of that year
The next recurring order wasn't going to really take
Play some filler neck Spring by which was 05
So that it was oh crap what do we do between now and then
Because you would
Generate some Revenue in New Zealand which is presently expensive
Transition right about that
We knew we couldn't continue as they were costing about 1400
$50 to make one to make one
And so we knew we couldn't continue in one of the things that I didn't realize at the Super Show in 20
AO3 2003 I said to you that I had people come up to me various things I'd an individual come out to me
With a business card who said I manufacture Sporting Goods in China
If you ever need a manufacturer call me
And
When we reach the stage with Costco at the end of before we said
Okay we got Mexico
Which I have to assume was going to be
Because it's going to reduce your costs.
Well here was the thing that was so critical to ashes the key scipy was
That was essential we had to make sure we could get intellectual property
Protection but the China everything
Not everything
XVideos
Be careful and we had to be careful and the other thing is that the rods that
The keypad unwarily
They were all about technical know-how
So we weren't prepared to move that so even to this day
Most of the original
Manufacturing components
The rods
And the net
Material
Can we use we are using the exact same manufacturing partner
They've come a long way.
Through the whole journey
We've never deviate
Or not but we moved
All of the Steal
100%
Out of the labor
Associated with
Producing an assembly into China
Alright SUB-2000
You got to wait till 2000
Five four
Big order
How many people are on
Where I think at that point we
Between our Engineering Group
Our sales teams
We might have been 35
And you're burning through cash
Yeah we were burning car
We were hanging on
No I was running my payables long we were hanging on for that
Costco delivery
In Spring 05
Soaps when Costco came back to
Spring of 05
What code to be about 3265 p
65 pieces
Finance that right cuz it'll tell you first do they pay you like
That's right so we we I hit the street and found
Found somebody who
Bought into a Costco.
So so this is somebody in this is interesting this is somebody who
Looks
For people like you who
Get a get a purchase order from Costco
Need financing actually make
The product and I'll loan you the money at a high interest
The high interest rate
Yeah
That was your life
It was our Lifeline in it and it could be fairness
To this day
It is the reason we survived in store and thrive
Even though that order along with
Make it profitable you know you're a long road to go we weren't
But but
Prove that we
Because Costco representative Mike bigger animal than just Canada we went from Costco Canada
To Costco
UK is UK was beautiful being safe we got to go from Costco Canada to Casa
Japan which made no sense to us we didn't really know what we're going to do in the pad but we end up selling 370 trampoline
And then we got to go on Costco.com there eCommerce
New platform for them not in store in 2007 I guess it was
Costco is Pinellas point up until 2007 your biggest
Contract virtually in in the Northern Hemisphere and then are only
I we were selling Direct in places where we could but they were basically 90% of our distribution
You are now in this thing 2008 please stop this
Translate
Did I was probably the hardest
So what happened
Is there as we got more and more and more
Successful with
With the product and cost
Some of the buyers they were really proud
So they would
Show off
The product
In a real
Flamboyant where you don't have any
Prominent position inside inside a Costco
Mr. Senegal was
He opened every cost
Costco open
And there was a big opening at Halifax Nova
Scotia on
May 13th
It was a Wednesday 09 never forget the date and it might be
This is Chris
And he'd gone to the store at the time he was still opposed
Even though we are being really successful
He was still uncomfortable
And so what he walked in the Halifax store
I got a phone call from the president at the
The time of Canada Costco
And they said
We're done
And they said we're done
I said no no no I don't understand we're not how can we be done and then we just get the part guy which is
In 2008 we decided to build their own Factory in China because we were satisfied with the quality so I invested
$5000000 in building a Chinese Factory
We did it because this was God's go we're going to be in store this was going to change the face of everything that's so weird
We open that factory on October of 2008 and all in preparation for a
Pro 2009 with Costco and on the May 13th we were told we're done and it was just cuz they
Play Gone overboard in that store that made the trampoline one of the single biggest highlights in this grand opening and how
Fun facts
And he was just pissed because it was so
Present invisible
He walks in there it says
What is the trampoline doing in the center of my Costco
You really knew I think we were below the radar great numbers weirdo great numbers for sporting goods
So I was told if you need to talk to mister
You got a call on a Saturday morning in Seattle
Was given a telephone number to his direct dial to his death
Called Saturday morning shaking in my boots I call
He was extremely polite
Sheraton
Reasoning within reason and he said I have made my decision, but I will honor any purchase orders
That we have issued
Up until the end of this
So he purchase orders that are issued up until the end of the month
It will honor those
The phone and I went
Oh crap
And my next call is to
Every Costco buyer Act
Give me a PO Diffie
Cuz you know you got a month left
I had less
I had to salvage
Spell the 16th of May
It was a Saturday morning
And when
At 14 days
Pio's took longer than that
To get usually
Wow
So what you do
Where was really good business skills learning
Session I step back and I said okay we have a product that has unbelievable safety
The quality and innovation
6 we have customers who love our products
I mean
Our best marketing is on existing Springfree cost
Springfree customer has a Springfree Trampoline
If a parent who says why I really don't like trampoline still sell it
Each other friends and neighbors and 50% of our sales came from our customers so we said
Wherever spring trees are in backyards we have to make
It really easy
In our biggest Market
The time based on
Costco delivery address
This was California
MCI
So we opened our own
First Springfree retail store
On the off ramp
Of the Costco has
Insead
In Seattle so Islands in mm
Well this is a late 2009
So there you had
Showroom
Could try it
Kids jumper
We called it the we called it the Springfree experience
And that store proved to be
Phenomenal
Only successful
We were blowing the doors off the profit
And we're just going like there was I think there was very few retail stores that were doing
The profit per square foot that we were doing out of that store at store
Sell these things like this we are great dealer Network we established
Quick as we could in the US they had trampolines on Parade floats
They went to every Fair they went to every neighborhood they connected with the communities because we knew where we had ship
We had we had these weather it was a pop-up store or whether it was a permanent experience Center we went
The consumers we went out there we'd the shows we had the stores and show that there was a business model which was
Different than Costco
So we took a direct-to-consumer model and we use Keith as the face of the organization
So he was the one who conveyed
The story
The the attributes and the commitment to safety and quality silkie
So all the sudden like you've got to represent this
Product right to the world
The media interviews
Letv
You are a self-described introvert
I Can Only Imagine
Yeah
Hey yeah you're right you're right Steve
Did give me warning
He said what would you like to be the Dyson
What are the two mean
Would you know Dawson Dawson vacuum cleaners
Sewing head looking this
Dawson doing his thing I thought
I suppose I could do then
If I come across well you know maybe they can use it maybe it'll help with selling so
I said yes.
So then he says Rockville
Come to Toronto
We got to have a week
And we can
Filming
And I'm thinking
But this is big deal this is not just
102 little
Afternoon
Choose one of the scariest weeks of my life.
So end up
In Toronto
In this big Studio
And find myself with
3 cameras
And lights
People around
Microphones in front of me and I said what we just talk
And you didn't
Cytokine NSA
Will you come across really genuine you know you
You really come across well
And how did it come out
Phenomenal
It was okay and you didn't
I mean it sounds like you were actually
Expanding pretty fat
Yeah we're over 400 employees
Oregon expands to that number of employees years before that
Costco pulls out
You know
Sometimes you do stupid things
What we did is
We decided to cook on home and Costco pulled out but we actually went deeper
So we increased our commitment in the factory
China we increased our Direct
Strategy we increased our ability to open and direct retail stores to raise money
Fortunately enough we had we have been reasonably wise
We've been saving for those expansion opportunities and rainy days so we needed to raise I would probably
Invested maybe 5 to 7 million dollars in the factory Construction in a couple more million into
Dollar stores
I think we had a debt raised in about time $3000000
Even maybe two thousand ten years but we didn't stop investing the car said like
This is that risk we kept thinking that that opportunity to big big opportunity was
When did you start to see that life 2010-2011
2011 to 2013 were phenomenal years for us within the global.
Will I get lots of credits Keith
His design was
Always flowers
So that issue of safety that we kept talking about
We now had
8 years of experience
So instead of saying we're the world's safest trampoline but we've only sold 2,000 you know we were actually saying we've got a couple hundred
Thousand trampolines out there and
We actually have some
Statistics now in key started writing research papers and
Have a measuring RC
Statistics and we were going you know
We remove 90% of the
Product related injury
So
He's taking his designers remove 90% so we got that message out
Kiss videos in the way we distributed them
And we got traction
And we got real traction
How much how much does a
Springfree Trampoline cost
Where are we having six different sizes fit ranges anywhere
I'm probably yes 1602 $2,400 so this is
Premium Prada
Very
Make for a while
Yeah Keith always said that whenever he put a Springfree into somebody's backyard and I've agreed with them and we've continued that it should be.
That's it they should pay the money
It should go in the backyard.
Zero maintenance cost
And there should be
It support Costco in other words
If they got a problem
We back at so we have a 10-year warranty on
The whole bra
And how are you selling
On average in a year
You know we look at that you know are probably 30,000 is our annual volume and and we build our business Ma
All around that we've had years that have gone much higher and we've had some years it a little lower to based on some of the economics
I mean we open the factory 2008 we lost Costco and there's a global financial crisis
Cuz I can tell you that wasn't the best year
Yeah I'm so weak we had a tough
You want me to talk to you that might have been a 18000 piece year
I can only imagine is first
456 years
Does non-stop
Just non-stop
Hustling
Working
Try to get this out to Market
Calling
People getting rejected
People send you why are trampoline who chooses what are you talking about no they're not safe
NN is it
Is it still like that today
You know for some of our staff there's no question but it's fun like I got to tell you you know
You want to be in a fun business be the trampoline business cuz there's never been a circumstance work when the mom and dad
I'd have to see their kid on the trampoline for the first time after they've made him a Springfree purchase that they don't go
Straight most people don't know we exist but when they see us they go
I got it
Do you have a trampoline at the headquarters in Toronto
Yeah every every one of our offices has trampolines absolutely in the Wii then other constantly being used
Austin various forms board meetings
At we do at the you can see some office meetings it'll occur on a trampoline
We're still a 1/2 time
Trampoline camping
So well
So do you
Do you consider yourself
To belie
Lucky that
Cannabis business is managed to
Become no sustainable over or do you think it's because of your
Intelligence in and hard work
Why don't nobody
The Intelligencer
But
Due respect
For the employees of organization
And for my wife
And my kids who suffer
To the early days this is been about hard work
I was very poor
Fortunate to meet Doctor
Keith Alexander
But being fortunate was
What about a lifelong friend that I got
And Keith what are you like
Do you feel lucky that all this
What happened
Amazing kisses
Prodigy
Persistence and perseverance and Grit
It's it's both of those
The closest both of those I do feel very lucky to have met someone like
Divas
Being prepared to be
Very persistent
Otherwise I like to think of it
For me the invention process as my part of it is that it's it's like having a child
Conception is quite exciting and he is that eventually it
Stuff to make people of all the time and then you get lice control this list control and
Booyah child meats and where they go and how they grow up it's not very much can you control it all as Allah
Roblox
The customers let Steve Alexander
Picture of the Springfree Trampoline and Steve homes the CEO of spring free
Professor of mechanical engineering at the University of Canterbury in New Zealand
According to company Springfree has sold over 400,000 trampolines worldwide
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Hear from you about
The things your building
The first
I quit thanks to her
How I built this lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing radical easy
Big thinkers
Focus on developing Big Ideas
Try for free at campaign monitor. Com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and your business
Hey thanks for sticking around because
How you go back
Is it a story starts in the winter of 2015
Cindy heilman just move to Toledo Ohio
Twitter husband Chris grew up in Sydney was having a hard time just feeling super
Almost like depressed about the winter
Florida
To Ohio is kind of bit of a culture shock
So gloomy
Being from Florida
Cindy needed warmth and Light
And lots of candles which meant lots of leftover candle containers
If they were in glass jars I would hold on to them
In a cabinet we buy candles and say okay this is an early night
IPod with music
What are Q-tips and we can use it for something around the house
Ceramic containers I would normally put a plant in it
And we have
Tons of houseplant
This went on for two Winters
Cold weather
Candles
Candle containers
By March of 2017 there was one big change
Cindy had become a stay-at-home mom which was great
Except for the weather
So one day the friend sent her a card to cheer up I was wondering why I had
Somebody like little
Boxing.
Onnit those bumps and dots were actually seeds
They were embedded in the paper and instead of
Rolling the cart away
Cindy could soak it in water
Put it in a
Planter and grow wildflowers
I just thought it was the coolest thing ever
And
I must have felt lucky to happen
The same time City found a bluish gray planter pot and she really wanted to use it
Oh I can put some candle wax
Finesse and
Just try and make a candle she said hey
You tell these
And I got to do the math my head is like that's going to have to be
$30 can I pay $30 for handle
You just bought me a $30 candle last week another idea
They can make a candle in a planter pot
And then
Use that paper with the seeds embedded in it
For the label people be able to grow wildflowers after they're done with the container so they don't have to throw it away
So they got to work
We had no idea what we're doing we're just watching a bunch of YouTube videos
Different
Pinterest ideas on DIY how to make a
Handle 2 months of melting wax all over based
Cindy figured it out
And then Chris said okay we think it's a good idea but will it actually
Sell so they went to a trade show to find out
I was really Blown Away by
How emotionally invested people got into our product
A lot of
The guys
They would have their girl with them like this is so cool product isn't it
Do you want one and that day they sold every single one of their candles and
Covered all their expenses
And made $8,000 profit is also a couple days worth of work and that was enough reason for Krista
To consider quitting his banking job because Chris and Cindy have been thinking about starting a business together for years
So we were in a really good financial position to be able to
Take this type of Step so it really didn't feel very risky toss at all until Chris left his job and join.
Cindy in their basement
They took $4,000 out of their savings to buy waxwing
Pots and see paper
In the 850
Candles
Amber 5 months at more than a dozen trade shows they sold
Every single one of them
I mean it's backbreaking work going to these trade shows every weekend because
Remember we don't have weekend working really long days and then we get back it's okay we have to make a ton of candles so we can beer
Rate for next week of the next event
Over the past year Chris and Cindy moved their business online
$50,000 loan to
Scale-up
They hired some employees and even move their little
Candle making factory out of their basements
Is married business partners
They're still struggling to find the right balance
Having a business out of her home for the past year has been a huge
Difference
We just pick you know two or three nights out of the week like okay these two or three nights after idling goes to bed we're going to work on our
Business and the other nights it's just about us when I can talk about business and it's going to be all about family
Survivor Founders Chris
And Cindy Holman if sold more than 12,000 rowing candles you want to find out more about them
Or hear previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course if you want to tell us
Your story go to build. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts while you're there please do give us a review you can also write to us at
HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet to get asked how I built this
Our show was produced this week by Kacey Herman with music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Kearney JC Howard nor could she Neva Grant Melissa Grace Anna's meshkinpour
And Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Candice Lim
I'm guy Rising even listening how I built this
This
Is NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Built this campaign mod
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com