I quit thanks to
How I built this
Sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing radical
Big thinkers
Can focus
Developing
Big Ideas
Try for free at campaignmonitor com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and your business
Unforgettable
So before we got to show I want to tell you about a
You how I built this live shows
Attend
East Coast this fall
Supported by American Express
First I'll be heading to New York
September 10th probably talking with Chris
Christina Tosi of Milk Bar
At Town Hall
And then I'll head to Washington DC on
September 12th
With Tristan Walker of Walker & Company at Lincoln Theater
Get your tickets and find out more about our Live Events including a
3rd East Coast show
That will be announcing very soon
At NPR presents. Org
And I
Hope to see you there
Okay so
If you wanted to you could
Literally fast forward almost any point
In this hour long episode
Almost any point and hear different
Incredible story about how Gary hirshberg almost
Lost his company almost failed
It is venture
Listen to the whole thing start to finish
I guarantee it is
Totally worth it
This episode first ran back
October of 2017 is
F&n
Hope you enjoy it
On many occasions I would tip toe over
To the office to
To call my mother-in-law to have a chat to see if I could borrow another 3520 500 to make ends meet
And one night I heard the Click Click of call waiting on my mother-in-law's phone and Meg was calling from the house to say
Mom don't do this but your wife was telling her mom not to lend you money for the business
It sounds like she will she had no reason
NPR
I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movements they go
Farmers & Accounting lillybelle
Barn
And threw it into Stonyfield
One of the biggest yogurt brands
In America
All the stories that we told on the show so far
I think it's fairly safe to say that Stonyfield yogurt has had more ups and downs
Really more down
Then just about any other
And it's a pretty unlikely tale to begin with
2ego hippie farmers
With no real desire to build a cup
Wind up
Building a company
They start small
Milking their own cows making their own yogurt selling locally
The nun
And then eventually
Spreading themselves
Wait
Too thin
And sliding into
Deep.
A whole slew of near-death experiences
Ever
White died in the second group
Hebrew into water the most
Popular yogurt brands
In the United States
And one thing about Stonyfield co-founder Gary hirshberg is that
Even though he didn't really set out to build
The company
He knew what it took to run one
Because
When he was growing up in Manchester New Hampshire
His dad owned and ran a pretty big shoe company
You know it was in those days they were probably
50 shoe manufacturers in New Hampshire alone
And probably
150 in New Hampshire Maine and Vermont
So how many people did your dad's company employ
Several thousand I think at their Peak they were at the 2800
Wow
These are true company Champs
Course in those days manufacturing was going to the state
Was built in the in the region of the country were built on things that we made
The dark side of that is that when they
Essentially
Get because of Cheaper labor from abroad when the domestic
Shoe industry collapse
No all these communities did as well
And what happened to your family
Well it was really a 303 for the family's business
Went bankrupt
My parents got divorced
And my childhood role model
A died suddenly of spinal meningitis how it was a
It was a wake up here
I mean did your lifestyle change
Overnight cuz I will probably pretty
Prosperous
Family iPhone
Yeah that we were certainly comfortable I was a ski racer I
You know I wasn't
Every worrying certainly about the next meal or bend in
Getaway
Travel up north on weekends for skiing we had a
Home on a lake
But yeah it it you know the world I mean I think everybody at 14
Deneb conscious
Sting
Starts to
Edit your life
Undergoes
Changes better my case they were kind of expedited
My father I got it and began drinking
And so I had to ask her to confront
All of that
And
You know watch to sort of all the rocks
Just suddenly turned to mush
Hear my mom became a single mom with 5 kids I was the oldest and how does she support you what is she
Well yes okra
Again because
My dad's
Business
It was gone now
You know there was a huge amount of tension there was lots of battling over alimony which
For money that didn't exist so
She wound up becoming a buyer for a local family-owned Hotel chain actually close friends of ours
Which eventually sold to Sheraton and
And gradually she parried that into becoming ultimately the senior buyer for Sheraton worldwide
And then from there she became the senior buyer for Disney for the Epcot Center
When they built that so yes she she was like literally
You know Mom with 5 kids running a little general store part-time is kind of a hobby
To becoming a dino Global XX
So disliked
Major change in your life happens at the age of 14 which
Of course
It's going to have an influence on you did you
Did you start to think about a business about being a businessman that early
I mean you said your parents were both entrepreneurial
No I I started to think about running as far as I possibly could away from it
Obviously the bankruptcy didn't happen overnight it was a result of a steady decline am I
My grandfather my father and my uncle were all in the business and I used to sit
Or work it there and I would listen to them screaming at each other know they were arguing you know
Passionately
About what to do about this downturn
And so to me business was this thing where people got people yelled at each other
Are people hung up phones on each other people were stressed employees lost their jobs
And it been on top of that
Serious
Pollution so
It led to my deciding that business was the worst thing on the planet the last thing I wanted to do and
LED made a really pursue a career in The Sciences environmental Sciences
Suicide would you do after high school
I went off
Yelp to a college that was
Just
And overtly
Liberal arts non-business environment is Hampshire College
Joker skin burns and
If you want to get business knocked out of you that's
Yeah
Yeah but stick with it because it turns out that it was probably the best training for an entrepreneur
That there is
It's cuz this is a school
That has no credits no requirements no grades
You only pass
Matriculate through by Contracting
And making progress with an individual
Professors who take you on as their
Essentially Apprentice
And in many cases the
The funding of
At work I mean I wound up
Diving deep into ecology and environmental Sciences
And
Turns out
I was
Those hating business still and thinking
You know again now I thought
Getting educated I realized my God we're warming the planet were toxic
Define word depleting
Waterwood disturbing you know biodiversity everywhere it's all because of Industry so I was
Receta radicalizing in my environmental beliefs but
But actually getting Business School
Bells all the way
Should I get
College that
That you went and worked
Yeah
At the time there was a little ethological research institute on Cape Cod called the new Alchemy Institute
And they were advancing the idea of using wind and solar power building releases
Sustainable food source
Customs long before those words were in our vernacular in
I went from
A windmill
Apprentice to Windmill technician to executive director and
And I saw them on The Cutting Edge
Which of them
Of how we were going to need to grow food in the future
In-N-Out around this time you also meet
Sam human rights
Right
And he is the guy who's going to become your business partner who's it and he
He's also running his own organic farm
Right so he was mostly teaching organic farming methods raised beds
Biological Pest Control
A greenhouse season extending
Basically kind of back to the land types
Stop. With that with an organic Focus
AC running this is a non-profit and just
Oh yes it was a non-profit
So we're both we're each running nonprofit
But I got really excited by his work and of course he was back here in my native New Hampshire
Which I loved and he's older than you
Oh yes he's about six
16 years old or Samuel
At that time
Had six kids
I was a single guy
But
You know we became Fast Friends
And a he asked me if I would join the board of the world
Education center to help him
With his money racing
IMDb have a hard time raising money in the first place
Well right about that time Ronald Reagan came into office and
Essentially
Cut off the lifeline
Sustainable energy research sustainable AG
So essentially money dried up
For these nonprofits and so we would sit at Samuels board meetings
At about the Royal Education Center
And by the way
Critical to this whole story he had one cow
Animal Ebel
And Samuel was experimenting with yogurt
And he was
A fermentation
Nutcase
I mean he made
Sauerkraut
Pier One
A kimchi
If it fermented he made it
When I say he made it he made in
Incredible
Foods anime
This wonderful yogurt
From his cow has one cow
And we would sit at these board meetings
Eating bowls of butter
Absolutely incredible
Playing cream on top whole milk yogurt
And I'm just a back
Up one step Samuel is originally from Brooklyn
I grew up very poor
In Flatbush but he got to know a lot of these old
Jewish yogurt maker
Down there
And they taught him yogurt making
And what they explain to him is it's very simple it's all about the weather
At meaning times and temperatures it's about the weather the humidity the temperatures and he
Answer Samuel for his family and for the school experimented with yogurt for many years
And one day and unfortunately none of us can remember who but one of us said
Why don't we start selling this stuff too
It'll make up for the lack of
Grant money cuz it was
Nigh impossible to raise money during that period
And
You know
Seemed like a pretty good idea so
Samuel
Was able to get
Some Catholic nuns
Add to provide a $25,000 Grant
Nuns
Yeah
The Sisters of Mercy
Which is
You'll hear the moment the appropriate name
Are they were taking Mercy on these two crazy entrepreneurs
They were selling their modest
And they were wanted to turn their principal into a
Local community action
And Samuel use that money to build the first yogurt works
And
About the time that the money came in which was April of 83
When we opened
I decided that
I was
Pretty interested in joining him full-time not so much to run the yogurt but
I thought that I could
Help him
Run his farming School while he did this little fun
Yogurt mint
Texas Lookout I'm going to
Join you in September
Took the summer of 83 you move to New Hampshire to tip to start doing this full-time
Right I moved into a
Three-story wood heated log
Cabin with no Plumbing
Can I put solar cells on it and
And it came and families live there
And our interns are
There's one big kind of Happy
Crazy
Powdered milk in yogurt making
Operation
Yogurt system start
Being
In things are put into
Jars and
How did you get
Two customers
Did you brush England for sale
Well we started with one cow
Send me use the money to buy
6 Marquez
So now he's milking 7
He
Finances
This little tiny Factory in
Tiny little room that you could only really described as a closet in a
1792 Barn
With a wood wood fired boiler
And
The way it worked was he
Put in a 50 gallon stainless steel tank
We bought plastic cups
And
Sammy was a very
Charming and persuasive guy in after paying for his first shipment of Cups he managed to somehow get continue to get shipments
5 months without
Paying for any more so
He started producing April 9th 1983
And took his first
Six packs of yogurt
Drove down to
The local supermarket
Tell her words and said would you guys sell this
They didn't know what the heck this was
And
They said what price should we sell it at 7 said I don't know whatever
Whatever price you think
We were not business peep
So we started selling
At a dollar 49 a quart which is the same price down and was selling
Hey by the way was only making courts
Six packs of plain cream on top yogurt
It was like Ambrosia guy it was the most incredibly perfect
Product still the best thing we make
So you guys just start to
Basically
Sell it locally
And
Eventually
The harwich port
Because you know this is good
Selling
By the way below the price
If we could afford
So Sam is a great
So we eventually hired a young
Local
Guy to drive a van
We couldn't afford a refrigerator van so we just told him to drive fast
But yeah so by the time I got there
A 5-month tinnitus
Samuel head
Probably about
$50,000
Versailles
And
My gosh the product
Was selling through but he couldn't keep up
And he was out of cash
And
Course he wasn't paying bills
He was out of cash because
What is the lag time between
When he's getting paid and he had to pay for grain to feed the cows he had to pay this guy to drive
And bring the yogurt as I told you before he wasn't paying for his cups
But he had to pay people to help
And you have the $35,000 it started just appeared overnight
Honestly I don't know how it got to
To 5 months
Because
When I arrived
On September 15th of 83
Hit Samuel had these old army surplus.
Masks in this farmhouse
That the three desk
For piled high with envelopes on open mail
Mister okay
I'm now the executive director of the relegation Center
And the vice president of Stonyfield Farm
And I'm going to spend my first Atwoods in the name of the farm Stonyfield
I'm sorry yes
Are still there
So I spent the morning separating
I thought the checks
From the
Bill's the only problem was
There were no check
I Samuel any money that I come in he had used it to buy feed
You know lubrication equipment
Fuelwood whatever
And
By 11 a.m. that morning my first day
I calculator that we were $75,000 in the red
So what did you do
Well I did what any self-respecting entrepreneur does I called my mother
And I borrowed $30,000
From which she could ill-afford as I told you before she was
You know her own
Business women with for you no family but
You know what I had
A good fundraising scale so I went too many of my former funders and many of his and I said look can we
Can we borrow
These were the the Thunder siphonic that you had run back in Massachusetts
Right well Samuel had a handful of
Foxwood been his fenders like I said he he raised $125,000 so they were
They're probably 20 or 30
Wealthy individuals and then I had raised a million dollars a year so I had
You know by net worth
Individuals out there and I
Look what I told him was very simplistic
You know the first
10 years of artwork
Was all about proving that you can grow food organically
But if we're going to be successful with this revolution I said to the funders who had gotten us there
Then we're going to have to prove that you can actually make money doing
And we're going to have to
Build a model Enterprise
That will show that you can
Avoid the use of pesto
Besides avoid the use of hormones
Cows
Support family farmers
Not depend on fossil fuels
Etc etc all the things that we were doing in the nonprofit context
I said you know this is
I'd like to ask you to join us in the next phase which is
Helping us to
I build a successful business and instead of asking for a grant I'm asking you for a loan
And I wound up borrowing $125,000
Okay so you go out and you start raising money and did you and and and Samuel sit down and say
Construction is businesslike II we are co-owners is a
Joint venture like how did you did you ever do that
Well we did because
One of the things I did was I
Hired a lawyer
Cuz I knew we didn't know what we're doing and the first thing this lawyer
Said to me was he said Gary
What percentage of the world Education Center's revenue is coming from the yogurt
Well that point
It was getting close to
75%
And he said well guess what you've got to spin it off
Because under IRS rules that
Makes you a business
Not a non-profit
So Samuel and I realized
We're going to have to buy this from the Royal education
So we agreed
To a split
In the company
And then I
Went out to our lenders
725 k
And I said look up will you take stock in this company
We did our first private
Placement
You know threw a dart at the wall figured out the value of the business
What's the time
Well
We thought we're going to Value it at $1000000
By then in 1984 our sales were up to
Around 200
50000 a year in this is Justin in New Hampshire or all of them
Well
By 84 we were starting to
Push the boundaries
We're selling the about 20 stores
And
Eventually we started selling to a
An Independent Grocer who had seven stores
I called Alexander supermarket
Is now part of Hannaford
In the Northeast
Anda
This will give you the real flavor for this what was going on here someone Sunday night we're having dinner at the Caymans after milking
Hand of the phone ranks and Jack demoulas the nephew of the
Owner of the demoulas Market Basket
And says Samuel Le
Why are you selling to buy competitor this little seven store chain of Alexander's and not to me
He had 34 Stars
What time is Sammy said well
How to be honest Mister demoulas we don't have enough cause he said we'll get some more goddamn cows and he slammed the phone down
And we took that is very
Good business advice so we went out and
Do I heard
Even further and
Denso we
Now realize we needed to
You know
Get serious about this and so we did manage to lease a small refrigerator truck and started
Delivering actually to the Market Basket Warehouse
How much yogurt were you making at that
We're producing now about
360 cases a week of yogurt
And a case is like 24 cups
Six packs of Courts
So by the end of 84 we were our run-rate was headed
In the start of half a million-dollar range but you were probably spending more money than you were bringing it right
You have no idea we were burning
I mean I kept
Not
Weekly cash flows not daily cash flows I kept our leak
I knew on a Wednesday morning how much money had to come in that afternoon
In order for us to buy then the cup guy and pick it up
You know Sammy wasn't paying I'm so
Now we are on very short terms with everybody I mean
My fundraising skill turn out to be
Will it be nowhere without Samuels yogurt making skills and his family's unbelievable attention to detail they were
Perfectionist but we were also we would also be nowhere
Without my ability to keep getting credit and cash because it was burning
Believer on fumes
When we come back in just a moment have Gary and Samuel begged and borrowed
How to keep Stonyfield going
And how they almost lost it anyway again and again and again I'm Gyros and
You're listening to how I built this from NPR
Hey everyone
Two of our sponsor
Who helped make this podcast possible
First floor how I built this 2019 lead sponsor
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Do understand that each business
Is as unique as a fingerprint or barcode
Taylor's intelligent Insurance Solutions to fit every businesses
Very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase
The policy at hiscox
Dot-com
Hiscox
Business
Trench
Thanks also to Capital One
Capital One Knows life
Dustin alert you about your credit card
That's why they created
You know
Capital One assistant
The caches things that might look wrong with
Credit card
Tipping duplicate charges or potential fraud
Then sends an alert to your phone
It helps you fix it
It's another way Capital One is watching out for you or money
When you're not
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capitalone.com
Details
Just a few years
Before starring in Book of Mormon
Andrew rannells
What's playing on Broadway
Doing and I quote
It's Karate Kid
The music
This is the punctuation
It's Karate, Kid colon the musical
For legal purposes the stories behind
Every Tuesday on it's been a minute
NPR
Play Welcome Back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
So in the summer of 1984
Gary and Samuel and Stonyfield
Almost
Broke there
Basically running on fumes
Electronic bring in more money by
Just
Finding
Kmart stores
To sell their yogurt
In those days
A Whole Foods didn't exist yet
But the holy grail for natural products was a little priest or chain called bread and circus Arts events
Became part of
And that one store in Cambridge
On Prospect
And you know we were selling now to
Demoulas Market Basket
This is now I'm talking to liability for
And
And we were desperately trying to get down there cuz we knew that
If we could crack
Bread & circus every other little natural food co-op in New England
Would 10 take us in
And we kept going down there
And they
Said no no no we've already got you know hippie yogurt made by somebody in Vermont
In their teepee with their wetgo you know they didn't need
Another
You know organic yogurt from some
Crazy people in New Hampshire
What you guys do
So in July of 84 I had my 30th birthday at the
The farm in my I had my old Ultimate Frisbee team
Come up
To visit me most of them lived in Cambridge
You might imagine
And
I said look
It's wonderful you've all come if you want to give me a really good birthday present good under Bread & circus
I'm prospects
Cambridge and asked for my yoga
That was on a Sunday on Wednesday
Mary Carol Skinner the buyer Bread & circus called and said Gary I don't know what's going on but the man is suddenly gone through the roof
We're getting all kinds of requests for yogurt when can you get it in there will I got in my car and I
Made the first delivery. Afternoon
About
A month later we were her number one selling yogurt
She took us in the other to bread and circuses
And off we went but
It was my frisbee
I mean
You know that's what it takes. You know I always say we can ship the yogurt 3000 miles
Celeste
18in that makes all the difference you get in people's mouths and then they're going to ask
But it was the best-selling yogurt
Bread and circuses
Loved it but you were not making a profit
No that's absolutely right
Stressful
Utterly
It was impossible.
This was crazy right we're growing
We're booming and we're burning cast soap
Crazy
Yeah we're 24
7 Samuel had six kids
Cuz it was sort of indentured servitude I mean
You know it was hard
If they were going to have dinner that night it was hard for them to say no to
No milking are making and by the way
Hit several of his kids were Arts
Just absolutely
Astonishing
We good yogurt makers they had their father
And mother sense of
Pride in the product
And this is around the time we meet Meg
Become your wife
Yasso
A month after that fateful meeting with Bread & circus
We had our Summer nofa Conference
Northeast organic farming
Is it turn that I was the Keynote
What speaker
And so I started talking about this Enterprises
That was now
A year old and
You know all of the dreams of
Organic farmers that we were sort of like
I didn't talk about our financial problems
Show the
The best possible that if you build it they will come
And I right after I finish my speech this
It's very
Adorable
Organic farmer from
New Jersey
Who is running her own non-profit
Farm down there
I waited patiently to ask me a question will that
Turned out to be what
Now my 31-year wife Meg
And
We began courting and
A Thanksgiving that year and 84 Meg introduced me to her family
And her mom had been
The Deputy Commissioner of Agriculture
Weather for New York State
So she had a kind of an egg orientation
At one point she kind of whispered to me that she'd be
Okay with
If I needed some money
Would lending me some
Well course I needed
Sochi
Banda
$50,000
And
Now we're heading into 1985 we have now launched small cups of
Unflavored yogurt
I
Now needed to raise about 500 thousand
Cuz we needed to buy more cups more fruit you know
People expected us to pay
So
Doris had loaned us 250
Towards the $500,000 as your mother-in-law my mother-in-law
And
I started raising then I got to about
275 300
I just heard of a month or so later
Well I think we can increase
Insouciant Chris to a hundred and eventually I got across the Finish Line got the 500
Why did you need so much money
Well if the factory itself
Was probably 300,000 the factory
On Stonyfield Farm
Yeah the little we call it the yogurt work
A little Shoppe
You know what's up
Drafty Old Barn it was
We needed to switch over from wood
2 oil
We needed to just get more modern we needed to get the warehouse
The barn
You made sanitary we had to get real floor drains we had to
Stop being a
Kind of a kitchen operation
And what a cows how many cows do you have
Well that point we were up to 19 but
One Night in this same era
Sammy without milk and heated milk
The first of the 19 cows and the power went out
Samuel came in and said
You know I need help
Cuz he has his electric milker so Louise and I went out and started milking well
You know it was freezing the cows hated it if you haven't hand melt
Let me tell you that they didn't do it
It was a nightmare to Kaiser
Kicking over the bucket we had these
Kerosene lanterns in this firetrap Barn
You know everyone's well the car would kick one over in the milk
Spell on the lanterns and
We finished milking the last
Kyle at about 3 a.m. in time to start milking the first
And that was the night when we realized you know what
We got to sell the cows
You had
To sell the cows because
You guys could not milk them
All by yourself
Right
And until the next morning
We reached out to a
Local Jersey farmer cuz we're using all
Jersey cow milk
And said look what you buy are cows and start selling us milk well he said I'm not going to have anything to do with that
That Organics
And he was fine with hormone-free antibiotic-free but he didn't want to
Fetus cows herbs and buy organic feed and put that was your condition
Well
Honestly we had no condition
We were Beggars not choosers so we briefly
At this moment in Stonyfield life we briefly departed from organic
You had no choice
We had no choice
Did you get that disturb you did you
You felt like you were
Betraying your values at that Mommy I guess because you were
You are hammers you send me money
But you had this demand and you
You had to make and you didn't have enough cows
Yeah and
I not only had all these problems but I had my mother
And worst
My mother-in-law's money
And so you know what that makes
A guy pretty practical
You know venture capitalist
The reason they want
What they call f&f money first friends and family money
It's cuz they know that you might is enough
Supernatural things get rough you might
Get up and walk away if it
You know
Some Harvard MBA with a tie
But if it's your mother's money
Yeah and so now we worked for our moms
Which must have been pretty stressful
Oh yeah you know what happened
In this farmhouse
I always had payroll on Thursday morning
And by this point is a half a million dollar business
And I never had cash in the bank
That night before payroll
Never just this has become our way of life
And so I thinking Meg was asleep
Ann Arbor
Bedroom which is about 50 feet from my office I would
On many occasions
Tiptoe over to the office to call my mother-in-law
Have a chat to see if I can borrow another 3500 2500 to make ends meet
And eventually Meg got on to this one night I heard the Click Click of call waiting on my mother-in-law's phone and Meg was
Just calling from the house to say mom don't do this with your wife
Was telling her mom not to lend you money for the business because
She's living in a nightmare when she saw
How crazy was it mean we had chimney fires we had
The well pump would go out
The power would I be wearing this Hilltop Farm a long way from anywhere
Well she had no reason to believe in it was insane
But why did you believe it and did you think it was going to three years into this thing
Are you not making money you are
Make that big time
Yeah
Well
Say this
Meg
You know fortunately loved me
Even more fortunate probably loved the yogurt
And we have nowhere else to go
Is she giving up her job done on her Farm in New Jersey and signed on
To this crazy damn Enterprise but here's where the story if
I know that you think it couldn't get worse but
Taza
Lily Tomlin says it
It is
It got a lot worse before it got worse
Well so now I'm going to jump
A year-and-a-half
We've now expanded the plant we're buying milk
10 or 12 Farms
I'm going to guess let me just tell you the number we are at about a one-point
$3000000 a year run rate
And we have Max
Out this
Little farm there is no
You cannot squeeze another drop of yogurt out of this
So presumably you are looking to
Another Factor
Right
So spring of 86
We are
Out of capacity we contracted with a little dairy in Western Mass
This is Greenfield Mass
We were desperate we did not do any
Have the financial due diligence one would normally do we just
Got our way and then we started making yoga
And it was
Great jamming all of a sudden
Pave roads
You know
Regular power
A dairy and we thought we were
Coming out of the woods yeah
The yogurts being made somewhere else
Never see it yeah yeah
But now we're on the bend into the fall of 87 October of 87
A fateful weekend the weekend of the crash of 87 and Wall Street
But what happened for us was on the Thursday night
Of that weekend
Becky capeless the bank there for his
Manufacturers Bank
Call Mia
At the farm and said Gary would you like to buy this Dairy
The theory that that was producing your
And I said no we
We don't have the cash to buy their dad.
And I said why you asking she said well
They're in their third year of their
Small business administration loan guarantee and the SBA has enough to not going to renew it
And therefore are back my boss is going to have to
To pull our loan to him
And that means that he's probably not going to make it
The next morning at 7 a.m. that their bank went in and put them into chapter 7
Padlocked
The place locked it up
Mike Epps my Lids my fruit my yogurt
Was in there
But suddenly this thing is in receivership
Wait a minute your production comes to a halt
Outsource
Blake production facility
Stop
So it came to a screaming halt worse than that
I had to come up with $100,000
To take my get my inventory out of the building
Because again we owe them co-packing phase now the backs the owner
And so I had to go call my shareholders
And
Find $100,000 within hours
And so I did
We got our inventory out
And that but now we have no Factory get your making no yogurt so we have no yogurt we have what was in the factory
Also
What can we do if we took a look at the old yogurt work
Hilltop Farm
Where the roosters are now living as his son of a gun we got to come back here now by then our volume had grown to 100% more
You know when winter has been exceeded you could not make enough yogurt at Stonyfield Farm where you were living
Right right
But that didn't dantas that we can send me when I put on our Carpenters aprons went out
And kick the roosters out and restarted the old yogurt
Unfortunately equipment was still there
And by Monday morning so it was $100,000 that we had to
Borrow to
Payoff
The dairy
And then we had to put about
$100,000 into getting this place
Up and running again week
You know we borrowed and burn and Burrows and you know I went to all the shareholders and
You know what course
They have no choice but to land because everything they had ever put in was
Monday morning
We begin
Action against Stonyfield Farm now
The problem is
In order to keep up we have to
Mapreduce
Twenty-four hours a day
7 days a week
Assembler I had to make yogurt every other night
And guy this began
And continued
420 months
And we've started burning
Embrace yourself for this
You started burning $25,000 a week
On top of the 200000 that we had borrowed
So now I am in
Deep you-know-what and
How much money do you think you
You weren't
Like a million
Dunmore
Well by the
Bike by Christmas of 87
You know running this Factory for 2 months
I can tell you we were already
A $600,000 in debt
By Christmas of 88
We were 1.9 million dollars in debt
Bye
Christmas
Of the next year
We were 2.7
Million dollars
Can you put shareholders
Say
I'm getting nervous
IQR
Has it been a while here
And I email
She's like a lot of money
Every one of them
And you know what you have to know at the punchline of the story is that I wound up by the end of this.
With 297 individual investor
There was no way to find common ground with an Institutional Investor
How to write a venture capital
Believe me I
I knocked on every door and they were like take a hike
Right
What about your shoulder
How did you end up dealing with
I
Stayed in constant touch with
Every single shareholder
I was in constant contact with my creditors I couldn't pay fruit suppliers I couldn't pay
You know our fruit supplier had lost
$75,000 when that Dairy went chapter 7
And somehow
They had
Not been paying attention and they
Continue to ship us fruit back up at the farm
So they
They figured it out you know
3 months later that
They were now into us for 125000
And I
Guy said luck
I can't pay it but
Can I come out and talk to you
And I borrowed a credit card
From a friend and
Flew out cuz we've certainly had no credit
So that the Cleveland and met with the
People and I said look here's the bad news we owe you a hundred twenty five thousand but
Here's the good news
Necedah current growth rate
If we can meet orders
We will be a 250
$50,000 a year customer for you
Within six months
So here's what I'm prepared to do
I would like to see if you would Advance us
Another
$125,000
I will pay you back
Starting a 6 month at your interest
Whatever you want to charge which is a joke cuz nobody
No Commercial Bank would even lend to us
I said I will
Pledge my stock as collateral
Which was a joke cuz it was a liability not an asset
And finally I said and I will pledge that I will buy exclusively from you
Not from anyone else so that was a joke
Cuz no one else would ever sell to us
And they said well Gary it's an interesting
They said could you mind if we go up and talk and they went into the back room
And son of a gun half an hour later they come outside you know what we believe in you were going to do it
Nmi at am I summary of that story and so many others of this. Is simply
If you don't ask you don't get
And Desperation you know breeds this thing where you just have no shame anymore you have to
Asking now I'll just tell you the punchline of that story is those guys have sold Us in the 30-year
Dear sense
And if so
Probably
250 or 300 million dollars worth of fruit
Amazing
It's crazy because at this point in in all of my interviews normally
It's were talking about how the entrepreneur like made it through the troughs in the
Crucibles and just you know to start making money hand-over-fist but you are still in crisis I mean your
Company is
Am I doing well
You didn't even have a factory to make yogurt at this point you you needed a new one
Yeah
Nmi ultimately found one
It was a dairy in Northern Vermont
And
We
Negotiated for three months with this dairy in Northern Vermont
To become the answer
Go to this whole thing
Namely
They would produce our yogurt
Samuel and I would focus on sales and marketing
And we would become partners and they would get
Pay the price for every cup
Tokyo Garden
Just like the other day but this was a much larger
70 million-dollar company
So D day comes
In April of 88
To go up and get the
Bastille sign and we had negotiated a deal that
About to in
And I went up
Gemini
Left the farm up at this point Meg is pregnant with
Son number one
And
Of course I've got now
I now have over $1000000 of her mother's money
Okay
Like money she could never
Everything they had
And a man comes to me at the door and as we're leaving
She said you eat you promise this is done right we're going to
Because I've been milking every other night
Right no vacations no brakes no no
I'm leaving now to go sign the stalemate
You promised me that all the details are worked out that when you come back tonight
Where
The beginning of
Really going to happen
Absolutely we have nailed down every last
Drove up to Vermont
When I got there Sammy one of the rest
Restroom at the lawyer's office
And I looked at my
Instead of the 2-inch thick
Agreement that we were going to go over
It was a letter
Timmy
It said dear Garian bottom line is
Dr Gary Samuel
Basically they decided to trade
Just to steal the company from us there there
They said we've decided
That you guys need us more than we need you
We're going to
Take over what we're going to do is have all of your shareholders convert their
Stock into debt
And you are welcome to work down there.
With a credit of one penny
Perk-up Forever Yogurt
Every cut my hair will take 2 years
And at the end of the two years will negotiate your future employer
So wasn't a deal it was
Steel
Wow
Wait this this was just sitting
On the table this letter that says
Orrefors you
This is
We were stealing
And all the while they're looking at me and that one guys winking at me like you know do the deal sign
In your best
You know your wife's back they're desperate for you to solve this get to
HP smart
Tell me what not even come into the room I got up
I heard some things I can't say on public radio and grab Samuel
And got in the car
And we started driving now course as luck would have it
Don't you know an April blizzard has started in
So no cars are on the road we've now got
A two-hour drive back
And worse than that one of us is going to have to make yogurt at night
And worse than that
I have to face my wife
And so we start driving
I turned him I said what what will you do now cuz
I knew we're going to have to sign the deal I I knew it was over
And I said
Any setup
I guess I'll do something in sales
And you know my heart sunk right this is a guy who created this
Incredible yogurt I mean he was a genius who is making the most perfect product and now he's going to sell widgets
So you basically thought
Or at least
Sam thought that
This was it I mean you guys were mean
This is the darkest of the dark
Hours for burning $25,000 a week
We're taking money we cannot ever pay back
We have to go back to this Farm we have no solution
And so I turned to Samuel and I said listen Samuel
Just for the fun of it what would be the cheapest yogurt plant we could build
Somewhere that would actually cover our capacity
They said you know
I was thinking the same thing so he flipped on the dome light in the car pulls out his pad and we start designing a yogurt
In the car in the car we're driving in this
I'm driving he's designing
We got back to the house
About
10:30 11:00 at night
He goes in to make yogurt
I going to see Meg shoes
Wakes up in
She says
So the deal signed is it down I said no no no
That is not going to happen but we've got a much better idea
I slept alone that night
Over my office
And the next morning
At 7 a.m.
I was up
At the SBA office in Concord
Small business
Administration remember they
They will guarantee loans to business
So they make it possible
For banks to lend
2 high risk
But you certainly were and you were I mean you you guys were in
That you had no plan to come fill your orders
How are you going to talk them into
Is it getting you alone
Well we had figured out that we could build this
Factory
For a 500 and
$97,000
So I drove up
Vspa and I
Sat down with them and they never
Normally you don't go to the sbu go to the bank to go CSP but I sat down
You know stoneyfield to pretty
Popular brand we're well known in the state so I
I meet Bill Phillips the head of the New Hampshire SBA office when he walked in at 7:30 and I said
Bill
Here's the deal
We can build this Factory
597000 we need an 85% loan Guerra
And guess what we've got a bag
The back of New England's willing to lend us that was a little bit of an exaggerated
Jason day
This is Stone Soup
Another story
I said Anna and and I knew
That I had to come up with
20% of it
Shareholder
Equity so
And I said I've got the hundred thousand hundred twenty five thousand from the shareholders also not quite sure
Bill symbolism Theory
If you got the bank and you've got this
Plan and
And you've got the
Cheryl Dizon will happily do it I drove from there to the Bank of New England
Set timer to look guys
The
SBA is going to
Provide the loan guarantee and I got the shareholders will you
Do this loan
And they said well at the SPCA of the word of course we'll do it and if you
You guarantee the Equitable do
Call the shareholders to a meeting in Boston the next night
Get together with as many of them as I could had my mother-in-law on speakerphone
Here we are guys
We got the bag
We got the SBA all we need is your hundred twenty five thousand
And
To make a long story short
We got their money
How much money did you raise
All told
Including paying off the debt
Two and a half million dollars
And opened our new Factory nine months later
In Londonderry
Where we are today
And did you both you and Samuel to give up
Big chunks of Iran
Oh yeah by then Samuel and I were down to
To 10% each
In the company
Now we also had stock options like wheat we hadn't turned back
The end of 89 we began Manufacturing in this facility
The business is now doing
3.4 million dollars in
Shoe sales
But we lost 1.4 million that year
The next year
We did 6.5 million in sales
And we lost
The following year the second full year in the new Factory
We did 10.1 million and we made $125,000
This is 1992
March 92
That that was our first year making money
To the nineties are this is just
The growth. You guys are on the trajectory and when do you know that you are not sustainable and
Things Are
Are looking at
We hit
4 million dollars in around 95
Now we've got
Stability and cash flow and this gave us the courage
To go back to our roots
Initially with one farmer and eventually now with 1755
Begin buying organic milk again and of course organic has evolved at this point
Whole Foods has become a reality I'm in the organic sectors
Rio
So
In 95 we converted back are playing home if chords to organic
96 we converted our small cups
97 relaunch
Strength
98 worth 78 million in sales
99 or 100 million + sales
And that's
When I began negotiating with Jenna on
Have them come in
At this point
It's been a long road right 83 you start the company
You get a hundred million sales by 99
What was the reason why you decided to sell
You know huge steak toot-toot
Down to the French multinational
Is yogurt
Dairy products
So the answer is
The 297 shareholder
I mean some of these folks
Came in
In 1984
Without
Children now they have kids going to college right I mean they
Do you need a return on
I had no legal
Application but I felt a moral obligation
Shinto
You pay them back and Samuel also was ready to retire
So
My idea was
I'll sell
My company to you you buy out all the shareholders in my partner
But you leave me in control
By then I was up to about 20% ownership
Diet through the earn-out
And I said
United
Commitment I'll stay on for a really long time
But you got to let me keep running the shop
So I talked
The 21 companies 20 of them left
Actually even then on left and maybe
The original head of m&a who came to see me said the
Gary do you mean to tell me
We're going to buy 80% of your company and you'll still be on
Core
And I said yes
And the banker and the lawyers and everyone laughed and
You know two years later that's the deal we signed I I spent two years negotiating with them
So you remained the CEO of the company
End up in the 2000s if I'm if I'm
I guess I have my server
Remember this
Like all of a sudden
Greek yogurt chest
Loaded
And you guys
We're not a Greek yogurt
What did that
Due to your
Sales
Well Greek is not 50% of the ogre
The thick
Unusual creamy
Taste of Greek
Just
Just caught on
It just simply caught on
And we have a wonderful incredible Greek line
But it's only for us about 15% of our sales
And you know
While we're not
The leader in Greek we are the leader in organic
I think we're something like
80% of organic yogurt in the US
How much of what happens to you and your success is because of luck and how much because of skill
Oh
Luck counts for a lot of mean
I was lucky to meet my
Incredible wife and
Turn amazing mother I was lucky to meet
Samuel I was
We were lucky to find people who lend us
Money despite how
Syllabus was
Scale helps you know
What made this possible was Samuel
And his genius and his incredible skills
Okay without that Superior recipe
None of this could have happened where you and I wouldn't be talking to yourself
Of course kill counts but
You know school has plenty of fantastic entrepreneurs who
Failed hue
Wonderful skills
But just didn't
Have good luck
This
Small little hippie like yogurt thing that you
Has made you very wealthy
It's
First thought was that ever important you did you
Did you always want to become rich out of this
All I wanted was my mother and my mother-in-law to get their money back now
I could you not know look you know we began this
Interview by talking about my father
His failed business and all that
Tragedy
Came of that with all the people in my
Community Center
You know I
I was never
A believer that making money was the Holy Grail
You know I sit on many boards now I work with wall streeters and
Look I know the
Best way to convince these guys to invest in organic and
Renault buses to show you can make a lot of money so and that's
Basically we did me despite all these obstacles
You guys hate
Yeah
Laughing joke that we had a wonderful company just no Supply and no demand and no one knew that
There was such a thing as better yogurt and certainly no one who would organic
I and yet
It's interesting that my dad
And my mom by the way in both cases
What I now realize I got from them was this
Belief in myself that
It didn't matter what we
What's going to happen
If if yogurt cups are leaking if
Stores weren't accepting us if competition was coming on if I
Couldn't meet payroll
You know there was always going to be away and I I learned that from both
And and your your mother lies she still rap
Sad that she just passed
A couple months ago
Sorry to hear I'm assuming that her million dollars was in the end of
Very good in
She did
Extremely well see
She and I still Kept Secrets I was
She passed it's a nearly 97 and
I can tell you that
The risk she took
Was Tony Phil was probably whenever
Greatest Point surprise you know she always had this conversation and
Begging and pleading her mother not to mess and Taurus always had this one line what she had for decades witches
Maggie I'm a big girl I know what I'm doing
It's going to work out
And she was right Gary hirschberg the co-founder of Stonyfield yogurt by the way back
Same here we first spoke to him
Danone sold Stonyfield to another company called black Talus
What are the biggest Dairy companies in the world
Any amount like Alice paid for Stonyfield
875 million dollars
Which is not bad for a yogurt business that began
With just one cow
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you are building
But first
Equip thanks to one of our sponsors
Fundrise
Innovating the way people
Invest in real estate
Sunrise mix
Simple to build
Folio of
High quality real estate
Affordably
Is it fundrise.com built
First six months of advisory fees
Do you curve has inverted in the past this has been an indicator that a recession is on it
Way will this time be different
Listen to the indicator from Planet Money
NPR daily economics podcast
Define doubt
Hey thanks for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that today were updating a story that we
First ran last year it begins with Carin Luna ostaseski
In back in 2009
She was working in marketing
In New York City
After work one day a friend asked me if I wanted to grab a glass of scotch and I said no I don't drink Scotch that's
That's my grandfather
But the friend took her to one of those places that specializes in sky
And that night I tried four different brands and I instantly fell in love with a brand called Oban 14
And I love the Beauty and the nuances and the complexities of the spirit into almost instantly
Karen became a scotch drinker
She started reading about it and then collecting it and then eventually evangelizing about
I became that friend Tina that was always trying to convince everyone else so you should try skeleton everyone always said the same things
You know it's burning my nostrils it tastes like gasoline it's too expensive
Hey I already have all this amazing scotch in my personal collection
Maybe I could just
Blend my own when is designed specifically to change the way that you think about scotch
Very smooth approachable that has a lot of vanilla and caramel and citrus and just a little bit of smoke
Starting out in her kitchen I would take two brands that I thought would go well together
I take a measuring cup and free glasses and I would put
When that was measured 50/50 another 25 75 and the other 75 25 and then have to renew blend
And I did this quite a lot and I came up with some really bad not so great tasting Blends like even to summon know that
Jump it before you and tasting it but eventually after about six months of experimenting
Korean came up with the blind you really like
At this point she was living in San Francisco and she starts to call and emailed dozens of Master blenders
Is the only country that makes Scotch witches Scotland
But time and time again I just got so many nose and fact they were a Dino's 80 nose
It's an old boys club more than anything right especially being of all things and American woman living in California
I think from a third-party I heard about yes that's that crazy American woman that's trying to create a scotch brands
Finally
The 81st person was the one that said yes we can help you
It was actually two sisters that they work for their fathers Scotch whiskey importing business and it was just
Amazing moment that I realized that this could actually come together
Raise $48,000 and use the money to blend her first bottle of Scotch
Since we last spoke to Corrine Sia scotch has been doing pretty well it's on sale in about 1600
Stores across the country
Has made its way into some major retailers on the west coast including Safeway and Target
Mcf
It comes from Gaelic to the name Sierra means the number 6 and there are six whiskeys in the blend and a friend recently
I pointed out to me that it could stand for
Scotch egg
Awesome
Sia scotch
To our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org of course if you want to tell us your story goat
How to build. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe it Apple
Podcasts or wherever you get your podcasts you can also write to us at Hy-Vee tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet ask how I built this I'm at Gyros or shows pretty
You're so sweet by Jed Anderson with music posed by rechtien Arab Louis thanks also to Julia Kearney The Immigrant
Admission for Jeff Rogers AR intern is David ja
How I built this
This
Is NPR