So I want to tell you that we're coming to the Twin Cities for a live event on Wednesday July 17th
I'll be talking with Dan and Angie Bastian co-founders of Angie's boom chicka pop
How is history teacher and a psychiatric nurse started making popcorn
And eventually got it
Anta stores
Coast to Coast
The show is supported by American Express and
To get tickets
Go to nprpresents.org
Hope to see you there
Singapore start the show
How I built this Summit sponsored by American Express
Is coming back this fall to San Francisco
It's happening on a
October 22nd and
23rd and this year it's
It's going to be amazing
You will have the opportunity to spend the day with some of the most in
Aspiring entrepreneurs in the world
And many of them will be hanging around a chat and give advice
Literally
People like David neeleman of JetBlue
Stewart Butterfield
Looks like Sara Blakely of Spanx
Kevin Systrom of Instagram Marcia Kilgore of bliss Jen Rubio of away
Tim and Joey from all birds
This conference
Unlike any other you
Ever attended
It's designed to build
Nurturing
Community Builders
Come join us in San Francisco October 22nd and 23rd
Hopefully
I'll see you there
To find out more about the summit
Go to Summit
. NPR
Really good or I'm something really bad and really bad I'm a big problem
And look what I've done I've let down all these people all these employees all these investors
All these people who believed in me and I just couldn't live with that
NPR how I built this a show of that innovators entrepreneurs idealists and the stories
Dave Dahl after years
Prison drug he's turned his life around by baking Loaves and healthy whole wheat bread
Dave's
Killer Bread
Clear lessons we've learned from making the show
The story matters
It's the why you do what you do
But more importantly
It's the thing that allows your customers to
Deepen their connection to your product or brand
But companies and businesses don't always put their stories on the label
Think about Roxanne Quimby selling beeswax candles
Farmers markets in Maine while trying to scale-up Burt's Bees
Oravsky towels wondered Pastor burrito shop in San Francisco's Mission District in the late 1980s and
Came up with Chipotle
Now it's highly unlikely that you buy Burt's Bees products or butt Chipotle burrito because of the storm
If you're a fan of either company
Probably just like what they make
But in the case of Dave's Killer Bread
The story was true
Early success
And it was printed on the wrapper of every loaf
The story has more struggle
And probably
Any story weave
Featured on the show so far
It is 20 States all was a pretty messed-up guy
A loser those are actually his own words
And he spent a lot of time in prison
They thought he might even die Behind Bars
Eventually
Transformers thinking
And what was released from prison
Went home to his family bakery
He started making bread
Really good bread and people loved it
And the family bakery group pretty quickly
Seven years on they were selling Dave's Killer Bread across the Northwest doing over 50
$10 in sales
They was born in Portland Oregon in 1960
3 where his family ran a small bakery
Your mom and dad were Seventh-Day Adventists
It's a denomination known to practice a really healthy diet
No alcohol no caffeine
Lots of grain
Indeed family
They were very conservative
My mom was very religious my dad was a believer
They were very strict
And we were expected
Be honest we were taught
B
Truthful we were taught not to fight
You know everything was about getting ready for the afterlife
Heaven
What's your parents do for a living what was there it was their business
Well they were Bakers
And my dad was a
Hard-working man
We did lots of different
Jobs are jobs until he was able to
Muster up enough money to buy a bakery that was failing and
That's where he started back in the 50s
And so they did a lot of birthday cakes and donuts even and all that stuff
But
At some point my dad
Decided
That you weren't
Do more
More whole grains and
Gnu animal facts
Networks news
Revolutionary the time
Yeah but that was definitely the Seventh Day Adventist influence
So because of their religious
Reviews he's he's thinking
How much are making
You know healthier whole grain breads which must have been kind of a
Hippy dippy saying in the in the
Late 60s early 70s right
Yeah that's a funny thing is my dad was the opposite of a hippie
He did he did try to go with more of a liberal
Sort of liberal mindset for a while but
He even stand hippies
Maybe we'll just get so upset then
Zippy's Wahiawa Hawaii
He had to like them because they were keeping him
Business but
There was a Justin
You know he was he was basically 4% of a Nixon Republican
Earliest memories just working in the bakery with your siblings
Yeah some of the
Stand-out memories
We're maybe going and visiting my dad
Where he was working this you had to be a certain age and certain size to be able to
Work in the bakery
Yeah be able to get your hands up over the work table
And I was nine years old when I was
Rams able to start working of course
I couldn't wait to start working
And what would you do in this Bakery as a kid
Mainly we had one of these cookies machines that had $2 that would dispense cookies
And we were making natural cookies
For these
Happy places
We didn't work on Saturday because we were 17
Right that's the day of rest right and the church that's right yeah but Sunday's
We're wide open ever soften our biggest day of working
Are the Adventist
That was their day off
Recreation
What's Sunday
So I was a little bit reason I became more and more resentful
That young age that I wasn't able to go to these
Be a part of what my my peers were doing
But
Yeah we work
We work our butts off on Sundays
And his Bakery was not like
Hugely profitable really you did not grow up with lots of money right
No we we work for a little bit of money
I remember starting at $0.25 an hour
And part of that money part of that $0.25 went to paying for my school and clothes
So what do you remember
Like at what age do you remember starting to
Rebelled against
Against repair
It must have been about
11 or 12 probably 12 by the time I started looking at
Sing just like
Well
I don't believe this
Goffin height
You know I read
The Bible I started up
Grayson siriboe
I made a decision
When I started having doubts that I would just read the Bible and hopefully God would
Tell me
You know what I need to know
And it didn't work
I'm going to just give me more.
So
I started being more and more
No fighting with my dad mom
By the time I was 13 14
And
My mom was just really bummed out
About it cuz she tried everything she could to try to help me
Get back to the face
My dad was just mad he was just angry
Yeah it sounds like
At that point was probably sir typical teenage
Rebellion
What are you doing
Drugs that pointer or not
No I drink a little
I think I was 14 when I first drank some beer
Smoke some weed
Eventually it was got to be more and more of that
Not really agree with me to didn't do me any any favors
But at this point I was trying to find my way
Outside of the Adventist world
And
Find another misfit
Did you did you finish High School
No I took off
Itrip
On their second day of my senior year
Pick up cross country got stuck in the Braska and turn around came back
But you just took out you just like
Decided to
Just go
Ashura
I always was like I was wondering throw myself into situations and see what have
Android 17 and
I took off on this trip and I was about as naive as
And agreeing about life as you could get it
It started a
Sort of a lifelong thing of running away
I'm changing
Going somewhere and having to run away from there you know
Everywhere I went I was running away but
There I was
Every time
I guess pretty soon after you've dropped out of high school and we're trying to figure things out you
Decided to
To enlist in the Marines
It was just one more when were grass greener on the other side kind of an idea
And a friend of mine
Women's emergency was another Misfit like me another you know we would call ourselves losers that gas station
Do you want the Marines and it was just
He came back transform
Art's First Transformation I ever saw in my life
And
I thought well you know they can make a man out of me to write
But I went in the Marines and I wasn't ready for that
I just got hell I got help from those
Jokes.
And
I couldn't take it I wasn't I wasn't built for it in those days
Then I didn't have a thick skin at all and I eventually took off
Ran from there
So you head back to
Portland after that in
What did you do what do you remember about that time
Wasn't too long after that that I ended up getting married
It was just another crazy idea
And
I meant
My my first daughter
And we got married and
I was drinking and at this point I probably started doing
Cocaine
I was just doing cocaine but I wasn't at a level on a serious addiction level it was just a recreational level
So you are 22
Yeah kid
And you didn't
Really have much
Teacher
You know many fly prospects for the future
That's exactly yet I mean at that time I had no
Perspective on
You can go out in
And learn to become too
Create a life for yourself but
I didn't know that I didn't see that and I just thought I was born to lose I don't know anything everybody else
Else knows more than I do everybody else has
Is more
Built For Life
And I like myself I had such add and even though nobody would have
Calling 8080dn downstairs and I didn't
Have anyone that could diagnose me like that
I couldn't focus on a conversation
What we're having right now there's no way I could
I couldn't listen to anything and that's no problem I had the Marine Corps as I
I couldn't listen and I also was
I refuse to wear glasses and I was supposed to wear glasses
So I couldn't see
The chalkboard
I was just like
Lot of stuff with converging there
And a lot of bad stuff
I was just low self-esteem depression
I am I my thought was always
Well who wouldn't be depressed with a life like mine you know
That's a tough time in life for
Truck from most people
In general
Your brain is changing there's all kinds of things happen in Europe
Set of all of a sudden expected to be an adult here you are you got a child
With what appears to be like a growing
Alcohol and drug addiction and
Undiagnosed depression
On top of that
All those things and then I would smoke weed
I would do acid IB honesty
And
Almost always of the terrible results because
Your mind you can't go into
Trip like that
I have a my mind it's all torn up
I just gets worse
Remember the first time you use
Yes I do is the best it was my first transformation in life
It was the first time that I saw that my life could be a lot better at least an
Might think
The time
Wow and liquids retarded pranking
And
I'd always been warned Craigslist
Only for the
The lowest of the low
But at that point I was like well
I am kind of the lowest
109 brace
And
I didn't your very first time that I did the math
Put it my arm
And
I was instantly
Happy
And
Ready to go
And kick ass and
They made me just forget all the things that they were messing me up and I kind of just left the world that I was in
This bomber world that I was at and went to a world where I was happy
Problem with it would be when I would run out
And that happened a lot
Does yuan have money to
To get more if you have a job
Yeah
The first
You know I was working at the bakery
This is your family bakery
Yeah and last thing in the world I wanted to do was be a baker
I didn't want to be with my dad was I didn't want to be what anybody my family was
I
Didn't want to be
This guy always stop being a baker was a sissy thing you know
But I didn't know what else to do
Eventually it was unsustainable
And so I lost that job and I
Started doing
Car burglaries then eventually business and house burned
To the pain
For the dog
And you would steal things in like take him to pawn shops
Well we had
Countryside I would work with guys who have a little bit more experience
Vision
They would
Find ways to
Transportation
You know I I would feel guilty at times when I was robbing someone to see the kefir
Did they add I would feel that guilt and I never actually saying I'm sorry
The one person
But
Didn't matter I still have to do what I have to do
So since around like 1986-87 and this is going to be the beginning
Like 14 years maybe more maybe like 16 years
Remember the first time you were incarcerated for
Berkeley
Like you members but what you how you felt where you were we scare you
No
Does that time I could almost
Come to the conclusion that I was eventually going to go to prison
And that would be a good learning experience for me and I didn't like prison don't get me wrong I hated it
But
I also looked at the start of a badger
Who I was now
Will you
Were you ever a person violent or angry did you have
Was that inside of you
Throwing up bile
There's a lot of anger in my family that's one thing that
What sort of
The team with the territory the baker's all the Bakers in family we were all angry that
Just angry with
With the world with each other wasn't
With everything yeah I think
Looking Back Now I think my dad had similar problems that I had you know mine
He was
Probably bipolar like me
I saw him angry and I saw I'm depressed I'm angry and I saw today
So it sounds like during this period and in prison
You were cuddling with a combination of
Depression and anger
And
Addiction
Incredibly low self-esteem
Very long
I'm suicidal
Many many times
In my life
I would I have been suicidal when I put that needle in my arm
And so
You know you got understand that right
I was
Back Against The Wall nothing to lose
But I did it
Wow you are and I guess we should contextualize
The spit while you were
Imprison
The family bakery was still going on right
Your brother was involved
With it
But but why you were in prison
Your dad passed away
Yeah what are you were you able to go
To the funeral
I know because
I was confined
We talking with your dad at that point
In around the tire yard started to
Want to talk to my dad
But I wasn't quite to the
The point that I got
To later when I really wish that I
You don't got final
Know some time with them
So you're you're serving your final prison sentence you were going to be
You going to be incarcerated
For long time
Something happened to you
Made you start to think about
Your life in
What you wanted to be what
What was it what happened that you
Define God as a religious experience like what what was it
It was like that
My own form of God I guess
I experienced enough adversity
Enough
Time where I couldn't run away
I was either going to take myself out I was going to find a way cuz I really decided there's no reason why I should be able
But being at the end of my rope like I was
Finally
Did something that they talk about in AA I Surrender
I said well I'm going to let these
Authorities may be able to help me I'm going to give them a chance to help me
And it was a big deal because it's like you're telling on yourself in there you know
Last thing you want to do is tell the authorities
What's on your mind
But that was the wrong advice there right advice was just let down your guard and get some help
And I wasn't long after that I got called in and
I didn't tell him everything I didn't say I was suicidal because I didn't want to get in more trouble
But he said
Well look weird without this stuff compax or y'all try it
Rashad and
It was a Chantix quite a while to take effect but
Very quick with me and I
Sometimes I don't know how much of it was just the humility and
No deal that it took them to make that happen that change line
Yeah I think it might have been partial partially placebo effect by thinking
I think the drug did help
It works
I've been on a waiting list for a computer aided drafting program which was a vocational training opportunity very rare
Very rare
A great opportunity
Found out
The first I was just scared to death of it
Computers and your drafting I have no idea what they're talking about
But this time I
I didn't give up and I think a lot of the reason why I didn't give up is because of those meds and because I
I come to the point where I love and acceptance of who I am
Urgent Care Winona
I thought of miso
So I had a great time I just started within a couple weeks I was having a blast in there
And that changed my life
So you're you're in prison you're taking this drafting computer
Braided drafting course inside course you are
On antidepressants
You spent
Most of the previous 15 years of your life
Prison Blues sounds like
Assertive woke up one day like I'm almost 40
My
My perspective is changing I'm not your Dremel anymore obviously this is not working. I am not good at that
Definitely say
So December 27th
2 days after Christmas
You are released
The day you walked out of prison your brother Glenn
I reserved
Pick you up right
Remember any of the conversation was
I don't know who is he
He's your older brother isn't English 9 years older than you was he
8 years old
Was he
I don't know did he scold you was he judgmental Rosie just like hey you're out
No no I think that it seems different to me but he was still worried
But he
How to see what was going on when I was doing the Drafting and things and just gold deal where
Stop blaming people
Accountability
I didn't blame the system
The judge
It was all luck
I did this
I can I'm the one who's got the power to change it
So
I think my brother was a little bit
Put off by my
Energy
It was a little bit too much
Ikea
I can understand that I mean I would be wary to write
If if
That was me he had been sort of
Dutiful Network
Phone number for running your parents
Bakery in business and
Yeah he had managed to keep the business going various Ways by telling you cuz he was a hard worker and some
Mark
Somehow they managed to become contract
Manufacturers of
Stratford Trader Joe's which is really the best butterfly
Business before I go
So when he picked you up after you released did he say alright listen you know we got some work for you at the bakery
And watch coming and not working for us
A couple days is that is that what he said
The way I remember is that I asked him if I could come back
Cuz I've been thinking about how I
Make you think I can make a difference in the company
And show
He
Gave me that opportunity
I mean
Improve myself at the very low
Brie Larson
4 bucks an hour
Just baking loaves of bread and basically
That was the
Priority
Spread
Is a bigger thing was the marketing is how how can how can we appeal to younger
We were getting eaten up by the big guys who figured out ways to sell bread that was more popular
Sure I mean Glen
He said he could see where he could see the writing on the wall at the big
Companies
We're coming in undercutting
I mean they were probably there crossword
Follower
NHRA Fred wasn't telling you had to do was you had to do something right
In order for this business to grow
VA circuit asked you to kind of look around
Yeah I figured it out
The one thing I think they're the coolest thing that my brother
Dad was
Connor just let me do my thing you you said well
Very very much about their and stuff
Because of my experimenting with
As a drafter that's what you do you
Replicate
And then you
Make it better
Right yeah
That's what I did I would replicate other
Friday's our brother kind of bread they were they were popular on the market like we were just experimenting in the bakery and just
Trying different
Flowers out in Grantsville
I had always wanted to make
Get bread with great text
And
And one of the things I love is natural whole grain cereal
It's not
Beat up too much
Got to have some good shooting and stuff
And it doesn't matter to be weed oats whatever
So
I made a Soaker where you take the grass greens
And did you make them soft enough to make bread out of
But not too soft
So is texture that I was aiming for
4 + I was going for sort of a brown sugary flavor
Without brown sugar and soy are used organic cane juice and molasses for that flavor
I wanted to be like a masterpiece Sunday of our two and I didn't call it to the bread right away
Call the police Brad
The first one another
Yeah beautiful blue collar to act like I was aiming for
Attitude attitude
That blue color
Is just blue cornmeal
Like you rolled the labret the dough
Into the inside and out
And
Every breath that I made pretty much are named first
And then I created
So I never think I wear makeup
Europa Blues by one of my for My bride is going to be called Blue
Cuz I love the blues I like then I was like
Well the other one was always killer Brett and I always wanted to make a variety called Killer Bread
And the biggest difference in it was it it was made with nuts and seeds rather than just
Seeds and greens
When you were experimenting with the different kinds of Breads in the
What would become Dave's Killer
Red Lake
I don't remember taking that first low-fat remember remember knowing that didn't remember about that
Oh man it was great I never forget it
It had a great fullness to it
Your beauty
To the shape
And the blue Carmel was
I just made it like no other bread before it
It was really beautiful
I took it out of the oven X5 low
And
Tasted it
Pretty quickly and as I girl got this is good I mean
It fits my flavor profile
You know what I want and then I gave a loaf
Toarmina's guy
I think we had like 25-30
Employees at the time that the maintenance guy
Took one home and it came back the next day and he just couldn't stop raving about
Eventually. No more people to
More people are starting to
Jd.com
Goodbye
Kid cashew technical question because obviously right like I Made bread and
I mean a big things before and
Can you take out of the oven and eat
Right away like whether it's a chocolate chip cookie or a piece of bread
Is amazed girl
The test is whether it still good 4 hours later right
So I can imagine your bread was amazing but like this had to be
Bread that considered shelf of a supermarket or grocery store
So I had it like
Still great like I don't know
5 hours later
The next day we party every would beat it
Not because that's very hard not a good test
Oh how good it is and you know
The process
About how it's done and rotated and everything
Now it's got to be got to be good for 5 days on the Shelf
There and it's got to be good for a few days once I get it
Yeah they don't
People
Really didn't expect it to be the last forever
Cuz it's natural and doesn't have
Chemicals in air
Yasso
Herb actor
That was my slogan just say no to bread on drugs
Those days that was pretty popular slogan
Alright so you make that loaf
Your maintenance guy comes back the next day
You know that you're onto something and then did you did you go to Glen your brother and say
Hey try this out
Yeah I wanted him to love it you know
But it wasn't his idea of a
Killer part of a great brat
What are given so much credit for
Is that
Even though he didn't really like my bread
He understood that it wasn't his taste buds it matter
Totally
Give him props for that
He wasn't controlling
Like most companies
Would say I hate you
We got to keep this in this price
You can't go beyond this and
Fortunately he did not say that
I remember when we got to the point
Realizing we did a cost analysis on it and we started realizing how much we're going to sell this for
And it was it more difficult bread to make that and then
The average loft bed
How much did you have to sell it for
We went to the farmers market
And we sold it at $4
Mandu nothing brings was 450 cuz if the nuts were more expensive
Count for 4/4 50 in in mm 1X
Expensive
Yeah
I think everybody was worried about the price
And
They also they didn't like the bread I mean in the
Hopper
The upper management of the company small company but the people they've been around for a while
It was sort of a
And this is why bread is and this is not rich so cap
So what we did is
It was actually a opportunity this was actually a project that
My nephew and I
This was our opportunity to build equity in a company
And that was really what my brother said he was he would always on 51%
But
He was going to give us an opportunity to buy into the company in the in order to buy in
We had to produce sales
Sweetheart to increase revenues
CU Century Spanish
User created a separate company
To sell these are for the brand separate brand
And my nephew and myself we ran that
We ran the operation this is Glenn son show B
And then she'll be used like a prodigy kid you know really smart kid
Even graduated in three years magnacumlaude
Latte volume say that
Willamette University Witches of East Asia
Good University
In economics about the
He gets out he's 21 21 years old he gets
The same year I got out of prison he gets out of college
Walker and he had a whole different way of looking at things
And he really didn't like me be around but
We were partners and we managed to
To find ways to work together and
We had our own duties at waiver
Riverdale for the most part in that kind of
Episode of each other's way you were the guy who came up with the actual
Product you came up with Dave's Killer Bread
But
Let's let you serve reflecting the true moment
I mean
It's probably unlikely that
You know Dave's Killer Bread would have become a brand at this
Point
Without
Your brother and his son's business Act
Arbitration possible for that
Wake up first of all my dad starting what he did
You been on my dad was basically a knucklehead like me
I worked his butt off but he didn't really
Yeah I know he wasn't a businessman for saving his like that was his Focus he was creator
And he was a hard worker and that's what I see myself as
My brother and my nephew had more definitely had more of the
They were looking at the finances
All that stuff more than I was always
Passion
And so
There was a lot of disagreements on how things should be done but
Honestly
There were many times that because it it felt so bad
That way we the way we got on
Dad
It almost derailed
And
What was so what was so hard about I mean I mean obviously
You know your side
Story but I mean
What was was it just a Personality Clash like
Definitely
That was definitely the attitude that while this guy comes out here in these kind of a
A wrecking ball
Just got here just ladies I could Cowboys shoot from the hip
Downdraft the stuff he does fails and you know
You are crazy
Did you guys founded this
Brandon 2005
Right and no one knew what Dave's Killer Bread was in 2005 no one is really going to know what it was for several more years
Welding
Attention to get attention was there tension between you and your brother and your nephew from the
Beginning like even
I'm getting really
Very very frightening
Oh my God
And the way I always thought it was
People love my story they load what I gone through and how it overcome it
But my family
Was too close to it or something and didn't
That way
And they saw his more like well he doesn't deserve this
But I I went out and
I had a lot of love
From the
From the people in the community.
You talk like you're storing loose and look what I'm doing now
Yeah it was in the actually wrote my story put it on the back of the bag it was like a few paragraph
I've got in front of me it starts semi was a four-time loser before I realized I was in the wrong game
15 years in prison is Pretty Tough way to find oneself but I have no regrets
And it went on
Describe
Does Pratt University
They trying to make the world a better place one loaf of
Bread at a time
That must have been incredibly powerful for people to see that on the packaging and this is when you're still just selling at farmers
Rockets ride
Yeah and
I would sit there Tyrell standard Farmers Market
Passover bread
Do this doctor this attorney at law
Sweethome professional person and
People I never would have met
You know and I started meeting these great people and they loved the idea and you left the bread
Pretty
Pretty soon after you launch did you did you put the cartoon like the caricature
Have you on the on the
On the rapper yeah you know how that came about was my Wii
My brother my nephew and myself
Sitting with you copyright attorney Mike
My type
He said it was bread great you know you got
Goodnight I think the name parade
You know what you're missing is a logo
My brother had been suggesting that we have
A picture of me on the back with my guitar at with my story
And I thought that was a good idea
But when I heard this guy talking about the
I said
I started sketching
And I ended up scratching the idea I had was
This guy
Who represents me
With his guitar
And
Dave's bread in big block letters all this is
Painted on the wall on a brick wall
Are and our
That somebody comes along with their
Red spray paint contacts killer over
And that doesn't ever show up that nobody ever gets that from looking at the
That what we ended up with
That was originally
Oh yeah that's the killer now I see that that's the graffiti on the rug I got you okay
Logo is really hard
By the way I read an end and please be honest with me
Just was this level with me I read that you add on
I asked I rather you ask the cartoonist to make your biceps bigger in that cartoon
I said no I don't think about you
I need a bigger
Cuz they're they're definitely a little a little exaggerated
And they like the idea of calling a Dave's Killer Bread
They is no it's interesting thing we went to a marketing firm
Tell the story this ex-con is Killer Bread
Band
They're like now that's too risky
Allison hunt
I can't remember the Dynamics of all the situation but I did get kicked out of
The marketing meeting tonight
Very you know
Number to happy about that but eventually I know that my brother and my nephew came around to the idea that
The killer bad idea and they're contacting which was going to be acceptable
You know this marketing firm is full of crap
Let me come back at Dave and his family take their Killer Bread from the farmers market to the supermarket
And then later
Why Dave was banned physically band
From walking into the very company he helped start
Play with us
I'm guy Roz and you listening to how I built this
From NPR
Everyone just a quick thanks
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast
Possible
First two are how I built this 2019 lead
Sponsor
Hiscox
Business insurance experts
Do you understand that
Each business is
As unique as a
Fingerprint or barcode
Tailors in
Halogen Insurance Solutions to fit every business has very specific needs
Which may explain their 97% customer service rating
Get a quote for purchase a policy at hiscox.com
Hiscox
Business insurance
Thanks also to E-Trade
With all the jargon
Best thing to feel like a foreign language
E-Trade makes investing simple by providing
Personalized
Guidance
Terms you can understand
They let you get started in the market with as little as
$500 and then help you learn as you go
You don't need to be a pro too invested
E-Trade
For more information
Etrade.com NPR
E-Trade securities
LLC
There's more to watch and read these days than any one person can get
That's why we make pop culture happy hour
From NPR
Twice a week we sort through the nonsense share reactions and give you the lowdown on what's worth your pressure
Listening
Prescribed NPR pop culture happy hour
Welcome back to how I built this from NPR guy Raz so into that
5 Dave's Killer Bread is getting more popular the lobes are selling their media attention
And people love the story of Dave dalby ex-con turned his life around with bread but
To this point he's just been selling the Lowe's at the farmers market and that's just a seasonal thing
As the market was coming to a close around November ish before like or how you going to hell
Are we going to have this bread
And
Nebraska
Tell your local stores don't stores you buy it tell them you want the bread there and they didn't taste
Started and we got into one small Coop and we got into one vegan grocery
And then in a couple more months we got into New Seasons which was like
First big
Big Break
But it was
Boyle's Law
A lot of work doing all those demos
Oh my God
I think so
You launch this
Your brother and your nephew
It's got about 30 employees obviously you're sort of a side project
Of nature bag
Make it right I got time this
At that time
It may not be so fast but look when you should look back on it
Like
Within
I think five years
You have $190
Employees
Working for you what
What was the turning point do you remember what when it just started
Blow up
We were at a small okay we had a 15000 square foot facility that was making nature baked when I
I got out of prison
Within a very short time we outgrew that
And
We had to find time on the floor to We Are
Where to share our time
With nature bake production and we are totally different cruise and they're actually kind of that each other's throats kind of like my
My brother and my right hand
We moved out of there I don't know how many
Employees who probably at a hundred plays or so it might I don't think we even had a hundred of the time you probably 50
When we moved out of the
Add to Bob's Red Mill sold facility
We know Bob's Reverend I could we go back a long way without Bobby's Valley show
That I know I got her one episode and I enjoyed it
And Bob is great he's a wonderful guy in fact
My dad
Was Bob's first
A holy flower
Wholesale custom
So you guys move until you move into an old Bob's Red Mill facility to expand production of
Of Dave's Killer Bread
Yeah and
The biggest challenge we had at this point
2007-8 I can't remember
My brother needed to get
I didn't have any credit I didn't have anything
Sure sure
Martin Museum Showbiz young and didn't have anything
Established
So
Glenn have to go to the bank put up his house
Couldn't get our regular Bank
You're one of the biggest banks in the country
Wouldn't take a chance on me
Yeah so we had to get a local bank who was willing to it'll take that chance in Philly High retire
Interest rate
Riccottis a million-and-a-half to move to this new facility in a million 1/2 to us then was
A lot of money insurance
And there was no cash for support.
Ratings are based on future
So he put up a basic mortgage
Take out second mortgage or line Credit against his house
If you love The bit right to get some Capital to fund the business
Yanez house wasn't enough to
Burton collateralized
Dial.
They have to take a chance on
And everything maybe they would have owned everything
We have made it
So how are you able to to get any equity in the company if you had no
No cash like how are you able to
Get any ownership over this
Benjamin my brother sold it to us for our percentage of the valuation of the business
At the time that we started our project
Right and instead of owning a certain a larger percentage of Dave's Killer Bread I settled on a small
Entire company of nature
Yes
And I'm very glad
So-and-so had you guys
Continue to to expand like
Check into
Bigger chance
Costco at how did you do that
What Costco
I would get this letter this I got this email from somebody at Costco and buyer
Chain
Our customers are asking for your bread
And we would like you you're come up and present to us
Well
We were still at
The old facility
15000 square feet
And absolutely no way we are going to be able to have a Costco
But the fact that we
Add Costco coming with a big factor in how we got
Actually executing the idea was a whole nother matter
It took us a long time to
Finally reach a deal and finally have the
Ability to produce enough bread to meet gospel demand
And we just kept working and working and working and promoting and
We're able to secure
Partners in Commack
Co Manufacturing
I sent the other other
Facilities at 1
Bake your recipe
Be to your specification
Cuz you couldn't possibly have done that
All on your own for Costco right
Does the scale was going to know if possible
I know and I'll tell you what man when you have a cold shower of a product
Trying to get another culture II
Adopt it
Is a hole
Is a whole nother challenge
Create
That product
Have consistent quality
Weather reel
Was a real bear
I would
Go and see the operation surprise them
And I was very
I'm pleasantly surprised myself sometimes Suunto
We were able to get it right
Button people
People will cut Corners when they get a chance
And so we
Did work our asses off to make sure that that didn't happen
To Costco I mean the Costco deal
Clearly transformation
Because you had to scale up fast
Increase number of employees and it was going to
Create huge
Remy stream huge windfall
At a certain point
About a third of your Workforce
So now you're getting close to
The 300 people
We're ex-cons like was that was that a hint
Was it deliberate thing like that you think are hiring other ex-convicts
To work because it's really hard to get a job when you've got
A record made from your desk on
It was special then it's
Got a little better now
You know I had a certain mentality about that that came from my own experience of having Transformer
I like I was like
You know this is something this is a real thing
People do change and when they're ready
How great would it be to give them that opportunity and then we get an amazing play
So it just made sense to hire some of that
But that wasn't something weird
Hannah Wednesday
Once once they're temporary services in that's how we
McGregor people generally share once they found out
Dad we were felon friendly it was funny. All they sent us
We were hiring so fast
Dad are we ended up hiring a lot more felons
And it just worked out
I think around
I think it was like 2011
2012 Yukon O2 in like 40
15 million dollars
Selfridge
Which is phenomenal
And I guess I guess around a time you you get an offer from
The private Equity company
Dubai in
And I bought out
The Catholic company in 2012
Exactly how I feel
But I think around this time like the relationship between you and your brother and your nephew is so bad that at times you guys were little
Emailing each other in the same office
Which from an outside perspective
Just seem so
Sad like a
I think people would say what Kaiser
You're so successful like
Protestant so great
Hiring ex convicts
Are you seriously not getting along like
It just seems so
Weird but then of course family Dynamics are complicated
They are
Yeah I don't even know how to explain it I
But we did have it you know this is why is this thing we ever did
And I think this
Was Predator my brother
That we got someone
That could
If Isis is guy was actually a family business advisor but mainly menu for succession plans for things like that
Right but he said
You guys need a vision and a mission
You guys have it but you don't all agree on what it is
And
He was right
And once we got those established
And they're pretty simple
Like one of them like to Visionworks
Make the world a better place one loaf of bread the time
So I was
Gratifying
They agreed to that
And so we were able to
Solve some of our problems and get along and
Be in the same room
Cu
I mean pretty quickly and I guess by this point 2012 you
You became famous like you are the
What does caricature on the bread
People want to know your story you're doing media you're speaking
How do you feel about that did you did you love that attention
I did because it was for a good reason I felt I always felt like I was doing
Good work
You know
Like there was a purpose in for the first time in my life I had to
Purpose
It was just
Unbelievable
What was happening in love I was getting and I really couldn't keep up with demand for speaking
But I never
Had a prepared speech
You know
I was just so out then like.
As You Are
As your profile was
Growing
Do you think that it had an I mean I must have had an impact on your own
Eagle races naturally it would have normally the more attention you get the more people hanging out the more people telling your amazing the more people
You're awesome you're great all day visit like
You probably can't inflate
Yuri get right
And I tried you know the thing that helped me so much with my transformation in life
The two things were acceptance and humility
Yeah and so when this was happening I was always telling myself look you know I'm very fortunate
Blessed and grateful for this
I was always trying to tell myself
Stop that
And
Unfortunately
You know I took my first vacation a few years hence
Went to Mexico
And
I discovered tequila
It took me years for it to have to graduate to a level where I was really an alcoholic full-blown alcoholic
But you were drinking all that all along White even after
You got a prison
A beer or two here and there
The other people would get wasted
It was until things got easier. Easier and I have more employees during my working
Eventually it was easier to drink and just be a drinker and
Milo, successful I'm kind of a rockstar see there you go there's that bad creeping reunion
And so I can afford to do this and I even would call myself tozzi of bread you know
Apple speak to a group of kids like that
High school or whatever and then right afterwards. Celebrate by
Drinking 1/2
And then I drink the other half later and you know and then eventually it was a half gallon
I think it's safe to say was a pretty
Rough year for you to attack
That happened that year
Do the moment that year where you were
Outside of the
Cover story of Dave's Killer Bread of the facility in Portland in
Maybe you were
You're drunk or you are having
Mannequin
I had drank for several weeks at that point I'd
I showed up that day
I had decided that day that I was going to
Go against the new CEOs mandate that I was not supposed to
On the property
I was very rude
About this and watch on a property because they thought you were disruptive at that point
Yeah they
They just
Well
One of the things that happened was
Before this
Iodine up to my cabin. I just cabin on Mount Hood
And
I taking some guys with me and one of the people
One of the guy that took with me I shouldn't
Original buddy there was
That we were Joe Patti's way back in the day
Replica cabin long story short he leaves
He left in your car right there my car
And I let him
Yeah I was like you stole it Irish
I was too drunk to even
Use my
Lose my head
And
This guy ends up
They find him in a ditch 40 some-odd Days Later
Decomposing
It's really everything in
Yeah company
First of all
Said well you need to get an attorney
And
They started
Been out of control
They must have been worried because
Four Seasons first of all
You're implicated
Whether you know not directly but indirectly in this guy's des and
And you are the brand you are Dave you are David kind of distracted and
And there there was horrible
Yeah and honestly you know when that guy died
I was heartbroken too
You know
Yan final aeon
November 14th I believe was
I have been not drinking for
68 weeks I got I don't know for sure
I was getting more and more resentful and
There was there was becoming a clash between me and the company and hear this company that I work so hard
Gillibrand
So I'm feeling this loss and losing my company
Losing my grandmother
Baby
And one things leading to another and finally
That day I showed up at bred quarter
And I'm not quite your level
I see this cardboard cutout of myself
And without actually forming the thought in my mind what I was thinking what I was feeling was like this
Sky
This cardboard cutout of me and be here in this
In the storefront and I can't
Enchilada pasta
I never liked it anyway so I punched it
And it didn't make any sense none of it makes any sense
But at the time
I realize that's you know it was just resentment
And the day just got worse from there
Yeah I mean it
It got a lot worse like
Like you ended up
I think later that night
You ended up a ramming your your SUV into
Two cop cars
And you were right
I went to jail
For like 36 hours
And I was seeing all this stuff about me on TV
And I wasn't you know I was freaky
But my attorney tells me
Look dude
You have to check in
To Cedar Hills Hospital
Palmetto Hospital
Because you're not quite right
Eventually
I did follow his advice went there and checked in
And stay there
For like
Two and a half weeks and it was a good move
So this is now the beginning of the next
Episode of your rebirth
Because
It already had that reverse in 2001 in prison that
And you kind of
Amazing
Run of success
And then
Really hard
Yeah
You know after that two and a half weeks in the hospital where and which I was very
Hypomanic and just like
Laughing joking knucklehead
I was back in my home
I hit the bottom I had the biggest
The most painful bottom I've ever hit and it was after I read this story about myself in the Willamette Week
Breaking bread which was reading bad
Sure
And
I
Got rid of thought well that's funny breaking Brad Hendricks with the Breaking Bad logo and I got
That's cool when I'm still in a good frame of mind and then
I would say a good friend of mine but she just happy
Until I read that article and it was the worst thing I've ever seen about myself
I just hit me that
Wow I have
Hybrid
I'm a big
Problem I am Eatery I'm something really good or I'm
Something really bad and I'm really bad
And look what I've done I've let down all these people
Always employees
All these investors
All these your people who believed in me
And
I just couldn't live with that
It just hit me so hard
Panda
It took me awhile to come out of that depression
I mean it really speaks to this idea that
Cuz at this point
You already had some money like
You were clearly going to
Become a wealthy man
And it was already welcomed at this
And we sold the first half of the business
Made it speaks to this idea that
Money doesn't solve
Everything in oftentimes can can exacerbate
Things right it's like
Cast from the outside somebody might say
Your life
How did the right and you're saying but you can't understand cuz I can
Can't even understand
You couldn't I couldn't explain to your cell phone
No it's a it's a
It's Unique
And
Over the moon shatter circumcised
Yeah
Money has nothing to do with happiness
Never never has I knew that from the beginning because I was so happy without ever making any money
I am used to having money now
So I would hate to be without it
But
Really
Things are good because
I'm good you in my space
At that point after you history hit that low did you decide
To do alcoholics anonymous
They had to say you really have to do the writing
I didn't really have a choice I've liked
Alcoholics Anonymous
Yuan the 12 steps are just great
Very meaningful
I probably go anyway this point but
Something I have to do
Is a struggle for you everyday
To avoid alcohol
It has been a time
But not been quite a while
One of the things that I have some insurance policy and I
I believe it helps his
Vivitrol
That's the brand name of this thing that's kind of very modern antabuse
Did you take a shot
I just shot every month
What what is a medication that that's Roblox inhibits
Not supposed to enjoy you would really enjoy yourself on it if you get a sword girl why
Why screw around with it
When it's not even going to be a good experience
That's a very good attorney
So you are
Right now
At this point in your life
In recovery still and really working at it the company
Seoul
Entirely sold Dave's Killer Bread
No longer owned by the family of the
Get sold for
Almost 300 billion dollars and you
I'm your nephew Shelby went on to do other Ventures and he's involved in investing you've got
An art gallery in Portland
What's your relationship like
With your brother Glenn and
Internet future hubby
Well it's
It's in limbo I guess
I haven't
I would like to think that someday we will
Do more family than just like
Former business partners
It's not it we just don't talk
Sometimes we have family gatherings that have nothing to do with
They're not put on by any of us and we might meet meet up there
But what I want to do
This is weird I'm telling you this instead of that I'm but
I just want something
Real real
What happened you know I don't want
I don't want to
Force anything in
I just hope I just hope to have
At the end of this before we all die
Ditto sexy my brother and myself
Now that we're going to find something some peace
You know
When you think about
How do you think about your story is amazing
Maria Dobson the downs and the
And all that you've been through which I think a lot of people could identify with because
This is not a seamless
This is not a simple story of going from one success to
Another success like
Keypad
You have a lot of ups and downs and you
And you're open about in your honesty
Super Soul thank you
I realize the power of
I realized it really early on
That a lot of people care about the story
And they would have been for the bread the story by wouldn't matter that much
Anyway it feels good to talk about
How much of what happened to you I mean the success of a
The good sides of
Do you think more because of
Your hard work and your intelligence and your skill and how much of it do you think is
Is because of locking and
The luck that you know
Shobie and Glenn were there too
Take a note
Sorcier in that product a
Potential
Samantha Testa
Ebag
Yeah
Lot of bad luck before we good looking
When it comes to being a millionaire and becoming very successful businessman
That is not something that
Would have happened probably without
You don't have any nose associations
But who knows where we're going to see tonight
The most demiracle evolved
This was the transformation I had in prison
That was What mattered
Because my mind was
Free I felt free
And
We're having the contrast between the adversity that I've had my
And what I was going through
And I mean just being able to create and
Just keep working towards something
You know
That was that was the miracle
That's Dave Dahl
Co-founder
Dave's Killer Bread
How do I get the cartoon version of Dave is still on every package
Get the bread
Biceps as big as ever
Dave no longer has a mustache that's in the package but
Play his guitar band name
Dave Dahl and the killer granddaddies
Can't hear they are
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
Things your building
The first
A quick message from one of our sponsors Squarespace
All-in-one platform to build an online presence
Run your business
Squarespace.com NPR
Free trial
Then use the offer code NPR to save 10%
First purchase
Website or domain
What if videogames can help you and your child Bond
Alert important
Scallops
NPR life kit for parenting is
Taking on screen time
One of the big things were working on right now is the concept of resilience
And not quitting what's up
It's hard sometimes you lose and lose and loose
And games
Great with that check out life
Kids new guidance
Meantime or subscribe to life kit all guides
Oliver app
All-in-one
Hey thanks so much for sticking around.
For how you built that a story starts with
A recipe
Black pepper essential oil in Caleb OTC Buckthorn
Auntie Greek mountains Erica foyt she lives in Livermore Colorado with her husband Jason
Seasalt clothes Capricorn arrowroot elderflower
Go into a natural deodorant
That Jason and Erica make and sell is called Hit liquor
Emphasis on the liquor vodka whiskey whiskey
Key ingredients in pit liquor deodorant because like most spirits
They can actually kill the bacteria that make us smell bad
But beyond that whiskey has cannons in it which are antibacterial in and of themselves
And then it's something that's fun anyway all this came about a few years ago when Erika was pregnant
She was looking for a natural deodorant that would work without making her break out and so Jason
And decided to see if
He can make some
Even though he had absolutely no it's
Experience in deodorant like
His day job
With an it I actually spend a lot of time reading textbooks on deodorant
And on armpit
Old textbooks yes there are actually textbooks Unturned
To alter out 2016
Jason was trying to find the
Perfect Blend to fight Bo
Mixing vodka whiskey and essential oils
Black teeth
And then storing these concoctions in mason jars around the house
He tested all of them out
On Erica
He stopped showering his armpits he stopped watching the
Wood
Come to me
And say I Street st. John's wort and vodka on this armpit and I have juniper berries and
This weird tea from China
On this other armpit I want you to smell him and tell me which smells better and can I just say hear that
Imma show we talked to a lot of Founders were also married couples
But this
This is like a whole new level of collaboration if you've ever stuck your nose in an armpit you don't have good eggs
Vacation
And I finally got
Sick of smelling
The book I think you have a winner
Please stop I'm done I'm tired
And it turns out Jason really did have a winner
A mix of tea and vodka and whiskey and essential oils
That works really well for him and Erica
But what about everybody else
So we
Reached out to her friends on Facebook and said hey anyone want to try a natural deodorant that we formulated
Can their friends signed up
They tried it they liked it words
The spread and
American Jason kicked it into high gear
They raised a little bit of money and they've started to ramp up production of the deodorant
But then
Customers
Complain about something the couple had not anticipated
They were really angry with
He's white spray caps that we had
Like people
We're telling us that when they sprayed the cap
The alcohol was
Viewing up around their finger
In like a fountain Italy
Looks like Old Faithful
So are kind json tried different
Cat's butt
The captain claw game
It basically lead us to a place where we're sending out free cats
Three bottles of deodorant new bottles
And we just we basically just Hemorrhage money
After a frantic search
Erica Jason eventually found a cat that was
Sturdy enough
Deliver the deodorant
Set the bottle cap prices
Almost
The company
It seems like it's almost like falling down Alice's
Side rabbit hole
In Alice in Wonderland
Is it's just so incredibly d
And there's so much to do it's scary
Terrifying but the bottom line is it's
The blast pit liquor is now averaging about $20,000 a month
Sales
And the company hopes to be profitable by this summer
And by the way
Some of the folks in our team have
Actually sampled the deodorant and
They say it works and smells pretty great
Very clean neighborhood bar but
To be clear
It is not drinkable
So don't drink it
For the same reason nobody
Drinks are hand sanitizer nobody should drink
Cody should drink 3002
Jason Floyd
Is white Erica are the co-founders of
Pit liquor deodorant if you want to find out more about the company or your previous episodes
How I built this. Org
Npr.org and thanks for listening to the show this week you can subscribe apple pie
Cast or wherever you get your podcast and while you're there please give us a review
You'd also write to us at hidta npr.org
I sure was produced this week by James delahoussaye with original music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Our editor
Thanks also to Julia Carney sanaz meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Is David Rock
I'm guy Roz and even listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR