Support for how I built
Send the following message
Come from Michigan Economic Development
If you want to start or grow your bed
Michigan is the place to make it happen
Learn
Why by searching Michigan pure Roberts
We had a great artist
And he did a woodcut portrait of Bert and we started putting that on the package
A very conscious decision to use Burt's face he have a long grey beard and long grey crew
Curly hair in a bun as a woman who could never measure up to this
Glamorous image in mainstream cosmetics and beauty products you know I felt like where
Going to put a picture of a guy that everybody is going to feel more
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Stories behind the movement
Roxanne
And turn it in
Burt's Bees
One of the biggest natural Personal Care brands
In America
Every Sunday at my local farmer's market
There are people who sell homemade hot sauce and
Handcrafted wallets
A woman who sells mohair
Scarves using the mohair from her Angora goats
Going to your local farmers market in
Seimei
Back in the mid-1980s
And if you happen to be near Bangor
You might have come across Roxanne Quimby and
Burt shavitz selling jars of honey
How do you from birds
Own beehive
Turning right
Maybe by a jar and move on bird and Roxanne will keep on doing what they were doing you do what you were do
Doing
Except Roxanne.
Do we make and sell
Candles from beeswax we have or
Can we use the beeswax to make
Other stuff
Okay so you can kind of figure out where this is headed because of that of course
Is what happened
And even the rocks and never intended to build a
Billion dollar brand or even a million-dollar brand
Get
Just happened
Of course a lot of that had to do with Roxanne
Passionate
And drive but the idea was never to build something massive
What's a farmers market product
Today
Walking to any drugstore in the US or even overseas
And you will find an impressive display of Burt's Bees products
Lip balm lotion soap
Shampoos
All labeled with the face of a heavily bearded man named
Bert
The likelihood that Roxanne Quimby would build a massive company or any company at all
Was so implausible back in the early 1980s
When she was a single mom waiting tables at a diner
And a decade before that
She drove across the country from Massachusetts
Scrum
The San Francisco seeking out a simpler life alive
Without lots of material needs
It was
Adventure
To go all the way to the West Coast
From New England and New York
It was a great unknown
And I had always wanted to be an artist on the time I was 5 so it seemed like a natural
Place to go Art School
I guess you got there in
But like 1970 around then
Tell me what tell me what your impression of the San Francisco or like
I think San Francisco kind of
Unlocked itself
To me while I was there
It was a pretty little town but the
Depth of experience that I had their took some time to
Assimilate and understand you know by
I crossed the great cultural
Bridge
While I was out there
What do you mean by that
I learned
To think
Differently
And
To probe more deeply
Everything needed to be re-evaluated and
Looked at
Again
So you start to sing
Like what your old the way you thought of the world
Before versus wrong
Well it was too Limited
And I think that
The material world was
Two important
And
Really
It's not as important as
I was taught that it was
We were encouraged
Make a good living both of my sisters
Mbas like my dad did and
Earning power and ones achievements were emphasized
I took a turn
To the extreme left
When I went to art
School
Rejected
The
Pursuit of
Material comfort
Who's really quite wonderful
Yeah
An insult
Yuan San Francisco and you're
Kind of going through this
This transformation is personal transformation of rejecting your
Go out earn money kind of
Where you were raised which was the way many many many
People raped
And
What did you think did you think I don't need that life I want a different life it was
What did you start to think about the life you wanted to have
Well I wanted meaning
And I wanted to live deeply
I was
Very influenced by Thoreau
Who wrote about it
Quite beautifully
I was looking for Transcendence
I just my world just got bigger
And I felt my relationship with it
Expanded
I guess you had a boyfriend in San Francisco at the time
And the two of you decided to like
Go off
Around the country to find a place to
The web
Yeah
This is George Saint Clair
Your boyfriend
And and
And so we
Would you guys do just
You took off Elissa
Yep.
Saturday I'm sick
Shh. We had $3,000
We went to
Vermont
And the Vermont
Realtor
That we spoke with
Sad that
You couldn't buy any land in Vermont for $3,000 but tri-main
So we went to me so your intention was to go
Somewhere in the country with $3,000
She Wolf
How much land you can buy
Yes and why did you want to
Do that what were you going to do on the way
There was a movement at the time the back
To the land movement
Aldosworld
People that had left City Life
And
We're just like a
I was doing it
To strip away everything
That civilization had Laird on
Me and see what was really important
So
The land that we bought we built a little cabin on it and had
No running water no electricity and so
It quickly
Became more aware of
How those things affected your life
When you didn't have them she had three thousand bucks and how much land did I buy you like how many acres
That's a lot
What to do
Well there were a few books
You could read about how to build a simple house
In the woods
And we would pick people's brains who knew more than we did
They were glad to see some young people moving to Maine because we've had
Quite an exodus of young people so
Hayward
Very friendly and helpful
So I mean
Did you build a cabin did you build a house on a slab
Yes
How long does it take to I'm assuming this is
You get there in the summer is like 70 and 1975 or so some
Like that
And then how long before you're actually living in a
A place with a roof over your heads
How it was the way too long
We had built a little screen house
Where we were sleeping which was a little ways away from the house we were building
And
It was getting into December
And we are still sleeping outside
Basically it was outside
Was so hard to get out of bed in the morning out of the sleeping bag
But you know everything that
Could go wrong
Take out
And
Enoteca
A lot longer than we thought it would
Try to get Undercover
But
We had a roof over our heads
Did you heat
We had a wood stove
Yeah
Like this like pre global warming Maine
Into December
Yats
Stream
But there were others
You know we weren't the only ones
Do you build a house and you like
Still no running water electricity or any of that stuff for that but you do have to eat so how are you making a living
Well
The good thing about not having all the amenities is that it doesn't
Take a lot of money
Live
We had no
Bill's basically other than food
Cut around firewood and
Had a source of water which was the spring out in back
I waitress
A day or two a week
And George worked at the local radio station for
Add a week
So couple of days a week we would go out and work for
Things that
Needed cash
Are you do this for a couple years right you guys are living like this for
Several years
Yeah
I think we probably lived out there like that for maybe 7 years or so
Wow I can't around
Like in the first few years you actually had children
Children who are still in grow their grown up
Date they were born in this
Like Homesteader
Kind of houses out in the middle of
Yeah they have very fond memories of it
We never had to argue about
TV shows
Yeah
So
You're living there you're with your waitressing a little bit
George is working
Get the radio station you got two kids
But probably still he didn't need a whole lot of money
Get through the day
No
We were living on about $4,000 a year
I'm just trying to get into your head that
Was that your vision for life
Life that you were going cuz it's kind of
If there is an idyllic about
I mean
You're out there
You're far away from
The rough-and-tumble of civilization
Cities
Was that
Your vision for the way you're going to live your life
It was simply a way of
Having a
A secure
Home
And
I think it was
I'm very idyllic
Kind of dream
But ultimately
It didn't provide enough
Stimulation for my
Personality
Why
What's your personality
Well I think I'm
Kind of a Restless person
Pretty curious
And
Interested in the way the world works
How tall
Put together
So we were
Pretty cut off out there
So you guys are out there and
I guess your marriage were or partnership with George Kenosha
Was not in great shape because you guys
You did separated a certain point right
We did yeah
Hanna and Lucas were six years old
And I moved out
And I moved into another traffic allows even further off the road wow
Is like 80 82 or
GrubHub Reagan there may be 83
So you are a single mom
Qkids
On your own
That's
Tough going
Well although I was a single mom their dad was a single dad
Right he definitely took
A lot of responsibility for their care
And so
Every other week
I had the opportunity to go out and do what I needed to do or
Or whatever sure
What are you happy
At that time
Probably not
You know I don't think about
Being happy that much I feel I think more about being fulfilled
Yeah you feel fulfilled at that time
I did
Yeah I felt like I was making it On My Own by you know
Living by my wits so to speak yeah
And I like that and I like the unknown it was an adventure it was sort of like fishing you never knew what you were going to come up
My boyfriend
And that was always fun at tested you're my resourcefulness I always thought
That was a good thing too
To test and keep nimble
Yeah
So
You are in Northern
Northern Central Maine
Mid eighties
And how did you come across
Burt shavitz
Well he was
He was well-known
In
The neighborhood
Because he was so unusual
What you mean
Well as usual at the time to write
Yes but he was probably more than usual
What do you mean like what do you mean when you said
Well he
He look like an old rabbi
Anyway he has a long Gray beard and long gray curly hair
And he was
Bachelor
And sold honey on the side of the road
Off the back of his pickup truck
And you just Neubert through the community you weren't
ORD 32GB
Meet him on Montfort
Particular day
Well I did meet him personally when he pick me up hitchhiking cuz I didn't have a car.
The time
So I got to meet him but I think I was vaguely aware of him just because he was one of the fixtures
In the
Area and he would sell honey
From bees that he raised
Stripes
To eat so you can meet me to cyber and
He sells honey and
That's it likes
See you later and
And
And then you go off
Your own separate ways
Yeah I was waitressing one night or two nights a week
And
Used to stop in to use
The Payphone there
He didn't have a phone
And he lived the same way no phone no electricity in a little tiny cabin
That he had hauled over to his property
It was a turkey coup
He was quite proud of him
Very
Eccentric
Hermit
Fellow
But there must have been some kind of connection that
You forged because
Yeah I guess you decided to
Yeah
Oh I was very attracted to him
He was kind of a inspiration for how one could live
Very independently and with their
Phone unique
Set of
Rules I was very inspired by his lifestyle
Of working with him I have some if he wanted any help
With the bees selling honey or
No actually tending to the beach so
I followed him around for a summer as an apprentice
And did a lot of heavy work hauling supers of Honey around
Extracting
I learned all about the bees and I got to work with Burt what was what was he like was he talking
Zquiet
Yeah he didn't say much
He was pretty quiet and he's about 15 years older than
He was about 50 of the time
I was about 35 I think when I
When we
Matt
And
You just the sky was fascinating
Like he was living this life.
You wanted to kind of
Model your own life
Yep he was very inspiring to me and you know it's all kind of mixed up with the bees and
Nature
As well
It wasn't all inseparable
I understand like when you were you were just really curious about
Bees about his lifestyle and him
You like Sammy was interesting
There was no spark in your mind.
Hey maybe we can turn this
Listen to a business
Yeah after the Summer where I apprenticed with him
I suggested that we
Could
Package the honey
In nicer containers and
Salad at craft fairs put late little labels on them how was he selling naughty
Well he was selling them in used gallon jars
Gallon of honey
I know
Burt funeral like
Let pickles and relish come in
Is the restaurant business
Cheerleader say they have burtless
Put put it in smaller
Nicer jars and see if we can sell it at like
Farmers markets and stuff
Exactly
Yep
Yeah and he like that idea
Yeah he he was fine with
So I
Ordered some
Little plastic honey bears
Easy chairs
Yeah
And we failed both of those
12 oz of honey
12 lb
Yeah is how he sold it
And did you have a
The label on it and stuff
Yeah you know we use pictures of bees and
Titanic
Make all these products
Gif
This was I guess in
And today you can imagine going to a craft
Artisanal handmade organic non-GMO gluten-free
Free range fair trade honey from takes like
Hands like where you marketing at that was just like a bear with honey in it is like
Honey for sale
Well we did our best I would say
We tried to make the packaging really
Cute
People would want to buy it
And you know honey is a pretty pure product you don't have to
Sell it too much most people think of it as being
Fairy
Pure
No additives
From nature
So we didn't have to really push that too much
I think we call it pure main honey and so you would start to sell it where
Are we would do Christmas craft fairs at the local high schools and Junior High's in
Right around the area
You just selling it at these will end in poor people by naughty
Flower sales
Good
Good like thousands tens of thousands
200 rounds
Not that good
I remember
A
Really
Good show
At the local Junior High where it was $200
What's the take of the day
That was a lot of money to me
How did you guys name go from
Honey 2
Making candles
Well when you extract the honey out of the honeycomb it's capped over with beeswax
The biggest kind of cabbage
So it doesn't drain out
So you have to uncap it and you're cutting off the
Beeswax cap
So that's your
Beeswax
Can I ask you a question about beeswax it's wax it's like really waxy
Soft
Stuff that you
You can put a wick in Inverness
How do bees trees how to make
Perry producer
They have glands
On their abdomen
Just like we have saliva glands sure
So their glands produce
Flat disk
Except beeswax which they
Then build into their honeycomb
So when you pull out like one of those sheets
About the hive
Honeycomb
How do you get the wax off
You have a hot knife
And you uncap it
Set the hot knife
And the Beast wax
Pet
Was capping the honeycomb
Becomes
Available
Call to do whatever you want with it
So you had all this whack
End
Is it pretty easy to just melt it down and turn it
The candles
It's simple
I don't know if it's
Easy we have
Many disasters
But
It is a simple process you just heat it up in the beeswax
Separates from the honey and floats on top
So you so you start making candles and then
And then doing the same thing bring them to craft shows and selling them
Yep
How had the power sales had to go
Good instantly instant success
Well we
Certainly not every show we have
Some real bad shows but good enough to keep going
So
This is what about a year after you and Bert start working together something like that
In a three-point did you say
Aeroflot
If a friend asked you so Roxanne what are you up to
Would you have said
Yes I'm not going to Miss B thing like what
Orscheln honey and
And now we're selling candles and it's
I think this is the something there
Yeah I think I would say that
It was pretty exciting because I was maintaining my
Independence
Using my
Sense of Aesthetics
And
Making enough money to live on
Roughly you know by like 1988 or 18
I like how many candles are you eat were you selling a year
Well I
I don't remember exactly how our sales went in the 80s
But we were growing every year
My original goal was a $20,000 in sales
And then when that goal was achieved then I set another goal of $1000000 to say
And sales by the time my kids graduated from high school
So I read that you guys got a
Pretty big break
In 1989
There's a boutique in New York
Cold Zone
Came across your candles.
At a trade show and then ordered hundreds of them
Yeah yeah how do they find out about you
The owner
Or one of his
Buying team
Must have
Come across us at a show somewhere
And he ordered our little teddy bear candle it was a little molded
Candle in the shape of a teddy bear with a
Plaid bow tie
Under his chin
And he sold hundreds of them I didn't use fulfill those orders
It was you and burden like how did you what you do
Just worked all the time
No I remember working long hours
Digital hire people
We started to hire people
Slowly
Some of the local ladies
Would come in and give us a hand but
We were still in a
Building that
Was
Not
Really A place you'd want to have employees work you were acting some birds turkey
T-Rex
Just rented out a building to make
Yeah it was an old one-room schoolhouse
When would you guys call the business
Well
He had
Kind of a stencil that he had painted onto every beehive that said Burt's Bees
Because the bees were
All over the countryside
Yeah you couldn't keep them too close together
So
We would have maybe 10 hives
Bearden
Maybe 10 5/10 miles away there would be another
Beard with 5 or 10
Hives of bees in
On the hives he would stencil his name
Eventually it became Burt's Bees
By the way how did you
Have so much wax
Did you have to add beehives through a certain point that you have to buy
Yeah we had to start buying it
We had 50 Hive switch
Was fine for a few years and then we didn't produce enough ourselves so we ended up buying other people
Beeswax
Around 1989 when you got the
This big order
From this New York Boutique
You had to hire an accountant and it was a
14 year old
High School Boy
Who became your accounts
Is that
Is that true
And we called the school
And we
Tell them we needed someone good in math
And so they said oh we have just the fellow he's on the math team
He came over after school
I know he would
Pay the bills and he would do the payroll
And he would make the deposit and the day that he had to make the deposit walk up to the bank he would wear
Fursuit
It was very important
To maintain our dignity have the bank
So he was our accountant I would say he was more of a bookkeeper
It's very serious and focused in
Responsible
Yeah I mean
Roxanne it sounds like you were actually pretty serious
Unfocused
About this
But that actually
Converting just stumble into this
Company but as you saw it
Takeoff and as you saw people
Show interest in what you were selling
You are
Making strategic decisions
2 time lay the foundation
For what would become a business
Yeah it was we were learning a lot
Neither one of us had been
Involved in running and managing a business
So everything was trial and error
Lot of experimentation
Bar fails
We
Went to the School of Hard Knocks
What was what was the biggest
Disaster
Amber Lyon
Well I remember 5 gallons of a product we called boot food which was a liquid
Combination of
Melted beeswax neatsfoot oil and
Beargrease
What's beargrease
Just the facts
The rendered fat of a bear
What do you do with that
Pet products
You rub it into your leather boots
To waterproof them
Keep the leather supple
Not very well
Spell horrible by God
I know it was so bad
Oh yeah
And what happened to this
It spilled all over the
For 5 gallons of the greasiest smelliest post horrible stuff
All over the floor
That was a pretty big
What's the waist I mean
We were selling it
Couldn't been
Given your characterization of bird is a
Just kind of
Really independent
Back to the land kind of guy
What does he think about this growing Enterprise I mean all of a sudden
Start a business I mean in and not just
Burton rocks and selling jars of honey and wax
Candles but like
New York boutiques ordering this
I think that he probably wasn't as happy about it as I was
He had no use for
Any changes to his lifestyle he didn't have children for one thing
And I'm
Far more ambitious than he
Was
Yeah
But he went along with it because he could see how important it was to me
Was Burt
Fairly easy to work with or was he like
Stubborn and difficult
He was a prickly kind of guy
You know he wasn't all warm and fuzzy
So
People including myself gave him kind of a wide berth
We divided up the work
He would
Collect all the overdue bills
Overdue
Accounts receivables
And he was a fixer
When things broke down or needed maintenance he was
Always willing to do that
And I was
Very Hands-On with the product development
And
Getting the product made and shipped
So we had different roles
1991 Burt's Bees hits
Amelia half dollars in sales revenue
Do you remember that you remember thinking
My God we are doing a million-and-a-half dollars of Revenue
Well
I should have remembered it
But just moving too fast it was moving pretty quickly and we were everyday was a
Another
Problem
They just had to be solved
On the Fly
Without enough resources or time because we were in hurry
Trying to fill orders
So I didn't have a lot of time to
To think that I wasn't expecting this sore
Just kind of had a tiger by the tail
Yeah and I was hanging on for
Dear life
When we come back
Hi Roxanne adverts personal relationship started to unravel
Justice the company
Started to take off
Stay with us
Gyros and you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for NPR in the following message come from servicenow
Making the world of work
Work better
Their cloud-based platform and solution
Deliver digital workflow
That create great experiences for employees and unlock productivity for your whole come
Servicenow digitizes the work your people have to do
So they can do the work they want to do
Using technology
To make people more productive and engage
More it service now.
Support for this podcast in the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good days start with
Straight jeans
How did they make them so great
Madewell starts with premium.
Then offers men's and women's styles for seriously everyone
Also you can recycle any brand of jeans in a Madewell store
And they'll give you $20 off a new pair
They work with the blue jeans go green program
Turn old jeans
Housing insulation for communities in me
Terms apply
Ready to find your perfect fit
Stop by a Madewell store or go to madewell.com
Hey bucket back to how I built this from NPR
The early 1990s
Burt's Bees
Has just hit a million and a half dollars in Revenue
One thing we did not mention in part 1 which you may have figured out already but
Roxanne and Burt
Play work
I was saying the word just business partners but
Romantic Partners as well
At this time 1990
Recipes with selling mostly candles and other things made with beeswax and
They sold those things mainly at boutiques
In and around New England and New York
But in 1991
Roxanne had no idea
I will take the company in a
Brand new Direction
You can't reduce the price that would
Go on to become
One of your best songs not your most famous part of your birds bees lip balm how'd you come up with that idea
Well we were making
Other products that were basically
The same formula
We were making a furniture polish which was
Wax and oil and the boot food basically was wax and oil
And lip balm is basically
Wax and oil
And
We put a couple of
Amenities in it like vitamin E and and peppermint oil but it was very clear that people
We're more interested in buying
Products for their skin and their lips and their face
Then they were
Buying
Products for their furniture and your future
So once
That became clear
We phased out of
All of the other polishes that we were trying to sell
And
Started focusing on
On skin
And we eventually stop making candles as well
You subbing candles because
It wasn't profitable or was make sense
I think because it wasn't
Scalable
And
The
Skin care products which were basically blending and filling it was a very simple
Manufacturing process
That could easily be
Scale
And we were making handmade candles so to go to an automated system
This required a lot more time Machinery in space
And investment
That I didn't feel wood
Have the same return so we dropped the candle
So we're now like in 1991 Burt's Bees is growing
You hit a million a half dollars
And you're going
In One Direction
Sanlitun
You were
Counter Culture art student or a homesteader
Living in that you know tencent stuff
But you are kind of starting to become
The Sting that maybe you kind of rejected I'm not criticizing you at all
I'm just it's just interesting right that you kind of have rejected
This whole world
But you had an axe
I know it's ironic I thought about that
Did you ever reflect on at that time
I think I did yeah
Suddenly money became so important
Not for what it would buy but just because it was
Critical to the operation of the business
Keeping track of it
And
There I was keeping track of the
Cash flow money in Money out paying bills sending bills
It was sort of a simple version of
Capitalism
Which I had rejected
Years ago ya
You are not a trained MBA or business
Person but obviously you have some intrinsic Talent me you understood this in a way that
You could see what Burt's Bees could be
And you were just doing it
Well I had Role Models I had selected out companies and kept them in my mind
And ideal
So I had examples cyclic what
I had a big sign over the production floor that said
Lookout Elizabeth Arden
And you know I really felt like
If if Elizabeth could do it so could we yeah
So you guys are
Growing
You're hiring are you overwhelmed with how many people
Did you have to hire in Maine
Engines going
We had about 45 tell a lot of people to sort of over yeah
Was that hard did you
I mean cuz you at this point I guess you're like a CEO or a de facto CEO is not the official CEO
I would say that was the most
Challenging part of the job
With managing people are you juice
See yourself as a people
Full person
Not that
Much know I can be
Yeah
If I have to be but
Again just going back to my artist
True self
Artists usually work alone
They're very comfortable in a writers and Painters
And I I like that Miguel
I mean would you
Consider yourself
Introvert
I would say I was pretty introverted yet
Yeah I'm very happy having a very quiet lifestyle
In 1994 you guys made a decision to leave Main and to relocate to North Carolina
Why I mean
You're such a main person and it was
Jemaine
Have product
What what prompted the move
The location was
Very difficult working in the extreme northeast corner of the country
Getting more centralized
What's important for bringing raw materials in and
Getting finished goods out
So North Carolina was much better situated in terms of being halfway between Maine and Florida
And a direct shot out to the West Coast on I-40
The geography was excellent
There were other cosmetic companies
In the area
Revlon was
About 15 miles away the body shop was about 30 or 40 miles away and there were a lot of pharmaceutical companies
Things that use a lot of the same
Glass jars and caps
And that sort of thing
So are expenses
Went way down
We were able to hire
People who were trained in the industry and who had a
Experience in that industry to come in
And help ramp up production
And computerize our office
Billings
There were just a lot more people down there that were trained to do those kinds of things
Yeah
I am so
You have this new location and then presumably
Bike equipment and supplies in NJ
You're like running a fact
Yeah
You know it certainly wasn't a very sophisticated operation
And it wasn't a state-of-the-art factory right
But it was doable
We used a lot of used equipment we were making one of our products in a big mixer that
Duke had in its cafeteria for mashed potatoes
And that we we had a bath salt that we were making into cement mixer
So in a Wii with hobbled it together
Took in the mid-90s cuz I don't remember Burt's Bees in the mid-90s right
Where would you have seen a Burt's Bees lip balm or lotion or soap
You would have found it in a independent gift shop little small gift shops
Dotted all over the country
And it was just organic growth
Based on these small gift shops all over the country
Andrea marketing
We were doing a
Kind of a Grassroots marketing
We would make little sample products
And we were giving those away
People we also had catalogs
That were
Almost like a current-day Blog it would be our products but it would also talk a little bit about
Company in
I told stories about Burt and his dog and some ingredients stories
He's so people would follow the story so that was kind of a thread that they would follow
When did you design
Now iconic
Logo of
Bert's face
On the packaging was that there from the beginning
We had a great artist
He is
Lives up here in Maine and he did a woodcut portrait
Of birth
And we started putting that on the package
Few years into the program
That was a very conscious decision to use Burt's face
Because I was
I guess
A little
Resentful
Of the way women were used
To Market
Products
And
I saw
Some of the big
Cosmetics lines
Really exploiting
The image of women
And defining them
Through the advertising and packaging in a way that did not respect
They're full
Gap
So
It was important for me not to follow that
Weed
It's so interesting because I would have thought that you would have
First face on there because
You know of the authenticity of this guy who was really the real deal he was a beekeeper in a Hermit and
You know the consumer was connecting with this
Authenticity like that's why I would have thought you would
But it was it was about sexism
Yeah I think that
You know we had to do with authenticity and invert
But it also had to do with
Gender X
Deportation that
The beauty products were
I think they were known for
Known as a woman who
Could never measure up
To this glamorous
Image that one found in mainstream cosmetics and beauty products that you know I felt like I'm
I'm not I don't want to do that to women
So we're going to put a picture of
A guy that everybody is going to feel
More beautiful than
So alright so you guys are in North Carolina
Running this company is
It's a late 90s
Were you
Able to pay yourself a decent salary
Well at one point before we left main we decided to pay ourselves $36,000 a year
I didn't spend a lot of money I didn't need a lot of money
And
Bird eggs
It's you you buy them
When you Incorporated your 2/3 C 2/3
You buy him out and he kind of
Retires
Yeah
Although he
I think enjoyed
Going out on the road
And being burnt
Yeah in signing t-shirts
And tapping the mascot
Yeah
When he sort of was out of the picture
What was your personal relationship with him damaged or you not getting along from your perspective
Yeah that was pretty much what it was
Our relationship had gone South
And
If you don't mind
Well it was sort of a personal transgression that was
Very hurtful to me
And
It kind of pop the bubble
Anyway
Took a lot of inspiration from Bert and his lifestyle and his authenticity and
Is independence
And I found him to be
Quite admirable
So after the
Break up
I'm lost
A lot of inspiration
He had this
Yeah
Alright so
If This Were A Movie Roxanne 2.0 movie where like
You would just go to the end-of-year b99 13.8 million
2030 million 2000 160 million
Counting big stacks of cash and you know smoking cigars
But it is phenomenal like how do you go from 30 million
260 million in one year
Was it just phenomenal salespeople was it like what was going on
Well it was scalable
Every part of it was scalable once we automated filling it just make more
More product yeah turn it to 11 yeah
Fabulous
And just more and more stores were asking for these products
We spent a lot of time focused on the consumer
So they would
Try the product and they would want to go to the store and get a full-size product and they would ask for it and if a cuss
After a product that's a great sign if your store ran out
The customer came back for more wasn't there they would ask
Hey where's the Burt's Bees so
That kind of a pulling strategy from
From the consumer
Really helped a lot with growth
And it was a Tipping Point where it seemed that everybody knew about it
You know when from nobody knowing about it to everybody knowing about it and I'm not exactly sure
What
That Tipping Point was but it took on a life of its own
You
Sell 80% of your
Shares
The company in
2 hour
An investment firm
Not clear how much money
But a lot of
Pens
Of millions of dollars
Unsettling about all the sudden coming into
Yeah more money than
Adevarul
Imagine
I'm not really know I wasn't unsettled by it
I was thinking about the ex
Exit strategy very early on
Is that because you just didn't want to
Deal with the hassle of running a company
Yep it was something that became
Somewhat routine after a while
Going to big box and
Drugstore chains didn't seem very exciting or creative to me but it was clearly the next
Stop
So
I felt like
It was time to
To turn it over to the professionals
And I just
Trouble very constrained very disconnected from what originally was
An inspiration
Army
Imagine
So you go you're gone at this point 2003
You really leave the come
Eat you
Became very wealthy
From
This tiny little
Company that
You just
Started accidentally
I mean it's a pretty remarkable right
Yeah I guess so I mean I don't live two different Levi I have a more freedom now than I did
When I had no money but
In a certain sense I have a lot of freedom then also because I had nothing to lose
Yeah that whole theme of
Freedom is important
Timmy
Always has been
Meantime you were really
Starting to become passionate about
Conserving and preserving land
Starting in Maine
And you've given away
Huge amount of your money
By buying land in Maine and all the country and giving it to
Federal government to Maine
And other state agencies to develop parks
Yep
Start to become your passion
Well I had been living on the land up there for
Ears
So I knew it
And
With most
Beauty care companies
A lot of money
That they generate goes into advertising
Yeah I've heard even the 25 cents of every dollar goes into advertising
Sing so we didn't have that expense
Because you know guerrilla marketing and and Grassroots marketing is not very expensive hell and we had
Put all the money we needed to into growing the business at
Still have excess cash
And I felt like
We needed to find a very solid investment
And soul and seem to be
Rock-solid to me
Yeah but I'm President Obama named
Anu
National Monument
Larzelere and that land that you
You donated to the national parks
Katahdin woods and Waters
Katahdin mountain in Maine
Shavitz
That's the way he was eight
A remarkable got a really fascinating person
A film about him
Which is really interesting and
The point where you said something that
Probably was alone hurtful he said I never want to see
Again
But
Have you kind of made peace with him and in his memory in your relationship
Oh yeah I have
I was in love with Bert
Yeah and we went through a lot of changes together
Had this
Child
Burt's Bees together
Raised it up
Off it went
I still feel very very close to birth
I think about him a lot
He was a quiet in his
Inspiration to me a muse
Did you have a chance to talk to Burt before he died
In a certain way
Yeah
I was about to visit him and my girlfriend went up to visit him the afternoon before I was planning to go
And she called me to let me know that she didn't think
He was going to last much longer
So we sort of had up phone
Yeah
Correspondence and he did actually pass away later that day so I did miss
Seeing him in person but I just remember him you know at his prime
Some people
I criticized you
Because
Well you got me
Most of the money out of the company
Do you know
It's much what's your feeling
Habitat crew
I feel that
I was the more responsible
Party
For managing wealth
I could
Do the right thing with it
And I don't know whether Burt would have really used it very productively
He came from a family that had
Samwell
And he chose not to use it
He didn't do anything
To help
The community
With the wealth that he did have
And I felt like
That was something that I could do and have been doing
Do you plan to give away most of your wealth
Before you die
That's hard that's a lot of work isn't
Figuring out where to go
We should go and feelings all the incoming pictures and all the people who want some of your money and never get tired
Well I have
Both of my children each are working
So they have responsibility for Distributing
Funds every year to
Grantees
According to the mission that makes sense to them
So I do have help
And I'm pretty spontaneous
About the way I distribute grants
I don't have a real formal
System
I just
But you know either
Rings true to me or it doesn't
Yeah
When you see Burt's Bees today it's going well my Clorox
Givenchy purse by Clarksburg
Billion dollar
A 2007
Unbelievable
You see it everywhere
CVS
Walmart 7-Eleven is it
Tubing with pride is it is a wonderful
You'll see that
I don't pay that much attention to it I guess
You know I mean I certainly notice it when I'm at Whole Foods and I walked by the
Burt's Bees display always catches my eye
But I think
I've let it go you know in many ways I just
It's something
Apart from me now
So the question I asked everybody was
Put on the show rock
Nasty witches
How much of your story in the success of this
Do you think it's because of
Your skill in your intelligence
And you are working how much of it
Because of just a lock
Well I was born on July 11th
Which is 7-Eleven
Also I
Have felt lucky
For a long time
You certainly have to work hard but
When I look back at some of the critical events that were
Heart of
The destiny of this adventure I certainly couldn't have pulled those off that had
Ftb locked door
Divine intervention and there's been so many of those
The right people came to me at the right time
So
That has got to be luck
That's Roxanne Quimby
Co-founder of Burt's Bees
Every passed away in 2015
Roxanne made a donation
Burt shavitz his name
Helping a brand new Jewish Community Center
In Portland Maine
Roxanne has also been named to Forbes list
America's top 50 givers
You do use any other products
Well the one product that I was using is been discontinued
Slip on eucalyptus
That's your recipe right
I hope so
Weekend
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things you are building
The first thanks to one of our sponsor
Microsoft
Technology is accelerating faster than ever
And things that once felt far off
Are making a real impact
Can our lives today
See how AI
Powering business innovators
Microsoft
.com
Slash
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it
It's time now for how you built that
And today
We're talking about
Dating app
Any dating app this is Carlos and his dog Hugo and Carlos
I'm a single dad of a sweet Wheaten Terrier who loves to play and make new friends
This is a dating app with profiles of people
And their dogs
Very friendly and well-educated never bites
Always wagging his tail let's go to the park and let's get your dogs to play
So the voice you just heard is Lee Isaacson and her story starts in 2016 when her younger sister Casey
Had this country breakup she was dating a guy
Tried to be a dog person for her
By the end of the relationship he didn't want the dog in his apartment he would put towels down on the couch so the dog
I didn't touch anything
And she came to me and said I wish I just knew from the start that this wasn't going to work because of my dog
Citrus.
Could there be a dating app that might solve this problem and app that goes beyond Tinder
An app where someone like Casey could stay up front
Me and my dog
We are a package deal she has a Cavapoo and there is truly nothing that looks more like a teddy bear than her dog
It's always said you know someone can't like this
Then clearly you know you need to find someone without at least a little bit more dog person in them
They start to kick around this idea and they realized the way people take care of their dogs can say a lot
What about their personalities how much money do you spend on your pets or other things in the house
You know how clean you keep your house
Things like that might predict whether to dog owners
Are we compatible
Does your dog sleep in the bed or out of the bed do you let your dogs on furniture you always pick up dog poop on the
That's a big one that's a big one and by the way if you are listening and you have a dog please to pick up the dog poop off
Off the sidewalk
Just a favor I'm asking
Anyway in July of 2017
Sisters began developing their app only has a background in journalism and Casey works in
Advertising design they had never done anything like this before
Surfers they pulled their money together and their dad put in a little bit to
They got into an accelerator program
Spaced out a cheap Tech officer and a team of developers to help them build the app
We actually went through for development teams because Liam Casey had a hard time finding
Just the right match that can be very scary when you have a limited amount of money
To build this product and you see it either
Taking forever or you know not looking the way you want it to and watching your money drain at the same time
But after 7 months there dating app was ready
And they launched it
On Valentine's Day
We weren't the first dating app out there so we were able to learn from a lot of other people's mistakes
There have been interesting dating apps that I've tried to launch nationally
And they get a lot of attention really quickly
But because you need a lot of people in one place in order for a dating app to work
They just fell apart so we decided to get the word out city-by-city
Starting in New York
They thought this would be the best way to build their user base
We even hosted events in each City these big dog friendly parties pet companies paid the sea
Set up booths that revenue and dog owners well they're always looking for places to bring their dogs
So they would come and stay in England
After each launch
We can Casey saw a spike in new users we knew that was nothing more valuable than getting a lot
I have people in the app
So are you there could find more people that match with seven more cities la
Boston San Francisco Detroit New Orleans Austin and Chicago
And they're bringing in more Revenue by charging pad companies to put ads on the app
This means after a year they've been able to keep the app
We are Texans app
It's called Big has more than 20,000 users and growing and yes she knows what some of you sing
People with cats are thinking
Where's my app we get the cat question all the time you know surprisingly we actually get
The horse question all the time course people definitely need to have their own conversations to
But for now
Big is all about the dogs
And the people who love them
If you want to find out more about Lee or hear previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. NPR
Do you want to tell us your story go to build. Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and why you're there please
You do give us a review
You can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org and if you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built this
Our show is produced by JC Howard
Music composed by Rumpke never blue
Thanks also to be a venkat nor could see me but Grant Melissa Grace Anna's meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our intern is canvas lip
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email Tampa
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder and customer support 7 days a week