Support for how I built this and the following message come from America
Express
You want to build your business
Can help building
Your business with financing Solutions
Eligible business customer
The powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Business
Really quick before we start to show
Just want to tell you about a couple of how I built this
Live shows happening on the
East Coast over the next couple of weeks
We're heading to New York City on
Camper tent
Robbie interview
Christina Tosi Milk Bar
A town hall
Rasta doing a live show on
September 12th and watch
DC with
Tristan Walker
Walker and Company
You can find out more about our lives shows and
Your tickets
NPR
Presence. Org
One more quick thing there are still some tickets available
Go to the how I built this
Summit sponsored by American Express
What's happening in San Francisco October
XXII
23rd at the Yerba Buena Center
It's going to be in
Credible event
Founders bootcamp
JetBlue Instagram Slack
Away Jenny
Splendid ice cream
Spanx
Many many more
You can find out lots more about the summit at all so you can learn
How to apply for
Summit Fellowship
The deadline is
July 31st
Free admission to the summit
So check it out
At Summit
NPR
. org
And
Is he there
You went to a bunch of bags and
What did they say where they were they eager to lend you the money
Bank after bank and they open to discussing another's and you know event
Ashley found a partner that worked with us in Olympus the money
What kind of collateral did you have to come you said you know collateral so well
Personal guarantee which was our home earnings ever
Who sings at the minivan
Is how I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs idealists
Sam the stories behind the movements
Built on garage
Sebastian went from Poppin kettle corn there freezing Minnesota driveway
Building an international snack brand
Worth hundreds of Millions
Dollars
So there's a piece of career advice
That I've always struggled
Because
Halo
Any advice is to follow your passion
Follow your passion and
Everything will fall into place
Accept reality
Somewhat different than that scenario
For starters
Everyone has an obvious passion
And then not all Passions
Easily translated into sustainable careers
But if you heard most of the Founder's on this show
You might conclude that
All of them pursue their passion
Like James Dyson trying to
Build a better vacuum cleaner right well in fact they are all passionate about what they created but
For the most part the passion came after the product came into being in the case of Angie and
Dan Bastian
Neither Dan nor Angie ever had a particular love for popcorn
It wasn't their passion at least initially
The idea behind buying a kettle corn kit they needed a way to earn
Somebody to save for the kids college fund
Sting and selling kettle corn seems like a reasonable way to do it
Dr.dan literally son Unidad for kettle corn equipment he convinced Angie that
They should go for it they could launch it out of their garage in Mankato Minnesota and then
Garnet Little League games are in parking lots and that was how Angie's kettle corn was born
It would be the beginning of a rolling right along our the freezing cold days
Crushing debt and the stress on their marriage and finances but 16 years after that
That kennel kit arrived annie's Boom Chicka Pop
Soul to a huge book
Quarter of a billion dollars
It is like many of the stories in the show
Seemingly improbable
Do people with no business experience no
Connections no real passion for popcorn still managed to build an incredible company
A few weeks ago Dan and Angie told me how they did it
In front of a live audience
Ordway Concert Hall
Saint Paul Minnesota
Wow
Those Rowdy Friends
So welcome thank you for being here
And you're still with you and then we're obviously get to win
If you mad
You grew up
In Indiana you grew up
Safari
Yep in a in a Mennonite Community can you
Tell us a little about your childhood and your upbringing
Sure
Well my parents were very young they were 18 and 19 when they were married and 19 and 20
When I came along and they lived in a
Trailer in the back of my grandparents
Yard and on the farm
And my parents mad at Ben and I Heist
Anansa growing up you went to the Mennonite church and you are
Really part of the night
Community
Culturally religiously socially all men and interest for people who aren't familiar with
You know what's Mennonite culture what it what is that
Me and I will see modesty right and so like
Did you
I don't watch TV and go to movies and do all those things as kid
Little risky
Little different upbringing
It was very sequestered it was very protected I was very loved and cared for and very soon
Simple and I didn't know I was an oddball
Yeah so you grew up in Goshen Indiana
Yes
You grew up in in Mankato right I mean that's where that's where you from
So I grabbed Mankato third of four boys
It was kind of
Chaotic
Get X in a household I'd say fun in a good way heading
In loving parents
Had an incredible experience growing up
Fairy
Competitive
All of us boys played Sports so
Few heads were thrown through the wall
A picture of a
Nnn were you were I mean
Tell me what about you
Evacuar school like where you can student in school
I love school
Are you going to ask me that question
Why did I love you
And
Fed
I grew up in an environment it
Didn't necessarily encourage me to go to college
It wasn't until my
My aunt Christine in Colorado Springs
Said to me when I was 19 like why aren't you in college
I was the first time anybody in my family said
That they thought I had some potential or I believed them to think that I have some potential
Tension of doing that
I don't know what I didn't know what you know I I just said oh my God should have you think I could go to college and she said of course
College
I took a
Chemistry cup
Course that summer just to prove to myself that I could do it and I got to be so I was like okay I think I can do this
So I'm going to college
Went to school come easy to you
I mean it was
I probably would have been diagnosed as ADHD back in the day
You know it's just hard hard for me
Fortunately I add
You know my mom was really great about keeping me keeping your finger on me that kind of give me through school
And I had to really smart all the brothers that allowed me to get into a really great school st. John's University
And you when you went and I think you said history in college and and was your
Finished
When you finish college was your
Idea to become a t
Teacher
Toward the end of my senior year I think I did a like a month-long a little internship in a classroom
Install
Just love
The kids are kind of realized it was my passion
And that was really good at
And I could
Kind of manage the classroom how I wanted to rather than
Being told you know this is how you need
Dutee Chand I
I think it really connected
RNA in entirely separate Universe Angie you went off
To study nursing
And you end up
In
In Santa Fe right or in Gallup
And was that to begin your work as a
As a you are psychiatric nurse
Yeah I was just saying I was working in Atlanta at Georgia Mental Health Institute and I was interested in transcultural health
And so I got a Traveling Nursing position
Which was in Gallup New Mexico and they have the contract for Indian Health
And with the Navajo tribe and the Zuni tribe
It's for their end
Psychiatric
Cairn
I was like I'm going there I want it I want it I want to see what this is like
You also Dan end up in Gallup
New Mexico
Teaching
High School
I had a family a relative that was working at the hospital
In Gallup New Mexico and I ended up moving down to Gallup teach at the high school
I just so happened that
Ang
Was working at the same hospital where my uncle
So that's how we met
You met
Uncle I thought he introduced you or you just met at the hospital
We met and Rogers kitchen
Uncle Roger's kiss you
My jaw was broken
I have broken my jaw
Hatch dinosaur
I don't know I don't I was not eating well not to add painted in the elevator and fell I'm if it's broken
My jaw wired shut and my friend Raymond who was the social worker at the hospital was a good friend of his
And he said let's go over in
Hang out at Rogers
So we went over to Roger's house we hung out and my job was why are Chuck and Dan said immediately
You broke your jaw broke my jaw and College
When I was in college
I was playing baseball I got hit by line drive
And
So Angie
I can relate to it like when she walked when I walked into the kitchen her jaw was wired shut
And it's like I know what she's going through she's blinding food she's
Like doing all that but that was kind of our connect
Java
There was a group of people that lived in Gallup
Open hang out together
You know it
Scallop is a
Very difficult place in a lot of people come in and work in the schools and hospitals and
There's a group of us that were there doing that and we would just go hang out and
Do happy hour every Friday night
We kind of got
How to know each other that way
So start hanging out eventually you guys
Apple
And
I think within like 2 years you got married right
New Mexico where we just kind of had all small wedding but had friends and family coming
Watch us get married a year later your daughter is born 95 you guys move to Santa Fe
Write for a brief period and then
You eventually moved to
Florida
You're young couple and you got a child and
Tickets to Florida
We just kind of said hey you know maybe it's time to get
A little closer to grandma's and grandpa's your family
So you move there you start working for a clinic
Eye clinic at Coastal Recovery
Center which is a mental health clinic
And then what did you do
In Florida
So I stayed home with the kids tattoo
Credible
Time with them and I also
At the same time
Start the entrepreneurial process in which I started a
Yeah what do you mean by that mean
Cuz you're
You're the lead parent right you are at home and and Angie
Working
I don't work at this golf course
How many inches mom would take care of Annika trip I just
Slap bags in
Tarts and I was just
Wish I was good at I guess it and I got free golf I started this golf business where I'd setup Turner
For corporations
I didn't get real far with it but I only have one or two turnips I think but it was it was just kind of a good experience of
And I had started
Thinking about you. Can we do something together is there an opportunity to do something
You know once this was winding down in Florida at we realized this wasn't an so we had some other ideas flowing through her head
But you would basically kind of start to think about hey you know
What will a business be like
Look at it look like this like idea started
Kind of
Enter your mind
Yeah I got a lot going through my mind guy so I don't I don't know if I was really like Focus
Anything specifically other than
Don't mention I wanted to do something together we didn't really know what it was we're getting food at the time
Restaurant Co-op
Caffe type thing where we could do it together and we could
Go after
I think both Dan and I have
I have this sort of restlessness about ourselves like we end
And like
When one Adventure doesn't work we're onto the next adventure
Like let's go back to Minnesota let's go to Minnesota
You wear your friend and you guys decide let's go to Mankato
You wanted to be near your family
Yeah it's so excited
To move back to Mankato I got back into teaching cuz when we move back we were thinking of
Like I said opening up a like a cafe
Some type of
Food
Place in
We just realized it was going to be too expensive we were
Prepared for it so we got back into her careers I got back into teaching
And she got a job with the state hospital
Alright so you're back in Mankato
And
What
What is the idea
For kettle corn even
How do I even happen
Like you're going to your job you are a nurse
You working at the clinic right
And you're teaching
Can I just tell you
What we were doing all of that right like
Successfully employed everything and yet we said oh
We don't have any savings like we got to figure out a way
To put some money away for our kids
Does college fund do we have to figure out how to create something here so that we have
Money cuz we both just
Absolutely valued education
I'd like a six-year-old enough for year old or three year old
Started yet everybody's already got a college
Binding of
401 whatever that is 409a together
You're something else
Yes
IJoy tide be teaching during the day
And then and I get home and Android going to work at 5
Until like 1
So at night time when the kids were bad I'd go online looking for different businesses and
You just search search
And what what did you what did you come across
So icy
Yeah like what were you type things in the Google like this is purely goo
Early Google you type in like
How can I make money from a side business
Or your search parameters oh I don't know I but I somehow it's just stumbled across
A
A site that said make thousands of dollars every weekend or day
Poppin
Which is like
A total scam
Eureka
$10,000 into it we realized
This is a potential
You see you see this and you think
Yeah what
This is cool like and what it what are the sites say like
It just it had popcorn
I just like I said
And I said she's at work and I said Ang this is something we could do on the side I'm a teacher
We could do this on the weekends during the Summers
You know we could pop with this
I remember distinctly the phone call I'm in the middle of maybe a takedown
Or something like that medication for a patient that's
Severe Ana the phone call your husband's on the line
So I ran back to the nurse's station and he's on the other end in Isa
Aunt
What do you think about kettle corn
I like I like kettle corn
I don't even know what it was it was
I thought of it as popcorn I knew it was kind of like sweet and salty but
I don't know if I had ever taste yet but it looked
Like a cool side Adventure where we can make
Thousands hours every weekend
So what did you do did you did you
New Order
Like what did you order
We call them and we bought it on a credit card like everyone else and
We bought it we we got a cattle
1/10
You know if you got a fair one of those out there kettles
And all the equipment a table
It probably
Wasn't worth
Theater 10000 but we it was already a prep package
Deal that they shipped
Bishop used to make kettle
And you and and basically instructions on
You know the proportions of sugar salt and oil
Oh my God
Does couples
Out of Gig Harbor washing
Tens
Their own entrepreneur
It started like they were building
Sandy's kettle
And these packages to sell to kettle
Corn vendors
And they were making a bisque
Is it
It's like I don't know how many
Quartz is it
Yes it's if you go to fairs UCP
Open Flame degrees
So do you remember like unpack
Getting the stuff and like looking at each other and Save
Let's make kettle corn
Exactly what we did
I know this seems far-fetched but it worked it really were
Wait no so you unpack the so the stuff arrives
This is really like
Free
2-day delivery
Amazon delivery
Rico down our alley our Ally was to
Too small so I pulled up on the
Street outside and we had to haul these
The alley
Okay
Like garage that
We were on the phone
That first batch of 5 batches with
The couple who had sold
Equipment
Trying to figure out how this work
So it was just it was a little cat
And then after that we had it
And then we just like the recipe
It's basically a
A kit that you could
Go and
Sell kettle corn
Could you I mean at that point could
Tampa 1010
Sell it or did you like out permit and all that stuff that was my job to do them
Research.
Get us license get the health department or whatever and we can we had to
Actually find a place
That would let us stop and sell
It so that they could infect us
So was the first place that agreed to let you set up a tat
Rainbow food
In front of Rainbow Foods at
Supermarket supermarket chain but they let you set it up in the parking lot
There in front of the front door and we decided to do it the night before Thanksgiving because we thought that the Trap
I think would be good
Vision 2000
It that so that's November 21st 2001
This was my first
Winter in Minnesota so I
I decided the date that we were going to do it and Dan was like well okay
Okay November 21st
Let's see what happens and fortunately it was a beautiful fall day and
It took us an hour to set up and we
Sold $300
Of popcorn
Damn I mean your family is in Mankato
I guess your brothers were maybe around Christmas
Like when you said
Mission hey
What are you doing this weekend
Kettle corn
Shoe market under 10 what was anybody like
That's weird
Yeah
Weird experience
I wouldn't get into this but there were a couple kind of crazy ideas that we had experienced mented with p
Before
I like a network marketing gagan so my family was probably like
Here they go again
Here's another
What is a harebrained idea
You don't for us I think it was more about
You know we're trying to
China just spinning our Wheels
We could figure out what we wanted
What to do when this was a way to get sick
$10,000
I have to imagine investing that kind of money
Then was
Oh yeah, big deal
It's a big deal
Well
0%
You got to pay it back
Another credit card to pay off that credit card
There's a lot of credit cards going around
At that time so you start selling popcorn first time
You separate annie's healthy
$300 for popcorn
Ziploc bags and
There's no
Twist tie bags
And you're just hand
Scooping it in
Selling is like amazing like
The difference in what
What you pay for
The Colonel's Inn
You can sell the popcorn
Four right is
People told us no one would pay
$3 AR
$5 for a bag
Popcorn
Whatever but
They said it's really good
SO3
She come home
What's the next step
Let's do this again like it made itself
I don't know it sounds exhilarating a little bit now that we like
We're in this
Like we're actually doing this
Beaver still
Teaching you were still doing your what would you seize your students like on the weekends or would you see
Wake me up folks in the hospital yes
And they would look at me like
What are you doing
Yeah
Right I would have liked
When I was in the clinic in the afternoon I saw patients I was a nurse practitioner writing prescriptions and making worth
Frozen
And then I'd run home and I change into my kettle corn clothes and go to the
Go to the local baseball game or with Tanner whatever and we
Make kettle corn and sometimes
My clinic patients would be at the amateur baseball games and they would come up to the table and look confused
Yeah cuz you were just running a prescription now you're selling me cat far
Exactly in my message was you can always be more than one thing in life
You can
All right
TiVo license you got pants
You got a kettle
And what were you calling the company
Kettle Corn Cafe
So 2002 you take the winter off
Cuz you can't really sell it outside Campbell pop in January
Snow
Because there was a girls basketball tournament at minutes
Set a State University and they didn't have any concessions
And so we said here's our efforts
And you have to do it Outdoors right because the propane and we put the tent outside the garage
And it was snowing and we just put the sides up and we pop it out
Outside and delivered over to the
College
All right I think it was
That summer
Of 2002
Where you basically
Started to sell kettle corn at the Minnesota Vikings
Training camp
Rights of what how did that happen did you just like go there and set up
Should you ask them
I'm assuming if you could go and set up a
Detent or no you didn't
And when you ask what they say yeah you have to pay us
Certain amount of money if you want to set up
Anti-hero
Yeah I mean
With the Vikings
Former College classmate of mine that was assistant
Athletic director
The college at Minnesota State University
And he
Open the door for us to set up our tent
At the training camp
And I think
There may have been a fear Commission on that but
We thought I mean that was a huge opportunity for us to make some extra money we got the deal on it
Go in there to see the players train
So you start
Selling popcorn there and I guess
One of you has this idea what
Some
Let's send the players a team
Popcorn
Yeah right like let's leverage this opportunity
Because
Dan
Like most minnesotans are huge
Minnesota Vikings fans
Yeah but I didn't understand it yet
Because I just moved here
Yeah he was like
Minnesota Vikings
Everything all about it and and
You know it was at the time of Randy Moss and Dante
Culpepper and you know that it's like
All that that era and and
He was like wouldn't it be fun if the player zetar
Let's figure it out let's figure out how to make a
Just made tons of bags of kettle corn just made a few phone calls
Just to see if we could give it to
To them
We waited and we waited over to call back
No we got a phone call back and they said so we
I hear that you have some kettle corn that you want to give
The players
We'll take it as long as it's free
So we're like
Okay
Don't give it to him for free
What's up we pop 220 bag since
Send it over to them
And you didn't even know if
The Place Riverside
Nebraska room in Sunrise
So they came to the sales marketing team came over and
More less offered as a contract on the spot
Yeah I think the I think the sales
People to Viking saw it as an opportunity to bring in another
Company to another sponsor
Cuz it wasn't like
Free to pop kettle corn for the Vikings there was a fee involved in
And we didn't really understand that until we got really excited and then all of a sudden
Hey we've a great opportunity for you can be the official kettle corn of Minnesota Vikings
But it's going to cost you a sponsorship
$8,000
It doesn't hurt to be the official
Fake Bake set preferred
It cost more for the word official
What we said
We're going to be official
All right so you are
Starting to sell in front of this is like
Football season
You're going there every weekend
2 in front of the stadium
Tailgaters
Not inside this day
Stadium right Justin
And were you I mean
Will you selling autocal economy doing well
Yeah we were selling
I mean
Every Sunday we get up at like 5 a.m. pack the trailer and
And take our equipment up and we'd be up and ready to go by 9 a.m. they had a party on the Plaza
Kirby Puckett
Drive in front of the Metrodome
And there be a band it doesn't matter if it were there was a blizzard or if it was
10 degrees or 0 degrees
The party was still on
And we pop kettle corn
No we had friends come and help us
Volunteer France audience right now
And
I have to see my mean your car
Works at high right at salt sugar
Some oil and
So weird
So when you were probably making
Somebody or but not too much money a little bit of money or will you
Actually was it will you start to be able to save for this college fund
Not really
It all went back in the business
We bought a trailer we bought more equipped
We bought
I don't know
Heater
For the
And I don't
Everything seemed to go back
So
What's the socratic turning point we start to get attention because I think within a year or so
A local supermarket chain in Minnesota approach uses
Hey
You know did you guys want to sell your popcorn
Kiridar stores
Is that what happened
Oh yeah so we started
After a couple years of being this outdoor event company
We start realizing like this is not something we want to do
For the rest of our lives
It was any
It was an opportunity to reach people but
We thought you know is there another way to get
Are kettle corn into people
Leanne
We we started in 2003 two years into it I Quit teaching
And I started focusing on the business
Was skin tearing get to work
Full-time support
In the family as well as helping in the business and
We met with the local grocery chain Lunds and Byerly's +
They said
More less
Get your act together and come back and talk
Skip nutritional panel get Packaging
In all twist ties don't work in grocery stores
Popcorn with twist ties for cellophane bags
So what did you do how did you
Did you start what you just said
Will get her act together and we'll use
You see us again
And
It took a six months we found a small kitchen
We bought some equipment we moved the operation indoors
And got that
That kitchen license
And we came back in six months and lunch and what is your packaging look like
At that point
It was like a clear solo bag with a label that we
That we would
Paste on taluk manually by hand
So you are still
You were stealing the bag so I trip in the engine I in
Whoever else we could find wood
Do these labels
Every night he'd slap unleaded what was it called
Well we called it an
Because somebody said you got a name your pop you got a name your product cuz it can't be kennel cough
Cafe Rio
We didn't know what
Popcorn with
Call really
So we went to the grocery store when we looked online
And what we thought the time was in the grocery store it was Orville
It was Vic
It was
Cracker Jack
Cocktail and Thomas Harry and David and I just
Turned it down and I said
Where are the popcorn with
When we come back
How Angie's kettle corn eventually managed to get into Trader Joe's even though it almost
Didn't and how it eventually spread just about
Everywhere I've got to stay with us you're listening to how I built this
From NPR
Support for this podcast comes from American Express
Director of global sales strategy Chase Hines
Explains how American Express works with their customers
Define the right Financial solution
Your business is a lot like solving a puzzle
Each customer is different each business is different
We really want to understand what your goals are for the year
For three years
And what would
Extra financing do
To help you achieve
One of my customers is a long-standing
Family-run restaurant
And Sons dream was to open up a second okay
Finances are a little bit tough as they were just running the business
And
We were able to partner with him understand
Exactly what he needed and help him open up that second location and now they're onto their third
So whether it's a need to open a second location or
To fill a big New Order
We want to make sure that we're there for you along that Journey
American Express wants to help you move your business forward
With flexible financing solution
Chat with him today to see if
If you're eligible
Or does it americanexpress.com business
Learn more
Terms apply
It has already been uneventful summer in Polish
Yeah between the 2020 debate
And the president's battle over immigration
There's alot going on
And when there's news you need to know about the NPR politics podcast
Is there to tell you
What happened not to mention we're hitting the road so you can meet all of the 20/20
Contender crazy
The NPR politics
Subscribe
Hey welcome back to how I built this guy Raz
And Angie it start to get their popcorn
Local groceries
Stores in the Twin Cities
They are still doing most
The popping and bagging in
Delivering
Barely making enough money to buy or anyone
But then Define two people
Who seem to be willing to help out
Well we hired on a genie we're retired
Third grade tea
And they helped us out
They were married they retire they just wanted to do something together
And they said we don't care what you pay us and so we said well we can pay you $8 an hour
For both of you
Mac picture
They were two demos for us in one store while we would be in another store and get over
What time we're able to
Brookhaven more
And they said yes
Because they were kind people and they wanted to help. I mean at this point you know
2004-2005 I mean how are you financing this would just through the sale of popcorn
Guy I don't know
I'm not sure I mean yeah we were probably going further and further in
To be honest
Pictures of a continual dragon
Totally chaotic and
Just
Doing doing doing
I mean we used a lot of credit cards refund
All the money back
There was a time when
We had enough credit card. That
A family friend came and helped us
Is accounting he looked at her books
Just said you know
Why don't I just
Give you a loan
Here
We can relieve your credit card debt can pay me back
But I don't want to see you going on
Vacations in
Spending money at the golf club
What's the question right it's
You started this out
Create college fund shirt
Orchids
And it sounds like for the first seven years
You just buried yourself further and further
Into debt like
They were they were never going to go to college this plan right
Hey and the other thing is we had the misunderstanding that when you have your own business you
You don't you own your time
Yeah
The opposite is true
The business owns
Your time like we were like
How did we go so wrong
I'm here in that in the first five or six years were you thinking
I mean we're in debt
We're working
All the time
It was hard
I mean it was it was really
I mean
I think early on
Urologist
Just takes over your life
What did you guys fight
All the time
We did we
We fought a lot and maybe that helped.
We're not ones
Fair words
Each other
But I mean
How does you compartmentalize like
You're dealing with
Patients with serious mental issues
And then you're like I was one of those patients guy
And then you are pivoting to
Kettle corn
Well okay at the end of the day
I mean even though all of that stresses there we're both
Pretty tolerant of you
Each other we
We were committed to
Each other and
Both of us
Pretty kind
People
So we
We gave each other some latitude
In the hotel
Situation and we just
Yeah I think we both just said
Will be fine
Like we'll get through this will be fine
It was really hard to refocus
And to realize that
You know we got to keep moving
Forward here because we're
You know knee deep into this
We have to find
A way to continue to
Not really understanding where it was going or what the outcome
Future outcome was going to be still
All right I think it was
Around 2000
You had to
Get a loan
To get a much
Speaker spacing
A million-dollar
And you went to a bunch of bags
And
What do they say where they
Were they eager to lend you the money
No
They were not eager even though you had
Clearly you
You had Revenue coming in and
If we had dad
We didn't really have any collateral
And I mean Looking Back Now I
I can kind of understand Banks
Position at that
What time where we were
And it was just it was a long journey was really hard
The bank after bank and they just said what
Yeah and we had we had communication with some
Do you know a bride A banks in
Somewhere more
Open to discussing another xan
It was just I think ultimately
We just
Weren't strong enough
In a strong enough position for them to lend us a lot of money we need a lot of money
Money to bury bigger facility to ramp up production
Cuz we had just at this point decided to move into a big bigger facility a 25000 score
Looking for you at that point
Probably at that time 2006-7 maybe 20 ish
Colorful timer mixture archives
Yeah
You know eventually
I found a partner that worked with us in
A banking and Olympus the money
And what did you have to
What what kind of collateral did you have to buy me you said you'd no collateral so we'll probably receivables and
Personal guarantee
Which was our home
Yep future earnings
Everything but the minivan
Your kids are getting older and
You guys are
And your forties at this point and you know for a lot of people that's kind of a
The turning point to you start to think about okay in college and always seems an end
Was any part of you nervous about that
I don't
I don't think he had a hat when you make that decision like
If you start going down that path
You're going to crack
Is the bottom line was
People loved our pride
We just had to figure out how to make it better more efficiently and how to get it in the Moorestown
What did Buddha mean
Play a little bit of frustration right
Because people prank cops music
Angie's I love
Your mechanic or it's awesome you guys are crushing it or so it's so great
Anytime you're struggling financially
What time is it like when you when you don't have any
Real money to start out with an all you have is ambition and
And potential and skills
You count on those things
You know to make your way through you know and so we never really had any money and we did all kinds of them
Amazing things in our lives you know so if this whole thing went South wedow a lot of people a lot of money but it wouldn't
Stop us from
Living our life
Did you feel the same way Dan
Yeah
I'm pretty
I have a pretty high tolerance for
For risking
Dad
I mean it was about
You know if we had money is put it back in let's girl girl girl growing
That wasn't the scariest
The scariest part
Came
The next spring of 2000
This is Trader Joe's
Best wine Trader Joe's
Yeah and stroke before so we had
We were just very process
What's Raiders and we ended up getting
How did you even get to Treasure
A lot of phone calls in a lot of product being sent
To the bar
It was
You know I think finally the buyer got sick of me
And like said
I finally got ahold of her she was in her office
Marcy was her name and she like
Is that alright
What are you got here I've tried popcorn
Before. It's not going to work and I said
You haven't tried our seeing what's that line that all of us uses
That we have the best productivity
Anyways she she liked it she said already did you send it to go out there
We
She agreed
To bring a saint
What was the order that she
Cheaper than she put in an order for
What does that mean how many bags of popcorn is that
That was
What for $500,000 worth it was craziness and that would go all across the country and Trader Joe's
Xi'an in this is a one-time
Deal well
We didn't know she was going to try and we obviously had some problems
With some
Clumping
That first order and she immediately called and said
Fix it
Kind of done
But at the same time the scariest part was our line of credit for $150,000 to run out
And we didn't have any money to pay you 4:30 or 6
60 day wasn't going to be paid until later in June or July or something
2008 to deliver it
Where to buy the supplies
But I send them to have enough money to buy.
Corn and salt
Alton so that was
Terrifying
It was like we were this close
How much did you need
Well
There was a credit card that
Came through the mail
Just another credit card
And it said
Call for
$100,000
And I got on the phone one night and said
Can we
Get this hundred thousand dollars wire to us and our credit was good
And soli wireless $100,000
Act like a hive
Percentage and so that allowed us to get
To fetch Xing
Call like when they send you a check
I don't remember what it was in her bank account quickly
An inch
We could buy supplies
And we could
It was until we got paid by Traders
And then Traders came back with another order of like 25 trucks
Cuz it was going Bonker
That that's when we turn the core
How did you actually physically make all that popcorn
How many mm
You just have to hire
Tons of temporary people or
Permit people like added that
How'd you do that still working in the
Yeah
Red X in hospital
Say that
We were fortunate to
To look to hire people during 2000
7 in 2008 when the economy was started in the tank and so there were a lot of people looking for
For working
And you guys were not
And that affected by the economic downturn and this is dance
This strategy is when
When things are going south
He's going north
You know so I think we
We just knew that there was opportunity out there cuz a lot of big companies were pulling back during the
The recession
And we were getting vibes from stores and from Warehouse Costco and others
That hey there's an opportunity here if you're willing to invest
Is others are not
And so we
Win 4
At that time and and kind of said we'll do this this then that we kind of said yes to everything
And we had because of that we had to hire a lot of people
Quickly
Working of plants we can manufacture enough to ship out
So you are starting to sell that mean you're really good
This is selling
Well
At Trader Joe's
Do you know what your Revenue was in 2009
Maybe
34 million
Pretty gray I mean you have started
Realize there was
A chancer until 2010 working as a nurse
What was the turning point for you where you thought okay
Now I'm going to be in this you know full time
I'm going to stop
Enough
Well I had I had
Left
The state
Because there was very little flexibility
Aunt at the state hospital so I had left the state and
Started my own contracting business so that I could contract
My time and have my own flexibility and say this is when I can work and I can't
So you're still
Basically
Supporting family
Is not you are not taking income from the company
Quite yet
Yeah we had a mortgage to in a cell
That was we were doing pretty well in
In that regard bit
But I started weaning my time back because Dan would call me and he would say okay we have a
Costco meeting on May
May 12th or whatever can you move your
Clinic around in
Go to Costco
Upshur
When you did those meaning when you went to Costco how did you pitch them would would you Dan would you have Angie
I'll be the face of the product and make the pitch or did you make the pitch or did you guys
Bounce off each other like you doing now
What initially I
Did all the sales calls early on
And then by the time we got to 2008-9 10
Especially
After that when the end came on full-time
They wanted to see her
I mean sure her name was on the package
And she
You know told the story really well
So I kind of
Took
You know instead of just accepting Ops and sales and every I kind of stay focused on
Kind of the operational side working with Greg my brother
And kind of managing the team and answer focusing more on work
With the sale sign
You guys get a
And an outside investor
Sherbrooke
Capitals VC firm
Come in
Make an offer
Did you feel at that time you needed
You needed to have that
Capital
Growing in the way that you
Kelly wanted to
Honestly we don't know what they wanted we don't really understand private-equity we didn't know I mean
I was in a business person I I didn't know exactly how it work do you know and
Anstine and so was more my brother Craig who
I started taking some interest in that and
He's the one who initiated the dialogue with Sherbrooke after they contacted
Asar
Funny he said you know we don't need the money now but if we're going to continue to grow we're going to need money sometime and we on
Understood that because we had just been through years of like oh God we need money
So even though we don't need it now it makes
Complete sense to us and now we were in a position where we didn't
Need it and that's the time to go ask for it so
Okay
Obviously helped because
At that point you decide
Begin a Rebrand and to introduce
To move Beyond just kettle corn
Right and they okay so he a couple things that when they
When we decided when we understood what private Equity was
It's about like I had only ever seen
Put in the movies and they were
Deconstructing businesses and they were the bad guys
These biscuits
Private Equity was a
Small shop and they were had built Brands and they were interested in
Partnering and we said we wanted our people success to be
You know 6s along with us can you help us figure out what to do and they helped
Set up
An employee Equity pool
They helped us set up a board
The setup
Professional sales team and build a marketing team
A whole.new
Entirely new ball game
Like we understood partnership cuz Dan and I were in partner
The tollway and so now we just had another partner
You know we had
We were now
Our business with marrying their business
Until what was the impetus to
Your kettle corn is your bread-and-butter right what is the impetus
At that point
To go to
Yo
Salted Popcorn buttered popcorn other flavors was it
Was it that was it was at other people saying hey you know we want
Flavors
Well in 2011 we were the natural and organic snacks
Right so that's where we live Costco
Target display
Yes for a Target and
And in a lot of regional grocery chains doing very well in the natural organic sex
But it is to me when I looked at it on the Shelf it looks very masculine
I used to walk the stores and just
Stare
You know stare at the
Best healthy snacks
Does the national organic snacks that were aimed at women I thought looks like they assumed we were all on a diet
And so I was like
Okay
Like we can do that but we don't have to
To do it in that way
So let's do that along with our kettle corn let's do more let's we built out
And Innovation started
Product Innovation map
And started looking at Innovation as more than just the product but in the messaging app
Did you I mean it
This is also coincides with like the gluten
Free
Explosion right which we are still in
Did that did you also
Will you also able to kind of ride that wave
We absolutely we would have mothers
It's calling us
Saying is your product certified gluten-free
This was early on
Dan cell phone was on every single pack
Because that was our business is our business number
And so
His cell phone was ringing it would be some mom standing in front of a Costco pallet thing is here is this allergen-free
What's the reason I did it I did it early on before
We were very big and I want it all complaints
To come to me
And it just
We never ended up taking it off
Until come through
We heard all these mothers calling us yet we got to get certified gluten-free so we did
You decide
Find
Somebody help me
With a new name
Google branding age
We don't yet
And what and what what names do they come up with
For really boring ones and one that I thought we thought was interesting
It was called boom chicka pow pow
Good name
Why we laugh
Bright light
Richard Powell
And it just the brief was like hey
We don't want to be diet
We want to
Elicit curiosity
Something different
We want to be celebratory
And come from a pig
Addition of empowerment
So this is going to be Angie's boomchickapop
Pow wow
Pelon pelo
The days that
We were all at one table
Together and we had a business
Analysts at the end of the
The table eavesdropping on the presentation
And after the creative agency laughed he said you know boom chicka pow pow is 70s
That would not go down well in the Mennonite Church
No
It would not be said and how did
Do you know
So we said okay but if there was energy
You know the rest energy and it and it it has
Struck the right tone
We just told him go back and fix it they came back bun
Chicka Pop we launched it in May of 2000
How to draw
Customer base respond to the new name
But we have buyers
Said said
Sprite and and we don't really like it they don't really get it
Wechat people internally that said don't
Don't do this
You know
There were two of us women on the leadership
Mary Hanrahan was our marketing director and myself and we
Fought like
Yes we want this
Because it is
We are not going to do and she's Nearly Naked we're not going to do and she's skinny we're not going to do Angie's whatever
That is right we want to own something else
It's going to be fun
It's going to be creative it's going to be dimensional it's going to celebrate
The feminine and
You know for years women have bought
Chips
Send everything that
I had that you know are marketed to men and we don't think of thing about it and so why not
Put a package out there that appeals to women
And I will stand and it was at first non-GMO branded popcorn
On the market and it it be
Became our number one selling
Xq informant
After 9
Wow
So I think around 2014
Tpg growth comes in a bigger
Private Equity Firm they buy out
And
And take a pretty big steak in a cup
Company and
It's real money
And I think
At that point you guys started to distribute
Money to
People who have been with you and work with you for a long time
Yeah those granted Equity shares
Became liquid
For our staff
Best three days of my career probably was transformational right
I think so
Yeah
Remember
Remember how much money you were able to
Millions
Millions of dollars wow
And I mean
Probably doesn't happen very often in Mankato right
Like a liquidy
A liquidity event I'm not I mean right now
It doesn't do it was an emotional
Time I mean it was you know
For everyone that
Had given
You know everything to us for in the company and and
I mean it's still emotionally
Thinking about it but
It was
It was kind of a thank you to everybody
And then we got to do it again
And 2017-2017
ConAgra
Huge
Company that owns
Many brands
Buys out
Door Company
Reportedly
Quarter of a billion dollars
Astounding
Prpopcorn
I mean
And the brand I mean
Talk about it
Great 8000
$10,000 a day for a fly by night
Kettle corn
Kettle
Man
Now world
Wish I saw that
Add on Google
So they buy it out and
I mean
What
Did you even have time to absorb what that meant I mean
Where you just
I don't know the last 3 years from 14217 1/20 PT came on
We sold
Pretty picture of our ownership
The tpg
I mean
I think if we had to jump out in 14 it would have been really hot
But we we we were
Have 3 years run where we were able to kind of slowly step
And participate
As much as we wanted to and as much as
The staff needed
And so I think when 17 came
It was the 14th sale
Was much more emotional
In the sense because it was like
Oh my God we did it
Yeah
And that whole thing about like Haley
We started this to
Put our kids through college and have enough money
Yeah now we're doing that for
All the other people
People
I mean you also
I know you are
Brandon Bass
And you are on contract with
ConAgra and then are you involved with the company at all
Donnatal
The fact that you came into such a
Substantial amount of
Of money
Has it substantially changed your lives
Has it
CNN Sohail
Yeah I mean
I don't wear Minnesota don't like to talk about money
I think
Yeah it's I mean you know we just weave
Got into
This later in life
And so
I mean
I'm still wearing these jeans that I've had for 10 years so
Those are nice dads
Yeah I noticed those
I noticed those jeans
But yeah it's allowed us it's giving us an opportunity to
Do things that
Never would have
Could you have imagined when you
Order that
Cattle and it arrived in your garage and you were like
Mexican burning the corn the popcorn like
That you would go on it would go on to be purchased for
Order of a billion dollars like
16 years later could you
Could you imagine that
No
No never
Not even not even
Probably
Halfway through or 3/4 the way through did we think about it in
And that way I mean it was just for us looking at the next Horizon
Nginx
Thing that we needed
Get to do and the next right thing
That we needed to do
I think more engine or just talking about this
I think more contemporary entrepreneurs
Probably are thinking that way
I mean we start in 2001 I think for us
He was just
Kind of knot on the radar and it wasn't like
Everyone was starting up food companies or
You know different businesses as much as it is today
For us
It just kind of grew
We grew into a
Anchor into the Good Fortune of it
Happening
I have
Done
Interviews with
Cofounders who were married
4 and are still married
Some cases
Melissa & Doug
Are still married but then there have been examples we had an episode recently EO products
Leaderboard
They kept the company going
You guys
Had a marriage
Your family a partnership
I was just running just just being married and having kids
Write anyone who's
Experiences that their stress
Raichu argue and and that's normal but
Running a business together on
Top of that in a business that
For years and years
Grind
Really know if it's working and
People calling their stress
How do you
Survive
That's hilarious
You know
At the end of the day it's about love right like you just
You decide
Do you love this person yes
UW are you willing to
Commit to this person no matter what
Yes
You know and
And I think
For Dan and I we both had that sort of
Frame of mind
And
You know it it doesn't make it
Easier
But I think that
You know both
He and I have the
Mindset that
We're going to make something work
And I'll by God if anybody can make it work will make
Make it work
And
You know it I think it just took
With the business and with our marriage just recommitment
All the time
You know every day every week whatever
Whatever it meant
Yeah
Do you think Danforth you do you think that
What you achieved
And his business was a result of your work and your scale when your intelligence or do you think that luck played a big part
I knew this question was coming
Lol you know
Guy
I think
There's a ton of good fortune that is coming our way
People have been so embracing and in
Incontinent helpful and so many ways so many people in this crowd
Is the reason we're up here
But we put a lot of
Energy into creating an environment that
Was about
Giving
To the consumer giving to the
The customer
I think there's some skill in that I think I was blessed with the ability to interact with people and
Build rapport pretty quickly and I knew the importance of that
And and
Had so many other gifts the marking side the creative side that
Initial Finance side
That we were able to understand our talents and pull it together and
You know no doubt there is Good Fortune a lock that comes your way at the right time things happen a credit card mailing comes in
I mean it's there is there's luck involved in this and we were just
Fortunate at the right time we made some good decisions and rebound it
Well from some bad to sit
Angie
You know I've seen a lot of
Really good people work
Just as hard as us
Or harder
And not experience
The same
Fortune
That we've had
And so
I think
It does
Take I mean we made a conscious effort to
To create Goodwill
And positivity
And when you do that
I believe that that comes back to you
But you can't do it without hard work
Angie and Dan Bastian a boom chicka pop
Angie and Dan Bastian at
Ordway Concert Hall
Saint Paul Minnesota
By the way that original Kettle they bought
Angie and Dan no longer own it
ConAgra about the company in 2017
They also acquired that old kettle
Nancy believes it is now sitting in the back of a
Very large storage facility
Somewhere in Minnesota
Thanks so much for listening to this episode of How I built this
It was pretty sweet by Rachel Falkner with music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to our Live Events
Team
Prescott Rachel McGrath John Isabella and Andy huether
Thanks also to Julie Carney McGrath Jeff Rogers and Santa's meshkinpour
Our intern
David jar
I'm guy Roz and you been listening
PR