So I get some more exciting news
How I built this Summit happening this fall in
In San Francisco
On top of the amazing yes
Taken 2 on the main stage
Will have breakout sessions
Throughout the summit
Speakers like
Katia Beauchamp of Birchbox
James Park
Eric Friedman of Fitbit
James Reinhart thredup
Sadie Lincoln
Barre3
And many many more and also
Just launched
How I built this Fellowship
The fellowship was started
Make the sum of the accessible to entrepreneurs who are working hard to
Bring their business ideas
The life
But might need a little extra help.
To get there
This year
The fellows will
Free admission to the summit
Along with special programs
Help their business
Does grout
Visit Summit. Npr.org
For more information
And be sure to apply by
July 30th
So it was literally an afterthought that you would be able to write a review on Yelp
That teacher almost didn't exist and it was in fact Russ right before lunch that like I remember in Peking
How to write a review
No one's going to do that because we didn't think anyone would write reviews for fun
That was preposterous
From NPR how I built this
Innovators
Entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements
Gyros
Places to drink and shop Yelp public company now value
Billion dollars
Okay so think about the last time you read a review on the internet
And then use that review to help you make a decision
Maybe it was
Which restaurant to eat at
Which brand of
Toaster to buy on Amazon
Or maybe even witch
Podcasts to listen to
Internet reviews
Height of a fixture of Modern Life
Please review sites have put a lot of power in the hands of consumers
Simatai powers
Great customers
Taco stand
Barber shop
Can totally booster popularity
But at the same time
Besides an ulcer
Irritated a lot of business owners
Because one bad review can do a lot of damage to a business
People who got this whole thing started
Is Jeremy stoppelman
Jeremy co-founded Yelp
The story of how he did it well in a lot of ways it's a classic Silicon Valley startup story
Along the way as you will hear Jeremy cross
Elon Musk Reid Hoffman Steve Jobs before any of that
Pull up in Northern Virginia
He was born in 1977 his dad was a Securities lawyer in Washington DC
Founders we have on the show
Jeremy was still a kid when the PC Revolution was happening
Is that
Brought home a computer for him and his brothers to play with I mean the first it was fascinating to learn
How the operating system words because of the dossier to the command prompt then it became very
Quickly about video games and that really sucked me in
Epicurious well
How do you make these
Not really fun to play but like what behind them
Ants that starting out on a journey answer reading
Another manual
Just started
Uncovering the Mysteries
Bit by bit
At age 14
You opened up a Charles Schwab
Account
Yeah probably
Tyson 2
And my dad being a
Involved in the sea
Securities industry
And I was very interested in young companies and how they grow and
Buying and selling stocks founded
Exciting to me
And then also you know you've been earlier before I opened that account that I was trading baseball cards even though I wasn't
I wasn't much of a baseball fan I was collect
And trading baseball
That was the baseball card bubble
In the early 80s
It was
Side to my mom's Chagrin she still has boxes and boxes are worth nothing but but
Like a Jose Canseco rookie was going for
Like 40 bucks yeah
Yeah
Side of
That's a lot of money in the
Did you have a sense
What you wanted to do
With your life already at that point
I didn't dream of starting a tech
That began from a pretty early age
Around the time that I was doing
Investing for teen
Yeah I was reading
Forbes I know there was a
Forbes is 14
There was a sex I think it's called out front
That would never tell entrepreneurial stories
Not
Two similar to this podcast but a very brief Little Italy Ohio here's a
Couple of entrepreneurs here's what they're doing here that's going to taking off
And I just was really exciting to be the idea that you could
Take technology Marriott
What business come up with a novel idea grow it into a thriving company like that is just something about that
Exciting
Actually went to college at the University of Illinois where he studied computer engineering
Move to San Francisco where he got a job working for a company called
At home it was an early provider of high-speed cable internet
But it was a chaotic time for at home. Just completed a merger with another internet
Jeremy didn't last very long there
I was seeing and hearing enough weird stuff
Just like this is not the kind of place if they going to be long-term and because I was very lucky
There was 1999
And that man my phone was ringing off the hook
With recruiters trying to get me to go interview with other companies
So I was constantly tempted
Free LinkedIn recruiters finding out that you even existed
Dial into the phone tree
So we called the company and then start pressing
Extensions or just going through that you know that
Countries to try and
See if they can reach an engineer and then they would put you on all these startups
Does company
Yeah it's crazy times
And where did you laugh
So
In one of the startup
Agreed to
To me it was one called x.com
Carrie's name to it fortunately it was not pornography nothing to do with anything typically associated with an axe
It was just an online bank
Anyways
A little tiny office on University Avenue in Palo Alto
Really bright individuals
That I interviewed with and then the last person that I met with
What's that day
Was Elon Musk
And what was your impression of Elon Musk did he make an impression on you at the time
He made a strong impression
I definitely like them
Right from the get-go
It was also
Inspiring
Now here is a 28 year old
Put already sold another company
Any of these incredible Ambitions for
Somebody's going to need
Yeah said right out of the gate or we're going to
Take down Visa in master
And I thought
Is it just kind of crazy like he's a
Crazy person yeah he's got this
Crazy idea that these insane Ambitions he's got a lot of confidence
It was kind of mind-blowing like
I don't know about this
This guy but I just have to
I have to see what's going to happen
Okay so so x.com
What are they do like what was their business
Yes.com originally started as a bank
Turn online bank
It was very easy to sign up
Take your money from your bank account and shifted into things like an S&P 500 fund
High yield money market fund
I was doing some kind of
Cool Cutting Edge online banking stuff that was fairly new
But they also made it very easy to transfer money between accounts with just an email address
So if you want to text. Com account
Read me if you didn't I can send you a payment and then you could create an Xbox, count very quickly and get your money
PayPal is doing something very similar the only difference is they weren't running a bank they were just kind of a money transfer service
So
You accept a job with them
You become one of their engineers
Was there a sense that you were building something
Big
Is there like that kind of excitement or
Or not necessarily that for now
I mean I'd say it was more than that
And by the time that I joined
There was already a product Market
It was already growing really fast
Prius on eBay
Someone would win an auction on eBay they want to pay
And at that time there weren't a lot of really
Fast efficient easy online options
Incel
X.com fill that Gap and then also confinity which was running the PayPal service
Number one competitor was also.
It's all very much like we were in a
Very scary race
We were
Worried every day who is going to win who is going to get ahead where we growing as fast as they were in vice versa
So she's very intense,
Petition
And that first-year decks.com do you remember just working all the time
Day in Day Out
It was pretty intense I mean
I was only at the company maybe two or three months before it was an ounce
PayPal
Andexxa, merged
I'm so I had yet and intense 2 months
A fierce competition and stress
And then all the sudden
Where all these new College
Your enemy becomes your work like I remember
Yeah we had a little like happy hour mixer type
Big thing
Where are the other teams got together
And it was
LOL yeah I was an interesting feel like I hear these people that you've been
Really worried about really stressed by but now
Dear new colleagues
So in that merger you got
I mean I'm not going to name all the name
Elon Musk
Is there
Peter thiel is there
Max levchin is there
Maybe Reid Hoffman was was in that room
Yep
Is it possible to look around the room thing
Everyone in this room
Is
I mean I would say
It was a bunch of ambitious
Smart people right skillset
The right time but yeah I did I don't think you could have really predicted it
Obviously Max was already
Pretty far along for 24 year old so is it was obvious you know that he was going to be someone interesting in the industry computer deals
Same things I said the top Executives you probably had something
The other players in the industry but I'd say the rest of us we're just all
And just getting started
You got promoted to
Head of engineer
The vice president
Engineering
Once that Mercer have
You are still
Real young
Do that cuz all of a sudden you're like
I can charge him
Least 20-30 maybe more people
Yeah I mean a retrospective
It's pretty crazy
25 yet I wouldn't say I was
Super well qualified but you know we made it work
We put out a lot of features and functionality we kept the side up
That's what's important
Bur
That was your you are an engineer
You're not a business
Yeah I mean I think
I did have
An interesting combination of being able to connect
Communicate
Understand
People in other parts of the organization outside of engineering and then translate that
Into you know the lingo in the Motions of
Engineering
So as I
Became an engineering lead in an engineering manager and so forth
It felt very natural and it felt like
I was actually pretty good at it
It's alright for me
Yeah
Just two years after the merger
K'Nex
Common PayPal
Gets sold
EBay acquired by
Yeah we know the stories of
Menus
Founders Inn where they they did did you walk away from that like
Financially set could you have just
Not work ever again or or no
No
Pick up something like 1.4 1.5 billion dollars
Certainly top management got rich in the
Maxor Peter could have retired if that was there
Wanted to do
But I think that's actually an interesting part of the story
If you had all these Bright Young ambitious people they definitely got capital I made some money
But it wasn't so much
That is necessarily was like
So you decided
The point
I might go to Business School
Like you
Been through a startup
Acquisition
As an employee
You got a little money under but not enough to
Live off
Rest of your life so
Business School
Yeah
After
PayPal was bought by eBay
Especially since I've gone through a merger x.com and PayPal
Who's pretty
Traumatic
Dramatic because
How to combine the two culture
Yeah and there's so much
Drama
Within the two companies once they were combined Elan was
Like it was
It was pretty crazy
Until when they took over I had a feeling it would also you know not be that fun to be a company that
Maybe
Swallowed up by very different cultures
And so forth inside it just
Like all maybe I could go
Do business school maybe I could get him somewhere that would be a pretty good school and it let me look into that
And then I applied
If you different schools
And actually Harvard is the only one I got into
Some celebratory I was very excited
Pretty much wanted to go to sew it. I got very lucky on that and then went off to Business School
To buy going to sound like like going to Harvard Business School
Wanted to
To get a better grasp
Spawn like
All the
A part of that what
Stemmed from
The Silicon Valley coming from wisdom at the time
Leslie post.com
Bust
Was
Founder engineer types
Focus on engineering
Is I thought about getting an MBA that would
Round out my background to give me more flexibility
Give me more credibility like I did want to start a company which I still hope to do
It would be awfully hard for a venture capitalist
He probably has an NBA
To say oh you know I don't think
Running the company
Tickle work
I'm sorry. I thought it would be nice
Alright so the summer comes summer of after 4
And you come back
San Francisco the Bay Area
For the summer
What was your plan that
Well
Month prior is actually coming back
I reached out to my old Network
Until I reach out to Elon I reach out to Peter till
Reach out to Max
And Peter right off the bat offered me an opportunity to come to Clarion capital
His investment arm
And it was very morphe
It's like we have no idea what exactly are you doing
But you say he's certainly a spot for me and
Jacksepticeye
And then maybe a month later like Elon actually took a little while to get back to me and I think it's about a month later
B-Line reach out and said no you should come work for me at basic
And it's kind of a funny question
What would have happened if you wanted responded faster I probably would have gone to SpaceX just cuz
I don't know headphone versus
Rocket ship
I might be tempted by the rocket ship come from
For the summer
Yes I arrived in San Francisco and I meet up with Peter in his office and he mentions
You know what
Max
Has a open up an incubator
Call Demerol Ventures I'm an investor until he essentially offered me the opportunity instead to go work with Macs
Cheap Uconnect with Max levchin
He said he get working on incubator
So I got to Max's little office little dumpy office
Recliner room and
Yeah they were it was just a bunch of different folks working on little internet ideas
Now what's going to be the next big thing on the internet
Which I actually was intrigued by
And I thought what is a fun exercise like I've always wanted to start a company here it it's like this is
Is it a trial run for me to see if I could come up with a compelling idea that I could pitch Maxon that he would actually get excited
What were some of the ideas that you were thinking about maybe starting
I had a bunch of
Silly ideas probably the silliest that I can remember
Was
And idea for a joke phone call
Site
You can go there and you can
Pay for
A phone call to be sent to a friend or something like that
Another that was actually
Pretty close to a good idea
What I did realized that
The economics
On
Streaming video head
Gotten a lot better
But I didn't have the full inside I just
That there was something going on a video that was intriguing but I had to put that one on the Shelf
There was
Some interest with an incubator around the local space it was
And we were observing that
Craigslist
Who's killing the newspaper
Business
Bicarbonat classifieds
I said put a spotlight on the yellow page
Looks like hey here's another old media business that hasn't really been transformed by the internet
You can look up
Basic information
You know an address or phone number
And said I got to figure out what would be
No better than the Yellow Pages
And as I thought about it talk about it with my co-founder rushing into is another
Early PayPal person
It reviews
Capturing word-of-mouth bringing it online
You're marrying it was social networking which was motor technology that was just emerging yet kind of friends her in Myspace
Send intriguing but we didn't think you could create a social network
Just around reviewing thought
I'd be a mechanism
Russell Simmons
He was someone you knew from PayPal he was just
He was also at Mr event
Yeah
Yeah that's what I came to the incubator
Kiwis
And one of the people that I most frequently
I would spit ball with and bounce ideas.
4th and actually
I give him credit for being very encouraging
Took us about
Couple months baby month and a half or so really zeroing an idea
And when
Trying to come up with
A new business idea in this case new internet idea like
You feel like you're spinning your tires are not productive you don't know what you did the whole day is he's got there speaking in like
Jotting down notes and ideas
Sometimes I feel like I was just getting nowhere and who
Yeah
How is very positive and like know you're on the right track with keep doing this and
Until we're actually out
Batting around this review social networking and how but what's the mechanism
And I said to him and let you know what like if you ask me a question
And what's a good doctor in San Francisco like I like I love to be the expert I love to reply in my
Give you this helpful information
I thought of this sort of like back and forth conversation questions
Npip emerge well maybe we can build
Aside around asking friends for recommendation
And so we thought
Withnail the car that we thought we had a mechanism that would pull reviews out of people because of course
We didn't think anyone would write reviews
Preposterous
It's only got back to the office
And we were just like bubbling with the
Excitement we saw that we know how to do this local thing
What were you going to recommend
Like what kind of businesses
Well whatever business that you happen to need you could turn to the service and say you know hey
I'm looking for a great sushi restaurant in San Francisco
And then I would blast out to your friends and then your friends would click a link could just be able to type the name of the place in my quick note and then it would be
You saved in this
In his sight until overtime would build up his incredible wealth of knowledge around recommendations and everybody's had
The initial idea
Cleric post public reviews
When you would be asked you would ask that the central part was like coming ask a question
Of your friends
It would email your friends to click a link they could submit reviews back to you
It was a half-baked idea
But we're excited and that's what matters
So you Russ come up with this idea to have like
A website
Where people to get recommendation
You take it to Max election
You say
Emacs
Here we go
And he says
He says
I'm not sure
It is generally like a poker face kind of guy but he was he was like nah
I don't know maybe
You seemed really excited about it that's good so why don't you think about it
Overnight
And then if you're still excited about it tomorrow
Then I guess I'll find
Would you leave
Pitch deck
Getting a business
Just like
Tiny butt
Yeah I mean I've got to come back and talk to Max about that moment
And I think what he would say is
He was just excited at the combination of
Of me teaming up with Ross
And the fact that we're both like engaged in fired up to try something and he figured
Something good will come of it might this might not be the idea but like if they get Off to the Races
And part of it is
Maxwell surprise himself at getting people
Dropout of school 2
Pursue business opportunities
I think he also saw it as an opportunity to you know
Hear me in a different direction than finishing Business School
And get me involved in a project which could turn into some
Did Russell Simmons
Before you got the money from Max
Silver Sable
What are you going to do like you're going back to
School a couple
I mean that conversation basically started as soon as we got Siri like once we had the idea once Max it signed off on it
That
Began a process of me figuring out what my options were
Sorry
He has started
Researching
Could I defer a business
And unfortunately pretty quickly I realized
That it was not very difficult
Call to defer my degree
So you decide all right I'm going to
I'll drop at 4
I will start this thing up and end
How much did Max give you gas
Smacks committed to the million dollars
He got a
A large chunk of equity as it was 40%
Yeah I know we just started
Working on the product
It's interesting because clearly like you work
With Max at
PayPal he knew you he knew Russ
You didn't have a business
You didn't have spread
Cheats of how much money you would make
He just
Gave you a million dollars
He must have really believed
That you guys
Make something work cuz that's
Even for a rich guy that's that's arrest
I mean definitely it was
It was bold to commit
Real money
To these very high risk
Projects man he had essentially three or four
He might have been for the total count in the incubator
Out of those two
To really worked out
And then to did not
Oh yeah
I mean I think that's the nature of the Beast
Open Silicon Valley is
You're working on very high-risk projects its R&D
Fight nature most of the projects are good portion them are not going to go anywhere
Ideally want a portfolio approach
If you can make that happen
I want to ask you a kind of delicate question here which I think is important for people to
That's enough understand when starting a business
Max had
Capitals world quiz
He gave you a million dollars which you needed to start this
Company but you had to give up
40%
Of the company
That point
Do you think that
At that point
You just did not have a better option like that was
Truly the best option to take
I would say
Given the circumstances of the time
In a 2004
We're still recovering from the.com
Answer the idea that
Yeah 26 27 year old would be working on an internet start-up was just very out-of-favor like
No it like that was part of
I think we all definitely were successful as they were just so few people
Working on new internet ideas in 2003-2004 around that time.
And so you know Max was early and he was one of the few so I think he and I deserve the equity that he got
Artsy U business school and you guys start working on Yelp
And and I read that in that fall fall of 2004 where you guys are going to work on this
The name that you really wanted to call it was Yoko
Like
Local
Which action is it like name
What happened to Yoko
I mean I thought
We would combined local and Yokel
And then I went to go and try and buy the domain
And there was someone that
That wouldn't part with it
Offer any amount of money
It's that proofs frustrating
And there was a another guy named debater David Galbraith
Who
Was thinking about it as well and he was the one that came up
With y'all
And we pitched it to us he was like help help
Yelp Yellow Pages
So I had some
We are really smart connect
And it also turned out that you can buy for $5,000 right there
By putting in your credit card like a domain squatter
Found it and had put up a page saying it's for sale
Savannah
Two other folks
Overheard the conversation in the incubator came over and
One of them was Scott banister
Who have been involved funny enough in the naming a paper
The PayPal actually
Paint of a fancy consultancy
Degenerative
Inside got back a hundred different option
Scott Bannister is a friend Max
Pointed out immediately PayPal
Scikit PayPal we have to go to PayPal and like
Canvas Knox
Geneva name
It's a similar late when he heard y'all peep I bet your name you're crazy
We're buying it right now
And then he and this other guy Jared's at Town him
I bought the domain for us
And
How we got that was at
That was all right so you've got
This thing that
Your building and by the way I mean $1000000 a lot of money but you got to pay people you've got server space again
Right
That's not going to last that long so I had to assume you quickly had to go out looking for more money
Yeah
When we got pretty far along
Building site within 3 or 4 months
And right before launching
Emacs encourages us to go pitch so I went and hit the road
Sandhill Road and talk to maybe
10 or 15 different forms
And since we got locked out of the room
It did not go well now
What were the questions for you like
Do they not understand what it was I can understand that
By the way it wasn't entirely clear that point website
People just volunteer
Information to get the email drowned like what's going on
That's her
I don't blame them
Pushback was it actually had nothing to do with the ideas so much as
The people presenting it
So in our case we're young
For technical interview
Kind of like what happened in the late 90s and so everyone still have PTSD from the.com bust
Who are the common refrains to me was and is it straight to my face was like Hey you know yeah this idea is kind of interesting week
We might be willing to fund it perhaps but
Would you be willing to step aside so
What weekend is it
A real quote
We can bring in a gray heritage
Wow
Like I was a casa conventional wisdom was like we need adult supervision
Executive
And so there was this feeling that enough
With the kids already
Yeah we need
Established
Professionals
If we're going to find some sort of
Your new venture
Were you were
Preparing to Launch
And I guess
By the end of 2004
Right
October 2004 are you able to raise any outside money before then
Million dollars in financing
We started conversations with
Venture capitalist
The weeks
Prior to launch in an extended all the way through launch
And of course when the launch happened we got some initial press
Stuart Little
Obit of Industry price
But also our data
Is people are trying to use
The site was not
Super encouraging
It was not you launch this thing in October of 2000
4 +
What no one shows up
The party
Pretty much you know our moms were on it and maybe some friends
Did any part of that sap your confidence
Yeah that was a very dark.
I was pretty worried that I had
Made a mistake and that I was leading the team off a cliff
Come back in just a moment and Jeremy his team relaunch the Yelp website with some important changes
And it started to see people besides their own mother actually use the site
And also the moment Jeremy got an unexpected phone call and some advice
Gyros are you listening to how I built this
From NPR
Thanks to one of our sponsors
Who helps make this podcast possible
Are 2019 how I built this
Lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
A campaign monitor
They took email marketing animated
Radically easy
So the big thinkers to focus on
What they do best
Developing Big Ideas
Specially crafted templates
Turn key designs
He campaigns
Get results
Best part
Drag-and-drop editor
The job done in
Airtime
Try for free
Campaign monitor. Com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and business
Unforgettable
Thanks also to wetransfer
Wetransfer surveyed over 10000 of their users in nearly a hundred and fifty countries
Found out
The people get their biggest most creative ideas
Step away from the screen
That's why everything we transfer designs makes
The most of your time
Their tools are simple and beautiful ways to bring I
Ideas to life
Get you back to yours
Find out more at leave
. Buy wetransfer
Dot-com
Drag his
It's been around for a while in the Kabuki tradition in
Japan Inn Minstrel show
Embody
But one TV show made it mainstream
Now
We break down drags current Renaissance
On NPR's it's been a minute
Tuesday
Oh and one more thing
If you love how I built this
Check out my new podcast
Best wisdom from the top
It's a show about how some of the
Greatest leaders in business
Politics managed some of the biggest corporate and
Professional crisis you can ever imagine
You can find wisdom
Exclusively on luminary
It's a new app that allows you to listen to all your
Favorite podcasts plus a bunch of amazing
Exclusive shows
Just for subscribers
Shows from people like Lena Dunham Trevor Noah
So brand Leon neyfakh
The creator of
Slow Burn
And many many other
Download the luminary app
App Store
Go to luminary. Links guy
Free no strings attached
Strap
Hey welcome back to how I built this
NPR
Arise
Tokyo flight 2004
Right
Co-founder Russell Simmons launch
Yelp
Really no one is
Using service
At this point Yelp is
Primarily a website
People ask their friends and only their friend
For specific recommendations
InStep model
Clearly isn't taking off
Jeremy sits down
To get an idea of what people
If there was one really critical
Inside that we had as we were looking at the data
Which center around review writing so it was literally an afterthought
That you would be able to write a review on Yelp without being asked a question that feature almost didn't exist
And it was in fact
Ross
Right before lunch that like I remember him peeking over
Should there be a way
Write a review
If nobody asked you a question you just brought it wanted to write one of my
No one's going to do that
You know what
Why we added in somewhere
Prince.
And it turned out you know something
Precocious users would find that feature and when did right
The first review they would then go on to write a second or third degree that you can see in the data like I could just see that when someone wrote a review
More often than not
The right stuff
If there was something
Obviously entertaining or interesting or
Cathartic about reading reviews
And so with that Insight we started rethinking how we designed the site
And instead of being about
Asking friends for recommendations
Maybe it should be a platform for you
To recommend things just to The Wider world
And so we redesigned and put the emphasis on you
We gave you a profile that is
Those are borrowed from the social media world
We also you know took a page out of the blogging Playbook
Working say your reviews showing
Chronological order on your profile
And a bunch of this features and functionality we bundled up
And Central
Relaunched
Recite in February
You're sort of thinking okay
Let's relaunch this
Yes and
Give people
You know the power to
Evaluate
Sting whatever they're using
And then
We'll see what happens
Shifted from
Hey the only way that we're going to get reviews is if you're asked a question to
Hey maybe reviews are for myself
Expression
You're just like someone write a blog for
You're fun to talk about what's going on in their life
Or what have you
Like some people want to talk about restaurant
Answer some people want to
Yeah I talked about it a great mom and pop business
Patronized in like
There's actually people out there that want to do that
Frankly I could identify as one of those people because I was doing it I was getting I was like
This is fine
I want to do this
Erie Lodge
The option return
Review and then
Blow up or is it still kind of quiet
With the relaunch February 2005 it did feel
This really different
You know when we rolled out all the new features and functionality within hours we were seeing people pop up on the site that
We didn't know
Wasn't a relative
Weather friend like we have no idea who that person is in the writing review
Is that pretty cool
Yeah it didn't mean that we were like I hope you know jobs done let's
What's lean back in like wait for the sites
Growl like we still had
Tons of things to figure out and work to do
Be there soon after launch
We started thinking about will how do we really jell the community that's here in Sanford
I'm just trying to participate on our site
Yeah we did our first in-person meet up
I was some early users and that was
A total surprise
You invited them
To like Gathering what
Talk about
Restaurants Catholic what would you do
Yeah interesting Lee like right around the time that we were about to relaunch I hired a marketing person
It said this Market person Nash
One of his first suggestions right as soon as we had some users
Was let's meet him and
We work on the
Products like I
Do the wire frames that I work with Russ and we figure stuff out I don't go and meet people that's hot
I don't do that
You know you got to do what you got to do it and say he arranged me of it was like two users people we
We have no idea who they were and we met up you have for happy hour nearby bar and the crazy
I assumed that the first users of Yelp would be early adopters
You know my mind were technology site but I would actually say the early users of Yelp Urban early adopter
They're looking for what's new and cool and interesting in our city
The focus is like what the honey restaurant you've been to that booty that's really cool
And frankly the demographics for different it wasn't all a bunch of Engineers and young men
Those first two users both women actually
So
You got that million dollars in the summer of
Mm
I meant that it was only in like November of 05 or you got
Really the first
Outside raise
$5000000
Soap so that million dollars
Was it raining out
We were definitely getting down to the
Lower end of that initial financing I think by the time we see
Secured
Are Aron financing
You're pretty close
Baidu
One thing that did seem to be happening is like it did feel like
The company with Ally users
We had traffic numbers going up into the right
Yeah certainly wasn't all figured out and I wasn't 100% confident
I'm still a little gun-shy because we've been shot down
So badly you know the year prior
But you know as I gauge the reaction that I was getting from metacarpal side of some sense of what I think we have enough to raise
Did you get what you get nervous when he would pet
I'm definitely
Especially like actually approved to be
Super valuable
And when Max pushed us to do the fundraise write it
The first launch in October 2004
In one of his
Reasons that he gave why we should do it is just like crack
Doesn't hurt
And
Yeah that ended it like I was super nervous I'm sure
That time around because I
Didn't know what I was getting into eye
I never talked to
Capillus really like I just had no idea what's going on
And so when we went around the second time I at least knew what the office is look like I knew it
People look like I knew what some of the questions would be
I came with more experience
I'm sure it came through
Yeah but I was still
You know young and just figuring things out so I'm sure I wasn't
I mean
Did you have like an inner voice that was sort of
Imagine you're in your twenties you've got a bunch of people now
Put their Laden
What company are you saying yourself
Who are you why do you think you can make this work
I need my biggest fear was
We had so obviously we knew that we could
Bill you know use full internet
Service like we can make it functional design features
We could engineer then we can put it out there the question was could we connect the parts so that it turned into something that people really love
And also top-of-mind was Max was one of my most
Valuable
Professional contacts and hit committed $1000000
Would seem like an awful lot of money
And I was terrified that I was going to let him down and then I probably would only get one shot at this
So was yeah there's a lot going on I was definitely worried about the implications of
We didn't figure it out
There is a llama say
Fetishization of
Failure in Silicon Valley you know
Culture of a fail fast Fail Hard
People
People who've already had some success
Or you know what that the stakes of failure aren't that high
And it sounds like you were actually really
Terrified feeling there's no glory in Failure nobody wants to fail
I mean obviously I do think
Silicon Valley can be quite forgiving a failure
True
But it's still not pleasant and you don't want to do it
If you can avoid it
And I remember a
A guy who is branded a Serial entrepreneur
Told me
I'm only a Serial entrepreneur because it hasn't worked out Nobody Wants To Be A Serial entrepreneur
Yeah
So when you finally raised money
After the first million that Max
KVUE
When the investor said okay how are you going to make money
M5
What did you say
What was your plan
Giving it
A ton of thought between looking at Google and how they were making money
App search ads
And looking at citysearch
Which
Leo had something similar
On the local space it felt like other some obvious business model
We don't have to
Worry too much
You know not time is it something that makes ensign
It was worth pursuing
Did Yelp
Pretty much
Naturally
Kind of
Just become
Primarily
Restaurant
Review site initially was at
That would happen
Definitely one user join
Yelp
And get excited by reviewing
They tend to
Start with restaurant
And part of that is because you have so many top-of-mind
It's really fun to talk about all your favorites
Send the dishes that you had
It's
Super Freak
So just living your life you always experience more restaurant and have more to talk about
Where has
Yeah hopefully you don't use a plumber very often
I mean maybe a great plumber
Obviously people do talk about that on Yelp and that's
Great
But it's not a great
Starting point
For fun
And frankly that was
The part of the key to all success as we tried to make y'all
For the reviewers
Really about fun
You know why are they spending their time with
That is why are they
Writing these great funny interesting reviews
It's because it's a hobby is
It's something to do contributes
And we always try to focus on making sure that Yelp is
So
Initially like XO as you continue to raise money
10 million
Was there any
Revenue coming in or was it just
The idea that the
At least initially was just
Get more and more user
Mostly was focused on growing the community of reviewers
More content more reviews
Recently added photos
And also it with all that content
10K more traffic
Because the more review content we had generally the more we would show up within Google
Web search
And therefore that would attract more users which would increase the size of the community you know it's art created this positive feedback loop
Yeah from a business model standpoint it was something on our minds
So it was probably
End of 2006
That we really got serious about building out advertising
Products
And eventually landed on pretty simple ad model and it's actually have a Yellow Pages business works
Newspaper business work
Magazine doesn't work so we just started with that because it was
The least friction business is already knew what we were
Point
Or you can dress like
Able to actually see that
This wasn't to turn a corner but this was actually becoming
A million unique Visitors by the middle of 2006 so
2 years after
Max levchin
That's a lot of unique
Visitors
Summer 2005
Was really about getting the
In out getting the initial momentum which was really San Francisco so getting a San Francisco community of Katrina
Readers writers reviewers
Going
And you're showing that that would result in trap
Once we got
Financing the question
Became what can you do it anywhere else
Is it just the San Francisco phenomena and actually like that was the funny thing trying to raise
That round of financing
Yeah the most common question was like well San Francisco
Is that just unique
It's a bunch of hippies they like to help other people
This isn't going to work in New York
And I said that was what once we had the money on board
That's what we aim to figure out it's like can we get it to grow and happen in New York can we get it in LA can we get in Seattle
It's a 2006
That's really what we were focused on was
Spreading city-by-city
Make sure that that we filled the Gap and you know competitor couldn't be us
But also to prove that the model really good scale at least across the US
When the iPhone came out
You cash
Pretty early I thought you wanted earliest apps on there so did you know or did you feel like right away this is going to be is it going to be
Change everything
For us yeah I mean we had enough experience with mobile liquid built a website
Which was like a early
Version of the web for really crappy
Mobile phones
And it was very stripped-down and pretty much unusable
And we need the Internet really wasn't happening on mobile device
Until we saw the ice
It was just
Obvious
Is that okay finally the web has arrived on the phone this is really
Exciting so we knew we
Did you get involved to play some role we adapt our site something was going to happen to
Make room in end
Service fee iPhone
So we actually had a nap ready to go day 1
Albany app store open
When you launched
In the App Store
Have an impact on your business
It didn't have
No I mean that there was no real business impact right away
Is it feel like
Very important for the future in the long-term health of the company
You know where time you were pretty small startups till we have very scarce resources so committing real resources to building an app
Was controversial
Within the company
But it did feel like
This is a historic device this is the future we have to be there we can't
Restaurant in Laurel
I think that we're going to still be winning this game if we don't
Win-win mobile
So
With
This kind of Prada
Write with a reviews
With that territory
Really pissed off business owners right because
They're going to be restaurant
How to get three or four star reviews or bad reviews
And you guys
It was some class action lawsuit
I mean yeah Yelp has always been controversial
Because
We host people's opinions
Hence
And not every business
I want to hear the feedback or is open to the feedback
It's not
Totally dissimilar to a restaurant
Critical
Restaurants have a love-hate relationship with their local restaurant critic or certainly did you know the years
Past
Where are sure if they got a great review they thought
The restaurant critic was wonderful but if they got a negative review they were
Upside
No take that and multiply it times millions of users
And get to be added
Christian conversation
But ultimately
Having all this word-of-mouth exist anyways
Bring it online
Create a lot of value for society book for small business owners who cannot stand out
Wake me up with relatively modest Market
King budgets
If they deliver Great Value great service
You have their word-of-mouth is right there for everyone to see their great reviews are there
But it does come with obviously the occasional
Negative review everyone gets done
And that that hurts
Get on the flip side I mean I feel like
Everyone has had this experience where you look up your favorite restaurant or whatever it is on what album
I love that place has to be right
Well Everyone's entitled to their opinion so if you think you know the four star place should be five well
Open their Red Review and I think the reason why y'all has been successful for so long and such a strong brand
Because like more often than not
But it says 4 and 1/2 stars and there's a couple thousand reviews there you can be pretty darn confident that business is doing something for you
Lockhart
You guys got an offer from Google
Into thing is 2009
Buy you out for reporting for half a billion dollars
Totally life-changing money for you
And
Your partners in investors like you all could have walked away
And then you could have started your next thing
Why didn't you take it
It was a complicated dynamic
Nowhere
Doing quite well
It's interesting at that time to
Considered cozying up
Do Google which has a worldwide presence is where canto
Completing sword International
Expansion
Wasn't an easy call
And there is a course like
Behind the scenes dynamic between Executives and
We had we had been
Staunch critic of Google
Even then and continue to dinner to this day that they were scrubbing
The internet and
Taking the reviews and
Present
Is what their own information or what
Yeah I mean
We started by licensing our content
To them
In a way that
We thought was reasonable and then over time
It became clear that they really wanted to compete with us directly
And collect reviews themselves
And so then they said to us while we're going to collect reviews but we still want you
Who said we're not going to
Compete with ourselves in your Yelp like property that you're building that makes no sense so thank you very much
Like we're done
I said that actually prompted the car
Well maybe we should
Is it really all right well you know where venture-backed we have to have the
Now we have to take
That's seriously macondo
Completed it
And ultimately
I couldn't get together and we saw very exciting independent path and
Taking additional financing and then going public
And that
Was equally exciting to me then you're not getting swallowed up by Google
When Google offered
I read that
Steve Jobs called you
Yeah
True
Is it crazy to get a call from
Steve Jobs
It was crazy
It was probably one of the craziest moments
My career still to this day
Yeah he said
Don't tell the Google
We think you're great company
We think what you're doing really interesting
Didn't say I will Apple in as interested you but he did say
Is this about money
Because apple has a lot of money
And if you need financing or something like that you got my number now so you should call me
And
No I thought that was probably blowing smoke
It was pretty wild it was very surreal cuz he was at was like when I picked up the phone at
And heard his voice I was afraid it was like talking to God
Even so right when that deal with Google is on the table billion dollars
2009 it must have been difficult to say to say no to walk away from that right
It was definitely not an easy decision for anyone involved financially but it also felt like
We don't have to do it we have a bright future we could take the company public we had full confidence that we could do that we knew that there were in about
Masters ready to finance us but
The independent pathlight prior to that moment I did see myself as kind of a young entrepreneur
I'm not a public company CEO I really didn't think that I would ever be a public company CEO
But that moment force me to seriously contemplate was that true
Could I never imagined myself as a public company CEO and
What I thought I might not be comfortable but some of my best decisions are the ones that push me out
My comfort zone and cyan. The more I thought about it the more exciting I might maybe I'm going to fall on my face
It's pretty exciting on the last at all so I'm growing into being a real what I would call real CEO
Headed towards the public markets really see myself that way I'm curious
When you get
Criticized
Like I already did an AMA on Reddit
Back in
There's some people just said mean
Right next to the public eye
I get mean comment
Unsocial media
You care about any of that doesn't even ever get you
Down
I think if you're doing anything important in the world
Then you will have critics
You'll have people that don't like the dynamic
I haven't been created
They don't like the powershift
Yeah they like the old way of doing things
And so
You do have to take it with a grain of salt
Like certainly had moments to get down
Especially if you spend too much time reading
All the critics but
You know and there's also room to learn
Trump critics
Guyana times we've adapted or we are kind of heard what people are saying and tried to
Mitigate
Some of the problems that people are trying to bring to art
Until you don't want to completely cover your ears and it frankly that's what I would tell
Your local businesses
I don't want to hear it from the reviewers
But the fact about her is like in this is true with y'all to most people actually like you
Human nature to focus on the negative
We all do it
How we remember it more strongly
As I think it's important to try and like pay attention to positive
And that'll keep you
When you think about
Where are y'all busy
Slayer public company your
The CEO of Apple company
Heading towards Augusta
Billion dollars
That boy remind me to eat would that mean we're talking about
You going down Sandhill Road like nervously kind of
Pitching to VCS who are
Poking holes in your idea and
Not particularly impressed
I wasn't that long ago
Yeah
But I do feel like Canada
Proverbial frog in the pot
Certainly now as you lay it out
Tess pretty wild
But it has felt like I just very natural progression and always challenging and there's
You know I always knew
Things coming up the
Problems are trying to solve and goals you're trying to meet
The twisty-turny path it hasn't been like a straight line
And I don't anticipate any of the years ahead will be a straight line either
How much of your
Because of
Intelligence and how much do you think
I probably give it 60% luck
First job
I do feel like
Circumstances
Play a big role
Obviously I worked hard to
Be able to understand technology in
You have to look at the timing of
The fact that
I John PayPal PayPal
Success that entire group of people
What started dumped out back in the Silicon Valley all with capital
At a moment.
Are people
Weren't really focused on building new internet companies that sell you had all these confident technologist for PayPal all working on new intern
Ideas with capital at a time where
Sound wide open that's lucky my view but
If you're unprepared for that you can miss out obviously so there is a preparation aspect but you have to
Definitely pay attention to the luck to in and now it's not just all you
Stoppelman co founder Yelp and as of the first quarter of 2019 Yelp users
Posted 184 million reviews and of course with that many reviews you do
Find some gems for Grand Canyon National Park
The same thing really big hole in the ground
National Park one star no concierge or valet parking
And my personal favorite a 2-star review of a jail Washington DC
I spent a few nights here the police were very nice and it was so cold but I made
Friends and the cafeteria lasagna
What is dope
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the things
Your building
The first
A quick message
From one of my sponsors
Microsoft
Today
Innovators are using artificial intelligence
Transform how we work
From The Way We Grow our
Our food to the way we Brew our beer
See how they I
Powering business innovators
Microsoft.com
AI
This week marks the 50th anniversary of the Stonewall uprising
A turning point in the movement
For LGBT
AcuRite
So in this week's episode of the storycorps podcast from NPR will revisit the very first documentary are found
Thunder Day by say made back in 1989 called remembering Stonewall
Listen And subscribe now
Hey thanks for sticking around because
Timeout for how you built
And for a few moments I want you to imagine the secret life
Outdoor cat to an outdoor cat is not being fed by
Human
They will spend 80% of their waking hours hunting for food
This is veterinarian Liz Bales where they hunt then play with their prey and then eat that small meal
Small meal is probably a mouse
And if your cat
Just roaming around in the wild
I need several mice a day
What are cats
Tell wake you up at four 5 or 6 in the morning to be fed they gobble up their food and vomit
They can be aggressive or destructive
All of this is
Is because indoor cats get stressed out when they can't hunt and kill their food so even if your cat is never
Lived outside Mother Nature has ingrained that
Predatory behavior that need Intuit
Wants to recreate
Okay but how how do you recreate the hunting experience and say your one bedroom apartment with a totally Spies
Spoiled indoor cat
Will the answer to that question just cut cancel is a few years ago when she was driving home from a Veterinary conference
I mean it was pretty instantaneous from the time I drove home I drew it
I mean 5 minutes
And what she Drew
Was mice
Five little mice
That had a fabric exterior so the cat could use
There
Teeth and claws in the in the play part of it if they wanted to an inside would be that little mouse
Size portion of food it's really only
30 or 35 calories
Her portion of food that a cat needs at a time
But the important thing is you wouldn't just plant these mice down with a cats
Football supposed
You would hide them in different parts of the house and then they really start
Hunting and they said maybe we'll get down or not praying position with her their front feet are lower than their butt and
Go running around looking for it's really fun
Anyway at this point came all of the
Typical stops
The entrepreneurial Journey so the very next day I'm walking past like 8
Totally chance meeting at a neighbor's house with the most perfect person you could imagine he said
I'm an inventor and a medical device manufacturer
And I said well you need to sit down
Partners worked on the 1st
Zayn and my partner Sue and I so did ourselves in her kitchen with her mother's sewing
Prototypes I would go to my
My colleagues at work and say hey take this one home see what your cat thinks of it and so we had end-of-course raise some money
$136,000 to be exact
Day 4 of Kickstarter when we met our goal and we all were on the phone together when we hit the number and that was
Super fun and then she went to a big industry conference and got a lot of Buzz it's the largest
Pet product convention in America and they have a new product
Category and gosh darn it we won the course during this whole happy-sounding journey
Which was also experiencing a ton of stress and sleepless nights
Is issues as always
Was money money goes lightning fast
Each spend for the website for the packaging for a designer
Is it a good spend are we doing the right thing and I where am I going to get more money from and it's a lot of worry
But things have now kind of settle down for less
Since launching the cat feeder in 2016
She's gotten it on to Amazon and chewy.com and into small pet stores across the country
And she just partnered with a pet supplies
Distributor that's working to get her product overseas
And all that is great but Liz actually has bigger ambitions
She wants to completely change the way our cats eat
1 plastic Mouse
At a time there's 96 million cats living in homes in America
And most of those cats are still eating from bowls but if we can really get people to understand
Dad cat behavior and have the tools to to change it in their homes
This is the opportunity of a lifetime
Pet veterinarian what is bales
Philadelphia Liz has now put her Veterinary practice on hold to manager business full-time
Doc and Phoebe's CAT Company
Indoor hunting feeder to find out more about it or your previous episodes at 12
Podcast page how I built this. Npr.org and of course
If you want tell us your story go to build. Npr.org
We love hearing what you're building
And thanks for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe it Apple podcast or wherever you get your podcast and why you're there
Give us a review
You can also write to us at Hy-Vee tea at npr.org
And if you want to see
Tweet
It's at how I built this
It was pretty sweet by Casey Herman
With original music composed by Rammstein Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Carney sanaz meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
David jaw
Gyros
And you been listening
The how I built this
This
NPR
Support for this podcast
Message come from odoo
Want to boost your business
Check out a new business game
Scale-up
It's fun it's
Smart and O do offers at 4
For free shipping included
Use promo code NPR on
Odio o.com
Flash scale-up