So I want to tell you that we're coming to the Twin Cities for a live event
On Wednesday July 17th
Talking with Dan and Angie Bastian
Co-founders
Angie's boom chicka pop
How is history teacher and a psychiatric nurse started making
Popcorn
Eventually got it in
The stores
Coast to Coast
The show is supported by America
Express and
Are other Live Events have sold out fast
Get tickets go to NPR presents. Org
And
Hope to see you there
And one more thing before we start the show
I want to tell you about a brand new disc
How I built this Summit
Which is happening this
October
San Francisco
Wheeler New Deal for group tickets
Buy for summer tickets
V absolutely free
So bring your co-founders your leaders
Innovators
Dreamers
And grow together
How I built this Summit
Supported by American
Express
To take advantage of group discounts
Email HIV T Summit
At npr.org
And I hope to
See you in San
Cisco
I would find myself with friend to a kind of
What is now at the stage of the curia where things are starting to take off on that and we got to dinner in and around the time
I will and I would dread when I would come to me and asked what I was doing much body would show up until it
When we leave on the it inside us
Doing this little thing and good luck with that little Feller and it was just it was
NPR how I built this
Show that animators entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movement they built
An environmentalist and a professional
Soccer player from New Zealand has been called the world's most
Comfortable shoes
All birds
So for every human being
New Zealand
There are six
Cheap
What's that sink in
E621 sheep to human ratio
That's down from a peak in 1982
When they were 20
2 sheet for every human in Newsela
New Zealand's population is
Pretty small
A little under 5 million people
But the country produces more than 10
Percent of all the wool we use
And what is Eland is particularly good at
Is producing a
Type of wall that
Is considered to be among the best
It's called Merino wool
When it comes as
Bernie Merino sheep
It softer lighter and less
Scratchy the
Type of wool you might find in
Christmas sweater
Note 4 Years Tim Brown was aware of his country's prize export
A decade to realize it was the perfect material to build like comfortable and breathable
The kind of shoes you could slip on for a run or just wear around the house
In 2015 Tim partner to figure out if they can actually find
They raised
About a million dollars from investors to launch allbirds in March of 2016
It almost instantly Auberge word up the world's most comfortable shoe by Time Magazine
Today just three years on their shoe company is valued at 1.4 billion dollars
But what's also incredible is how unlikely it is that they even met in the first place
Joey grew up in Marin County in California of course grew up on the other side of the world
And even before he seriously got into shoes he was playing soccer professionally
Repeat it at the World Cup
It was raised in Wellington New Zealand in the 1980s and 90s his mom was a nurse his dad worked in
Prophets
From a very early age
He found himself in the world of soccer
First in the fan and then
Is a player
It's a really popular sport
In a nation that loves its rugby so the Jaguars was as this went on to be become more more
Autumn Aloft upson-lee someone Mom's family was disappointed
But it was I was soccer not rugby
But that was something that I love to do and then keep doing it in there any when I look back by the time I was sixteen
That was my ID today
My friends were doing and I was starting to get a
Snuff
You know of something that I could do well and something where I could carve out you know if not a career
Play it was a God if I could make the museum another 20 thing
Super talented soccer player
Cuz you got a scholarship to to come to the US to go
University of Cincinnati
Play soccer how did you end up there
I ended up
Getting about six scholarship offer
And then I found in Cincinnati
A design school
Which was the subject
That it was Sonic
Night we met and so Cincinnati was where I was where I hit it
And I hadn't visited
It was it was probably I feel like
The first
Adult decision big decision I've made with my mom and dad will like
Who make a mole make it work
I remember
As part of the application they put the mortgage
Yeah but the house
Zapata
Acrylic swivel cb&i he's good for this
You want to do it
Go back to 100%
And also
If I wasn't a pint of Cincinnati's
Can I change
Okay so you end up
Cincinnati
Hamasaku
And what what was
What was school like was it intense was it
It is you're doing soccer for 40 hours a week and school the other the design program was
It was a five year program
They wanted to break you down
And build you up over
Body is literally
In a fierce Foundation year
Pounding Piper
Not using computer
And literally
Going through a very very traditional sort of design education
And it was difficult because the whole wide world
Department, had the training in the afternoon
And I had a studio Avery
Just about every day from 1 to 12 and then
And I can still remember
Sprinting across campus
Changing anodes instruction some agreement with a couch
Then I can kind of be a little bit
The warm-up or something and then
I could do this to Dion
Somehow made it work but it was it was intense from the beginning
When I look back on it I did was I was
Who's the fair men appreciate but I
I found something
That I I was in love with
What was it about
Art and Design
That connected with you
It was the it was a solving a problem is I found a place that was
Catch rule for my curiosity
Approaches that I
It took me a little while but I
And with the help of a couple days
This is our realized this was
The design was
Was actually not about the
The output it was a
Prices
Of problems
And if you applied you could apply
Thanks
Alright let's positive for sec
Time in Amarillo
Turn to Joy
Scituate you grew up in in the Bay Area
And when you I mean you know you grew up here and then you end up at Berkeley was a great school but was that was that your
Sort of idea you want to stay in this area you want to go
I wanted to go to a great place to challenge me
Want to do engineering
And I also wanted to try and play soccer
And so those are the two guiding factors that
End up leaving me by deduction to get to Berkeley
Were you a good soccer player
I was all right
Yeah
I need a play-by-play to Berkeley as well
Until I got injured
Great soccer player
Where are we We Are Tonight go and let go in the alley and end challenge anyway
Alright see you were you finished Berkeley
And you
What what do you want to do with your life at that point if you know
23 whatever most people don't really know
Were you thinking maybe a school maybe I'll do
Like that or did you have a sense of what you want to do
I really didn't
And then
Simply night I just
Latched onto this concept of
Business Consulting with
It was marketed to me as
If you don't know what you're doing this is a great way to get a taste for
A lot of things
Cuz I got cool that sounds good cuz I definitely don't know what I'm doing
And so I asked
Went to a couple of
Does little intercessions they have on campus
And
Doctors company Deloitte
Sounded amazing
End up jumping into there and did their Consulting Group
It in a lot of people that we've had and how I built this
Did Consulting work
Mesa
You know that experience
Consulting with different Industries
And that sort of how they got their ideas
What was some of that Consulting work
You are doing
Tell me my most transformative one
Was I work for
A client was a garbage
The garbage company
Has the second largest garbage company in the country
And I was
I looked at fuel
I'm looking at something esoteric like fuel surcharges yeah
And I was negotiating all these Trucking Fleet contract
I was literally doing deals in Atlanta
I would go to a landfill and it would
Every time you walk in and
The guy was running label. Yep smells like money
Cuz it would smell really bad but
That was worth it
Dallas
Business success
And it was really as really eye-opening it was very Scrappy
I know this is something I actually really loved it
And and I ended up leaving Consulting because I
That that really early Taste of
Entrepreneurial business
Just got me an ending the berry you almost can't help it Journey kind of like
Dennis Wilson
I guess mm in
And I latched onto this concept of
Environmentalism through business
And using business
For good
And doing it for the environment
And so I decided that business will be a good opportunity to
I kind of refined my interests and help
Really focus on getting into that sector
Too I guess you got a pan to the Warren school
For you I mean
Was business school like the jewel of business school with business caucus
Sandbox
You know I'm just going to come up with some ideas and then get out of here and
Yes actually
I was
Searching with the all the engineering schools in pain
Defined
Acquainted acquainted company
But I can help
Take the technology out of the university and start the business
And then I also got to just
Come out to the West Coast where most of the cleantech
Style of
Business was happening right now it right then it was it was solar-wind biofuels biochemicals
And that was pick shaping is France 2
All right so you are
You graduate
With an MBA
And you went and got a job
With a
Lichen Environmental
Technology
It back in Bay Area right
Yeah company was called solazyme
And
Solazyme was
Doing something really unique
I in the biofuel space they were using microalgae
And and doing it in a totally different way they were growing this microalgae and
Huge fermentation vessel
I was
Completely captivated by the
Technology
Division was to basically
Be there the next source of
Of liquid
Fuel and chemicals for the entire world you can make oil
Serve a biofuel from algae
Yeah
You can turn it into fuel
And it was
Yeah but actually incredibly high impact for the world if we could get the technology right and get the cost down
Mount it to a place that was
Meaningful what was the response to your
Your idea
The response for
The company was incredible
And we were
I joined in 2009
And
We ended up going public in 2011
We raised over a billion dollars
Has money for the business
When it was it was
It had a legitimate shot of
Of doing something special
And it got towards the end of my my time there I think I
Linda huge amount about
What not to do and then ended up I think unequivocally being being a pretty big failure what was the failure
The entire business
That they got it it went bankrupt and then it's been acquired since
Spare some of the remnants of the technologist do every
The investors lost their money on
Lottery
And you
And other people who made a commitment to that company probably lost
Out as well right cuz you play got some equity and then
You sure yeah I mean we we
Weird dreams of of Fortune that supposed
But yeah what what I took away from that experience was
Incredibly rich
And towards the end of that I started looking around at
Tana difference
Opportunities
Because I ever find what I want to see you and I and I saw
What I thought was
The path to make a different kind of a company where the output of that business
Really high
Let's just pause
First attempt because
You eventually would graduate from from the University of Cincinnati
And then you went to
ASAP Virginia to play soccer professionally semi-professional
Play for a while
But then you eventually go back
And play professional soccer in New Zealand
Yeah
And I found myself
Signed on a multi-year deal to play
Professional sport
In my hometown
And I was now part of a New Zealand same that headset
It's Target of qualifying for the World Cup in 2010 and I was I was kind of on my way
Well I wasn't a quickest when it wasn't my technical
But I found a White Rock
How to combat a career that involve me doing a couple things
Really really well
What were they
Being
Foot and running around a lot
Chicken people
And tackling people and getting a bull off the appliance and giving it to the good Plaza nothing you or Defender
I was a midfielder but I thought you know I kind of a
What about defensive responsibilities that was about tackling in about aggression in a
That running around I'm getting a bowl and then it was about scoring goals when you getting lots of penalties called against you
Cuz you don't strike me as an aggressive
Kind of
Guy but I guess the competitiveness with something
Bruns and me whatever it took
To win
Bets
You know that was within me and I took a little while to realize that but it was it was there and I was just was competitive
So you are I mean this is in your circle
Twenties and into your 30s
How did you think about structure in your life did you think okay I'll play soccer and then I'll get in till I come back to soccer management or something
What you know about that I was probably starting
Singly focused on this on the sporting career
And abnormal
Think I'd a good living
My friends that have gone to University and we were getting consulting jobs
Apply for my country
That means
We can never have a small group of plaz
That realize that we have
Potential Charlotte oil cap
And if that was the
The special source
Drive me to kind of
Get through the
The humdrum no retainer professional sport and keep trying and keep improving and keep looking
Because there was this logic rise here in the slide your sense of purpose
And the prize was getting to the World Cup in South Africa
M2010
Yeah formica
Also the. Your life I guess when you
Start to come up with the idea for what
Would become Auburn
One of the other cool things that happen
Is I got a sponsorship.
From one of the big guy Sports
And I felt like
And I could go to the shop and get what I wanted really but I was wearing logos all the time
And is it I was I was a minimalist
And I remember still
My dad broke up
What's my debit lockpicking logos
Of clothes
And so the idea that this was
It was like I said everything that I was wearing her
It's just like a Swede
Completely
The antithesis of everything I stood for from
Ingrained to me
The University of Cincinnati
And I guess the other thing it was happening
I just had a
I had my afternoons
I was training in the morning and I was
Credibly Firestone sport Rite a lot of
And so
I started to get curious about
Tequila problem
Articulation
With the problem of
The problem of something simple
It was impossible
Dafont and a New Zealand it was sort of
Just like a nice slip on Earth
Like a lights up sneaker
Rite Aid ahead logos on it
Will you boy
Keyboard
Chuck Taylor
Brighton was there wasn't too much
And Chuck Taylors
The great Butternut super comfy it was it was one of those ones
I just saw a problem that was
It was mine I didn't write a business plan
And something off season one of my soccer Seasons I want to side with the
2015 of the year will you kind of go off
Open your wrist
What sound Factory
Online
And I went and visited one
Where was it in Indonesia
So you are serious you were like
But I know I'm going to go build a comfortable shoe it wasn't about comforter
Design
It was a design observation about
Category
Complicated
I've cried enough
You just said I want to make a shoe
That's a server high top
Like a Chuck Taylor without logos yeah I'm going to I'm going to go do it
It was that simple
And I tried to do a New Zealand and realize that
Extra long suit
Disappeared from
Nobody
And so I said walk I will it scar
See if we can do this
And I greatly
Underestimated as I'm sure Joey would have kissed how complicated it is actually to make a shoe by the way did you know how to sew a mean
I learned that you didn't learn that design school
But you make patterns you cut them out like you didn't have a sense of how to draw rings
Justice for
And I had photos of
Other examples
Shoes that I thought
Close
But that was a
And I thought
We could go
Make this I think if
If you could make it you could sell it
And this potentially
The business
And it started to
Get really really interested in this idea
Entrepreneurialism
Building a business of making things this is why your ass while you're still a soccer player
And I'm kind of
ABC and fox I mean on the World Cup
Everything was training was thought that was that was not ran through it myself but this was my mean to escape
Did this was in 2009 you would not actually really start to make a shoe
Like 5 more years later which will get to know I'm not not really
I might shoot straight away you made sure you straight away and I saw them to my team
Okay so we'll see you made them at this Factory
Rihanna Shut Up and
So you actually put
All your cash into the splits and my brother was helping
With some of the selling
What were they made out of
Canvas and let you know some Lita
Some New Zealand later I was tripping other again
Another Riot an experience where I walked into a Tannery for the first time and started to understand why
How bad that
Materials
Write all the chemicals that go into the leather leather right and just understand just generally
Just
You know where these materials were coming from a ring of the samples would come
And you left in the Box I would smell like
And I think that opened up the idea of exploring differ
Materials
What were your shoes called
It's a particular time I think the name was
With my initials
To be
And any idea was a no logo shoe that was comfortable
Made out of canvas
Different styles of the hardtop on a laptop
And I sold it to my teammates
For like
4T boxer laws
Made them peifu cross
And I
150 box fans
So you sold it but you could have sold 1000 pairs we did it we did a pop-up shop in Wellington and you know
I think it was the beginning of
Of an interest in this category in the process of selling
I'm selling the shoes the design story was
Was one part of it I think it reside with people
But it needed something more buy for me and for
Product the flight was okay
But it wasn't
It wasn't differentiate
And you know I think I remember reading a magazine one day
About the wool industry in New Zealand and we'd actually we put some wolfelt experimented on some wolf out on the outside of sunburst
How's it going
Which was wool not used in shoes
What if we could do that
That would be hugely
So I can die with the help of
Of
Some friends of the time put together a ground on a whim
To develop a wool and textile
Faithful to making the upper of a shoe that apply to the New Zealand government
It was
To research how you could turn wool into shoes
22 actually Mike
Because it didn't exist
And you know I think the backdrop in the context around this was the easy on 45 and What's a shape
It's a hugely important Legacy industry in New Zealand that is going through a really really tough
Tough time
And do not think that
That was searching for new ideas
And you categories and it was kind of right time right place with a
A random maybe obvious idea
That haven't been done before in and we got lucky and so
Probably around the world couple of before this ground
Research lab in Christchurch
Set about trying to make a fabric
All of this is happening
At the same time that your team is is
Finally qualified for the World Cup qualified
David Wilcox the first time in 1982 and the 2nd, 2010 so that was a big deal
We're undefeated
The only undefeated team that will count
Because
We drew three times and didn't get out of that
Has Spain won the World Cup
And it was
That was an enormous at
And this was an easy one thing that I mean was ranked
The smallest nation of the world cop we were the lowest rank
And we went in there and
I mean even to qualify was a norm
Conversation
Yeah
Wow
Attend the World Cup what were you up to
He had at that was actually just about the time when we met
And how did you meet
Well ten timid started dating
A lady named Lindsey
Hell he has subsequently married American
She's from you
We met each other at a at a wedding I come back to visit one of my old teammates from Cincinnati
And going to the wedding and stop by to see some friends in New York and I'm sitting next to the lenses
And Lindsay
Chewy
Lindsey new
Because
Back in
Maybe
Mm
Early early part of that decade
At Lindsay and Liz my wife
Where am I
And door mats in college Colorado
Oh wow yeah
And today they've been
Super close friends
How well over decade
So I got to meet Lindsey in
When when Lindsay Cameron and introduced us to Tim
I thought it was pretty good but you guys have met
But you were doing your own thing he was
Playing soccer in
You started a nice guy
Tim uu
Retire from football
Play soccer and then I realized
This is this is
Where are you at the park scene
Bike Tour upper
Two-year contract
And
I did this time
The idea of
Going back to school and studying all the subjects that I'd avoided was interesting and I
How do I want to go back to London where I was born and where my father was Froman
So do I deserve being able
Go back there
And study was was
By the way out of sporting some ways in the best of Wisin
I know and ended the opportunity to kind of step back and
And stop this
So you decide to do a
Degree
At London School of economics
With this idea for a shoe in your mind
Yeah
And a little bit of shoemaking also
Troubleshooting
And I showed up and and and did the
This couple semesters and I will say your name
Went off to Kellogg
Northwestern
And you are able to take the pic of classes
Now that you want the truth
The quarter that you or the other.
Are you there
ISO shop at Evanston and I walk into
An entrepreneurship class
With a physical card cost
Who is a former CEO of walmart.com in this
Pretty a special purpose of the air
And
He sent an email out he said everyone
Hestia coming
And that you've got
3 minutes to pitch an idea to the class
And we will
Form teams around the Beastie no ideas and for the whole
You have court are you
Yoga Loft
This business idea by pitch the idea of Wu shoes
And I think people thought it was a little bit of a jack
Yeah but for whatever reason it got selected
And I found myself a list
3 months
Penis idea
I'm truly
Actually building us into a business
This idea of wool shoes which
What you'd really been touring with Sam 2009
An hour around 2012-2013
It's
Starting to get some traction
Yeah but but I wonder I mean
Was anyone saying like
How do you turn
A scratchy wool into
And 2 shoes
Everyone
Sid
But there was something about the idea
That people sit on you but how did you describe it to
People because I'm saying to you
Tim
I don't get it like I here's my wool sweater how do I translate that into shoes
How would you describe
I will fish delight I realized that wool
Scratch
So what's up
Copamarina
Okay is a different sheet
It's okay and it's a fine material on software
And then you will have to talk about not just the material you acted
Benefits of Massage
So what
Are you going to do this there must be a reason and the reason is
Because will has leaves
Miraculous properties
Any people
What it is as much as people kind of
Loft the idea this has been a consistent thread I think on some level they so to see
That's interesting
And try goatee into that course and
To London Austin my time at Kellogg and decided I was going to watch washers on Kickstarter
Okay but so
To do something on Kickstarter what you did in 2014 but to do some have Kickstarter
You need to have the Prototype you need to have
A lot of things
Had you what it what was it what was it
We called called allbirds
No it was a decide renamed it again and it took another crack at 9 then it was cool three out of seven
And it was going to be very very
Simple design original
And and we can be made out of wool with us
The humans rights Kickstarter
You start the promise people that you're going to deliver them the shoe factory on Google
Where was it in Portugal this time
And I flown over and was a tiny Victory and I'd made I think
I was eight pills of samples
And I went home to New Zealand for Christmas
I shut up
I needed to shoot a video with my Dad's friend
Do I dye a sheep farm
Just outside of Wellington
We have one day to do this and my dad's
Friend
I remember showing up on the morning off
He went in
About the shape so they could be in the backdrop of this video and
I very nearly pulled out
I was running this script and I just it was one of those moments you think this is dumb
And my brother
Literally drag me along to the farm
And said you stood what's the worst that can happen
And so we went we went ahead with it and shut up
Show the video of an ultimately
Launched the kick-start of a wind live on March of 2014 so you make the video you say hey
Hey I'm Tim and I want to tell you a little bit about Merino wool in the shoes that I'm going to
Create and I try some cheap around and it's yeah that's a little
It's kind of a little
Flight of the Conchords disc maybe I did I heard a little weird and funny and
But try to really hone in on Unser
You know what is a different one that is end
Quick log on and I was back in London
And I remember
My phone just got a gun
Picked up
Boston Museum media okay
It went on the kickstarter time pageant and only mailing list would I send out to have interesting projects and
It went to a hundred
Near $20,000 and $4 and I had to stop it
Because I didn't have enough that was a
Yeah
And I
I just thought this thing out
Because you didn't even a fool
And Lindsay
Head
Had sent this out to all her friends and
United
Boyfriends.
This project
Have you can support them in and Joey was one of the earliest, and what was your day
Play under $100 or $120
Going to get you a pair of these
First wool Runners ever created
First wool Runners ever created all right so you do the kickstarter you configure one of the contributors
Joey
Tim you raise more money than you need and
And which sounds like a great
Bing
But actually it wasn't it was it was actually
Stressful sometimes
From the outside when you've had the moment of greatest success that still at the moment
You must Ensure
You must scared
Ski
I have to go deliver on this now and then
And executed and end
This is going to be really really hot
When we come back
The moment Hotel reached out to Joey
For help
Joey went from being a customer
Partner
Helping build all birds
A billion dollar brand
Play with us
Gyros
How I built this
From NPR
Just a quick thanks
Two of our sponsors who helped make this podcast possible
First
Wix.com
How I built this tells inspiring stories about founders
How their businesses
Has found success
With wix
You can create a professional website for your own business
Choose a template design for your industry
Customize it to match your brand
With Ascend by Wix you can connect with your site visitors capture leads and manager customer relations from
One place
Get started by going to wix.com hpibet
To get 10% off
Thanks also to SimpliSafe home security the beliefs
Fear has no place in a place like home
That's why they made a completely wireless home security system that can be self-installed in under an hour
SimpliSafe sensors are built to protect every point of access to your home including doors windows and
Garage
More than three million people have already protected their homes with SimpliSafe
Get free shipping
60 day money back guarantee
Simplisafe.com
Built
How many candidates are running for president
Maybe more to come if there's a lot
Tracker
Is why the NPR politics podcast
Hitting the road
The introduce you to all the people running
President join us on the campaign Trail as we interview the candidates
To ask why they are the best
For president
Follow along this
Spring and summer
Driving to the NPR politics podcast
Welcome back to how I built this
PR
And I Rise
Tim Brown has launched his idea for a new kind of wool shoe
R Kickstarter
And people respond right away they raised 120
Thousand
Just a few
Few days
What you mean is that Tim now needs to get to work fast
To start filling orders
Had a couple young guys cuddle with information We Found Love spicing
In London and
You know I spent probably the worst year
Trying to make this thing happen
Every mistake you can imagine
And I remember that
Vista Factory at the young guy he gone over the sector Nicole me at 1 to any guys we got a problem
The sector has made the men's and women's shoes exactly the same sauce
That's bet there's like a one-and-a-half this could be different sure where we going to do we got no choice
Going to have to just
We just have to send it out
Joey you are a customer that Kickstarter campaign
I was I was one of the lucky customers who order two men standing at a women's 10
And it was fine
I know it was not fun
I was pretty bad I didn't you
When I when I 10 customer service
Which was
Tim Brown
It is recommended that I take out the insole make a little room more room for myself Seth wow and since you didn't have any more while there was no
No exchanges or anything like that
Can you play something to me when you make $120,000
Kickstarter
Amazing it's a lot of
Cash
It probably did not pay
For all of the origins of a film
Was financially
And so I was tapping into my my savings at work
Rapidly dwindling at the time and
Living in London in
And then right at the end of that we sort of
The factory in Portugal
Tom decided to go bankrupt
Right at the end of this shortly after we just delivered a study idea that we were going to come
Troy mcmorran
Oldest business in Gulfport to the next phase of
I had to do a Missy Dash to Portugal to go rescue the
10 oz of watermelon
From Effexor
Okay when you finished
Fulfilling his orders
Were you like
Okay now I've got it
Create a business or you likes
Or you like I'm done with
I just kind of summer in between
And I did that that year was
Was awful and it was
I would find myself at dinners
With woodlands and her friend to a kind of hoodies now at the stage of the career with things are starting to
To take off in that
And we got the dinner to go around the table and I would
I just have a drink when I would
Come to me and see what else what I was doing
Lunch with Mike unplug my body would kill up into a little bowl and I was so excited whooshes and
When we leave the dental people pet me on the head and say that's
Lovely
Sing this little thing and good luck with that little fella run it was just it was it was
It became clear to the
Doing it by yourself
Really hot
And that I was good at some aspects of it and there's a bunch of things that are blue
You know you're doing your
Call your friend a favor and just wants to pour them
But I have to imagine that at least initially you're not thinking
This is what I want to do I want to leave my job and go do this or right
If you asked me at the time I would have left you
Usmes. I'm just going to support this
I did think it was it was really cool and I mean
Looking back at that video as I as I once in awhile do when we're chilling
New employees not all birds
A lot of the things that Tim
Intuitively
Shaw and talked about in that video
Are exactly the same things that
We talked about today and I think
Are Tim is tennis one of those
Unbelievable intuitive marketers
Connect with
With people and understands what is missing in the market and
And that was clear from I think they won
Sir Tim I read that
After the kickstarter
Android ndk
Fulfill those orders
You're kind of exhaust
What's the name of this nightmare
Mymercy
And you're trying to think what am I going to
Do with it
This thing you were contacted by an investor
Who said hey
Fitness on here would you let me buy into this
I found myself on a plane to New York speaking with someone from within the
The world who had seen the traction and
The product and liked it
Locked it and I went and you can spend a lot of time in the movie three aspects of it and they put out they put a deal in front of
And that must have been pretty gratifying me I have to assume you were getting a little bit nervous about your Finance
Situations are there putting a dollar figure in front of you must have been
Quite nice I was starting to think
What do I do next
I've been through this really difficult year and I was like what
Why am I doing
Making whooshes what was this evening
Answers through my mind and we get to simatai
Enough
Do understand the deal
But you better that it was complicated was, and how much time did you have before you
Does things on the table and
And Lindsay
Chic
She goes you need to speak with you about this
He comes from this world he's
He's a customer of the project
Piano
He be an interesting person to circle the Sun
And so and so I didn't even want to give me the
10 minutes
It's good and it's bad and you don't really have
Anything else
Do you want to show us around yeah can you give me a rough sense of what they're offering you
It was
It was some upfront capital
That would convert to equity
Depending on how the business performed
Involve car moving to New York
And I wouldn't
A big chunk with a large large chunk of
Majority of the majority
And see if he left with like
2015 something like that
And so Jojo
Took a look at this thing for me and
They jumped on the phone and he hasn't just look
He
I'd really really good friends close friends that it looked at the caudal up to that yeah
Heat gun for
What did you think when you saw it
I thought
Yeah I didn't think that
There was any ill intent from the from the guys here except the deal but it was
It was vulturous
In the way
After I read it
And I thought that it was taking
Advantage of a great idea and trying to sink their talons into
Into this business and
It what 10 would have been left with was not
Great Tso
Did I told him at that time I was like
Like luck I wouldn't take the deal and I wouldn't
Run the business this way
But what was his alternative
I said that time I looked at it this is the moment and in my life to that I'd been at Souls on for 6 years yeah
And
I had a very consistent experience
And I mean I cannot look back and laugh a little bit now like algae oil kind of sounds like the pill like 2,000 version of
Snake oil salesman
But I was
Big multinationals and chemical companies
Big brands
And there was like a couple of these just Seminole moments where I would
I would have an idea I would go talk to the right people you'd want to talk to if you had an amazing new material
That happened to be really sustainable for the Atlantic
I pitched it in had multiple meetings
And everyone at first is like I'm soup this is amazing
Exciting idea wheel of the sustainability mission
And then you got okay well let's do this you
And then it turns to like this
Really
Inane sourcing conversation where they're like
Just do what we do now do it cheaper like we don't really like we don't really care about the sustainability Park
Is is not the words they use but that's the sentiment that's conveyed
And so I just realized it is
Super frustrating experience that
Dip Brands big Brands they said they cared about sustainability
But in reality they were just paying lip service to the idea
I'm sitting here and Tim comes with this
Not just a concept but like a pretty
Flushed out idea with
Kickstarter success
Really resonated with me from a sustainability
Perspective
But it was also about an opportunity to
Sell shoes in a totally different way than the industry had
Never done before
Okay so
You see this term sheet
The gears start turning in your head Joey while you're thinking wait a minute
This actually
There's some
Legs to this thing
And actually maybe I can talk to
Tim about
Sort of using this shoe idea as a vehicle for
Sustainability
Yeah I read
How to spell cradle-to-cradle I remember the intro chapter
I talked about one of the scourges of the Earth
On pollution in the environment being
The Shield
The number of shoes and Anna
20 billion Paris
The shoes that are made every year
In the us alone
The average American kid woman
Man this
Day by 8
Paris per year
Per person
That's two and a half billion just the US
It's all these things are sitting in land
And until what you put into
The chemicals in that any material that used to produce it
AR
They're incredibly important and no one's thinking of
And so
Yeah the gear started trying little bit and I started thinking more and an ear look timing is everything
I asked him but my family I had I had to really young kids
Did the time
And lives in and my kids were gone for the weekend and I asked him
If you wanted to fly out
From London
And and just talked about the concept
To see if
If he give it another go and maybe we could work together we can work together
Yeah what you think about that
I jumped on the plane
And I flew out to San Francisco
And I'm enjoying all spent the week waiting to get any pick me up at the airport
Listen 2015
This is in an early 2015 and we spend we spend
The Weeknd
Getting
Getting a little bit drunk and and talkin about a families and getting to know each other and walking in the house of Miranda and really Justice
What am I do like to work together and try to understand if that would be a good idea or not
So did you resolve that weekend
Try this out to make it go up
By and large yeah
Atlanta back in London I found the person to do it with
Why did you think he was the person to do
I think I found a guy
That
On the surface was very very different from me but maybe
On the night shift a lot of
Similarities in terms of attitude and approach
What sound
Maybe I kindred spirit ends of
Competitiveness
Which we both said that I thought that was an attractive
I think I found someone that could do all the parts of the business that I shouldn't be doing and and that we potentially
Could be a great grandpa
Can I ask you guys then this is important cuz a lot of people to listen to show
The cofounders are two people involved
And a big part of the show is Lessons Learned
Write as a roadmap
Can you walk me through the
I don't know if it was difficult I don't know if it was uncomfortable or unpleasant the conversation the two of you had to have
When you decided how you were going to structure
This company because you've been working on this
And you had this idea but
Just actually take
Tim's idea but
To turn it into a
Totally sustainable
Harbin
Free carbon-neutral
Product which will get
Cheap you're both coming in with big ideas
How do you divide the company of
I needed that
Do that very quickly in and very simply
Ivory MO
I think the important part that we both understood was that
We doing this alone and become an experienced it for a while
Doing it alone is
Really lonely
And I'd always been of the opinion that
I was going to do a business I wanted to do it with someone cuz I I knew my shortcomings were
Substantial
And then I would much rather have
A piece
Something big
Then
Lot of something
Lakes Mall
And so it what you know and I think he respected what I was going to bring to the table
I'm particularly the future that doesn't say it wasn't
End up being a reasonably
Reasonably quick conversation and I think
Neither of us have I really look back at least I should Landon left back and never regretted that so you're dividing up 100% of some
Something worth noting
At that point which is always
Challenge because you never know what
What's going to happen in the future
And then you both
Decide you are
Going to both
Be the CEO
Yeah you know we we
But I was having a lot of the conversation
The financial community
And
Yeah you going until like someone's office
Like okay that's awesome but can I talk to
Yeah right
Cheddar's at Yale first London
Jason London he's also he's also doing other kinds of conversations that would be an N subsequently we knew that
Press
Like talking to Media was going to be relieved
At Tim is going to go have a media conversation
Cute like
They would also want to talk to the CEO was just
And we both knew what each other prior
Something really special to the table
That the other one
Didn't didn't ring
And now and said that it wasn't just a semantic
Title it was really
Actually
The fundamental contribution
Warranted that kind of split responsibilities that summer
A 2015 you're pounding the pavement Joey trying to raise money
How much money did you think you needed to raise to get this thing
We at yeah we did our little business plan which is remarkably inaccurate but we
But we decided that we needed a million and a half dollars
And we felt like that could get us through
Huge amount of
Marketing branding work in the beginning and then
Buy a whole bunch of em
Inventory and we wanted to buy a lot of
We have this mentality of
If we are going to do this we are going to fail Superfast or succeed really big
And so the idea from the beginning was direct
To Consumer you were going to
Have a big marketing campaign to attract people to the website
And you were going to have the shoes in a warehouse and then you could just shut them out
Yep
Basically that we were going to launch simultaneously in the US
And New Zealand on
Just website
And did you have a date in mind
We did
March 1st 2016
Wow and you were working out of your house
And my mother-in-law's apartment okay in in Marin
Tim you're wrapping up in London preparing to move to California to get married on June 6th 2015
Then to move to California, California
OKC
You spend
Basically a
Full-year
Raising money from investors
And perfecting the design and in doing everything you need to do to create this
Turbo lands
Sustainable
Wushu
What was your
Game plan
What do you do with a
We will
We had to build the brand
We had a quarter instrumental
Conversation with a guy who has previously been on the show called Eric Ryan from
Sweet would sit down with a movie sit High we want to build a different type of
Who is Brandon we believe this
Probably solve and we can make
The shoes that I
They're more comfortable that a bit for the environment
Zeppelin what do you think
He said to us
Fantastic
Taipei seoul
On the back
Just get on with doing it
People that buy sustainable products that bike right products
And the only reason for you to do this
Is because the rest of the world
Far behind with I need to
And get on with doing it
And and Doug Mike
Sustainability of hotteebrand mic
Make the attributes of
The product of the sustainable materials the story
So you you thought Comfort was wavering
Comfort was the weather
It was the problem to be solved
And we were going to solve Comfort through sustainable materials that and I believe that Comfort experience but we're also better for the environment
You Know What It Seems
It seems obvious yet comforters
People buy shoes in
And
Comfort often is equated with
Ugliness fu
Dad tells you he's got a couple pair of shoes you should know that look very good
Said you were bringing great design and pairing it with that
Shaving the Comfort through materials that will
What's a better for the environment
It is really kind of the
Northstar for the business
By the way how did you get the name
Git branch show me a lot of different names
And ultimately
Landed on ubereats is a sort of this
Whimsical encapsulation of
Hope the type of business that we wanted to build
Fisk Avenue Zeeland was it was nothing there but birds was Robards so I was a little nod to the pro
Provenance of the story Inn
And the idea that we should trade more lightly in the in the white that ended that we might products
Yeah
And so we chose that and Joey procure the.com
And we were we were
So you launched on March
My fresh
March 1st 2018
The big red button or Saturday ride bike riding outfit you launch it the website goes live
What happened to your inventory
Yeah we saw through it really fast
And where were you holding at inventory
We had a warehouse in Connecticut at the time
And we sold through
Within I think
A week and a half we started having
Sizes that were sold out and you did all this Lake was shopify's weekend ya ya te technology enable let's do this
It's really late today are
Yeah yeah
It's the thing yeah we started
Direct-to-consumer as a concept has been around for awhile but the technology has
Developed and so it allowed us to
Take advantage of things quite inexpensive life from from that infrastructure that that stuff
I mean that's amazing cuz anyone can use it
Colleges available to anyone
Affordable
Salesforce technology Shopify all this stuff is out there
In some ways that the barriers to entry to the launching a new business of Nevada
And others
And otherwise it's it's never been more competitive
But certainly you know we were able to do that
Reasonably easily
You lunch and you just start
Selling out
Fast
Was that
Incredibly exciting or did that create
New
Kinds of stress
It was weird
Who's like
Neither of us would have said that we are like really successful
At that point
And
In some ways it was great like obviously it's certainly better than not selling any issues set up so don't get me wrong I mean
Like 15000 parisot that was a lot
And then we start selling through really fast
And then we
Both found herself
Acting strange
This
Is that you was like letting the air out of a balloon it was like to eat you have this unbelievably stressful 7/8 months of
Of of working for this
Singular creative piece
This product
And then you put it out there and just see what happens
End
It worked
Ostensibly yunnan people
15000 or close to that that bought it
And then we're sitting there like okay the stress is gone now is like
Maybe we like had too much of a Swagger
And like I think it was funny like that
The most successful X on the outside
Maybe you look on the inside
Especially where we were probably maybe at one of our worst moments as a partnership
Why
I think we just started you know we started
Maybe I was probably
Getting over my skis and talking about things in design
And maybe Tim was
Doing some things in in the area of the business that I was Stronger at that
That that maybe you shouldn't have been
And we we were at we were like hey
This work like
Step off
Test memory it weird with a beer
I must be like
At the end of March
30 31 days
And we
We got a million dollars in sales in the first month I mean it was it was crazy
And with no way we didn't
We think we
We blew through our
First-year business plan
Kardashian and like
WeChat
Really short amount of time
So we were
Beyond any
Doubt that it was it was working and we're having this beer and we're like both eyes watering up
And
Ayye
Yeah I don't like how this is going
It was one of those moments where we then,
Fell back on the promise we made
Kylie to our wives
About not ruining their
Relationship in
The fact that if we were going to make something successful it was going to take two of us
And we got to work on this and and this is more important then
Whether we sell out the next color whatever because from the outside as you say you would have thought oh man this
Because crushing it great job
But this is really want attention begins it was. It was at that moment it's funny it has
Through the Journey and then they usually they usually linked up from the outside when we had that we've had the most success
Whenever I mow to be high-fiving in
We had a moment and it was I don't think we'd get found a kind of a
A mechanism
The Carnegie
To get stuff
I think we just been working and I saw beside he drowned and you know it if it's the joke about
Pretty deep and we found ways to sort of like
Purge the system
And reset the machine
And
By the time that kind of came out in it and a little bit of an avalanche of
What kind of motion in
Cognizant
And I you know I think it was we realized
That we needed to manage this more effectively
That our relationship
Would be
As important as the strategy
Yeah is as important as many of the things we were doing that in that needed to be
He worked on market like any healthy
And it's also there's a directness in our relationship that
We don't have that
At like
You can't just
Can just talk about superficial business
Cast that are doing wrong or right like it you know where like
Did
This is not good
Like it's going to be a different direction for us to work this out with
And at
I'm just getting to the heart of issue not letting it calcify it's it's
Give it no time
Nip it in the bud and move on and have super low ego about it and I think our personalities
NRI respect for one another is what kind of
Lends itself to allowing that strategy to work and might not be for everyone
What's a Nae just a self-generating Thing Once you launch
Suspicion is
It was just after the race
It's like
You were getting more attention than you getting celebrities wearing it and Gayle King telling Oprah you got to try these on and
Play Barack Obama wears an I mean
Is that what happened what it did just continue to cut a snowball on its own and obviously
Did Media stuff but
Are or was ever a moment
White wedges
Service slow down you said okay
I don't know
Yeah I don't think there's like a single moment but there was there was moments
Xian August the front page of the New York Times
Get on the
Front page of the business section everyone
Shoes and
That catalyzes a bunch of attention and then
Hey get a moment like
Smashing Gayle King's a lot in the media
And I think
We just gave it time to you know we we didn't sell we sold one
Style the wall Runner
14 months
Did we win do anything else except the wall Runner
And I think that
It's hard to create new doubt about what you stand for
If you have just one product
I got helps you in and it just being methodical and intentional about that
Not taking advice from people who said
Turn it out faster drop more colors drop more Styles you know
You guys
Have
You guys are a b Corporation
People don't know what that is essentially means you commit to certain sustainability practices and and
The way you serve treat your employees and compensation Etc
It's a big thing you know you talked about the materials that are used for the shoes
I know Joey you were
Very influenced by
Sustainability
Let's talk about this for a moment I mean you're still
You got to get the wool from New Zealand it's got to be spun into
This material then made into shoes in a factory that is probably
You know using electricity
And then put on ships and then sent all
Over the world
Is it possible to make
A carbon-neutral
Shoot is that possible with with all those things I've just
Describe
Yeah it is
We're not there yet
And I think we when we started this business we had a really
Clear
Ikea
We wanted to be
Wanted to be like a tree
You wanted to suck carbon out and spit out oxygen
We want to be back yet
And we knew we were we were quite a ways from
That ambition
But
In the problem of climate change is that
Businesses pollute
And
And Society pays for that
Yep the companies don't pay for it and that's the problem
And so we've we believe that we should pay for it
And so
We have committed to be carbon neutral and the
Across all the dimensions that you said from transportation to the electric grid that the factories were in Korea because
How much cleaner grad than other places in the world
Sure but we still we still have emissions in in the way that we make the shoe and transport it and ship it to
Customers for e-commerce
Until we pay for a paper offsets for the remainder of that
Natural bridge the gap between the idealism and the practicalities of so where the rubber meets
The proverbial Road despite your idealism despite your commitment to
Creating this
Thing that could be carbon neutral there people are going to want to return on their money
I don't really
Care about that even if they say they do
Even if they say they do the end of the day they're going to want to return on
So what happens how do you
How do you protect this thing that you built and keep doing it
I mean cuz at some point a big shoe company Nike or Adidas might say we want to buy you for 40 billion dollar
End
And then they happen
Well you know
We don't believe that there needs to be the tension
Between financial success and success for
Other
Purpose Driven aspects of our business and namely the environment for us
I think that's true for a lot of businesses that we have
We have a lot of debates inside the company because there's always a balance like
If something cost
20 times as much
Yet it's way more sustainable and maybe you can't do that
Yeah I'll take that take that choice
But on the margin you can absolutely do it once a little more expensive
It's much better for and it falls out of Northstar of of making a lower carbon footprint
Shure product
Will do it
I'm at Swedish don't we don't see that tension I think
That the other aspect is
We built this into the charter that come
So our Charter says we have a fiduciary responsibility to our shareholders
And we have a equal responsibility to the alarm
And tell if camera are no longer in the business
And some other
Some other person takes over
That they still have a responsibility to
To do what are Charter says unless they get two-thirds of our shareholders
2 hour
Devote and say that
That they don't care about the alarm
Until
We've kind of
Embedded this in the fabric of the
The company
It so people have to know when they sign on for a financing
This is part of the deal
I want to shift
You mentioned
Tell him that there was a time where you were dipping into your savings it was stressing you out back in
RV both of you feel
Like you can breathe a sigh of relief now that you're financially your on stable ground cuz your company is valued at
Billion points 6 or do you still have stress about
Financial math
Yeah it's it's never been about what we need to rest really need much money
Can be happy and live so it's never really been about
The big valuation of a company or anything
I think we have enough
Anxiety between US just
Push forward
That regardless of it while we're still in there we're still
We're still cranking and push angle
We we prepare ourselves more now than we used to paracelsus
When we started the company
Or certainly efficiently
In a better situation financially
Little less
Financial stress
But but yeah this
Did the anxiety
He still is Papa
You're always sitting there thinking of between things
You could be doing better and in anyone who started a business will know that
That feeling I'm often times people asking a question must be able to work long hours
And you like what it's not that's the wrong question
It's it's like when you start something
Just hanging beads 6in in your Brian and
You don't shut it off and it's a voice that's there
24/7 / time and
You constantly thinking about it then
How you know if I retire from Spore tonight
That the head is pressurized moments of getting out in front of
Lots of people at times in and playing sport but this isn't in some ways
Write a memo sustained pressure on its it's a very very
Cool things to do in
And I was certainly we've had some some good progress but we got a long long way to go to achieve what we want to
How much do you think this has happened use because of Locker
Xavier Skilling Ann Arbor
You know
Along the way
Weather
Bee mating Jolly roller
The difference
Characters along the way that
The pop tops Hemingway the right time
Calculate anything other than
Then lock
It was a dude a lot of different off ramps along with Jenny where if you were logical and rational
You would have stopped
For whatever reason
We
You know we keep going and
When it's
Just seemed like it was impossible
We met at the
Find a different solution in and keep on going a little button
You need that
If we had any luck
If I had any luck personally I mean I think we've been given an enormous leg out without families
And without my mom and dad and now without without wives and and
Yeah that was a
That was a loving household that
Khaled education that encouraged us to go in tight wrists and do what we wanted to do and
Not everyone has that and it's been enormously important part of the journey because I think we leaned on them
I know I have
Achievement
It's very very Italy to keep on guy
I think they're at their inextricably linked
I've always thought of lockers
Some random event happening to you
But
That happens then what you going to do with it
And I think we've
We've had the good fortune together to
Have great
Timing
Across a whole host
Thanks
Start a business in
Put up a website and seven months and reach 10000 people in in a week
But we also you know we received and capitalize on that opportunity and we worked super hard
And made some good decisions along the way to
Turn that lock into something that was really positive cuz I just I just think you can't can't really separate those those ideas
That Contracting unfortunately we've we've done a
How to get rid of both that's Joey
Who is willinger at Tim Brown founders of allbirds
The company recently rolled out a new material for the soles of their shoes
Health sweet phone made from the leftover parts of sugarcane which would otherwise
Turn away
Are there ongoing effort to make allbirds a carbon-neutral shoe
Instead of keeping the recipe of secret did actually open source it so that anyone wants to make soap
Rolls out of sugar can do it
And please do stick around because in just a moment
Hear from you about the
The things your building
But first
I quit thanks to her
How I built this
Lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
Email marketing radical Yeezy
Big thinkers can focus
Stop developing Big Ideas
Try for free at campaign monitor. Com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and your business
Unforgettable
Blackface
Stupid yearbook
Blackfishing
Israel antisemitism you got israel and colonial
You have go-go music
Versus potential
Code switch
We take it up there
The reefs
Text
Chop it up with us
Pay thanks for sticking around because
It's time now for how you built that and our story today comes to us from Kirby
Daily
From White Salmon Washington and Kirby and his family spend a lot of time
At the beach which means they have all observed one of the great wonders of marine life
You care about it all the time you hear about the
Beach umbrellas that fly through the air and land on somebody's car
Those things blow down the beach like crazy
Turn right the big gust of wind a metal stake and just
Do I have to Brown
Kirby just wasn't satisfied with the stuff that was on the market
Lots of
Inexpensive tent Stakes that you pound in with a
The hammer or Rock
There's no really good to list solution that would hold in all weather conditions and that would work in
Can sand Woodwork in Play Because Kirby is a professional woodworker
He started to Tinker around with ideas
Ask for a better ground anchor
He was inspired by one thing
In particular you've probably seen it
And it looks like a gigantic
Wine cork opener
And in case you haven't seen this giant wine cork opener
Think
Pets
Because
People use this Corkscrew thing is
Is kind of an anchor to help keep their dogs
Tethered outside
And
Because the screw threads have quite a bit more surface area
It increases the surface area between the soil and the ground anchor
A big screw like that
Could be great for anchoring all kinds of things
Shade or rain structures you know the big tarp over an outdoor kitchen when you're camping
Artists at art festivals
Their boots with all of their art
Experimenting
Prototypes
Looking for a company to make the screw
And while he's doing all this
He has this huge
Earth-shattering Epiphany the internet
Is amazing
Kirby was able to locate the perfect recycled plastic
Take the screws
And then Kirby did a Kickstarter campaign about 3 years ago
Erase $45,000 in bloom
His product was launched
The crazy thing that kept happening over and over again is when you get a phone call or an email that says
I'm going camping on Friday
I have to have these for the weekend
And so I don't know how we went from this
Product that never existed
2 something
People have to have for the weekend and they're upset if they're not going to be able to get it
Okay great story so far right
But then one morning
Got a year ago
Kirby gets
Email you know an angry email
And it said I ordered your screws
From this promotion you did on Facebook
And I haven't gotten anything yet
And I thought
I don't even know what this is we were not running a promotion on Facebook
Probably know where this is headed
Scammers were starting to get into Kirby's business
They were copying his photos and design and advertising cheap knockoffs and way undercutting his prices
So as soon as we would
Report one of these for trademark violations is how we would take them down
One would disappear and then
2 morewood pop-up
So Kirby actually did something
Unusual
He sent his own product for free
Anyone who would made the mistake
Buying a cheap knockoff
Meanwhile some of his loyal customers kept reporting The Knockout sites
Deleting comments warning new customers about the scam
We created this
International
Police force
Probably a 50 or 60 people
If it would email us everyday and say here's another one
And
The whole thing is
Started dying down
Scammers eventually went away
Kirby has now spent about a year running his company full time
With his wife and the same year as company launch 2015
His daughter
For a long time my wife and I refer to Dennis
Twins and they both had their
Frustrations in work
Really proud how both of them are growing up
That's Kirby or daily
Is product is called orange screw it
Colored Bridal
Made just under $1000000
To hear more about the company or do your previous episodes head to our podcast page how I built this. Npr.org
And of course if you want to tell us your story
Garfield
Got npr.org
Thanks so much for listening to the show this
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcast and why you're there please do give us review
Can also write to us at HIV Tia npr.org
If you want to send a tweet
It's at how I built
It was produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music
Opposed
Tiara blue
Thanks also to Julia Carnegie saunas Michigan
Grant and Jeff Rogers
David job
Intern
Garage
And you been listening
The how I built this
This
Is NPR