So back in the 1980s
Rod canion left Texas Instruments with One Vision
To create a better portable computer
He had no idea he
28-pound invention
Would not only compete but also beat out
Computing Giant
IBM
We first ran this episode
May of 2017 and there is a lot
Of great stuff in here
Enjoy
Well they take over and push everybody out
In February of 1984 IBM introduces their own portable into the
Our order stopped because before it actually was introduced they were showing it to
The dealers and customers in they just stopped arguing ours that was that was a very very life threat
We have this Factory running full speed and no place to go
From NPR how I built this
Show that innovators entrepreneurs idealists the stories behind the movement
They show a personal computer startup compact Sig on the biggest computer company in
The world and one
If you have a PC at home or at work and
Some software like
Word or TurboTax
It doesn't really matter if you have a Dell or an HP or Toshiba because if it's a PC
It will run PC software and that makes perfect sense right
Believe it or not in the 1980s in the early days of personal computers
That is not how it works
If your computer was say in IBM
Well you needed software written for and IBM
And IBM was the biggest
Player
Star
Some people thought that IBM would eventually Crush all the competition and become the only
PC maker
Wasn't your typical Restless entrepreneurial guy infected he had a good and stable job at 10
Instruments as an electrical engineer and he was pretty happy there
One day in 1981 his managers assigned him to work on a new project and it was something
Believe would not work
And he started to get frustrated
Basically was being told to go spend the next two years of my life being my head against the wall
And end up in failure
So at the moment
Rod started to talk to to close colleagues at Texas Instruments Jim Harris and Bill mirto and
Basically said maybe we should leave
We met
And talked about how we're going to go start a company
And there a lot of startup companies in California in Silicon Valley
One of the first things we realize is she these guys are having fun they're making a ton of money in
They're not any smarter than we are they just
They're just out doing it themselves
There's also this awareness that something really big is going on in that personal computer Market when I be
Diameter the market in August of 1981
We realized that
That market
It was going to explode
And then what happened is fall comdex came along
We went out to the
Conference since all of the companies and all of the things going on it which is
That did it we went back to Houston and talked about
We're going to miss this if we don't get going so
Jim Harrison I turn in a resignation
Right away
Amaretto
Waited because
His wife was about to deliver their first child
And you have family to write
How many kids did you have
What are you nervous at all about just quitting without any income coming in I mean
Were you worried at all by doing that
You know I don't remember being worried about it
The three of us none of us had any money to invest so what we did was we saved up
Money and the idea was
We'll give ourselves a runway length
Civ 6 months
Come up with an idea and go get funding
And I think
This is an adventure
Let's go see what we can do
So so what did the three of you serve land on the idea that
Eventually turned into combat
Well the the idea came to me
Actually one morning
Strange how you remember those pivotal point in your life but
I was thinking about the idea for a portable computer there were
A number of them that existed at the time
Probably
Just guess
15 or 20
Well most people
Remember the Osborn
It was made out of
Cheap molding and sort of
Strung together
It had a 5 inch diameter screen
I had two floppies but you could have mediately see some ways to make it a lot better in a week we decided we could do a 9-inch
Screen in about the same size box
Well that seems small turns out it's about the same size is
What the
Original iPad screen is
And we could make it rugged so that when you carried it it was
Not damaged
But
Not worth really spending the time on unless we could get some software that already existed
Because
I had learned that the key software like spreadsheets and word processors in and others
Every different brand of computer had to have its own version of the popular software program
So I said well what if we could make
This great portable run software that already exists
I knew that the IBM PC
Was relatively unprotected it would be a
A challenge but it could be reverse-engineered
Legally
And we could make our computer
Run the same software
And that was the idea that the send a chill down my spine wow
What's wrong with this idea there's there's got to be something wrong with it it's too good to be just hanging around here
At what point did you say okay we have an idea let's go look for money
So I called up Jim Harris and then later got bilmar to involved and we
Thought about it talked about it and decided you know that that would be a great product if we can do that
Let's put together the business plan and so that was the next thing we did I mean
It was very quick from the 9th of January
To when the idea came up to the 22nd of January when we met with the venture capital
We basically
Put together I am a very short for page business plan and prepare to meet and discuss it
And what did they say when they die
Well
They were coming into town for another meeting and we
But this business plan in front of a man
Begin to describe it
And
Then they started
Talking to each other either one of them said yeah I had this idea you know like three months ago
And I said well
If you think it's such a good idea why aren't you more excited about it and I said well
Look
We like the idea we like you guys
But we're new in this
Industry
So what you need to do is we need to send you out to Silicon Valley and go meet with Kleiner Perkins
Enough
They are the best then we will
So we
We basically flew out to
To Silicon Valley and we went in to meet with
With Jon Dore
And we spent a good morning probably 3 or 4 hours
Being
Question
And
Turn off
About a week later
We got a call that they were willing to invest and
So
It was a go
Okay so it's 1982 I guess and and you've gotten your investors and in what you do
Get to work building a prototype
Well the first thing we do is
Begin hiring people
How's the three of us
We're sort of
The head of each area but we need
Engineers mainly to go figure out how to reverse engineer in huh
Designer things how so we hired three engineers
And importantly they basically had to build something
Pretty similar to tune IBM PC
Except pretty similar didn't cut it and you had to be exactly the same in order to run the software
From an internal temp
And so they are
They came to Workforce right away
And again
First reverse engineering product
And then designing our own
But were you convinced that you guys were going to succeed
You know it never crossed my mind that we wouldn't
Succeed and as I look back now I think
Well that was such a long shot
You know our expectations were very low
What is exceed mean if it didn't mean become the industry leader it didn't even mean become one of the leading couple
Is it may build a company that doesn't go out of business
That has a product
That salsa a real need
And
You don't lose money on
We felt like we know how to do that
How long does it take
For you from that point in
I guess the first or the other early part of
Me too
Until you had a working prototype
So we
Start the company February 16th
And from March
Until
Early June
We had our first prototype ready
The deadline was determined by the national computer conference
What you just happened to be held in Houston that you're the only time I think it was over in Houston
To show to
Potential dealers
Digital computer store owners who would sell it
Tube magazine
Writers who would write about it when it came out
An app to get feedback
And others basically to find out what people thought about this product
So you come up with this prototype
And at that point
Where are you even manufacturing these
These computers
We built
Factory
Inside a leased building
North Houston
We heard manufacturing people Lake
Put up reproduction Lionheart people trying them on how to build it and
Began to build
The product
And we had a plan
That basically allowed us to build
Probably I'm going to say 20 25000
Computers
By the end of 83 we didn't begin actually turning out
Finished units until January of 80
Just to be clear when you talk about a portable computer in 1980
You're talking about a
A machine that way
What's the way
28 lb
This is not even hand luggage on an airplane
Well we did use it as hand luggage but
Skepticism about that
Nelly that you had to plug in Ethernet
People began to call them
Transportable computers which is more accurate
It was also very rugged
One of our key engineering talents
What's the building
So that it
When you dropped it
Survive
And of course your portable would run any software
Written for deeply IBM
And another competition did that right
That's right
And basically
Laid in 82 as we had our first prototypes
Bill murto and then I joining because there were a lot of computer stores around the country
We would go out and make an appointment and go in and and show
The computer store on our product
And
Show them the computer they like the way it looked and when we
Show them how it works it was very nice
Screen was nice
But when we told him okay just pick up any of the IBM
Software
Off-the-shelf tennis shrink wrap box
And put it in the computer and see if it runs and when they did that and it ran
Their eyes
Lit up
They got excited I thought about it a minute and they wanted to order some right there
Let me say something like okay I need five of these next week or I've got it I'll give you an order for 25 if you can ship them
In the next month
Bill and I got back to Houston and compare notes
It was like women every one of these theater said the same thing
What we just stumbled onto is this
Pent-up demand
For portable version of the IBM PC
It seems solid but we've never thought of our product that way
This is a portable computer if it's a niche
And you have software because it runs all the IBM software
But if you just step back and turn that over and say
Everybody out there has an IBM PC in their office
And what they need every one of them needs one or more of is
A portable version of it
And we happen to have that product
People were wanting to take
Leasing home for the weekend or even overnight 2
To finish their work they wanted to take them out to customers
The show them
Their work and soul
It was a much bigger
Market than anybody anticipated wants
We had all the ingredients together
Weren't weren't you worried in 1982 when you are going to dealers and showing them your product that
And saying hey you know this is basically
This could do everything and IBM could do
Except
It's portable World War shoot you guys worried that IBM would come after you
No because we hadn't broken any laws
Yeah we did reverse-engineer the wrong following
Advice from top-notch intellectual property lawyer so we were very careful around that
The product was not
Protected by patents and any other way they unfollowed more or less
The General Industry Direction and so
Building a computer that was
Similar or close to it was not a problem at all the fact that we
Took the time to figure out exactly how there's made the software work
And made ours do the same thing it was not illegal
It sounds like you guys really launched this in a stealth way that IBM probably didn't even
Care about you thought you were just probably just above a flyspeck of a company
That was making this product and when you launched it in 1983
I don't even
Even know who you were
Oh no no they had no idea and nor did they care I mean even after we began to the store to get some positive
Results and getting into stores remember we were portable they didn't have a portal so initially
Play it was very easy for them to ignore us because we were truly
Fly
In that first year 1983
How did the company do we sold 111 million dollars worth of Compaq computers
Wow
Expanding like crazy at the beginning of that year you just had
A few hundred maybe like blasting a hundred people working there
We had about
About a hundred people at the end of the fur
It's about right and about 600 by the end of 83 so you can imagine
How much hiring we were doing
And expanding and
Now this was not a one thing at a time this is multitasking
Bringing on very competent people in every area so they could
Here's what needs to be done and go get it
How how much were you selling that
First portable computer for
It was it listed for 2995 for a single floppy
Unbelievable
And who your customers was it businesses was it individuals
It was mostly businesses
But
A surprising number of individuals
Could see the value in it
And if their company wasn't buying it for them then they would do
They would buy it for themselves
Thousand bucks for this computer in tens of thousands
This point
IBM is starting to notice
Oh absolutely
Absolutely
Hey
You know in February of 1984 IBM introduces their own portable into the market now
Our order stop because before it actually was introduced
They were showing it to dealers and customers head
They just stopped ordering hours
Market they take over and push everybody out
So we had his Factory running full speed
And no place to go
That was that was a
Very
Very life-threatening
So you guys are freaking out
We're freaking out the industry speaking out it's like they're ghost compact you know they're there
They had a good run but it's over when we come
I'm back at ride Canyon made sure that it wasn't yet over stay with this guy Raz
How I built this
NPR
Support also comes from Fidelity invest
As a Fidelity Wealth Management
You get a dedicated advisor
To help grow and protect your wealth
Find ways to minimize the impact of tax
And make clear recommendations for your full Financial
Learn more at fidelity.com
Fidelity brokerage Services LLC
Support also comes from Goldman Sachs
Four insights from leading thinkers at Goldman Sachs
Text Honda state of Mark
Industries and the global economy
Listen to there podcast exchanges at Goldman Sachs you'll hear a range of topics discussed
From the tech IPO land
The China's economic Outlook
And much more
That exchanges at Goldman Sachs available on Apple podcast
Spotify
Stitcher SoundCloud
And Google Play and it gs.com podcast
This message comes from NPR sponsor
Capital One
Is reimagining banking
I offering accounts with no fees or minimums that can be opened from anywhere
In 5 minutes
Capital One
What's in your wallet
Capital One na
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Gyros
Really good first year of sales for Rod Canyon and come back
But to put it in perspective
Compact sold about
53000 computers
And that same year
IBM
They sold
Computers
And so in 1984 when IBM decided
Compete with compact Head to Head
Everyone knew it was a major threat
So tried call together the management team for an emergency meeting
You know what do we think we ought to do well the manufacturing of people said
We got a lot of temporary people
We were hiring so fast they came on as Temporaries initially in
And we can lay all them off immediately and we can really cut back production
Cut backer cost
And it was It was a
I have to say a very dire
Down to the meeting everybody was like you know it's all over
Took all that in and
Add it all up and I realized
You know if we're going to come out of this
With a happy ending
There's only one way that's going to occur and that is
Let's assume for a minute that IBM's product is not better than ours
That maybe it's a limited
Supply and the Dealer's once they see it
Begin to order our product again
We need to have product available to fill those orders
So
Here's what we're going to do we're going to keep building these things were going to store them and wait for the artist to come
At the August never come
Yeah we're in deep trouble but you know what we're in deep trouble anyway if they order
That was the plan
I'm not sure everybody was
I'm bored with it but that's what we went off and did
Winner of storing these things in the in the trailers
Tractor trailers 18-wheelers back
Yeah and parking them in our garage
Parking lot
When that failed up
Borrowed space and Friends parking lots around the the town and Buy Mid
February we had about 20 of these trailers full of computer sitting around Houston
So what happened how did you survive
Well
What happened is IBM introduces the product
The kick the tires
It's announced that it is unlimited
Supply for a while
It was not a better product when the bad product it just wasn't better
And so just as we had hoped almost the best possible situation is the orders came in and we had the computer stuff
It's like they had been holding them back and so not only were they arguing isn't normal right they were sending all the orders that they had been holding
Everything fell into place just at the right time and then we took advantage of
So what explains
What explains the fact that they didn't Crush you
I mean it it sounds to me like it was one of
Two things it was either
Total luck
Or it was that the IBM portable computer just wasn't that good or maybe
Both
Well anyway you look at it
Good luck I mean
It was a lot of luck involved but what happened is
We have had a year
To build great relationships
With the dealers
The dealers actually liked having somebody
Other than IBM
Because I be almost the
Get on the 500 pound gorilla
Then I knew it
In any case
We continue to sell like crazy and outsold the IBM portable
Throughout the year I think by the end of the year we were out selling it
7 or 8 to 1
Edgar 84
By the end of 84
And
We tripled to 329 million in our second
So by your second year you
Tripled
Sales
What was the first time you remember
Compact becoming part of lyca of the mainstream conversation in america
Well
Depends on
How big do mainstream is I think by the end of 83 everybody in the industry knew about Compact and we'll sort of
Marveling at what was going on here
You know this idea that
People can use all the same for referrals
All the same things that were designed and built to run in the IBM PC with it with software or Hardware would work on our computer
IBM may be underestimated as they didn't really study what it made our products
Successful they could have easily put us out of business if they come out with a a real comprable product
Yeah and it wasn't once you guys show that you
Could build an IBM clone
A lot of other companies realized it was possible to do the same thing right
That's right
And the fact that we took off and set sales records main everybody else
Did including by the way the
The big guys h p t i
Deck all
Violate followed suit but by then we had
Really establish ourselves in the market in
You know the thing that
Tookus
From 600 million and 80
6 to 1.2 billion in sales in 87
We came out with our own desktop which was essentially three times faster than IBM's desktop for about the same price and
Begin to establish
Ourselves is not only the portable company
But also the high-performance company
IBM try to kill off all the Clones when when they released the PS2 in in 1887
Was designed so it could not be cloned right
Yeah
That's right
That was an attempt
To take this thing that has gotten out of control mainly due to Compaq
And bring it back under IBM's control
So IBM comes out with their new architecture and claims that this is the way to go
That that all architecture has run its course
It's going to run out of gas very soon and so you don't want to follow it to the end you want to get on this new horse
And IBM has it
And so let's go
And
That's where IBM's
Marketing
Strategy got them in trouble
Because
This thing not only didn't run all the software it didn't run any of the softer
IBM's new computer did not run IBM's own software
It didn't
Now they came out with new IBM soft
So if you wanted to buy this new product
Youku
Buy all new peripherals and all new software
And they would claim that it would outperform anything else in the market
So at the time the right and you're saying that
Emily companies many companies already had
PCS and software IBM was saying
Buy the Snoopy s2o and you're also going to have to invest in new software
You make it sound crazy I told them it was normal that's the way the industry had always worked and they they still hadn't bought into this industry
Standard idea
People
Believing that
An understanding that it was important to be able to run
Your old software on a new computer
It never happened before
Compact Pioneer MN
They wanted to get rid of it as quick as they could
Was there a moment where you were worried that that actually would succeed
Oh yeah
Never
Question
They had a good chance
To succeed now what kept us going and what
I guess gave us
Confidence that we had a pretty good chance was
We outperformed to IBM's best products
Every step of the way
Until there was a significant part of the industry that looked at the IBM's claims
Little magazines
Afraid to write
Compaq outperformed cibm by
50 to 100%
In spite of it being a BM we were holding onto a pretty
Solid position in the market
Because
Ours was always higher-performing
It seems like
At any juncture
In your first several years
IBM have they just done
Something a little bit smarter strategically
Could have crushed you
There's no doubt IBM could have crushed us a number of different ways
And at that point in time
I can ride so it's it's
5 Years From the time you launched to to the time you're doing a billion dollars and Randy Wright
That's right
How to change your life your own personal life changes all of a sudden you like
I'm assuming you're you become, rich guy
Yeah it'll certainly compared to where I had been I was rich but then again we
We knew that that was a
A fragile part of it
I did get a divorce in 1980
I know it was
Sad part of of what happens in the
The net Arabic
I'm sure it had something to do with it
The stress associated with
All the work
The time I spent at work
So in 1987
Going through divorce
A simple divorce is hard
And then IBM comes out with his new computer designed to basically
Put you guys out of business
How did you deal with it how did you cope with all that happening
You looking back on it I would say it's probably denial
Yeah it's pretty effective tools
Not letting things
Impact you as much as they might in and sort of other situations is
Something
You have to do there I mean
I felt like I was
Learning as I went and I was doing a good job
There was personal turmoil
If you want to throw up another layer on top of that
RadioShack tried to buy us in late 86 in early 87
So that was going on at
Same time all this was half
So you were just
Should your personal life you were just kind of
You compartmentalize that you were you just had to
Put that in a box
Focus on the stuff
And not let that
Depress you
Yeah no
I've got three kids and they're getting to be
Teenagers in
There's little league and there's all of that in and I'm
Trying very hard to get away at the right time you'll see a school play
That's where most of the stress came from trying to do it all
If you can just cut off part of it and say I'm not going to worry about that it would be one thing
But trying to do it all in and not drop any balls
That was pretty stressful
Where you going home
Leo eating like takeout Chinese food I mean done with your day
Crashing usually yell no I
See pictures now
Of media
During a fast food minimum McDonald's bag or a Wendy's bag
How you just ate when you cut that was sort of secondary
Getting everybody
You taking care of getting the meetings done getting
Decisions made
You can look at my role as making decisions
Yeah I was making all the decisions but all of the cute ones I had to be involved
And they're always a lot
I guess about
Sleep what ten years after you guys lunch compact
You drafted to the board of directors
Did they fire you
Almost exactly 10 years later
Why what was going on
Well
There's several levels of
Looking at the Dynamics there that on the surface it's a matter of disagreement over how fast
Move into the lower-cost arena
Like-like lower-cost PCS
Yes
The chairman of the company Ben Rosen
Thought we ought to move very quickly and so quickly that went back we got to go buy a product from
The Taiwanese or Japanese or
Korean
Supplier
And my argument was looked It's Not What It Seems
We can get the market as fast as
Anybody
With our own design
And I think at the board meeting
The board decided to replace me with the number two guy with x
Pfeiffer
Patachou
How'd you get that news
Well we had a board meeting were
Been proposed that idea and I left the room and they
Deliberated it for quite a while and then made the decision to make
The change
But it was clear that was the direction they were going on I knew that's what it
I was going to be
I was also somewhat burnout and I was
Strange mindset
I kind of wanted to get out of that that pressure it was
It took me a while to really look back and understand that I was
A big part of the problem of why it ended up going down that path and I and I regret that
But it is what it happened and I guess under the stress I was under and kind of
Gotten into this Frame of Mind where I need to get away
The
Disagreement over the low cost
Speed to Market
Was just the catalyst
Allowed it to happen
Almost
Guided it to the point where I
It's going to be far
So when you were at me this is the company that you found it
That you built
Yes
And then you were
Removed from that, I think a lot of people hearing that would say God that sounds like such an injustice
Cuz it's your idea
You created it it was your sweat and then it was taken away from you
Brazil from your perspective
That was fine you you weren't kind of
Your time
What's over there
Helsby clear
Where are you
Fortune 500
Corporation
In a world leader in a big industry
And just because you started the company doesn't give you any right
To continue to run the company
Are the dates to be run by somebody that can make
Good decisions and can manage
That complex in operation
Which I think I was doing
Okay or maybe even
Very well up to that point
What time so that's
I don't see that as the reason
That I needed to leave I think it had more to do with
My friend of mine and sort of a burned-out
Situation
You were in your mid-forties at that point
Soap so pretty
Pretty young guy
Accomplished a lot
Did you walk out of the company with
Fino financially secure for you
Set for life of that one
Yes absolutely
No course
Continue my life
Actually the whole life became a much less stressful and
Then I got involved in investing in and some startups and early-stage companies and try to help them succeed
Not all of them dead
But then
If I leave all to wear I really just like helping entrepreneur start their company in
Try to help them avoid a lot of mistakes
Do companies make
Compaq it was such a Powerhouse in the 80s
Is a Fortune 500 company
Does billion dollars in Revenue within 5 years
And then you think about all of the companies that that it was associated with her that way
Competed against
Do you know
Apple IBM
Dell
Microsoft
Texas
All of those companies still exist
And compact doesn't
Existing Wireless
Folded into HP in
That brand is no longer
Here
In anyway is that a cautionary tale for some of these powerhouses we see today like Snapchat or Uber
Or Facebook I can't even imagine not existing
You know it really is that's certainly something I
Didn't Envision when I left I guess I just wasn't thinking that far down the road
Yeah of course you never know the future
The decision to merge with HP was a financial decision
But the end result of the way it happened is it compact no longer exists and that is sad because
It's got such a great
History and played such a key role in actually forming the way the world works
And yet
Most people you run into on the street
I've never heard of
Calpak
Crazy annie's
It is crazy yes it's sad but
It's also life
If you know that's that's a
We started out to build a company that would last
And I think that's the case with ain't going to feel like
Dell or Microsoft
Apple
The leaders of those companies maintain enough control
To make sure that
It never
Got into the hands of somebody that looked at it just
Purely from a financial standpoint
If I had been there
If I'd been leaving the company
We would never have sold
We would have
Figured out a way to
To solve the problem
How much of your of your success at compact was because of
Just your hard work and and and smarts and the hard work of Jim and Bill or
And how much would a wizard
Good luck
If you would ask me that in
The 80s
Play the ladies
I would probably have said it was
90%
Intelligence
And inside and
Work
And 10% luck
But to tell you how perspective changes with time I would say today it was the other way around
We did a lot of good things we came up with a good idea
But if you look back at any of the things that could have gone wrong
And what if
Either slows down or stopped us
I mean there's an endless list of those
So the fact that
Yeah okay we dealt with those issues as they came along but the fact that there was a successful path even available
Is pretty
Pretty doggone lucky rad Canyon founded Compaq computers
With Phil mirto and Jim Harris in 1982
Brad still lives in Houston where he mainly invests in other people startups
The story of compact David and Goliath struggle against IBM was the subject of a very
Cool documentary
It's called silicon Cowboys what kind of computer do you use today are you a MacBook Air
IPhone you started the PC Revolution
And please do stick around because in just a moment we're going to hear from you about the things your building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsor
American Express
You want to build your business
They can help build your business
With financing solutions for
Eligible business customers
Powerful backing of American Express
Don't do business without it
Terms apply
Americanexpress.com
Slash business
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's
Time now for how you built that and today we're updating a story we ran about a year ago my name is Dan
Nicolazzi I live in Germantown Wisconsin and about 16 years ago in college
She love to knit scarves for her friends to the point where they start
Search Kpop Ranch out of a hat made it and I finished
I said I thought and it looked at it and there was a
Big weird hole in it and I thought I made a mistake I tossed It On The Ground really disappointed
Good thing that when she did that her dad happened to be in the room my dad selling there
Are you sad will put you through that
Curly massive hair on top of Danica's head so just for fun she put her hair through the hole in the house
I don't know who said it but remember kind of a collaboratively the room looking
That looks good
So Danica started to wear the hat with her ponytail
Bump sticking out of it wherever she went on campus are traveling around the country people would say the same
Main thing
Where to get your hat I like your hat without realizing it
Danica had solved a problem for people with long hair because
If you got a ponytail it's uncomfortable to pull a knit hat over it
Anakin what kind of silly to you know this weird bulge on top of your head so after Danica got out of car
And after she got a full-time job in the chemical industry
She continued to knit hats with the Spurs
Strategically placed holes in them
And then she would sell them online
Where I
Thought that it might
Stay where I was keeping a job
Forever and ever and I was actually kind of thing going back and getting PhD in
Chemistry
That's not what happened like I get to work and I think
I could maybe be making
Just about you know what I'm making here if I made more hat and right around this time
To notice there was competition other people were making hats for ponytails
Sochi innovated
She made multiple opening
To accommodate different hairdos
And she even figured out how to hide those openings so you could wear the hat like any other hat when he wanted to
And all the knitting took a lot of time so Danica started to
Get some help I start getting a lot of emails
Afro manufacturers in China what's on my website saying hey we can make these for you
All right I don't have a lot of other options here
I'm going to try that
So okay she found a few people in China who could have missed the hats they were actually a lot of things made
By people in their home
But they were all turned out to be different sizes and a little bit different shaped
And some of that was was just the nature of handmade but
They couldn't go on
Danica realized she couldn't grow her business by knitting the hats by hand
Asking a lot of different Engineers she found one guy in New Jersey
To design her a knitting machine that would put holes in the Hat
It can make
I had every 18 minutes
And I have to stop toilet about every 6 to 7 hours
And so I can get about
Pat and a day
Tax company is called
Peekaboo ponytail hats since we last spoke with her
Danica has been thinking about marketing peekaboo hats in countries like New Zealand in Australia where is winter
From June to August so she can keep selling her hats your round and she's working on 5 News
Design if you want to find out more about Danica lazy or your previous episodes head to our podcast page
How I built this. Npr.org of course if you want to tell us
Your story
Go to build
Npr.org
I think so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us at Hib tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet is at how I built this
I sure was pretty sweet by Casey Herman with music composed by routine Arab Louis
Thanks also to Julia Kearney JC Howard newer coetzee Neva Grant
Melissa great sanaz meshkinpour and Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Slim I'm guy Roz and you've been listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand custom
With mobile-friendly email temp
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaign monitor. Com