Support for this podcast
In the following message
Did come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for
We're seriously every
Stop by a Madewell
Or go to Madewell.
Define your
Perfect pear
Just before we start the show a bit
Of news
Last year
After a year of doing live shows
We decided we wanted
Deeper experience with you with
Our community
So we decided to Launch
A full day how I built
The Summit
It was so amazing and fun that we're doing it again this year
This time we're doing it over two days
It's happening
October 22nd
XXIII
In San Francisco
With support from American
Express
And this year we are doubling down on our main stage speaker
Able to hear from and
Probably even meet some of the greatest living Founders and entrepreneurs in the world
Including Sara Blakely Spanx
Stewart Butterfield
Slack Kevin Systrom and Mike Krieger of Instagram Tariq
Breed of Edible Arrangements
David neeleman of JetBlue Troy Carter who managed
Gaga
Marcia Kilgore of bliss Jen Rubio of away and many others
Including special surprises
And on top of that
Will have doesn't
Side session
Experts
Special guests on everything from them Nuts and Bolts
Starting and
Scaling your business
Two ways of
I'm thinking in a more Innovative in
Creative way
The food is great the coffee is great the party is super fun
Is one of the best
Investments
You can make in your own professional and personal development
And most importantly
You will meet people who will become lifelong friends and contacts
Please join us in San Francisco October 22nd
23rd
At yerba buena Center for the Arts
To find out more tickets including early bird pricing available
Just a few more weeks
Go to Summit. Npr.org
So you probably heard of or maybe even ordered
Zappos
And if you've heard was found
Then you'll know that
His Mantra is that Zappos is a customer service company
It happens
To sell shoes
If you haven't heard this episode of
Before
The Tony doesn't really care about
Shoes
Two pairs
He's a huge introvert
Anything some self is a very
Weird guy
And also he lives in an Airstream trailer
In all these factors
A part of his very quiet
Very quirky personality
Explain Zappos unorthodox
Management style
This is a great episode and it's
First air
January 8th
Enjoy
As Zappos was growing
It was also losing my money and we also need my money for
Inventory and so all of this was happening at a bad time in terms of the
Dot-com crash back in 2000 so is pretty much impossible to raise money from anyone you could not get
Investment
Even if someone wanted to invest in an internet company the last thing they wanted
Online shoe company
No one would ever buy shoes online
NPR how I built this a show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist
Stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Roz and how old school mail-order catalogs inspired Tony hsieh to build
One of the world's biggest online shoe retailers
You know it
Zappos
Billions
You only have
Four pairs
Is that the rice
Yeah roughly Maybe
If you are now
But what kind of shoes you wearing now
Right now I'm wearing black ASICS
I have a pair of
I'm actually not talking about shoes at all
Investment customer service and Company
Talk forever about
Those two things but I can't
Choose okay so as you just heard one of the most successful
Shoe salesman in the world
I care about you
And also
He's really quiet
Nice app
Write definitely
How do you cope with a new computer company
When you got to talk about the people Inspire them like how do you find the
Energy to do that
I'm probably different from a lot of
Goodwill CEOs where
Analogy of a greenhouse where maybe I
Company
Paseo
Ibiza
Strongest
Tallest
Most charismatic plant that all the other
Strive to
One Day become Maybe
And for me I really
Taking my role
As more about being the
Architect of the greenhouse and then
The other pens inside will flourish and thrive on their own and so from a I guess
Comfy prospective buyer charges
With people that are just naturally more extroverted and a little bit
We're too because I heard that when you apply to Zappos
Test how weird you are
I believe so yeah I think our application
Pause button
As far as I know.
Question still there
So on a scale of 1 to 10 how weird are you
I would say maybe in
There you have it
Tony Chabot the guy who built this huge company with more than a thousand employees doesn't really like shoes
Is he's an 8 on the weird scale and an introvert and people who study companies and
Company culture come from all over the world
2 Zappos to 2/10 quarters in Las Vegas to see how it operates
Because as many of you know at Zappos
There are no typical bosses employees have a lot of autonomy to make decisions
But at the same time
About customer service
As you will hear even think of itself as a shoe company
Basically
Is a company that sells good customer service
In the story of how Tony got there
Begins as these stories often do
In childhood
Asian-American parents
Practicing piano and violin and other instruments and
During the Summers for example practice 1 hour
1 hour violin and
And this is as a kid summer vacation and so
I would actually
Get up super early
And
I would actually just
Play back a recording of myself
Violin
What you'd play Eric
Recording of you practicing the violin to give your parenting impression that you were
Actually practicing the violin
Right so because they were
Sleeping but they get here so
So that was my way around that it's like a Ferris Bueller movie
And strangely
Every week when I went to piano lessons or violin
And so the teachers I understand why
So anyway Tony eventually goes off
College
Graduates
In the mid-1990s
And it's not like he goes right into starting Zappos
That first
He goes to work for Oracle as a low-level program
I wasn't there for very long I think I was there for
For five months and it's just straight out of college and
The actual work I was assigned to do was
Pretty boring and this is right about when
The internet
Is the World Wide Web
Started
I remember
Didn't even really exist I don't think the summer before or at least two summers before
And at the time these web design and hosting
These were popping up left and right and so
Sunday
Decided to do that on the side while we were both our day jobs were at Oracle but during lunch breaks in at night
Would go
Start selling
Designing websites for
Local small businesses
Yeah and then we had this idea for
I at the time
Advertising online
Very very very
Today if you go to
Any website
She adds all over the place but
Back in the day if you went to a website and it had an advertisement on it
Was actually kind of a badge of honor because only the really big
Websites
Yahoo
Have advertising customers wait till you guys were trying to build it like a web-based ad sales company
Ashley's
Intend to start
More of those things we were bored in
Let's try this and see what happens and so we literally just
Contacted you a hundred random websites.
Interesting
Maven contact
Reba
Back then people
Dresses on the website
Like what Master El Rio
What was your pitch when you email them
Basically that we're trying this thing out and
You just
This little piece of code into the your website banners will start showing up
You send us your banner and
Make sure that it's showing up on other websites doing the same thing
We weren't really trying to
Pet show asb
Would you in this experiment you want to
Participate
Okay so just so I understand you you basically got like a lot of small websites to join kind of a network and then
Agree to run ads on their site
And you were like the middle that right you sold those spaces on website
Companies that want to advertise
Yeah
Wow
Friendly Goods
Hanover
Two and a half years we end up going to come pick me up which was called link Exchange
It's about a hundred or so people
And then
Apparently ended up selling the company to Microsoft
+ 90
5 million
This is not how this narrative is supposed to go
I mean you are so young
3 years after you graduate from college so
I totally overwhelming that that that that happened so quick
The whole thing definitely seem very surreal but
At the same time
What a lot of people don't know is the real reason why we ended up selling the company
And
The real reason was
Because
Company culture
Dragon completely downhill and
I myself try to getting out of bed in the morning
Go to my own comfy
Which is kind of a weird feeling
Because when I was
Just five or ten and we were all friends
A lot of fun we were
Typical.com startup
Back and we were sleeping under desk that no idea
Weekly was
Work around the clock but it is
Really exciting in
Fun drawing and as we started
Highmark
People we eventually ran out of
Either friends or
Friends of friends in
So how to do it
How to do interviews and so on in
Not everyone we hired was good for
Culture and by the time we got 200 people
It wasn't anyone's fault
Death by a thousand
Does Cassandra paper cuts and
That's really what led to the sale
Taupe Subway what do you just like
Cashed out and moved on
Well in Silicon Valley
Usually there's a four-year
Soon as a 4 year vesting for
Your stocking I'd only been there for a 2 and 1/2 years
So
Really had to stay for another
Going to have after Microsoft
Acquire.
In order to get the
Full amount of
What the deal was
But I ended up at
You just walk away from
That way
I guess I could have
Usually just sat around for
For your nap
But I was
Buddy 2
Move on to the next
So just to be clear you you could have made
Much more money if you had stayed for
Another year-and-a-half
You walked away because
Cuz you were miserable
Yeah I think I just started going down
The past of just trying to make sure that I'm
Intrude myself and
Doing things
Because
It's what I want to do versus what is
Maybe
Status symbol
Or
What Society
Expects me to do
I ain't the one resource that we all
We have the same
Time
10 yd waste
Okay so fair enough
You part ways with link Exchange
An Endeavor that you open an incubator like where you invested in other companies
Adventure frogs
And we race about 27 million roughly half of that was
My money and then the other half was from
Other early
Link exchange employees
Add money from the acquisition
And for me when I first got started in that my thinking was so this will be lots of fun
Oceans of lots of different Founders in different internet company
But what I realized was that for me
Actually found that investing was pretty
Boring and I felt like I was sitting on the sidelines all the time and I really miss being part of
Building something on your radar
Almost actually
Didn't get on our radar because I remember getting a voicemail
From
Founders apus
He said he had this idea for selling shoes online and we were getting random
Pictures
Everyday and so
It seemed like maybe
Custard powder bad
Gladius who's going to actually
Try on shoes without seeing them in in person
And
Right before hitting the delete button on on the phone at Heathrow
That made us change your mind one was that Footwear
At the time was
40 billion dollar a year industry in the US
And I'm not into shoes at all so that was
News to me
And then the other interesting fact was that
At the time
Mail-order catalogs with paper
Allies
That was actually the fastest growing segment of the Footwear industry in the US and
That represented 5% so 2 billion dollars a year
And growing
And if there's clear proof that
People are going to
Remotely
Try on shoes
And so in our minds
Internet is going to be
Much bigger than just paper
Order catalogs and so
That's what made us ultimately decide to invest
Okay so when
When the founder of Zappos next
What's windburn
For the first time what
Motion Pro
He just seemed like a pretty casual guide
We listen just said
MCU
Next don't have any Footwear background
On base if you can find a shoe guy
Turn that that there's a shoe guy name
Fred Mosley
Who was working at Nordstrom at the time and
He told Nick
I'll join in
You find an investor and so
Are we on
Smelly friends
The company and
Working with Fred
Wow so so at what point did you realize that
You know you want to be more than just
The passive investor that you wanted to be involved in the company
There wasn't really any one moment in time it was more
We were also running an incubator at the time and Zappos ended up
Moving in and
On the same building and so we just
Started being able to help them or in
Slowly
Just evolve but it it was gradual thing it wasn't like
One day
Wasn't really helping
Next day it was
Like a time when people are still kind of
Freaked out about using credit cards online right so
In in the first year of that company where you actually selling shoes
Yeah I mean
So in order to test out the hole
Concept for real
Nick with Ashley
Just got down to the local shoe store
Take pictures of all the shoes that were on the wall and then put it on the website and if someone bought something then go down to the local shoe store
Buy the shoe event and ship it
Obviously
Not making money from each of those but it was really
Really cheap and easy way to
Test the actual
Demand
So that's how you would get
User gauge what
Your mom finally just whether they buy shoes online at all
And over time we've learned what brands they were interested in and then eventually
Got to the point where
We wanted to make money and so
Burning through cash
Respond to how are you finding the
So after the link exchange sale
Set the money aside
For investing and also
Bought a bunch of
Apartments or Lofts that were in that same building
In San Francisco
Yeah this is right in San Francisco
And I'm basically
As Zappos
Growing
It was also losing my money and we also need more money for inventory and so
I ended up one by one selling off the apartments in
Sound like when in Monopoly when you you buy hotel or houses and then you have to sell them
Lose money on the sale
That's basically what would her
So how many permits do you have to sell
All of them eventually really believe this thing was going to work
Yeah well so all this was happening at a bad time in terms of the.com Crash back in
Mm psoas
Pretty much impossible
Raise money from anyone
And there was also 911
And
War in
Basically it's just
Abandoned
Economic environment and especially
Recommend
As investment
No and also the huge companies like
Pets.com never eCommerce dead
We're kind of imploding at the time and so
Even if
Someone wanted to invest in
Internet company the last thing they wanted to do was invested
Online shoe company
No one would ever buy shoes online
When we come back in the moment
The secret sauce that helped
Zappos
Blow up
And a hint
It had nothing to do
Which shoes
Gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
Thanks to one of our sponsors who helps make this podcast possible
Are 2019 how I built this
Lead sponsor
Campaign monitor
A campaign monitor
They took email marketing and made it radically easy
So the big thinkers to focus on
What they do best
Developing Big Ideas
Professionally cracked at templates
Turn key design
He campaigns
Results
Best part
Drag-and-drop editor gets
The job done in
Airtime
Try for free
Campaign monitor. Com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and business
Forgettable
Thanks also to ZipRecruiter
Hiring used to be hard
Multiple job site stack
Resumes
Today hiring can be easy
Only have to go to one place to
To get it done
ZipRecruiter
ZipRecruiter sent your jobs over 100 of the web
Leaving job board
Been ZipRecruiter scams thousands of resumes
Find people with the right experience
Invite them to apply to your job
Try it for free at ziprecruiter.com built
We're back with a new season of Russian
Yeah this time we are following people who break
The rules part of the business
In my opinion the best revenge against Isis
Mitsubishi Maine
I'm not supposed to
Pinch
New episodes
Every other Wednesday
It's how I built this
Stream NPR
Gyros
The early 2000s
And Zappos
Struggling
Economy isn't doing well and
Basically at this time Tony hsieh is funding the company with his own money he's doing that
By selling up a bunch of apartments that he owes
There's a
This was not a good time for the company
Did I mean every week or two we had to make a choice between do we make payroll or do we pay half of our vendors
Or 3 sell another apartment
But you can
Just selling apartment overnight user
So did you actually have to lay people off it in those early days
Yeah with him
First a couple years
The reality of
You really are out of cash and we're out of
Options and so
How to do a layoff notices to come take down
Even begin to turn it around how did you get to a place where you were able to make it sustainable
I think for us
Addicting point was
Spell deciding
We wanted to build a brand to be about
The very best customer service in
That wasn't baked into the model
From the beginning
They came later
Ganso in the beginning we always wanted to offer a good service but
It wasn't
Until we decided we wanted to build our
That's what we
Ashley wanted a grant to be about that
The most important thing
It led us to do a lot of things that
Would not have made
Any sense if that wasn't on your starting so
Examples would be
Offering free shipping both ways
Cuz
Very expensive to do and
We were just around trying to say maximize the
Profit margins than we've never would have gone down that path
And yes we would have made more money in the short-term gern
Those days but then we can have
Dog bark
Brandon Ray
Occasionally
I think
When you actually
Want your brand to stand for something or just have some sort of purpose
Anarchist
It's about to be about the very best customer service and cuts
You do things that
Kind of nonsensical
That your competition wouldn't
Yes it's there was a point where you really just
Find yourself like
This is your this is what sets our company
CNN
There's actually a phrase that
I think one of the employees in iron
Call center Ashley
Came up with
Started describing us as
Weir service company that just happens to sell shoes
And so for us
That's
But we're having 10-20 years now people won't even realize we started selling shoes online and
Imagine one day there could be a Zappos
Airlines are Zappa's hotel that
Is really just about
The very best customer service
Zappos
Cable
TV
To be great I need that
We are open to anything where
Service can be a dimension okay so Zappos becomes a
Huge deal
And then like
Entropy
Is what I guess
In 2009
You sell to Amazon
Cancel Amazon that actually approached us several years
Before 2009
Just wanted to
Clara Stanton
And basically
Becoming Thane acquired ends up joining the mothership band
Cannabis it's it's
Original identity and so we set
No
Very quickly
And then they actually in the ears and
Denon 2009
They launched a competitor called
Endless
And
Was basically
Lunch
From our prospective
Be with us in ultimately
They weren't going to
Be able to class then
Watch essentially
D&M and when
And so they try that for a while but
We continue to grow and so
I think after several years of
Them
I'm assuming I don't know
Details
Losing lots of money trying to gain market share through endless
They are precious again and said
Okay we
Well let you guys be your own separate
Subsidiary with your own separate culture in own separate way of doing business in
Happy report
7 years later they free Maine
Totally true their word and
We've been able to continue
Our own thing in our cultures
Very different
Interesting from
Amazon's in
And so from our point of view it was really
Just asked if we swapped out our prior board of directors with the new one
You are so young
I'm going to eat you still in your early 40s
Anytime so much
So where do you see yourself in like
20 year or 30 year term
Are you
Still running Zappos are you
Are you doing something else
You know cuz if you ask me
20 years ago means apus wasn't around but I would imagine
It's only going to be there
This
So I don't know I mean I generally don't
Try to think that far ahead
I guess for me it's just making sure that
I'm doing what makes me happy and
So many people are
Unhappy
Ladders jobs
For various reasons I could be
Target Celtic culture
Lack of autonomy all those things are
We want to
Hopefully show that there's a different and better way of
And I just work but I just think of his ass lights
And
And help spread that I guess
When we were kids that show lifestyles
Yeah and like
You became a very rich
A famous person right
Change the way you live your life
I mean right now I live in an Airstream which
A trailer like a fire
50 square feet
Everything
Yeah
We've got dogs running around kids running around myself to alpacas
I and I just love it cuz
There's just so many
Random
Amazing things that happened around the campfire now you just
Go outside and I actually think of it as the world's largest living room
And I guess for me I've always
Like I'm going to
Pay for experiences but not really for
Things
Just because
Experiences
I think I realized
Homologous
Make me happy in
It's funny cuz I was
Weather this morning
I having coffee with a
Friend of mine in an Airstream in
We were talking about
I think was a quiz or something
Where the question was
If you
If your house was on fire and you could only save one thing
Anyhow what would it be and how that way
Be a really good way of
Getting to know someone and
I was just looking around my room streaming
IPhone Maybe
And
People ask me what
My definition of success is in
I would say
For me it's
Getting the point where you're truly okay with losing everything you have
Tony hsieh still runs Zappos
It's by forcing himself to do something uncomfortable every single day
And the date we spoke with him
He decided to dye his hair red
And Spike it up into a mohawk
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about
The things your building
The first a quick message from one of our sponsors
Wordpress.com
Powerful site building tools and thousands of themes to choose from
Users can launch
The site that's free to start
Room to grow
Get 15% off any new plan purchase
At wordpress.com
Built this
Everyone wants to raise kind kids
How do we even do that
We often just
Expect people to be kind
We think I know you're a good kid you're going to be kind the evidence shows kindness
Is it a skill
When it takes practice
Find life gets new guide on how to raise an awesome kind kid
Apple podcasts
Word npr.org
Hey thanks so much for sticking around
Because it's time now for how you built that
And today were updating a story we first ran
About a year ago and this one starts
Back in 2015
When Mike boulos was working as a lawyer
Chicago
And move to a new firm in the new office my new desk was just
One of those typical dances kind of mounted to a wall
But yet in downtown Chicago
Is beautiful floor-to-ceiling windows out to my right overlooking the city
All have floor-to-ceiling Windows in our office
Can relate to the main problem right it office desk that is not in the right place
The perfect place to be would be the window
Get this beautiful view get the natural sunlight I'm like there's got to be something out there for that Mike was looking for
Wedge really
Fit to be mounted
Directly to a window
Started looking online couldn't find anything and that's when kind of like I always like to do
How did the Home Depot in Amazon and started to buy the parts I need to build it okay so first thing on Mike's list
Suction cups that could attach a desk to a window
Portwood on the desk but laptop
Books and stuff
So I shot then I found some good suction cups that you know held about 40 lb they said mount
Wanted them with some string that I bought from Amazon and
Critters really rudimentary almost kind of
Cat bed looking thing
It wasn't too bad for a first try but it was bouncy and it
Was too narrow to really work as a desk
And it was at that point that I stepped up and I found the
Types of suction disk that they use to install commercial grade glass windows in high-rise
Sounds like this is perfect
These are
Ultra durable ultra-strong and intended for this purpose essentially
Okay so Mike now had the critical section he needed to affix the desk to a window
And from there
He built 18 prototypes and finally
He had the desk you been dreaming of
People started walking by my office
What is that I want that in my office.
School where did you buy it
And that's what kind of lightbulb quick and I was like well I should really think about mass production and really bringing this to Market
And around that time Mike went to a party where you met a guy named Jason then
Tell Jason about the desk eBay
Immediately the light bulb went off in my head
Yes more light bulbs it turns out Jason grohowski was a real estate advisor
It was his job to help businesses improve the design of their workplaces
Pencil in the desk that Mike has invented
Here's Jason
I've seen how culture within spaces is changing how all the new buildings are glass how
Everything is about bringing in the natural light for employees and just productivity and health and wellness within spaces
And so I just got super excited other we need to we need to do this
Are we to take us to the next level
Mike and Jason soon started working with a design firm in Chicago
It made even more tweaks to the desk
And by January 2017 they had a prototype ready so they launch the kickstarter that April
And made $25,000 in just the first day
After we close out the kickstarter we had to fulfill these orders
So then it was
Let's go get this made they had all of these orders and no manufacturer yet
Show a month later this is May of 2017
They found one in Singapore and by November
Chase and Mike went there to check on the desks
Before they got shipped
I look at the unit unlike something doesn't seem right
And I play with it
And the lever snap
At that point we had 2,000 units already made all the components made
And we're like this is something that we can't let out the door
So after a month of sleepless nights and many design revisions
Jason and Mike finally got the Liebherr right
In December they started shipping their desks from their Singapore manufacturer to their customers and more than
40 countries
They're not both working full-time on the company is called spu
And their death comes
Fully assembled so you can install it on your window in just a few minutes and then
Enjoy The View
Refocus
So
Closely on our computers all of our work day is
Just streaming our eyes to look at close objects
With dust you you're actually allowing yourself to relax your eye and look out further
And since we last spoke to Jason and Mike
They got a TV show called Shark Tank
Three episode are just a few weeks ago
They landed a $150,000 investment
From one of the sharks
Hoping to launch two more products later this year
But still to this day if you email a company with a customer service question
Jason and Mike will be the ones getting back to you
You want to find out more about desk
You are here
Previous episode of podcast page how I built this. Npr.org of course if you want to
Tells your story go to build. Npr.org and thanks so much for listening to the show
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please
You do give us a review
You can also write to us HIV tea at npr.org
If you want to send a tweet
How I built this or show was produced this week by run teen Arab Louis
Who also composed the music
Thanks also to
Slim Julia Carney nor could see neither Grant stand for
Rogers
A guy Roz and even listening to how I built this
This
Is NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built
Best campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email
What's a drag-and-drop email build
Older and customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com