Okay so it's some point in the past decade
You are
Someone you know
Probably on
A simple pair of cloth shoes and there's a good chance
That's those shoes
They have been taught
Because in the past decade
Blake mycoskie built a multimillion-dollar shoe Empire
Inspired by a simple cloth shoe he once saw
In Argentina
Pippa blake Journey
Cashews
A lot of detours
The story first ran in
Enjoy
Well I kind of freaked out and I got this like smaller
Army of interns to help basically be customer service to email and call all these people let him know that
There is no chance that they're going to get their shoes in the four days or five days the website promise there's going to be more like
Couple months and I literally pretty pointy Cyrus took a taxi to this guy's house
House one Torres who is making the shoes in his garage Force the time and I walked in and with the
A little Spanish I knew I said something like muchos Zapatos rapido
NPR
How I built this
Show about innovators entrepreneurs
Idealist
Stories
Behind the movement
They built
Turn a Goodwill Mission into a multimillion-dollar shoe Empire
Create a business model unlike anything anyone
Seen before
So I should
Probably let you know
Right at the exit here that
Today's show is going to be
A little bit different
Because normally
In the first half of the show we hear the story of how an entrepreneur painstakingly build his or her
Business
From the ground up
And then get a
How it goes from there right and in in normally it's just
Business
But with Blake mycoskie
It is not just one
Because
Before he even turned 30
He's already launched
Four companies in some of them did pretty well
And as for his best-known business Tom shoes
What have you been going to get there for a while so hang tight
Blake's very first business dates back to the mid-1990s when he was a freshman in college
Grown up keeping up pretty good tennis player
He even played against Andy Roddick and ice
And Blake was recruited to play at Southern Methodist University
Everything was going according to plan
That is until one day when he injured his
Achilles tendon
I've had this
Spitcast on and crutches and I wasn't able to play tennis for
Several months I had
Did rehab
But everything I can do is actually couldn't carry my laundry
I'll head down to the facility in the college dorm
And so my laundry
Piling up in my room and my roommate
It was probably not liking it that much and
This is hard to believe but this is back
Before any search engine so we had to yellow pee
And I remember looking in the Yellow Pages
Define a place that would come pick up
And deliver my laundry back to me because
I physically couldn't do it
And and there's nothing like that in Dallas that I can find at the time
There come to the campus and do that and
That ultimately led to
My first business
Easy laundry
Blake partnered with his roommate and eventually they figured out that the key to getting customers
Listen to the students
Actually through their parents
So the next year
Quienes roommate got a boost
At the freshman orientation
The parents are kind of going there's kind of signing up for every
They're getting the books they're getting this again that
Navigate to the laundry thingy
They don't know how long we've been in business or if every kid on campus does it or not but
Cashiers
The chance to
You know sign their kid up for something that's not that expensive Ville
Help make sure that the kids don't ruin their clothes or freshman year they haven't been used to Washington
Drawing your own clothes
Roseanne
Sometime that they can use for other things
We are pretty good
Kitchen
Within the series like two or three days we did like $80,000 in
Prepaid laundry sales
What's the year
When are the actually expanded to four other colleges in Texas
And then they were doing so well that Blake dropped out of SMU to focus in
Harley on the company
And after a few years
They decided to sell it
So at
Blake walked away with about
$100,000
And lots of time
To kill
And I actually took a trip out to Los Angeles for the first time
And I'm just take a little bit of time off is it a cup
Friends are going to school out here
And when I was in LA I saw these
This huge
Advertising displays on the side the building
Now
Drawing of a Texas I'd never seen
I never seen like a massive
Add
I'm for an iPhone or a movie or whatever
Your painted on the side of a building
Yeah there was a lot of that in Los an
And I noticed that they're not only was a lot of it but there was almost
Exclusively advertising movies and
TV shows
So the specific industry the LA was known for
And I remember sitting there that she's thing at Mel's Diner on
Sunset I'll never forget this moment
And I was looking at this massive ad for I think one of the first Jurassic
City Park movies
This is so powerful that there's no way you can tune out this type of our ties
It's bigger than life
It's exciting
You know I wanted to go see the movie because of the DeWalt skate was so exciting it
Underneath a had a name of a company van Wagner
Company that owned that space
Can I call Dan Wagner into the AI company and I really want to do
Really big in LA and unsalted add you anyways could I rent this side of the building on Sunset and it's as well
Actually have a year-long contract with
Warner Brothers for that one
So we can't we have mother one in town
How much would it cost if I wanted to rent this one and he said something
I think you said it was like
$85,000 a month
You are a course
Pretending like you just want to get the information
If he says 85000
85000 a month
I'm thinking hold on that means that building owners making over $1000000 a year
Just by renting
The side of their building and he has two sides cuz the building
Faces Sunset two different ways
The $2000000 on one building
And I thought there's no cost like all you doing is just painting or putting the vinyl on there's no like actual billboards
Structure
Steel and all that stuff you have to do like this it
This is incredible
I just start thinking to myself like who would pay 85
$5,000
And like
Why cuz there's no way that can make
Sixth Sense
On a
Cost per thousand or an advertising
Images 9f
People that drive
Sunset
What I was thinking
And so the reason I basically came up with my mind was
It had to be you
You had to be there like all the studios in town when
Their movies
On the note on the street they want to show the
Actor
Starlet like I can put you on this building and like how big a deal is that
Isaac in Nashville the time and I made a quick
Assumption that the country music industry had maybe not as big egos but definitely some big egos in town and
What if I put country music stars on the side of the building
So is that is that what you did
Yeah so I went back to Nashville and got after it in
Mom found out that you know there's no one that has ever done this in Nashville
I and it was very
You're challenging to get the city to allow me to do it ultimately I had to
Convince the city
Because I had the highway beautification act which
Kept people from putting up any new Billboards I think like after year 1984
I'm so
What I ultimately came up with after like
Countless City Council meetings
Discussions
This and that was
I was going to
Actually make the city More Beautiful cuz I was going to create country music art
And so what I did was I actually would put the album cover
Of the new Dixie
She checks are Shania Twain or whoever was coming out
Album
But there would be no like
Call to action no light
Available at Best Buy for 999
It was just that the art of the album
And by doing that
I convinced the city I was adding to the landscape of Nashville which is all about country music so what would you do
It had this idea all you have to do is give me
Decided your building and you get
See I did it the thing you don't ever want to do especially when you're 22 years old again trying to talk to the 50 and 60 year old people who
Apartment complexes
You don't want to use the word ID
Because if it's just an idea then it's like
You're not going to inspire a lot of coffee
Yeah because people can say
I don't like your idea
I don't believe your idea but if you say I have a business
And what we do
Is wheelies
You know the side of your building
And will guarantee you this amount of money
Money per month and we're going to resell the side of your building cuz we specialize
In selling advertising
To the music industry end
You'll make money on NASA that you never thought you would ever make me
Wow are you
You're basically hustling
00 Hustler I mean there's no doubt like I mean anyone is an entrepreneur
Especially if they start really young
I mean you got a fake it till you make it
And
You know and I was I was never being
Dishonest
Nostalgia saying
This is what I'm doing and they had nothing to lose like by signing a contract
Just me
Then they were basically saying okay if you go out and least this
The Dixie Chicks
Jose
And you can lease it for 10000 bucks
You're going to give me 30% of that
Just for me allowing you to do this
That's that's $3,000 a month
To a place that made with charging $500 a month for apartments OKC I just
Created 6 new apartments that they didn't even have to take care of
So how did you get the first
Company or who are
Label to agree to let you work with them to put their album art like how did you even
Have those connections an end
How did you make that
It was just cold calling you know I mean found out who had albums coming out
Did some research and then
I contacted
Yeah the marketing person said hey I know you're getting ready to promote
Get a disc this album and
I have a way you can promote it
Larger than Life right here in Nashville it's going to make a big impact
You can be one of the first to do it
Miserable things that marketing people love to hear ya
And and
Who's your first client was the first piece of art that you put up on the sun side of a building
Amy Grant
And
We did it on the side of a Ramada Hotel in downtown
There's a picture of me and and my partner who is helping me with
The time standing in front of it
You know I'm that cover the Nashville newspaper when it came out and it was great and then what we had that with credibility
And then we just started
Yes I want in writing
Left
What did the label pay for that
I think we charge for that one about
I want to say 15000 a month
So if you work we are probably cash flowing. 10000 a month
Answers for that one wall
Do you think you have the confidence to do that because you had done the laundry business
In college
Yeah I mean I learned a lot I've started laundry business name
So I didn't you know kind of hustling and building and having employees and learning about customer service
The morning Valley things for about 4 years
So when I had this idea I had to pay a little bit more confidence
And you don't have nothing to lose you know it's like they they were going to say yesterday weren't and
I've always been good with you no like
Just Taking Chances and
And see what happens
So eventually
You
Black Nashville
Which US company
So I end up selling the company to Clear Channel
Take me to company that was really big in the outdoor advertising we ended up having walls in Nashville and we
Expanded to Dallas to
And once I got to Dallas I realize that this was like a
A big business game like I'd had some
Small successes
But it was very quickly that the big companies like the viacom's Clear Channel is van Wagner
They were onto my game
And it was going to be hard.
So did you walk out of that
Teal
More less
Set
Pretty set yeah I mean
Every everything is is relative right
But I definitely had a nice
Cash flow
Coming in from that that I wasn't having
Jumped Outlet find a job so when I moved to LA
It was more kind of
Car finance
Exploring what could be knack
Text and I was fascinated with reality television and how is B
Popular
This is like right after like the first Survivor came out and it just fast
I think the competitiveness in me
I did Venture that you know like all that
And
You're not worth thinking about
Applying
Survivor and we actually did apply for
Survivor Wii U
You wanted to be contestants on Survivor
Yeah
And
The casting people Survivor also
Show casting this new show called The Amazing Race
And they called us up and said hey I
I don't think we can put you and your sister on Survivor but they knew about the Amazing Race and so they
Can I talk to send to
Thinking about the Amazing Race and so we got into the process of
Being interviewed for that
And we got on
And then the actual show itself is 31 days so we literally disappeared from our world for 31 days
We can really tell anyone we're doing
Super confidential
We just like disappeared from my country to Country right
Yeah it's all of the world and
We're done the hard part was the show with and start
Caring for another you know
Couple months
So we couldn't Taiwan
What happened
You know if we won or if we didn't win how far we got
Not to spoil the ending for anyone cuz
Is there 2002 but you barely
Almost
Want you guys almost 1 billion box
Yeah
And thankful you didn't cuz I think that
That would have been a positive thing at that moment
It probably wouldn't have
Been good for my
Further Drive
An entrepreneurial state
She sits The Amazing Race and XIV Soldier
Company
And what I mean at this point you are kind of
You like 23 24 25 you have
You're 25
You've got this
Check coming in
From Clear Channel
Ubitus presumably you didn't really have to
Work if you
Bright enough to whole lot
Yeah I mean I was definitely about the money like you
Every business of EverStart has been more of a curiosity
And it kind of what if
And so
As I just got off The Amazing Race
Looking around and seeing how
Popular reality television
Be coming in
Understanding the basic metrics of
Advertising and what advertisers
There's one
Targeting and all that
I just got really excited at the idea of the network of
If you really having your own channel
And it would be
Play focus on reality and reality
TV stars that like a cable
Tvl
It just amazing to me because I remember when I was 25
Funniest random bike
You know start my career. But
I mean
I don't know Timmy 25 girls who sang
Restart cable
TV channel like that
It's a pretty
Bold idea to have
Yeah
I mean absolutely
But I felt like you know I feel like it was pause
Opelika
Just
It seems like
I was in this position I started to understand by being on the show
When did interested
People hiding
We're just about finding the right
People that knew how to do it and then figure out a way to channel
Their energy and
Get the right capital
All together to do it
So so did you raise money for it
So I did
So I
Basically
I tracked down
Are the gentlemen who is the founder of the e-channel
And somehow got a meeting with him
And then he kind of said
It look like it's so competitive now to start a channel
No
Probably about
Klystron 9 box maybe 700
$50,000 you would need
Just
To get
The lights turned on
And I said why I definitely have
Have $750,000
Did the time bet on this right off the gate
But I do know some people
Who really understand reality
And who have some money
Maybe they'd invest in my idea was it
To go to all the winners
Are the reality shows the last
2 years
And get them to invest
You said you guys should all the best let's start a reality TV
And I got them all to invest in and then I put some more money in it
Within a couple months I raised 7 + 50000 +
We lunch
What was called reality Center
So you raise money and then
And then what do you do start
Like producing a reality show
No the whole idea was it we were
Acquire the content
Next to nothing
You know I to Teresa
And then we would act
Late do,
Mystery Dinner Theater where you had someone come on it was on the showtime
Talk you through quote app
That's a good idea
Yeah so we had it was
But you know so we really don't have to spend money on
Hunting is more about trying to get
Which ultimately was
The Achilles heel and wide
Twerking
Do we have to go to LA
Comcast
Time Warner
Charter needs big organizations take car cable networks
The host all the channels
And convince them that they should
Give us a slot
Of the 105
And ultimately we couldn't convince
Of that
You know it's funny cuz I I sir you
Tell the story and I think of you as somebody who
Has really
Try to make the world a better place and I don't know if it's
If your 24-hour reality channel would have made the world a better place. It wouldn't have been I'm so thankful that it didn't work
I would write 5 in a shoot myself if I was running light outside
I mean there's something
Genius about and something
Really horrible
What happened with all the people who
Including you put who put money into
Unfortunately we all lost
It was really hard.
Pretty depressed for a while
I've let go everyone
It was challenging
So when that
All kind of collapse
What did you
At the Disco
So I mean companies three that that now we are thinking the overarching theme of my aunt
Rural Life
Which I'm really thankful for is been like there's been no
Connection
From one business
To another
Literally been me following
Kind of my Curiosities and the serendipitous
Conversations
Experiences I have
And so the next business
Holy that way
I was actually at a barbecue
As we were
Kind of closing down
The real Channel
And one of the
People that work for me they had a son that was
15 years old
When he was there
And I was asking him what he was doing that summer
You're making small talk and waiting for burger or something and he told me he was doing driver's ed
And I said all that
So exciting I mean learn to drive
And he responded like
Totally in uninspiring way I mean you just said like
Yats
Okay you know I go this
Please
The teacher boring
I pretty much sleeps
To the class
First off this is not good our future drivers in LA or sleeping
Anchor their driver's ed class
Method
Make Me Feel Good by getting on the highway in the second thing is like
I mean getting your license
Should be like this amazing experience for 15 year olds
And there's got to be a
A better way
To engage them
Yeah and I just thought guys like all these teenagers
Just trying to be online more and more
You know maybe there's a way to
Can it take this
Driver's ed instruction and learning
Into
The technology
Teenagers from bracing out though
So I had this idea just kind of started a new
Type of driver's ed company
We would do all the instruction online
You have to pass things
In sequential manner so you can really make sure that they're learning and they're paying attention like
It couldn't just like
Cram for the final test you would have to
You get the stages almost like a video game
And I recognized it
One of the ways to get them to pay attention and be more excited
Did about
The actual learning to
Drive
Was
To have
Driver's ed
Teachers that were
Going to hold teenage
Attention and the best way I could figure out
Do that
Was I hired only
Models
An actor's actor
Basically
Higher like Attractive people as the Hebrew Attractive people
That teenage
Boys and girls
Be like
You're totally idolizing
And I need that would spread fast
On the internet I mean there's a lot of
People in La that are you know that need part time work need flexible schedules it between auditions and
They're trying to make it and I was really lucky I found some guys that were already in the business
Death of online traffic
High school and driver's ed in
They kind of really knew the business and we ended up being partners
I was a 33%
Send partner in the new company that we formed together with
The two other guys
How did you get the word out about it
Once again even tried to mail Flyers
All of the
Fliers or Flyers at at high schools
You know lots of that
Lots of new targeting on
Myspace
But it is a true brother
To clarify to listener
We are going to get to the
Good that you did the world we will get to that
We will get to that
So it to you you got this
Force business
The driver's ed business
Is going really well and
I mean
Could you have
Just continue to do this car thing
Forever and ever or did you think that that was going to be the rest of your life
Yeah I never think
I meant I never thought
Like one business
Was going to be the rest of my life
Probably until Toms Blake mycoskie when
We come back tell me a random conversation in a wine bar in South America led Blake
Thompson and his biggest business yet I'm guy Raz and listening to how I built this
NPR
Support for this podcast
In the following message
Should come from the Annie E Casey Foundation
Developing solution
Strong families and communities
To help ensure a brighter future for America's children
More information is available at aecf. Org
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace is the all-in-one platform to build an online presence
And run your business
Create your company's website using customizable layout
Along with features including e-commerce functionality and mobile editing
And Squarespace offers built-in search engine optimization
Go to squarespace.com NPR for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off
Off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from
NPR
I got a ride
So it's 2006
And lakes driver's ed businesses
Taking off
Making good money
Life
But he's feeling a little bored a little
Restless
So he decided to take a break and
Do something a little unusual
He thought
What do I learn to play polo in
Argentina
And
Who's actually
After about being down there for about 3 weeks
When I met serendipitously a few women that were
And Wine Bar
That were talking to me in English which is nice as most everyone is speaking Spanish and I didn't understand most of what they were saying
And when I
Asked about what they were doing
Explain they were doing something
Hey characterizes a shoe Drive
And what that meant was they were going around
Collecting slightly used shoes from wealthy families in Buenos Aires
How to take two children
Who did not have shoes and couldn't afford shoes that needed them to go to school
And I was just really taken by
By their passion for this project and the fact that
Kids just outside of Buenos Aires to dinner
Shoes cuz
That was something new kind of new to me and
You know I asked enough questions to get interested
And they offered me to come with him
Help distribute the shoes and I said sure
They said
Check out this
Yeah they were going like a week later and I was going to be down there still on
So yeah so what happened
The experience was
An amazing one of me I didn't have
Really any experience
Point about volunteering or
Being in a place of
Poverty and
But I saw these kids really light up
When they got the
These shoes and they weren't even new shoes these were used shoes
Biggest potato
The kids were acting like it was
Christmas Day weather
Parents are excited and
Joy and if we put
She's on the kids who played with him to jump rope Loop
Quit soccer we did all these things
And it was just a great day
And so I went back that evening and I was talking to my
Paula teachers in Vallejo
About the experience
And
And telling him what a great day I had and how
Nioh how satisfying
Wasn't
How's it going on and on
You know I can hear gushing
With enthusiasm
And then he asked me a question that I really wasn't prepared for he said Blake is it this is
Amazing what you've done and I'm
I commend you and
Doing this in my country and
I know what area you were in today and at the very challenging area
Families
Is it but what happens when the kids
You grow out of the shoes
Is there when they wear out of
It's our only pair they're going to wear out of
And I said
I don't know
And his question kind of haunted
Give me to be honest cuz all of sudden I thought guy
We actually do something good or did we just
Further propagate a problem that they're going to have down the road
And I remember that night like
Actually having a little trouble sleeping and kind of wrestling with this
This question he asked
So
I woke up the next morning and when the things I've done since I was
Like 15 years old as I write in my
My journal on my server
And I found a cup of coffee and reading my journal and
Cat thinking about is questioning
It all seemed like cats this idea of like
Okay well if I really want to help you
These kids which I really did I really connected
This group
Maybe I go and get all my friends to donate shoes a couple times a year and we bring them down
I thought well
Yeah that's
Once again dependent on other people's donations and what if they don't do it and
And it doesn't seem like a very sad
Sustainable way
To give these key
Kid shoes and then
That led to
You know what
What if there was a busy
Set up a charity and donation
What if I actually started a
A shoe business
And every time I sold a pair of shoes
I would give a pair away
What
What kind of shoes did you have in mind
Volcano at the same time I've been Argentina for about a month and I've noticed that a lot of the polo players and evens for the girl
Girlfriends were wearing
The shoes called the alpargata
And it was kind of like an espadrille type
Canvas shoes that was
I'm very different
Can anything I've ever seen in the US
And just like
Magic card game together
What if I sold these shoes
Is that everyone down here is wearing
The people who never seen them
And come back here and give away shoes to kids and eat them
What did you how did you even get started
So we just started meeting with people in town made these shoes
Asking them like a can you change this
They all folks crazy because what they all
You know what the country is in Argentina with everyone appreciate that she was there really inexpensive and they work on disposable and they were
You know. Something that
Put too much investment into
People can buy them
You never
Month or two or couple months
I need a new pair
And so
They thought some of our changes was in
Make ashy way too expensive
They didn't understand that
We had a market
Hey cuz
If you were paying 40 bucks
Caravans if I can make something to eat
Have the same you know kind of longevity then
They're paid 40 bucks for this
Small-time artisanal
Shoemakers ovadia
We will make it in the garage is or making them in
Indifferent yes small little Barns and factories
So we got
Some ideas in
They protect them really rapidly cuz they were small organization
And we made a couple hundred pairs of like prototypes
And
In the name Toms
Was birth
There are created down there to be
Because
When I totally hear what I want to do I said
I think if we sell a pair of shoes today
Will give away a pair of shoes
Tomorrow
And will come tomorrow shoes
And our slogan will be shoes for a better tomorrow is all around this word
Tomorrow
And
When it came time to
Put a tag on the shoe
We couldn't fit the word tomorrow is on
Attack
Tigers with small in the heel
So we shortened the word tomorrow's to Thompson
And that's how the word Tom's game
Until you get back to the US How many pairs of shoes did
About 250
What's your idea
Could you see if this would
Work like because you could have come back to the US and people would have said
Or you could have sold them all and then
And then what
Yeah it was definitely
I try to stress this
List of people I mean
Of all the businesses
Did I started this was the least
Business of the business
Janet the irony of all of it was like okay there's 250 kids in
Santa's Village
I want to come back by Christmas
And give them all a new pair of shoes
So I'm going to go sell these shoes and I'ma come back
And then we'll figure out
Like it was not a business it was
Clearly like
This is a way for me to
Kind of stay connected to this amazing feeling I had it helping these kids
And an excuse to come back Georgia
Tina which I'd totally fall in love with
And and that was it and I still did the driver's ed business I'm still kind of
I'm having normal life
Is an entrepreneur
This is kind of be my side project in my kind of
Own personal
You know
Fun philanthropic
Experiment
And so
When you came back
Tell a
How did you
How old is she
What you do
I mean first I say I kind of got
Some friends and mice
Cistern
Girlfriends and stuff
DeKalb IL
And they luckily they like them they thought they were cool and they were different than they liked
It's dial and they love the idea of their help
Can someone what did you charge for
Originally
Price isn't
And so
I sold a few pairs that way and then I got
The people local people in La that worked in
NPR that I
Had met through friends
Two friends
To help me
Try to get the
The story out there cuz it was a really in
Sing Story
And at the same time they knew some like kind of cool trendy kind of fashion stores
Don't like the carry stuff that no one else has in the sea
Clearly that
Answer my first account was a store in La called American Rag
I went in there with a lily a backpack full of shoes
Some pictures of the kids that we had helped in Argentina
And
You know the girl's name is Courtney she was a shoe buyer
And I sure do the shoes
I'm sure they like them
And then I told the story and then she just loved
It's like this is totally unique
Chipotle
She asked me how many pairs I had to sell
Goodwill Yucaipa
Start 250 episode about 30 pairs
So 220 Avila website
Selling him as well and so she took I think like 85 pairs
Put a little display in the window
Add American dragon that was our
It was our first big account
Paramore the funniest and most
Amazing
Hearts the story and really, turning point all of it was
This woman Booth more who was at the time and the leading fashion
Writer for the LA Times
Chi
Was in the store American Rag and heard about
The story
And she asked for my information
She contacted me and She interviewed me
I did interview at or the story
Emailed her a picture of one of the shoes
Newsstand the next Sunday
It was like on the cover of the calendar stick
Daily Times
And that day we sold
Hundred pairs
On the website
Wow
They only had like 80 pairs of
My apartment 80 boxes and stacks of shoes
2200 Paris Portage
You do
Well I kind of freaked out
I also did what I think let entrepreneurs doing a time of dire need a start
It's me ads
Tips for interns
On Craigslist
So that good
And I got this like small army of interns
The help
Basically be customer
Car service to email and call Aldi
Did people let him know that
There is no chance
Said they're going to get their shoes in the four days or five days the website
Promise there's going to be more like
Couple months
Longer
Because I had to go back and make them in Argentina
You literally had to
Havana plane and go back like 3 days later after I get the intern set up with
Like laptops and phones in my apartment I said okay I'm going back to make
Issues I took the article
Do I need that would never believe me
And I literally
Filipina Cyrus took a taxi to this guy's house one Torres who is making the shoes
In his garage for
The time
How to lay her meet me there
And I walked in and
With the little Spanish I knew I said
Something like that
Muchos
Zapatos rap
And yeah I know
Just got cranking and one called
Some friends over in
Other people who knew how to make the
Issues and
We got our own little kind of small little fact
Are you going in this old barn
I down there
And after a couple weeks we got to work to make about 900 pairs
I'm out of this little operation
The lottery for weeks
So you have
2200 pairs of shoes
And
Did you ship them back did you like
Stuffed animals
Suitcases like let me know his like we put them in like big
Boxes in and they flew back with me on American Airlines
In the cargo area there play
See what kind of LAX
With giant boxes of shoes
Erase back to your apartment in Venice and the interns and we started
Shipping in the house from Bach like
So did you have boxes made and emptied it look professional or did was it just like
Justice shoes
Padded envelope yeah basically until we got the UPS guy
To actually
Comstock Park
I pick up every day wishes
Is great sweetie Netflix
Take him all the way to
Play sand so
I'm serious we are running shipping the stuff out of the apartment everyday and
And then because of that we getting more orders online and we started talking
Doors
Damn you are like on a roll already at this
Is playing right now
And then the next big break was
We got a call
From Vogue magazine and
And that funny thing about that was I had just seen the movie The Devil Wears Prada
Summer I see Meryl Streep video playing Anna Wintour
And I see how
Challenging she is Anne Hathaway's character and when I got a call from
From Vogue to come to New York to me
I was horrified I wanted you to come there to meet them
Well I'm the one interview me and they did read the LA Times article
So
C I went and interviewed me and then later they did a photoshoot in Venice and
Next thing you know we're in Vogue and when were in Vogue
Just all kind of
What exploded
Everyone the crazy thing is it
People just assume like we were like a real company when we are in Vogue
And so
We are getting calls from my storage all the country even
Celebrity star
That was also the benefit of thing of being in LA and that it was just
Such a radical idea like no fashion company or shoe company has ever like
Giving something away every time they sold it in
I think that naturally appeal to certain
Celebrities in
And they also like
You're wearing things
Other people don't have in life
It's new and so
So we just started like without any work on her own we just started
Sing celebrities wearing the shoes and they start being photographed by the paparazzi and then it starts showing up in
Things like People magazine and US Weekly and
Okay
The craziest moment for me was when I saw a stranger
Actually wearing
That was about
Three or four months later I was actually in New York
Trying to sign up some new stores
This is bright before Bo came out
Discouraged I was going to that airport to fly back to LA
And actually wasn't wearing my shoes I was wearing a pair of running shoes anyways I'm at American Airlines checking in
The kiosk and the girl next to me
She probably mid-thirties
She's wearing red para tops
At this point like the only if you ever seen the rain
Get my parents
Friends my interns
Made my neighbor
You know and I was so excited
Like cures like
Total random person wearing a pair of shoes
So you had to talk
Yeah
Ty says we're doing the checking as excuse me I said damn
I couldn't help but notice these shoes you're wearing
They're really cool what are they
And she like
Ligament stress out there Toms Toms Shoes
This is like the most amazing comp in the world I might not really tell me about it
Check when I bought this pair of shoes
They gave a pair to a child in Argentina
And I am right
And so I said well actually
You know
MSU Blake II started Tom
Dead Silence
You know like like
She just said
Can't believe it
And then she listens
Why did you cut your hair
And that was our main question in the fighting was why should I cut my hair why she knew I live in about all this stuff was
Because of
At this point now
You know we're on Facebook and where
You know we're promoting on YouTube and
She had not
Just a customer she'd gone online in like learn everything
He could have got the business
And it just really started to
Kind of like
In my mind
I'm up
Entrepreneur and mathematical stamp
Point B a quote
Vic
It's just
Everyone who bought
Pair of TOMS new
Morris knew that
When they were buying a pair
You guys would do a parrot
A child in need
Yeah me and your early days I think that's
The primary
Driver of why people bought Toms
The shoes were
Frankly not that good a quality
They didn't last as long as we had hoped they would I mean
Yeah they were different they were stylish Etc but
That the giving was at
The huge huge
Is driver in the early day
I mean I'm like a turtle
Am I
3 years behind everybody else
And I think the first time I heard about Tom's was
In 2009
This commercial
Yeah what was that about what happened
So I
It was doing a lot of media about Tom's
And so I think I was doing a CNN interview
And
The woman asked me
She said how in the world do you run your business cuz I just got back from Ethiopia on a giving trip
And she's like
Yuan Yuan Ethiopia last week you were in Uno Argentina 3 weeks
Before that any of this fast-growing business
Like how you running this company and
Being in all these places we are giving out
Issues and I held up my Blackberry at the time
Which I had and it's a disc
I said I can literally
Approve designs take orders
You know
Do everything from this
And I can do it for me.
Someone who worked at Bebe d&o at age
Who AT&T with our client
Saw that interview
Enneathought
Man this guy uses AT&T this is the best commercial we get everything
And thankfully I did use it
They called me out and they
I said okay well we going to talk to you about an idea we have
Commercial
My name is Blake and I'm the chief shoe Giver at Toms shoes they went with us on a real giving trip in Uruguay
When you went and handed out
Choose when we choose
They filmed us in our office
I need a network with great coverage because for every pair of shoes that we sell
Everything was just
Holy realtoy legit and they made it into
A very different type of
Commercial for AT&T
But it just hit a nerve with people
That was a turning point
What that made that turn Tom's from like
Kind of this
Fashion
Nice thing to a major
Yeah I mean that was a turnip
What does now I mean your millions and millions
Of Americans Elite Four
Sing our story multiple times throughout the week on different shows and commercials than
And that was
Just driving the business
What's in an incredible way
And by this point had you
I mean I'm assuming you you hired
18 to help you
Run this
Growing business
That's right cuz you were probably doing
Like what kind of Revenue are you doing
Every art that point we are I mean we did the first
Steer
And business
I want to say we did
About
The second year we did about
3 million
And the third year we did
Like
15 million
In the fourth year we went to excel
When we went from basically from zero
450 million dollars
Sales on an annual basis
In like
7 years
You know I think
We can go faster
Just green shoe company in the world
Insane
Yeah it was insane
What did you find to be
The most hardest thing about growing so quickly
You know
But after that commercial Nephew just started like
Golang game bus
Imagine the shoes
Making Usher and Ein even I mean even until just
How to say recently is the last
2 years
Making the shoes has always been the hardest part
Because none of us were Shoemaker
None of us were
You know production
Can people anyways all
Just different people I met along the journey that
You had a passion
Jennifer you know
For helping kids and doing something disruptive and having fun in life
And so the discipline of being great making shoes is always
And something that we've struggled with
And we really just recently in the last couple years gotten better at
I'm wondering about
Something to happen around 2011/2012
You decided to just take a step back from
From from the whole companies
Drop off the map
This is Hawaii
Well
The other business was
Was becoming
Pretty
Corporate
Pretty kind of bureaucratic we had
You know what leadership team that we had built that was
You know maybe not running it the same kind of way that we used to in same passion in
I didn't feel connected to the mission of TOMS and
That and I was questioning like is it something with the rest of my life or like my other entrepreneur gigs is it time to go and do something different and
Until I just thought the best thing for me to do which I've always found is when I'm
Struggling in statistics
Getaway in
Can be alone
Sometime in
And I did that what did you do did you get you just like
Go take a hike
Now I'm at the Austin Texas where I originally love often and I just got married and my wife and I
Side to move to Austin
Every year
Melissa company became super corporate and you are kind of disillusioned
What happened to make you want to
Return to it
Ultimately I realized there was more to be done
You know like we had bigger
Ambitions than what we had accomplished before
Now I feel like
We could use our model to help more people with more products
I had enough new things
The kind of get my energy
Again
You know it was just time for me to come back and is really my wife actually she recognized that I was
Kind of getting into a depressed state and Austin
And I just realized I was gone that I loved it like I missed it I miss the people I miss
I'm being in it missed the challenges yeah
Pressing you refer to Tom's
What is a movement
Rather than a business obviously
You know there's some people are cynical about that
That's just Blake
Use it you know yet he's just using that as a way to
Generate more interest
Is that like is that how you see it a movement rather than a business
You know I think I think that
The movement part
I really felt that
Where are customers
AR
Rain gauge
In the
The effect that they're having with
And that
Maybe buying a pair of TOMS has the
The first step or maybe it's
The 10th step
And their desire to
To be more conscious
Consumers in human
And so
To me that is more of a movement
Have a way of thinking
It is a business
Like you
Menu you've read and
I know about
Do you know
Over the years people have said look you know
This might sound like
Great business
Actually * is
Disrupting markets
Raisin and
Traduction not helping alleviate
Poverty
And you know
Directions
Creating other problem
I mean try some of those criticisms
AR
Aren't there some
Ameritas
Damn right
Yes I mean the first in kind of most
Prevalent criticism
Has been like okay if Tom's really want to make a difference in the
Communities
They would not
Just focus on a dude focus on job creation
And that criticism was really difficult to hear it first because frankly I just didn't know how to
Address it like I agreed with it
You know what yes and Theory would be amazing to create a bunch of jobs in Kenya
But I mean
How in the world am I going to figure that out
I like everything else
But ultimately back in mm
I think it was
R12x
We made a pledge to
Manufacture as many shoes as we could in the countries that we give in
And today were manufacturing over 40%
I've already giving shoes in country
Trees like
Kenya Ethiopia India
You lots of different places
I'm we're also giving
So was that was that a direct
Response to your critics are sort of like saying you know what your right
It was it wasn't it was a it was a humbling experience
Experience in one where we had a Express and vulnerability and say okay we don't have to do this. Try it
And we start small we scaled asthma
Groudon and it's actually been
You know now it's something that we pride ourselves in is part of our business
Fitbit the idea of the buy one and then we'll give one to somebody need really you know you guys are crazy you are credited
Really starting to smiley
Probably weren't the first they were probably other companies out there doing this but
You know you did this on a very big scale and since then a lots and lots and lots
Companies
Have follow that model Warby Parker
And it's been good for business
Sleeping really
Really good
Yeah I mean I think of all the things we're most proud of
Diatoms is like the Legacy that we
You created in in this model has become
Not just
Irrelevant model of Toms but with lots
The companies around the world and it's encouraged even companies
To be on the one for model
To incorporate giving more into their actual business
Business model not just
A check that they write at the end of the year you know
To a non-profit
I think about like
The Arc of your
Curry rice
I mean
The laundry business for
College students and the
Outdoor advertising company in
Reality TV channel Anthony
TN driver's ed
School
I mean very different from what
Did you get with X write like
Very very different
Do you think that you could have done Tom's without
Without doing all those
Biggest companies
I don't think
Tom's would you wear this today if I hadn't had the
Experiences
The thinking behind Tom's was always there but it was always something that was more in an order of
Make money first
Help others second
Because that's how every other business person I've ever known
No I never
Headed rat about anyone that was
Helping people as they were building the biz
And I think that Tom's is
Is like my soulmate Abyss
Slenderman is like
I get to be
Be creative
Get to find meaning in that
You know I I I
Recognize it
Amount of wealth
But now my wife and I were responsible for was
Far more than we would ever
Men think about
Spending In Our Lifetime
And so we made a real conscious
Decision to take half of it
And in committed to investing in social entrepreneurs
That's a big part of my life now is
Actually investing in the Next Generation
As a way to solve problems
That that we are faced
Denso
That's been
A huge blessing and all this is well-liked mycoskie founder of Toms
Shoes by the way Tom's is giving away more than 70 million shoes in 70 countries around the world
Back in 2014 Blake
Sold half the company to a private Equity Group
Up until then Tom's had never had a single investor
Do people call you Tom
All the time
Would you ever say if you say yeah
People say hey Tom at the airport I'd turn around because if it said hey Blake cuz I know that talking to himself
Please do stick around because in just a moment
Hear from you about
Things your building
But first I quit thanks to one of our sponsor
Airtable
Whether you're building a
Product finding your very first customers or scaling your business
Airtable is
Powerful enough
Your team on track
Get $50
Credits today by
Signing up at airtable.com
Built
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it's time now for how you built that and today were updating story from 2
2017 about
Gamers gift is a nonprofit co-founded by Dylan Hill when he was a student
At UC Davis so our biggest thing right now is bringing virtual reality the headsets to
Children's Hospital
Assisted living facilities
And people with disabilities goes all the way back
To the fifth grade when Dillon's best friend Chris
Was diagnosed with cancer and had to spend months in the hospital
I would visit him every single day and what I saw was my friend was no longer the kid that I knew
And my solution was to bring the video games because I knew that those would make him smile Chris eventually did
Get better and stay friends and that experience always stuck with me and I remember looking back on it at
Well those video games really helped us
Sunnyway fast forward
To senior year in high school
And Dylan is now doing volunteer work in his spare time
But he's not all that happy with it
I volunteered at a food shelter
And instead of spending time with the homeless
I was in the back
Packing bags
And then obviously all these things they help
But it would just wasn't rewarding
Dylan kept thinking about the video games maybe
There was some way he could use them to tell people
Chris we're doing a little random Googling
And Dylan said hey I wonder what it would take to start our own charity and we googled how to start a non-profit
Get to me song
Wow this is simplified into 6
Steps
First make an LLC
And then get in touch with the franchise tax
Bored
Actually some of the stuff Justin hot
Sounds so simple but
Eventually Dylan got his mom
To guarantee a blanket
For their nonprofit and they became a 501 c 3
I think we probably Google every single line on the tax paperwork
Because we had no idea what a lot of it meant but
I mean we have the internet you know we can figure out anything
Cancel after they got it sorted out Dylan and Chris started to raise money to buy video games and VR head
Headset
First they sold baked goods door-to-door
Finna get some donations through an online service they were starting to visit hospitals and other places in
In California sharing VR and games with
Children and adults
So for example there was this man Dominic who's living with cerebral palsy
And he's always wanted to drive a race
He's only able to communicate by moving his head up or down but we can put a headset on him and we can pushes is real
Wheelchair around his living room and we can emulate
Him driving a Formula 1 race car
Let's still in Hill
Who co-founded Gamers gift
Along with his friend Chris Betancourt
A lot has happened
First right
That story
Chris is Leukemia returned in October of 2017
And his prognosis
Was not good
Took Chris came up with a bucket list
Things he wanted to do before he died
And Dylan wanted to help
On that list
Beat a world record
Chris and Dylan wanted to register the most
Bone marrow donors in one day
The world record was 2976 to social media
And they got 3715 people to register
And they got something else something they didn't really expect a match for Chris
2 months later Chris had a bone marrow transplant and today he's cancer-free
If you want to find out more about Gamers gift check out our Facebook page
Did your previous episodes head to our podcast page
How I built this. Npr.org
Of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build
. NPR
. org
And thanks so much for listening to a show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and why you're there please do give us a review
Gastritis at HRBT at npr.org
You can also tweet us
At how I built this
Are shows produced this week by run. Bill Potter with original music composed by runty never blue
Thanks also to me event cat Tracy Howard North could see leave a grand Melissa Grace Anna's meshkinpour
And Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Candice Lim
I'm guy Roz and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
The u.s. and Iran have been at odds for a long time and we tend to think it all started with the Iranian Revolution
In 1979 but that's not the whole story this week on through line will take you back to four days in May
1953 that changed the USA Ron relationship forever through line where we go back in time
First and the present
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign money
An email marketing platform
Used by more than 250 thousand
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days ago
Campaign monitor.