Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here so
There's a place in your town or city where they do
Do amazing pizzas or
BBQ or tacos
So great that the line snakes out the door
Idaho Jerry Murrell had in mind
And when he wants open 5.
One place
Burgers and Fries
Keep it simple
And he deliberately look for a hole in the wall
Somewhere kind of out of the way because
He thought
If you can get people to come there
Then you know you got something
Free Grace
He first ran this episode
June of
It's a really fun one
Android
How did you even know how to make a burger
I mean where you a good home chef with anybody in your family come from my hometown
We know how to make burgers I know how to cook potato that was bored yet
You dueto grill-a-burger out of fried potatoes and that's all you really needed to know
From NPR
It's how I built this
A show about innovators entrepreneurs idealist at the stories behind the movements they built
I'm guy Raz
Tiny Family burger joint in Suburban Virginia became one of the fastest
Growing restaurant chains in American history
Jerry's going to move it
Surgery
Okay
Can you see me okay
You ready
No
Introduce yourself please if I met you at a party I'd say who you with
I'm Jerry
Morale
And what are you do
So hamburgers this is the founder of Five Guys Burgers and Fries
Jerry Murrell is 73 years old
And a long journey to get to where he is today
He was born in a small mining town in northern Michigan
His dad wasn't around that
Cheapest a
An adventure he wasn't very family-oriented
He was a stunt pilot that's probably why my mama have got a divorce family really
Catholic school kid
Where was
To say are you going to end up selling hamburger something so
Didn't work heart did get through school and eventually
University of Michigan
I got scared there I said my God how my going to make it in this world with all the smart people around
I think that was more intimidated after I got out of college then than ever
So after college Cherry moved back to his hometown and he married his high school girlfriend
I got a job selling life insurance and they had three sons but the marriage didn't last
Ended up leaving and taking the kids to Florida and for Jerry
That was a low Point kind of floated around for awhile lived in different cities it wasn't sure what
Used to do with his life
But he was sure of one thing
You wanted your kids to live with you how are you do that
Why didn't know yet
Around the mid-1970s Jerry was offered at consulting job in the DC area so
He took it
And he moved to Alexandria Virginia
And that's where you met his second wife
Cheney
An effort situation stabilized
His kids did actually come to live with him
And it was also around that time when Jerry decided to
Become a financial planner
I was
Shocked at how much money that was in the
DC area size I'm going to go back there
Financial planning business
And I got my degree from Mom
Bryn Mawr
And I started
Town Financial products
The people in the DC area
And then
That's what I did
To the boys move in with you
All of a sudden you got five people per household of 5 people
And that was basically what you did you Weaver financial planner
As a financial planner I tried a few businesses I started Oil Business
Some texts
I did a couple of dumb things
I tried to start a water bill
List of all things I thought were selling bottled water back on within a good idea
And everybody laughed at
An hour timer
Is in the early 80s
Clayton Middle 70s
The worst one was loyal because I started a company then went down to text
Found out that
They were waiting for me because I was from the East and they're going to take all my money
Heading with my my my wife and I went into the real estate business and leave
We were experts at
Buying real high
And then went to a crashing
Got to get rid of it
Okay so if I get this right
And you were doing financial planning
Is your mean
Job
You had like all these business ideas that you would try it on the side
And basically never no more
Cracked
I really didn't know what I
I'm just lucky I'm just lucky that
But I got the hamburger
What's a Genesis
You want to hear the short side of the Long Island where I grew up
Name push em up Tony
Push em up Tony
Had a little tiny hamburger place
With a picnic table in it
And he had a grill
And you didn't sell anything except hamburgers
Wishing happy
Anna
Cuz people used to come from all over town to get hamburger
And then when I move to Washington
Yes couldn't Ocean City Maryland
Where to place the numbers on Boardwalk fries there's a place are called Thrashers
20 places on Boardwalk fries
But only one place had a long line and a fracture
So me and the kids got indoor mine like hamburgers fries
Cheapest simple might work
And that's where the idea came from
So what did you do did you
I mean did you go to your wife and say let's try burger joint
Yes what you say
Docker same thing the banks
Set at the time you guys on your mind
But we are
We did a little different
We said let's not put a lot of money into
Unless
Final
Place where the rent is real low
Out of the way
Where nobody can see it
Play so why would you want to do it that way
And we said well
If we can put it where
It's hard to find
But if we can get people coming there
Then we know we got something
And this was in in 1986
Yes
Where was the first location
Columbia Pike and Glebe Road
In Arlington Virginia
And it was like a little place in
Rent was cheap invoice
To put up to our first only put $35,000
And what did that cover
Everything
The
The ranch
Equipment equipment
We found junk equipment rebuilt it ourselves
It was
Stand up only
And
Chad
Matt were still in high school
Jack chambless I think I'll be 13 or something
Anna
I said I got some money saved up
Recology
You want to go to college
And now
They pretty much said
God would rather do something else
Wake up go back for a second
You set your kids down
And if you had your kids college fund and you said to them
Hey look I got this college money I will send you to college
Or
You cannot go to college we can use it to open up a burger
Right
Were you a mean
You can imagine today like a parent
Saying that to their kids and then other parent saying
Your mortgage in your kids
Future on this burger joint yes did you have any of that feeling in your mind like maybe this is not a great
Know something was telling us it was right thing to do
Probably look back on it was probably assumed it was Cowboys kind of crazy here was crazy
It didn't seem crazy.
For some reason we all seem to be on board with
I was really surprised cuz
The kids Jump Right In in
Work tired
January tired
She kept all the books
I was amazed how the HobbyKids jumped into it
And what is the story with the name how did Teddy to come up the Walmart one of my lawyer said you should incorporate
You need to have a name
But as he fills out the papers
This was so well thought out that we didn't happen
So
Me and Janie and
Boise
We had that
Three Sons
Plus one more summer
Janie
My stepson wasn't born yet
So is
Four Sons with me so we can walk will call Five Guys for now and then we'll change it
So they get the papers fill out
Will changing the lawyer said okay
Okay sign on your first day of the opening day 1986 did you two discuss have a grand opening
Knotweed in it
Emma first open.
There's no business at all on their quarter 12
And then one person finally walked in and
12:30 wheeler
We were almost packed we made money for my very first day
And
We were breaking even and we're paying our rent
I need an employee's right cuz everybody was a couple employees but mostly was a kid
And we were
Paying them some time 7:15 hour or something like that how did you even know how to make
A burger
I mean where you a good home chef with anybody in your family a good chef
Listen to come from my hometown can't make a burger you can't live so I'm in that we know how to make burgers
And I'm from where I'm from is posing was right in their eyes and they raised potatoes
I grew up in a finally raised line potato I know I know how to cook a potato
And I know we know how to cook a hamburger that was both yet
Univera grill-a-burger Out of fried potatoes and that's all you really needed to know
Where did biscuits ingredients from
The potatoes in it
How did you know
How to Source this
We went to
Thrashers
In Ocean City
And looked on the potato bags
And we found out they came from Rigby Idaho
A guy named Rick miles
Small potato dealer out there so we got ahold of him
I wish I could you show us
Potatoes
We did not know what the time that he was small
Now he's become a multi-millionaire
We buy are potatoes from him
What was so special about his
Potatoes
They were sold by Thrashers in Ocean City
So you said
If there's a line outside this potato joint the potatoes must
Is Miami good recipe good
What was five guys offer
Was it burgers with all the toppings and all that stuff
What we did with a kids
Jamie and I would not
Tell the kids how much we were paying
For the product
WeChat
Whatever pickles you want to put on there
Hamburgers
You guys pick the pick
So they were trying different brands and different pickles
Finally they turned up with the most expensive pickles are where
And we wouldn't say anything about it would say okay that's a pick what you want by those pickles
Then we will buy the most expensive cooking oil you want to cook in and
That's where they cook them on Ocean City
They wanted to buy this bread from a little baker
Arlington that made really good bread
Brenner's Bakery
Best bakery in Arlington
But for my restaurant
Expensive we're paying about 7 times
Trump
Hamburger buns McDonald's
And what was the burger going for in 1986
I think we're selling something like three times four times at McDonald's with sound for which everybody said we are crazy would make it that way but
We didn't let the kids know
How much we're paying for any of the food
So they would just go out there and
Whatever it was
If they like it that's the way it was
And what was the thinking behind that
Strategy
The thinking was that
They're going to pick the best product
They got to take with a customer likes what they like
Get Give an example how ridiculous it is
Kids like to certain kind of mayonnaise cuz it was sick
Ana Patricia
4 things together and that we were buying our mayonnaise at the time from a guy up in the
New York City that was really hard to get along with and so when we hired our first purchasing agent
He said there's no way that mange is this important no way
Because this guy was so hard to deal with so we had all the family come in and do a blind mayonnaise cake
And to this day I can't eat mayonnaise by itself so we had like nine different
Dishes with mayonnaise and tactical spoon and everybody would
Taste of mayonnaise blindfolded and he shall I prove to you that you can't tell the difference in this mayonnaise or any of
And after the Ashley took a bath salts off my wife myself and all the boys pick the same initials
Equal Employment and I was a man in New York
So why
King and I what we would do it at the end of the month we look at them
Versailles
And then we look at
How much will pay for
Food and we say we got to raise our prices
The kids didn't know why we raise the prices
But we would always say
Food cost to stay around 30% whatever we got to do
We got a raise prices
Erase price
And we have
If we have to worry about price
We don't want to be in this position
Okay so you've got this first Burger Joint right
And how did people find out about it
How do people even know about
The only way would be
Somebody else down
They said there's this great
Burger places little like
Walk up Shaggy to try it
Sprite
That's the only way they would have found out about
There was a place in DC when I first moved here at office.
Impoundment lunch and breakfast photos downstairs
It was an ally
And it was nothing on the door if I remember right just a steel door coming off the alley
But that
All offices around there
Go to this place
And there was I marked and it was an ally
Anna
I was always impressed with the fact that that guy could do that much business out there and I knew him I know much money was Meghan
Nice old it
And within three months it was gone
The people were going there for the food
And it was working
And I sure want her to think I can do that then
Will just open up at the corner and people like herself, that they don't like us they want and then we won't be in the business
Coming up how Five Guys did stay in business
And how they grew Way Beyond Virginia
Even though it's the last person who wanted to do that
Please Jerry
Play with us on Gyros and you listening to how I built this
NPR
This message comes from NPR sponsor Squarespace
Squarespace allow small businesses
To design and build their own website
Using customizable layouts
And features including e-commerce functionality
The end mobile app
Squarespace also offer
Built-in search engine optimization
To help you develop an online presence
Go to squarespace.com NPR for free trial
And when you're ready to Launch
Use the offer code NPR to save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
I'm guy Raz
Chokecherry the sun's open
Tiny burger joint in Arlington Virginia
And it first
People knew about it through word-of-mouth
Record
Eventually
Newspaper started to write about the burgers
And then the lines started to get longer
So Jerry and his family started to think about opening a second location
But
They needed the money to finance it
I remember going in the bank
You going to do what
That was just a laugh. Us
But that somebody Sons
Said we got friends
That their parents got a little bit of money and they know Five Guys is doing good
Maybe we'll ask them for
For a few thousand
So we got
That should we had about a hundred fifty two hundred people
That would be blowing anyone time to give us money
But not as investor
Just for loans
We did it a different way we did it as investors would say
Give us $5,000
Will give you
Certain percentage of the
Gross not never that
Prophet
Cuz it was always too many ways to get
Cheap people that way
So I said
We'll give you a certain percentage of the gross
Will give you the money every single month
And
Anytime you want your money back you can have an abortion while that's
Stupid because you have a blimp
I was going to come and ask for the money back
But my method to my madness was also that
I said to them anytime I want to pay you back I can
But I knew someday
If this thing was successful
Are you going to get better financing
I can go back to these people and paying back anytime I want
So you never gave them
Said they weren't Equity owner
Not in the real sense
We just made a note said
If the store does
20000 week you get
Certain percentage at every week
And we gave him the money
Exactly on time every month
We could always go back and ask for more money so how much money did you
Did you raise for to do store number 2
Waffle House store number to we probably only had to raise Maybe
But we had we had a lot of people that just want to throw money at I say like the burgers
They like the fact that we are making money and what they were getting paid every month
I had about
75 people I didn't even know on that list
And I used to say to everyone
Don't put your money in somebody else's business
It seems like a lot of people saw something in Five Guys
Were you
Fully committed to this or did you or you don't feel doing financial planning program Financial
What at what point
Do you say
To your kids your wife you know I'm going to give up
My job
And I'm going to focus on Five Guys full time
Well that was almost the day I got hit in the head with a broom
I must have been having a bad day at the office or something and I went home that I said my wife I quit
You got to be crazy I said Mom I'm done I'm not going to work anymore
I'm just going to
Concentrate on the burger business
She was
Pretty upset
Because she thought this is too risky yes
And that you thought
I think we can make this
I will I just I thought it was fun
Yeah I was told my kids I said
You don't have to be in this bed
If you want to be
Make sure it's fun pick something you like to do in the business
Okay so now it was like the entire family focusing full-time on Five Guys
What would like roles did everybody play
Well
Jamie is like a a general and she is very organized runs office and everything but
My kids were able to go to investors and so I I kind of if it wasn't for
For them and my wife there be no Five Guys I didn't Bill Five Guys
Isis
Set around thinking that this thing is growing so fast I can't believe that you know they came up
But most of the new ideas
They pretend they listen to me soup I've lived in in the Washington DC area for long time off and on
Remember you know driving to Virginia
In like you know 1999-2000 to get Five Guys burger in Virginia
But when it was still just what four or five locations
Up until 2002 you grew up to five
Shops and were you doing pretty well with you all making a decent living at that point
You guys must've been rich
No but the thing is we had figured out the nuts and bolts of the business by then
Most franchisors
Start off
Franchise
We didn't start off the franchise we had no idea we're going to do that we started off the build family business
And we put 17 years into it
We figured out
How to do it right
Yeah so what I came time to franchise
We had a
Perfect system
How did you done at that point say
You hate books franchise
Build this thing out
Sons came to me about
The 19th
Late night late 1990 inside
Trying to convince me that franchise
And I was dead set against
Really.
Because I didn't think there was any way I could convince other people
To do what we were doing
So how did they change your mind
Well
There was a guy
Name Mark Moseley
It was selling franchises
For another company
She been watching Five Guys for a while
And
My kids
Got me
To meet with him I didn't want to do it
They bought me a book called
Franchising
Dummies it was written by
Dave Thomas
Show the guy from Wendy's
Yes okay
Amazon I rather than that and I
The legal stuff
I was amazing all the rules you have to follow on everything
So where they talked me into it
Because of her when you start franchising
First of all, the franchise either you're not going to worry about food cause I pretty
Sounds pretty stupid
You Got Talent franchise either you're not going to advertise that sounds pretty stupid
You going to tell him that you're only going to sell hamburgers and french fries
We're all going to be open later we got to sell alcohol we got to watch Food cars Suite
Shop around for rrproducts
I said I don't do that
99.5
We buy from people and we're going to stick with him
That was all hard to sell the franchise
But we we got through that
And I remember Mark coming in
Cuz he was going to be our salesman
He said he's going to sound like I can't remember how many stores are first year they're going to sell but I said
50 just cut down to 25 you don't have to sell 50
And I think within a year-and-a-half two years we sold 3500
We saw the whole United States
Your burgers were still a lot more expensive than absolutely
Girl
Man takes longer to get a burger so
I need the business model is different so were you worried, did you ever think
Gill maybe this works in Northern Virginia but I'm not sure this is going to work
Somewhere else
Absolutely scared the heck out of us
You were talking about the long wait
I used to have a sign that one of our stores
That said if you're in a hurry
There are a lot of really good burger places
Near here
Can I help
I remember the first franchise store we opened up was in Richmond
Alaska Walmart
Goderich
Nobody's you know who we are
I couldn't sleep the night before
Richmond that's like down the road 90 miles it's nothing
But I couldn't even sleep last night
Nobody's going to know who we are Richmond Stover successful
And then I said well
Now we're going to go to
North Kim
And I said no way we're going to Florida cuz people will
Nevermind
Product in Florida cuz they're older people
Florida
I got a hundred stores in
Florida Sun
The idea of going from
Five stores in 2002
Thousands of stars
Within
A year or two years we didn't go to thousands of storage we sold
Franchise
Those are still being built out
In the United States
We got about 1400
Avabel Tower
With all the territory the United
It's gone was that just
Mind-boggling
Mine bazzi
Anna and I was I was so proud of my kids that didn't go to their head
They're still my kids
They work just like they used to they work hard on everyday
What does it mean
What's it like to work with you or
Five sons and in your wife I mean
They're all involved in coming to work with 8D to do a different thing for the company
Well I have one son that
Just love
Doing stuff in the store
Make sure they're painted ride
Decorated rice
He's really into that
So that's his job at 1:40.
Fanatic about the food
So he goes around the world putting on shows and how to cook things right stuff
I got another assignment that that he's really into the financial part of it
Grabbed it and I'm glad
Because I don't understand a lot of
Expressions International
Everybody's kind of found their own little debt show
Business layoffs
Some of my teaching some light working in the field
One of them just loves
Taking care of making sure there's no food borne illnesses in The Fanatic about Auntie loves doing it
Amazon item find what they want to find and there's a gap that can't be
Nobody will hire somebody
Is your family still there
The primary owner of the company
Yes wait we on about 75% income
Me and my family
We took in a fairly big investor when I first start franchise
They don't interfere in our business at all they gave us
Big chunk of money
Larry entrepreneurs do when they saw something
Five Guys
What percentage of the actual
Restaurants do you guys own does it does
14 1500 restaurants Whittier
We have a joint venture and Great Britain and France and Germany where we own
With her partner half that's about 6
Thesaurus and then over here we own
About 450 out of the 1400
How many countries
Total is Five Guys
In-N-Out
Where am I Great Britain
Which
I guess it's still want country advocate for now UK and now we got 60 stores are weird
Rouen France
We just opened up enough
Sean's did Jose
Docker storm
Madrid magat
Several stores
In the Middle East
So I
I think a lot of people when they get a little bit successful
They look back and try to figure out how they did it
I can't figure it out
You still got enough.
Do you think a lot of it was luck
Who sings I give a lot of credit to my balance great believer in
Intuition or a higher power
God whatever you want to call it
Great believer in not
Listening to my hunches
I could have my own that's for sure
I kiss my wife cuz
Seems like to me without them nothing
We were lucky real lucky
Real real lucky
Do you
Your vision was not to
Open up a burger joint your vision was to get
Your kids to live with you
When you and your wife divorced
Which that was your I guess that was your real success
Getting your kids
The best things I ever have in my life is my
Captures no.
And the best thing that's happened to their mother
Which is my ex-wife
It's the fact that
The Rambler
Do all kinds of wonder
Yeah
And you still have a
Pretty good relationship with her
My current wife
Hatuey William
We got a lot we don't know if she's benefited from your
The success of your sons
How did being
Financially stable
End
Set out of that change your life were you able to do things that you
You couldn't do before
Well
Most people that I know
I've known
Since I've been a kid
When I started Five Guys I let three or four my buddies that I went to HighSchool with
Buy stock in my company
Cuz I thought it would be a great thing for them
Canadian ham
Little bit better
And one of my had a loan on them
And they're all millionaires
But we're still
Same old people I mean I just had
Bunch of money
Friends down from my Michigan a couple weeks ago on my boat
Florida
We drink beer together
Same as it was
34 years ago
You can lead a pretty Anonymous life like no one you're not walking on the street no one's like there's Jerry the founder Five Guys
Know that my wife always says
She gets upset of me
Sitting on the front yard
Mercante beans
I always wear Levi's
But that
I don't
I don't know other people look at me but
I don't I don't think anybody put on airs out
Yes it's amazing you said earlier that
That when he was a kid that the nuns said you were going to sell hamburgers
What about
Your mom
What would she thought about
What you did with Five Guys hamburgers
My mom like a bird
Shoe cobbler with nothing with a good idea that my mom used to say
If you can make a good hamburger
Or serve good drink
Or give a good haircut you'll always
Have something to do with you
Have an income
Jerry Murrell
Founder of Five Guys Burgers and Fries
All of the restaurants in franchises around the world
He says they are approaching 2 billion dollars in Revenue
Oh wait four years
Five Guys resisted selling milkshakes years ago after considerable debate
Some stores decided to start selling them with Nixon flavors like peanut butter banana
Strawberry salted caramel and of course
Bacon
And please do stick around because in just a moment
We're going to hear from you about the
Things your building
The first quick thanks
One of our sponsors National Geographic Valley of the Boom
It's about the first.
The internet
W2 bus
Sundays at 9/8 Central
National Geographic
Watch the first two episodes
On demand and on the mat
Gotv app
Hey thanks so much for sticking around because it
How you built that
And today we're updating story we first ran
About a year ago warning if you're a parent of small children
You are about to hear about poop and barf because those two things
Are at the very heart of Hannah England's business
She has two small children of her own and if you ever wondered what happens inside one of those
Family changing rooms
Well
I walked into the bathroom
And
There were two moms one was at the changing station and her baby had just how
Had a blowout like
Major like up the back all the way to the neck
And this is going to be a situation that every mom
Get themselves into
I've been there and see nothing
Once you've cleaned up your kid
What do you supposed to do with all those soiled and disgusting clothes especially when you're not at home
Just cringe when you have to stick that in your diaper bag
And then when you have to open it after a full day I mean it is not pleasant
After the clothes have festered in your diaper bag for a day
It may become impossible to get the stains out of
All the Scott Hannah thinking
I came up with this idea when I was putting my three-year-old
Too bad and it came out to the living room
Just started describing to my
Sister-in-law and my husband
This bag that's soaking bag and I and I kept filling in the blanks what if we could
And what if it had this
And then they looked at me and they're like
Well it sounds like you just invented it and what Hannah and vision was a water type
Plastic bag
That you could keep in your diaper bag
It would have a soap pod in it
Kind of like the pot that goes into your dishwasher
So that when your kitten pooped or barfed all over her clothes
You just throw it in the bag
Add water and well above clothes
Soak in soapy water while you went about your day
And then I kind of just hit the ground running because
I thought I need this in my life
Show about 2 years ago
Hannah started calling manufacturers
Basscenter prototypes of
The plastic bags and she and her husband began to Testa immediately
Fill it with water and steal it and hang it upside down in our living room and kitchen soap
To look for drips and leaks because
We want these things to be able to hold up in a mom's diaper bag and that's like going to combat
Nothing work
The bags of Braker the zippers are come on down and water would get everywhere
Joe Panik
Kept calling around until she found
One manufacturer in Wisconsin who seemed to know exactly
She need it
And he goes well I think we're going with this deal that's actually really aggressive for your utility and I said
Exactly wanted to be aggressive a seals so aggressive
But you would have to use scissors to get it open
And then Hannah felt another manufacturer to make a very gentle soap pod
Finally
She designed the outside of the bags
Classy black and white stripes and one of the design itself to knots
Scream like okay this is a bag for
Soiled poo
Kickstarter campaign to raise about $12,000 and for a while
Look like she wasn't going to make her goal
But then an amazing thing happened the accounting software company QuickBooks found out about her
QuickBooks has this program where it support small businesses and so someone from QuickBooks enter a mess
Search fire Kickstarter that basically said they were going to back you for the rest of the way it just showed up on our
Kickstarter thing
And my husband of course was going nope this is some weird fraud thing and I laughed at him and I
What kind of fraud puts money into your bank account
Normally they take money out
Hannah was right
It was not fraud
And in December of 2017
She shipped her very first production run
About 5000 bag
To those Kickstarter backers
A company is called
Wash it
Later
And since we spoke to Hannah last year
The company has moved from her basement to an actual office in about two months ago they started selling
The grab-and-go version of their diaper bag it's become an even bigger success than their original product
If you want to learn more about Hannah and her company wash it later
Or hear previous episode of podcast page how I built this. Npr.org
Of course if you want to tell us your story
Go to build. Npr.org love hearing what you're up to
Thanks so much for listening to the show this week you can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please
Please do give us a review
You can also write to us at Hib Tia npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
How I built this
Our shows produced this week by Kacey Herman music composed by run teen Arab Louis
Thanks also to be a venkat JC Howard nor could see nieva grandson as Mexican for
Jeff Rogers
Our intern
Gyros and you been listening to how I built this from NPR
Support comes from our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this
Campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand Custer
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week