Support for this podcast
In the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define your
Perfect pear
Hey there we messed up
We made a change to our web servers that we didn't expect
To have any effect on podcast
Clearly we were wrong
And it forced a bunch of episodes in to NPR Podcast feed
Resulting in downloads
You didn't ask
It also made it hard
Or impossible
You find and listen to your favorite NPR Podcast
We are truly sorry for the
We fix the root cause of the problem shortly after we discovered it
But it's taking awhile for that fix to make it to all podcast apps
If you unsubscribe from the show
Or any other NPR show
Please take a minute
To resubscribe
If you're still having problems
Please go to npr.org help
We're taking steps
To make sure nothing like this ever happens again
Thanks for listening
Hey it's guy here
And you know what are the things I love
Astronaut noises
What did you start at
Tell people about your idea
Because some people keep it a secret
Susan Tynan
Check she shared her idea for framebridge with anyone who would listen and some people actually told her
Oh you know why I thought of doing the same thing
But Susan was the only person to actually go out and do it
It's an awesome story we first ran it in November of 2017 and if
She's already heard it is
It's worth a listen again
Enjoy
There were days
It is possible this thing doesn't scale
And it's possible we want
We can't keep up with the order so the issue was not that you were framing them badly but there's
Oh yeah we're framing that perfectly just took too long
We started to see
Really angry emails
People saying like
This was
DeBerry special gifts
For my grandmother's 90th birthday and you ruin
And
It felt terrible
NPR how I built this
Show
Innovators entrepreneurs
Stories
And the movements
They felt
Gyro House
Dispense $1,600 framing posters
And then turned her sticker shock into a more
Portable idea
Call framebridge
So therapy
Pieces of artwork hang up in my house that
Cost a lot less than what it cost to actually frame
You know you drive to the
Restore you get the Madden you pick
The frame glasses
You're down
400 bucks
And then if you're like me
Framing stuff you end up turning a closet in your house
Do you like a
Photos and artwork Storage Center
And this is exactly the opportunities about 5 years ago
When she starts how to make framing
Cheaper and
Easier
Now at the time
Susan was already a veteran of a bunch of startups
Mostly failed but those experiences she figured out how to raise money to start
Framebridge
But I like a lot of the companies we had on the show
Framebridge is still in its building base it's still working to become a sustainable company
And Suzanne is still working like crazy still starting early
And still staying late and she says she got that
Run a small business on Lake Erie in Cleveland
Tugboats meaning the little votes that helped big boats and so it really
Operationally intensive business and
Our family really revered
Providing for our family and then
We ate dinner at 7:30 because that's when Dad got home from work
That's so cool like
I've never
Met anybody who
Who is involved with the tugboat
There's something just iconic an awesome
So are you know I certainly have been on my share of tugs and I think
My one soda party trick when I got to be a teenager was that we were
An event downtown
And there's a tug out on the water you know my dad would have them
Honk your horn when they went by us
See your dad and did you were you involved in
I mean we pinch and I remember you know if the receptionist was out would go in and answer phones for my dad and
We are certainly
This again like reverence for were
And what it took that it didn't come easy
Yeah I can just imagine my dad on vacations on the phone or
Are the phone ringing late at night and
If something goes wrong and
In a business that operationally intensive it's really gone wrong so
I remember that
Drama
Do you or did you grow up thinking
Entrepreneurial like I'm going to be an entrepreneur because
A jamming were around the same age and
I don't remember that
BMV Parma
Culture
No I think it was my dad and I thought I was going to be the boss but
But I didn't
That wasn't like I'm going to be the boss and great things come with being the boss it was like and all the responsibility that comes with that
And soy
I guess I had that vision of a business career
He's but you said you didn't think I'm going to go to
Vista College NM
Like a lawyer
No idea
And I certainly had a lot of ideas
None of which were great like there should be a pancake delivery service
But you know what
I was always thinking along those lines always solving consumer problems
Susan went on to study at the University of Virginia
And then she got a degree at Harvard Business School
She dip your toes into the
Startup world for a little bit
And then
She went to work at the White House during President Obama's first term
Battleground 2011
Susan once again
How to start a bug
So at the time
Some guys I had worked with previously
I had started a startup
In a hot new space called daily deals on soda company was called living social and I
Was watching them from afar
I was just started
Jealous
Blowed it was social Groupon that was the daily deal thing and if they're still around
Ndnu
Seeing friends of yours and you were thinking
I got to get into this I got to get on it I am so jealous like truly a joke
When when one of them called
And asked me if I wanted to join I sort of had like my desk packed up I was like I'm ready
Wow
Cheap a cup and you are like
Great I'm going to do this and what did you do at looking at ID
I'm so
How work was he sent emails with deals to local
Merchants & Shop
And so they decided they would do some specialty ones
Paradise Run Travel and hard meat
Do anything else
So I did
You don't first
Family-friendly deals and then
In-home services so like what kind of deals
Yasso deals for
You don't things like Gymboree and child care services and things like that things that a family might be
Be interested in apple picking
And then it was just like what else could we sell into what other group
What was that time like is ime Newsom not that long ago were talking about like
67 years ago
I mean
I remember LivingSocial here in Washington DC
It was
YouTube
It just seemed like everyone is throwing money at it what was it like working at a time
It was really really exciting
You know we were all relieved driven
We were all really bullish
We knew that speed mattered and in that case in that industry really
And so it was fun cuz we had to unlearn I had to unlearn some things I was coming right out of the White House I mean you had to
Like this email doesn't have to be checked by 10 people we just got to get it out the door and
That was exciting
It was like a gold rush
I didn't speak to you remember what LivingSocial is valued at
Now a couple billion
Yeah
Remember even the business lines I was running I got to launch when I got 280 million in sales like
Get out of your house
So was it just insane were you working all the time
Yeah I was
I was working a lot but again it was coming from a job where I work a lot so
Clearly something I'm used to
And also it's funny cuz I had you know
A baby at home and it was certainly a startup
Party culture as well and I found for myself there at a certain became sore like
Dementor aunt
Do a lot of people like I was where is a little bit older
When did you start to see
I don't know things at LivingSocial kind of
Turn a little bit when did you start to notice that maybe
Maybe this isn't going to
Work out the way
Everyone
Thanks I will
Obviously you see
Metric to see growth slowed
And it makes you start to question certain things
And then obviously you see Talent
And so when
You know some people admired started to leave
Just even
Composition of the whole experience begin
Penta LivingSocial capacity
What what actually went wrong
You know I think it's a multi-part answer some of which
Was
You know that
Exchange was really that local Merchants would get
Loyal
And so that had to be the case
And I think in some cases
That trade-off didn't exist and so some of the best Merchants said not in
Anymore and so then
Females wearing is exciting and they didn't have the best
Restaurants in stores in southern customers
Speaking lessons
Did the idea and so it was that
It when that cycle was reinforcing it was Unstoppable but when you know started to unwind
It got hurt
Did that give you an insight into
Stop
A thing of
New things new technology new products new apps like I don't not to pick on Living Social or Groupon Europe
Neither tons of these examples where you know one day at company's value today
5 billion dollars
And then
It seems like a year later
It's sorta like the emperor
You know MP
Closer
Google what is actually what's the value here
Well I think no doubt it led me to a business that I could
So I think yeah I just learned
Give me some of those businesses are hard to
Hard to know whether they're going to be transformational our Fleet
So at what point did you decide to leave
So
Growth was slowing and I think
More importantly I thought my personal development was slowing
And I thought you know I really
I want to run something
I just do and I always sort of just
Feeling that
Were you anxious about your future
I don't think I was anxious about
My future
At that company I was anxious about my future
In general I just wanted to get on it
And at that time I had started to think about building my own business
I'm in and I with my head was going there when I got a job offer that sounded
Melissa Zoe
Woodworking for a taxi app
It's called Taxi Magic that was actually had an iPhone app to hell.
Uber
And so I thought well that was sorta scratch this is
That'll be close enough to do in Miami
But was it a well-funded startup
So at the time it was but certainly nowhere near Living Social
Free snacks
Oh yeah yeah
Foosball the whole thing
You know that company
Sales Retreats beautiful graffiti on the walls
CTE
You were trying to convince taxi companies to adopt
Taxi Magic app or whatever and then
You would click on the app and then you can order text you that was
Align with hex magic that works exactly and how long did you do stay there
I wasn't there long I was there only about 7 months
Because
As soon as I got there I realized
I really want to do my own thing that I just that feeling could not be sated
In another way
Yeah and so what
What did you have to do to start a kennel
Brainstorm possible ideas did you have
Idea
For a long time
I met someone should make custom picture framing better
How did you get the idea
Daddy originated
Truly back probably
Eight or nine years
I had
National parks
Posters
I've never had bought on his annual hiking trips out when
On with my sister
And I took them to a local frame store to be framed
The terrible experiences
Really intimidating and
Really expensive
Like more expensive the posters much more expensive and the framing was for
$400 each
You spend $1,600 on
And so you were thinking what this has to do somebody has to change this
Do this again
And so
I just always had I like I had a mixed reaction even towards the posters when I finally picked him up three weeks later
I just thought I'd like
How did that happen to me
I just started going about my life and I kept noticing thing
That I would like and I have will you can have that you can frame it
Chester Patterson
Because it this is I'm having flashbacks to my conversation with the Warby Parker
Which it was similar because glasses are so expensive
And they were asking why I mean
Plastic and
Ghettos some hinges
It's right in Super Why
Why is the framing
Why am i spending so much money
Sofer a local store
They don't
Store any inventory
Is there any of their materials in their store
And sew in or when you go in and you select from the thousand
Frame styles on the wall
The
That bring sword actually buying those
Materials for your
When you
Place your order
Text week
And it's really heavily marked up you're buying from a distributor
So our Innovation which I doesn't seem like much of one was really like
Why don't we choose frame styles We Believe are beautiful
Invest in them and make it centrally
So you can't so so basically you have
Some options but not
Not internet
40 styles
I'm rotate
Driven by Trends but we don't
Yeah we don't overwhelm you with a thousand Francine one
And you have the inventory
Then we have
And the concept was that
That you would roll up your artwork
Nail it in and then it would
Come back Frank
Yes that was the concept the concept was for less than half the price of a retail store
With very clear upfront pricing you choose from a
Beautiful selection
We mail your Packaging
Email us your art
We send it back to you in a couple days Reddit
You're working a taxi Magic
But if you have this idea for a long time what was the
Spark that actually got you
To do that to actually
Believe in
Make goforit multi-step
LivingSocial I sold a lot of
And so people I new customers are looking for a deal on this
This category but didn't
They still didn't like their experience
And so that
Validated
And then
When I get to Taxi Magic I had
You know
How many smart people are competing in this category
Can I have a category
I am just so eager to make better
And nobody's thinking about it
You you started to tell people about this idea because a lot of people are secretive at the beginning
I think I don't want to view my deals I'll steal it
You told people about
This idea you had a dead and it was essential I did because
Yeah I needed to know what people actually use
Did people think it was a good idea and I started talking to everybody.
You're truly an image of me at a cocktail party or at
You know
Ifriends baseball game and in just thinking about you know
Telling people the concept in then I kept hearing the same stories about
Either me or my partner
You know
And in the story was always involving $600 worth of Framing and I bet I wouldn't believe it and I do believe it that's why I'm
I'm going to fix it
But everybody present was like saying to you
What an awesome idea Susan
But like
Let's just be honest here
A million conversations like that happen everyday
To this day at least twice a month someone says you know me and my friends we were talking and we were
Coming up with that same idea
We have an idea for a framing
Company disrupting framing company
Is is an idea enough
Yeah a lot of their lot of really awesome ideas
Now and ideas
Wheeling hour
I mean I so let's at least an hour sorry it's
It's worth
It's all the hustle
I mean into were you
Like financially secure enough to take this leap to actually
Leave your job and try this
No
We're living a life that required
Too hard working
Parents and required to salaries for Mortgage in r
Two kids they were
1 and 4 at the time
Two little girls and
It's obviously child care for them
So yeah it was kind of a crazy time to decide to start a business
And I think a lot of people
Tell me all the reasons this
Couldn't work
So what was the first
Think me so the first thing you did as you start talking to people and tell him about the idea
And
What was the first like
Concrete thing you did did you
Did you know anything about Frank
I knew nothing about framing
So certain most notably a kind of for a framing course
That I took at a Hampton Inn
And
So they actually take
Bring small framing
Equipment into conference room
Sponsored by
Just like somebody
I'm you can learn to picture frame and really the advertisement is like
Look at the highest margin business
Come learn how to frame
Learn how to frame then you can start to open a shop because
Cuz the margins are so hot
And so
It was really important for me to make sure I knew
What is getting into on the production side but also
Yeah they make sure it was
BECU
You leave your job to to learn how to frame
I leave my job to learn how to frame
And I go to a trade show in Las Vegas
Just two
Just to check it out just to check it out
Because I thought
Yelp
What have I gotten myself into
I just whispered wandering around looking at frame styles like they actually
Add opinions on on on WhatsApp as I liked and
And had some design learnings but really I just thought like
What am I getting myself into
I remember standing alone on the Vegas Strip
Just having paid my way they're out of my own pocket
Thinking like what am I doing like am I ever going to pull this thing
What when was x-ray shown
In 2013
Debt ratio
Set 2013 and in what year were there like taking notes and to just
And what did you do with that information
I was still in the you let me make sure I'm not missing
And then also like well gosh I'm going to have to get started so I have to call these people up and tell them I want to buy a quip
And one bite you know what
Develop contacts in the industry
There are few folks I met their who are still vendors to this day and I really give
Them credit for listening
Because I do think most people just
Orton
Oh well
Absolutely didn't
To this day I think I'm still trying to explain to people it was really kind of reverence for the end product
That I started this business so I actually think
Getting something custom framed
Really really special
And so
I believe that I just believe
More people need tax
But presumably some of these
Frame folks were like
We don't want this kind of disruption we don't want
Your Harvard Business School degree to come in and make this thing cheaper for consumers
That what you can understand
Of course
And so going on in building this business I have
Run into that a number of times but I think
It requires someone out of the industry to be able to sort of plotted from the consumer's viewpoint
And I think by this time I did felt like
Too late to back out
It and so at that point I started trying to
Kitchen Masters
Why did you decide to go to investors
From the get-go rather than
Just pull together
Money from family and
Anywhere you can get
A little bit here and there and
Yeah I joke a little bit that we were somewhat on lean in the beginning
In that
We Believe
I believe
That in order to actually
Do this business well and had to be done it
Such a high
Holiday
And that was that the site had to look beautiful
Packaging had to be
Branded
You had to trust
Awesome enough to roll up a diploma and
Send it to
And I really thought like
There is no
Really minimally viable
Product version
Like that anything to just test whether the concept worked wouldn't
We had to do a great and we had you are so
So how did you
As you get the money to do this cuz I have to assume you need
Did a lot of money to build
An app to get the materials to hire a team like YouTube how much money were you looking right yeah so
Hilarious I remember saying I was looking to raise $50,000
And initial investors saying you realize that's not going to
Enough money
But you know once I really got into it
We raised $2000000 so we were going to raise a real round
Navigate where you like a million half dollars value
What you say that did you didn't know what to say how I didn't I didn't know any of those things and quickly learned in you learn because all them
Meeting starts assertive meld together
Anyone know things along the way but the pitch was really clear and
And when I'm really proud of we built the business
Which was
Wenzhou
Look
I say we because there were some people on the PowerPoint
Pizza Shack
Who now have joint
But they were just like aspiration
So yeah it was just
Okay custom frames too expensive
And
Pretty big Market it could be way bigger
Is someone made it less expensive and less of a hassle
And here's I'm going to do it
How did you find people to even pissed
So an investor at Living Social
But I met for breakfast he was actually wondering why I had left Living Social it was just a sort of a social call
And
I had no business bitching him at that time cuz it was really not a strongly enough developed idea but I
Told him
You know
I pointed it frames on the wall and said you know those should only cost $100
Do you know that
And
Should I leaned in and said you don't you should do this
He's a really intense guy
And so
I thought well gosh that was the reaction
You're like validated right there yeah and so I
Yeah tag Savage of rebel
So so he's aching in the Mid-Atlantic
Pretty well-known investor
He is a well-known investor and yes
And he also calls it like
Casey's at so I knew like this is not someone who would be
Breakfast or lunch with this guy and he's like
Go for you got to do this Susan
He said that there's a good idea
And so great we left and about a week later
He's at me a one-line email how far along
And I thought
Yes
Okay
And it certainly it was not a promise of anything but it was enough to make me think
Like this is a nitrogenous we got it
I have built this
So he said pull up UPC
This Together come up with you know what are you doing next
How you get this thing off the ground and come
Which this thing for real
Find a pretty good presentation I thought of
Of how I would pull up
First guy to give you the money
Yep and I went in and I went through everything in the deck and he said
This isn't
I don't think there's enough
Here
That we can make
Annabelle Smith
What how does
He goes from saying go do this to saying
Yeah I don't I'm not feeling it
What it what was it that he did not
Like about your
I think you didn't like the certain
Uncertainty part of it
We had
Yeah I had an idea that I would pull everything together but
Yeah
I didn't have anything yet
And so
I think he felt like
I can't come back and say I found this great early stage company but they haven't done anything yet
And I remember walking home that I was
The difference I need
The cat but I walked home that night thinking like
Oh my gosh
Crestfallen
So that's done now you got to move on to the next
Yeah and by this time
You know I'm spending money at a trade show at a framing course out of your own pocket
You are not independently wealthy no longer
It was you looking your bank account and entering if it is a certain point where I'm going to hit a limit like
$10,000 - $20,000
Lost $30,000 and I'm going to be in big trouble
Yeah I remember actually having it
Serious conversation with my sister
In
January of 14
I was staying with her new your cousin
So Many Masters are in New York
Interesting on her couch and she was her like
Big sister I'm the one who has to tell you like eventually
You going to have to give up
In the moment has Susan Thailand got off her sister's couch and into her own framing.
Gyros near listening to how I built this
From NPR
Hey everyone just a quick thanks to one of our sponsors who helps make this podcast possible
Quit
Quip is designed to make brushing your teeth simple affordable and even enjoyable
Now the whole family can get
Refreshed with quip
Quip is one of the first
Electric toothbrushes
Accepted by the American Dental Association
It now has a new
Kids brush with
The same built-in 2-minute timer
Pulses every 30 seconds remind you
Switch sides
It got sensitive Sonic vibrations for healthier gums and a multi-use cover
Airbrushing on the go
Get your first refill pack for free
Getquip.com
Built
Thanks also to ZipRecruiter
Hiring used to be hard
Multiple job sites tax
Resumes
Today
Hiring can be easy
And you only have to go to one place to get it done
ZipRecruiter
ZipRecruiter since your jobs over 100 of the web's leading job board
Ben
ZipRecruiter scams
Thousands of resumes to find people with the
The right experience
Invite them to apply to your job
Try it for free
Ziprecruiter.com built
Everyday you wake up to that long to do list
Uppers gives you the latest news in about 10 minutes
So you feel all caught up on the world
Catching up on your life
Hey don't forget to walk the dog
Listen to up first every morning from NPR news
So before I get back to the show
Don't you know that
On Thursday Macy's
I'll be taking the show live on stage
Portland Oregon
Receptivity
First people to ever build a big business
Tofu
Is best known product
Probably heard of it tofurky
Is now so iconic that
Politicians of actually
Hardened it on Thanksgiving
Anyway tour life shirt with ceph
Supported by American Express they are super fun
You'll have a great time come out and meet us
Get tickets
NPR presents
. org
And hope to see you in Portland
Hey welcome back to how I built this from NPR
Kyroz
Has first investment pitches went
Nowhere
A lot of people told her to
Give up
Of course she didn't cheat convinced
Some Engineers to help with the website for framebridge
Promise that eventually
She would pay them
I really convincing Engineers like this is all happening we're going to get money so
Starfield
Sebastian start Kodi
We started building
Framebridge
But I mean
Even at that point anywhere so we're finding what the name for framebridge would be
And
Yeah so I started building as though it would be funded obviously anything that required a big check I couldn't
Obtain
But otherwise certainly I could get you know
Samples of materials and things like that and so I just started
Feeling as though it would happen
And
Meeting anyone who might
Be able to write a check and just using using your own money for bits and pieces here and there my money for bits and pieces
But that point things starting to pick up more and I think
Again a lesson in just
If you're moving as though the business is going to work the rest is going to
So that point I had gotten connected to another investor I knew as well
National investor a
At female partner
Venture Capital firm
Who and we had lunch and I told her the idea and she said you won't believe this I was
Searching
Last week
For the solution
It doesn't exist I looked for
Should I love this
I get it I I know this need exists
And
Cheating
It wasn't that easy
It was definitely a series of meetings in sort of a show me how you're putting this
Is together
The same way with a lot of like blue show me more in the next time you show me more
And so she was the first chat
It's actually sign
And a how long did the process of when you started
To raise money to when you ask you raise the millionaire million and a half that you needed how long did that
Meetings wise it was
You know
10 months
Really intensely probably about 4
Felt
Really grueling but I think is
You know as these things go through an EZ run
That's fast yeah 4 months
So you have
Like a little over million bucks in your hand
In your bank account you're looking at those zeros
What do you do with that money
First thing I did was hire my first
Employee
I'm a woman and Tessa who would work for me
Previously
And so truly the day the wires hits
She quit her job in
And what you do
Everything
Everything is like runs merchandising and creative but I mean we did
Everything we
Began actually doing a lot of products and
So we were sitting in this co-working space and we are getting these boxes of
Mount wood chips wood mouldings being sent to us
We shouldn't really go and I
Every night you know you have to bring your butt
Leave with your boxes
And so we would Uber home at night with boxes of
Example materials but we just started
Again doing everything on all fronts like meeting with packaging vendors meeting with UPS like it was just a
In hindsight I don't even know what that work plan look like but we were just reviewing every single thing at 1
And what was the plan like with that with that seed money
The plan was to build a NASA website and
Launch
Yeah so the plan was to build an app and a website and to find some framer friends
To do the initial production
And remember we had for the first 9000 frame
I don't know why we said that for the first time. Just find someone who'll do it outside frame company
Okay
And I think that was a way to get our initial investors
Comfortable with the fact that we were
Add no experience on that manufacture
Ringside but you had to find a framing company that would do this but they were expensive right so we didn't
So we started talking to
Yelp framers in to see if we get them interested in what we're doing and
We realized
I took a lot of questions like
We couldn't control quality we wouldn't be certain about anything and both of us
Sticklers for for quality for precision and we just did that
Do we realize in order to even buy materials
We would need a warehouse
And so
We need a warehouse we might as well get framing equipment
And we might as well
Make the very first
And so had to tell her investors like
Congratulations
You're going to own a frame fact
And we drove around
The DC metropolitan area which is really an area known for
Industrial spaces
But we found a space
And started building
So you ordered like
Equipment to make frames
Which I guess is like
Play band saws and I would like Willie Wood
Did you get so we actually
Had a guy through our travels we met a vendor who said
You've talked to this guy who sells used equipment
And he's a great guy on death frame store and said like a Moonlight for you guys
And help you get this
And how did you tell him to take like from the time you get your investment
The time you rescued launch
Set up the website.
And the app how long does that take
We got money end of February by April we signed a lease on the facility
Production facility
And July
We did a sawfly
Yeah it was but I mean
We felt under pressure I mean we had it again a lease for a warehouse and not a funk
Ring website
Elise for warehouse
You up with you paying rent on
And wear your investors like okay guys come on clocks ticking yeah they definitely were I think every week
Pre-launch
Belts carry what from an investor perspective and fungus and unknown
I mean this was just a real
Field of Dreams right this was a i bad customers really want this service
Until we launch
We wouldn't
Launch in July of 2014
How do you get the word out
Right so hilariously we started with me it was a password protected site cuz we didn't want to be overrun
I'm which was not to be a worry so we launched with with that little beta site in July and then August we opened up and
I told her everybody when you on Facebook
Got a couple orders
But they were all Serta you know
One degree of separation to degree of separation I went to college with that guy type thing
And so we started to send out for him
TED Talks
The Press
And
First couple months we got
Two big hits architectural digest and in
You just friend
Like random sings insensitive
We were like
What exact
Wakaliwood
What frame style would this
Editor and this Maga
Is Ian like
What is something about their life we can figure out
Interesting young we were really thoughtful
And those those were really validate
What about you
And
Did that have a measurable
Impact
Show in Arabic
At that point we were selling so few anything with measurable
So is measurable
But everything sort of manageable
Every time we had said like
Will really be coming in for selling a thousand frames
And we had told her head of production
Be prepared
And he was in the framing industry and he was like good luck girls like you. Get two thousand francs a month
And that was true of the first month or two and then late October
Someone a home decor blogger wrote a blogpost and we had our first real sales bike
And that was the first day without okay
Like it's on
How many
Orders were you getting in a day
So at that point we were probably would felt
Overwhelming we're probably getting in 50 years
The for folks who worked in production we're making the frames
But
B team of us who were not making the website and marketing everything where the shipping
So at 4 p.m. every night
We pushed aside our laptops and walk to the back of the factory
And bubble wrap
Package.
Including you the CEO better believe it
You are you are like
Wrapping up and
You better believe it I had I truly remember
An early board meeting I was on the phone and I thought oh my gosh they don't know that my hands are covered in
Paper cuts like they don't get it it was just
A level of all hands on deck
Trek Continues okay but we are approaching our first holiday
And
This guy this part-time had a production came in one night and said this was an earlier
Too much stress
Yeah I started didn't sign up for this thought I'd get you guys started but I don't need this
And
I said that we're about to hit our first holiday and things are picking up like I need you
I don't need all this with us
This is the guy who's running the brexit
Timeout
And you said
Well I'm not sure I can say what I said no I think I tried to appeal with the light
Please don't let me down
But there was really sure that he really would like I just
I took you this far
You freaking out
You know you do everything and so that was one of the you know they're probably a dozen times or you say like
Is it the end of the end
Yeah yeah
And I've been using about everyone in like your investors who believed in you and then you believed in this guy who said I'll just work part-time and
That was fine and how did we get into this
So what you do
Don't I immediately called a friend who would work in operations for LivingSocial
And doki
Put me in touch with another colleague of ours so
You don't miss
Mutual friend colleague
I'm with in between gigs and said this will be funny I can do this I can learn
Tie me up and so truly within 2 days
We had a new
Hadoop production
I'm who had
No experience in warehouse but was
And how long they take like 2 or 3 days
And he knew how to make friends
No but he was sufficiently ID and and really thought it would be fun
He just said like I can do this and we knew I mean
Yes
Super nice and super smart and
Day three he breaks his leg
In the factory
So I was like
Okay well we're out again
And so then
We just started
That the four of us
That Regional
Corporate team had to just stand in and
And figure it out at that point
He came back on crutches and we got through our first holiday
So you guys make it feel like Christmas and then
I just couple months later you hit
I'll take another crisis right
Yeah
We did a really clever Father's Day from
Commotion
Where we asked about this style of your dad and head
Uniqlo
Craft paper designs if you had a preppy dad or
Hipster dad
I was really clever marketing but
Broker Factory basically
Adjust required
Did they match
Not only all the components of a custom frame but also the right craft paper
And we started to slip into
A production
What what how many orders did you get
So we started was really the daily issue and that we were
Telling about a hundred rain today in making about 70
And
When we got into this Father's Day back login
That's something diverse
Summer
There were days
It is possible this thing doesn't scale
And it's possible we won't dig ourselves out it won't scale because you you start to realize we cannot keep up with the orders
We can't keep up with the order I mean that's a good problem to have yeah it felt like a good problem to have except we were also
Oriented to customer Delight
We started to see
Yeah really angry emails people saying like
This was the very special gift
For my grandmother's 90th birthday and you ruined it
And
It felt terrible
And I remember
Having this really intense debate about do we send the email to customers who think it's going to come in 3 to 4 days but says it's going
Two to three weeks
So the issue was not that you were framing them badly but there's
Oh yeah we're framing that perfectly just took too long
I'm an answer that leads to the bigger
Can we get out of where we are today and
Can this thing
Cuz you need to confer to work
It has to be as convenient
Quick as going to like
Your local frame story has to be quicker our customers
Charter internet Choppers they care about
They're and Tuesday they're getting ready for something they're doing
Saturday in
Tell me how you how you were sort of organizing your
Life
Because I'm imagining
You got to talk to your investors
You're bored
You got a Brazilian emails coming in
You're also like running the staff
What did you save everyone is like
Screen and tear your hair out
Yeah I remember
Hosting a board meeting
I'm at our production facility it a like a rented
Conference room nearby
Cuz I thought maybe I should bring them in on this backlog issue and they should actually
Take a tour of the facility and see what's going on
You don't Maybe
In this case honesty is the best policy
So I remember touring with them and they saw these like numbers on the board like let me get this straight
You have that many yet to build in your building this many a day
I got
That math is
Isn't going to add up
And so
I adapt when I just had to
You can't
Yeah run two truths you have to
Yeah
Bring everybody in with what you're dealing
How did you solve the problem
We heard a lot more framers we got a talented
Add a production operation
And who knew how to dig us out
Really it required all of us just give up
Weekends for a couple months
To get out of it
I remember one conversation where I said you know
We're not going down like this
And a woman who runs product for us that we're not
And so I was like okay
We sealed that
When I go down like this
I really was thinking
I once read that like
How fast
You can drop off
I'm a burpee is correlated with your life expectancy
And I think that's a lot like
It's really how bad like oh
The production
Manager quit
We got a new production
You like it's like that as fast as you can
God
When did you start to
CDOT the light at the end of the tunnel
We had sort of a
Euphoric
Next
So how many seasons really big for us
App for uploading digital photos to I mean edit
The great is he gay
So with Bigsby
Holidays and so
I think once we had
A professional operations team
And we lived through that crazy
Spike of a holiday season we realize like
Zofran Bridges is
3 years in now
Is it is it like smoother sailing
With the company or do you still have prices
Now wait there's always a crisis
What would
It's always what you didn't see coming
So I'm relatively
Bentley the beginning of this year we were raising more money in
Assertive at this stage in a in a
Then towards cuz it's your job well done with business here and so I had spent months on the road talking to investors include
Putting my own and
Stitch together
A round of funding
And I had been told I was to receive a term
The finding
The next day it was
Tuesday weather
So where does that Monday and I
New Tuesday I was getting intermittent starting to feel a little bit of relief
My job is to
Think strategically
Focus on the customer portal to keep the business
And so
Was feeling good I was doing my job
We had a brand-new CFO
He was 3 weeks and on the job and we were talking that
Monday night
And he said you know you're going to kill me
Navigation
We got to get this thing closed
And he said that
I got another job
What
Yeah 3 weeks every week set
So whatever works for a business knows that people watch
Cuz I mean you're like what's going on there if you're see about leave so I
Immediately newline
She's going to Spook the hell out of everybody
Turn trouble
Yes
Most importantly is going to
These investors
And so my first thought was
Shut up
Why did you tell me that
Because it's one thing to leave but like if you leave me right now I have this knowledge
And a half
And so
His credit had been in the running for public Company CFO job really big job is his dream job those things happen
The time just could not have
So
I left the building like a ghost I remember couple colleagues asked me about minor things and I like couldn't even answer them
I went for a run
Sodalite
What do I do I just get the term sheet close the funding and then say ah surprise
This guy is leaving
But you can't
When answered
Just heard a frantically called
All the members of my board to try and get out ahead of what I knew would be
Pili
It's sort of an explosion
Wish it was
They reacted by saying
A mix of things
This is really bad you know that yes
We'll get through it by the way that you that you are trying to
It's a lot of money it's a lot of money on the line and so you can
You know
People
I want to believe $79 is going to
A good company you can't blame them
Then I remember I'll never forget a one of her
Board members he said always on vacation but I'll try and call you and he called me and I could hear a steel drum band in the background
And he said
We're just going to have to do so well disguised
And I said okay
You're right that's what we're going to do
And so then they said everyone
Started to come around but I had to do sort of like
Yeah Sports Psych
With everybody
Wait to say like come on you believe in this business you believe in me we got this we're going to do this this can throw us off
I mean I really had to like
Bring everybody together like it was the beginning of
The company
And so you got the money
And we live to fight another day
What's the difference between your company in so many times
You're still in the thick of it
You are not
Like
Able to just sit back up
Where is the throat
Yeah like what's going to happen
Men with their major competitors like are they going to try and lunch stuff we're doing probably
You know what we get to be a sustainably
Yashow healthy business
Yeah it looks like it but you know but it's really
Require certified Commando crawl
Uninstall crazy amount of work
All the time
Yeah it's a crazy amount of work all the time like I said they're just
So many talented people now to share it
But
I can't help myself like I
Do always want to be
Skimming
No customers
Four tickets and things like that
How much do the
Point of view race
Lee Priest 37 million dollars
Meet at some point all these investors
Oh yeah they want something they want something back and so they're going to either and their two options recital you go public
Or you sell to somebody else
The only options
Likely
Do I think we can be a big enough company to go public
Absolutely anything read me a fundamentally good enough company to it and understandable and Evan a forecast of Alaska business to go public
I believe that
I also believe
All of those things that make us interesting
Would make us interesting
As a partner of another business
Does it I mean obviously you couldn't do what you've done without those invest
That money
What does any part of you kind of think
I wish I could figure out how to do this
Without
Taking a money yeah I've given up a tremendous amount of ownership biting people
Shocked by how much
So at some point
I bet I'll reflect on that but
Really I think a lot about the fact that I don't think it would have worked unless we had done it in this really
It's really high quality way and
The money allow me to recruit
Truly the best
Terrific people
And used very good materials and
You don't have a very open liberal return policy and everything that has to go into
Building a great company and I just don't think I could have done in another way
I think a lot of people
People here 37 million dollars in inches
Assume that you have 37
Billion dollars
But
Give me a heart that is that that's not the case right
No not the highest paid member of the team
So that is interesting I think that's very confusing to people
There's a lot of
This thing is real we employ a lot of people
We are growing really rapidly those are real
Not like
Swimming in money and throwing it up in the air
No
That is a funny thing
We still have
You know cash-strapped conversation
YouTube to friends of yours just
Assume that you're like
Rolling in cash yeah I laughed cuz I started to get a lot of things from like all the
The schools I went to
A lot of Lego
But the thing is is that there's a very hyper
Possibility you will this will make
Thank you very rich
If this turns out
The way your investors imagine you imagine
I can make you into a very rich person how important
Right
It sounds
Cute but I cannot be my focus
It truly if I take my eye away from the ball at all
On what we're delivering
It will
Just like
Has to be far away the hardest thing you've ever done
Oh it is so hard
I laugh about
I work a lot of startup
Like that has nothing to do
It is not it is like barely even pepper
For this
It is
Extremely hard
I mean it's just
It's like
I almost think like
Come at me like I have any merging
It's so much stronger like I'd like you to throw anything
As soon as I know that you guys are still in the in the building mode
And face of the company
This is a question that I asked you to pretty much everyone on the show which is
Do you think that so far you know
Your success in this
Success of framebridge is
Because of your
Hard work and intelligence or
Or is a lot of it just like
Yeah of course a lot is locked
Truly Almighty early team
Spock from different jobs
And so
A lot was
Being able to
Really pull at everything together and then like I said it's really a wine zero datalattice luck
But a lot is hustle and I think
I think a lot about the intersection
I guess blocking
Belief
I believe in this idea I believe that I could do it
I still believe it will be a big business and I think that
Translate salak
I'm so light is like I just believe
Enough
You know one thing we don't always talk about it on the show is just the amount of personal sacrifice
It takes two
Build a company right like
Pinotage
Time
Spent away from your partner or your kids your family and
Probably haven't taken
You know a lot of vacations over the past 2 years
It is still worth it
Oh Absalom
Absolutely
And it's really
It's the
People understanding this dream part that's worth it it really is
Walking through our facilities and seeing what people frames
Like that is just amazing it's like
I believed you had this stuff and you did
And so a truly I'll see someone and I'll have like a scarf from the running of the bulls
That passes from
Disney World am I
Like I believe
You wanted to bring that stuff and you got it you understood what we did
And you're doing it with us and that is just a citrus at 3
What is the most unusual thing that you've been asked
Sweet dreams a lot of unused
Usual things
We did frame
A ponytail which Wisconsin
But
Butcher
You know we're up for anything
My favorite actually won one of my favorite
What is a
Cardboard
Piece of a kid's fort and I had the rules of the fort on it
And
These kids when they were young and the mom and saved it and bring it for them when they were in their early 20s
Now they're framed
Rules of the fort but they were really
Really endearing
Be kind
Like the rules were really
It was like the way you should be
And I'm in the mom wrote us a note saying you know any kids get iPhones I think of him every
And this
Like what hands down
The best of Christmas
And so I was like
You get it
That's Susan Tynan founder of framebridge
If you don't we kept mentioning the amount of money she's raised
37 million dollars
Book that was almost 2 years ago
We just check back with Susan and she says framebridge is now raised about 82 million dollars
And that First Investors he pitched
Tige Savage Revolution Ventures
The one who encouraged her to start the company and then told her he wasn't ready to invest
Well he did change his mind he actually invested framebridge and every subsequent round
And today
It's on the board
And please do stick around because in just a moment to hear from you about the
The things your building
The first
I put things to her
2019 how I built this lead sponsor campaign monitor
Campaign monitor
Making email marketing radical easy
Big thinkers
Focus on developing Big Ideas
Try for free at campaign monitor. Com
Campaign monitor
Make your emails and your business
Hey thanks for sticking around because
Now for how you built that and today we're updating the story we first ran about a year ago
In the story begins in South Florida where land Testa grew up
Every year Lin and his family would pile into the minivan to go to Disney World
And he loved it but
Like everyone else he hated waiting in those long lines the summer before I went to graduate
School
I took a trip to Disney World with my twin sister
And we waited for two hours in line for this ride called The Great Movie Ride
I was baking in the Florida Sun I thought to myself you know my God there's got to be a better way to do this and in fact there was
Is a better way to do this and let the right guy to figure it out because he was going to graduate school to stay
Study computer science
And I went to my thesis advisors and they said I want to write a computer program
That solves this problem and soul in decided to do his entire Master thesis on base
The most efficient way to visit Disney
Yeah the first paper I ever wrote was 1997 this is 10 years before the iPhone
I said you know one day we're going to walk through Park and we're going to have use hand-held devices
GPS and something's going to be feeding at the wait times that arise and it will optimize your route azure
You're walking through the algorithm that would help people breathe through Disney base
Based on how busy the rides were at
Any given moment
And when the iPhone eventually came along when turned that program
Intuit app utility app
The ride you want to ride in the show you want to see in the meals that you want to eat
And the Apple tell you the order in which
You should do those things to minimize your wait in line lens at first came out about 8 years ago and
I actually stumbled across it and his company touring plans with I was planning my own family's trip to Harry Potter
World so
So I have to tell you I downloaded this this thing and it work amazing we would have been stuck for like hours
And is that pretty typical how much time can like an average family save if they use the app so
On a busy day we can save you for hours in line pretty easily
I'm in a situation very often where I'm driving home and then ways is like milk with make a right turn here and then
I'm going to like the wind East Suburban Street and like what I noticed they're like four cars behind me
They're also using Waze and I'm like this is
This is the ways of vacation now it's writing so what happens when everybody at the park is using your app does it stop
Saving you time right so we thought about that early on and here's what we do we know
When were sending people to each ride and we know how many people eat right can handle in a given hour
What say you would send you a dumbbell with noon and we know that it takes about 3 seconds for download a handle every
Person in line and you and your family of four to Dumbo we will add 12 seconds to the wait time
So that the next family gets whatever the wait time was possible seconds and we're constantly adjusting that truck today
Is free but the company makes money by charging a $15 subscription
Other specialized data about when to visit Disney parks and how to map out your trip
Recently when was able to take the technology from his app and spin it into another company
That helps patients with diabetes figure out what drugs they should take
Meanwhile you expect touring plans will make about 1 and 1/2 million dollars this year
I mean people overtime I have the greatest job in the world
My job is to go to Disney World
And make sure other people have fun
Doing it
Len Testa
Is the founder of
Touring plans
If you want to find out more about Lenor here
Previous episodes of podcast page npr.org and of course if you want
Tell us your story go to build. Npr.org
And thanks so much for listening to the show this week
You can subscribe wherever you get your podcasts and while you're there please do give us a review
You can also write to us at HIV tea at npr.org
And if you want to send a tweet
How I built this
Our show is produced this week by Rachel Falkner with music composed by rmt never blue
Thanks also to Julia Kearney JC Howard nor could she Neva Grant
Sanaz meshkinpour
Jeff Rogers
Our intern is Candice Lim
Gyros
Mustang
How I built this
This
Is NPR
Thanks
Who are 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand cost
With mobile-friendly email Tim
A drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days away
Campaign monitor.