Support for this podcast
And the following message come from Madewell
Where the motto is good day start
With great jeans
Madewell offer
Premium denim styles for seriously everyone
Stop by a Madewell store
Or go to madewell.com
Define Dior
Perfect pear
Hey it's guy here and
By now you may have heard that herb Kelleher
The co-founder of Southwest Airlines died on Thursday
Her boys 87
And in honor of her we wanted to re-release this interview I did with him back in November of 2016
It is still one of my
Favorite all-time episodes of How I built this
Because his story
And the way he tells it
Is delightful and funny and also eats
Truly inspiring account of
Sticking with an idea
When the odds are stacked against you
So here it is
Here's to Herb
And enjoy
You were basically introducing is really low fares were these Airlines trying to match your prices
Yes in some cases they were and we told the Republic of Texas that
You could fly at the lower fare but if you paid the higher Fair we would give you a free bottle of whiskey
And so for a couple months we became the largest liquor distributor in the state of Texas
From NPR how I built this show about innovators
Entrepreneurs idealist and the stories behind the movement they built
AOL
Centric Texas lawyer turned a crazy idea into Southwest Airlines now one of the biggest
Airlines in the world
Could you could you to start by introducing yourself mr. Keller
Naked herb if you would her
Please can you just say your full name
This is Herb
Kelleher
And your best known as the
Founder of Southwest Airlines
How how old are you now 85
Okay great perfect
We are very excited to talk to you about
Dumpster jump in here for like two I mentioned that before we really started our interview
I need some time to just chat with her and I learned some interesting things about him like to eat for breakfast
Normally for breakfast I have
Cheese crackers
And what he likes to drink
Wild Turkey Bourbon
And that he's been a smoker for
Pretty much his entire life
I just enjoyed the magical
Mystical Aroma On Site
I'll smoke
So how soon after you wake up do you have a
A cigarette
Well it's
The nanosecond with your cheese crackers
In before buy cheese crackers
That were the story of how herb launched Southwest Airlines 50 years
66 to be exact
Herb was a young lawyer
He's living in San Antonio Texas
He had started his own Law Firm helping clients to start companies
And one day one of her plants got and Rollin King
Cosmo
Hey I heard of this Airline call Pacific Southwest
Flies only in California
And I have an idea it looks
Let's meet for a drink Rollin
Came to me with the idea of setting up a similar operation in text
And how soon after he sort of floated this idea
To you saying yep
Let's do it let's start a company
It was a very short period of time
Maybe you know
Like a minute
No it was longer than that I was just joking
But was that a very short days within days
Within days
What first I was very skeptic
But then I did some research and discovered that PSA was very successful in California
The Texas supplied all the requisites for an intrastate Airline
Because it was a big state that had large metropolitan areas
Far enough apart to justify flying
And so Houston Dallas and San Antonio where the obvious first Target
Because they were the three largest cities in Texas
What did you know about Airlines
Well I knew nothing about Airlines which I think made me eminently qualified
The start one
That because what we tried to do at Southwest was
Get away from the traditional way that Airlines had done business
So I started with
The tabula rasa blank slate
And I think that was very helpful
So at this point in the how old are you by the way at that point in your life
I was 35
35 okay so you had on your family for children
Four children and you beat that the successful Law Firm by life was it with your life
Profitable at that time
No it was not notably profit
As a matter of fact
Warren Buffett reportedly joked about it at one time and said
If a capitalist had shot down the Wright brothers
At Kitty Hawk in 1903
The economy would probably be better off
And so it didn't have very great returns
It was constantly
In difficulty
Why did you
Even think that this was a plausible
Idea
I think it was a real or
Of doing something different
Doing something that was exciting
I really always have
Had a great deal of curiosity
And then I thought to myself what you know
Mostly adults
The United States of America
Haven't been able to fly because
The Court's power
Is too expensive
It's too expensive for you they just thought it was business people on expense account
And so
What I'm saying is that
In terms of
Market analysis
There was a huge untapped
Market for flying out there
Okay see you decide with Rollin to start a company was that right
DIY actually Incorporated in March of the 1960
7 but of course I was just a piece of paper
And we started to raise seed money to the extent of about $500,000
We were set to go
I am Warrior Competition like at the time of their other airlines
That we're doing these Texas life-like flight between Houston and Dallas and end each other place
Oh yeah they proved to be our biggest adversaries because they were not exactly
Warm welcoming and hospitable we didn't get kisses on both cheeks
When we announce
That we intend it to
Create an intrastate carrier sobran of continental and trans Texas
Slater Texas International
Really took out after
And I get this involved in political fights and and fights in the court
And they just thought that they would
Apply their incumbency
And their financial strength
To bleed Southwest Airlines to death before I could ever fly
They were suing Southwest Airlines
Direct what was the argument what why would they send you shouldn't Opera
Well you know the arguments that they made in court
We're actually all kind of specious
And this is one illustration of where
People attempt to use
To manipulate the governor
To prevent competition
That's what they were up to
So how long does it take you to fight these
These legal challenges
Well between the time when I start working
Informing Southwest and the time we flew our first flight
It was four and a half years
Wow it took a little pertinacity
Yeah
During that time
The company ran out of money
Add a 1969 the board of directors
Had a meeting and talked about shutting the airline down
Shutting the company down
And I said well how about if
Iloo gate
For nothing
And pay all the court costs out of my own pocket
Would you be willing to continue on to those circumstances and they said
Osher
So happy
What was it motivated you to fight for
For 4 years
I want this Airline
First of all I was idealistic about
Because I figured if they can prevent
Southwest Airline
Some introducing
What Southwest Airlines proposes
To provide to
The consumer
Then
That is
Assign
That the free enterprise system is failing
And one of the things that motivated me was to
Is that validate
The free enterprise system
And another one was
Of course that's it was very hot competition and
I like to win
But what's up
Like what I don't get is it was such a huge gamble anyway because you you could have spent those four and a half years
Fighting and then winning
And then Southwest Airlines might of fizzled out anyway
I'll tell you what guy you put your finger on something
Because
If you had taken a poll in
In the state of Texas
After we filed our application
I can show you
The 99.9%
Of the population of the state of Texas
It's like this single never come to anything
I'm very serious about that several people told me that they said
They were glad to see
How how much the flight energize met in that I was enjoying it but herb don't get yourself it'll never make a dime
Did you ever get sad or depressed me how did you keep your spirits up
Wild Turkey Hill
It may provide
Haggai it may provide a little boost
But frankly my spirits
Just don't get down
I don't stress very easily
I'll give you an example only
They have stress classes at Southwest Airlines years ago many years ago
And up
They invited me to come over and speak
You know the fella that was running the classes
He said to the class who said we know
Herb undergoes
A lot of stress all the time
Hotel the class how do you handle it and I said
I don't have that I liked it
That was the last time I was asked back to the collapse
So
So you I mean what you were going in and out of courtroom
For 4 years
How are you making a living at that
Well I'm still practicing law
I mean I was doing a lot of other things during that time which led to very long week
Walmart occasion I was in the law office
For two full days and
At the end of those two full days I've went home shaved and 1/2 a fundraising dinner for Southwest Airlines
But that's
Scott of the
The perseverance that at the Mandan
To help get Southwest Airline started while still practicing law
I'm doing many other things
So what happened to the court with the with the Southwest
It went
Through the United States
Supreme Court
And through the Texas Supreme Court twice
Before we could fly
And the Texas Supreme Court handed down
An order
19 hours prior to our first flight
When was that
Well that was a 19th June of 1971
We start flying on June 18th 1971
What was the flat where they go
The first flight
Went from Dallas to San Antonio
But the one that received all the publicity went from Dallas to Houston
And we were the underdog
Okay what sort of David vs the Goliath
Seattle not just one but three of them
So there was a lot of news coverage about it and that's the reason people pay a lot of attention
2 is finally getting underway
At First Light by the way
No I wasn't I was busy work
To make sure there was a second flight
Do you remember that day that the first like to Goffin
Remember why you felt that you feel like
Finally this is done
Oh it was wonderful. I'll tell you the experience I had
When the first airplane came in
It was over a in Fort Worth American Tanger
So I went over there and there's this airplay
After four and a half years
I would have stuck my head
In the back of one of the engines
And mechanic grab me
Hold me back and you said you realize that thrust reverser goes off
It will decapitate you and I said at this moment I don't give a damn
At this point Southwest Airlines
Advertising it starts
Flying many Ripple with it was a flying more than one route was it flying multiple routes
What was Dallas Houston Houston San Antonio and San Antonio Dallas
Do one of those legs
Well on some flights we had the fares as low as $10
Those we had theirs as low as 15 or $20
We were about
45% lower
Then the other carriers
So how are you able to do that how are you able to charge
So much
Such a lower fare than the other
Airlines in Texas
At through enormous
Productivity
But but how I mean I'm assuming you said a few planes
What we start out with
And then we got a fourth one
We had to get rid of one airplane in order to meet our payroll
Right after Southwest start flying and so
We decided
That we would fly a for airplane schedule with three airplane how you do that
Ten-minute turns at the gate
We bring that airplane in
+ 10 minutes after
Stopped at the gate
Ditto
It would be pushing back again
And we had airplanes that you never operating
12 hours a day sometimes so each one of those additional flights
Representative Revenue generation opportunity that the other carriers didn't have
Okay but even so I mean
Those other carriers
Like braniff and Texas International right
They were charging
Much much higher fares and it couldn't
Just been you turn to plans around faster
No it's a whole condo think you're right about that
I was just giving you an example
Out with the 10-minute turn because it's a vivid one
Addition to that they were by definition
Monopolist
They had been under 40 years
Federal government supervision through the c a b
That the Civil Aeronautics board
Yes right
And during that time if they had a little thing Angel problem
Of the cab would just give them a fair increase
I hope so
That's how their fares got so high
As compared to what we were doing
Since we were regulated by the caap
Okay so you weren't regulated in the same way but what were you doing other things like
Paying your employees less
Well it dependent initially we were paying them less
As the years went on
We were paying them or their total compensation
I was superior to the other carriers and in addition
When we turned our first very slim profit in 1973
We set up the first
Profit sharing plan
In the American airline industry
And I think they made a profit of I don't know a hundred thousand dollars that year or something like that
But that would alter course
Stupor billions
Enter employees pockets
And your employees were
Were you nice as well
Yeah we were the most heavily unionized
Carrier in the United States
Are low-cost were not due to being a non-union carrier
Since we were
More unionized than our competitors were
You were basically introducing these really low fares
Woody's Airlines trying to match your prices
Yes in some cases they were
There's no question about that so matter-of-fact braniff at one point
Put in a lower fare than ours
What's it called an introductory Thayer course they've been serving Texas you know for 40 years by that time
But if any of that one of the things that came out of that was
We maintained our full fares
Add we told the Republic of Texas
If you paid the higher fare
We would give you a free bottle of whiskey
And so for a couple of months we became the largest liquor distributor in the state of Texas
To her about flying at that time is like a madman
Let me know
Tumblers with
Skyauction
Glamorous experience with Southwest was competing on price mean you will not
You were not doing in fly cocktails
Like what do people think of your service versus competition
God I got a story to tell you on that
It was Thanksgiving of 1971 remember we've been in business since June
Yep
And my sister-in-law
A delightful lady called me mine Law Office in
And she said her butt
She said I just flew from Houston to San Antonio on Southwest Airlines
I've traveled most of the world's Airlines which was true
You know she was a world Traveler
And she said I know you're going to be a big success
You got the best in-flight service that I have ever experienced on any Airline
And I said
Am I glad to hear that how many passengers were on the airplane
She said just me
In just a minute Southwest goes National and Herb convinces Travelers at Airlines
Do not have to serve in-flight meals
I'm gyros near listening to how I built this from NPR
It's how I built this from NPR
And I Rise
1970s Southwest Airlines
They still only fly within the state of Texas
In 1978
Something really important happen
Congress decides to completely deregulate the airline industry
And for Southwest Airlines
That means
They can now start flying to new cities
Outside of Texas
Herb At this point you Southwest is expanding and your competitors are no longer just Texas airlines you're competing
American Inn
And and and Pan Am and TWA rightly National major International carriers start to become your competitor
Were people skeptical that Southwest would be able to compete in
In the big leagues
Oh yes
We were described as a Texas Airline that could only be successful in
The state of Texas
Okay
And then we were described as a
Sunbelt
Airline
They could not be successful outside
The Sunbelt
There was a
Press conference for winning the Baltimore
Where were the reporters there said that
Waiting on mr. Larry said I know you've been very successful out west but
Now you're coming to the east
The most competitive
Part of the country as far as Airline Services concern
And I said yeah it's so competitive that when we start out here
We're reducing your existing fares by 60%
How competitive does that sound at that time
Were you guys already serve No Frills
What we were no frills we're in the sense that we were short haul
And I got it
Restrict what you can do you have relatively short flight till like peanuts
Some drinks exactly and then pretzels
That sort of thing but you know
When we start flying long haul lights
From San Antonio to Los Angeles
Where to press conference
Email to announce new service
And
One of the
Reporters there said
What are you going to serve
Meals on those flights and I said no we're not
We're going to charge you $400 less
Bertram
Right
And I understand you can get a pretty good sandwich at Jason's for $400
So when I would point is you give up your life actor
Actually that was at the request the board of directors in 1981
Can you were still you still had your own law practice that you were doing other work for
Throughout the entire 1970s
Oh yes yeah
And I'll tell you the truth you know I didn't really hang her
Doobie
For corporate life
Because
Little boys have a lot more freedom to do their own thing when and where they want to
But we hired a very excellent fellow named Lamar Muse who was a real battler
To get the company off the ground in operation
He had substantial Airline experience
Bad. He did a wonderful job
And so you don't find me a 1981 we lost
Successor to Lamar
And the board director said to me you've got to do it and it did you want to do it I felt I had to do it
And I'll tell you why because the start of the 1980s
You had unemployment of 10.8%
You had a double-dip recession
You had the air traffic controllers strike
Then Lamar Muse the guy we had to get the cut me off the ground he launched a competitor against just gold
Muser
Southwest Engine lost a competitor
Yep that's 3 years after he left gold Muse there
Well I thought it was some Modern modest on his part
But because he called him user after himself
But where you at where you like what are you doing I mean we work together all these years
We bought him later
Can you buy some later
Yeah when they're on the verge of bankruptcy
We bought these are
But it was there
In 1981
So I figured I'd better do what the board asked me to do
And come to Southwest Airlines
Full-time
Was making money at the time
Yes
We've been profitable every single year
For 43 years I guess now
You must be the other airlines crazy because they were
A lot of them have had good years and bad ear
But it seems like Southwest is just
Has never had a
Bad here
Well we've had years when
You know earnings were down
But we've never had a loss for a full year since 1970
Me too
And we never followed an employee at Southwest Airlines when the rest of the industry during that. Up until
Has probably furloughed I don't know
A million-and-a-half employees
Throughout the world
Basically
We
Look at history and said this is a very dicey business to be a
Delta Airline business
Yeah
So we may be flamboyant from the marketing standpoint but we're going to be very conservative from the fiscal
Go stand for
And
Light
Established
Arul song
That we're going to pay 80% of the cost
List of all brand new airplanes from internally generated funds
And actually wound up paying 100%
Promotional airplane
So we had
The largest percentage
In our Fleet of owned airplane
Of any carrier of any size
So so
What does that mean
Well I mean
You're not taking on that
Right when you do that
So when you get into bedtime
You're not threatened by the deck payments
Which is put cameras into bankruptcy and out of bankruptcy and back into bankruptcy you know for
35 years
You heard from from the outside from listen to stories
The airline industry
Seems so
Brutalight is it do you think it's more Savage than than other Industries
I think
That it's more competitive than other Indus
Mysteries
And one of the reasons for that is
That our principal Capital assets
Airplanes
Moovit 540 miles an hour
Yeah
And you know if you have a shoe factory
The fails in Seattle as an example
You can't
Within hours transport that chew Factory 2
Chattanooga Tennessee
To compete there
But if
You're Seattle Air Serv
Versailles you can have your airplanes
In San Antonio or Chattanooga
Within a matter of hours so
The very mobility of your Capital assets
Breeds a lot of competition
Did you like that competition. Did you like being an airline CEO and
Imagine all that stuff
Was it fun for you
Well I have to adapt myself
Yeah I love being with the people at Southwest Airlines
That was like a fountain of youth
For me
They were so wonderful and entertaining and
Ghetto
Great to be with
That part of it but
When your pricing lawyer pretty much
Do Your Own Thing
And
It's a swift Pace wealth
Things to move as swiftly at first
What I came to Southwest Airlines full-time and
We're moving swiftly compared to the rest of the
Airline industry
But not compared to my experience
Were you pushing for expansion and growth and all those things during your tenure
Oh yes I mean Southwest Airlines expanded enormously
You know something very small base
But I soon realized
It was a speech
That I want to hear
Where a guru said if you can improve a corporation 5% in a year if that's a miracle
Oh okay I was trying to do 25
Maybe that's why I feel a little frustrated
So it really brought my thinking you know more in line
You know I'm taking
Even if it might have seemed like it
Play a slow process for you
The fact that Southwest was growing and
Can Prevail in this industry is is pretty remarkable as pretty unbelievable
Given that you know so many of those early competitors don't even exist anymore and some of the great iconic Airlines
TWA Pan Am
Exactly many other
There are very few left
What mistakes did they make that you seem not to have made
Well
We just did things
Differently
Like market share
You know is shibboleth
Supposed
I told anybody I say
Mention market share I'd punch him in the nose
Because here all these big companies fighting over their market share and losing money and following employee yeah
Let's focus on profitability
And if we have 4% of the market were profitable that's better than having 94
Percent of a market and being unprofitable
What's the value of Southwest
Overall
Oh
Probably
20 billion dollar something like that
One of the biggest
Airlines in the United
At in the world
In terms of passengers
Sunbelievable
Yeah
It really is
It's like I've had too much Wild Turkey
Fantasizing
Weather when you started the company
How much how much did you invest
Personally
I invested $10,000 which must be worth
Quite a bit today
Imagine if will is going up some
Since then
But
That's a company
That's what I thought was
Requirement
Of good leadership
I was turned down pay increases
Bonus increase
To set a good example
I thought for all of our people
Corsa stock that I got
Rose enormously in value but that was in lieu of
Cash compensation
She will be mainly Cade with Woodstock
Yeah basically was socket I got to do is kick out just to give an Exemplar
When I did
The stock option deal
In lieu of pay raises for their pilot so they could Southwest Airlines
Stock up
In lieu of a pay increase
I took no pay increase
Along with them
I'm not trying to single anybody out but
There was a
The head of an airline that was smaller than Southwest Airlines and on the verge of going out of business
Do salary and bonus for three times what mine were at Southwest Airlines and that's the way I wanted
Are you from worried that some me know some young you know
Herb Keller type
Characters going to come around and put up some upstart Airline and knock Southwest office
You concerned about it all the time
I wrote a letter to her employees
And
It was about my 10 for most concerns for the next decade of Southwest Airlines okay yeah
Number one
Was us
That we ignore competition
That we get complacent
That way
Get cocky
And I use the line thinks Mullinax volume will get bigger
Think they can act big and will get smaller
So could happen one day
So it's possible
You know I'm up
History buff
And if you look at the largest companies
And United States
As the 19th century turned into the 20th
Most of them are gone
The central leather company
+ 1900 + 1901
Was the 17th largest company in the United States
But it didn't anticipate
What the Advent of the Ford automobile
Was going to me
You know what it did
It made buggy whips and saddles
And never stop doing it until it was gone
And if you look at countries
Boys look at companies
They perish
If you have any sense of History
You realize that and you don't try to avoid it
You're hearing the story of how you made this happen and all the work you put into it
I wonder if you think your
Just wired differently
To be able to
Put up with all that stuff for so many years
Well I said yeah I probably am wired a little bit
For many people and they're probably very happy about that difference themselves
One of the things is that
I never look back
You know I don't spend a lot of time regretting things
It went wrong
And furthermore
I think
I've always had a great deal of fun
Out of what I was doing
And you know
People would say to me why don't you why don't you burned out
Yeah you know I was working 100 hours a week
Love Land Rover simplywell is easy
When you have a passionate joy and what you're doing you don't burn out
Herb Kelleher co-founded Southwest Airlines 50 years ago
And he served as CEO and then on the board
Before retiring in 2008
Featherweight herb Kelleher once resolved a trademark dispute with a rival airline are both using the slogan
Planesmart
He was all this not in court
But the challenging the other CEO to a public arm wrestling match
Which herb Kelleher lost
You can see that entire arm wrestling match
Just go to Google and type in the malice in Dallas
Thanks to our 2019 lead sponsor of how I built this campaign monitor
An email marketing platform used by more than 250 thousand customer
With mobile-friendly email.
What's a drag-and-drop email Builder
And customer support
7 days a week
Campaignmonitor.com