Virus
Eagle One
Packaged beans
Find json Keppler editor-in-chief of motherboard
And this is cyber are podcast about hacking
I'm feeling in this week for ben maku
Good morning what's the number of mobile devices explode so does the number of attacks on our cell that may be easier to hack into
A personal cell phone then you might think
Call recorded a private conversation and said that recording to a random contact which in the coming weeks
Millions of people will get new phones computers Amazon echos Google Home Smart coffee makers
And other Internet of Things devices
All these gadgets come with their own privacy surveillance and hacking risks
But there are steps you can take to minimize your exposure
Suicide be a good time to talk about the motherboard guide to not getting hacked or comprehensive advice on digital security
We release a new version of the guide every year for the last three years adding and changing things as hacking threats and security
Best practices evolve
Here with me today to talk about the guy is Harlow homes
Director of Newsroom digital security at freedom of the press Foundation
And Lorenzo franceschi Baker I a senior staff writer motherboard who wrote a huge chunk of the guide
So we recently published our third edition of the motherboard guide to not getting hacked
Eldorendo can you talk a little bit about
Where this project
Began three years ago and
Where it's at now
That's a good question actually
I don't really remember how we
Thought about doing this but
The question that inspired us to do this I feel like was
You know what do you tell people
About how they can protect them
It's like if someone comes to you and says
How do I not get hacked
What do you tell them
And the answer for us was like a
10000 words
Article
Which maybe is not the best answer all the time but that was the
I guess I was dead
Yeah maybe a little Overkill
But yeah I edited the guide the last 2 years
Send
I'm
I think
For me it's something that is growing out of arm
Reporting where
You know Joseph and Lorenzo and other people at motherboard are often
And talking to hackers
Getting sources
And generally being paranoid about their own security but we don't do a whole lot of
Journalism storytelling
Pokeball how to put
Check themselves
So you know we're not we're experts in this only in that we try to Fort
Macaron
Data and information answer
But especially grata bus
Writing like
What we do
Forest house
And that's a ways pretty well into
Harlow what you do day today which is
Teach journalist
Indeed
And I would actually say that
Seeing your guide and other articles that other news organizations
I'm is kind of the best line of defense
That we have in you know like a advancing that message
So not a lot of
Journalist and not even just journalists Everyday People
Whatever hat you're wearing at the time can afford
2 or know about
At the type of digital security education that is out there
I'm and so it was really really heartening to see members of the press actually like promote these messages and
And promote these
Tools and practices
And also just like make it consumable
When people come to you at freedom of the press foundation and say hey we want help
What are they usually asking
Well it depends and usually have a
A conversation with the news Oregon
Two kinds of assess what it is they at
Actually do need
Sometimes it is what we like to call the low-hanging fruit which is mostly what's represented in
Guide such as you are so such as how do we address
Credentials
Security
And sometimes I ate it actually over the years it's
Become a little bit more Nuance in a little bit more granular so
Sometimes we have reporters who either
At the request of their news organization or individually just because they're concerned
I have questions about how
Shoot further protect themselves
After you retaliated against for something that they print online
Wherever
And so we
Do I work on things like reputation management
Defense against doxxing
Defense against a lot of tactics that we did see him grow that was covered by so many of these news organizations
Such as yours
I'm growing out of like in 2013 onwards
Sometimes it has to do with source
Communication I prevent myself as much as possible so if I do
Say it let me know
I'm but I prevent myself from saying
Source protection because it stinks
Credibly in
Incredibly difficult time and it depends on so many factors
But Source communication
10 is
Another thing
That people reach out to us
As for the reason why is because there's a lot of nuances it's not only like what you know technically what you should
Should be using
But it's also you know
What we like to call the first Contact
Conundrum witches like
How do you properly
I'm prepare a a source or a potential source
When all they know is like you know how to DM you on Twitter
And how to like level up their security in order to have them or confidential
Communication
We also
Talk to people about like
Metadata and Genevieve
The pluses and minuses and using it in a journalist
Practice
We have sometimes like the Morris
Extreme stuff which I find absolutely fascinating and is what really really in passions me about this job
Because I love gadgets and getting away with
Stop
You don't like the word stream stuff like
Sandboxing and air gapping and extreme travel scenarios
Yeah I learned that you've done some extreme travel scenarios I think you know you want to do a big story about Kaspersky
Ski town in Mexico
Chicago Avenue
Prepared
You know you made like a throwaway email address to use talk us through what you did to
Therefore that yeah I was a little paranoid about that trip
So
What I did for the trip was
I got
A burner
Phone
Which is also I guess
Like a water that doesn't mean exactly what you think it means I also have trouble with the term burner
I like to call it a travel phone
Yes I got it I got to travel phone
I didn't use my work email while there
I
Has Jason said I created an email
Difficulty for travel
And I just
And I told my significant otter to
Expect communication from certain people if something happened I was
Probably being too paranoid
I don't know it was a it was a good exercise to think about
You know what I should worry about
And that's it
And an ultimately I feel like that
The key question
You know I think a lot of people try to
Think about tools as Solutions
And tools can be a solution but they are not
Always this
The first thing that you have to ask yourself is what are you trying to protect
And boyfriend
Indeed
Saying you signal you store is not always there
So that's this concept that kind of goes through our entire guide witch
Threat modeling
And I think
One thing I like to bring up
From time to time and I think it'd be
Considered light
Very insecure messaging but in a very
Situation at
Who is quite secure
Which is I knew someone whose
Boyfriend was
Surveilling
Her phone
And
You know
Was looking at her messages and looking at her
Chaste looking or emails
And so she would message on words
With Friends
Which had its own mess
Farm
I wish
You know that guy didn't
Know about
And that's a very specific and extreme
Situation like you wouldn't think
Words With Friends
Is very secure message
Platform
Can't start probably doesn't
But
You know she was trying to
Hide
Certain things
From him
And that was enough
So
Sweetheart would you guys talk about threat modeling with
Journalist
What can the average person
Take away from this
Idea of like water heater
That is
Fascinating
Anixter
I had not
I was unaware of the words with
But it's
Exemplary of something that we definitely Duty
As Lorenzo said you know the old adage
Did you signal use
Is taurine is
Kind of like insulting to a variety for variety of reasons
I'm and
The reason is not because like any of these
These Technologies are bad and they're actually the state-of-the-art
But that's only on the technical level
And there are so many kind of concessions that you have to make in order to have an
Ineffective
Conversate
So what we actually do in our trainings as we t
Teach this along a major
So if you can imagine like an X and A Y ax
And along your y axis
You actually know that's the vertical line what you have is like
How effective a particular platform is
In allowing you to have you know the kind of confidential conversation that you need
And so you know they act like once again like signal does
Really really well at that but then we also have other
Applications out there such as like WhatsApp such as Facebook Messenger
Such as Words With Friends
Apparently
But then and you know they they all have their different rankings on how
True they are
To you know
Technically speaking maintaining the confidentiality of a conversation
But as your attitude points out there's also this XX
That's where it's like how available something is and how applicable it is given a certain situation
And this is always going to be subjective and so
For instance
Signal is really really awesome but like you know like it's
Really
I guess it's
Mostly prevalent and mostly accessible from
The hacker Community because you saw that episode of mr. robot or whatever
I'm so there are only going to be like a certain subset of
People who can have a confidential conversation with you
Over signal
And also I'm not only like this apply to people who are in a domestic violence situation
But also applies to
People who might go through a border crossing
If someone sees signal on your phone you're going to be open till like extra questioning if not worse
Or if you're in a country where you know like actually you can't reach
The Google Play Store because
You know Absentia
Whatever and so
Being as like signal is not available
Currently
Over any other means
That's going through you know bar you from using
And so
I'm this is why you know
Maybe like something like WhatsApp is a little bit more appropriate for the situation just because the the
Fact that it's so ubiquitous
Gives it a lot of cover
Right by MetaBank City great
Place to have a certain conversation
Even though we know that there are you know just kind of flaws and implementation in WhatsApp but you can just kind of
Get around it that way
I'm as long as
People are just
If not using
Unibasic
Text messages I think
There's a lot of wiggle room in
Right so I think I in our guide we say over and over again the reason that the guy does
Is 10000 words and not
You signal used tour end of story
Is there's an excellent gift though where it's like Bart Simpson just like
Banging a pot saying you signal used her you could have published that should have done that
But I think the answer is always
Plate it depends
Depending on what you're trying to
Protective
You know but there are some sort of like overarching best practice
Is why the guy that
Is that all
I think
You know I don't want to
Run through the entire thing here you can read it on motherboard if
If you're interested but
Some basic stuff is like
Use two-factor authentication for most things
Unless you are possibly subject to sim hijacking
Which is our first episode on Cyber so
If you are subject that use a different
Sometime two-factor Authentication
Lorenzo can you talk a little bit of
About that
Yeah I mean to factor is a great example of
Server and advice that I want as always
Given everyone when you know
But like
If people are relatives they know it Christmas or Thanksgiving ask you like what should I do not to get my email hacked
Like two-factor multi-factor is a good answer
But the pitfall is
You may depend on your phone number and your phone number may not be as a
Secure as you think
And that's all we talked about in the first episode and we reported on it
For a while
And that's a great example of like how
A tool or rather a concept that is
By itself good
Can still be weak
Or rather has a week
And you know we go back to you single you store like
You know tools are tools and it depends on the situation it depends on
It depends
Who is going after you
If you wanna put it that way
Yeah so this year we beefed up the two
Two-factor Authentication
Transection of this
Send recommended
You know most people
You should probably use
An app base
Two-factor
An or a
You know with the app it's not really that much
More difficult than using
SMS
Just a matter of
Setting up sass
Some settings and
Internet
Harlow
A job and that's another place where there are also like a lot of nuances that actually have two
To do with you know the way that people actually use things
I agree 100%
That locking down
Your phone number so you don't have to rely on SMS messages for two-factor Authentication
Is
The best like you should definitely be using an app-based or hardware token
A solution
That said there are a couple of things that people should think about when they're doing two-factor Authentication
And this
These are tips that I've learned after like you know years of working with it and making mistakes myself and also seeing people
Struggle with it
The first thing that you should know is that
Most people go for you know Google Authenticator as their go-to for
The software token the the app-based two-factor auth solution
Just know that you know there are cases where those will not be backed up
So if you drop your phone in the toilet or like it gets
You drop it in the subway you're going to struggle because you will not have access to those two
Actor off tokens and so
Migrating over to a new device
Is something that you have to plan for in advance
I've been in situations where I have kept phones
4 years in a drawer because like I mean
The two-factor authentication codes from off of that device before I move it over
And also like the more accounts that you use
The more cumbersome that beat
So just be aware of that
There are apps that are alternative like coffee for instance or 1password
Which will allow you to you know like I keep those
Two-factor auth codes linked
To an account
And that means that your two-factor off codes are synced online and that means that your your security of those two-factor auth codes
Are linked to the security of
That platform
That you're using and so that's another thing that you have
Have to wait
Finally I always want to remind people that whenever you're setting up two-factor authentication which is
Is amazing and you
Should continue to do so
Be aware that there are backup
Either you know in the case
Google there might be like 10 codes that you can printer download to a file that you
Somewhere safe
Be mindful of that
And do take the time to print out those back up
Codes because if ever you get like totally locked out of your account
That's going to
To help you out of
I think we're doing this episode now because it is around the holidays when a lot of
People buy new device
Isis and
Also our hang out with family who say how can I avoid getting hacked
You're playing grandkids sysadmin
Witches
What I like to call
Yeah it's great
Hello what do you do when you get a nude
Device like what are the first things that
Tattoos
Pura d'Or
Migrate to settings
Name something you set up
Years ago
I kind of like to do it manually because
I'm a little bit of a masochist in that way
But a table. It depends on the device if it is a new phone the first thing that I do is act
Actually go to the restrictions
This is
Speaking from an iPhone perspective
Go to the Restriction setup that restriction pain which is now like buried Within
Screen time for some reason
And I use that there parental controls that prevent an iPhone from doing anything fun
And use that in order to just kind of rain in the apps that are going to be on your phone
Another
Let's see whenever I get an Android device
I like
I just have a look
At
The apps that are on there and make sure that like I'm using the granular permissions in order to rein them in as well
I think another thing that actually so like
People are going to get
Internet of Things devices like you know I was smart coffee machine or
Light bulb
That you can program or whatever
They're so pretty colors
They're super cool
I guess like this isn't necessarily something that you do with those
But be mindful of
The fact that they
Cher
Internet connectivity with other devices like your phone like your computer or whatever that you might want to protect
A little bit more
So cool thing that you might do is actually setting up an extra Network on your like home router
In order to just like enforce a little bit of separation between the the the coffee machine
Gene and you don't like
Like the phone that you call your mama on
Let's see what else
I don't know oh yeah and like you know who be Alexa and the
Smart. You know the Google home in like all of those things
You can also like you know do the same thing exercise caution that way
But maybe that's the coolest thing that you can do is like when you have visitors over the holiday let people know
Conversations might be monitored and something Google
Yeah I mean
The way that I come down on
Google home and Alexa
Psoriasis
Not even once
It's like put it in the trash
And I mean I might be being a little bit too paranoid and especially because
Some companies are better than others like
You're probably a little better off with a homepod then you are a Google.
Isn't even Google. Is that right is that it's an Amazon Echo.
And to actually one of the things about that is
If I get all kind of falls down to account
And so like when you think about
How awesome Google
Is in giving you control over how your data is managed
Rather how your
Count is managed and safeguarded they're far better than Amazon at that and so like if it all
All falls down to you know like how
Yeah how easily configurable my account settings are
And like yeah
Go with Google although like I totally agree with you but it at all
In the trash
Yeah I mean we not to get too far into this but I do feel like I'm buying one of those
As a gift is
A little NF
Just in the sense that you are
You should have to opt into
Now putting us
Speaker in your home
But at least some of the privacy setting
Targeting
Better so hopefully you didn't buy your mom a
A Google home
But if you did make sure the settings are all set up on there
This is an interesting conversation because I've been thinking about getting
A surveillance device for my cat
And I was reading a story yesterday on the other times actually that review
A few of these devices that are like at specific
I guess or marketed
For pet owners
And I like the fact that they reviewed the review devices
With that in mind so like they gave them to it one of those
Information security specialist
And they did like a
You know it's an analysis of the risk
There
And I was thinking like should I buy this path whatever brand name or
Just buy a nest
Camera or
Just put up
An old Android device
Pino
In the corner so I can
Make sure my cat is not killing himself shout-out to Haven
Cool app
I built by The Guardian Project in collaboration with freedom of the press Foundation
That turns an old Android into a
DIY security device
So my fear there would be
Like is that Android phones secure
And does it need to be
I have the same
Cuz I just got a dog and I have no idea what he does while I'm gone so if you have any thoughts
On Androids
You know you want to put as a security camera in your house
See what your pet is doing but you
Probably don't want it on the internet
Streaming at all times
So I'm
First off
It's definitely like you know you might have concerns about Android security especially if your phone is really really old and
Not receiving the proper updates and we all know that like
As Android devices
I guess
Get older
The
Their vulnerabilities
You don't like
Definitely
That said that a lot of like you know the
A privacy piercing invasions that happen with
Ghetto home surveillance
Devices
Happens to be that
Those devices are
Exposed directly to
To the internet in a way that and a potential attacker could like you know just kind of brows them on Showdown
Right or are linked up
To IU no third-party services that have not put as much resources
Into the security of that overalls
System that makes it vulnerable to
Two people eavesdropping on it
Are surveilling it
We
You know that means you're going to do what you want to do
But ultimately
One of the
The benefits
To Haven I'm actually is the fact that
One year it can be configured in order to send
That
Data over signal to your phone number Direct
Play so there is no third
Party
That is able to have like a
Unencrypted access
To you know
Your securities
Or you can also configure it to go over of hidden service over tour
So hidden Services actually cut out like
The entire
The possibility
City of
Another purse
Being able to access
Is that because you share that hidden service
With yourself and with whomever else
Legends
So I would do want to do like maybe a rapid-fire advice
Segments here
And because there are some things that probably everyone should
To do I mean maybe there
Some
Exceptions
Spy I think for the most part
Like good advice don't reuse passwords
Oh gosh
Yeah
Dory's password
Ever
Use a password manager like
Your LastPass or 1password or
Keepass do you have a favorite
I love
All of the password
Managers
Keepass
See is my hands-down favorite
1password
Really really awesome LastPass Lovett
I keep your apps and your operating systems up-to-date always sort of update the software
Especially if it's a
Security update
I don't think there's any
Controversy over that
Is there
No there's no controversy about that except sometimes I I find it
A little bit disheartening that you might be an Enterprise situation and
I give that advice but then like the IT person is like will actually like you know.
Bespoke software on the new version to hold off
I'm like oh God
I think other reasons people don't update are you know the pop-ups are annoying and they feel like they have
Take a note security update like every 3
3 days and they're like
Tomorrow I'll do it tomorrow
And also sometimes
Psy
Yeah new operating
Systems on older devices
They run a little bit
What's slower so
I think that's something we're
The software developers have to get a little bit better at chess
Just making sure the
That there you know their updates
Breaking all devices are made
Making them run super
Slow I think I was gone a lot
Better at that over the last
Fierce but
Yeah and I'm in an axon 7 and I
Maybe
The next iOS sir
And the one after that also
Some slow down
Other stuff
Disable Flash
Wheatley core that
Yeah unlikely
You probably don't need to do yourself cuz Chrome and other modern browsers already
Do it bite
Default I don't know exactly an hour all the rules but
You so don't have to worry too much
By default Google Chrome
Actually which I really really
Appreciate their default setting is to notify you if like a site your visiting
Requires Flash
Which is great
Harlow where do you come down on anti
Virus
It depends
Full force off of Windows
Defender
Is already like you know I'm pretty capable
I worry about there certain situations I worry about like the Telemetry aspect of it we're like it will just send random Fire
Files off of your computer to to Microsoft
However you can still take advantage of Windows Defender and
Still you know like
Tone down the telemetry
I think that's
There are a couple of
Good ones
On the market for you no like
For your PC such as
Avira
Which is
Bayside
Germany Avast
Does the old standby that everybody loves
And also for mobile the
Group Lookout
Has a great antivirus especially for Android
And also they contribute an amazing amount of research into mobile
Security ecosystem and
They should just
Commended for the work that
I learned that you want and Antivirus conference
To start writing
Answer this question of whether or not we still need antivirus in 28
18 cm
2019 South
Where did you come down at dangerous conference ever since he left the country for this
It was a very good conference
But I learned that the question whether you should use antivirus
He's more controversial than I thought I did not think that
My Twitter followers enjoyed fighting over this so much
I kind of wish I did before writing the story
But yeah it's hardly said a really depends
And what I learned about it when I like talk to people about this is that
It's better to have it than not
In most cases
But you know obviously if you are for example let's say someone who makes
Tools for the US government
Did they use
In very sensitive
Operations
Maybe you don't want to run an antivirus on your home computer
Because then those tools may end up getting uploaded
To a Russian company that may be asked
By their garments
Talk about it
That is not writing example it's like something
A story that was reported last year
So yeah I mean I like that word
What lightweight telemetry itsa very nice
Swore that
It's kind of like
What does it actually mean
And the it means data
Or files from your computer end up on somebody else
Computer
So you have to think about whose computer it is and who can actually Force
Company to
Andover
I'm so ad blocker I'm a huge fan of bad blockers
Script blockers that's her
Nothing
You guys both
Them
I am
Also I think that I teach
People in the low-hanging fruit
Discussion
Is how to put their Shields up on basic web
And I recommend three things
A reputable ad blocker I personally like
Ublock origin I sometimes like those three
You know there's a couple of other ones out there but like you know those are the two that comes to my head
Also I using a heuristic
Stick based tracker blocker like
The best one is
The Privacy Badger by the f
And also
Https everywhere
And those three are getting pretty much like your Shields
4 route
And also fun fact you should
Should be able to and you have to dig into like the
Extension settings
But for each of those enable them in incognito mode so you know when you're doing your private browsing
I'm using are quote
By the way
When you're doing that private browsing
You still have it
Right and on that note
Don't Go Wild on
Extensions
Biondo's like
Trailer been a lot of
Ostrich eggs
Elite data or have active
Do we still on data.
In general
Be careful about what your
Yeah you're giving
Or I'll priorwood
Yes agreed agreed the cool thing about
Chrome is well two things I mean
I personally wouldn't
Diaz Cavalier about the
Extensions that I allow into my life but
You should definitely be aware of the permissions that they asked
For so you can kind of Judge
For yourself
Also take advantage of you know the different personas so at least if you're going to have like a
Crazy
Extension that I don't know like replaces
No instances of the word Trump with like a
Picture of a cat or whatever
If you're going to do that
Do it in a different Persona so I worth it
But do that in a different Persona so you're just like you know you don't
Expose your
Private browsing or your most important browsing
To you know a potentially malicious
Extension
And also there's a cool flag if you
Dig for it and you know like Chrome / Flags
That
Is isolate site
Ya site separation
And so it's like it what it does is it
Further boost
Your ability to you doki
Malicious browsing from affecting other tabs and other windows
Another controversial one where do you come down on VPN
Like I feel like a few years ago it's like using VPN always everywhere even at home
I
Now there's like a little bit of discussion over with like whether you really need to use
All the time but yeah
I love them I love them so much
I understand
The
The controversy there
I'm so
Definitely what vpns do is you know they protect your ISP and other people
On the network from knowing exactly what you're doing all they know is that you're on it
Imenso
One of the reasons why
Certain privacy Advocates kind of minimize the importance of VPN
Has to do with the fact that and we should all Pat ourselves on the back
That art traffic is
Increasingly in
It's only really really really amateur and unimportant sites that are not h
PPS
They're only http
Answer one of the reasons why people were so enthusiastic about you
Using a VPN
I'm especially on networks that they don't control like in public like at a Starbucks or in an airport or whatever
I'm have to do with the fact that when sites were not encrypted
They were sending a lot of data like such as usernames and passwords and stuff like that out in the clear and hackers can grab it
I got it
I'm answer now like that's less of a danger and by the way if people aren't aware if ever you are on a website
And the
Form for your username and password
Is not
Encrypted
Meaning it doesn't have an http
You will know
That like literally anyone with visibility on to that Network
So
But that's it
Vpns are an excellent tool for guitar just
Kind of
Keeping your browsing history out of the eyesight of your ISP
And from a privacy perspective especially since like you know the
Since it was ruled
That is
Huskies
Quid
Actually use your browsing data in order to like
Serve you ads
That's actually a laugh
I feel that like you know I just don't want to give that dated
So this is actually the primaries
Yia
Very very much
So we have time for one more tip each
I'll go first
So when we talked a little bit about but not
A lot is
Making sure the app level permissions on your phone
You aren't leaking your location data or
Have permissions that you don't want them to have
I'd recommend just going through iOS or Android and
Honestly deleting any apps
Apps that you don't use or don't trust
But beyond that you can turn off
At when they're allowed to access your location and
If they're allowed to ask
Tessa Dever
It's especially important on things like
Strava origin
Is anything I
McMaster
Positions and then
Keeps that
In upload it somewhere
Pilot you have any any last
Stop parting words we covered a lot I think
No that is very very Sound Advice
I will say one thing
This is an extremely paranoid thing and this is definitely not advise that 99% of people
Will take but turns out Lyft will still work Google Maps will still work if you have your location
Services off
You just have to manually
Type in the address
And also there
Plenty of ways
I'm outside of accessing your GPS
That
An application
Can ascertain Where You Are
There's a really really cool site
And project called wigle.net which associate
Physical locations on Earth with IP addresses
So you know what I mean that there's more than one way to
Just kidding cat
Since when
All
Traveling Industries holidays
Maybe don't
Dumb tweets
About where you're going if you don't want the whole internet to know
Maybe don't post a picture of your vacation if you don't want the whole International
You know I like
I go back to the original question or one of your first question
Which was my trip to Max
The code for the Kaspersky conference
You know if I was going to Mexico for vacation I would
Take different precautions then
If I was going to Mexico
Comfort security
So think about that like
You know when I went to Mexico for that conference
Jason knew that I was going my family that I was going
And probably didn't renew because I registered online but
If I'm going to have
Personal
Maybe I want to like tweets from the airport or you know
Think about that life
Intel Twitter
Basically public
Facebook
Is anybody can be
Just think about that
I think Cindy screenshotted and shared elsewhere even if
Even if you have your
Privacy
Private art
Friends only
Thank you guys for coming
This is the audio version of the motherboard guy's not getting hacked
Abridged the whole version is up on motherboard. Vice.com
I can Finance you Google it
We've updated it now three times
I walked it again next year or
Next time we need to make
A massive change because
All the stuff is always in flux
It's always changing depending on different threats in a syringe
Thank you very very much
This week's episode was produced by me Jason Keppler
Record by Mitch rackin
It was edited by Dean White
Thanks for listening to cyber will be back next week
In the meantime please tell your friends about us and consider giving us a review on Apple podcast