Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered imagine
Update your computer
Channel
Well that's exactly what happened last year just thousands of people
Cybersecurity pros of The Perils of so-called supply chain attacks
Any types of attacks hackers compromise a computer's Hardware at the fact
War poison a software update from a manufacturer
Tricking victims into installing malware
Last week motherboard contributor Kim zetter revealed one of the largest and scariest
Supply chain hacks in recent memory
Hackers broke into the servers
Taiwanese computer maker
Asus
Didn't push an update
Thousand people
Kaspersky lab researchers
Attack around half-a-million Windows computers
Received the update
The hackers only targeted
About 600 so sister
It's not the first and won't be the last pack of this
Time
Can I ask you today
With us to talk about this Brazen supply chain attack
Attack
Have a ball
In the last few years
I've been McCoo and this is cyber
Very important question
Aces to Aces
I don't know
Beautiful scenery will go with a C
Let's talk about this cuz it's you know
A supply chain attack
By Nation
Those don't happen very often
No they don't
Just because of the nature of them
In this case you know they're tricking the software update
And to install the malware on customers laptop and they also signed it with
The attackers have also signed it with legitimate Asus
Digital certificate so it
It looks completely authentic
How to use a receiving it
And how many people did this
The fact
Well Kaspersky lab researchers were the ones who
Discovered this and they said that at least
$57,000 of their customers got infect
But that's only you know what they can see
And so you have to sort of extrapolate that to other AV companies
And other
Asus customers who maybe don't have
Antivirus software
And
Under that estimate
Kaspersky thinks that probably half a million Fest
Avesis got infected
I spoke with semantics in and at least 13,000 of their customer
Rolfing
It's already at that point we're up to 70,000 that we know of
Xiomara second here
And just
Why do you explain to me what
Supply chain attack is
Visa V Nation
Can States win their
So supply chain Attack Just refers to an attack that happens
Usually it is referring something is happening during
Manufacturing stage
Or assembly stage
Or we called interdiction
Whereas
Equipment is being shipped out to a customer
Someone like the NSA
Or the
CIA or someone else
Will intercept it
From FedEx
UPS
And then do their manipulation and then send it on its way
I'm so those are the ways that we know friends at the end of season
Or you can get either.
Famous Bloomberg story
About the manufacturing plant in China
Or Taiwan that was
Inserting malicious
Does Chip supposedly
Inserting a militia
Chip on the motherboard
So those are the ways that we traditionally think of
Supply chain
Haven't even better way is
To do with the way that
This happened with the Asus
Which is
To hijack that trusted Channel
For updating software on the customer
Where's machine
And it's not even something where you have to actually
Physically plant something inside of a machine
You're actually
Doing advice internet
Is a lot easier in that sense
But it you know your ear
It's should be harder because you're trusting
That those manufacturers you know that they
And interactions with a lot of
Customers and is it supposed to be at rest a channel
You have this assumption that those
Vendors are protecting their Network
Better than the average net
Certainly you're hoping that Microsoft
An apple and all of those update networks are doubly so
Secure
But this Asus example shows us that if an attacker can get into that too
Why shouldn't they be able to get into that too
System in the same way
That other people get in
Phishing attacks
Something like that
Signing server
So they're on a server where Asus was signing it smell wear with it
It's legitimate digit
Certificate
And so those signing servers should be better protected
So Asus
A Taiwanese
Computer cam
Is hacking a very
Sophisticated
Spectacular
Supply chain attack
What's the going
Who
Who did it yeah
I have some
Suspicions
Yes I was probably the Chinese
Kaspersky has tied the attack
Potentially
Tooele group
Previously known as The Shadow pads
Crew
Who had attacked South Korean company
And then
Supply chain attacks
And also tie them to an attack of
In 2017
I wish we that we know of
We know of as CCleaner
CCleaner was
Security software
Someone got into the
Supply chain are the Deliverance mechanism for
Updating. C cleaner tool
And those attacks are believed to be attributed to Chinese
Packers
This is what this is what was interesting
The researchers think that the actual
Asus
Intrusion into its Network
Came through CCleaner
So CCleaner when it was infecting C
Distance also was targeting an infected a lot of systems
But it was also it had had targeted list
And on that targeted list was
At least two Asus computers
But as I started to Asus
Computers inside AC
Asus Network
Computers
And so it's possible that the attackers use CCleaner initially
To get into the Asus Network
And then set up their attacks reviews
Network event info
Heather's
Not that I'm suspicious of wanting a nation-state wanting to
Have access to a wide array of
Say 70000
Who knows what's on the
Computers but why
What do you think
Happened
What were they target
They were targeting
They were infecting about half-a-million systems
Estimated but
They only appears we targeting about 600 of those in the how do we know that
Because in the malware files that Kaspersky
Collected from customers machines
Hard-coded into those files
Were 600 hashes
And the cracks those hashes cryptographic hashes
And those cryptographic ashes were actually
Unique Mac addresses
For specifics
Tim said they were targeting
And so what would happen is the malware
That came through the Asus Network you would get onto
A customer's machine
And it would immediately look for the MAC address on that machine the MAC address for the network
On that machine
And and they would hash you would hash that Network
That Mac address
And if the hash on the MAC address on that
And I'm users machine
Match one of those Mac addresses
Hashed in the
Did hackers malware
They knew they had a targeted machine
And they would instruct that machine then
To reach out to the internet
Two website at the attacker
Controlled and to download a further back door onto those
600 machine
And we don't know who those 600 people were
And we don't know
Exactly how the attackers
The Mac addresses of those
Machines
So you're saying is
Is this kind of a case of
The 70000 people were affected by this
Only targeting 600 people
It's kind of wild that
An update
That was for thousands of
The people
Add a few
Thousands of people were kind of caught up in this nation state hack
I'm using the name that the Kaspersky gave its shadow Hammer is quite apps you know there using this method hammer
Infecting
Kaspersky says
Half a million probably
Using this
Massive hammer
Half of my existence
When really only they wanted was
Is there any idea is to
Food OC
600 computers belong to
No but I mean Asus said in there
Statement there
Find me whenever
They released
Statement said that they
Starting to contact customers and so
Does that mean they know who those 600 customers are
And they are contacting those people or or what it's a little unclear
So
Yeah that's a little bit of a mystery
Interesting
I mean I guess I'm thinking to myself like who uses Asus
Computers
I like I think I had one when I would like
Like I was
I really
Chord
University student
Targeting the Windows computers
They making a systems that are
For home
Security systems
Things like that laptop system
So
You know a lot of computers that considered I think the fourth or fifth largest
Computer maker in the world
There are government agencies that are probably using Asus computers
CertainTeed Corporation
You know it's pretty widespread
Yeah I mean
Clearly if there were willing to
Do this attack there must have been some
Some reason for it
Especially
Given China's sort of
Intent on trying to hack as many people as they can in order to get
Tardis information
Yeah and also interesting that the command-and-control server had already been closed down
By the time Kaspersky discovered this in January
So they were pushing out the malware through the Asus server
Between June and November
And those 600 targeted machines then we're contacting this
Command and control server
I'm only until November so either
They got all the machines that they needed to get by November
Something caused them to shut down the program
November
But that's
That's awesome
Sting is weather
All of those 600 computers actually got hit
And then got that second
Can a back door download
You're going to struck me about this is
Just as similar to some of
Some of the Snowden
Leeks
Like you mentioned earlier interdiction how do you say you know
Intercept some of these devices and plant stuff inside of them
Hacking someone's router update
That's always something I've known that the NSA is done they get ahold of his
System and
They asked you to install an update and really your
You're downloading
The payload
Is the malware that's going to be able
Go to track
Your device
Well that's different is there targeting you right so you let say you're in a hotel right and you're on the Wi-Fi
And suddenly you get this pop up saying that you have
A new update waiting for you right
So that could be someone on the hospital Network that has initiated this pop up on your machine
And it takes you if you click on it it takes you to malicious server and you get malware downloaded
So that's something targeted right but if you're talking about getting into the vendors
Update system that's pretty bold and brave
And we've only seen this the first time that we saw it
And it actually wasn't even specifically this case
But the first time we saw it was with the flame
Spyware tool
Which we believe was created by the same people some of the same people
Probably Israel
And in this case they didn't ask
Get into the Microsoft
Server
But what they did was they tricked Microsoft
Into issuing them
A legitimate Microsoft digital
And then instead of
Subverting the Microsoft server
To deliver mail worth from Microsoft server what they did was if they were already on a network
They would redirect any computers on that local network
They would redirect that update tool on those
Computers
2 militia server
But they control so anytime that up that Microsoft update tool
Was initiating
Transaction to reach out to the Microsoft server
To see if there are software updates
The malware on that Network would
Intercept
That communication
And redirected to a malicious server that the sauce
That the attackers control
And then they would get a malicious file downloaded
Extend that appeared to come
From the micro
Server
So
So that's the only known case
That we have in the wild
Nation state
Intelligence agency
In the West
Using that tool and I don't believe that that was the US I believe it.
Probably is
What can
You know regular
Consumers do
To kind of avoid that avoided not being caught up
Not a whole lot I mean that's the nation-state attackers are good at this right they do a lot of planning
And they're smart about the ways that they do it
I'm getting a digital certificate I mean that they're taking all the boxes right there taking all the Box
Because of your trust
It's coming from legitimate server
It's digitally signed
So it's funny though that there was a
There were some early signs about that this was malicious
All right about this in the story a link to a Reddit for him
Back in June 2018 where
Sam Aces customers
We're discussing this I mod
Alert that they were getting on their computers
To download this update
And they were suspicious about the f
But they said there's a
Suspicions
By the fact that
It was
Digitally signed
I with a legitimate certificate
And also when they uploaded the malicious
This file to virustotal
See if any antivirus program
Detected is malicious
It came out clean
So all those boxes
You know that you
Utech
In order to check whether something is trustworthy
Passed the test
And with the Fallout been for AC
I mean today
This must not have been great there stock
I know it's Oasis has been in trouble before over its Security in 2016 the FDA
DC
File some charges and complaints against it
Embalmer abilities with iCloud updating and it
It's also a software updating tool at that time
Cases have been notified by customers
But they had a problem
And sat on it for a year
Before
Lee addressing it
And then notifying effect
Users
And so it is
Tftc
In an agreement that it would establish
Security
And auditing program that would that would be subject to Independent audit for 20 years
So I don't know
You know how that auditing is implemented but it
Taylor lee Wesson
Catching this
And so Asus responded them finally when it did come out with them
Response
Said that it was releasing a patch which is ironic right because it's asking customers
Hey if you think you got malware on your C
System updated with this update your system with this new patch
This new software update that we're giving
And trust it
Now really trust it
So they've also said that they've implemented
Some extra security on their servers so that it can
Can't happen again
But again charged previously
DC
And this happened after that
So I'm not sure that
There's a reason to believe that any
New implementations
To secure their Network
Can be trusted
As I said I think I had one in like 2010
And
Not even because I wed weird internet habit
But within two months that thing was like
An infection
It's like
Like pot I would just open it up there be pop-up well that's just you
That your
I don't know
I didn't really have much at that point
A lot of bad English literature papers
Do you think this is actually going to
I just make people little bit
Insecure
Quick yes to that update that pops up on there
Computer
Yes I think that I said that's a dangerous Matt Blaze
Professor at Georgetown
Has a great opinion piece in the New York Times this morning about the
Stephanie's concerned
That the greater risk here is
That people will stop
Trust the software updating tools
And not update their system
The vast majority of
Are valid updates
Secure update
And just because
In this one road case and maybe a handful of others
If those turn out not to be legitimate is not a reason for people
To just leave there's a
Systems wide open to attack by not
Catching them and updating them
And I have to agree with him on that I mean I hope
Fat people
Won't completely mistrust but I think it's it for the security Community it does it's a red flag right we have to come up with
Better mechanisms for
Securing the distrusted Channel
Two users
And also finding better ways
To verify
That these
Software updates being delivered to us are legitimate
I mean and also a kind of no shade to Asus but
To me it sort of
He pays to get a
A better product that's more trusted because they will be secure in their
Veteran
It'll be harder for
Go system to be hijacked by say China
I don't know I I'm I'm reluctant to
Phrase one company or or denigrate one company over in another
If we go back a few years I don't know if you remember Adobe
Many years back I don't know maybe 2009 or later
Attackers have gotten into their signing server as well
And they weren't they weren't delivering
Malware from the Adobe
Server
But they obtained
Certificate
And we're signing their malware with a
Legitimate Adobe
Certificate
I think ultimately this can happen to anyone
Maybe
Assuming that apple and Microsoft are bar more secure we hope that they are
But still named companies like Adobe and others
Deliver important software
Can be struck in this way
That's a good ending play right there a little Doom and Gloom
Text Kim
Lorenzo franceschi
If you like the show give us a review on Apple podcast
What time your friends about us we back with more next week