Virus
Eagle One
Packaged
In Spring 2017 teenager walk behind a woman reading the metro in Northeast Washington DC
Put on a choke hold
Be quiet
He said delete your iCloud
Grab her iPhone 6s
And ran away
The iCloud security feature a cut down on the number of iPhones
Ways to remove iCloud
The fish the phone's original owners
Or scam employees at Apple stores
Deeds coders and hackers participate in an underground industry
My phone said they can then resell the
Hundreds of millions of us
Use find my iPhone
Find her phone
When it's just lost in the couch or maybe left at Starbucks
It's been stolen
And now with activation lock
Turn off
Find my iPhone
They will not be able to reactivate it
Because they don't know your iCloud username motherboard editor-in-chief Jason Cavalier Inn
Senior staff writer Joseph Cox
But the last few months diving into the notably complicated world of
ICloud unlock
In the ways in which involves not only physical and cyber crime
But also the otherwise legitimate independent
IPhone repair
I've been a coup
This is cyber
Spent the last few months working on this investigation about the underground world of iCloud
Packers and Unlocker
And robbers and how it all relates to the repair industry
I want to start here by talking about
How the iPhone has changed
How
Petty criminals
Steel phones
Yeah so when
Afifa gum drop someone off the rifle
Just worried about the pinto
When will go
Two cases of
Steve's domondon
Then the victim removes iCloud
From the
People Tennessee complaints
Behind I mean this
Security mechanism
Is actually having
Dim sum
Tangible physical consequences on how feves
Actually trying
Right so I think most people would agree that
This is a pretty good
Technological security measure in aggregate
Yunnan
You want to make sure that iPhones are not worth
$1,000 if they're getting stolen
But like you said
You know these are still taking them
So just to be clear I mean this has changed the behavior criminals but if you go back even further I mean 10 years ago
If you had an iPhone and someone took it
Naked Juice
Sell it on the black market no problem and move on with their lives
To sell what are these
Pacific
Security measures that were talking about
Right
So yeah apple introduced
Something cool
Which is not
The PIN code to use for access your phone
It is the surface features is
Tonight would win
Email login to iCloud and say hey my
Stolen or lost
Batman kicks in
Activation
Anybody can find
Cancel device, Justin French
I'm without you
ICloud
Password and email address
Essentially
Expensive
Any fees they need that
To be able to actually
Remove stains from ants
Wipe the phones then someone else
Can you use a
Securely
I technically
Security measure and it has impacted how
Eaves to operate
Install
Necessarily
Even though
Criminal just going to change
Bedtime
Sing with this Market
Embarrassed
Epsom
Increase by
Activation lock
Right and I think the specifics here are important to
Explain just because there is a lot
To the speakers
Various different types of locks
Like you said it's not the PIN code
I it is the iCloud password which is
Basically your Apple account ID the one that you use to log into the App Store
Or iTunes for instance
And what happens why is it such a big deal is
If you reset the phone and sell it
And iCloud lock is still on there
You can't
Associated with a different Apple ID
So you need the person's original password in order to
Need to turn the phone on do anything with it you also need it to download apps
Azure use iTunes
And
This is very important when your resetting your phone or if your
Stealing a phone because
You need to be able to disassociated with
The original owners account
Andre associated with the new owners
Yeah I mean when you doing
Accentuate
You stole them
Actually
This phone is linked to North Harbor Town
What's the process
Even though
Define believe that
Access headless
Right so a criminal will steal a phone and then if they don't
You know hold up someone at gunpoint and ask them to remove iCloud lock
They are then stuck with a phone that is a brick
Bye
It's still obviously a inexpensive piece of electronics
And criminals have figured
Hey I'll just steal this phone and hopefully I'll be able to figure out a way to remove iCloud
And then they have you know a very valuable device
So what do they do
Like because criminals have found ways around this
Right yeah so
Even when the criminal has the phone
They main offices.
The target to remove iCloud themselves I still want to get up
To do this next
Play some souls or they can they provide the siren
To someone else
You could probably do on their behalf
But the next stage is that going to try to fish
The iCloud
Impossible
Akame trying to get someone
Gmail password
What's the credentials or anything like that
It's essentially the same
Process
Cottage industry
All professional fishes
You just spend all day every day
Trying to steal people's
Lights out
Apostle
62 storms Avenue
Very highly
Customized fishing kit
Switch
Show me where the phone is
Make people sick
Make a send text messages
We should had to come from a fool sayings
A please
Skated
Fishing kits
On the planet I mean they're not bypassing two-factor Authentication
But they do appear to be
Which is
Lower the barrier of Entry
To these relatively low-level
He's no Russian
It's still streams line
Process
If it was unnecessary
I've known about this problem for a
Q years because I come across
A group of people who want to unlock iCloud locked devices all the time which I'll talk about in a second
But I'm curious
How did you come across this how long have you been monitoring these groups and where did you find them
I think somebody started working
Gemelli
Find out how
Fishing kits
Is it more research on identifying
Particular groups that use
These fishing kits
Avenged I just managed to
Infiltrate a sweet tooth
Telegram
Chat room
Wishes you know
Just say
The group Chats on the messaging app and this is why
A lot of the actors were exchanging
Tips
I'm asking people for advice
Uploading photos is that successful unlock
A
Nexus stolen phone when where am I going to
Jets
The password and how can I get about that
Basically like it's clearing house
When you are my son gets
Stolen
I miss a good chance it could end up in one of these traps
20 more as well
This is why
I was in there for
I think
Intitle before I go
Rostra
Congratulated us for sitting in his chat room so long
Yeah it
East it was just sitting there and trying to absorb what they were
What they were doing because of course
I-17 ology wilderun lingo
Weekly
How to reverse engineer
Figure out how they were actually getting information on phones and how they would actually look
Right so so far this is a pretty interesting story and that it's got this melding of
Physical crime and cybercrime But ultimately the hacking involved is not
Terribly interesting it's you know as you said
Custom fishing kits
Sally seen it a million times before with a bunch of other types of hacks
So there are a lot of interesting wrinkle to this one of which is when you try to reset an iPhone it will say
Please enter iCloud password and then I will have
An email address but it will only show the first letter and the last letter of the email address and then in between it will have a bunch of
Asterisk
So presumably these
BDubs Fishers don't really know
Any of the information about the phone that they're trying to look up or the or the person's account so how did I get this
Yeah it seems like a hog problem but there are a lot of
Stop thief could find out
Information
I mean Festival when is a stolen phone
It will say on it hey please call me on this number cuz this phone is stolen oversleeping
With these fishing kits
Incendies
Convincing the victim
Please go ahead and log in with your iCloud email address and password
Email address
Potential
Of course you could also do social media stalking and some other research as well to find it but it's
Messages
Seem to be one
The main ways
To find out who these people actually have to talk it when they got hold of her stolen time
Right but we also found these look up tools online that have
You know at least some information about
The phones
Neo specs
And when it was
Just purchased and stuff like that which comes in handy
When you're trying to do this other method of
Unlocking an iCloud locked iPhone
So that that's another reason why I found the story to be very interesting is that
There are other ways to unlock
A phone
It's just you need to get apple to do it for you
And that is a lot more come
Implicated
Psoas
IMEI number
Which is a unique code given to every single phone
Attack on Titan
Into a website
Return with information such as
Hey this is just on the carrier
Campbell's condensed
Fill out a
Receipt
Invoice
Photoshop templates that are online and allow you to enter
Whatever you want and make it look like
Stereo receiver
Yeah yeah yeah
Acrylic paint by number
Hey is
Is a
It's a ready-made template the look
Looks really legit
You just have to
Listen to the information you found about the phone
Take it in
And it should match
Hopefully be enough.
Convince someone
Specifically we found genius manager
Would be after that remove
Be like that
What is 2 using these tools
Which are being utilized
Right so it's this social engineering that's happening at physical Apple
Stores
And
Presumably this happens we know that Apple Managers can request an unlock
And we also know that Apple can
I do it remotely because you had some emails from Apple
From that
Hacking group.
Don't mention that
They can do remotely
Yes I do
Yeah she said you may need to go into an Apple Store into it physically
Recipe for Machop
Gmail
And say hey
I'm stuck
Looked at my phone here
Invoice
Unlocked like that which
Seems like probably an easy way to do it Robin having
Courage Julio.
Cigar International store
And do it in person
You can just do it for email
Screenshots of emails
People posting
The Shining
Right so in my reporting I heard over and over again that this does happen that
People go to the Apple Store
We have internal documents from Havel that show that a manager can request an unlock
But I also heard from multiple people that
If you get caught it's very bad like
Beetle
You can probably convince a lot of
Managers are geniuses to do this for you if you pretend to be
You know someone who
Happened to forget their password
But if they see you coming to store over and over again and you get the same manager they're going to know something is up and you're going to be blackballed in some
Amway
Whitby I mean I suppose it's
East Summit approves you with an University selling subwoofer
Used.
Persecution around it
Do not move
Something else
I like crying
Even though as well speak about
This industry does intersect with no legitimate
Wright's repair
IPhone signs
Deciduous topre Donnelly
Yeah it is I talked to someone who study this quite a lot
And he told me you know not every iCloud lock iPhone is illegally obtained but
Every method for unlocking it is currently illegal
And I think it's now a good time to talk about
Who is actually trying to unlock iPhones Beyond thieves
Just because it's at
It's pretty interesting
So I came across this story or at least
Piqued my interest about a year ago
I'm in a lot of right to repair face
Facebook groups and
The right to repair is Basu this political movement of Independence
Irepair folks
Sort of like the corner store that will replace your iPhone screen
Or the
Random person who will fix a John Deere tractor but is not authorized by John Deere to fit
Fix a tractor
Who is
Fighting at the moment
Better access to
Parts
Tools diagnostic information
Etcetera
Because
All across the electronics world
Take manufacturers like apple and Microsoft John Deere IBM Etc
AR
Trying to lock down
The ability for end-users as well as independent repair people to fix
The things that they normally own
And apple is
Notoriously bad at this
They have been sore blobbing against
Legislation at every turn
I in Norway.
Sued a guy who
I bought aftermarket
Get parts from China and Apalachee lost that case
In the United States they worked with AIDS
Department of Homeland Security
Security to
Prevent aftermarket and third-party parts from reaching independent repair people
And so
There's basically this apple versus the independent repair World mindset going on and
This is where
Locked iPhones come in
Because
Not every single iCloud locked iPhone is stolen
When
Someone breaks their phone or when someone doesn't upgrade for their phone from T-Mobile
Or Verizon
Sprint
They will take it back
Tula carrier
And someone at the
The carrier is supposed
To say
Hey can you please remove your iCloud
From that so that we can refurbish it and resell it
That happens most of the time
But not always
Often these phones
Person the customer service person forgets to remove the iCloud or ask their customer to remove the iCloud
And then it becomes a brick and suddenly Verizon has
As a brick a phone
So what they do is they sell these phones in bulk at
Carrier auctions
What are called
And people in the iPhone repair industry by them
They buy them in bulk
I've talked to
About a dozen
You know people who own iPhone repair shops
What's this point they say
That they came across you know
ICloud locked
IPhone
All the time
So
There are all these out there on the market but there's nothing
To happen
There's nothing happening with them
So there's some people in this world who are stripping them for parts
They're able to take like
Take the back camera or
The volume buttons are they charging port and put it onto a consumer's
You know otherwise unrepairable phone
And this is how they get their parts because Apple won't sell them
And so
There's naturally a lot of these people who
Have you
Dozens or hundreds of iCloud locked iPhones
And they think
Rather than stripping is for parts
Why don't I figure out how
How to unlock
Yeah let me know
Is sort of like an uncomfortable
Alliance
Is between the small legitimate side and then is cool
The highly legal really really shady
I can
Supply chain like these two
These two sorts of Industries would never really meet
If it wasn't for
Decision
What do people kids
Skip Hop
Right yeah I spoke to you know dozens of people and
A lot of them are like
I won't buy iCloud locked devices from people who walk into my
I store because there's a good chance that it's
Stolen
But if I'm buying it at a carrier auction I know that it came from T-Mobile or Sprint or what have you asked
Sheri on some of these insurance companies
And
They didn't have a phone they legally own but that they are unable to unlock
And so if they buy a phone for yunnan
Two hundred bucks
They can part it out
You know
Sell the various parts in make
Got a couple hundred dollars or they can get iCloud removed and resell that phone as refurbished
Stan Getz
Six seven eight hundred dollars
So for them it's a lot less work and it's a lot more lucrative if they're able to remove iCloud
So there are people I mean I talked to a lot of people in the industry most of them said that they don't deal with iCloud
Unlocking
But there are people who both
Do this in person scamming where they will go to the Apple Store and ask for an iCloud unlock and then there's also
Also people who use the services that just
Was talking about earlier
Yes I do
She say when
You have this very very strange crossover between the people who need to
Unlock the iCloud phone just because
And then you have people who
Holding
Marriage
Between these two
It is and most people seem to be very uncomfortable with this the Facebook group I was mentioning where I first learn
Learned about this
You know they have posts
From people asking like hey do you do iCloud unlock
Do you know how to do iCloud unlock
Every single week I've been in that group for
Years at this point in time
I seen it over and over again
It's gotten to the point where
The more legitimate side the people who are like I don't want to touch this
Is that all
Say we shouldn't have this in our group at all
We need to ban this
This sort of
Behavior we need to ban people asking for this
Just because
It's going to make us look
Illegitimate
And there's one guy who's very prominently involved in the right to repair movement his name is Michael oberdick
She is
The owner of I Outlet which is
Store in Ohio or a series of stores
And he sort of went
To YouTube
And posted this
I guess you would call her rants
Basically saying that
People in the industry need to
Clean up
Because they're never going to get legislation passed
If there is the
Is perception
That they are
Working with hackers and
Shadyside
Industry
How am I supposed
Set a border in the boardroom in a room with a senator of a state
Fight for the right to repair
And say
Yes we reserve the right to the parts of digoxin
Tools
All the things that we need from these manufacturers when we've got people
Is a business model
I'm sorry but you're the reason why
We can't get ship pass
You're the reason why
We can't get contracts that we need
You are the reason the industry is looked at as a
Ugly stepchild
Knock it off
And I really think that Michael is right here because I've covered this
Political movement for quite some time and apples arguments
Gangsta
Are that you know these people are breaking our terms of service fees
These people
Cannot be trusted if we sort of give them better access to our tools they will take advantage of them and
Will you
Become conduits for hackers and thieves and and stuff like that so
I think that the movement really does need to weed out people who are working
With hackers to remove iCloud
But they are in a really tough situation because
They can't get parts any other way
They've often acquired these phones legally and they have no options from
Apple Jacks
Remove them
So I talked
To a couple people and they suggested
You know maybe activation lock should only go
Phone has been reported as
Is lost or stolen
I don't know if that work from apples and
Apple didn't really want to talk to us for
The story
But it is the sort of like weird underbelly the industry
And
And a weird melding of both cybercrime and real life
Crime as well as the Grand Marquis
Right
How to repair
So we publish this story last week and
I think the response was
Sort of instantaneous wasn't it just
Yeah I mean usually also we publish
A piece that people interested in a few emails about oh that's cool
Quite a few different people reaching out
Simply saying
Hey can you help me
Remove iCloud from iPhone
You shut down
At least this time I would let you like did you even read the peace
But it literally
How it goes down
Clearly
Ya love interest
People try to find out how to unlock
Yeah and there's one method that we didn't really mention or go into detail on and it's really crazy and I don't know all this
Specific so maybe it's something for another
Marquis
But
There are refurbishing factories in China
That will basically
Take off a little chip
On the motherboard so they use a microscope and
Tweezers and takeoff
The CPU
And then they are reflashing the CPU on a chip reprogrammer
And putting that ship back on the board which requires desoldering and all this stuff is it's very Time and Labor until
And save and afterwards
They basically have a device that is iCloud unlocked because they are
Essentially creating a new device
Buy flashing
A new IMEI
Hi number to it
And that's just the whole nother level that we didn't really get into but I heard of
A few times
And folks in the repair world are like
I just
I can't even fathom
Having enough time to do that but it is happening and
There's YouTube video of it it's very wild we'll put it in the show notes
The wild world of iCloud
IPhone unlocking
We will have another follow-up to Ed sometime if we can ever figure out that China
Story
Just if I want to do a quick update to a story that was on this podcast
A few weeks ago
We basically spent
$300 to find location data from a phone that we asked to be tracked by a bounty hunter
In the meantime you've done an entirely new investigation
That is a very similar but different thing
Regarding location data and bouncy
So can you give us a quick update
Yeah and the original piece it was one cup
CNN we
Where is England
Instances buying
On the Block
Case
Are we going to 10:00
Shine another company was selling to around 250
Hunter's bail agent
Things to Independence
It confirms that some of those also selling the black
Scale
And the new investigation
Cell tower
Mattel toys of Elsa being selling
GPS
Which is highly precise
I'm usually only reserved
Investigation is on motherboard. Vice.com
I don't think we'll do another episode about it but definitely worth your read
I just have thanks as always for joining us and we'll throw it back to bed
This week's episode was produced by Jason kabler
Recorded by Gene White
I'm that nakuu
If you live in or around Brooklyn cyber will be doing a live episode
On March 2nd
At the on-air Fest at the Wythe hotel
For more information about the show
Check out on your face
Dot-com
Come hang out
Thanks for listening to cyber will be back next week