Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered everybody's concerned with out of the end
Turn basement or whatever president called it
Or the scary hooded mr. robot figure messing with their Smart Home
Those pesky Russian hackers destroying democracy one thing the hacking scene doesn't always consider
Is the real world pentesting hackers
It's kind of OG involves social engineering
Sometimes their stories in their human skills May building individuals are not only hilarious
Expose the biggest flaw in the corporations or agencies are hard to improve
People
Today we're talking to someone who calls themselves Jack
Do the physical pen tester and also brags about breaking into building
I've been a coup in this
Decipher
Tell me it's
Jack for like dr. Jekyll and mr. Hyde Wright
Something to
Yeah that's correct it was a name given to me that's what's the beginning of my
FSI career
It was a
A friend of mine Tinker Psych
Was commenting on how
Adorable and sweet I appear in normal everyday life and then how vicious and scary I can be
You and I when I turn on my bad guy face
That is like your Jekyll and Hyde so that we can my Twitter handle
Okay so
Just to be clear
You call yourself a physical pain
Correct
Correct for the most part yeah
And what is a physical pain test
So a physical penetration tester is somebody who
Pretends to be a bad guy depending on what the organization or the company is real
Really worried about we could pretend to be burglars after physical assets inside the building
Or week
You could pretend to be
Hackers after technical asset
What's inside of a facility
And so what
Nitrogen testers do in general is they
Actually
Bear hackers you hear about
The target haxton's the the Home Depot hacks in like all of those had
A criminal
Mind or criminal organization behind it and that's what we do is we pretend to be those Criminal
We actually work
For these
Company is so we're trusted insiders basically who
Break in or hack into
The
The technical side
And we try to steal all this information but in
Instead of
Turning around and selling it on the dark web or something
We
Take it all back 2
Their security team or The Blue Team
Our management and we say this is everything we got access
This is how we got access to it
And this is how
You can start fixing
The holes in the vulnerabilities in your
So
I might
Go in and find that these places have
Really
Pickable locks and no alarm system
And so
In that case I might piano
Be able to pick the lock and get into
Facility in the middle of the night
So I mean this is
This is really like it
Old school hack
Aspect back to its over this OG hack
I would prefer to think of it that way.
Okay so I am
Law abiding citizen you are as well
Help
How
Did you learn
The skills how did you get into this
Because I know some physical pain
Shirt
So I I got into it and I really
Interesting way I was originally
Studying to be in journalism I worked for a radio station for a while helping to
Mapreduce
Chosen
Doing things like setting up
Energies and things like that so I got to learn to
To talk to people
And be able to make them
Comfortable and what might be an uncle
Situation
And
I also made a lot of friends during this time and
The hacker scene in Dallas which is where I'm from
So
Jack the Bear Brown
It was it was
Such a supportive
Awesome community and
Hi I would go to them for
Technical experts and subject matter experts
Stories
And
There was
A friend of mine who's doing Network penetration testing
And he got to do a physical penetration test
His boss asked him did you want and he was like
I don't know how to play I don't know how to lie to people I don't know the first thing about lock-picking like I'm the wrong person for this job
I'm freaked out by it
And I kind of sick joke
Can I do it for you at like
Lying and sneaking in the middle of the night like that movie
I'm totally down for that
And I was joking but he was like oh my God would you like I can get you on the contract that I bet you my boss with blood
What happened
And
I was just kind of stoned earlier
Okay yeah like if you think that we can make that happen then let's do it and
I don't know I just I I kind of naturally
Spell intuit things like
Things that are
Harder for some people and I don't know if this is something I should be proud of the things like lying
Do not do not
Very difficult
Are not very difficult for me
They coming up with an elaborate ruse and why you should trust me and I'm actually from headquarters
All of this stuff is
It kind of wears off
My tongue very easily and then you know aliases and all of that so
I don't know I think I feel like I was kind of built for it I don't have any special training or anything like that I
I have gone to
Training sense but
Starting out it was it was just
Vista
Me and I I did pretty well at it I think
I don't think you could have done this
Before that were
You know inside
Three-letter agency
Where they at
Absolutely all this stuff happened
I am not unique in any way shape or form like this stuff happens
All of the time and it's not always
Legal it's not always
Ani like a private
Basis they're absolutely folks who do what I do for the government and for other countries
And they do it way better than I do it's just a matter of whether they can talk about it or not and I'm going to bed
Do I ever run into them I do occasionally
And and it's always interesting to be able to
You know kind of share my experiences with them they can't necessarily reciprocate
But it's
It's just a neat little
Any little thing when you're able to
To talk to somebody about
You know what I do with
I haven't had a lot of training and for them to say like yeah you're doing great to know that I'm
I'm kind of operating on a
CIA base
It's kind of cool I don't know if I'd go that far but
But that they can take a look at what I do and say yeah
So you're sexually doing
Whittier High to do at times and this is my understanding of it
Is essential to do corporate espionage
But then bring this information
2 top management and say look this
We got
You don't have to patch
In a certain way and instead of it being you know a lot of code
What's your patching is the human vulnerability
It's either the human vulnerability or physical ones now and I'm the human one was the one that came really naturally to me
To be able to put people off their guard Beauty
Tell a lie or give a pretext that was good enough for them to just kind of dragon say okay that makes sense that was natural for me
The physical side of things
It's something that I've learned over time so now I can assess things like axes
Control systems
And I can go to management and say
Yeah your badge tacky the readers that you're using a really old and they're really easy to hack
Coffee fix
Your you're
This is how you can fix
The security of your parking lot
But that's what
Physical penetration testers and specialist
Do I do is I'm on a red tea
I'm on the Walmart right team and we have a
Group of hackers
That actually
Externally hack into our Network
And try to
Take up things Lake
Personally identifiable information or credit card information
Customers
That customer databases things like that
Do the physical infiltration for them so right now I'm in means
To an end
So if I were an ordinary penetration tester an ordinary physical penetration
Aunt Esther
I would probably start off with Blake
Easiest thing
To take advantage of vide I
And then I kind of work my way up
To the D'Amore
Easier ways
Of being able
To penetrate the building into it to see like we're
Ultimately
Statline
What's where like security was like wait a minute something doesn't make any sense so wide
Slowly get more ridiculous
With
The methods I was using to get in
And
That is really valuable service with all you're doing is testing
Security physical security
But my team needs me to do for them is to break into a facility
And gained access to Lake a and unlocks computer or password threat
Non sticky notes which happens all the time
And I take that access back to them they didn't use it to escalate
Stealing
Really valuable
Information that could
Could possibly be
Used to damage
The company's bottom line or
Okay have you gotten caught
No I haven't but I've been doing this for about
Three and a half years now
And I say that in the lease
Arrogant way I possibly can
Because it's
Chester whites
Sprint problem
And you can talk to almost any physical penetration tester
And they will tell you the same thing that it takes a lot
It is almost
You almost have to try to get caught right now
It's a matter of
Your people not wanting to be rude
People just wanting to go about their day-to-day lives a lot of pee
People are not
Necessarily invested
In the well-being of the
The company
And so even if they do see something suspicious if it's not something
That causes them to feel unsafe they might ignore it
It's very common problem
And I've been
I feel like I've been close
Stew being caught a couple of times
Like right on the edge
Like oh crap this is it this is when I get caught
This is the day and it and it hasn't happened yet
Self
I'm I'm really looking forward to the day I get to tell that story like
Bravo slow clap
You guys finally caught me good job
What's the first thing you do
Before you go to a job do you try to figure out
Movie
Employees are
And you going to social media
Cuz as a journalist
That's probably what I do
Absolutely
So as soon as I know
What
Kind of
Jobs I'm in for
Soon as I have
Like a Target or an address I will immediately first thing I do is go to
Google Earth
I want to look at the building from a bird's-eye view I want to look at clothes
Up as I can on street view
I want to know
What the parking situation
Looks like I want to know what the
Entrances and exits look like
As much as I can gather off of that and then
Yes the very nice
Next thing I do
Is I start
Scouring social media and I spend
Hours
Looking through employee social media pages and I mean it I probably spend
Probably like 40 hours
Peace on each Target looking through
Information on Instagram Facebook Twitter I want to see every
Picture that is ever been posted from this site and so I'll look up current employees past employees
I want to know kind of what the
The office culture is like
I want to know what the badges look like it's a big one
I want to know what the badges look like
Before I get on site if I absolutely can
I typically don't have a ton of time
Actually
In the vicinity of these
Target site
So I will have may be anywhere between
214 days
If I'm lucky
Time
It's a matter of
Money really is what it comes down to and this is pretty standard
You can talk to most physical penetration testers I think and they would tell you the same thing
Is that companies
I have a hard time affording
For you to not only fly out to
Wherever the site is
But also put you up in a hotel and give you per diem for food
If I'm if I'm being realistic like if I'm targeting
Something like a distribution center I want to spend a couple months
At the very least
Watching just sitting and watching and seeing things like when the cleaning crew comes and
You know is there an overnight shift what is the the security guard rotation looks like there's a lot
Lidopro question
That I need to answer in order to get a realistic idea
Of what I'm going to be up against when I do finally go in
But we don't have that kind of
Most companies don't have that kind of funding
To put up
Pastor out for
Weeks or months
So we'd have a much smaller window of time to work with
Are you working constantly or is it for like a contractual basis
I swear it's like
You'll get out you got a contract
And then you'll work literally
Play two weeks straight
And then your off
Back about your and you're
Four months ago or so I was a contractor
I've since been taken onto the internal Walmart team and
Contractor it was
Much longer periods of time between
Assignments
So I would work for a week
Or two and then I'd be off for like a month and a half and then I work
For 4 days and then I have a week off and then let your wisdom. That's kind of the way
The contractor life
Work
But
For me now it's much more heavy taste
I am almost constantly on the road
It's got its pros and cons
For sure
I love it and
So you spent a lot of time in Walmart
Spending a lot of time in Walmart
Thankfully we're all over the world and I am never ever bored
Well I'm glad that you're
Spending time in Walmart
For me
You're welcome I'll take the bullet for thank you
I appreciate it
Say who you were
4 or 10
Can you give me an idea of
The types of places he worked for
So
I have
Broken into
Buildings ranging from Lake
Ordinary
Stores like
Storefront places where it's just
You know a couple employees who are
Dare to manage sales
Manufacturing facilities lots of Office Buildings
Data Center
Data centers on occasion
Distribution centers
The range could
Not be much wider
Probably the one thing I haven't done is
State government
Type of facilities and Military
Facilities
And I'm not exactly in a big hurry to make that happen
Different word for let's say like in our universe
Broken into an arms
Look at Lockheed Martin
No
No no no no
Pen tattoos that go into those
Tattoo places in
They dragged out you know that you like
Sweep
And they they dragged out all these
Different devices
Hooked up and
They broken in
In two places they should
Bourbon allowed in
Side of
Yeah absolutely about. Stye mean
That happens all the time
I haven't personally
Done anything
About
Holabird but I know people who has
And it's
It is really interesting
It's really interesting work I know
You know there are people out there who
Beijing Airport
And I thought
I've broken into some facilities that have armed guards
But nothing like government contract worker
Can I get this
This question a lot as well in a lot of journalists do
Like tell me your craziest story or one of The Crazy Ones
You thought of where
You know either you saw it
How the hell
More
Oh gosh
So
There are a couple of them
Probably the very first one was
Was one of
The bastard went it was one of my first
I was just really nervous I had very little experience
And
I did a little bit of
Reconnaissance and found out that the building was
Just kind of it was it was really dizzy and
I I was like I don't think I really want to
I don't think I would want to work here
I cannot wait that just looks like a prison
And so
I think maybe I could
Use that so like overnight I created this
Website for an Architecture Firm and I had
I had business cards printed out with like an alias
With the spark
Architecture Firm on it
And I called in the next day
Aaron's
Bianca
I found this Target online
Who had just this really incredible social media presence
Once and did a lot of volunteer work
With that
With like maternity
Services in New Moms
So I called her up
She worked with HR I think
Calder up
When I said hey I just wanted to let you know that you know we're doing some remodeling of of our facilities and we've got
Architects coming at the
Is interior designer coming out from
CNA lower San Bernardino I can't remember
She's going to be coming out to us
Facility
If you could just like bring her in and let her look around and ask questions
And at that point all I wanted to do was bring my laptop in
Plug into their Network and running in my skin like that was the end goal
If I could prove that I could get on their Network
And have access to the machines
Stop
That was the goal
And she was a little bit confused she was like but
What is the reason for the timing if this like normally I get
Heads up if somebody
He's coming in from out of town
And I was calling pretending like I was from their headquarters
And so I just started Lake
Breaking down a little bit
Looks like
You're right
I'm really sorry
Kind of on me
I was told to do this
A couple weeks ago but I've had a lot on my mind
Because
I am
7 months pregnant and I'm having some
Health issues
Immediately like her tone change
Turn like a little bit of Suspicion to understand cold-blooded
It's pretty awful but this is the
Stuff that like
I I hate
Saying that I don't have a conscience cuz they do and I do feel bad when
When bad things happen to good people
But if I'm pretending
To be a bad guy ultimately
My goal is to tell these
Stories and to protect people from this happening to them
So it's it's not as bad when I look at it through that perspective
She just immediately started like wanting to Mother me and
And take care of everything so that I had this
I was like if my boss finds out I messed up on this Lake
I'm going to be in so much trouble and
She's like okay well don't take care of you no don't worry about it I'll take
Care of everything
Give me the name of this
You know what your architect and and maybe some contact info and I'll take care of it
I hung up and I showed up the next day and she was in the lobby waiting for this
Interior designer
Not realizing that
Obviously it was the one on the phone with her body before
So where
This conversation and I able I was able to
Loser for a little while and
Plug into the network
And that ended up being
My way in was through social engineering
And calling ahead so let her know
Thought I was coming but I definitely leaned on that idealistic motherly care
Side of
People
And that's not the first time or the last time
But I've done that
I think it was
It was
Probably about a year-and-a-half ago I was working with a partner
And we were overseas we were over
Garcia's at the facility that I never seen
Foran in the country where I didn't speak the language
And so I called pretending to be with a charity organization that this company works with
And
I asked if I could have a meeting with them just to say thank you for all the hard work
You did
And they were absolutely obliging they let us in we were able to plants are back
Storage device
While we were inside the building having
This meeting with these people
I remember
Driving back to the hotel on the way home and
My partner
Was just really upset it was kind of his first big social engineering gig
He was like we ride to the
This poor people like we were supposed to in
They thought we were there
Friends wechat
Screw them over
He just felt really bad about it
And I said look
Where
This is what we do
Supposed to be bad guys and bad guys don't care if they hurt your feelings or ruin their day
Aliens they're out for money
And we are out to make
These people's jobs more
More secure
And he turns to Migos have you ever been tested for psychopathy
I was actually going to ask that exact question I'm not I'm not even joking
I was like
Have you gotten tested
That's a sociopath
I'm happy
Serious question
But no I'm kind of afraid to
No I I really don't think that's an issue like I I do have a lot of hair
These people like I
I don't go around
Am I pergert
No I
I never done anything like that
I do I do this because I care and it's not like I go around my personal life lyrics
No sew absolutely not not
I had
One individual
Fired for
The
I was able to get gain entry because he posted a picture of his uniform and badge
On a Facebook group
And this was probably my third or fourth
Test
And
He
Didn't do anything except post that picture because he was so
Proud
And like
His mother had just passed away or something and it's like I wish my mama could see me right now
And
Oh God
I know I know exactly exactly
So I was able to take the badge and and when I I did the penetration with the badge because everybody assume Bible
Because I have
It looks like
An exact
That's what it was replica
And afterwards
Hold during the debrief I told them several times I was like look
You want your people to be
Be proud to work here
You want
What's this kind of attitude where
Badge of honor
For them
You just need to
Train them up better you need to make sure that they know it is absolutely against
Your policies
To post pictures of their bats like this is not an isolated incident
And
Unfortunately what a lot of
Companies
Want to do is
Take that incident
Fire that person
And say okay we solved our problem
We are now
Sakura
The fact is that that is not the right answer
Retraining people
Not only increases their
Loyalty
To the company it also creates
Harder attack surface you're going to have a much harder time getting past people
School been through a test like this and retrained
And are now more aware than you will have just like scrapping your entire security force and then in
Installing a new one a brand new one that hasn't been tested
Pathways
General 8 yes I agree
I agree with you
But ultimately
If this is the reason for this has to make her company more secure they're doing themselves
The service
And they're also being extremely disloyal to to the folks that work for them
If I end up being their response
Tear in the hacker
How do
Other hackers
See
I think that a lot of
Traditional essay traditional hackers
Like just strictly technical hackers kind of see what I do as witchcraft
But that's okay because I see a lot of what they do as just complete
Black magic as well
I'm not very technical
Penetration tester I
I haven't
Entire team
Of folks
To handle the back
End
You know as far as hacking into the network is
Is concern after I've gotten that physical access for them
So
I
Don't
Co Lottery
Stuff that goes on over there I go in
I say okay guys I got access
Is 2 + unlocked
Computer
I planted this rubber ducky that you gave me
And
EBay turn that into
Okay now we have access
To all of the
All of the credit card information for every customer that's ever come through
Or
Week now.
This to all your private health information and now we know how to make everything more secure
Anatomies
Mind-blowing and I think
Jennifer Lopez
Folks on their end
Social engineering is just something that they don't want to get involved in as well as
People in light of people
Are very few who
What kind of straddle Both Worlds
And I
I just think those
Those people are super
But I also love being able to work with
Multimix
It's almost like that that differ
Trending now
The person who goes
Does the NSA or the person
CIA
Human versus Cigna
Yeah that's a good way of putting it
Well this is
I don't know who I'm speaking to now
First I thought you were nice and now I don't know
Jamie as well
Thanks a lot for being on the show Jack
No problem
And thank you so much for having me
This week's episode was produced by Lorenzo franceschi bicchierai
Recorded by Mitch Kraken and edited by John northcraft
Thanks for listening to this week
Did you like the show give us a review on Apple podcast
What time your friends about us
We back
Whitmore