Eagle One
The package being delivered last year investors Port 5 billion dollars into cybersecurity startups
The whole industry will be worth 170 billion in 3 years
According to a recent estimate
There's so many investment companies it's hard to keep track of
Yet
Are we all really secure
Is the infosec industry really keeping us safe
And is it even focusing on the right problems
Next week tens of thousands of people
We'll meet in San Francisco for the year's biggest information security Gathering focused on business
Vrsa comprar
Kelly Shortridge
Is the vice president of product strategy at capsule8
New York city-based
Security startup
Kelly has a background in economics
Investment banking
And I studied infosec Market
She's here today to help us understand
Why do you put 2nd Street
So big
And what's wrong with it
I've been a coup in this
Is cyber
So
Tell me about this
Overly inflated
Cybersecurity Market
The place
Yeah it's
Pretty nuts ha
There's a huge problem right now
In the information
Security industry which is
Is namely that
These startups are an actual
Play solving
Problems that
Security practice
Kissner's house
Are mostly chasing what
Buzzwords
But also problem
Apolis rather than the
Relief
Jamie was the most buzz-worthy we talkin like
You know
Synergy corporate Synergy like that kind of thing buzzworthy infosec
Market
Earlier today actually
Published the
Teen Edition of my
My infosec
Bingo card
Included
Automation
Comprehensive
Actionable in
Insights
ReThreads
Intelligence
I'm trying to think of others
Scalable
Scalable wantaddigest here constantly
This is the never stop
Exactly exactly so when optimizing so is a joke
Your price is an optimizing something what are you even doing you don't actually have to
Say like oh we're optimizing 4X
You just have to say it soft
Becky
Sudo militaristic term
I think that's right I think it's appealing to a certain
Ego and maybe and I think it's
It's not
Perhaps an unpopular opinion to suggest that Security Professionals often want to see themselves as
Heroes in the organization story
So having these very
I like big
Powerful words
Can you know one for example is in power.
That inherently has the word power in it right
I think a lot of times there's the the challenge between
Security people off and being The Gatekeepers at these organizations will also frankly feeling somewhat helpless
Is there an able to get
What do they want done
Did you say
In the fact that this
Is kind of
Parley's this
It's over-inflated nest
Is it creating problems rather than
Actually solving any is a sort of like a we looking like said this or the.com bust
On the horizon for
Cyber security companies
I'm skeptical that there's a bubble in
The fact of the matter is the most
The vast majority of startups
Spell and I don't think information security
It's particularly special in that regard what I will say is I completely agree it's causing more problems than its actual
Play helping
Nick very few startups
In the ecosystem were actually again solving real problems instead of their
Springside fear uncertainty and doubt to try to
Get the customer to believe that the problem
Set the solution to solving is worth
The time but it isn't actually
Then you have a bunch of shelf where all these
Tools that cost millions of dollars that people don't
And abusing or worse
It cost them
Countless hours of
Countless man-hours every month just to maintain them and nothing actually gets better
Are you going to name some names of the smooth company
I am not I'm gainfully employed by
Actually a startup in which I actually believe so I wouldn't want to jeopardize any potential relationships there but I will say
Say if you hear
Company is again
If
You're reasonably a tune to the security industry and you can't figure out what a company does from
The first half of the main splash page on their website
I'd be skeptical
And with your background
It's a bit unusual and it's
Perhaps why I focus so much on
Buzzwords in the actual dynamic
Exit the market in venture capitalist is I started my career in investment banking
As a mergers-and-acquisitions banker
Recovering information
Security as well as data analytics
And then I started my own start a push was acquired and then have been in product roles on the security vendor side
Gone the way of my studies
A lot of the kind of Behavioral economics Dynamics
Of the industry and Thursday
Bullmastiff
Misaligned incentives
So it it Blends pretty perfectly with looking up
The finance side of
Misaligned incentives
Okay we know where is somebody from Wall Street over here
How do you say I'm sure you in your in your past
You tried to find an efficiency
Yes absolutely so the economics term would be market failures
And certainly given the
High tension high risk
Nature of information
Security
It makes people more prone to cognitive biases which is exactly what marketing people want
Right you want people to be scared he want them to be making these kind of
Fast unconscious decisions motivated by their emotions
Centos
Things like buzzwords there's a reason why people actually use them
Likes
Like the the term cyber long ago
About
2014 events
I started seeing sort of these
Albie's ex-nsa
Cheap
DHS
CIA
Etcetera etcetera and they were all some had no technical background in actual
Infosec
And suddenly the pouting
This idea of cyber-security and how this is the neck
You know like the Cyber Pearl Harbor quote by Panetta
Kicked off this Frenzy
And then all the sudden you started seeing these
Internet companies popping out of nowhere
And then
You started seeing
Cyber security of the cyber security industrial complex
Kind of replacing the military industrial complex
So much
The extent that you start seeing
Actual advertisements for cyber security in the store
Extremely militaristic terms
In places like the Beltway
Or in train stations in DC
Trying to specifically
Advertise
Two. Agent
CIA
Feed this
It's the second system of government
Going into
Private sector
What is now what a multi multimillion-dollar industry
It's interesting the Beltway ecosystem I would actually say if someone sells
Contained unreasonably separate from Silicon Valley it's
It's not a dirty secret it's pretty well-known that selling into the government is even worse than selling into big Banks as far as
Insanely long sales cycle
Very unreliable you have to jump through all these hoops
Compliancewise so
Most
Early-stage startups probably aren't going the FED route
But the Beltway again you do see a lot of former government people solving problems that are very specific to
What they experienced in their prior careers so again it's its own little egos
Now banks are are the prime
Sort of
Target for some of these new startups to these new infosec community
When you have a sec
Companies
Isolate
It's so big Bank environments are considered
Some of the most complex as far as
Security challenges so
If you get
One of their logos on your you know testimonials section of your website you were considered pretty golden but again the sales Cycles are pretty
It's starting to shift I would say that was definitely true 5 years ago but now having one of the
Tech Giants
Logo on your pages
About equivalent
How big is this
Industry
Give me a number
It's above 50 Billy I've heard anywhere between 50 billion and 100 billion
Wow
It's it's massive as far as VC funding and mean
Over 5 billion last
Here alone
I mean now you're seeing some
Some commercials on
On major networks
Describing hackers in Cypress
Security
I mean places where you would have seen a Bud Light ad
Replacing it
Yeah I think I think it's a good thing that there aren't too many consumer-facing information security starves because
I think
Level of understanding about
Security is
Even last on the consumer side the Enterprise side so I can that presents the opportunity for
Pernicious marketing to sell people snake oil
But the consumer Market
That's absolutely true I think
There's been a few interesting studies showing that a lot of users expect
The organizations and services that used to provide the security and not have to consume it themselves so I think that's the
The Saving Grace of
Too much fun on the consumer
Is on the other side
This this business plan
That seems to sort of Taylor to people
Lack of complete
Knowledge
On Cyber and they want like a a one-size-fits-all remedy and this goes even two people working in big-time come
Buy something
Words the cyber
You know you're covered
Everything that's right Landscaping
The covered that play everybody wants that magic Blinky box that solves all their problems I think fundamentally people don't focus on
Turn off on the fact that
Overall security processes and Enterprises are
Really broken
Just fundamentally broken the mentalities are often broken again
Blaming users rather than understanding how to
How to fit security into the
Workflow is and then
So banging your head against the wall and they hope that technology will fix everything but it can't
At a certain point
You can hire as many people as you want and buy as many fancy Gadget
Do you want but if you weren't using the people or the text the right way you're not going to get any
Disclosure
Existed in this
Cinespace for a while has been that
Companies are really embarrassed
To come out and say that they had problems
Migas desert
Government secrecy
And fear kind of
Ratchet up this industry further
It's an interesting problem because my contrarian opinion is that
Breeches
Don't really matter that much for Enterprises if we look at even Equifax but Target mostly his
Entirely recovered from the recent hadn't that's the one where it
Affected
Versailles even perceptively for the most part the stock goes down
Maybe 1% the first day and bounces back up by a week later so most the time of big
Breach becoming public
Isn't actually any sort of death knell for the company
Fundamentally this
The stickiest part of the budget is always compliance
I would just
The sexy part of the industry so you see
Very little
Startup attention there
And frankly
Skinny people that want to work on complain stuffing that's part of the reason why they want to focus on all the really sexy technology cuz they want to feel
Oh not just doing a PCI
I'll let you know I'm stopping the Russian Hackers from using O'Day against you know my
No 1000 nodes in the middle of nowhere
Benefits we've been speaking out for about 10 minutes
Finally we hit the Russian hacker
Windsor sing shift is everybody used to
Want to claim that
A nation-state attack them to your point
Cuz it's a lot less embarrassing if it's
The government-sponsored Entity hack
But now and with cyber insurance
Is there a Carvel it's where you can actually get
Payout if
It was a nation-state because
Is technically
Active warrants so it's not covered
Insurance so now companies
Really care about Act
Turn the other way where they want to prove Noah wasn't actually nation state has a criminal group so we deserve our insurance
So you're going to RSA soon
Next week right
It is next
Or this week
Because it's where
This week at RSA
Yes yes
Coming at you from the future
Yes I am at RSA already RSA right now
What do you expect from
Oh man so it's 40,000 people so I don't expect
Much other than you know crazy crowds lots of marketing gimmicks buzzwords flying ever
Redirection at you
And very little substance being spoken
I will say that the mean value I personally find from RSA is
It's everybody goes and so you can meet a bunch
Most people in one place I think
I've been going since
2013 and every year I find less and less utility and checking on you know what's
Newest and latest Technologies I think the last wave that was actually interesting was
What are all the cast music
The cloud
Security Brokers which
If mostly all been acquired other than that scope
But lately there hasn't been another cat
Big wave of
Sexy innovation in the space or says mostly
No I've already heard of all of these I know the picture know the buzzwords so
You sound
Like you need to calm down cuz you sound wildly enthusiastic
Think about
I know I know I think they're very few people I know outside of sales and marketing
It actually get
Super hyped about it some of the parties or
Pretty okay but
Good luck finding a hotel under you know $500
Defcon
You know what I mean it's like how fun can actually be
Yeah mean death, at least has
A little more character I feel like our essay is if you had the the most
Bland cardboard version of our industry
I hope I really hope some RSA organizers
Heard you say that and run into you now at our side
To see I do have a press pass because I have written about RSA in
Play companies in The Innovation sandbox
Before so
Cardboard boxes
What are the two forget my exact phrasing but it is emitted cardboard
Cut out version I'm not sure it's that basically just a very
Doll if you Stripped Away all the fun and excitement of you know Finding vulnerabilities or working on really awesome techno
Allergy to actually protect users and you just
Distilled it into it
Stickiest
Cena worst substance if you like
Damn alright
The most customer service I want ya ya I think unless you're really trying to
Sell or put yourself out there is a vendor it's not necessarily worth going in there is value if you're security practitioner UK
Can kind of scope out all the vendors in one place
But
I personally think they need kind of
You know
Quiet
Kind of like this room
Quiet little boots you can rent out so you can
Escape all of the noise and Madness for a little bit and then
Go back out in the
Start speaking which of boom and infosec
Companies
You know our our
Infosec reporters Joseph Cox
And wenzhou
Belts just get
Inundated with emails all the time
Advertising music companies
I mean I myself get a bunches while I know what the Huawei is not the same thing but I've been getting hit up by Huawei like it's
Like it's a Bad Axe
In the last like 4 days
Wow I didn't know a lot of those companies
Are doing the same thing like money
We got this
Check out this product
Ail
Remind check your email
Don't worry you're great
What is the deal with that does it doesn't work we don't care
I don't it must work on someone because why else would they do it I was actually curious now that I have the RCA press pass I've been receiving the
Does emails I think the most
Amazing
And I use that word in a very specific meeting phrase I saw was Radical math
There's a company
Radical math
Math 2 kids in the 90s
And was it's by a doctor smarts a doctor
Smart teacher
Is radical math
I guess but
When you read something like that it's very hard to want to then take the meeting but very
Phew it was clear that
They're blasting he's out there was nothing kind of personalized about the emails with all just
Canada the buzzword
You know it
One of my friends had snake-oil served over word salads in an email form and there's nothing particularly compelling about
The craziest things when you don't get back
Some of these press releases
They like follow-up no cable why didn't you like to talk to us
You're the worst PR person
Have you ever spoken to a journalist
We didn't answer you
I mean
Only one reason for that
Right exactly yeah it's m it sounds a little bit like nice guy Behavior
Why aren't you noticing me hey pay attention to me I'm entitled to
Your time
Or I just recently read an article and vice and it's really interesting it's about
Women who get who break up with Matt and get these really insane text messages back
Centerfold things
It's almost like that
Except I didn't even break up with them
Yeah there's definitely some
I think there's a
A lot of elements of toxic marketing and that's not to say marketing is actually useful marketing works
It gets the
Attention so if someone is legitimately searching for a problem things like a CEO actually work because hopefully they can find the solution to the
Their problem
The issue is when your
Solution isn't actually solving a problem the only thing you can do to actually sell
Is
Really insane marketing and aggressive sales tactics
Rather than
Speaking hopefully reasonably plainly about the
Technology obviously everyone dresses
Is it up a bit
The certain point
You know either your product passes
The tester it doesn't and if it doesn't
I think
The
Scary thing is these companies have enough self-awareness that they overcompensate on the sales of work
Okay see you have your crystal ball in front of you
What do you see this
This whole industry going
Right now the next to give you a time scale that say 10 years
10 years out
Well by that points will we have to shut down our data centers due to climate change
Few years when I can say is that
That's good
Yeah they're they're a bunch of startups out of
Entirely overfunded they received
Yesterday's be sometimes series C rounds
When their sales were still comprised only of their
Personal Network
They haven't really tested in the broader Market
And so
In a generally there will be kind of a mercy round by existing investors they listen this is your last shot to try to make it
The certain point they're not going to keep
Just throwing money into a hole that they do
Do that for a surprisingly long
Sometimes I think over the next two to three years
Some of those will get m&a exits but
Not all of them well
And Ferb
Are listeners who don't know what an m&a exit is what is it exactly
Yes so a recent example would be Cisco acquiring a Duo security so it's when a
Generally larger company acquires a generally smaller company either for cash
Or equity
Critical events
Oakley trade in
And quite often you usually don't get your
Return value if that's
It it depends odoo a security absolutely did but
Sometimes in critically if you
Don't see a specific
Amount
The purchase price
What's an ounce
You know that it's
Sew-in in finance there's this concept of materiality
So if
But then again with Cisco is a by Duo security I think
2.35 billion that is material to their earnings at
It's important to their investors
So they have to stay with the prices
But if it have been for
20 million it's disco they don't really have to say with that price was so that's that's kind of a test you can use to
Determine
Particularly if you kind of inside info into the last evaluation by Adventure capitalist whether or not there was a
This is to say you think there's going to be sort of this consolidation
Assembly smaller companies in the next few years
Some consolidation I think we'll still see
In some ways more fragmentation particular as we see like the private-equity giant scooping up
Some of the big players
You either see more consolidation
Which I think is is frankly likely or you see that they're trying to
Differentiate themselves more in the markets I think if I had a crystal ball
That would be really helpful cuz right now I can see it going
A few different ways I definitely the thing I'm certain
Of his the fact that many startups will not see successful exits in the question is what
And I think a lot of these as I mentioned the TechCrunch article.
75% of all investors in information security startups
In 2018
Only invested In One Security startup they're not experts in the space
Dabbling in it but
Cuz it's a hot thing and they saw a headline in the Wall Street Journal
So I think most of those investors go away and the ones
Your experts
And kind of Judge quality a little better and
I think it's similar to what we saw overall in Tech
We saw people like Google coming out right
Because the investors that stayed and really understood text
Understood what the quality
Is there a crash
At all
In in inside
I think it depends what you mean by a crash I think
In the next
Buffet next three years it will be harder for
Some security companies to raise more funding I'd I think the
Just huge pile of money that's
Charlie continuously available right now
Yeah you can think of it that way that's for sure it certainly feels that way to some csis I think
It's going to be harder to raise money at a certain point I don't think that's even nessus
Play this year I think it's in
A few years when
Investors have to really see hey I'm not getting return When were the VC
Time Horizon is anywhere between five to seven years so there's kind of a lag
Between
When you
Noah startups going to feeling when you really feel that it's failed
Ergo the
You know the song
The infosec
Bonfire Investments
Will
Probably go out
It's possible if you ask Veterans of the industry's I've been in this industry now about
7 years in one way or another
If you talk to people who've been there since the 90s
To them this is really
Depending on who it is it's
Either the second or third wave of information security startups
So for most startups in Tech startups in general obviously the recession was a big
Lifetime but if you look at like when McAfee and a lot of the other
Original antivirus and endpoint tools
Who created or even look at
Palo Alto networks and FireEye those were created in the last
Kind of wave of infosec startups
What we done is we've forgotten all the ones that didn't work out right
Still remember it let's say the duo Securities the zscaler is the octaves of the world
Don't forget about you know the $300 is
Mm
19 that were funded and didn't
Workout
Well I like
Dandong
San Bernardino
Yes
Thank you for coming to tell me about
How bulshit descendants
She can be yes absolutely I'm always happy to talk about all of the sudden Buzz wordiness in the industry
Thank you for having me
This week's episode was produced by Lorenzo franceschi bicchierai
Recorded and edited
Papa John North
Thanks for listening to cyber
We back