Eagle one package being delivered
National Security reporter with Vice and this is cyber
A podcast for motherboard about hacking their voting machines are vulnerable to hackers on Friday
Packers were able to penetrate a touch-screen voting machine in less than 2 hours
You've heard it before disinformation campaigns Colbert plans hatch
Deep inside the Kremlin by dark Putin to use Astro factories
Facebook ad buying sprees ninja hackers just do Hillary's emails and embarrass the Democrats
I mean it kind of works
We say election acting
Need something more
Sling very specific
Today we want to talk about what real election hacking is
We brought in motherboard contributor and actor recording Legend
Kim zetter
Just want a piece for New York Times magazine called
The crisis of election security
He doesn't call out Russian hackers as a key
Spectrum
Democracy
Instead
Something around me
Voting machines
Carry out
Civic duties
Benedetails
Terrifying
Tell me
What is election hacking exactly because a lot of people throw this term around
Yeah I hate it
Election hack
Should only be used
When you're talking about
Aberdeen
Cutting machine
Yeah the misinformation campaign
On Facebook
Twitter and all those
That's not election hacking
So throwing up a shity meme on Facebook now.
Not alike
So what are these voting issue
What do they look like
What's the software
Two primary types of voting machines used in the entire country and one of them is called a directory
Cording electronic machine
And even worth the ballot itself
Motor boats on his digital and the boats are digit
The other type of machine is called an optical scan machine
And it is a shame that
The Builder
Mixer selections on a full-size paper ballot
And then scanned into an optical reader operating
System on these machines
Scyther
Windows XP
Or Windows PE
Cuz I'm kind of software that's embedded in ATM
Okay so what about these machines
What makes them so susceptible to which ones we talking about specifically that you think
Are the one that we should be worrying about
All the machines are problematic anytime you're talking about software there's the ability to subvert it
Right
You could go after the individual machine that the voter is using
Or you go out the back in network
Which is probably more efficient because
Start hacking the source
Machine that touches all the machines and accounting
However you could
Introduce a virus that could potentially spread to other machines because many of them at least
Precinct are Networks
Together
Also the end of the movie
Action there is a memory card gets put into the machine
That takes
Steve-O totals from it and cats
Walked over or driven
To Central collection office work been inserted into that Central tabulator
And has there been actual
I'm sad
Niggling elections in the past using this kind of method like
The past one that just happened the midterms
Weather temps or
Do you have reason to believe there were
We don't know
The intelligence
Agencies will say that they've seen no signs of anyone
Trying to subvert houghtaling
Equipment
But their view is limited
Isaac feystone signals intelligence
Human intelligence that kind of thing
These machines have been vulnerable since 2000 and
YouTube
And so it anytime in those last elections going all the way back anyone could have gotten into these systems already
Even if you was intelligent just looking for current activity and chatter
They're not going to see something that's already have
Prior to their
Air monitoring at BAE Systems
These are members of Congress
They work hard to approve budget grants to sort out election cybersecurity the one for 2018 was
380 million box
These are
Child hackers
I mean contestants stay
Captor keyboards to prove that within minutes
America's election it systems are a piece of garbage
35 out of
39 youngsters taking part this year
We're able to do just that so are you saying that
That
If you're born actor
Black Rock Sheraton
It is
Sara Lee or maybe
Extremely easy to
Manipulate
The American
Election
We have to
Go from
The distinction between remote access hacker
As opposed to someone who is physically close to machine
And
Your ability to alternate
Action increases
If you can get into one of those Central machine
Now it takes some skill you need to understand how the machines work but the machines are sold on eBay
Some of the software has been exposed on the internet a decade ago
And so it doesn't take much for you to actually get a machine and study it
Researchers who look at the Kimberly subvert them after just a couple of weeks of studying them fully
Okay
If you are Russian you're trying to
Manipulate this watch
What do you do
How do you do it and how do you knock
Get caught by hacking
Other many ways I could think of to Suburban Collection
If I were Russian hacker I would want to go after that elects
Action management
So election officials will tell you over and over again
That none of the voting machines are connected to the internet and that's just not true
Many of these machines have embedded modems in them
At at the end of the Alexa
They dilated and transmit those totals over
The cellular network we should be centrally the internet
2D election manager
System
So that means
It's open
2 malicious connectivity
If you can get into that election manager
Assistant
And then once you're in that system then you sit there and you'd study at or whatever
So that you're ready and set up for the next election that comes
And that's the one that uses birth
So you think it's possible that something like the midterms that just happened were sort of this test
Case
What is
Stimulation for
Foreign adversary to see how they could
Potentially
Manipulate the big one in 2020
I don't think the midterm would have been a test case like I said desus that doesn't involve more go for more than a decade
There's no reason to believe that actors haven't been studying these
Symptoms before
Baby Gardens.
You know
Really looking at 2000
King because the Russians became obvious
About an intense to subvert election
Weihai
Russia as an enemy
Long before 2006
16 right during the whole Reagan administration against like that has always been there and the technology has always been there
Stealing place
I am any places God during that period
Not to the extent that they are now it was really 2002 that we got most of the machine that we have today
Why did we get new machine
In mm
We got new machines because of the debacle of the presidential race in Florida in 2000
After that happened
Lawmakers
In the Congress and Senate
I decided that they didn't want something like that to happen ever again
They decided wrongly that the punch card machine were actually the problem
And they wanted to get rid of them so they created their bill that would give States
Billions of dollars
In order to upgrade
Shooties new electronic voting machine
And they were sold on the button machines because the vendors convince them
That's
Going fully electronic was the better solution
Eliminate people
I'll get the people out of the way
And you would eliminate
Problem
But actually they created just a different
So are you okay
If you wanted to do this
Strategically
If you're foreign adversary
Do Target
Like County swing States
States themselves like Florida or Ohio to
Minorly
Manipulate so that you can
Get away with it
Everyone says because the administration of our election
Star voting equipment is not centralized
If you can't throw
A federal election but that's just not true
We always
Every presidential election
It always comes down to a couple of Swing States and often the even just a couple of critical swing districts
Any particular districts
Where
Are you might also be able
Suppress the vote and cause
Photos to be dropped from the voter rolls or things like that
Then you can
Manipulating election
Emily sohn 2006
16 with the effort by presumably Russian State actors to get into the voter registration databases
If they understand that capability
I was going to say we know that Russia
Overall net
Will there be an appear to be going after the voting machine
But they were going after the voter
Castration databases
And if you
Getting some and also those records or delete voters from the voter rolls
You can prevent voters are actually casting. So it's actually much easier
Big Lots of Voters
Prevent them from ever casting about
Then going after the ballast
The cells of trying to alter those Balance
Okay so here's a thought
In some of those too close to call
Situations were still in right now like in Florida
It is possible that somebody manipulated some of those votes
It is entirely possible more possible that
Someone manipulated to go to registration databases
And suppress the vote
If you noticed the increasingly in counties and states
We're having more and more provisional ballots
Beasts of balance happen when a voter goes
Is the pole
And they are told that we have you down here in the database indicating that you already voted
Or
Does a problem with your registration we don't see you registered here
Until you have a window of opportunity after an election to determine whether or not
That provisional ballot Isabela.
Only get counted if both
Election officials and the voters and resolved that
If you can cause more and more voters
To vote provisional ballot
Give more more ballast that are up
And that time. After an election
Is very very tight
Again you can disenfranchised voters
In multiple ways
And you never actually have to alter the software
Okay so when you speak to see
Security researchers
What do they offer is the alternate what's the better sis
Denise Kern voting machine
Will the focus
Is not nut is not really on the system the better system the focus is on a method
No matter what system you put in place there's a possibility of it being subverted
The real focus should be on
Verify
Location of the result
And the only way to get that is through paper ballots
And through a mandatory manual audit
That will
Verify that the digital tally is
Sewn old school backup
Yes but you never want
To do that without an audit you always want to have
Some kind of manual verification
That the software is acting
Is it supposed to act it hasn't been supported
And
How long is lawmakers pass audit laws Without Really Consulting with people who actually understand statistical audit
It didn't really do a lot of analysis
Just trying to figure out what would be the best audit law
And the laws for
Getting these machine
Or created by lawmakers who didn't understand technology and ignored the people who didn't understand technology at all of them
Those parties have ignored
The real
4 years
Who have tried to steer them towards systems that have integrity
Do you think that sort of
Unwillingness
To change things as sort of
A way to benefit both
Parties when something's really
They close
And really tightly
Counting.
Are you all sorts of different
Things to
I don't want to think that
Hardee's
Are benefiting from this chaos
Huarache Nike
There's been a lot of
Attention focus on the fact that's the voting machine vendors have
Close ties to the Republican Party
And in many of the
States where there's been a resistance to
Instituting practices that would provide more
Integrity election
It's been in states that are controlled by
Republican
So in Georgia for example
There's been a lot of resistance for more than a decade
Switching to machines that have a paper trail
But
I won't go so far as to say that
The reason across-the-board we are getting more secure elections
Is because some political party or another is benefiting from them
This whole Facebook Fiasco the
Information Warfare against the US
That might be the thing we should worry less about we almost should worry more about these very hackable
Voting machine
I think voters
Depression is
The quickest and the easiest way
Dalton election and
To prevent voters from voting I mean if you're looking at memes and
Twitter and fake news on Facebook and things like that
It's very
Obtuse
Result that you're looking at right you don't know if the right people are going to see it
You don't know if you're up to changing minds or if you're just getting at people who already believe the thing that you're trying to get them to bleed
You don't really know what the insult
So I'm just going to be
If you can go out to the voter suppression.
By altering voter records
But registration database is preventing voters from voting
You're doing a direct info
You're hitting the election right at it
Core
Preventing photos
From casting ballots
Is the most effective in the most efficient way
Alternate election
In other words one could maybe work in the other one will
Almost certainly
Yes. Only will it more certainly work
You're also creating a real distrust in a democracy because every time of voter goes to the
Pool
And they're told you already cast.
Or you don't actually live here you moved
All those things that they know not
To be true
You're introducing doubt
In the Democratic process to these voters
They're going to mistrust us
Justin Moore & Moore
And so you not only
Achieved first of all preventing the voters
Casting a ballot
And preventing their votes
Getting counted
You're also been showing that mistrust in the entire Democratic process
Listen to cyber
This week were produced by Jason Cavallari
And recorded by Mitch Rapp
If you like the show please subscribe
Miss review
And tell your friends about it