Decoding a virus
Eagle One
Packaged beans
Did you know you can make money watching Netflix trailers on your phone
Did you know that people have Earth thousands of dollars a month programming hundreds of phones
To watch Netflix trailers
Video game trailers celebrity gossip shows
And sports
No one
Is really watching
Well in 2019
This was called
Phone farming
Just imagine rows and rows of phone scrolling through social media apps
Simulate the engagement of a real human
All the while making money for their human overlords
Motherboard Joseph Cox dope into this world by making his own mini phone Farm
He's going to tell us
Inside Story
Thomas bizarre phenomenon actually works
I've been a coup
This is cyber
So Joseph
Let's talk about this because I
It's kind of sounds absurd to me
People are using multiple phones
Creating phone Farms
To get paid to watch Netflix
Look Trailers
Yeah so you usually see these phones phones in China go viral weather Seas
Racks on racks
Cheap Android phones and people cooking through them
And that's the stuff like mini play some Facebook or
Who sing the reviews of an
Instagram accounts with followers
Do Facebook post go viral overnight
Ever wonder if it's actually legit and what could be behind those crazy Spike enter the world of Click Farm
In America
That all people who will buy dozens or hundreds of phones
And then they will get
Pays
To watch Netflix trailers
A video game trailer
Whatever it is
They will sort of chiba system
And instead of just getting paid
United by one company for one person to watch it
The game it
Bring as much revenue as bus
A gray area
It does violate terms
Service of summons
Elitist just show the phone farming is also
Nothing in the state
Some people literally set up these multiple phones
Any Stoner dislike repeatedly watching these
Trailers these
Videos
And just racking up
Views
Withstand
Creates
Actual capital
Yasso
Explain the app
So usually
If you want a website
And there's an abscess
Someone
Presently the company
It pays the effort to be that because they want to know if only put my product in front of somebody who goes to a sports website
To look at my trainer
Or something like that
There's another ways Knox
Incentivized traffic
Wechat
We're going to tell people if you watch this as well
We will reward you in some way
That might be freaking Essentials of digital coin
And if they get something else they could exchange it for a gift card or a free item or something like that
And in some cases you can even do it for cash as well
But if you do it enough
Legitimate reason to do that maybe
You're you're staying at home for a while maybe you in between jobs
And you want to get some sort of a
Disable School in Tampa
You may use one of these apps
It changes when people buying dozens hundreds of phones cuz clearly knows he's actually watching the message
Australis freshie Digest
Is this just one person with Hunter
Pics of screens
And that's what the weather don't ya
Stuff comes in yet but there is a legitimate part of this boxing
Strategy blank lady gets abused as well and then that's where
Define phones coming
Dispensary
A bunch of
Zombie phone
Target
Eating up the strap
The only deal
Situation for the same phylum as if they would download the app
They will set up and then we'll need to be
Minimal interest
Sometimes that can be the case
They will have to also have to download special software
It would then simulate
I click on the phone with
Because the Apple say hey you might see that
Because of course some of the app Developers
They don't want to become a pro diver they're trying to relationship
My business
Set in the same phylum as wolves download an app one coil switch
Replay the finger strikes on the phone so it looks like a human still in track
What's the device
And that's why you get to the real so sketch
Treestuff
Some Farmers want to stay away from
Of others
Fully embrace
I just got a fool
Grey Bicycle
So you actually made this a mini Farm protest
Ethereal
Yeso
Most people I spoke to in the states
Who have a fan Farmdale have between
I don't know 2250
Maybe a 400 phones
Just to see how this ecosystem in the supply chain what I just bought
Cheap Android phones on eBay they were
2499 some ZTE
Much cheaper for $10 I was just
What's the rush
BMW used
The packaging was a little bit busted but
Vines
And I set them up with an app
Kool Pak TV
Which
As we mentioned does allow you to watch these nuts
Netflix
Because it's an easy thing to show that
I'm pretty sure this company is going to be too happy
People aren't actually Digest
I tried it and I have a feel about it
But essentially I'm maze
Some money
From my phone's just shining through
It wasn't much money
I think in all we probably would have made
$1
Approximately over
Just a week. Before phones but again if you will
Racking up to 50 or a hundred phones
You can generate
More money as well
You do have to put in the work you do sometimes have to tap yes I'm still head depends how far you take
But there's people that have made thousands of dollars a month off
2017 that was apparently a pretty high points in an ounce of the year
As well
Every month excluding the winter mod
I was able to make over $1,000 a month from
And I got close to $2,000 a month in 2017 for the whole year but I never quite made over two grand a month
I spoke to said they were making
$1,800 a month
With quality phone but believes I have between 50 and 100
But with minimal interrupt
Passive income
It's coming from just doing us
It has however Maurice
Leeds
Going downhill
Apparently especially last year in 2018
PiZap Networks
It's not exactly clear you know
So the chicken-and-egg problem me that what came first
Irrespective Revenue dickow.
And these are
That's when Mike is much money on the phone phone is ultimately
Assemble make something like
$10 a day now
Prayers before you know they will make him a little more
It's all kind of reminds me very much so
The
You know the countless stories that came out I thinking sometime between 26
Were you happy
Bitcoin Farm
Around the world in China
In Iceland
Ancient Iceland
Endeavor
Mining for Bitcoins
Where did industrialized this this online digital economy
And it was just a bunch of machines
Come mindlessly at work
And you had this human Overlord making money
Yeah definitely it does have
Some residents with that end
I should say there is a large
Community
If YouTubers and other commentators around this and they definitely do also intersect
So what's up with the cryptocurrency
Take me to take
Some will be mining Bitcoin or base on a much smaller scale than if he say maybe the Chinese
Bitcoin Farms with something again
If I'm found to be on a smaller scale they'll be larger in China
The awesome the others will mine
Currencies as well
And just generally that resistance of Viber
Get rich quick
Some people do that effectively but I also imagine it can pull some people in
Maybe
Don't put that much
Fulton to it and maybe a spine of the phones and other very disappointed when the random 18
You know one or two dollars or something
It requires a lot more for
I'm so sorry
Ethical approach
Anime
Annie's phone demeanor
They're obviously not buying ready-to-use
Brand new phones off the rack
What were they getting them
Yashow eBay is good one or two companies
Tracfone Account number do they make very cheap Android devices that get in there as well
Just online maybe Amazon
It doesn't matter if the phone is used inside of the one I bought
Apparently I couldn't even register it
Because it was so old
It wouldn't work on the currents
Poutine that works at least that's what the personally by said in that was a reason he was selling them
As long as you have a Wi-Fi connection
And you can run these devices free that is absolutely fine
Of course
Some apps that come with the text that you are running
95 * 50 phones will from the same
Wireless router and then the same IP address to make it blocked
Ambi to have to go down to someone
Volume
What are these companies that are actually
Paying for these
Services
Where do I see advertising there their shows there
Celebrities
Gossip shows
Sports
They can't be happy about this
Right so we didn't hear back
From Netflix but we can kind of use
The advertising or the ad Networks
Approach
This was a proxy firewall that is
Because I just
Big companies aren't going to be happy
The trail is a kind of
Fooling this
Pretentiousness
Pitts window Visage
Pay attention to
The one person I spoke to
On that website was just discusses fighting farming
An app Network actually pulled out
Websites anymore
They believed because of her on the phone, please
Because they would just go
Today is Wednesday at Abu
And a prejudice
And sort of this or around this industry that people don't really want to be involved with and it's understandable you don't want to
An end-user client like Netflix or whoever
You don't want to be paying out Network
Distribution
Well now exactly me to come defeat the entire purpose of it
But what I do find interesting about this as well as that
You know you had some
Packer typekit or person
Prasad hits trailers in and saw the potential for them to
Create a bunch of phones just watching us and making money I mean there's something to be said about even just a.
Perspective
We're now in
Dimension there is this legitimate way that you like what I'm going to trade my attention
Well
Why don't you just pretend I'm a hundred people
Do I get a hundred
And that's essentially doing
How much power does a
Because to me
Think about this
I mean she hook up a thousand phones or let's say 150
Phones
It's a lot of
Power
Yeah I mean when people mine Bitcoin or ethereum already
Electricity cost
Because running a rig is going to
Emergency room signage energy
The American Founders I spoke to say I did bring the up but they didn't seem
Overly concerned about it and I don't know whether that's because
Maybe they just haven't paid that much
Maybe it's another business or whatever
Actually doesn't conceal all that much electricity I mean
We only did with full phones
So it's hard to say but
Android devices are going to take up a lot less electricity very generally speaking
Then you know
A big Bitcoin mining
So
Yeah if you have enough time to take up a lot of electricity bill at least the people I spoke to wasn't overly concerned about it
But I may be just because they're not frightened the same scale losing massive Farm in China or China
This story I think
Just thinking about it
It's it's really about what the digital economy
Has done
That this is the way that we're finding
Fighting to make money
I mean this is how we roll
How people are actually
$1,800 a month
That's a living
It's a living
Making digital
You know
Machines are slaves
Mimicking Being Human
There's always going to be people
Finding a way to hustle to scam around something in them
The reason I was
Attracted the phone Palms
In the first place Bevo
The large ones in China or even the smaller ones in America
Is that it provides almost
A physical
Space
An artifact
Of
Prude
Endocet
Only in Snapchat mean you made talk about Frozen all we really have to say
The human illnesses
Social media manipulation of face like so whatever
Physical space
Taking up in the actual Wells
With some dick
That's what you want me to
Well I look forward to the next
Weird-ass thing you bring to the table for us
Today's episode was recorded in edited by Andrew bercik I host of it and I produced it
You'll hear from us next week