Or walking to Defcon
What can we expect
So we're here at Defcon 27
The 27th edition of was probably the biggest
Maybe wear this
I can conference in the world
There should be 25000 30
Thousand people here
For the weekend
You are sounding way more enthusiastic than
Think your face yes
Should I start again
Virus
Eagle One
The package being delivered hackers spy
Eyes cops Silicon Valley Bros technologists and even politicians descend upon Las Vegas Nevada
Would become
Preeminent hacker conference in the entire world Defcon
For cyber journalism it's a Non-Stop store Sebastian social circuit in casinos or hotels with Larry
Top 40 hits in the site of high-profile arrest of hackers like Dimitri Skyler off in 2001
Las Vegas last week after he gave a presentation on software security at hackers convention
Clear up the porter say he is not a hacker
They say he was drawing attention to security flaw a reference to the famous hacking movie War Games
All right
Flush the bombers get the subs in launch mode we are at Defcon 1
Wasn't always so mainstream
Besides countless infosec talks in Capture the Flag games used to be sort of an Arctic access
Attendees trying to outdo one another by infiltrating each other's devices
Or hacking personal information as you can imagine people take precautions at Defcon 2
But the paranoia runs deep I caught up with domaintools malware analyst salary at the conference talk just how
Seriously people take their
Surety
So do you buy the whole
Defcon like did you bring like six burners
And
I got 10 for a hat and a mask to make sure people and see your face like
What is this stuff
That's hilarious. No I
I run my iPhone and I run my MacBook in my iPad
And I
The only thing I do difference
And not really even a different is just I run a VPN
And even then you know it sucks
I don't want to say there's a lot of hyperbole but I think there's a lot of
Myth and would have been the mysticism and height
Surrounding
What happened to your Defcon and bsides and black hat and all these security
You know
Attackers are information
Security I should say are generally
I'm really busy right now we have a lot of things going on and we have a lot of events going on in
The notion that people are
I'm spending a lot of time trying to attack others is
It happens you can't say it doesn't happen because it does but the light we have to look at things through like a likelihood
And the likelihood of something bad happening is
Really really low you know to the average person walk in the cast
Tina Flores
So I personally don't believe in the hype that much and
I think it's a bit of a hyperbole just
Be smart about what you do
Like any other time
It becomes this
Really weird
Wave someone to tell you about
Ghost stories
Keep a call man I was once I was in a
Ever after my color
I'm like mr. robot nearly cannot it's just that con relax relax
It's so true man it is there's a lot of Indian OIC
I think that's probably also part of
The security Committee in general we like the kind of
I don't want a cigarette were falsely hyping up stories but there is a lot of like hike their work
You know I don't think it necessarily needs to exist all the time you know it's
It's not as sexy and it's not as sophisticated as people make it out to see me sometime
* 2
Strickland a sense of
People being attacked like personal people being attacked on
Water just walk in the Casino floors and
Technology has advanced so much
That a lot of these comment
Acts are so much more difficult to pull off nowadays
So back in the day if we took a time machine back
10 years ago 5 years ago
It would take me about
In a 5 Seconds to jump on Saint on
Community WiFi network
And steal passwords
Https
90%
Stealing passwords is it
Kind of complex now it's not as simple as that you
You know I didn't die
So the notion of oven Elite hacker being on the same Hotel network is you and stealing your passwords
The likelihood of that
Really really low my life savings LED
The odds of that happening to
An individual nowadays
Almost in
Avenues in the hotel Wi-Fi but I don't use Hotel Wi-Fi in most places
Just because
It's like it's clean as a hotel swimming pool
Like I think so I just
Scene the mask
But the facial recognition masks
People are wearing and
Just all sorts of I mean I get it I get it but like
At the same time
I either like you must be playing dress-up or you're that stressed out for like
4 days and for me like I'm stressed out
Having to chase
Packers round 2 interview
You know I think one of the problems is due is that there's
A lot of self paranoia this
Community was Brad out of this paranoia right
Some people call it healthy paranoia
There's a thing called threat modeling to
And threat modeling just
To be super quick about it is just
Take a look at who is the type of individual that would attack you
How to build a defense around that right
If you're walking down the street and like a
Shady part of town and
You know you're going through an alleyway
You know you kind of have to threat model okay what's the likelihood of me getting
Mugs here and
What do I have to lose and
Maybe I should just take a different street
There's a lot of individuals in this community and you know I know I'm going to
Did I make you
Polysom enemies by saying it but
I think lyrics
There their way to
Paranoid about things
In a wearing these in a facial recognition mask
It's like wow
We're in the middle of Las Vegas worried
I thought the amount of cctvs in this area are
Overwhelming
Another
You know tons of people in a public areas like what are you I don't understand what you're trying to hide from or who you're trying to hide
And what's the likelihood someone's going
You know recognize who you are and what's the impact of
So what if somebody knows who you are right here
You know you have the threat model it but however if you're going to a country maybe like China where we've seen
Weaponize facial recognition
I think you have a legitimate case with Chinese government has plans to use this new biometric technology
Does demented Soul zartarian rule the country has ambitious plans to develop a vast National surveillance
System based on facial recognition
The likelihood of facial recognition being used against me
Fire
Absolutely
But if you're a bad guy
You know attending this
Because there are some
Do you know I would question you even being here but you know the ones that do and use facial cleansing facial recognition
Okay maybe I could see that I still think you're silly
Traffic
You said you were that masking like
Your other
Like you become different in a Target like
Ironic that you're attracting more attention to yourself by wearing a mask that is
Design said like
Make you not be recognized
This is part of that hypocrisy that I see all the time in the community that
I just got a little bit kind of frustrated with like
For example out yesterday I was meeting
I was meeting at Buddy's buddy
And I was like all you know where do you work at and
The person does
Extremely paranoid and just
Said I work an undisclosed
Okay Manuel
You probably work at Arby's that's cool man whatever like
The paranoia is something I just I personally don't get
Because you have to throw model it otherwise you are just
Maximum stressed out all the time
I'm just trying to make conversation and say hey how's it going
You know where do you work what are you doing
Met with like
Oh I can't tell you where I work
Okay well I guarantee you don't work at the NSA so
What is an acceptable answer to the NSA
I totally get it like
Tell me where you work but
He do infosec for Arby's or something
I'm saying what you do right now
I work in
I agree with you
Certain point I'm like
He's going to ruin your life
Cha cha
Try to run from this you know like
Got to just live your life
Spin the wheel
So my partner in crime in Las Vegas
Search for death comment
This year was motherboard reporter Lorenzo French
July
I caught up with him after
Give me his thoughts
Illustrious
27th year of death
And how the infosec
Cyber commute
Lorenzo Defcon 27
Is it any different from the last
Either you've been to
Anyway
Well in some ways it was a little different it was more spread out it was
Culver
3040 Calle
So it felt like it was bigger I think the organizers said they was around 30,000 at 10.
Please which I believe it's records Jose heard a lot of people say that people were nicer
Which
I'm not sure
I can confirm cuz I
You know it's hard to tell but
I heard it inside on Twitter from a lot of people you know who noticed that
The goons who are also.
Volunteerism
And I'll do a little bit of security as well as mineral tell people where to go and help people out
Lasa
Aggressive in other years
Tube to put into context the Goons
So to have this
An attitude that it's collect Rollie and a little bit like abrasive by pump purpose and supposedly in an endearing
Greenway
But in the past few years people
And I'll complain about them because
They can be
Just rude
That's something I got kind of I picked up on because you don't pass use I've been there
There's always this
You know overwhelming fear of the Year again
Actor
People are out to get you I'm a one year I think
I was told like
Not even
Go near the cell phone towers
Don't even don't even turn your phone on if
If you don't want to go
Maybe we can come to this
If it's just this
Troll
Traulsen
But
This is the first step, I think I've been to that I not only observed on Twitter
And in person
People being like nah I'm not about that
That toxic shouldn't
Yeah mean as I said I don't know if this is a concerted effort from the organisers or maybe just people growing up
I think it's it's a result also
Culture
In general
Changing
You know earlier this year we we reported that there was a Facebook group pretty popular Facebook group
Made up of a lot of
Ratably well-known actors in the scene
I was like
You know sharing and commenting and talking about a lot of misogynistic
Shitz and ditto
I'm putting down women and making racist jokes
And then some of these people were connected to a conference call derbycon
Obviously their Beacon
You know said that they were not responsible for their their volunteers doing this.
I guess what I'm trying to say is that I think this year
Israeli wine
Keep playing the accuracy and then realize that there was some
Toxicity
That needed to be addressed obviously the problems are still out there and I don't want to say that everything has been song
But the fact that a lot of people noticed that can be nicer is probably a result of this
You know
People just realizing that they need to do some
In general they need to be more welcoming because
Can always 2019 you can just have a conference where
Dudes
Stop
That I can seen is much more than just man
And the in some ways defconn is always being pretty welcoming you know
They've had this
Article queercon for years
You know it's very
It's very common to see a trans folks and
You know nothing on gender conforming people at Defcon
But
Yeah in some ways maybe this year was even better and even more welcoming and that's great I mean I think that's how it should be
At the same time so we had some people
Women calling out some of the the b*******
On Twitter which I thought was
It was excellent
Assertive
I could have said it better myself
Sometimes when you hear the way
Hackerman
Talk about things
It's not
It's not cool it's not fair and it's also
Really aggressive
I just passed we were in there but
We had we are drummers
Or rather we heard reports that
During Defcon 101 which is basically the
The welcome to Defcon talk at the beginning of the conference
Some people are making
Inappropriate jokes
And that's obviously not great but I think the Silver Lining that is that they were called out and
A lot of people talked about it so probably next year
The organizers will make a point three
More inclusive and nicer
In general
The one thing we did was we asked so many
People when we got a lot of interesting answers
About what they think
You know
Writ large
The infosec cybersecurity community can do better we got a lot of things
Comments
And I think
You know everything ranging from
People thinking it's toxic
If there's anything you think
The cybersecurity infosec community could do better
What would it be
Be less toxic
More
Inclusive I try as much as possible that
There's
A couple of people in the industry were a big rockstars and
You don't make anyone else welcome
You know
People thinking
That the service
Yeah I think that's
It still
You know despite the fact that I do believe that things are getting better especially this year
There's still a lot of work to be done
You know it's still not easy to be a woman and infrasonic it's still not easy to be a black person in infosec
I think they can do a better job of
Hiring outfit
African American
And there's a
A huge disparity between African-American representation at a higher level
You see African-Americans at the help desk to the system admin level
But when you start to go up to see So Co and Auto salvos
Senior-level positions you don't see a large representations of African-American so I think that as an industry
We can strive to do better as much as we're doing for women which is very great
I also think that we can make us a map for for African Americans
Going to take a while
And it's got to be to take an effort from everyone you know a concerted effort to call out bad behavior
To make an effort to be more inclusive make an effort to be more welcoming
I know make a point that
Do you know
Despite what some people think you can be a good hacker without being a man
That whole
Idea of like hacking people getting hacked
You know very prolifically at
I desk on it mean that some really toxic
Yeah I agree and I think it's another way to put a barrier you know it's another way to scare new cameras and maybe even
And discourage them from coming to that, because it's it's unsafe you know it's like you're going to get high
In conclusion if we look at that sits
It's like
Defcon is changing
And so is in for second Cyrus
Security and it seems to be not slowly
But we're starting to see it
And that was
Sort of my takeaway from
Miss lap desk
Yeah I agree I think it was encouraging to see so many people noticed that he was nicer and more welcoming
And as I said before I think that is a long time coming and it's the only way for the community to get better
This week's episode was edited and recorded by Brian Arnold posted and produced
I mean that not to you will hear from us