Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered they are the hackers hacker that nobody knows back
Nobody even knows if they're just one person or several all we know is Phineas Fisher as hacked
Embarrassed and exposed some of the world's most powerful spyware companies that have connections to places like the
The FBI doesn't of other law enforcement and spy agencies all around the world
Then they vanish completely Without a Trace its mother
Reporter Lorenzo franceschi because he has been one of the Premier reporters on the beat
Several times
Well we made contact with Phineas Fisher again
I'm Batman coup and this
It was a summer of 2014 I think it was the week of black hat and desk on
Which made it pretty funny actually when this happened
So
Someone
About time
Someone hacked into the servers of Kingfisher
German British company that makes
Spyware for garments
All around the world
And adopt
All they could find online
So this is a pretty
Classica hack
M Leake
Cooperation
The goal was ostensibly to embarrass the company and damage it as much as possible
How to give
How to give listeners some contest finfisher
Has been in the news especially during those years for selling
Spyware tool
Questionable government like Ethiopia
Other Middle Eastern countries that used it to spy on dissidents and Taurus
So this was clearly an attempt to you know
Got some revenge and punish them for their
Alleged crimes I guess
The individualistic responsibility called themselves Phoenix Fisher
Play on the name of in Fisher
And they came out on Reddit
On the
R / Anarchy
Subreddit which was very interesting choice
And
It was clear that whoever was
I'd like some anarchistic
Ideals answer of you know anti
Anti-capitalism in Thai
Surveillance ideas
After this hackers completely disappeared
And then what did you hear
About them
So fast for a year
Almost a year in July of 2015
Hacking team the main competitor of finfisher gets hacked
And older stock account online very much in the same fashion as in Fisher
And we're talking
You know company emails
Source code
Yeah internal emails beta
Varian document Financial staff
Spreadsheets
And I just had the source code which was very bad cuz that bad that point anyone could just
Download it and make their own action team spyware
And obviously clearly this was
This was a big problem for customers cuz they had to stop their operations to
Recover from the hack
And I called that hack and I initially immediately I thought
Could this be the same person I mean
I can't even kingfishers are very similar companies
That the way that they had happened was very similar
I just had a guy
Feeling that this was maybe the same person
Set a time that I can Team Twitter account followed me and it was under the control of the hacker
So I DM them saying hey I'm a journalist can we talk
NBA agreed and we chatted for a while and then
The hacker used is all the Twitter account that they created for the finfisher hack
To claim responsibility for the hockey team hackers well
So by using their old Twitter account babe
Prove that they were the same person
Sun or the same group
And what was interesting after that was the day instead of Disappearing like they did
Taylor before and this case has Fisher stayed
They remained and on Twitter
They tweeted here and there they trolled packing team another espira companies
And they didn't really
They didn't disappear like they did the year before
And then months later they had more hat
They have to listen in Spain
Then they have to turkey's government
And
They were clearly trying to inspire more people to get to become hacktivist
They published on my fastest and you know it's time to take control
It's time to fight back against yuan
Capitalism answer with the surveillance Society
And companies like temperature in hacking team
And they were trying they were clearly trying to
Encourage more people to join their cause
So what does the infosec community
At this point
Think
About face
Beneficence always been an interesting character for the infosec community
Everyone has always agreed that the hackers
Are very skilled
I was cleaning the work of someone that knew what they were doing
So everyone was always very curious about who they were
It always seems to me that Phineas Fisher kind of comes up among infosec people is sort of
One of the Worlds
The world's best hackers
In This Very classical
Old school way
That you know the community
Be about right
Like it's sort of like the LoveSac
Packers
Looking for a very skilled and they're kind of the burn it down and our kiss
Types
But this is somebody who
Repeatedly has gotten away with
Is very interesting character is funny
He's right upside details and I'll people who are very impressed when he published power reactor both conditioner
Hacking team because
He went into all the details explained very well
Show the step by step
And I know so he was funny and interesting you know when
Two years ago when we interviewed it when you interview them for the cyberwar episode synesthesia requested to be
Represented by a puppet
And
That was like something that
No one I've ever thought before and
People still
Talk to me about that
Ben interview I mean that was one of the
What are the highlights of my journalism career
I got I got I got to talk to a puppet use my skills and real series way
But yeah yeah
Embodies it though right
It's like that kind of trolling we got trolled there but it was kind of a trolling I was willing to accept
And it was an interesting sort of execution of old-school hacker culture
And it was
Literacy
See within that that made me think okay this is
Is this can't just be
You know
Some
Government off in disguise
Is government off
Very rarely have
Any understanding
Agriculture
He's also like
The fact that they stayed around and
Remained on Twitter and try to rally
Troops and you know encourage other people to join the cause
It does not seem
I got them I would do
So yeah it really seemed like
The person was or the people behind them another persona
Truly believe what they were saying
And I've interviewed them many times and I didn't really feel like
They were different people
I always felt like it was the same people
But you know it's
Other email or chat
Pretty hard to tell
But even your ears after our first conversation and they were able to reference
What we talked about in one of those prayers coming station that was never published
So they gave me this
Feeling that yeah it was still the same people
So what are
Some of the
Series
Surrounding
Who
Does this be many and it depends who you ask
So I think the leading theory still is that
This person or group of people was just an activist
And the Tylenol stories
Seem to agree with this
Last year we obtained
So a report that into telling investigators police investigators
Wrote after the hack
And you know they follow the leads all the trails and eventually they concluded that
The hack was motivated by political
A reason
Batman that likely the hackers were packed
Other than anybody else
The Joe Manor a veteran
What is Cyprus
Security reporter comes out with a book on
Wake up with a cow
Activism
There is a
Reference to
The origins of
What's in the US intelligence community
Believes about Phineas
Joseph presented
Define theory
He reported that
The US intelligence says privately concluded that penis Fisher is likely a Russian government operation
You didn't really go into the details of how they reached a conclusion
But it is a theory that makes some sense
I think it is at least as
Plausible
That
Phineas Fisher is a Russian operation
Maybe through a cutout
Then it is that
He she it
Is
What is xian
Supports to be which is a like a politically-motivated
Immorally Chris eating
Yo super talented hacker
So it's more like
You looking at
Destroy the evidence
I gathered
Alarm in circumstantial
It seems more plausible than instruction
And I can go into why but I would say I had sort of worked that out
On my own and then I ran it by
Some people connected to Western Intel and they're like yeah duh and that you know I don't know
They didn't give me
Inside information
Except to say
And I quote one of them
James Lewis
Is well connected to Intel folks
Is saying
You know that's the assumption
At least because we have seen similar operations from the Russian guard
So few years ago
A group claiming to be the Cyber caliphate
Accident with his friend
TV channel
Tv5monde
Took it offline
And then
On Twitter this group claimed responsibility
Years later though investigators have concluded that the Cyber caliphate was just a fake
Persona created by apt28 which is Russian intelligence
Something similar happened with group that called themselves the Yemen cyber Army
Saudi company
And then they came out and claimed that they were like
I'm sort of a yemeni
Writing Center
Organization
But then again it turned out that
He was actually again the Russian government so this is dessert
Strategy that employed before
So it does, it is possible it makes them sad
What doesn't add up completely is that
Men
Claims that finishes last hacked which was against the Turkish
Green Party
AKP
Shows that
Penis fish write some sort of
Is aligned with Russian government interest
That that hack was
A strange and also at the time I'm not sure that turkey in rush hour on the best terms
I just I think the motive is
It's not enough to prove that
So I mean have you
Did you talk to
Chris Fisher recently and asked
After the book came out and I saw that paragraph I emailed them immediately and asked a what
What's up have you seen this
What are your thoughts I'd be curious to know why you think
And they responded that
I was
Ridiculous
They said that it was almost
So dumb that it didn't
Deserve a response
But eventually they explain that the theory just doesn't add up because
At the time Russia and Turkey you were not on good terms
And it just didn't make sense for the hack to be politically motivated in that sense from the Russian perspective
And they also explain how the
Controversial emails that sort of
Docksta bunch of them
Turkish women ended up on weekly
Beneficial said that they share the emails with
Someone in rojava
Which is an autonomous region between turkey and Russia
Bat penis Fisher
Reports because they're like I don't care
And the goal that was
For them to look at the emails to see if there was anything in useful for their cause
What happened was that penis Fisher is contacting version of a shed than with somebody else who had contact with WikiLeaks
With the request not to publish anything until they told them to do so
Wikileaks ignored
And after the
Elko
That summer they just published everything
Which was not what answer to why nor what is contactor in Rwanda
Sort of contradicts the theory that
He was just working for the Russian government trying to
Tiffany sister give us a statement
Yes Phoenix Fisher agreed to respond to Joseph's men's reporting
On the condition that we got someone with a fake Russian accent
To read this message
Knock knock not quite a puppet this time
Yeah hard to see the puppet on Apopka
Okay so without further ado
Here is
Phineas Fisher State my
In a heavy Russian
Very
Important contacts
No one talked about
Is that a year earlier
Russian turkey
Diplomatic incident
Which had been entirely resolved before the heck
Happened
So I'm not really sure what my point was that to us
But anyway Russia
Was AKP strongest supporters during and after the coup attempt
So why would you want to attack
AKP
Because we all know Russians are tricky bastards that like to play both sides and stuff.
The most logical explanation
It's clearly Russia stuck in the Cold War I guess he never got the memo that America
Boogeyman is Adams
Russians
Personally
I feel
Like I'm more of a Charming chicken
Turn the fancy bear
You know I think
The thing about Phineas Fisher to me that's the most interesting it's just a mystery
It service Phantom quality
It's almost as if I kind of like
As a story
Dennis Fisher is being accused of being a Russian hacker
Continues with this
Hacker anarchic
Legends
Yeah I think on one hand I would love to know who finis Fisher is
But on the other hand it's such a better story if we never do
No
Satoshi nakamoto you know it's like
It's a mystery.
Listen to itself and the leave the door open for so many series and accusation
And that is the most interesting part of the story at this point to know the computer hacking hacking team hacks for
Very important but what
Really matters now is
And this person is still around and despite having embarrassed
Two companies that are you know very powerful
Customers and connections all over the world
This person or people are still around you know
Typing on keyboard ready to strike
Again
There's something very Robinhood about it
Yeah for sure and
That is something that
Doesn't happen very often anymore in the world
No no it doesn't
Well thank you for answer
Thank you hun
This week's episode was edited and recorded by Andrew bercik produced by Lorenzo franceschi
Hosted by Yours Truly then McCoo and the voice actor we used his name is moti margolin
Shut off to him for being the voice of an attacker will see you next week