Eagle One
Package being delivered
National Security reporter with Vice and this is cyber a podcast for motherboard about hacking
Yet again
There is stall over the place how did this happen I mean did this just jump off of a truck somewhere or
Is this
It's almost Christmas which means Nintendo fans are anxiously awaiting the December 7th release of Super Smash Bro
Brothers ultimate
The company's biggest game in years
But earlier this week the gaming World got some unexpected news
Pirates at the full copies
The game online weeks before anyone was supposed to get their hands on it
The week was one of the worst Nintendo's history
Can a company quickly begins lying to get copies of the fighting game taken offline
But the damage was done
Super Smash Brothers leak is spread far and wide thanks with small group of hackers on a piracy server called
Xanax
Nintendo switch all about dropping games early
Motherboard senior staff writer Joseph Cox recently embedded in the switch piracy community
P****** games are leak
We found was much crazier
Reminiscent of the early days of hacking turf wars
Some people in the Nintendo gaming community
Weak games
I mean they're basically two ways the first one is pretty standard where
If you're in America and the game is coming out a day or two earlier you get someone in Australia to buy us and they'll dump it
The Conch Richmond
Interesting
Is when people will download the game from Nintendo servers
Beijing Kryptonite points in the complex
Solo ReliOn
Journalists
Games reviews
YouTube is
Diesels of people that Nintendo is trusted
Review copies of the game
To Dentistry the code to unlock it that way
There's a big overlap
Between
Religion list in the YouTubers on the review is
And the piracy
A community as well that definitely don't mean
Okay if it turns out that some people
Are actually pretty toxic and going after each other using hacking
Yes
Community you think will be lovely innocent with Mario and Zelda from whatever maybe
There are parts of it that will
Package of a
Doxy Choppers and publish information online and just generally really screw
Isha price
Like if they have
Some sort of rivalry
The really going to act
Give me example of this happen
Between
Packers
Nintendo game in space going
One case was a Geico
Put Simon he makes a
Tool which lets your PC talk to Nintendo says when you could
Download games okay game updates
It can also be used for piracy though
And try to get games earlier
Someone on full-time and I'm ready
Posted the wrong version
They included special codes
It would steal files from anybody he's used to it
I know he could then use those files to download even more games
So who's trying to piggyback off
Qualities of a Nintendo fans
Kid games freedom and screwdriver
And tell me about the
Piracy group
Yes OU you have my individual Pirate's who people who just download games will distribute the most ever Maybe
Then you have fees
Games
And group
Beaufort MO
There's a lot more attention that is 1 cold
Teen X
Asakusa
Babe
Released a tool that
Robber ironically if you didn't pay for it
Hayward temperature
Killswitch
Which of course is Right strange when we talk about pirate
It was stealing games in the first place
If you stole this off where they didn't like that
Destroy my sweater
And then they both have stolen code from other developers included that in the products as well
And then in another case
You'll have these open source communities
Does rivalry that because when one group is selling a product and everyone's distribution for free that's not ideological
Frictionless
And then that's the coolest when you get back in adults
These people where do they find it
Probably the majority of this community
Twerking and discos
Be gaming
Social chat platform
So you be logged in in
If you're playing fortnite or Minecraft at the same time it will stay that next
Profile
Y-disk
I mean why not take a gaming forum
I guess
Seoul today
Privacy social benefit to it
You send someone a link you click it you're in the chat room
But you typically handle into that
Private space unless someone send you the link
And then ease of access
You look into a Discord server your time to come out on
And then the said was massively give you a list
Okay
Fazoli's free Nintendo games you can just download
So they really like
Automated and organized to protest not just of guessing the games also distribution them as well and that's intimately tied in with her
How they communicate
This type of hacking that these
Individuals
Are undertaking I mean is this kind of
Flexicrew Kitty stuff is a sort of basic or is this actually
Sophisticated
So when it comes to hacking the switch
Self
Is pretty dimes
The cases they have
Get possible that these protections on the console itself
They have to find exploits
They have to then
Find a Weight Watchers levers Lowe's
An entire Community around developing the software
To use those and then
To download games as well
It's a really complex
Supply chain
Different hack is doing different things. Ultimately download game
Forgot to ask why are these hackers
So sophisticated
Vacated and going after
Nintendo switch
I mean why not use that for something more
Either lucrative
Or I mean hey one that works
Yeah it's definitely not the most lucrative hiking job I mean nobody's really buying
Nintendo switch exploits on same way they bike ride Zero day or maybe
I mean at the end of the day I love it.
Comes down to
These guys are in
Sanely
Passionate
About Nintendo
Is Hardware software
Chinese games
And that comes out for the full moon
They want to understand how old is console works I want to understand how the ecosystem works
And
Some of the people don't think I'm pirate games they may just have to consult and really enjoy understanding how it works
Villanova's go to the next
Stop stealing as well
Why does this keep happening
Nintendo
Some of the big difference between the Nintendo switch in the Nova consoles like
The PS4 and the Xbox One or whatever maybe
Those two are pretty much connected to the internet all the time
Online connectivity is like an essential part of the products in online gaming as well
Switch is possible
So it's not always going to be online
When you connect to the internet those consoles can check his best empires in games
Best doing it
Suspicious connection whatever maybe
With a switch that doesn't
I mean
Nintendo will still ban people if they tax it
That's probably easier to get around those tracks
Switch news on the PS4
So is Nintendo even aware that there's
Users
Of their products being duct stenosis
Hacking war going on
The mouse game between the Pirates
Nintendo
There was a old floor in Monastery switch chip
710 to eventually fix and that if you buy move multiple switches cause it's to piracy on it
They also change how the service where I can host switches communicate with Lowe's and that's will spank
Proof that being said
It is pretty easy to guess around
Elise Nintendo's
Scans for pirated games
Xbox One pirate who
If you have loads of games and that's like Donkey Kong was that was a
Don't get banned immediately
If he changes Nintendo to Nintendo and just put a bee in the
Company is even nicer
So is really rudimentary Tech
Song
Ashley furniture
Joseph you're somebody who I know is almost an Espionage expert
How did you get tips to the Nintendo gaming Community hack Wars
Yeah so we gone to the story originally because my just had a Jason Cutler wrote about Mario Party
Releasing two days earlier
And we feel well that's pretty interesting but then he gets a Torrance
Twitter direct messages
People killing in this community being lights
It's a lot crazier than that most games
Will come out 2 weeks
Before
Street dice
The strange thing was
Someone was apparently got around to these Discord servers
Messaging people saying
Hey I'm Jason from overboard do you want to chat about that
That was
Someone impersonating already
Clearly trying to get information
11 people makes dogs them
Maybe they make motherboard look bad
Stop
Instantly
There was something else to the screen and see like a Shadyside
This is like counterintelligence
Yaya counterintelligence
Counterespionage amount
Please switch piracy
Almost just make you laugh like you normally report on some really serious stuff and all the sudden you're getting into this Nintendo
Hacking War
Cesspool and it kind of looks similar
When you deal with hackers
Who would like not nation-states and no organized by becoming also the people who
I'm still the same numbers all the switch hack is whatever maybe
They can be technically sophisticated
Give less of a s***
And they will do more outrageous
Stuff like this
Presentation please may you know of course
Hold themselves back will they organize themselves back
These guys have less inhibitions about f****** each other over
Anika manifests itself in
I mean let's talk about this
Doxxing a
Aspect is it something else
Across-the-board
What are some of the examples of these guys doxxing each other
So one case with some sort of internal doors
Disagreement in the largest Nintendo piracy
7 we not exactly sure what happened
But it ended up with people with non-disclosure agreement with Nintendo
Probably Developers
Open maps
Employees
Bing.
This is how people sold
Debates
When they consulted by hacking or Sober by Tool King
How to buy dogs
And then
In another case
Some of the doxxing is
Pretty transphobic
As well I mean you going to have this in a loss of communities and lost it for hacking communities
Particularly
Virulent
In Nintendo switch
You see this transphobia that clearly comes through
In the comments of a post with Lee passing information
And let's talk about this
The transphobia
Watch Friends movie
To say that
This isn't
You know I'm seen in The Gaming Community we know that misogyny and homophobia kind of
Very much
Is pervasive
Yeah it's hard to say about Lee
Aqi motivations of the
Individual DOCSIS I didn't get in touch with them but
You can definitely tell as a heavy transphobic vibe
From the comments posted
Orthodox think this happens in communities elsewhere as well
Particularly pronounce
Penguin
Multiple trans people get dogs
And then
Really talkative
Pacifically full.
It's almost like they would talk to his not just
Because
There was a disagreement in the Nintendo switch hacking scene but really because I trans as well
I just a question I have to ask is
You know
Why
This is all just because
Somebody or
A group of people
Really really
Super give a s*** about a game
I mean it's the same way when you have
The Minecraft that is ddosing each other at the end of the day that is just a video game
Some people really want to screw out
Some people really care about the reputation of the rain said some people just want to watch the willowbend sometime
And in this case some people really care about the reputation tour in piracy group
I mean the end of the day elevator
Comes down to
Prize
I mean how many times you heard of
Hacker
The Dark Knight
Call rights
Men just want to watch the world burn
Thanks for listening to cyber
This be produced by Jason Tabler edit by Galen Mullins
And recorded by mitch rackin
If you like the show please
Describe the review
And tell your friends about us