Eagle one package being delivered today of a company that all started with
Millions in CIA funding its top clients are the many alphabet agencies comprising the American intelligence
Industrial complex gallivanting conservative billionaire founder connected to President Trump
Basically your private spyware dealer
Hawkins surveillance software to the US government
You probably haven't heard of it but it's name is palantir
Actually use palantir to do evil things
Apart Parts these Technologies new technologies are are never intrinsically good and
Lately motherboard reporter Carolyn Haskins expose the disturbing Big Brother powers of their top secret
I'm Bandicoot and this
Decipher
Let's start from the very beginning
Okay
What is palantir and how did it be
Right so pounds here is basically a big data aggregation company and it specializes in
Data from all different types of databases
Companies
Etc
And working for a really big client they can
Mesh all of this information together
And make it actionable and find Connections in a way that an individual human probably wouldn't be
Baidu
So it's been sort of a favorite Organization for
Big government agencies law enforcement
Branches of the Department of
Homeland Security
Branches of the Army and the military
Anything that's dealing with Intelligence on a Mac
Scale has Power Ranger on the radar
So it's an effect this is sort of a private Spike
Company in in many ways
Private spies
It's a good way of putting it I think it's worth noting that
There
County organizes information that other people already have
You know so it's not like palantir is
Ended up itself
Like
Taking data from like
Crime records arrest records
Public records
Other types of
Sources
The organizing and combining it
If that makes
I need information ended up
Itself is useless unless you can do something with it if it's not organized then
Anyone who wants to take advantage of it in any kind of way is going to be able to do that so that's where I found her come
There were talking about spy Networks
Spice in general
I mean information
Power
Right it's the
Houser How big intelligence agency
C-3PO to
Find
Ways of seeing population
Ways of seeing your enemies because they can
Quantify
And analyze data
Yeah like if you can break down
An individual a suspect that you're interested in
And the hundreds of different little data points
You're getting a much
Different picture of how to approach that you know
Tell me about Peter Thiel the founder
Yeah so he was
The founder of one of the early investors I mean you might know him from
The Gawker lawsuit you might know him from
Funding different types of Ventures throughout the years I think
Remember that Island story where he wanted the funds
Island basically you
Kind of this weird bonvillain desk character
That's probably the most efficient way to describe him
Gunning for who's the more Bonville and ask
Person on planet Earth
Yeah yeah
And of course he's known for having sources
You know
Right political associate
Directing his MBA
Ways that reflect
Now the beginning a palantir one thing that always caught my attention was
It was a pain
Early
Recipient
Gif
Yeah
I think it's a good example of
If you're like a company in your early stages in your able to get a government contract I can really
Float you through those septic
Polaris
Bring me to a level that you might not be able to otherwise
I've been busy with your stupid ascribing is this company has had deep connections to
Intelligence agencies in the United States
They do actually contract with
The FBI the CIA DHS
Special forces that they have in the path of the Desert from the premium
Law enforcement
And defense contracts in the entire world
Right yeah and it's interesting because so obviously palantir isn't the only company that these intelligence Asian
These are giving
Big money contracts to but especially when it's combined with
Other types of contracts with
I don't know for instance like
Thomson Reuters
Beer which is just basically another
Policing law enforcement School
Can be combined with credit Paul which is like
A predictive policing school which is sort of been criticized for
Sort of
Broken Window style policing perpetuating that style of policing
I'm so the danger here isn't even Justin talents your itself it's the way that it can be combined
Using multiplied with every other contract that the government has
And this is a company that was like originally exposed in 2010 by
Anonymous hackers
Visit has been floating around for years
Now
You got to scoop ritas
Something was doing with the police
How do you get it
Right so
I was sort of interested in palantir is relationship
West law enforcement agencies around the country so I filed
Over a hundred I don't know the final tally just
Public information request with local police departments around the country to see if they had any kinds of
Contractor correspondence
With palantir
And almost all of them came up empty except for Palo Alto
And Palo Alto mentioned
Do the Northern California regional Intelligence Center
They had access to palantir
Software
So then obviously I filed
Another
Public records request.
I called the ncric I was told recently that is called Nick Rick
I guess I'll just call it neck Rec but anyway when I followed it to Negra
I guess that's when I got back
Over a dozen documents that really shed light on
The relationship between
I was here and then and
What came back included
A user manual which
Filled with dragon was very difficult to parse but
If you started just go through it carefully it gives you
A decent amount of insight into how it works on a practical level
And I also got payment records and such which
Indicate that
Over 300 cities and 14 counties or able to get access to palantir through this Regional ontology
Concentre what's
Sometimes called a fusion Center because basically its role is to take data
From tons of different sources both public
And private
And to combine them to work on special types of Investigations
But what's interesting about the ncric is that
Local police departments can say
We're working on this case and we need power and fear in order to solve that so it can be used to
I dress pretty much any type
The crime that you can think of
Sweet describing then
Is piece of software that
Police officer
Can type into a database
Namor
License plate
Naked Zen
Put together all of the vectors of information across public records
And
Federal state records
Municipal records
Start to paint a picture of an individual even if that person is not
Guilty of a crime
Right so basically
I don't really get into detail about like
The subpoena process I mean in terms of like the automatic License Plate Reader
So that's kind of a big feature
That's highlighted in the user manual you do have to enter a case number
People search you have to
To put in
A reason for doing the search
And whether that person is innocent or guilty or not
I don't really get into that in the article
But
It seems intuitively that there's ways that this
Potentially be abused
The fact that the
Search field is kind of an open field
But
I think it's worth highlighting here is just with your power of the tool
And the fact that you're able to get
I mean not even just
Name address
Gender or sex
And that kind of thing you can get
Email
Bank account information anything that's included on your license like height weight eye color
And if you're combining that with data from the automatic License Plate Reader
You can see your travel history
Because if you're associated
With a particular license plate
And
They've been able
To capture that at say like a toll booth or something you take a picture of a license plate
To that so you just type in the license plate number
You can see where you've been
And when
Because the location in the timestamp they're both locked
So
Sweet describing a sort of this
This truly
Very modern
Powerful
Big Brother machine that is
That is essentially powered by palantir
The CIA funded
It's really like
Like omnipotent knowledge
It's really really incredible and unsettling
Disorder think about
Just
Galaxy information
I can be
Used against different types
Individuals
And Hound
Making a profit off of
This is something if they've designed that they didn't then sell around the country
An around-the-world to I think they work with other governments
They work with corporations to major corporations
Yeah found here is a really
Expensive software in fact sometimes it
So expensive that
Different governments
Can't afford to renew it
But
Lucky for the governments that are using them at least in the case of the northern California regional until
Elgin Centre
And what's called a Perpetual license
Which means that even after the last
Contract. Expires they still have access to palantir and they can still continue to use it
I just won't get like
Updates
So that not only
Eliminate
Paper trail
There I'm in terms of like after the contract. Expires but
It basically means that all of this information is
Indefinitely in the hands
The police
Now I'm just probably good time to ask you
What does the name pounds
Here come from
Well
Apparently it's from Lord of the Rings
And it's some sort of
All-knowing orb
Full disclosure not read Lord of the Rings
Full disclosure
Lord of the Rings near Dover here
Parable monstrous wizard uses
To look around
Middle aerosat anyone whenever he wants
Yeah I love that
What old is Bruno Mars
We have worked
Yeah it's great when you're putting the moral Foundation of your company until like an evil nerd thing
That's great very reassuring that never ends well
Imagine reading that book and being like
That sounds great
Imagine that being here take away I mean
Again I think
Wait I did read I read The Hobbit
I did I do know that there's very clear distinctions between Good and Evil
Seemingly when I read it so Saruman is not a good dude
She was actually at one point
Like a semi good dude
And then
Becomes schist
Montana
Like a monstrous evil character
This is what Peter Thiel took his inspiration from when he's like you know what I mean
Bu founder of
Surveillance company
And I'm going to call pounds
It's nice to sort of take pride in that and
Michuzi
In character
Fur for him
But you know this is a company that has
Incredible amount
Of power but also the relationships that has
Also
Incredibly powerful right so we know that there's been some weird connections between palantir Cambridge analytica
And Facebook
This is a company that has is not only itself extremely powerful and has
A lot of relationship
Within the US intelligence community and longpoint
In fact the most powerful agencies in the entire world
It also has these weird relationships
With
People like Facebook
Is Mark Zuckerberg
Did you ever hear Mark Zuckerberg testimony when he was questioned
In the senate committee on palantir
I don't know if I did actually I remember watching the Senate testimony but I don't remember that but suppose
It is incredibly weird
Do you know who palantir is
Baidu
Some people have referred to them as a Stanford analytica
Do you agree
Senator I have not heard that
Okay do you think palantir taught
Cambridge analytica press reports are saying
How to do these tactics
Senator I don't know
To me what makes this company really fascinating and and
The story that you did today
Exposing
This manual
That allows
To catch a glimpse of just what the company can do and get on you
Is
There's a lot known about it
Yeah it's
It's funny because there's been a lot of stories that have been done about
Apologia can manage different types of information systems but if you just
I mean let's say if you go on like palantir is like
YouTube page and look at his promotional videos I made a video that's like how does palantir work
It's just a bunch of Graphics that show nothing
Mountaire brings in many databases into one system
How many pounds are brings in the following database
Crime and arrest report information
Field interview cards
Automatic License Plate Reader information
Like they absolutely no insight into how this works
On a practical level
I was interesting about the Goddess that they actually include examples of the interphase and what happens when you make a potato
Type of search and the type of results you got
Like for instance you can make a search for a person's name
Get a lot of results and then
Filtered on the right side by different types of like
First and last name matches different addresses
And pretty much any possible datapoint associated with that person and there is like
I got two dozen different datapoints and like
Another half dozen data points that
Describe those former datapoints just like hundreds of different ruminations
Away season catalog
People
That's the thing is that
People Like Us
They're working in the space note palantir is
And
This company could
Information on Earth
But the wider public has no idea
What town
Right
And I think
I think Thomas has gotten some attention lately because of its
It's contact with ice
Which is expiring soon and activist of men
Speaking up and
Encouraging this contract to end and even when palantir was invited to host
Conference
I think if I think it was at one of the University of California campuses
Activists were saying that they didn't want to volunteer to be
Conference that it would be
An insult to the kind of business that it does because it basically manages
Different case records that can be used
To help build up legal cases against
People who
Could potentially be
Deported people who are being held in detention
And so it's gotten attention in
And not contacts
But I think what
Sort of makes me sad is
The fact that when I
Find out about this whole Perpetual license
Like even if it's contract
The palantir is
Aspiring
I mean we can look at what's going on with the ncric that doesn't mean that ice won't be able to use palantir anymore
They're either going to get a service that works almost exactly the same way
Which as matter fact that's what's happening with that
Particular agent
They said powder is too expensive
We're replacing it with SAS
Which is basically going to do something
Similar
And with ice
Even if they don't renew that contract that just means they won't get updates or like Live help
If there are troubleshooting a problem they can still use it
They can still track and log immigrants in build cases against them in that same
Detail oriented way
This really is like the machine of
Big Brother
The Leviathan
Yeah
I don't know
Just kind of bums me out
I can tell a story really did affect you this is something you really care about
Yeah I don't know it's just
It's disheartening to think about like
Every single way that way you can move the world is
Can be against us
I feel like it's been something that's been really
I don't know how
Something about it
About it a lot lately like
In a hunter related somewhat unrelated note you know just the fact that
A lot of stores are peddling to
Like not accepting cash
Meaning that you know
If you're using your debit or credit card these are all Purge
Just as I can be
Tracked and can potentially get into
Other people's hands whatever this is
A data broker or some other kind of way
Every system that catalogs are moved is not designed to be used in our favor and never is
You know what I think is a great example of that like is to as long as that information is actionable
It's going to be used against people
Yeah
Just leaving in terms of like
Bringing this back to Lord of the Rings and again speaking vaguely as someone who has not read the book
I don't know it's trying to have these
These understandings of Good and Evil especially when it seems to have a
Pretty clear association with evil and the book if I'm speaking correctly
I don't know there's just a lot of things that seem to be in cancer
About that
Xiamen
Well Carolyn thank you for being on Cyber this is your cyber debut isn't it
Thanks for having me you'll be back on again I'm sure soon when you
Discovered something else that will piss off a Silicon Valley spying on me