Virus
Eagle One
Package deal
Used to be the Presidents had to be like war heroes or at least serve
Gone to an Ivy League school and been in some weird sanctimonious Noble family of New England
Open 2020
We could be facing a much different type of pedigree
Hacker in Chief
Former Texas Congressman Beto O'Rourke
The latest candidate
Enter the race for president
Of the United States
He's already one of the top contenders
The Democratic ticket
It will face off against Donald Trump
He also happens to be a member of one of the most OG
And most radical hacking groups
Of all
Time
The Cult of the dead cow
They were Anonymous before Anonymous stop pissing on the seat
The well Sac before lulzsec got on his diapers and so on and so forth
Born online in the 80s in active
In to mm
The legendary group fought against government surveillance internet censorship
Expose widespread vulnerabilities
To the dismay of Corporation
I mean the CDC is known to have literally coined the term activist
Adecco 1998 released back orifice
Early version of a trojan horse exploiting Microsoft vulnerabilities
Allowing hackers to gain control of any system using Windows
Which attracted the interest of the
Yacht
At the time the group also claimed to have hacked into the system
TIAA
Last week Reuters revealed that Beto O'Rourke
Whitney early member of the group back in the eighties
And going by the handle
Psychedelic
World War
We're here today to talk to Oxblood
Longtime and influential member
Blue Beto's Secret
Before
It was revealed
World
Explain the Godfather Packers
Sat down with us
Bado
CDC
I've been Mac who this is cyber
No news has it been 4
CDC San Simeon
News the biggest news
To bring you back in the map in a long time
I mean it was
We knew it was coming
Because
We've been speaking with
Patrolman the author of the book on the CDC
And a better was part of that book
So we knew it was coming and people were thinking of well it's is going to be in trucking we were actually much more focused on
We just started figured out okay there's going to be some residual interest but
Just like say on social media
I think my name got Associated somehow with one of the early tweets about the announcement and the next
250 new followers nothing my God what is this
It's just kind of crazy but
I think I'll of course we're going to get more attention and
A lot of people
He sort of grew up with the CDC
And we've been through because the group's been around so long I mean
Started in 1984 so been around for a thousand years
At this point liking in the internet here is yeah
Yeah I think it's because we've gone through a number of iterations there with BBs days and then
The early web days and then there was the releasing
Back orifice
Activism after that sand
Revenge Shirley quieten
It mostly because you know
People have
Jobs mortgage payments
Kids
We've been doing a lot more work but again the group is
I mean active in the sense
Instead
We're still very much connected to
Either you know startup some people working
Government some people work for military contractors it's
Is pretty broad the Spectrum to the CDC grew up
Am I being clear it's
The Cult
Of the dead cow
Exactly did I die
It's kind of funny that everybody
Who hasn't heard of the group before they hear a CDC and they're confused
The Center for Disease Control like what it what are those guys doing on the internet
Yes it is the CDC
And
Going to be fun
Moving forward especially
Sing the kind of reactions that Beto gets
And you started in in 1984 in Texas
Sister named after a slaughterhouse
A peek at that Dusty files that are online which I'm sure the traffic on those
Change completely over the last
Over the last five days
You know you got a real sense
Sort of like this
Old school
Hacker group
You know you say a lot of outrageous
Shet
Anarchic
And you'll have that start
Originally it was just a
Very small group
People
Just like a couple of local guys from
Lubbock Texas
And then
The BBS scene was just sort of taking off and
Mostly it was
Young guy
Teenage boys
And
At the time I mean
Access to
Two computers friend
Was more or less limited to
Kids who had some cut usually who had some kind of connection
University Town signals to the early
HotPads for like say
Boston
San Francisco
Houston University towns with
Computer science department
Like every other guy I know
Who started at that time usually a parent
Worked in Tech
Or
The mask
Department of some University
So they tended to be
Middle class
Young
Men boys
In University Town
And then
That was kind of the
I don't know that that's exactly the structure of it but
You know where these things were starting up
And then from that
Bulletin boards for just kind of popping up all over the place and that was really
The beginning of the scene and so the
The CDC
Should have hooked up with
A bunch of
The board said they had an affinity within the group sort of came from that and the reputation
For the group spread
In the early days to those a bulletin board
I thirst for you provide milk from my balls love it
Good gorgeous but those that do love me or leave me
Beat
How has rhythm
Wax my ass rub my balls
The cow has risen
Provide the Psychedelic warlord with with potatoes handle
And you know
He wrote some pretty outrageous stories
One of them being
Basically something that was like a murder fan
ICU
I'm running down to
Two kids in his car and killing
Who is Extreme
I mean but again I'm not going to
I'm not going to
Fault someone for something they wrote when they were a kid
Yeah I mean I think that particular story is like
Kind of bad Stephen King writing and I wouldn't be surprised if he would be reading this kind of stuff himself
Is really voracious reader
Plus the fact that young guy as you noted and
It was more lesson keeping with the the tenor of the chief I'll collection
Everybody was trying to sort of
Be outrageous and test boundaries
One of the
The first files
Auntie Monroe underground which was the BBS set
A swamp rat
Or Grandmaster rat is he is now called
Who started the CDC is called a gerbil feed bomb
And it's
Crazy annie's
It's
I think it's hilarious
Still one of my my favorite Chief I'll spend
Definitely you know
Young Smart
Guys who can type fast and are trying to compete about
Who can be the most outrageous
Or
Just the sort of test what you can get away with online
I think it's kind of like you know the more outrageous you could be the more attention you might get
And the greater the reputation you might have in the group so
I think things were very competitive under a lot of young elf males in the group
And quite frankly there's
It's just that we be grown up and and write better than we used to
Yeah I mean it's also just seems like it's very much so
Like a lot of
OG packing
Especially in that.
Shantrell each other
You know
Do as much as
You can just order
Buick split
It is possible
You may not always mean what you say or what you
You do you're just
Doing it to
Frankly just to f*** with
Agree
Especially at that time
With the age of the kids and kind of
The direction to tpal groups for moving in
It was a big competition that is sort of gross-out party
Idyllwild
Really was done tongue and cheek
I never liked it the first time
I came across
The CDC in a bunch of these other groups
I spend a
Ton of Time online reading all of these files and some were just horrible in
You could tell they were bitten by people couldn't especially right well
It is kind of silly in a certain way and then I kept coming across the
CDs out of the text files that were
We're coming out of the CDC and I thought
It's something about them I couldn't quite put my finger on
I always thought there was something a little deeper going on below the surface and it reminded me of a comment that
Who wrote this but there was some kind of profile in the New Yorker
About David Letterman
And the phrase I remember was said he's the king of knowing silliness
Now you can say
Ridiculous things
Tonya you couldn't figure out why they were funny but then
After awhile you realize I was actually a little bit deeper
Everything not to
Overthink this too much
You know something I kind of picked up on from the CDC that
Of course silly on top
I have the feeling that
The people associated with the group were doing really interesting and different things so
That's What attracted me to do
ICDC in the first
Tell me about Beto and what
His involvement
Was
Initially
So he was Huey psychedelic Warlord
Yeah I mean I maybe not
Best person to ask
Because I wasn't associated with the group at that time but from
From what I've heard
He started a board called Taco land
Which was I believe named after
A song from the Dead Milkmen
And at that time I think it's also interesting like
Roughly 1908 1984 when the
CDC was started and there were other
Roots
Around
The holster the punk ass hoes was a huge
Thanks
I know that punk really influence
A lot of the guys very early members
Of the CDC
Adjust the added to do it yourself
Andy institution Andy organization
This this whole kind of spirit of
Breaking out starting a new way
Kind of rebellion
Against a friend
Forms weather is like
No government through politics
Baby
Rihanna
Business this kind of thing
It was
And that also was very much
Certain part of that scene in the sense that he was definitely
Influence that sell young teen by punk music and then
Got his own thing going on I just think that
As a result of that she made
Connections with
Like-minded people in that singing
And then he stayed within the orbit
Of the CDC for a while
Yeah
I think he was active as far as I know he was active for both
For five years
And then
When he was I think it was about 18 he went to
You move to
New York P was going to Columbia University I think he's studied English
So
She was in New York and there were a couple of people like their number of
Assertive
Hacker groups
Then
More or less located or a lot of the members located in New York there is like
Legion of the underground and masters of deception and probably a couple of other groups
So there is definitely a scene in people would have known each other
And a couple of the CDC guys were in New York and of course
There's the
Hackers on planet Earth convention
That happens I think it's every two years in New York so
Etta would have pain
Definitely in and around that
Altruis University days
And if you worked in some kind of bias
Speed during that time
As far as I recall I went to a party
What's that
He would have been there I mean is definitely at the same party
I'm sure I would have met him because there aren't a lot of people but I don't really distinctly remember meeting
Somebody posted a picture the other day of the same party and
I recognized everybody and I
I thought I kind of recognize bad O2 because
He stood out a little bit because everybody was kind of like blue hair or black t-shirts are y'all dirty punky
And he's kind of look
Barry J crew
Yankees always being
A kind of different guy and also I mean one of the interesting things about the cult of the dead cow
It's not what you would call your
Typical hacker group
Like people come from
Meaning of course there are
People with huge
Security in Computing skills
And they're also
You know the number of people who get all their
On computers and they work
UNO online
And we got a Wacom
PhD
One guy was
Former assistant district attorney
Another warmer
Some College University professors
And one guy who passed away sadly a few years ago was a former contractor with the CIA
And you know
Duckling read that
People in the CDC we're kind of
Keeping this
Secret while Beto
Rose the ranks
Why was there an interest in keeping this
The secret that he was a member of
Well I think the true reasons first
We realize that
His association with a group
What could cause him
Either
Male some embarrassment or opening him up to attacks together thing and actually that
More important reason is that
People are in the CDC you're having
Everybody is used to handle
Basically Ruland and people with handles that we just don't disclose
You know who is in the group we don't attach a handle to a name
It's different
If
Somebody else themselves and they say okay I used to be a member
My name is whatever in this was my
Formal handle that's fine
They chose to do that so you know people can talk about it or not talk about it
It's just been our policy that we don't
Y'all talk about who the members are we don't put names to handles
Do you actually interact with a bunch of these
These members
Almost all of the members eyemed
I'm pretty sure I do know their names but fairly often we just refer to each other by handles
I'm definitely like when we're in public if we're at like some kind of conference everybody is introduced by there and Allure
We refer to each other by Handel's it's just kind of
A protocol
But I think there are like some people
I know that I I've heard their real names but it's just that I keep forgetting them because I identify with them
Much more by the handle
Do you agree that
The Cult of the dead cow is sort of this
Precursor to anonymous mean you know a lot of people say you coined the term active
We were definitely the first group to use the term online
We
Decided
And it was something that we wanted to work in
And in some ways you can say that
The CDC and Anonymous have sort of structural similarities be started out as
Sort of fun
You know media pranking groups
You can say that we weren't that serious in the beginning
We were just about
Having fun in publishing text files and Anonymous was
Doing whatever they were doing
You know on 4chan
And then at a certain point
Anonymous
I decided to go public in a certain way and I think it was Project
Chanala G
Which was the
Anti-scientology campaign that they started
So
They started being more active
And showing up
NBA kind of physical presence in the streets and
Doing that kind of thing so
It actually created a huge
Rake in the group
Dad
People who were the original sort of anonymous people
4chan
Just like Furious Sunday
We're calling all of today
The people who are doing assertive hacktivists style and painting
They started referring to the most immoral f***
The insult
Was not the f**
Army for using bad language
It was the insult was moral
That they were doing something that was like who needs that you know it's
Stupid
You know you're ruining the reputation of the group by becoming so serious
That was kind of the the anonymous side of things and the split in that group
And then
Back I guess it was 1999
We started officially started working and hacktivism and there wasn't like
A split in our group I mean it wasn't you like people weren't outraged within the cult of the dead cow
Actually
Pretty much everybody thought it was really cool and was quite supportive
I think it was much more outside the group that we got some criticism
No lots of people think that I ruined the CDC because
Started bleeding
Serious
Evolution of the group it's just that
You know we figured that
You know we're interested
In
You know helping people who were
Living behind National firewalls to get on the net
We started developing circumvention tools and
It was never to do anything then to help people get access to the net we weren't we didn't have a specific agenda
You know we want you to you know do whatever it's just get online
See whatever is on the internet and then do whatever you like
So
There are some similarities in terms of say the way
But what's a cult of the dead cow an anonymous got started
And there was a sort of evolution
In the group
Hell yeah I guess
I mean some people have said that the
Anonymous couldn't exist without the CDC in a way
That may or may not be true I'm not sure I have a
Complete opinion on that
Similarities with the groups and
Topeka quite honest I mean
I was really impressed by
Some of the stuff that Anonymous did especially during the Arab Spring
Valuable work and they should be respected for that I mean the groups within Anonymous that did that of course
Wasn't
The group is all I'm in their number of cells doing different offs
How is it that
Did the CDC went from like this
She file sharing
Group
You know the group that
Dropped black worth
Essentially kind of Harold in this
List. Of hacked
We started 84 and then I guess it was like around 92 or so
When the web
Weather Cutler
It was kind of like the shadow CDC was back in the
Yoobi Bi-State
And it was also a very kind of marginal thing like
Really not that many people
Where in the freaking CNN that have computers and word
Dialing into
Bulletin board systems
So it was definitely a certain time
And a certain community
Particular a song
By the time the web came round I mean the
The core group in the CDC was there and
There was a bit of a revolving door
Echoing on the
People sorted
Came and went in there
Sort of new Evolution of the group
Southern a bunch of new people
And
We were
Getting used to being on the web
And I think also a lot of thought
That you know it's time to do something new
What can we get involved in at the time Microsoft
Was like it was a huge operating system but absolutely the worst for security
Kind of the enemy of the hacking community
Gary change company now that takes
Security
Seriously
Patak's and like 97 98 99 in there
It was just
Joke
As far as those security was concerned so we decided that we would point that out and
It was a combination of putting together some really
Incredible soft
And then having a sort of media operation
So it's like we were our own
Sort of
Software company NPR age
It just sort of caught everybody's imagination and it was a big alternative party
We turned into a bunch of sort of Internet rock stars
It was a very different
Internet then
I was supposed to know there wasn't really it wasn't a social media Intranet
So things have changed
There's lots of mainstreaming
A lot more surveillance
That was fun
Yeah it was basically an evolution of coming from a sort of
Very much an underground scene
Into the mainstream
And I guess that was really the big difference
Okay so
We fast forward now
The 20/20
Presidential alert
Beto O'Rourke
Some say the leading candidate now for the Democrats
We could
Ostensibly
Have the first president
Who wives
Part of a hacker
Being a member of that group yourself
And seeing what's happened with The Cult of the dead cow
With Anonymous and then seeing that
I mean does that blow your mind a little bit
So is I mean it's it's definitely interesting and I think in many ways inevitable
I really think the most interesting thing is that
With somebody like Beto or
Or candidate
Or a person of his age and experience
The way everything is going I mean everything is digital
There are things like cyberwar and
Election tampering and all kinds
Things going on
Online I think most people
Knowing where
Society and politics is going Winfield Dairy comfortable
With somebody who is comfortable in that world
And especially
You know it
If you have those kind of long-standing connection
Yeah like you know what security is and you you know how you can get
The best advice about how to
Pretty much do anything online than that I think it's an f+ I think it's fantastic
I think the the only assertive tricky bid if we're talking about Beto
Is
Opposition research and people trying to slam and smear the guy
First Step he did when he was like
14 15 16 years old
But I think also something that's interesting
Barack Obama was the first
President and presidential candidate to
Smoke pot
At the time he did that
People talk that's no big deal
And it was kind of a nothingburger for a lot of people and it wasn't a talking point after that okay
The country doesn't care
I like I kind of think we're cute
Approaching.
With
Beto and in Canada
People talk about you know when I was 14 I did a little hacking and I did some phone freaking
I'm not proud of what I wrote but you know I learned a lot
I know how the internet works now and stuff like that
I think the
It's really like I don't really believe this whole sort of better ways hackers story
You know in a couple of weeks I just don't think it's going to have much resonance
I need as as an attack
No I don't actually think it's going to help
I mean he's like his here's the thing is
It's very clear that Donald Trump has a very limited understanding of how the internet works
Besides
Twitter and even then
I'm not
Kosher
But
And that's interesting because other than Obama I don't think there's ever been a president
Who actually understands the
The internet
In a way that
Younger people or Internet specialist
Do
And I think that that is going to be interesting to see how he wields that if
He makes it out of that
Democratic
Cool Canada
I mean I think it's definitely a generational thing like the older the candidate
More than likely
Less they know about
The internet being online the digital all of this stuff
Generally speaking the younger people are then the more they understand
A teenager when he got his first computer
So you know when you have a goat
30 + years of experience online and with computers you're going to know a fair bit
Are you somebody like trump it is actually a perfect example I mean he doesn't even use he doesn't have email
Is never used email
And although he's on Twitter I mean I think he just understands it as a vanity platform
Eddie knows that
A lot of people he can cut through
News and his tweets become the news
It is himself as a kind of
40 character
Publisher
So you can get away with a lot and
His bully pulpit is used to bully people
I think people
Like this
Beto candidates like him of his age and experience
You're definitely the future
And I think increasingly
People will trust them to make the right decisions and feel comfortable
That they know where a society and technology is going and maybe even going to help
Paper way to the Future where these things are going
5G is coming up next year
That's going to be a huge deal it's already a
Certain political deal with the white house trying to
Hammering away at Huawei and
And influenza
Policy decisions in different countries
Who is going to deploy
These Technologies and what vendors are going to use so
If something is only going to get bigger
And we want people to understand
I mean look at it
They can be the first
Cracker and cheese
Actually this is very interesting thing and maybe a contrast about
Say the current Administration and whatever the next
There's no sort of cybersecurity czar
Other than I think maybe Rudy Giuliani mites
I have some kind of title
Be somebody like Julia he knows absolutely nothing about the internet I mean next to nothing
And
But the kind of people we need in those positions
You know the kind of people
Either work for the military or the NSA or
Some kind of
Computer handheld technical genius I mean these are the kinds of people
You want filling these positions and none of them are there in this current Administration and
Moving forward I think that's something that will definitely be seeing and could even be a campaign issue
Another
Well thank you for telling me about
The possible neck
Hacker
President and chief
Ever going to have
And forgiveness little school old school knowledge on one of the founding communities of
Hackers
You really going to be in a book
What mean you are in a book but
Sims 4 weird light
Historical moment
DIY Dino that romance book is sort of on the
History answer the participants' the revolving door of the CDC in
Where the group came from and where it's going to
I think it's it's going to be very interesting I'm not exactly sure what is going to be in this book
I think it's going to be a good reader intro man is a serious writer
And she's done some other good stuff
Master phenomenon
He's the right kind of person
To do this kind of book and I think we're all looking forward to it
Me too
Thanks so much
We'll talk soon
This week's episode was produced by Lorenzo French sedky recorded in edited by John northcraft
Thanks for listening to cyber we back next week