Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered next to the best iPhone hackers in the world
That's the question hundreds of people watching him we're all wondering
Bueno just one thing before thing thinks the white elephant in the room exact
Did we get it
Well
Could ask us next time we talk
Smile as you wrapped up one of the most anticipated talks at the black hat security conference in Las Vegas
In August of 2016 in attendance
Researchers from a company that sells iPhone crack and services to Cops around the world
Packers and apples own employees
Soilmec had dumped explored the secure Enclave processor one of the most closely guarded secret app
Apple encryption
On the iPhone
No nose how we did it
Motherboard senior staff writer Lorenzo franceschi because
I spent the last few months solving a mystery
And in doing so he stumbled upon a hush-hush iPhone
It's become one of the most important rules in the multimillion-dollar iPhone hacking industry
This week I'm talking to Lorenzo about his investigation
We've also scored an interview with a dealer
Clandestinely sells prototype and rare iPhones
On Twitter
I've been a coup in this is cyber
Lorenzo
Breaking the iPhones and Apple products
Not very easy
Yeah used to be easy but we're talking about 10 years ago or more
These days breaking into an iPhone
May actually be the hardest thing you can do as a hacker
Almost everyone agrees that the iPhone is the most secure computer on Earth
It's the most secure
Yeah I mean the most security can get your hands on
Because I don't like back in the old
Hacker scene
Like jailbreaking an iPhone
Big deal
Like you're basically
Human walking across
You know the infosec community
What was that guy's name
The kid who broke it
Gmod I interviewed him
Yeah I used to be that people would just like post
Get out there
Bedazzle
Be dozens house hacking iPhones on Twitter or YouTube
And brag about it
These days people don't do that and it's all because
Not only because it's harder
But also because
The Diwali of that is so high
UW just don't give it away on Twitter or YouTube
Let's look at something like vulnerabilities and the the price for is your day on the black market Iran
The open market
Very high for iPhone
So
What is this winter Jack was talking about like millions of dollars millions of dollars
Crowd fans and stuff like that
They offer literally like three four million dollars 2 million 1 million depending on exactly what vulnerability is bad
We're talking about
Yes at least six figures
In some cases
7 figures
Which leads us to
Your latest story
Which is to say
Maybe it's not so hard after
Yeah I still hard but one of the things that make iPhones really hard to hack
Is that they're basically
They're almost Black Box
Price
You cannot
Just connect your iPhone to your computer and start like
Going through the file system read the kernel or whatever
I guess is not bought
And that's because apple does not want you to do it because one of the
Strategies that apple
Employees to make it to you know make their phones more secure is to keep the to make them very obscure
It's what's called a security biopsy
Security
A lot of iOS
Is impossible to read as a user at Seminole just found an iPhone and connect to the computer
So what we found is that there are special iPhones if you will
Some people call them prototypes some people call them development iPhones
The more Technical and probably accurate way to call them is a fused iPhones
These are iPhones that have security features
Either turned off or that you can turn off
So
Assault describe them as a pre jailbroken iPhones
Play centuries are iPhones with fewer security
Measures enabled
So if you're somebody researching
And iPhone
Din tai fung researcher
Going through this phone and finding vulnerabilities on it
Far easier than if you were to have
An actual just off the market off the shelf
IPhone yeah I mean it's still complicated is still something and not everyone can do and like you know you still need to know what you're doing
But essentially the barriers of Entry are lowered
You know it's like
Breaking into a house
Where the
Lock is already like
And I'm broken or something like that
That's a terrible metaphor
Yeah I mean it's nothing infosec
Yeah I mean you still need to do the work and you still need to find an ability you know exploited and whatever
I cannot see buddy that is the first time that that allows you to
You have a head start
It's a little easier than it is
If someone just sends you an iPhone
But now
Who has Beast
So far as we can tell everyone who does security search on iPhone
Asda
But this includes also some very
It's very almost in city of companies that
We've reported on
That also
You know use this information maybe for the dark arts of infosec versus
According to our sources companies like cellebrite
Have them and abused them in the past
These companies don't like to talk about this security researchers don't like to talk about this like the sources that we have in the story are most
What's the anonymous
FR multiple reasons but also because
It's kind of a
Open Secret in that community
So people who hack iPhone for living know that these devices exist
They know that their friends have them
They seen them
But they don't like to talk about it in public
Because
First of all
It's unclear
If it's legal to
Even have them
Because
These phones essentially the or the way that my sources have described it
The fall of tracks
Or they like Escape
Shenzhen
So someone in China is like
Taking these phones and getting in getting them on this underground grey market
And selling them to celebrate
Companies like
Potentially NSO group correct
Maybe
We don't know about any self example celebrate we're pretty confident
What kind of companies are celebrating NSO group what do they do
Yeah these are companies that essentially their whole business is hacking iPhones or providing tools to hack
Do iPhones or remind the kids of satellite they also do Android hacking and stuff like that
But these companies don't just do that they also support some pretty brutal regimes they sell these tools to whoever pays
So we're talkin about
You know celebrate used to have a male celebrities rumored to be the company that broke into the
Some of the famous San Bernardino iPhone
Where if you remember the FBI wanted to read the date on inside of this locked phone
I belong to the terrorist to kill the
2000 people in San Bernardino in that 70
So these are companies like we're talking about the the other company that was named in the store is called coralium
They're not as well-known as cellebrite and they're not exactly and and iPhone hacking company what they do is
They provide a platform where you can emulate iOS on a computer
So you essentially connect to
Grantland.com if you have an account there pretty expensive
But and then you can just create virtual Machines of iOS which until now and they're the first
Odoo it was impossible
It was impossible because apple as
Specifically designed the iPhone to make that almost
So coralium is used by people such as a security which is a company we wrote about last year does it cost
Can I profile them
And what is asthma security vulnerabilities into Android iPhone
Homes and then sell those tools and tell those vulnerabilities
Governments around the world
What kind of government
In the case of Azimuth were talking about five eyes
So NSA CIA FBI MI6 and MI5
Responding agencies in Canada and Australia
But yeah they're like Anna so essentially there
During that business
They are selling things to government
Define vulnerabilities and instead of reporting reporting them to the companies where they found a polyp in
They sell them to government
So that you can use them to hack people
And I guess that's the thing to about something like this
When companies that typically make money
Selling
Ways of breaking consumer goods
Like the iPhone
I'm not reporting them to Apple
But rather
Using them to sell
The government set a reviews than four
We can only imagine what reasons
This presents a pretty big problem to Apple
That that sells itself
Asbestos
Security by obscurity
We're better than Android Androids buggy
It's insecure don't use it where the best
Cuz that is essentially just undermines I have this whole Underground Market that
Has
Basically call Bush on that has long touted the security of its products
As a marketing tool you don't like I mean they've used this literally as marketing you know years ago it was those famous ads
Where do you know the younger looking guy was making fun of the older looking guy was like supposed to be windows
And it was like oh you have viruses I don't you know cuz I'm a Mac
You know more recently at CES this year Apple put up like a giant
Adding Las Vegas saying what happens on your iPhone stays on your iPhone
Basically saying you know we respect your privacy but also our phones are more secure than Android
I know they are like they still are
I mean we could probably the Bates weather
A Google pixel is
Almost as secure as an iPhone
The point is that you said
There is a growing industry whose job is to hack into iPhone
And it is fueled by these devices at least in part
Are you part of the suit for me is like
It's typical
Hacker
Behavior to its
You tell them you can't hack something is
Scared for you it's
Difficult to get into
And then suddenly now you have this
Group of very intelligent
Possibly nefarious
Minded people
Court and 10th
I'm breaking into the iPhone
And they
Sounds like
They will do everything they can to do it
And some of these people may be the same ones who apple is invited to the
Bug Bounty programs
Which is not going very well as the reporter in the past
And this was Apple's just to remind your audience Like in 2016
Apple launch the ID IOS bug bounty program essentially asking the iPhone researchers independent
Independent iPhone researchers
To reach out to Apple and Report bags that they found
So that they would be rewarded with
Pretty good rewards and I were talking about off 220 and $50,000
And the
For around a year
Program basically
Did not gather any reports
As far as we could tell
Because no one wanted to
No one wanted to record this box because they're not that
Cheap
Essentially what what apple is
Offering is too long
Or what you can actually get in the tub multibillion-dollar
Apple which I think is it is
One of the most
I think it is the most profitable businesses in all of America and all the world
Is getting peanuts for these
These mess up
Xiamen Peanuts movie is not the right word for you
Elsewhere
Money Talks
I mean it goes back to like her who pays more and
Yeah what are your priorities the only feeling iPhone researcher
Do you want to give the back to Apple and get like you know a tenth of what you could get
If you give it to
Cellebrite Lawrenceville or
The roadium
I know you know
Some people
Will tell you that they prefer to get paid less
And reported to Apple
Some people will tell you well you know I'm going to get paid more and I'm going to go help the good guys
Aunt Paris and bad guys
Detective companies that say
Did you list we can have the terrorists
We all know just like weapons companies
They use the same sort of subjects
And it's quite often not quite true
Cuz we don't love these different types of
Organizations are described are also in touch with
Repressive regimes that use it to track journalist or activist
So when Apple's n
Advertises itself as the most secure platform if your
If you're going to buy a cell phone you have to buy cell phone that is but
If you're going to
Goldust
I mean
This really blows kind of the cover off of
Maybe it's not and
It's certainly
You know
The Apple Store
That seems to be sort of this church
Of Secrets
Stand power
Is not so powerful as we think it is
Definitely I mean like let's put it another way like if I'm an iPhone hacker or someone work
Which of these companies
And I and you know my living is finding his own abilities
Or I want to find and I want to hack a iPhone for whatever reason
I can just go on Twitter
And their sellers like we
Like we talked to three different sellers will advertise this device has openly on Twitter you found one of these
The other three of them actually so
It's not that hard to find you know like if your
If you know where to look and we're talking about twitter.com we're not talking about some
Obscure website dollartree.com Auntie Moyer on the Tor Browser
People are already are if you do this work
And then you can just DM these people maybe they'll ask you to like talk another Channel at some point but
Essentially you DM on Twitter and you say I want one of these
And they tell you okay
It's $5,000
You give them $5,000
And a couple days later you got it in the mail
And you can start packing I
Yeah if you know what you doing
Yeah and that you also need a special cable which these guys also provide but
That's like the cheapest paying like it's $500 for the cable
You know that that is not the problem
So
Again all you need to do
Talk to other guys
Get the device and start hacking
The question is does Apple have any idea about this
Apple knows about this as far as we know they did not talk to us for the story but
We know that they they are aware of the fact that there are some of these devices out there
And we also know that they're trying to climb down on it
How they're going to do it it's unclear and also
Is it even possible it's also unclear because again the problem is that
Apple produces millions of iPhones in China
It's impossible track all of them
And it's impossible to keep tabs on every employee who walks into Shenzhen
So
Take this device has somehow escaped
As as my sources of put it
Escape the factories and they found their way on Twitter
Can apple actually track them down take them all down
We probably not know it's just a
Epic scale problem the others too many iPhones are there
And
It's just impossible to keep track of them
But they also want you to think that
Their phones are easy
Easily the most secure phones out there and there's almost no way of breaking into them cuz even the FBI will have to
Ask for permission from Apple to get access
Yeah I mean what apple is doing this probably not I mean obviously they're trying to stop this flow over
That fuse devices on the market
But what they're also trying to do is
Make the iPhone just harder to hack so that even if you have one of these devices
You still you're still going to struggle so you know they're improving the security of the device itself that I'm improving
The security of the processor that improving the security of like the hardware itself
Are making the hardware like
Even harder to analyze and even if you get a knife when you open it up
You can just connect to we know the processor or RAM and like start analyzing it
So every year they try to make it harder and harder and they don't without relying on
The security of the supply chain which clearly
It's not that secure because this all ends again
You can just buy them
And as long as you have 5,000 15,000 $5,000
Whatever they ask you
You can find them
Which can be pretty profitable if you're somebody looking to
Turn that
5 $20,000 into
Mp3million for vulnerability that you sell to somebody
Yeah yeah exactly I mean $20,000 for someone who's going to sell
The product of that work
Or like a million it snow
If that is kind of peanuts right
That is not that much
So you've arranged for us to actually
Meet one of these
These
These dealers
Cancel one of them lives in New York
And he's actually going to be on the show
Okay so
Why don't you tell me
What do you do what brought you here today
Security research
Shandong
Lot of Apple journalist
Security research is that what you call it
But as I understand it
You get
I mean you get used sexually
Jailbroken
I grant you a break free jailbroken iPhone to say like
Apple's very secretive about the way that they keep
Their security very tight around their products
Able to get some of these
Tobocman
Like
Device that Engineers use
Or
Factory use for testing
And you can use those device that you have a lot of like
Sports that's not normally open
Now you can do
Do a lot of cool stuff
Which you can find vulnerability
Yes it is finding vulnerabilities and iPhones as you know as a security researcher
Very very difficult
And those ass is mine you know iOS is pretty much like
Epoxy
Reach
And dos
Opening like those
Quartz
Is pretty much the
The Portugal in May
They got louder
You can dump the entire file system out
You can find
Jessie all the clothes and everything is compiled but you know
You still can find
So
Okay
How do you get this device
Connection with flight
People work for
Accompany
And also
You get more time to China
Fun Factory
Dumb Junction Heights
We have a Ops Team
Pretty much they do a lot of development
Like the dybala
Decent amount of
Stuff
In China
I don't know why you do it but you know you have
Devil
Okay so you get these devices from these people at mean is this at all legal
I mean for those I don't know how they got out but
I mean
IPhone
Standings
Stolen and
Warren
The factory you know
The factory
Do you produce a lot of like
Pre-production just to make sure like they are the manufactured
It's good that you go before you know
You people
Produce like a
Revista Vice and those to my supposed to be like
Started
Destroy the user through a hole on the motherboard
Or they just tased Ward but you know
People whom
Am I responsible for that
Sometimes we don't do that they sell
White
Those huge quantity of those
To like
The marketing
People like you
Won't know the work for the company
Likely work for the factory
Yeah but then you get them though I buy them
You buy them from those from those people and then you sell them for how much
I'm selling them I'm not my main thing is not selling on my main thing is you know
Getting those devising hand and research and also research with other researcher you know there's a lot of people out
Bears doing it
At the same time
Selling it
Not for profit but you know for I mean I'm sure you get some money for it
How much how much
I don't know probably like
It depends on the device if it's like a DVT or like
Engineering validation like that that that CVT
You got
Couple thousand to
Easy over
You're getting you're getting
You're getting your
Squid with lights
People that song
Along the line who got this device out
To sell it
Okay so who buys Leasing
Home security research
22 individual and also company
It's like
Songs like tencent
Alibaba
And also
Person look like
Alibaba
You know you're getting so basically I mean
Yeah we'll cuz they're buying and if we're going to look at sort of the history of Chinese
Text companies quite often they rip from American companies
That they do let me buy them too
Porsche I want
You know they can either report
Dropil or utility to release
I don't know release like a jailbreak like
Pretty much
To the public
So do you think I mean
Should I question for you do you think something like the Chinese government Chinese intelligence
Mickey size in 2016 things because they'd like to be able to break them when they have to I'm not sure
Government but I'm sure the scump
Maybe definitely do you know what the companies are doing that means the government are doing it
Yeah I'm not sure but you know maybe
You know Huawei those kind of like Huawei
Like meizu those
Audible
But all those kind of companies are there buying like
Ambient reverse engineering those sites Hardware as walking out
You know what happened
When do you know when iPhone 10 come out camera and two lanes and their vertigo
And
When iPhone 7 come out the all dual
Horizontal cameras
Those people those company
Why those prototypes and then you know the
Pretty much
Just recreate themselves because you know people want
Stuff that's closing Oaks
I mean stuff over here like I phone bill cost around like
Hundred dollars
What are you trying to
It's like
And again we just people antenna
Fortunate people want something similar
But wait for tomorrow
And in order to do that before or a little bit right after Apple release a new device
I have to get their hands on you know
Do you have any idea how much this would piss off Apple sending you were doing that I mean absolutely yes
Infuriate them are you worried about ever getting any legal repercussions because of this because they've got a big legal
I got a lot of money to throw people but I'm not
I'm not
The person who did this I'm not a person who getting them
And I'm not a person who do the vulnerability I'm not a person who hurt their business
I'm just
Research
Wanda
And you sell them off like you you advertise on Twitter do you know
Some predator on eBay used to but you know
Apple is getting
Sirius on
EBay dolls Amazon
So you know deep deep and people
You still can fly
A short amount of time that people who sell listing I bet there's a decent on people food
Other handsome photo guy device or like
Pre-production device
But you know more likely people sell them
Like to solve
Server order
Collection
When you see apple advertising itself as the most secure
Device
Company that creates lots of the iPhone or
You know MacBooks
Being the most secure versus Android or PCR
Deep but you still think it's kind of b******* the fact that you're able to find these devices and
And find vulnerabilities and sell these phones to people who
Then we'll do the exact same it is not because you know
4liker
Production device
For like a release device
You actually cannot do anything
All the ports of logs
That means you can
Funny Bone ability and also those device came with
Dupree like
Pre-release version of the iOS so it lets us a iPhone D20 prototype for the pointy
Is
Pretty much iPhone
Whatever the farmer came
Before release is what exactly you know when device came out release
People have to
Spend time to find out availability
Apple just push more firmware updates
Then
So
The only thing that people want
Like security research rice Ace Hardware vulnerability and they seemed very rare
Are you see those
Hargrove on like that
Psiphon for iPhone
Freaky eyes
Bootrom exploit
There's naturally no way to fix it
Unless you release a new
But you know those things became very very hard to find
And they're getting very good like
Apple have their own
Swd table
Like
Software development table.
Those special cables
Special software
They're getting
Very smart and the
Use like server-based even if you have the stolen Hardware
Or like the hardware store you are not supposed to get
You still work
Don't be able to do a lot
Because a lot of things require a server Authentication
Required accountant
She don't feel like what you're doing is
Is hurting Apple new devices
It's not
But you know
You can if you want to but
I don't want to
Stuff like that
What about the people you sell these devices
It depends on
Weather
I mean that sounds a little bit like you know I'm going to
Yeah I guess some people from fentanyl unlike what they do with it what they do with it you know they could like
I'm not doing it for profit or
Something like
Find vulnerabilities not for me
Threatening
Apple or anything like that
But you know it's always hard to get a
Piece of
Divisive
Piece of things that you would not normally be able to get in the morgue
Collector
So it is interesting to sort of for you to do
Put these out there at the stuff that
Go to the break at 2
Which is this classic handkerchief
Exactly what it
And these devices are widespread across the end
Some of them are more rare than the others
Gbtc
The last stage is it's a lot you know
Did you get your hands on one side
Well yeah you can find
And all
You know a lot of even high school kids
Interior very affordable
They're pretty much
Close to the retail
Has Apple ever contacted you personally to tell you to stop doing this no but their lawyer did took down my listing
That's it
See that you're literally not afraid of that s*** at all you're not afraid to get
Do it
And I'm not
Fronting the money
Right
I'm literally just collector
And summer collection
A better way to look at it
So what which ones have you sold reason
Which iPhone
The recent one is sold at Yuan
Person Florida
It's very famous
Like
Running iOS
Illinois no wise device
I'm pretty much like a virtual machine that runs iOS
One of the r
It's pretty much like a
BBT
But it's before that it doesn't have a very very
Industrial look
Enclosure it's not a regular enclosure I so that
Northside store
The Peabody Opera
To some collector
How many busy cell year
Like 20-30 of those
Depends on people
Really like depends on
Can you have an in in China
Buckets
Devices
The device and dumb
The either ship to them directly
Or should I
To me directly and not use those like profits you feel myself
Get my hands on
Verix
It's almost like
Apple screwed up by sending Albans
Device
Manufacturing to China
Because now yeah you know insecurities are coming out of it because Factory workers
They're not
Airline employee
Carryover by
Prophet
So yeah those people ready you know hate their jobs
And now they're trying to make a little little bit more cash bite you know
Game of survival
Which
What do you call yourself by the way
Online
On my Twitter is like
Pretty names like
Apple internal
Score
Pretty much
Apple internal store
Almost like you're actually part of Apple
Right but Apple internal is actually a apple
Internal it is is that is a term that he called but you know
The store is busy they selling those devices or selling stuff like that
And there is also somebody named like a Point journal app store their busy side of Wonder Labs
The prayer for me I'm some Harper Vision me this week's episode
Jason Keppler
Recorded by Gene White
I'm that nakuu
Thanks for listening to cyber we back next week