Eagle one package being delivered
But the Cavalier private surveillance industry like only called various companies including T-Mobile Sprint
AT&T selling phone location data with middlemen companies that Hawks on the black market
In one recent story motherboard reporter Joseph Cox has been following wouldn't become a bloody Trail
I'll be back to real time location data I've been Mac who and this
So Joseph
Where does the story begin
What happened exactly walk me through it
So
Anime afternoon
To federal Offices
Walking to a Nissan dealership
In Texas
They tell the manager or the owner that
We trying to capture this fugitive Ramon Hutchinson is on the run from Minnesota to Florida
Dodge dealership
There was a family of five in a dealership as well just going around people buying car
SMG security
Rimowa
Rob Hutchinson from behind
Truelancer the fugitives belts onto a table that's a scuffle trying to grab it and then we'll
That are all 2000 Schultz
Presumably
Acrostic settings and Freeman's I pursue after.
This is exactly scream cyber
So what happened that that was connected to it
Right yeah it is about
Montessori initially
But then we found that for lease documents from a company called search at 1
This is one of the fans that provides is rotation taser to bounty hunters
In that
Thomas the Train vacation dates it was used to track
Once a bounty hunter
Outside the dealership
So
Wheaton
If phone location data was used
2 track
Ramon Hutchinson
Triple shooting
That is data showing the phone from Minnesota again while Justin was on the Run song
Was located or pins
Several times in the Run
We couldn't determine who actually owns that phone
Because it seemed to you about the Tiffany new number and wasn't
But you can finish records and yeah you to see that someone
Was looking at a wedding bouncy on the square
Pasta
Deschutes
Today is
Technology element and potentially a date to Southern elements as well
So what you're saying is there was
This incident
That on the surface
Looks like
A bounty hunter
Arrest of
Fugitive gone
Corley
But there's
Potential
Towards
The fact that they were using
Location data
Attractive person
Cathay
Inevitably
Guide for
Yeah I mean we can say for sure
Austin Motors I suppose always framing sizes
There was this tragic event with free people died
And someone somewhere
Was presumably connected to this Instagram account
Locations of the mobile phones 806 wins the shooting off to be some
Joel
To try to pick up The Fugitive
Someone just happened to look at these phones and see where they would like
It's
Indicative of the sort of
Incidence
Sanitation Taissa Canby
Linksters
Edustar shows this I mean this another example of how
Signals intelligence
Tracking technology
Is now being served
Proliferated
Like this
Yeah I mean
Senator Ron Wyden
Of course he's being very vocal
On this subject
He said that
It's not just me
Privacy it is about
Safety
As well
And again I say that they say
You know definitively trance was used to track
Clearly this is
This is an issue of Public Safety when free people dying
The family of five
Against the law
As well
It's not just about
How does this this event I mean is very tragic
Rebuild on the reporting that you
I think it shows more of a
Human face
And the consequences
Around the states again
I'm stressing that with note saying that they salads
To the killings of the motives of course I'll be ridiculous these people died because there was a violent
Shootout
What it does to char
The States was being sold in
The real world
I mean you look at other dating stories like
Cambridge analytica wishes
Something about
Kisame
That doesn't really have a huge tangible impact
On someone
You now look in a case like this
Seems like either of us as well considering just how why do you use a service was amount bunches
It shows that there is some something wrong
Immediate
Concrete
And visceral
Supposed to
I mean nothing
It does for me it's sort of
I think we still even in
2019 SS
Happy Cinco
Of the Cyber is very
Sort of
Impenetrable and weird and crazy
It never really ends up with someone
Undead
And this is the case of it actually showing that
Not only are these Technologies widely available but
Either being used and
They can meet about things
Yeah I mean I think it touches a bit on the same tribout's toolkit which is this
When you physically have access
When you put it on there
Application guess who was our messages
It's ever been used in pieces
Relationship status show
A concrete
If somebody using
A piece of technology
A few years ago with it being relatively
Obscure
Disassemble sofa
Sing
Where's the location that has been sold by the carriers
AT&T T-Mobile and Sprint
Trickle down to
Use cases
When you look at the dates
How many
Particular charm is used to locate
The same account is located the bounce
His phone off of the shooting
Over the course of the number of years it was also used to rotate some 4,500
It was used Batman
Thousands and thousands of times
And that leads
Maisel supervisor
To believe that this person was selling
That phone location Des rocs s
On the black market
Cuz normally people need to paint.
500 phone number
Even if you were counting on
And according to the terms and conditions of this
You're only supposed to use two IP addresses you know this is to minimize abuse
Maybe you can write from your mobile phone or you know from to workstations or something like that
Connecting 24 Rainier from Israel School across the United States
So it does look like
Not only is it
Unprofessional people apparently connect
Estate sale
He looks like Elvis are we selling it as well
Of course
It does make you wonder how
If these kind of like
Smaller
Security Bounty Hunter forums
Access
This kind of Technology
It makes you wonder what
The NSA would have
Or what some of these
Larger more well-financed
Intelligence age
Have at their disposal
I mean we saw that recent
McCoy
From a cybersecurity company that suspected Chinese records of broken into a numbers
Telcos to get location information
Cool records not so strange
That is clearly
Unintelligent
Sleds
Operation
Retaining names Nation
What made me
Look at it twice was that
Well if you're in the US you can just buy them
Hacking you
Chinese hackers retard sing of the UK or maybe European tocco's as well when you probably
You can just buy some locations
Well that's a very
Very happy thought
Think that that certi
Very private data is
Of course after reporting
Patelco recess Mouse stops. And I believe they
.
By the beginning of
So is no longer on going
Abilities
Still
As far as I know the black market trays
Even if people can't get hold of this States
The telcodata
Supply chain
Carrabba's
There must be
I mean especially when
You know that this location
Data can also be very profitable
Right
Yeah I mean
Isaiah
If you millions of it as a new Boston tens of Millions
Millions
To say it was a lot more
Older people elsewhere or not
Supply chain
She might issue off of 50 Grand
To pull someone in
You spend
A few hundred dollars maybe she's thousand dollars on the black market
Exception to process
If you didn't sell anything on the black market you can do a mock-up alternator 200-300 400%
Is the people in the Boston
Supply chain
Probably has
Imusa games
What store carries
Abusive, when looking all the states
And you suspect that there's more stories like the
Newberry trash
Timeout
Yeah absolutely I mean even from
When T-Mobile responded
Two-letter
Call the company
Theta
I imagine that the are going to be more stories
Like this
Round of 16
I'm we're looking for leads us to come up as well
That is sort of the issue with the story I feel like even though we've done several different hospitals on the
Based on
Illegal documents and data from inside the company that resources shoes
I really feel like his cliches is the way only seeing the tip of the iceberg
Thousands tens of thousands of sirens Benji located this way
The has to be more
Abusada
Absolutely well this story definitely struck me and I
I really wanted to the Showcase it
Hi Joseph thank you for being on the show
Thank you appreciate it this week's episode was recorded and edited by Dean white produced by Lorenzo
Francesca and hosted by me Ben McAdoo you'll be hearing from us next week