Eagle one package being delivered
Notorious and chaotic hacking groups out there it's like a Hollywood hacking movie but it's real tonight
Netflix hit by hackers 10 new episodes of the streaming services hit show Orange is the New Black
Reportedly leaked online before their scheduled release the hacking group dark Overlord climb
Didn't pay a ransom dark Overlord they are threatening to leak what they say
Exclusive documents relating to the September 11th attacks
Mysterious packing group the dark Overlord tweeted a link to an encrypted file will be providing many answers
About 9/11 conspiracies for 18,000 secret documents leaked they said
Latest in a string of high-profile hacks by the dark Overlord who pop celebrity plastic surgeons schools
And a studio that works with Netflix their motivation is simple they want money and they're not
Not afraid to extort people 4th we spoke to Joseph Cox who's been in contact with this group almost since the theory
Beginning of the Rex boys I'm National Security reporter who this is cyber
So Joseph what did you do
On New Year's Eve
I want to have free one
Was out partying I was fat
From today
Laptop chassis
2 smackers who adjusts
Dump some files
Electricity with the 9/11 attacks litigation
I want to see Iran in the
Exactly how I think you would spend your New Year
My Friends by Queen released
Surprised by texting me
Who's happier you are the hackers I don't know
Yeah I mean
It was chill with me
But just bad timing you
It should just write just a chill New Year's Eve talking too dark
Overlord
Yep yeah exactly I mean the talk of those has a habit
Singing
Some pretty inconvenient times
But that's just a start again
Are you certain
To walk me through this
Who is dark Overlord because that name is
To me that's just a
Classic
Beautiful
Old school hacker naming
Yeah so this may be the first time as some people go to the doctor
I saw subtracting to the min
When they were hacking medical centers
A listing that dates on the dark web
I would deliberately make her already high price
So he clearly wasn't
And then they started talking to media room
Giving them dato to them even more pressure on the rectum
And they
Changed over time is God love most
Sophisticated
Brazen
Some of the facts and campaigns now
I just really
Over-the-top dramatic
What's the violence
In a way
And then
CCR violin swing by violin
Yeah but maybe find the song
That really aggressive
So when they were exposing one company they sent me the text
Descendants 2 the daughter
All the CEO of someone like that
It was stuff like tell Mommy and Daddy
We have everything and they going to give us
In one case
Stay Gold Austin
That's what they said from schools
And then used it to send mass text messages to the children saying hey
We going to come shoot some blow up your school
Today in Toronto
Lego
How the heck is what
When it comes to that Brazen the snow Christmas
Funnily enough really open with that
Motivation
They very clearly say when.
So activists we care about magic internet money
That's all they care about
They just want money
Yeah
Where is some tattoos made
The motivation
Magistrate's Office
And it comes across as pretty genuine
They just totally financially motivated
Maybe it Tanya citigo
Is Stephanie the money
This is a clear a clear example of sort of like
Black hat
Straight up like I know Grace with the only way
Maybe will be a slightly different stages when they released these
Electric 911
I don't care about that school
What is this 911
Legal firm hack
About what do they do
So
Duncanville O-Town
Altitudes
A
Atleagle family links to hiscox knotheads Cox directly
Link to it which handled some litigation around a 911.
Several years ago
Hiscox has she announced the breach your neighbor
So that it isn't you but that what is happening is the Taco Bell is going public saying you're going to get us money
Steadily drip feed these documents house
Open to the public
Download
Best kind of bad
Usual approach the boys different hair is just how
Publix
Really pushing
Twitter pastebin and
Really going WiseWay free chance gym as well
What's in these documents
That's exactly music huling sort of some of this
Loose Change 9/11 conspiracy theories
Really
In a drip-feed fashion and style is a few preview documents and then they also sent out
When they release the key
And to be honest the actual documents themselves interesting in the moment
Best legal letters between penalties and Lewis
The TSA in the
And they seem quite innocuous
I know maybe the saving the really good stuff until the end cuz I still need incentive for the victim
Hey
Maybe they didn't have all that good stuff
Conspiracy theories I mean my inbox is now full of people who would not stop emailing me
About
911 truth
And like I haven't seen this
And they just pull up my inbox
Idnyc
50 Cent playlist
Like some
Territorial people all like
Tangled
They just really want to know if jet fuel melts
Beams
Yeah face
I mean I downloaded documents
Provide them anything at the moment maybe it will later if they don't move
Yeah just a load of people and a load of 911 truth is in my inbox
But I mean if you're to go by historically this dark Overlord group
They haven't been bulshit they've had stuff in the past I've been out of there not been
Genuine
Every dices en Place Kissimmee
Come to verify
And that is the medical sense day 2
School days stuff from Gorilla Glue
The little blue company
They have two real igloo
Yeah they had a really good witch
Okay
Yeah that's how I'll get the wine
The cost of Industries the every single day every single piece of HR procedure
Has
Turned out to be legitimate maybe that changes later on
The
Past experience
Pikachu
Do they have Gorilla Glue I mean what
Why and what did they do
Bugatti for any Target
Did they can compromise and then try to make
So in the case of Gorilla Glue
Bagel 500 gigabytes of data personal emails professional stuff
I think some text messages as well
And they even
Because I was saying that Lil we have the secret formula at all of Gorilla Glue
And some upcoming photo switch
Wasn't the most enticing and parolee wasn't in the greatest public interest so I didn't really mention that but
In the world itself
Just because
Anyone there
And was like gorilla glue do they have
Cyber security team that could help them
Respond to that store
Not that I'm aware off
I mean presumably they did bring in
Play forensic people lost with that seems to be a theme in that
Come people get pops by the dark Overlord
And then by Raul who ever Maybe
Will come in
Call the clean up after that
I mean when it comes on
You don't have to think about it very much because
Straight away
The dark Overlord will tell the victim hey it's us
Is the previous stuff we've done and I've seen these emails
And this is why the media comes in
Because the dock of Zelda with hospice like
Archival portfolio of work
They can send that to the victim
Hey do you want to be impossible with oil
Why I don't want a friend maybe like
They can see this
Anakin makes up restaurant
Have they ever called the victim
And extorted them
Oh yeah so it was one case where an associate
I think he was an actual name member
Someone who went by the
Handle across the Cockney who was arrested
A couple years ago
They bring up the victims and they have these really busy over the top
Audio tracks like SoundCloud rap
On the phone with like a beast in the background likes things
Hey I thought you said
Do you have that
Yeah yeah we have nothing we can play
Hello
Levi gets to decide
You can suck my dick
Tell you that I love you
You work in fact that you've got a good beat
Chuck-E-Cheese
Check it out
We probably going to get one cool for me
Funny looking sure deserve a problem
I'm going to call you some fuk
You work at Weis
Have a good day
This plays into by the overdraft
Progressive
Nonsensical Whimsical and just really unprotect
Empezar like that
Change that targets will change from
Two schools to businesses.
Potentially government contractors they will send these audio recordings that will send text messages to students are schools in Russell Springs
They
I mean I guess this is like like classic like they're classic hackers who really don't
They really don't give a f*** and they really
I tried to talk with the victim
Every way they can I mean I've had conversations
Bands with one member
But he's talking about how they
Psychologically
Try to manipulate
I know what I'm doing and it's incredibly deliberate
And
And your steering contact your in contacts
So it comes and goes
Are your interactions with
Service
Black hat hackers
Yeah I mean starting
In 2016 may be very active on Orem salon
Encrypted chat with something and then they may just appear
I did maybe even longer
Backup offer some dates
We not interested because it's not a public interest or is the target which is umbrella
A reason or something
And then they just randomly came back with his 911
Free stuff
So
Yeah they're really unpredictable
But when they do come up
They probably have something of Interest
I mean it's interesting as well because
They have so many assists scattershot of targets
I mean I haven't heard of hackers that
We'll sort of
Hawk
The formula
Of some weird
You know kind of
Ridiculous
Industrial company like Gorilla Glue that
You know do you want the recipe for the glue except for Chinese hackers that are trying to
Take this and give it to
Sumner corporate attorneys within China I mean it's just you have
The law firm that dealt with 9/11
How do you know who it is
The start of the
The theme that's it
Seems to be a wide array of people
Yeah and then also even the Production Studio
Links Netflix
So then the end of leaking in the Orange is the New Black in the various other episodes is like the shows they will just go
Did the
Yes I didn't hack
Netflix directly it was a production
Studio
But cannot just shows if they can get access to something
Crew
Ace Hood Posse
What's something like that then they're going to do that
I've got a hell of a lot of coverage
Yeah and if you read how it was covers
It was clear
The Down koplo News if I went to variety as a novice the Entertainer publication
Is going to carry move like that because it's Netflix
Open sleeper it they think a frontal more information before they gave it to me
The rarest battery when it comes to choosing Outlet
To get MS
They're very sad
Yeah they know exactly what they're doing
They already meet you Saturday in that they
Will attempt to entice
Agenda list with the correct amount of dates
And Abel
Go to different Outlet
Story is here
I need something like Phineas Fisher
That I've spoken to before
You you you know it it's Representatives one person
But my suspicion was always it was 7
This is the case here is the same thing here
Yeah I know
I imagine
Is multiple
Because there are so many different
Office operation
I mean they have hacked
At least
50 Target
I'm not walls
That was when I wrote about the last year
17 quiet for a while
Probably beaten
Working in the meantime
Debra a rapist
And pee like a resource logistical level one test and probably can't do that
Blending conversations with them release date
Who said I am leaning
I just like the
The professionalisation of it they sends to fix
A literal contract
And it says like the taco veloz Solutions LLC agrees to
If you give us xidan Bitcoin and they make the victim
Sign a contract
So so bizarre
It seems to be professional in industrialization of the
Extortion
Whimsical nature
Contract
Yeah it's like they've got a Comm specialist a lawyer
Hacker
Who's doing the
Miscommunication
There's a lot of media contacts going on here especially now with the 9/11.
The times Financial Times
American Publications as well
Like this, be one person
Whatever it is it's
It's pretty I mean
Kind of Genius
Yeah
Evil Tina
And
The most malicious
Come across
Genuinely
I mean you have state taxes are we doing it
Is a bad job
Because it's too late country so that maybe pacifism in the states
Unemployment
Is it just about the money but they come about
So happy we're going after let's say when you look at something like the iCloud hack
Have they gone after celebrity
Please before
Yeah so they targeted a plastic surgery in London
Which
Serves to several different celebrities are allegedly
Royal family members as well
I couldn't confirm
Royal family members
To speak
And send the celebrity side
To verify
Dante's
They sent me a load of photos off
Pre and post
Plastic surgery operations which of course included
Lots of photos of people
But that is
Information
Teejet identify pajamas
And this was like Hey if you don't pay we're going to release these photos
Shoutouts to prince Andrew for no reason at all
I don't know
If they edit a
Slight twist in that story
Plastic surgery the IT guy that
Trying to send the dark Overlord a malicious file
Witchwood reveal their IP address
And told them
I should have done that
Wow today they're on top of their game
Opsec
Is pretty incredible
As far as I know
I mean everybody makes
Mistakes
These are one of the most
Solid
Discipline
Increase of democracy
And how would the authorities
The FBI's
Definitely eveline investigating
This group as a UK authorities
I mean
It was even a
Nyko press event a while ago
FBI director Christopher Wray
Perhaps another couple
Basically they have penis
Scribus
Which
I don't
Agree with
Is Terrorism is a break Pacific thing big tiny kids United
Saladin viewed by the rapper
Namely
Pick up victims
Damping heavily
Investigation to the point where
That was a security researcher very was very pleasing
He did nothing wrong
For the FBI
Local law enforcement been really hard on him
Trying to link
So
I would not be surprised
I like some of the
The Talk
If you know Chinese
I mean with all due respect
The authorities it's not as if they're taking
Power grid at least not yet
It's just
It is
Quite stranger these guys
Philippine currency
At least
I just saw
Publicly
I give you an apt like more the government group
Typically clients
Insinuating the soccer field is
It's just that
They are certainly the Pea
Baby teeth
And I still going
If anything
More more aggressive
Have any authorities
Caught anybody
Connected to
Dark Overlord
So
The authorities arrest
Nikon he used to handle
Crossed the company in the UK
Somehow connects to the group
Alan Serbian authorities
Someone
They say it's also connected
To the dark overlord by perhaps lemon winter
When that happens
The darker blue Xanax High
And they just carry on
Abnormal I mean it have no impact
Or least no visible impact on the reparations
Maybe that's because
People who do get busted and then operation or perhaps
Date of service billing and I can carry on
Well maybe that person Serbian guy
I shouldn't have anything to do
We don't know this
Even when authorities do
Debbie's really smooth
Apparently connect
I haven't
I haven't heard of a group this
Successful that doesn't seem to have anything
Connected to the midterms
The Heat
Because the only one I can think of is Phineas
It's just completely
We stopped
Authorities
Yeah they just going and going and going
And showing no signs of slowing down I mean
They'll probably
Get shipped eventually like maybe a cup
Fugazi
No yeah
Mean everyone's luck runs out usually
But
So far this group seems
I mean their opsec is impressive
I mean maybe they have made mistakes
If they had you would think the FBI would be kicking down doors
Immediately
And not to mention I mean you look at PCH
HQ you look at the authorities in in England and these are pretty
I'm going to tell you this
Dupree outstandingly
Powerful agency
That have a
Pretty Keen sense what's going on
British Network
Yes exactly
Gchq is working on it but they have
Recently
Play Store
Combating cybercrime
Tostito
I wouldn't be surprised but yet
The Dock of Louisiana have
Mount snow demos
Capable
And yet they just keep on going
So I mean I know you just
Got in touch with them for the first time in a little while but I mean what's next for this 911 story and wheezing
Next for dark Overlord
Lourdes to
Trying to push out this 911 story
Released one of the
Decryption keys
They trying to crowdsource
Some more as in castles in Bitcoin in ml
Maybe at once
I imagine they'll trying to
Documents
I don't see them jumping the whole thing just yet
I will be playing
Ola psycards
Straight away
Latest Medtronic
Story out more interviews or die
Chemist is well
That's what happens for the dark Overlord next
I mean
This one
Sage
Over the next few days or a week maybe something like that the media loses interest
Uno's
Quiet
And then
The police bring up again
In three four five six months
With another hack
I mean
Sounds like it
Exactly I mean they are alive
The reliably professional for lively
Spring up when you haven't heard from them in a while
This week's episode was produced by Jason Kepler Kraken was edited by John North graph
Thanks for listening to cyber we back next week in the meantime please tell your friends about us
Review on Apple podcast