Virus
Eagle One
The package being delivered some American politicians have been known to well
Not totally understand the internet sample who can forget when Republican senator Ted Stevens from Alaska
Famously said this in 2006 while debating against net neutrality
You know current president seems to rely on Aging stereotypes of
What a hacker is supposed to be lots of other people could be somebody sitting on their bed that weighs 400
It's okay that said there were few American politicians who know the internet
On this program we've had Senator Ron Wyden
Key for all intents and purposes
Is one of the biggest surveillance Hawks in the history of the US government
An issue after issue too many of the leaders in the intelligence Community have not
The Congress in the dark Congress has been given an inaccurate statements in effect and actively misled
But on this week's episode we're going to be sitting down with Dutch new member of Parliament
Beretta shotgun
She's well-known infosec Community as a politician
Who knows the ropes of cybersecurity in a way that
Beaufort colleagues do
In the past Chaka has been
And called on International laws governing the sale of cyber weapons
Government spyware
And exploit
I'm done nakuu
So thanks for being here Marietta General wanted to talk about
Sort of the proliferation of spyware
Nation-states
And how the
Affected global politics and also
Human rights but
You recently wrote an op-ed
About the regulation of government spyware
And I wanted to know
Being who you are and in your
Government
Why is it such an important
This has been a concern of mine for many many years and I've been pushing for changes in
The EU laws to make it more
Control
Who gets to buy
These you know
Police
Level
Hacking tracking tracing and surveillance tools
After looking closely at what happened
During the popular uprisings
North African and Middle East and how they were cracked out
Very clearly was not only
Individuals
Students
Journalist
Human rights Defenders were empowered by the use of
Technology mobile phones and connecting and self-organizing
Documents
Human rights violation
But it was
Clearly also
Dictatorial regimes
Military Intelligence services
And their beliefs
That were using
New technologies
In ways
To repress
And the more I started following the thread of
What technologies these exactly were the more I
Trace them back
And
To democracy
And so I think it is an unacceptable boomerang
That has has allowed to
Continue
When
You made or us made or israeli-made Technologies are sold
To repressive regimes
Clear violation
Septicology that NSO group it has developed on
Spell ceiling
Dictatorship States like Saudi Arabia
Is being used by Visa
States in order
Tattoo as spy after activists a4u merized journalist
Like your message
Specific
Marketplace
It's very much reflects sort of this
Conventional Weapons
Industry
And you think
It means you think the two
Are the same word or two have a lot of
Similarities
Yeah I think they have in the sense that you always have the risk that win
Weapons or Technologies are
App record for
Controls
A rule of law Anchorage use like for example countering terrorism in a country like the Netherlands
Country where the rule of law certainty protects people and
Where are the thresholds for the use of
Very invasive
Technologies is high
But if there's them proliferation and and the same technology turns up in in a handful of other locations then
Its fins out of
Control and that is a
The same with
Many examples that we've seen in the image
Traditional weapon ended
And what's interesting is that
Used to speak about digital arms
Ulta to make it clear to my colleagues who may not be working on technology on a daily basis
Do you know why this is
Serious problem
And I got a lot of pushback especially
Savefrom
Human rights groups
She said you're militarizing the internet as Etc but I actually think that the mechanisms of proliferation
And the Harms
Is caused by
These hiking and masturbating stools are actually very very
Comparable to the traditional arms in
I completely agree and I think it is difficult for p
People to
Stand that
These
Tools really do a navel
Militaristic
Acts
Price same way an AK-47
Help
Sight words
What helps repression you know it gives more power
To the kind of dictatorial Human Rights for press
Singers names that are already so powerful that they can silence
Descent and now they can do it in it
Near the invisible way I mean normally the world cries out when there is blood in the
Sum when there is
Bullets fired and
You know when tanks roll
Roll on on public
Squares but here
The silencing and the tracking and the dragon people out of their homes
Listen to torture chambers and prison cells happens nearly invisible
And it sits on top of that enable by
Western made
Technologies
So I think there could hardly be a clear case for the need to really rich
Prix fixe box
Citrate
When you look at something like the Boston or agreement of Mount Hope IMAX
Pronounce this correctly
Actually. Tell me what is the Boston agreement how does
How does it affect
The spyware malware ended
So it is an agreement between a number of countries including the US a number of European countries of Russia in August
The broad set of countries in other words
That have agreed on certain list
That enter into
The force when there's like an embargo
So it's basically preselection of embargo
Tools
And
There are some
Technologies in the Dual use category on
The Boston a list
But certainly not all
Because of these business or breed once every couple of years and
I personally believe that's European countries do European Union because it is a democratic and it has high
Human rights standards
Should go much
Further than busting our because the bus in our Arrangement is
Originated in
Security concern
And the concerns that I believe we need to have our also very clearly human rights
So should there be something that's that's more expensive in terms of
Governing the trade
The Cyber weapons
Trade
Should be International agreement
Well I mean what we've done here in the European Parliament is already gotten a majority behind what we
I believe the new EU standards
So
That means
One listing more Technologies as
Needing to
Obtain a license before export so you basically
Credit check
Before you know just allowing
Export to anyone
Who wants to purchase
And then secondly you assess whether there is human rights
Concern
And we suggest
To do that on the basis of existing criteria existing combination
Human rights violations so that it doesn't have
How to become overly politicized and complicated
Would really
It'll when when certain condemnation
The violations of already happened then it automatically means that you cannot just
Self
As a letter Italian or French
Or a German company
Systems
To the authorities in those,
And what we've also done
Is recommended that there was much
Stricter control of the end-user
Because they're there seems
To be a lot of leeway
When you for example sell to the government
Avocado
Maybe on paper
For countering terrorism
But it made
Practice Act
CB
You know find critical journalist
To track them
Let you know where they are to know who their networks are their sources are and then to
Use that information
Can against them
How to build a case
To torture them to accuse them etc etc so
We need much more clarity also on who
Who gets
These Technologies
For what for
You take something like
The hacking humans
You know key years ago
Such a
Story in that
We saw a company
The recruiting spyware and selling it
Repressive regimes
The software allows for hacking team to basically infected
Infecting in the sense of
Put a virus on our on
Essentially have full access
Bacon
Thanks I can download files
Like you like you said
The Technologies are are proliferating do you think that
There is
A hockey team in Europe
Right now that we don't even know about that is doing the sets of Faith released
I would bet a lot on that
I think that it's
Completely in transfermarkt
That is now estimated in billions
Heroes of value
And a lot of these companies
Have no interested in having their reputation
Should know you know they go to trade fairs
They they deal in the dark corners of
States with with
You know track records of very
Repressive
Actions against
Human rights Defenders or dissidence
Opposition figure
So yeah I'm I'm sure that there's a lot we don't know yet and
I think transparency house
To be another Alamo
Because what we've also seen you mention hacking team win
Used to operate from Italy
There was also Aria Spa another
Italian bass company that that's old
To Syria
To the Assad regime when the crackdowns on the popular uprisings war well no
And you know it is not only the selling of Technology it's not like a box
Your ship from a distance
It often involves
Consulting
Training
On-the-spot assistance
How these technology
Abused so
What we need
Besides
A transparency on which companies are active on the market and selling what
To which buyers we also need much more
Accountability
Avi export
Controls Authority
Because
Perhaps it's no coincidence Perhaps it is because of good journalism in Italy
But perhaps
Subnautica
That there are a lot of
Very active
Companies in the hacking and surveillance
Technologies in Italy
And that there have been a number of incidents on covered where they actually sold
Despite sanctions
Two countries that were not even allowed to receive these
Technology so
The need for oversized and the need for transparency is very urgent
On the part of companies but also on the part of governor
What do you make a something like NSO group
Right now that's me that's been in the news for multiple reason
How come this this company is
Just been able to
Continue to behave in
Beatley improper ways and
Yet
You have government still buying their stuff
So on the one hand
The problem is that our laws are lagging
Behind
So even though
You and I and many people hearing this my
Immediately agree that
You know to have a journalist
Triton Tracen later murdered
With the help of these Technologies is not a desirable out
It's also ironic I think that an Israeli company is
Is providing Arab dictators you know their so-called enemies
With with their weapons
Choice
But the point is that even if we think it is
Unjust and fundamentally wrong
The laws do not forbid it that was so I think we need to step up the laws I would have liked to
Seymour European leadership
In the parliament weave
We spelled out how we think
You know much better safeguard
Should work but the member State Governor
AR
Very reluctant
That may also explain why this NSO group has been
Getting so much space I mean
I would be surprised if there aren't very good relations
Between the Israeli authorities and the
This company
Because I'm sure they would have landed in if they if they would have
Had concerns and
I believe
The company is now in
In the hands of
European investors
So I think we need we need to ask them to tough question
Sounds like what is going on are there no ethical
Benchmarks are there no limit
What's to the cynical sales of these
A tools that have
That have clearly
Let the way to the murder of a journalist
Forgive me for being pessimistic but it's also sort of this
This feeling that
You look at the top weapons
Stealing countries in the world and their all
Some of the most
Respected democracy
Where people have socialized Healthcare Etc
And their countries and yet
Sweden
Sell tons of weapon
Different countries
And the same sort of goes for
How we allowed this
Someone wants to make money off of
Cyber weapons or surveillance
Tools and
Word
I think there's a couple of things that we may want to look at as well as one
That there's most likely
Even though this is obviously not discussed on the front pages of
Newspapers but there's probably
Quite close relationship
Between the intelligence service
Is off some of these countries
Is and
These companies
That may also enable in a other use
Their Technologies once they're in the hands
I think that's an area
Scrutinize more I can't do that as a parliamentarian but I think during the
Smite or
Whistleblowers from these companies might I think that's
That's something that might explain
Why governments are so relaxed
So I think that's
The Death Clock
Simply Market power you know not to not to
Barriers up
Against companies
Is it still an argument that
Also brought her business associations have you
I spoke to a number of
A business associations who were upset when we wanted to put
Stronger controls
Complacent
We're dealing with a very
Specific Niche this does not
These measures do not impact
You know the vast majority of
It is just about
Standing for
Principals at end end
They should have meaning and I fully agree that
The same lack of responsibility on the part of democracy
These can be seen when it comes to Conventional arms
And when it comes
New surveillance technologies that aren't by the way becoming faster
Smaller and
Cheaper everyday
So you would say then you have this situation where
Intelligent agent
These are working
Hand in hand
Companies
To ostensibly
Cell
Surveillance tools
Regimes that they're trying to back
Well I don't know the details of the relation I think it deserves more
Investigation I don't think it is necessarily the ones they back maybe it's
The ones they wanted
Information on
I don't know exactly about the link
And thighs
Because I just don't have the overview a lot of this
Is anecdotal because we have no food transparent
Which is a problem in and of itself
But I do think it is
Curious that now
The member states of the European Union
Are not moving ahead with
Putting stricter rules in place even though there was a clear majority for it
Is your pee
Can Parliament I work for
Security researchers
No making sure that's for example we would
Speak of exfiltration
So not
Natsu
Put up
Problems
For pentesters or
For you know
Good face hackers that are trying to help improve the cyber
Security of
Accompanies and then institutions but really to focus only on the illegitimate
An unauthorized
Accessing of
Devices
And I'm taking out a data unknown
For example right so we
We worked with civil society
With Security Experts
Across party lines
The cross nationalities to get
Get to a better place
We suggest also
Judy list
Encryption technology
Another We're updating the Expo
For control list so I think it is really
Much more up-to-date but the governments of the EU member states are nothing but also I really hope that more journalists will look at why
Countries like Sweden
Finland Zara
No part of the majority that wants
See progress here
Seated scribe
The situation for your software
You need to get some support
From the government and from
The EU Parliament but there was sort of this
Misunderstanding with some of your colleagues
Just fundamentally didn't understand
The way that the internet works I mean
You're leaving now the EU Parliament
If I'm
If I'm correct
Yes which is unfortunate I think you know you have the infosec community in ND
I mean
Citizens
Of the Worlds
Who really need politicians who understand
The internet
Because
Right now even to this day
In the United States around the world
Politician still fundamentally don't really understand
The internet
Why do you think that is
Why I breathe very important to bridge the gap between the world of technology in the world of politics but it has to
A two-way street write a lot of Technology
Expert
Honestly do not understand government
Either so let's try to extend a hand both ways and I will be committed to
To Bridging the Gap and whatever else I
I will do next
And I'm confident that in the next
Class of members of Europe
Can Parliament there will be more tech-savvy
Members of Europe
Parliament's included because
Part of this is is a natural element of of
Apartments I mean I don't know so much about agriculture even though I do vote on it
And also you always have a division of labor
And on the other hand it's
Might be a little bit of a generational issue
That's just to keep up with all the latest Technologies
It's it's a bit of a challenge if you are further removed from their use
Or
But I agree it is very urgent
To have
Up-to-date knowledge before people start
Proposing
Regulatory intervention
Search United States there's definitely this war on whistleblowers
That's been going on August
The Trump Administration is
This is gone after
Journalist
In any way that you know both Obama and
George W bush
Didn't do released
Extent of it
What do you think right now the situation with
Assange and
How
Governments
Are starting to criminalize
Not only journalism but
Whistleblowing
Why I think whistleblowers needs
To be protected I believe press freedom is one of our greatest Goods in Europe
We have our own set of challenges all the
Asean countries like Hungary
Italy
You know where
There's a lot of pressure
Poland yearly weather rule of laws on
Under Pressure so
I think we have
To all be very veggie
To protect
Freedom of expression
The Press
Space for independent press also with a crowding-out
Of advertising
By the Big Tex Flats
So
The Whole Health
Abdomen
Percy and The credibility
Of democracy
Globally very much
Depends on
It's well being at home
And we have
We have works
Pharmacy you're on your way out
Government right now but where do you see sort of
Nation state hacking and
Surveillance
Generally
Do you see this
Adidas shoes
Getting better for the public or do you think we're kind of headed down a road that
That is not so good
I've been consistently surprised at how little attention
The commercial Market of surveying
Barstools and
Fuse
Of these tools by government
And then the proliferation of these tools really actually gets so I'm very happy that you were
Focusing on it in the
I see big
Ferredoxin
You know hypocrisies
Between
The outrage that I hear when another
Inno setup
Steps by the Chinese authorities Visa V minorities were in the use of
Facial recognition
Ocean Technology or
AI is being reported I mean we're clearly worried about the buildup of the survey and State
China I'm worried about the two
But I don't understand why there has been all the link back
To assess hey what are we doing here and you're up and why is our markets
You know nearly unregulated
Near the unregulated and
I also believe that those
Stu
Phenomenon will come together because
Imagine
Just imagine that other countries are going to
The more Innovative ketchup
With the levels of technological progress
And will be market leader soon
So let's say
American European Israeli companies may lose their Edge
And will lag behind
And let's imagine that our markets are going to be flooded with commercial spyware that's
You know Chinese authorities are going to sell to
Criminal networks or
A big Corporation
Other non-state actors who knows right I mean
We were done probably
Beat ourselves
Looking back why we did not put in place more
Control of this Market in the first place which would then give us a much stronger negotiating position internationally would make it much more credible
If we would halt
Search in Chinese technology if we would have began
To halt
Some of our own
One final question I have to ask because obviously you're you're a member of
EU Parliament
And it's
Serve the burning question surrounding
Do you and
The UK right now
How how is
Brexit going to affect
The internet in your
What is very much depends on what the
Brits are going to do at the end of the day because
Clearly
There's a large group of people in the UK that believes that the country can compete better
On different standards and different criteria so let's imagine
That they would lower a data protection
And all kinds of data related
Standards right if they would you
Start of a race to the bottom
Then you can have an impact
But my sense is that
Contrary to all the political one-liners that you
You here
Relation between
The British
European markets
The dependents
Since therefore of the UK on EU standards is so
That it was
To be very difficult for them to Simply
Pick and choose and
Have other standard because they may gain
Some trade with
With third countries but they would lose
Compliance and alignment with your
Key market so
I hope
That the shocker
Effect will be minimal
But I could imagine
Choices will be made which would
Include lower standards and
It'll perhaps they want to become
The hub for commercial spyware who knows
I have not heard that tape
Before that it's possible that brick
Could be
They could be the commercial spyware hub
Well I don't know either I hope not of course but
You never know I mean something
Something will probably change if they want to have a new Competitive Edge and there have been speculations it also
Much depends on which government
Are going to be in power
You know that they may lower the center for data protection
And then
Who knows what that would lead to
Right well thanks very much for coming on the show and we will continue to look at the car
Commercial spyware industry around the world and
It's unfortunate that you're leaving the EU Parliament but I'm sure you're on to great things as well thank you very much
And enjoyed discussing is very important topic with you thanks so much have a good day
Today's episode was recorded by Dean White
Francesca Pizzeria
And of course posted by me that neck