Eagle one package being delivered four years us officials have been sounding the alarm about
Impending catastrophic Cyber attack an enemy strike damaging or destroying real life infrastructure and
Causing real harm
Without using any traditional weapons just computers some like then defense secretary
Leon Panetta
World War II hyperbole to sell the threat
The collective result
Abby's kinds of attacks
Could be a cyber Pearl Harbor
Others preferred a more recent
Is a cyber 9/11 is a cyber Pearl Harbor
Within the realm of possibility
Different storage areas of impact
But amplify the Marvin Ivanov again look we're really facing a
Potential
Cyber 911
Cyber Pearl Harbor
Despite this alarm is rhetoric
There's actually not that many examples that have happened recently
There's of course stuxnet
And in 2015 Russian hackers took down parts of a power grid in Ukraine
Causing a blackout for a few hours
Then in 2017 a piece of malware known as Triton
Almost caused an explosion in a refinery in Saudi Arabia
So how real is this right now it is
Should we really be worried about a cyber 9/11
What does that even mean then
What does heaven look like
Today we're talking to Robert Lee
Former NSA analyst and now CEO of Drago
Infosec startup that tracks hackers
Grafter critical infrastructure
Industrial controls
I'm done Aku and this is cyber
Thanks for being here there was this disruption
What happens
Recently
On the West Coast
Lot of people worrying about it and thinking about it in terms of
Infrastructure tax
What did you make of it
Yeah and I mean it's an important thing
And I think this is
This is always where we have that that difficult why I'm Nuance right on like one hand going to talk about the importance
Something and highlight that is
Horton
But on the other hand
When things get highlighted in the portal
Faster than a contact of infrastructure It won't always assume
Destruction
Power grid failing excetera is it really hard
Talk about something important
I'm not in that level of importance
But it was an important issue so basically
From what we understand
Remote adversary
Charlie Weis
What's hacker what are going to call it
Compromise advice or try to compromise of iso the head of vulnerability on it supposed to be a Cisco networking gear
And then try to do so
I'm cause of denial of service on a device with it was intentional or not
And then Allosaurus the device
What is routing
Communication
Associated with
Disability
I'm in supervisory control for discrete operation so you think about it
No impact
No power loss
New customers would have noticed
And plenty of backup procedures
Baidu
Someone doing electric power control that loses visibility into at least you know
Left on ideal
So it's it's
In the same context
Extremely important
Williamson security devices
And on the other
Extreme it's no this is not what we're talking about with
Cyberfest created and so forth and Hague
But it's kind of sits right in the middle
I mean that's the thing right slick what is
I think we even talked about
The first time we spoke was
3 years ago
4 years ago
And you know that the same time
Line persist
Cyber Pearl Harbor is that even you know is that even possible is assuming it
That that risk of
That hacker
Where hackers are nation-states in the power grid
Turning the lights out is that become more reality or
Do you think that
Since you got into this game
We actually gotten better
I think in a lot of ways were getting better combating it but we we kind of have an evolving Landscaping
If you want to look strategically
At the issues that the industrial Community faces
One of those
Resounding issues
Is that we are moving to more homogeneous
Commonality in our infrastructure in the vendors
Applying sites and then maintaining and monitoring them
And the more and more homogeneous are retarded becomes
The easier it is to
Scale 1 attack acrostic
Enter Lottery
The other big scenario is that
Get hyped up that really aren't possible become a little bit more possible
Every year if you want to think that way from a technology not quickly
But it happened
Moving in that direction
I miss largely the heterogeneous ever sucks that we have that
Really makes it
Difficult for some of the types of attacks that but people theorize about
I'm even we talk about electric power grid there's not one
Bread in the United States
But not as if you're taking down a grade or take it out multiple grits to see that kind of affect
So are we moving no more hungry she has ever talked to her a time that does make does attack more scalable yes
At glacial speed
It's not like meowser
Next year cuz you
I'm by the same time or Defenders are sitting wartime
Forgetting their environments understand were happening on the operations ecology side we're seeing War
People get involvement events of industrial Control Systems every year
I think the balance is what your kind of alluding to with the
Cyber 9/11 and Pearl Harbor
Stop
Is
We need to be thinking about what do those big attacks look like
And then
Not lose our imagination and what can happen so that we can prepare
But we don't need to freak out the public and thing in it
These things are really likely that
Edison power company tencent
Spear phishing email
Doesn't mean lights
And so that's where the hype
I'm so I think it's getting better
Yeah I Dreaming is a lot of hype around that and I think some of it has to do with
Some companies trying to Hawk their Wares to
Clients saying you know we can protect against the cyber
Pearl Harbor
You know one thing I did
Even said this to me
4 is
Kind of event
Steel hinges on
Actual kinetic Warfare between big nation states like the US and Russia alike
It's not as if
Russia
While they may be sitting in our networks right now
If he were to do some sort of attack like that that could get link to them and that would create real-world issues
So why would they do
Vital us infrastructure including the power grid under cyber Threat by Russian government hackers
Potentially giving the Kremlin the ability to turn off the lights
Yeah there's there's always been there as long as long as I
In doing there's always been The Narrative of
China and Russia have
When are grades that they can activate it anytime
Causes destruction is only an aspect of intent
Something is really interesting important understand and
And why they would do something it is
For the same time
Like half a narrative is false
Cuz
Various State actors
I have the capability to get to get access wherever trucker gas
I'm having some of them has shown us time and time again yes
But it's not like they're waiting in torment with a
Killswitch deployed across the
Environments is not real
I need to be shortened big shortening
Yes what are the timeline it would take for them to do something for sure
But it wouldn't be some immediate thing
I'm addicted just take advantage of it.
Quite a bit more
I'll take ya
Blackstone labs
But
I do think a lot of people focus a lot of those major events and that's just not what concerns me
But I do think the kinetic world comes into play there
I didn't gif
A Russian State want to take down the Eastern interconnect the United States correctly
We're going to war or something close to it
And that's
That's not what freaks me out what freaks me out
It's got to fold one
Would be the smaller events that don't rise that level
I could you take out electric power indeed
Zz430
You take out the rule America somewhere for for 30 minutes
Still scare the hell out of population
And have a psychological impact that still probably has impact on policy
And maybe even there's an overreaction in Congress that horses is regulation that affects
Kill the industry overnight yo
I'm that that's a problem
Or what about adversary getting
Into sensitive industrial networks they shouldn't be involved in meteor Refinery or wherever
And accidentally
Triple R systems
And cause damage Amelia seen similar before where
In 2014 as an attack on a steel facility in Germany
And by all accounts as it's difficult to know these things
With pi degrees account
There's not a lot of
Brunswick Works in Suffolk
I'm done but
By all accounts it looks like the adversary
Accidentally cause and effect
That led to massive physical destruction across that environment
How do you
Cope with that between states when
1 state looks like they just got attacked by another two might have even been Max
I worry about
States being idiots
Doing things I should be doing and accidentally escalate tensions
And I also worried about some of the smaller
Time affects where you go
You still have a huge impact but doesn't rise to level one
Look at that the first example that you described as sort of
Perfectly fits in with a lot of adversaries right now looking at the United States looking at 20
820 and just
Trying to promote General chaos
Trying to create an app
What category
The US cover
Yammy I think that
We always think I think
The Westin Resort
Pearl Harbor now.
Cesar 911
Analogies when it comes
Attacks on
Ourselves
And less about the sort of smaller
Events that could really
Could actually really disrupt us long-term
Annie's a very fair character
And I think it's harder sometimes
If you want to be worried about the large
Well if you like your powers are no electric
Example letters for more
The farmers Archer Hector the entire world I don't like things Avengers are effectively
Industrial companies Bend
But the other great always end up being alright.
Example
And we look at electric power if you want
Change How We Do
Your transmission and generation
Big Lots
Our sort of sites
There's a definable
Number of touch points
And we feel like we have the power to go in
When you talk about these smaller events you're talking thousands
Two players
And it becomes
Bar Les
Definable in terms of
How we're going to get out of that problem and feels almost insurmountable
So it's not only that going after the smaller players
Still have exiotic effects
Scare the public
Influence policy and elections and regulations and everything else
But it's also really difficult for the Defenders
Going to scope those issues and and what they actually want to accomplish across all those sites
I'm so many ways to end up being a really
Billy smart Target
So your company you say that you track
Adversaries at 1
Disrupt civilization
How do you track the sepsis
These are two players
What are you doing how do you vet that they are in fact
Adversaries
To civilization
Like I asked
You know what to do with that like
Company monitor safeguarding civilization with
I love the idea of that and
It's not just like big
Companies that can pay a bill
Also love
It's not just
Our friends if you really understand you got to take care of civilians
People out there where they
Yeah living operator
I think it's hacking
Structure is
Egregious an RV
Against the rules if you will
Freddy's Dead
Tom brosseau
Technology companies so
Most of it's where we have our customers we have our technology deployment Center
And we're in those networks in the middle of arms are getting feedback from
I have an Intel team that essentially takes that day.
Plus bother date around the community and
I'm Partnerships in
Normal traditional ways of getting access to the data anyways
I'm in turn that data into intelligence about
Exist
I think the interesting thing in outside of our company but just for the CEO take away the larger community
Is pre 2014
I'm the only really talked about 1 or
2 Industrial Drive
Cell
We talked about like one hour name and then maybe one or two
And when my team
Really try to take it out it looks different 2015
Enter poking around and we started getting more more
Collection out of the industrial bar men
Started seeing more more things though
Sackler crackington
Are nation-states
Team
Targeting industrial operation
Run the World
And ends
It's easy to highlight
Team but I think
What's more important as an egg at Methodist
The community is
As we
Get better collection we find a lot of
Stop
Bangla narrative
Over the years has been oh well there's not a lot of dust
And reality weed
Staff had slick Schrodinger's IDs and we just don't look into the enough of that works hoping that's not dead
And I and I think as we ease
Gone and started looking at these industrial networks and getting access and and and getting a disability
More more
Becoming a parent
Target all along but
State some teams in
Tree crafts and things you never seen before
I think this time the reasons a targeted organization. Only military and and destruction
It's hotter than electric Robert
You want to steal intellectual property of accompanying
Not going to be in the you know the windows email environment it's going to be
And how their manufacturing their goods to the Pharmaceuticals or
Or you know how their expert duesing
Steel and doing a really good way I mean
Massive amount of wealth
Do you think Mimi nation states that are engaging
I would say mainly Nation
End
There
Components
I mean by that is
In the same way
We'd expect the United States government to use their defense industrial base
We're saying
Exactly the same thing with other states
Where it might be a hacker for hire taipei
Grouper people that are
Developing exploits for sale
But they're becoming components of Mason City operation
Without seeing a
Criminal element by them
Installs go Target Industrial
We're seeing States would have influenced in
And operations for the state efforts
Now you know
There's been a lot of the obvious players kicked around like
China and Russia and even Israel two stomachs
Stand
France
I'll be there
New big country that have the capability go after
Anchor compass
What about
Places like Saudi Arabia and Venice
Look at you see the kids around a lot is that true
In terms of them being aggressive or then
I think it's fair to say for any modern State and this is
This goes down the collection like why outside of
Why don't we hear a lot about NSA operate
Wound because they're not really a good
Cyber threat intelligence
Community in China
You know or we're not seem like a lot of Russian firms
Doing this type of analysis
What's the closest we get to it as I can cuz Friskies great team doing
But it really comes down to like where you're collecting and then announces you're putting on top of it why don't we hear more about
Pakistani
Cyber threats
I'm because we're not in the Indian energy
And so it water is threatened
Being geopolitical and Regional
I miss it if I can least a crafting until this work happening out on the
Global scale like it would normally but just in this case
And so Venezuela Saudi Arabia Algeria
Egypt
Brazil leader Neymar play Arthur's sword of a modern
Entity that has a strong intelligent
Community it is a highlight later they have a
Cyber component do that
They betray irresponsible not to for their own country
And Industrial
Control Systems rice yes
Have you come such a main component of having statecraft and policy influence and Alex property theft
And it just is a natural evolution
Getting a lot of cases
It states tend to try to get parity with
Each other one state have the capability another state wants to be able to have
I capability as well
And so as we're seeing
Morley saying seeing a sort of coming to life
It's also very commonly States try to keep up with each other
No
You know something big
Big news
What happened late last night that a lot of people in the infosec community were tweeting about
Today
Was
That
IDF
Apparently undertook an airstrike against some hack
Hamas
Cyberark
So I know you have experience in the government
First of all how does
How does one country
Identify what is cyber operative is
And
To your knowledge have you ever heard of
The US government or other Western Nations targeting hackers
Core
Quote unquote
Part of a terrorist organization and
Deemed
Cyber operatives
Yes this is a super wrench
Just in case and I think
Yeah I do see a lot of that kind of joke and I and I
I'm really not trying to disparage everybody all at once
But it is very interesting to see like now ever since New Year's
And I'm really good technical folks all of a sudden become international relations theorists and Military experts in overnight
It is interesting
It's a it's a real laugh riot
Auto Sale that is
Annette specific case
A lot of glass
You know Israel
Has a walk lifestyle
Target.
Places they're going to strike and
Excel does a moth another they're going to go after
And I do the other play attention that reads
And it's and it's unfortunate but they're they're just everything from rocket strikes.
Proverbial feedback
End
I'm interested to know
If this really was a
We targeted them because it was a cyber components
And this is what happened
Or if it wasn't just part of the normal
Hey this is the next Target on the list
And let's see if we can
No
How much do this is PR effectively
And like States messaging to each other
And how much it is real
But it but let's let's just take it at face value that is
Real
B
One of the
You public cases
If I'm not mistaken
And I wrote this week's Rock This Way
Just probably just Got7
But a couple years ago there were
Discussions around
Drone strike specifically targeting
Cyber
Experts
Isis and Al Qaeda
Effectively that folks that were using
This is an owl a recruit people but also see if they can't do someone hacking
Operation
It was in a release
Stacy say
I just found one today said
Dino targeting Isis internet cafe
Yeah exactly that's why I like without
Star Citizen
Do I think this is
The first example of
I'm do I think it is a very
Public high profile examples
And the fact that
Israel through an official
Mechanism would still there
Makes me all sorts of sad that Twitter's official mechanisms
But through it official mechanism came out and said this
Purpose of this was to go after
Aoi cyber operator
Yeah that's
I think it needs to be thought through and and kind of analyzing and
It would be good to get more information
Amit is a very important
Events
And from a holiday know who it is or that I was looking at that facility I mean
Tattoo components that one
We was talking about after
We should be hard
But it's not
Impossible and it's not
Or like it's getting easier over time and what they knocked out hard I don't mean like
Couple people can figure it out if you like as an adult
Requirements to work towards like
That organizations can really work towards it
Doberman
Really have a hold over that I think
If you're looking at the ability to understand
How would attack happen
Private sector wins over
Everything in those Networks
Therein
Senior tax making patterns out
The best cyber defenses
An innovation or saying that
But in terms of
Attribution
Government monopoly I like some of these companies have gotten really good at it
But there's also a lot of times.
The wrong and
I'm just nobody called him out or have the ability to call him out like when the last time you seen a major event or come out and go
Oh yeah was an axe
Never
There's no way we're getting it right a hundred
Is just marketing
But in this case
State of Israel says hey we had after you something that it's highly likely that they did
Usually when states do that they're they're very confident
And
Yeah especially with ones that are stupid
In the space that is usually not just
CSI cyber forensics
Texas yearly humentum signals intelligence and everything else well
And it's not like that Israel doesn't have an amazing human capability around Lawson and then the region
And then you tell it something I'm coughing they came already answer
And I also cannot imagine that Hamas is the most sophisticated in terms of
Hiding a threesome
So I think it's I think it's less of a case of did they get it right and
Case of
Was that at
Play the purpose of the operation
What's the kill them based off of
You're not being a cyber operator and and what does that mean for the community
Black Nike I think that's one four states that got to work through
Yeah and you think I mean for me my big my big question
I'm not doubting that they are cyber operators
Is it that's what Israel calling
My question is
Is a cyber operator a hacker capable of taking down a power grid or we talkin about
A guy who made a couple memes and is a propagandist
Has been
You know painted as such
Inflation in that in in the western Nations have done that
There there certain
Their ways of classifying these kinds of
Internet
Operator
You know what I mean that I have
Never felt comfortable with how States
Refer to anything
Nuggets
Sometimes it
Yeah that dude is
You're you and you felt malware
Wagon
Yep that that's real
And they're like yeah
Ana Garza
That
Hacked cyber command account
I clocked in with the default credentials like that's not the same man
To make fun of somebody
Will Derek
Terrorism
Stop terrorism
Like that Sky just like
Made fun of you and until I think there is
Got it it's
It is terrifying we look at
Space because
Neither of you and definitions of thing let me we seen this one in
You know what you call a terrorist
Horses
A diffident it is a very thin line in many countries
And so when we see cyber operators doing
Arizona military operation
What does that actually mean
Again a very very thin line
Any discussion or not relations of a special
Turn of Articles around from conflict alphabet even like me
Iran conflict
Like there's there's a whole view of
What you can do and Howland
Of course rules of the road for proportionate responses and
And I don't know what happened
Did they try to break in
To this really
Israeli government that works and they got caught and they also found it was other things going on and so they destroy the building like okay
Was it somebody
Yeah
Shitposting online
Like I doubt it but if that's the case
Alright Rob thank you for coming on and telling us about the Dire Straits of the Cyber Pearl Harbor or 9/11
That's coming our way
Like you're at me
Which episode was recorded by John northcraft
Produced by Lorenzo franceschi be edited by Sophie cases and hosted by me and Mac who
Please rate write a review for us on Apple podcast will be back next week