Eagle one package being delivered
A daring plan to meddle in American elections attempt to get Donald Trump
The White House it was happening before eyes but few people suck coming and even fewer we will
The Russians use internet trolls fake Facebook accounts and hackers to drive a wedge to the Humira
Can people from ending America and around the world became like a shot in the dark disinformation
Something we thought was just a cold warrior Relic was back and back big time since then
Congress has held multiple hearings on how to counter disinformation campaigns
Facebook Google when other Tech Giants have shut down thousands of fake accounts and called out
And American spies
Back back more than two years later we're also trying to figure out exactly how the Russians did it
How to get ready for 2020 do we even understand the problem real Schoenberg is the director of intelligence
Research
Celsius Advisory Group a consulting firm based in the US
Schaumburg his colleagues research and simulated tax but not just limited to the Cyber domain teltik us
Understand what a real-world information operation looks like
So information operations tell me how does this fit into
Quote on quote
The cyber
Well fiber is a part
Information operation
And I think
That first week
We kind of have to disentangle
. right because we here to term
Information operations
Throwing around a lot but
Really what we are focusing on currently
India Public debate
Is influenza
Like we talked about
The social media aspect
Make a call
Amplification
But that is really good
The influencer part
All information operation
So information operations is actually
Broad spectrum
Where cyber or offense
Defensive cyber operations just
Small Park
Right Thursday
Psyop part
Thursday
Electronic warfare part
Etc etc
So we basically have a misunderstanding in the public domain
Of what we're actually dealing with
Cuz we are focusing
Strictly on that social media aspect
Not just that we're also folks
Kissing on it in the very packed
Nicole way
Information operations
Have to be looked at
In the morning strategic fashion
So
In that one year timeline 5 your time at 10 your time line
Which is something we're not doing it all at
At the moment
Right End
At the same time information operations
In that strategic science
AR
Very hard to quantify
It's all qualitative
Write how do you measure influence
I mean not to think he says especially when you look at
You know
Mini golf in the room
The DNC hack
Podesta Etc
I mean
How much did that actually affect
Jimmy
You can't quantify but the only thing I can say is
That information operation
That influence operation it had some effect
Right so what I found very interesting is that it took us a very very long time in the public domain
To figure out that the DNC hack was not more than
Supporting operation of Greater
Plot
If you will
I thought so
Whitby 10 to look at all these things from
Very narrow vertical
Right so
If you have a cyber background you kind of look at okay
This target
Was hacked
Maybe dorsum implants
Maybe something else happened and that's kind of the
The area that you can find yourself
Easy 20%
Thank you you
Kind of look at an actor
You kind of look at Melissa's domains etc etc
Not as easy to graph
That influence part and how one domain influences another
Domain
Right as much
Harder
To disentangle
It takes a lot of effort
On everybody's part okay so then give me an example of how does a how does a larger operation
How does that look because I mean
If you're looking at it from an exit is it really what it comes down to his ass
Essentially
I'm not sure Espionage is that the right way to look at it but it's certainly a game of intelligence and Connor until
Our sacred sacred
It doesn't necessarily have to be statecraft and
The greater scheme rights not just our major adversaries like Russia and China
I think since 2016 musina raizel
Not just private team but also political operatives right
2016 Regatta results
How you feel about it
I want your thoughts are on
It was a watershed moment where a lot of people realized
Owee
We are fighting for hearts and Minds
Forget about all this kinetic stuff that's like dangerous and
No cost a lot of money
We realize we can just use small Nimble teams
To try and influence a Target demographic
I think that's
Where get more complicated because
We need to
Distinguish fact
And a conjecture
Right
So if you want to understand information operations or the influence part of it
Write a ghost
2 motive and intent
All the particular actor what are they trying to achieve
So that that an intelligent perspective goes beyond
Attribution
Right is not just figuring out
Who shot
Who fired
The gun
But it's also who pays for it and what were their motives
Right. So that's much harder to figure out than simply oldest person fired the weapon
And that's what we have
So if you want to figure out motive and intent
And
The adversaries estate actor that means you need to have visibility in how that stayed actress thinking
Commercial entities I'm going to have that capability
And
4D
State actors who do have the capability
Once they have that capability they don't want to give it up
So I think that's part of the issue for it the US government
Psych what do we know and what can we say publicly
The USG doesn't want to venture into the speculation and conjecture area too much
But
If they can somehow prove hey this is what the actor was thinking
Then the actor knows all we've been compromised one
One way or the other
Which you know
It's not good for whoever's watch
Okay so you're saying that obviously this cyber aspect of it or some of the influence
Operations that occurred likes you know the DNC hack it was
Supporting
This whole operation
Wlppr
Familiar with that hole
You know Russia tried to steal the election kind of
Merida that we keep hearing
What was the operation walking through it
Well
Again it's a very hard to say with certainty right because it's conjecture
More soda than dealing with facts
What I think we need to
Reevaluate is that this
Wasn't about an election per se
It's about it
Weather
A campaign targeting the American people
Write the election result itself
Did not necessary matter for Russia
But it's about amplifying
That you know discontent
I'd it's a long-term operation
Don't know if you've heard of a
Yuri bezmenov
Was the KGB Defector righty defected at the
The late 60s
And in the mid-80s he gave the TV interview which can find on YouTube
And he basically talked about you know strategic demoralization
How that's a decades-long pro process
Program right and then that information is
Half a century off at that point
So
Free
Factor in all this
You know
Yale research all these new technologies that easily create Echo Chambers
Write Facebook Etc Google
A very easily create custom Echo Chambers for
For anyone
Right through targeted advertising
All that good stuff
That
Fire Apparatus
Really allows
Foreign adversaries to influence
Us
At scale
Nowadays
It sounds like there's some sort of relation
Stream the Russian government unless
I'd say
Allegedly the NRA
Is that what you're kind of saying you're you're trying to create
Chaos within your adversary
Or the Tiger adversary
Mistrust
Its own political system
Is that when you're dealing with it on a global
Level
Their weekend
Right the way I person look at 2016 is was a continuation of a long
Perm
Systemic attack against her
Institution
Right and we weep now basically mistrust everything
If you look at censorship
Right we can look at the Russian mob and you can look at the Chinese model
Chinaberry
Thoroughly controls what information is available to its citizens
Directions
The date don't have those constraints
To the same extent
From where I sit I think the Russians learned after the Cold War
That if you very narrowly confined information available
To your
Population
Then they will trust
Whatever information is not unit is outside of that
Supply chain
Right so if
When people listen to voice of America they trusted
So in the long run
You know for oppressive regimes
They start realizing
If we
Filter out
Any kind of descend
People who do not trust the government will trust that dissenting voice
Sophia simply you know
Let everything go
All these different opinions
Or facts
Are allowed in the public domain
Then how you determine
What is fact
And that is basically one of the big fights that we effectively have going on right now
How do you determine what is real
When there is a million Echo Chambers out there
All you know is having that unique answer
That is suitable to to you and your Target demographic
That is the
Long-term scary Park
From a societal perspective
I need some else to do with you no are you familiar with surcouf
I'm not sure
He was a Russian czar
Political theorists
Putin's henchmen
Created this whole idea of
I actually had a background in performance art
Yeah sorry was your pronunciation
Threw me off
Surah kahf
He essentially says
Are you create
Mistrust
Between all political
With Anna Target
Rights over for Putin what it was
Was the Kremlin would directly
Finance
Both left and right
Wing parties
And organization
To have them
Fight each other
When then the obvious answer to all this the only person that you
You trust him it's all is chaos is a
Strongman
Like Putin
Well it's a you know anything is possible nothing is true
Rights of wonder
Trust at that point
Right and then it really
Start revolving around your Echo chamber
Right at and you will
Just accept whatever information is given to you with an echo chamber
I know if you kind of trying to translate that into you know all the social media that we are absorbing
I mostly through our smartphones right
A lot of it is about agitating
A person
But can you believe that this just happened on that point you are you know what happened
Right right there.
It's not about you know sides
Just getting off
Everywhere
I didn't want to find yourself you know when to add jatate it State you become more susceptible to whatever messaging
Somebody's trying to feed you
So
I'm in the long run
Fact is
Is really one of the fights that would that we have to fight
And looking at investigative reporting some of the reporters that we
Talk to this started to realized as removing more into
A data or information based reporting
Rather than just
Talking to people
How do we trust open source
Sprite substitute high-back to cyber
How do you trust something that that you find on virustotal
Right Wit Me Assume everything that's uploaded to virustotal
Is trustworthy
Uploaded by
Somebody who just found something interesting
But what if somebody starts poisoning that well intentionally
Right and you can
Therefore seeds for
Right because people go through virustotal
This repository of all these different binaries and other stuff
No mostly malware but
Alex Lewis
Oblique
You can basically plant historian
People basically dig through a dataset
They find something out this is interesting maybe this actor tried to
Target that particular Target
But how do you verify that actually happened
How do you know that
Somebody didn't put that
There on purpose
That maybe frames North Korea
Or whoever whoever
What do you do in this face what it what is your job with your company
Well in our company we basically
Whitney deal different clients
So some clients realize old
We are a long-term Hard Target that realize
All week we are dealing in the complicated space
We are starting to see reputational attack
Right we are being manipulated
And how do we counter that
Or you staying at their dear
I fall apart from something else that happened
That that mean not directly tied to them
But still they realize order something going on
So we offer both Services as well as training as how do you
It and how do you defend your information supply chain
Right in that information supply chain
Affects both you know the way you consume information or the way your systems consume information as well as
How do you produce
Information or news
When it comes to Newsroom
How do you
Verify the integrity
David step
Where in this information supply chain
Exists the possibility of influence
AR
Observation
What do you do to Connie tell them like this is what you
View
Nono isn't it goes Way Beyond a tweeting tweeting is
Not really on our radar I guess to some extent it is but it's not but it's
Looking at
If if let's say it's Newsroom
It's like
We started having some conversations
About you know how are your reporters being influenced
So some of these conversations go
Are no longer just
Oh watch out for that malicious
PDF
But watch out for you no sourcing and all that kind of counterintelligence
People that are kissing you know the story of The Washington Post actually caught
The people trying to sell them as a fake story right so
That's basically that the shift
That we have to undergo from a very
You know
Tools based approach
Like I use this piece of antivirus and you know that protects me from
Malware
28 more
Pronounce long-term Conger intelligence program
Are you trying to figure out you know where are my weaknesses and our people actively
Lee trying to exploit us
It almost sounds like you're selling like
Counterintelligence to all these people like how to actually spot being
Being manipulated but also
Being used as a source being
You know I mean
Something like
And we don't know for sure who the motor for hasn't come out but there could have been an opportunity or chance that
Wikileaks was like an onion
Unwitting
I said
Allegedly the Russian
And they were given information that they then
Disbursed
Two larger
Public
Is it stuff like that
Do we have to be aware of where the
From my perspective the reporter
You kind of
You will always
Especially if you're getting government information
You think why am I getting this
Why am I being fed
Right yeah I mean it's
Basically what it comes down to how do you do Connor and Telugu
Smart and actionable manner
How can you figure out you know
I was trying to Target you and in what ways
So what you're saying is in the Modern Age there were in right now in 2019
It is so volatile the way we consume
And fling information
That we now need
A new way of interpreting it and accepting what facts are
We can't just
Sort of Take One Source even one new store in
Here we are
I think that's very much on the mark
Right we we have to as a society we have to rethink
How do we consume information
Cuz
What was effectively happening right now is we're trying to consume information real time
Are the adversaries have you know dear cyber capabilities or whatever you want to call them and they can feed that disinformation
At machine speed
Fact-checking happens at human speed
That's a losing proposition
Writes it so hot how do you deal with that and applies to a newsroom also applies to a financial right if you're a hedge fund
You know how do you trust an information that you and Jeff
Or you think about artificial intelligence
Okay
Okay you get all this data
How do you verify that it's actually good data
So
Especially in in some of the sectors that don't have as much
Experience with adversarial data whatever you want to call it
Right or adversarial influence
How do you know
Kind of reconfigured the lens through which you look at
Damn
We are in a hole
I'm here in a whole heap of trouble I have to tell you cuz I don't have you been on Twitter lately you seen it
I was on Twitter this afternoon and I could feel myself getting agitated this like this is not good in that nightclub
Used to be that people would call Twitter a hellscape
And it would be like
Integrate word hellscape
But now that I see people call Twitter a hellscape I'm like that's not even
Close to what it actually is
It's so much worse than that I mean it's
It's fantastic in a lot of ways
As a source of
Information gathering
But it's also just
Usually represents
I think
The worst of humanity
Ingested information and
You know
The return cycle it's
Like
Go on there sometimes and I'm just like
Right and then whenever you feel that agitation that's When You're vulnerable to influence right as the Soviets said agitprop
Agitation and propaganda
Kind of bird the foundation if you were
Yeah really is now
Itsfunneh somebody asked me this recently they said but what about the US
The us do this
Are they good at it cuz it seems like the Russians have been
Pretty amazing at this for a long time
Yeah from where I stand I don't think the US
Is particularly good at it
I think intelligence States like Russia and China are just inherently
Better at it right cuz
You grow up in that environment it's what you know
It's all very cloak-and-dagger and it kind of comes natural to you
You know all this subversion cuz you're not you're not very surveillance state where
Where intelligence
Is capital
Right exactly cuz it's a you know it's
I mean I wouldn't call Russia a totalitarian state but I think
China at this point is
Pretty much.
I think it's fair to call both of them intelligence date
Right and one that is the environment in which you grow up you haven't
Very different way of
Of of looking at things and
Looking at
How information flows
How you know
To do this thing that scale
Have you ever heard of the protocols of Zion
Of course which is
Which is crazy because it's literally was the first
Real
For people who don't know what it is it was essentially this
Meetup conspiracy that was created by something called the oak Rana which is essentially it was a czarist intelligence
I am it was probably the first really truly
Sammy modern intelligence
Agency
They created this
Complete garbage anti-Semitic
Pamphlets
That
Describe this
Jewish conspiracy
Conspiracy to take over
And it was spread Wireless
Still want you
To this day by some people true
It's insane
I mean that's that's an important operation
Again going back to pizmon of
Hayden rezanov
It is that right 85
Percent of the KGB was focused on active measures
Right on another
What's something that was
Repeated by other defectors
Later on
Right so 85%
Was focused on the influence operation
Psyops or whatever you want to call them
In the US
How God I mean doors
Dirt dirt dirt or so many
I think it was a
The stuff about
Fake news about
Our disinformation I should say about
Churches being burned down in the South and I think the Clinton admin actually yeah
Issued a note on
So
That's how high it went
Are how high can go
Enough
It's constant
Right but it's
It's no longer just about feeding you false facts
If that's the term I should be using
To begin with
It's not just about feeding you this information right it's about
Genji
Trying to constantly remind you lately
Tok what is fact what is fiction
And making it harder for you to
You know distinguished
I mean it's really insane to because
You get this world right now where
The term fake news is thrown around by Avril
Everybody
I mean
It's wild like
Soccer players
Fake news
Analysis story
Politician
Actors
Everybody
People cultural significance
And it's it's so widespread
I think it's become
Not so much
That is actual fake news
But
It's now become I don't like that news so I called fake news
And that that's part of the that's part of why I don't work so well
Just to think about it in different ways that one of the Prime directives off prop
R6S
Propaganda is
Propaganda has to be total
You have to be confronted with it all the time
Right
So not now
I get to blast like
2 years or so we've just been hearing about disinformation fake news and all sounds
Very terrible
So not now we're slowly trying to
Bu Force antutu
Idea of hey we need to legislate
Problem away
Which
When I started talking about this problem or actively back in 2015
In the lead up to 2
Do some stuff
I was like this is the long-term strategy
Holler adversaries
Nick that they will want us to train Legend
Just laid our free speech
We will see that some sort of tactical victory
But in reality will be a strategic
Defeat
So that is I think where we really need to
And I'll start thinking about hey how do we do any of this stuff without curbing
Are free speech
Cuz if you start curbing are free speech.
You know
An American
Right and there's a lot of conversations
About
Free speech
That I think are
You know
Are you with a lot of crazy s*** with free speech though it's
Batman is Ernie true but I think about it and I'm going back to
Decide decide think about spam or malware right
It's
How do you legislate that problem away we haven't been effective for the last know 20 30 years of Mesa
So think we can legislate this problem away
And the other thing then to consider is that
Foreign intelligence agencies aren't going to care about our laws
They're going to do their thing they're going to be undeterred
So what are you actually
Attempting to fix
Who are the big players
I mean obviously we got rushing mean they're one of the biggest
It's not the biggest
China who else
Iran is becoming has become more active
You can even try and look at some of the stuff that North Korea has put out is an interesting way of
Trying to position themselves
Right
Again a lot of it is conjecture right that burden of proof goes beyond attribution it's about motive
And intent how do you figure out
Why somebody says something
Write two people could say the exact same thing
But one could be you know
Well intended in the other person could be
You know up to no good
So simply
You know looking at it a lot of stuff is being said on social media isn't that
You know doesn't give you that clearer picture
And the other thing is because everything is so out in the open
It's very easy
Or
Actors to basically look at whatever disinformation campaign DC on social media and comp
Right and then repurpose it for their own agenda
I mean we say that US government has no it is not very good at this
But I was probably the best of manipulating
Unpopular
They look at something like the way right now
They're selling this
This war in Venezuela a possible war in Venice
Escuela
And it's pretty wild
You know
So the way I look at it is that
Targeted advertising as basic
Sickly allow direct messaging from anyone in the world to a particular Target demographic
So the idea from that say 50 years ago that a state
More or less had a monopoly on messaging
It's
It's people
It's it's it's population
Not that notion is
It's gone with targeted advertising
So what are you saying today you're saying it's not just us government doing this you're saying it's probably likely
Some of the interested parties
Who are
Trying to spread Pro and paid
Venezuela propaganda
I guess I'm not talking about
Venezuela at specifically
I'm just saying targeted advertising gives everybody to tools
To do targeted agitprop right well I'm going to read between the lines there
Cuz I mean New York Times debunked at this video of
Burning Convoy
But it was the
The Maduro government that I've done it
And then
Turned out now actually was
With the opposition
With Molotov cocktails
And you know these were images spread around by
Major US Government figures
As almost like this pretext of how brutal this Madhuri
Not to say that the
Regime is infertile but you know going to invade a country
And it's
Sovereignty
Is
You know this is a much larger question
But
You know they did that
The Iraq War
Look at the way they stole that
You got some US Government classified
But it's
Again about motive and intent
Generally speaking right what water
What is the
Historically the message that the US has
Does tried to convey is you know little boy
Liberal democracy and all that good stuff right has been generally about freedom
But let me put it differently the work we do is agnostic
Right
Wake me simply look at hot how are
People being influenced
And that's kind of
Hour or cyst
And that's kind of word starts and ends and
You know I'm not here to talk about what
You know the us or any government
Has been doing
I'm here to visit
You don't look at this impact on society
And
Look at how we
You know consume information
Rethink how we do that
So which I think we've got a serious problem with
Right right
Right out how do you do reporting
In a place where people are actively
Retargeting sources
I mean how do you
How do you create truth
In a society like this
What's so fragile
Like how do you actually do that
We'd like to think it was much simpler
But I think now
Seeing a Fallout
From that particular election like
You put it at the watershed moment
Whether you like whatever happened or whatever outcome
We have to accept that there is some sort of
Yeah War Friday it but I think the biggest one is obviously
A War facts
Right it's
It's War facts and it's a war about not just facts but you know
Institutions that you believe in
And that is
Very difficult
To comprehend I think as it is a larger demographic right we obviously have an interest
Send it
In this particular topic and
Want to figure out how we are being manipulated
Enough for a general audience
Instead they don't think about
Things right I think we're getting there though
You know I think people are starting to see that manipulation
Looking for example even the sort of this
Suddenly we have
Public discourse about
Billinghurst
Possibly wrong
Right liquid
And these are things that
We're starting to see
Sort of these these Global contacts
Of manipulation and
Powerful institutions
Right and also I think
Outlaw that has to do with
What happened in the last 4 years
Right around for years
2016 even before that I would say
And I think it's
It's changing
Our perceptions
Yeah our perceptions are being reshaped
Entirely
Righttime
And some of that
Mike
Expose power structures that we
We weren't familiar with
And some of that might be too
You know
Influence was in a bad way right if you go back to bezmenov Etc
It's all about how do you make the adversary
Think
In a way that they are going to do something that is
Is good
For you know
Somebody else
Right how do you get somebody to act against their best
I am in that matters
That is the core of
What we're dealing with that a
At the global scale
Give a good example of how maybe cyber with combined
Effectively with
And influence operate
I think the
Best example to date is
Notpetya attack
Back in the 20
T17.
Primarily affected Ukraine
But spread well beyond Ukrainian
And it basically
Western Logistics
Supply chain
So that was a
A piece of malware that
Pretending to be ransomware
But there was no way to recover your data
Do all these machines that were getting hit by notpetya
Eyewear non-recoverable
So it basically created huge havoc in the Ukraine
But it didn't stop there it is attack is being attributed to
To GRU
And in 2017 we saw at notpetya and notpetya post itself as a ransomware attack
Tackett was being pushed
Through app
Tax software that is a very popular in Ukraine and bite
People or companies
To do business
Ukraine
So it was pushed out as a malicious update
And as a result they say
Sickly anyone
I was using that piece
Softer by not picture which
Subsequently
I spread through all these Network
I know it was
The worm that
It hit all the networks of the
These companies that are
Are using that soft
So
Banks in the utilities etc etc were
Crippled in Ukraine but didn't stop there was
Also
You know Ukrainian business partners or whatever you want to call them
So some of those companies were major Logistics
Supply chain companies
That's on the leeward
Out of commission for a very long time
Mark Mark
FedEx
In-N-Out
These major major companies what we're hit
And
What was interesting there is
The first element is
Deposes ransomware soda first
Wave of news
A new ransomware is hitting all these companies
What's going on
And the second wave of news basically a focused on the
Usage of Eternal blue
From the shadow broker leak
Basic set of one of the ways
Stop patches spreads
Is through here and effect thereof was
We basically sauce Rob Joyce
Then at the White House having to defend a say in its usage of these
Is after the the biggest Cyber attack in history
I did this was
Estimated that more than 10 billion dollars in damage
So I'm right at the point where there should have been major major push back
Underwest saying hey we condemn this
The pack
Instead the West Was more or less backed into a corner
The disconnect
Between a lot of intelligence agencies
Observe that attack and it
Fallout is very very different from how the news media and the average reader
Observed at follow up
It's effectively conjecture
I should point that out
But if
The gru have planned this
It certainly worked out very well for
Right just it it would essentially did was
It undermines
It support the West has
In Ukraine
While also
Effectively taking out
You know
Kind of machines in that country
And I'm sure
Weakening Ukraine
Image
Business-wise
Abroad
Nearby
Isolating at 4
Right right so there's that and again that the US wasn't able to push back right tus Ojos hitter
Does well
But
Instead of pushing back saying this is unacceptable
Write cos
Again. This was a destructive attack and I think up until notpetya all the major destructive attacks that we know
Like
The power grid
Write rain in Ukraine but but also you know that the hits against our
Saudi aramco or you know
How to replace the
They have all been confined to one particular company
Right
These were destructive attacks but it's extremely extremely Target
Vs notpetya which really spread far and wide
Right up so that that's a whole different set of norms that are
You know being transgressed
I thought so. You're needed to be a strong push back saying hey this is unacceptable
Cuz this is a major escalation from
Assembly targeting one
Particular company
And instead
You know wait wait wait
Would that the outline base
Simply said you know any
You know
Did that that they were anti-nsa witch
Again
You know people can be
People can have that view but it wasn't the right time
Does that make sense
Okay so last question
If you can give anybody some advice like
Common people right now
What would it be to sort of not being manipulated what would you tell them
I think I would start
It's saying that
Freedom of speech is
Extremely important
Sometime we can't give up
That up
To try and fight something that we
We can't legislate away
React we haven't been
Successful with
Legislating
Similar types of
Problems there's nothing
To suggest
That legislation will
Net positive
Secondly I would say use ad blockers
Target advertising is
One of the main ways we are being
Manipulated
And a third I would say that
Read newspapers or or rather you know
Get your news
Fromm
Places that actually have time to do fact checking
Right so it doesn't have to be a newspaper per se but you know go to reputable places
I did not do in this week's episode was produced by Lorenzo franceschi because I recorded by William Flynn