Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered fancy bear ATT 10 Lazarus group
Charming kitten these are all the names given to government hacker groups in did you pay any attention to cybersecurity
Russian hackers Chinese hackers and groups are usually called apts
Government-sponsored hackers
Today Department of Justice is announcing of to hackers associated with the Chinese guy
The FBI suspect the hack was perpetrated by Russian intelligence in an effort to elect Donald Trump
All we know is that the hacking group responsible go by the names cozy
Bear and fancy bear cyber team known as fancy bear has also gone up
Target in Europe and Russia this week were talking with Eva galperin
The director of cyber-security with the Electronic Frontier Foundation
Show me state Hackers from Oliver every corner of the globe because countries everywhere are growing their cyber armies
There's no signs that's going down I'm National Security reporter Ben McCune and this is side
So pretty crazy
Few weeks in apt line
Just like every other week you
Stop just to start this off can you just tell me what does a p
Apt stands for advanced
Persist
Threat
And is usually understood
2 min
State actors
Though honestly
Plenty of other groups could probably
Describe
Persistent
Abt's are are usually trotted out sort of in contrast
To criminal groups
That are doing
Celeste Target
Why do people call advanced persistent threat
For what
Consternation
So the the thing that is generally thought
Distinguish nation-state actors from non nation state actors
And I will
Not pause
To go on a rant
Stolen directly
Amara town
About why we shouldn't call him dick
Is a doctor's there just a doctor's nation state has burst
Specific meaning in political science
But this is what we do
Go ahead and taking it up
It just sounds
So the
The ways in which state Act
Thought to be different
Criminals
Is that there
Schools are differ
So they have a
Group of people
Coup
Full-time job is
Breaking into the targets devices or accounts
Stay if you start work in the morning they finish work in the evenings they have
I accessed
No more advance
Twirling because they have more money
I am
They are willing to be
T-shirts
Which is one of the reasons why it is called a persistent threat
So it's a combination of the fancier tooling and patience
Along with us
Tendency you to be very narrowly targeted and therefore
Harder to find
I'm busy that's exactly it right there their government hackers
That there
Exact job
The shop the office
Every single day
Go after a Target
Until you
Obtain what you need
And then go home
Isn't that kind of
Interesting things
You know people's perceptions
Of what
Cyber armies are these
Government hackers
It seems a lot more kind of fancy and clandestine
China for example
Dave
Track somebody's
Chinese government hackers
And they see that they are extremely active between 9 to 5
Beijing time
I'm a break at lunch
Yep that this is just somebody's job
On one hand that makes
It
Carter 2
To protect yourself against
Because I'll keep coming at you until until they gain an advantage
And on the other hands there
Not that ideologically invested
And in owning you
They're just doing it for work
But one of the ways in which
State actors are considered
Very different from criminals
Is that they're harder to protect against
And the reason that they're harder to protect against does not only because of their fancy or Cooling and potentially willingness to spend
More money on
Uncompromising the a specific Target
But also because you can't just use the security posture of
Outrunning the other guy and outrun the bear
I if you specifically are being targeted that you don't
You can't just make yourself a harder Target
Then
Other acts
Or other journalists and think that that's going to be enough
I am that's one of the ways in which
ABC's are differ
Frank from trying to protect yourself
And you're also dealing with an adversary that you
Likely will never apprehended has the full protection
State like
I say China or Russia
Yeah I mean what are you what are you going to do
Doj issues indictments
BJ's against Pacific Russian hackers
Pacific Chinese hackers add it's unlikely to come to anything
And people involved in similar hacking
In the United States against
Target's outside of the United States think that this sets a terrible precedent
Because they all imagine indictments coming down
Name exam
In in other countries and it's not unreasonable to think that this is not a president that the US should be say
And to be really simple about what's the like
Top 10 nation-state hacking
What are the who's the most active
Who's the most advanced
Who does the things that you know Uke
Say
It's sort of advancing this whole geopolitical
Space online
Well it really depends on what you mean by that
It turns out that you don't have to be super advanced in order in order to compromise most Target
Generally five eyes countries Plus
China
Israel
And I would say Russia
Are are
Thought to be the most
Takeda.
We're definitely thought to be sort of at the at the Leading Edge
Of nation-state espionage
Others the famous James mickens quote in which he goes on and on about how old you are if you go up against the Mossad
So
Israel is considered to be
Tremendously advance
Highly determined
If your
If your attacker is the NSA
Do you have some
You have some very serious concern
You can mostly need to concern yourself with mitigation rather than being able to keep everything
Completely under wraps
So
Are generally thought to be the most
Advanced doctor's but it turns out that you don't have to
To be varied
Eastern Oregon
Successful
The wrong for example is
Tremendously prolific when it comes
To test phishing campaigns and campaigns of malware
The same goes for
Ethiopia which we don't normally think of is as a major cyber actor
As far as we can tell Ethiopia Ethiopian government the previous Ethiopian government
I bought just about every
Commercial hacking tools that you can possibly get your hands on and had attempted to use them against
The opposition
Ever since the change in government
And not any Pio Pio we expect to see that sort of calm down a bit
We've also seen everything UAE
Saudi Arabia
Bob Crane
I'll add it
Same goes
Score for Mexico
I've used these are all sort of
Lesser
Last of Us Takeda doctors but they have managed to be
Successful
Genesis tinting series that you know you look at the Middle East right now and some of those countries
Such as.
Are the countries that actually
Seminole eating arms buyers
In the entire world
Actual kinetic weaponry
We're also seeing service
Similar of
Malware and espionage
Tools in exact
Same area
Not everybody who is who's running around
Stockpiling
Military weapons is necessarily upping their cyber-espionage game
But for political reasons
In the in the Gulf you've definitely seen an uptick in both of these lines
Quite simply because
Espionage
Goes goes hand-in-hand with kinetic Warfare
And so is considered to be EPO part of part of the Pikachu
So when you are engaged in kinetic Warfare you also want to know what the
What your opponents are doing
Because it allows you to be more effective fiction
If you are in a in a position as a state where you're trying to say avoid kinetic Warfare
Espionage is also considered to be useful
Way of approaching
The art of espionage
Which is an argument that Espionage prevents Warfare igneo by allowing
States to have
Soda
Air release valve
I so that they have option
Instead of
Just blowing each other up
That I buy this argue
But
Do think that states by
Into it and so they invest very heavily in a
Sweetheart
When they're gearing up for chemical warfare or if they're in the middle of it
I thought I believe us considers the cybers
To be another
Theater of war
Well I mean that kind of goes to the hole
The holster of uproar
Hysteria around Russia
Sort of
Almost god-like power
State Government whenever
Now we pause for me to laugh
Yes using the mighty powers of fishing John podesta
Russian government has managed
Shoe high back in control of Our Lives
That is a
Tremendous exaggeration
On what hand
Russian and Ukrainian and other post-soviet actors are extremely Act
Active in the space
Boost
In terms of
State espionage
Spying on
Each other and spying on
United States like the
Russian Ukrainian spy
Is
Dizzying if you try to keep track of it
But also
They have a long history of criminal Acts
There are a lot of
Of cybercriminals breeding inside of the post-soviet states
And in Russia at least were very long time it was understood
That if you wanted to engage in an online crime
That as long as you weren't ripping off Russians the rest of the world was fair game and you would have a safe place to sit
As far as I know that is
Nobody sent me a memo on
Like what Russian cyber crime is up to but I tried and I tried to keep an eye on it
And
Because of that understanding
There is a
There is a large number of criminals with considerable expertise
Study is
That the states were able to draw
Yeah sort of that pooling of talent that happens in Russia where there's legitimate evidence out there so
Suggesting the UEFA
SP operate
It's somebody's clandestine
Sites where they're able to
To get some of these
Blackhat
Some of their bidding
And it's a great way to
Make sure the United States
What's your kind of nose
It's your
You know we didn't really section at 1 so
So sorry
It allows
It allows the rush
Russian government to have a sort of
Plausible deniability
But there's also just a whole question of how plausibly deniable
Do they want to get
These days
You you can actually fairly strong attribution and
It's not like anything's going to happen to Russian
Inside of Russia travel to the United States
There are no real consequence
The difference
Between what states
Presents
Is just
You know the sheer proliferation of these agencies now and these different governments that
Have
This new capability
Online
Or do you think that this is something that's always been around and
It's just sort of evolving
Just like
Every other country
Have had the internet
I do think that the extent to which
State espionage
Become less
Expensive
And especially digital Espionage has become
Inexpensive
To the point where you can
Contact a company like NSO group in Israel or hacking team in Milan
And for a few hundred thousand dollars
Cats get access
Target's mobile phones
You're definitely seeing this
Spread among countries that are not thought to be on The Cutting Edge of espionage
Big thing that has really changed since approximately 2010
I is is not that the capabilities has have improved
It's the
Your average person was likely to be a Target is carrying a tracking device
The proliferation of the mobile phone
Has really changed every
Because it's such an incredibly tempting Target
Because I carry such a wealth of the
About
People that you might want to know
And
As a result
There's a
Just a lot more to spy
Well that's a neck
Extremely depressed
I should bring the Christmas
I mean I don't get to choose just
Did proliferation of intelligence sources
You know it in
2007 or 2008
Are Target
Platform was
Three devices in the you know you going to see
You go after somebody
Post Addison
And in the present time and you have 18 device
This is where you can get into their Wi-Fi
Absolutely
Even more disturbing than people are installing things like Alexa
So now you have this sort of always on listening device
Turn your music on your lights on and off
I read a story this morning about a guy who had the requested all of his information from a man
DPR
And Amazon accidentally sent him the voice recordings
From some other user who had an Alexa
I did not have Alexa
Absolutely knew that the Alexa recordings were not him
And you could find out a lot of it
Extremely personal stuff about this guy
Based on that
So that's really
Disturbing
We're definitely making it easier and easier
4 First states to spy on us
By just making more and more information available and filling our our homes and our lives with device
I heard a story about Vladimir Putin
Once before wear
Apparently
He doesn't use a cell phone
He doesn't touch a can
Computer
And he only issues
Top secret
Commands
6 floors below
I don't know if that's true or not
But Mafia like a mafia Capo just seemed like maybe the only way
To Italy
Mostly evade your information or having a hot Mike situation
From happening
That's certainly one way
And again is very different Target
Then say you were me
Number of people who would like to know what Putin is doing at any given time
Is much greater than the number of people are interested in my life for yours and the amount of trouble that they're willing to go through
Is much greater
So it's really all about
Yeah I wonder what he is doing right now
Posing shirtless for Ocala
What about
The way that
Let's a journalist
Activists
Regular citizens have been
Expanded
Target foremost
States cuz you know
Look at someone like
Khashoggi
There's reason to believe that he was being spied on his well
Not everything track
I mean you look at the journalist that were killed in the CR early this year possibly being tracked
As well
How's that space
Evolved
In the last year
Will it used to be that if a state wanted to
Physically track somebody's location they had to send someone to go follow them
But as I said before now we all conveniently carry tracking devices in our pockets
I am so if you can own somebody's phone you can get their location and if you can get their location you can learn
An awful lot about
Someone who they're communicating with
Again
This is
Why The Safety Dance
Security of these devices is so incredibly important
Because they provide
This incredible wealth of information that is so useful to States
And having said that
Kind of information that is useful to
The states is also the kind of information that is
That is used
Domestic
For example abusive partners
That's a very similar relationship to their target
Say an authoritarian government does
To a dissident
Are they want to keep track of them they want to know what they're doing the wonder where they're going they want to know who they're talking to
I had
As it burns out
You can deploy more or less the same technology in order to do this
I think in the midst of
Venus week
Facebook
Do Jess if they were giving up
Add information to some of the other bigger
Search Mediacom
Doctor user
Now you know
And I don't have to
Bring up the Snowden leaks
Is it really can t protect yourself
From this sort of bronchitis
Does Big Brother
He's in the end there always seems to be some sort of Ace in the Hole
The bad guys
Well
What are the things that I did at BFF a few years ago was I led the
Right of BFFs privacy
Security advice
Two Ordinary People and vulnerable people in general population
Surveillance
Defense
And
One of the ways in which I tried to get people to
To think about surveillance self-defense
Is threat modeling
To really sit down and think about what you wanted protection who you want to protect it from
And the reason why this is incredibly important
Is that trying to protect everything all the time from everybody will just drive you
I it is impossible and you should not bother
But that doesn't mean that you should give up
It means that you should really just narrow it down
To what am I trying to protect
By trying to protect
Against
I am and
You make all of your medications accordingly
For example if I am particularly concerned
About
A stalker
Or a government
I'm going to do very different things than if I'm
Concerned about ads
And adware
I'm concerned about my parents spying on me you or
My school
Or my church
These are all different things either different people with different levels of capability
And the things that I need to do in order to avoid them are different
I remember a source once told me in
The intelligence
Community when it comes to apts
Is there targeting you
The only thing you can do is slow them down
Cuz they're going to get it
One way or the other
It depends
Again it depends on the EPT it depends on how determined they are to get you
And how important
Often
Find time is it
Especially if you are if you are a journalist
Or if you are an act
Activists and you just need enough time to publish your story or to get your action out
Then being able to delay the people who are were spying on you or trying to understand what you are doing
Is
Sufficient
You don't always have to
To keep your opponent in the dark
You just have to keep them several steps
Behind you
So he's one of my my last
Cuz I wanted it cuz we haven't really spoken about it
The elephant in the room
China
In the news lately
Apts
What is China's Main
Sort of geopolitical
Goal when it comes to using you
Well
What are the interesting things about China is that they have a variety of a peach
I am in much the same way that Russia's apt landscape is a many
Splendored thing
So many bears
ISO interview
Bears
There are many pens
So in China we have a bunch of
Different
Government organizations that engage in in-state hacking
There are also sort of
Para government
Organizations organizations that seem to
The theme to act
With the blessing of the government
And there are also criminal organizations and there's kind of sub
Overlap between
Similar to Russia
So you see
State Espionage being used to uncover
Sources
Stories
Especially stories surrounding political issues
UC State spying being used
Aya for State Control
For example control of the weaker population in Northwestern
Northwestern China
Angie
And you also see criminal activity and sort of corporate
Which is sometimes
Personal
And other times is.
Kind of in conjunction with
What state goals
A frog sample stealing intellectual property so that a Chinese company can manufacturer
American company or european companies products
More cheaply and therefore
This is more of a personal question for you and the SS but
Do you ever think in a PT
Targeted you
BFF
More than once
How did you react that
I wrote it up
I really don't feel published
I like that
Muscle knots not backing down
I'm going to
Extremely lazy
Security researcher
Nothing would make me happier
Then is governments good
Send me there malware directly
It saves me the trouble of having to find it
12 a.m. PT is out there targeting Ava
Let's get started at GSF. Org
Spell it right
Les Paul can talk a little bit about dark caracal
So
Earlier this year
ESS
Worked with
Security researchers at Lookout ad we uncovered a campaign of cyber espionage
That covered both the mobile and desktop device
That seemed
To be
Based out of Lebanon
And was targeting
People would be of interest to the Lebanese government
We managed
The Crackdown the physical location
From which
The administrator was logging into the portal
And it was a specific floor of a specific building
Run by the general directorate of
Lebanon in Beirut
So we can't say exactly who was
Who is behind this campaign but we can tell you it's coming from inside the room
And what is the interesting things that we discovered was that this was the
Same
Infrastructure that had been used
For us
A spying campaign that EFS had reported on a couple of years ago
Which we called operation men
Monroe B&B
Cat
Wildcat wishes
Native to the steps
Kazakhstan
And this particular campaign was targeting people of Interest
To Alex.
So we spent some time looking at y
These two campaigns might be using similar infrastructure
For example why is Kazakhstan spying on Lebanon
Why is Lebanon spying on Kazakhstan
We think it is more likely that this is a shared infrastructure which is being rented out
Put the states and Criminal
And we've kept track of this for the last
A couple of years
And we think that this is probably the
The new frontier in cheaper and more
Turn key Solutions
To government spying
Or lower end States
What you're saying is
I mean for 1
This is an example of assertive emerging country using these tips
Tools for their own
Chipa claims but also lebanon and kazakhstan where outsourcing it
The privateer
Yes
That is what we think
Any idea who that would be
No I can't tell you who's running that infrastructure that is a story for another report
But what I can tell you is
That we think this is
Kind of the New Frontier of
Cheaper and cheaper spying
And it solves the problem that you can see in the hacking team emails from a couple of years ago
One of the problems that the lower end state
Was
That they had difficulty using hacking team products
They didn't have enough of the staff that spoke English
Or that had the
The training to understand how to use the
The tools
This made it more difficult for them to do their spine so you can look through the Theo kind of
Trouble tickets that were being that were being sent out
And you can see I think it was
It wasn't cut
It was like
Azerbaijan to Turkmenistan
Bistan
Where they just didn't have anybody who could communicate with with hacking
Team in order to fix the problem with her and play
And what are the ways around this is just to create a portal
So you have a
You have a
Third party
Service
The that makes affordable that you can then log into that makes
Spying even easier and requires even less training and even less of
A language barrier so we think that that is why what is happening with sort of the
The lowest
End of
Estate buying
Yeah but you do is South Sudan if I remember correctly
That says you didn't bought those tools from hacking team and then
They couldn't even
Use it and I didn't even the hacking team
Employees were making fun of them
That sounds about right
I think that's what it was
Seems legit
Having said all this
Going forward what worries you
Cities in the future
Nothing that really worries me about apts in the future just
Just from this week
Is amnesty International's report about a campaign of fishing
That they've seen
Targets in North Africa and the Middle East
And one of the most interesting aspects
Of this phishing campaign
Was that they found a way to search
Convent
Two-factor Authentication
At least
For application the application method
Send SMS
2fa this would not work with
But like are you the key or
Up like any other
Similar key
And I find that extremely disturbing because most
Most 2fa solutions
Are are vulnerable to this attack
And while we
Racine similar attacks
From five eyes
From the extremely
What we consider to be high on doctors
I it is very disturbing to see
The same sort of attack
Filter down to lower at doctors
Because
It's it's only going to get cheaper and easier and more automated and this means that I need to see
Start recommending you the keys
Two more and more people and I need to start pushing more platforms
To support
Better forms of two-factor Authentication
It used to be there just getting
Platforms to support any kind of 2fa was considered to be a major
You need to support keys
If you don't if you don't support keys are you
You're not really keeping vulnerable populations safe
So basically you're saying is meme the attacks are getting
Wiley more sophisticated and easier and cheaper to do and more and more countries are engaging in this kind of
Kind of tool
Problem this week's episode was produced by Lorenzo franceschi DKI and recorded by Mitch Ragan
He was at inviting white thanks for listen to cyber we back next week
In the meantime please tell your friends about us and giving us a review on Apple podcast