Eagle one package being delivered
Siri wrong
I don't like you T Series
Nothing Personnel kid
But I must go all out
Just this once
Bobs or vegana whichever will it be set the fuk down is a reason I'm here to spill.
Realty
November 50,000 printers started suddenly printing a message urging recipients to subscribe to PewDiePie
Most popular star ever with 80 million subscribers to the printers were hacked
Because they were dangerously exposed internet the same hacker hacker giraffe
Again this time I can Smart TVs and Chromecast devices to autoplay a video promoting PewDiePie and
Urging them to fix their exposed devices things only got crazier from there a few days later have a draft
Remorseful statement from PewDiePie fans and heaters
Bi and surface and safety transmission by saying they were hanging up
How something that started in good fun become so toxic
We were talking about the board staff writer Samantha Cole prison following this drama from the beginning
This is cyber Samantha first time on the show
And you're going to be on the show right now because you did an article on somebody called
PewDiePie it's cute that you say it like you don't know who he is
His army which will find out it will not like this but
I only found out
About
PewDiePie because I got tweet a few times
Where someone said
Somebody looks
Like if
PewDiePie and I had a kid and they were ugly and I kept getting it and I was like who the f***
Is PewDiePie
And I checked it out and now I know who he is
I'm sorry for I think it's just because we're both white guys with beards is not exactly like a
I really like we look alike
Fair enough but I'm bi
But of course
Like everything on the show
How to let you down a bit of rabbit
What happened
Yeah so just to get people in my contacts
Who don't know
PewDiePie
He is a YouTube most popular
I got the flogger
Vlogger
I don't think so
I feel really dated this a fogger but yeah he's the most popular YouTuber
Right now he's got he just broke
80 million subscribers so
That makes him the most popular ever
Yeah he's he's a pretty big he was going
He was doing this like
War with another Channel called T Series which is
I'm an Indian channel that also has like a ton of subscribers and ever growing really quickly and it was like a big deal like with him and his fans Aiko
Are we going to get
Passover by T-Series
So that kind of
Kicked off like
But we're going to talk about today wishes
I'm all of his fans kind of crying the other and saying like we have to make sure I like
P by Cezanne top
Kind of craziness witch
Then led to people doing some pretty wacky s*** with
Hacking printers in Smart TVs and stuff
A very quick to London
That's so but he's some sort of like comedians / he also reviews games
The game blogger yeah he does like twitch stream
Yeah so he's
Kind of a personality I guess
So you can call
Any has just like this very committed following us
Ignore that 80 million right
Yeah yeah it's yeah just forget Himalayan salt
Yeah it's quite a bit and people get really
Really into
Getting
Part of this community
Buy followers
So in order to keep him on top
A figure emerges
Hacker giraffe who is the hacker
What a white hat hacker
Yeah call him a white hat hacker in some of the covers that we've done but just be kind
Define that term
That's when someone is doing hacking to expose
Vulnerability is that
Not necessarily to be malicious but to say like here's what's wrong with your devices are like yours with exposed to the internet
Here's how to fix them that kind of stuff for like it's usually someone's doing it for like
Bug Bounty or like some greater good is involved in this they're not
Hacking
Hurt anyone
That's kind of why we call hacker draft that in the article that we write but
It's a little different in his case because he's just kind of
Releasing these things out into the wild
He's taking over people's smart TVs
Printers hundreds of thousands of printers
We're printing PewDiePie like subscribe
Cheats
Paper
ASCII art of fist bumps and stuff like that
It's like pretty fun and funny but it's also really annoying annoying and not really
Are you the smartest
It's not
Quite legal
Devices in that way so
Yeah that's
The background of
What he's up to
So he was doing this
All in an effort
Keep PewDiePie on top so he was
Essentially
Going I'm sure he's doing like sauce cans of the internet
Things
Seeing what devices are out there that had vulnerabilities
And then
Putting them in any way could visually or otherwise
To just say so
Support
Twerking
I mean it went
Pretty viral you know lots of outlets including us picked it up when it happened
So yeah I think it worked
I don't know what the actual return on looks
Driver's license
But there's some people tweeting and saying like oh my God like my workplace printer just
Started Lake
Spamming us with
Chi Phi sheets of
If her and likes
People were like really concerned when they're like Chromecast we're playing a video that they didn't
Put on there
And tweeting about it or like
I'm reading about it so I think it worked that way pretty freaky
But I guess
If it's just on like
Swedish dude
Yelling about whatever I wouldn't be as
Freaked out
Yeah that's where it kind of I mean it is
It's supposed to be kind of
Fun and funny
Kumon oldschoolhack really in a lot of ways
Through this like
Very kind of
Old school hacker culture like almost phone freaking or something like that
You know it's not necessarily something really
Intense and dark
It's not dark over
Yeah exactly it's it's
Harmless
And that way
But
So what happened to hacker giraffe
So that's kind of where this
Took a turn for the worst so hacker draft was kind of
I mean he wasn't really well-known before this I don't know if you've done it all I had not heard of him before this
But
Blew up as far as popularity people were by the sudden like
Keyboard
Hammond Eastside of website and like
Kind of really leaned into this after the printer hack
And had like a little bit of notoriety as far as that
Then got it for it but
Then after the Chromecast
TAG watches in
December last month
He came out with this long
I guess there's like a statement
MyPay spinner something like about how
He was being threatened and harassed and people are coming after him and
I'm frightening his family and all the stuff
Gathered from this
What kind of vague all of his way statement was that
People who
Didn't like PewDiePie work coming after him and it was just
I mean the thing is like it's kind of hard to say why are people why are you harassing phone lines like the reason is because
This culture is very toxic
There's not really real reason a lot of the times
People
Do
Shity things to each other on the internet
It's a Troll Army versus
The Troll Army exactly I don't know if it was so much like
T-Series vs. PewDiePie if it was just like people getting into this black
Scaffold
But
I think the last straw for hacker draft was somebody in
Like a
Server somewhere he was chatting with someone
Said that the FBI was like investigating him
Yeah it was eating disorder like someone told me later that it was somewhere else but it started in this court, where he was
And
Basically saying that like the FBI is
Watching you like watch out like
You should really stop like you're being sloppy and he
Totally like
Freaked out like
I mean it sounds like you know he had like panic attack or something like had like something kind of breakdown where
This was like the last straw and posted this blog and then post a really long
Like 20 minutes
Monologue about howl like he
Was no longer going to be
Hacking or
I involved in these pranks are involved with
Stuff anymore just completely scared him off
Most of you are probably wondering what happened
Why suddenly deleted everything and why is going to leave right away
No
Twitter didn't shut down my account
Nobody hacked into the account
And no
Nobody
Got
Nobody came
And
I wasn't caught by authorities
Over the past month
I have gone under this area
And I have
Given the chance
Finally teach people
What hacking really is like
And what
What you can do with hacking and cyber-security I was given this platform and it felt like a miracle
But for the past month
My dams have been filled
With the threat
Attempted dachshund
And
A lot of people have just
Crazy
Crazy what I have to endure day by day
I'm no celebrity
I'm not conditioned
To wake up in the morning and read a couple of DMZ
Of people telling me to go kill myself
People telling me that they hope I end up dead
And people saying they'll call the cops
And report me to the police and law enforcement
That is not the kind of life that I was prepared to live
And the internet is not happy place
Today
While I was in my Discord server
I received I received a DM from someone
They claimed
Are they said
That the FBI was building a case against me
Are they telling the truth are they kidding are they trolling doesn't really matter
I lost my ship
I lost
Every single piece of my s*** that I could ever lose in my life
I was already on Pantone panic attack I was already on panic mode for an entire month
Going after Chromecast
Didn't exactly help
My free
I went ahead and I burned everything to the ground
The servers gone
Cloudflare account is gone everything is gone GitHub and get others gone
Patreon is gone
The PayPal that is linked to the picture on his gone
Everything is gone
Doggone song Burn to the ground
The only thing that's left is the
So basically what you're saying is
Packers rap wasn't about to do that said time for
PewDiePie
Disappeared
Yeah basically yeah I mean I don't know how how much disappeared he is but he is he's not hacking anymore he says
Greenfield Cemetery
Louis
Printers you was going after a Chromecast any
The Wall Street Journal
Someone dead we don't know if he did
To someone on behalf of
PewDiePie
Hack the walls
Yes
That's a whole other under the cia's worried about PewDiePie influence
Yeah I mean I
I don't know it's like it's it's a it's a B for the ages that's for sure I did Wall Street Journal staff
Goes back to T-Series thing also and
And maybe I can give his last year Thanksgiving
17 maybe that far back but
Wall Street Journal published an article that was critical of the pie and said that he had
Amplified some like anti-Semitic
Imagery is when I got and
Disney saw it and pulled there
Support a few pie
That's why the most Sinister thing we talked about the entirety
Yeah yeah I mean that's I'm not super wet read up on that side of this but
The gist of what happened with Wall Street Journal last year or year-and-a-half
Whatever it was
But yeah Disney kind of sever ties from PewDiePie and said we're not going to support the channel anymore end
Obviously you guys fan didn't take kindly to that and
If I like talk about it on streaming on his
Channel and stuff
And
Someone hacked Wall Street Journal to do the same kind of thing as a printer hack
So what happened
Well basically Wall Street Journal site hacked with
Play the pro PewDiePie Messi
So the hacking never stops does it first we have all the printer hacking
Turn the printer hack hacked
Happen again just
3 days ago
PewDiePie printers hackers
Strike again
What to do when sad
From teeth
Subscribe to PewDiePie printer hack
My timer printer just told me I need to subscribe
Speedify
Subscribe
Stir fry Burger
So basically this article somehow I appeared on the Wall Street journal's web
I have no idea how the
The big props to ever pull this off
I mean that's hilarious
So
Keep items to have a very
Seriously committed group of people backing him up online
Yeah and
Southlake possibly
A very committed group of people
Yeah yeah definitely yeah he's got a lot of influence especially it mean
This is very Community has
Yeah people are willing to do crazyshit for him which is
Interesting to me
As far as YouTube goes he's not bad
Get a lot worse stuff out there
Yeah he's a
He's gotten into some heat before with the anti-semitic stuff we've written before about how he's he's about women on his show
I'm a bit problematic
It was maybe last year where he was doing like one of those compilations of showing like women on Skype
Stream on Twitch
And there was like an AI like facial recognition
Eye-tracking thing that he was playing with
It was supposed to track where your eyes land
You can probably guess where I land if you're watching these
Okay
And yeah he use them drugs right language
And then we called it out and said this is not okay this is not really how you can
Women on the street is a such a double standard with like
I'm using their content
For your Channel
Then also harassing them
And he wrote that article
Yeah
Take a wild guess or actually I'm going to ask you out right how was that for you
Dozier go
Wow I just harassing emails
Yeah I have a hate mail folder now
Devoted
Mostly because of that
Yeah I mean that's just kind of
Just being online
So it's definitely not
The exception to that rule but
Yeah after we wrote that his
Cannabis fans
Took that very seriously which they should
And
Article on his phone all night
Sprinkler play
Agency like
What we burn everything which is totally in his right to do that
And yeah my DM's are
Full of people still mad about that article does he ever responded to what
What the backlash has been for you as a female journalist doing her job definitely not and I mean especially with
December 6th hourly I know a lot of other journalists
Especially
I'm deal with the same thing specifically from his
Sending messages harassment
The threads
Stuff like that so it's
A lot of the same stuff that hrakert Packer draft
Is getting
But
It's our job to do it and I think
Yeah it's
It's amazing to see kind of that
That culture
Take a turn on someone who's in that
Culture
So Haggard
Really big fan
But
That same toxicity turned around on him when he started doing
Publishing stuff and saying like
Like that so
Yeah I mean it's obviously is symptomatic of something
Vigor
What does essentially mean
In some ways you must have had some
So now.
You know
Camaraderie with
Package arrived from knowing what that person's going through cuz you've done that you've had the same thing happen to you and
I'm sure you didn't I've been in similar positions
Before
Definitely I wanted things he said was he just doesn't know how people deal with this he doesn't understand how anyone can like cope with us
This level of harassment everyday
And I think people are very critical of
The media being critical of you pie.
Fanbase
Look at yourself
This is this is what your fans are doing to people and he
Go on to the channel and says like
This is rad like
Keep
Keep doing the
The hacksmith
Someone hacked
Printers
Worldwide urging people
To subscribe
To PewDiePie
Thank you printers
Very
I'm talking about even printers are doing their part
Now I saw this on Twitter and I actually thought it was fake I didn't really take it seriously but
The message was basically printed and told people to
Number one unsubscribe from teeth
Number to subscribe to PewDiePie
Share awareness tell everyone you know
Anne Brophy
That's what I need
That's what I'm talking about
It's important to keep me on top is so funny
I love it
Please keep it up
Just don't do anything illegal okay
Cuz I will look bad on me
That's the only reason
I mean it will look bad impede
Whoever that
Does he ever has he never come out and say like
Stop harassing
Women not that I've
Scene
He might have stood up for people something inside like
Stop harassing women are stop pressing
People online in general
But I haven't really seen that it's usually kind of a
Jokey way
He likes that there's like this Army it's like that's
That's part of the bet
So yeah I mean he talked about Packer draft on one of his
Videos
And kind of acknowledge
Him and put his
Handle from Twitter everything on
His video
I'm wishing Amplified who he was
Keep doing it
I don't do anything illegal
Which
Heritage
I was like I don't want to get in legal trouble
You know like haha but like it's already
Been done has PewDiePie ever
Responded to your comment
You've reached out I'm assuming
And there's never been a
I mean I guess the great thing is you were harassed
And
Yet you
Still wrote another article about PewDiePie I mean it's part of the job it's all we got to do
Yeah I think it's important to
Bring the stuff to light when it happens
And not everyone is going to realizes what's going on in somebody's platforms unless you're in it
And yeah that's
The biggest part of our job as journalist has to be in it
I'm so
Yeah I think it's really important to
Disappointed
Out want to have
Happens to point out f***** up stuff when it happens because
It happens a lot
Because of the most
Popular YouTuber
Your
Help
He doesn't need you to write me
An article about why
I think he's amazing and I sucked like know what he doesn't need this
Isn't easy to hack for him
It's like more content for him
This week's episode was produced by Lorenzo franceschi
Picture I recorded by Mitch rackin and edited by John northcraft thanks for listening to this week's episode
Did you like the show give us a review on Apple podcast or tell your friends about us we back with more next