This episode of cyber is brought to you by ADT Home Security
Service motherboard editor-in-chief Jason Caballero ATT wants to help you design your next Smart Home
They'll help you install everything from video doorbell to indoor and outdoor cameras smart locks and lights
And it's all controlled from the 80s
The app or the sound of your voice
They've also got like eighteen thousand employees safeguarding these homes with connection to First Responders at all times
And you're going to get the latest Innovation and smart home security from ATT combined with 24/7 monitoring
Trusted name in Home Security
Yeah it sounds like the smart home gadgets and cameras that were designed with
Security in mind which is much different from hey I'm going to go by
Doorbell camera from eBay and put it
On my front door and help that no one hacks it
It also sounds like that really creepy hack that happened in mr. robot
Where Lego house is like taking over see that wouldn't happen if you have ADT Home Security
And if you get one of these home security systems their custom designed for you by the company
Visit att.com podcast learn more about how ATT can design and install
Secure Smart Home
For you
And your family
Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered barely a day goes by I'm washing
Without pungence worrying about what the Russians will do in 2020
The 2020 election
It is already under
Attack you thought I was going to say underway under attack
We assess
That foreign actors
View
The 2020 us elections
As an opportunity to advance their interest
Will the internet research agency Russian Troll Army strike again
Will the gru Russia's military agency
The candidates emails and pass them on to WikiLeaks once more
Is the United States
Prepared
The counter the attack
No one knows the answers but everyone
Is freaking out
On this week's cyber we talked to the Grog
Probably the closest thing to an infosec celebrity in the entire world
The drug recently spoke about how the internet has changed its information and information operations
Annie's here today
Tell us all about it
Youku
And this is cyber
What's with what's with the name Satya Sai saw
What's the status
Big rock now it's
What's that
Oh
So I basically I figured that people were freaking out that I was the Grog too much
Okay so I made it obvious
So it was more like a normal name
Right people
Freak out less even though
Xavier seed drug sounds
More crazy than Grog dinner it sounds like way more boarding school
Do you know what I mean
Bright like a boarding school
You act like you want for my internet Incognito straight till like
Chetan Hill Repertory
It's cool or whatever
It's the only thing that makes
Make any sense
Flight status
Yeah
The broadcast Maybe
Changing up
So your Fanboys and fans
. just
They're upset about it
I know but like
It was
Weird like basically
People will have a
Sorry for some reason they're they're pretty negative in their opinions of me
And so
I figured that
To some extent it was the fact that I didn't have like a normal name
Like I've already seen that there's like a change and some of the comments that people have liked that they're less
I bet they don't focus on the name as much
Anymore
Right I got used to be
The thing that might help people off
But it seems not to anymore
I mean we were just discussing this and
We were all of the opinion that you're kind of one of the most
You may be RV infosec
Celebrity
Which is
Kind of funny but everyone knows you
Yeah yeah I find that very very crazy like
If it makes no sense to me at all
I mean you clearly know you're talking about how do you why you think you became so popular among everyone
Everyone have you heard people be like I know
What is actually
Okay
Cool man
You know I really don't know I think
Part of it is that
Other people have been working for a living and I've been unemployed
So just been able to like
Stay engaged and I don't have people censoring the output that I have so I can just
No right and posts
@will whatever I feel like
And since
You know I'm not
A complete idiot
Can putting out stuff that I think is good and has good analysis and other people can see that
And so
Like volume stuff
And then
I'm also kind of an a******
Go to bed
So I don't really read the whole back when like
If someone pisses me off or like they do something stupid or like
Company makes mistakes I don't really soft pedal
That much
Probably don't have that like crowdstrike or you know Facebook
Handler being like you got to stay quiet
There's not someone who censoring me
Am I part but
Yeah. Have someone going like you need to corporate-speak this I can just go like what f****** idiot would do
Look at these morons 8230 web shells to get some data
Not like well you know
Play serious breach
Level of sophistication fairly on CNN
So you know getting to another
You big Topic in the end
Infosec right now I mean actually I would say
It's just a topic that
Keeps on giving to the last
3 years
You see the end of it
Russian hackers
Information
And you you rehearsing spoke
About how the internet blew up in
Warfare
So I was just wondering
How do you think
The internet
Quote on quote
Has changed
It's it's weird and some I so like
I personally don't believe
Stats
What was the troll Farm stuff had as big an impact
As the media likes to portray
The media likes to say that
The troll farms and everything at a huge impact because it's absolves them
There their coverage of the leaked emails
New leaked emails was what really
Through things
That was a major
Impact
Nike campaign that was the
Big saying
Mutual Farms
You know like they probably just speaking me
You're speaking to a small audience you know preaching to the choir to degree
But
All that aside
Fascinating brother troll Farms is if you if you want to explore how that
Total propaganda
Has changed from the historical
Propaganda that we had available I'm going to just look at specifically
Black propaganda which is what they were
Doing whatever impersonating
Members of the target audience to active like we're one of you and here's what we think
I never thought of it that way
Insightful perspective
Gay people
Star Lawn
Used to happen when when Black Hawk Down there was being dumb
Is that you would be
Trying to imagine yourself
Into the position
Of your target audience than you'll be some trying to
Create a message what you want to do
Empathize with a message that speaks to them as if you care about them
Message to direct them to do something that's not in there
Best interest
In your best interest
It's a fairly difficult thing to do
Also
It's it's
Complex you know you need to have someone who really really knows
That target audience
And that is a very hard thing to get these days
What internet is allowed
Is you don't actually need someone who really really knows the target audience anymore or you can simply
Test the reaction in real time
To how a particular messages doing
And the feedback loop is now very very Tite
It's literally in real time
You can tell which messages
Are rednecks in which messages are working
And you can
Course correct
As you go along and so
Allison historical you needed to serve genius-guy
We come up with these ideas you throw them out
4 hours called a comeback which
Return on weather
The message has landed or had an impact
And this could be
You know you your release a rumor
In France
I need wait for it to show up in Turkey
Did measure how long that took
And it's alright
If it's not from France to Cherokee it must have resonated quite well with the target audience and we can assume that this 8 weeks
Journey
Maybe it went through Germany as well
So
Not that seem to work well in this other one that didn't show up didn't work well
So you have this may be in about 2 months
Lead time to get any feedback
I'm 2 months and awards are the really long time
These days
You can have
Is he back within seconds
So
Youku
I guess that's that's what really changed every
Genius
By their own stuff tonight
Genius power
This thing is going to work really well
Just having something I could go like yours 10 ideas let's see what works
Or at least three did ready well the seven pay attention to okay drop those
Out of these three what are some
Variation
Let's see if we can get better engagement
And that means that you no longer need to have
A genius you don't need to have
A really really good
Person to do your black propaganda you just need someone who can do data analysis
And do regular marketing
So
These days you basically just need your your basic entry-level marketer and copy editor
And someone to look at your engagement metrics and come back and say okay
Not of this campaign is going really well this one's not going really well
Now what do you want to do and then you can maybe test if you wants her in like
All the stuff it's it's no longer necessary to have someone who's good at this you just need someone who's adequate marketing
And if you just I'm just
Testing constantly
The history of information Warfare at least
From a modern contact
You know like
Which is why
You're looking at rush has always been
Dee Snider
New York Rana
Created the protocols of Zion
Completely
I still going like 1905 1906
It essentially created this whole conspiracy around
A global Zionist movement against
Quote on quote would have been
Most of
European powers
It's still in circulation
Denso
I mean look at that but then
You look fast forward 226
I mean do you think Russia
Got better at it
Or do you think it was just sort of
Actually
Do you think Russia did a good job in
Attitude formation War
So I think so
Like to be completely fair to the Russians playing information war against the Americans DeSoto playing on easy
The Americans are very pretty gullible media is not particularly critical there
Much more chicken by getting things out quickly and then stove patching
Afterwards
Oops
It turns out we didn't mean that entire story that we ran
For 2 days
Here's a three-line correction on page 812
And so
Because
It's a it's a soft target
Russians
Who
I mean
If you look at the British stuff
That was
The Pinnacle no one has ever been that good again even
The British have lost the ability to do what they did then
The Russians never met
Pete they still haven't but they haven't dropped
Low
No it's Century of being a medium level information Warfare
Power and they've stayed at that level
The US on of like Nazis Peaks and valleys like when Wars come up when I suddenly need to do a perception management
Propaganda
Since it's our birthday
Forget everything
That's the last time I ever have to do that
And then the next one comes along with
Slowly build up capability in that as soon as it's over they drop it on Wii game
So
The US has never been particularly good
Britain has basically lost its role
No one else
Instead of really playing the game very well
So if
If you are like the one-eyed man in the land of the blind
Basically rush it like that
Not the absolute best but
But they're slightly better than everyone else
Saudi
Interesting things
Was Russia is that they they're not
Afraid
Of information Warfare and they also view information Warfare
As part of the
Job of the intelligence services
Stay David much more expensive you
On how
You've liked these Security Services should work with the state
These are things
Cirrhosis
Progressive Auto
Yeah
Very big
Idea fly
Switch
You know actually do exist
But it's kind of because of these guys really believe that Russia's being persecuted
And everyone who can should
Stand up and join them
And some of my good cybercriminals and
Show some of them
Are legitimate some of them are you helping in person
All of these things but they
They really have this expensive you which allows them to include civilians as part of their
National Security apparatus
Recipe book in the US the idea that like you know citizen hackers would help the NSA
Is
Like it's literally Unthinkable the idea that
If someone has the US hacked Iran
Stop & Shop
Do you like the NSA
Iranian stuff has a bunch of information
Then I say we go like all right we've turned it over to the FBI
You know you're going to get raided
Not only that I think
Indian essays
Also immediately
Did up until
Released recently
Pretty bad recruit
Just because the perception of the government has
Then what it was
Bicf find a very interesting
But likely the sheer hate that the citizens have
Or
Their security apparatus
Is very strange to me
I can say that because I've
Looking at police state I
Tonight I live in other countries where you are like the xcr bad things
You know I guess I've
I've seen stuff in countries with like
Security Services are actually secret police
Like if you go to the Middle East
Their job is to find anyone who disagrees
With the government and torture them
Not like
BFDIA yeah there
Turn of dicks and assholes but they're not literally out there
You're not grabbing people who go to demonstrations and torturing them and killing their family members
A line that they don't cross
Despite like all the bad things that they are they can be with the icy icing
Americans really have a pretty good one
Generally speaking
In terms of their relationship with their citizens
Ansible Liberty
Exactly like
They're pretty good
Like
Compared to what they could be there they're quite as you know people should be happy for that and
I think that there's actually opportunities to do the
Fix the system from within
I like you you couldn't say in like it a Middle East Country join the secret police and be like I'm going to
Mahabharat from within by climbing the ranks and then getting him to stop
We have two dissidence
But you could join the FBI and be like we need to change the way that we go after Packers
And you could actually do that that would be
A viable thing that you can do
So
I think that
The recruiting problem is actually hurting the community more than
It's hurting
And I like the NSA
Speaking of the intelligence community
Speaking
Do you think it is prepared
The 20/20
Election do you think you know cuz there's a store that came out
This week that Trump isn't listening in
Doesn't care
About the Earth are assessment that
Alexa
System is is
Is vulnerable
Do you think it is
Like I said I know that
20/20 is going to be a mess and
Realistically twenty20 has started already
But if you're going to do an infowar campaign you don't slip start
The week before
It's not like a paper that you can stay up all night and
Now this is a
Spend a lot of time
It's right thing and putting the time in in and stuff
The long process of building up an audience of gaining credibility
Of acquiring data that you're going to use up doing the analysis
Like all of that stuff I've already started
If you hurt if you're not already preparing
Or your attacks in 2020 now you are very very far behind
I think the lack of response to 2016
Is that is basically signal
That's anyone who wants to
Can get away with
Now this
There's no reason to hold back
So last time you know the Russians are sold out in the Forefront
China has always been involved
Doing
Investments of shady donations and things like that
Now
You know they them as well go all out and do whatever they want
Shouting simulator if you think I'm doing the money thing
But they've got cyber capabilities
They want to
Look up huge botnets on they've been doing a lot of infowar hacking League stuff
They found that their operations don't work very well but that's
Not in that neither do their assassination programs either
What's actually fascinating about that is that if you
If you look
HD coverage
You realize that all of that was an information War campaign
Run by turkey and it was
Absolutely brilliant
Like I think that that needs to be taught in schools
So
Just how brilliant
Did the information campaign was
It's coming out of Turkey
Yeah so like I would say that again
Yes obviously somebody did something absolutely horrible and it's great that they're getting
Done for it
Breaking news tonight in a very dark subject the murder of American base Saudi journalist Jamal khashoggi specifically what is it
De facto Saudi ruler Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman ordered the killing
According to reporting which first broken The Washington Post
The CIA has concluded the answer is
Yes
But unless turkey had run that information campaign the way that they did
This level of visibility never would have appeared and if you if you look at it the way that they did it
Was a one they had all the information already
CCTV
Recordings
I do absolutely everything if they dump
What was that at once it would have been one or two new cycles and I'm going to vanished
But they kept trickling yes slowly
And the way that they said it was okay again there are rumors of an audio feed
You know
Anonymous officials
Suggest
The next day it would be like
Anonymous officials from you not like the CIA confirm there is audio
Then the next it would be like
We have
Seen a summary of the audio transcript
Not in the next day if you like
Portions of the old year released so there's always something slightly you
And they really played the media very well because they know that like that is immediately if you if you just look at them
Chlamydia from a semiotic point of view
What makes something newsworthy is not like a
Platonic ideal
Superlative
Novelty and all the stuff so like
What they were doing was supposedly this like this is the best
So right now like the best thing we have is
This probably audio the next savior like actually we've got something better
We have confirmation that there is order
Actually got even better than that we have a
Portion of the audio
You won't believe what we have
Something way better than we have
So they they kept
Hitting
Buttons that they knew
The media has to respond to
And that allowed them to spend some of weeks going over this
I'm keeping it on the front page
And because of that
It was
Super effective and I think if
Anyone is going to do infowar correctly
They should look at how the turkey
People ran that how how turkey
Did that attack and they should copy that exact
I got was genius
And you wonder if that will happen in this
Upcoming election cycle me
One thing that
I was speaking with some of the motherboard crowd with
Recently
Was that
You know the Canadian election is
Coming up in
319 so
If you want to sort of
Test out some New York
Capabilities in
See how they might work in
Can a similar
Country
To the United States
Domino's Pizza
Perfect opportunity
Yeah I've been invited to be involved with a couple of Canadian election security things that I'm working
And all I'm with the government
Yeah yeah
Aware of this
Now that they need to
Weekly Insider we're asking
Is Kaiser prepared for a social media Cyber attack like the one the Tilted the 2016 US elections
From my point of view I think
A lot of people serve
Overestimate their value
Targets
So I don't know that
And I don't know if you want this Surly burn your capabilities
Beforehand
Because
You know one of the things that happened in 2016 is Russia burned a lot of infrastructure
And they made everything a much harder Target like they went so overboard
Public
What now
Everyone is aware of
If they haven't
Being so over-the-top
Then it's total being like Oh yeah right
Russia
Come on
Pull the other one
And I would have been able to do it again because no one would
Believe that that was a real
That was a real threat
Holyshit going to watch out
What are these Russians do that thing again now it's like bought bought bought
Hysteria
Yeah yeah absolutely
It won't be bots in that way this
This time around that's one thing that I
Nike precaution against
In discussing
The people here because
What I'm saying I wanted to pass
Houses by you
Is more
I believe there are at least
Some
Woman nation-states were starting to look at
Sort of extreme inside
Of the internet
And trying to incite
Mistress of the entire social
The entire Society
Of the United
Skate and create
Violent
Like-like accelerationism
The whole thing is like if you look at qanon it's literally
Some assholes posting gibberish on one message board
It is formed this entire social Community made up of people who
Don't have
A community in that just joined in with us
They believe so the
Like you you look at their slogan where we go one we go all that's a huge thing about Community that's
It's almost there what would Jesus do
What song am I singing
Concept
Is really strong for social Bond
End
You know the fact that these days the world
A trunk and that the distance between any two node
Is very very short because we roll online
So when they used to be very very long and we used to live in villages
You know the shortest path to your neighbor
So you tended to identify
You know the US was the village that you lived in
People that are new
V
Baker
And so on so you found things in common with them and that's what
Hold you together
These days
You don't need to go just on Geographic locality it doesn't need to be
The Village
You can say or I
You know we are interested in chess
And chess is a global community so you can
Identify as a chess player and part of his chest
Environment and that could be the part of your identity that provides you with community
Obviously infosec
Mike infosec is our community that's
I will identify and that gives us a sense of
No belonging
We're still struggling with a you know
The US versus them I'm trying to be like this isn't the stupid developers that are putting bugs intentionally into their coat
Stop
Thanks to this demonizing thing
But yeah I think
If you if you also look at
One of the things that people were very very worried about the domestic Warfare
Which
They talked about but which
The Russians didn't actually do like the Russians did straight up
Propaganda
I thought they were
What they were putting out
Waze
Literally you know like Rosie the Riveter we can do it
Is very much
Saying like you're one of us
Because you agree
With this other messaging
We're trying to get all those
I-10
That's the thing that you if you want to look at memetic Warfare look at
4chan
Look at Splash Pole look at
What is people who are doing
You know recruitment against
Young men
Old women
Getting involved in the alt right
You know and they're they're doing it by sound like
Here's something edgy and amusing and like
You can you cancel them
Say this but thank you don't like to why you like
Its a joke relax
Don't take it so seriously
That allows them to
Cat people
In an answer in a little bit you can get them
A little bit more in a little bit more eventually
You know that's your recruitment funnel
That's Tuff I think that's a real memetic Warfare that you want to look at you want to duplicate
How you're going to run
Are you going to do it the way that the
And Staffing
Very very impressed
How they've been able to go from
When was the last time that Nazis were a serious problem
10 years ago no one was going like we got to get the Nazis off Twitter
Like literally we have to get the Nazis off Twitter
You can blame that on memes I think
Make a solid argument
Down to memes I don't know if it's
True as like the only reason but
I think it's
Definitely a part of the reason
And um
And I think I think she was like you said there they're literate with
With our culture not our society because they're part of it
And
I think with some of the alt right is doing right now is there really tapping into
Some key things of young white men that are
Angry about
Creating
Memes
Specifically
Before that I might give you look at
Have you seen like the hashtag honk
Can honk lyrics
And mahogany
It's about to die from the Yang Yang and all that it's it's it's really
Really scary
Propaganda
But it's getting a lot of play
You know
That's
The unsettled
So I think
One of the advantages that the other ultralight has
Right now over
I won't say the alt left
Is that
The alt-right is actually having fun
If you join the left
Does like I'm going to be super liberal
What happens is you have to police your speech to make sure you don't say something offencive
You have to make sure that you're like falling all of these rules stay on the inside
Where is if you join the right you can say whatever you want and you can piss on people and you can you know being an a******
And if you are 17 year old guy
And you're looking for what you want to do and it's going to be like well I want to be in the group that lets me like
Being an a****** and is going to encourage that
A group that gets upset
Because you know I'd I fail to recognize someone's non-binary gender
So I mean
To say anything about the left being bad on that sounds like it's
All great however it's not a wonderful recruiting tool saying
Join us
And stop having fun
Versus
Join us and
Json any one you like and we're going to think that's awesome
You know I like you can come be one of the lads
Write a minute which which fits into sort of like
Very typical
Youngboy masculine b******* where it's like you want to come here and egg houses
S*** on people and be angry
How to do it and if you on the other side there's
There's respect
Wood stairs
Yeah and I mean like long-term obviously as a society we don't want everyone shiting on it
And I like that's not how you build a civilization
Now it comes from respecting people and having and I like
Let's not treat everyone like s*** all the time
Clearly that's not what you want but on the other hand we don't have
A way where we could have like
Take
All of that
Aggression and energy answers
Siphon it off somewhere
You want to go and die for Allah
You want to go and Jihad Somewhere In Another Country far away from here
And get shot
Like rats
What do you mean at 7 to study government
Is it for years
It still does.
He sort of backfired a bit when you guys who didn't get shot came back now with several years of war experience and
Daddy of like yours how you get rid of government
And then Shannon and then proceeded to launch an attack against your
Kimo's
Check it outside that then sent the world into a decade-long
War
Local domestic policy
But you know the good with the bad
So I need
I can hear your dog scratching
So I don't want to
Kikiwaka
Any longer
But
You know do you think
Bus is prepare to die
Do you think the US
Absolutely no
As I said
The reason the US is not prepared is that the
The major stuff that work was the hacking League
The preparation that needs to be done is not so
Regulation requiring paper ballot
You know which would be great
It's not better algorithms of Facebook
Keep fake news from
Things Brad which again would be great
It's newsrooms going
The Russian intelligence is giving us an exclusive access to
These emails
Let's really think about what we want to publish them rather than
Publishing them as fast as we possibly can
B
The Domaine stuff is going to be like the media still has the biggest
You know they don't necessarily have as wide an audience as the social media does
They have a very very powerful Gates
Keeper and validation rule
And
If they're not exercising that
Then they
Are becoming validator
Anything that comes out
And they become the de facto
Amplification arm
You know whichever intelligent service is
Taken advantage of
End
People
Are there doing some sort of introspection
Well I mean at least we're not Facebook
I think because of that
You're going to see the same problem
The game
Because
Yeah as I said
Is immediate the one like
Yes social media had you know all of these things that were shared and
Massive exposure
But most of the stuff that was shared was you know Washington Post articles on New York Times articles
The big problem that too is that I think this is what's scary is I'm not sure
You know we as media
I have learned
So to speak is that
You during this whole mother reporting there were a lot of
A lot of problems
There was a lot of
It was pretty clear that I think that there was a select group
People are really did want to get
This collusion narrative down and it didn't
Now you have this hole
Set a rejection of what we've been reporting on in
Even you look at the idea of a
Obstruction of justice in that report
It's so overwhelming that's why
What happened it
Clear that there's
Unprecedented amount of
Corruption that went on
In the presidential Administration but
The people
Of United States are not as interested in listening to that narrative
Cuz
There's been this sort of
Full Sail
Attack on trying to make sure the collusion narrative worked and it didn't
Yeah and that's actually one of the
If you look at that
Would be an excellent example of
A Long play information Warfare thing where you can live
Trick the opposition into over-reaching
And then as soon as they've ever reached
You can go back and be like look because it didn't go all the way to 11
Then clearly saying it went to 10 is also bulshit
Warehouses in an hour to 10 and they try to say it went all the way to 11
And that wasn't the case but it
Obviously
Because you can
Part of it
You can discredit all of it
And that's that's one of the reasons I don't like the term debunked
Because debunked
A very
Sweeping time
So I would see frequently in 2016 people are saying
You know
That article has been debunked
Can I be like a 2000 word article where one paragraph
How to have a correction with their like you know it wasn't Moldova it was you know
Montenegro
Like you know actually there's a small correction made because part of it was wrong but the rest of it is true you can't
Say
All of it is wrong just because part of it is wrong
That's actually one of those
Bias just like the fallacy bias
If an argument contains a fallacy
She believes that the entire argument is wrong itself
The fallacy
MSN
It's it's really shocking to see the level
Level political
Banks that should have been going back in
Force on Mass
Because
If you look at this even with with a k
Completely objective lens
Okay there that doesn't actually appear to be
Occlusion
To that ignore the
Haidian
Construction
Is going in the long term
Sweetly damage United States
Especially if you
You can't have a President Who
Who behaves that way and in his role
And you say that that's okay then you know what the hell is the point of having it at doj that separate or having a
Converse that
Provide oversight you may as well just to let the king exactly and let him see how that goes yeah and it's and then you think yourself
Whatever
Russia with
Planning in 20s
You can't really say whether
Directly after
Back to the ballot or not
It's really impossible to come and get
Stat like that
That said
Whatever they were planning to do they tried
Defected something
And I think
Never in your wildest dreams
Would they have seen the level of the
Destruction
That has
Existential destruction
To the United States
I mean I'm pretty sure that
2017 Russia was having buyer's remorse
You know they're like in our weekly investor all of this to get Trump and we were supposed to get the sanctions removed
That didn't happen
Now we're supposed to get something done against Ukraine that didn't happen
I like they they weren't getting anything
Positive
It wasn't a positive return for them
You know that the status quo
Bots
What a
Have now gotten several years down the line is that the u.s. is tearing itself apart
Internally and so is NATO
Yeah and it's and it's similar to brexit
Like if you if you look at it
Brexit
Russian
Pretty sure was involved
I'm pushing. It hasn't been as
Widely delved into
But not the
If you wanted to take the UK
Out of
The running as a global power
And just live TV
Paralyzed
For several years
An ineffective and unable to do it
Anyting
Brexit has been a godsend
Not that they literally
I don't do
Anyting
They they they even managed to take the you know 20-year peace process in Northern Ireland that
My phone was very very happy for
And throw it out the window
And you know you know how people getting killed by the IRA
Which
You know is these days that should be Unthinkable you know that's something from the 80s you know the early 90s
You know I shouldn't be
Coming back and get it is
Simile in the US you know
You could say yeah like Trump didn't lift sanctions
But the whole process of having Trump come in and how
Things are being sold
Corrupted internally
You're getting a huge win in taking the us out of the running as
A global power like I'm not able
To operate as effectively
And that's
Massive strain on natureware
The US is basically like
Be the shoulder that everyone lands on you
They were the main guy and everyone was sort of like
It's literally like it
It's the it's the wettest of Soviet Union dreams
Like it's crazy
Literally
How many years
Now since
The following there funny things are looking up
All of this is amazing when you look at you no rush is basically it's a
Economy-wise it's a developing Nation
With a rusting nuclear Arsenal and pretty much it's smaller than Canada
Yeah like they've got
They they have
No GDP their life expectancy is plummeting
You know
Yeah
Beijing population say they don't have
You know Innovative industries that are driving anything they're there a petrol can't be cold
Country
You know all of these
Things in your life
These guys are
In the real world they should be a nobody
They should be a Yemen
Okay well
Nice nice to have you onboard and everything you know
Enjoy the hors d'oeuvres and
Mingle
Not like it where they shouldn't be at the table
But sure they are and they've managed to become a Power broker
Power broker status
And they
Got this much larger than life
Emma just like you know this evil mastermind that's controlling
Everything I'm pulling strings and making all the stuff happen
And it's completely undeserved
Well Thaddeus thank you very much for being on Cyber
This week's episode was recorded by team light produced by Lorenzo franceschi bicchierai
Edited by Sophie cases and hosted by me please rates and
Share with your friends and I will see you next week by