Eagle one package being delivered
$300
Two Bounty Hunter moments later you got sent a Google Maps screenshot
The Bounty Hunter
It's on the current location of the phone that Joseph asked him to track no hacking required
A report from website motherboard revealed T-Mobile and other cell providers sold data to third parties resulting in
Information sharing location
Motherboard investigation into the Shady unauthorized sale of cell phone location tracking data shows the terrifying
Ways which are personal data is sold and mishandled first by telecom companies like chemo
Mobile Sprint and AT&T and then by series of increasingly obscure middlemen and data aggregator
The companies have names like Amigo and micro belt you probably never heard of them
Adeno
Where you are this week
We're taking a deep dive into that world first
Motherboard editor-in-chief Jason Kepler will talk to Joseph
Investigation
About how bounty hunters
Antique collectors
Skirt the law then I'll talk to Oregon Senator Ron Wyden about the Fallout from the story
In about his quest to keep your private data
Private Roku
Decipher
So Joseph earlier this month we published an investigation that you've been working on
For quite some time
In the peace
You bought location data from
From someone that we had
Consent to track
From a bounty hunter
CareSource
Where did that information
Can come from
Yeah so this wasn't a hacking tool
Spying device
It was actually base of the cane
Enough from the Telco itself
In this case T-Mobile
Is constantly communicating with other networks
So tmobile AT&T or Sprint
Can you send text messages and
And they sell it for a profit
Adams a trickle-down
Companies
Turtle Beaches
Right so did you I saw some people staying after we reported
That you bought this on the dark web I think one of the companies said that we did not find this on a dark web this is not
Dark web service as far as We Know
Yeah this is an adult website as in it's not say
Cool website like alphabay where you can buy drugs so bad
So whatever else that selling out
Word of Mouth Network bouncy house
Capability
Because so many different Industries in companies have access to the states
Roadside assistance
Car rental
Eva Peron e Property tenants who wants to background check
Oh maybe you renting the
Quotation
And clearly some of the most a reseller
Write a big one and I think we can get into this later is bounty hunters
And debt collectors
And so-called skip tracers which I guess is an industry
Term for essentially bounty hunting
And finding people
Who have skipped bail or have
You know someone some money
You know these are being
Sold
Two private parties
Buy data aggregators who get it from
Telecom
Companies Direct
And this is a pretty big business
This is not just
Being used
Services that are good for
The world
I need the two main question quote legitimate use cases of the states would be roadside assistance
So that's why you broken down somewhere
The insurance company is going to come through
I was trying to locate
Another
Family Financial
So you do a online transaction
And the company wants to check the
Is this person actually in
Same country weather claiming to be maybe the arcade dress matches and so notation notches on
So they should be on the way
YouTube
Chris hiestand
I'm use cases but haven't yet
Bounty hunters
Bail bondsman in
Street
Even though
Industry I was still able to hold it
Let's talk a little bit about how this
Actually went down
I remember when we were actually doing it we were sort of like
You know they can do the Ping at anytime and
We can get
Live real-time location of that phone
Basically insta
So
How did it work from your end as much as you're able to
Yasso
I have to contact my source and then he was buying
The
Location
I'm paying for his own soul
This is quite complicated
Trickle-down
Tell my source hey please go to that I get from a phone number
He passes on to his source
Do that and he's the one who actually has
Today's Rock
Into
The system
Location
Originally we tried this with a Verizon
Verizon will not speak to me they will speak to other Publications but for some reason they don't reply to my request to come in
It seems.
Do bounty hunters do not want to geo-locate
Verizon phones
Verizon will send a text message to the phone
On Wednesday located
You don't really want
Because it's going to be
Tipping off the target
And instead we provide to the T-Mobile
Am I sore
Saturday
The capability to work on tmobile AT&T or Sprint
Companies admitted they were selling the station this way
T-Mobile was the one that we successfully located
Case number
Mysore and incense
Just look like a Google Maps
Interface
Little talks on the map
Add a circle indicating Route 500
Of where this particular phone was
Interspecific parmesan Queens
So it's really easy to understand this
I'll choose
Language is it literally just
That's why the person is
And the reason that this works
Is it's not hacking your phone it's not using the GPS coordinates from your phone it's using the
Cell towers that your phone is
Connected to
Which is why that data is able
Come from
Providers
I just want to be
Be clear about that
This is a very similar thing that happened
Or was uncovered
Few months
To go by the New York Times and Senator Ron Wyden who
Ben is going to be talking to you later in this
Episode
I disappear
Securus
Company can you just explain what
Securus was
Yasso
Navigation with a bouncy house
Effects of a company called micro builds
I'm in the New York Times
Mastication
In that same positive supply chain
The company is selling it to the end client
They focus on one quotes Akira
Prosecutors who selling it to law enforcement
You did not require a warrant
So prison officials
They found documented cases using MS Access
To try cover official rules on even judges
Patelco stock
To that company
And then of course several months later we find that
Even doing it in arguably even worse used
Which is not even lower. A private business
So I do want to talk about why this is so concerning because
Like you mentioned
Yes there are legitimate uses
For this but
A lot of
The companies that are ultimately buying this
Data Arabic Shady
And so I wanted to
Track it from
The Telecom company down to you let's just make that very clear
How did
You get this information
Like T-Mobile what was the next company what was the next company and what to do companies
Do
It starts with
T-Mobile
Patelco
Adam goes down to
Suncoast location aggregator
Does two of these one chords
Locationsmart
These are the ones just directly underneath
Dave and salad
To an unknown number of company
Buy micro belt fits in
Is my Securus
Fitzsimmons well
Busy number
End user client
This was a bounty hunter company
The question quote legitimate
Trade
Because then they were just use that they said that they shouldn't still pains
But it's also where the black market
So
Sold out dates for access to a source of mine
It's a very long convoluted supply chain of dosa
V u get away from it
From the top
Patelco
Clearly had no idea just out of date was being used
Until we talk
Right and
The further away you get I think that this is
Does editorializing a little bit but the further away you get the less
Send less legitimate
Cats
These companies are a bit Shady we looked into some of them
Some of their just social media presence has and their YouTube presence is
And this is us amigo CEO chirag bakshi a few years ago talking about
Why you sounded to come
Zumigo has birthday unique solution
That leverages
The power of mobile data
Including location
Salsa industry
Challenges
You will see a solution for
Transaction validation
Device Authentication
Nky
Sbi know your customer
But I'd be remiss
If I didn't mention the power of a location
Data
For marketing
Are you nice
Patent pending technology
Makes up the only solution
That can locate a phone
Anywhere globally
No matter what no matter where
Using a GPS simulator or Wi-Fi router
Easy
Where the mobile phone thinks it is
But not when you do it from the net
So
Chirag In that clip says that
D'Amico
Uses location data for the purposes of fraud prevention and in Sumter
Cases marketing
We don't know which company zumigo ultimately sells to but we do know that micro built
Is one of them
And micro belt is
A credit reporting agency I guess
Is how they build themselves
But they are also
A company that sells
Databases
People to
Bail bondsman
And used car salesman and landlords
And do you remember the name of the
Specific
Tool that they they have
Yeah so this one was cool with a mobile device
Verify
And that's the
Location
Right so
Is you check out micro builds YouTube they advertise to
Bail bondsman and two so-called
Skip tracers
Switches
Bounty Hunter
Here is one of
Here's an ad that they put on their YouTube for one of their products
Address nonexistent
Because now there's a way to know everything
What did it take to expose
Master of Deceit and deception
A 25-cent surf report
Microbilt enhanced people search
It keeps you one step ahead of anyone
From accidental skip
Do professional debtors it's the world's most advanced database for collectors
Now it's updated with all new data sources
Including information that is reported directly to microvilli
And aggregated oleate micro belt
Michael Bilton ants people search
And then I just want to be clear
Last year they had
An audio webinar where they talk to
Two people in the quote-unquote asset management and Recovery industry
And this is where things get
Pretty shady and in my opinion
These are the debt collectors and the bounty hunters
And
One of these webinars which was sponsored by micro built
Was called
What you can and can't do when skip tracing
How do you start a know when you're being
When you're short of getting to the line of being deceptive or maybe when you
Cross the line
Wait wait
Treinar tracer
So many times when you're talkin to third parties you'll be asked a question like will
Is this about a bill is this about a debt
Do they owe you money
Who do you work
And you know if
Utila people I'm sorry but under Federal I can't give you that information or
I'm not going to give you that info
Obviously you're not going to get anything out of them at all
Two braid man spear linguistic technique there when someone says it is
Are you calling about a bill
We repeat
The question are you calling about a
Bill
And then we would say something like
That's a very
Strange or unusual nobody wants to be a stranger.
Strange question
Why would you ask me
That
And they will reply back
You know we don't have to answer
Question
What we're taught
The time we were in grade school that we do
They will answer that question will I know that he lost
Job and excetera
I know they moved I know they're having trouble I know somebody
And then you reply with with another mural District word
Really
End the conversation moves on
You never had to
To answer their question
Gave you actually gained information
Without giving them anything
So consequently
That is a good technique to train your collect
And then they're not going to be breaking while they're not going to be saying things that they
They shouldn't say
That's one way that we do
You have gone right to the line and we talked about stepping over the line
But you you haven't broken the law
But let me tell you have gone right to the very precipice and looked over his
But you haven't broken the law
Be careful and again you only very
Experience collect
Can use techniques like that only very stupid
French dip tray
What you just heard was Ron Brown he is the
The president of CSI Group which is an Oklahoma
City Base
Asset management and
Recovery company
He also runs a website called Manhunt seminars
And he's very into
Saying that he
Is company hunts The Most Dangerous Game
Game which is
Humans
It's kind of like it's is really wild
And on this webinar
She talks about the
The fair debt collection practices Act
Which is a law passed by the US government
That's basically set
The rules for what debt collectors and bounty hunters
Can ask
Friends of
The person that they're trying to
Define without
Breaking the law
He talks about going right up to this
This end of the line
Many talks about
Neuro linguistic techniques and manipulation
To get
Information that he can then use to f
Actually locate the person
And
From these webinars it was very clear that
People are using these
Tools
It's not just
You know the old fashioned social media
Searches and calling up
You know friends and relatives
They are buying data from these data brokers
They are using companies like microbuild
Which use companies like zumigo
Which get data from the telecom companies so
Yeah this all does trickle down in a pretty scary way
And in a way that
Yeah might be technically legal I think at one point he mentioned
You know a lot of bounty hunters or X
C using more third-party
Data brokers
Because
The fair debt collection practices Act
Doesn't actually cover
Weasel waterfall technique
When were skip tracing
And obviously with with agencies today and the dip
Rage
We'll start out
With what we've turned free site
And we can't find them on the social sites
Supreme sizing
Thing with drop-down
Odoo the page lights
The difference
Data Brokers that are gathering up the data Fortune
Can we pay for that
But
You don't we
Trackpad
The cost of it verse
Is the recovery
3 percentage
And it was like a waterfall you gather at Summit
Each weather
So there are these quote-unquote legitimate uses of this data at least technically legal uses at the moment
Which do include
You know the things like
Ron brownlees
Talking about
But once you even go a step further where
Just anyone can buy location tracking data
Why is this such a threat why is it so
So scary
Yeah spread sound from the original Source Pimentel toes
The risk of abuse
Just dramatically increases
Bounty hunters
Individuals may just spawn a girlfriend
I just was told me is what happened
Among these people
One citizen has access to that data
8 time it appears do whatever they want
Because Microtel
Amigo the Telco companies they only found out about this abuse
When we told them
Cadence
In the first
Staley found out about 2
Up to this point
We have no idea
I feel like I mean maybe it would be very
Suspicious
Someone with locating 10005 in a day or something like that
Is it based on a trust model
You've told them that again uses for the sheets but she doesn't worry all the way.
Tencent
Play leader Consent means nothing
The promise
Because we were just about anyway and find a phone
Right before we publish the story We reached out to zumigo and
Micro build
Who both sad
Yeah we don't tolerate a
Abuse in our system but
Could you leave a worm
Looking for it.
Closely
There's a difference between
Tolerating abuse
And actually enforcing against
I'm clearly they weren't really doing
I like how you look
The Bounty Hunter bail bondsman
Estates of the middleman say they said they were going to use it for the adjustment that person they have a lots of money
Coming in from
From the Bounty Hunter
They would kind of feel like pushing response
You can't just go on the Promises
If you're inclined
Like
Datetime to technical measures
Such as always pushing a text message to the phone
Maybe oversee
Some
Legal
Clearly something is working
And it seems that Elko is known as well because they smell
Brighten one one other thing I heard during the webinar
Webinars that I listen to
Are is the fact that
It's very important to these companies that
This I'll be invisible
That they don't want to alert the person that they're looking
For that they are looking
So you know they were talking about
You know if you are
Using Facebook
Define someone make sure you don't friend them
Do quote-unquote read only on Facebook
And
And it's interesting you mention the telcos cuz they're obviously very
Involved here they're very
It's ultimately they're making money off of this data and it
It's something that they
Should be ultimately responsible for because that is
Sort of who you're originally giving the data to
Or it's or unwittingly giving it to
But it's interesting they are actually involved in this in a
Different way to
And we don't necessarily I don't know this
Civics of how this works
But one of the people on the webinar his name is Ralph Lesinski who's
Is the senior Vice President of Finance
Diversity
Diversified
Consultants
Mention.
The telecom companies are actually one of his biggest
Clients in terms of
Finding
These people
Collect debts for
So for example
You're more than half of our
A business
Lies in the Telecom
Field
Sanya collecting
First cell phone
Yelp
Skip trace phone number
Become the light blood
Because we found a
Exclusivity contract
Data sources
And being that were so heavily
That is the NFL
Telekom Arena
Im4us
Each count upon placement
Because we're looking for
Cell phone number that that consumer in essentially
No longer has
Not only are they giving the data out
They rely on bouncy house
Counters to find
People who are not paying their bills to the toilet
Companies
Vicious cycle is there
Benefits
Ryan this is necessarily from the cell phone location data because
They actually have that
But companies like microbuild
Have other databases and you know
Build out webs of
Information about
Who else you are connected
2 and stuff like that
On this specific use case that rap was talking about
Was
I people who
Get a
Subsidy to buy their phone or lease their phone from a cell phone provider
And then they just like turn it off and do
Disappear off the map
Maybe they sell the song maybe it's just
Secures
And
Technically
We still on that phone so then they are
Looking to get a back or looking
Get their money
Ey
The telcos wood sign
275 students
But it is still
Uncomfortable Alliance that were there also providing at least some cases
The dates of these companies May then also going on sale
Right right
I want to end here by talking about what the Fallout from this has been
This is obviously a huge story when he
Published it
And you know you went on various
Talk shows Nightly News
I think
Tucker Carlson wanted Yuan I died you didn't do it
But you know
Besides this wasn't a big deal and it's gotten a lot of attention and
Some actual changes
Yeah so sounds from Leiden
Was quoted in the original story
Please contact him because he has two states
Sphinx
Legislation would be a good idea here
Hey this is one of the Avenues
The lawmakers are exploring
After the peace
Various
Other Sciences join the SEC
To investigate
We then had
Congressional committees
Cooling for an emergency meeting
Fccc
Elko json
San Andreas
ICC
Define to do that during the ongoing government shutdown
We'll see if when the government comes by if the government comes back
Fingers crossed
Rite Aid
Weather
FCC does investigate
Ambulette service in the growing pressure on them
Catoosa
Yes I'm in the school
Is the political realm the telcos AT&T
T-Mobile and Sprint
Access to microdose
They also said they're going to stop the sale of location dates
Two fatalities Odessa
In general
Include
The roadside assistance
Play this is such a liability
Even when the trying to go to The Limited use cases
Juniata hands and into other people's exercise control
So
I maybe you can send
A legislation perspective eventually it
Probably makes no sense
It companies Austin Tyler
Right and I will need to get super into it but
I can think of other ways of doing roadside
Assistant
Besides cell phone tower
I mean there apps for this where you connect
Play give them your GPS
Data in and stuff like that knowing
Yeah yeah if you will
I'm with an American Insurance company or American Roadside Assistance companies
Resume
Cuz it just seems so obvious
But you can download an app and then hey I can't type my location track please could you come find me
Sending the phone's GPS locations and
Crucially is doing it with concern
The user is pushing the button to say hey I would like to be located
The fundamental
The dates are the unused cases
Legislation
Savannah Technical measures
It's going to rest on
Consent
So I'm gonna throw it back now
To ban who is going to talk to Senator Ron Wyden about
Cell phone location tracking his privacy bill
He's been very anti-surveillance
You know one of the most outspoken
Senators on this
Tissue over the last
Decade or so so
I hear is Ben and Senator Ron Wyden
What was your reaction
The story that Joseph
Butt out last week
First of all I was just
Just thrilled
Joe Cocker
Ran that piece because
It really allowed us
The bus
Open again
This issue where we thought the wireless carriers were dragging their feet in for
People were following this let me just kind of give
Quick historical summary we essentially
Caught
Through this
Prison
Information sharing operation in 2018
Set the wireless
Carrier
Monopoly a real sweetheart you know arrangement
For making it possible
Offer what I call the Bottom Feeders of in of the internet that people wear
Data Brokers buying location information from all kinds of
Shady operation
When we caught it
All of the carrier sent me letters in 2018
Thing we're going to
Stop that
.
Renee understood
Point that
Williams
Good Folk
Set motherboard in Vice City
I'm making that is
No location tracking is a national security in a personal
Safety nightmare
So we catch him in 2018
They claim that they're going to stop
Not a whole lot of qualifiers
Say we're going to stop
And then we had the Joe Cocker
All the good Folks at. At motherboard basically get a bounty hunter
I'll give him a couple hundred bucks and we saw that
At least three of the four major carriers that basically dead
American Consumer a bunch of baloney
And father was a republic service
Melamine that's the thing right this is a year-old this is this is not new
So what
What are you prepared to do as a senator
To stop this issue
To make sure that this doesn't happen that you don't get another letter where the carriers tell you
Oh
It's never going to happen again it's going to end right now
Blah blah blah because it has
And I want to pick up the discussion right there because that's the point
That I've
Been making
Is
Hey they made me promises to me in writing
In 2018
Now they're making these promises again
And so a lot of folks
Send the media and the like
If it's all wrong what do you think of that
Permit me to be a little bit
Skeptical I'll believe it when I actually see it
And there is a real pattern
Now in the technology
Space
Where
Essentially
If companies get caught
Irresponsible conda
Too damn
Apologize
And three they pledge
It won't happen again
And then of course it does happen
Again you can almost
Set your clock by it I call it the
Wash rinse and repeat
Cycle
In the technology
Area
And so I want it understood one I'll believe it when I see it
And
You know people by John legere of already kind of change their story initially
She didn't say anything about how
In 2018 had to wait until March 29th
Todd Sweeney
Beyonce now
We've got it in
Bet it
In Black
Letter lot MF part of my privacy legislation
We have a provision that finally will have some real
Keith
So that when you catch him you don't just slap their wrist or wait for their next
Promise
We should be followed by some
Pretty much meaningless gesture
We have a top provision we called do not
Crack
So that
People were following this this debate would have an option
Tarulli
Send signal signal in the marketplace
They don't meet rack
Now you know I understand that
Senator Kamala Harris is also me know she's outraged by the story as well
Do you see this is sort of a bipartisan issue as well it is their Republican support
For something like this
Well I hope so I saw today
Dead several Republican house members had sent a letter
Expressing concern
And frankly the Congress are good
Are expressing concern
The question is are you going to go beyond
Expressing concern
And be for tough
Enforceable legislation
That has real teeth for example
One provision of my draft privacy melon for people are following is debating go online wheel of their comment
Is
We want to send a
Signal
About how
Serious
These
Privacy issues are as I say I think
Potentially
They are
National Security personal security nightmares in fact
Again when it comes to expressing concern the company's are pretty good
Sheryl Sandberg Jack Dorsey came to an open intelligence committee hearings we don't have very many of them so I always used
Dumbest kind of
Rare special opportunities
And I said Point Blank
I believe
Personal data
Personal privacy
Arnel Nationals
Security issues
I would like to ask you miss Sandberg representing Facebooking demister Dorsey
I would like to ask
You all feel point-blank do you believe personal privacy is a national
Security issue
Both of them said yes
You just keep pushing the rock up the hill
And as part of our legislation
I want to make clear
That if the
CEO
At one of the countries
Company
Company with more than a billion dollars in Revenue
Lies to the federal government lies to the American
People and the agency that would be responsible in our bill for handling this is Federal Trade Commission if they lie
Why did the federal government
They would no longer
Just get a slap on the wrist big face serious Financial penalties
And face the possibility of jail
And
That is essentially what's done with respect to the big financial institutions in sarbanes-oxley
What I'm here
To say the people were following of this
Good enough for the big banks that are the good enough for the big technology companies
I mean winter describing is how
Somebody's big telcos lied to you last year
Because as Joe Cox Show
It was quite the opposite.
Discontinued
Not only
Did Jo Cox
Show it
Joe Cocker
Basically by giving a few hundred bucks
To the Bounty Hunter
These companies could get away with it
Essentially with impunity
You know they basically we're showing their disdain
Legislators
Regulators in others
And my guess is
Head motherboard
Not blown you know the whistle
My guess is that we probably would have found out yet
Some point
Somehow
Did they were basic
Leave
Reaching their pledges
Did they made to me in 2018
The reason it was
Search public service
Is that Joe Cox
Exposed it for a few hundred bucks
Made it
Clear the TV wireless you know carriers were just walking all over the pledges
They made
Me and effect United States Senator and the Senate
And
Most valuable part of the whole thing
The session of Congress their bills being discussed
And
And that's why I was glad the motherboard
Lookeba Hawkins issues for years movie looking back on
Snowden Revelations and we saw big telcos then being abusive with same types of things
I guess now you don't forgive me for being a little bit skeptical is
At what point are these companies going to be properly investigated
Answer to brought their feet
To the fire
Because this continues
Let me take you back
Little bit
Confirm history
You remember what happened on January 18th 2012 big day in Tech
No
More than
Million Americans
Texted tweeted
Call
Visited
There
Senators
To say
Do not
Override Ron wyden's hold
Coming up in a few days
On a very flawed bill
That would do enormous damage to the internet
Bill for called tipping
SOPA
Basically with a
Rabble the architecture the internet was called the domain name system
And be built the pipa and sopa bill
And the fact
That we organize
So aggressive
Stop
And we basically organized weekly meeting
Now with activist groups
The grass
Roots power
Of online
Activist
And if that time
More than 40 United States senators were co-sponsoring
Is beer very flawed Bell
And I kept telling the leadership of the Senate
Hey folks
I want to be stripper is here
But the reality is there are millions of Americans
Spend more time online in a week
Then they spend thinking about the United States senator in a year
When they find out
These bills
I'm going to do so much damage
Turn the internet they're not going to be happy and you're going to hear from them
And
The leadership basically told run the good guy knows about this text darphin
Can usually people say well
Keith from Oregon in a which always accompanies this story
And I would just say
I don't want to be difficult here but you are going to be pretty surprised
And on January 18th Wednesday
I'm more than 10 million Americans wait in
And on Friday
January 20th Harry Reid not very happy
Call me up said you won
Your bum hole is going to Prevail or not going to
Very flawed built would do so much damage
I'm to the internet
And so
That is kind of a textbook case
The activism that is possum
I will tell people following this debate
I don't think we're there yet
On privacy
We are not at that kind of
Flashpoint
We're in fact you'll be a nationwide
Mobilization and websites will go dark and all the things that we did
In the battle to defeat Pippa in the instapot
But I think we're getting there I think people
Are seeing that these mega-corporations are vacuuming up everything in sight
All the
Personal information and
Where you go and what you do and what you buy
Emma like
I'm not going to tell
Anybody falling
Discussion that we're there
In terms of tobacco
And sofa
Kind of mobilization but I think we're getting there
We're getting close
Especially when you look at something like
Sonny's key government positions
And I'm talking about the advertised of the world
Who are
You know I think a lot of people would agree
Friendly with
Big Tac
Are friendly with tacos
I want to ask you
How do you praise
Advertise
Job so far and what do
Well you can take
Or five big issues with his net neutrality but
If we just completely setting it out and obviously as allegiances to people we worked with us then
PPL pay bill for Amanda and the light
But this last week where he
Used to have
A staff
Briefing
A German Poland been very helpful I found these kinds of
Very helpful figure on all these kinds of
Issues
Really takes
Cake because
He basically said they really have time couldn't work it in the guy who can do cat videos and talk
What kinds of other things.
The purpose is to keep people entertained Online Beta end time to breathe
Staff
Of the Commerce Committee the
Premier
Committee in the house that deals with privacy issues at the request of them
German pelona well-respected figure out that one really take Takes the Cake on a GoPro use nulo
Sitting out his responsibilities
Cerwin thank you so much for
For coming on the show we really appreciate
Thanks for having me let's do it again
This week's episode was produced by Jason Keppler
Jon northcraft
Norcraft also edit
This week's episode
Thanks so much to Senator Ron Wyden for joining us
And thank you for listening to this week's episode
If you like the show podcast
What time your friends about it
We back with more next week