Eagle one package being delivered last December Canadian
Arrested the CFO of Chinese Tech Giant Huawei semi from us charges the company made deals with The Rock
That coupled with the persistent Talk of the war for Global 5G Network Supremacy it in the U
U.s. versus China has made Huawei a media buzz word for nefarious Chinese spine the heart
I'll be allegations
Huawei skirted us sanctions on Iran doing business there through banks in the US
Via a subsidiary called Sky come but the link isn't entirely unwarranted in the last year
Years the US has charge Huawei with stealing trade secrets from T-Mobile Dan companies from using Huawei as networking
Equipment and Anna sale that's phones to military bases the Chinese company is a global leader in Telecom
Equipment and one of the world's biggest smartphone makers
What's the US Congress and others have won the Beijing could use while ways equipment to spy on the world and
For the record Chinese State hackers have stolen everything from F-35 fighter jet plans to Benjamin Moore paint recipe
Fortinite lifts the veil on a kind of Invisible War China unleashing its full spy power
An American power grids and the wealth of American Manufacturing
IG Networks
Proliferate
Where's the tech company being unfairly portrayed whatever your position Vice news reporter William Trenton
Just went to China on a Huawei media Junction apparently the company is trying to get Western reporters to see just
How amazing and friendly the company actually is what ensued was as Turtle describe to us on this episode
Super weird
I'm done now and this is cyber
Well thank you for coming obviously
They are having me
Always good to have more advice people on the show on the production
So you were just in China
I was
And what was that like
And what were you doing there
It was really
Weird
That's like the main way to describe it
It was super weird
So I went to China because
A few months ago
I saw someone
Tweet about
An open letter
That was posted in the Wall Street Journal and I think maybe the Washington Post
From a senior official at
Huawei
Is this Chinese
Medications company
And the open letter was like you know hey
Is a lot of controversy around us right now but
We want to give people the facts
And Us Media you guys deserve to get the facts
So send us an email
We're going to give you the facts
And I was like
I like facts
That's
Literally my job so I sent them an email not knowing what would happen
And in the reply was like okay great
Come to China
Okay cool that sounds
Crazy
Back and forth for a couple months
And then they were like
But it was extremely bagel
And then this
PR guy came to the office with like
Head of US Government relations for why that I came and met with us here
A few feet away from where we're recording this
And they still didn't come to China
4 week and we'll show you stuff
About Huawei about yeah
And like we're just going to we're going to take you
Behind the car
And give you the tree
And also you'll be joined by 10 other journalist
More likeable okay
Yeah this could be pretty interesting
The jungle itself will be really weird so be good story and they're going to let us film stuff
I mean in the lead-up to the trip we had no
Like I had to get a Visa approved to get a journalist Visa approved
Which is
Apparently extremely rare
And they weren't like they were not sending us
This letter we need
From
Their headquarters or whatever to take to the consulate until two days but
Yeah oh man so we can I go and I like to submit it and I can have
Weave
And then like the night before my flight I still didn't have my journals Visa
So I told why I like guys I just
These are like you waited until two days before they're like that will work on it
Send like 30 minutes later I get a call from the car
Your Visa is approved now
I like okay cool
So I go and pick it up the morning if my flight was weird to me this company that claims have no
Allegiant Sartor involvement
To the Chinese government is like
Is able to quickly pull strings to get visas approved
Yeah that was a weird
Pretense
And then you went
And was it what they had
Promise to you
Using look behind the curtain
So we started in
Oh God there's a whole other thing
Which I still don't understand why and I
I think my guess is like
For surveillance purposes
But they had a
Start in Hong Kong and then once we are in Hong Kong for they're actually going to start the trip in mainland China
In Shenzhen
Try to stay ran away Hong Kong one night
For no reason
So we went to Shenzhen and then we had a meeting
In the hotel lobby
The hotel
Was owned by Wawa
I was coming to Amber Plaza
It looks like a
Nice hotel but
Company
Until we sit in the lobby was there anybody in its yeah there are a lot of people in it and it had its own little like Village of life
Like food and restaurants and stuff
And I mean apparently it's like
Huawei employees from around the world in like vendors and people that they bring to China stay there
Is there any way we sit in the lobby with the
Actually when we told you they were tender and was coming from places
Forbes and wired
What we actually man
Is a guy from
Telecom trade magazine and an Instagram
Black slacks that you flew all the way to China to hang out with an Instagram influencer
Just what you always wanted this guy was really nice but he didn't even
It was like a extremely alert ear
Instagram influencer and he did
He did ads for Huawei like he is receive money for them
And then the telephone trade guy
Was doing branded content for a while
So we were the only actual journalist on the strip
I wish we found out only once we were in
China
Well
I mean I was you I'd watch the peace
And the one thing I kind of strikes me about it is that
You definitely have this sort of
Dislike
North Korean
Government junket
Propagandistic
Feel to it
Maybe not as obvious he's extreme
But
I mean did you feel like it was something like that you feel like you were being spied on during the
This junket
So actually I had a lot of
Surveillance anxiety
Going into this
I spoke with someone who
Was a reporter in China for like a decade
She was telling me like
Tell me the words to use for now
Forecast
So yes I had a lot of anxiety especially because
I know they were going to Fondren was fine whatever but I was also like
Going inside the company
That would
Like assist in building the technology and spying on journalists or like would have the capability or like Runza Networks
Feel like
I was going to be like Devil spider
Sorry I was having a lot of stuff and bring that a laptop with you
You know I brought a laptop but never opened up I brought a burner laptop
How can I just never, you swear on her phone
When I went to the consulate
New York City I didn't
Tight yeah and I assumed
4 compromise the whole time
This is actually not included in
The peace pipe
In the in the lead-up to me going
There was
Nike the DHS find out about this somehow
And I got like
I kind of like set up this call but they had already known about the trip somehow and we're like
Very keen
To know every detail of the Trap
What's and then at the end
Of the car were like yeah and you're just like assume that you will be on camera at all times especially in your
Oh yeah
I like
I guess it's like there's nothing I can do
Tell me I'm still trying to figure out if there's any like surveillance
Had experts listening to this out there we stayed in many hotels in many different cities
Every hotel room I had with always right next to the elevator
Why
Why there's no way that's a coincidence
I feel like it's real
What time I left the
The Huawei own hotel at like
For I am mostly jetlite and I want like
Smoking cigarette
I had a guy like Follow Me Down
Call me back
For one thing it could be
Is that
They put you on
On certain floors that they would put people they will see value
And they put you near the hotel near the elevator
But you wouldn't go down further
Into the into the actual floor
And see how there's nobody there
Oh
That's
Yeah I'm heading Elsa could have rooms like that that are surrounded next to it that are also there in order
Stern actually rooms there
Fake doors
That are
It's maybe it's somewhere where they actually literally like a backward right now staring at a
At a window where you can see
It could very well be that
Right yeah that's that's one way of doing it
I've heard a lot of weird stuff like I've had that happen to me in Russia
But one thing he's doing the Cold War was
I used to go in
And take a s***
In your hotel
Room
And just leave it there
Like mind as a like
We can do whatever the f*** we want to do
There's a lot of weird tricks but I'm sure you were a hundred percent being spot on
You might have been hot honey potted
I'm sure they probably tried to see what was going on there
Yeah
Yeah I mean I really
It was weird because I was like
Maybe
Like I'll get a glimpse of it
In some way
Like a tweet they took us to this the state-owned Telecom
China mobile
Crazy has like 900 million Subs
Lycoming Street times
Population of America
They were showing us like 5G antennas on the roof
And there was this guy with like a huge DSLR just like taking pictures
Like this guy's taking pictures of it I don't know who this man is
And then like a PR guy at the end of 00 he's just like from some communist
Oh okay
Picture
Yeah it is it is very weird
It is all happening
Surrounding service
You know if you're listening to if you listen to Trump he wasn't even other
Punnett on both sides of the aisle
Yeah you know this
5G
Who's going to win ultimate battle I've seen it described as
Ask parallel to the new clear
Race or parallel to the military-industrial complex that we're trying to get
Countries to buy our stuff and not Russia stuff
Now it's China but now it's wires
It's the internet
I mean
It's clear that like Huawei is also under attack
Yeah
Yeah I mean there's just like really fascinating dynamic
Going on
In that
5G supposedly this revolutionary technology the internet speeds
Dance master
But no one else
As it stands like in this current moment
Really has the capacity to build a fire
There's Huawei
China and then there's like Nokia and Ericsson and you're up
But they're like
12 to 18 months behind
So
You know unless you really want to be
Super late to this you kind of
It seems like you might have to go with Huawei
And there are
You know Western countries that are happy to do that like Germany
Is
Proceeding even though the US
Intelligence agencies are telling Germany that
We might share less intelligent
This extremely valuable
Your intelligence
If you use
Huawei products
Jeremy doesn't seem to have
A problem with that
There is a lot of like
Really smart people
Who questioned the accusations that the US
How does it make you feel when you hear the rhetoric from the US government when they imply that Huawei technology
When she has a back door in it
And not Chinese surveillance agencies could
Use that technology to spy on people around the world
Will Jada
Inkkas shoes
Beagle
Salem111 argument rights of scenes I think it's
I think this might be the most accurate and I'd love to see what you think of this
Is that
The concept of them using those networks and spying on us
It would likely won't be any easier
Or harder than it saw it already is for them
And
To protect intelligence to protect your Networks
Do you really need
Huawei American
Cables to do this
Like it'll probably doesn't matter either way
But the question is
Does global influence matter
More
Importantly then
The sort of intelligence
Right I mean that that's certainly part of the question because it's like
Will be here
Make a ton of money
I think
There's also concern
Lyca leverage points
When your Networks
Manufactured by the
Chinese company that
And clearly has some involvement with the government
Some capacity
It gives them leverage in
Negotiations like the trade deal
Where they can
I don't know what the last software update
Or patch
To your mobile network
Degrade them
Or if you want to get
Like really apocalyptic
Turn them off
Yeah like
Or like how Russia right now even
Even though I will threaten Eastern Europe
Every once in awhile that. Shut off the Natural Gas
Cops yeah yeah I mean just like any of the stuff that Russia has done to Ukraine over the
IMobile
So I mean
Is there a backdoor embedded into every
Chloe motherboard
Bike hard to say
Well will it give them leverage if
All the Americas Networks
Use
Their infrastructure in technology
Yeah I think that's a good breakdown
It's almost like they're using this this this siphoning of information back door
Argument
As the more compelling
Argument against them
Weather Network Phyllis rating
The best that you can sell to the
You think like that mean in Chinese
But how about the Chinese kid
Stop you from
Engagement internet if
Something goes awry
What is harder to sell
Like you kind of sound
Make a crack pipe
When you say that
I mean you know it's true it's probably the more plausible argument of the two but they're like
Like when you can just you know it helps your argument rhetorically when you don't have to really explain it because you'd be like
Listen is classified in like
The Chinese are doing Espionage and
All the stuff is top-secret and listen live
We're telling you the best stuff we can hear
There is a top secret document there is a lack of information
How to backup
That is just like
That's the biggest thing to keep saying that
But getting to that this has been going on for
Yeah this is just
This year
I mean the US government
Along with most five eyes countries
Have
Ben
Sort of excluding Huawei from bidding on things like emergency service Networks
4 years
And they been doing the same things in brief inverted I'm from Canada Red briefings
But the conservative government did had
Years ago saying
We cannot let Huawei
Get access to
Our Network's cuz they will spy on us
Security top secret
This is not a new thing it's almost
It's coming to a head I think really and I mean like
China mobile the state on
Telecom has been petitioning the FCC
To enter us markets
For like
8 years now and just got denied
Very recently
Time this has been something
Keep playing out for a long time and is now
Now being Amplified by
The fact that
5G Networks
And and I think
Relationship
But the really funny thing is is that
I think what we're describing is
Especially given your trip
China
So you couldn't really get any answers from Huawei on anything
And then oppositely
Here in the US
From our government
They're doing the exact same thing
Yeah they're saying beware of
Chinese spying and not really
Providing any real evidence to that
So it's it's kind of
Case of what's going on
I mean what were you saying that the US government has lost
Sister bounces well
Yeah
Right yeah I mean and and they're not willing to actually disclosed the surveillance that Huawei
Is or isn't doing honest
Which I'm not
Obviously
Agree they probably are but
They're not providing anything
To substantiate that in a very public debate that is actually going to call
Serebii
Very important going forward
We've been we've been like you theorizing here a lot but there was
One thing that I I found out
For sure
That fits like shotgun
That day it was set I mean we all know it to be true
But it was so shocking that they
Like fumble this so hard and let us film it was kind of incredible
So there's this amazing Dynamic on the trip
There are Chinese people people people who works for Huawei and lived in China and work in China
An American PRP
There is a time
There is an American who lives in Hong Kong when he lived in New York and one who lives in terms of
And set the chase fellow chase ya Chase
Cisco
And so one night
All the pr people go out to karaoke
And get really drunk
Until 4 a.m.
We did not go out
We were like
Resting is studying and
Camping guide
Breakfast we find out that they're all super hung up
Which is amazing
And so great Ambassador question
And so like no one really knows what's happening on that day or the Torah like eating breakfast and I'm just kind of like
What's going on and no one really knows what they're doing that morning
Eventually a Chinese proficiency
Let's go to our store in the mall it's like 20 minutes down the road so it'll be fine the American PR people are like
Great we've never been to one let's go
So we walking in a camera drawing
And it is an exact replica of an Apple Store
It is not inspired by or influence their similar to is literally an exact replica
The wood grain on the tables the badges that the employees were wearing
The way the products were aligned
And I was like oh my God I just interviewed a senior official the company yesterday who told me that the company does not steal intellectual property
They were standing in this like church of solid Electro property
And so I saw the video and you were very frustrated it is and it you are completely right
Apple Microsoft
I'm Samsung and I'm pretty sure everyone has very similar Concepts and terms of the stores
Fundamental differences in their stories
Do you
Stupid do you think we are like this is
You're being very rude to me by bringing me here at the straight-faced I'm not appreciating this
American Handler said that to you
This isn't this is there's an amazing memory the American Handler
Chase the pr guy is like
Smart outlet
Samsung store in Microsoft store
You know what really differentiates
Is here is the product
Products interesting
And I turned to my right and there's an exact airpods knockoff like the exact
Just a Huawei
And I like how that up and I was like all I just kind of just like put these in your ears and like they float on are they just like
Locked away after
He was not
My friend with me
Ask. We did not have any more casual conversation
Well
You know
He was wearing Shades inside the store actually in the in the in the peace
And I didn't clock that but now that I know that the backstory podcast
There was that PR guy we had a WeChat group of just like the pr people in US
Coordination
At like 3 in the morning he sent a message to that WeChat group. Just said
No it's just that help really just a help
At what what did happen they went to karaoke there's this with one last PR person there
Has helped others just layer of weirdness to me is just like
Dislike bumbling operation of trying to convince us
And it was just like
Falling apart at the seams
Every minute
McNeil no knew what was happening and why we are going your way
I mean
This is also like that that service theft
If a property is
Is also very common
But the Chinese government Source said that this isn't true it never happens and you bring out like the j-20 fighter for example
It looks exactly like the F-35 the same thing man
When
Chinese five-spice
Exactly
And there was another thing that I'm I'm actually not
Sure about that I don't want it I don't want to like strongly make this allegation
But they but they took us to an R&D facility
RR testing their smartphones
And there they showed us a video and it one point the video showed kind of this
Mechanical arm
Touching a screen a bunch of times to kind of test
You know that the screen works at
Price of the million times
And I wasn't sure if this is the exact same product but one of the things that Huawei is a LED strip
Stolen is
Then call Kathy
From T-Mobile which is a device that test
The screen a lot of times
And I was like is that
You are not authorized to ask this question I was like what are you talking about
But this is by the end of this year but I was like okay well we weren't even allowed to film in there so I was like okay mental no
Yeah they showed us the thing that they bite
I got to say your frustration really like in the peace
You can see this the steady decline your color as a glaze
Yeah you're the weird part about it is like
It went down it was down down down as miserable I want to come
Because we went we went to Shanghai and I didn't notice but we are staying at the Ritz-Carlton oh my God
It's like they brought it you know they brought us there and they would have paid for it like a
We had let them they would have paid for these very fancy
Hotel rooms
And they did pay for it for everyone else who's on the jump
Trademax influencer guy
They had all their food and lodging pay for any we paid for it because
Ethics and standards
I just like being there in this room that I could never hope to afford
On this trip that taught me literally nothing with 17 hilarious
So that I mean that's why there's a CNY
Laying in the bathtub
That's when you've lost your mind
Yeah
Yeah you're just like I've I'm done I'm sick of eating the same thing over and over again
I watch the unedited footage of that
Seeing them in the bathtub the other day and I was like
I forgot about this but I was literally cry
Cuz I was like what
This guy got in the steaks and no 7 house like this affection
How long are you there for
This week
Long enough
Totally I mean they could have
Really showed us all the
Important things in a couple days
I think they
I mean once once we're at the Ritz-Carlton became clear to me that like
They're really trying to win us over
I just say
The lavish
Gift Spark
Hey we didn't accept any
But I mean if
I could see like
You know there's there's iowaassessors talking to his Telecom trademark guy he's like
You know you going these companies junkets and they're always really nice I'm like oh well
You get to go on this like sweet trip to China for a week
And I pay for all of it
And if you write something nice I'm sure they'll invite you
Weird
This is true of
Yeah
But I was just so busy
I mean especially with something that
Powerful vent
Kathy Wright
Chloe X Factor just like
Some weird app for their like
So I can use her app and write amazing review
This is
4 most powerful countries in the world
Yeah
I mean NFL Stars has serious links to the Chinese government
Right yeah that was there was another part of it is
When I interviewed this
The senior official the third ranking official
In a completely different everyone refer
4 to as Madam Chan sheets
Like the Hat
Communications
I asked
With
My amazing and fearless producer Karen yuan the story
Had me Oscar
What her involved
In the Communist party was
I asked her
She said no you know I'm not the Communist party and then I said well
Do you know anyone
In the Communist party in your comfy shoes like where I live
I've never thought to ask
But the president and founder of the company
Ren Zhang FEI
Is
Known in openly associated with the obvious party like publicly known
Information
And his daughters in jail in Canada right now
Or in
Yeah he's awaiting trial and exhibition
That she I mean this is like
There's so many threads today
She is there for allegedly orchestrating a scheme
For Huawei to help a ran
Subvert us
So there's like 5G there's like
But it's all part of the same chess match it precisely
Who is really interesting is I'm sure you're on this list as well
But right around
5G when trumpets are tweeting about in summer
And then right after that the
When man was
With the rest
Live in Canada
Yeah
My like
Huawei press release
They just started
Inundating me extra for a day
Yeah they're really aggressive
And everytime I move flares up it would just
Like I get
Crazy bunch of emails do you notice that you're getting
Huawei targeted
I don't know that's because I like research the company all day long
But it's like I see on Twitter.
Like app
Get the Huawei facts
Yeah I mean they're being really aggressive in like bringing
Bringing us media to China is part of the
Take to get their message
We didn't get interview with
With ran
But other folks have which is like
Really rare
Normally do interviews
Yes
It's like they're playing their there I mean
Part of the strategy is like
Us Media push
And inviting us
Well I'm glad you came home with a cool story yeah you came on the podcast talk about it we can even get into the
The food you ate
But
How to be pretty amazing
Well thanks for coming thanks for having me appreciate it
This week's episode was recorded by William Flynn produced by Lorenzo franceschi because I posted by me and Ed
It Is by Sophie cases you will hear from us next week