Eagle one package being delivered hi I'm Jason Keppler editor-in-chief
Chief of motherboard and this is cyber are podcast about hacking this week Our Guest is nationalist
Charity reporter Ben McCoo will you might know as a normal host of the show Ben and vice can I report
Lamoureux recently spent months and better than a secret neo-nazis social network called the base
At least one person in the last two years there's been a lot of reporting about how the election of Donald
Trump as involved in the far-right and violent groups online and in real life but often were talking about hate
Memes are well-publicized rallies the base meanwhile isn't focused on memes has been
Explains their focus on meeting up and carrying out violent acts in the real world
So bad you spent the last few months tracking a
Cell
Neo-nazis online
Tell me what is the base
Okay sell the bass
I found out about the bass
Online because
I made a habit of
B&D bunnies
Neo-Nazi Milton Twitter circles
And
My reporting partner and I'm a clamorous
I've been breaking a lot of stories surrounding atomwaffen division we can get into it atomwaffen division is after
But
It's actually people who could be Neo-Nazi Terror
We've kept on them in much the same way that ice is active online on Twitter
Or what
Fort Lauderdale takedowns
We've been noticing
That these groups
Behave much in the same way
These are American Neo-Nazi groups and also there's there's only so many white people in the world so
Just imagine literally any country with
Native white people
Has a Neo-Nazi
Aspect to it honey Nazi
Aspect to it
Play selection liner Norway or England
France
Italy
And
One individual particular kept coming up
In almost every Circle we looked at in the guy's name is Norman spear
And I don't know if that's his real name we suspect it's an alias
Susan Sorensen that we did
It's possible it is his name
And he kept showing up in the circle
Bonafide atomwaffen division group members
New Ulm fall autumn
She obviously came up on a radar because of it
And I kept an eye on them and suddenly I think sometime and
I want to see August or July
Eastern advertising has been called the base
And what it was
With a place and use advertising as a sort of survivalist self defense network
But yet
All the propaganda that he was
Putting out there was extremely military
Resting stuff like when shit hits the fan
Apocalyptic thing in the United States refer to one
You know society disintegrates and it turns into a race war
There was stuff advocating
Essentially Guerrilla war in this is a guy who also put up videos on guerrilla warfare
Techniques
Manuel's
And you claim to be an ex
Iraq war Afghan war veteran
And I start to think what is this thing
Send me the Twitter account shows up
And then there's a WordPress
Account connected
Were you can go and you can apply to get inside of it
Piqued my interest
And what did you find plague what is
The base
So with the bases we found in this is after quite a few months
Of monitoring the Twitter accounts modern the people involved with the Twitter accounts
And then also we gained access
To their vetting process and then also there secret chat Noir
So it's kind of like a Discord but it was on
Riot chat in much the same way atomwaffen division had
A Discord that was infiltrated by propublica
We kind of got into the bases
Lightshot and washed it
And
Saw what was going on
Right so you served describe this as a
Paramilitary social network
Very small very insular but very dedicated to real-world action
What did you find on the base because there's a lot of
You know white supremacy Neo-Nazi forums chat rooms out there but this
Is it totally different so
One of the goals of Norman spear that he
Advocated for was he said the movement
Essentially
Fascist white power movement around the world
Is way too much about
Twitter trolls
And online chatter and not enough about
Wheelworld Meetup
And hang out
And let's be
Together
And go Fargo
Which is
White supremacy
Possibly a white power State you know
Score settling with race traitors with
Different
Ethnic groups
Black Americans Jewish Americans
So in order to achieve that
What the base was doing for my reporting
With funneling these
Extremist
Far-right
Twitter trolls
Also some of them were
Very much affiliated with real groups
Finally I'm into the base for this website
And then once they got vetted and then were in the actual secure chat
The planned
Regionally meetups where they would go and learn things like
Paramilitary skills
Bushcraft skills and I was one thing we started Wonder was you know how much of this is real
They're actually meeting up in person
Enter the photos of them meeting up in person
And
You know we found a library that they were sharing with
With stuff like
Chemical weapons production by weapons production
Weapons handling
Gunsmithing, saying we
Explosive bomb making
And then we started seeing some insane shatter
To be honest with you
Stuff that was going beyond the realm of LARPing
And into the space of
You know even some online militant groups
Won't
Say some of the s*** these guys were
We're saying
Stuff like you know I really want to get together with some people and plan something for real
I'm paraphrasing
Indirect action
Something with explosions
In reference to the Pittsburgh shooter they were also
Completely valorizing somebody who'd gone up and shot and killed mother
Individuals innocent people
China place of worship
For you know carrying out these attacks against
Juice because
Surprise
Neo-nazis
The real problem with
People Jewish faith
And the stuff they were saying about them running the country that are very much reminiscent of
Of the individual that wants that synagogue in
And shot the people up at least 11 people are dead and six more wounded after a man walk into a synagogue near downtown
Pittsburgh with an assault rifle and 3 handgun
An open fire
And that's what really for Mackinaw
We talk to ourselves
This is really going to something else we need to
Run the story soon
Because
We brought this to the Southern Poverty Law Center
We said luck we found this group is
This is what they've been discussing
What are your thoughts
Essentially they gave us
A massive statement on how this is
Exactly how
Right-wing extremism
Acts of Terror are organized
And learned
And take place
Norman spear didn't respond to requests for comment
Sent before Bend article published
But after I went online he sent the following
The base is illegal survivalist and self-defense Network for sharing information on those topics
And for organizing training sessions related to those topic
It is not engaged in paramilitary training
Nor is the base a militia or paramilitary organization
You have taken lines from chat logs
Specifically out of context
In order to fabricate a fictitious and deliberately Sensational story
That simply isn't true
Were they actually talking about
Specific
Planned attacks online or what
There's no incidents of violence
That have been
Attributed to the base
Yats right as of yet no
I'm not aware of it
The definitions to atomwaffen division
Are there lights members atomwaffen division within an atom was envisioned being a
Neo-Nazi
Doterra group in the United States that the FBI is very much all over
Yes
Do they have connections to killings and racially motivated violence yes
I did these people talk about direct actions
Against
People they didn't like
Ie
Races of people didn't like
Absolutely
Now
Have They Carried anything out yet we don't know and that's actually the thing that's really scary about the
And that's what a lot of extremist
Onlookers
And critics War
Will say is that this kind of place where you're given access to a lot of these tools
Or these manuals or these discussions were things are ratcheted up
And people can possibly meet regionally
Which we know that they were doing
That's where some of these Lone Wolf attacks
To carry out that's weird stuff
Happens and that's the really scary part is all it takes is a couple of these people
If I could so sequestered
And so funnel down into this group of
Real true believers
You have
Almost a maximization
Potential harm that can happen
When you're discussing these kind
Right and there's discussion on
Todd the bass about note in real life meetups
2 plans
Tax rate
No they would say let's meet up
Train
Let's train for the future
And learn skills together
Right I mean while they trade stuff like I remember one sweet the Norman spear did was
How to cover up a sniper killing
So if you kill someone with a sniper rifle
In public
How to make sure you wipe
Any evidence of your gun
Being involved in that attack
Meanwhile there's also tweets from the base
About counter-surveillance measures Against drones
Against being followed by federal authorities
And this is sort of the stuff that they were they were they were trading at
Which you know it doesn't take a
A rocket scientist for PhD
In extremism
To know that this is this is very much to do a terrorist
Right
So
Serve in the lead-up to the 2016 election and after that
There are a lot of articles about Trump's Troll Army and white supremacist memes and Anniston Madrid memes that
Going viral
And I did a lot of recording
At that time just
It's about you know how these memes are made and how their
Brad and that's her thing in there Amplified by the media and that's her thing
You spoke to experts in the space who said that the memes that are made by the base which there are means and there
You know much more vile than the certain things that you probably seen on Twitter liveries
Specific you mentioned sir
Pittsburgh shooter there's a lot of memes about that guy are they talk about
Wanting to make memes valorizing him
That's where you spoke to said that these means don't need to go viral in order for there to be like real-world impact
Can you talk a little bit about that absolutely Miss goes back to even sore the trading of information and manual
That's right
What it is is your in this Echo chamber but it's an extremist Echo chamber it's gathered people who really are True Believer
How many create things
In that space
When you know your audience
Better than anyone else
There's this opportunity to make someone
Extremely angry
Extremely
Galvanized to do something
So
You know I mean I did a lot of work on that as well on the alt right
And some of the amines are putting around
I'm happy
And
Memes
Or maybe the most powerful
Visual tool
From an actual neurological stand
It is coming the CIA is interested in something
NATO's in
Send something
MIT is interested in
And when you have a specific group dealing with one another knowing exactly what they want to read
When you read that you can be
Potential lone-wolf especially when you're also on the other hand provided with
Manuel's
Describing
How to create bombs
Right does not suggest that like the memes are the thing that push people over the edge we can't know that for sure
But
You are taking a group that is already shown that they are radicalized and
Your amplifying it because these people have been vetted and they're sort of
Talking to sort of the most extreme
Aspects of this ideology right absolutely any that's exactly how it works and it you know
I started getting to terrorism reporting originally
When I was inside of very similar chat groups
Very similar online activities
Advice is not high
You know it looks the exact same that's one thing that's really shocked me about this
Is that
It's all very reminiscent
And I spoke to a lot of booze
Does individual
And they behave and speak exactly like the end of
Different
With the means of using
Secret chat networks are using the apps in a beer using
To organize
And galvanized and radicalize your movements
I mean this is tried-and-true by someone with prolific jihadist groups
Yeah I know that some of your early reporting at motherboard was about survival Western
Freedom Fighters or whatever you want to call them who went and joined Isis
I'm curious you mention that the makeup is very similar just in terms of the chat networks and the types of things at their share
Do you think that they are learning from each other or is this something that is just so native to like online poll
Alltran organizing at this point that you know if you want to have liquor
Clandestine
Organization this is the type of way that you do it
I can absolutely learn
From one another
The bass learn from
This
You know 2013-2014 movement of Isis where they use Twitter they used
Your chat. FM Instagram Etc to organize
Galvanized
I think they learned that in fact
The base
It's called the base
I know that they're aware
Hbase means
Al-Qaeda in Arabic
So at the end
That's me
Is RBC a tongue and cheek
Way of looking at
Themselves as a terrorist group
That's not
Completely confirmed I don't know why they call themselves that
But clearly
There's some inference going on now
I mean absolute learn from them
I think it also attract quite honestly the same demographics of
Young man
Core online
AR
To some degree or another
TekSavvy
Cool
Are looking for a Cause
Are angry
And who else are pretty good at Twitter
Yeah yeah
So you mentioned the Southern Poverty Law Center which is this nonprofit group that tracks hate online in real life
I think most of the United States but possibly worldwide
I'm curious you know what did they have to say about this and also you know is the US government aware of this happening
Is anything being done to stop it is a proliferating
Well
Answer that last question first
Every single chat platform
And almond application
M.
That the base was on
Go to the mall
Including Gap
Which I thought was pretty shocked
It was almost as if
The base
Extreme
Forgot
Which of the wild one
Right and grab is this very like right wing
Offshoot of
Twitter
Yeah I called Neo-Nazi Twitter yeah and I know that they don't describe themselves that way but I don't really care cuz there any free
Free speech and I'm going to freely say
I think it's Neo-Nazi Twitter
So they're all off. I think it's blown up
That said you know I'm tracking where it's going next
And we'll see
RG3 is aware of the base
I can't say for sure
But I certainly gathered information
That would suggest
That the FBI's wear with the bases
And
Is aware of it
Connections to atomwaffen division
We mentioned earlier the Southern Poverty Law Center
Which is this group non-profit group that tracks hate in the US and I think worldwide
What do they think about this
How
Can we fight it I guess
So they actually told us that I'll never wear them as well
Norman spear who is the founder of the bass
And the bass
And they said
After that it's
It's tough to know exactly what they're doing
But they were there were incredible resorts in terms of
How they saw the base
And what the cultural reference
What the
Historical
References were that the base were used
And how dangerous that was
Very much playing with things like
That Timothy McVeigh was inspired with
Yeah this is the Oklahoma City bomber killed a hundred something people
He was also
Veteran of the Desert Storm operation
It 1990
And we also knew that there were
Members of the base
Who are saying I was a veteran
And I served
One of them even said
I know it's like to kill women and children
So the Southern Poverty Law Center was extremely aware of the base and was tracking it and that's who us
It is an organization that
Is all over
The far-right
Space
Editing criticism
But that said
The fact that they knew what it was or was it to us was okay
This is a real thing
You know it and I just said I kept seeing
Since
February 2018
I kept seeing Norman spear everywhere
With these accounts
Yeah I mean we talked a lot on motherboard just about the role that platforms
Display in sort of amplifying and
Helping people
Conjoined be sort of like
Far
Extremist movements
And
It's crazy that Twitter was allowing this to happen
For so long like you're tracking them for months and you mentioned the article that they didn't take down the bases Twitter account
Not until after you asked
In about it
So I mean do you think that Twitter has any handle or any idea
How its platform is being used
In this way or
Are they just ignoring it or are these people using Code words to like
Talk about this earthing or is it happening in the open
I'm pretty shocked that it stayed on Twitter for as long as it did
Because some of the stuff was pretty insane like I think there's no way that Twitter didn't know about it the only
Anything that I would suggest
Is that Twitter Captain open
Because the FBI one of them to keep it open
BFDI
Watch it
NC was involved with it
Because as a terrorism reporter
These accounts
Before I find them
And when I find them incredibly
It begins the mapping
Of course
Right
We talked about
Few times about the parallels but
Between the base and Isis and Al Qaeda
And how they sort of
Lake Mirror each other a little bit
And I know that in 2013-2014
Isis was doing a lot of like propaganda videos a lot of I mean
They posted beheadings on Twitter and
YouTube
I know that atomwaffen division has also produced
A lot of videos as well I mean are there is there video is there probably end up coming out of this or is it something that's
Still largely relegated
Chat rooms
No video
But definitely a lot of
Photo
Propaganda
Was coming out of the stuff that was actually done
By somebody who is
What's graphics
Who knows how to
Use
Photoshopping weight
Simplistic
If it were me
Making it
But absolutely never also
That was one of the moments that
We thought was
It was interesting
Process we are watching this chat room
They were pictures of
Meetups
And then
The next day
Come back out
And it's more of the propaganda photo
Stylized embossed dialyze embossed
Terrawave is what they call it
Style
Terrorwave
What's interesting looks like atomwaffen division
They have
I mean
List of people that are
I know how to use these pieces software
The graphic designer
Annie play
With
All the motifs in the imagery
That
Isis absolute play with their
They have it they have a book club
Where they read Siege
MCV beingness Neo-Nazi apocalyptic
Incredibly vile piece of writing
About a really
Vicious race war
Slash Guerrilla War
Carried out by neo-Nazi
By James Mason
That is
The Bible about a muffin today
Right
So you did a giant investigation
A very good piece of Journalism
Service monitoring
What the base is
What is the neck
Step for you as a reporter or like what happens now I mean living kicked off some of these platforms but they clearly still exist
It's definitely be continued
There's a lot of information out there that we're Gathering
I would also say that
Both Mac and I have eyes in the
Entire movement
And we were looking at it very closely
I think
You know
You mentioned the 2016 presidential election
This is something that's really obviously a lot of
People biking on a
The real thing
The
Election of Donald Trump
While some of these people openly that we observe do not like him
It is Galvanized
This entire movie
In a huge way
Because
Now you should have mainstreaming
Some of the same opinion
50s guys
Hold
Except they're not as
Extreme belill sanitized
A little sanitize right stuff at the border
You know the Caravan
This is something that the base people
Realize was kind of b*******
But also they hate image
They hate
From South America
America coming to
You know but the other thing I remember as well is that
These groups that have been galvanized by Trump
Also consider the government
The ultimate
Ultimate
As new Nazi movement and far-right movements evolve
When the evolve to the government is the enemy and it is a moment
Guess Chelsea
Said this
When that happens that's when violence
Take place when real things have
And you know for us
We guys are not on this
And we're in a container report
So we mentioned that there is all this literature about how to make guns how to make chemical weapons and bombs
But they also talked about
Reusing
Yunnan military grid
Bombs and weapons
From World War II
Yeah well and this show is it
Bass really wanted to be
You know we wanted to cry out all Neo-Nazi movements NY Power movements Milton
White power movement into one group where everybody could serve be outside of each other
And not have to
Engage with one another
Opinions
But also unites in the one
Fact let's make this
World
More white
And more militant
Let's go to war with Society
And part of that meant that they had followers
In Europe
There are a few members who were discussing
How
You could dig up
World War 2 munitions
In
Germany
Pacifically
And create ID
The mighty style bombs
And how they should pass
This information off to some of the people they know that are in the base where in Europe are the European Brothers in
What's the actual term
Carefree
Which is a wildly
Insane concept because people actually die every year
In
Germany the stuff is still active
If we drop so much on
And stop just goes off
It's such as goes off like in a farmer's field
You know so that was pretty wild when we read that because that's also something that you know
I know Taliban is done
Digging up old Soviet Munitions and strapping them two barrels putting nails and screws inside of them and then
Convoy us comprehensive boom
Mass
Destruction
So yeah I mean this is the kind of stuff I was engaging with
The last 3 months and also stuff like that you know we left a lot of things out that are
You know, typical of white power websites
You know stuff like they're discussed
Killing
Black
Babies and eating them
And that you know it was a joke but like you know
After wild the stuff gets to you you're reading and you're just like this is so hateful what is going on in the world
Sialic
Shout out to my ex
Search my girlfriend hurt a chonce kefir
Keeping me company in disguise
Yeah that that's so
It's very upsetting
Yes I mean
Done with a lot of reporters like this
Sweethome json is kind of
Reporting where
Your rings. Constantly
And you know I'm sure Joseph
Addison
Lorenzo you're just reading stuff it's just
Painful hateful
What's something that I've talked about a lot with academics
To say you know
You have to be careful that you don't
Like that you take your own mental health intake
Consideration when you're reporting on this sort of thing and that
A lot of people go into this thinking it's joke
And suddenly like they're radicalized and I'm not saying I haven't said reporters but I'm saying it's very bad for your like mint
Mental Health
To be reading this her stuff all the time
Be careful on
Oh yeah I mean I think it's like you go into it thinking
You're putting on this and it's
We all had this I mean a lot of people I know is that I work with
Lorenzo Joseph
Who
You going to be like wow I really wanted
Storage brake needs to watch when you're not sick
Isis whatever
And then you start doing it and it starts to break your heart
Because you get a really Grim view of just how hateful people are towards one another
And when I was in the belly of the beast in the base it was like that it was she knows it's a deeply upsetting thing to read
Constantly has people after taking their days
Talk about digging up
Munitions
The murder minorities with
If this is
Wow the insane
Yeah yeah
Well it's a really good piece I think it's important to sort of
Shine a light on some of the stuff so thank you for doing it and I know that you're not keep recording on themselves
I guess we'll see what happens next wish that this was the end of the story but probably
Probably 7 also had an excellent job posting this week of cyber
Thank you
You'll be back next week
This week's episode was produced by me Jason Caballero recorded by Mitch Radigan
It was edited by Dean white thanks for asking the cyber
Will be back next week in the meantime please tell your friends about us and consider giving us a review on Apple podcast