Eagle one package being delivered
Anton Aku National Security reporter with Vice and this is cyber
Podcast for motherboard about hacking welcome for very first episode
2 minutes report revealed that may be much easier to hack into a personal cell phone than you might think so cocky
Packers
The cyber
Cyberwar
The internet
The stuff gets complicated really fast
It's no wonder a lot of people don't know what it is or how it all works
We're going to break down a type of hacking
I could have fact
No this isn't Sony getting
Door somebody selling NSA hacking
It was talked about
Small-scale
This is about you
Phone
Imagine
She woke up
Did this phone
And I'mma leave you alone
Why would you do something like this
Is that how we make money these days
Okay I don't have any Bitcoin
Granny Ripple or something
I don't have any Bitcoins
Whatever man whatever
Whatever floats your boat you know
Yeah
I don't even know how I would do that or why why are you doing this
This Guy Sebastian
Eating something cold
San Jac
Another voice on the phone
Guy getting hacked
Sentences
Something really unexpected happened
So for this story I want to talk to motherboard Lorenzo franceschi beat your eye
Superstar cyber security
About his report Joseph Cox's story
Bright solar wenzhou
This phone call freak me out
Yeah it would freak me out there
More importantly I was confused by it
How exactly did his work
Sam jacket
Custom jacking or also calcium swapping or Port out scam old
Turns out the same
Can jacking essential is when a hacker decides
To steal your phone number
For whatever reason
And the way they do it is that they call your cell phone provider that's a T-Mobile AT&T Verizon whatever
And they pretend to be you
So they call them and say hey I'm Ben
I need my phone number cuz
Maybe they invent some story that they lost her
Phone or whatever
And they need the phone number reactivated
Once they do that
What happens on your side as a victim is that you lose
Your phone service
So your phone becomes
Phone calls you cannot receive text messages
That's the only warning you receive
Sometimes you got a text message saying you know
Hey this is T-Mobile
Thank you for calling us we transfer your phone number and
You know usually
The way victims of disguises me
Is that they freaked out because I like
Wait a second I did not call T-Mobile
You know what is going on I cannot make calls my phone is bad
What's going on
And in the background what's happening is that doctors are
Using your phone number to reset all your account
Or to try to hack into old account they can
So I'm usually what they do go for first is your email
Because your email gives them the keys to
Other services
Think of your Banks probably of your bank accounts are registered to your email
If you have a cryptocurrency account it's probably registered to your email
Even though airplane miles
I probably I just hit you imagine all these things that are
Link to your email they can get into
At that point
So basically that call
Wow incredibly unsettling
It's when the heck is going portal
Yeah any fact
If you got that call is on his good news because then you have some amount of control
Because if everything goes according to plan which most of the time in Portia it does
You're not going to know what's going on oh you're going to see that your phone lost service
And you know you might not even be alarmed because maybe you're on a high can you like all well
There's no service here
But in the meantime some
19 year old
Idiot is
And I'll steal your money
So what exactly can you do
To protect yourself again
So here's the bad news
There's very little you can do
Unfortunately
And that's because
The hackers are attacking
Phone companies that are attacking you about through your telephone provider your cell phone provider
There's a few things you can do to not silver
Bullets
Fun things you can do is at
The passcode to your cell phone account this is like separate from the password that you used to access like your online bills
It's only a password that will you will use when you call you know your T-Mobile your AT&T or whatever phone
Provider you use
And that's going to be busy plea used to verify that it's really you
So the idea there is that if I'm trying to hack you and I'm trying to pretend
I'm you calling the phone company
I have to provide this
Code
So that's a great idea that means you should work
Batting practice I heard the several stories of people that got hacked by a Sim tracking
And they
Had this cold and essentially the hackers just
Went around it
So that's one thing the other thing is
Behind Siri two-factor authentication should be great because
You know it's not just your password is also the second code
I actually didn't hear the real twist
That surprised me when I started working on the story
Two-factor authentication in this case could actually hurt you
So
Two-factor authentication all that stuff that everyone is cyber community tells you to sort of the
Bulletproof
Way of making sure you don't get hacked
That doesn't actually
Two-factor is good as long as you're not using your phone number
Because that's that's the key right
In the hackers get control of your phone number
Then they don't even need your password
Like it basically becomes one factor and they control it
Because the way to factor works most of the time is that once you give Alice a Google right
If you are using two-factor on Gmail
You give Google your phone number and that's not only used to deliver you know this
Codes that you use for logging in
It's also used for resetting your account
So let's say that one day you hit your head on the on the wall
And you forgot your password
You can go to Google and say hey I forgot my password and will Google will do is
And you a reset link on your phone
If I take control of your phone number
I don't even joke
So the way to make
Two-factor work in this case is to eliminate your phone number from all your accounts
Or use a phone number that's not
A real phone number as in
It's not a phone number provided by a company
Like a telephone call
So you can use a Google Voice number a Skype number
Any other kind of voice over IP number cuz those numbers
Are not going to be as easy to hijack
As
Craigslist
Sweet walk me through it
If a hacker is trying to do this or assume Jacker
How do they come across getting the numbers just finding out the number is and then
And I'm getting information from the dark web like how do you get it
Yeah I think the best way to understand how these attacks work is just peanut run through it
Let's pretend that I'm a criminal
And I'm trying to hack you for whatever reason maybe I know that you have a lot of Bitcoin
So I choose to Target you
The next trick is to find out
Your phone number
Which in some cases is may be hard in some cases may not be very hard and I like white pages you could use White Pages you could use
I don't know any kind of other online
Service like that
And once have your phone number I just need to figure out what provider you have which is also relatively easy I think you can just
Google the number and
A bunch of websites will tell you of the provider is
So that point
I'm calling your provider and I'm pretending to be you
And I'm saying hey I'm been I lost my phone I lost my SIM card whatever I use you know I can invent whatever story
He's got to be more credible essentially
At that point I tell you know the customer service
Specialist I tell them
I need you to transfer my number to the new SIM card they already bought
I have a new SIM card here
Avenue phone
I just need to
What they called portals
My old number to the new SIM card
This is what it depends on who you're talkin to what company you're talkin to
Etc button Siri they should
Try to verify that it's really you right cuz I'm not then I'm Lorenzo
So maybe they can ask me
Okay Ben what's your social security number
And then unfortunately that's in theory that should be secret but we know that it's not like Social Security numbers get so
Hold on the dark web
Correlative cheap
You know T-Mobile lost 50 million of them couple of years ago
Equifax lost $150 last year so it's like at this point we should probably consider Social Security numbers
In a semi-public with the last with questions like what was in a mirror
Pat Quinn x 40% X don't even ask for
After the number sometimes the question is what was your last home address which again in theory should be secret but
He's probably on some of his website like Wednesday
You can totally like
Type in somebody's name
Find addresses this is the real weakness in this whole pack like
Cell phone providers
Really not doing it
Anything to stop this
I mean that's a little unfair they are trying to stop this obviously
Baidu
The way they verify your identity
Through a phone call
Is totally
Not enough
And that's where the criminals come in because all they need to do is essentially call up T-Mobile say I'm banned give me the number give me mine
A number which is not my number it's your number
And T-Mobile gives it to them
Another point of game over
So what did the guy
In the phone call your source
What did he do with me no cyber
Security expert night imagine a lot of people aren't
How do you prevent this and what did he do
Yeah in this case this is a very interesting case because
Your mother was explained before like
The interaction usually is between the criminal and you know the AT&T or Verizon
Person
In this case and what's interesting about this case is that the hacker went directly to the victim normally the interactionism
Between the Acura Criminal
And the cell phone providers
In all customer support person
In Disguise that I can call the victim and essentially tried to it
Stardom
And the victim tried to talk him out of it
This is how you make money
Why don't we
Why don't we talk this through what I help you you see my udemy
Is there a way you can use some help
I mean with like figuring out how to like make a
Living like that f****** people over
And I feel like semi feel sympathy for
It won't you tell me what
Why are you in a situation where you need this money so badly
Cuz I did something
That I truly regret
About a year ago and
Longer than
3 months now so
Okay
That's okay people make mistakes I understand and
And there's no judgment there
Can you be a little more specific with the types of mistakes
So you've made and when what you got yourself into
Well let's just say I'm a beast
The wrong guy over
Basically I got
Jonah in the mud
Money right now
Do you know a somebody's been in the situation I had somebody I've had somebody Mentor me
And help me
And I would like to be able to give that back to you
Allison
You threatening me and making me send you Ripple
To be able to pay someone else back
It is that's going to be a very temporary fix
Who knows what's next your mindset is wrong
You're just trying to get to the next stop you're not thinking long-term
You're not thinking about the Sebastian who you want to be one day
I don't know who you want to be when I don't know anything about you to know if you have a family
I don't know if you have
Parents I don't know anything about you
But you're not thinking about the Sebastian
Who wants to create the life for himself
That is what you were going to want in your future you're not thinking about that you're just thinking about how do I get
$3,000 or 10. Whatever it is to get myself out of this situation and get by for the next 6 months am I right
Yeah I guess you might be right
So basically I did was
He
Engaged his Humanity the hackers Humanity something you don't see very often
Yeah and that's
That's something that
Working this case I think because
Some of the people doing this kind of attacks are usually very young Atlas
You know the people that we've been able to
Identify
Or talking about like
Teenagers or early 20s
You know I know this is going to sound it'll be like a stereotype but these guys are really like like a guy in a hoodie is parents basement
Yeah it's really likes you know the people that have been identified and arrested so far in DeSoto
TurboTax are all I think the oldest one that we know of was like
26 or 27 I think there was a guy that was 30 something
I bet he was like one nineteen-year-old 121 year old
You know I sent you a people that I've
Either just left high school and or just got into
College Seducer all essential young men
Not having
Fully developed
Frontal cortex
Exactly I mean it's as much as it sounds like a stereotype of the hacker it weighs like that it's like young people there
Gamers sometimes they're very upset
Obsessive gamers
These guys are young a male
Board that you know like if maybe
If it's a more than all that much to do because they're out of school
So yeah I threw you like young people with not that much to do and some
Death some skills obviously because
They know how to trick people into doing what they want so their social engineers
So this particular case though
This guy doesn't seem so much bored
Adidas
Desperate
I think what happened here is that the criminal went through the usual protocol quote-unquote
Or this kind of attack
And basically ran into a wall
You realize that
The only chance
To get what he wanted was to actually
Story. Of the victim
I think it was kind of a Hail Mary he just went for it and hope that it could like
Compass direction to
Give him what he wants
And
She end up getting
Can you give me an apology
I wish you wouldn't have ended
Well
I respect that
Yeah man
Alpine you know
I think
Do you have potential in just got to go down the right path
Just go to sleep and touch base tomorrow
All right
Iron Man
Sebastian
I appreciate you being there
Stand up human being
Yeah
Thank you
Good night buddy
Good night
Good morning
In a way these are really targeted tax obviously because they
The hackers are going for specific people
What types
Two people are retarded
It could be anyone
But only in the sense that to become a Target or a victim you need to be someone that has something that they want
2018 Tigers actually wants
Bitcoin
Why did Yuan
It depends
Sometimes obviously Bitcoin is very
Appealing because it's
Essentially money
Special unit last year when I was like worth so much
Other times
They attack you because they know they have a bank account so they want to get money
All the times is more unusual or something that you would have thought about
Sometimes they target you because you have an interesting
Social media handle
And by interesting susmita handle I mean
Something that is short or something that spells out
A common name like rainbow or sex
Sore
Video games or something like that
The reason why that's interesting is that
There's a
Son of a gray Market online
What is social media handles
So if I steal your you know at
Facts or at Rainbow
Handle for Rainbow Six
Yeah Rainbow Six I can then sell it for
Practically a lot of money on this
Weird
Community called OG users
And when I say a lot of money I'm not talking about you know millions of dollars but
It can be like 100 200 Maybe
1000 mm
I don't know how much of this is the legend that I'm watching this is truth cuz it's really hard to verify but
I heard those stories of like handles being sold for 20000 $30,000
And you know again let's remember these are like
A really young people that
A lot of money for
College student
So is it rare for you to see these types of hackers being
Sympathetic
Yes
Because
You know when you think about criminal sometimes
You think about the stereotype you know it's like
Ruthless
And
You know you're thinking about the bad guy that will do whatever it takes
What they want
An office in this case you know
We're still talking about criminals but you don't dare you mind and again their young
So I think some of them just don't realize what they're doing anyway
Like I'm not trying to justify them both
I think that
The interesting thing here is that
Some of them don't think that what they're doing is
Crime
And they don't think there's a victim
Essentially they just want something and they think they're somehow entitled to it
And
They don't think there's anything wrong
It's kind of like a game like your style of them are gamers
Yeah exactly I think they do see it as a game and that's probably why they also do it in groups
Troodon group
Because
In a typical attack is good to have a few people cuz
I heard stories of like
Attacks where someone was let's A1 gang member
Was trying to find personal information about the victim
Another one was
Calling the you know his cell phone provider
And another one maybe was handling the actual lyca SIM card
So
Not only that's like a division of a skilled and labor I guess
But it's also probably like a little bit of a game you don't deserve maybe guys the
Play fortnite together and then when they got bored
Playing fortnite
They play this other game which is stealing
PlayStation handles or Instagram accounts
From
Total
Strangers
But in this case it's not some guy
In the city
Is Basehor maybe it is
But even sell this
This particular person
Come across as
Really emotionally
Actually human
Yeah that we have another interesting case like that to this was like
Two people
Two criminals they call the Beast couple in Utah
And they
Well they hacked her because she had the
Instagram account at Rainbow
That's what they wanted because they thought it was
What's something
And they called her because they took
Need to cover her phone number
But they couldn't get into her
Twitter I think
They were able to get into her email
I'm getting to her Instagram but they wanted their her Twitter account which was also at Rainbow
Because the other thing is that if you have a rainbow on both Twitter and Instagram then it's worth more than just a dream
Rainbow on Instagram
So they called her and essentially they were like hey
Give us your Twitter account is like
No
And it wasn't it wasn't another interesting case because they played I don't think they did on purpose
Are they played good cop bad cop so the first guy that called
Was like
You know f*** you give us your Twitter without ruining your life
You know what God has for you
And then Wendy's Capital started to like
Waste our time and
They also tried to talk them out of it it didn't really work but they were sort of like you know slowing them down
Then the second guy came onto the phone call
And was like hey I'm sorry about my friend
He's a little bit of a
Yeah he's a little bit angry whatever
We're just trying to be nice
We just want your Twitter
And so it is just like I remember interviewing the Kapil and they were like
Obviously we were very stressful so we were like what the hell is going on you know where these people that are like
Now they sound super young and they are just
They just sound weird
How much money are they getting out of a
Some people are probably making very little money because only go for is like this
You know Twitter handle them into Commandos
Add event after esl which is
You never know how you're going to get money or not
But the the real
Criminals in my cereal I mean the diprose
So to speak
Are the ones who go after Bitcoin investors and cryptocurrency investors and those people
Are making millions
Like little Millions
We reported on the case of a guy called Joel Ortiz
Who is a 19 year old guy from Boston
And he was part of the gang you don't deserve see my Jack and gang
And he's accused of stealing
Something like
Five or six million dollars
Throughout
A few months
And the way they did it was essentially targeting people that they knew had a lot of money
It's still unclear exactly how they chose targets
One of the few
Mysteries
Of these cases
But what they did was Target people that were like
Publicly talking about their Investments on cryptocurrency
Think about people that are on Twitter talking about how I made like
X amount of money investing in this
Token artist
Cryptocurrency whatever
And then they went after their phone numbers and ones that their phone numbers they could get into their like
Coinbase or Gemini
Or whatever cryptocurrency website you can think of
And
Take all their money
Savannah to me with one of those handles that they're after
Maybe medical likely to get hacked
But I'm hearing more that this hack is possible
On anyone
Yeah I mean
Obviously if you're like
Someone who brags on Twitter about their
Cryptocurrency Investments
You should be careful
If you're someone who has
You know one of these cool
And those you should be careful but it really could happen to anyone and it's not just you know I don't want to scare anyone and you shouldn't be scared
Because there are ways to
Minimize the risks of these attacks
But it could be anyone because
In the last year when I was reporting on the stories I really heard from
Average people
Images
Regular people like me and you and
The only reason they got targeted because
Some twenty-year-old thought that they had someone in their bank or someone in their cryptocurrency account
And they were easy to Target because there
Information was in line
And so they went after them
So that the takeaway here is that it could happen to you there are ways to minimize the risk
Event happening to you or you losing money
You know I've got an emails and voicemails from
50 year old mom son year old guys
It could really be anyone because all you need to become a Target is essentially be someone
Cool maybe it's the money or maybe it's something that can be worth some money
And as
Digital presence
And you know that all of us
And unfortunately a lot of our
Personal information is out there so once I decide to hack you for whatever reason
I can probably do it this way
Cyber the production of Vice media and motherboard feel like me to show subscribe on Apple podcasts or where
Wherever you listen and please leave us a review
Helps other people find the show
This episode was produced in edited by Sophie cases