Eagle one package being delivered since its Inception
Jigsaw formerly known as Google ideas with the technology incubator with bold ambitions
The world's biggest existential problems with Technology Solutions like helping journalists from being DDOS attack
Going after Isis Senate campaign
More than 300,000 people were drawn to the anti Isis YouTube channel Surfers actually clicked on jigsaws
Suggested at three or four times more than a typical ad campaign about 9% of the
Those who were presented with information
Made it out to be
Is Corporate overlords do-gooder Enterprise meanwhile Google employees
Having none too happy with their employer thousands of employees walk out of Google offices in more than 40
Locations around the world today protesting a company's handling of sexual misconduct claims this week
Motherboard Asus Lorenzo Francesca on the potty talk about his months in the making investigation
Do jigsaws workplace culture turns out behind closed doors jigsaw isn't what it's cracked up to be
I'm done Matthew and this is cyber sword
Too deep in the infosec game
You obviously get lots of tips and lots of
Source is coming Tuesday
Information
How did you first
Uncover
The story
About
Good question
I've been following jigsaw for a while now
Probably like 5 or 6
Axios
Because I always thought they were a very interesting company
And for those of you who haven't heard about jigsaw jigsaw is basically
Fing Fang / incubator within Google that does
Both studies and great products
Essentially make the internet better
So we talkin about you know anti-censorship products
Vpns for
Communities at risk
Like you know Iranians or Chinese people
Stop light
No research on
Resume online
Disinformation and stuff like that
So basically this is a company that has a very
Amazing public profile remember I've heard about jigsaw it's always been
Advertising itself
Like internet savior
Yeah pretty much that that is a very good way to put it
And ever since they were born which is
Almost 10 years ago
At the time they were call Google ideas but
Same group
Agave Brandon to jigsaw in mm
15 / 16
When
Google reorganizes alphabet
Yeah they've always been in the news
Are there
Very out there project
Standby out there meaning like idealistic and
You know overly positive project
Argues that
Trying to find solutions to
Did us attacks against journalists
Is bad
That is a great
Initiative
And have done some good work
But we heard a few months ago was that behind the scenes
In a within the team within the company
People are actually very unhappy
And a lot of people had left over the years for various reasons and obviously we can't say that I've run is left
Because they hated working there
But there's definitely a large chunk of people who left
Because of that reason
And moreover
Google enlarge
I've known that
The team has been mismanaged
And the employees that I complain
4 years
And
As you can tell Google
Hasn't done anything about it
What you're saying is
You found at this company that's revered publicly
Behind closed doors actually is this
Friday mismanaged
Its employees have
Serious issues
The workplace
And let's also
It brings back to cyber this is a company that works with internet
They work with International governments
They partnered with ngos that though they do a lot of interesting infosec work like
Citizen lab for example
Access now
Basically an NGO that you can think of that doesn't need digital rice or Internet activism work
They partnered with our list
Baidu
So this is something you heard rumors of
For a little while and I mean to this pick up steam right around the time of what's a some of the emerging me to reporting that it happened
There may be some me-too stories we don't know about
We don't have any evidence of it
The story is more about toxic workplace culture
Core management
People that feel like their projects are going nowhere
Also there's there was definitely a widespread feeling
And the priorities of the management was
Got press
And good PR other than actually do good work
Does the case that we discussed in the story
What are jigsaw partnered with citizen lab
Or something called this
Security planner
And these are actually really good initiative aware
They created a website that
Teaches people out of
Think about
Security and how to think about protecting themselves online
But there was a little bit of a controversy at the end of the project
Before it was launched
Because apparently
Jake Owen who is the CEO of Jigsaw and
I'm depressed
Habitat
In the beginning
Was angry about
The fact that
Jigsaws logo was not
Going to be on the homepage
Security Planet Project
And sort of got mad about it and
At some point you know
Fought with
Shenzhen Library
Jigsaw
About this
And our sources were like you know it felt like
Baseball
Better busy
Call and say it's not worth helping people if we don't get credit
And this is just an example like all my sources pretty much Echo this
Everyone feels very itchy about coins focus on VR
There is a wallet out of his office at the
Jigsaw office
With
Framed newspaper and magazine clips about colors that Dick's has gone
Which you know I'm sure happens in all the places
I don't have any evidence that happened to Google
It's kind of weird
And most importantly the employees there
Like me or my opinion doesn't matter
People want their think it's really weird
That they just talk
Prescott
And who is Jared
My name is a jerk
The alphabet
And I also work as a chief adviser to the alphabet executive chairman
But more than that I'm just really in
Interested in the Nexus
Geopolitics and Technology something which I think has been
Convergence
For more than a decade and we're finally in this moment where everybody's waking up
Jake Owen start his career
Condoleezza Rice
State Department
Bush the Bush Administration
And then stayed
When Hillary Clinton took over after Obama won his first
And then present and when he left
The state department
He was tapped
To have this new
Cool thing that Google which was Google ID
The idea behind Google ideas
Was
Essential E2
Look at some of the biggest security challenges in the world through the lens of Technology
And at the time
Before our team
Add improper engineering resources before we became a technology organization I'm we were really just trying to
Understanding
And think about
How technology played a role in them and
How that affected
A company's decision making
I don't know exactly how this came to be but
Basically it sounds like Eric Smith
Who are the time was Google CEO
I told Jared hey do you want to
Have a team within Google
Tommy Sotomayor think tank with in Google to
You know Tagalog is amazing
And is
Really tough challenge
And when I started it was a very small team
When it started they didn't even have an engineer
It was really bootstrapped by colon and a couple of other people that are still there
Any quickly grew although it's never been bigger than
50 or 40 people
You know for Google did you still
A small team has male initiative
Adam Gardens so much good price over the years
You know if you Google jigsaw
Google News
You'll find what kind of Dino magazine articles
News articles talking about their initiatives
Sota case of Justice company being a lot of bark
But not really much bite
Yeah there's a lot of that to like even people within
Jigsaw of both current and former employees
Have told that they feel that they have and we achieved much
Antonio's
And to be fair these are problems that really hard
Solve don't seem
Yeah actually that's one what
That's exactly what our sources said like these are impossible problem to solve
Seoul measuring progress in measuring
Assassin's really hard
So we shouldn't be too tough on them for this because they deserve credit for at least trying right Facebook doesn't have a t
Teen like this apple doesn't have a thing like this
Microsoft doesn't have a thing like this
At the very least they're making a
Even if
Probably
Pretty small
The words of the most shocking
Revelations that
You found from the
Story when you were due
We can't discuss overly specific
Stories because our sources were very careful
They're all worried about getting either soothe or
Hino retaliated against
Yeah that that says a lot already
Most
Stories were like managers taking credit for their employees work inappropriate comments
Dismissive comments
Toward the population than people that are actually in theory the targets of their work
So
You know minorities or
People in the Middle East
People in Africa stuff like that
A general like
Lack of awareness
I guess for
Stop that they actually should be
More careful with so it's it's a lot about a lot of these like little things that overall make you think that
The people who lead the team
Dan Marino
And Company brass
Not particularly good
Two women either
Yes there's something we talked about in the story that
It's basically at some point over the last 3 years
So many women like felt mistreated and undervalued
Bad sometimes they would like
Cry
In the bathrooms
And at some point he would have been so often that the women at jigsaw put in the bathroom store
I can't
I can recover after crying so like you know much driving cream mascara and other like stop to us
Essentially hive
The fact that you cry during work
Go back to
If that's without anyone notice
I got to say when it when I think about jigsaw and I think about
CEO
I think to myself
You know this is a company that has all of the telltale signs
Having connection
The Beltway
Intelligent
Community do you think that it is that an allegation has been thrown around
It's definitely something that a lot of people in the NGO world have wondered about
And by that I mean people that I've worked either with Jigsaw alongside jigsaw or Ave
Have some awareness of jigs
The fact that corn comes from another state department and the one of his
Right hand people
Stop Carpenter also the former diplomat
In the US government
As always raise red flag
In some circles
And also there is
Nissan Chester
You know it would be unfair to just point it there
Resume
Because they are just because you're in the state department doesn't make you
CIA
But there have been weird cases and we are the occurrences that are worth like pointing out so far
Temple in early 2018 Vista Higher the Crown Prince of Jordan
Or a job or an internship
Didn't call an internship but they hide them for 3 months
How to work a jig sizes
Security analyst
And
I'm not a Jordanian politics axberg but officer Jordan is
An important Ally
As the United States in the Middle East
It has a pretty good surveillance
System within its Country and
It's intelligence apparatus is very tied to the American intelligence
I need to be held by some local jordanians whoever had to you know that they're like
Applications Center in Suffolk
And this was not known until we revealed it was very careful not to reveal this
Like when they emailed the whole staff
Saying please welcome the Crown Prince
Is going to start in a few weeks by the block
Someone asked who's is confidential and
One of the managers was like yeah please what would rather
Keep This Confidential for now
And there was even like
I mean this email is super we are like the
The most like
He prefers to be called
Hussein
And please don't mind the security detail outside of the Google off
So it's like
We ask Pixar like why did you hire this person
What was he doing what were these qualifications and
The response was
We cannot talk about employee matters
Just thought of a typical
Is a typical response when you don't want to talk about something
Yeah I mean as I said like they did not announce it a time there's no like
Almost no public trail of it and yet and yet they're still announcing an internal
I don't know exactly why they decided to announce
Internally I think employees would have noticed
First of all
Also I think they wanted to preempt
Internal controversy
Because the employees who are there the time who told me about the
Crown Prince of Jordan working there
Lorelei confused what I why is this
This guy working here
What's going on did you get a
Job interview
Did you get the same job interview I got because
You know it says people may know go ahead with Google is not easy
Have to go through a lot of
Interviews the process
Such as long as complicated
Yeah it's pretty well known to be a very tough place
I got a job
And I think at some point
The I don't know if it wasn't all in the meeting or in some internal communication but
One of the jigsaw managers was like yeah you did an interview we interview him
In his helicopter on some trip
Vancouver Lake
Well
Does that mean
Luna Park
A few months ago
So Google and jigsaw reach out to a bunch of ngos at some point last year
And they were like we have a lot of
Security keys made by Google that we would like to send two countries where there's a lot of
Government
Hawking dissident
So the idea was to send in security keys
To make the decisions on Human Rights Act
And once the ngos responded saying this sounds good
Google Center in India
That was like
You can receive this you can send them to the account trees
Around the world but
Do not send them to North Korea Iran Syria
Cuba and other countries and obviously the reason for that is
The sanctions regime in the US
D&J was also like you cannot talk about the existence of the security keys with people there
And it's like not a lawyer and sanctions
You know are very tough I understand that
This contributes to
A lot of the NGO world
Being very skeptical of jigsaws actual intent
Tencent
Are you still at the actress
The question like this is like
She saw it coming from a company like Google
Which is hacked by China
And still continue to pursue the Chinese market
For a long time right when when that happened which was
The so-called
Aurora
HAC
They
Did the Chinese market they resurrected there
Chinese search engine to Hong Kong and stuff like that
And for years over visit like we'll never go back
As we know thanks to the intercept
Amazing Scoops last year
They are
Back in time
Yeah they're reading about it seriously now
And it's probably going to happen although it does seem that internal
Protoss
An internal
The internal strife that these regulations cause
At least slow them down
It kind of bags we question right you know you see how
Many of the Google employees that
Striking
Google was violating its
When will it stop
Your tenants
To not be evil
But
It's interesting to meet you CDs
This infrastructure that has become Google and then
Has become these come
Jigsaw
They're so big they're so powerful
So much money
They almost seem like State actors now
And when they on the one hand say like we're trying to really be amazing on the internet and solve units
Major problems
Like this information online terrorism
Etc etc
And then on the one hand there
You know
Trying to get into the Chinese market or just at the US are backing the Saudi regime where which sanctioned
Decapitation in murder of a journalist
And then on the other hand
Preaching from the
Pedestal
I mean Apes
It's sort of this obvious
Hypocrisy
Goes on in our society nowadays
It also shows just how powerful these companies are now that we actually can help
Hold on to this
I mean jigsaw itself is basically
Start of a diplomatic arm of
Google maybe that's not how they would describe themselves
I know if anyone has ever described in that way but
Looking good newsmaker there like they're you know what is so bad guys
Lilia former diplomat
And they
Hino de deus
Stop at
Define of the plumber
You know they go to Davos
And like meeting with other countries and governments and they know that
A royal family member on their team
It's just
And that's the only one we know
Yeah and so it's like really like
The question is what are you doing what is the actual goal and you know I don't want to go all conspiracy
Fury
Here I don't think that
You know I don't think they passed the data to the
The CIA the song X
Say
It's like why you are saying that
Now these companies like Microsoft
Something Google are so big that they busy
Can do
Are posted on foreign policy goals
It's insane
That's a good way to put it
You know what
So one final question I want for you
The story doesn't scream Lorenzo
Francesca Bakery
In like the perfect way
Because you know usually you were putting on hacks and breach
But this is you know this is workplace culture this is
Looking at Google and saying you know that I was going either one says they are
Why is this was it so important to use nympho
Reported to report
Motherboard Vice
Braids large we've been focusing a lot on
Labor issues labor and tok
And
To me this was
Another example of
Google search
Reality behind-the-scenes ripe for years companies that Google and Facebook
Have looked
It looks like
Havens of amazing
Working condition
Casino that free food
Have a bite
Colorful by
Bikes that you can use to walk around
Move around the campus
And in reality it's
Their offices
Much like many other
That's right with the
Bad Bosses
Crappy working conditions and stuff like that
And also in this particular case
He was really like
Canada Public Image that
Jigsaw and Google we're projecting
Corso Mastiff
And the reality
Like in the story we have
A few quotes
Scrum
Internal forum
Where women engineers at Google disc
Jigsaw
And at one point one of them
Address employee says
Social justice
Is initial waiting
Jigsaw
And I don't trust chicks
Just saw a star
And it's like
This is the team that should actually get
This kind of issues right there
They're basically going to sign for it yeah they're designing products for
Places like Iran and Syria
Other countries where you know basic human rights are violated and
Seems like they're not respecting their own workers rights
Well thank you for
Checking your producers had at the door
The interview getting grilled by Yours Truly we will be back next week
This week's episode was recorded in edited by Dean white produced by Lorenzo franceschi VK
Hosted by me and Max who you'll be hearing from us next week