Eagle one package being delivered
Macros hipster take on white supremacist him in the unity of them buying online
Publication known as unicorn Riot what they did was dumbest series of 770,000 messages
From the identity evropa Discord slack and other chat channels exposing the group's attempts
Is the deadly unite the right rally in Charlottesville
The plan was to go mainstream Indie player in American politics
Identity evropa try to Rebrand as simply pro-white decrying their Neo-Nazi labels I think that would be a major
Yes if we can finally start having a dialogue and not so one of these oh we need to talk about race but let's go
Just bring on a person of European Heritage she's going to sit there as a stool pigeon as a yes man
Reveals that was total BS the Unicorn ride dump is an example of how people are
Trying to fight back online against a growing radical popular Neo-Nazi extremist
Right. Things like the ideologies that spawned the Christ Church Terror attacks from ever happening today
Hey we have Freddie Martinez I got none within how can circles who's a member of the Unicorn ride team that took down identity
Europa to tell us what it's like tracking Nazis online well thanks
For coming on the show today
So tell me what is
Unicorn
Riot
That's a good question. Is a decentralized
Alternative media Collective
So we cover everything
Fromm
Like social justice issues to environmental issues racism
Avalon doing journalism
Other people aren't doing but we checked
Big restaurant rustic stands
We work very hard to uphold like Barry Sanders on ourselves
So
Yeah that's how we approach
Decentralized
Group
What was the ethos
Exactly I think we try to tell stories at like
Most people aren't covering our efforts around the taxes Pipeline and telling a story about the
Struggles against him in the time where other people weren't doing that
The Intercept of a huge series about
Private and Military contractors
Working to effectively you know call.
A threat to National Security
And so when we were when you can write with doing that reporting or ethos is like we're going to tell the story about
About like not only like
Glad struggles indigenous struggles
Environmentalism
And like you know several social
How to write
But we did it at a time when no one else is doing it so I think are already those who just to go after
Stories that no one else knowing
Cover
You know and we didn't really really successful at doing that
And you also seem to be a collective of a lot of different types
The people
Yeah you know you have Developers YouTube journalist
People like yourself
Everyone sort of involved in this I mean
For lack of a better reference
Seems almost like a professionalized anonymous
Sing way we all consider ourselves journalist in different capacities
Neurologist
Web developer video editor
We all
Collectively story
Incredible about this recording is that it doesn't take a 50-person research
You know kind of bootstrap DIY
Independent journalism
Can have really impactful results
Stories
If you guys come onto my radar as someone who who does all reporting on the far right
When you do the shoes ironmark Stomp
Of neo-nazis
And their chat logs about a year ago
And you know you
Who is the bunch of them
And then you got to do it again
With a group called identity evropa
So why don't you tell me
How did you come about
Dumping what was it
770,000 messages of this group
So I did need Europa is one of the largest Neo-Nazi groups
And the US
They were one of the catalyst
Organized
Unite the right
Rally
Hallettsville
So we had known them for a long time
We've had sources many sources
About
They were trying
Get published
I'm so in this case we had about seven
All right chat messages that we published as well as
Slack Channel
Are there
Bits of information that were given to us like
Unlisted YouTube channel
Largest stories
Our reporting
Used
I need also this group was trying to sort of Groom itself as a much more palatable version
You know we're just provide you know it's not that bad we don't hate other races or anything we're not Nazis
With this chat log
Dumb basically showed that
That was
So the messaging is really important to them
They are
Are closely aligned with other
Star recruits
Your call
Generation identity
I'm GI
Because Europe has berries
Speech loss after vacation
They're very very careful about their images
And so they're very careful about
They say things like
I mean they are careful on the River about
Don't you know
I'm call for violence
But they're exactly
I just want to hear about it
So a lot of it is just kind of like Romaine disorder
Hipster Nazi like as long as you wear khakis
A dress shirt
So a lot of what they focus
Cassandra Lee
Presenting themselves
Which is just like another
Dog whistle
White power
Building is this
The chat
Dump also expose that there were what like seven members of the military that were involved with this group as well as
Some people in law enforcement
What's surprising is not
Are people in the military or law enforcement
Or anything like that
Surprising
Is just like the public reaction
The public will sometimes
Email us like hey
I think my girlfriend is dating a Nazi
So
We were surprised that there were
You know law enforcement and military officials
EMTs
School teacher who
Expose today
I'll be part of this group there was a GOP
Officer
Who works for the governor
Who sings like
Those names
In particular are maybe a little bit surprising but it's just the organizational level
Professional some of these individuals
Everyday Society
I mean they really try to make it seem like they weren't
Major
Engage with major neo-Nazi
Literature and like that but then they had this big pamphleteering
Game of the replying with her dropping tons of identity evropa
Pamphlets around
Aries all over the US
And they called it project seeds
We will see gif
Code for James Mason neo-Nazi
Insurgency Bible
Author similar to the Turner Diaries witch inspired Timothy McVeigh to blow up
The alarm City
Federal Building
That's revered by loss of Neo-Nazi group
Like I'd like information
But the entire idea with Siege is that you
Create random acts of violence
Inside out
So when they call flyering projects that have a private literature server
Where there
You know
Read Tara Taylor read books about
The protocols of the Elders of Zion
Conspiracy theory book about how juice wrld
Your videos talking about
Well I don't recommend
All of these sort of intersections
Also like these books
Nazi propaganda
Layer with like
Only if you want to read that on your free time go ahead I just don't
That's really how I
I mean
Two dozen
Freddy you're obviously well known in the hacking Community as well as how we first met
When I was hosting the show cyber War
How did you how to unicorn
Individual sources
I came to the
The project because I
Ran into a colleague who was
Helping unicorn riot
And
They were you no writings
Very basic
The journalists do their research
Eventually we
Turn data into what's now the Discord takes platform
I'm so we have a group
You know
Anonymous Developers
Volunteer their time to make these chat logs readable and searchable
I'm so over like the last
Year
People have dedicated
You know
Hours and hours and hours and third time
To make it so.
Like we have released
1.7 million
And so one of the ways I got involved
With this work was
You're making
Easier to do
And then
Once you read
500 million chat messages
Then you can actually understand
That's how I do it
Yeah I was going to say that
The whole database is actually more searchable zevran a lot of
A lot of Stories on the WikiLeaks
Database intern
The Stratford
And unicorn riot what is a lot easier to
A lot easier
Yeah it's cuz we use a lot too so I can every time you need
I hate you
You know it's like one of those
Often
And you know we're using the same software tools that we watched
Obviously
So what's next do you have
Any other leaks coming
Look
Purpose
All right recruitment is always to get more members
New our faces
Dakotamart
You know wiring events
The impact of our reporting has been that
People are leaving this movement
You know in to some degree like
It's not a thing that you want to be associated with
So that's one
Like aspect of like what I think it's important
The other thing is that we do have
Upcoming stories
We're trying to figure out like
What are the things that's going to happen
Maybe next few months is figure out like how do we tell stories
Yahoo news
In Uno
Awesome person who is o
Officer in a school
Those are not like different stories are kind of the same
And they're linking lots of different ways
And so we're trying to figure out you know I think the next thing we're going to do is I tell stories about life
What are these relationships actually look like
There's a third story
That is really like how to use
All link together show the
Person who shot up the mosque in New Zealand
She was sending money to Martin snow
HGI in
Austria
Who's very costly pipe
I think the New York Times Are story about it today
About how this mess
Shootings are all
So what inspired the other is what we know
And the internet has a lot to do with with
And I saved the internet but
Online chatter and
Different platforms really help that
I mean the
US law enforcement uses
Right
So yeah so trying to figure out
Work
But there are more stories coming
So I can
No one's out there listening to the strattons worried about like
Are you reporting
These are these groups or not
Obviously not healthy
Annuities are actions
And Michael Jackson
Isa
That's like that's just like my personal
So basically
Any neo-nazis were listening right now
You might end up on a unicorn ride dump
I mean look this is a personal
Certainly do believe that people can change
I just don't think there's anything you need
And
What's happening
I just like
Everything is like there's nothing there so I don't know why
Stick around
Skroutz
Well I mean keep up the great work it's
Seems like it's going in the right direction and I'm sure this will not be the last time I hear about unicorn riot
Exposing
A white nationalist proof online by nuking them and showing all
Chat logs in that
Love to be out of this line in recording
But
You're not a suspect that it won't be the last time we talked
Definitely
Don't believe wallpaper
Thanks buddy
And now it's more recent big news in online white nationalism came via a giant scoop
For motherboard
We broke the Facebook will be undertaking an all-out ban
I've white nationalism
Onyx Black
More than that from one of the architects of that scoop
Our editor-in-chief
Mr. Jason kapler
So json
You're one of two reporters
Who might have broken one of the biggest door is at
Vice has ever had
You broke
That Facebook would be
The outline
All white natural
Yashow with Joseph Cox who's been on the show a few
2 * 1
Have been
Can I first say that your beard is look
Jessica day
Why is getting long so anyways you been on this story for over a year now around me
Day of last year
Joseph Cox
Gain access
Json Facebook
Internal con
In moderation documents
Ideas of the PowerPoint slides that
Is giving Twitter
The moderators
Basted eggs
Here's what you should do
Levi's.
To take down
I'm an
On this document
There is one
Pacific slide that was like
Raise up where was one presentation that was like
After the Charlottesville unite the right rally
Here's how Facebook handles why nausea
Amazon wipes
CNY
And at the time Facebook said
White supremacy and racism is ban on AR platform
But white nationalism
And wife separate
Are allowed
Explicitly allowed
Do not remove it
And they Define white nationalism using literally the wicked
PDA definition of white nationalism
Which I don't have in front of me right now but that they pulled it directly from there
And they're like
Their argument was that
White nationalism and
And white separatism are not in
Apparently hateful and that
They are actually could be inclusive
Which is like Egyptian
Sir this is something that keeps coming up with
Not just people but tech companies I mean how do you how can you justify
Oh I think being white is the best
That's not race
Right and it's it's because Facebook tries to
Treat all people the exact same width
Out
Taking into a
Counter like the history of racism or the history of power dynamics
It's in the United States and other like Western
So while you have white nationalism which is like very inherently tides
White supremacy
Andre inherently tide
Racism and segregation and slavery
You know
Facebook wanted to allow a nationalism
Because they wanted to allow things like fast
Not really this
Same thing
I mean that support national news apps
Absolutely not even close
Brightwell Facebook singing was like Hey if we banned white nationalism we all set the band black nationalism we also have to be
Basque nationalism in all these other nationalist movements that are in a much smaller and also coming
From groups that don't inherently have a lot of
Power.
Like unlike White
Unlike
You know the white race
States
So I mean obviously that's nonsense because you can Facebook can ban whatever it wants to ban is
It's just that enforcing it is slightly more difficult
Ethical because
They have to
Neil make more rules
And so Facebook has many different rules they're very special
Civic
Like when we did this
Investigation we found out there are dozens and dozens
Examples like this
Where it's like
White nationalism was loud white separatism was is allowed but whites
Supremacy is not
It's like what yeah so like a different example of this and this is completely absurd
Is that Facebook doesn't allow like nudity on its way
Website but it does allow breastfeeding mothers on its website
Because
That's like an allows artistic to
Depictions of nudity
Because they're been back lashes
Photos taken down
Make it so specific as to say
You are not allowed
How to post anuses on Facebook like
Like this is in there. You're not allowed to post an actual butthole like no anuses on Facebook
Unless it's a political commentary
Which means that you are allowed to put
You're allowed
How to photoshop
Anuses on to Donald Trump's face
Where his eyes are
This is an actual example with an actual photo
Like that is allowed and don't take that down but then they have another example that has Kim Jong un's face
And his mouth has been replaced by an anus
And there's a butt plug going into the anus
And that needs to be taken
Because that is sexual content because it has a butt plug
I dislike
This is like written in Facebook documents that are like sent
Two tens of thousands of my God raised around the world and it's like it's an absurd example but it's like
These are the lines that Facebook
Kids drawing
And this is how they are ultimately moderating
Speech for over
2 billion people across the world
See you this story
You stay on top of it
In terms of distance classic appointing estate on top of the story and then we fast forward to now
Yes we publish the story were like hey
Facebook allows white nationalism and obviously rumors
Is very bad
You know you had civil rights Scholars you had
Black history experts and you had these
Civil Society groups being like
These are not different things
Facebook should make
The distinction and they start putting pressure on
So they are like hey Facebook you need to change this
This is very bad
And
I think back in maybe cept
Amber
We learned that Facebook was real
Considering
This
Like it was reconsidering its stance
A story that was like a Facebook
Is reconsidering this but we didn't know where they're ultimately
So last week
We learned that Facebook finally did make a change
I and it is
Now treating white nationalism and white separatism the same as whites
Mercy witch
Brings that much more in life
You know one thing about this story that's interesting is like Facebook has not had a good year
Very clearly and this was one of those things that it did
Even I and I am definitely a Facebook hater
Thought to myself
But
Is the right thing to do
Yeah I mean this is the right thing to do I think
The people that we talked to her like
Why did it take so long but also like
Thank God they finally did it
And I will
Just sort of couch that in saying that
This all depends on how Facebook actually
End up enforcing these policies
Is because we do know like we do know that things like unite the right were organized
Did you know that they're openly White
On Facebook
For organizing or in groups were talking to each other
And we know that they use a lot of code words we know that they
That you know have learned to evade Facebook
Looks content moderators
And a good example of this is
Facebook says that
It's only going to bandage
Explicit white nationalism
And white stuff
And that
Basically finding implicit or
Coded versions of it
And removing it is
Is too difficult
Duet scale
Like they're just unable their moderators are not
Trained enough
How to be able to
Figure that out
So they're just going to leave it up
For the time being
And Huffington Post actually had a pretty good article
I had a great story about
Yeah so I don't know a whole lot about faith Goldy
Probably you know more I douche
She's a racist
White nationalist
Kind of troll
From Canada
She recently attacked one of our reporters
Online with a with a photo
Insult a great reporter
She's definitely someone who
I think for a while she had on her Twitter profile like white Nashua
Yeah she is in an avowed White
Looks like that's the label that
Uses I believe so
You know here is a great example of something that Facebook
Probably should remove under its policy
And she posted a video where she said like
I am a black nationalist which I think was poking
Poking at Facebook
You know policy saying that they're going to
Continue to allow black nationalism
And also said yeah white populations in white majority European Western countries are being
Quote replaced by non-white people which
It's obviously referring to
This conspiracy theories flashlight
If it's bad enough to call but like this idea Boise
It's very much so
It's
It's reference even though she doesn't realize that she's referencing
Micom she's referencing
Hitler speech
When she sings
You'll see that what you're saying right now
As historical press
Write an endless coming from like an invalid white nationalist on Facebook said that this doesn't violate the policy in the
Leaving app
And they told the Huffington Post that we followed up with them they told us the same thing so
I mean on some level it's very good and it you know for me personally like I'm proud that we were able to
You know report this
Historian cause Facebook to make a policy
Sea change
But ultimately it's only going to
Be as good as
Enforce
If they're drying such a
Narrow view of white
White nationalism actually is
Then it's not going to be that
The question is
If you have Facebook doing it find them we'll see what the enforcement is
Anatomically
We don't know
For a while exactly what it does
But
I mean
You wear DC right now
Twitter
YouTube these other
Shoe Fashions of
Neo-Nazi militants
Not taking the harshest stance against
Yeah I mean yeah you've had some gray reporting on this
As well which
Yeah you
You reported that a lot of
These
Web hosting podcast hosts have been taking down
You know that domain names are the servers of a valid neonoe
And meanwhile those same people are just
Regrouping on YouTube
Toobin Twitter
The biggest offender to me
Internship not doing anything
Are there like
Frankly doing
Nothing and then
But I think the crazy thing is is
What it was Isis
We saw Atkins
Completely different attitude
Which kind of puzzles
Yeah I mean
Yes there was a completely different attitude toward it
And
I everything everything I say here is just kind of like speculation but
You know obviously YouTube
And
Twitter and Facebook are all American
Companies
That
Ino
Predominantly operate in English like in their corporate
Setting in their corporate world
They can take down ISIS content and if they over-reach on that like they're not going to get the
The blowback that they're going
To get if they overeat
Answer
Taking down like white Nashville
Are whites ever
Isamar whites
Like you seen
Here in the US
Facebook accidentally took down a Chick-fil-A appreciation page
In 20
14 I believe and called it a hate
Croup
And Facebook admitted that that was
A mistake
And mistakes do happen because there's snow
Millions upon millions of posts on Facebook
And Ted Cruz
To this day
Is like
Heading on Facebook saying that they're biased against
Conservatives because of this decision made
Presumably by one single person
In 2014
Like as a mistake
Whereas you're not going to get the same sort of pushback if
You know you are taking down
Things that are quite Isis but they are
In that realm another serve like
Muslim extremist
Type content that maybe doesn't rise to the level
Where if it was white nationalism a wimpy taken down
Buy YouTuber by Facebook
But you get what I'm saying oh no I think they are
Comparison I would dry I think
I think
The same reason Donald Trump doesn't come out
And condemned white Nash
Terrorism
And actually even
Admitted
The thing
The same reason
That you're not
Twitter Anthony
Coming down hard on these
I think it's the same thing as
Because
Ultimately
In some form or another
They need their
Right right I mean yeah I think that
When we reported that Facebook was taking this down
You had Fringe figures but not
Really like
Hardcore Nazis like sort of light
Bright figures who are not
All the way right but are kind of like a Candace Owens of the world like Facebook is coming for us now
Acts like this is
The slippery slope this is
A bad thing they're going to come after
Conservatives
And the blowback has been
Not quite as as strong as I
I thought it might be
But you can imagine you know YouTube taking down something like
You know some of these larger influencers likes
Steven Mall in LA
I even like Jordan
On some level
Like if they start
Taking down that sort of content the blowback from their users going
Ridiculous
And I think that they are being extremely
Cautious to the point that it
It's hurting them
Like
In your reporting we found that
They are not taking down
Actively neo-Nazi
Content
Absurd
Yeah they said hey we're demonetizing this or putting this behind like a cons
Content warning quick
Through thing we're moving lights for removing comments
But
You can still find it on search and it's still there
And they know they exist and they decide to leave it up
Exactly
Like I don't any that exactly exact same people that you know web host have already taken
Down these are the same people like these are outright
Recitations of audiobooks like
The Siege audiobook witches
The the
Definition of Manifesto
Atomwaffen division
Right and so I mean this is violent content this is
Actively hateful content this isn't like
Debating
Race Theory it's
Like debating it's like actively hateful and actively built
Yeah and yet it
Still online
Yeah I mean
I think that the platforms have a lot to answer for in the aftermath of Christchurch I and
Pittsburgh and all these other
No Terror attacks that were
2 White
I think that
It's you can't say that
The internet definitely cause
What is the tax
Definitely radicalized
People I think there's
Just a lot of
Aspects to that but it's clearly one important part of the radicals
In process
Clearly an important part of
The
Propaganda machine and the information machine
And the fact that they
Have done
Such a bad job of taking it
Down and that they haven't acted as
Quickly and as
Forcefully as they've acted
With things like Isis
It just demonstrate
Grace that there's
I agree completely and I think
I think this is more of a reflection of where we are
Socially and politically
Then just
It's an internet
I think the internet's where we go to reflect on
Who we are and what we do and how we grow
Group together
And I think that the world has a much bigger problem with it
Extremism
Then we'd like to
And I think the internet always has a
Yeah I'm very interested to see where this goes because there was an interview and then you are
X with
I YouTube
Head of product I believe forehead a policy
And you know his answers were
Or bad
Like a terrible
It's very
Right they don't seem to have a handle on the problem they don't seem to have a handle on how bad this is I mean you have
Play PewDiePie the most
Popular YouTuber
I believe still
Very close to most popular YouTuber
Is making videos that
Are gateways off into these ideologies
It's like if you stay on there and you click
Through the recommendations like the algorithm will eventually push you in the
Radical
Radicalizing path
And Facebook hasn't reckoned with
Is recommendation an inch and it hasn't
Reckoned with
How it does search
And ultimately hasn't reckoned with how it deals with
These popular but Fringe figures that
Platform
No
It hasn't
Honestly this is me just being baffled
That they haven't tried
Cuz I think to me
Like anybody else who
Saw what happened
Christ Church
And just
Daniela the referencing that was going on from the terrorist
And what he said it was so obviously
But he was
You know
He's at least in the mix online mix online in a way that is much more than just a passive
Epatha viewer
And to think that there were
Figures involved with that
That wouldn't be banned or you wouldn't
Look at something so horrific
We watch the video
Yeah yeah he said it's like how could you not watch that and what can I do to stop
Someone from
Thinking these things
Yeah I think if you want to learn more about what
Facebook and YouTube and these companies value you want to read the big Bloomberg story that was published
Earlier this week
Our last week I guess at this point
Where
I know you two was chasing
Engagement
At all
At all costs like you know people within you two were like hey there's a lot of bad stuff on our platform like
Can we get rid of it
And you know the people at the top or like
Well bad stuff does well
Yvonne Gage with it people
Comment on it people
Shareit
And they were chasing engagement so
My sweater yeah it's the same thing and I think it's like
Until that changes
These problems are going to continue to exist
Agreed on that
This podcast was recorded in edited by Dean white produced by Jason Tabler and Voice by your side
Truly