Maria's email account recently been broken into
So when news broke out
That the Ashley Madison
Might have been hacked
The fault of her information being where it shouldn't
What's fresh in her mind
Using an online search she decided to check if I email wasn't somehow registered on the site
Thinking nothing of it she also put in her fiance's email address
Suffice to say
The wedding was canceled
Rick's marriage
What's going on for two decades
I had a couple of kids to show for it
Somewhere along the way
He and his wife had lost
Perhaps it was his 3 hours commute to a tiring corporate job
Or her overwhelming duties
Real estate Houma
Rick
Hit a full-on midlife crisis
Buying motorcycle even getting a tattoo
He was on a binge for things exciting
It led to him thinking about an affair
He never did anything with his Ashley Madison account
But after the site got hacked
Rick received a blackmail letter threatening to reveal his membership
Instead of calling the bluff
Rick owned up to his wife about what he done
She left out
The front door
That evening
Luckily for WIC
Cheap eventually return home the next morning
He and her
We're about to begin a long journey to Healing
John was a pastor
Magic
He had a wife and two children and in his spare time he enjoyed restoring automobile
John had struggled with depression and addiction in his past
But was known among his students is a great teacher with a penchant for fun
John's name was included in Ashley Madison delete user accounts
Before his wife was able to find that out for herself
She found his body
And suicide note
It was bunkers
It was completely crazy
Because the media grabs hold of this story
Like no data breach that I've ever seen before
And
I think when you know the details of what the Ashley Madison website was designed to do its maybe no surprise
That the British tabloid the Press around the world TV stations radio everybody
Wanted to talk about this adultery said we should be next
Hi I'm around Levi
Welcome back to the malicious Life podcast by cybereason
Ashley Madison is a website for cheating spouses
Sort of like a reverse eHarmony
Maybe an emerald
Tinder
The service is owned and operated by Avid life media Incorporated
Heretofore referred to as a
Now under the name Ruby Corporation
Based in Toronto Canada
Noel biderman founded the company
And could most often be found in suggestive promotional photographs
Smiling Pepe
Creepily
With one finger to his lips
Due to the covered nature of the Ashley Madison service
Most of the public has been either unaware of his
Existence
Sheer popularity
Need to clean for example
Do use a base of 37 million people from over 40 different countries
One point
Just seem to be an outlandish Lehigh number
When Ashley Madison got hacked
Made International headlines
Why
Because it wasn't
Just the major events
It demonstrated
How does information even more sensitive
Even more significant
Then your credit card or your social security number
You'll see
July 19th
It was 9 p.m. on a Sunday night
Brian Krebs
An infosec blogger
Received an email from an anonymous informant
We are the impact
We have hacked Alm completely taking over their entire office and production domains and
Thousands of systems
And over the past few years have taken all customer information databases complete source code
Repositories
Financial records
Documentation and emails as we prove here
And it was easy
For company
Who's main promises secrecy it's like you didn't even try like you thought you had never
Pissed anyone off
Alm has been instructed to take Ashley Madison and establishment offline permanently
In all forms
We will release all customer records including profiles with all the customers secret sexual fantasy
And matching credit card transactions
Real names and addresses
An employee documents and emails
Established men for backgrounds
Is another Alm site
Which connects young women do sugar daddies
A hacker or Packers calling themselves the impact team had just posted this online Manifesto
Website
Call survivinginfidelity.com
Claiming to have stolen all of the airline companies data
To demonstrate that they were serious
The impact team included some of Ashley medicines internal data in the post
Including samples of user information
And the mapping of the company's internal Network
Reaction to the first Ashley Madison data dump
Was Swift and loud
It became international news
And 37 million people around the world
Begin to hyperventilate
YCO nobleman
Personally admitted to reporters what happened
Publicly as Ashley Madison customer service lines became overloaded
Company Representatives
Refuse to acknowledge
The legitimacy of the attack
Those who called in with questions and complaints in those first days
We're giving a range of
Excuses or simply disconnected from the line
Now there was a ticking clock
What they comply or call the hackers Bluff
The company was able to wipe the hackers original later from the internet
North bitumen
Seem to believe they'd caught the Copa
He told Brian kerbs quote
We're on the doorstep of confirming who we believe is the culprit
And unfortunately that may have triggered this messed up location
I've got their profile
Right in front of me
Older Works Prudential
It was definitely a person here that was not an employee but suddenly had tests are technical service
Import
The press release from the company ended with a quote
From Kaufman, TX
Quote
I have no doubt
Based on the work I and my company are doing
Will continue to be strong
Secure
Banquet
Keyboards
Continue to be
It didn't appear that the company would be begging down from the fight
Behind the scenes a LMU is much about their hacker at the moment of bitters men statement
As you do about the same hacker
Right now
Still with the faith of the company at stake
Something had to be done
Whoever the impact team was
They were careful
To cover their tracks
The dump to sneak peek of The Stolen data on the dark web
Only accessible via an anonymous Network client that leaves no trace of its users
Information about it leaked out
Anonymous tips to the media
Within the doors of Alm no trace of intrusion was found
In essence
The criminal robbed the house
And left
No DNA no fingerprints behind
Really all researchers had to go on
Was the day date
And speculation
I am Steve Regan senior staff writer at CSO online
And one of the reporters who covered the Ashley Madison stuff back in 2015
There are some context clues
You can take away from the communications englishes
Probably not their first language
They are proficient in English so they've been educated
They know
Networking hacker parlance but when it came to sentence structure and things like this
They weren't
Fluid
Like a natural speaker would be they were more
It's hard to describe what I'm thinking here they thought they were
They were not Nuance like a natural speaker would be like
But fluid and in the conversation you and I are having
The nature of the breach
Is evidence
That it must have been conducted by a current or former employee
Because who else
Could have had that level of excess
Internal databases
Right
Notice how this was all based in speculation
John McAfee
McAfee Security claim with 100% confidence
That Alm hack was an inside job
Also claimed to be sure
Of the hackers
Gender
How
Because they refer to men as goldenport scumbags and emphasized Valentine's Day in the
Manifesto
You see what I'm saying here
Nobody
Really knew anything
It didn't help either
That
Didn't have much of a security apparatus in place
One would imagine that for a company that deals in secret sexual affairs
Security would have been of highest priority
Minuet
An analysis of Ashley Madison's cyber defense infrastructure after
The Heckard
Experts pointed out to some notable
If not glaring flaws and how they handle their ultrasensitive data
Here's Graham cluley cyber-security journalist
Unblock
We do know
There's some of that security was quite weak for instance at first the passwords which were exposed
We thought they would significantly strong enough and
Well nothing tripped but enough that they can easily be tracked and then
It was late to reveal the actually they were bugs
In the coding done by a flea medicine so. I think it's something like 15 million
What's the password
We're relatively easy to crack
And once again we have the problem there a people reusing passwords on multiple sites
The finding Graham is referring to
Come from the work of a hacking team called cynosure Prime
Cynosure is a small group with small following
Epiphyseal themselves as a password research Collective
Their work on the Ashley Madison data dump
Was anything but modest
All in all revealing almost as much about Alm minutes users
SVP
Deem themselves did
Understand how they did it you have to know
About cryptography principal called
Hashing
You know those people with
Really convoluted signatures
They can be really nice or really messy
Either way
You're like
How in the world did he get from
Rent Levy to that jumble of nonsense scribbles
It's kind of like that
But for computer
Different hash algorithms
Work in different ways
But in each case you start off
With a file
Whether it be a movie page of text anyting
And the bits of information that make up that 5
Get process
The algorithm
The result will be a number that might seem totally random
But crucially
Just like a signature
Each hash is the specific result of the input data it represents
Even if my signature appears random to you
It's not
It's a specifically based on my name
And it's not subject
To change
Regardless of the day
Time how I'm feeling when I write it how many times I write it
Why I'm running it
What I ate just before I wrote it
Anyting
Bottom line is
That cashes need to appear random
So that they review nothing about the data they represent
However because they aren't random steak and theoretically
Beat reverse-engineered
Team Ashley Madison Case most of the passwords or hash
Orcutt the graphically obscured
Using strong hashing function that would make them practically Bulletproof
Reverse engineering
However 15 million of those 36 million hashed passwords stored in their database
Contains a specific variable
Token Spanish War called
Dollar sign login key hash using md5
Md5 is a hash algorithm designed in 1991
By 2004 md5 what's considered broke
What does this mean
Hashes are built to be
Fast but not too far
Fast so that the hatching process doesn't take so long
And not too fast because any hash
That's so quick process
Is also quick
Crack
Md5
He's kind of like the 90's boy band
Cryptographic hash function
It was good for its time like when the Backstreet Boys were catchy but not too annoying
Md5 was fast but not too far
With the computing power available today however
It's far too quick to crack
Even the regular laptop can do the job
By the time of Ashley Madison hack
Md5 wasn't just
Broken
Broken Shredder
And talked into can't
Like busting out some New Kids on the Block on Spotify
You could say it's better than nothing
But that's about all you can say for it
Md5 is weak by today's standards in fact
That even you or I could possibly break it
Pier
Let's say the data I'm going to hash
Is a string podcast
Let me
I'm going to a website online that auto generate an md5 hash for the password
In all lowercase
Got it
Okay here's my hat
It's a C9
CEF
What is goes on for 27 more characters
But I'll spare you the rest of it
Sounds complicated
Right
Kind of like nonsense
But remember what you just learned about hashing
Each character in that hashtag is directly drawn from the data I put in
In this case
The stream podcast
If my string work podcast
Would it be the hash would be entirely different
Not just randomly differ
But specifically different
To reflect
Batman stream
You may think
How in the world would I be able to
Crack this hash function if I didn't already know the data is represented
Try this
I'm now on google.com
I'm going to copy and paste my hash into the search bar and
What
Free or the first for search results
Weed podcasts
Podcast names and nicknames for podcast
End podcast
That's not a coincidence
Simply by doing a Google search I was able to reverse-engineer this hash result to reveal the string
What's supposed to be obfuscating
Now do you see white how broken md5 is
Google won't work for every md5 hash
Especially
Passwords more complex than
Podcast
But it's telling that at least and a certain parameters
Cracking an md5 hash
It's only the same amount of effort as say
Finding out how old I am
PNC by the way
H2O
Cynosure was able to review 11 million passwords in the first 10 days work
And the other four million shortly thereafter
Over 40% of the passwords from the site
My explaining the md5 hash
Tokens
Cynosure also posted some of their favorite passwords
Which range from dumb to dirty to just
Sap
Sad by the folks who chose
I Think I Love My Wife
Why are you doing this and cheaters never Prosper to entering every time The Exorcist
Then there were those who are more introspective
Like
Just checking it out
And good guy doing the wrong thing
Those who are catching into the whole Ashley Madison scam
Like nobody here and
They were robots
And those who thought they were clever like my password is password
The best password ever
And this is a good passer
Now back to the week of July 28th 2000
With no leads on who their attacker might be
The only question left for Alm to ask
Was who might have wanted to do harm to that company
That's of course
Is harder to answer
When you're talking about the website
Promoting and facilitating marital infidelity
As I mentioned earlier
Some thought the hacker or hackers
Might have been a disgruntled employee
Someone with close ties to the company
How else would they have known so much
About eight limbs internal systems
You might be interested to learn.
Pay Atlanta employees on the whole
Seem to have a pretty good life at the company
For all the sleeves and a morality of the service
You think their office headquarters would be filled with
Bad Dudes being inappropriate
And coming up with
Evil plan
Actually
It was quite the opposite
Employees who are paid handsomely
And there was
Free beer at the office
The financial post
The business-oriented paper-based in Canada
Spoke with the number of former employees describe the office is quote a fun place.
Get scared about its employees
There was a course another side to working at Alm
Those who spoke with the financial post had to do so anonymously because
To work for a
Requires signing a non-disclosure agreement
Lasting
Long past your death
Those who did speak
Cami and blatantly manipula
They described
Calls from anguished
Family members name the blame on Ashley Madison for ruining their families
Even threatening the lives of the customer service representative
And their families
It appears all Ashley Madison employees
Lived with this lingering dichotomy
Of their daily lives and underlined dirty thing they were helping to make
Still anyone working for Alm would have known what they signed up for from day one
If it were a former employee who hacked the site
What reason would they have for doing so
If it were a disgruntled customer or family member of a customer
How could they have such
Deep knowledge of idiot Lambs computer systems
Necessary to accomplish so successful the heck
The impact
Steam spice how careful they were
Dude leaves small Clues to their identity in their Manifesto
Among their issues with the lewd and immoral nature of Ashley medicine service
Fraud deceit and stupidity
Alm and their members
The hacker or hackers also took issue with one particular feature of the website
Ashley Madison offers a full delete feature
What about users can shut down there counting wipe all trace of it from Alm database
Payment of 19.99 dollars
Because of the nature and flea medicine
The future is invaluable
The impacting pointed out that they were able to find data on all users in the site's history
Including
Those who paid for full delete
The delete function was turned out
Julie
Semitic
Why beads impact
Team care so much about this fool delete front
Is the hacker was some vengeful wife of an Ashley Madison user why would she give it any mind
It seems like the sort of thing a former account holder my care about
Oh maybe an employee
The Mayfest though it seems
Only raised more questions
Benny dancer
And then
Who was one more mystery left on soul
When Brian crafts
Tweeted out his story introducing the Ashley Madison hacked the world
He got retweeted
Bike One account that
Seemed particularly noted
Why notable
Because if you were to click on that account on that day
Would have seen among other things
This tweet
Quote Ashley Madison source
Launchpad dotnet forward slash
Ashley and Co
Received no likes
And1 retreat
It was also posted before any single media Outlet including crabs
Got word of the story
In other words
This had to be the impact team 40 someone with closed tight
Tedious Zoo
View zoo on Twitter
Is aquatic fig
His name even sounds like some sort of
Comic book villain
So we can assume it's fake
His social media pictures of stock images
Austin of various African American male models
He pretends to live in Hawaii even setting his accounts time zone to Hawaii
But some digging around indicate his Australian
For five years has it been
Trulicity
Sending out hundreds and hundreds of messages per month despite receiving little or no respond
Sometimes
He brags about hacking Government website
Are the times
The tweets 10 take the form of 140 character drama
Here's one string of messages
He posted
Just before the Ashley Madison
Quote I turned away from all of that when most folks will do anything to have power wealth
And witches
The best decision I had ever made
Then I simply turned up in Canada
Live there for a year
That was the beginning of my new life
Sweet as ever as I can even a match
And then
I simply disappeared
While on the same time lining up everything that I will need for my long voyage
Another life
That I have always wanted
That's claims he moved
Canada where Alm is headquarters
Would not have otherwise been notable
If not for BV of other red flags
Surrounding is a count
A few days after the first Ashley Madison data dump
Toronto police gave an otherwise standard press conference on the matter
With a few interesting tidbits of information
They revealed that Alm actually first became aware of the hack on July 12th
One week before news of it went public
When employees if the company
Found an intimidating noticed from the impact
Steam on their computer screens
Accompanied by the song
Thunderstruck
By ACDC
AC DC
For those who don't know
He's a bad witch
Like originates from Australia
NSU to zufall aware Mike Note 3 of his
From August 4th 2012
Do a Dutch cyber security company website
Just hack into
Quote next time it will be Thunderstruck
Hashtag
AC DC
12 hours before the first news broke out about the attack
Zoo
Was tweeting up a storm
In one address
To contact who presumably for privacy reasons
Heat does not tag in the post
Zoo rights
Quote settle down amigo
We are setting up a replication server so we can get that show start
Import
The Tweet included a screenshot of the sort of replication server hacker might want to set up say
If they were holding onto stores of sensitive corporate and wanted to release it to the public without fee
Fear of losing their copy
If you saw this screenshot yourself
You might notice another tab open in zoos browsers
The YouTube video
AC DC
Sandusky
The show eventually
Was about to start
In later posts
Zoo denied being the perpetrator of the airline
His role in the events
His true identity remains unknown
To this day
In fact
Even weeks after the initial attack
Neither Alm they're hired security no Canadian police
Could find the culprit
You could call this a huge failure
Oh you could point to all the evidence that the impact team meant business
That they breached every corner of Alm service
Did they were willing to release the most sensitive data online
And that they did it all without leaving a trace behind
Perhaps aoins biggest failure
Was under estimating their opponent
Both Ashley Madison and
Established men
Stayed online essentially golding's it impacts team to do their worst
In the end
What happened when the impact team release the 60
Gigabyte data dump
Stolen from Airlines database
That'll be the topic of our next episode
The second and last installment of the Ashley Madison hack series
Will explore the fall out of the hack and how it was used to Blackmail isn't even unrelated peep
Including one of our cats
We also talked about the inner workings of Ashley Madison and how Bots were you
To do
Clueless customers
All this and more
Next time
Maliciously
Thank you for listening
Visit malicious. Life or subscribe to a podcast
Read full transcripts and download
Are there physics
If you have a great story to tell for a pointer to an interesting fact that you know of
Let me know
Ran and ran levi.com r a n l e v i
Borat ran levy on Twitter
Follow at malicious life for updates on future episode
Malicious life is produced by TI media
Thanks again.
Wandering the podcast
Lemoore
Cyberreason.com
Bye-bye