Eagle one package being delivered last week a video of Mark Zuckerberg
First online
What are you saying didn't seem right I wish I could keep telling you that our mission in life is connecting people
We just want to predict your future behaviors Spectre showed me how to
For free
Yourself the more we own you really just admit to the ubiquitous and Godlike powerful
Facebook exercises over modern civilization nice try but no
He did not because the video was a deepfake story about
How group of artists in AI Engineers video of Zuckerberg saying things you would never say
Then upload it to Instagram come in the wake of the Nancy Pelosi deepfake video controversy was amazed
Major troll one of the most powerful people in the world to expose how the Silicon Valley judge controls
Jesus to take steps against the proliferation of fake news on its platform for this week's episode salmon
Tell us more about the hellish world of deepfakes and whether or not it's done made Facebook think twice about a con
Who in this is cyber
Price of Sam the deepfake beat you own it
New York Times even bites your stuff
Let me know
Would you say that this is maybe one of the most
Maybe the biggest defect story that's happened
So far one of them
Recent months
Yai
I've been really
Fascinated by how big this has gotten as far as people talking about it and using it as like
A way to theorize how deep
The future in a really tangible way
We haven't seen
It's actually
How did you first get into
Yeah that is if you like Asian his right now but in late 26
Teen motherboard found someone posting
Algorithmically generated p***
On Reddit
So that's
Can I wear that began because I was on the sex work and Warren Beatty and also
So interested in AI
So
Yeah that was a perfect Confluence of those things
Discover right place right time
Evolved from service revenge p*** ass back to where
People put their ex-partner or somebody there were just
Morbidly obsessed with
Into a p*** videos that are this
Extorted Ave
You know
Troll
Venge
Revenge fantasy fast forward now and it's like his dr. Berg is actually talking about ruling the world C face
Which is maybe not uncommon like untrue
But
I think we're now I mean
Tell me if I'm wrong
We're bordering on to the the fact that this is actually going to start effect
In politics and
Society
Yeah I mean I think it already has affected Society in a way and definitely mean politicians were talking about it I think
Biden said something about deepfakes like
This weekend
I was never going to make a deepfake 2
Brotherhood
Yeah it's that was the the origins were using women's images
Without their consent
It was celebrities and reformers to
Crib set
Have tons of them business out there
So yeah it's
It's been really interesting to see what kind of evolved into being
Panic of life
Deepfake
Tomorrow weather
I just I just thought about that I was like
Shadman I don't know like maybe
Have a caveat with that it's like it's not going to happen but like one day I'm going to eat my words as like
We're heading to The Fallout Shelter
Zuckerberg one definitely
It's kind of made its Force Facebook to
Restate and reevaluate how they
Deal with misinformation they've had like misinformation policies
4 years
It's really made them kind of
Assess
How they're going to handle things like nolita videos
Look like one
And then
Recent examples of that
SodaStream particular though the goal of the artists and the AI Engineers that were the basis
Six video
Did that before
What were they trying to expose
They just came up like an art project
In UK
It's
An installation where you go in and they use
Your data to show you
I'm not really sure what things about yourself I think
But
That
The Jeopardy fake was part of that are insulation going to promote it
They didn't explicitly say that they were trying to like
Make
Facebook do anything they were just putting it out there as like
Here's an example of
One of the biggest
Like
Leaders in Silicon Valley
Same things that he never said
So really just kind of charge anyway
Speaking to the power of
Pot Farm
So yeah I think that was their intent with this
This is the kind of poke
The Beast a little bit they definitely sick
So yeah that's
The video if you watch it he's talking about like control of Stilton still in data and like controlling the future and things like that so
It's very ominous it's very ominous I also seems like something he would say or like
It's what he's thinking about and breathing heavily
What are you saying
Is what took it off to being fake I don't think that
Like if it's
Volume has going for your feed
I don't know if
It would look like a video of Zuckerberg like
It looks like him
It doesn't seem not like
Right for sure
But
I also
Maybe I wouldn't take the time to really verify it I don't know
Videos on the neck raising your feet
Like a lot of people who just pitched share like rush to share it
Yes a lot of like share share first ask questions later
Do you think
That this really came off of
Videos of the Pelosi
Controversy
I think so I think they're working on this before the pussy video
Came out but
Yeah I think that
It got the reaction that it did because of that video because that wasn't an art project that was
Meant to be
To trick people into thinking that she was drunk like that was malicious intent definitely
Yes albums of people shared that millions of views on that
So it was just
Fortuitous timing I think on their part to release the Zuckerberg one right after that
Because they're not really dead
Hershey's questions forward and can I say okay we'll Facebook
Take this one down because they didn't take down the clothes he won
Dunedin
So has this video actually
Force them to
Rethink what they're doing what what is Facebook done
In the wake of this
I mean they're we know that they have
They have said they have told the artist
Who made like a brick one
That's
Because of all the media scrutiny because they're under a lot of pressure about misinformation that they are having two kind of
Evolve these policies basically
And they're constantly
Influx in changing internally
So yeah they might not be like a policy that played out
Publicly that they are changing but
They're definitely thinking about
If their policies are robust enough
In the future
To prevent this kind of thing
They told us
Their official stance on this is. They're going to treat all of these videos the same no matter who's in them
If
Fact Checkers Martin is false then they down rank them so they don't show up on like
Hash tag on Instagram or
And stories
On Facebook there
Less likely to be like tomorrow dead by the algorithm and your feed
If their balls
So that's kind of
Desert Sands now
I think it's a lot more complicated than that
Internally for Facebook but
That's what we know why have you been so reluctant on this I don't I don't really get it
Reluctant to take on the videos yes
Seem like it's so obvious to do that
For the Pelosi video also you know there has been videos
Deepfake that's deleted edit Aveeno Trump likes
Speaking really
As if he's drunk or something
You know there's some videos out there that have been
Borderline like woah this is kind of
Misleading
I don't want a fake news a minute
Pacific news
But
I don't understand Zero Tolerance policy on the
Yeah I mean It's tricky because
I mean they're really they are in a catch-22 about this
If you start giving Facebook the power to take down everything that's
That you deem is fake or satire or you don't like that they're mocking your
Favorite Canada or whatever
That's definitely I mean that's not a road we want to go down
So
It's
I mean I think that a lot of experts agree that it's
Better to leave these things up and make them very clearly
Marked as not real
Two experts do agree that the best way to sew
Sports Adventure
Videos is to say
Explicitly all know
These are false
These are not real
Yeah definitely yeah I mean a lot of a lot of my first year so yeah it's
It becomes kind of a First Amendment thing it's like well
Is this
Beach
That should be protected or not censorship if we take it down
The answer is usually
Yes
So yeah there right now if you share something that's
Later deemed as fake
On Facebook and get a
Notification that sounds like something you shared
Yesterday
Is
Not real
Here's some more information about it
The best
Way to handle it right now
I see these things are evolving so fast
It's really hard to say
What will be best
Pretty sure but it's just damage control
Right now
I'm throwing this information on file
Of course you know the story is not about
Hacking
Some sort of
You know shadowing group
Steal something which is what we're usually covering here but
One thing I think that it really shows
Is the Integrity of data
Going forward
And how
Once
It presented the public
And how we interpret it
Means every
So you know I'm wondering a lot of people when it's fashion 2016 when you first started reporting on this
A lot of people were saying you know sort of
Sound in the apocalyptic
Alarm bell saying you know
Deepfakes are going to ruin Society ruin our lives ruined countries
There is growing alarm over the use of altered videos online
Especially those known as deepfakes
Which are highly realistic-looking and inaccurate
There are concerns about their growing sophistication and the risk they posed a national security
Do you think that's actually possible being
Someone who's so closely reporting on it do you think it does have posed that threat
Quote on quote to democracy to
Online
I think it was the threat but I think the threat is how we perceive
What is real and what's not
I don't think the threat is
Yeah I think that's definitely the biggest rat is educating people on
How they share things
Looking at things closely before they share them
Yeah it's
It's definitely
Arthritis far as
Coming up to the elections like what will be seen
As
True and what's not an especially
If you can put something out there
Real and people say oh this is fake
Doctor
Whatever
And if everything is fake nothing
Nothing is Vegas kind of that
That kind of excitement
I think that this is definitely not a new problem
We're dealing with the same kind of stuff as we were dealing with
Like the early internet like what is real what is real life
So I mean
It'll be interesting to see how
How does
Play the
If are the elections but I don't
Things are going to see like
People
Making fake
People Mass
Believing them because
We have had them at awareness about
And that's part of why we were born on it and a lot of research now is
I'm including like ethics statement
Which isn't really cool to say
Data engineer
Before they put it up
In the wild
When what where
What do you mean
I mean you know you put a research paper in it would just be like opens or whatever
Are you very open about
What you're done and what you made but like
Then you leave it to the media or at the store
Yeah there's groups a kind of
Grapple with how to deal with it in society and now their questions are being asked like in the papers themselves like lbs
Action on
Ethics statement
Think like that
It's kind of
You're getting ahead of
Free
Preact addressing the questions OB surrounding the technology
Just doing it because we can die for doing it
How to raise awareness online
Methods
Or
Improve eye protection
Things like that
It almost seems like deepfakes in terms of political
Medical standpoint
Could easily just be sort of this
Evolution of rumor
How people spread uses spread rumors about
Counter candidates that they're against
Except this time you have an actual what could be like Donald Trump saying something racist
Jackson.
Something you know I don't know what else like declaring war on someone
You know it
It seems like it's a sort of an evolution of that
And it's really up to us whether or not we're going to be
Did anyone believe that you know of at least a mess
Believe the Zuckerberg video
Did anyone report on being like Zuckerberg said this I don't think so because we set the tone on that like we were the first
About that so we broke up
So ain't that kind of
That's something I've seen a lot of people talking I like how it looks so fake because it's obviously fake who would fall for that since I well you know it's fake because
Cuz I told you it was fake like
Exactly he was saying something else he was saying something really boring
And it was like his voice
But yeah
His mouthing everything is not his words
Do you really believe it it also looked pretty real
I don't think I keep seeing with this ever since I've
World with aware of defects is likes just how close closer and closer it's getting I'm not singing is like a
Is this
Video itself perfect yet
Wow that's getting
Closer and
Closer to
The possibility where
A deep fake looks
Exactly like
Reality I think that's the thing that I
Waiting for cache
You know I if you look at these fake Natty look at that one in particular versus one that was a year ago and
Still at
Massive differ
Improve so much and they're improving as far as the mess the message that they use them or they make them with
They can make something with fewer images now I used to take a dataset of like
Thousand
Before and now it's
She was like 1 to 8
How was the one they made Mona Lisa
Yeah
So
That's been really interesting they're making them with just
Text input
Now you can just type in what you want them to say and it'll
Generator
And the UK cities is like
Cannot read cut a scene or is not required like
Something
Jamaica Movie
A long time in a lot of like Manpower but you just
Let's change that line
But I mean it's
That's very easy for
I want to do
So you say that Biden
Waiting on this
In terms of
He actually said his campaign ever pretty
How do you see this
Affected employee
Landscape going forward I mean this is something that a lot of people
I've been wondering about
I can tell you
Spokane wanted
2 disinformation people
And they can't tell me exactly what 2020 will look like but
The consensus is
It's going to be a hot mess
Chaos
Do you think you fix will pay partner
I mean yes
I think so I think just the fact that we're talking about it means it will stay apart
I think that Congress people have been using prefixes like a
Buzzword almost to talk about
Using it interchangeably would like this information
So yeah I
I do think that it will
Play heavily in
The political Affairs but I
I don't know it's hard to tell how much of that is
But
Panda tree and how much is
Real
Yeah
Because he's always this this this concept and I want to ask you about it
How
Potentially a nation-state could start using
Deepfakes to sort of
Plant misinformation
About
Certain people within
Other
Dislike her
Targets of their Etc
Do you think they have you seen any evidence of that or
Is that something you think could happen
It actually it happened in Malaysia there was a
A video
Eyewear
I it was hard to tell if
The video of the deep fake or not and it was being reported on like is this any fake we don't know
Think it ended up being real at the end but that's kind of that example of like
Everyone questioning real thing
It was that was caught having sex with another man right there is a video going around
People saying Muhammad azmin Ali has denied
Reports on ASX
Video puppet sings implicate
Kim
In a statement issued on Wednesday evening he said quote I categorically deny this vicious lie
Upon me
This is nothing but a nefarious plot
Assassinate my character
In an attempt
To destroy my political career and then another video is posted where
Would like giving address and saying
She confessed it was him or not he was like giving address about it
MP4 like oh that's
That could be a debate
Right which
I mean
Intrust Bank
Yes I think we are saying it
Used in other countries
Butts
You're not super widespread yet but just the fact that it exists in is out there
I guess I could be
The future is
Will tell whether or not a real weapon
Yeah I think
Writing
Brightwheel
How to disable wait until you but
Girl out of people smarter than
Me working on this
From
An intelligence operation standpoint and I would say the real value of it isn't to sort of take down someone because
I think eventually when something is fake it'll likely be
Exposed to space
Photos
It's tough one by that was
Complete acceptance
Truth
Manipulated by installing a Morales
But I think for one thing if you look at
The weather in Russia and how it's it's
It's actually undertaken
Influenza outbreak
Misinformation
To try to promote chaos
Within a system
Tennis serve break
But too disorganized
And I see deep fakes a sort of a potential for that he look at this one in particular
That's what it is
Destabilized Facebook
Even though it wasn't something that Facebook
Gotten
Yeah I mean yeah that's
Definitely
I really good point just that these are not necessarily
It's not that we need to have an answer on things are rather a true or not it's
That the questions being asked to begin with
And there's is uncertainty
In the air about it
The fact that Facebook is kind of
Just because of this one
Amazing multibillion-dollar company Sprint challenge by group of artists
Kind of impressed
Where do you think
You know deepfakes are going to go next at a lot of people are not
Question I mean I think they're just going to keep getting more and more realistic
The pace
This is crazy
As far as health
It's gotten more real
I think
Yeah I think we're going to see more just manipulated video.
Like with the pussy one that wasn't a deepfake that was just
A video for slow down a little bit so she was slurring Her speech
So I think we'll really see more
Of that
Yeah
I don't know it's
It's hard as I I mean
Detective
Seeing so many people working on this issue and I trying to detect it
Detect fake videos in
Turn and democratize
How that works
Has been
Really fascinating to see
Are there any more like private companies get it on this game the
One of the groups that made the Zuckerberg one
Is basically like an ad agency they're like
They're making
Buy custom
Bespoke defects
So it seems
Not
What's capitalism will find a way to exploit something super evil
Natural stuff
It was always going to end up being
Metabolism just like everything but
Yeah I think that
That normalizes it a little bit
This is like
What is the value of a
50 facts thinking about it like what's
What good does a deepfake bring what good could it bring
Hollywood uses deepfake all the time like they
The use of
To swap in like
Carrie Fisher in Star Wars and I think I got us kind of example are we to bring. But
It's always been like a big
Budget
Yeah
As far as like
The Greta Van also hardly seems like a good thing
Like that are definitely I mean they're not
They're definitely
Interesting and
Worth talking about
The gutter
Making them and improving the technology is
A lot of times just having these conversations and talking about
Things like
Temperature
Body autonomy online and
The guy who owns
Your face
So yeah just
As I
As a thought experiment
Good
I don't know good as I do
So weird working forecast
Telling that this technology really emerged
Interests
To exploit
Yeah exactly
Yeah that's kind of let me know it's kind of felons the Wayside as far as how we talked about the face
It's now it's a lot of like
Politicians and who will
Who will influence the election by using a deep fake butt
Angry singing There's a journalist in together
Does Target have ID fake and
Harbor Fallout 4 map
So yeah I think
It's still happening
All the issues around it as far as like who owns are images online
Things like revenge p***
What's up big issues outside of your face but do you guys going to bring some to the 4 or so
Yeah I guess it's a good outcome of this very fuzzy top
Well on that note it was good to have you in cyber again glad we weren't talking about PewDiePie
But we will probably have you on again to talk about
This week's episode was recorded in edited by Dean white produced by Lorenzo franceschi BK
And hosted by me Ben nakuu you'll be hearing from us next week