Eagle one package being delivered at smartphones become ubiquitous
Pageants in everyone's pockets and purses criminals just like the rest of us have moved online and behind them
The cops and feds followed earlier we showed you how sophisticated cybercriminals forget it
Some of the most prolific drug supplier used What's called the
According to a report last year cybercriminals stool 16.8 billion dollars and 30
Percent of us consumers were victims of a data breach and it's not just run-of-the-mill credit card or identity theft fraud
Terrorist extremist groups organized online drug dealers sell their products in hard to locate online markets
Criminals steal millions of dollars in cryptocurrency investors in high-profile Bitcoin
Authorities doing to stop them
Today we're talking to Elizabeth Roper the chief of the cyber crime Bureau in the Manhattan District Attorney's office
Roper's let investigations in dark web drug dealing
Sim hijacking and other cyber crimes
I'm been a coup and this is cyber
So thank you for coming down to the
Vice
Studios
Thank you for having me not often we get the government in here without By Invitation
So thank you
Well I have a lot of problems is a time so I
Thank you for coming in
Under these circumstance
So you obviously
Cybersecurity and hacking
It's kind of gone through this hole
Transition of the last 4 years
You know at one place
Really scary
Packers
Hoodies on in their pants
You know I think we're getting to a point where we're all
Accepting
Finally
That's cybersecurity and cybercrime
Is not something that's sci-fi
But it's a real thing and it actually happens
Now I guess what I want to ask you about is
How is that evolved the last
Decade in terms of the authorities in
Then your Tia's office actually looking at
Cyber crime and then also
Yeah sure so I think one interesting thing about
The perspective of our office meaning
A local Prosecutors office as opposed to a u.s. attorney's office the FBI
You know where our jurisdiction is is really Manhattan
Right and we work with a number of agencies we do some cases in-house we do some cases with the NYPD
We work we do work with Federal Partners often
Service
Homeland
Occasionally the FBI
But we're really a local office and so
When we
The cybercrime in when we talk about cybercrime
We're kind of seeing
Really every part of
Like the supply chain
In terms of the information that's being
Compromising kind of monetized
Via the Cyber Network
Mark Streit we're seeing
That kind of end users who are going into
Retail institutions in Manhattan
Financial institutions in Manhattan
And using for example
Identity theft victims
Social security number to open a bank account using
Credit card number to buy a MacBook
You know what have you
And then we also see obviously kind of the
Step up from that the recruiters were going out on Instagram who are
Recruiting people to engage in this kind of conduct
And I'm kind of on the other end of the spectrum
We're also working up the chain and seeing the more sophisticated cybercriminals
Who are operating
With a high degree of anonymity
Who are
Monetizing that information once it's been breached to a writing the malware that's responsible for the breach
So we're kind of looking at
This whole universe of people and and you're right
There is
Kind of a veneer of
Mystery and an anonymity particularly with respect to the more sophisticated actors in so
It's a it's a real challenge to unmasked
Funny when you say it's your very local in Manhattan
It's like when I think local police I think I'm from Orleans Ontario Canada
And I imagine that the Ottawa Police are not as such
Fisticated at this
As you are but also because you
Deal with
Everyone
I mean everyone comes to the city
Yeah that's exactly right I mean I saying
I think we do have a pretty sophisticated operation
Hello compressor
Computers office for sure
Part of that
Is you're exactly right Manhattan is a hub of Finance at the Hub of retail
It's a hub for Innovation so
You know we have a big Tech Community here
And with that comes
All the types of crime that are associated with
Those business
I think
Another kind of advantage that we have that we're lucky to have is that Manhattan
For the past several years has had really
Low violent crime
Our office has been able to focus a lot of resources on this particular threat right weave
We've really
The DEA
Has been really
Supportive
And kind of cutting-edge in terms of devoting resources to both the prosecution of cybercrime and also
The prevention of this kind of crime kind of recognizing that
A crime prevented is obviously a lot better than one process
You know you're you're within the government and you're seeing it from their perspective
And I often wonder is there sort of that generational change where it's no longer
Boomer generation of looking at the internet like the
It's very
Spectacular weird thing they don't really understand instead of seeing it as though this is dated at life
Cybercrime is
Simply just crime
And we all have to
Yeah I hope so I mean I think
One of the cool things about our office is you have a really multi-generational group of people you've got people who have been there for 40 years
And then you got people who are right out of Law School
And I think I'm on everyone there's certainly a recognition that
Quote unquote cyber is kind of
Apart of every case
It used to be the case that might be rowood
Filled every
Question a request having to do with anything that was sort of on the internet like
How do I go on to Facebook or how do I
You know investigate someone who's using email to
In in furtherance of criminal activity and I think now there's really a recognition that
That's such a fundamental part of every case
That we all kind of have to be
Literate
In that regard
And I think there is an increasing acceptance that just
These Technologies are here to stay and that's not a bad thing you know cryptocurrencies not a bad thing
You know iPhones aren't bad thing these are all just technologies that are kind of
Part of our everyday lives and have a lot of good applications and we just have to figure out
How to how to investigate crime in this new space
Does that ever ever have any those those moments where you want to go to the iPhone and you can't cuz
Let me try to do that recently
Somebody tried to do that
In our forensic lab
Does different digital forensics for the entire office
It's not just for my pierrot although they sit in my Bureau so I do get a lot of kind of visibility into what's coming into that lab
Increasingly I don't think this would be
Surprising
To anyone but it's increasingly mobile devices right we're getting fewer and fewer computers
More and more phones
Yeah sometimes they're lock sometimes it's hard to get into them
Is a fascinating new report out on how the FBI managed to crack into that iPhone of one of the San Bernardino shooters
Pain professional hacker
And that's
Yeah that's a challenge
For us it's one of
Many
Are you aware that you have to
Purchase any software in order to
Get access to those
Does phones or is it something you do in the house
So
I would say the bulk of our work is is done in-house right
But we also like I think most kind of
Larger law enforcement agencies use certain software sometimes
To get around you know to get into mobile devices
Obviously is always accompanied by
A court-ordered warrant or consent of the device's user
But yeah if in those circumstances we've gone to a judge we said hey there's probable cause to look in
Inside this phone
The judge says yes I agree
And we still can't get in
Then yeah sometimes will employ like one or more I guess
But you would call workarounds or software is to
To try to assess
Do you ever get any pushback From the Ashes
Tow companies themselves
Software
Devices
Well yeah I mean apple is obviously sort of
Been out there a lot saying we're not going to
SS
Lawn Force
And getting access to our devices
There's been a lot of back-and-forth over that
I think the reality is
They've kind of
Made their decisions with respect to how their
Technology is going to work and so we're kind of in the position of
Doing what we can to get that out of
Right when you're in the
Perspective of someone
Who trying to investigate a case
You're never going to just say oh there's this
Potential Treasure Trove of information that would help me can I get to the truth I'm just going to
Say oh well I can't look at it
That's so you're going to try
Obviously within the bounds
I know what you're authorized to do to to access
This scene is kind of a win-win in that way where Apple gets
Privacy first face and you guys get
Actually get
Beijing Yuan
I don't know I mean
This is
Just my opinion
I think
Look the Privacy aspect is obviously incredibly important
I think the downside is that you have
Companies making this decision
Write Caesar
Businesses that are making decisions for business reasons
Arguably
When the outcomes are really public policy outcome
In my mind be decided by lawmakers
And not by
Providence
And there is a giant debates
I mean I'm sure you probably get this question a lot but what is
What are the more
Crazy
Things you seen
In your Tanner
Yeah that's
That's an interesting question I mean
We've seen kind of
A whole range of things we handle a lot of
It's primarily kind of financially motivated
Cyber crime rate so identity theft bank fraud
We handle some kind of
Straight up cybercrime law
Online festive intellectual property or other
Data
We handle
Some online child exploitation cases
I'm some cyber stalking cases obviously
We both can be a little bit crazy
We had yesterday
Relatively large case announced
Where
My Bureau was able to identify and take down three New Jersey residents who are operating a pretty low
Scale narcotics operation
And that was a first for me because we don't
Typically in the cybercrime and identity theft Bureau prosecute a lot of
Big drug cases but this was a case where
These particular defendants
As it's alleged at least at the stage
Operating a darknet sort of storefront on the dream market and also a specific site
That was accessible via tor
To sell Alprazolam vs xanax
Academy in
And possibly some other controlled substances
And they were
You know using the anonymity sort of afforded by that technology
Accepting Bitcoin and then laundering the pros
Then it was via the money-laundering angle that we should have came into it
And were able to take down this pretty significant drug organ is
So how do you go about
Intercepting the evidence you need
In order to build this case I mean
Is this I'm assuming that you are not doing this I'm assuming that you've got a team of what
Forensic type
People that
Well then
Do you for you
Yes or Bureau
The bureau is supervised is actually a really dynamic
Group of people which is one of the things that allows us
Space
Obviously we have attorneys we have about a dozen attorneys who come with
You know different backgrounds themselves some of them are former narcotics prosecutor is summer former
Street crime prosecutors
But in addition to that we do have a forensic
Laba pretty state-of-the-art forensic lab that staffed by
About a dozen forensic technician
And those guys are really interval to the work that we do they're kind of like
The X-Men I think they're like each one of them has a different sort of specialty
Weather at
You know getting into encrypted devices or doing vehicle forensics
They're doing forensic
Exxon
You know
Android devices
Apple devices
That work is really important in terms of building these types
And then we also have a team of
Dedicated sworn investigator so essentially
Like detectives but people who works
Specifically for
The District Attorney's office
And they'll usually be the ones who do the kind of
Work that you're describing right like that
Val go online and conduct an undercover
Purchase of Contraband whether it's drugs
Identifying
And so that's typically how we
Get that information
The one burning question that I wanted to ask you and you
Personally I want your personal take on this
A bad decision your ad
So you get on the MTA
The New York Subway system
Do you log into the freeway
I would not login
The free Wi-Fi you would not want you would not log into the free Wi-Fi why is that
You know I'm not I'm not a technical person so I can't talk to the ins-and-outs of kind of cyber hygiene
Decision
I'm doing that versus not
I've just
Thin enough cases of
People being compromised to such a devastating
Affect
From the MK Wi-Fi so sorry
I totally cool
I hate it but got to go on
Yeah any any open wi-fi I'm just
Terrified of
You say no
How much I mean honestly cuz I think to myself too
Damara hotels here
How much are those
Targets
For cyber criminals in terms of
Clearly you're getting
Very International
Yolk line hell
Yeah
Those must be
Absolute Honeypot
Not that I didn't think that
Hotel wifi
Cleaners at the hotel
Hot tub
Right yeah I think that's probably
Analogy
We've seen yeah we've seen hotels being used
For that purpose
You know
Both
5 people looking to
Take advantage of the Open Wi-Fi and and
Conduct some kind of intrusion or learn information about a Target
And we've also seen it used
By criminals
Looking to kind of mask who they are and what they're doing
And that's probably more frequently what we encounter right we're trying to figure out what who was
Doing this bad Act
Using
The IP address of
Such-and-such busy
And so we're typically trying to kind of unravel the thread from that
New York to tell me who but
Has there ever been anything surrounding Trump Tower
We
Interesting question has there ever been anything surrounding from power we don't have any open investigations that
Right there was some cyber activity there I think sometime in 26
Waterfalls in your jurisdiction so I thought maybe
Yeah I know I think that that's a fascinating story
I've read a lot about it
But yeah we don't have anything Act
With respect to
Are you seeing any Trends right now that you see something that
People should be aware of
In terms of
Falling prey to cyber
Criminal within this city
That you say
Yeah I think
I think there are a number of things that are kind of trending right now in the in the
Cybercrime space
I mean you guys have covered the Sim swapping phenomenon I think and that's something that
We're certainly seeing a spike in
I used to get those complaints
You know years ago when people were doing
Sim swaps
Targeting kind of the OG handles or
You know traditional Financial
Again
But with the Advent of crypto and the increasing popularity of it increasing
Sort of legitimacy
Cryptocurrencies I think
We've seen a huge uptick
Infant slapping cases
You know partially because I think you have a lot of
People in Manhattan who are active in that space
And also just
The ease with which
It can be done and I think people to serve realizing that and and
Taking advantage of it
So that's something that makes me nervous just because it is such a devastating
And it's so easy to do
Another thing that
We see all the time that we're just getting inundated with our what people and kind of law enforcement called business email
Email compromise
Cases
So that's the type of fraud where
Someone well
Breach one or more email addresses
Within
Financial transaction or
A real estate transaction
Something like that
Belle learn enough about
The transaction that's happening
I just want to be able to socially engineer one or even both parties and
So for example you know if you're my real estate attorney and I'm about to buy a house
A fraudster might
Breach your account
Send me an email either directly from your account or from a spoofed
It looks like it and
You know kind of mimic your phrasing or
The end of the way that we typically correspond and say hey
The plan has changed instead of bringing a cashier's check to
To the closing just wire your down payment to this account
And
It happens a lot with businesses
But we've also seen it happen to individuals like in the real estate example and it can just be incredibly devastating because they're
Entirely wiped out
And unlike credit card fraud were typically you have some coverage from your
Credit card company
These are transactions that the victims are authorizing and so the banks
Typically won't
To never get that money back
I usually
Wow
Yeah so that's an incredibly
Problematic type of crime
We're seeing
Obviously New York City criminal syndicates are well known around the world
Various
Tattoos of Dave
How are they leveraging
Cybercrime
I'm thinking of the
Typical players
How do they use
At all
The typical players meeting so I'm thinking like cartels and thinking Italian mafia
Thinking
You know
The various
Communities of
Gangsters
Okay and how are they
Leveraging this
So I would say what we see is more chemistry crime organizations leveraging this
The staff so
We have a lot of
Defendants who are current or former gang members who
You know maybe even have long records for violent crime
Who suddenly will find themselves
Running an identity-theft organization and going on
Tour on two legs
Pescador jokerstash or one of these
Higher
Profile carding shops
Buying credit card numbers and sending people out
To use them
And I think there's been a realization
Among criminal organizations bad
This is a much lower exposure higher-value type of crime
To do and so that's something that we see a lot
I haven't seen
You know more kind of
Traditional organized crime
In the cybercrime space although
It wouldn't surprise me.
Going on
Missionary it sometimes you work with a national
Agency partner
Yeah
DHS
FBI unassuming Calaway CIA
Smother
And I said maybe
We don't really have
A national security folks
That's right so we're working
More more with
The law enforcement side of
Of things
So while NSA and CIA are focused on National Security issues primarily we're focused on
Traditional lawn for
And so
Crime that happens
Usually in the United States with that affects the United States and then can be prosecuted
I'm in the Uso
We haven't really work
Match with National Security
Organizations I mean our interests are
I don't want to say
Even necessarily aligned you know
We will sometimes share knowledge about you know oh did you like have you survived realize that this
To exists or you know this information is
This is kind of out there but
Typically know we're working with traditional on
Cuz I'm just thinking I mean this is New York City you have
So many people coming in and out
Including some of the members
Agencies
De autos
Yeah and also you know you have the UN here
Yep
Right
So you know that you didn't have the UN Summit every year
When
Traditional law enforcement lock
What's this city down
In such an insane way I can only imagine that
You
Somehow Havoc
Affection
You know what enters your orbit
When that happens
Since when you have UC
Jeep Summit
Is there any counter
Espionage counterintelligence or decide to
The work you do
No I mean we're not you know
Mayberry obviously we're s or a pretty sophisticated operation in
The cybercrime space
But no we're not doing
We're not doing Espionage cases we're not
Really looking at
State actors
We're not
Investigating
Any kind of like nation-state attacks
Or activity or anything like that
It's it's a lot more more traditional and buy traditional you know I don't mean unsophisticated Wheatley certainly
We prosecuted foreign Nationals who are
Conducting
Attacks are committing crimes that touch
New York City
But it's
Mostly financially motivated
Cybercrime right it's not
Espionage it's not politically motivated for the most part
It's usually what kind of Financial in
How did you get in
Did you think you were going to be
Doing
Cybercrime Giovanni background of that nothing I'm trying to you know
With all due respect I mean I'm not I have no technical I didn't
Take any computer science in University either
Yeah my friend
She didn't either
It's all right with the lawyer
The lamest
I call you guys vampires but lets you know what will play full play nice
We can talk about that later no I don't have a technical background at all
You know I
Majored in English in French
I came to the DA's office and
Starting out almost everyone handles kind of every type of
Crime that
That comes in and I personally found
The kind of complex Financial crimes and cyber crimes to
To be among the more interesting because they involved a lot of proactive investigation
As opposed to a street crime where they cannot come in the door and all the investigation is done
And you're just moving on to
To prosecute the case
So in my gyro we do
Kind of most of the
Work is upfront
Proactive investigative work so we're trying to kind of put together those puzzles and
The
You know if we can kind of put someone
As they say behind the keyboard or
Figure out kind of what the distribution network is with the money laundering that
And I just
Have I found that really interesting and have been really lucky that
Our office is incredibly so
Supportive of this kind of work and have gotten the opportunity to work on more and more kind of cool cases
In the space
Can you can you talk in Broad Strokes about some of the
Investigations you have going on right now
Yeah sure so
I think I mentioned that
We've seen kind of an uptick in Sim swapping and we have one active
Case that's
Been a little bit publicize where we had a a 20 year old Ohio man
Doing Sim swaps of Manhattan residents and others
As it's alleged in
In the complaint
Pick up a case is still pending
And we have a handful of other
Search similar investigations were Manhattan recipe
I've been targeted in
Similar scams
I could talk a little bit about
A few recent historical cases that are that are not active but that might be
Interesting
One case I think that illustrates was kind of like a breath of the context that we see was a case against
Originally 17 descendants
But only three of them went to trial the trial happened in 2000
It was a trial again
Well it was an indictment against a business called Western Express and then a number
Of people who were either employed by that business or used it
And this was in the days of
Pre cryptocurrency digital currency so things like e gold and webmoney
And Western Express was a business that
Essentially acted like an exchange for those
Digital currencies and you had people in the New York area
Who are using that business to
Hey
Carter's
In Ukraine and Russia
To get compromised credit card info
And then that money was being laundered
So we were able to identify and prosecute both
These kind of
Local people who were
Find this information and then using it you know to buy cars to buy
Clothes to buy whatever and install stuff on eBay and
Kind of enrich themselves
And then we were also able to identify and process
That kind of credit card with a called dumps vendor right who is selling
Credit card information
Online and in our case he had sold about a hundred thousand credit card numbers
That have been used fraudulently
And that person we were able to
To apprehend
And increase and extradite
New York and try and
So that's kind of an example of a think what I'm talking about is like
This whole ecosystem kind of
Converging
Manhattan
Yo it I mean I can I can imagine in
It's the nature crime rate at some point
International is going to end up in in Manhattan exactly was that was that a Greek national
He was a Ukrainian national
Who we had identified and we were able to learn that he was traveling to
And I think you see that a lot right people who are making a lot of money
Conducting cyber crime they want to
Have fun they want to spend the money they want to go on vacation
He was traveling to
Degrees
And we are able to work with
International authorities in federalist
Do you see a lot of
Actors in Ukraine kind of involved with cybercrime here in New York
Yeah so we have
Part of our Bureau
Is
The cybercrime
Intelligence unit and so that's a small but very specialized
The people who are conducting these really long-term proactive invest
Applications
Into
The types of criminals that I just
Describe right people who are traditionally overseas who are
You know kind of this Elite
Group of
Cyber criminals who are
Conducting breaches monetizing the information that's
Betaine VIP
Breeches
And
I don't want to say those
People are
Necessarily located in Eastern Europe
But they're all
Frequently
Russian-speaking
Until we found that that's a that's a skill that that's important to have
Because that has sort of
Emerged as like the language
Pitressin
That's said that
Governor that
Yeah
Are you saying Russian hackers have been in the news recently
I don't know I feel like I read that somewhere the latest in the DNC email scandal
Is that the FBI suspect the hack was perpetrated by Russian intelligence in an effort to elect Donald Trump
Forgiving SNL's McIntyre jokes about Russian hackers
Yeah I think it's it has been in the news recently for for the kind of
Splashy politically-motivated activity that we've been seeing but
From the perspective of a financially motivated activities
It's obviously
For a long time
So another sort of
Case where we saw this kind of convergence
Transnational and local cyber crime was a case where
StubHub have been breached and they they identified
Thousands of user accounts that have been victimized by account takeovers to essentially compromise passwords and usernames
I've been used to log in and take over
Thousands of users accounts
And purchase
Pic of using music
So either using
The stored credit card information that you have on file to Stubhub or using credit card information that have been stolen and some other
Either way
Millions of dollars of tickets
Were purchased
And then resold
And with the investigation found was that these local individuals were
Responsible for
Reselling the tickets
I'm at a much lower rate and kind of laundering the proceeds
But they were getting instructions and getting the tickets in the first place
From a Russian national
Who was actually conducting the account takeovers
The painting that compromised credentials conducting the account takeovers
Buying the tickets at kind of market value and then passing them along for resale
And the money was being laundered
In the United States
I'm in Canada in the UK
I'm in Germany and so that was actually a case that we collaborated both with
The city of London Police on with the RCMP in Canada
My best friend
Is that right
Yeah I know we're actually were in court together
I didn't get no like right now I got a court date
When this comes out
Albion Court
Wait were you the money launderer in Canada who is
Glad amazing at hacking
Really good at it
Yeah so that was that was another really
Cool example of
Working with International partners with local partners
To bring down not just the kind of end users of the information but the
The higher-value targets
It's right who are who are actually breaching
Accounts
The information
I could be mistaken
And my mind's a little fuzzy on this but I think the Mueller investigation
The team actually had
Somebody who was
Very proficient in
Investigating Russian cyber
I would believe so yeah cuz I think this has been my experience
Bleeding in from
Russian cyber crimes
Intelligence
What temperature would be
Tomorrow message
Yeah
Well thank you for
Coming down and speaking with us thanks so much for having me
This week's cyber was recorded and edited by Dean White
Produced by Lorenzo franceschi Bocelli and hosted by me