Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered imagine a world where I most critical instruments Adam
Democracy could be corrupted by hackers
Voting systems
On the internet
Malicious actors potentially manipulate
Potentially change computers
Are voting systems use for things like the presidential elections in 2016 and 2012 and ostensibly for
20/20 working on the internet
Unhackable
Meanwhile we've all been focused on the information Warfare emanating out of the Kremlin and what's going to happen to know them
Numbers from now I first would like to mention election security this has been and will continue
You to be a top priority for the intelligence community
We assess that foreign actors will view the 2020 us elections
As an opportunity to advance their interest broke the news that
Actually
Researchers found voting systems were online and these included systems in Wisconsin Michigan
In Florida all well known for being key swing States in presidential elections
We caught up with him to discuss her massive scoop
I've been a coup and this
Cyber
So can
You got a really massive scoop
Recently do you want to walk me through
What you found
I work with some researchers
Who had found for years
4 years of voting machine vendors and election officials
Have been telling the public
After mm
16 election
That voting machines and even more importantly of feedback and election manager
The program buddy machine
Are never connected to the internet
Have never been
Or never
And researchers found that that's not the case we already we already knew that voting machines are
Motivating in transmitting boats
On Election night and said that modem transmission
Is an internet connection
And these researchers decided to try and
See if they could find those
I'm systems online that are actually receiving the boats that are being transmitted
And I did
They found the servicer outside the firewalls Cisco firewalls
They
Are developed a footprint for what these machines look like on the internet behind that firewall
And then they did searches and they found $35
System is Aaron in 10 states
So in essence you found out that
Diesel
Machines are actually on the internet and
Acceptable
Attack
Yeah I mean
This is kind of the Holy Grail
Election Integrity because the
People who have been trying to get attention to this issue over and over again
About the hackability of machines and everything
They're dismissed constantly because they're told over and over again while the machines aren't connects the internet's they're not hacking
And that's the Resurgence it comes to voters as well before every election
We keep these machines off the internet
So
Arriving to this point
Finally
After two decades of them saying this and getting evidence that yes indeed they are
It was
Really significant and also a bit of
I can't climax because it turns out
The Buddy machine Gunderson advertising this all along
When I start to look at contracts and the researchers found some schematics
That the body machine vendors had submitted with the request for proposals when they're getting contracts
It turns out it's right there in the Emmys contract it shows diagrams
Of these machines connected to the internet through a firewall
So
Remarkably no one was talking about it before
And then
You know I am remarkably while they have that in their literature
Literature that they're literally giving to election officials
They're also telling election officials
Really remark
Why did they lie then why did they say there's no way this is
Events in their mind are not lying what they're what they're saying is that it's part of the
I'll give him the benefit of the doubt that they had it but they don't understand the technology
Very generous
But it's allowed them to
Tell election officials that
If it's behind a firewall their interpretation is
It's not directly accessible
If you got that fire one friend
And so therefore it's not on
The Intern
If I had said what we have something in front of the sea
This time it is on the internet we have something in front of the system that protecting it
That's still problematic because how secure is that thing that you got in front how secure is a firewall
But it would have been more honest
Right
Instead they were saying no no these systems aren't even allowed or permitted on the internet and we would never put them on the Internet and they're not
Not on the internet
And that's
Something that's very dishonest
Representation of what what it is
I want to point out these vendors are the ones installing this
So they're not it's not like they're giving them to the
Election officials and then they don't know what they like
The doing
They install them on the inner
I mean that said election officials have
They need to make sure
It happens I mean
Look back
The 2016 election
I'm in a lot of things that people said were
Hacking
Was really disinformation
But this is a case where you have 35 devices on the internet
Some of them in swing States
That that actually can be meddled with
It's sort of shift our Focus.
4 years doesn't it
What really happened in 2000
We don't
You know what
If we looked at 2016 everyone said there's no evidence that any Boats were
I manipulated
No evidence of any voting machines were hacked
We know that there's no way to know that because no one ever actually different examination
I'm not saying
Machine for hair
Are manipulators
But
We were told a certain scenario
In mm
We were told a certain scenario in 2017 and 18 and 19 the machines aren't connected to the internet
Now we understand
But there was an entirely different scenario happen
In the summer of 2002
16 when Russian hackers were getting into
Voter registration databases and trying to get into
Campaign offices in NC
These voting machines were on the internet
And that changes everything now
I mean I completely agree with you and also just looking forward to 20/20 vision how
We just found this out
You broke this
And maybe there's more
Maybe some of these machines were manipulated you're right
I'm so not prepared either to say it happened because you just don't know if you have the evidence
Russian intelligence was behind the DNC hack
Incident is Raising questions about the security of our country's overall
Pectoral system
Voting booths are voting tallies themselves
Be vulnerable
20 20 I mean
What's the temperature in makes me think
What is possible
The problem going forward in 2020
There's been no friends
Examination
If something happened in all these years that they've been sitting there
We won't know
Because no one is looking at them
So it's not just taking machines off the internet now and saying okay
Now we're good
We don't know what's already on the machine
And that's the problem
And no one is looking
No one seems to
Care to look
So we can say okay we caught the problem
Right machines are now
The researchers think I'm coming down after this
But that doesn't tell us what damage was already done if if any damage was
And so going into 2020 we're still in the same situation we were
10 mm
Where we really don't have a clear view of what the
What state of vulnerability we really are at
Bea systems
You know where they remotely accessible by an attacker and could be
Say
Remotely affected them from thousands of miles away
Potentially it really depends on whether or not what what kind of effect they had depends on what they did or what they might
I have done
But also what district is was so we have
Different kinds of voting machines everywhere
And so if they got into a counties machines
Optical scan machine
Rebecca paper ballot write-in so
The problem there is that most jurisdictions don't do improper audits
Even if you have that paper back at
They don't even look at it
Or they do an audit but it's an insufficient audit
So if someone has gotten into machines
If someone gets into machines in 2020
That's why paper ballots are so important that's why audits risk limiting audit or so important
That's the only mechanism that we have the most
The only reasonable mechanism that we have right now cuz we don't do forensics
To know if something went wrong
You know
We describe their almost sounds like
If they did get high
What's wrong if they have that
Elsafe
It have to know that they got hacked and then do a review that if it didn't know they were they wouldn't even do it with that
Books about the problem right now with the auditing laws
There needs to be mandatory audit laws
There are some states now that have audit laws but those the audits are insufficient
Federal legislation
To force the states to do risk limiting audit
Take it out of the hands of
You know
Losing candidates cuz that's usually what happens when someone challenges them election
Take that out d politicize it
Make it so that it's mandatory every election has this kind of audit
I'm not the kind of thing that will
Catching anole
You don't wait for
A problem evidence of a problem to go look for evidence right
You just
You do this routinely and then if something pops up there you have
For further investigation
Do you think
That going forward there will be enough done by the US government to
Security systems come 20/20
I think the
We don't have enough time for 20
I mean
One thing was remarkable for me with the story this week
Set the adjust been working with election officials
Mm
16 three years now and it's taken him some time to get up to speed and get the trust of them
But for 3 years now they've been telling us that these systems are getting better that they're doing more work that we're improving security and all that
And yet
The most basic sing the most basic
Problem that we have an election would be
A critical election system connects to the internet and they didn't catch that
So
No
We're not ready for 2028
Do you think we should just go to the paper ballot completely across-the-board I mean is there anything we can do
This is not a problem having a software review the ballot
The problem is is that you know if you never look at the paper
You can't just trust the software you have to have a backup
When you do banking you get a receipt from the ATM right that's your backup
If you could see your bank statement and it shows that you didn't put money in but you've got the receipt saying that you did that's your back
That's why it's so important in elections that you have that back up
Not that the butter takes away with it from the with them
From the polling place but that you have that back up and that you require
Election officials texting look at the backup
So do you think that this is probably a bigger threat than some kind of
Rogue fake Naga this information Facebook account or group that's going out there and spreading misinformation
Listen to us
Targeting grouper
I mean
Voting machines themselves
It's kind of easier attack
Because what you're doing this information you don't know if sexually
Influencing anyone right
People are unpredictable
Did you really hack their mind
With a voting machine if you can do it if you can get in you know if you hacked it it's
Pretty
Haircut black and white
And there
Years of
Years of training at hacking right so
If they put their efforts at it yes
Quit Suburban election easy Rising
Possibly then disinformation campaigns
I wrote the story.
Panther release
Brighten picture for 2020
When is already election a lot of people are
Duke the country is polarized to think that the actual systems we use
AR
In trouble
I mean
There's no other store like
Underpin that more
I agree with you I think that it's a shame that we don't really pay attention to this in off
Election years
It's only when we start to get a campaign and everyone is
I'm aware again oh yeah this is election season that people take this seriously
But it doesn't really matter if matters that they are taking it serious
I'd like to say that I think I think God for the Russians
There hasn't been a lot of squabbling what we've simply said is
The facts
Which are that
Based on
Uniform
Intelligence assessments the Russians were responsible for hacking
The DNC
I've been covering the election stuff since 2003-2004 and getting people to pay attention to it is it's it's been an effort
And all it took was the Russian stinging somebody registration databases
I'm also happy in the DNC
I'm not I'm not going to make light of any of this
Doing that really put this issue on the table in a way that is
Pokemon I'd say that you know
The emergence of
Casting journalist you're not going to get another store
Freak me out but Jen's that'll happen again before 20/20 hamster
Yeah it probably will
I wish it would be like this
Is
Importance and its
You know it
It underpins why why I do this why I spent two decades doing this to uncover something like this
So we have Jason Capel here yeah I see if motherboard to talk
A little about a
The last week's Roundup of cybersecurity news
So
One story or one sorcerer that one
Hi like it's been amazing
And I know it's been
She's been getting tons of
Respect in Cypress
Caroline Haskins has been doing some great
Reporting on ring
Tell me about it
Yeah so bring is Amazon's
Home security surveillance
Camera company
And over the last few months we've been reporting a bunch of stories based on public records that Caroline has foil
Read from local cities all over the country
About Rings Partnerships with
Police
So we've learned all sorts of crazy things like
Police can access
Ring videos with
Without a warrant they can just like asked
People in
You know they can
Get footage from people's homes
Just by asking for it
They have been so encouraged by Amazon
Ring 2
Post light
Crime alerts on this app called Neighbors that integrates with ring
They have also done this
Really
I think crazy
Thing where at
They've used taxpayer money to subsidize the purchase of ring cameras
So it's like
Ring will offer $100 disc
Count to
Consumers and then the city will
Literally sell them to the consumers
High-end
Ring pics
$50 off
Find the city of subsidizing the purchase of
Private surveillance
Cameras that they are then using as a
Ceramics Network
They're also doing things like requiring that cities and police
Apartments that work with Ring 2
Run
Through like all the press release language
Before they send it out
They're requiring them to literally advertise these things it's just like it's a really
Creepy and sketchy
The thing that's happened
Yeti stories
They completely just made me think that Amazon is
Literally taking over
American cities it's a shadow economy
Is Shadow drop shadow government Shadow infrastructure Shadow economy
It's like
Amazon has done sting operations with police forces where they put like a
GPS tracker in an Amazon box
And the Nae Nae
Partner with people who own ring devices
To surveil
Surveil their porches and
See if anyone steals them
So I mean
I think we're still like sussing out what the
The endgame is here but it seems that Amazon is trying to protect
Psych package delivery service by putting a camera
On the porch of every
Man woman and child home
In America
Well like every Great American Monopoly just becomes part of the
And speaking of another
American
Monopoly Monopoly
Gargantuan American
Tech company
We got a memo
From Google
Last week when I tell me what is about
Yeah we have got to Memos from Google in the last few weeks
That one was written by a woman who said that
Company was
Discriminated against
Her while she
Is pregnant
And
Did she is title like why I'm not returning to Google after my
Maternity leave
And it was like maybe this 3000 word memo that she
Descent 2
You know a few different internal listservs there and it went viral more than 10,000
Messiah before
Publish the article and
I'm sure more people
Now just be
A lot of people read that article
And it's basically just saying like
This is not a very good place
To work as a
Is a woman
I had I got a lot of snide comments while I was pregnant
You know I was taken from a leadership and management role and was
Play into
A non management role even though I had you
Perfect reviews and it stopped that love me and that's worth
Nothing
And yeah that went viral within the company and then
Last week we publish another memo written by
A black and
Employee forum
Employer
Google who's
Eat a little bit
About why he left
And he's he called it
The burden of being black at
And mentioned
The fact that
You know his colleagues were willing to talk about current events and
And had all these really strong a
Opinions on like politics and
You know Warriors and all these other things but then when it came to issues like police
Brutality
You know the death of
Eric Garner at the hands of
If you know the nyp
PGE
No one
Saturday thing
And then he started back setup with
Just mentioning that you know his
Collies were making fun of immigrants and making fun of
Aynax ensign
Stuff like that so
And it wasn't just that they weren't willing to speak
Stop it was also that there were
You know some
Overt
There is some over racism that he
Experience as an imp
Employee at Google
Don't be evil
Let's talk about
Apple
Any iPhone
Yeah let's hit all its head all the big
If you want to do the big five we can do it
So Apple
Apple
Sued this company called corellium which is a
I believe it's an Australian company but
It may not be
This is Lorenzo's domain I'm just
What is editor
That basically creates virtualization software for iOS so they are
Gripping the software from iPhones
Sandra creating it on
Computers so that's
Security researcher
Can probe it
And this is really helpful for
For people who wants
To try to hack
And fine
I found zero days
Another exploit
And Apple
Is suing that company for bass
Copyright infringe
And this is
Big deal because
Black hat
Earlier this month Apple announced that it was going to be giving out
Hotstar likes
Security
Researcher Deftones
Two people who could then try to probe
The iPhone in Find 0 days and it also announced it is greatly expanding its bug Bounty program
So they're basically saying like we're going to make it easier for researchers
To try to probe the iPhone so they can find vulnerabilities
And then
You know a week and a half later they're suing one
The company that makes one of the most important
Diet research
Earlier this week it was discovered that
Apple made one up like a hilarious f****** a really bad one
Where they unpatched vulnerability that
They had previously patched
So they're on iOS
Stop for right now and on iOS
12. 3 day fix a bunch of vulnerabilities that Google headphone
In the iPhone
And then in 12.4 they unpatched one of them want to ask
And they still haven't fixed this a recording it like I don't know
3 days after this has been discovered
I'll probably be fixed by the
Time is it
But for the first time in years
Someone has released a full
Jailbreak for an iPhone
For free to the public
Unless you stopping like all the time in the early
Mm
Because
People are finding bugs in the eye
All the time
But now because vulnerabilities in the eye
IPhone art worth so much
How much money
People are holding those very close to
The chaste because they're not going to lie
Published
Vulnerability in the iPhone
They can sell for $1000000 to
USA or whatever
So
Yeah this f****** is so bad that
Set security reset
She's like well they're going to fix it a day anyway here's the jailbreak
You can now jailbreak your iPhone
For the first time in years
Crazy
Skype
Listening to
Phone calls
Skype with listing of phone calls
The translation service
Contractors at Microsoft were listening to like if using Skype
Translate calls
They were doing
What Microsoft is calling machine learning which is better known in the real world as
People and Idea Center somewhere where
Underpaid and listening to it and making
Ensure that the tree
Nations were cracked
We also learn that they're doing this
Cortana
Come out and resend
Recent months
Facebook has been doing this
Google has been doing this
Microsoft isn't doing this so it's not a huge surprise but we talked
Custom contractors
Who have a
Been listening to both
Skype Cortana and finally
Today
We found out there listen to Xbox voice commands
Cell
The great thing about this Roundup is
Just a round up of all the
The Terrible Things
Yeah and then still do we have Facebook face
Could be the last
Yasso Facebook
It was found that the Chinese government was putting
Is there a bike anti Hong Kong propaganda on Facebook in the same way that
The Russian government did in the lead-up to
The 26
16 election Facebook seemingly caught it quickly and took it down Twitter was actually allowing China to
To promote this stuff
Crazy
I'm an Instagram announced a bug bounty
For malicious 3rd party
So that's a
That's another story that we wrote
Small news but we got to hit all the big companies so there you go
And that
Has been
The Round Up this week's episode with edited
Forged by Brian Arnold posted and produced by me that not too you will hear from us next