Eagle one package being delivered
We talked a lot about spies and now we're as much as I like talking to are very prolific motherboard
Who else better to talk spicy about the intelligence industrial complex than our next
Breaking news this evening is the identity of the man who sent the Obama Administration in to defend and explain mode this
His name is Edward Snowden
Think they're going to say I've committed grave crimes on a feudal violated the Espionage Act
They're going to say you know I 5/8 in our enemies in 2013
Edward Snowden hillford thousands of top-secret documents from the NSA and its spy partners then fled to honk
Kong-rey gave them to chew journalist
The rest as they say
Was the nsa's worst nightmare
But from those weeks and countless lives we citizens of the world
Got to see for ourselves what modern Master villains tree look like
6 years later
She's now living in Moscow after the Russian government granted and political Asylum from there's none started working
With the freedom of the press Foundation
Sometimes tweets about the news
Today we got Snowden to log on to encrypted chat app to talk about his life in Russia his thoughts on the arrested
WikiLeaks founder Julian Assange the state of press freedom in the United States and around the world and the charm offensive
I spy agencies such as the NSA his British counterpart gchq
And this
Is cyber well thanks for coming on Cyber
I was told I can call you at that show
I guess I'll
My mom calls me Benny but I think we should probably just
Yeah that.
Sexy
I want to know
It's almost six years
Who is the month
Lejeune right
Century hosiery
How does it feel to die
Expect UD
Where you are in Moscow right now
No I mean it it's funny because you know
I just sort of growing up in the intelligence
Russia is justice
Terrifying
Place you know it's it's it's Mordor
I'm and I hadn't worked Russia's at Target I had worked East Asia
Am I operation
Buffets
You know I had a little bit of familiarity
I would like Japanese
Mandarin Chinese
But I've never used Russians
Understand anything about it and you know I never planned to be in Russia
I've been when I was leaving Hong Kong
En route to Ecuador ironically enough
Captain Russia
And the funny thing is you know
I had always worked
Overseas whenever I get the chance
I was stationed in Switzerland
You're up and then I
Stationed outside Tokyo with an Air Force Base
Imentor
Living overseas wasn't surprised me it wasn't unusual but
Russia was definitely definitely the biggest and most unexpected
Gabrielle paderewski
I've been in the hospital
Because all my work in my contacts
English
It's not as good as it should
So I mean
One question people ask me when I said I was interview
They want to know what are you do today I mean I'm assuming you're not cooking spaghetti with your girlfriend all day anymore
Looking for my all day
We live together I'm and it's it's it's actually really nice
You know I expected
Life was going to be a lot harder
You know I expected end up in Guantanamo
And so life has actually become quite normal
Majority of my life
I is my work at the freedom the press found a
I'm where I'm done
The president of the
Are there
And we work on technology
Basically to make the
Justice
Effective
Day-to-day work of Journalism
A little bit easier a little bit safer a little bit more secure because it's becoming so much more difficult
Journalist
Are being treated
Increasingly as legitimate Target
It's right for all these different foreign intelligence agencies
For all of these authoritarian regimes
I increasingly
That we've seen even just for Corporation
If you look at the even academic researchers
Such as in the case of
Are you have these groups like Black Cube that are being hired by you know who knows like he was a private intelligence
And they're going after
Akademiks
Journalist
I even people at think tanks and general policy circles
I'm in Tinder trying to get them to say something
It would be incriminating
I so they can discredit their reporting or their research
I'm in insulting the question comes in what do we do about this what can we do
About this
And how do we avoid
I'm unfortunately the the direction that we're headed in
Which is
An arms race
Between Ordinary People and ordinary journalists and Order academics
And he's very well-read
Operations
Governments
Because we're going to lose
Right but if it's a fight that we haven't asked for us to bite that we have
There's no choice between gauging that we're going to have to do our best
That takes a lot of time
So when you were inside the intelligence community did you ever see
What's say something like the NSA targeting journalists
Yeah actually this was publicly reported in some of the stories that came out post 2013
I'm particularly journalist
Saw in the Middle East were like Al Jazeera
Right because this is one of the dangers it is when a government starts to feel like they can decide
Who is is not journalist
Too short
And deserves the journalistic protection right
I'm in ultimately that that comes down to meaning
You know are you American
Or do you work for one of the
Largest
Signs for the most privileged
Best Western
If that's not the case right they'll find an excuse to the Fine adjust Geisha that they simply won't even ask her consider it
I know go look this person's work
To us from our perspective as spies
Has what we call
Foreign intelligence
Value
Neither report
So go ahead
You know
I'm always being active journalist and and motherboard is a lot of
A lot of work that I know governments would be interested in
Me my respect is always
All I can do is slow them down because if they really want it they're going to get it so I have to be able to just sort of
Sandboxes much
Impossible
An order
Yeah
Maybe by the time I get to it it doesn't matter anymore
Well
It's a yes or no
I mean that that's partially true but the idea that you can't do any
The idea that you can't keep yourself from being hacked
I'm he's actually not true
I'm the question is
Who can you stop from behind how long can you stop them from hacking you
At what level of resourcing and budget and Manpower
Are they going to have to allocate again
You
Is an individual Target with all of your different precautions
To get what they react
If you use a stock iPhone and use stock apps and everything like that
I they can get you my pretty easily nowadays
Unfortunately every swerve iPhone
Is is running an apple iMessage underneath it
I'm at and that's why we're finding tremendously long
And that's not the case that we thought in the past
Is the encryption that uses is quite good
But what happens if this means basically the Apple ecosystem
Islamic
Which means every
IPhone I has you're not the same operating
Because people are actually catching which is a good thing we want people to be up to
Today topless
But it also has a stained stock Suite of apps
I just got the same sort of firmwares got all of these hidden programs that are running on every phone that you don't interact with
My databases
And this is true whether using Android or Apple's IOS
But the problem is with Android it is with blessing a curse
Androids
Catching
Sort of
Landscape
Is an absolute disaster
Because all these manufacturers
They pray these phones they sell these phones and then two or three years later they've banned
The people who actually
Provide the
Software right
Is running on the very low level of your phone
These are the things that are controlling like the
The radios
Connect to cell phone towers or
Wi-Fi hotspots right there on all the time
I'm the basic features of the phone
These can't
B
Updated
Stop by the actual
Own Bender
They have to be updated by the chipset vendor people like Qualcomm rights and nobody's the average people have
Herd of Qualcomm
But they make the chips right like Intel makes them for laps
Anywhere describing to is is like
Target
As welfare agencies
All these bands all these things are exploitable
Target surface
Stats on these phones
And for Android
It's not being patched which is a disaster for older phones because everybody's vulnerable
But at the same time because it's not a monoculture every phone is broken and slightly different way
Pinstripe
Isis actually quite difficult for these exploit vendors to have a universal X
The works against any Android phone
Women are from different
I so it's hard to get for the skeleton
Where is what we found is Apple's taking security quite seriously
I'm an event much better about privacy for example in Google
Because every phone is running the same software
Increasing watch juicier Target
For these now private companies that are operating out of places like Israel in French
And
They hire all of these guys called exploit Veil
Calipers right which are basically just reverse engineers
We use there their powers for evil
To look at the phone
And just attack
And see if they can find something
The breaks
In a predictable way and I'm usually when they do something basic something fundamental that every phone
Has to do in order to function
Like
Accept SMS message
And this is what I message does an iPhone
So what they done if they found ways to basically send evil SMS
IPhone
And this will then load
The arbitrary
Write code that is written by the attacker
I despise by these corporate intelligence agencies whatever
I'm by Fu Nobody by the Saudis in the case of
I swear Jamal khashoggi
Circle of contacts
And this will allow them to take over your phone to the point that
You know you carry around
In your pocket
You paid for it
A Benelli attacker they own it
I can turn the camera on they can turn the microphone off
I can get all of your contacts and yet everything that you saved all of your
Messages of a file that's on the phone and they can take it back home and they can get constant updates whatever's on the screen you know they can
Screenshot of it anytime
And they can see what you were doing in this the new state of play
And until we see apple really pick up the pace here to harden
On these basic functions hopefully the new iOS
I'm in really change the way I message horses
Stop incoming text
This is going to be an ongoing problem and it's really dangerous
Apple iPhones reviews
Basically by everybody
Journalism in journalism and in government and policy right
Kind of Rich they seem to like iPhones
Speaking of press Freedom there's something that's happened recently in the news
Was Jonas songs which I know a lot of
People
Immediately thought of you as well cuz you know it
As you are you're in Asylum right now
Julian Assange the founder of the anti-secrecy organization WikiLeaks
Was arrested this morning in London
7 years after taking refuge in an embassy there
The United States will seek his extradition on federal charges unsealed this morning
In connection with an enormous League of American intelligence nearly a decade ago
What was your perspective on
How
The US media has been dealing with this situation in particular and
How do you think this affects
Press freedom
I mean I I think it's really disheartening to see this happen
Number
When someone when you look at the timeline
Behind
Chisme Ecuador's decision
To revoke a sign
From Julian Assange in the first place
They got a loan from the IMF for some ridiculous amount
4.2 billion dollars
At one month
Before they they
I'm ended the week after
Julian has been kicked out of the embassy right and taking off to prison
For all his work
With the Chelsea Manning disclosures back
We have Ecuador's president going to the United States
So to get a pat on the back and you don't nice
Job
15 years
Journalists who've been covering the store that you aren't really looking at that
Because Julian I'm as an individual is it such a tragic
Sloth
Figure out me before and I still don't agree with what's been happening to him
So for people who have been phone cases
It is really unusual because when people think of
A Julian Assange and you know a lot of Americans now hate you
And even though
People who are on the center to the left part of the spectrum
I have been singing his Praises during the Bush Administration
Now they're on the other side because
Political choice
Election
But his is journalism right though
It is quite difficult
I think criticized because it look when you talk about
The emails that played such a big story in that
Election cycle
These were reported on by basically every major
Everybody
This wasn't just a weekly leaks
The New York Times Washington Post Der Spiegel
Everybody
Cupboard
Because it was a profound
Publican
It wasn't even a question these words for the hidden workings of power in the story said things like
The DNC right
At the core of the democratic
Formal Democratic party infrastructure
I had sort of a lined in secret to rig the primary against Bernie Sanders
And it's not that you don't no one imagined that was possible a lot of people believed
I thought that was the case but no one could actually
Prove it
Right now until you have some kind of documentation
And this this is the kind of thing we're like
Regardless of whether you like it or not
Disagree with the election
Journalists are not supposed to throw in
It's the sort of one side and I think this is one of the criticism
Is people rightfully see him as very much against
Because they have a history
It's so difficult to see how they can justify this charge at this moment
In the absence of what is
Obvious which is that the political winds
Turned against Julian Assange is an individual
He's very much disliked
And that makes it very unpopular.
Temperature last very much need to sort of
Hold their nose and do this even though they don't like the guy personally
I'm because if you say that the entanglement
Status causes and the problems it creates
Because when you look at this chart
What the government has actually charged
It's something that has been publicly known for nearly a decade
I'm the chat logs of the sort of famous Exchange
Between Chelsea Manning
Who was the source of the
Clojure
And someone who is alleged to be joining a van but was actually using a secure an anonymous messenger
Call jabber using
Protocol come off the Record
Actually supposed to provide a capabilities
It's trivial to forge these chat logs
But anyway putting putting that aside
You even if you believe this is a Smoking Gun it says you know Chelsea Manning and Julian Assange in the foyer
Lawyer with the candlestick
The crime that their alleged
That they're alleging happened
Is Chelsea Manning
I took what it's called a password
Which is basically just that end in coded
I'm other password
So it's not just you know
Written on a hard drive like you know
You know you don't have
Kitty mittens written anywhere on the hard drive is stuck
To be able to reverse that
By attacking it by breaking its reveal what the actual password is she can use
This was provided by Manning to this person is alleged abuse on
I'm in this person said you know hey I'll take a look at it I'll pass this to my guy who knows something about it
They'll attack and we'll see if we can get in
Right
According to the FBI they're not even sure if it happened
No no no no no that was an affidavit
They actually say that it did not happen
I did directly say look they did forensics
On Manning system that this was pulled for
Are the hash was for a service
Program to use
For an FTP program
I heard it was not logged into right so they they had not actually succeeded in breaking
They had not used it
But the government is alleging
Just the sheer fact the mini said hey can you find out what this password is
And if you can give it back to me
You know it is not even release on Jazz idea from that the chat log
I am the DJ is going to look
You know this is a crime where to charge it just the
They call it a password cracking a green
Which is enough
Is enough to indict someone
Right right even if it's not used to it to get access to more classified material
I am the government says they believed it was only used
At the store cover Manning's track many didn't want to be logging in with like
Username Chelsea Manning right and doing whatever so they wanted to use the swerve Anonymous account
To do it
Cheers
Here's why I think this is such a problem
What we have
Is an allegation from the doj
Julian Assange was a
Part of a conspiracy
To break a law
Right and this is actually when you think about the wall right this is actually a pretty low-level infraction
Relative to the things the scientific you stuff in his life
Yeah
And then
Even though they're saying they have conspired to break this law
It didn't actually happen
For whatever reason
Fake because of incompetence whatever reason
They weren't successful in actually committing the crime but the conspiracies enough now
There's another big story in the news right now you might have heard
Call the Mueller report
I was about to ask your take on it
Right until the meeting of the Mueller report is so you know there's two big parts of it as I understand and I have already
12 hours at least we
Vice news Reddit all in one shot and I think of Mac broadcast
Pretty liars
And I'm about it
Actually read the whole thing
The broad outlines are pretty well agreed on
The few people I suppose you have read this and you know
Analyzing it for the rest of us normal
And so they said the report breaks down into two parts
What is a sort of the Russian side right which is about
Russian electoral interference which is basically
Like trolls
Posting stupid Facebook ads and like bad memes on Twitter
To try to change boats you know but
They had like a low-budget they didn't reach out that much but like every definitely trying is what the reporter
But they can't sort of
And that's a true
Okay whatever
Then the other side is the sort of hacking and leaking thing where they're saying look the emails from 2016
Our source by their Legend Russian military
Very intelligent
Another thing this was passed after Wikileaks what's interesting about this
It's not charging with this
The government saying you know they don't have any evidence the weekend things to do
It was Russian military intelligence
What's the time
Russian military intelligence got it but they sent it to WikiLeaks WikiLeaks
I'm bringing the campfire connections Trump so they like alright well you know it it sucks nobody likes and but
We can't name them
But then there's this whole second half of the report
Are entirely separate crime
Right which is the crime of obstruction
I'm in on this side
The special counsel
10 separate instances
I think
I'm weird appears that Trump or people in his administration
I'm are basically
Conspiring to obstruct Justice
What
Are the special counsel does not conclude again like pin this to Trump
Is breaking the law
It is very interesting way given the context of what we talked about
They look
Trump absolutely ordered all these people in for his for a free to shut down right
Fire Mueller he tried to get rid of
And all these other people can't remember was sessions whatever
But he tried and he told like his White House counsel he told all these guys
You know stop
The scary time for talk to me you know I shut this thing down
Which is obviously
Obstruction
Or at least
Conspiracy to commit
Obstruction
But
It didn't actually result in a UPS truck
Because the people that
Trump order to do this simply ignore
They went off and they told their buddies like Trump is telling me to do crazy things
I'm turn my resignation letter all of these other things
And so
They say you know Donald Trump didn't actually commit obstruction
And so we're not going to charge
Maybe
There's something in here that Congress wants to bring her whatever but we're not going to
Any attorney general immediately when he saw this
You know who Jesus really sort of carrying water for Trump all over all day long on this issue and oh my God
Right right he's like you know spinning the reports doing all these things like what we see this and you know
A mother didn't charge this we're not going to charge this you know extraction no collusion whatever
Let's move on
Isn't that interesting
Right
The DJ's defense of not charging Trump
This case is they say look he tried to commit a crime but he's too haplessness failed
To actually do
And the same time they're charging you in a song
Under precisely the opposite Theory
Julian may not have actually crack the password we don't have any evidence that
We're going to say something that the agreement
So this is a real question the two-tiered system of justice why do we have this double standard here where do the president and you try
You can skate right but if you're a journalist of your publisher
Particular who's vulnerable because you gone too far out on a limb and now you've lost Outlook support popular theories against you
No one
No one can argue
At the work that you've done in the past
Hasn't been
Of real publican
Right it may not have been
Right
But the newspapers are all running the story
These are important
Where's right these are about
Real centers of power in the world
Why is it the journalists are being held to higher standard of
Behavior
The president
Well actually I was I wanted to ask you that cuz it's something I keep noticing online
Is that there's various intelligence
People are people who are ex-intelligence
Who just died
Openly
Hate both
You and Julian Assange
With the fire of a thousand burning Suns
If it is interesting to me too because these detective also become popularized during this Mueller report
And if you look back
In 2013
When you made your disclosures
The NSA had a well-documented problem recruiting
Yeah but now
What I find really wild
Is we look online on Instagram and like gchq has an Instagram account the CIA
Is tweeting pictures of puppies
Like
What the f*** is going on
When was the school
When did we when did we decide our intelligence agencies can do this
I think you see what's happened here the intelligence
Agencies have drawn the
Conclusion
At least from public perspective from
The backlash
13 right
In 2013
Intelligence
Around the anglophone developed-world right the US
UK Canada Australia
I would call the five eyes
Inspired to create a secret system of mass
Performing
What kind of Bolt
Collection
Likes to call this the phrase
Which means selecting records on all of our
Patience right you know people listening to this podcast right now going website
Ordering something from Amazon sending me mail
I look at you know whatever you doing
If it's going across the Big K
Strike the big back
Everybody's Cafe
What do you like it or not
It is getting what we call ingested
Intersystems
On the Run by the intelligent
Interesting parse Broken Out In Session eyes 2 pack
All these things so they can chop up your communication with everybody else's communication
And search through them
Interesting
What's a your credit card numbers on the list
Phone numbers always
You're not always that all right
But you send an email
And you mention a name someone who is
I'm but it actually happened
Things go through
Answer this giants live in an analyst
Like me sitting Hawaii
Are able to parse through this right and you can type anything in the world in anybody's email address anybody's anything
And it pops up on your screen
I'm innocent when this happened
Everybody me we was like look this is a violation of at least
The US Constitution's Fourth Amendment
We actually had
Swervo
The US
District Court
Kiehl's
A rule that not only were these programs unlawful
I bet they were likely unconstitutional on the basis that means even the Congress tries to change the statute
McCants
Flush the case
I'm and they flushed
The program 2
Try to save
This larger practice
And in the Wake doing
Write this sort of damage control
They went maybe the real story 2013 isn't
If we got caught breaking the law we got caught violating everybody's rights and solution
Instead we're going to do is we're going to try to change the laws to be more flexible more comedy
Out of the same time
What we really have
Here is a PRS
We have a friend of miss you
And so yes this is what you said they get Twitter accounts that get Instagram accounts and puppies and everything like that
They want to be friendly they want to be on your side
Answer the Trump presidency has very much been
Guest
Unto these people
Deep state
You could call it
John has been quite quiet
Since this Mueller report
Finally he's got nothing to say no no moralistic diatribes to throw
How to tweet at at the president
All right so he's he's immediately sort of scampered back on the blog
Because he was all over Network news although the corporate media
Contributor only shows now
I'm where he's using
Service dismantle
Authority that people presume
From having you know a little lower third as you get introduced on the new show that says you don't former director CIA
I need just insinuated all this stuff about how
He's in bed with the Russians and he knows it's coming Mueller's got it
He's going to nail this guy
And then you have to report comes out every way
Wait I thought
You said
Yes I thought you had some sort of secret knowledge that this was all going down
I need my money is that you have these characters of popped up and drain the reporting in 2013 I think
You know quite rightly a lot of mainstream media
And journalist were
We're investigating and looking at these figures and what they've been doing in the last few years
And then suddenly I remember feeling like
Being a weirdo
Parallel universe
Now this person theme Champion Don Colbert
And everyone's just
Everyone in their in their in their their rush to two
To go after Trump
Just decided to
Accept any and anybody
Contucci that it was
Kind of you know you looking at the Modern mediascape
You got a Wonder
Where is the political affiliation
What's going on
All right I mean this is this is kind of one of the things actually that gets back to the Sunshine for which he'll never be
Forgiving people
Focus so much on the song
And they forget what's real
Which is
Why was the son's noteworthy
Why was he in for
Why does nobody care
About this weird Australian guy
Who is trapped in an embassy
Brighton in London
I'm an Indian surf courses
Cheap printed thing
The people needed to know
All the people wanted to know
But the larger should have
Maurice Moore corporate media
Would not touch
And this was because of fears of backlash because of you know this Saturday.
I'm but
Whenever somebody else breaks the story first
Then the world Taiwan right because it
I'm we actually saw that the same kind of
The same kind of dynamic
With the Steele dossier
All right which was all the salacious things
About Donald Trump
I'm where it have been shopped around all these news Oregon
None of them would actually report on that go again
Credible is not credible until BuzzFeed
Put it on the one did it than everybody was talking about right
But there was also a problem here
Which is
We have
So much today
The journalism and politics
Accusation
Rather than actual evidence
What are the things that is I think quite disappointing to see about the money
I'm for both sides by people who want to bury Trump and people who want you to put them up on there
The shoulders and racing down the street
Tour the parade
Is there snow evidence
There's a ton of alligator
But they don't actually say this is you know why we believe
This this is the source of it
So we can look at the actual facts
The same thing with Steele dossier right eye one of the reasons why it was so problematic to post that why
A cause a backlash when it stopped
I'm with the media who very much like rightfully the public
The public wanted to see Trump
Because his is policies
Even some
I will acknowledge
I did his character is morality just isn't one of these
It's simply not there
There are people out there
With red hats on right now
Arthur glad don't understand power
Right there glad Republicans are power will do anything to keep the last Democrats out of power
And look you know they pick their side they have their politics might not agree with it whatever
Albert at least Leafs
Even those people
Right
I'm even those people who are totally on something just because they want the power
Look at Donald Trump
And I go look this guy's a dick
Right we know he's
We know he's a bad person
Our
Terrible
Person
We've seen this happening and you know country after country after country
Iuc with erdogan in turkey and I know you see it with or Bond and hungry see with Putin in Russia right
I'm where these guys don't look
We no disguises feeling
We think he's an effect
Our
In in this case in the trunk AC stuff
Abilities kind of a bumbleride but he does have us or power
But the problem is
When you just like so much
That you're willing to set evidence
To the side and simply believe any bad thing about
Because you think it advances your cause
York remastered vulnerabilities
Because if it is not
One of Donald Trump's
You
Very effective political attacks for his side
Expect
Sprite is saying the people
My opponents the people on the other side read the people who want to change in government
They are liars
But they are Fabricators they're inventing things
To manipulate
But it's scary though because what you have now
Is MattyB putz's
If you talk a lot about this
That
You know this Mel report in the reporting around it
Is basically this Generations wmds
Because ultimately
It was nothing
And
The trust I think that it did any damage
Done
I really I wonder
Going forward in my profession how we can sort of undo some of that
So that guy
Directions to Racine and mistrust
In readers and viewers
I think it's a little bit generous to say nothing
Write it in something
Occlusion The Smoking Gun
Promise
A new it exactly active conspiracy with the Russian government rights
Like a plot
Stop it he's going to do all this
Changes
Sanctioned
They had made Deals they have
Incapable morons like Carter page right
Who can't interview
Without you know like it just breaking out into the most guilty looking sporkful in like Flynn
How
Either they're not the 80
But these individuals write these are the ones who we have folks like Rachel Maddow have a tremendous
Turns out
Even the redacted version of the Mueller report
Is like a really good Ragu
It's just better the second day
And it's not just her right but she she gets singled out a lot and sometimes unfairly
But sometimes very fairly
Because of the aggression in the singular Focus
On a story
Ian with the evidence
This is that concept again
There's evidence for because they stopped
Caring about evidence it became a struggle against an idiot logical Battle of Truth
Light
Injustice versus the
Forces of Darkness
Rather than look these are the facts
We need to follow the facts and get to what we can prove
To hold these people to the full account of the law
And instead what we have is if we have a kind of tribalism
It is corroding and breaking down
Bonza fraternity there's time together every society
Write this is happening
States
France
Xiaomi UK
But even within that like people are
They are
Ceasing
To believe
That we can even operate from a common set of facts
Because we are denying
What is true
Annie's provable because it is contrary to
Our purpose is Our intention right our our our sort of
Outside of the battle
And we are
Fabricate
The fact that we believe Survivor arguing
And when that happens on both sides right
We lose the ability to have any kind of rational
Kind of
Alice exchange where we can actually
Work together
I mean we can find a consensus and go look
I don't agree with you
I will oppose you
I will try to achieve my goals but
I will recognize that what you were doing is it least based
The truth
I don't want to say you know Trump is a victim of this because he is
Very much one of the champions of of modern untruths
I'm but the sad thing there the reality is
He is getting hit
With the same thing that he create
Right I'm in the problem is
If he was just getting his just deserts right in his sort of
Journeys reward
People might be okay with that why they might think it's karmic Justice right
But once you started that
What is Pandora's Box
You can't put it back in
No one trusts
NBC or CNN
This is the thing
Who do you trust
Who can you trust environment is motherboard
Every sentence
Motherboard
Wwd
I get called on on Twitter quot off and I got called a terrorist and a traitor because I'm now I mean
Court right now is the
RCMP in Canada because I refused
Comply
So far with a production order
To give up all this information on a dead Isis Source actually I'm going I'm going to
Court
This week or X
It'll be airing on the dad
Acoma Court
And I also I just I wonder sometimes
You know I I also do a lot of work on far right and I get
I get people calling me
You know
SELECTED store
You know I can't go anywhere it's just on Twitter I just get attacked
On either side of airport in the far-right
Or a report on on on terrorist because
Jaundice
Because
There just seems to be such a pendulum
And nobody believes
I think you know I'm part of this there there's an observation bias but there's also definitely change in public narrative
In a way that we can I
Play nowadays
I'm one of the
Biggest mistakes of the media
Dwight
Need a ride from from
Small-time independent Bloggie folks to the the biggest plush in a million-dollar
Salaries
Newsroom
Every time Trump has tweeted something
They've made it news
How they react to it
Right right right
They have explainers about like what Twitter is right
I'm so now your grandparents your parents your kids you know you niece and nephew
Everybody's going on Twitter
Because I want to see what it's all about right
And so if
The demographics of Twitter hitch
Right now everybody's on that and that has been representation
People who are
Did you're not invested in the community like they don't have any sort of connection to that
Are there new arrivals
And this is something that like you have to accept you have to absorb you have to understand
But I don't think
Any of the public figures that have been so comfortable on Twitter the last couple years
Directions thought about then realized what's happening day just seen a become harsher and harsher and harsher
People who aren't used to this they're not like there's a whole new influx of Holland population that's looking
I'm on on that note
I think if you're not getting criticized
From both
Indus
Atmosphere where everything is hyper-partisan
You're not being
Fair
Because it's a journalist I think who has a real commitment to
Simply what the fox say
As opposed to what the desired narrative is
Journalist for Their audience
You're going to piss everybody off everytime you
Story or you know maybe this story won't do it for the money right next
Weak will
I'm in this site I think is
It's unfortunate
Did we have an audience know who takes everything personally but
The question is can you blame them
When you look at whatsapp
Happened with this
Oh you know
Effort
To sort of unseat trump from the White House
I threw this Russian conspiracy narrative
It clearly didn't pan out
You know now he even the Democrats write the Democratic Party
Who hates this guy will do anything to be thrown them is going all right when we struck out of Russia but
Obstruction we're going to get him on that right
And okay fine you know whatever but
We have to have some accountability
The fact
We have had the chairs
Congressional intelligence committee
Open the house and the Senate
Who are doing the same things as the John Brennan's as but James clapper's
We're basically going to look
Kind of top secret clearance
If you knew what I knew
You know you be ready to slap cuffs on this guy
Abaddon the report comes out and everybody's like where's the
What do you want to ask you speaking of journalistic
Institutions
Were you disappointed to see when the intercept
Close down
Discord archive
I think the most disappointing thing about this
I was the fact that I learned about it from the news
Like look
I am
I
I'm not
A journalist
I don't work at The Intercept I'm not
On the board Explorer slow
They Don't Own Me
And I understand right
Are there also not the sole custodian something
Barton gellman of the Washington Post
He's got a copy
The New York Times has copies Garden has copies to
The speaker has copies right this is distribute
All these other news organizations have stopped
Publishing for years
Because it became more expensive in longer for more
Instead of like the short
Punching news pieces
Which is what you know the large appetite is in an in journalism today
What remains in the archive I believe
It is stuff that is going to require much more substantial effort
Basically
Book
Text work
What you need real researchers
Sit down
I'm in to connect all the dots that you can't get across and send them
50 words right
And
The Intercept really was not designed for that
Unfortunately
None of these news organizations were and they were supposed to hand this off
At academic institutions
But that just hasn't happened because the academic insta
Look
We're dependent on grants from the federal government in the US
The word the government's Kino going to complain and go over you know you're giving this
So whoever
I'm into I am sympathetic and I understand that waves their hands
At the same time
Oh yeah I don't think it would have been a lot to sit for you to ask for Haiti
Give me a call maybe maybe ask my my feelings on it
And I am
Understand where it's at
But yeah you know
I I think anybody would agree
Quick signal text are you can Skype
Right right
I'm sure they would be just a ton of NSA all over that but
You know I'm sure you're also used to that as well
Hey Ya
I mean it it's not like I'm you know in hiding that that's the funny thing.
People are always like
Edward Snowden from an undisclosed
I'm in my apartment guys in Moscow I say this all the time.
I'm not going to tell you my street address I don't want you to know where I live right by you don't know now you know your street address either
No I definitely don't feel no way I live you don't want your audience feel like all I didn't like that story
Yeah and I'm not I mean
Famous I'm like you know
Have a podcast that's what I mean by that is
No I'm actually living a much more public and open life now so you know I'm doing interview with you right now
Copy this calling almost certain
Do you know when you saw the Assange thing go down
Did you get a little like roof
I really don't want that to happen to me
No it was more the case where
You know I I I told you before my plan
Event end up in Ecuador
Right
If John Kerry and cancel my passport because he thought it would be an effective political attack track in Russia
I can think it's sort of smear be by association for the rest of my life
You know I would be in Guantanamo right now worked at
I probably won't even made it
The point of the CIA
Hand in Latin
That was really the sort of more what I thought
You know that the whole thing is it's not
Really about me
And this is the thing with the most rust
We have these conversations with
Anybody
Because I'm afraid
Xiamen name that people run
Recognize right
They're always sympathetic and I understand is a human intro
England it didn't come from me right now
Isn't my political advisors right there always like oh you know you want people to connect
Think positively of you
Look guys I don't matter
Right that the only thing I did that it was a real you know
Significant impact
With sourcing this information to
Like I lost it by the time I was out of the hotel room
Route Hong Kong
And
From that point on right like I can be an activist
Boys I can talk on the sidelines
Humble what happens to me
Doesn't really matter
However
From my side
The reason I came
Time for drive is not to make a better life for myself I I live on firing and really screwed myself
But it was the customer something I believed in right which is a we were going in the wrong direction
Stay that way
Orkin Roach
Writing in history
And we have a chance to
Turn toward what we see everybody doing right
The whole reason we see this public embrace
Ivaldis spies and you know former CIA chief
What would presume to be liberal
Channels and outlets in newspapers
And you know their there they're sort of glorifying
These people
They're doing it very utilitarian way
Miami
I'm afraid of what my enemy
With the power
I'm afraid with the future will look like
I'm afraid that the world is dangerous
And so I will make a
Anyone who says they can help
Anyone who says they can fight
And that's what these people are doing right but what happens is
Now we have given so much power
An agency
Applecore literally trained
To lie and sweet
Burnt
And basically damage
Democratic and Republic processes
Or sort of elite institutions
Remember the Office of the President
Right
The White House
Is not an expression democracy after the election
I think it's
They have been granted powers
But this is now in the hands of a group and its
New Chanel executive branch
Who is very much going to use this to political ends
And we would like to believe
But they will use it for the purposes of the benefits of the public that has elected
In a lot of cases to do
What from the best to the worst presidency
They have
All
Obama abused
Bush abused Trump is setting
Records on abusing it
Right now I'm sure if you look back at you Nick Carter
Jimmy Carter did crust
Thanks
Are you are you a Bernie 2020 guy
You know I I don't endorse any candidates because I feel like eating and I worried that it might be a kiss of death
Where them cause more
More harm than good
I'll say about Sanders here
Is that when you look at all of the people Democrat
CDs
Certified
Corporate Democrats you know
The Harris Booker
40 gigs
And all these guys are are are fairly Corp
Right are you got Warren who's you know a little bit less corporate
And that's encouraging
But you also see the machine very much
Aimed against
Sanders and Warren even though that they seem to have a little bit of friction between them
For the same spot on the ticket
The thing that I like about
Some of these folks
Starrett particularly
When you look at someone like Sanders
Is you know what they believe
You know if you look at every crisis if you look at every problem if you look at every foreign policy views that the United
Places in Fulton for the last 50 years
This picture of Bernie Sanders at a protest
INF 30 years ago
Screaming.
And I think
When you get to that age
And you have that kind of established
Track record
Angle look
I don't agree with all the man's policies he might have things that are different
But at least I understand who that person is
And that is not something that you can say
I swear a lot of these candidates
Who their policies and in their beliefs
Are are very much purchase
And sponsor
And I think that
Is the kind of politics
That has led us to a trump presidency
So one last question that is
You know it's
Pretty controversial for you I know you've tweeted about in the past and
Heart of Nubian internationally-renowned whistleblower
But I know that you
Used to get weird
Spicy photographs
On Twitter in your DMs
That's still happening
You know
It's that has mostly dried up I think because I'm out of the headlines which is nice
You do you do still get them sometimes I'm but it's actually a little bit
A little bit sad
It's not something
And that surprises it's it's from people who have I died
Pretty up
Mental health issues
And that's the you know that that's part of the internet
Is
You got all kinds of people out there
And it might you know it it might be the kind of thing that you make a joke about
It's funny because
And I understand
When we think about what the end
It is the new public,
That's right it is the street
When you look at the street when you look at the bus when you look at the subway today
Nobody looks at each other nobody's talking to each other unless they're going with each other they've been brought their own crowd
Instead of looking down at screens
And it is these screens that connect people out to the world
And while that is both a means of interconnection and engagement
Not everybody has the skills
And just at the General Health and the good privilege
Of the way
This word characteristics they enjoy psychologically
But they can handle this and so they end up becoming more isolated and then become more delusional
And they turn to violence
Or self-harm
And I think there's not alot ways for people nowadays
Get that kind of help
And I'm not sure we're going to see that get better
Until we as a c
Society improve
In a real way politically because right now
These are the topics of conversation that nobody
Talk about that nobody
Cares about because
The world is on fire
I lied
One Last Cry
If you don't mind but I know you probably have some
Dumplings to get to or something like that
What's in vodka
Hey how about some pizza
Russian Pizza
You can eat it or Miss
I'm an American man you know they got like Papa John's
C-man
Start just one last question
Was it you were tweeting about it
A few weeks ago
Have to do with dark matter
It turns out the Lori Stroud who is the one that brought you to the NSA and in Hawaii
Has been public publicly denouncing dark
I was just wondering what you thought about that
So there's
There's a little bit of complexity to that story Lori Stroud
Is represented a lot of these stories is like being my
My boss
This that and the other
Am I believe she signed form
I did was to get the referral bonus
About my boss actually set in a different room
Was not
Stroud
I I did know Laura Stroud and you don't seem like a decent enough person I do know our
I'm very well because we only worked
Weeks
That was my last
Before I left
But it's it's
It's good that someone is coming forward
Bostonia Public Record about what
At the same thing time I think it is profoundly troubling
2cp
A crew working
With the NSA
Stop.
To basically use Mass surveillance because the team that I was working with her mom wasn't masturbating
We take those skills
And that understanding
And then basically sell them rent them out
To the most authoritarian regimes in the Middle East
I'd use them
Against human rights Defender
Right and journalist and activist
End in her public statements
The only time she's actually bothered by
When she has sent human rights Defenders
In her own words
To prison
Right and I think they said
Demands spouse is on like house arrest now
Monitor by the secret police
The only time it bothered her
Was when
An American
Got caught up
And if the full extent
Of your
Moral universe
Is whether good or bad things happen to Americans
Lights
Only belong to Americans
I wish I had had more than a few weeks to to send beside a person
Like that some
Because I I wish I could have reached
Well thank you very much for coming on Cyber I really appreciate it
It's been a really
Discussion
Any last-minute advice for me if
The Acadian federal police
Say I have to go to jail for this
Look
I am not going to tell anybody you know marching prisoner or do this Saturday
But I will say this
The decisions that
People like you make
Stand up for
Fundamental
The are the only thing that constitutes public rights
I'm Yoona freedom of press freedom of speech know what is that stuff mean
Unless people actually standing
And that
Your rights are are just letters on a page right there did not going to jump off the page and
And protect you
The law doesn't protect people
People protect
If there are people like you
Who are willing to stand up and shout
The government
When it goes beyond what is permitted what is authorized
What is able
To do
No one will set
Boundaries and enforce them for the Publix body right
Relatives the government's
Asserted privileges
We aren't living in a free and open
Society we we don't have rights we have privileges in there
Search subject
Terrorvision
Andre location
At any given time
So very much respect
Are people who are willing not just to say to believe in something
But actually stand up
And I'd say thank you and good luck
Thanks very much
Ed
Take care buddy take care
This episode of Survivor was recorded by Gene white edited by
Produced by Lorenzo franceschi bicchierai and hosted by me