Eagle one package being delivered
28 Charming kitten or equation group has become a booming business dozens of so-called threat intelligence
Companies keeps having them and sell subscriptions to fees where they provide customers with up-to-date information
I'm with most advanced cyber criminals
And government hackers are up to one of the companies with perhaps the best visibility data
Call Telemetry in infosec speak is none other than Google
The internet giant has more than 1.5 billion active users on Gmail more than 1 billion people who
Use Chrome
And more than 2 billion of their Android phones
Recording around the world
Today we talked to the person whose job it is
Define hackers in that Giants
Like really really really Giants
Haystack
Shane Huntley is the director threat analysis group
Also known as tag
Google
Existential Google's hacker hunting team
The other ones task monitoring who's networks for criminal and government hackers
Okay so tell me what it is exactly you do with Google
My job title is on the director of the
Analysis
I was a part of Google security
Analysis group
Is
Something the Company formed about 9 years ago
To deal with
Serious and government threats against Google Now use
So
Are on the team that
Specifically looks at
Trying to understand
Over Frets out there the
Are threats to a site uses
How we can detect them how we can prevent some
How can just drop them to keep values the same
Domingo is that
There is a lot more stressed out there
Apcu novel threats.
Suddenly
Abby company like Google really needs to defend against so we're the team that does that
So I definitely had friends before who've gotten some of these
Is emails from Google where they say stuff like
Your account
Has been attacked by a nation-state actor
And
You know you need to
Responses to
How are you so sure when you send an email like that where you said is a nation-state actor cuz it's occurred to me that that seems like a pretty strong
Something to send to somebody
So the black one out their ID
Out of the person that came up with you some push this through Windows a lot of
Scepticism even do this in the first place
It wasn't doing it for quite a while now
And
It seems to have a good effect
Slacks off acacia
Actually send it Valera
Yellow warning alert directly in the browser because
We don't want people to copy this is an email
Sucks you should actually see it
In the browser cell phone
I'd like a pop-up
Warning indicator
Is that we've seen something weather has fishing with us malware or some other Behavior
That
We're pretty confident that in a matches what we understand to be the sole
Technics oil specific indicators associated with
Scuf impact
Traductor
200 defense read actively tracking some way
And
The cause of that
We believe that that's a special message you should
Steve Madden
You know so
We can't tell you all the details but we want to tell people that
You know you really should think about this
And we don't know exactly what action you should take in most cases
Give you some suggestions but
Really depends on who you are
But the fact that you're being targeted
Some people Wild
Reciprocity
Some people has a big surprise and I might need to change things
We really try and provide the information
As you said the still a possibility of false positives especially if it's the security researcher doing research areas
We're pretty confident we can tell the difference
Between what looks like
Got meds for back to work and what looks like say PrimeWay
You might want to get into the
Starting to blend those lines a little bit as the year
Okay so
You send that alert when there's an attempt or when they're actually hacked
Attempts
So it's a sign of targeting
Notice on compromise compromise
We immediately like
Title is actions help with security town. I change those things
What is an addition to that
When we seen some form of the tents
We actually let everybody know that we seen some attempt against
Information
Anderson something about
4000 yuan
Amongst the crossover
Gmail and Google service
State-sponsored attacks
Is somewhat rare compared to all the big things but is still a fan volume
Compared to what some people would imagine
Tecumseh State actors
What types of people are they
Normally targeting is it
Say journalists
I think it runs the gamut I think this
You know
Governments these days
Espionage
Buy soda for the local Security Services will start today
International Security Services
I see a wide range of what
The different Trek routes go off
Summer
Going out to people because of pot of they like Espionage Mission so might be going off the like
High-level government officials
Some people are going off to
Journalist slacktivist is speaking out of
It's going off for individuals
It really runs quite the gamut
And
Pretty much anybody who's interested
Entresto has information that's valuable
One of these
Staples
First Imagine and
Sometimes he blasted
You think this is a democracy
Be quite different to say somebody who would win
You're one of the major political parties in the US that quite different immigrants
Either the same or slightly different redactive
Where where are these attacks being born from I'm sure you have an idea
I think the big
Is that all over the world
Alcohol
Is that
Most Nations
Any sort of sizes
Is the keishin now actually having some form of
Hacking program that we can fit a pot of this
We not sign
We don't just want about somebody coming from Russia we don't want about just somebody coming from North Korea
Every month we actually take the full range of everything we've seen
Are we really like
You know sometimes we going people and Country Aida didn't tell you like country be at the same time he wanting a plain country bathing talking to buy
Country I
We are
Icon of goal is to
Really wanted to take or I use against all
States
That's it a few years ago I mean motherboard apologist story
And it was on the report that was Sheriff s called peering into the aquarium
It was a reference
To the name of Jerry's headquarters in in Moscow
Tell me more about that
Yeah I do believe my name is
That is a paper we wrote and excited
We do look at all the 4th actors out there
Ads
Yeah I think this nobody is working and sweating until that isn't looking at rush hour on the attacks in some way
Of course every major power including Russia
Is applier in times of doing attacks against
Why are people on the internet so
Definitely it's right after we take seriously when we woke up
So there's no discrimination is what I'm hearing would that also include the United States targeting different people
Yes I think
We definitely do not like to give a free pass
Anybody to hack I use
We have our defenses
We are looking to
Warn anybody receiving time to buy fishing on malware
And
Finding useful as possible about the
So are you staying for the trends in the
In the global cyber security
Parking space
Right now is that a lot of these
No tools
And agencies
Are proliferating
But you let's say you know 10 years ago you would have had
Have the big three operators a big four or five or six and now you're looking at a whole landscape
Different nations or is it you know is it a hundred
Yes exactly right is definitely the number of factors
Just people seems more effective so that investing capabilities locally
Is Osiris Market from providers that
You know a couple hundred thousand dollars will get you
B series turbo kit
It's from some of the providers out there that is selling to
A range of different
Countries and times
The other thing that we're really seeing is that just a tooling off-the-shelf what you can download off the internet to do this sort of attacks
Really becoming easy
Fat
You know some of the tools that I've been used by penetration testers about Security Professionals are also being a
Easley used by government
What's you like go off
We'll see some to like you
Powershell Empire
Which is like a
Download Rocky Harbour some other side
I was saying that use by a range of different nations in their attacks and we feel like a fishing platform like evil jinx
Again
Philly Bible on GitHub
Quite well written used
Penetration tester
Mixing of things actually does make detection harder
Working out what's what
It also makes it very easy games any niacin to get into
Is your a
Even a very small nation and you have a very small intelligence budget
Like really the cost of Entry here is like are a couple of University students
Get them to download some selfies and dad and I can stop fishing people hacking people wear if they wanted to get into like
Running human operations of the CEO building spy satellite
Serious amounts of money
Really.
Most approachable way for any country to do Espionage I think everyone's like that
Have you seen some really surprising countries get into the game in that way
Yeah we have nothing. Just seeing really surprising Soto small parts of countries as well like
You'll see
You know it's something really local police like local police a local Security Services like
Somewhere
Almost
The city level in x
People started to use these
I could go against local criminals
Local stratso look like today
Stop it doesn't need to be beat up a national capability
And we danced all the way down to like
Sub-regions or even really small countries to do the basics
I need massages developing nations are there because you know you look at something like
The hacking team
Revelations icon
Came out there was University campus cops
Does capabilities
United States
Absolutely and that's the biggest differences
Dislike
Between like disease days more about the intent Rollin the tool
Supposed to be used in all sorts of different ways
Even seeing
People going off to like
Domestic abuse local people
Like going out the members of
What an abusive relationship going after spouse Princeton
Actually seeing some of
Saints Row hacking tools been used
Nation-states
This is a technique
Gain access
People's information
Now when it comes to through this proliferation of of intelligence agencies using his
Capabilities
There's also been a proliferation of threat intelligence companies coming out
With the latest report saying
This person's done this or naming something
Some group a funky name but whatever one knows what it is
Fancy bear
For example
Do you ever
Look at those and think yourself now we've been looking
The same group
You think that's pretty much like
You know
What I think
Is one of the
One of the benefits teams around the world and we definitely talk to cowpots
But the commercial industry also
With like the other major players such as like my counterparts and yellow
Micheladas company
On the hallway scene different paths
The same picture
It's like that old parable of the elephant
People looking at different some people are starting to see the trunk
I think most of us in the world to stop and Converge on a reasonable understanding about what's going on out there
I think it is interesting that you know The Branding and the condo
Commercialization of the
Play supposed to go down. Bad in this world that's the
Able to respond to motivations both attackers and Defenders
So
Go to where I can get
What are the vehicles that the Defenders security industry everyone else is trying to work out in
How do we turn into products different variants
Jason X
Is it security company is a goal to make you secure or is it legal to MyQ
Afraid so you buy more
Probably a little bit of thought
Trying to balance those motivation
Episode that
I need 50 Ava need to be able to get out there means.
Play publishing World. Which has the real good side that we have
Json sharing
The downside is that
Sometimes it does make it harder to track things as
People immediately chasing the publicity in the new hall of fame versus the what can we do to really think about this rock
I mean Google has one of the
Better
Threat analysis team
Because you also have one of the biggest data set that Google must be attacked
More Time by nation states than almost anywhere else
In the world
I don't know about the attacks
Statistics
Definitely say that we definitely do
Get a lot of disability
Suppose we have so many used
And because we had so many uses of a sad like
I used to being targeted by Spaceballs for the taxes
So it does allow us to see the
A picture
I also think I'm very lucky
Italo technology to draw
That was a lot of
Initial analysis
Swell a lot of us about actually understanding the day this is what a big data problems be processing problems
I just wanting the Google you know has
Ability to process large massive diet
Engineers building like large-scale system
So we can sit through
Medabots of malware
We can like
Deploy things directly
To do protections into Gmail
Miss y'all thing I really like about the team
Is that
Are we not just producing summer pool at the postal website
95% is like a teligence or more is directly going to the people who are defending
Google actually building the systems in defense the surest adjusting the defenses
Try nicely block this in real time
I think we're having quite a
Identify this problem
Making your taxes with a lotta
So I mean in some ways would you say that you're getting better information and RB
Becoming better prepared to face
These kinds of attacks and even say the US government
Because you're getting seems to be
I mean just talks
Anthem
I think everybody has his strengths write like
U.s. government has like their own advantages
192 US government.
Google likes younes comment on government spying us Steel
Huge
Also they have was not pausing
Intelligence agencies have
Super secret things to the laws allow them to do that
You know somebody in
Cobra setting
Jerry Strickland
Play sings by the book
Isn't able to do
So did we have different views
But I do think that
The days off
Yeah the government having a monopoly on this understanding and it's always locked up secret understanding what's going on that's so much better than any
Anybody else engulfment is really busy. I think
Did Connor
Strong thread until team buses mine or some of the bee commercial ones
I definitely must want an evil
Even footing with
Sort of like big five eyes governments are all the golf Missoula
But then I told me everything I know as well right so
I don't know
Will I have some magic noise
That's not available
People on the outside
I got asked to I mean you must be pulling some of your employees nusret intelligence
From those exact cover
In the Bible
I have a few people to come from that world including myself way back in the day
Like almost 9 years ago now
There is some company company
It's surprising it's only a couple actually that if
How much water rain sexually
What about
The whole DNC
Hacking
Phenomena that happened
Did Google see any of those same actors
In their servers going after their Gmail accounts
We did not have any
Logic
The same way.
NSAIDs
Did those same groups
Did you see them actively trying to go after your network
Or your Gmail
I definitely give the definitely was targeting of
During the
No public nature of this week
Regards to
Gmail uses with targeted
During the campaign and even leaks around them they should have been in the same time frame and 26
Mini pig clothes
By the Saints redacted
The DNC hacks and also some of the legal operations so
Isopoda like
Lodgic Champaign
It was
Going on at that time
So in terms of the threat intelligence analysis
Group do you ever have any political fears of disclosing some of the things you find because
Obviously Google has commercial interests and threat intelligence is just completely
You know open
In terms of what you're finding
But you know
You could upset Nations I've seen you to look at something like citizen lab when they find something out about a certain country
If there's a political blowback is that something that you're
Faces as well I think it's something that everybody has to think of
To certain degree but I suppose the
Harvesting
It's like
General rule is
Not to
You know tight sides but not really that food pushing in order to like push a political agenda
Archangel Street
Quit here in the facts that
We're trying to defend our systems now uses against
And
I think
When we take that approach as opposed to a more activist approach like some of these other groups I think that puts us in a better position
I hate to stand on
Anytime softer why we doing
Playing favorites will not picking sides without trying to
Used to some political measure because
The company wants right this isn't a cool business a cool businesses
Allowing people to
Use that services to use the internet and
Always security attacks wrestlers getting in the way of that so
We just want to solve the problem to allow using
Cuz I mean I guess you know any any
Broken
The internet is broken it's broken forever
Absolutely and if the trust in the internet
Is broken as well it'll say just limits wallpaper
Can do like
Always attacks actually
Make it so people don't want to use the internet they conquered the benefits because
Spinning without having to worry about attack so they worried about using
Information so
You know we want people to be secure we won't be able to get all the benefits of this technology in
Don't have to spend their entire lives having to
Nope
Because really worried about threats Golfland Factor otherwise
And how about your
You know Google's relationship with businesses in terms of disclosing what's going on if
They're being particularly
Targeted
Is that something you do actively
Cuz he misses well-liked definitely fry businesses
On G Suite Navasota products and something responding to do
We also do a lot of like engagement industry in flag
You know we definitely make the calls to different people would have some sort of tea attack
I promise to give like white glove service everybody on the planet but
What's something serious out there we definitely doing gauge very strongly
What are all the things we've been doing more recently is like really looking for exploits out there in the wall as well as
We found that
What sound exploits
Seem like you know
Summer competitors
Somebody using eggs exploit against Microsoft
Look at the teams pushed and the patch
Turn around 2
Help paying security products against active attacks
Bosporus your face see something being using his that products we didn't expect that
Dentsu
Provide information about some hole.
In 2013 after the Snowden leaks a lot of these big companies like Google like the big telcos
Etcetera
You know a lot of people lost a lot of trust
And what your company does another companies do with data and terms of it
It's relationship Visa V government
When
Users are using the stuff in your at your collecting threat intelligence cetera
I mean how how can you sort of make people believe that
Google has Andrew threat intelligence group
Have their best interests
Adhar
And that you know in terms of government disclosure and their data
They're not going to see any any
Let's say attacks on their privacy
Degree you have to work out
And how they behave
I do think so
2013 Snowden leak
Swear
You know
A huge Advantage for us.
The whole industry and how everybody thought about
Technology in golf
I do think what we do need to say is that
We do
Have a pretty strong history of
Pushing back on the golf man
Really trying to be independent
We are an international company
That tries to
Yoda Fable II uses
But also
We have to think about the range
That I think
One of the downsides of
Snowden leaks
Is that you had everybody worried for a long time so lie about
Anna Seifert
That's not thinking
What's the tension from some of the other day threat actors out there for numbers
I think I actually happened frudel 2016 with
What's the election
Interference accusations that
Now some people realizing that yes there is this water range
Actors out there Beyond
Just worrying about what it was
What Snowden published
Is there a group out there in particular
That keeps you up at night in terms of 8
I think the group must keep me up at night is the one that I don't know about
In times of the
Who is that the one that I really know about
I feel that I'm really able to the fan
But there's always that out there
Should we haven't had a really big incident
Long time
Again, Google
And
Is there some active
Comforters that I don't know about
Song
Group whether it is like you know probably paid mercenaries will somehow 18 from some golf
We do everything we can to look for them we haven't seen the oven
It's always in the back of my mind
That we have to be ready
Trying to look at how to catch them if they did
You see any Trends in terms of attacks by apts
Out there on Gmail at 8
Gdb like
Going after two Factor authentication goes back in 2016 it was fishing automated phishing email
Attempts at
Gmail
So I mean is there anything else you're seeing that's
This come out
Caltrans one is the
Yunnan normal focus on mobile devices
Centigrade so trying to either
Triple push users to install things on their phones or two
Yourtronics black people
It's very important very interesting that I think
As more and more people use spotify two-factor codes
Looking at you no send fire SMS OST Barn app
The series attack isn't even the sort of mid-level serious attack is
Getting
Bitterroot freaking uses
Misunderstood
Kings Inn
Security
Even among Security Professionals is the
Occasionally
Fat
If it's a six-digit code and you're entering into a website then
Just as much as I can
Your password
But something like the
Fido security keys
GBK make some of
Muhammad
The used ones
That really so twice
Websites
A copy Fists
The really works
Multi-factor Authentication
What's
Against certain attacks like you know
It really protects you against your password in your password dump
Password reuse
Bought
That kind of the code entering ones I think of being able to be stolen by more more
You know more serious attackers
And then that's the
The thing that worries me is well that people think did the two-factor Authentication
Magic Bullet
Sign up for it you could be a SMS message and then you totally unhackable
That's certainly not the truth
Is the Pledge time to get as I mentioned before of the
The mixing together
State-sponsored all the word of the world like
North Korea spends more of a time trying to steal Bitcoin these days
It's been a trying to like get National Intelligence from all week until so
Makes it hard for me to draw the line about where I should be putting my assets
Great thank you so much I definitely enjoyed speaking with you
Noah's been great talking to you yeah and thanks for having me on
This week's episode with everybody in white and produced by Lorenzo franceschi because I
Give us a review on Apple podcast will tell your friends about us we back with more next week