Eagle one package being delivered
Known that the simple alphanumeric password or just the simple password wasn't enough to secure our identities on
Online nowadays stuff like two-factor authentication and send jacking I become a real thing
Step verification help save others from accessing your account Improvement
Red 2 online identity management IRL lives in
Inseparable in the midst of an online identity crisis
Maybe
On today's show we're talking to Wendy nather and OG the infosec world who knows a thing or two about identity
Daft
Vacation
She's with the top people working on this problem for the successful startup Duo security when he Central problem
Which is all really everyone's problem can we actually secure our identities online
If not can we manage to fall out of constant breaches I've been Mac who and this is cyber
English opening
How are you doing
Good good
So we wanted to talk about the Integrity of your online identity but I wanted you to take me back
When did passwords in the internet for personal accounts
Really take shape
When did they really take shape well
You know I think somebody decided at some point
When there was only one system you could log into that just remembering the password was going to be okay
And so you know using fallible organic matter for primary credential storage
What's a good idea to
But it's not anymore
Clearly
Cuz all of us have
Are dozens or hundreds of accounts now
That's the thing is like how you keep track of all of your password people use password managers but even that
Interview bit of a pain
It is really difficult
Because not
Everything works seamlessly together across all the difference
Devices
Susan platforms that you want to use or application
So why did the password itself
Become you don't like
The username and the password
Become the norm
Will a
At the time it was the only thing that
Wasn't
Dependent on
Physical security so
It used to be when you logged into the Mainframe the only way you could do it was by going into the building where it was
And getting access to the terminal that was hardwired
And the Assumption was if you could get in that far you were supposed
Used to be there
Do you mean
Back when the internet was first created
Abacus
For the internet
Was created
It's like when the first computer
Was credits
How far back
Yeah yeah pretty much
These computers are more accessible you can get your hands on them
You would
Be able to work with him or maybe all of 20 minutes at a time
Flipping switches
Putting info
Paper tape
For something like that
By the 1960s
Computers has become very
Inaccessible in very difficult to use
Because everyone was so worried about the economic
I learn programming on Mainframe computer
In 1974
The whole basis for the username and password goes back to the
Physical
The actual physical act of going into a building
And having to login with your name
And your past
Yeah absolutely until that the only thing they figured out was
Well let's make sure that Wendy can't login as Fred
So let's just
Nino
Give Fred a password and tell them
Never to you no tell it to Wendy or anybody else so that was the one Secret
That nobody
Share with you
The only thing that was only yours
And
At that time again it was
Consider good enough
Then the internet
Hello virtual reality
Interactive appetite searching for a website
Write an in even been when the internet or what what later became the internet was first being to
Developed it was still on multi-user systems that everybody logged into it one system
And everybody shared that the
Personal
Computer wasn't the thing yet
So you still needed
Individual password
For those
For those users
M&e personal computer did come into play
Play and so did the internet
We just by the fact okay
Kept the same
Password
Security measure
In places we did
Right if you had one PC
And you had one
Someplace else you thought well I'll just
The same password it'll be easier to remember that way
That really didn't change for a long time because I mean even if I think about it for my own standpoint
Like two-factor really
Only was widespread I would say
Is a widespread
Very
Nervously
Like 5 years ago
With 95% of breaches involving account takeover
Two-factor authentication is the most effective method
Prevention
Yeah you will five years ago I started using two-factor authentication with hard tokens
About
24 years ago
Wow
But I mean mainstream use
Chestnut Inn
Right right so we know it was an Enterprise usage
For very sensitive
Critical systems
And it didn't become a
Consumer thing until recently you're right
Is there any notable acts that happened
In terms of Internet Security
Where
We were forced
Username and passwords
System doesn't really
Well it became
You know it is
As the web
Spread
Peoples
Your consumers
Started using
More and more
Different websites
You know by default again they started using
The same passwords across all of those
And not only
Where are those passwords
Generally easy
Gas
If you knew anything about the user they became easy to reset
Because
Again the more presents
People had a mind the more you can find out about them
And use that demography
To pretend to be that person and reset the password
At the same time
Criminal started stealing
Passwords wholesale that weren't being
Stored securely
So they didn't necessarily have
Crack them
War it was very easy to crack them and then they could go around trying them everywhere
So is this the 90s on this first of it happening in terms of utilities
Identity theft
Passwords and crackers yes pretty much
You know if they have you ever seen war games
Where the character David Guetta found out where they wrote down the password for the school computer
They change the password every couple of weeks but I know where they write it down
There's lots of different
Or finding out somebody's password but that's
We started back then
Cisco's back
Pretty far
It sure does and it's
Just now reaching
You know critical mass
Where it is
Becoming an everyday occurrence
It's the people's
Passwords are being stolen in different ways
And
You know that there are a lot of just
Problems that we're running into
When we need to let
People use those accounts
About hours
For good reasons but
Don't need to be able to show
That we gave
Information that they didn't just
Spray control
So he was back in the 90s and obviously you've been around infosec for for a long time you're in the game
Weather experts like yourself who are sounding the alarm saying look like
Like this
This pattern of username and password is really not
An effective way to
Peoples
Online
Identities
Oh yeah absolutely people have been saying it for decades
And why hasn't changed
Because the risk
You know the impact
Breeches
Hadn't been strong enough to get people to move away from what would otherwise be a vegan
Convenience
If you need somebody start memorizing different
Strings
Of of passwords that was too hard for them
And they figured well it's a very very
Small wrist
That I'm going
Since I'm just going to keep doing the
It was easier for me
For the most part at work
But we finally got into
The point where anybody
And get breached wholesale
And now people are starting to think well maybe we better do
What are the alternate
What we are working on a lot of different options
So
The measures that we've had up until now
Using different fact
Indication like tokens
Or apps on your phone
Those things are getting better
Some people still find them to be very clunky but we're working on additional standards like Web author
Also called
Where we hide a lot of that
Machine-to-machine
Negotiation from the user so they don't have to do it or type it in themselves
If you think about all the users who are just using Touch ID or face ID on a mobile phone now
Because it's so much easier than poking at it really tiny keyboard
You'll see the direct
That we're going in
To get rid of past
Two biometric Olmos
Facial recognition Biometrics or Oregon yubikeys things like
Physical toll
That you can plug into your
Computer and just have to say
You know yes
I'm here please log me in
It's almost like we're going back to
Physical options
Refused
For time immemorial
You're right where
Kind of going back and forth and trying
Print things and
And saying you know well the ER this is lot easier touching it is
Easier than typing it
So
Can we just do this instead
I do remember watching Demolition Man
In the 90s
I think it's Wesley Snipes character steals an eyeball from somebody who has their eyeball
Recognition and remember thinking to myself there's no way
I will live in reality
Eyeball red
Will you would think so it actually I just saw a trailer with the new Fast and Furious movie
Where one of the character is
Yo has an unconscious person in
Slamming his face up
Thanks and it keeps saying access
Denied Wham
Access denied
So if you know that's that's still part of our pop culture and
That's going to be part of our daily life
Would you say that we are right now at a crisis
Online identity
I would not say it's a crisis
But we are getting to
Maybe discomfort
It's a better thing or
Is that the problems are getting wider and
Ben Weider
Spread
So what one of the examples
If you need to let somebody else access
Your account for some reason
There isn't a really good way to do it you know if you have
A two-factor authentication app on your phone
But they need to get into your account do they switch it to their phone or do they use your phone you give away your phone
And then what about
The application that you're trying to log into that
Trying to detect
Weather in attack
Got a hold of your password
Prodigy
Are you going to run up against their fraud
Detection even though you have
Permission to be in there
That's a big problem that we haven't solved today
Uses for the exchange of a
Accounts
That seems almost unheard of to
2 Exchange
Credentials could essentially mean
Eaton said she packed.
Medication it's like
I'd give my account name my username and password
And my two
Two-factor to let's say
My partner
All the sudden and they have to change my number from also my number
It gets very complicated
It really does and I ran into this problem when
I had to take care of my parents after they were in
Capacitated
When my father had a stroke I had to break into his
Computer
And into his email account so I could reset his banking passwords
And continue to pay their bills
Because there wasn't a good way
To say
And you know to go to the bank and say you know he's been incapacitated
Can I
Can I take care of this because
He wasn't dead
I wasn't
The inheritor of
I just needed to get in and help out
So what we don't have good mechanisms for that today
Yeah
Simpler icing people there's
Has been controversy around people
Losing your Instagram
Instagram
Has
Time of
Your password or
Decide your
Breached
And it's no longer yours and proving it's yours
I mean things like that are happening and
And it seems for the
Simplistic
Because you think to yourself
It's just an Instagram
But the way that we live our lives right now
I mean our online lives
These are very much are
In real life
Lights
Yeah yeah very much so it's
It's yourself it's your identity it's your reputation
And
You know we know how crazy things
Guess when something goes viral in the
Romwe
I don't want to be a Luddite
Or something but part of this
The obvious question to ask is Will should we just sort of quit parts of the internet and go analog like should I just
Go back to the 19
81 and you know right things.
Not use the internet as much as I Care Limited
Yeah I I don't know if that the Bible answer I know that that people pulling back from using it
White so much
Can be you know very healthy
But yeah for all of the business that we have to transact online
I don't know if there's any good way to go back
Now without
Really severe distress
Is there really anything we can do in terms of
Staying ahead of hackers it seems like
Such a game of
LeapFrog
You know you got
Two steps ahead and
LeapFrog you and then you
Program in Saint sauveur
Yeah it is very difficult and I know that there are people who are working
To try to
Figure out ways to create identities that are less hackable
And
To protect against fraud now identity theft
Prodigy buried if
Things
They're often
So confused for one another but for
Pretending to be
He is different from say
Stealing my credit card number and using it to pay for something
You know that's not actually pretending to be me
That message
You know fraud and Theft
So
We have to address these thing
In different ways
With we have to address the issue of identity
And figuring out how to separate that for
From access
So that you will know that
If I need to give
My
Teenager access to my account that we can tell the difference
Between us
You're not pretending to be me
They're at getting access
My resources with my permission
So we have to work on separating those and making those easier for consumers
To do
What did you first
See this as a major problem
You thought yourself
This is not going to work
Was there a moment back
Sandy 80s
We thought this
No I didn't think about in the 80s and in fact
Took me a long time as
Security professional
To understand the
Perspective of non-technical people
Would come
Complain and I'd say what
What's your problem
But
And you don't ask things
As things progress
And I started having
Try to manage
Not just for myself
But for my parents were in
Acetate
For my children who are still minors
Didn't know how to manage their own accounts yet
It multiplied so much that I finally
Initiated what the problem
What would you say are
Some of the things of the most
Horton saying
That
People listening to this
Should take away
From you and turns
They're on Limited
The way that they keep their password
What they can do to
To further secure
Their own
Well one of the
The worst things I think we ever did as technology professional
To everybody else is said first of all
You have to memorize
These passwords
They all have to be
They have to be really complicated and you should never ever write them down
That that was just silly
Because nobody can hold that much in their head
It is perfectly okay to write something down
And
Secure it
The same way that you would you know your credit cards
Like if you have to write down a password
Put it in your wallet
With your
Or keep it at home in a drawer because at this point
The danger of somebody breaking into your house and finding that book
Passwords is much smaller
Then the danger of somebody
Going through and brute-forcing guessing passwords online
From a disc
So you are perfectly okay to be writing
Passwords down and keeping them at home
The other alternatives
Courses to use a password man
And that will get you a lot of the way
Towards
Securing those passwords
But also
You know use your influence
As a consumer
With
The different entities that you're doing business with and say
You know it is what they are asked
Love you is difficult you should push back
And say
I need an easier way to do this can't you set up a biometric
Can't you make this work with my password manager
Because
Consumers do deserve
An easier experience
When it comes to managing online access
And I mean just
Finding a way to
Do it where I don't
Don't feel so sad
Stressed out about
When I changed
Phones for example
Coming to figure out how to get all my accounts on my it's almost like the biggest
The biggest hassle them all
Beyond
Yeah yeah it it it it kill most feel worse than getting hacked because you're just being frustrated everyday
Nothing to show for it
For coming on the show
Thank you very much for having me this week's episode was recorded and edited by Dean white produced by
Lorenzo franchetti BK and hosted by me you'll be hearing from us next week