Eagle one package being delivered everyday 1.1 million
People travel through American point of entry according to statistics from US Customs and Border Patrol
Almost 700,000 are people coming in by land of those numbers
Almost 300,000 coming by privately owned vehicles
The same time depending on their way in CPT gets fingerprints photos biometric data
Passport IDs and license plate numbers of all the millions of people who crossed the border
Which is why when motherboard reporter Joseph Cox reported in May
The hacker known as
Boris the bullet Dodger
Yes that's undoubtedly a snatch reference
First Supply
The bullet
His heart is the Hemet process
Just impossible to Kill the Boss 2
Said he'd hack a license plate reader company called perceptyx
Been posted a large cache of the stolen data
On the dark web
Now less than a month later CBP issued a statement confirming a data breach at Roberts contract
The details of which line up with
The Prosthetics
We can't confirm perceptyx was in fact the official breach
One thing is for sure
The news showed how your data
Did you willingly give up to the government
Can you hack and dumps online
Against your will
About the story we got mr. Cox
And motherboard EIC Jason Keppler
Discuss just how massive
Vacations for future data retention are
Just think about it
This story comes on the cusp of groundbreaking attempts by the CBP
Use facial recognition software
Along the border and
Collecting visitors social media information
That's we've got for today's very Big Brother episode
I'm Batman and this is cyber
LOL oh well guys
Thanks for being on the show
He's our first three three person pod the first three person pod
Amazing
Two interviews at once
I'm very lucky
Milwaukee guy Marvel Round Table than anything around table
How much for Round Table atmosphere
So just about start with you
So we initially go to tip
On a Thursday morning or mid-afternoon from this hacker who killed himself
Which is completely a snatch
Snatch refere
Yeah absolutely
Old English m
Gangster movies
To get this email
Reached berries of a company's before
Is pretty common nowadays to
Break into somebody's doing the date
So you can see Miles saying
Becoming cool except
And they choose available on the dark web
And then we were posted.
Pizza Company
I mean
Only railings
Sting
In that involves the US
Evening directly because
Very good
What's with customers of this contractor
It was a pretty run-of-the-mill
Data breach
At the time apart from
Cookie Simpson
Information that round boulders
But that was it was kind of normal takes prehistoric
Did you know what
Government Apartments
I mean in that other references
Did the DEA and Customs and Border Protection
Dino
This is so fly PDF
Ndia is not focusing
And then
What is a lot of reporters on Tallahassee and she went through and provided was this
Contacts
Department
Stop
Deceptus has worked with in the past they have these
License plate readers installed on their 60
Do US Canadian on the Mexican border as well
Toshiba
Rescan license
Ryan that used to work with Northrop Grumman
As well which is
Obviously
Hi us
Military military
Contract
But it's time we we
Like Joseph said we didn't really know
What was Indus
At the time did you contact Customs border
Troll
Various
People who would be affiliated with this
Contracted
As far as I commanded the only people who take it back to us was
An employee of the
Exid
On the
He says they on Friday I believe
Statement to Major Supply
Yes the breaches happened
Pending legal case
That was possible verification
Thoughts
Then
There's nothing
Around 11
The core Services explosion
When CPP transition statement
Did you have to find it yourself over this and then I got sent to you
So the Washington Post reporter that
As well as
BuzzFeed TechCrunch in a
A couple other places but they all reported at the same time and it was a press release that's
He sent out
How to select
Shield
Journalist
When you saw it
You thought yourself this is
Basically the Washington Post ran a two-sentence article that was like
He said that traveler
Data
Has been hacked
Installing
And that's all that's all it's that
And I was like oh holy s*** this sounds exactly like
Call Joseph reported a month
So I just was offline because
He is in a
Time zone and it was
Like later in the afternoon so I emailed cussing and barber
Patrol and I said hey
Like what's going on here is this
Perceptyx hat
And they send me the same
A statement that they said
Send to everyone else
And I think that's what
Makes this very in
Interesting or it's not that interesting it's more
Ascent
Not to do around
I act like this because it's obviously
Extremely sensitive data
Ncbp handle that in
I'm probably the worst boss
Possible way
Strike because
You read the initial statement
Matthew said they say that
Well
Some hotties of stolen
License plate images and quote
Triphala images
Collectible
CPP
When you leave.
Statement
And basically the headlines rule saying that
Oh my God
Customs
You got into quite rightly assume this
Quotes of entry into United States when your face gets kind and a single queen
And it sounds
Absolutely huge I mean to be totally honest
When is Jason said that it was late for me
I see a message and I come online
Initially I didn't even think it to the fact that sounded so much bigger
Turn the story when he published a month ago by the phrase and if the statement
And by leaving out
Who many specifics
It seems that customers really
Blew up
Significant
What is Northline
As far as We Know
Old is the information provided noshiko
Did JFK
Square photos facial recognition database is like some some journalists instead like facial recognition database.
1 by
Hackers from CBP and like
That's not what
ET sad but their initials
Steven was so big it's a
Traveler images you know stolen from a sudden I come back
Yasso
And then they said that
The Traveler images
Nvidia Cuda
Do you have some specific
Points of the folder and specifically like to go free
Lanzhou
Does traffic
Wow
This is like a perfect
Timers Festival why did they wait a month to damages find down for whatever
How do you say to this way to
24 hours to get the information
It would have been so much better
The clocks in some capacity
Additional statement
Significantly reduce the impact
Yeah I really want to know what's going on here because TVP has been
Pretty vague about
Just like the specifics of this
But it said you know on May 31st
CBP learned about a subcontractor getting hacked
I think we reported the story like
May 20-something they made the statement June 10th it's like
Why did it take them so long to gather information and then
Why wouldn't I be in the in the original statement because they sent a second statement like
2 hours
Where's later 3 hours later but it was already too late it was like
Washing posted renovada New York Times send a news alert like
It was out there and people are writing about it and
I'm not sure how much
Like I haven't really seen Congressman like we need to have hearing then sort of like having that hold next
Step of the new cycle happened but in any case
What were ultimately talking about here if this indeed was the perceptyx hack
Which CBP hasn't said that it was
But we
I think it is because they sent
The Washington Post a Word document titled
Perceptyx
It just bungle it's like
PR bungling and usually the way that this works is
A company or the government will say
Oh yeah like some data was stolen it wasn't that bad and then it comes out later like
Actually this is way worse than originally thought I mean maybe there bumble
The cover up a little bit of the damage
Control
And they're not really seeing the scope of this because mean
For me hearing this story
Yes is a journalist I hear
The two statements
For how much
F****** that was
Giving us
As journalist more
Nation to go with and also
Making a story much percentage
But the fact that there's a company
That had
Private data of citizens in people going through the Border this
Miku gives their fingerprints
Knowingly to the US government for nothing
Right everyone I've done it
I'm sure everyone else is done at the country that border Global Entry
Yeah
So when we agreed to give information to the government
Neurocore
Chocolate reasons
The US
That doesn't mean the date it was only going to be
With the cousins
Right at school
A huge chunk is going to be with contractors and subcontractors in Dunedin
Megabox
Exactly Manassa tell you this Joseph even though
The stuff you did on geolocation tracking
SIM cards
I mean this is something that you think you're getting up information
Knowingly
Protected in
And it's going to trickle down
Yeah and even if you don't even know where it ends up
Could end up with
I'm you out these exact agencies
Are pushing for bigger and bigger
Powers midnight I was reading at CBP
Wants enhanced facial recognition
Spider-Man spider verse is getting better than old example now
YouTube how to remember that course
Snowden was working for Booz Allen
The company that employs
Edward Snowden this not the center of the US surveillance program leaks Booz Allen Hamilton
Is there a name technology consultancy firm domain client is the United States
They work with nearly every Federal agency from the Environmental Protection Agency
To the Department of Homeland Security another one of a number of private contractors who profits have exploded
Since the huge rise and US intelligence spending since the early 2000s
When we do have
Significant tysabri choose from
Intelligence agencies
Samsung
Humane Ohio
Will do
More than anything
Actually
How do you say
We just a truck Wheaton
Actually know where it's at
We've no idea and it's just
Its and it's shocking to me that CBP
With the statements we going back to the
Thea questions
These statements
How Cavalier they were at first
To sort of schluff it off
Yeah and then
I mean what's
Well system traveler images and Justin Traveler
Less than a hundred thousand people that's a lot of people
Yeah I know I don't really know
What sort of cyber security
Investigative powers
You know
TVP has at the moment or this
Sophistication but clearly it doesn't seem that too
Sophisticated
What's going on here which I think is
Is pretty concerning
You know in that statement and initials
Statement they said
You know none of this data is available on the dark web
And we haven't
Published
The store yet I'm not sure if
We will get it by the time this
Podcast comes out
To be determined if there's a story on motherboard
About this
Then we did get it and if there's not then it didn't really work out but
This data the perceptyx data is on the dark web Joseph is downloading it
Tia Torres taking a really long time
And the file names in that
Play suggest that this data is on the dark web
So
It's either a different hack and
Play custom border patrol
Isn't saying who was hacked would you guys should say who was hacked
It's the same one and Customs and Border Patrol has no idea how to download anything off the
The dark web
Or
The data that's on the darkweb is something completely different and all of the
Like what is what is the date on the dark web
Because
It's license plates
And
It's images
You know
It looks like it's from the border
Yeah I would just ask that of course we can.
When and how
Want to publish this but yes
Downloading the data
Is troublesome
And if we going on the assumption that it is accepted
Is it good
CPP before they go to the incident response company in whoever that maybe he'll be a little more and I have the number of expertise Augustine
Maybe they simply did not know how to actually obtain Nastasia
Without going into specifics is not as simple as going to websites impressing download you have to use a very special
Traffic through tor
Because of that
It takes a hell of a long time to download try to irrespective house Austria
CB said that was
Some specific information on the dark web
Looking at the
Smile Direct
Released
It looks like that date
Is the
Goodwill Seattle
It just also shows how Lucy
This defense
And surveillance
Contracting works the US
You know I keep a certain point you're getting these
The third-party contractors
I'm sure they getting paid quite High
And they can't control the data
But this is something it's so indicative.
The entire process
Government Contracting for very serious
Yeah I'm in a lot of these companies obviously they have people go through
Security protocols and gets
Security clearance
This isn't stuff like that but
Once it leaves
Is the US government like
You said it's
Not the safeguards are not
They're in the same way
CBP set at this company didn't follow
All the guidelines but I mean we don't know that to be the case
Could be very easily that this company just got breached the way that
Tons of supposedly secure companies get breech all the time
I mean here's a question for you mean
If we can say this
But this hacker
Do we know I know Joseph
She said
Does a hacker you know
Today hack similar types
The Targets in the past this seems to breach a whole slew of different companies that insure
When is the other targets completely covered with an internet infrastructure
Particularly popular in Germany
Shops
Companies
The Mandate when it comes to identifying and choosing targets I imagine
It's anything that happens to me
When they hatch.
German company
Full and then some of the company also told me that
Doctor refuse to answer any question
Antiseptic
Didn't elaborate time between extortion attempt
Gibson
Packers preview
Activity I mean that would be my sis gasoline as much as I sit there like some stew Financial
Is this a case of a hacker dumping only a trickle of what they have
And trying to maybe get there
Company to play ball or
Do you think
But they got to put it on low
I mean typically you receive small amounts online and then
Trying to extort more money that would make sense
Mike's Pizza
That is no
A song
Even 10 gigabytes
Material this is
So much stuff
Sure maybe they have some more but at this point it doesn't even matter
Ambassadors
Business
It doesn't seem like a sample
Ncbp is there any any question that they'll come back and give more information
Honest well I can email a wave secret about saying Hey look
You set the specific information was on the dark web
I believe it is there is some evidence and they do just
No comment on the
Austin
So
I don't see them
Initially being more forthcoming by again because I do
Is possible for any effects
People may not believe that was Alexa
Senator Ron Wyden asking
Inform the people who hides
Included in the states
We don't even know if the government agency that she knows that at this point
I do see them potentially issuing more information how helpful.
Is going to be is
Do you think this is at all
CBP is ability to then go to Congress and ask for water powers
I don't know I mean I'm sure some
Lawmakers may be wide enough his movie use this as sort of an example of
Hey if you want to expand Powers especially this is the sort of thing that can happen
The most convincing arguments in the world
To think about
People
Maybe to make sake
Because it is a useful case study 2.2
Yeah I mean I guess everything to is the world needs subject very closely
Try explaining this breach to somebody who's voting on this
Who doesn't quite understand
Subcontracting
Twista balance
Company
5cb
BP
Equal CBP serve wrongdoing I get to them maybe they'll think of
Add some more policy
Initiative to it and you can
Prevent this from ever happening given the face recognition powers that they
I mean I guess just remember
What you mentioned earlier
Ace Hardware
Even government Department
And I was there a debate tonight Correctional the program Society ends up alone
The end
Superuser little people caring for these food as well
You know what other countries that don't do this in terms of what state
Maybe in five eyes
NATO
That just kind of data to government departments
No as far as I know
I mean again
It's just a contract
He's such a
Voice of hearts
Because of course they technical know-how or the ability
It's going to be within the government
Governments don't go to Country
Because the contracts can do it cheaper will because maybe they have knowledge
Right
In this case
I can't really I don't want to
Speculate but
This seems like a
It's almost a
Content
That's why I was
Do you want to
Get that technology
Reggie from that
Company
You know use
Will get yourself what if the subcontractor
Using the
The actual License Plate Reader
And the information retention
That seems like something that can be easily
You changed attention when you coming through this
According to the CDC statement
The second one it was
Only one last month.
Hello longer
Not long ago
Yeah it just depends how much these people collect bees
Of course if you don't collect
Certain pieces
It's not going to get breech tonight something to probably
Companies
Social contract
Aloha tattoo
Noah most of these types of companies that get rich like this do they pay
How to say I mean the
It does happen
Especially when it comes to
Snow White Witch
Marshmallow
Deliberately looks down a device sometimes
Hey are you
Toronto my role for down to try to take them out of the system
It's
Is difficult to say another
Another Hudson group
Face claims
The same
Another
Generate pressure
2% off Xmas tree Spokane
In a previous episode
So
Is apparently effective
Wechat don't show how much
EPay
Victims aren't really going to war
Will you think I'm taking his
Perceptyx maybe they got breach no way that was
Pretty difficult
To do
And
CBP statement saying that
They screwed up
I serve also feeds into this naming and shaming kind of
Environment of service
Security.
You know the minute a company gets
Breached we all
Kind of pointer finger and tell them
Oh you're the worst
You should have done better when really they were taking the precautions
And nothing the day everyone's going to get hacked
Yes courses how to say we don't know exactly how pathetic
I was just say that
I believe in the day
Secret be issued a statement I did get back in touch with
Antisocial
Who sings this
Was
You without
Even just replied hey unwell
Thank you for asking how are you doing and then he said that
I think that idiots manage the company
Don't have
The highest opinion
Office company.
Doesn't he have more sympathy for
Well worth the bullet Dodger I get strikes again
Hi Joseph thanks for being on the show
This week's episode was recorded by John northcraft
Edited by Gene White
Voiced by me and produced by Lorenzo franceschi DKI
You will be hearing from us next week