Eagle one package being delivered so citizen lab track government
As you can imagine the human rights Watchdog likely pisses said governments off
Motherboard a pillar of cyber security reporting but there are those who wants
Recently private Spy Service of some kind was hired to go after citizen love but citizen lab
Back and oh so spectacularly I'm about to speak to John Scott Realty in Racine
Any researcher at citizen lab who helped entrap in a sting operation have a spy trying something
I've been a coup and this is cyber
Start this off
Can you tell me what is it
So citizens visit research group
Based at the Munk school at the University of Toronto
And
More than a decade be focused on trying to understand
The different kinds of digital thread
Face by
Civil Society
So that means
Hacking attacks against journalists
Or attempts to limit the freedom of speech
Online
And our interest
These days
Is heavily focused
On
The growth and proliferation
Tools for hacking
And how they get abused to Target
People like human rights defenders in descendants mothers
And how many enemies
You have
Well I think we also have a lot of friends
But I certainly this case you just that we've done something right and that someone doesn't like or do I
Yeah because that's the thing I mean this this story
I know there's been a lot of
Talkative Ben connect
Did some of the work you did
Identifying
NSO group and
Connection to
Saudi Arabia
Take me to that
Chorizo
We've been working on this
Company for awhile first
Showed up in 2016 when off and on sore
And uae-based human rights Defender was targeted
With Pegasus
Spyware
Since that time we focus on trying to understand both the sort of global proliferation of this technology
So when governments are using it
And then digging
Pretty deeply the specific cases
Of abuse
That research took us last year
And some work live on a colleague bill marczak
To discover that a
Canadian permanent resident
Named Omar abdulaziz
Wheat-based in Quebec
Was targeted
With Pegasus spyware
Now
Omar is well known for being a close confidant
Of course
Brutally murdered
And the Saudi consulate
And assemble turkey
Last year
Yeah it's connected to him
I which is obviously something that was extremely high-profile
And we know that Saudi intelligence
Is pretty ruthless and how they've been going after the
Two I think part of the big
Concern here and Surly the concern that Omar has had
Is that she was working very closely with
And we doing things that the
Saudi government
I really didn't seem to like
End
You know his concern of course is that maybe some of his
A Communications with your mouth
Or intercepted because his phone
I've been hacked and that that that may have been part of the dossier compiled against GMO
Relate to
Meeting
What happened in Toronto
So
Discontinued
Research investigations after that case
But towards the end of last year my calling Behar
I received an email Arlington message and someone was trying to get in touch
And this person
Who represented himself is Gary Bowman
And said that he was a South African working from madrid-based Financial technology startup
I was interested in talking to my calling Behar
About
Financial Solutions for refugees
And of course Financial things are big problem for refugees just getting banking or a credit card can be really hard
And this is something
Which behind as well because bahari's himself
Katrina from the conflict
In Syria as well as being an employee
Citizen lab
So the conversation
Moves from LinkedIn to email
And pretty soon Gary is setting up an opportunity to me
At the Swanky Shangri-La Hotel
And Toronto at the end of last year December
And instead of being a conversation about financial Technology Solutions for refugees
It's kind of a conversation about Bihar
Who is Rey's parents are
What is political beliefs are
Does he pray
Does he hate is real
And then it becomes a conversation about citizen Labs work
And some pretty sensitive things
Involving our work
What role are we playing in some lawsuits against NSO group
What else are we working on
What else
Do we know
And when he's not asking Matt
The question seemed to be trying to go to the hard to suggesting that citizens have to work
On episode group and reviews of the spyware might be motivated by
Auntie songs
Citizen lab has lots of projects
We work on the censorship of information we work on hiking groups around the world
Handful
Different companies that make commercial spyware
But this gentleman
Was only used to be one company
ISO group
Which is kind of a bit of a giveaway mean it's also
White sloppy Tassimo
Questions.
Might lead you to think a certain way about who he asked
Unless you think that
District of Gary Bowman
Figure is trying to do is actually about four or five things
At the same time so he's trying to get
Bajar de maybe say something that could be used against Bihar
And he's trying to get whatever juicy can
On the citizen lab
Annie's been tasked with getting very specific questions
Answered
And he's looking for some kind of potentially
Compromising
Information on Bihar
That's a lot to do in one conversation into my mind it's a little bit of his conversational
Smashin crab so it's absolutely clumsy
But I think that
Observations that is probably
I got to do this a lot
And it may be the case that
Even if during the course of the conversation
The person who they're targeting becomes a little bit suspicious they can just evaporate when the conversation disappears
Nobahar
Notices he's being
Recorded de Zenon
Parmalee videos being recorded based on the way this moment character has replaced a phone on the table and pointed microphone
Business end
Edwards Behar
Now
As soon as that conversation was over bar called me and said look I think something really
A strange has happened here
And we can really
I take a look at this
So we do
And my colleagues and I determined
Really within a few minutes
Digging into this
Gary Bowman identity it just looks like some kind of elaborate fake
And we conclude okay
It looks like somebody is targeting us
Under false pretenses
Too long after that
I get in touch
With a Raphael satter of the Associated Press
And
Raphael using the Associated Press resources
Confirms that the address is used by
A company flametech
Don't exist in furthermore
Registered as a company
Anywhere
Moving from there
We get ready to do some kind of a publication
And then
Like
Perfectly timed moment I get an email
From somebody who represents himself is Michelle on bear
Amisha wants to talk to me about kites
About what
Will sue
When I started doing doctoral work a little while ago
I was putting the Buy cameras on kites
And flying them over slums in West Africa to look at flooding I was trying to try cow
Urban flooding was leading to political conflict
And violence
In Senegal
And this is something that is
Findable
On the bottom of my
Personal web page
And Mr lonebear represented himself
As an investor
It was instead using this
Admittedly janky technology
To try to do a really big money a large-scale agriculture in the infrastructure projects
In Africa
Action point
The team message that I got from lombera felt a little bit like Mad Libs
With a buzz words and jargon pulled from my own website
And baidu
So as soon as I got this
You know I fought
Great room designs it looks like I'm being targeted again
Let's see how long we can play this one out
And maybe turn this into something we can reverse on these guys
And did you ever
Reverses
Well boy did we ever
So the conversation progressed
From that initial email which of course I responded to immediately
Sounding excited
2 Series of email exchanges where I portray a version of myself that I felt my
Confirm
Wanderers theory of me which is
I'm excited in GT graduate student who would just love to talk about this you know goofy kite
Methodology so
You know I'm sending this guy messages with links to papers and I'm talking about through the development of new technology in the field
When I'm not doing that I'm saying how exciting and relevant it is
Andher proposes a phone call
And I decide okay well I'm not going to give this guy
Any real information about me
But I am going to give him a burner number and more than that I'm going to create an elaborate pretext
Opera stabbing
New York
So
I paid a burner phone
And then create a bunch of red Post in Craigslist posts
Submit myself to
A bunch of 411 Directory services in just about every thing you can think of
Entreat the legend that I'm in New York apartment.
Which also gives me a reason to tell mr. Bear that I'm a little bit cash poor at the moment but I think you know when
Would Peaches address
You're almost like you're all your honeypotting this guy in some ways
Will
You know I really want him
Come to the meeting with me
And so the challenge there is
Try to drive me to that conversation without seeming
Treger to museum
But he noted to play into his
Is stereotype about
What I thought but I think he thinks
I'm all about
He's good at making the calculation that you work
For citizen lab which
Does some very
Barely not cover up you deal with the cover world
And I know you all to be very knowledgeable about that
Phase of intelligence
That you're being
Thinks you're completely night
Well he may have just thought that you know if you talk to me about kites I wouldn't connect
It's my primary employment
So you know
We get to this phone call
And there I am sitting waiting for the phone to ring
And the phone doesn't ring
WhatsApp call
Nothing
Doing
So I sit there heart pounding
And think to myself
Shoot
He's on to me I've done something
I've been too eager
And it looks like this is going to work
Africa and it seems like
This
LS1 coil have to be postponed till tomorrow
No problem I say
Boy makes me nostalgic for being back in Africa when it was hard to make phone calls
So the next day there I am sitting in a hotel again
And this time lol bear does Cole
And right off the bat
I'm kind of taking it back because up until that point I've been having a word perfect English conversation
With a person on email
The call however begins in fluid French
Which is the language that I speak but I don't make a huge deal about it
I'm certainly it's not how most people would would reach out to me
Bear would like nothing more
Then to talk to me a little bit about kites but
Preferably without a lot of specificity
Which is good because I haven't thought a lot about kites in the past I hate you
So we should have both playing along this conversation
And pretty soon longberry suggesting it'll be really great
If we meet next week in New York because he's going to happen to be in town on business and
Why don't we mix
I work with pleasure and I have a nice meal
Great Ice Age
Let's make it happen
So longer than follows up
Suggesting a date and a Time
Introducing an alias
Thomas and Buckeye
Which is as fake as lombaire
Who's going to tell me the location once that's
That's my view that that's a ruse
In order to try to preserve a little bit of operational controls are not tell me the location until fairly late in the game
Making it hard for me to serve set a trap for them
And who knows maybe abused at location before
Whatever
So I'm in the meantime course communicating with the Associated Press
And I with Raphael satter
And Raphael and I are going to run this is a stay
And so are Rafael's going to bring some AP
Videography and a sports photography Talent sphere
And I'll have the conversation
And that is single from me
Lisa dwan
He will show up
Cameras rolling and ask Miss your lumbar some pointed questions
So
Waiting with
Impede breath
For this guy to respond finally the day before very exciting
Is Thomas in vodka
Alias tells me okay the location is going to be the Clement Restaurant
At the Swanky
5-star Peninsula Hotel
Great
Time to call Raphael and get him to get himself
And his people are reservation at the same Hotel
Same-restaurant
So fast forward to the day of the meeting
We're at Thursday of last week
And I'd spent the night before
Burning the midnight oil trying to
Fit a really small camera into a necktie
And I
I didn't know we have a lot of materials available as I start abusing like
Nail scissors and deconstructed hotels flipper
Wish I was using to kind of hold the material
It was kind of a reproduction it all felt pretty haphazard
So I arrive at the restaurant
And the person at the front or asks me you know
I got a reservation at I'm looking for this guy
Mr Lombard
Go back to the restaurant we go to the very back
And they're at a table behind a pillar
Is
A gentleman who looks
Sort of like his picture on LinkedIn
And before I know he's getting up and hardly reading in French
And I can bring me to another table
This one with my back to the restaurant
Nice window good lighting
And within about four minutes
Of the conversation beginning
Mulberry saying sort of offensive racist French things
And I think trying to get me to laugh along with
And I'm still thinking of myself
Gosh this guy's pretty bold right
You know we're barely started and he's already trying to get me to do this stuff
Well you know
He may have experienced that you know sometimes people get up and leave so he's got to try to get something in early
Write at least a minimum viable product
484a
Professional
Albeit
Somewhat bumbling spook
And it's for having this conversation which ranges from him talking about having cigars with the
I'll president of Africa to his daughter who's my age
On the phone call he told me
It was his son who is my age
I realize that there's a person who
Saturday nearby table and who's busy holding his cell phone
So I think okay
I think I get a sense of the layout in process that they're working here
Also mean while you're wearing a button camera
Well I'm wearing a couple of things
And by the way if your program needs like a lightly-used body mic with a little bit of chest hair on it
I've actually I
What's very you're kind of like
Working
So
One of the challenges in the conversation was to trial
Play out in a way that felt natural one of course
You know your mind is anything else but relax
So sorry Focus remix conversation making sure
Too pure to be the person who is enthusiastic
I think as I think he thinks I am
The conversation ranges in for the first hour it's mostly in French and we're mostly talking about Africa
And kites
And this and that
And I get the sense that you know the guy is kind of enjoying
Portraying himself as a high roller who smoke cigars
Nice mbutu sese seko and Idi Amin and everything else that he says
WhatsApp
Yeah I think all these African leaders
Yeah it was it was definitely he was playing at Full Throttle
And then
In about an hour in
The conversational pivot that I've been waiting for happens
To my great pleasure
Amuses to English
Which of course
It's going to be good for his transcription
And good for mine
And begins asking me questions
About NSO group
And make some kind of hard pivot
From some pretty
Intense and disturbing conversational topics like a novel about
And I'm Muslim and Jewish boy who grew up together in France and then
As adults they must
Kills his Jewish boyfriend
And by the way
Is citizen lab
And I know some investigations in Mexico that we've done
But there are some counterfeit features about this
Dial do I soothe the briefcase is
This is legit and one of them is that he's got
So when we got this sort of chief of no cards that he
Shifting back and forth and is he looks at me
Listen to the audio you'll discover that there some pauses
This is what he said shuffling his
Is cards
You know look at him and smile and act like it's the most normal thing in the world
To have a dinner conversation with a person who's basically running off a teleprompter
Better at one point
You know he doesn't want to like hold the pen
And the note cards in his hand
Will eating sweet props the new cards up against the glass
And then is holding a
Panacea
And
Normally you know you hold the pen with the
Coin
On
The paper
He was holding a pen with the cap of it pointed toward me
And because the light in the angles
I could see that there was like a hole the hole in the top of that cab
He was pointing towards me my conclusion is
It's either a camera in there or microphone
He's trying to point at me
Okay so I got asked at what point do you just can
Will
You know we've been playing along for an hour and an hour and a half
And us
I get this message discreetly
From Rafael sangheili
The batteries on our lavalier mics are running low
Can we speed things up
And I I would have been happy to
Finish my creme brulee
By Thomas
At this point you know Michelle is also ask me some questions about my mom
So I decided
It's time to wrap
This thing up
I decide to
Send the signal
So I send the signal Rafael
And then
Start distracting
Michelle
Raphael satter shows up
Cameron toe
And
How is pulling up a chair and sitting down next to me she'll
Just as Michelle turns and sees him
Resulting in a moment of pure surprise
Do this at all scare you
Some of the work that you do knowing that someone's going to pay
Samax Israeli
Intelligence official or defense official 2
Spy on you and to try to
Essentially
Destroyer
Is look
We must be doing something right if somebody is paying all this money to send people
Around the world
To have a fancy meals with us
And try to get us to say things that could prejudice
Public view of our work
So we must be doing something right now
I'll be honest
With you it's very concerning
And this kind of behavior is
Unsettling
Which also does though is really highlight
To me and my colleagues
Importance
Continuing to pursue this work
And doing this as
Encouragement
To continue the work and to continue the investigation
Honestly I can't think of a better motivator
I've been a situation like this
And you know I
This is total in France
But you know this is hot on the heels of some
Some work that you did
Essentially upsetting the Saudi government
And particularly
What you imagine is
Is the Saudi Prince that is a
The center of
Brutal murder of a journalist
The only moment during the conversation when I felt a bit of a chill
Was when he laughingly suggested that after lunch we should go together to a cigar bar
Yeah and I really did not want to leave that restaurant you know he came in with some people
I came in with some people and
Wild horses running
How to drive me
I don't actually think that there was any concern there
But as you said
Context what was going on
Obviously
I was going to
I mean
It's fair to say
This kind of establishment
What does intelligence mean
Engaged in it
As reporter as well and there's
There's certainly this
You know this overarching fear that you can have
When they're around because the other people who are
Need to do
Criminal things for governor
So here's the question
Are they bumblers
Or the threat
And I don't think it's a
Either or I think it's
I think it's a bit of both
I think that this person
Probably have done this sort of thing a bit too much and become complacent
That said
I have no illusions
It's about the complacency of his employer is
Or their motivations
Tattoo harm to The credibility of the work that we do
Absolutely
I mean I guess you don't from
Another standpoint
If it is indeed
The people that
Very widely been inferred to offend
Purchasers of
EServices
Came down on
It's sad that
That's happening
And that's
After the fact
If there was a global outcry
About
A brutal murder
Of a journalist
We don't know who hired
The company that hired Michel or through What You Know series of intermediaries that took place in
We really can't say
Quit wifesavers a company or government
I did it
What I will say though is that
The
Commercial spyware Industries 50 years
Responding to Reasor's like ours by saying look at the end of the day we're ethical
And
And although there may be some misuse
We're trying to support law enforcement they were trying to support you know the identification of terrorists
And criminals
And I think
Case like this
Really makes the point
Bed
The industry is kind of
Out of control
I'm capable of behaving very recklessly and ways but that don't seem to have anything to do with the law enforcement or catching turn
And a lot more to do
With trying to discredit a researcher is working in the public interest
Raphael satter broke
Associated Press
So please tell me from the start how did this happen
This one fell into my lap and I was really really lucky
John scott railton at citizen lab
Give me a ring or drop me a line and he
He said that hate something pretty odd is happening
He explained to me that one of his colleagues have been lured to a hotel in Toronto
And had been quizzed in detail
About his work on the NSO group
Israeli spyware company
Added after the meeting
The guy was so weirded out that
He spoke to John about it
And then other colors
Citizen lab
The whole episode and they realize that this guy
The guy that they dead
The researcher met at the hotel was not who he said he was
And it is company didn't look legit
And that
This look like this have been some sort of weird undercover operation
That's why I said well alright that sounds like a pretty cool story
Intuit
So we started
Everbearing details
Of what this individual had been saying to Citizen lab
You can have pizza Department
Damn this is not
This is not a real witch
Yeah I was pretty clear that this institution was not legit the company that this guy claimed to work for his company called
Flametech
And if you go to the website
Although it doesn't exist
Did go to their website
You would see
The kind of thing that you'd see on any kind of sintex start up in a bunch of gobbledygook
About blockchain and Bitcoin and
You know context defined
Future
And
It all seems about as non-credible as
Any other
Silicon Valley
Weird startup
Except that in this case
It didn't really seem to be anybody working for flame sac
We we looked at the guys LinkedIn profile
And he had a kind of strange Moody black and white photographs with sunglasses
The kind of thing that you
That you use if you didn't want anybody doing any kind of facial recognition on you
And we look through the LinkedIn pages that were associated with the company
And John Scott Realty in spotted that
At least one of the guys was using a piece of clipart
As his LinkedIn profile
Our stock footage rather
And answer that already got John's
Fishing shop
And I went to the library and I did a bit of research
And I looked up
Playing tag on the Spanish business registry and I realized while there is no flame tacking in Madrid or anywhere else
When did anywhere else in the world
So this company wasn't registered
They didn't have a registered trademark
They the company Executives who claimed to live in Madrid wasn't in the Madrid phone book
The little by little we started to confirm John suspicion that this whole thing was
Except
I think the question you asked yourself next is
Who is this guy
And what is flametech
What's Baha'i
Batting around ideas
Who is behind
And of course
All of us were intrigued by the fact that this guy
You claim to be called
Gary Bowman
Add ask questions about the NSO group
Prove anything
Direction the middle of trying to
Puzzle our way through this
When John Scott Realty himself
Gottman approach
From a different company
This one in the Agri Tech business based out of Paris
Called CPW Consulting
And and I was really about to
Hit the button on a story to send to my editor went when John said hold up
Iva now I've been contact
And we looked at this company CPW and once again
Same pattern
Kind of
Vague websites
With a bunch of
Very
Big business descriptions
And when you dig into the French business registry you realize what there's nothing really there
So we think we'll all right
Now there's
Looks like there's a second company in the back
And usually gets exciting because
The guy wants
Stew meat
Okay so they agreed to meet again
In New York City
What are you do
I get very excited
Start with this is a great opportunity
It said that this poor guy by her.
Rosati was lured to this meeting
They tried to ask him leading questions about Israel they might have
Recorded him who knows who they are
But now we got a different kind of opportune
We got an opportunity to actually ask
Play to be undercover agent
Himself
Not only that but we can do this on video
So not many people know it
He probably read at the Articles rcap photos in in the American Media are the English-speaking media
JP actually has a has a big television service
And I thought what this would make
Great television
So I fly to New York on short notice
I joined John husa was already in the city
And so we agreed that because
John is a little bit concerned that
Somebody might be tracking them that we're not going to meet up in person
Add a time
We start working on a protocol for what we're going to do at the
Hotel because by now
This operative
I said why don't you come and meet me at the Peninsula Hotel at the restaurant we're going to we're going to get a very nice lunch together
And John makes arrangements
For a couple of uninvited guests to show up Midway through the lunch
So I make a reservation under an assumed name at the restaurant
And I bring along my AP college
Camera hidden in
In a duffel bag
And so we try and dress up all the way
Apparently didn't dress up quite well enough
And we sit down to dinner and as luck would have it
The the waiter brought us
Directly
To the table that was
Across
From where John and his undercover operatives were already seated and already deep in
The conversation
So now what we have to
To do is wait for the right man
This is the
Straight up spicy
Even weird it right because as we get into the restaurant
I have a strange feeling about one of the guys
Who's sitting
What's a catty corner
A Jew or just over my right shoulder
He's sitting there alone
And
Kind of staring into his phone he's sort of scowling
And he's just got a
Pick up in front of them or maybe a coffee cup
And he's not ordering anything to eat anything for lunch
So that's a little bit strange and all he does is
His phone around sort of scallops
End up having nothing except the deed the cup of coffee
And then leaves and we make icon
Sit down
So I feel like that's a little bit odd and John and I have discussed this ahead of time we said
It probably won't be just the one operative in the restaurant
These guys are professional to probably have other
People around
And
I think I'm getting a little bit paranoid
Is that the guy
If is it another spy
What about the people at the bar
You know they're hanging around they don't seem to be eating anything there they seem to be glancing over in our Direction every once in awhile
Do I have to
Keep driving keep my eyes on the menu and on my
Lunch partner because in Siri were there to have lunch together and
Conversation
And we know that we both clock John and his
We realized we probably shouldn't look over we shouldn't stare we don't give anything away let's just have a nice meal
And that actually proves more challenging than expected cuz the 8-piece budget doesn't stretch that far
And the stuff at the Peninsula Hotel is really expensive
So we start strategizing about how we're going to
To squeeze out
About $70
To cover our meal and it's a real challenge
Okay so tell me what the confrontation
Do you actually go
You ask him
I can overhear the conversation that the Donna and each other happy
Half French half in English
And then at 1
Point we have a photographer who's loitering around downstairs she's she's waiting for anything.
Happen to anybody
Hotel
And she's getting a bit bored because what we are trying to enjoy about half a dozen oysters
And two glasses
What line between us
He's out in the cold waiting for waiting for something to happen nothing's happening so she texts me and she says
Is this thing really happening
You know maybe John realize that the guy was legit after on they're just having a good conversation
And that's when I can over here over the noise of the restaurant the words NSO
From the other end of the table
And that's when I think okay
Definitely confirmed
This is exactly what we think of it
Highway
Patiently takes about 2 hours but I wait patiently for John signal
He sent me a text message
It says okay
Now
And then I
Send a little text message
Photographer downstairs saying keep your eyes peeled something's going to happen
And then I turned to my lunch companion that I say alright in time
So we both get up
John at this point distracts Michelle by having him look at something out the window and wow look at that tax
Things that affect
And I Wander over to the guy meanwhile address
The cameraman
Stop the camera out turn it on
And I sit down
Right next from Papa chair
And I say hi Michelle it's really nice to meet you
Shaking hands and stress
Concussion
And how does he react
And it's got you
I'm 60 Minutes got your stuff
He's not happy
He he seems to stiffen a little bit
He shakes my hand and then rapidly pulls away
Keystart
The kind of cover his face a bit
And finally when he realizes what I'm doing and what I'm asking him he says something to the effect of
I don't need to talk to
And I say
Actually said I really think you're going to want to talk
And I get out my phone and I show him a photo that my APK
Comparison
Just taken
His office
And I say
We had an AP reporter who just want your office in Paris
2 minutes ago
And she took this photo
I saw what you did that she took a photo of his office
With a piece of paper in front of it saying
Hi Michelle
And
And I say
Well I mean we wanted to be sure that he couldn't
I didn't want him to be in a position where he said
No you have the wrong idea I just have an office
Listen Paris I'm allergic person I just wanted to prove
Spike the football
To really prove Beyond
Andy Dalton
We had been there we called him on it
He doesn't exist
There's nothing he can do
So he sees the photo that I show up
He starts putting his stuff away
And he says
I know what I'm doing
A little bit of a cryptic remark
So I say we should what do you mean you know what you're doing
And then he starts repeating himself he says stuff to the effect of I don't
How to talk to you
You have permission to film here stop filming me leave me alone
He gets up to leave he says ciao
And then that's when it just gets misterbini
Because
He tried to leave the restaurant
But then
The waiter
I did the waiter tell somewhere he realizes that he needs to pay the bill
So he have to come back to us
Meme of the camera still rolling
Right and I'm asking technician what's your real name
You said who do you work for
Michelle what do you think about the NFL group
And he's trying to spin around the room avoiding the camera avoiding me
Meanwhile John is also recording him because John had a GoPro on a mini took the GoPro out
Confrontation starter
So the guys being filmed from two different angles he's getting questions from me
He doesn't know where to put up self
And so he it's like a slow-motion Chase around the restaurant
As it goes around one table and then another table
And then eventually finally
He sort of breaks off and goes into a little back room
The restaurant
And complaints to the staff and thanks them for the bill
And at this point we figure okay
I think that's about all we're going to get out of this
I'm so fancy
I mean I think you put it best
At first we are describing this is like a John le carre novel and then it ends with this mr. Bean performance
Where are your kind of
Slow speed chasing him around and it's
Just kind of
It was a little bit that they can
You know I showed somebody
The video
And she said oh I
Sorry for the guy and and I said well
Feel sorry for him he's
He's there on
On some sort of a mystery mission
This is part of his work and presumably this is the kind of thing that
When can I expect to happen when you do this when you go into this line of work
But I must say it was
It was bizarre and I did expect the confrontation to last this long
I really thought that we just be assured from the restaurant within the within a few seconds
Sigma camera
Instead we were there for a good for 5 minutes
With this
Relatively weird situation of the guy
Trying to hide but not really trying to hide
I mean while the other people the ones that we caught
Earlier in the restaurant
They are talking to their phones real fast
Real hardly
Walking up and down
Stairs
Somebody somehow seems to pay the bill without any of us noticing
Strange stuff is happening so it is a little bit
Kind of hi in Spanish
And it is a little bit low comedy all at 1
I mean how bad can you feel for somebody or group
People who have been hired probably for thousands of dollars maybe
Essentially
Exploited human rights watchdog
Look at this right we don't we don't get paid to feel bad or not feel bad about it
It is what it is
I have to say that watching the video what it is hard not to
Feel a kind of
Of a pity for the guy
Or or or at least cringe a little bit
On the other hand
You know what this is this is the job and and I think that
John might say the same thing too I mean of course it's
It's outrageous
To have
Academics and researchers
Targeted in such an underhanded Way by I think
That's pretty unambiguous
But on the other hand this is the kind of work that we get into
And I wouldn't complain if
Somebody that restaurant had secretly taken footage of me and I was participating in a sting operation
So so this is what everybody signs up for
I mean that being said I think that there does need to be more attention to be
These kinds of things
I just happened on us soil
Right so when does wonder if
This is the kind of thing that
That needs a officials to look at
Justice is served asperges son on the kind of thing
Is this legal
I don't know the answer that question but but I'd love to somebody to look into that
I mean how do you feel
From the story I mean that having covered it
Are you a little bit nervous but now you're going to be targeted because
Yucca
You have to think I'm taking it you know I don't put words into your mouth but I'm looking as an onlooker
And I know that there is
A Saudi connection to the citizen lab
Report that
Goes into summer suspicion around who is hired
Spy on them
In varying incredible terms
Absolutely embarrassed
Eventually I mean if he's not ex-mossad he's asking
Intelligent likely
Me neither
Enemies
Aesthetic mist
Penis as it was
These are enemies that I don't
Sherpas
You
Here in journalism you want these kinds of venom
Sprite and bananas far as this guy is concerned
I think the New York Times recently identified him as some form of former or retired Israeli security
Official
And does yeah course it's a little bit
I think I'd be I'd be more concerned if I were John
But
But nobody planted again to the story a bit more let's see where it leads
I'm not really intimidated so much as
Little bit excited
But I won't hide the fact that yeah it's a little bit nerve-wracking at the night after the story
Make sure the door was locked and
I'll certainly be looking around
Little bit more hard when when you know I kind of have to go to your meeting or when somebody
You knows me out of the blue and stay by Cairo hookah great story for you
I think I might might hesitate a little bit
Well
Raphael
Thank you for being on the show with us
With an incredible story and I'm just glad to have gotten to talk to you
Personally to Beyonce
Totally fanboys
Thanks for that I really appreciate it as a huge motherboard fan
Absolutely honored
And I hope to talk to you guys again sometime soon
What episode was produced by Jason Tabler
Recorded and edited
Bhajan Warcraft
Thanks for listening to this week's episode
Did you like the show give us a review on Apple podcasts
What time your friends about us
We back with more next week