Eagle one package being delivered to the president of the United States
Some of his supporters journalists well we're your enemy
Is the enemy of the people and they are still CNN fake news MSNBC
That's really the enemy of the people we know the recording to reporters Without Borders for the cpj
Journalist being killed just seems to be going off now we that we can be ideal Intel targets for
Intelligence agencies and law enforcement
In other words we are under surveillance more than ever
Vulnerable to cyber attacks
Spine
This week marks 6 months
Best of Hrithik and outrageous murder of Jamal khashoggi by the Saudi regime
We point the Jets hat chats between him
Dissident
Health is killer
Think about that
Today we got Runa Sandvik
Former hacker turn senior director of information security at the New York Times to talk about the very hard
Task
How she keeps journalist
Safe online in 2019
I've been a coup in this is cyber
It's 2019
How do you protect
Journalist not only in the field
But
Online
That is a big topic for 3 years now and
When I started
The
My role was to build and create
And lead a security program for The Newsroom
And at that point you are considering
Security Basics and just started the awareness of the whole Newsroom
You are considering fishing
You're considering travel you considering the source communication and then in addition to that
Depending on
The desk
Individual the team the story The Country someone's going to
You can then add on top of that situated measures that they can take you can start looking at
Mobile phones
Travel laptops
Are gaps and what else
People need assertive bailed out
From there what you need kind of training is needed what kind of Hardware is needed
But it's like it's not like it's a quick
One item is not like it's something that's
Done and complete
Today it is a program that is consistently involving
Building out reminding people that is there
Yeah I mean also your you didn't exactly start at like you know the
The South Boise times
You know it was like you started the New York Times
Which is I mean
No shade at
Motherboard and the place I work at but is probably the number one target or one of the number one targets of nation
10 states of
Which doctors who want to exploit kernels because
You have some of the most important information
In the entire world
I would say that that goes for any immediate work
Really
I would argue with that even Vice
Would be susceptible to the same type of threads
Said any other media
I'm in the same goes for mediaworks another
Yes
I mean to put the difference being you're getting people who are getting information
.
Say the CIA or the NSA would want information like that
But you're
Let me near Times number one Target in the sense that it's the most obvious Target for somebody's Nation
To get information
Because you know as I have spoken to lots of
People in intelligence around the world then
They always tell me I have from Ulta
What you say
Journalist
You're the best targets
Your s*** security
And you have a lot of information we want
Before I came to the times I work with a lot of freelance
Reporters
And
They haven't even heard of more challenging
Position in which
They have the same
Type of sources in many cases and trim suggest the Insight the entitled to level that they're at or the info that they're providing
But the reporter has even less support and backing in terms of security
Or it support or
Hardware someone ensuring their laptops or after
Someone helping them secure their email
For example
Until you have this late challenge in that
Industry
Mediaspace of how do you secure
The people who are receiving the information and then interim how do you secure the sores and ensure that level of
Conn's is secure and to underswap
And I think there a meteor
Like the X Lake Vice
That have the
Resources to have an in-house team that can help provide that support that in-house long-term
Support in planning and initiatives
Are there a lot of music stitches don't have it
And I mean
Freelance
Porters are often the ones even
Traditionally before
Cell phones in
Computers in the internet what were the most vulnerable to
Tubing kidnaps to be
Being killed in some areas
Because quite often didn't have the same
Security apparatus
Supporting them
Yes the same challenge goes down for the jewels
Now you mention there was some sort of like
I mean kind of getting it on up to date
Maybe some out of resistance was there is there a difference between when you're trying to teach let's say
And Alder
Reporter
That hey you should download signal
And when you talk to his sword
You should only use signal
Is there a is there a run the gamut
No I think I think it just comes down to how your teaching it
YouTube two parts to what you asked about the first part of how do you get someone to use
Safety signal rain
And I would say that
It's more about how the trainer is
Catching the tool
Anything else
Because I can meet the keys to you that if you use this app with me
We have come into an encrypted comms and messages that
Auto delete after a set period of time
Those are not components that you care about that message is just not going to land
If I on the other hand say
Uses app and we have video chat emojis and you can call me for free maybe that is more of a pitch that is
So when you've been trained different types of people you need to be able to have cigarette very quickly what kind of message is going to land
Right okay so then how do you I mean
Well then how do you sell that to anybody other than the Nationals
Security team
The important thing is that you know I've had the same conversation with you about had some friends were lawyers
And I said to them you know when you do some of your and spoiled you wasn't very big companies
Imogene do you ever use encrypted apps like no sew open
Open source might beat you know you your information is very valuable
Talk to a lot of people
As a people
Like no way I'm not think I'm not going to get high
Does it sits in the messages today
Do you have to start making it more specific to a used skis that day Caribbean so that if it
Sew-in in some cases the
Individual
May just have to
Experience that on their own before they actually start taking the steps that they should have taken a long time ago
But in other cases you just have to come up with
A use case scenario and example and anecdotes
Historical example
That makes that land with them
And in some cases even just saying
If you start using this app with your desk
Kingdom dad
Becomes
A normal component in your workflow and so suddenly
Alice and Bob also on your desk using this app to actually communicate about something that is sensitive doesn't stand out
In any way shape or form this is just
The app that you just have decided to use
.
So I mean
This is a very broad question but how important is it
For journalist
To take their online security serious
Follow up questions to that is how important is it for journalists to protect their sources
Bright
So would you say that right now if you're a journalist near protecting
Asaurus
Or can you sing with why would you think it's irresponsible if you're not taking some the precautions
That you would
You would suggest
Absolutely it mean if you're going to argue that you would go to jail for a sores
Why wouldn't you turn on two-factor for us
Brain
You can say that you are willing to take the steps that are necessary to protect the stores if you're not doing that
Digital site
Bright
Have you ever been involved with
Say I'll give an example
The Interceptor story
I got to do with reality winner winner.
You know
Some information that she gave them leaked
Urban asked in terms of I got this sensitive document
Orbitz
Sensitive
Piece of information
I'm going to go out with it
To the public
I'm going to run the story
Is there anything in this that could
Reveal who this person is
Having been part of
Discussions that touch on some of the
Portions of
That example
Baidu
I do feel like The Newsroom has its own
Policies and guidelines and standards are and how they've that the information that they
Get in then how to go about doing that they don't necessarily provide the actual price
Mangetout copy your photo album
The full printed out copy that
Let me just read a quote or the
Different ways in which you can verify the data that you've gone without
Giving away
You know the in your job I can imagine that
You also try to prepare people
For adversaries
That could be trying to get there in
Who are some of the adversaries
That you had to sort of prepare for
MPEG reporters for
I can't go into into details but I would say that it is really very easy can you can be everything from
Maybe at one point we know that a story is going to get
Certain hateful comments on Twitter
Or we know that a reporter is going into
Country where we suspect that their devices mean be searched at the border for example or
We suspect that they may be using some quick question and coming back home
There are so many different use-cases just depends on then the reporter the beat the
So they're working on Country they're going to
So what do you do to you
Because I've been to I've been to a few
Contact Iberia
I take my own precautions when you're going to say somewhere like let's
Say Afghanistan or
Eastern Ukraine
What would you tell the reporter to bring their
Cell phone with them
Or would you get a burner things like that
If you can get specific
What I do
For myself is I have a travel laptop and I have a travel phone
Set any point in time those devices are then clean and set up for dead trips
Specifically
So I'll have
The apps that I need access to I'll have NZ
I'll have a way to get the
Credentials for the systems that I need access
Hysterical happy phone numbers that I need on the specific trip
So that is any at any point in time those devices are lost or stolen or seized
I would only be exposing information that is
Relevant to perhaps that trip
Specifically and not like anything everything I had
Ever done in my life
Write a nested sort of
I just take the precaution that if he gets
The border and they want to start searching things and did you get access to it there's nothing to search for because there's nothing on it
Are even just in a case of
Someone grabbing your phone
Are you locked up being stolen or you accidentally leave a device in a taxi
These things happen it doesn't have to be
A police checkpoint doesn't have to be in
Interrogation at the airport like
You travel and things happen so let's just like trying to make sure that
If something does happen whatever that looks like that
Did they lose
Quote on quote
Is contain and you have a good sense of what that might look like so that it's not
Everything
So I know that like I mentioned earlier
Spies do tenant Target journalists because they're sort of these
Traditionally quite easy
You know easy prey because we're not we haven't traditionally been known to be very good at
Standing how to protect ourselves
Digitally
You have a lot of data we've got a lot of data though
Right
One thing I know that happens in
In other places in terms of
Special governments
Where do sweeps
Offices
Etc
Do you party responsibilities
Sweeping making sure that let's say the New York Times isn't bugged
Physical security
I'm falling under
It doesn't
So you're protecting a network
So it's completely information security
Information security
We do collaborate closely with
The team that is
Responsible for physical
Especially around
I'm only threats and harassment because there was came sometimes they start as a physical
Component but the Escalade online or by sea
So we do ensure that we are
Keeping each other up-to-date and in the loop on the different things that could happen there
On them
Hard to answer that question cuz I would say that we
Probably see the same type
Stop sign any other media Touareg
Either Caesar could see if they went looking for
Right but I meant to say
Are you seeing
Attempts at
Ida penetrating a network
Buy a phishing scheme
In order to
Gain information or you actually seeing
You know infiltration operations
Historically the time has been targeted by nation-state actors like China back in 2012
And we also see the lake
Whenever a common adware
Scam Bitcoin scam thing floating around so it's like
Whatever it is hitting
Other immediate words
We are likely to see as well
Rights of one of your reporters
What phase during a story that's quite sensitive and it's on say Russia
You might give them a
You know profiles
Security checklist in order to make sure you can
Security information you have in this is what you make you my
Expect when you publish the story Etc is that fair to say
So when you do that and in some cases
But
Dad model at scale would require
The reporters to come to us for everything that they do
So instead the approach
Tutu training is like you you established like a
This awareness Baseline in The Newsroom and on top of that you can start doing more specific training
West jefryn desks weather that is the
Investigations to ask some of the foreign bureaus
I'm some reporter said you know right about certain hot topics
Help them
See what to look for with your ex
How to deal with it
What did might look like on the screen what am I look like on like in their inbox on their phone
Things like that that is knowledge that would be very specific and helpful to them that
Certain desks is not going to benefit from then for example
Right so it's like you almost you have sort of a Baseline tradecraft
Security training set up like the farm for the New York Times
So you have the
The onboarding training that you get when you join the company
And that is like a security awareness
I would say Basics it's like that
Something to get you started and then from there we do have additional
What I would say would fit into the basics package and then more targets
Specific guidelines on on top of that
The New York Times was there always someone like you there or was this something that was a concerted
Referred by the X
How to say look this is becoming
A much more complex issue
And we need to hire somebody
To teach a reporters how to do
Back in 2001 as a 2014
At that point I had done work
Or the Tor project
Katrina water reporters I had done a lot of
Independent work with media Works mostly means
Scandinavian but also a couple in the US
Answer to work at the intersection of media in
Security for for a long time
And I think I'm meeting with it then say so at the times you were just talking about
Like they're doing what they're up to what I'm up to
He was talking about the challenges said
They were having an especially the certain needs of The Newsroom and it's just a very different field
And so I suggested that
That's exactly what I do so I would love to come and do that for the X full time
7 mm
16 was when they were able
How to create the role in Avatar
And I mean your advice we have a weave similar position
Anthony has a journalist it's been like one of the most
Helpful things
Even if sometimes
It seems like I already know this
Even just having someone
Taking a look for you
Example running
I had
Experiences with a run a background check on you as Security check to see where you're vulnerable
When you do things like that
What's been the response
Yeah last summer
Kristen and Nina on our team launched a dachshund Workshop
Initially with a doxxing cert service Ware
And if you gave us
Permission in writing
We would spend about an hour doxxing you and then telling you everything that we found and then teach you how to either
Lockdown the data or
Delete it
And then we don't turn that into a workshop so now we teach you how to dox yourself
And then
Which steps to take
And some guy has been really really helpful both for
Are working to connect with The Newsroom but ultimate for The Newsroom to start learning what kind of stops what to look
And also help their family members and their friends to the same thing
That sounds horrible
Doxxing yourself
I think I would destroy myself
I think between dad and lock-picking that we did last year I think a lot of
Criminal attorneys Canada
So clearly doesn't know what they're doing do you have to take some really basic steps
To take them to like
This is two-factor Authentication
Yeah so I would say like
We would start with passwords
Two-factor
And then sir to see how the conversation goes looking for
Some people that is a really really good start
I think other people are
Already up to speed on those two and they're already familiar with the advanced Protection Program from Google
And they had to Factor on
Everything else and they want to talk about burner phones
Franklin
But you can't approach someone who's not familiar with your doctor to talk about burner phones because
That
Workload that process service for challenges the pros and cons is just not something that's going to land with something some cases you
You have to start over
You are ideal which may be far higher up than where they're at and really meet them at their level to give
I'm some type of training
That's going to help them
Love a lot even if it's not to the level that you would like to see him be at
Right away
Have you ever had a situation when you sent a reporter somewhere
And you're like
Is actually like not a great area
There's not a lot you can do
Intensive whiteleg sending them links
Country oar
Let's ru7 country and the surveillance is so serious
That
You
It's
You're like you got to be extremely this is
Next level
You have to maybe not use your phone at all
You have an office in Moscow we do have offices in mainland China we have offices in
Hong Kong rain
People's travel
All around the world
How do you how do you defend your office in Moscow
Fry's must look a lot different than even China
To some extent yes and but again a lot of it is also
Early
Similar I think again we are teaching
Then face level
Plus the specifics on top of the van and then depending on the individual
What to look for in addition to depending on the country at the desk
Beat
Whatever it is that they're up to
I think that
While we are trying to teach
I think a good example would be to talk about the mobile apps and which ones are
The best ones to use 460 CARICOM
I'm so like instead of us trying to stay up-to-date on
You know the pros and cons of all the different apps that are out there cuz there's like constantly anywhere as everyday why not
I just teach
Here's how you evaluate in it
Here's how you evaluate
The
Country you're going to the situation you're going to be in the meeting that you're going to have with a source
So that at any point in time
You feel like you're in a better position to
Figure that out on your own so you don't have to run back to us every time because then we're going to become the funnel in the blocker for you get
Your work
Bright sunshiny enable disable of doing something
Don't think yourself I mean this is sort of how I've seen it
When I got a broader even here
That
Securing information and trying to keep people from prying into my information and knowing what I'm doing
Especially when it comes to a nation state
I literally just try to put up as many Roblox as possible
But I assume that at some point if they really want to get it
Probably
Can I get it
I think the way that we talked about that in infosec
Community over the past couple years is like making it more expensive for the attack
In terms of
If the password for your email is password and you have no two-factor
It's really easy to get in at that point like they don't have to try really hard they may not even have to like fish you
To get access to the account
If on the other hand you have Google's Advanced Protection Program
Meaning you have a password you have two-factor your email does get a bit
More
Squid Sweet Annie
Then that's going to be a much more difficult Target for an attacker to
Approach
Darden additional layers and you can put on top of that
Meaning the attacker just has to invest more time
More people more pools to go after you and the data that you have verses
Someone who doesn't have all of those features in place
And so in many cases
I'm it's just about
Like you said just putting up as many roadblocks as you can
Knowing that if they really really really wanted to
I mean it's sad too because we can do this and we can scrutinise are apps and which apps are great and which ones aren't
But you know when you look at
The example of Jamal khashoggi
She thought he was communicating on WhatsApp which is
Route to be known as a fairly secure chat app
Funny enough
It was comprar
The device
The device is not the app
No
But again
You could happen
It could happen right
Yes
And I'm sorry to say that
He was contacting me
Via my cell phone the one that was hacked
So I'm pretty sure that they were listening to
Interviews
They were leading the conversations that we had
In the case of a
Well resource well-funded
Powerful
Attacker
I need the touch of attackers that Target to me
Reporters
Yours probably
I mean when you see something like that that happens
Maybe I'm giving yourself your own job reference but
Did the New York Times think of stuff like this is why we
Investing
Security
Information security
As a journalistic Institution
I would say that yes that's the part of it I mean how can you going back to
Why this is needed how can you argue that you're able to protect your sources if you're not investing
In the security
But the company needs as well
And what's been the response among reporters since it since you came on the scene
I think it's been really good I think everyone's been very positive very welcoming
A lot of
People have a lot of really good questions like it's it's it's clear that
They want to learn the big one the info they want to know how to take all of these different steps
And it's so interesting
Think I do not have a team that is very available in RI accessible that can
So you can give any really simple piece of advice to a freelance journalist out there
Please listen to this
To secure themselves what would you tell them
I would say ensure that your
Phone and laptop are up to date including apps
You something like
Dashlane 1password LastPass
For passwords
And turn onto
And don't get an Asus
One more question
IPhone or Android
Which one
Secure
I strongly prefer the iPhone
I think apple has a really good track record
Securing their phones
And also for
Having a razor
Strong stands on
Privacy and
Security
It's not just saying that that you couldn't get to the same point with an Android phone but I feel like this more
Tinkering and constellations
Settings and
Elizabeth Moore
With Android phone
I mean I agree I had an Android phone like
5 years ago and I remember I got a pop-up ad on it
Without it like
Even being unlocked I thought to myself
This might be a problem
I might be
Vulnerable to a hotel Wi-Fi or two
What are some of the threats that are faced
When it comes to the online space
Staying
Safe
You would say that
Inter goes back to the challenge
Ensuring that everyone has that bass line
Where
Up-to-date software and apps and passwords and
Two-factor
And
After Dad talking about the different roadblocks that you can put in place and ensuring that
Different people are able to leverage different
Settings to provide additional
Safety
Cuz I think
In terms of the
Actors
We are going to see everything from
Sophisticated actors and all the way down two more
Commodity adware scammers
And things like that
So it's really hard to pick anyone because it's her buns the gamut
Right but there are scenarios where I'm sure you might say to a journalist like looked
You going to go to this country and
Or even here
And
Spy agency is going to Target you
That could happen if their hair is wet
Batman switch
Alyssa.
Like whether they're in New York or the traveling to a certain country
Doesn't really matter they can still be a target for
An agency in any country
An agency from another country even being here
Well thank you for coming into the offices and advice to talk about
Tell me a very very important and near and dear to my heart
I think it was fun
Thanks so much this week's episode with produced by Lorenzo franceschi.
Recorded and edited by John northcraft we back