Virus
Eagle One
Package being delivered right around two years ago Marcus Hutchins better-known
Why is hacker named malwaretech was at the Las Vegas airport waiting for flight to go back home to the UK
Was hungover coming back from Defcon the biggest hacker conference in the world and that when the feds came
What's more at the time the twenty-three-year-old security researcher was hailed as a hero
Stopping the spread of the wannacry ransomware worm
On this week's cyber we talk to Marcy wheeler McClain journalist who covers National Security
She's covered this case from the beginning and it's going to tell us the story of Hutchins and where he is today
So
Marcy take me back to the beginning
What happened to Marcus Hutchins
2 years ago after death
He was
Getting ready
I need to board his plane to go back to the UK
The FBI came up to him and said hey we need to talk to you and brought him down into and
Interrogation room
And critically for the story interviewed him for 90 minutes
And then put them under arrest
And he was
In detention for over the weekend until he got a pair of really great lawyers
And it's
I know it's over
Marcus Hutchins who is he
And why was he significant story among the infosec community
What is a malware researcher
In May of 2017 when this Global malware launched
Across the globe called wannacry
It looked at first like an attack just on hospitals in the UK but it's now becoming clear that they smell delicious soft
Run Riot around the world
She did what he normally does which is register
The domain.
Seems to be a command and control for the malware
And
Unbeknownst
To him that ended up sinkholing the malware
So he stopped
The largest malware attack in the world
To that point in arguably
Would have
By just registering a domain and save the world
From probably some of the most malicious ransomware that's ever been created really
Based off of
So
Nsa's tools get leaked on online
And the US and UK government
Now attributed to North Korea
Turns it into this Global malware that but he
On his day off
Ends up shutting down just by Regice
For example in the UK
The the hospitals were being shut down because
They couldn't operate their computers their computers were being
Shutdown
Is that kind of impact that entire factories were being shut down
Because their computers were being
Basically held Ransom
And as I heard it she was hungover
At Las Vegas Airport which I cannot confirm or deny I have also been hungover after Defcon
The defense
I've been partying quite a bit
That he had slept virtually not at all and they also hinted at the fact that he had used
Some kind of drugs although they did not officially say what that was in Port so that it actually came to be
The issues that was litigated over the last two years is whether or not
When he was interviewed by the FBI
He knew what he was getting into because he was just wiped from being a death on all week
Why why did the FBI
Want him
What what do they want them for
Okay so they arrested him for Computer Fraud and Abuse Act because that's what you always arrest hack
And the Chargers really into
They arrested him
Having written
Hold that had been sold
To an FBI agent or Homeland Security investigations agent or somebody in the Federal
Back in
Teen
In Wisconsin
So it was malware called
Kronos
Stop
Had been renewed
In a couple of
Iterations and
Still sort of is used in some attacks
And he had written some of
Didn't happen yesterday at that point
It was
2 years old at the time
They would add some charges later but it was two years old at the
Prime
But he had been at Defcon here before
So
Somebody in Wisconsin
Baijiu
Piece of malware in 2015
He comes to Defcon in 2016 they don't arrest him then
He comes
Defcon in 2017 he's a hero
That's when they decide to
Is there any connection to that
The government says
Their explanation for why
They didn't arrest him in 20
16th of June 2017 is that
Somebody that
He gave
The malware to to pay off a debt
In
2014-2015
Basically
Became a narc
And one of the things he offered up the government was Marcus
And he has
West Hutchins showing Hutchins basically admitting that that he had written this malware
The guy that gave him up
Was not processed
That guy actually
Didn't did still
Did Robin
So the guy who committed the actual crime
Was not arrested
Marcus Watts
Why the FBI so intent on going after him
So this guy gif
Does the government chat logs involving her
What happened
According to them I think it was late 26th
So
Their claim is
They didn't
Have this evidence
Hutchinson sole 2016 and so the next time you come back in the United States
Which happens to be after he had
Wannacry
Then they decided
To arrest him but the other thing that's going on is it's very clear
Quotes from the court record mother things that I've
Been Told
Stop by him but by other people who are familiar with what the FBI was doing at the time
It's very clear that they wanted to arrest him to turn him into a name
So even in that first
90 minute interview with the FBI
They were saying
Tell us about these other
People you know
So basically what the head down whether it was in late 26
Teen p*** 2017 after they works
Trying to figure out who had sinkhole Wanna Cry
Bighead dumbness
Map of who Hutchins new online
And there's a guy named Benny who was his
Co-conspirator who's the guy who actually sold the malware
Had some ties
I think it's you
Ukrainian
Kind of
Network of Ukrainian hackers that a different part of the FBI not the part of the FBI been arrested
Hutchins not the FBI people who actually interviewed him
A different part of the FBI was investigating those ukrainians
Because
Hutchins
How to Interactive
With some of them online the FBI in their Infinite Wisdom said hey
Lex arrest
A guy who just
Save the world and try and turn them into our informants to get at these other half
That's the hope that's okay
I mean that's what the FBI always does
Why did thought it would be a good idea with the guy to just save the world I don't know but I'm not the FBI so I can explain to him
Remains in jail in custody
Just for the weekend
Motherboard Vice
Reported that he had been arrested and so the infosec community came out
For him and said we're going to raise money we're going to get your lawyers were going to be taken care of
There were some people who
Learned that he had been a rough
Did
Well they were still in Vegas so they stayed and came back and you know kind of rallied around him and so
I think the FBI assumed that he would not
Good lawyers
And once he did that sort of screwed up their plants
It's been litigated until very recently
Is the two-year process
So that he pleads guilty
In May
And
When you goes to sentencing that's literally the first time he's in a courtroom with the actual judge presiding over his case
And so when it came to sentencing the judge was basically like
I have no idea why the government thought it was a good idea
Prosecuted the guy who just saved the world
It's about 90 minutes from to say that ultimately
Chad Hutchins
At the beginning
Has there been a weight
To go to the judge and say
What do you think about the wisdom of Prosecuting the guy who just saved the world on charges that are years old
That the government agrees he's not engaged in criminally anymore
What do you think about the wisdom of that then
We might have avoided that hold to your process
But that's not the way the US
So what does this whole thing say about
The FBI and its
Perspective in a relationship
Towards
Packers
I mean it's a larger question about their
Towards how they solve crimes
Because they're always going to want to go for a foreman
Even though
Have they gone to Marcus
Instead
Do you know these Ukrainian hackers
Probably would have answered just as honestly as he did when he was
You know about the arrest
But they chose not to
Do that they chose to try and Cora Simmons
Is this relationship
That ended up not working
Hutchins been when he was interviewed and still to this day says he
Didn't have the information that the FBI wanted in the first place
But
They would have avoided this embarrass
You know they went for having
The corporation over him
Rather than just asking
And asking at a time where he was cooperating
You know not just on on wannacry but he was cooperating
With
The ncsc in the UK kind of equivalent in the United States of DHS
And chasing down wannacry in you know
Responding to malware so
He was working with law enforcement anyway which is one of the things that
The judge said and sentencing by the way
So it
Just it's a name that the FBI decided
Is that in the United States they were going to find a way to try and course
The Sabbath that's what they did
Infiniti no heat
Didn't he
Didn't have the in
Mission
They then felt
Obliged and I mean this happens
In a lot of kinds of cases
Bait bait bait I think felt obliged
To continue with the prosecution maybe believing that if they did so
If you were facing more coercion then he would
And
It just another cat going down the path
It was never a time and never a person who said
This is moronic
Turn around
Tell him to go home
And just stopped
Does process
And that's really
I know I've heard of
People within the FBI who were like this
Cuckoo for several reasons one because it
Stupid into because they do need to cooperate with hackers
And with researchers
And
And what happened to Hutchins was
Just so inane and it created a lot of bad blood with him from community
What does it say about the Computer Fraud and
Exact and how it's going to
Be used for
This as a press
Dangerous
For anybody who's in in eastern time
Wisconsin
And it wasn't just
Cfab ended up adding eavesdropping charges wiretapping charges basically
And in a number of places
Around the country
Software is not
Centered a wiretapping device
And Hutchins
His lawyers argue
You died and lost
And so now that's a precedent in this District
And again
They argue
Iudex selling malware should not get your prosecutor to CFA
They lost on that
And
The government
Seated and getting him to
To plead guilty under CFA
Because the alternative for him
Was
More more prison time
She's going home
So it works out for him
And he's not going to be subject
Milwaukee
But there are going to be you know some
15 year old kids Milwaukee who you know that the government is going to use these precedents and say
If you're researching now where we can go after you for CFA and end that is
Really dangerous
Also how do you you know how do you alienate the very people that can find this stuff
And inevitably save the world want to be hyperbolic but
It was unprecedented
In the sentencing hearing
Is he basically said you know it's not my job to park new but you sure
You should probably go get a part
Because you
Should be able to come back
This country and help us
Shut down
You know cyber security threats like you did
And to do that you're either going
I need a waiver or you're going to need
Departing so you should apply for a pardon
And you know hopefully that'll work
Again
You said
You just pissed off
The infosec community and made
The act of trying to understand how malware works
Criminal
So what next for Marcus
What's he going to do
What are the thing
The judge made of
Saying was that he had no intention
Rice
Immigration and Customs Enforcement to get their hands on Hutchins
What happens sometimes
If you're a foreigner in the United
States and you have been convicted
Is there's a formal deportation process and that
Can
Sometimes lie
Detention by Ice
Tomato
What's the point of saying look I have no intention
That ice
Their hands on the sky I have no intention of him being another
Statistics
If I were Marcus
I would leave
Sooner rather than later to prevent that
Happening
And he's going to return to the UK and
He's going to work
Again still in security and in malware research
And
He said he wants to
Do more teaching
Do more teaching of young people so they don't end up
You know developing criminal past
Contact
Did for him
What I find so interesting about this
Cases that it's obviously not a whistleblower situation but it's a situation where
The government wants to know something from you once information
You don't give it to them
They find a way to punish
Before I missing something I find we're seeing more and more of when it comes to stuff to do with infosec
Go to come to do with things that
Are involving sensitive
And it's just a real shame the
Clearly very Talent
The guy
Had to go through this entire ordeal
To the Head
Essentially be acquitted and now go home
It certainly Within
The hacking
Community
You know there are famous
Does cases most
Famous Abu but there are plenty of them of somebody who got flipped
So yesterday in the whole cyber security industry and the hacker
The hacktivist movement
Was
Shaken by this news
That's a Buddhist
High-level hacker Anonymous and
The leader of the subgroup Caldwell sec
Had been a government informant for months
So the FBI has this habit of
Leaving that's how they solved
These cases
Obviously that's how Hutchins
Just got in trouble in the first place
Because they had flip some other dude
And he gave up Marcus
You know that's sort of the way the FBI thinks and
May not be
True
The really important
Point here is that
Hutchins
Didn't have the information they wanted
Or at least he still claims he
They didn't have the information they wanted
And there was no way out for
There was no way for
Reset and say oh well
We tried to call
You're not going to give it to us you know they just kept doubling down and doubling down and doubling down
Isn't this a real strain of Vengeance there too though
You know it's something you wouldn't
Spectra government
Yeah it was interesting because
The day that he pled guilty there was only one other journalist
In the courtroom
The entire back row
The courtroom was
Skilled with FBI
And you could get was at including the two that had had to take
The stand
And you know
They were those two agents
Embarrassed
They both
In various ways that they'd fuk up
And because they were embarrassed and because the cross
Computers were embarrassed I felt like
You know okay we're going to we're going to do this
Superseding indictment and we're going to get
You now
And
You know that the embarrassment of the FBI and the improprieties if they were mild
Improprieties in the arrest process
On the part bus
Agents
That might have been an
Trinity in a government that
Was working at my donut go to bed an opportunity say oh you know what
We had a screwed up on this arrest
We don't think it's that important anyway so why don't you
You just get on a plane and instead they just doubled
That's the way that is the way the
The FBI
Andy rj10 store
I think they tend to once you get in the system
We're going to find a way to prosecute
You one way or another
And it leads to
It can lead to
Do you know
Well
I mean I'm glad he's going home. This is wrapped up I hope he does get that part but
Yeah that me thanks for coming on the show to talk about this is very important case
Snow today
Today's episode was recorded in edited by Andrew bercik
I hosted it and I produced it you'll hear from us next week