Eagle one package being delivered
Is a Hollywood trope
But it's real
And thanks to the internet of things sometimes you don't even need to hack the car directly
Packer that goes by the Alias L&M found a way to hack almost 30,000 accounts of people use to GPS
Tracking apps
By taking control of the accounts to hacker not only access to users personal information
Putting names emails and home addresses
He also gave me ability to kill Lorenzo
The two GPS tracking apps are called pro track and I track they're made by two Chinese companies that not only
Excel physical Internet connected GPS tracking devices
But also the apps to monitor the cars
In other words it's the internet of things inside a car with default passwords
What could possibly go wrong
Has This SUV drives down the highway these two hackers are
Pulling off the unthinkable no matter what happens don't panic
Even turning the wheel
Today we're here with motherboard reporter Lorenzo franceschi bicchierai
About this hack
What's really sound like a rejected script from a Black Mirror writers tape
I did not go and this
Decipher
Florence you got a bit of a scoop
This week
On
Something and I think a lot of
Security researchers at least in the lot of people
AR student
Because
It's sunny we all use cars
Car hack
6.11 what did you find
Yeah so a couple weeks ago
A hacker that I've been in touch with
Here and there
Message me saying hey I have to GPS tracking companies
And
Not only I can monitor thousands of
Cars all over the world but I can also like killer engines
Headed Hilder engine
Yeah and initially my responses like okay you're full of s***
But then I
I talked to him and I you know I talk into this
Story and yeah I mean
Probably
He was telling the truth
So what happened here is that
He was able to figure out a way to hack into the accounts of
User than customers of these to GPS tracking companies
One of them is called the protract the other one is called I track
They're both
Owned by larger Chinese companies do not relate to each other but
The platform of the use
Is the same we don't know exactly why but
Probably that the same third-party provider of software
But anyway the guy
NACA figured out that
Every customer as a default as a password of one two three
Four five
6 which is like classic
Don't do that password
It's so dumb
And so
So you figure that out and then he realized that he could
Use the API for the two apps
To essentially Brute Force
Or gas
All the usernames
So we just fed the API with a script
And
Like randomly
Tripe every username you could come up with a rather is program
Could come up with
And try to login with the default password 1 2 3 4 5
This way he harvested
Besides
Around 30000
Accounts
Which means not only he got the information that the
Users are within the Earth
Pounce but he also logged in as them
So we could you know check out
Their fleet of cars
And these apps also give you the ability to
Stop the engine
The way it works is that
Let's say that which is by the way one of the most
You know typical
Car hack worst fears
Almost like equated to
Getting access to the power going to turn the lights out this is like
Getting into cars
And killing their engines
When you're on a highway or when there
When they're driving in the street
Yeah that's kind of like
Probably one of the nightmare scenarios eating pussy right
It's cuz we talked early it's like one of the craziest
Apocalyptic things
Yeah like we see any movies you know it's starting to be like a
Like a troll before hockey movies or
Act like Fast and Furious I think at a car hacking the last movie
Am I ready for this
I want every trip with a zero-day exploit in a 2-mile radius around that motorcade now
Is over a thousand of them
So in this case the hack was not that dangerous as far as you can tell
Because the way that this works is that if you have Lexie a fleet of cars
So you're like a
Company that sells floors or you have a
A cab company
You can buy GPS trackers like actual physical Hardware devices you put them in your car
And you connect into the engine
So these devices are now
Some of them at least are connected to the internet
So both the company that got hacked ER
Not only provide the app
Apps are they also provide the higher
So you buy the GPS tracker in selling your car
And if you want you can connect it to the end
Andy apps
Allow you to stop the engine
If you want
So like I think that the use case is
The driver tries to steal the car or the car gets stolen
Cats lost whatever
The good news is that at least for one model that we
Wearable to verify
You can only kill the engine if the car is going under 20 kilometers per hour
12 miles
That was kind of the case as well with the fact that you're the same as wired
Story
About car hacking
What's Charlie Miller
Connect to kill the engines at
Like a hundred miles
Broward
Yeah I don't remember
What was the limit thereby
There was definitely some sort of Fail-Safe or limitation that
Made it a little bit less bad
Yeah it's still I mean it's still kind of creepy for sure because
Incredibly
This whole story is
Makes people think twice you know we're not going to be
What are the point where cars are
Going to be increasingly on these types of Networks
Know that we have
The Advent of smart cars that are just going to drive us around
This is
You know what
Only a few years away probably
Yeah
Probably end
And even without like
Self-driving cars like we probably don't realize well first of all we don't realize that
Basically cards right now even you know what the card you got at Zipcar or whatever hurts
Those cars are essentially computers with wheels
And that doesn't mean that you should like
Freak out and think of you.
Someone is going to hack you while you're on your honeymoon or something but
It's still something that we need to
Grapple
And something that manufacturers need to grab
Listen to that credit the major car manufacturers
I've been a lot of work
Securing their cars
I see how they hide
Sakura researchers date you know they created
Security teams that did not exist before
But the problem in this case and the story was that it doesn't matter what color you have if you install one of these GPS tracking device
Slices and you use one of these apps
Then
It's kind of a supply chain hack
Ride like this guy hack
A third party that was inside this car
And even though it could probably not kill anyone likely and you know who is credit hacker said that he never try
Try to mess with the engines because that was not what I wanted to do and that was dangerous
But even if you didn't even if it was not able to do that
He could like track
Cars all over the world
And
Let's try something you don't want to do is if you have a
You know why these companies that uses Wireless app
So
I mean it's kind of scary that today there's like companies that ship software
With 1 2 3 4 5 6 has password
I mean that's the response of
Amazing probably responsible especially when you know infosec communities is shamed users for doing stuff like that
Let alone
Actual companies that create
What are you thinking
Yeah it's insane I mean it's 2019 guys like you cannot
You cannot expect users
To change their password
Without
Telling them to
I mean
I think we
Spoke about this in the podcast before like
The industry blames victims
Too much right
And in this case
Will you could say wow this is the user's fault they kept her default pass
That's not I mean the real problem is that the company allowed them to keep it if
I like the way it should work is okay
Maybe when you create the account
You give them one two three four five six for whatever reason I mean
You shouldn't bet
Even if you do that
Then Force
A change of password after one day or I don't know right away
Like something like
I mean the question becomes like
Where's the quality control
I mean it seems like the reason I contacted both companies and one of them did not respond to
Are emails
And the second one immediately went on the office
Which is a red flag
Right away like do it like
Why are you contacting our users
Are you involved with the hacker
Everything is fine and it's like
Guys like really in 2019 during urine come at me
For this yeah and you know maybe there was something Lost in Translation cuz they too Chinese company so I don't want to read too much into the Earth
Tone of an email like you and I was an email but
He definitely seemed a little bit like
Who are you why you asking all these questions and
Are you working with the hacker inside
No, first of all
Sit down
Like your uses are in danger right now
So maybe you should worry about that
So yeah mean
Going back to your question the quality control was probably nonexistent
I guess I'll just this whole
Hack makes you wonder
How realistic is that mass hacking the future of
The cars that are going
Over 50 miles per hour in
You know killing the engine
But how possible is that going to be is it a science fiction as we like to think it is
I think in my opinion.
Very unlikely unless
Allison company does
Something really stupid
And I'm saying that it's unlikely because
Think about iPhones for example
Like we talked about this end up in a podcast a few weeks ago
Like you can hack
IPhone
Looks like no one is denying that and you're going to be able to hack cars and
You know that's always going to be eight
Possible because softer will it bogs
And Packers will find his bags and exploit
But one thing is to hackmon single-car and one thing is to like
Target thousand
So for example
We haven't seen a warm
Like a virus warm
For iPhone
We haven't seen like
Massive Attack
For iPhones
So if car manufacturers can
Take that model
Replicated
Then they'll be able to limit the damage
Which is to say again
Probably someone will get
Killed by a hack
In a car one day
Or maybe already have
Probably we will not see like
Hundreds of cars on the same Highway
Like
Getting their engines killed all at once
Like I think that was actually
The plot of
Right
I mean I remember there was
It was all these conspiracy theories
Back in 2013 when
Journalist Michael Hastings
Is cards
People saying you know
This was a car hack
Is conspiracy to kill him by the CIA
I would definitely I would not want to plan to
Conspiracy theories
Pukaar hacks are possible
Yeah I mean we saw it with that famous wired article and video
Like
Those guys are Charlie Miller and Chris valasek
Just took a cruise
Jeep I think it was
They started it and figured out that they could not only monitor like cars in real time
They could take advantage of a bug in the system to
Kill the engine model cars
And
The letter that insane video where
Andy Greenberg is driving down the highway
And they start playing music on his entertainment system and you know it's all laughs and then
Without telling him they killed the engine while he's
Crying on the
On the highway
So
And yeah that was sort of a controlled hack
That was
What could happen
Right like that was not a stance that was not
I'd there was a bog
That was fixed
Eventually
The bad guys could have found it to you know you just got lucky that I mean who who is this who is this hacker
What's what you done before in the past
He attacked a bunch of a
A couple of
Stock companies before
He doesn't want to say where he's from or who he is
He only goes by L&M Hawaii
So it seems to be kind of like
A random Park
In the sense of humor just a guy who likes to hack stuff
His methods are a little strange because
Like in this case it reached out to
The company's inside hey I found I hacked you
Do you have a reward for me like a set of a bug bounty
We should not have bug bounties work like
You can't pack companies and then ask for a bug bunny
Lockridge animal
Did the company sent him
And the company was like
We don't have that much money and can you give us a low price
Which is ridiculously funny as well but also
Kind of sad because
Again like these companies are used by thousands of
And
But probably very sensitive stuff you know like
Cabs or whatever the
The cars in there
Their trucks
So
Yeah do you see this up a pack
Increasing the next few years
I think so because
Again like I think car manufacturers are doing a decent enough job so far
That's also
We don't know exactly how good they are
Right cuz it's all this is bringing you
Cars even used to be connected to the internet
GPS trackers did not used to be connected to the internet with like Android app
So the chances that
There's some companies out there
Cutting corners and Binoo using third-party developers that have no security training
It's pretty high I mean these things what might happen here like this to Chinese companies Outsource the development of the
The app
And did not realise that
Whoever developed the app
Was shipping it with a default password that
And one can Gastly
Literally anything else
Progressive
He was mentioned in the
API
The question is to is
The connected Hardware that could
Come with
A car that is smart
As well right like it's not just necessarily
Biggby
The engineering of the software in the vehicle as much as it is
If third-party apps that come in and say hook this up to the car and it can do this
Where's the quality control on Van
Yeah I mean it's it's it's both hardware and software like
If you think of a car as a
Computer on Wheels then you have to think about okay
Is this car getting update
How is it getting on
How long is it going to get
It's cuz you know like
We change phones every 2-3 years
We can computers ever
A few years
But people keep cars for long time
So as these cars are getting connected to the internet are they going to
Keep getting
Security update
For how long I mean that's the question right
If I'm buying a car that's connected to the internet right now
Is the manufacturer committing to
Patching it
And if yes
For how long
Will I have to pay for the patch or not
And if I have to pay for like the updates
Maybe some people will not do it
When you drive an automobile today
You are driving a big computer system that happens that wheels and a motor in the case of the wired article and
That famous car hack
The car manufacturer
He should patches I think in that case they sent out actual USB keys
Two customers so that they could update the software
And that was I think
That was the first time that something like that it happen
And but where can I see more and more
In all your iPhone gets
Updates
Arie
One or two months marlesta mean it's not regular by like
Every year obviously there's a new job paid but
Throughout the year you got updates
As you go
You know you wonder if the government's going to get involved with Superman dating some standards because unlike yourself
Blow up when you're listening
Jenna Liddell
Trump blow up on your head
Kill you
But driving in a car is Samsung
Best Buy C
Price Samsung user
But yeah you know what I mean it's it's true
Like
A car can kill you in a lot of great points like you know
Computers and phones
Again today
Gizmos
What's the worst case scenario I mean obviously you got hacked it can be bad right depending on where you are you can lose all your money
Iron Man games
Yeah but here were talking about something that like
Life or death
Another question is as well you know you say
You said earlier like oh
Probably
This won't happen unlikely
But then
You look at something like the Boeing crashes
That just happened
And these weren't hacks but
This was software-related saying
And
The company clearly it looks like at least the allegations are
That it really was was
Short cutting
A lot of things in order to
To sell these these
Des Plaines quicker
So you know what
How quick does not happen with
With cars it's something to think about
Yeah I'm at mean maybe I'm just being optimistic or skeptic or you know I'm putting too much faith into this time
Can corporations in the hope is that
You know these are companies with a lot of money so hopefully they understand the risks
And they understand that
You know even does one person dying from a software bug
It's a huge cost
So just think about how much bad press Uber God when their self driving car crash
And kill someone
In the US
Is that worth
The extra software development that you need is it worth you know the security search that you have to pay
I mean
I think so I mean obviously I don't have the budget and I have a company
It's easy for me to say but like
Again we're talking as you said we're talking about life and death
Like something like this is a PR nightmare
You know like
Somebody's iPhone getting hacked is a something is a PR nightmare that you can control right it's not that bad
I like somebody's car getting hacked and then
Dying or killing someone because the brakes don't work or something
That's
Like me know that's
Krampus
News for today
I mean call me crazy in a Luddite or something
But you know we're not going stuff happened it did make me think
About how willing we are
Select software
Overtake the human operator and smoothies very key
Places you don't even like it's
Trust technology understand technology and it's going to get better and better we're even the human operator will be
Will be out match but in these early stages it seems like
We are prone to these these lapses and
In the actual
The mechanics of this
This type of software yeah definitely end to go back to the story we don't know exactly why
This password was
Set
2 1 2 3 4 5 6
My explanation and I'm guessing I guessing or speculating is that
Simply
It's the simple way to do it right like
You just give
Every user the same password and that way you don't have to
You have to pay for some password
Generating yeah I don't know it's just it's just makes it simpler right so so if you're cutting Corners like that
Those are the risks and I just said yeah like
Especially the beginning one where you know we're putting the internet on this devices and maybe we're not thinking about it it's very
The problem is that I don't think things are going to get necessarily better as we understand the technology more because
The more we put softer on this
You know machines like
Cars or even airplanes
It's got more complex and with more complexity that will be more bugs
I'm with more boxed it would be my hat
So
The key to all this is to really
Think about
Why you want to put like the feature that you want to put on your machines
Very carefully like Tijuana
You know do you want the
Plane engine to be connected to the internet like probably not like
I can't think of a good reason right
So
Yeah same thing with the car engine
Should be connected to the internet
I don't know
Like why would it be unless it's a self-driving car and
You want to take it over to remote
Even in the case of like a stolen car like
I mean I understand that killing the engine in that case can help but
I don't know it's still like what are the trade-offs ride like I'd rather not have the Internet connected to my car and
And accept the risk that if you get stolen I might I may not find it
Well I'm at gloriously happy note
I think we can end the podcast
Thank you
Lorenzo thank you for having beer
Interviewee have a double hat today
Just Shameless self-promotion episode
Yeah yeah yeah that's actually paid you to love me on the final
Naughty suggested it
This week's episode was recorded by John northcraft
Headed by Sophie cases produced by Lorenzo franceschi begin and hosted by me
Will see you next week