99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
Visit 99 percent invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Here at the San Francisco Main Library
And that is Dennis paoletti you walk into the library as a five-story atrium
He's an acoustic designer
And it also is very hard and reflect
All of the
Plaster concrete reflective material
Companies hire him to make their buildings
And boardrooms
In cathedrals
And public spaces
Sound better
When an early scheme had the architect had the main information desk bright in the
Little Havana
Floor plan in the center of that five-story atrium
The commotion that would go on
It would be disastrous for
People had to work there to try to hear
The visitors coming in asking for
Trying to communicate
One of the things we recommend was it just
Bad information desk
Of the atrium
Tuck it under
Some of the mezzanine
Pretty simple
Pretty minor but
To make this made such a big Improvement
I would like that
Set smart and Simple Choice to tuck the information desk over to the left side
So patrons and Librarians could actually hear each other
Created the
Wide open
Circular entryway
And no one really knows how to walk
Bumping into someone else
So this beautiful
140 million dollar building has an added feature
That certainly was not on the architect's plans
It's a hat
Jankity
Retractable movie theaters
Hairstyle Velvet Rope partition
Helps
Create the proper traffic
And right there are 15 feet apart from one another
A minor Triumph
And a minor failure
Of design
In the Epic of Gilgamesh
The god gets so infuriated
With annoying
Cast of their human Neighbors
If they send a flood to wipe us all out
And when you walk around the city
Pretty easy day
Side with the Gods in that scenario
What is noise
Noise very simply is unwanted
Sound
Did used to be called environmental noise
People are beginning to get interested in looking at
The city's environment
Has something unique to that
In San Francisco
The cable cars are always interesting point of
Discussion is that sound or is that noise
Well for tourism business examples
That sound that's good that's money but believe it or not we've been called into people who are annoyed
Goodbye the sound of those planking Bells
Or the cables that run under the street
The job of acoustic design is not just to make things quieter
Sometimes the best way to design a space to have less noise
If the add more sound a reading room in a library
Quiet quiet
It is so quiet
Anybody
Flipping a page in a book turns out to distract everybody else
The problem acoustically
The background noise level
It's literally too quiet
We often come into spaces like that and add background noise
And that's why small parks and cities usually have fountains and if they don't they need one
They may be visually pleasing
The sound might even matter more
Fountains give you this
Comfort level of acoustical privacy
Masking
Unwanted noise
What's your noise
China Merchants Bank
When I'm home in
That's my place to relax
The neighbors always start mowing the lawn
Thorax Anatomy the days to listen
Little people people are annoying
Listen to the city and let me know what's your favorite sound
And what's your noise
And how is it enhanced or drowned out by
The design of the city that you live in
But the building where you spend most of your time
Leave your comments at 99% invisible. Org
99% invisible is produced by me Roman Mars and support from lunar design as a product of kalw the America
Steve architect
Francisco
Rent-A-Center
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The bunny genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com