This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The Mind enter Barcelona's most famous Cathedral often stretches around the block
La Sagrada Familia
Designed by Antoni Gaudi draw so many people to see it that the neighborhood is congested with tour buses and
Taxis in scooters
Some three million people went inside the church in 2016 and another 7 million came just to stare at the outside
A bit strange Behemoth structure
If you travel around Spain you'll see a lot
Old Gothic
Churches
Producer Katie mingle was in Spain earlier this year
But this one is different
First it doesn't look like a Gothic Cathedral
It looks like it was built out of
Phones
Are sand or like it just
World out of the sea
Like a fractal
It looks organic somehow
But there's another thing that sets it apart from your average
Old Gothic Cathedral
It isn't actually old
LD wasn't able to build very much of it before he died in 1926
Most of the church has been built in the last 40 years
And it still isn't finished
Which means that Architects have had to figure out
And still are figuring out
How gow do you wanted the church to be built
We are all together in that room is
Special room
The most important part of the
Feeling we are building
That's heronema Boucher
One of the current architects of the building
He says the clues to understanding how to move forward on the construction of La Sagrada Familia
Are kept in the room were standing in right now
In the basement of the church
Photosynthesis radio can you describe what's in this room
Now let us Shelf
With
Fragments
Little pieces of
Plaster make
Small
Boy died geldi left elaborate plaster model of the detailing his plans for finishing the church
What about 80 years ago
They're all basically destroyed
Now they're in pieces
Is it doesn't look like
Just from this and those little pieces that that would be enough
Dilate
Figure out the hole
Thing
I understand that it's difficult to know what we have to do if the main architect is not
Cartier how is not with us what we try to do is
Understand
How he thought
And it's not easy
I know
It definitely hasn't been easy for the new Architects to recreate and understand the vision of Antoni Gaudi
And there are people who think
They shouldn't even have tried
But the building should have stopped
Took out east.
But it didn't
The building is currently the longest running construction project
In the world
And The Architects are still trying to understand the mind
Antoni Gaudi grew up in a little town called where you
Switch like Barcelona
As part of a region Spain called
Catalonia
And although he's become one of Spain's most famous art
Yode would never have identified as Spanish
He was catalonian
Through and through
Catalonia has been in the news recently because of its movement for independence from Spain
But in many ways this movement isn't new
Catalonians have struggled against the rule of the Spanish for centuries
Castlevania has a separate language castle and it is always felt very separate
That's gay Stantonsburg n
My name is Guy Stantonsburg I'm the biographer of Antoni Gaudi
Pennsburg and says that as a child growing up in Catalonia Gowdy spent a lot of time outside
And was completely enthralled with the natural world around him
What he would later call the Great Book of nature
A lot of kids are curious about nature
The fur Antoni Gaudi it was different
It became a total obsession
He seemed to absorb essential lessons from the patterns and shapes he saw in nature
The insects were walking and flowers grew the way that A Tree Grows and where it's raised up
Brooches
A dried-out snake skeleton
Honeycomb
These were Nature's Perfect Construction
Pittsburgh Aldi a deeply religious Catholic
God was the master architect of these Flawless organic structures
Eventually God he left
A small town in the countryside and moved to Barcelona for University and then
Tree School
When he graduated in 1878 the director of the school said
We are here today either in the presence
Savage genius
Or a Madman
Gaudi began his career at a difficult moment in Barcelona
Industrial Revolution and brought thousands of workers from the countryside into the city for factory job
They were toiling in terrible conditions
Packed into filthy tenements drinking dirty water
Diseases like yellow fever in Colorado
We're ramping
In the midst of all of this suffering a Bookseller name shows up Boca Bay of begins selling a fundamentalist news
Paper
Kind of reminded everyone that their misery was punishment for their sins
Surprisingly a cool song
Pretty soon broke up with making quite a lot of money from his Catholic guilt seemed newspaper
Kept apparently on the hidden under the tiles of his book shop
With the piles of money he was accumulating decided to build a church
Women to inspire the common Folk
Toledo religious life
The church will be dedicated to Mary Joseph and Jesus the secret family
La Sagrada Familia
The first architect at Boca Bay hired quit after a year and he went looking for a new one
Legend goes book of Isaiah had a dream one night blue eyes man would come to the rescue
The very next day book of Isaiah saw the person from his dream in real life
Drawing in the studio of another architect Inu
And he says what are you older man
The man he had seen was Antoni Gaudi in immediately
Boca Bay hired him to be the architect
Of his church
Greatest job in Spain
At that time was given to this completely
Who is completely online twenty-nine-year-old
Done
Very little work
The basic floor plan for La Sagrada Familia
Had already been laid out by the former architect
And Goldie would stick with it
The church will be built in the Neo Gothic style Which is popular at the time in Europe
Miguel D also wanted to charge to be something completely unique
Inspired by Nature
And by God
What county wanted was a building which would actually have
The kind of harmonies
All of the celestial sphere is the idea that everything
As a home mini in nature
And if you got that rice in your building
The building itself with spiritualized
That said Gowdy would never allow the building
Outshine gods
Creations
So he set a limit on how tall the church would ever get
He felt that he didn't want to be told than God's handiwork and God's handiwork
We're close to mountains
Only the sign
La Sagrada Familia would be one or about three feet shorter than Mount montjuic in Barcelona
Just to keep it humble
In 1883 when Gaudi started work on La Sagrada Familia is first matter of business was
Finish the Krypt
Which had been started by the previous Arc
The Crypt is essentially a small church under the bigger chart
And a place where important people are buried
In fact I was buried there when he died in 1892
9 years after he hired Gowdy
Sagrada Familia Crypt was big enough to hold services in Endless kept everyone happy while Gowdy took his time designing the rest
The building
The book of Isaiah died management of the construction passed through various hands
Purple Galaxy
There was only one plan
That really matter
God is the client and God is never in a hurry
After the Crypt was finished Gowdy begin to build the first big wall of the building
The nativity
Facade
He would work on it for the rest of his life
But it was important to him that this facade get done first
Because
It would be the Bible written in stone
Which
People if they couldn't even read or write they could look at the building and btools about
The values of the Catholic faith
LD was a sculptor as much as an architect
The wall would be full of stone sculptures depicting biblical scenes
The baptism of Christ Christ in the workshop with his father flight to Egypt
With a life-size donkey
The stone sculpture of a donkey in that c was actually cast in plaster
Become a real life donkey
It had to be particular to the Donkey
It looked as if it had been through the desert for 40 days
One of these workers actually wandered the streets until he found the perfect
Starving donkey
Which he exactly hand it over to Gowdy
Each of the donkey and the Donkey
And he Costco
Antoni Gaudi also tried making plaster molds from live human beings
Yeah she tried to do with one of his workers but we almost killed him and
I decided that maybe that wasn't the best
The way forward
This all took an incredibly long time
But eventually the wall started
Telestory in stone
And it featured hundreds of celestial and Earthly creatures
Little snails crawling all over engine tortoises
The song became crowded and cluttered and teeming with life
Lumist swamp fish
Can the quality of the stain oozing out of organic
Shaping of the building it was very unusual
Barracks Road
Antoni Gaudi was slowly building a Catholic Church
But not everyone was convinced that
Catholicism have anything of value to offer the average working citizen
Leftist saw the church is getting rich from the tithes of the poor
They sold them as being wealthy as being parasitic
As living off them
Communism socialism and anarchism we're taking hold in other parts of the world and in Spain
He left his parties thought they could offer the struggling worker a better life
Conflict between leftist in the state and left us and the church
Oar concert
For the Lost Decades of the 19
Century
It's probably on the average something like two bombs every week
In the center of the city
Brother years Gaudi work on other architecture projects in Barcelona
His work is Peppers all over the city
Impalas is Pavilions and extracting homes
His sinuous in skeletal architecture was unmistakable
Everyone in Barcelona new hairstyle
A La Sagrada Familia is a project
That consumed him
He realized the coast he could never finish it in would never see it finished in his lifetime
My 1926
73 year old Antoni Gaudi had never married and was living alone
He spent a lot of nights sleeping in his
Studio at La Sagrada Familia
Too obsessed with his work to care about his appearance
He was
Looking up it's like a tramp actually busy
Trousers what held up with safety pins in a bit of string
On June 7th of 1926
Gowdy is leaving work
And as he crosses the railroad tracks and runs amoeba
Antoni Gaudi was left nearly dead on the railroad tracks
His body was found he was taken to the hospital where he died three days later
LD was buried in the Crypt under La Sagrada Familia
His last years have been consumed with building the church
The Barcelona have not forgotten Gaudi
Brown's of people came out to mourn
It was just an almost a quarter of the population
Castlevania turned up in recession
Thousands of people that
When Gaudi died he left behind a largely unfinished Church
Withstood was a massive wall
The Nativity facade
One Tower and the Crypt
His colleagues and apprentices
We have a lot to do to bring his full vision into being
Look out he had anticipated that other Architects would finish his work
And he left behind detailed drawings and models outlining exactly how he wanted his magnum opus to be built
For 10 years work on losco De Familia continue
Very slowly
Much of calories former team stayed on
Even though they could have gone and started their own project
They were loyal
It was still work to be done
The jewel ring still existed
They continued walking away
And then in 1936
Abstain from the north east south and west
Don't want to Spill the lifeblood of the Spanish Civil War
Begin
The decades-old conflict between leftist in the state and finally come to a head
The Republicans who were in Alliance of various Latin parties
Fought against the nationalists
Which was the lines of fascists and other conservatives
Led by General Francisco Franco
The nationalists also have the support of most of Spain's Catholic clergy
On the 18th of July two days off at the start of the Spanish Civil War
A group of young anarchists break into the studios of Goldie
And smash everything with hammers
All the multiples everything is smashed up into tiny little bits
When they're done smashing daylight the place Ablaze
Everything Burns
Including the architectural drawings
Absolutely everything in fact
The following day
Trying to come back and bum the Nativity facade
Which is the only one standing there with Gowdy's
Which
Miraculously they failed to do
Catholicism was under attack during the war and by the end of it
40 churches in Barcelona had been destroyed
12 people associated with the Sagrada Familia project including some of its managing patrons and clergy
Have been killed
The war ended in 1939
Leftist law
The fastest 1 and general Francisco Franco took control of Spain
Should I use eco
What is all over
Few workers return to gaudi's Studio to salvage what they could
They very carefully
Picked up in boxes
Little sections and fragments of of the multiples
Unlike archaeologists do today they started piecing them together
For the next couple of decades the remaining Architects and other workers
Try to figure out how to move forward on the construction without Gowdy's plans
But outside the church there was opposition to moving forward at all
In the 1960s an impressive group of intellectuals and Architects including Le corbusier and Alvaro Alto Road
Golden open letter opposing the continuation of La Sagrada Familia
LD wasn't only an architect they argued
He was an artist
And you shouldn't attempt to finish a work of art
Without the artist
They felt that
This was a total waste of
The time they should have left
Just the original Nativity facade
Almost like a Gothic ruin
That as a homage to Gaudi
And the Gaudi wasn't being well so
But the patrons of the project would have none of it
The building was never supposed to be an homage to Gaudi they argued
It was always about something bigger
That said they would try to honor Gowdy's original Vision as Faithfully as possible
But it would be easy
The models and drawings had been the roadmap for how to move forward on the construction and they were burned and smashed to pieces
And this wasn't just any Cathedral
All these years have been designing something
So unique
So complex and so completely new
But it would take his successors
Years
Definitely get a handle on it
The church still had no interior and no roof
It was just walls and Towers
A construction site
Open to the Rain
I first went to Barcelona in 1977
But I was 20
That's architect Mark burry
Mark actually been told an architecture school that Gowdy was not worth studying because his approach was to
Esoteric
That he was sad
Two extraordinary and that there was no school
Meaning that there was
Nothing to say you move alone this just got blurry more curious
So he went to have a look at the Sagrada Familia himself accident
Meeting the 290 rolled architects
Directions to project
And had died
They have been young Architects listing to Goudy expanding his latest
Discoveries
When they were students
The old Architects were ready to move on to the interior of the building
But they didn't exactly know how to do it
They knew that he had a system
Facebook geometry
Then use a system which translates into
I got a building methodology
In other words The Architects knew it was
Theoretically
Possible to figure out how to create the rest of the church
But it was a Monumental task
They pointed burrito couple of boxes
Monster Paris models
Invitation to come and join the demon
Have a mistress
Puryear burry work with the models
Trying to extrapolate the geometry of the rest of the church
Based on the pieces he has
After a year
He managed to draw out architectural blueprints
For one window
It was a start
Mercury didn't stay long at the Sagrada Familia
He was only 20 and he had to go back to New Zealand finish school
He returned to work on the church
10 years later and found that when he was gone
Anew thingamabob
I've been moved into the office
Computer
Thought these computers must have something to offer cuz I've never actually personally tax form
Winberry finally touch the computer he figured out that it had architectural software on it
But the software wasn't capable of dealing with Gowdy
Trying to do
The complexity of gaudi's designs with
Too much for architectural software of the early 90s
Marie wondered if there was anyone else who designed with similar geometric complexity
And finally you landed on it
People who design airplanes
He started using aeronautical software to figure out an architectural strategy for the interior of the church
And because I had to spray sophisticated software by accident undiscovered parametric design
So we were working parametrically from 1991
Parametric design uses computer algorithms to allow you to plug in different variables
And see what the end result is each time you change something
Mark Berry was one of the first Architects to use computers to design this way
Eventually figured out that Frankie Ruiz team had also started using aeronautical software
To bring Gary strangely shaped curvaceous buildings into being
Is it Frank's office and talk to their technical team and compare notes
Eventually Gary Technologies with help from work break
Went on to create their own parametric design software specifically for Arkansas
By the early 2000s
Many of the most exciting new projects in architecture
We're being done this
At the Forefront of this was a church design over a century ago by Antoni Gaudi
La Sagrada Familia
So from being the selection is a man interesting
Irrelevant it became actually the
Delete projects in the Hall of the digital Revolution affect
Parametric design allowed Mark Berry in the other Architects to move a lot faster on the interior of the church
Without this technology
It's possible they would still be no
Inside the sea
It was only a few years ago in 2010
The Architects were able to put the finishing touches on the interior
Now people line up around the block to get a glimpse inside
And it really is breathtaking
Partly because of these incredibly tall columns that Gaudi designed the branch out like trees at the top
Stop and are capable of carrying
A tremendous amount of weight
When people go into that building I'm not suggesting
It is necessarily always a religious experience
The shock
And surprise
Of walking in trailers doors
Into this explosion of light
The light
Coursing through giant stained glass windows
In the afternoon it's a red orange light
And in the morning it's a bluish-green light
And it filters through the huge tree like columns
You feel like you're in a forest
And you feel very tiny
If you're very small
You feel as if there's a hold of universe above you
But the building is still not finished
I'm in An Extremely Loud metal cage elevator that runs on the outside of the church with head on emo
Bruschetta
The architect volume at the very beginning of the story
And Anna Barbie who handles press for La Sagrada Familia
It's very safe Anna says but it doesn't feel that safe
The elevator is shaking and we can see Barcelona getting smaller below us as we rattle up alongside the tower
Church
The elevator door opens to a spec
Angular View
We are standing on the top
The Sagrada Familia
I have the parts
Over there
Barcelona city blocks stretch out all around us
To the east we can see the Mediterranean Sea
Until the South
The mountain that Gowdy promise not to
Surpass
When the building is finished there will be 18 Towers
Including a new one right where I'm standing
This one will be the tallest of all reaching to 560 ft or 170 m
I don't email is working on designing it right now and he's using the fragments
Gattis plaster models to figure out how to do it
These will be Jesus Christ Our in the middle
One of Anjali
The Architects of the building will be finished in 2026
The 100th anniversary of gaudi's death
But there is still a lot to be done
Meanwhile some of the neighbors seem set up with La Sagrada Familia and all of the congestion and Taurus
It brings to the neighborhood
Sometimes they're a little protest
Against the place
Like this one in 2011
Where locals chanted
No more tourist buses
The want their neighborhood back
The bigger the building gets
The more Taurus
130 years ago
Joseph Polka Band decided to Bill Foster about a Familia
Cleanse the people of Barcelona up their sins
Inspire the common folk to live a religious life
He picked a piece of land on the outskirts of the city
What cows and goats would sometimes wonder
He probably never imagined that it would become tourist attraction it is today
Architect head-on T-Mobile shadow
Does one of the perks of working at La Sagrada Familia is getting to be inside the church
When no one else is there
Hermes
Is Israeli special
To be alone or to be
With not too many people
The church only holds one Mass a month right now and it can be hard as throngs of Taurus bump into you with their
Are selfie sticks
To feel connected to the building as a place of worship
Geronimo let me come into the church with him in the early morning before it was open to the public
So that I could try to get a sense of it
Are you going to feel that
Espiritual en.
Maybe somebody somebody or something more
Goddess symbol
Ansgear
To me and I'm not a religious person
La Sagrada Familia is not so much a testament
The God as it is to humans and what they can create
The Gaudi would dispute that assessment
He once said
The creation continues incessantly through the media of man
The man does not create
He discovers
Coming up we discuss Kaldi's revolutionary models for La Sagrada Familia in a segment that was just
Too nerdy and dense for the piece itself
But it's new
The too cool not to mention it at all
That's right after that
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa that Alexis talking to me and my wife isn't
All hearing. Voice
Technology
She talked to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to
Special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are soundscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
E9pay
What are things you mentioned that piece are these models
That were destroyed and
How important they were in realizing gaudi's vision for La Sagrada Familia
Little too technical to get into in the piece
Costa
Noses
And I asked him to come to the studio and explain
Gowdy's modeling technique
And why it is so important to the creation
La Sagrada Familia
Like a lot of artists
Especially once you'd like to use
Preferred to work in models rather than
Models help them experiment with really complex
Control structures
And Albany
Model out structural Arrangements test things out
Photograph as models in
Over the photo
But the bottles were behind all of the
If they were driving the design
And one of the things that you tried with a lot and bottles were variations on what's called a
Okay so what is a
Catenary
Catenary is
Curved shape that a hanging chain
Assume
Under its own weight
Basically picture
Electric lines
Suspended between you
Okay so you're driving on the highway
C2 utility poles
Electric line goes across time and there's that natural Boeing
Of the electrical wire
And that is
The catenary arch
Exactly
And that term is actually
Drive from the Latin word for chain
And it was already well-known by gaudi's time that an optimal Arch shape could be made
By mirroring
A catenary curve vertically
Basically you take that hanging curve
And you just flip it up
And that becomes the model of your
And that Arch
Distributes building loads efficiently
And a lot of Gothic
Okay that makes sense you take this boat to chain
It crepes
The optimal Arch when you flip it over
And when Ukrainian churches in the gothic style this is a
Good way to create a good
Model
But I already took the idea further
He hung strings other strings from other strings
They added birdshot
To weight them down at structural intersections
Need treated these
Huge intricate wire frame models that
End up looking a bit like
Like chandeliers
And then God would use mirrors to flip
These vertically
And study the shapes they created
In order to shape his own elaborate building skeleton
And it sounds a lot like what
Leader Architects to use soft
When they
Did 3D mod
Yeah there are a lot of parallel
In essence
Long before parametric design was a computer software
Gowdy change
Parameters in his models by moving strings and weights around to see how
Who's individual modifications
Could reshape an entire
Structure
And then a century later people came along and finally made these digital
I could be anybody
These handmade models have been doing
Allowing Architects to see how small changes with ripple out
To their entire design
So you know what you can imagine
It would take like
Call Amanda
Moving around a little bit
And that deforms like all the other shapes
Self-destruction rap
Right and then
Software you do this and
Nail dust off our cranks long and does its thing
But in gaudi's time
You would move a weight around
And you'd see how the
Connected set of chains with all kind of deform by adding
A little bit of birdshot
21 Little
That's amazing
And it looks stunning
Yeah the results are amazing
A lot of people you know they think Audi and they think of you
He's beautiful sculptural scenes in these details
He created
Underneath
All of that
Is this really lovely structural logic
Instagram Familia
The Tostitos are
Beautiful but so is this internal framework
Columns and arches
Vault
Branches up and out
Creed II
Fractal Forest
Spell because
Dowdy didn't spend a lot of time teaching or
Explaining his methods are really writing about his
Designs
And because his work was so out of sync
What modern is for trying to do with the time he didn't always get a lot of recognition from the architectural list
So he's like a starchitect but in hiding
Yeah pretty much you can eat
Yeah he's a Trier starchitect who doesn't spend all of his time bragging about
That's so cool
These models are
Really sunny their mazing to look at and we have some pictures on our website correct
Yes we have a ton of pictures of these bottles
That he made as well as
The really beautiful Church
Help create
Thank you so much
99percentinvisible which produces Wheat by Katie Mingle
Mixing tank production by Sharif
Music by genre
Percocet is the digital director and the one Among Us who actually went dark at
The rest of that includes Avery trufelman Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall and me
Roman Mars
The folks at La Sagrada Familia for spending so much time showing us around
It was a true privilege
More detail on everything you are today
Takeout guys van hens Bergen's new book
The Sagrada Familia
Kaldi's
Heaven on Earth
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99% of is what part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all a podcast
We are supported by the Knight Foundation
And our listeners
Just like you
You can find 99percentinvisible enjoying discussion about the show on Facebook you can't win me at Roman Mars in the show at 9 p.m.
I will work on Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Article about the oldest national monuments in the US or any of the other Design Story that we release every single
You have to go to our website
Sunday 9 p.m.
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com