99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
We need to talk about something
Constipation
Abdominal pain and bloating
You tell yourself
It's not that bad to take laxatives you modify your diet and exercise routine
Thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
You don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Five podcast
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Deepa boss they grew up in a very small town in Southern India
With meanly books
To keep her company
I'm an only child so there was no one to satisfy
Fight with and play with at home
And she didn't have many links to the outside world
This was the early 90s before email took off or AOL chat rooms realize there
Creepy potential
That's producer of Vivien Leigh
But one day when she was 10 years old
Deepest father brought her home a children's magazine with potential penpals listed in the back
Back then the idea of the pen pal was very popular
Do have a penpal who lived
I brought was with a big tank
They were pen pals listed from all over the world
Asia Europe South America
Antifa decided to write to two girls living in Russia
But there was a problem
This particular magazine actually came from a second-hand shop and was completely out of date
The magazines that my dad phone for me love
I think the early eighties or so so I would
And I found them much later in the 90s so that was almost a third of 728 year Gap
But even though seven years has passed since they listed their addresses in that magazine
These two Russian girls
Who are teenagers at the spa
Actually wrote back
People actually still have a lot of these old letters
In redmi 1 from one of her Penthouse named Marina
Audio Depot
How are you
Thanks for your letter and photos
I was glad to see your letter
I have a family
Mother father
And sister
I found this very small
But I like
It starts off pretty predictable
Send Marina starts talkin about some of her favorite
My favorite actors are
Shahrukh Khan Aamir Khan Govinda
Anil Kapoor
Karishma Kapoor
They were all
Indian
I like India
Indian films dances songs except
I have the collection photos
Actors songs from Indian film
Deepest Russian pen pals were obsessed with Indian films
More specifically Bollywood
They seem very very interested in
Bollywood
Bollywood is the Hindi language film industry that comes out of Mumbai India
It's a portmanteau of Bombay
The former name of Mumbai where these films are produced
And Hollywood
Bollywood is often conflated with the film industry as a whole
But really it's just one very flamboyant
Slice of it
It's usually packed with elaborate song and dance sequences
Fight between Good and Evil
A beautiful hero in heroine
There's very little data
Left foot into
Sedation so you know that okay there's this guy this is good
They going to fall in love and then
So just end up happily ever after
It's a fairytale I think that's that's the best way to
Describe
When she first got the letters
Deep I didn't think much about her penpals Bollywood fascinator
It wasn't until years later that it's trucker
Just how hot it seem that these girls all the way in Russia
You so much about
Shahrukh Khan
Anil Kapoor
I don't think I really processed what they meant that somebody's been so far away in some small town witch
Probably was
Just like to know the small town I was growing up in
Before the internet
Why were they interested in
Movies that even be probably weren't watching as
What deeper didn't know that
What time was that Russian Bollywood fandom wasn't unique to her pen pals childhood experience at all
1950s right up to the collapse of the USSR
People in the Soviet Union were completely infatuated
With Indian Cinema
While the United States was in the grips
Beatlemania
Bollywood Mania
Was taking over the USSR
There's even a famous story about an Indian actor in the 1960s who is visiting mosque
He was quietly waiting for attack
Out of nowhere she was swarmed by Russian Bollywood crazed fans
He jumped into a taxi to escape
But instead of the car racing forward
It started rising up into the air
These fans had lifted the taxi over their heads and carried it down the street
It's possible that story has been embellished over the years
But it speaks with very real very intense connection between the two countries
India and the Soviet Union
Had completely different
Politics
Languages and cultures
Good for a brief time
These two Nations found the actually had a lot in common
And realize this
Dual love
Of movies
In the beginning in the twenties especially film
Stop
To be
Very important economically
Together with 4th grade brought lots of money
2 + 8
This is Carole radziwill golf film critic and historian based in Moscow
He's basically the Russian Leonard maltin
I'm watching you both 1000
Samsung speaker
And in the early years of Cinema rossakoff says that Soviet directors were at the
Forefront of filmmaking
Not just within the USSR
What in the world
Lenin himself said
Of all the Arts
Brusque
The cinema
Is the most
He believed that a film had the power to reach the masses better than any artist medium
And that it could operate as
Art and propaganda
At the same time
When Stalin came to power
Scales tipped dramatically
In favor of propaganda
Everything was controlled even personally by Stalin so the censorship for
Was Freddie Hart
You have the crystallization of us cultural policy
Bethesda Row Cinema and the art and the
Jen everything else
Needs to follow a set of
This is due. Rajagopal and Senior lecturer of Eastern European studies
The University of Amsterdam
She said that this set of artistic rules was called socialist realism
Socialist realism dictated in a sense that all books and Philippines to have a standard narrative
Fillmore show Gloria proletariat struggle
Conrad does heroic Acts
All will see the ideal Soviet society and understand the true meaning of communism
Roll credits
Socialist realism limited artistic creativity
And
World War II didn't help
A lot of the factories on Dorothy Industries at Cinema houses in theaters have to be closed down
Carol razza coffee
Explains that the War caused a shift in the Soviet Union's moviemaking priority
Rather than spending money on me
Taking a bunch of movies a year
Soviet Union wanted to concentrate
I'm just making a
Cancel
A well-produced
Before the war
Russia
Soviet Union made about
70 film speed
After the Warriors became five
Tencent
But yeah
The idea was to make fewer films
To make one only successful film
Impossible
The state wanted to focus on quality over
Which in some circumstances
This could be a good
But even at its best
Imagine of Hollywood was only producing five movies a year and those movies were Schindler's List
Million Dollar Baby
Sophie's Choice the Dear Hunter in 12 years
Their masterpieces
But going to the movies would be such a drag Cinema
So the USSR was producing fewer movies than ever
And the trajectory of Soviet Cinema
Mirror. Of Soviet life
Strict censorship
Can a rejection
Anything remotely
Bourgeois
Goodbye 1953
That would finally begin to change
With the death
Of Stalin
Google book
Score of U
After the death of Stalin
Great changes in the film industry
In 1953
Nikita Khrushchev came to power
And he wanted to chart a new course forward for the nation
In 1956 you have this momentous event when push of gifts what is called the secret speech
Philippe is not so secret because it turned out within a few days everyone knew about it
Khrushchev denounced Stalin's cult
Personality
It kicked off a period known as the
2crucial thot
Hundreds of thousands of prisoners released from Gulag political repression subsided and censorship was relaxed
The cruise ship also wanted to make ordinary citizens feel more free
And happy in their daily lives
Octopus hole
De-Stalinization as a
It's called in the 1950s is it
Kind of shift in the rhetoric about
How to
Address issues of everyday life
And part of this large debate
1%
Milk consumption
Is
Are people really having a good time I mean it really is as simple as that
Are people really having a good time is a simple question that marks an important shift in the government's priorities
Intrusive
Decided that one way to ensure that people were having a good time
What to get them back in the movie theater
Turtles giving people a sense
Stability right the war is over now these aren't normal times
You can also just go to the movies
You can just hang up
Friends it's also practicality
Can you need to rebuild our economy
You need to draw people back into the Seattle you need to generate revenues
But in order to get people to go to the movies
USSR had to increase the amount of films playing in theaters
Which required importing more foreign film
America was the biggest movie producer at the time but this was the middle of the Cold War and a majority of
Hollywood films were seen is
Inappropriately
Capitalist
And so the USSR went looking for someone else
A new fun friend
How to get entertain millions of fun starved Soviets
Without offending their political Sensibility
And it found the perfect candidate
In India
It was very important to the Soviet Union to have
A friend in India at the
The time in 1947
After years of fighting British colonial rule
India
Became an independent nation
Soviet Union at the time was looking to build relationships with developer
Countries
And even though India wouldn't take an official side during the Cold War
It still looks like a promising choice for friendship
It was
A country that had a very strong Anti-Imperialist
Politics
And political sympathies amongus intellectual
Ansel
Both of these things made it actually very attractive
Site
For the Soviet Union
Try out
It's geopolitics
Baby it was that this would be a cultural exchange between the two Nations
Soviet Union would import Indian films
And India would import the same number of Soviet
To become cinematic penpals
In 1954 the Soviet Union took a big step towards this artistic partnership
I hosting an Indian film festival in Moscow
East Roosevelt
Huge event
In the beginning of the 50s
Because the Indian film
Came to Russia
This is Carole radziwill
Russell golf was just a kid 19
Before but he still remembers this Fest
Spell because
It was the debut of a Bollywood film called avata
Which translates to the vagabond
Nevada centers around a Charlie Chaplin
Trap character
Forced into a life
The crime but
True love makes me see the error of his ways
Full of sentimental music
Lessons in Morality
Allied deep longing
Stairs
Troubling misogyny was the biggest
Ever commercial success in Soviet Union that.
Navarro was literally the number one movie in 1954 in the USSR
Selling over 63 million ticket
To put that into perspective
The top grossing movie of 2017
Star Wars The Last Jedi sold 57 million ticket
I was born in 1966 so long
After but I do remember people singing
That song in this movie had such a such a
Can impact on the show Victorious
This is Anton Sea-Doos off
He grew up in Uzbekistan when it was still part of the USSR
And he remembers just how huge evado and other Indian films were for Soviet audience
After that first film festival in Moscow
Don't star Raj Kapoor
Quickly became a mega celebrity throughout the Soviet Union
Truck drivers had the
A photo
Although
Kapoor on their windshield
Next to Stalin
That Indian actor that we mentioned earlier the one who was mobbed by Russian fans and
Hoisted into the air in the taxi
That
Was Raj Kapoor
It was so excited to see him that they apparently lifted his back
Sheetz
Angela cat
Yet such was his popularity
In the US
Raj Kapoor became kind of a cultural Ambassador between the two car
When he visited Moscow and 19th
He spoke about the ways in which movies can bring their country
She's closer together
And even quoted Lennon's original feelings of what Cinema could accomplish
Cinema
Is the greatest weapon tomorrow
And at the peak of their Bollywood craze
Soviet movie theaters
We're constantly showing Indian film
So they will be 20 movie theaters operating
From 10 a.m. till
2:10 p.m.
2 hours a day and
Have a good half of them will be playing
Indian movies
And even the music from these films became popular
Maybe a little too popular
Neighbors in the apartment complex at
Family leave
Water playing Indian songs
On the vinyl
From 6 a.m. till
Oakley midnight
Sometimes the same song
Over and over again
The ussr's intense love of Indian Cinema
Sometimes even seats into the content of Bollywood films
Deepa told me about a Raj Kapoor movie from 1955 called shree 420
Which the main character nods to the close relationship with the Soviet Union and one of the song
This is very old and very popular song called Mera joota Hai japani
I'm not
This is going to sound really bad
Mera joota Hai japani in English
If I'd known English standings
Listen Hindi Translate to
Buy shoes from Japan
My trousers are from England
But most importantly there's a lyric that says
The Hat on top of my head is from Russia
It's very curious.
LOL torpedo Sinatra.
Obviously a communist wrestling
Knowing that they have a very wide Russian audience and the
Sully's good marketing
Strategy to include them in the
Annoying the song
Upland
It's hard to say exactly why Bollywood
What became such a phenomenon
On in the Soviet Union
The reason is that they offered something you simply
Couldn't find in Soviet films
You do not see the kind of unbridled
Personal emotion that you
CNN
You know better
I mean those who don't like it
It's a It's Over the Top
Right here
See how Raja gopal and again
So it's
Innocent swear
You have a man and a woman and they fall in love and then you have
Full songs that are only about
Falling in Love
Right and then you have
Dance sequences shot out in the nature
Avenue have
Rainfall at fault and a drenched and they're in love and their exultant and there is this
Unbridled
Tents to Indian cinema right and there are no boundaries
Do what you can feed and how you can express those feeling
But it wasn't just that Bollywood fell
Exotic and if
The exuberant sentimentality was certainly unfamiliar
There was also something deeply relatable
At the core of Indian Cinema
Indian and Soviet films were both often about
Self-sacrifice
A world divided into Good vs Evil
In class struggle
But logical Palin conducted a number of interviews of Indian film fans in the former Soviet Union
And a lot of them pointed to something though
We don't quite have a word for it
So I know the Russians would say to me ways to watch Indian movies
And a douche as they match
And the show is the Russian word for
Seoul
The soul sister
Talking about
Isn't an individual soul
Instead
Shaw is kind of a nationalist
Or a collective identity
The duchenne that the Russians like to talk about their soul
Is Wanda in Jaws it is
It's it has been through hard history but it in Georgia
It's resilient
It's kind of
Spiritual in that sense of not being attached
Immaterial Pursuit Santo dystocia
They believed was one that they shared with Indian
Bollywood films played on theater screens in the USSR right up into the later years of the Soviet Union
The towards the 1980s a new technology change this cinematic relationship
Forever
The end of the Soviet Union
Coincided with the new Arrow
BHS
And that's
Exactly when
Arnold
And fellow made the
Lately
Removed
Raj Kapoor and other Indian actress from
From the screens of ordinary
Soviet
Audience
In the final years of the USSR
Rather than watching shree 420
Where is Zita and Gita
A lot of people preferred watching bootleg videos of Conan the Barbarian and RAM
The Soviet Union collapsed
American film and television quickly
Flooded the market
Hollywood isn't totally gone
There's still a channel on Russian TV that broadcasts Indian films and television
Twenty-four hours a day
And if you ever do karaoke in Uzbekistan
You might just hear an old man singing songs from Nevada
Okay so that's the first Apple Store
But
This was a one-to-one exchange right so
Now we're going to talk about all this Soviet films that were popular in India
And how deep abasta grew up with
Posters of Soviet film stars in her bedroom
Not so much
We never watched any Russian Film in India
In those years
Unlike Indian films push for a widely beloved
All parts of the USSR
Sophia films for just not popular in India
Any movie theaters weren't great at Distributing Soviet movies
And when they did
They often screen them late at night when no one would even want to go see a movie
How do you spell
You know
Devious and Samba soon's I mean
You know you watch them
Hey it's not the best
Hours
Seriously you try watching tarkovsky stalker at 11 p.m.
And staying conscious
I tried I failed I never look back
They bought
Almost
They distributed them much better than we ever did this
Offense will much more popular than their sons were
And India
The real
Soviet films just didn't have the same mainstream appeal is Indian films did
Course there were surely Indian film nerds with thick frame glasses who can appreciate Russian Art House
But on the whole
People in India just born is drawn to socialist realism
But do you know Soviet film never really took off in India
The goal of a two way cultural exchange wasn't a total failure
It just took another form
Here's Depot Boston
Soviet books
But flooded into the country in all languages
The USSR made Soviet literature widely available
All over India
Beautiful
Hardbound Russian class
4 translated into multiple Indian languages
I'm available and
Incredibly low prices
They would several generations of Indians
Who grew up on these books
So we had everything from the tallest I pushed in the siskiyous
All the greats of
Russian literature
2 children's books to Science and Technology textbooks
Deepa told me there wasn't even a bookstore
But her bookshelf at home was filled with great works from Russian author
In fact I think I was
About
When i picked up maxim gorkys mother
That's all I remember was my first
Bigger.
Novel
Assassination because it was like a big booger
Baton
It was hard born
Shooting on to read
Pushkin selected works and Dostoevsky the idiot all before the age of 17
People grew up and became a writer
And she believes she has a lot of growing up surrounded by Russian literature
Obviously
I know reading these books at that
Age
Definitely influence the way I
Already know the reactants now the way I
Right
Snow
Because
I did them at a very formative
Edge
And I still have a deep connection to
How to tease
To these books
As I was talking with Deepa
I kept thinking about the intention of this whole cultural Exchange
The influencer
So I asked her
If she thought it all about the fact that those books
Or part of some larger geopolitical
Propaganda scheme
Yes I do think about this whole propaganda side of it
But for me
It was
Literature for itself
To be enjoyed because it is great writing
I don't think anyone's going to no one's going to remember a politician speech
But you talk about books are you talk about Sin tomorrow to talk about
Music and that stays with you
Casablanca dress
How exactly did the Soviets watch all those American movies that flooded into the Soviet Union at a time when not that money
People had a VCR
Will they watch them on the movie Buy
Vivian tells me that story
After this
You
You inspired it
Xfinity create internet that puts you in charge
Bra
Your movie marathons are better
When you can stream them all night
Video chats for Grandpa's birthday it should be possible from anywhere in your house
And when you can pause wifi before bedtime
Putting your kids
Gets a little bit easier
So Xfinity reimagined Wi-Fi
And created Xfinity X5
Because for the best Wi-Fi experience you need speed
Coverage and control
This is beyond wife
This is X5
Visit xfinity.com
XY
To learn more
Make yourself and make it stand out
Wood squares
Create a beautiful website to promote your business publish content sell products and much much more
High Moon Squarespace sites Roman mars.com to show
Kiss my work
As links to my TED Talk
Radiotopia even has a sign-up
For the 99percentinvisible Weekly Newsletter
It was really easy to make mad at myself which is how I know that you'll have no problem making a Squarespace site
Christmas Bayside, invisible for a free trial and when you're ready to Launch
Easy offer code invisible
Oprah 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed in a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Just talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remedy for all hearing.
Voice technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPR
So I'm back in the studio with Vivian Lee who
Prieston reported that story
And
A little piece of this story that I forgot you started that
Didn't fit
In the story
Yes that is very exciting for me a while back I stumbled across this article
The Atlantic
By someone named Del Mar
So Eleanor is an English professor at Biola University now but he was born in the city called Baku in the
The Azerbaijan Soviet Socialist
Republic and he grew up watching a lot of movies in the Soviet Union
Before the fall
USSR before 1991
Yes he was born in 1979
And he said that the 80s were kind of an odd time to be a young person and a movie buff in the USSR
Because it's pretty close to the collapse of the USSR and that tension and anxiety tended to seep into stove
Media
The 80s
Work
Dark and cynical
I think that was rude
Did in the films and shows
Words that were made
It's a lot of it was
It's just sort of
Dark
Critical and hopeless
We talked about
Is making people turn to Bollywood Cinema to have some hope and something like that did that what he did
He told me that his
His first crush was
Hema Malini from Zita and Gita
But he actually watched a lot of Hollywood
You still didn't make it into the Soviet Union
Import American phones
Cold War there just very selective of what they would screen and Stones were heavily censored or edited
And Elmer told me about this kind of funny example of a classic film that they used
Play the one I always think about is
Some Like It Hot
Was Marilyn Monroe in the Soviet Union it was
Actually translated
Girls only in jazz
What is better
He told me that no scenes were often cut or edited out order
Is translated completely differently
Need to change the contacts
A lot of them or
Spicy lamb
Which was also
Cleaned up and there were some scenes
That were complete
LeConte or translated differently
But towards the end of the 70s bootleg movies were a lot easier to get ahold of because of the VCR player
And so this is how a lot of people like Almar First Watch uncensored American
The way you say VCR player is if
You are of an age in which he's never touched one really thick
Plastic dhs's
So you should just say VCR
So he had a VCR player
Yeah it's like this is how he first watch
Uncensored American Pie
What you told me the first action film he saw was first Blood the original Rambo movie yes
Sand
It's kind of funny you eat like it wasn't even that these movies were exciting because they were illegal
But compared to Soviet films American films
Just offered a lot of
Stimulation
It's kind of like a barrage on the
I just remember the violin
The blood and
Sweat and machine guns
And yeah
Sylvester Stallone's bulging muscles
Can Boost phones were not County Fair shuttle tickets
At least in Baku where Elmer's from
People got pretty creative with how they scream these movies because they're still illegal at this point
I'm so he actually grew up watching bootleg Hollywood films in video bands
So tell me about
It's so in certain parts of the Soviet Union like from probably like the
70s to about the 90s
There is a popular form of transportation called the mushrooms
Sort of like a cross
Between a taxi
Panda bus
And they were these
Latvian Maids
Mini buses
It was like The Rock
People refer
Graphics
So during the daisies were just public transit but at night some of these rough drivers would convert their buses
Is into many mobile movie theaters
Interview they have
But TVs and VCRs are screens I got to get work really super common for
People that own their own VCRs in their homes on so this made it just a lot easier to bring movies to larger groups
Two people to watch together
And so are these
Land was he like it
What were they like ice cream trucks were they just would show up there what is actually exactly what it was like it was it was
Weird mouth and there's like no official schedule
I compared it to it like
Can ice cream van or
It just showed up
People be like the video van is here
Annabelle the kids
The yard
Did they get inside the van and watch a movie
I guess it's kind of like a Alegria version of watching a movie
What are those Entertainment Systems in a family minivan
The television and the VCR would be in the front of the van right behind the bus driver seat and there be curtains
On the windows to block out light and make it a little bit
More discreet from the outside
Will Sadler
Would sit in the bus
Spacing
Forward
And
One of my Vivid memories is
Smell
Stale cigarettes
They're all day
Sometimes people would actually be
10 year old smoking in a bus
But something that I thought was interesting was
The weight of these phones are translated
So it was
It was really common that the people who dug these movies into Russian
She speaks
Azerbaijani
Screened in Russian by translators
Or journalist or film critics by day and at night they would illegally translate Hollywood movies
And usually it was directly over the original soundtrack
Usually guy and usually in one take
Remove the old Dilaudid
Medela
I actually have a clip here for you to hear what it sounds like
So this is
A clip from the movie The Thing
And I
I don't know what the hell's in there
Dance 3D shelter
PayPal
Yellow poop
Choke
Muckleshoot bingo
Homophonic animal trivia
He's not really selling it
What is strange introduction to American culture I can't imagine what you must think that America is the
Place in the world
But I did say something kind of funny witches
That because of the way these films were dubbed over with you being able to hear both English and Russian the same time
He has a theory that it made him better at acquiring new languages
How I got so good and bad English we work
Curing
Add directory
The original
I mean he came here in
English is almost like I barely detect
Any kind of accident
This is
Based on his own wild speculation with a lot of people grow watching these movies but English is very good
There's actually great documentary called Chuck Norris vs communism
The Romanian woman named
Irina nistor who single-handedly Dudley
3000 western movies into Romania during those times so if you're interested in watching that
If people want to read
Original story goldlink
That's so good oh that's what a great
More details about the story cool thanks so much
99percentinvisible with Bruce's week by Vivien Leigh Mixon Tech production by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is our senior producer of coal state is the digital
Director Russell team is a varietal
Joel Rosenberg Emmett Fitzgerald Delaney Hall Taryn Mazza Sophia klatzker and me Roman Mars
Special thanks to Jessica Baughman has University of Washington she organized an oral history project called
Bollywood and Bolsheviks
Indo Soviet collaboration in literature and film
You find out more about Bollywood and Bolsheviks
No website
99percentinvisible is Project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
We are a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows in all of Pi
Podcasting
Radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook and Tweety me at Roman Mars and the show at 99 DIY
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
Chartreux home on the web
Is 99 pi
. org
Radio Shack near me
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight
Play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com