This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
When you're on Highway stuck in bumper-to-bumper traffic
Also do you start to feel the same
It's easy to forget
That you're in a particular place on the Earth surface Coast Oribe or a desert or playing
Mexico City is one of the biggest busiest traffic cities in the world
But it's also a Highland Valley
Over 7000 feet in the air
Surrounded on all sides by volcanoes
Sometimes these volcanoes spit up a little fire and smoke
To remind people of a volatile geology all around them
What about a millennium and a half ago
Volcano called
Fully erupted
Molten lava poured into the valley destroying an indigenous City
And covering 30 square miles in a bed of volcanic Stone today most of the
Is lava field has been paved over with roads and buildings parking lots devoured
Bible artist
City in North America
Mexico City
The producer Emmett Fitzgerald
But in the midst of all this urban sprawl
There's one spot where you can still get a good look
That old volcanic
So you can see now
Mm
Rocks
That
Executive team
1600 years ago
This is Pedro, Raina is a landscape architect
And we're in the Patriot ghoul they sign on helica logical Reserve
It's a small Park in South Mexico
Go City
It contains the Last Remnant
The old lava field
Looking down at the ground you can see Swirls and Fulton The Rock
How the lava was moved
The cooled although Centre
Teresa go
Yeah oh yeah
In Spanish. Corazones
In English El Pedregal means the rocky place
And it's a fitting name the ground tears made of purplish black stone
Covered in bright green lichen
Dry Brown grasses are growing up
Did the cracks but Pedro says that when the seasonal rains come
This whole Lance
Will transform
Theme rainy season
It turns green and a lot of chorus
Call ranch red
Yellow
Purple blue
A lot of wildflowers so this is
Beautiful
Pedro Cardenas
Probably the pager dolls number one fan
Kevin De bruyne
Of different species of plants
There are two or three
Endemic species
Only here in this place
Fine.
What is an orchid
And the other one is a cactus
There's also a tiny little frog
That only appears in the rain scene
Bug bite
But some nights
Penn Station
Listen to scrub the little
Fairy versus Magic
And many people even me
Are very crazy about that you like it
Pedro is not the first Arkansas
Pek to fall in love
With the better gone
Back in the 1940s this lava field became the Muse of the great Mexican modernist
Luis Barragan
Oregon is a giant Mech
He's famous for designing
Simple cubic houses painted with full bright color
Yellows and reds fuchsias
Is vivid
Single color walls are like the
Instagram background
Paragon design some of his most interests
Houses among the rocks of the Patriot golf
But in attempting to build harmoniously with this volcanic landscape
He may have accidentally
Led to its demise
And contributed to an ecological crisis that threatens the future
Of the entire city
Luis Barragan move to Mexico City from Guadalajara in the late 1930s
The city was in the middle of a building boom
And amidst all that construction and growth
The Patriot all about
10 miles south of
The city center
Was one of the few places that remain completely undeveloped
Paragon used to explore the lava field
On weekend hikes
What does artist friend
Barragan like a lot of other
Artistically minded
People
Putting Diego Rivera
Became enamored of the
This place
This is Keith egner he is an architectural historian at the University of Oregon who wrote a book about Louis Farrakhan
He says that Barragan fell in love with a paid real for its physical Beauty
But also because the landscape felt distinctly next
It was a place that the Spanish should never change
I'd never colonised
It was a place with interviews of the volcanoes that
We're so Central to a lot of
Mexican mythology next
In history
American decided to build their
He came up with the
Plan of building
Houses modern houses
Jade Gardens
On this
Again very distinct
Volcanic
Site
He called the project Los jardines de Pedregal
3 years this uneven Rocky landscape tutored would be Developers
The Dragon song the lava
As an asset
And rather than
Breaking up the lava and carting it away and trying so unilevel off the ground as
Other people might have done there are gone
Develop this idea to
Keep much of the lava and the native vegetation place
This idea was inspired by Architects like Frank Lloyd Wright who believed that the design of a building should reflect the landscape
On which it was built
Justice wright-designed his famous Fallingwater house around the spectacular waterfall in Pennsylvania
Barragan wanted to Design Homes inspired by this Majestic love
And so he decided that all houses in The Patriot all should be simple and modern and made from basic local materials
Streets
Should follow the natural Contours of The Rock
And lots should be kept for really large
How much is 30000 square feet
And that house is only take up a relatively small
Percentage of those
Lots
The rest to be left to Garden
Barragan was obsessed with garden
This could be apocryphal but
Supposedly he used to say
I don't build houses with Gardens
Idled Gardens
Houses
And he wanted The Gardens of the page a gall to be Odes to this unique volcanic landscape
The substantial portion of the original law that should be left on site and only
Small patches of lawn
Might be used
Distinct
Native
Trees and shrubs were to be left in place and cultivate
American began working in the Pedregal in the late 1940s
His first houses were carefully nestled among the rocks
And integrated seamlessly
With the volcanic landscape
The gardens featured little stairways cut into the stone
That allowed you to move to the space
There's even a spot in one of the houses where he
Huge piece of lava comes through the wall
If all this sounds pretty
Expensive
Well it was
Barragan's goal was to convince wealthy professionals
To escape
The crowded noisy City Center
It's a breath of fresh air and beautiful scenery
Philosophy
And he hired a photographer named Armando Salas Portugal
To really capture the vibe
Solace Portugal's beautiful photos of well-to-do Mexican families wandering through the Rock Gardens
Help sell barragan's lava lifestyle to the Mexico City Elite
You can leave in Paradise very static plays with a lot of lava
Cheaters Pedro, rain again
You came with your Cadillac 57 or your
Buick
You look like a Cary Grant or something like that so many people mix
Yes
We want to leave that way I know it sounds pretty cool to me
Right
You living in this
Rugged Wilderness short drive from your downtown office job like a sophisticated cowboy
Instead of a horse
I have money at that time I for sure
Boathouse
You weren't able to visit Mexico City
Armando Salas Portugal photographs are probably the best way to experience
Paragon Architecture
And his vision of Harmony
Between building and Landscape
The truth is that Vision never really came to pass in the real world
In the early 1950s Barragan got bought out
The project
And soon all his utopian ideas about how the landscape
Developed
Went out the window
What city was growing in
Breakneck pace
And here was this source
Cheap land
And so you can see in this aerial photographs El Pedregal in 1950
There's a few houses and Roads
Is there by 1959 the places
Densely packed
Houses in
Very much built up
The house has got bigger and the gardens got smaller
And newcomers to the area didn't seem to share barragan's Rev
Thanks for the love
They covered up the rocks with driveways and Lawn
Jade garden
It's full of non-native plants
And it's easy to think about this story as a kind of Iko architectural Paradise Lost
In part because of the way people talk about Louis Farrakhan
Cheese
I have come down to us in the scene of the architectural hagiography
The in the in the literature as this you know this Mystic Monk
Sort of remote from
Modern Life in many ways
And there's certainly truth in that
But at the same time
He was also a very
Successful businessman even a rather rapacious real estate developer
Exercise the Paragon
That paradise
Was always very ephemeral it was never really been
Meant to last and again I don't think
Barragan release
Expected it to last
Between the 50s and the 80s
Nearly the entire love
What field was developed
Today about a half million people live on top
The Pentagon
There are fancy neighborhoods in poor ones
Put aside from the Federal Reserve where our story began
The lava rock is basically gone
It would be fair to put that all on the lease paragon
But the irony is as much as he genuinely loved that lava landscape
In a way
He facilitated its demise
That's project.
Beautiful houses in Kalamazoo
Date trigger there there
The urbanization in
Insouth mix
And then starts
Develop
Urban develop this area
Pedro Camarena thinks that developing a patriot goal was
A fatal error not just because the rocks look pretty or we're home to some cool plants and animals
He says that covering up this unique geology contributed to a deeper problem
Ecological crisis
Playing out in Mexico City today a crisis rooted in the cities
Extremely complicated relationship
With water
Yelp for Mexico City
The trouble with water is quite complex
And it all starts
In the moment that
Someone decided to build
A city of
Upon the lake
This is Loretta Castroville
I'm I'm an architect and urban designer
And I do design design for the city and design with water
Castro Rivera says that the valley of Mexico is
Actually more of a
Beeson
It's a closed Basin it's like a bowl
Which has no natural water exit
So when it rains all the runoff concentrates in the lower areas of the Beijing
And
This bowl starts filling up
For centuries the Basin was filled with a series of rainwater leg
The Aztecs
Built their capital
Tenochtitlan
On an island in the middle of one of those legs
It'll causeways and canals and floating Garden
It was like the Venice
Spell mesoamerica
But when Spanish conquistadors satenaw tri-bond
They rebuilt the city as if it was
Just any old city in Spain
With a centralized grid
So that's when real trouble starts happen
Nearly every year when the seasonal rains came the colonial City would flood
We're talking serious flooding
After the flood of 1629
Mexico City was under water for
4 years
And in that moment
That the government
Viceroy decided
To open the first
Canal
Deadwood
Sorry to draining the lake system
Over the course of the next several centuries
Is Mexico City built an elaborate system of tunnels
Designed to evacuate rainwater out of the Basin and prevent flooding
Little by little the city
Drain the
An expanded out
Open the dry lake bed
But Mexico City also suffers from a second water
One that seems almost paradoxical
Even as it gets inundated every year with rains and floods
The city
Is running out
Of water
In the middle of the 20th century Mexico City population
Bloated
And all those people needed
To drink
Seasonal rain could have provided a reliable source of freshwater
The Mexico City had just built a mass
Subsystem of infrastructure designs
Specifically to get rid of it
And now with the 23 million inhabitants in the city
There's not enough
Drinking water to satisfy the necessities of all this
Enormous population
Today many neighborhoods in Mexico City don't have reliable run
Water
And then when the rainy season comes those same neighborhoods
Get far too much water
All at once
So we live in this Paradox of
Irving Plaza
And water scarcity
To solve the scarcity issue the city took to approach
A pipe water in from far away
And they pumped it up
From the uncle
Blueground
Which in turn created a third problem
In the early twenties of last century
Some Engineers saw
Doug D city was sinking
This is Manuel perlakuan he's director of The Institute for social research at the national
Autonomous University of Maine
Champion buildings
Science
Fight
Centimeters per year
On some of them
The reason was pretty straightforward
As more and more people took more and more water
The aquifer every year
The muddy lake bed soil began to crack
And crumble
Like a stale cookie
And that's why the city began to
Today Mexico City is pumping water out of the aquifer
Twice as fast
Does it can replenish
And the city has song about 30 ft over the past Century
Did you walk around Mexico City today you can see this in the landscape
Crooked
Skyline sinkholes in places
With the ground is completely uneven
Mexico City is
Flooded
Thirsty and sinking
And climate change is only going to make all of it more extreme
It's an impossibly complicated problem
With no easy solution
But with impossibly complicated problems
You have to start somewhere
And Pedro, Reina thinks that one place worth
Considering is the lava Fields about patriarchal
Let's take a look
What is the Pedregal I'm going to show you let me show you
Why this water
Run
Very very
Angela Bofill
Pedro is one of several architects
Who have started thinking about ways the city could recharge it
Groundwater aquifer
In most places we charge just
Isn't possible
The ground beneath the old lake is made
Clay that retains water on the surface
Prevent it from falling Underground
But in a few places around the edges of the old
The landscape is Rocky and permeable
You think I was probably
The best the best place
Because biggest lava fields
Are the most
Permeable
Geology
On Earth
Back in the pager call Ecological Reserve
Camarena bends down
And points to a piece
Lava rock
Take a look there's a lot of
Hoses a lot of a
Horse
Poorest very porous Stone thank you
It looks like one of those pumice stones
People use in the shower
To scrape dead
Skin out there
More less
Pedro says that for years when rain fell on the Patriot call the water would easily trickle-down
Through this porous Stone
Into the ark
Refer below ground
Can you stink
Game of big big storm
Do you think you can find the Lagoon here
Of course not
But the same cannot be said for most places on the old lava field
Because apart from this Ecological Reserve
Nearly all of the
Porous volcanic rock is
Gone
Cover up by layers
Permeable concrete
And so when the rains come
The water just runs off the pavement
The Source system
Pedro, Reina wants to chat
The only thing we have to do is
Depave
The araki
He feels
We have
80 square kilometers
Big lava flow
Obviously he's very very
But weekend
Debate did you understand what I mean what he means is get rid of all the unnecessary paid
Plugging up all those volcanic pores
Camarena wants to be paved parking lots and medians
Create volcanic infiltration Zone
Square rainwater could flow back
The aquifer
Can't create an infiltration Zone next to a toxic waste dump
Or you could contaminate the water supply the Pedro wants to carefully peel back the
Cities concrete skin
Disposal Ava and try to restore the data field
Because the old lava field is still there
Beneath all the asphalt
If you go to Los hardiness help in Tagalog
Today
The upscale neighborhood.
Louis Farrakhan started back in
The forties
You can catch a glimpse of this burial
Little pieces of lava poking through
Do the grass in the concrete
For the most part though it looks
Bike other affluent neighborhoods Mexico
A lot of Lawns with
Sprinklers
So they prefer to put a lot of grass
And let me tell you
Date spent nowadays they spent a lot of money
Are in irrigation
Pedro wants to shift how people in Mexico City think about garden
A while back he was asked
China Garden to go with
The public Arts
It was built in The Patriot golf 40 years earlier
And instead of planning a bunch of flowers
Shrubs
Just started digging
So I create that Garden
Only by Excavating digging
Gardening by subtraction Pedro calls this
Landscape archaeology we start with three guys
Old guys
Digging
Like archaeological site
They start to remove plants
Then
Soil
Then starts to appear
The lava field
Beautiful
It's a lot more work than planting tulips
But Pedro says that people in The Patriot all can do landscape archaeology on their own property
Uncover the lava and build Aragon style dry Rock Gardens that don't require any irrigation
But it's a tough sell
People want Gardens that look like Versailles
Yes we are very independent emotionally dependent in Europe
We still
Design Gardens like in France
I mean
Is ridiculous
Because we don't have the landscaper
France we don't have the weather we don't have the soil is mems very different
Pedro told me that there is one house in Los jardines del Pedregal
Where you can still see a true Mexican lava rock garden
It's actually one of the first houses built in
Design by Barragan himself
Back in the forties
The property underwent a lot of changes in the decade since
But a few years ago
A new owner a man named Cesar Cervantes
Decided to restore the house the way it looked in Barragan
San Pedro convinced him to uncover the original lava rock
And he did it
But now
Everybody told me
You have to
See you have to go to
Two sister house
See what's happen
No I I I I asked him and he said come whatever whenever you want
But I don't have time
I on the other hand
Have money
I am sister 70s and we are at
Gossip
Cesar grew up in this neighborhood one really wanted to see visible lava in their Garden
I don't remember even my father
Covering or getting rid of physical lover
Sabering dress
Or a swimming pool
When Cesar bought this house the previous owners had covered up the original Barragan Rock Garden within
Astro turf putting green
But
Cesar in a steam started doing a little landscape archaeology
We start removing and removing layers
Where is the grass fake grass and cement
And slowly the original lava field
Began to re-emerge
Back to its original condition extremely
Breathtaking
It really is
Cesar kindly let me take a tour of his home with a guy named Mariana esqueda
Before we got the garden Mariana showed me the house
The walls are
Thick and heavy
Painted this delightful
As she opened the door I was yammering on about something rather and the house
Kind of took my breath away
The project at The Gardens of picture. Like what
What's heat right wow
I just
Found
So quiet
Asylum
Yeah it feels almost like a
Like a church
After showing me around the house
Mariana let me out back
The garden
Weed scramble down a rocky path and then suddenly were surrounded
On all sides
Buy porous black lava
It was unlike any Garden I've ever
More like a nature preserve
Filled with Nexus
Chicken plants and animals
Slides
Circle lands like cockatoos
I mean like there's a
Girls like lizards Right There and Everywhere
I feel
Wild
Discomfort
Liquid
It's really beautiful
Cesar says that when his neighbor's first saw the Rock
It was cleared
They didn't even know they lived on top of
Lava fields
Did you want what did you do here did you
Where did you bring this lava from
Appear here
But Pedro, Reyna hope
Said if more people see these rocks
Maybe they'll follow suit
Dig up the lava in their own back
Rock Gardens in rich neighborhoods are not going to solve the Water Crisis
Not even close
But every bit of lava that gets on cupboard
Is a tiny step in the right direction
Towards rebalancing the cities relation
What's groundwater
A huge thank you this week to the Fantastic environmental reporter Zoe schlanger
Her great piece in courts about Mexico City's water problems clued us into Pedro Camarena and his work
Zoe has been a lot of great choice but water and climate change and other environmental issues
You can find links to more for work on our website
99pi.org
Have the break
We'll talk about the bigger picture and what Architects and designers are trying to do to solve Mexico City's water dry
Between the beats
Bongs and Charter of our devices
We're immersed
The cluttered World a man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexa
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is in another room and we're all hearing. Voice
Technology
You talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI fate
So I'm back with Emmett in the studio
To zoom out
And talked a little bit about the bigger picture when it comes to the Mexico City Water Crisis
Yeah and then she talks to Loretta Castro Vergara who's one of the Architects that we eat
Heard from in the story she'll tell you that it's a question of design
Design is really a key element
In
In this situation
For us
It's
The language with
Speak
Sweetwater
Oh I like speaking in the language of design
Yeah I know
She sounds like a 99ci there's no silver
Bullet design solution for for Mexico
Cities problems
But what she kept coming back to with me was a fundamentally
The city has to change its relationship to rain
Mexico City is different than
A lot of other cities that are facing water shortages around the world and if they do get
Brain if it rains it rains that you know Cape Town South Africa would love
To have as much rain as Mexico City does
But because of his history with flooding which
We heard about
In the piece yeah they've learned that rainwater is
Is bad
The problem for us
Seawater as our enemy
We have learned that water that falls
Is a problem
And we've learned that for the last
700 years
So it's really hard
Change
The way in which we see rain water
But they really have to because
That rainwater is an asset
That has been waist
Stood for so long
Literally hundreds of years
Focusing on the rainwater out of the valley
Fast as you can so that we don't flat out
And you know the consequence of doing that for so long has been like the desiccation of the Watershed
So this is Enrique lomnitz
Enrique is the co-founder of an organization called is flower Bona Urban Island in Spanish
And the whole
Go ladislau Urbana is to try and take advantage of all that rain to try to flip the equation on its head and say let's turn this way
Bring water into an asset
And to do this what they do as they design and in
Install rainwater harvesting
Systems on people's homes
And Enrique
Says that this makes sense for a couple different reasons one because
It provides people with reliable
Play clean water
N2 because it reduces the pressure on the groundwater aquifer
Rainwater harvesting systems like we used they help you avoid pulling water out of the ground and they help you avoid
Putting water into the sewage system
And the help of family
In parts of the city that are having big water problems
In 2009 in a neighborhood that had particularly bad
Water problem
Like people are starting to open their tops and have like brown water come out of the top number or just not have any water coming out of the
The top sometimes for weeks on end
Apparently
What is the weather for a Skype tape
But anyway designed assistance for individual homes
Is rainwater from the roof of the house
Filters out
All the kinds of impurities that you might have an in
Stores IT in a big
Tank for daily use
It's a pretty simple
Design intervention but the thing that makes it the work really challenging is that
You can't just mass-produce this system in and ship it out
Every house is different now so everyone wants these things
System is like a custom install
Every family has to be
Trained and taught how to use rainwater harvesting system and
What is for and how to use it and how not to use it and what's be careful of
Cancel the work ends up being really social you know you can't
Drop the technology
People you have to
It's a cultivate relationships and get them onboard
Cancel can you
Drink the water that clean water
So no it's not clean enough to drink
But it is clean enough for
For just about every other household uses could have that makes up the vast majority of the water that home
Music music
And so what is the scale that they're working on how many of these water systems are they
Tranny installed around
Yeah so at this point they built about 11,000 rainwater harvesting system so it's a lot but it's not
Not a lot in the grand scheme of things and mostly they've been
Doing this on a fairly small scale and going kind of neighborhood to Neighborhood very Grassroots approach
But things even in the last couple years are really starting to scale-up and then Mexico City just elected in
You meher
Her name is Claudia sheinbaum and she's
A scientist who spent
Haha yeah scientists
Any country really
But she spent her whole career studying environmental issues water issues specifically she's got an engineering background
This is all like really up her alley
And since her election you know just this past year
The government the city government has started to work much more closely with this liar bana ends and they really want to push
Rainwater harvesting on a really large
Scale
The Mexico City government was like dude this is an important project and we need to do a huge knowing all of the parts of the city that don't have
And we're installing we're going to be installing 10000 rainwater harvesting systems there this year
And if all goes well financed inflation like a hundred thousand or more rainwater harvesting systems over the next few years
So it's definitely a large-scale experiment at this point it's kind of one of its kind in the world
Possibly like scaling up
Threatened
Harvesting is the solution
It's really going to take
Home
Basket of different strategies
To get Mexico City out of this mess
We're going to get out of this situation by doing a whole bunch of things together
But that's fundamentally
Just create
Balance between how much water
We actually put into the ground and how much water we pull out of
Basic
And without a Milo Reddick Astro Regatta the architect
We are from earlier it's focusing on designing parks and other sorts of public spaces that also function as water in infrastructure
You don't like a public sister and then things like rain for a lot of
People
Or a public park that has an in ground water infiltration component where you've actually got rain water flowing back
To the aquifer
And so her goal is to create a whole network of green infrastructure so that when
And those rains
Cam the city
Can take that water in and make use of a
Innocent sandwiches
The city could really be, a sponge
So when we have one of these
Rain storms
Oldest public spaces somehow are evil
Who holds Rainwater
And keep it there
Until the storm
Passes
On that way
Theoretically a big rainstorm could be something that people are
Looking forward to and then hoping for rather than something that they fear
Because it would
Both collect water that they need and also mitigate flooding because the water would be drained to the offer instead of being on the
Surface and trap they're destroying things
It's true it's true yeah if you can if you can hold that water you're also preventing at water from turning into dangerous runoff
Does problems you know I mean
You should go to Power that like flooding requires its own you know the in order to solve the flooding problem there's other things that are
Are needed there are Architects that are actually thinking about
No bringing back remnants of the old Lake systems as ways to
Allow water to flood into these
Spaces I can hold and retain water and teeth people say if you know you know there's all kinds of things that
Fashion designers are thinking about their men Engineers to the big problem if it leaks
The whole water system is old and filled with leeks
Some people estimate their losing as much as
Is 40% of water and leaks so they let you know in terms of blow
A fruit that's a great place
Start also Wastewater
Wastewater reuse you know there's so many different things that need to happen and Loretta's points basically like we need all of it
Not waiting around to the best solution we need an all of all of the above strategy
Because what I see
At this moment is that we have enough infrastructure
To keep the city safe
For 30 years
So we can sink
Window of 30 years
We have a very big up
Opportunity
Putting up all this alternate Water Management
Strategies right
Then we could really use this 30
Yours for our best benefit
25th
Let's have this problem of we have no more water and the City
Disappearance no because we also know
From history
That many cities disappeared
Because of lack
Water right
How to find dollar real
Existential crisis about the existence of an entire city because of water
Absolutely
Young 2022-23 million people
It's really scary
But
But you know I mean honestly everyone that I talked to seemed a little more optimistic than
I was expecting and I think that that optimism
Comes from the sense that they
The city is really feels like it's undergoing a real shift right now and how it it thinks about water and how it
Deals with water
Towards
Embracing all the rain that
Flows into the basin
And the question is just like can that shift
Fasting
Get it right we can we can make another interview
15 years Federal see if it's working or not right
It was Booker right now
Thanks so much
Thank you
99percentinvisible with Bruce this week by Emmett Fitzgerald
Mixing Tech broken by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Kate mingle is our senior producer Kurt Kolstad is the digital director
Presa team includes senior editor Delaney Hall Avery trufelman Vivien Leigh Sophia ClassDojo
Rosenberg and me Roman Mars
This episode was supported by the Alfred P Sloan Foundation enhancing public understanding and engagement with science
And Technology
More information on Sloan
Pat Sloan. Org
We are project of 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative shows
Turn all of podcasting
Baidu mall
Radiotopia
Tok FM
One show joins Coast about the show on Facebook and tweeted me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 bi or gay
Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But the beautiful lawfield that we call home
Is 99 pi
. org
Radiotopia
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com