This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This past fall
200 people gathered at the Explorers Club in New York City
The building was once a clubhouse to feigned naturalist's and explorers
Now it's an archive of ephemera and Rarities
From pioneering Expedition
Big trucks to the world's tallest mountains the North Pole
And the Moon
Woolly Mammoth tusks frame a fireplace
A menacing polar bear towers near The Landing with claws at the reading
And a cheetah
Rumored to have been shot by Teddy Roosevelt
Sits on a plinth
Just upstairs
The Gathering was an honor of a new Expedition
Wanted search
Not a single animal
Best reporter Caitlin Swanson
The club was hosting a biological senses
An ecological survey so difficult
So complicated so taxing
But it has never been attempted before
And may never be attempted again
It is
A really big
Project
Like no I don't think
We've ever been involved in
A project of this scope
In our lives
It's like
Moving a little a small alarm me around
This is Jamie Allen
The census was his idea
And when he started
It was a small operation
But now Jamie is merely the tip of a vast pyramid of census related personnel
Including a logistics chief
Chief cartographer of veterinarian
An epidemiologist a specialist from the fish and wildlife service
And of course
The web team
And that's just
The core staff
Below them are the
The foot soldiers
The volunteers who must go out into the field
And do the actual
Counting 300 plus volunteers counting 700 hectares I remember hundred meter
+ 3000
Plus sheets of paper that we have to it's
Yeah Avast filings
Multiple office
And a team of hundreds
All for the sake of answering one question
I want to know how many squirrels are in Central Park
Squirrels
They're counting at squirrels
Dates October 14th 2018 time
On a chilly Sunday evening
I'm following stew
One of the Central Park census volunteers
Around the parks in Northern NJ
Run hide for Eastern gray squirrel
Which is like the squirrel
It's what you'll find in just about any American city
But especially Central
So we need to be on the 10th down there okay
Well I'm going to
Absentia
Following is we we had off the path
Over fences in through tile brush
We're slowly making our way to his designated area
Hectare 38e
Hectares are plots of land that measure a little less than 2 and 1/2 acres each
The job of a census volunteer is to count all the squirrels they can find within their assigned hectares
And only
Verisign hectares
Although this doesn't stops you from getting incredibly excited by every squirrel
Don't tell anybody you know in my hector
Buck
See you later
After every hectare in the park has been surveyed
All the data will get plugged into a wildlife counting formula popularized by the great mid-century Danish Amir
Squirrel biologist
Monthly car
If only will account for squirrels that were double counted and ones no one managed to find
And then finally spit out a number that the world has been waiting for
The squirrel abundance number
The total population of eastern gray squirrels in Central Park
Give or take
At which point you would be totally justified in asking as many do
What precisely is a point
And knowing the squirrel abundance number
What they're saying is like
You're counting squirrels like
Squirrels have a specific
Contacts
In people's minds
And it's to be ignored like it's assumed I think that
Because they're so common we know everything we need to know about squirrels
But it's true
The very fact
But no one has bothered to do a Central Park Squirrel census before
Together this most
Basic of data points about when the most common animals in our landscape reviews I kind of societal blind-spot we have in
Regards to squirrels
For a long time now
We're taking them for granted
Including the story
Where all this world came from the sky
Girls we see in our cities and towns are so everyday so ubiquitous so
Just
There
That is easy to assume they've always been there
But the truth is
They haven't
Mid-nineteenth century
You could walk
To a place like Boston or Philadelphia
Manhattan
And you would not see a single squirrel
This is Etienne Benson
He's a historian of environmental science at the University of
Pennsylvania
And he says the cities of the early nineteenth century
We're effectively
Querulous
These were animals you could only see if you left
And then even perhaps left the farm
Rachel went deep into the woods
And it was only when you went deep into the woods that you would have a chance to see something
Like a squirrel infect squirrels were considered so elusive
The very wealthy
I'd like to keep them as exotic pets
In 1856 an article in the New York Times described
A one-touch pet
Escaped from its owner's home in Manhattan
And when it was discovered in a tree
A crowd of people gathered in amazement
Trying to lower it down
Eventually the crowd grew so large and rowdy
The police
Had to forcibly disperse
So how do these eastern gray squirrels
These are exclusive Woodland creatures
Make their way into urban spaces
Well for starters is Etienne
They didn't
At least not on the road
What was so fascinating to me was to find out that they have been intentionally introduced
The squirrels that we all take for granted as we
Walk to the park
On our way to the gym or the office
Are only there because we put them there
They were deliberately brought into cities
And fed
And shelter
The first city that we know of to introduce squirrels was Philadelphia in 1847
Like many East Coast cities of the mid-nineteenth century
It was already a highly Urban environment
People urine for a taste of the wilderness
That the squirrel was seen to embody
They were captured in
The Wilderness brought into the city
And placed on a single tree
Almost as if they were animals
In a menagerie or a zoo
The tree was in the middle of a small public
Square and it was equipped with a wooden shelter and offense
So the squirrels could stay safe from the elements
And any would-be predators in their little squirrel home
A few other cities like Boston
Replicate
First the number of squirrels
With teeny tiny
Philadelphia started out with only three
Think of it as a trial run
Only this first trial run
It went terribly
When I started working on this topic I thought okay you introduce a few squirrels into an urban
Park
In a few years you're going to have 2002 Scrolls no problem
At the very beginning
They were essentially incapable of Survivor
The cities of the 19th century just didn't have the kind of large Park
An extensive tree cover we see
When you thought about Urban landscapes
Are very unfriendly
To an animal that required trees for food
In the classic storybook image of a squirrel
Always clutching in a car
And then that's basically true
Wild Squirrel requires deciduous nut bearing plants such as Oaks
In order to survive
Without trees
If the city had to provide for
The squirrels
But the squirrel feed often proved to be either insufficient
Are nutritionally worthless
So those first squirrels either died off
Were killed
Word opposites
In 1855 the reporter for the Boston evening transcript describe the introduction of squirrels
As quote
Absurd and reprehensible experiment
Which raises the question
Why are there no squirrels everywhere in American cities
I think it's more a model of if you build it they will come
Gabriel Willow is a nacho
Who specializes in animals
Species that live in urban environment
Study nature and educate people about the natural world
Specifically in New York City
And he says that in the late 19th century
Green spaces like New York's were undergoing a transformation
Areas of open land
When's multi-purpose field used for everything from cattle grazing
Slaughterhouses in Malaysia training
Being transformed into
Spaces of leisure
And by the 1870s
$3 we're leaving behind small busy
P-Square
In favor of large
Idyllic Park
And although they were designed for people
These new Urban Oasis
Just might be the best thing to ever happen to the eastern gray squirrel
The parks weren't just big
They were also designed to mimic the natural world
Take Central Park and Prospect Park in New York for example
Both designed by Calvert vaux
And Frederick Law Olmsted
Existing geology in hydrology
They took naturally existing small ponds or marshy areas and made
Lakes out of them
They also chose to
To keep the areas dramatic Rocky outcrop
Instead of blasting them away
That's been done with the rest of
How do you spread and so they were working with certain natural elements
These Natural Parks were filled with Hedges and lakes and streams
And lots and lots of trees
Including
To the great Fortune of squirrels everywhere
Oak trees
Red Oak is very common white oak is very common pin oak is very common
There's a lot of acorns around
Everything a would-be squirrel residence
Might want or need
It was in this
Oak dotted Acorn strewn landscape
Central Park in 1877
But a handful of eastern grey squirrels were introduced
For a second
Trial run
And it was not landscape that the squirrels
Virtually exploded in population
By the turn of the century what had started as just a few dozen squirrels now numbered in the
Actually this is around the time that people just stop counting
I mean how could you with
So many squirrels running around
Guesses range from the high hundreds to over 5000
In Central Park & Beyond
Squirrels became a commonplace is fire hydrants and telephone poles
No the other Newfound accessories of the urban landscape
And is this new approach to Urban Parkland spread to other cities
So did the idea of populating them
Squirrels
Eastern gray squirrels were introduced again
The place is like Philadelphia and Boston
Unwelcome
Seattle Vancouver in San Francisco
Eastern Grays were also introduced overseas
England Italy in South Africa
It wasn't just the oak trees in these newly Lush environment that we're providing sustenance for the squirrels
At the time
People considered it their moral duty to feed them
Up until the early Twentieth Century the dominant
Way of understanding
The proper relationship between humans and animals in the city
Is it centered on charity
Is centered on the idea that humans
Have an obligation or responsibility
To create a friendly welcoming environment
For certain kinds of animals to flourish
PDL city was one that provided a home for good animals
And banish the bad
So if you go back even and read like
John James audubon's account
A bird species
He might talk about the bloodthirsty
Hardcore it's a
Wiley
Raven and shoot Hawks and Falcons and Eagles
Because their predators because they were the other animals people
Mean
Whereas other animals like pigeons and of course squirrels
We're considered peaceful
More than that they interacted with
The site of a non-domesticated animal
Not only approaching you
Effectively communicating with you by soliciting food
Was a sign that civilized nature
So is only proper that you
Feed them
Estranged labor gave these wild animals and the residents who brought them into the city
A name
The more than human community
Stadium is to create a kind of
Fantasy world
In which
Every
Animal that is in the city is a living
Peacefully
With the others
At the Indulgence of the humans.
Around the place
Thanks for the more than human Community model
Urban squirrels live large
For decades
Nuts trees in humans feeding them extra food and killing off all their predators
They had it made
And in the case of New Haven for example there's even an article that I found that describes them as becoming so obese that they be
The fall from the trees
As the 19th century led into the 20th
And the squirrels were busy spreading out into
Suburban addicts in college campuses
No one stopped to wonder
If there could be such a thing as
Is too many squirrels
But as hard as it is to admit
There is no evidence to suggest
There might actually be
Too many
There is an ongoing
Matthew Harper is an information security expert
With 20 years of experience
And he says when it comes to threats to the US power Network
Forget to write
Forget Russian hacker
Send the case of the utility infrastructure
Humble squirrel that's causing most of the issues
By some estimates one out of every five power outages in United States
Are squirrel related
To be fair to the squirrel
They really start out with the best of intention
Squirrels need to build nests
And they usually build their nests
Intrigued
They also build them in anything that looks like a
Like utility poles
Transformers
And like all rodents
A squirrel's incisors
Never stop growing
Do they have to chew to keep them filed down
They mostly chew bark and branches and nuts
They also choose
Things like power
Inevitably
Some unlucky
Squirrel
Elna through the insulation of a
Powerline
Or step onto exposed wires at the same time and
Oh
Killing the squirrel
Ensuring the system
Keep track of all those systems Schwartz Matthew runs website
Called cyber squirrel 1
Which is a website which tracks
Squirrel activities
And attacks against the power grid
This is real
Cypress Grill
A big map marking the largest power outages caused by squirrels in the past 30 years
Take a year and you can find hundreds
Depends indicating squirrel incident
Laid out across
Lower 48 in Canada
There's a drop-down menu if you want to see how much is caused by other animals
But don't bother
When it comes to power problems
It's mostly the squirrels
Can you give me some examples of
Squirrel related power outages
All right I'm just pulling it up now
Squirrel
Last year 2018 College in California xidan happened
Cancel classes
Then in November of 2018 a single roving squirrel knocked out three substations in Upstate New York
Causing a string of power outages
For more than 12000 people
13 months
Another squirrel took at a polling station in Virginia on the day of the presidential election
Squirrel cut the power of an entire shopping mall in South Carolina
One week before Christmas
Taylor case in Canada back in April of impacted 55000 people
And those are just the big ones
In Austin Texas
Squirrels were responsible for over 400 separate outages
Kids in 20s
15 alone
But the greatest
Rodent related outage of all occurred in December of 1987
In the last place you'd ever expect to find an electrocuted squirrel
That story and more
SS
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Is talking to me and my wife is in another room and a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
Resent
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 99.
It happened on December 9th
It's kind of sad for me because I am a true animal lover
Member of the New York
That means you used to be one of those guys
ET yelling and screaming on the trading room floor
And it's simply this
Back in the day
Yell back in 1987
The New York Stock Exchange was
Everything to the world
Backbend in the 80s
Exchange control 85% of the global stock market
And search Raiders like Joe
They were the kings of Wall Street
We was a place to go we was so proud to wear all White badges with all numbers on it
And
Say we were
On the floor of the New York Stock Exchange
But there was also another Exchange in town that was slowly chipping away at their market share
Their biggest rival
NASDAQ
The NASDAQ with an automated
It ran on computers
It didn't need Floor Traders
And the Traders at the New York Stock Exchange
NBA trades in person by hand
He did it
SoJO still remembers the Glorious Day a rumor began to spread among the 4,000 traitors on the floor
For the exchange
We start hearing
Dennis extricated technical glitch
And yell by the time I got from one end to exchange the other might might have took about 30 seconds
Attic just Word of Mouth it just flies
Finally the electronic ticker tape
Scrolling along one of the walls of the exchange
Lit up with the news
Spend the ticket ape
The Turkey Thicket empresses flight across end
And we know
Their deepest
Darkest wish had come true
NASDAQ
FL
It was really a magnet it was a dream
And
The trading floor
Erupted
I mean you could ever Stephanie
482 minutes on December 9th 1987
NASDAQ was offline
Losing an estimated 20 million trade
And then we find out that it was a squirrel
A squirrel had chewed through a power line in Connecticut or NASDAQ tree with electricity
But it did not affect the New York Stock Exchange
Much to be Everlasting Joy of traitors like Joseph Sanju Amino
Should NASDAQ that's quarrel
That squirrel was Godzilla
To us on the New York Stock Exchange that little squirrel with Superman
Equation for
80 minutes
We were the Kings again
Set alarm for 2 a.m.
The score will pay the ultimate price you know for our
You hours of Glory that particular day
Squirrels have also been wreaking havoc overseas
In Great Britain
Eastern gray squirrels introduced in 1876
Quickly began to displace the native red
Squirrel
Driving it to near Extinction
In the eastern gray squirrel might be
Acute
The red squirrel is super cute
Can Google it
Is the love
And now there's only a few small pocket
Cuz the red squirrels left
In northern England and Scotland
This despite a massive eradication can
To keep the American Invaders out of
The Scottish Highlands
And you're up
They're officially an invasive
Species
But even as American squirrels were taking out shopping malls and stock exchanges in invading foreign countries
The very things that allowed them to proliferate in the first place
We're slowly being taken away
Starting the mid-twentieth century
Ecologist Wildlife managers and park officials
Started to re-examine Americas
Approach to Wildlife
They began to argue that Predators like coyotes and Hawks
Should no longer be hunted for the sake of a more than human community
That starts get replaced with an i really different
Privacy ecological view in which we understand those relationships are predation essential
To ecosystem as a whole
In his new ecological model
The ideal environment was no longer one that correspondent two Notions of civilized
Versus uncivilized species
But one in which a variety of
Predator and prey alike
Maintain
World population balance
With only minimal human intervention
It took a few decades for this idea to spread from the national parks into the city
But by the 1980s it had arrived
Along with the Predators
Which ecological reminded naturalist by Gabriel Willow
Is a wonderful thing
Coyotes
Are coming back on the road and we're not bringing them back
Ravens Ravens
The red-tailed hawk came back of its own accord
Other species we intentionally reintroduced like peregrine falcons and their thriving New York City
Has the highest population density of peregrine falcons in the world
For most of us the death of a few squirrels
Seems like a small price
Japan exchange for his Newfound biodiversity
Today there's no shortage of webcams
Set up by people who have discovered the Hawks Nest
Outside their 12th floor apartment Window
And while we've been busy welcoming the squirrels Predators back
I can do our cities
We've also begun to finally withdraw our charity
I think everybody should go check out squirrels they're pretty cool I'm Pro squantum squirrel
Gabriel and other natural has been feeding squirrels has no place in the new ecological model
Providing bread and other unnatural
Whole Foods
Can lead to a variety of
An acclimating squirrels to hand feeding
Can make them overly dependent on humans
And possibly pruned unstable population boom
None of which is ultimately good for the squirrel
Or the larger environment
Which is why 142 years after welcoming squirrels in
The fold of are more than human community
New York City
Is done giving hand
Good morning
March 1st 2019
What time is 12:05
Fritz Recreation
This past winter
New York City Parks
Department held a hearing
For proposed rule
That would make it illegal
Defeat any wild animal in the park
Attended solicit comments regarding the
Goodyear oil change
He's coming to become part
Gabriel Willow was there too
Although it didn't go down by the way he thought it
I didn't really expect
It to be quite eschewed
As it was in terms with almost everybody there was speaking against the regulations
Is criminal act that runs against the morals and rules of a civilized society
New York hospitals that the squirrels
Bishop doing the wild
The parks off the light
I don't know that I've
Encountered that many
Squirrel and pigeon
Ceiling fans in one place before
And I'll do the animals should be eating healthy food
They were not buying into
Ecological model
The parks are all are not nature there an artificial situation
We are part of your environment
When people Express concern that certain animals in certain Parks might starve
Gabriel
Tried to stand up for the hands off
Problem
But the Applause was tepid
Received founder and director of the wild bird fund
She was also against me
Take the proposed amendment to the rule
That's awesome in Chinese food
Exactly what effect
The blanket ban would have on wildlife populations is unclear
But regardless of the ecological impact
The biggest takeaway from the hearing
Was that the concept of the more than human community
That was still going strong
I'm here today as a voice for New York
Cities non-human residence
Because I see what's happening to our Wildlife Neighbors
As really
Truly tragic
The feeling that these animals
Our fellow citizens and should be treated with the same consideration
Has never fully gone away
It is not just about what we want it's about what the squirrels and all of the other than human beings
In our parks
Want to and they are constituents of New York City
I go to the park
People loved
Feed the animals in the park
On any park bench in any City
You'll see people throwing crumbs to the birds
And the birds approaching for more
It's one way we feel a connection to Nature
For just a moment
Both human and animal are doing something together
That shared experience between species
That's what the people that hearing didn't want taken away
Gabriel willow also believes that there is value in connecting with these animals
But he sees it as a reason not to feed them
I think people really
Crave a direct interaction and connection with nature and
Please
Go to the park
Observe wildlife
Feel that connection
You don't need to touch them you don't eat
To pet them you don't need to hold them you don't need to feed them like
It's actually more
Interesting and more valuable to stand back
An animal
Exhibiting amor
Natural behavior
What does grow long enough and you'll see it played tricks another squirrel
It's a squirrel carrying an acorn believes it's being watched
It will dig a hole
Pantomime putting the acorn in the hole
And then cover the whole back up
Although hiding the relay coordinates now
Just to throw its fellow squirrels
Squirrels have been seen carefully organizing their acorns by size and shape
Before they bury them
Biologists believe it's a mnemonic device that helps the squirrels remember
What they buried where
They have a specific call when I see a predator so if you learn a little bit of squirrel language
Like I know I know the hot call
So if I hear that I'll look up and often see a hawk
So for them to just sort of allow us to be there
But go about their
Day-to-day
Life
Is so much more powerful for me
There's more than one way to connect to the animals with whom we share our cities
Whether it's listening to that yet being of coyotes in the middle of the night
Singapore webcam
For the hawk nest outside your window
Or counting all the squirrels in Central Park
In March Jamie Allen and the other team members of the squirrel census
Finished Gathering their data
They plan to reveal the squirrel abundance number
In June
Etienne Benson says he doesn't know how many squirrels are in Central Park
But he thinks he does understand
Why everyone is so eager to find out
You're one of the appeals of it
Criss cross answers
Is just the same appeal
Dentist
Existed since the 18th
Safety switches
It's scared of people
That the world around them
It's not the only inhabited by humans that it's it is this multi-species
Class
Can I think there is a need and a desire there
To know something about your neighbors but since this is a form of appreciation
A way of recognizing that the squirrels are there
And that
In itself
Is beautiful
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Caitlin swell Jay and edited by Joe Rosenberg Mixon Tech production by Syracuse
Music by Shawn real
Mission music in this episode was composed by Jenny Conlee drizos
John neufeld and a query
Criminal is the senior producer of Coal City is the digital director
Russell team include senior editor Delaney Hall
Avery Chapman Emmett Fitzgerald hiramasa Vivien Leigh Sophia Oscar and me Roman Mars
Suddenlink this week to Susan Kirby in Andrew Christopher whose interviews
We could not get to include in the episode but
Without whose help we could not have made the story
As for the squirrel census
Following the announcement of the squirrel abundance number
There will be a squirrel masquerade ball and dance party held at the Explorers Club in New York City for details
Check out the squirrel census.com in the coming week
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced on radio row
Beautiful
Downtown
Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most Innovative show
Shows in all of podcasting by the mall at radiotopia
Tok FM
You can find the show enjoy discussions about show on Facebook including me at Roman Mars in the show at 99pi org
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But you can join the rest of us anymore than human community
And 99 pi
Daughter
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com