This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
On this so we tell stories about what we make and what it says about
Does human
But we never write those things on a 5-star scale
The anthropocene reviewed is here to correct that oversight
I love the show
By John Green he's the author of best-selling books like the Fault in Our Stars and Turtles all the way down
Kelso make some of the best stuff on YouTube with his brother Hank today we're going to be sure two of my favorite episodes of his new
Podcast that I think will be of particular interest
To an IPI listener have an interview with John about a lot of things like
Sports and Marine telepopmusik as an adult
I think you're really going to like it
After I got done talking with John I just felt good all day about life
Is great
But first
Here's an episode
The anthropocene reviewed
Hello and welcome to the anthropocene reviewed
A podcast where we review different facets
To be human centered planet on a five-star scale
Today I'll be reviewing a 17000 year old painting
And the Taco Bell breakfast menu
Let's start with the painting
So if you've ever been or had a child you will likely already be familiar with handstand
Cancel the first figurative art made by both our kids
Somewhere between the ages of two and three
Play children spread the fingers of one hand out across a piece
Paper
And then with the help of a parent
Trace their five finger
I remember my son's face as he lifted his hand and looked absolutely shocked
To see the shape of his hand
Still on the paper
A semi permanent record
Himself
I am extremely happy that my children are no longer three
And yet to look at their little hands from those early artworks
Is to be inundated with a strange
Soul splitting Joy
Those pictures
Remind me that they are not just growing up
But also growing away from me
Running toward their own lives
But of course that's meaning I am applying to their hand stencils
Complicated relationship between art
And its viewers
Is never more fraught than when we are looking deeply into the
In September of 1940 and 18 year old mechanic named Marcel Ravi. Was walking his dog robe
In the countryside of Southwestern France
When the dog disappeared down a hole
Robot eventually returned but the next day Robbie. Went to the spot with three friends to explore the whole
And after quite a bit of digging they discovered
Cave
With walls covered with paintings
Including over 900 paintings of animals
Horses Stags bison
It also species that are now extinct
Including a woolly rhinoceros
The paintings were astonishingly detailed and Vivid
With red yellow and
Black paint made from pulverized mineral pigments
That were usually blown through a narrow
Tube possibly a hollowed bone
Onto the walls of the cave
But eventually be a stamp
These artworks
At least 17000 years old
To the boys who visited the cave that day
We're so profoundly moved by the art they saw
That they camped outside the cave
Protected
For over a year
After World War II
The French government took over protection of the science
And the cave was open to the public in 1948
When Picasso Celtic cave paintings on a visit that year
He reportedly said
We have invented nothing
There are many Mysteries at let's go
Why for instance are there no paintings of reindeer
Which we know where the primary source of food for the Paleolithic
Humans who lived
Cave
Why would they so much more focused on painting animals
Spin painting human forms
Why are certain areas of the cave filled with images including pictures on the ceiling that required the building
Scaffolding
How to create
What other areas have only a few faint
And with the painting spiritual here are sacred animals
Or were they practical
Here is a guide to some of the animals that might kill you
Aside from the animals there are nearly a thousand abstract signs and shapes we cannot in
Interpret
And also several negative hand stencil
As they are known by Art historians
These are the paintings that most interests me
They were created by pressing one hand with fingers splayed against the wall
The cave
And then blowing Pig
Leaving the area around the hand-painted
Similar hand stencils have been found in caves around the world
From Indonesia to Spain to us
Australia to the Americas
To Africa we have found these memories
Of hands from 15
Or 30 or even
40000 years ago
These hands pencils remind us of how different life was in the distant past
Amputations likely from frostbite are common in Europe and so you often C- hand stencils with three
Eeyore for fingers
And life was short and difficult
As many as 1/4 of women died in childbirth
Around 50% of children died before the age of
Define
But they also remind us that the humans of the past whereas human
As we are
Their hands
Indistinguishable
From hours
These communities hunted and gathered and there were no large caloric surpluses
So every healthy person would have had to contribute to the acquisition of food and water
And yet somehow
They still made time to create art
Almost as if art
Isn't optional
For humans
We see all kinds of hand stenciled on Cave walls children and adults
But almost always the fingers are spread
Like my kids
But it's fascinating and a little strange that so many Paleolithic humans
You couldn't possibly have had any contact with each other
Created the same paintings the same way
Paintings that we are still make
But then again what the lascaux art means to me is likely very different from what it meant to the
People who made it
Some academics theorized that the hand stencils were part of Hunting Ridge
Then there's always the possibility that the hand was just a convenient model situated at the end of the wrist
To me though
The hand stencils at Nesco say
I was
Ear
They say
You are not new
And because they are negative prints surrounded by Red pigment
They also look to me like something out of a horror movie
Like ghostly hands
Reaching up from somebody back
They remind me that
As I was Walker Road
All history
Is current
The lascaux cave has been closed
The public for many years now
Too many contemporary humans breathing inside of it
Led to the growth of mold
Enlighten
Which is damaged some of the art
Just the act of looking at something
Can ruin it
I guess
But tourists can still visit an imitation cave
Called Wesco to
In which the artwork
Has been meticulously recreated
Humans making fake cave art
To save real cave art
Mayfield like Peak anthropocene Behavior
But I have to confess that even though I am a jaded and cynical semi-professional reviewer of human activity
I actually find it overwhelmingly hopeful
Bed for teenagers and a dog named robot
Discover the cave with 17000 year old hand prints
That the cave was so overwhelmingly beautiful
The two of those teenagers devoted themselves to its
Protection
Annette when we humans became a danger to that caves
Beauty
We agreed to stop going
Moscow is there
You cannot visit
You can go to the fake cave we built
NC nearly identical hand stencils
But you will know
This is not the thing itself
But a shadow of it
This is a handprint
But not a hand
This is a memory
Did you cannot return to
All of which
Makes the cave
Very much like the past it represent
I get the hand print stencils at Glasgow
4 and a half Stars
Exigo a listener to this podcast named Steven
Emailed me to ask if I would consider reviewing the Taco Bell breakfast menu
Good idea
Albeit one that would require me to eat a fair bit at Taco Bell
Which is a fast food restaurant chain with over 7,000 restaurants around the world
That was founded by a Marine Corps veteran
Glen Bell
Glenn did not start out as a Taco Guy
After serving in World War II he returned to his native Southern California
To seek his fortune in the burger business
Aranda restaurant in San Bernardino called Bells Drive-In in 1948
Is business did okay
But across the street
A family-owned Mexican restaurant called the mitla cafe
Whistling
Lots of tacos
Including its famous hard shell tacos
Bellwood off and eat at the mitla cafe and then go back to his Hamburger Stand and try to reverse-engineer those
Popular tacos
But you can never figure it out
So eventually he became friends with the family that owned the mitla
And they showed him the recipe
Bell started making tacos soon thereafter
Side note the mitla cafe was the setting for an important moment in American history in the early 1940s public
Pools and other services were segregated in San Bernardino
Latinos couldn't swim at the pool
Or sit in certain sections of movie theaters
Some businesses had whites only signs
And many schools were segregated
In a series of meetings held at the mitla cafe
Latino church and Civic leaders developed a plan to sue the city of San Bernardino
And they won
In fact the case Lopez versus II was cited by the Supreme Court and its famous Brown versus
Board of Education decision
The found segregated schools to be illegal
Will return to Taco Bell momentarily but one last note about the meatball Cafe
It's still open
And today is run by the fourth generation of the family who founded it
I've eaten there actually and it will not surprise you to learn that their tacos are vastly in calc
Superior to Taco Bell tacos
Taco Bell isn't really in the business of being
Good
It aims to be
Good enough
Inconsistent
And inexpensive
Right so of course the recipe for Taco Bell tacos was stolen by a white restaurant owner from a local Center for Latino community
Unity and activism
But the owners of the mitla cafe never publicly expressed any resentment toward Bell
One member of the family Irene Montano magnanimously set of him
He was a self-starter
And he did push those tacos
Indeed after opening the first Taco Bell in Downey California in 1962
New franchises of Taco Bell spread rapidly throughout the West Coast
Back then the menu was extremely simple
Tacos tostadas burritos Frijoles and chili burgers
And everything
Cost $0.19
Around the box safety in today's money
People loved it
By 1967
They were 100 Taco Bells
And they were 868
When Bell sold his company to PepsiCo
In 1978
425 million dollars
Selling Taco Bell Glen
Pursue the true passion of his life
1/4 scale model train Adventure Park
Call Bell Gardens
Bell was a lifelong model train enthusiast
But the park which had no rides that weren't quarter scale model trains went bankrupt after a few years
I mention all of this
Because I think it's important to understand
Glen Bell was not
Like
Passionate about Mexican food
He saw an opportunity in the marketplace
And he filled it
I'm not trying to bash Taco Bell I've had many enjoyable meals there in my younger and less nutrition Orient
Today's
And per dollar spent
Taco Bell offers more caloric energy than almost any other restaurant
A Big Mac at McDonald's
Two Rivers about 1.45 calories per Penny spent
A Taco Bell beefy Fritos burrito
Offers an astonishing 4.26 calories per penny
Also I recently ate a Taco Bell beefy Fritos burrito under the guise of research for this review and
For about 5 minutes after eating it
I felt almost euphoric
It was flavorful and intoxicating mix
Crunchy and chewy
And strangely sweet
The beef was stringing the tortilla suboptimal and I suspect I would be horrified by a thorough accounting of the in
Environmental and socio-political costs of the
The beefy Fritos burrito
But still for those five minutes
I felt pleasantly
And entirely
Satiate
10 minutes after that of course I began to feel extremely unwell but
That might be down to my generally weak Constitution
Institution rather than any fault of
The food itself
All I'm saying is the Taco Bell is not
Like
A mission-driven Institution
It seeks to turn a profit
And that's why I find it so fascinating the Taco Bell didn't serve breakfast until 2012
Burger King served its first breakfast in 1979
McDonald's introduce the Egg McMuffin way back in 1972
Maybe Taco Bell was late to breakfast
Because they didn't want to recreate
Actual Mexican breakfast food
Which is excellent but there's very little resemblance to the hash
Browns and cinnamon flavored donut holes
The Taco Bell eventually released as part of their breakfasts
Just menu
All of which goes to show again that Taco Bell as a company is not and never has been in
Twisted in Mexican food
Except for what could be
Efficiently appropriated from it
Which is why the taste profile of its breakfast menu more closely resembles that have Burger King
Did anything at the mitla cafe
I thought the donut holes were good
But it's hard to mess up fried dough
I found a grilled breakfast burrito Fiesta potato
To be
Like its name a bit overcomplicated
The stand out to me was the breakfast
French rap
Which wraps hash browns bacon eggs and cheese into a grilled tortilla
And that wasn't bad but
Mostly my Taco Bell breakfast was what Taco Bell's frantic and Relentless marketing campaign
Seem to fear the most
It was boring
I find it revealing that while there are Taco Bell's in Romania
And Australia
And Brazil
You won't find one in Mexico
Detroit twice in 1992 and 2007
But both times the restaurants face the same fate as Glenn Bells railroad Adventureland
You can add a valve to the end of every menu item
And you can make your catchphrase yo quiero Taco Bell
But if you can't sell your tacos in Mexico
Bank Mexican
I get to Taco Bell breakfast menu
2 Stars
Chanel ears my interview with the creator of the anthropocene reviewed
John Green
When someone asks you what you do
What in the world do you say
I usually say that I work in educational video so that they don't
Ask more questions
But if I'm
Feeling
A little more talkative I usually say that I'm a writer and a Utah
But I guess now I'm also a podcaster so I don't know what I do
How do you describe the anthropocene reviewed
Beatrice interviewed is show
Where I
Look at
Different
Facets of the human centered planet and then review them on a 5-star scale
It started out as
I'd like a bit
It started out as a joke I had with my brother
Because of Yelp
And Amazon reviews and Goodreads that
Everything now is reviewed on a five-star scale and everything gets a thumbs-up or a thumbs-down a wreck
Commander it don't recommend
And
What if we applied that reviewing
Framework
Like traffic cones
And that was the initial joke that I made with him or like argyle socks
And it goes like
It's good it's a funny bit
And so I think he ended up making a video
Where he use the bit
And then
I ended up
Writing an essay about diet dr. pepper and
Canada geese
And at the end of writing is essays I was like
You know this isn't very funny and I kind of thought that
It was going to be a funny
Bing
But I like it
And it interests me and because I started out my career as a book reviewer
It felt
Kind of like going home to me in a way even though like
It is
Obviously
A little sticky to be reviewing
For instance
Colorado on a five-star scale
There is something about the value judgment thing that's inherent to reviewing
That interest me
Is it a healthy thing that we are reviewing everything and if I start scale
In the world
Yeah probably give it to Stars
I definitely understand the urge to make simple qualitative judgments
About
Experian
But
If you read one-star Yelp reviews or you read one star Goodreads reviews
I make a lot of times there's
Some missing of nuance to put it generously
But also if you read a lot of 5-star Amazon reviews
There's a lot of missing of nuance
Yeah you know sometimes I read reviews of
Of my own book
I love you like
We both know it's not that good
Play
I wish it were I wish it were the book that you're describing and I'm so grateful that like
The book ended up in the hands of a reader so generous that they were able to make the book much better than the one I wrote
But
I do feel like it kind of oversimplifies human experience and it also gives us this constant urge to review Ave
Everything we do
Like now it's difficult to have a meal
And not think about it in the
The context
Of
A recommend don't recommend
Spectrum
And I don't know that I did that
Before the age
Good night
So when I was talking to
My producer and editor on the show is news crispr Rubio is dude we were talking about which
Stories to do highlight of the anthropocene reviewed
I said
I think I want to do to
NOK paintings in
Taco Bell breakfast menu
And pennies and Piggly Wiggly
Coso4
I was like no no no those are two
So is that how you view them
Yeah I try to pair them in ways that make sense
Tumi
So for instance when I was writing about the cave paintings at lascaux
I wanted to also right about the Taco Bell breakfast menu in part because it seems
So different it seems like a huge contrast
But also
Because
Really fascinated by the way that
People
Try
Make an impact
On the world or they try to leave
A trace of themselves and I was fascinated by the way that Glenn Bell
The founder of Taco Bell tried to do that and by the way that the
People who were painting the cave paintings at lascaux tried
To do that
I'm especially curious about the combination of Hawaiian pizza and viral meningitis
What made you choose this
Well some would argue that they're both forms of suffering
I read the viral meningitis
Essay before I wrote the Hawaiian pizza essay
And at the end of the viral meningitis essay
I was thinking about
Pal
There are all these
Phenomena in human life that are really resistant to language I think physical pain is the one that's
Perhaps most dramatically resistant
2 language
But for me there's also something about
Taste that's resistant to language
And
One of the reasons we fight I think about Hawaiian pizza
Is
Because we almost cannot describe to each other how it taste
To us
And so
I think some people say well Hawaiian pizza
Is amazing and your
You know obviously wrong to hate it and then the people who hated are like no no no no no you don't understand
How'd it taste
Tumi
And indeed we don't is it between May one of my pet peeves with
No basis whatsoever so it's not like
You know like I know I'm not necessarily right is I hate
When people use food words to describe other things
Like I hate it when somebody says that
Prose is delicious or something like that
All kind of makes me want to die
So goes the other way too like you can't use food words for other things you can use them only for food and there's not enough of them
Yeah well and even the food words that do exist
I don't know what they mean to someone else
Like I don't really know what Sumptuous means
Anyone who says that Hawaiian pizza is delicious
My definition of delicious
Doesn't include Hawaiian pizza and so I'm already I'm already lost
I have no way in and they can say oh it's a wonderful mix of
Sweet and sour
And I understand what sweet and sour taste like
But that is not a wonderful mix of
To me until it's that personalization of experience and then the urge to share experience like we we all deaths
Desperately wanting
Other people
To hear us and to hear our stories
Listen to know what our feelings feel like
And they can't
The temperature to show is literally everything on Earth
Kind of centered around
When humans
Orthodontist
Species on Earth
Yeah kinda
And
How do you then choose things to talk about
I choose what to write about partly based
On
Wisner suggestions
So
Wizards can write in
And a lot of times they have a really interesting ideas or ideas about why something is in
Everything that I hadn't thought about
The Taco Bell breakfast menu is actually an example of that I've never thought about the Taco Bell breakfast menu until somebody wrote
To ask me to review it and then
I was like this isn't that interesting and
But then I fell way down the Glen Bell rabbit hole and ended up reading Glen Bells like self-published
Commissioned biography
And
At the end of that I was
Totally
Fascinated by y Taco Bell
Didn't have a breakfast menu for so long
But I also have a running list
Topics that
I
Care about and I
Interested in and that I think I have a way into
Whether it's a story I want to tell about my life
Or
Just a story I find really fascinating
Like the cave paintings at lascaux
I learned about those
In my twenties
And I just spent a lot of time thinking about them and reading about them
And so I felt ready to write that
I mean each of these reviews
It becomes a small Memoir was that always your intention
Initially my idea for the show
Was that
I was going to be
Separate from the reviews
I would be like an authority on everything
I was going to be an authority on Canada geese and diet dr. pepper and cave painting
And the Taco Bell breakfast menu
And who I was didn't matter because I was
The authority
And my wife read the first couple of essays
And she said
You know I don't buy you
As
Authoritative expert in the taste of dr. pepper
I just don't think I don't think you're a chemical engineer I don't think
That you're a professional taster
And
I'm more interested in what your relationship is
That's when it became more memory
And
I do write about myself and I do write really personal things about myself
But I'm very careful
To protect
The parts of me that I need to protect
If that makes sense
Because I wasn't always careful
About that
And
And now I feel like I have
When I was younger I wanted so badly
To be
No no
I think what I wanted was to have
People like me
For some reason I wanted especially for people who didn't know me well
To like me
And it just didn't seem like that was such an incredibly desirable outcome
To have
Strangers
Like you
When versions of that started to happen to me I almost immediately
Recognized
That
What I
Thought it would give me
Was not what it was giving me because I never felt and I still don't feel
Likes
Strangers Like Me
I feel like they
Like
A
Construction that is only tangentially related to me
I'm obsessed with this thing Keanu Reeves said once
He said I love Keanu Reeves a lot
Someday I might someday I might write it Keanu Reeves and
La piscine review
Review
That one time Keanu Reeves in an interview said
I'm Mickey Mouse
They don't know who's inside the suit
And
When my work started to become more publicly known
That's how I felt
I didn't really feel like people like me I feel like they like Mickey Mouse
I was inside the suit
But I think the difference between Keanu Reeves in me is that Keanu Reeves
Knew who he was
He knew who is inside of the suit but I kind of didn't
Do you find it when you
Because you listen to a lot of podcasts and I assume
Before that or maybe
Listen to a lot of public radio and stuff when you find like a little tidbit of personal knowledge like when Terry Gross Road
Feels something to little about herself
Does it fill you with delight the way it fills me with delight
It does it does especially when Terry Gross does it
Because I've been listening to Terry Gross for like 25 years so
Winter growth
Shares even the smallest detail about her life I am completely
Oh I love it it's such a good feeling I just like I hope
Oh
Well that
That's always what I think to myself
Describe the piles of CDs on something like oh my God
Chest hours navigating yes
Now I could picture the entire home
Are we one of these
Learn about you overtime
And when I think they
Fun is
And I don't know if I would anticipated this app from reading your books and
Other things in from Blood Brothers
But you love sports
Or certain Sports I mean my growing-up experience was that the people who love sports were the people who
Who hated me
Ipf the same that these are not linked
Traits that you've decoupled them for me in these ways that I found really
Profound and so
You talk about penalty shootouts work
I know your
Love of AFC Wimbledon and in an Indy 500
Could afford me as a subject
The fact that you love
Indianapolis 500
I think that you could assemble the parts
Of your character
And
I could construct a version of you
That would hate the internet
Well yeah and it passed me did hate the Indy 500 in Panda past me did hates
Sports there's a lot of my first novel Looking for Alaska that something like I hate
Sports and I hate people
Two players
Support or participate in any way in the sports industrial complex and that was taken right
Get out of my high school self
I I would watch people care about sports and I would just think to myself
This is
Actually
The dumbest thing
That you can do with what Mary Oliver called your one Wild
Precious life like this is the worst
Possible
Way
For you to use
Use your resources
I've heard anything in adulthood if not to judge anyone else
West you become them
In the fullness of time you will become all of the people that you claim to revile
I think what I love about
Sports is actually the same thing I love about going to
Church which is
Not
Much to do with the extensible topic at hand buttons
Instead
The pleasure and joy that comes from
A bunch of people who otherwise might not have a lot in common orienting
There's love in the same direction
And I think there is a lot of value in that
And
I think what I like about sports's is the community aspect of it
Which is
Why I enjoy the Indy 500 so much
Much because it's
Huge
Gathering
All kinds
Of human being
And
The sport to say that its secondary would be an over stay
I mean there's no place
In the Indianapolis 500
Seating
Where you can see all of the Indianapolis 500 so it can't possibly be about the sport because you live
Literally can't see the sport
From inside the stadium
It has to be about something else and I think what it's about is
Tradition and shared experience
And being
In a community
I think really like in the end sports are about being
Sing together
I found in my life and I
I sent this in your life is that
You spent
A good section
Commune your life being defined by the things you hated
And then you took a hard pivot enjoying being to find more by the things you loved
Do you know why and how that happened in both you and I
I do not
No
When I was a teenager
If you'd asked me to say like 10 things about myself
I would have told you 10 things that I hate it
I would have told you about
What I was supposed to
I would have told you about what I thought was
Stupid and embarrassing and ridiculous
About The Human Experience I would have told you like
How deeply I reviled the Spice Girls
Who by the way
Need good pop music
I think I got fed up with it I got fed up with irony I got
Fed up with sarcasm
I got fed up with this urge to create distance between
Myself and emotion
I wanted to be cool and I thought that to be cool was to
To be distant
And then I stopped wanting to be cool
Because
To be cool this to be a form of cold
And I don't want to be distant from emotional experience
I think the risk of that is that it
They make you into a sentimentalist it may make you
Intuit some sort of like cheesy
Version of yourself
For me if that's the cost
Having
Tyrannize
Emotional experiences
It's worth
The cost
It took me a long time to like be okay with
That urge
Within Me
I just think that
Ironic
Detachment
Is
The single most
Overrated
Characteristic and human being
I like emotion I like to feel things I like to feel them intensely
And I like to be able to ask big questions without
Creating a lot of distance
It's between myself and the question
If you were to review other things near life the science Sports in the Spice Girls what are some of the things that
Had the most change
1 * or 0 stars to 5 stars
Oh that's interesting
Oh I mean the biggest one is marriage
I mean my
My 17 year old self thought that marriage
Which was
The
Stupidest
Institution
The human turd ever
Steve dove
End
I thought
Love being married
That guy was crazy I really really
Really love being married
I think the institution of marriage has gotten a lot better since I was
It's gotten a lot more inclusive
It hasn't
Gone
All the way to where it needs to be throughout the world but
I think that's one
In general
Pop music I was very dismissive of pop music when I was younger and
Now I listen to a lot of pop songs like you know that song Old Town Road by Lil Nas X
It's been mentioned a few times but I actually haven't heard it but I I've heard good things
I genuinely recommend that you listen to it it's a good song is it good enough
Tab my kids play at 40 or 50 times a day everyday no but it's very good I've also gone
One from
One star to five stars on
Genre fiction
Like mystery novels romance novels
I love a good romance
I used to think that
If they all end the same way and they're so cheesy and they're just wish fulfilling
Well
Shut up like what's wrong with wish fulfillment
Like what when did we become opposed to fulfilling wishes
I can go on that I've
If anything I got I probably know too critical of my high school self because that means it like in the next 10
10 years I'm going to become my high school self again so that the so that I have to like cease being critical toward him
The thing about my high school self and I don't know if you were like this
This is that I was very
Dismissive
Pop culture looks like large swath
High culture
.
My
Hatred of them is just super embarrassing like the quintessential example from my life is that
When I was a teenager I hated The Great Gatsby
I thought it was
I wrote a paper that I still have
That I should destroy
Before I die but
I wrote a paper that I still have
In which I called The Great Gatsby a bunch of Rich Yankees with Yankee
Key problems I grew up in LA
Contact
End
Like the lack of understanding
In that characterization of The Great Gatsby
Is a reminder that like
One-star Goodreads reviews are not necessarily
Reflective of the quality of a
Also like I'm so glad that my high school self did not have access to
Twitter
If he had like I would still be living with that and people would be like
Yeah this guy hates The Great Gatsby
And thank you
Making me born in nineteen
When you see
The things you make interacting with the world and the image I have in my mind is
Ant-Man reading
Fault in Our Stars in Bad Company
What are the moment of delight for me
But when you see your things that you make
Interacting with the culture of the world how does it make you feel
When it's things like
Ant Man reading the Fault in Our Stars
It's
Just like a wonderful delightful unexpected MoMA
And
That one in particular was fun because I was
With my son
In the movie theater
And he likes it out loud add that's your book and I was like I don't know
Did you know that was going to happen and I was like no how could I have known as.
You know called me to clear it
I would have thought they called you to clear it actually
They didn't
Or at least if they did they didn't call me that
But to be honest it can get
Overwhelming
I can get a little like
Scary somehow
Yeah I don't know how
How to say it
Scary remember right when the Fault in Our Stars movie
Timeout
Because it was
For a few weeks like fairly
Close to the center of
Us pop culture
Like a people were saying things about it that I thought were really
Kind of unfair
In the way that we always
Are judging
Popular
Cultural
Phenomena
I've always felt like if something becomes very popular there must be something at least a little bit wrong with it
It was weird and uncomfortable
To be in that position
But also things like having like a Saturday Night Live sketch or something made out of
If your works at
Paradies your work I get away it
It's fine and
I thought the sketch that they made was very funny
But
Yeah it was hard just not to feel really like kind of overwhelmed by it in a little like
Almost an urge to shut down
You know I don't think it's
It's a coincidence that I didn't write a novel for like 6 years
After that book came out
I've been interviewed on TV. Only a couple of times a handful of times
And I've never seen any of them I just can't
I don't want to know
I don't want to know if I felt bad about it I don't want to know
I just want to know it's hard now I mean you know obviously these are like
Incredibly
Rarefied
Problems that I am extremely grateful to have
You know like I definitely had a moment there where I could have chosen
A path
That I didn't
Choose
Like we could have moved to LA and or New York and and gotten lots of work and there were lots of opportunities in
What I
Kind of chose to do was to
Come back here to Indianapolis IN to work on making crash course our educational video series better and
Winter work on
The stuff that I wanted to work on
That was supposed to lower profile but also that I had more
Control over
Cuz I think part of what was so disorienting about that experience
Aunt was
Losing some control over
Both my work
And on some level over
Myself
Service like the way that myself was being portrayed in a magic
I'm really like
Interested in you deciding Tesoro pull back and do crash course and stuff instead of doing punch up on
Some scripture something you know it's not because
Uibe
The stain for those things it's just that no not at all know it's kind of like
Well I got my thing
I need my things break
Can I tell you my favorite joke I'm sure you've heard this joke but you never heard me do it
So
A moth walks into a
Microsoft Office do you know this joke I don't I don't know if I don't know it from that set up
All right
DeNiro a podiatrist office and
The podiatrist that's what seems to be the problem off in the mall says
Doc if only there were
One problem I mean you know my wife
Doesn't love me anymore Sasha's that she doesn't love me I don't even remember a time
When she did love me
My daughter has married a man who Midas
Spies
Who despises me
My son is a wretched failure and to be honest
When I look at him all I see is a reflection of my own failures
I just don't know how to go on dock
I don't know
Do you know
And the podiatrist says seems like a very serious problems
I'm a podiatrist
What brought you here today
And the moth says
Show the light was on
I love that joke
Because like the joke
Is that mobs are stupid and they just go where the light is on
But the other thing about the joke is that
Almost all the time
Humans also just go where the lights on
And so
I really love
Moments where humans don't go where the light is on and I really try and my own life thinking hard about
You know am I doing this because I want to do it or am I doing this because the light is on
So how would you rate our conversation on a 5-star scale
I mean from my side
4 and a half stars but I'm more worried about how you would rate it now I'm nervous
I could be getting in the moment but
I'm thinking Solid 5 stars
I don't mean to be
What are those Amazon reviews that you're skeptical of fight
Wheel of Life
It's been great.
After the break John Green reviews the Piggly Wiggly
And he just lays into the penny honestly is the angriest I've ever heard him
More anthropocene reviewed
After this
Here again is the anthropocene reviewed
99 percent invisible
Hello and welcome to the anthropocene reviewed
The podcast where we review different facets
It's a human centered planet on a five-star scale
My name is John Green and today I'll be reviewing pennies
Distensible form of currency here in the United States
And the grocery store chain Piggly Wiggly
Let's begin with the American penny
Which is worth 1/100 of the US dollar and is almost as old as the nation itself
The first US penny was minted in 1793
It was made of copper
Wait about half an ounce
And with the size of a contemporary $1 coin
Which come to think of it is a useless comparison
Since nobody uses one dollar coins even though their adoption would save the United States hundred
Millions of dollars per year
But we're not here to review the two star $1 bill
We're here to review the penny
Which since 1909 has featured the profiled face
Have US President Abraham Lincoln
The penny was actually the first US money to be stamped with a president's face
Many of the u.s. is Founders including George Washington felt it would be to Monarca Colton
Coins featuring us leaders
In fact the u.s. mint Act of 1792 explicitly stated that one side of copper coins
Should State the denomination
And the other side should have a quote
Impression emblematic of Liberty
Today's pennies weigh about a fifth of what the eighteenth-century ones did
And while they're still coated in Copper
Pennies are now over 97% zinc
Which is cheaper than
10 copper
But even so
Every $0.01 coin minted in the United States
Cost 1.82 cents to create
Last year the US Mint lost
69 million dollars
Minting pennies
That would be annoying but forgivable
Is penne served a purpose in our economy
But they don't
Money is supposed to facilitate the exchange of goods and services which
Penny's manifestly
Failed to do
You can't use them in vending machines are parking meters
And if you attempt to use them to purchase goods or services you will often be met with resistance
And for good reason I mean it requires over 2 lb of pennies around a kilogram
To purchase a single gallon of gasoline
And yet every year
The US Mint makes more pennies than all other coins combined
Not because we use them so often to buy thing
But because we don't use
We store them in jars or leave them in the terrifying Netherworld of our cars
Center console
And we throw them away by the million
Because panties
Do not work as
Currency
There are many arguments in favor of the continued production of the penny
I just don't find any of them convincing
Some argue for instance that in a penniless World prices might go up
And that those price increases would disproportionately affect
The poor who are more likely to use
Cash in transaction
But in fact eliminating the penny would not increase prices
We know this because many nations have already retired their Penny equivalent without any problem
From the Netherlands to New Zealand
We would simply begin rounding prices to the nearest tenth of a dollar
Instead of the nearest hundredth of a dollar
Assuming we had the common sense to also eliminate are $0.05 coins
Each of which cost
Point to send
Instrument
If anything this system would benefit those who use cash
Because they would spend the same amount of money
But no longer have
To deal with pennies
Which are so easy to receive as change
And so difficult
To spend
People often resort to cashing out their small denomination coins by a coin counting machines like Coinstar
Which charge an astonishing 12
Percent fee
For the privilege of turning your pennies and nickels
In the money you can actually spend
Other defense
Size of the penny that it honors Lincoln or that it's somehow limits inflation
Are just absurd
None of the countries that have eliminated one cent coins have seen a corresponding rise in inflation
And why would Abraham Lincoln want to be the face of a coin that is worth -69 million
Dollars per year
The whole thing is ridiculous
But then again
Righteous indignation at the ongoing existence of the penny
Is also
69 million dollars represents a tiny fraction of the US federal budget
Like we spend about 68 million dollars on the military
Per hour
We have much bigger problems than the penny
The United States is one of the only Nations that have seen life expectancy decline in the past 2 years
Despite the fact that we spend more on Healthcare than any other country
Are massive economic inequality is inhibiting economic growth and limiting opportunity
Our political system
Atoms are far too profoundly influenced by moneyed interests
And eliminating the penny
Will fix none of them
But our failure to bid farewell to the penny
Seems to me indicative of a larger political fail
We cannot accomplish
Simple and obvious things
Because there is nothing to be gained politically
By accomplishing
Almost all of our political discourse is focused on issues that can score points
And energized
Supporters
Should the Supreme Court nominee be approved as an issue that can drive donations
Should the penny be eliminated
Is not
In part because it's not very important
And in part because it's not very device
There is of course nothing surprising about the fact that Congress can't find the political will to eliminate
Penny's I mean
If Congress were drowning
Struggle to pass the throw Congress something that floats at
The US political system is complex by Design
Change is supposed to be difficult to enact
But I'm not convinced it should be this.
In 1857
The United States was only a few years away from a civil war
I know 160 years ago
Seems like ancient history
But consider this
Two of the grandfathers
Of my grandfather's
Fought in that war
On office
Besides
I know history can feel settle
But we
The results of History
Or anything but settled
So right it's 18
Political divisions over slavery are such that a year earlier and abolitionist Senator named Charles Sumner
Had been beaten with a cane nearly two
To death
In the chamber of the United States Senate
Buy a pro-slavery Congressman name
Preston Brooks
Go by the way
Would go on to be re-elected by his
Constituents
And yet even then
Is the house divided against itself with learning but it could not stand
The United States Congress passed
The coinage act of 1857 into law
Among other things
The ACT eliminated the halfpenny
Which has become too small a monetary sum
To be worth minting
At the time
The halfpenny was worth about $0.12
In today's money
Tumi the ongoing existence of
The penny symbolizes not only our inability
Need to find common ground
But also our inability to acknowledge the places where Common Ground already
Exists
In fact
I think the only vaguely convincing case one can make for the penny
Is that as a nation
We all share it
No matter where you're from
Or what news Outlet you rely upon
No matter your age or race or gender
We can all agree
That the continued minting of the American penny
Is an absolute abomination
Maybe it's worth 69 million dollars a year
To have something that we can all dislike together
And anywhere there is something kind of American
About putting our best president
On our worst
Bitcoin
I give the penny 1 and 1/2 Stars
In 1920
My maternal grandmother's father was working at a grocery store
In a Tiny Town in Western Tennessee
Like all us grocery stores
Is the beginning of the 20th century
This one was full service
You walked in with a list of items you needed
And then the grocer
Perhaps my great-grandfather
We Gather those eyes
Midway to flour or cornmeal or butter or tomatoes
Wrap everything up for you
And then charge it to your account
You'd rather wait for the clerk to finish your shopping for you
Or for a small fee you'd have your order delivered to your house later in the day
Like almost all grocery stores
The time my great-grandfather store also allowed customers
To purchase food on credit
Which the customer would then
Usually
Payback over
4 time
That's where it was supposed to be my great-grandfather's ticket out of
Poverty
But it didn't work out that way
Instead the store closed
Thanks in part to the self-service grocery Revolution launched by Clarence Saunders
Saunders with the self-educated child
Impoverished sharecropper
Eventually found his way to the grocery business
In Memphis Tennessee
He was 35 when he developed the concept for a grocery store
It would have no clerks or counters
But instead of Labyrinth of Isles
The customers would walk themselves
Choosing their own food
And placing it in their own shopping.
Prices at Saunders self-service grocery would be lower because his stores would employ fewer clerks and also because
Is he wouldn't offer customers credit
But instead
Expect immediate payment
The prices would also be clear and transparent
For the first time every item in a grocery store would be marked with a price
So customers would no longer fear being overcharged
By unscrupulous
What's Grocers
Sandra's called his grocery store
Piggly Wiggly
Why
Nobody knows
When asked where the name came from
Saunders once answered that it arrived
From out of chaos and indirect
Contact with an individual's mind
Which gives you a sense of the kind of guy he was
But usually when he was asked why anyone would call a grocery store Piggly Wiggly
He would answer
So people will ask that very question
The first Piggly Wiggly opened in Memphis in 1916
It was so successful that the second Piggly Wiggly opened
3 weeks later
2 months after that another open
Sandra's insisted on calling it
Piggly Wiggly the Third
Who win who stores the quote
Royal dignity they are due
He soon began attaching a catchphrase
Storefront signs
Piggly Wiggly
All around the world
Of course at the time the stores were barely all around Memphis
But Sandra's business did grow phenomenally quickly
Within a year there were 353 Piggly Wiggly
Around the United States
In newspaper advertisements
Saunders wrote if his self service concept
In nearly Messianic terms
One day
Memphis-shelby proud
Piggly Wiggly
When a dread
And it shall be said by all men
At the Piggly Wiggly shall multiply and replenish the Earth
With more and cleaner things to eat
Another time he wrote
The mighty pulse of the throbbing today
Makes new things out of old
And new things
Where was nothing before
Basically
Saunders spoke of Piggly Wiggly
As today's Silicon Valley Executives talk of their company
We're not just making money
We are replenishing
The Earth
Piggly Wiggly in the self-service grocery stores that followed
Did Weller price
Which meant there was more to eat
They also change the kinds of foods that were readily available
To save costs
Send limit spoilage
Piggly Wiggly stock less fresh produce
Traditional grocer
Prepackaged
Processed foods
Became more popular
And less expensive
Which altered American diet
Brand recognition also became extremely important
Because food companies had to appeal directly to Shoppers
Which way to the growth of consumer-oriented food advertising on radio and the newspapers
A phenomenon that Saunders understood better than almost anyone
During the late nineteen teens and early twenties
Piggly Wiggly was the single largest newspaper Advertiser in the United
Of course lower prices and fewer Clerks
Also meant that many people lost their jobs
Including my great-grandfather
There's nothing new about our fear that Automation and increased efficiency
Will deprive humans
Work
In one newspaper advertisement
Saunders imagined a woman torn between her longtime relationship with her friendly grocer
And the world will prices of Piggly Wiggly
The story concluded with Saunders appealing to a tradition even older than the full service
Chris grosser
With his protagonist saying
Now way back many years there had been a Dutch grandmother of mine who had been Thrift
The spirit of that old grandmother asserted itself just then Within Me
And said
Business is business
And charity and alms are another
Whereupon are Shopper Saw the Light
And converted to Piggly Wiggly
By 1922 there were over a thousand Piggly Wiggly stores around the u.s.
And shares in the company were listed on the New York Stock
Saunders was building a 36
Thousand square foot mansion in Memphis
And headed out the school now known as Rhodes College
But the good times would not last
After a few Piggly Wiggly stores in the Northeast failed
Investors began shorting the stock
Betting that it's price would fall
Saunders responded by trying to buy up all the available shares of Piggly Wiggly
Using borrowed money
But the Gambit failed spectacularly
And Saunders lost control
Piggly Wiggly
And went bankrupt
His betrayal at Wall Street short sellers
Presaged contemporary corporate Titans just as his Reliance on big advertising and Hyper efficiency did
Saunders with my many accounts of bully
Verbally abusive
Cruel
And profoundly convinced of his own genius
After losing control of the company he wrote
They have it all everything I built the greatest stores of their kind in the world
But they didn't get the man that was father to the idea
They have the body of Piggly Wiggly
But they didn't get
The soul
Sounders quickly developed A New Concept for a grocery store
This one would have Isles and self service
But also Clerk
In the meat department in the bakery
Basically a contemporary supermarket
In under a year he was ready to open
But the new owners of Piggly Wiggly took him to court
Arguing that the use of the Clarence Saunders name
In relation to a new grocery store
Would violate Piggly Wiggly's trademark
In patent
In response
Saunders defiantly named his new grocery store
The Clarence Saunders sole owner of my name store
Perhaps the only business name worse than Piggly Wiggly
And yet
It succeeded tremendously
And Saunders made a second Fortune as sole owner stores
Spread throughout the
He went on to invest in a professional football team in Memphis
Which he named the Clarence Saunders sole owner of my name
Tigers
Really
They played the Green Bay Packers
And the Chicago Bears in front of huge crowds in Memphis
And they were invited to join the NFL
But Saunders declined
Because you didn't want to share Revenue
Or send his team to away game
He promised to build the stadium for the Tigers that would seat over 30000 people
The stadium he wrote
Will have skull and crossbones
For my enemies who I have slain
But within a few years
The co-owner stories were crushed by the depression
Football team with out of business
And he was broke again
Meanwhile thesaurus body of Piggly Wiggly
Was faring quite well without Saunders
By the supermarket chains height in 1932
There were over 2500 Piggly Wiggly's in the United States
Are even today there are over 600
Mostly in the south
Although like many grocery stores
Is there struggling under pressure from the likes of Walmart
And Dollar General
Which can undercut traditional grocery stores on price
Partly by providing even West fresh food
And fewer Clerks
And today is Piggly Wiggly's to
These days Piggly Wiggly ads tend to focus on tradition
And the human touch
1 North Alabama Piggly Wiggly TV spot from 1999
Included this line
At Piggly Wiggly
It's all about friends
Serving friend
A call to the kind of human-to-human relationship
What's that Saunders ridiculed in that Dutch grandmother ad
The mighty pulse of the throbbing today
Does make new things out of old
But it also makes old things
Out of new
Today food prices are lower relative to average wage than they've ever been in the United
United States
But our diets are often
Rapport
The average American ingests more sugar and sodium than they should
Largely because of
The process
Pre-packaged Foods
As for Clarence Saunders
He spent decades after his second bankruptcy trying to launch a New Concept
Call Becky duzel
I totally automated store
That looks like a massive Bank of vending machines
And involves purchasing food with almost no human to human interaction
He was also one of the first business people to spend private money on newspaper advertising for political can
Running ads
Including virulently racist ones
For his preferred gubernatorial can
Saunders grew more vitriolic and unpredictable as he aged
You could never get the key duzel to work
The Machinery broke down constantly
And people found the shopping experience
Slow and clunky
He eventually entered a Sanitarium.
The treated people with anxiety and depression
The mansion
Saunders built with his first Fortune
Became the Pink Palace Museum
Memphis is science and history museum
The estate he built with his second Fortune
Peking lichterman Nature Center
In 1936 there journalist Ernie Pyle said
If Sandra's lives long enough
Memphis will become the most
Beautiful city in the world
Just with the thing Saunders built
And wasp
But Saunders never made a third for
He died at the Walla Sanitarium
In 1953
At the age of 72
When obituary opined
Some men achieve lasting Fame
Through success
Others achieve it through failure
Saunders was a huckster
He committed Securities fraud
He helped Usher in an era of food
It feels without nourishing
He was also a genius
Ahead of his time
Who understood
To the power
Branding and efficient
But mostly
When I think of Piggly Wiggly
I think if it's swallowing up the small town grocery stores
Only to be swallowed itself
By the likes of Walmart
Which will in turn
Be swallowed
By the likes of Amazon
Joyce called Ireland the south at heater pharaoh
But Ireland has nothing on American capitalism
I get Piggly Wiggly two and a half
The anthropocene reviewed is written by John Green edited by Stan Muller and produced by
Rosianna halse Rojas and Tony Phillips
Dopelord is their technical director and is brown mix music
The anthropocene reviewed is a co-production of complexity
And WNYC Studios
Every episode is a jam find it and download it
Wherever you get your podcasts
99percentinvisible was Bruce's sweet by Chris Berube
Mixing two collection by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Katie mingle is a senior police recruit Kolstad is the digital director
Resin team is senior editor Delaney Hall Avery trufelman turn Masa Emmett Fitzgerald Vivien Leigh Sophia
ClassDojo Rosenberg and me Roman Mars
We are project 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most innovative
Native shows in all of podcasting
My mom that radiotopia
You can find the show and discussions about the show on Facebook and tweet me at Roman Mars in the show
99pi or Guan Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to have links to the anthropocene reviewed and the entire
Catalog of 99 Pi episodes that John says inspired him to make the same reviewed
Say this because I
I know how it's going to sound but
What I was thinking about what I wanted to do in terms of podcasting I thought a lot about the way that nighttime
10% invisible approaches stories and that concept of always reading the plaque if you pay really close attention to something Uke
Generally
Learn in unexpected and exciting ways
All on the website it's 99 pi
. org
Radio Tempe
Before we go I want to tell you about your hustle another radiotopia show that you might like
Your hustle short stories about daily life inside San Quentin State Prison
From the perspective of those living in
Season 4 just launched
Africa Louis earlonne Woods got some
Exciting news last fall
This season will be a little different
Wrentham the other three
Perception is replaced
Do everything filters
Do
To the opening of the zoo
Summerlin Woods
I'm Nigel poor
And we are back
What's season 4 of ear hustle from PR Exodus radiotopia
On your hustle we bring you stories about what life is like inside San Quentin State Prison in California
Prisoners
Horrible
That will put the training
And forever and ever amen
And so all the white guys
Sing brother
How do I have a right
And this season
We're doing something really different
We're also telling stories about life outside prison
Polson
So that people ask me what it was and how long after we're then why do I have it on in like damn
Something like you locked up you still want to wear that how long ago to wear that outside stories inside stories
It all starts with episode 1 of season 4 of ear hustle from PR X's radiotopia
Is bat
You find your hustle Sports season
On ear hustle SQ. Com
Or wherever you get your podcasts