This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Andrew Weiland has always loved to read
5th grader with the kid who sat on a utility box during recess reading The Hobbit while everyone else
Play kickball
In Middle School
To learn the trade names of the book imprints
That published the druggie contemporary fiction that he was starting to get into
And in 2003
You dropped out of college
I moved to San Francisco to work for his favorite publisher
Mcsweeney's
It was my dream job
And working there exacerbated my already in
Spanish for pretty
Matthew Henry
I got to live out my fantasy of being an ink-stained wretch even if that meant logging 12-hour days an in-class computer
I edited essays and interviews played out articles
It's a weird amount of pleasure and typographical minutiae
Like italicize in Camas
And rewriting headlines so they fit the frame just so
Havoc Sweeney's books and magazines whenever just containers forward
They were works of art
And I was trying to take as much care with the look
Can feel if the print
As I did with you
Expression of the idea
But as much as Andrew love to print Pizza love
He also has a condition that will eventually change his relationship to it pretty radically
I'm going blind
Really really slowly
Right now it's like I've got a foot in both world
Blind and sighted
I have a degenerative retina
It's giving me severe tunnel vision
So basically no peripheral vision
It's like I'm peering at the world through a toilet paper
When it gets a little narrower every few months
I'm going to try to read this
See if I got it right
Can
We
My retinal specialist told me that I probably don't need to worry about losing the ability to read
For another five years or so
But I've already started using a special digital program to learn Braille
Which is not easy
B cockle
What I want to get a jumpstart in before I actually
Free
Rick Astley
What
A recycle
Can we recycle a metal can
I know I'll still be able to experience books for the rest of my life
I'm lucky to be going blind in the digital age
And the Golden Age of audio there's an abundance of well-produced audiobooks and technology that can read aloud
Almost anything that appears on a screen
Puzzles
Chinese can ride a unicycle or two puzzles
My niece can ride a unicycle or do puzzles
Does that mean my niece
Can do no such thing despite all that there's still some mellow tragedy
Any idea that in a few years I'll probably no longer be able to read print
After a life spent loving books there's now a real urgency for me in the question of how blind people experience literal
I find myself deeply curious about what graphic design might mean to someone who can't see
So I started looking into the history of reading Technologies for the blind
Traditionally books are visual objects
And for centuries now blind and sighted designers have been arguing over the most effective way to translate
Habitual ink print book
Into an accessible form for people with outside
Pres long as blind people have been reading there's been this tension between systems that try to stay close to the
Original form of a book
And systems that dramatically depart
Tomorrow ideas of what a book can be
Designers have made incredible breakthroughs to create non visual forms of reading for blind people
Find critic pointed out the designers have a bad habit of quote talking to the fingers in the language of the eyes
So the history of blind reading is really the history of finding a new language for the fingers and for the ear
One that captures the Essential Elements of the ink print book but
In a new language
That's Unbound from the visual
And that history centers around two main shapes
Lines
And.
Our story starts in 18th century Europe before Braille was invented before blind people were even taught
To read at all
First off no one thinks that it's possible
Formica
Kids II
Learn that's my cuts
The museum director at the American printing house for the blind in Louisville Kentucky
And if they could
No one knows how to do
Without access to education
Blind people were overwhelmingly poor
And employment prospects were dim
If their families had enough money and time to support them
They usually lived at home like adult children sitting idly around the house
Many others were forced to beg on the street
Dora handful of institutions in Europe to support the poorest cases
What a Pity the blind
Hid them away
Within this guy named Valentino he comes along
Are we was born into a family of Weaver's in France
Yes and he was a skilled linguist
He was first inspired to help the blind in 1771
We saw a group of blind people being mocked
Potable in Paris
They have been given dunce cap
And giant fake glasses
And they were made
Play musical instruments and pretend to read book
So are we founded the first known School for the Blind
It was called The Royal Institute
In Paris
But even as he's getting the school going
How we kept aside
And I wheeze
Sidegig
Is as a translator
And so every now and then go get these fancy
Embossed
Invitations Denver
And one day
What about we students
A kid named Francois Le Sueur
Touchpoint
And Francois Le Sueur notices
Is that he can
Feel something on these put on these invitations
And that gives a weedy idea the idea to develop this idea of embossed printing
Erased letters so in 1786 how he makes the first machine in Boston
Books for the blind
Treatise
Unblind education
It's written in print
The kind that sighted readers would recognize
Text is all raised so that blind students can
Fuel the shape of letters
It's a radical move
Matches the first book for blind readers in history
Basically the beginning
The idea that blind people can be educate
But there are a few problem
Well
First off no one can afford to buy the
Okay
That's because the books are messy
And prohibitively expensive
But they're also just really hard to read
They're filled with ornate 18th century letter form
With their curlicues and flourishes which are confusing to the fingertip
It's not until many years later
Near the end of Ali's life in 1821
Are very different blind reading system begins to
Develop
When that uses dots instead of lines
It starts when a captain from Napoleon's Army visit the school to share a system that he developed for French soldiers
The captain describes how the system allowed his men to silently communicate with each other on battlefields at night
This is a clip from a very Lively educational movie about the
Melee
I called it
The director of the school at the time let a group of students
Experiment with the emboss
Pages that the captain had left behind
And in that group
Was a 12 year old blind cat
Name the Louis Braille
Over the next few years he began to adapt that military code
Beurre blanc
Asthma alternative to raised print
Can't you take a break
No
I got it so that all the letters of the alphabet
Are represented by race.
Indifferent
Louis Braille simplified the military code in maximize its efficiency
Keep substituted D12. System developed by the captain
Into a 6. System
Which allows blind people to read faster by recognizing a letter
With a touch of a single finger
And while this code was inscrutable decided
It was a system that blind people need it
Designed by a blind person who understood intimately the needs of those reading by touch
Another advocate for the blind would say of Braille
It Bears the stamp of Genius
Like the Roman alphabet itself
But despite its effectiveness
Braille didn't catch on right away
It wouldn't become the dominant system in France
For another 30 years
It'll be nearly a century before it became standard for blind readers in the US
Because it was effectively suppress
My well-intentioned world famous visionary
Education
Around the same time that Braille was quietly developing his new readings
An American named Samuel Gridley Howe
Came to visit the Royal insta
He was doing research in anticipation of opening the
First School for the Blind in the US
And I wish I could tell you that well in France how discovered the wonders of Braille
But that's not how it went down
Instead he saw the raised letter books and he was intrigued
But in true American fashion
He found all their fancy flourishes impractical
And typical of European Xs
So we decided to make his own system that improved on the Europeans were
And he came back and he he modified it a bit
Which how established in Massachusetts in 1829
Because they were using a more
Gothic style font that
He felt was
Was a little
Two ornamental and more difficult to read
By touch
So fun about ways French books look sort of like an ancient tome in a horror movie
Whose letters rise up in fleshy protuberance
And how system is similar
But it looks more runic
Kokanee
Elvish
How sharpen his letters curves into
Points to make them more distinct under the finger
Alero for example
Is shaped like a diamond
How cold is new system
Boston line type
Boston line type is is really the beginning of
Literacy as we know it as a movement for
People who are blind
In the United States
And like the older French system Boston linetype was designed to be read both by blind and sighted
If you're able to see and look at one of these books
The letters are
Totally easily
Legible
Boston line type allows blind people and sighted people
To sit down together and to read there's no barrier between them
And this idea was really important to how
She didn't want my people to use a system
Mike Brown it was separate from what side of the Equator
Starwood isolate blind people and prevent them from integrating into the wider world
Long before the concept of Universal Design has been articulated
It was informing house thinking about how to design for people with disabilities
I know so you can imagine
The arch well we want our
Kids that are blind
Compared to use the same system that are cited
Right.
Sounds good right
But it turns out that
Racers are just not as good
So it's harder
It just is harder it's that's not intuitive to people who recited
Those letterforms are just not unique enough
From each other
Siding people look
Kane Brown
But under the finger those raised dots underneath your finger are just more Tanger
Kayla just
And not only that
You can write in Braille
Print it doesn't require a big heavy metal printing press
All you need is a small simple tool called a slate and stylus
That fits in your pocket
By the 1860s
Some schools of the blind in the US
Had begun experimenting with Braille
And while many faculty members still resisted it as an arbitrary in pension
Bose system
The blind students who were exposed to Braille
Argued passionately for its superiority to raise letters
The Missouri School for the Blind students passed each other notes and reportedly even love letters in Braille
Since they knew their teachers wouldn't be able to read them if they got caught
But how had invested a massive amount of time and resources into developing Distributing and promoting Basta
Inline type
He become a hugely influential celebrity in the field of blind education
He was a master fundraiser
And key to that fundraising apparatus was the spectacle of a deaf blind girl named Laura Bridgman
To have taught to read
Using Boston line time
Bridgeman was the first deaf blind person in history to get in education
More than a full generation before Helen Keller did
This achievement made Laura Bridgman and Howe
International Star
Which Hal leverage to make Boston linetype
One of the dominant print mediums for the blind across the US
Like how
Many of the directors and faculty of schools for the blind were cited
And many of them believe that they knew which sister
The most best
Well it's easy for me reading a print letter so
How do you say for them with their fingers she now in
I think it's a failure of imagination or failure of empathy or
A failure of
Experience
Catherine kudlak directs the Paul K Longmore Institute on disability at San Francisco State where she's also a history
She doesn't even really buy house argue
Boston line type is universal
You might as well is universal but it's
Universal in that way that the colonizer
Thanks things are Universal it's like
You know these poor native peoples need educating and will try to bring them up
To my level and make them like
Like me
Didn't get the blind
People to be there
Is a crucial part
Disability Rights
Refrain is nothing
Us without us
Yeah
People are starting to say it is nothing without us
.
I think how probably made a good-faith effort to create a universal system
One that predicted Universal Design
When did he hoped would erase the line dividing a blind from the side
Paradoxically
The committing so strongly to the universal page of Boston line time
How help delay the adoption of a much better system by close to a hundred years in the US
Assistant with a blind person
Louis Braille was the expert
But the early Twentieth Century how had died
They were growing numbers organization dedicated to serving the Blind and more and more of them
We're being led
Vibeline
In 1921
Leaders from the most influential of these groups
Gathered in rural Iowa
Deformed the American foundation for the blind
Bafb quickly became the most powerful blindness organization in the US
One of their first priorities
The dominant system
But Americans being Americans
The same thing happened at it happen with raised letters
We decided that we could design things
Is better than those pretentious Europeans could
Soho cottage industry a rose
With all sorts of competing system
Real knock off
So
Now we're heading into what we call the war of the.
Have you heard of that
We could spend an entire episode on the war of the dots with Mike Hutson Hazard trusting narrator but in a nutshell
Before Braille truly one out in the US
There was another 50 years of competing tactile systems
This. Drove many blind readers banana
Because every library for the blind was filled with book printed in these multiple
Sam keating sister
New York point
Moon type
American modified Braille
We're not going to go in
But at one point
Ahead of the
Perkins School
Abscess
You know
Convince another code for
The blind we want to shoot
The decisive battle in the war of the dots
Finally came in 1909
Cities like New York or rapidly growing and for the first time
They had enough blind children to start building day schools for the blind
And so they have a nice
Big 2-day knock-down
Drag out meeting of the New York Board of Education
To decide which
Code
They're going to you
In New York City
So they bring in
All the heavy hitter
Okay I mean everybody's anybody in blindness testifies
Spotty
And at the end I take a big
Can they vote
For break
Okay
It's the beginning of the end for the up competing code
My 1917
The rest of the country follows New York's lead in the newly standardized English Braille
Becomes the main way Plum children are taught to read in the US
And with their increasing self-determination and literacy
Blind people are more able to integrate into society than ever before
Blind children are starting to be mainstreamed into public schools
First time
Some blind people are getting office jobs using Tech like Braille typewriter so they can work alongside cited
As equals
It's what how had hoped
Boston
Type without looking
Before all rails advantages over raised print
It didn't work for all blind
Like the thousands of soldiers who are coming back from war with eye injury
Two hands
Umbrellas kids
As you probably noticed listening to me struggle to read that stupid sentence about my niece doing puzzle
Puzzles
My niece can ride a unicycle or tooth puzzle
Learning braille as an adult
Is really hard
My niece can ride a unicycle
Urdu puzzles
But it sound recording became easier and more affordable
Those people who become blind later in life
Add new option
Options that would transform our ideas of what a book
Canby
Translating ink print books into sound might seem more straightforward than building a tactile reading system
Deborah books were born out of a few thousand years of people telling each other stories
We all learn to read by having books read to us
The early efforts to make recordings of books for blind readers
Brought with them
A new set of design challenge
American foundation for the blind partnered with the Carnegie Corporation
And to publish experimental books
Sun phonographic Records
They called them
Talking books
They hired narrators and press the recordings on too long playing record
25 minutes
To sign
These books were circulated by blind people about a decade before LPS became available to The Wider public
The first audio books
And the first LPS
Were made for blind reader
But these talking books raised
Big question
What should a book
Sound like
How do you translate the elements of a codex
Which is a fancy word for the thing that we usually call a book
Book with paper pages in combining
How do you translate one of those things
Into sound
The definition of the book basically
Imploded
Right after these talking book started to be developed because
All sorts of producers a started to come up with new ideas for things that they would call talking books that certainly had
Had nothing to do with
The Codex form
She's professor at NYU who works at the intersection of media and disabilities
And I promise you the last academic
Can introduce you to
Sexy Dodge Charger for a minute and listen to his bringing Cathedral like song
The Cornell Ornithology lab for instance
Decided that they wanted
To take some of their bird song recordings and make a talking book for blind people out of them
Bank of America
When Snow White came out as an early animated talking movie
The AFP decided they wanted to make a talking book version of a talking movie
Walt Disney's
Snowflake and the Seven Dwarfs
Recorded solely for the Youth
Sublime
There was no book
Origin they called it book
Panda circulated as
Talking book but it was a
Audio description
Of the images
In an animated film with some of the sound files and dialogue from that film
Closer and closer
Big night then Snow White notices
Very quickly all sorts of things begin to be called books
It had a very marginal relationship to the book
Book form
And it's talking books became more elaborate and Theatrical
Warfield with sound effects and music
Some blind people grew frustrated
More and more blind readers wound up breaking their record players trying to speed up the voices of the narrator
They weren't listening for Sonic aesthetic
Pleasure they wanted the damn information
And the fancy Productions move too slowly for how fast they wanted
What's the thing that posed to make people listen to podcasts at Double speed as with raised letter books the ornamental flourishes of music and
Sound effects got in the way of blind people's desire for Speed
And so talking books began to sound
The Holy Bible
Read by Alexander Scourby
No-nonsense narrator
Alexander Scourby
Became more popular in the 1940s and 50
And their voices became almost like fonts
Standardized
Legible
And most importantly
Conveying information without getting in the way
More like the narrator's of Contemporary Art
What about 4
Darkness
The spirit of God moved
The face of the waters
God said
Let there be light
And there was light
The book historian Matthew Berry told me that if you bring up the name Alexander Scourby with a blind person of a certain age
Their eyes will fill with tears
Because of the associations they have
With his voice
They grew up listening to him
Reading
So perhaps this is my constellation is it become a blind reader
I can just trade a visual type
Bass Reverb
In some ways my fears about losing my visual relationship to books resembles the anxieties that sighted people have a
About the demise of print in the digital age has more and more people read on screens there's an old guard who bemoans these new
Forms of reading as inferior
These critics believe that the trustee old technology of the book
Will always be the superior vehicle for ideas
You can hear this conservatism and condescension not only in those people who Milani book
But also in the voices of people who say that you haven't really read a book
If you listen to it they contended that real reading only happens with the eyes
The history of blindness and reading shows that the way we read has always been in
The media scholars in book historians I talk to all told me the same thing
Reading doesn't happen in the eyes or the ears of the fingers
It happens in the brain
This is a nice thing to hear if you're going blind
It makes me feel like
Forget my stupid eyes
I'll still have my brain
That's where all the good stuff happens anyway
But this idea doesn't really soften or mask
The fact of blindness is
Inescapably
Leah loss
No amount of historical research or conceptual reframing can hide
Simple equation at work
I love books
April books
With marginalia and typefaces and dingbats
I'm going blind will take that away from
But I can't let that be my only kin
Conclusion
The blindness equals loss
.
Mara Mills told me about someone she met
The story could offer me an example of a different way to approach my life as
Is a blind reader
His name is Harvey Lauer
He's a blind guy who worked at the VA
Testing all kinds of Technology
For the visually impaired
When you turn on the machine
You here
All the sounds in the ear
This is Harvey using an optophone
Kind of scanner
That would look at text and turn it into a series of tones representing the shapes
Cast of the letters
It's another spin on Universal Design for blind readers
With an optophone
You wouldn't need to create special books
For the blind at all
But training a blind person could read an ink print book
Using one of these devices
Delta phone was first developed in 1912
But this recording
Is from 1971
Reading sounds like this
First off the line
And then we'll read
Incredibly
Some people actually learned how to read
After a lot of practice they can hear the sounds and decode the words they represent it
Reading entire novels using what came to be called musical print
It said the necessary functions of the
Using the devices he tested for the VA
Harvey could read by vibration
True musical Prince
Plus Braille and super speed up talk
Bucks
He reads using more of his body
Worth his senses
Perhaps anyone else on the planet
His colleagues called him a cyborg
She walked around with these devices dangling around his neck wherever he went
Emitting vibrations in synthetic Musical
Got to go to the I had a turn up the trash or after
Empirical
Bar told me that this sometimes lead to funny incidents of confusion
Like the time Harvey walked into a 7-Eleven and heard all these electronic tones coming out of the various machines in the
Play Store
He tried to coating them
Because it seemed to him like they should be alphabetic
And then he realized
Nope
There's just electronic tones
Harvey's mistake in the 7-Eleven suggest to me away that my future as a blind reader might actually signal something
Other than a total loss
Linus could add something to my life
Even if it takes something else away
Learning to read in new ways
Through new senses
Could increase my appreciation
In for the world around me
Harvey told Mara that he finds the electronic tones and chords of the optifoam beautiful
He said they remind him of Debussy music
Which gives me hope
That whichever way I end up reading
To spit up synthetic speech for Braille
Or maybe some high-tech post-op to phonics cyborg system that's yet to be invented that I'll find the beauty in that kind of
I really should use the other earphones and plug in the other speaker
Hypothesis are
Replace it with a more adequate one
Failure to find
Does not miss sellers
Give me the park composer Sean real
Al gives us a short lesson in Reading with the up the phone and break down the music they can pose for this episode using OptiFine
Phonic letters
After this
So I'm now in the studio with Sean real so the song at the very end
The story was a
Special song that related to the episode
So you can you describe I like how you made the music
Traductor
Piccolo section of the episode
Yeah so when we were doing our edit
Like
Everyone was just like
So fascinated
By the optophone at the end of the story and throughout that whole section everyone was just going
Like the sort of sounds of it we're just
Prancing and so
I had I was just like taking with howling music low as and I was
Like this would be really cool thing to use this
An instrument and so then I asked Andrew
Buddhist Peace FM
There was a way to get samples of
The alphabet basic
Not only like make
Music out of
The sounds but liked actually like spell something out in like make
IMessage
Have been lyrics to the song
I found out that it's very hard to actually write with with
Optophone
Samples but I'll talk a little bit more about that later
I want to play you some of this because
When I was listening to
The tape of like all these different letters
I was really struck actually with how intuitive it is
Cool
Okay what's your sign
First thing I'm going to do is going to play you a no
So here's a no
What the other phone is doing it's actually scanning tags
And so it's
Basically making an auditory
Shape of the letter so the O meaning of like the left of the oh you're going to have kind of like
To Midtown like very close to the middle and then as the circle opens up
You're going to have a tone
That is high on a tone that is low
And then they're going to close back up back up okay so yeah
Teutones the middle
And then
Expanse high and low and then goes back down to
To be in the middle in that crate
It's the shape of a now so weird
Skating across
What's a letter
As if it's just printed
Yeah I'm so here's here's that same oh again but slow down so you can really hear it
Okay
Another letter that I thought was the best letter x
Actually
Is is a w in Philly this one I think you'll really be able to hear this
Because
Unlike the or actually most of the letters in the alphabet
VW doesn't have any like
Vertical stacking so it's really just like
It really you really do like read it
Left to right
Like at a time so like you don't hear two tone simultaneously so you should be able to trace
The W as it goes high low
Hi-Lo
Exactly
So here's the w
Then here it is
Do that again
Yeah but I really love is that like
You can tell that the midpoint of the W is lower than the other
Turn the outside right and so they're choosing a certain type of w it doesn't go all the way it is Anna.
W with a middle goes all the way to the Top Line and then which one what goes in the middle
It's extremely specific to whatever
Whatever font you have whatever page your reading make sense
Southern making music I was listening to
A lot of rods have of
Harvey Lauer just
Playing with his optophone and kind of like
Being awed at
It in the same way that we were in so that was and so that was just like so need and so there's there's like
This type of him
Just
Reading numbers
I'm just like really getting a kick out of it
There's an open for by golly
Music
Define
These are nice numbers
He developed the other phone so like
He's probably the person most fluent in optophone he's in the world but like you said like this is us
Scanner that goes across
Any print that there is so it's like he's reading
Ascertain
Display qunar sometimes you know like I make a 7 with a crosshatch
Example
And so that would
Sound different than a normal 7 without a cross
Across the middle of
But yeah so even though
You know he knows
The optimum better than anybody
Everytime it scans a new
Font typeface
Get something new something new from that is all really enjoying reading okay that's so great
Yeah
So inspired by the APA
The phone you compose
A couple of songs and one of them was at the end and it had a message inside of it
That was a
A true optophone message
Inside of the song so what did it say
Very true about the phone message and said OptiFine
That's great cuz I always what you can kind of figure out and see
Stuff like that simple yet and that's and that's exactly like leading to my next Point like
I tried out a lot of like different messages cuz I originally thought like who I could like have like a hole
Sentence or something but
I noticed that
Because these sounds are coming just
One letter at a time
It was actually really like
Milotic Liam
Portent I found
Multiple letters
That that repeat
Optophone actually kind of has a pattern to it is
Opt
Oph
Oh and so it's I can so actually every three letters is an o
And so
It takes on the characteristic of music yeah okay
Swiss remind people
Other little Section music
Where you spell out
Sound so good
Could you hear the letters you had to tell me what it was
I heard it but
Understated voice a little bit
This is so amazing thank you so much and I'm so pleased that you
Crazy music
Inspired by
So much fun to do
I really
Yeah I really like
Being inspired
To do this
Okay let's hear The Last Song
That little bit about the phone tape
10% invisible
99% invisible with Bruce's sweet by Andrew Leland and edited by Delaney Hall
Mixing Tec Russian by Sharif Youssef
Music by Shawn real
Galicia Bruce recruit Kolstad is the digital director
Brazil team is Avery Johnson
Vivien Leigh Joe Rosenberg Edmund Fitzgerald Sofia klatzker and me Roman Mars
Meetings this week
Sari altschuler and David Weimer we found out about the story of Boston linetype from an exhibition they put together called
Touchless pay
Exhibition is also online at touch this page.com where you can see examples
A Boston line type and other precursors to Braille
Also to den Hale and Jennifer arnott at the Perkins School
Matthew rubery of Queen Mary University of London whose book about the history of talking books he is awesome
And walima leaves from Northeastern College of Engineering
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most innovative
Shows in all a podcasting
Fun Mall
Radiotopia
Hot FM
You can find the show enjoying discussed about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria Grand
Instagram and read it to
But you need to run to our website and see
Video of the spectrogram of the Octagon letters that sound composer
Is so cool
That's at 99 pi
Radio Tempe