This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the shadow of Silicon Valley San Francisco is home to a futuristic Eatery with a virtual cashier putting change
On the menu
It was a new restaurant
But opened a few years back in downtown San Francisco
It was called
Itza
Pizza a high-tech new restaurant where you order on iPad
And get your quinoa bowls out of
A cubby and instead of placing an order with a waiter or
Someone behind the counter
You punch in your order on a screen
Why do you swipe your car
And then a few minutes later you would walk to a wall
Clear glass cubbies
Go dark for just a second so you don't see the actual food being placed in the cubby and then when the food was placed
The cubby woodglo with your name
You tap the glass twice
And you could open the cubby and your food order was in there
Waiting for you
You tap it you get your food and you leave the fact that you can just order on the iPad pick it up
It's really about the most productive way you can get lunch
You never had to interact with a single person if you didn't want to he didn't have to tip
It was fast.
Hop in
Grandpa custom made
Quinoa Bowl
And then go back to work
Without even pausing your pocket
And I
Hated it
So much
Producer Avery trial
As soon as I heard about Eatza I was like okay
Great
Just what we need
To be even more removed
From our food
Not only where it comes from but also
The person who handed to you
Cuz it's not like it's a completely Robot Restaurant
Little people back there
Find the Cubbies
Weisinger avocados
Conveniently placed out of sight so that you don't have to say thank you
But you never
Actually tried
Okay no I never went
So take it with a
Big fat
Salt
And also know that I hated it be
Because it was very fun to hate
Is like
Juicers that connect to your phone with Bluetooth
You know just like stuff that is so
Completely Lampoon Ubly San Francisco
And so I did what I always do when I'm upset about a stupid thing
I tweeted about it
Instead of getting in a fight
A number of people on Twitter pointed out that
This restaurant
Is not a distinctly modern phenomenon
Something very similar existed at the turn of the century
Over 100 years ago
It was not a San Francisco thing
It was very
New York
I grew up in the city
And the city that I grew up in
And the city I'm living in now
Ain't never met each other
This is one of the New Yorkie is people I have ever met
Lorraine.
Well I write about New York history
So I'm always
Fishing around
Something that I want to write about
My grandmother lived on 40s
King Street and 8th Avenue I used to meet her under the clock of the Franklin Savings Bank
Saturday afternoon
We will go to Horn & hardart
Ask anyone who the kid in New York in 50s or 60s
They went to Horn & hardart
What's a popular restaurant chain that was in many ways
The Itza of the twentieth century it had locations all over New York City and Philadelphia
It had very solid standard fare with literal meat and potatoes
What's your favorite dish
And when the rain decided that you wanted to write about Horn & hardart
She got connected with Marianne
People don't always
Connect my last name with horn & hardart but when they do immediately
Play Store
Marianne hardart is
The great-granddaughter of Horn & hardart co-founder Frank
Har.
Together Marriott heart art and Lorraine deal teamed up to write the definitive history of this restaurant chain
Puppies to live near each other on the Upper East Side and they get along like a house on fire emails
Yeah
But Horn & hardart restaurants also went by another name
How much more famous name
The automat
What's the automat
It was the first time that you could go up
To a wall
Put money in
And get food
Hotworx
Fresh
Prepared
Inside a horn & hardart automat it look like a glamorous
Ornate cafeteria
But instead of human handing you hot food over a steaming counter
You put your tray up to a wall of little glass
Cubbies
Beach Housing a fresh hot portion of food on a small plate
Maybe it would be a side of keys
Maybe a turkey sandwich or slice of pie
Nichols
And the door that kobe would unlock
And you could just take
The plate that was inside
That food was yours
This place where you can
He put money in the squad and pick your own food so for children
You know
The parents would give him some money they would run up to the windows I can pick what they wanted they could put the nickel in and get their own food
It was a Realty
By the way I hit the Beast
And it was pretty good
UC automatic
In a ton of movies
Ranging from silent films like the early bird in 1925
To Whit stillman's Metropolitan
In 1990
Cake
Seeing a character in automatic
Told you there's a certain kind of American
One wants to go out to eat
Don't have the budget
My dear
She has no background
What's in this short from 1932
Opens with a group of people in Fancy
Dining like Royals
Then the camera zooms out
And womp womp
And this is also a punchline when Marilyn Monroe sings Diamonds Are a Girl's Best Friend
I help you
Audiomack
And none of these movies explain what the automat is
It's just assumed
That everyone knew
The Broadway columns in the newspapers to talk about
Who is singing at the automat
Gene Kelly when he was doing Pal Joey on Broadway
He and his wife will go over there and Gregory Peck would love their scrambled eggs or something
Count and Countess is coming in from Europe
We've got to try this
And they would sit down next to people who are flat broke
And you didn't have to tip
No
Wish
It's kind of like pizza
And that was the automat
100 +
10 years ago
The story of the automat started when Joe horn net Frank Hardy
Joey put an ad in a local Philadelphia paper
Seeking a business partner
And so they got together and they opened a luncheonette in Philadelphia
Over to you
None of that sits just add in the year 1888
And for a while it was just a normal Luncheonette
With famously good coffee
Until
Frank hardart
Went over to Germany
Right he was going to give himself a vacation
Their heart art encounter it's very early German vending machine technology
Bought one of these machines and brought it back to Philly
It was more
Rube Goldberg contraption
Rube Goldberg what does overly complicated German bending contraption
The food in the windows was a sample to
Display of what one could order
Customers with deposit coins
And wait around while someone in the basement
Cooked it
And then cranked it up in a dumbwaiter
It was a very
Convoluted way of getting your food but everyone loved the novelty of it
So they perfected it and then they brought it to New York City
About 10 years later
It was in Philadelphia the first automatic knife
Go to and then they came
New York City in 1912
And now
Equipped with a glass cubbies
Fast
But not because of a technology
I was just to get people in the door
The automat part was just as glorious gimmick
People came for the novelty
But came back again and again because it was solid
Good food
Good and cheap
The technology was
Custom Mechanical Turk
The only thing that was automatic was when you went in there and look
Look at this wall but what was going on behind those walls is very different
Behind the scenes there were people screwing around replacing all the food laws were scores of
Workers Mini Boom
Rapidly replenishing the food into the Cubbies
Starting out to bust and clean dishware
And is automatic expanded to more locations in both Philadelphia and New York
All the cooking itself
Happened in offside commentaries
These were separate kitchen and I took up a whole city block
There's one giant Central commissary in New York Giants Central commissary in Philly
Sauces in pies but a hundred
Which dispatched hot and fresh to automats throughout the day
Food for the New York locations with slightly different than Phillies
Through little Regional variations
For mac and cheese I think one had diced tomatoes and in the other one didn't you know there were some things like that like things spicy
Is a little bit sharper
The New York State star people are sharper their food
Burberry United
And how they look
Joe horn
And Frank hearted made it their business to make sure that when you walked into these
These places
They were really quite lovely and some of them witches Art Deco Palace
If they were beautiful
And that to me is a generosity of spirit
Because they know they're not getting
You're not getting the Carriage Trade coming in every day and on and ass
Asking for the wine list
There are those rare brands that appeal
La Crosse economic class
Ikea and Target
Horn & hardart
Was one of them
The automat
With a place
Anyone could eat
In a time when it was nearly unheard of for a woman to go out to
Eat Alone
Work from
People who just post up
Somewhere all day
And with the automatic
They could
Without Shame
And people who were just
Saving Face or saving shoe leather
Looking for jobs
Would be in their nursing a couple
Coffee all day and no one bothered them
We didn't even know that people would eat that way and then as soon as they could
They never could eat as much or as little as I could
Do they have total autonomy I just want a cup of coffee
I'd I really just want
5 pieces of dessert
I want this I want that and you didn't
I have to deal with what you should be ordering
How to order
And it could be
Kwik kopy leisurely
Use the boss
And be
Because everyone ate there
That's how they could keep it
It's so cheap
It was all economies of
Scale
That's how they made so much food
So fresh
And so affordable
It was all
Volume
Before McDonald's
Horn & hardart was the largest restaurant chain in America and one of the largest in the world this is Lisa hurwitz
Filmmaker working on a documentary about the automat
And by
Largest
I'm talking about volume
Just stopped
Somehow
Everyone knew about the automat
Marilyn Monroe was singing about it was in a ton of movies
Horn & hardart said more people than any other restaurant in the United States
And it was only in Two Cities
New York
In Philadelphia
For a lot of people they never could have imagined that horn & hardart was ever going to disa
The pr because it was such a big part of the fabric
Bank of New York City
Philadelphia
Today I can't ever imagine Starbucks
Hearing but it could
One day
You never know
I think maybe Horn & hardart got a little too comfortable and they couldn't imagine what was about to happen
What happened to the automat
Was the story of the American city
White flight and mass migration to the suburbs
American new homes with new cars
A new lifestyle
And of course
This changed how people ate
It became very trendy for women to be stay-at-home mothers
Taking care of new homes
Using their new kitchens
Taking care of the family
And
Batman
Les eating out
Sowell automatic used
Seven-day-a-week three-meal-a-day operation
They transformed into 5-day week
One meal a day off
And the people who went out to eat for that one meal didn't want
Send steaks anymore
You're on the go now there was fast food
Do you want to sit
You wanted white tablecloths and attentive waiter is in fancier food
Good that you couldn't cook at home
People have more money to spend
They were more inclined to have maybe fewer meals out
But to have nicer
Horn & Hardart's we're getting old
I'm looking kind of bedraggled
Customers and City governments were investing less and less in the increasingly neglected inner cities around
And so
Horn & hardart launches their big
Comeback ad campaign
In which
They dig in their heels and refuse to change it all
If you want something nice to look at when you eat at Horn & hardart
We suggest you keep an eye on your plate
The campaign was called it's not fancy but it's good
Although eventually it wasn't even that good
Horn & hardart got less popular
The food turnover wasn't as high
So it wasn't as fresh
There was something going on simultaneous
FYE which was that
The horns in the heart
We're being pushed out of the company
And the new people who weren't automat people they were fast food
The new heads of Horn & hardart realize that their greatest asset was not their restaurants
Buckeye real estate
So the really prime horn & hardart locations were franchised in too fast
Food restaurant
They were
The first
Burger King Arby's franchises in Manhattan
The automat lasted the better part of a century
Which is pretty incredible
Bless automat in New York
Triathlon
He much is a gimmick
Finally close
In 1991
I will admit that where I felt
Only disdain for
I was totally taken in by the idea of the automat
Like 100%
Sign me up for this place that is both highbrow and lowbrow or I can even a beautiful Art Deco dining room
As many slices of pie as I want without judgment
Enter some of that is just baseless nostalgia
And a genuine love of art deco
But
I think there's a reason Horn & hardart was in business
A hundred years
I think it's
Because it was always a very Human Experience
It wasn't to go container
It was metal flatware and
China
Customer stayed in the dining room to eat
It was always full of people hanging out
An ultimately humans seem to Crave some kind of interaction when they go out to eat
Even today
People aren't necessarily looking for an all robot kind of experience
Me when they walk in they want it to be
Easy and convenient and they want to
If they have an issue be able to communicate to someone who can take care of them
This is Gwyneth Borden
Executive director of the Golden Gate Restaurant Association
Which is the trade Association for the restaurants in the San Francisco Bay Area
2015 was the first year in the u.s. when the Department of Commerce was tracking it
People spend more money on dining out food then groceries
And increasingly what we have
Scene is food is
The modern form of entertainment
Demand for restaurants
Up which means there's a national shortage of restaurant workers
Especially in expensive cities like San Francisco
With the median cost of a one-bedroom apartment is now $3,700 a month
How do you pay for that while working in a restaurant
Labor costs overall risen
It's hard to find people to work in farming
Are the people working restaurants
Do you have to pay people more
The restaurant have been trying to get by with fewer people
With self ordering screens or counter service
Free describe a number for your table
But this can be taken too far
What we know for fact is that people will eat it on mediocre restaurant
For food but won't accept bad service
If you look at Yelp or TripAdvisor or whatever
UCM people's reviews that
Service is a really important factor
You know in General yet people write things about
Attitude not being great
But it was usually drives them to
To do that
That is
A bad experience where they feel like they were not
So rather than hiding the workers in the back
Automating the front of the house
Like Itza or the automat
The new automated restaurants are trying to flip it
They want the food to be served entirely by humans
But it's cooked
By robots
I went to one of these places in San Francisco
It's a robot burger restaurant called creator
But where people greet you and guide you through the menu
And place your order for you
Went down and drink
And then clear glass robots
Assemble your burger and under 5 minutes
But then a human called out your name and hand your order to you
And the secret power of this restaurant
It's not a central commissary kitchen
It's the 40 some-odd engineer's working in the office next door
Because whether they automate
The front or the back
These businesses are not just selling food
They are selling their technology
And that's true for Itza
They gone from selling quinoa Bowl
Selling their service
There two locations in San Francisco are now shuttered
With no signs of when the open again
Either wouldn't go on record for an interview
But their PR representative told me that now Itza is focus on selling their serving technology to other chains
Macaroni and cheese restaurant called Mac
Another chain called Wow Bao
Even at McDonald
It's pretty common to order on a screen
And salad making robot named Sally is mean put in a restaurant chain based in Louisiana Mississippi
In Alabama
Their new iterations of vending machines
Faceless delivery in robot chef
Popping up
Everywhere
The point is
Yes
Horn & hardart restaurants
Argon
But more and more chains
Are becoming
Automatic
Special thanks to Bro flag David Bordeaux and a moon announcer
On Ira Goldman
You can find out more about Lisa hurwitz documentary and share your automatic memories
Facebook.com
The automat the movie
Coming up
Robots that throw food
All in an effort to make that food
Seymour delicious
After that
When we were editing the story about the automatic brought to mind another story about robots
What's in food that we did a couple of years back
That I love because
It may be the most
Perfect example of the 99% invisible effort that goes into something that most people do not think about
But it totally changed the way we buy and consume food
Lemons are squeezing
Cabal the ads you see on TV or on billboards are on the sides of buses
It's an overwhelming number seem to be
Far food
This
He's our man
Bulls head
Google turkey
Egg and sausage pancakes
Morning I see coax in frosted glasses
Fajitas sizzling on the grill
A guy biting into the perfect hamburger on a sesame seed bun
Ingredients
Of course you know in real life
These Foods don't look like they do in the ass
Winter with a question from Isabelle Ave from Toronto Ontario
She asked why does your food look different in the advertising and then what's in the store
The great question Isabel we get off that a lot
And if you want to come with me
I'm going to take you across the street we're going to find out a bit more
In 2012 McDonald's Canada put out this video about the process they go through
Photograph one of their burgers
Let me introduce you now to Noah
Food stylist
I think it's important to note that all the ingredients
No uses are the exact same ingredients
The video follows food stylist Noah as he painstakingly selects the perfect slices of us
Onion and pickle pee places them on the burger with tweezers
And then precisely melt
The cheese just
So
Tell them Jack melting down
Then he picks up a plastic syringe filled with ketchup and a Plaza
With surgical precision
Maybe I'll put
Mustard ketchup
Actually ketchup mustard
Then they photograph this fancy burger and Photoshop at 2 perfect
They place a picture of a real burger just ordered at McDonald's
Next to the image of this
Stylized Burger
And the difference
Is striking
That's reporter Danny Lewis
I would like to eat the burger that Noah styled and assembled
The other one not so much
The last hundred years or so of food advertising have been shaped by this one simple
Real food looks bad
On camera
Shooting food and even photographing food is always been fiendishly difficult in that
This is Terry O'Reilly
Predict it
He was an ad man
And he now hosts a radio show about advertise
Called under the influence
Terry says the challenges of shooting food are obvious
First of all food is boring to look at when it's just sitting on a plane
Because food is he generally static
Then when you subjected to the Hot Lights of a
EStudio de food starts to wilt
It's just simple science
And so advertisers have had to constantly want that's fine line between enhancement and fakery
Trying all kinds of tricks
To get food to look good
For the first half of the 20th century
Well after photography it was widely adopted
Advertisers in magazines and newspapers relied heavily on illustration
The reason illustration
What's the preferred method was because you can completely control an illustration
Another word just know lighting issues there's no wilting food issues
A marketer could really completely dick
Tate what that food would look like right down to the to the strand of pasta
With an illustrate
Then TV came along in the 1950s and 60s
And advertisers face a whole new set of challenges
I'm going to show you how McDonald's deals at a Big Mac sandwich
A lot of them didn't really understand how to shoot food in a compelling way
In this add the hamburger just
Since they're on the counter
All the ingredients get piled on
It starts here with a lightly Toasted Bun
And then a pure beef hamburger
Sizzling hot
Without compelling visuals
There ought to be a voice over
Just describing the hell out of the food
Listing ingredients telling you how good it tasted
A little more sauce just for good flavor
Dill pickles
And the sesame seed crown
These early tv ads relied on relatively static shots
Advertisers would use a wide-angle lens mounted on a camera
A little but that's about it
There were lots of shots of boxes
The food did
Just normal food stuff you might see
Something being ladled out of a pot you might see you know a spoon
Serving peas at a dinner table or serving cream corn at a dinner table
So that would be the extent of the most
On top of the new challenges of television
Food advertisers in the late 60s found themselves facing new scrutiny the Federal Trade Commission with keeping a close eye
Ion TV app
Campbell Soup incident
68 they were introducing a new brand of suit that a lot of vegetables in it but the problem is the vegetable sink to the bar
So what they did was
Put a bunch of marbles in the bottom of the balls
Just too high.
The
When you have TC found out they threaten Campbell's with legal Act
Event led to a new push for truth in advertising
A lot of the old tricks advertisers had relied on in the past where now off
The table no more using glue
Milk and cereal ads
No more substituting mashed
Potatoes fries
But in the 1970s
Food advertising took a radical
Started
Open the door
Shrimp executing acrobatic flips
Lobster claws cracking open in slow motion
French fries bouncing across a table
Wasn't static anymore
Food was flying
And we've got one man to thank for the
Is new aesthetic
Albert Beauty
You didn't want any
Everything was always smooth
He wanted to
Romance
The food
Or whatever was in front of
This is Harry Drennan who spent years working for Elbert beaudin
That's how he met his wife
Set director Jackie Chan
I've been in the film business for
35 years 40 I don't want to say hello
The ads that can't until his death in 1996
Where unprecedented
Working with clients like McDonald's Burger King and Coca-Cola invented
Food commercials
Sandra Lee Pioneer the genre of advertising known
As table top
Many of the terms and techniques that table top directors still use date back to Buda
For example
The prep shot
Which tells the backstory of the Prada
Showing all that goes into making the food
You know the ones
Chopping a crisp out of lettuce
Dicing some juicy red tomatoes
He would make these
Elaborate banquet things
Raw ingredients
That was his look
And creative shots
That's when the camera zooms way in and lingers on some tantalizing bite of food on the end of a fork
Sexy and you know it's almost foodporn you know it's
Made it all real tactel to you
And the hero shot
The last magnificent look at the food
On the plate ready to eat
Usually in the final seconds of the advertising
Buchanan's big breakthrough was that he didn't just describe the food and promised viewers it tasted
He made them feel actual
Hunger with his image
His real thing is just food in itself its Essence is really sensual
You know what I mean
Juicy Hamburger commercial
Point of it
And I think that's what he introduced
And you'll never see it any other way now
Kendall and Drennan remember working long days and
Sometimes the long night
To meet budenz hi-standard
And to achieve his vision of flying food
Mouth watering clothes
They had to use a whole bunch of
Crazy tool
Like giant high-speed cameras that was burned through 1000 feet of film in seconds and then
They start shooting as it was like
Justice
All day long it was something
It was used for the ballistics but we were the first ones to do it with
Food thanks to these cameras beaudin could achieve
Super slow motion effect
You take a split second of time
And luxuriate in it
He'd have oranges Splash through a sheet of water
Condensation would drip down the side of a bottle
In order to get the perfect egg
Duden started designing strange
Rube Goldberg soda machines to help him get the job done
These Contraptions were called rigs
They range from simple spouts for liquid to machines that would drop pancakes into a perfect stacked
The catapults that would
Languages across the studio
And sure the production team could have just thrown The Oranges by hand
But with a rig
They could get the exact
Same results
Over and over
Which meant fewer takes
Which meant less time and less money spell
Also meant that they could achieve a certain level of precision and artistry
It was so much prettier than other people
It's work is
Far as I could see
He's beautiful and Lighting
And then with Iowa once he got into all the movement that me he was
He was ahead of the curb
Ice roll scene
About ready and action
Optimistic
To see how beautance techniques are still being used today
Danny went to MacGuffin films in New York
Okay so just
MacGuffin does commercials for Red Lobster Olive Garden Starbucks in a bunch by the restaurant
The date Danny was there
They were shooting a chicken sandwich so they are shooting a chicken sandwich
Sure Shot it looks like on a black
Sleep
A little tray of
Chili Peppers and garlic and stuff
A hand model stands near the edge of the table for the sandwiches display
What's another doing the crowning
Crowning means the hand model
Takes the bun
And put it on top of the sandwich
Does President there alluringly
Men take the crown off
Top of the chicken
Then the ground goes back on again
It took them all day to film this sandwich
The whole shoot precisely orchestrated
Relying on highly technical tool
Downstairs in macguffins proper I'm there all sorts of rig sitting in storage
A lot like the ones that you develop
But these are way more high-tech
Riggers today use lasers
And sensors and pre-programmed Motors
And depending on the shot or the rig
There can be some intense physics
To take into account
Like if you're trying to slice an onion into while it's flying through the air we break down the elements
Onion to a certain height
This is Anthony the robber
He's a special effects
Technician at MacGuffin films
And he designed a special rig just to get this
Shotgun Dan's computer-controlled so when the onions in the right spot these two sharp knives come through split the onion
Leave you with
Sliced in the middle
And slices of onion artfully tumbling across a table
Classic rock shop
But Wellbutrin may have introduced Rigs in action 2 tabletop
Some directors like macguffins Nick few.
I'm trying to get away from you
Fantastical Dreamscape
Pics of flying shrimp
And oranges
I think that's a little bit of an older point of view for next few ghosts at the idealized images of food that be
Tried to bring to his ass
Just don't cut it in a world that's now totally saturated with food poor
Well Butrans commercials often zoomed-in so close to food that you couldn't see the space around it
Tabletop directors like people start now frame there food in the space that you might see out in the world
Like at a restaurant or barbecue
You know when you dig into a lasagna do you want the sauce to go all over the place
We need to taco stuff going to fall out yet so let's shoot
Let it the flavors mix
It's all right so tasty
But the thing to remember is this
On the set of a food commercial
Everything
Is highly orchestrated and contrived
Even if the ultimate effect feel somewhat.
Because a 30-second TV spot by a firm like Magoffin can cost literally hundreds of thousands of dollars
Who's got to do one thing to make it all worthwhile
Sell a lot of food
I would say the number one rule
In food advertising is that the first taste is always with the eyes
So you trying to create a shot
That makes somebody's
This is Terry O'Reilly again
And he's fascinated by the links people go to sell something
He tells a story about working on commercial for a hamburger company
And watching an actor do take after take
Biting into a hamburger
And I'm gazing into a camera with a lookup
Total satisfaction on his face
Then you cut and then there's this
Right beside the actor then they just spit it right into the pale you know cut
Edit and you have any watch that happened 40 times are 30 * 1/20 and it's so hilarious to me
Just the mechanics
Evaporite
The illusion and the reality of creating if that's exactly it in a nutshell
This story was produced by Danny Lewis with Avery trufelman and Delaney Hall back in March of 2016
We have over 350 episodes in the 99 bi catalog just like that one and most of them
Owego Evergreen
So they're just as relevant today as they were when you produce them
To go into your podcast app
Download
All the old episodes
Don't worry about the episode title and description
All the topics wasn't boring that is
Almost a point but trust me you will love
If you going download all the old episodes right now
I could probably see that in her stats and that would be really fun to watch
You will enjoy listening to them too so it's a win-win
The ultimate story was produced by Avery trufelman mix into production by Sharif Youssef music by Shawn real
Katie mingle is the senior producer Kohl's data is the digital director
The team includes senior editor Delaney Hall Emmett Fitzgerald turn Mathai Vivien Leigh Sophia ClassDojo Rosenberg and
Amy Roman Mars
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PR except fiercely independent Collective of the most innovative
YouTube shows in all of podcasting
Fun Mall
And radiotopia
Ask.fm
You by the show and doing session about the show on Facebook you can tweet me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Bratz Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But you can peruse
The Bowl selection of hot and tasty design stories in the oven
Class Cubbies depositor quarter in the slot
And then it's all yours
At 9 p.m.
. org
Radiotopia