This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In 1959
After nearly a century-and-a-half of British colonial rule
People of Singapore took the first step toward their independence
They voted to run their own internal governor
British colonial rule was restored after the second World War
A series of colonial administrators have ruled and ordered our lives
Well times have changed
Top decided to run the Affairs of Singapore
It was a joyous moment
But they inherited a difficult situation
All of us
Wanda better and a fuller life
But a rise in the standard of living of all people
Cannot be created overnight
Singapore was bombed heavily by Japan during the second World War
And again by the Allies after Singapore fell to the Japanese
A lot of it infrastructure was in Ruins including the port
Which it brought foreign goods and a multi-ethnic multilingual population of people
To the island for centuries
No Port meant no jobs
Poverty was rampant
Most of the Island's residents were living in unpermitted makeshift houses
Crammed into crowded Villages throughout the island
If you don't know
The country of Singapore is
Tiny
Trading tarnation is really just one city
It takes less than 45 minutes to drive across the island
With traffic
But in the 1950s
There were Village
And those Villages were known as components
A local Malay word
Best producer Katie Thornton
She's a Fulbright National Geographic
Big fellow and has spent the last four months in Singapore
Compone communities were strong
Close knit
What's an easy
Multiple families might share one toilet or one kitchen
The compounds relied on gas for lighting
And most houses were made of super flammable Palm
Norwood
With roofs made of sheet metal
The government wanted to raise the quality of life for the people they rebuilt the port and created factory jobs they made
All the kids learn English so that Singapore could feel United under one language but the biggest undertaking of all
What's to get the people out of thatched roof Huts in into modern house
And one of the biggest challenges would be doing it with extremely limited land space
In 1960s they formed the housing and develop
Bored or hdb
I'm just 5 years later
It already has 400000
Well over 400 thousand people
Singapore's population
I've been be hotter than the last five years and these bright mother Mary plant
Nowhere in the world
West Germany
Is the rate of rehousing faster than in Singapore
By going vertical
When planning for growing population most urban planners
Expand their cities outward
But in land limited Singapore
That is not an option
Today Singapore tallest public housing buildings are 50 stories high
The tallest in the world
From the very beginning
The Housing and Development board went vertical
The people of Singapore demand high standards
Are there prepared to work hard and a capable of high Skittles
But then the sky is the limit
Singapore is acquiring one Hallmark of a great civilized community
Magnificent buildings
Today
Singapore is the third richest nation in the world
And 80% of singaporeans still live in East
Tall cement hdb Flats
There's about 10000 public housing buildings on the island
A new flats are going up all the time
It's not the glitzy futuristic Singapore Skyline UC and movies like crazy rich Asian
The buildings are tall and cement
How to block numbers on the side
Helping singaporeans locate themselves in the monotonous city of nearly identical building
Throughout the 1960s and 70s
Hdb public housing developments sprung up all over the country
Who is Moon as a historian in Singapore
She was born in 1960
Has lived in hdb flats for most of her life
She remembers watching this house in crop up everywhere on the Isle
They weren't all designed exactly the same
Pretty close
Design style is different
But what doesn't change is basically everything become like a matchbox
So you're leaving in a little
Hole
Insight
Concrete structure
As people moved into these crab concrete Towers a lot of the missed the vibe of their old community
What they called the compound spirit
But there was a lot to like about their new homes
Like having their own bathrooms and kitchens with electricity and Plumbing
A place where they can have their own
Privacy
A place where they don't get flooded every time it rains
And so people moved in
And the government kept building
And that the beauty just keep getting higher
Over the years
But despite the Privacy that architecture afforded
Yvonne didn't always feel alone
As a kid growing up in age
Hdb Flats
She remembers seeing shadowy figures
Floating above her bed
She asked her mom about it
So when I was very young
I told my mom
I say
Why is it that I see that you may just above me and then she said
Silly go this used to be a cemetery
Of the four Apartments even has lived in
Two of them have been on Old cemeteries
Might seem like bad luck
But in Singapore where land is scarce
It's not unlikely for apartment buildings to be built on land that was graveyards not too long ago
But building on top of a graveyard has his complications
And in one Cemetery
Call PacSun tank
The new Housing Development disrupted more than just the Dead
It disrupted a way of life
Yeah I'm a Pawn on you King
Growing up in the 50s and 60s
Mr. Kwan was a city boy
But his dad would bring him to eight miles from their home near Singapore's growing city sensor
The overgrown rainforest
Apex Center
To pray at the graves
Our family and
Killable youngboy
Wandering around
The Hillside Cinema
Walking through the grass
We we say prayers beaming offerings
Mr. Khan's family was Chinese
And they believed that if the dead were well taken
Care of it not only my peace for the Departed
It could also bring the wrecked
The Descendants
So Mister contest going as he got older
I'm going to the cemetery wasn't just a family affair it was a
Community
Function
Chinese migrants to Singapore
Set up Social Service organizations to help take care of their Community from the Cradle to the Grave and Beyond
Mr. Quan in his friends
Would wander the Untamed hillsides to the graves of their long-dead community
Members there they burn incense
Fake paper money
Things they thought that the dead might need in the afterlife
And then
They just hang out at the grave
So after the order prayers are said and done
We have a lovely meal of roast pork
Roast duck Sinnoh and so on and
It was a wonderful year and I when we kiss look
But you did actually
When you hear mr. Quan talk about going to the cemetery
You start to get why he enjoyed it
It was a nice change from the congestion
Cement
The city
And it wasn't just a natural scenery that was impressive
The tombs were amazing
People would spend a fortune on big elaborate Memorial
Stone lions and meticulous
Carving
Accenting Cemetery with sprawling
With these
Huge ornate tune
Lease at least 30 meters
30 meters brownies
Issue is about 33 yards you know
30 m wide
That could easily be bigger than a 3-bedroom hdb apartment
Today
Mr Quan is describing just a single family grave
On top of that
Text Anthony had a lot of shared Graves
One big Tombstone with Marcus huge area where members of a professional or social group
Burberry together
I packed something there was lots for all sorts of
We have elected
Retailers Association
Tupac's Atlas Associates
The opera singers Association
The
I mean you need me
An ideal Chinese tomb is supposed to be on a hill
So that the fortunes of the deceased
Can rundown
The future Generations
In China and in the Chinese diaspora
Stewart's Hill and Cemetery
Interchange
Saint of pets n Things
Means Health
The name translates to Pavilions on the Jade Hills a reference to the graveyards 12 covered structures
Where visitors could rest and eat after making offerings of the grave
Mr. Quan Remember Izzy's Pavilions well
But that doesn't mean he knew his way around the graveyard
With all those grand tombs the cemetery was enormous
324 Acres
That's about four times the size of Disneyland
And a country half
The size of LA
Sometimes
The driver of the Basel the lorry
Bringing us that would lose his way
We have to get some of the Villagers to come and guide us
When Mr Quan says they will get villagers to come out and guide them doesn't mean people from a nearby Village
He needs people
Live
In the graveyard
So people were kind of
Living among the tombstones is that correct
Yes yes
Yes
Text Santa
Was in fact a cemetery full of life
It was a self-sufficient Village
It's that began almost a hundred years before Mr Quan started
And members of Singapore's growing Cantonese
Is community realized I needed more space to bury their dead
They purchase land on what was then the edge of
Shifthound
And as the cemetery grew
So did the village
An active graveyard meant there were jobs to be had
Graves had to be dug tombstones carved
Refreshments sold to mourners
Show people built that group homes right there among the graves
It's actually happened in a lot of big Cemetery sets
Sprawled across a tiny Isle
The living just kind of
List alongside the Dead
By the 1970s Peck SanTan Village at almost 2000 Reznor
There was a large Chinese style gate at the entrance to the Village
Debilitated Town Clinic convenience stores with
That's Tintin Rouge there was a popular coffee shop and a dim-sum Eatery
And an open-air movie theater where people set under their umbrellas to watch films in the rain
Many of the residents work at a soy sauce factory in the village
Livestock was weird kids
Airborne and families race
All among the graves
Say what
I used to hang around a coffee shop
Ronda Rousey
Play
Play with marbles
Gumbo
That's Mister Lee
He just goes by Lee
And he grew up and text dancing Village
Ikids anywhere else on the island
And he climbs fruit trees and
Play hopscotch with his neighbor
The house was just a
A few houses over from the nearest grapes
Leave wasn't afraid to be living so close to
To the Dead
He did hear ghost stories
Since I was a child
All the people say
Ghost
Everywhere you go
Where was room
How many people died
Pulled Under by Whitley cause water goes
Attunement Pavilion 5 boasted to large Stone lion
Villagers would always complain that they came to life after dark and ate their chicken
But to lie and other villagers
Accenting
Was home
However
Life in a cemetery
Was about to change
As the hdb built more and more housing for Singapore's growing population
They realized
They needed more land
The Prime Minister explained it well
You don't have enough land for the living
The Dead mask
If we do the
1973 the government said there'd be no more ground Burial at over 70 Cemetery
Including percentage
A 1974
Those who died could only be buried at the
Single more sterile government runs
Cemetery 16 miles from the city center
Or for a fraction of the price
Could be cremated
Their ashes scattered or stored in a small
Iron
These were huge cultural changes
Not everyone was happy
But after the war in the nation's Independence a lot of singaporeans
We're willing to make sacrifice
Prices for the country's development
Acknowledge that burying people in big Graves just wasn't sustainable on a tiny Island
Also I kind of had to go along with the changes
Singapore has really limited freedom of speech
So when the government tells you to do something you don't have much choice
In 1978
It happened
The pet sensing Cemetery Association received a letter from the government
Saying a new
High-rise public housing development
What's going to be built on the cemetery
Their land was being rude
Remember they're basically two groups of people at Exxon thing
The dead and the living
And both were told that
Add four years to clear out
The people living in Pakistan think we're mostly relocated into new government housing nearby
But it took a while
A lot of the villagers weren't happy to leave
And they stayed as long as they possibly could
Sometimes a year is past the deadline the government gave them
To move
As for the Dead
In the association of family members who represented
They were eager to move either
Association wanted to find a way to
The keep a piece of their land
But no the longest
Prettiest
No more land area means no more
Len Barry
So that was it
So they hired a lawyer
And pleaded with the government to let them keep just
30 Acres of their original 324
Enough to have a temple and some administrative buildings
And to cremate
And build a columbarium
A building made to hold urns
Then all the sudden One Fine Day receive a letter
We wanted
30 Acres
And did what
Back to us
Antidote
We can only
Spell you a Takis
To the committee met and decide
It because better than the waitress
8 Acres was more than most Cemetery Scott
At least there would be room for a columbarium
A couple of other buildings
Still a hundred thousand bodies would have to be dug up from the cemetery
It was a huge daunting task
Lovi Poe
The advertisements in the newspaper
Telangana so common
Kiera Hogan
I wanted to use a whip
Basically
Resume degrees
They wrote letters to the families asking them to remove their good loved ones from what was about to be a construction site
But as the deadline approached
Only about half
Lansing's 100000 Graves had been on Earth
Bee Association members were at a loss as to what to do with a nearly 50,000 body still in the ground
Who would pay to dig up the graves cremate the bodies and give them another resting place
Association explain their predicament the Housing and Development
Book read to help them deal with the lingering dad
Which which is affecting of thorough
8/324 Acres of our land
Is he
Bacb and the cemetery Association hired people from the village to dig up the bodies
People like mr. Lee
The guy who grew up in the village at the xen thing
Please mom dad and brother all dug up Graves
Leawood walk behind
Carrying their Spades and tools
He studied how they remove the heavy soil from the grave and carefully broke the coffin
Then
He was ready to do it himself
Android
The Bones have sunken into the Earth
Scrape scrape scrape
Spades
To find a bones
Sometimes
Hello work is easy
We may spend about an hour looking at a tome
Pizza Hut job
3 to 4 hours
At first we was scared to dig
Any of the bodies were only just starting
How to decompose
Papillon
Icons on the shame to say it
Three criteria to be in this job
Bus
You have to have the Gaga
Second
Strength
The skill
So if you have no gas
That's the way you can do this job
After going to work on the hill
Diane and day out
She got the guts
Receipt
Again whooping are you on
Is futile to be frightened
You need to fulfill your application
Even if I'm frightened and alone
Istick need to complete the job
And he did
After years of begging
The 100000 bodies were all rooms
The half that were unclaimed were cremated together and Scattered at sea
And a solemn ceremony
Like many other living members of X and things
Lee and his family were re how stand in your buy hdds
Promotes the villagers the transition wasn't easy
Sure their housing was taken care of but you couldn't have a form in RI
Splatoon Stone carving Business Without burial
Libras lucky
He found work digging up other nearby cemeteries
That were also getting repossessed
Text something had been able to hold on to a taker
It was more than most people got
But wasn't much
Going from a 324 Acres Cemetery to 1/8 acre complex
The temple administration building in a columbarium for urns
Myspace had to be Maxima
There was also the issue of design Aesthetics
Foremost Chinese the tradition was Dewberry in Grand tombs
Like the ones at xen thing
When it came to building the columbarium.
Allstate Insurance
There's no real model
Harken back to
Columbariums were novel structure
Because the whole practice of cremation was pretty new to a lot of Chinese
Singaporean
Just 20 years earlier only 10% of the country's Chinese population
Mission was cremated
But by the time pek Sansing wanted to build their columbarium
That number was almost 70
Without much by way of architectural precedent for the columbarium
Apex hunting Association took a Gamble
They chose a somewhat controversial architect who cut his teeth designing brutalist superstructures
A modernist nametake hang soon
That project was
An interesting moment for me because I've been thinking about the problem of form
How do you
How do you modernize
And yet respect
The the traditions and the history and the
And Aesthetics of the bus
You certainly didn't want to build a warehouse
For the dad that he said would be antithetical to the quote nature loving and fengshui oriented ethos
A Chinese Berry
But it was days of problem of how to accommodate the number of
Nothing. Have to be
Interact within the columbarium
And so just like the Housing and Development board did when faced
The issue of overcrowding
Mr. tape
Belt
Up
From the outside it almost looks like any other new multi-story construction for the living
Before the columbarium opened in 1986
One newspaper said it could easily be mistaken
Bruh flashy new condominium
But the inside
Was different
Mr. T's columbarium stretches up over about nine different staggered levels
The building Rises gently the series of cascading stories and half stories
Forming cement pills
Like traditional Chinese tombs
The large windows and Skylight corridors
Made it sunny
Panera
Burns line the wall
From floor to ceiling
There was a waiting list of over 20,000 urns from the cemetery ready to move into pecs entangle and Bear
But nearby housing units for the living
Weren't so quick to get sold
As promised those hdb Flats were going up all over the grounds that are filled with dead bodies just
Couple years earlier
They called the development
Bichon
A mandarin version of the Cantonese
PacSun
Or Jade Hills
The new bishan development had everything the hdb imagined people needed
They opened a train stop
What Singapore cause Mass rapid transit or MRT
There were schools
Malls entertainment and easy access to the city
In other words
It was my ideal place to live
Except
For one thing
The ghost
Newspapers wrote about ghost sightings in bishan
The new MRT station there was known to be haunted by ghosts in the cemetery
Like apparently it was just common knowledge
Did you hear any stories
Everybody
China voice
Getting
Especially
The last train at night
There were reports of a ghostly woman who boarded the last
Train at bishan
And without Fanfare took off her head and put it on the
Next to her
Some passengers were known
Cast no reflection
On the train windows
Many of the residents who did move in
Didn't want any additional reminders of their neighborhoods McCobb history
The one tangible piece of evidence remain
One of the cemeteries covered Pavilion
Still stood near the new train station
Until the placenta Association got a call from the Housing and Development board
About
Shadows
Decedent
The races have been completed
They see Shadows at night
Around the Pavilion
Creepy
Ghostly shadow
What Shadows are they
I would like to stay one like that and then in the sea what are the Shadows
This coming really we were prepared to bring a cup of coffee and stay one night
Happy Davido Shadows
Dhdb told them the Pavilion would be demolished
Dissociation knew they had no say
The government already on the land
I had to oblige
Even if some of them weren't happy
The demolisher
Wasn't that funny voice acting
The last remaining structure
Optics hunting
To be demolished
And with that
All the physical remnants from the graveyard we're gone from the landscape
Cemetery was no longer a cemetery
It was a huge Urban Development
The multi-storey columbarium that people could easily avoid
If they wanted to
And
People forgot
QuickTime Bichon became an appealing place to live
Because he's already pregnant
I think the economic
Ahmad over rice
The spirituality behind so to speak, let's put it that way
People
Forget that this was a cemetery before
Many of the younger generation didn't even know of
Pick something symmetry really wants us there living on Summertree Lane
Many many other singaporeans live
On Old cemeteries whether they know it or not
So many other cemeteries were cleared for development and it still going on
Right now
Losing the cemeteries has forced a total one-eighty and how a lot of singaporeans think about dying
The first government crematorium opened in the early
60s about for cremations a week
Now more than 80% of singaporeans are cremated when they die
Substantially more than the US where that number is just over
50% and all of those Traditions that people like Mystic wanted
Burning offerings at having a feast at the grave
It had to be way down size
Lights to fit into the
The tight hallways
The columbarium
Today Singapore has for government-run columbarium
Pecan bariums also don't meet everyone's needs because they only house cremated from
Chinese are the ethnic majority in Singapore
35% of the population
And the country's Hindu Community as long practice cremation
But most of the country's large male Community practices Islam which doesn't permit cremation
So in 2007 the Singapore government implemented their new Crypt
Ariel sister
It's a prefabricated series of interlocking concrete walls
Like a deathly grid
Assembled above ground and then sunk into the Earth
But you only get 15 years in your own grave
Now you have to be consolidated
Ab216 bodies
Per grade
All this rearranging of the Dead
Has been a painful change for a lot
Singaporean
But there was also a widespread understanding
But something had to give in order to get so many people their own homes
On such a tiny Island
And
Let us be practical I mean
Symmetry Boutique
Couch Lance Bass
End
Deadline space
In my opinion
Must be sacrificed
And the Singaporean people did sacrifice
Not just the land
But centuries of rituals and traditions for their debt
All ticket homes
For the living
This cultural shift happen without a lot of resistance from the Singaporean people
But that is changing
I will talk to Katie Thornton about that
After the break
So I'm in the studio with Katie Thornton and I want to follow up on
What things are like
In Singapore today
I would almost everyone
Has some form of housing will there be
Public or private
Today there's a lot of infrastructure for
And there are only a few historic cemeteries left in the entire country
And all of them are slated to be developed
So like it still
They're still trying to take as much of that land is
Is possible
Yeah totally so like there's one other Cemetery that has actually been getting a lot of
Attention lately
It's called bukit Brown and it's another Chinese Cemetery
A lot of prominent early Chinese Singaporean businesspeople and philanthropist are buried at bukit Brown
There are a ton of those
Cornet tombstones like the one with the Quan describe
At the site
What are you going to do about those
Well in 2011
The government announced that they're going to
Expand a highway
Right through the cemetery and that Highway opened earlier this year
They had to remove 4000 Graves and a lot of the Tombstones were thrown away
And just like that text something the government said that they had to come and clear out the graves
Or the remains will be scattered at sea
Pretty upset like at this point is one of the only remaining cemeteries
Indian Tire
Country bunch of volunteers story instead of advocating for the preservation of the society leading tours and academics.
Involves and documenting the space
And it really spoke to people like
Grumman do you remember Hoon
Yes she was the
The person that was in the peace that
Was historian but she saw ghosts when she was a
The kid
Yeah totally would she just mentioned
Lake very casually
She had this job at the time she's working for a theater company and choose
He's doing a lot of traveling around
And sometimes when she was traveling should go and visit big like
Famous Destination type of cemetery
Eminem Road was announced she was like Hey I've never been to poop
Brown maybe I'll check it out I mean it's my own backyard
And then she went and it was like
Cut
Scene change
She totally changed her career
And why was this the thing that really really
Mater want to change everything what is she
Care so much
For some reason it just didn't really sit well with her that people who never play
Planned on being cremated and thrown into the sea might end up there
So she just wanted families to know if they had ancestors buried at 3
Because a lot of people had lost track so she quit her job and she put together all these family trees
Menchie's
Cold call The Descendants
And tell them that a grave of say their great-grandmother was going to be dug up
Remember Graves where she was like so sure that you could find The Descendants
But you would talk to the government and be like please wait wait like don't think up this tomb yet I can find the family
And then she would and should stay in touch with them and help them throughout
The whole process
Stand alongside the family is us
They dug the body
He's up and move them elsewhere
And she still doing it
Even after the road opened earlier this year
She's still working to document the space
She's been living off her savings for 8 years to do the work
Because she's worried that the rest of the cemetery is going to be developed
And also history will be lost
But she does think that there was
A time where maybe it made
Sense to develop over these faces to get living people's needs Med
But
The times a little bit different now
Like I asked her I asked you in about text hunting
And I'll tell you a little bit of tape about what she said
Yeah at the point at that point I'm definitely I mean
Uuuuu
Go for
Having high rise building to house.
People rather than to have
Cemetery for the Dead
Yes I'd like at that time she definitely saw it as
FedEx change indirect exchange between the living and the dead
But you feel like times are kind of
Different now like men might be possible to
Preserve
View old spaces on the island
So again like this is what she said about that
There was a need for it before
Is test you that need now
You know so it's like it is like
If this is gone and erase
Not replaceable and irreversible
We are talking about retaining a part of our heritage
You know
Did your opinion
About
The role of cemeteries
In life change
I think that cemeteries are these interesting and complicated historic sites there
Kind of an opportunity
People to inscribe
Their history on the landscape there's certainly like Rife with exclusions as well
People that excluded from Cemetery spaces
Based on their race based on their religion
Based on their class and their inability to access
Sammy like a large
Tombstone
But I think it's
They also present kind of an interesting opportunity to
Complicated history because they're kind of
More accessible archives than a lot of our historic archives
99% Invisible by Katie Thornton and edited by Katie Mingle
To Katie's mix into production by Sharif Youssef music by Sean real
Kurt Kolstad is the digital director the rest of team is
Senior editor at Delaney Hall Avery Chapman
Keith Orton is a Fulbright National Geographic
Digital storytelling fellow who makes audio and writing about how and where we remember the dead in our changing world
Her project is called death in the digital age you can find it online at hits Katie Thornton. Com
On Instagram at its Katie Thornton
This week on Instagram and sharing stories from
Voice changing Memorial landscape
Voice over by Mike go from ageless theater special thanks to
Kuikku
Presto cool guy
We are project at 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
Beautiful downtown Oakland
California
99percentinvisible is a member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most in it
Native shows in all of podcasting by mall
Radiotopia. FM
You can find the show enjoying discussions about the show on Facebook including me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
When Instagram and write it to
But we have a columbarium
Design stories with audio and visual
A99ii
. org
Radio 2