Thanks for the Robert Wood Johnson
Foundation for underwriting this special two-part series about the power of sound to affect
And influence our health and well-being
The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation is working alongside other is to build a culture of Health for everyone in America
Learn more about the
At rwjf
. org
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Sound can have serious impacts
Our health and well-being
And ever since people moved into cities we've been exposed to an unhealthy amount of noise
Cars power lines and a constant ding of our devices
We live in a very noisy world
Most of the noises we hear aren't designed to work together
This is the second part of our special series on sound and health supported by the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
We're taking a look at how I more intentional approach
The sound can help us live better healthier lives
And there's no better place to think about health
Vet hospitals
Is an anesthesiologist at Vanderbilt Medical Center
He spends a lot of his time in the operating room
The operating room is an inch
Christian space
Cuz we think of it it's like my cockpit if you will and anesthesiology
Related a lot to Aviation
We are culture of safety we have safety checklist just like Pilots do
We think of takeoff and Landing just like putting a patient to sleep and waking them up
If I can wake someone up from anesthesia we call it land in the plane
Landing the plane takes Focus
Hangzhou doesn't work in silence
It might come as a surprise but in the OR
There's music playing all the time
There's great data that shows that music improve surgical efficiency which can translate to an economic benefit
And music subjectively makes us feel good
And if you're working long hours being difficult
Court cases in the operating room
If you can improve mood certainly there's benefit
Who chooses the music
It's usually the surgeon
And if the surgeons excited the surgery is over and the Music Volume gets cranked up
It's really hard for us to be delicate and intentional and Artful
Elegant
Joe remembers one surgery where music was playing and then all the sudden
The patient's Vital Signs started the crash
Now my alarms are going off the music volume is high
The surgeon and I are having to raise our voices and almost yell at each other to communicate
Not because we're mad at each other
But just to understand each other
So Joan is researchers are trying to figure out how to get the benefits of Music in the OR
Without the risk of hearing we built this city on rock and roll
Well someone is having a heart attack
I'm working with another anesthesiologist on a device which is called the canary box
The canary box has two levels of alarm
Warning Zone and the danger zone
When the alarm is in the warning Zone
It haves
The Music Hall
And when the alarm is in the danger zone
It turns the music off
Fixing house sounds work together in the operating room is a step in the right direction
But it's part of a bigger problem
Doctors know more about the human body than ever
And are better equipped
To save your life
But still
Hospitals are horrible places to get bed
That sound designer Joel Beckerman
And he's right
Hospitals can be bad for your health because hospitals
Sound
Terrible
I think of when I walk into the neuro ICU and I hear the automatic door was open
Closes
If people walk by it opens and closes without
Anyone going in or out
And as I walk in there's the
How about people talking
And it might be clinicians in might be patient
Families
I hear the
Rolling of the
Big metal cart that houses all the meals for the patients
And it's the wheels rolling on the hardwood floor
Yochelson is electronic musician
Researching sound in hospice
Linux
Claudius
It's about
50 decibels
Pretty rose
It goes up
Yeezy 360 70-30 sometimes it hits 8290 this place as well
TV some perspective 60 decibels is the volume of an average office
70 decibels is about as loud as a vacuum cleaner 80 decibels is as loud as a garbage disposal
And 90 decibels is as loud as a motorcycle passing by your so-called
Healing environment
Hospitals can be really loud
But volume isn't the only problem
I hear alarms coming from multiple patient rooms
And I don't know what's wrong with the patients
The alarms are difficult to localize so I'm not sure which rooms they're coming from
And even when he knows what he's listening
Joe has a hard time figuring out what device is making noise
It could be the IV infusion pump
The epidural pump
The intra-aortic balloon pump the dialysis machine with ventilator
Joel Beckerman has experienced the same thing in hospital sees work done
There is a heart monitor that makes 86
It's different alarms
There's no way that
That can be meaningful to anybody
The scary thing is
Most of these alarms
Are false alarm
It could be due to a loose connection or a temporary blip in the patient's vital signs
But most of these alarms don't tell you anything useful
Still they saturate
The hospital sounds game
I go home at night
And I still hear the beeping of alarms in the beeping of pulse oximetry in my head
Clinicians are notified
Physician's assistant
I love those alarms like I have my address but I get excited
But the high from alarms is not sustainable it's actually pretty exhausting
The result is something called alarm fatigue
The problem with alarm fatigue is
That didn't sound which caregivers and
Learn to ignore
Means that they also ignore critical alarm
And patients die
This is a very very serious problem that needs to be addressed
People complain it's difficult to sleep at night
Distance to sleep it disturbs the arrest
Noisy environment
Could cause more anxiety Sofia and stressful patients
NBC
You know that young
Oh no
Is my baby going to die
You can lead to neuropsychological side effects such as
ICU delirium
ICU delirium is when patients get confused and paranoid because of the exhaustion of staying in.
Sometimes this can lead to hallucinations
The 80% of patients in an ICU I thought to experience some form of delirium during their Hospital stay
It's the sort of thing that can leave hospital patients
With PTSD
I interviewed
Person
Key hat
Peace
Daughter in Amazon 10 years ago in NICU
Betsy in ICU intensive care for infants
And there was this particular alarm sounds that kept going off
So even after
Tenias
If he hears
The sound steps
Simatai
To that on television or other places
He still gets
Disturbed reaction
There a long-lasting effects on the body as well as the mind
Noisli
It's the stress and stress hormones in the body
Stiffen our blood vessels
Which can increase the risk of heart attack
Disgrace
Unnecessary noise is the cruelest absence of care
Realtor that more than a hundred years ago
But I'm guessing hundred years ago there was no
Mustangs in medicine progress
It's like a side effect
Technological advancement
Things got louder
Right now you can't turn alarms
Softer
Silence.
But the FDA maintains a database
Found that
Nearly 600 Payson
Had adverse outcomes
Mostly.
From alarm mismanagement
We'll talk about how we can make the sound design of Hospital alarms as sophisticated and precise as the medical
Cool devices that are blaring the mouth
After this
Support for this special two-part series
Exploring the power of sound to influence our health
Comes from the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation is working to build a culture of Health that ensures everyone in America
Has a fair and just opportunity for health and wellbeing
Which includes exploring how our current or future environment
Will impact daily life
Learn more at rwjf
. org
When you think of the design of a patient monitor or any device
You think of the visual complexity of the device
And expensive the device
But why is the sound that's generated by this
Highly engineered visually attractive expensive device
Usually comes out of a very cheap speaker
Attached
Medical device
At least
Dissonant
Difficult
As a musician
At least
But you'll go isn't the only one taking a musical approach
Alarm fatigue
Joe may be an anesthesiologist but he's also a professional jazz musician
Infuriating isn't it
This is him playing the piano right now
I've been playing the piano since I was 5 years old
So the music and medicine was part of my life
Together for a long time
Right now alarms are loud and annoying
But they don't have to be
They just have to be different from all the other sounds in the hospital
Imagine that somebody down the hall where to scream
And it's not loud but you can perceive it
We have our attention diverted
Not because of the volume but because of the acoustic features of the human scream
There's an acoustic feature called roughness
Which has enhanced sensitivity in the Invicta
So we have this
Reflexive response
This has a surprising implication
4 alarm tone
Alarms
Can be softer than background noise and you can still perceive them
A lot of the alarms
Have
What's called a flat amplitude envelope and Sophie imagine the emergency broadcast signal that you
UCare on TV
That's a flat amplitude on for a minute on natural sound and R&B
The unnatural sound is effective at driving or attention
But in a hospital these unnatural sounds
Layer on top of each other
Creating a wall of sound that we tune out
Elsa create a struct
Harming our minds and bodies
Pair that
With what's called a percussive amplitude envelope which has an exponential.
The case I think about if you're clinking to wine glass
Together
That's
A sharp upstroke with an exponential decay Nexus and we have in nature
By changing the amplitude envelope
To something more natural
You can go from this
To this
But even this sound
Doesn't tell you a lie
The alarms need to be more
Informative
What we are particularly working on is how to contain information and sound
And that is what we call auditory icon
For example having a lub dub
Heartbeat type of sound in an alarm that is indicative of a cardiovascular problem
The result is something that can tell you exactly what's wrong
Before you enter the room
And that's just the beginning
I don't want to know just when something is bad
I want to know when something is trending
Chords being bad
I want
Visual signals that are always in my receptive field
Prices of monitor that right now I have to
Baby staring at it
I want vibrotactile information that is wearable and comfortable
And I wanted to provide
Signals that are not so strong that it gets
Geek
Or habituated to it
And I want auditory information
That is directed
To me when I get auditory information
It's
Information that can mean something in that I need to act upon it
Then we can use the hospital soundscape to do even more
Researchers are finding ways to give a voice
Is the people
Love lost
You think of a patient in the ICU when they're non-communicative
Or in long-term
Q care
Does patient often get neglect
But they
Have ways to communicate in a non-traditional sense for example to the autonomic nerves
Patients who can't speak or communicate their feelings are still expressing themselves
To their heart rate or their body temperature
So they're communicating but not in a traditional verbal sense
How can we take this physiologic
Signals
Turn them into sound in a way that we can start to ask your team
What these patients
What is people
Rst
The result is something called Bayou Music
Pioneered by
A colleague of Jose at McGill University in Montreal
Sensors on the patient's body to text vital signs
And that makes the data into sound
Heart rate controls the tempo
Temperature determines the notes
And skin sweat
Drives the melody
The result is actually kind of beautiful
Bayou Music is being looked at as a way for nonverbal autistic children to express themselves
Here's a calm State of Mind
And here's the Nexus One
You don't have to be a medical specialist to hear the difference
Our hope is that
We can make it easy to implement throughout the world where you don't have to be at Bay
High-powered academic institution with PSEG equipment to make this a reality
Joel Beckerman believes our Hospital soundscapes can be improved
From an unhealthy and dangerous cacophony
To something more useful
Imagine you could walk into a room
And
Be able to sit through enormous data sets
By sound alone
We actually create an idealized
Soundscape for what
Personification of data
Idea might be in
A hospital room of the future
Cardigan
Sounds good
You don't need to be musician you don't need to be really intensely trained for this
You can determine whether a pitch is higher than another were lower than another if they're pretty far apart
You can determine whether a sound is rising or sound is
Falling
A very very short period of time we can help
People understand
Those differences
Do all different
Healthcare data points
Do understand
What a patient
Needs for weather. Patient is okay and they can turn their attention elsewhere
When I was a music score
Piano teacher told me the more you actively listen to Jazz and you practice
You're adding colors to your palette
The more I study the more I practice the more I listen I have more colors on my palette
I can create a beautiful painting
That's another reason why we need to do this is cuz this adds colors to a pallet
And I think it's important
From the patient care perspective that we make the most beautiful painting that we can create
This special episode of 99% invisible was produced by Layla battison and Dallas Taylor
With help from Sam Snead play
Edited by Chris brunelle
Sound design
Buy Colin devarney
Music by genre
Thanks also to our guests
Yochelson and Joe Schlessinger
Special thanks to the Robert Wood Johnson foundation and man-made music who contributed as exec
And providing the soundscapes in the show
Sonic Boom how sound transforms the way we think feel and by
Go check it out
You can learn more about these stories and other topics related to Sun ecumenism and sounds effects on our health
I visiting info.
Sonic humanism. Com
Thanks again to the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
Their underwriting support of this special series
Learn more about their efforts to help create a culture of Health
At rwjf