Thanks to the Robert Wood Johnson
Foundation for underwriting this special two-part series about the power of sound to affect
And influence our health and well-being
The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation is working alongside other is to build a culture of Health for everyone in America
Learn more about the
At rwjf
. org
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Nearly everywhere we go
We're bombarded with
Human-made sound
It's especially bad Insidious
Cities in the past
Think about where you have
Horses
And Buggies clapping you here
Banging of wood against
Stone
Very noisy experiences
Best Joel Beckerman
He's a composer and founder of a Sonic branding and design company
Called man-made music
Then cars came along and we're sharing the road
With these horses
And so not only did you have
Horses at 1 rate of speed the cars at a different rate of speed so lots of honking
Of the horns
It must have been
Cacophonous mess
But things got even worse when cars came to dominate the road
You fast-forward to
Really
What the soundscapes were let's say in the 50
So in the fifties it was all about muscle cars
It was all about the loudest car you could have the Mustangs
Corvettes that were really really loud
We might not have muscle cars anymore but our cities are still noisy places
We're pretty good at tuning it out
But our Sonic environments have serious impacts
Are mental and physical health
So is the blurring modern soundscape
Movie killing us
This is part one of a two-part series
All about how sound can be designed create more well-being
And reduce harm
We really respond
To sound quicker than the other since it really becomes the Arbiter of all our sense
But many of the sounds we hear are created with very little thought for how they interact with each other
They could be a byproduct
Like engine sounds of a computer
Or they could be made intentionally like alarms or cell phone pings
At the doctor
Sound
Overhead planes
Air conditioning unit
Patios in stores
Pumping up music
Sirens and people talking loudly to be heard over the rest of the noise
You have truck
Buses other kinds of Transit and then unit mechanical things like Construction
Of course
Americar
The sound of cars
Is kind of inescapable which is
Depressing if you think about it
Has Kate Wagner you might know her from her fantastic blog mcmansion hell
Xi'an architecture and design critic and she cares a lot
About sound
Cars
Tend to drown out
Other things like Birdsong human speech
The rustling of leaves
Conversation things that maybe
Armored personnel are like Kelly Hold and it higher like aesthetic value
Joel Beckerman says we need a new approach to sound
One where we decide what we hear in our everyday environment
Really about
How do we
Use Music and Sound
To make people's lives richer and simpler
Joel wants sound to be something we're thinking about all the time
What cities have more noise laws than ever
Over half of the world's population live in urban areas experiencing
Way too much noise
Sound is measured in decibels
The louder the sound the higher the number
Quiet library is around 40.
B-52 8790. Supposed to be really close to the highway
The decibel scale isn't linear that means 80 decibels
Isn't twice as loud as 40 it's actually
10000 times louder
If you have to pull over on the side of the highway
This may be a flat tire or something
The sheer noise that
You hears
Play starlink
Of sound that is an 8 Lane Highway
The average level of car noise in a busy City
It's about the same as having your TV on at top volume
All the time
Some silly noises are designed to be loud
Police sirens and ambulance sirens
120 decibels
We might try to escape all this by sticking in a pair of headphones and cranking up the volume
But depending on what you're listening to
Headphones can be over 90s
Prolonged exposure to anything over 80 decibels
Will lead to hearing
So before we go any further
What we're talking about the idea of
Sound and health
Do yourself a favor
Get into a little bit quieter area
And turn this episode down a couple of notches
Your ears will thank you
When it comes to City sound volume is not the only thing
Not just how loud the sound is its
The character of the sound
It's whether or not you have control over the situation
That's Erica Walker
She's a researcher at the Boston University School of Public Health in a Robert Wood Johnson Foundation grantee
For Erica
Impact of sound
Is all about contacts
I live in an apartment building and above me where these neighbors and they had two small kids
And the kids used to run across the floor 24 hours a day
The sound wasn't more than 50 or 60 decibels that's the same volume as
The background music in a coffee shop
But Erica could feel that sound
Every moment
Of every day
I think for different people as different things but for me it was the rumbling it's that low frequency sound
You can't hear it but you know it's there
And you don't know where it's coming from but you can feel it
Living so close together we're going to make sounds that will cross over into other
People's faces
And that's not always bad
It's one of the reasons why I love living in sin
Sun Communities
Say that they appreciate the sound levels like they like hearing their neighbors
At the barbecue because it makes it feel like a sense of community so there is a positive aspect
But when we don't have control
That's what health problems start
Matthias basner is a professor at the University of Pennsylvania
He said he's out noise affects our sleep
The noises stress
Especially if we have little or no control over it
And so the body will
Discrete stress hormones like adrenaline
Cortisol that lead to changes the composition of our blood
And of our blood vessels
I would text you have been shown to be stiffer after a single night of noises
Exposure
People who are irrelevant
Exposed for prolonged period of time have an increased risk
For cardiovascular disease including high blood pressure
And myocardial infarction
But also in some studies high risk of
Stroke
A myocardial infarction by the way is another term for a heart attack
Aldovia risk increases are relatively mild
Relative to other exposures like smoking
King for example
This still constitutes a major public health problem because so many people are exposed
These different noise sources
And the World Health Organization published a report on the
Burden of disease
By environmental noise
And they base
Sukisho that in the Western European member states alone
1.6
Million healthy life years are lost
Every year
Due to the exposure to environmental noise
There's a study from the University of Michigan that looked
The effect of lowering sound exposure by 5 decibels
That could save
3.9 billion dollars in healthcare costs
And it would also save lives
There are so many other ways that noisy environments are bad for you
Think about allowed rest
There's a sound of the open bar
Puppy music
Your shouting at your friend
Everyone else is shouting at their friends too
Pretty stressful
And when we get stressed
Studies show we reach for comfort food
And alcohol
Academic performance
Are mood hurt or concentration basically
We are being killed by noise
And some of us
Or being killed faster than others
More after this
Support for this special two-part series exploring the power of sound to influence our health
Comes from the Robert Wood Johnson found
The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation is working to build a culture of Health that ensures everyone in America has a fair
And just opportunity for health and wellbeing
Which includes
Exploring how our current or future environment
Will impact daily life
Learn more at rwjf
. org
We know noise causes health problems but they can be especially pronounced
If you live in a less affluent neighborhood
If we live in a place for example with lots of environmental noise as do many people in American cities especially people
Bose color and low income families
Then we have to deal with essentially
Does mechanical
Sound
That can shave off sort of the high frequencies
History repeated
Relentlessness
Neighborhoods near factories highways in Flight paths
And usually they're the least expensive places to live
This is a noise equity
Problem
We should have the choice
Living in a space that is not doing damage to us
Without having to move
We should have the agency to Good Health good hearing health
We should have agency
Over
The things that could harm us essentially
The most obvious solution is to make laws
Some cities car about quiet hours
You can't run a noisy leaf blower or
Practice grooming in your garage at night or else you'll get fined
But there's a couple of problems with noise abatement laws
One thing
They're often used to Target
Vulnerable people
Noise abatement lawsuit of always
Singled out
Powerless people
People who
Livelihood is impeded
Middle class
Station
A quiet or orderly or bustling City Etc sort of like what the ideas
What the ideal soundscape would be for the city
The very first restrictions on city noise
Came in the early 20th century
Tree in New York
A rich woman named Julia Barnett rice campaign to silence the horns and whistles
Tugboats in the nearby Forest
All these noises were bothering her and her Riverside mansion
It's not hard to see the thread of connection from someone
Like Julia Barnett rice and someone like
BBQ Becky the white woman who called the police on a black family having a barbecue
Last year in Oakland
It was the beginning of what we call gentrification which is
Is pushing out those
Rely on the city for work in order to satisfy these sort of aesthetic tastes of the wealthier people who depend
Chickens were more of a concern to those in power
This is very much both a literal and a Sonic
Displacement
Is that they aren't very effective
So the way we currently
Regulate
Measure sound
That's Erica Walker
Remember the decibel measures how loud something is
The moose sound meters only listen to a specific range of frequencies
The kind that we hear with our ears
That's called in a weighted system
Does a weighted system that tells us that is only the sound so we process to the auditory system that are important
But there are some sounds we don't process with our ears
Once the pitch gets low enough we no longer hear it but feel it is that
Sweetly vibrational so is essentially that feeling so
When you're in a community that's in a flight path and you say it's
65 a weighted decibels
Your
Trappin out the components that come from
The lower frequency sound so you're leaving out
Story
Not only is it a flawed metric that using this metric to determine who's eligible for soundproofing criteria
Erika is working on a project called the community noiselab
And she hopes that by
Taking a much wider range of frequencies into a Canon
We can get a better grasp
How sounds are affecting our neighborhoods and our health
In the meantime
Kate Wagner says that there are steps everyone can take to make things sound a little better
Acoustics changes to the spaces here in
There are certain architectural and design choices that we can make to make our spaces a little bit quieter
Going to be 50 installation or have a footing for any other service
Expensive Solutions
Isolating noise
Get off sticker curtains which is cool because velvet is in
Velvet curtains might be a solution to noise problems in her home
But addressing the noise from cars and Industry requires a fundamental change to the way we live
Austin
The things that are making the most noise especially sort of industrial noise
Are the things that are
Perhaps not exactly the healthiest
For the environment for example
Takes a lot more noise to have a natural gas plant or drill or do what have you for any kind of
Extractive purposes and it does to have a solar farm which is almost entirely silent
The quietest City I've ever been in that was a major city was Helsinki in Finland
I was astonished because
The Metro are the subway trains and the buses and what not their silence
The
Train station
Are very quiet
That's partly because the majority of their trains are electric
But it's also down to the design of their station
From a mixture of materials sound absorbing materials and also psychoacoustic tricks like pumping in noise
That has this weird reverse
Effect of making things seem quieter which is a technique used in offices as well
The fins are able to make
Spaces quieter in
That idea that they should be quieter
Seems to be more popular there
Prepster quieter public spaces play a small part in making Finland reportedly
The happiest country in the world
It's a country that is
So taken into account
The public good
From all aspects
Things like Health Care Child Care Social Services
Robust
Welfare state and things like their outlook on sustainability
So cleaner quieter Vehicles make you happier
And when things are less noisy
Is a great opportunity
Please create a richer and more useful
Sonic landscape
Electric cars don't naturally make a sound
So if you've ever had one creep up on you
It's a really really scary experience
Joel Beckerman says
This Silence of electric cars
Can actually be a drawback
Total silence is not a good thing
Joel says that electric cars need to make noise
Or else they won't be safe
It's not the people in the car it's for the pedestrians to know that the car is coming
But the opportunity
Also to create a personality
For the vehicle for the electric vehicles
He actually worked with Nissan
How to create an identity
For their new electric car
Here it is coming right at you
In this case what we were looking to do was
Create
A car that had a personality which is really in association with clean energy
One of the things we know is it's going to be frictionless
When you hear a car
Accelerate
If it accelerates
It's very quickly let's say
And there is a sense of
Really smoothness
Lack of friction
There is a
Almost in natural ambience
To it
We actually used
Natural sounds
It still sounds like a car and it absolutely had to because we don't have to destrian to hear it and say oh what's that
Get hit by the car
Joe wants a future city dominated by natural sound
It also sounds that we consciously chosen
Some cities are already taking a more thoughtful approach
In the Tokyo subway station
Each station
Has a little tune associated with it
And if you know anything about the Japanese subway system it is packed
So if you're in the middle of a car
And you miss an announcement because it's noisy
Your son
You're going to miss your stop
The Tokyo trains have a short jingle
Unique to each and every station along the line
Like this one
Pre-K bukuro station
On the yamanote line
These little Tunes
That
Show up at each station
Helps you understand where you are
And also their pleasing their they're not a screening announcement
We could live in cities full of intentional sound
What's soundscapes that we've chosen
Really annoying
The nice thing is
You get to decide that for yourself
Because you'll be able
The mall
This special episode of 99% invisible was produced by Layla battison and Dallas Taylor
Help from Samsung
Edited by Chris Berube
My calendar
Music by genre
Special thanks to the Robert Wood Johnson foundation and man-made music
Who contributed as executive producers
And providing the soundscapes in the show
The sonic boom How Sound transforms the way we think feel and buy
Go check it out
You can learn more about these stories and other topics related to Sun ecumenism and sounds effects on our health
I visiting info.
Sonic humanism. Com
Thanks also to Our Guest Kate Wagner Erica Walker and Matias Bassinger
Can you find out more about Erica's community noiselab
A community noiselab. Org
Thanks again to the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
Other underwriting support of this special series
Learn more about their efforts to help create a culture of Health
At rwjf