99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
Is it 99percentinvisible where we are
I Roman Mars my name is Heinrich Boll Heinrich Boll became president the San Francisco chapter of the American Institute of Art
Architects in 1968
And we're having this conversation at the base of the Transamerica Pyramid construction to Transit
America pyramid began in 19
69 looking up into the building
The best view of of the building
In the beginning
Heinrich Boll and the Transamerica Pyramid
Did not
Get along
And the same
Cisco AIA opposed
Construction
Building should make sense
There's nothing about this building to make sense or sort of a silly
Design dunce cap we thought
Pyramid shape was
Nothing but
Hey
Let's call it advertising simple the top third of it
Just
Playing are in the era of Modern Art
Texture
Building
A couple of hundred
Beat
Symbol
Not
Considered
Proper Rd tomorrow
In an article in late 2009
San Francisco Chronicle Urban Design Rider John King summarized
Several
Of the Contemporary criticism
Transamerica
Pyramid
Does Kobe know that's right
Inhuman creation
Chanclas World's Fair
Space Needle assemblyman John Burton said the pyramid would rape
The skyline
It seemed to violate the
The whole purpose of zoning in Irvine
Buildings were no more than
This was Def
Division
Of that neighborhood
But over the course of 40 years
Something happen
Some people have never lost their hatred for the TransAmerica
Repairman
But other is like Heinrich balm and the AIA San Francisco who recently voted at 1
Top commercial buildings in the city
I've done a complete 180
And it all seems
Depend
From where you're standing
You could almost say
The further you get away from it the better it looks
And be certain nasty it's only a little nasty
And funny
Entry when the building
Was completed
Many of us
Who had a post
Realize that
Surfing need building on the skyline
Especially as a silhouette
The sun's going down
It's really quite right
The taller building since
Really
Pretty dull
And this
I know it wasn't dumb
I don't remember
Any discussion
Have
What is going to look like
Looking out
Columbus Avenue
Columbus Avenue is it diagnosed read
And
Abroad
TransAmerica building is right at the end
I don't know if you know the term
Vanishing point
Active
Everything
Goten diagnose 2A
Quite
And in a way
You tilt that vanishing point
Up vertically
And there's the TransAmerica building
It just is a big surprise
And had that been
Conventional
Modern building
Of the time
It would have been
Tragedy really
Say it's one of my favorite buildings
Not close up how it meets the ground I don't think
Never really got solved the triangle shapes in the columns are awkward
And if you look up at the building from Below
The spacing of the windows has to be
Pretty weird to accommodate that pyramid shape
Still a complete 180 I think that's really impressive
Strength of character
I had that same conversation with John King that's the affirmation San Francisco Chronicle architecture
Ridiculous article on this View
Really, really was quite surprised but I said that we didn't understand the problem and we were wrong and they said
Flashlight don't think I remember
And I say that before
99% invisible is produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar it's a project of kalw
The American Institute of Architects San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
Find out more at 99percentinvisible.
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
A movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com