99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars our modern world is determined by them
The Architects the designers they decide how you experience the physical world
But ubiquity of smartphones with GPS and compass and networking more computing power than we know what to do with
Has created this new space reality
Why on top of the physical real world it's an augmented reality and it adds a whole
Whole new level of creativity and design to the everyday world
Augmented reality uses the smartphone's camera
Attorney application to get the augmented reality button
When you look through your phone's camera at the now labeled and visible
Stars and planets in the daytime sky
Another app popup cool infographics with details about a bridge or a building
It's still in its infancy
The possibility of experiencing a hidden world on top of the world in front of you
Tantalizing so full of potential
I personally like to augment my reality
With sound
And that brings us to the musical smartphone app
Call rjdj
We are you know combining the world around you with your listening experience
As the founder of rjdj
DJ Michael breidenbach
So you know
The door closes
And something really amazing acoustic
Kaley Cuoco
Robert Thomas is one of our jdjs
Composers
Create swap
Week-old reactive music
84 mile
Changes
Toyota
Rjdj is comprised of scene
Which are analogous
Songs
But they're more like
Instructions
Are bits of music
Code for the Phone Zone Dalton synthesizer
Audio
Filters and these are triggered by the user
According to the composer
Plan
For the scene
Composing think of all these different
Possible ways to
I'm listen to
Try to come up with looks different ways
But that will
Create json
I'm very interested
Play the music
When the
Sound
Coming in from the field surrounding his is very glad you could have lots of really fine at Sky
Dudududu dudududu dudududu
So it sounds for the mic change the song to put the accelerometer in the phone that's the thing that senses movement time spent listening to
Show me a factor and even GPS data can be incorporated
In all these stimuli work in concert to create a unique
Augmented reality
And the way you look
Sprinter City
Ruby alter
From its basic form
I mean walked around with music playing in your
But those moments of musical synchronicity that changed
How you saw and felt about your surroundings
Imagine that
* 1000
Right now rjdj is mainly ambient pop and structured Noise by imagine what it could be
The world will become a playground
For interaction designers
It kind of feels like
Still seeing some in a beauty in everything
The most famous
Sofia Carson
Harmonica for reality
I had my wife may put on these patented white earbuds
To check out one of the scenes
The first time
Do do do-do-do-do
It's what a steel girder would hear up a steel girder can hear
Kind of like being in
Horror movie but not quite horrible
Present putting on a set of headphones
Block out the rest
The world rjdj listeners
Plug into a
Constantly
Changing Unique Sounds
Next
What they're doing
And where they are in the world
Imagine
Walking around San Francisco
Listening to a Mastiff
Composition of punk and Hip-Hop it gives me a history of the neighborhood I'm traveling
And a GPS will trigger a sound clip
Set from Alfred Hitchcock's vertigo
But I passed through Nob Hill
Do I need to do spells this week
I'm having one right now
Play the music from the tempo
Speed up as I
Scary out of the way of an obnoxious bike messenger
Is the path of an unnoticed oncoming cable car
My sudden lack of all movement
Line of payment
Pleasing harmonica
Drone from the iPhone ear
Which one makes beautiful
The sirens
The paramedic
99percentinvisible is produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar it's a project of kalw The Americans
Institute of
San Francisco in the center for Ark
Texture and Design
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com