99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
Visit 99 percent invisible
I'm running more the details are not the details
They make the design
John Adams
Coding legendary designer
Charles Eames
I'm John Hanson president
There's a conception in the public I think that
Design is a lot about making things pretty that shifting I think there's a big DIY
Why movement maker movement and people are getting a better sense of how things come to be we've always known how kind of buildings can
Navigate to Speed wash them go up
The products just kind of appear on the store shelf from somewhere from China
Right
But I really loved the process of design and love
Bringing things to life
The story that I want to tell
About the details that go into product make
Is about a tooth
But there's a bit of
Comfort Inn Ventura
Just released the perception
That requires that the
So I asked Matt Martin
Michaela
What matters
Tami Roman
Is that you are
About the fact
The John Edson
The present of lunar
Lunar under eyes
Same time you got complete editorial control
Over
How 99percentinvisible sound
So what do you think
You know what he said
This is the story of a toothbrush
Pressing is getting a design out there in the world and a prototype
For the other people can look at it
You can test it
You can evaluate it and then you can decide what you're going to do next
And it really is good
This kind of forced
Evolutionary
Reprocess
So the toothbrush company came to lunar with what John Edson cause a make
Pretty extra make
Pretty exercise
That's not really Innovation how do people hold toothbrush
But the toothbrush company didn't actually know this
So we engaged a hand
Kinesiology
But somebody who knows how people hold stuff it turns out there are five common to
And the meantime our designers went out and bought every toothbrush under the sun
We started to take the conventional flat toothbrush with bristles sticking up
And we use the heat gun and made a bunch of different prototype
We just
Those standard brushes into different shapes
Sissy fundamentally what was working and what was not
Hundreds of sketches and dozens of prototypes
One of the first things we found when we were
Molding our prototypes was that
At the time the reach toothbrush
Probably best known as
The most ergonomic toothbrush
This was all
Perception is only ergonomic in that it looked like a dental
And it was a dental tool that somebody else would use on you
Crook in the dental mirror
It's so that somebody can stick it in your mouth and manipulate it so they can see around
The reach toothbrush
Infuse yourself you end up with your hand back at you
Describe the bed
Straight handle is bad
One of the things we found was a
Batter toothbrush handle is more comfort
The fat is better than thin but it's some point in the process
Someone
Peppa toothbrush
Company said
Wait a minute
You can't ship a toothbrush
That's got a fat handle on it
Because it's not going to fit into those
1950s Style ceramic toothbrush holders that people have stuck to their walls
Part of their houses
But this turned out to be a good thing
For the toothbrush manga
They got a ton of press about it though here's the toothbrush it doesn't fit and Luna came up with a strategy anybody called to complain
We created the little nickel plated
Stand that
Send out this $5 component
Just like biological evolution Shore the organism adapt to the environment
But also
Environment
Add apps to the organism and now if you buy a toothbrush holder
It's going to have these
Gigantic holes in the top right so you can fit
These newfangled Cooper
In addition to the straight and fat handles the new toothbrush also had crisscross bristles angle
That was brand-new the handle was strategically flattened in parts to help you oriented
Fingers no
Which way the person
Appointed in your mouth and it accommodated all of the five brushing reps identified by the kinesiologist there's a
Spoon grip
There's the death grip
More women than men use
The death grip
When I asked Jonathan which was his favorite innovation in the toothbrush he name something that most people
Consider a lack
Designer anime
Just getting the toothbrush back
Back to having a straight handle not trying to do anything
Crazy through the neck
That's the best shape
You know those kind of
The
Directions
And that's a big
Part of design
The thing you don't think about or notice
Probably had the most
Thought put into it
99percentinvisible is produced by me Roman Mars
The support from lunar it's a project of kalw The Americans
YouTube architects
Just go in the center for Ark
Texture and Design
Find out more at 99percentinvisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com