99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
Visit 99 percent invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Two vast and trunkless legs of Stone Stand in the desert
In Ozymandias poem by Percy Shelley
The poem is
About
A historic monuments of a
Figure a shattered visit why
Who has a wrinkled lip
And a sneer of cold command
The statue points
To all the works around him
And the poem reads my name is Ozymandias
King of Kings King of Kings
Look upon my works
Do you mind
And the rest of the poem says that all of the works that the statue of
Appear nothing beside remains
So it's really a poem about
Set the figure remains but everything around it has
It appears everything that the figure in the sky
Be proud of what this is about another four
That once stood high above sand
This is kind of envy
All of the things around it all of the landscape that the statue was supposed to serve urge to
Liberty in philanthropy
That's all still here the San Francisco the statue was dedicated to improving is there
The statue itself
That's William Littman I teach architectural history at the California College of Art in Oakland and San
Francisco and we're walking up to what I think maybe the greatest place
Can olives
Francisco that few people have ever heard of
What was once considered the geographic center
Of the city
We come up its this
How to raise plants
On top of Mount Olympus
A massive Stone pedestal
That rises up
To nothing
If the base of a statue that isn't there once this
12 foot high bronze statue still on top
On a site that has some of the best views of the entire city the view is
360 view of the
The city the statue was called the triumph
Of light with a statue of this woman
It looks a little like this
Statue of Liberty
She was holding Aloft a giant
Torch the other hand cheetah
Piece of parchment
And below her was a crouched figure kind of reaching up
Do these two objects
Symbolizing mankind
Reaching for
For light and Liberty
It was erected in 1887 by VIN developer
Future mayor out of
Sutro as a symbol of Liberty in
Progressivism
It Sutra dedicated the statue
In 1887 on Thanksgiving Day
He told the crowd
May the light shine from the torch
Are the goddess of Liberty to inspire our citizens
To good and Noble Deeds
For the benefit
Of mankind it was supposed to stand forever
To be a Timeless reminder
About
The importance of Liberty and civilization in philanthropy but it didn't last
In the 1930s people referring to it as the mystery
So obviously people have forgotten about Sutro and his goals and then by the 40s or discussion about removing it after death
Decades of neglect
Sometime in the 1950s it just disappears
The people discuss it online where it may have gone
Sonos
People really do come up to this hill
The same things that you bring dog walkers and
Urban Walker
Come up here
Maybe through these kind of discussions we can actually have someone maybe decide to build a new Statue
Who knows what it would look like
Imagine that debates about how would you symbolize Liberty in
Philanthropy
Yeah I don't know if I would like to see anything else here does that
Does that make me weird
Okay
I know I mean that is
Then what we should have here is a little
Plaque
Telling people
That there was once this
Beautiful
Sculpture does light and Liberty
Philanthropy
And now it's gone
So that's what we need
Although a sense of mystery Zone
You know people look up in
Could have been up there
What is missing
99% invisible it's about the stories
Human made object
And maybe in this case the
Absence
Of the object
Makes for a better story
A monument to learning and light and Liberty
That's missing
It's almost a more amazing
Monument
That says more about it
About Justin
Neglect
And how a city forgets its past
99percentinvisible was produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar it's a product
The kalw
American Institute of Architects
Cisco in the center
Architecture and Design
Annette Moore NC picture
99 percent invisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com