99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get to board from UC Davis
Globally ranked universities
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
No quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The five basic principles of flags
Designed according to the North American vets
Psychological association
Somalogic
Dactylology is the study of
Flags
Cancel all that
Number one
Keep it simple
Blacks should be so simple that a child can draw it from them
Before I moved to Chicago in 2005 I didn't even know cities had their own
Flags most larger cities have flags on it
Pets Ted K by the way
Flag Express
Totally awesome
I'm the editor of
Scholarly journal on flag
Call Dwayne
A journalist Zexal ology
And that first city flag I discovered in Chicago is
Subutai Whitefield
Two light blue horizontal
Stripes
For 6
Pointed red stars across the middle number to the blue stripes represent the water
The lake and the river
Bull symbolism
Stars represent
Significant events in
Chicago's history
The design of the Chicago flag has complete buying with an entire cross-section of the city it's
Everywhere
Every municipal building
Fly the flag
Every 20 year olds
Messenger bag
Hoodie asthma
It's a distinct
Symbol of Chicago's Pride when a police officer or firefighter
Chicago
State flag on a casket
It's the city of Chicago flag
That's How Deeply it's got into the city
Civic imagery
And it isn't just that
People love Chicago and they're full of the flag
I also think
People love Chicago more
Because the flag is so cool
Positive feedback loops are between
Great symbolism
And civic pride
So when I move back to San Francisco in 2008 I researched its flag
Because I've never
Seen it
Before in the previous eight years I live here
And I found it
I'm sorry to say
Sadly
Let me start at the top
Number one
Simple that a child can
Can draw it from memory the relatively complex flag main component of the San Francisco flag is a Fina
Representing our rising from the ashes after the great fires of the 1850s
Powerful symbols
San Francisco
I still don't really dig the Phoenix
Design-wise it had too many details into many colors and it doesn't leave work at a distance
But having deep meaning
What's that element
Plus
Man large penis
The background is mainly why
The flag also has a
Central gold border around
Which is a very attractive
Define Elam
But Here Come the big no-nos
Custom flag design
No lettering or
Are seals never use writing
Think of any kind
Underneath the Phoenix
There's a motto on a ribbon that Translate
Next to gold and peace
Iron in war
Plus
And this is the
Big problem
It's a San Francisco across the bay
Bottom if you need to write the name of what you representing on
Your flag
Your symbolism
Failed
United States flag doesn't say USA across
The good news is
Best names
Might not be completely our fault
A city flag
Interstate that has its own
Name
On the state flag
What end to Echo Dot
Yep the California Bear Flag says California Republic
So maybe we can blame this all on our capital city Sacramento
Is awesome
I love blaming Sacramento for things
I like to say that in every bad flag there's
It's a good flag trying to get out
Well the way to make San Francisco's flag a good flag would be to take tomorrow off because you can't read that a disc
How to take the name off and the Border might even be made thicker so it's it's more of a part of the
Can I would just simply take the Phoenix and make it a grape
Big element
In the middle of the flag
The current
Got to go I would
Simplifier stylized
Phoenix detect a Big Wide Wings Bird
Coming out of flame
Emphasize the Flames the next time you find yourself with a vexillologist
I'm never going to say that word by
Bike expert
Park yourself
You're in for a good time
By the North American vexillological
It's not just me it's not judge me
99percentinvisible is produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar at the product of kalw the American its
YouTube Architects San Francisco in the center
Picture and Design
Look at pictures of flags and a guide to how to design a good one
Go to 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com