99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Launch control
Spacecraft design is a study in humanity
At least that's what Mary Roach.
My name is Mary Roach
Find the author of packing
Conformarse the Curious sign
In the beginning the designers of the space habitation module
The box where the crew live
Yep that's the one
They stuck with what they knew that spending time up there or in zero gravity people just intuitively designed it
Like a room on Earth there would be
Control panel and then there were little chairs ever seats that you would sit and it was makes no sense and you can't sit you would have to
Strap yourself
Do the seat the reason is simple
We are humans when we have a room we have a floor-to-ceiling we have chairs and tables and that's
What we do and that's how it was designed but getting stuff into space is expense
There's always a grand effort
To minimize weight
How to create the most
Efficient space pause
And all those human
Came under scrutiny
So then they went to the Other Extreme get rid of it all because in space
The walls becoming your table if you have a table and you put something down on the table the table
Doesn't act like a table it doesn't hold it they just floats off
A drawer isn't very good you open the door everything flies out
So what you have is pieces of elastic
On the wall like you know you pulled the elastic back and you stick your clipboard in there
And everything has been savell curse of the wall
Become
The table
You have a very very
Box
That you're living in
So that became the game
No furniture in a ceiling
Perfect
Utilitarian box
For the astronaut
Floats freely and uses
Is every surf
The great thing about zero gravity
We can use the ceiling week
You can put the bathroom on the wall but this is where the human
The capsule became over design
For the 02
Condition
And it became
Two alien
The humanity
Was lost
The one thing
That the crews decided that they were not okay with we're getting rid of it
Kitchen table like a dining table
My place
To gather around at the end of the day you don't have
Sit down or pretend to sit down
And talk about what you did over the day eat
Show me where humans
Human beings want to sit around the table
I'm gossip and talk about stuff and eat and drink
And the table came back
Small table and there's little pieces of elastic and velcro and they all
Hover
Around the table
So despite that
Horrifying scene in Alien
Table and a spacecraft make
Extra happy astronaut
Turn the living quarters there's now an effort to use Earth orientation
The bottom part is
The floor and ceiling above walls or walls the way that the Q the man is like that the lighting will be up above
It was always so that you know what the accepted orientation is
Can helps in the constant War
Emotions
And having everyone in the same orientation
It also helps the crew talk
I interviewed this astronaut Lee Morin about how
Troubling it is to try to have a conversation
With somebody who is upside down when you were right side up
Sort of lip reading all the time without
Realizing it and he said
When you go beyond a 45 degree angle
The other person starts to have trouble reading your lips
Is considered impolite to carry on a conversation
With someone when you are upside down
When you are differently oriented
I love these examples in the fundamentals of Otherworldly
Space design because
If you were to recreate that exercise right here and then gravity-based habitat in start
Scratch
What would you redesign
Wheatley
Wood everything
Simply evolve back
To the way it is now
Would US currency
Still beating
Lockable uniform
In color inside
Could we get rid of
Cars
Could we
Finally make the
Steampunk hers happy
I Have A Sky Full of Derek
My guess is that even the poorly designed and inefficient
Text would make a comeback
Because it might just be
Your dining room table
Crappy wobbly
Square honey I will
Fix it soon
Promise it might be that dining room table
It makes you
Happy Astro
99% invisible is produced by me Roman Mars
Support from lunar it's a project of kalw The Americans
YouTube architects
San Francisco in the center for
InDesign
Find out more at 99percentinvisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com