99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
Visit 99 percent invisible
I'm Roman Mars
99% of car trips in the US
And a free park
If there's one thing that urban planning and parking Guru Donald
Shoop wants you to understand
That so-called free parking
Is never
Free every time you go to a grocery store movie theater or restaurant everything you do has a bit of the
Spark embedded
Everything except one thing
Chapter Derulo's driver
Mister bourbon environment free parking is a given having a massive tarmac.
Comfortably fit a fleet of cars in
Also land a 747 is a huge part of
The Suburban landscape
But even in urban
Areas we are subsidizing paid parking
Because the red on them
Is below market value
We also collected
Play Paperboy
Parking with time
Cruising for parking
Waste
Revolt
Go to a place that you see the price of Wall Street Park
$5 an hour at $0.50 an hour on the street while you'll Circle The Block
Until you see somebody going out
Quitters if you do everybody else's problem
We do together that all adds up
Donald Shoup studied the amount of cruising from
Parking lot 15 block business
Near UCLA and found that in a year
The vehicle miles traveled
Walk cruising for parking
Was almost a million
Miles
That's
More trips to the moon or 36 trips around the Earth
Cruising for parking and double parking
St. Louis public transit
Dangerous bicycle
Destriant
And that is happening
Everywhere nobody his
How old is the cost
All this
Spanish Mother Parker Park
Supply
But San Francisco is looking to be the first
Major city
To manage
Well
Premise
I'm the manager vest
Look for the
San Francisco
The new SF Park project uses sensors and network meters to dynamically adjust parking prices
Overtime
The key ingredient is the sensor
Which sends back data about whether or not a car is a
Be there for the first time we're going to know what's happening on the street
And with that sensor data the parking authority starts adjusting
The sensor to give real-time data back to headquarters and the
New pricing is calibrated for the next month
It's demand responsive pricing
Different times of the day may go up in price
And meters in
Less traffic neighborhoods
May go down to entice people to park there
And walk a little farther
But this isn't just about
Parking
Sfpark is about making a better design
City
Lots of cities these days
Are interested in
Reducing Greenhouse
Gas emissions factor
This is the first time that
Any city has tested out
Parking base
Approach to congestion
That's good for people who drive but its
Really important
For people who are on the bus and just trying to get home
That the bus is much Bass
The goal is to have constant parking availability One open space for every block so that people get in a space
Faster in art circling the block
And their toxins viewing death machine
And it's not just Street
Pricing in the city on garages will also be dynamically adjusted to
There's no relation
Between the price of Park
Parking on street at meters
And parking lot
In fact
It's usually more expensive to park in a parking lot of garage
Rather than at the meter and that's just the opposite of how much
The plan is changed that relation
You should make it cheaper to park in the lots and garages
Attract more people just go straight
To those lots
Keeping this on
Free spaces available for those
Really value
I think it's beginning was press about sfpark is all the data about parking availability that will be accessible by the public and
In the image of some tech-savvy Superuser who is constantly checking their iPhone to find a parking space instead of
Watching where they're driving
Which if you picture for a second
Terrifying and
Create more problems than it solves
But I think this is the wrong image
If successful
It is a big F in the market sets the right value for a parking space
You will never
Look for parking with your iPhone because
Again the goal is one open space for Block meaning
There'll always
C parking available
There is no search
The things you use your iPhone 4 is finding out how much will cost before you leave the house
Where you can decide then if it's better to walk
How to ride the bus
Set of Drive
The key is that you don't have to know anything
Have an easier time Park
Like the best design and only works
If you don't the work
To make it work
99% invisible is produced by me Roman Mars
The support from lunar it's a project of kalw The Americans
YouTube architects
Sysco in the center for architecture and Design
Find out more and 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that guy
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com