99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible this is Stephanie Foo
Provide and maintain for the enjoyment of the public
From 8 a.m. to 6
Privately-owned public
Hobos
PPO POS
It has its logo that says public open space in the
Cannabis little like tree that shaped like a house
All of them have the Same Love
The city requires
It's a cool logo
Pretty small sign now
My name is Blaine merker I'm an artist part of a group of artists and designers called rebar for basic salmon
Popo
They're a kind of unique set of spaces that were required to be provided by the developer as a kid
Addition of approval for the developers building on private property
Their own most likely by the owner of the building
They look like public space they
Boa covered space in the most part this one that were standing in is granite walkways in the fountain and
Grasp but technically speaking these are totally privately owned
The only
Patches
Set the developer is
Legally obliged
To make this open to
The public and fill out anyway
And no one's quite sure what allowed here who's in charge and what
The codes of behavior should be
And just because they're public
Doesn't mean they're easy to find
The walkthrough to get to a public
Yeah
Cut nice art thou
We'll see when we walked
Security
W this moment where you're like okay I just crossed the threshold
Making eye contact
People in authority and sort of acknowledging them
That's not something I ever feel in a park right if you don't like walk into Dolores Park in
I feel like nod
Somebody like you
It's okay that I'm here
There's cameras
1 2
3 cameras in here
You want to try some bad
Yeah why not
Yeah let's do it
There's a whole set of invisible
Codes
And
Regulations that shape our Behavior
Most of us aren't really
Play where them
You hold yourself in public
Were you thinking
You can talk to
It's only by doing something that
Push back again
Text codes
That you actually can
Turtle eggs
Science is firing an electron
Add an atom
Where is
If you fire an electron in an atom he actually change
The course of Adam when you're in one of these faces when you start to push back against the codes of behavior if you actually
Change Kodi
Behavior
Look like
All right
We definitely played
Long enough probably to be noticed
Score one for
But if you really want to test the tolerance of a privately owned
Public open space
Batman may not be the best test
I mean if you really want to make someone in Authority uncomfortable
The most subversive Act
Especially right now
Maybe doing nothing at all
There's a few behaviors that you can
Sort of possibly do that allow you to the idol
Like
Cuddling with your phone or
Smoking
Or reading a book but
Just like lie down and do nothing
Not okay
I dropped attention to do nothing
The San Francisco planning and urban research Association which is better note
Spur has a great guy to all the popos in the city and recommendation
How to improve
Current and Future
Surepost
Including a proposal
Taconafide some of these rules for the sofa
Privately owned
Open Spaces
I think it's key to keep in mind that
Hobo's will never fully supplant the need for a true comment
Free public spaces in a city
Public entities
Rate
Hidden gems in The Knocks
Planning
Devon City
Even if you're allowed to play badminton
The fact that you have
The test for it
These these spaces
Aren't really ours
This episode of 99% invisible was produced by Roman Mars
Stephanie Foo
Report from lunar
It's a project of
Kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco
And the center for architecture and design or maybe tell the world about your favorite little private corner of the city
Go to 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com