99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman
And this week I'm talking to you
Directly the podcast audience who I like to call the 99
Percentile
And not the radio people because
Took a week off the radio show
Do some other work
Can catch up on some things
But this is actually a piece that I really want to present to you because it's an older piece I did about a year-and-a-half ago for a
Text show pilot
That never got picked up so it only got the pilot itself only got hurt by about
20 people
I really love this piece I put a lot of effort into it and I liked it a lot of my job
In general is to
Pilot shows in
And to work on new things
Sound design
Do programs
But
The consequences that is sometimes you make radio that
That isn't on the radio
Which is weird
And so this is one of those pieces
It makes it so appropriate is this actually represent InDesign
Problem in the problem
Problem or design
Challenge
Is how do we get humans on Mars
There's
Certainly technological solutions to this problem
There's a
Solutions that involve a lot of willpower and
Money maybe but there's also some out-of-the-box thinker
Might come into play
Some of the information in the piece is a little old so it's about a year-and-a-half old
There used to be a constellation project
Does the Moon to Mars program that
Obama
When the world ran out
The money
And
I think that's about it but I'll most of it is still
Pretty relevant
I think it's
I quite enjoyed
So I hope you enjoy it too so this the 99% invisible this week
It's called one-way ticket to Mars
Ignition
We can get tomorrow
That's easy
Break Earth's gravity in hurdle towards the red planet is
Totally doable the science fiction Park
Detect problem NASA says we'll take four decades to solve
It's how to get back
You can't carry enough fuel for a round trip
To have a
We'll have to make new fuel up there
Literally
Big of mine on Mars Harvest minerals
Whip up a nuclear reactor
Simple rocket
Not easy
But if you really want to go to Mars
Like now if you can't possibly wait any longer
James McClean
Has another plan
I think what we should have
Is a short program
Possibly a ten-year program like the Apollo program
Where we were
Actually
Devault equipment in Land one person
On Mars
And we would keep that person we saw
Supply
The prime thing that makes this feasible is that you don't plan on bringing this person back
I would have let that sink in
Alrighty
Play is now an oil and gas pipeline engineer over 20 years he worked for NASA
Safety Systems and the International Space Station
I know he no longer has anything to do with space you still
A man on a mission
I began to disturb that there were options as far as space travel to other plan
Planets that NASA wasn't
Considering I brought up in a technical meeting once it a guy was giving a presentation about NASA's
Plans for the future
He raises his hand and says this guy
When I send one person one way
One person because it cuts down on the weights applied to a manageable level
In one way because getting them back
It's really really hard
He was just astonished that anyone would would even mention such a thing at Justice
It sounded almost immoral
But the more I thought about this the more I
I realize that it was it was actually
Probably the only way that
Wechat
See this thing happen and you know what in our lifetime of the current generation here on Earth
Because all of the other schemes that I read about
Involve developing a exotic equipments going to take 50 years
You could call it a suicide mission and many people have
McLean says it's really no more of a suicide mission than the early Vikings making their way to North America
But I think it's really no more of a suicide mission than life
Itself
Explore would be going to live out a life on Mars
Dramatically
Shortened
Unbelievably harsh life
None the less
Well it wouldn't it would not be pleasant that's putting it mildly
It would be I guess like living in a submarine
You would probably live in a habitat that was covered with
Dirt
So you would only go outside occasionally
The conditions would be so Danger
Boris has a poisonous low-pressure atmosphere
Terry spacesuit better work
Forever
But that's assuming that you can leave your base at all because Mars is also home to the Solar System's largest
Dust storm
I can cover the entire planet
Vermont
And if anything breaks
Your toast
Or more accurately
Your pops
Because it can get down to 190 degrees below zero
Then there's the cancer-causing cosmic radiation
You better hope not
And it's only a suicide mission
From the astronauts perspect
The problem is that for NASA
It's more of a homicide mission
And that's a little harder to sell to Congress
But explorers get it
Mister second man on the moon himself Buzz Aldrin
Says the one way trip
Is the way to go
You really thick
You have trouble getting volunteers for The Greatest Adventure
In history
Right now the space shuttle
Has been demonstrated to be nice
Greenlee extremely dangerous a vehicle but
People are standing in line to get a chance to
Reply on the fastest thing on the planet people are willing to take that risk
For the chance of doing something remarkable this person is going to be more than just
Somebody to go down in history
If this person will be it will be like a
An Adam or Eve type figure legendary
Plus I have to admit
There's something about it
Captures the imagination
Doom
Lone Explorer in a
Cleaning metal tube
Daily Transmissions back home
It would be poetic
Beautiful
I'm kind of inspiring
It horrible
McCobb
It would be riveting
And it's probably never going to happen I think that's a non-starter from NASA
We're not going to send astronauts to Mars
Without the case
That's Chris McKay
Doctor Killjoy
I'm the deputy program scientist
Of the constellation
Activity in constellation
NASA
Turn to the moon on to Mars human exploration Pro
So he's actually planning NASA's manned mission
Well I personally I I wouldn't want to go in at 1
Play Mission and also I like the idea of that
We bring Mars into the sphere of human activity which means we going come and we going come
I don't see why we have to
Surrender to the technological challenges
Say okay this is impossible
Can't do it
I think
That's a cop out
What we ought to do is say well let's build better Rock
It's come on you guys engineers get to work
One round trip
Chris McKay and NASA think we should go to Mars once we're ready to establish a long-term base
Something like the Antarctic base
But there are humans there year-round coming and going and doing research
Boldly stay
Paraphrasing start
That becomes
Rotational
Innocence
What's the rush
Why why do we need to rush them
The author of The One Way plan James McClain is
So for him
There is a rush
Well it's
Some of these questions would be nice to answering in my lifetime I like to know the answer
I'd like to know the answer
People say well
If you want to see it in your lifetime
Respond well I'm not that old maybe I will with 40 more years
Unlikely but hey I go running everyday and I don't smoke the fact that it's in my lifetime or not is really not an important
Consideration NASA shouldn't
Major decisions based on the lifetime of its current scientists and engineers
And of course
That makes good practical sense
But isn't there something to this idea of a bold Apollo like 10 year mission to excite the imagination
No matter what the cost
Shouldn't we recapture
The Thrill of the space race
The way you win a race
Is
You exert yourself fully during the race
Even if it means that after the race you clap
Blob at the end of the finish line
And that's what we did at Apollo we exerted enormous effort we took our best people
Push them as hard as we could
And we won the race
And then
We clocked
At the end of it
The political context for space exploration now is very different than a race
The Apollo president
Is not the president
Follow here
And that's a big problem
Apollo was NASA's golden age when anyone talks about returning NASA to it
Former glory
That's the model they point to
Except for a small block of Interest training
Space camp craze of the 80s
The Solera of NASA only grabbed the attention of the world
When there was a horrible
Horrible track
James McClean ask you to imagine nightly broadcast
Mars day
Pairing with an astronaut
Over the edge of a crater five times deeper than the grand
Hearing stories from the base of a volcano so tall
It nearly reaches space itself
That's a beautiful sight in front row seats to the greatest and coolest Hail Mary pass
The history of humankind
One man one way McLean says
Inspiring NASA of his
But you can feel it and Mars
Slipping away
They won't even study the option
If they set up a small task
Force
Turn office to study this particular option I believe it would be obvious just from the technical stuff
Daddy's that this is the only way it could be done
Relatively low cost
And in a relatively short period of time
All of the other schemes are going to Mars
There's no way it's going to happen
Anytime
Futura forever
Forever is too long
Whether we follow the one-way plan or not
Maybe more than out-of-the-box thinking what we really need
Is another country to come along and start talking trash
Doris back into the starting blocks of another space race
China
I'm looking at you
I'm Roman Mars the guy
The modern world
Pleasant 99% invisible for this week
Originally broadcast into the headphones of some muckety-muck
At a public radio production and distribution company who did not like it enough to put it on the radio
Was good wasn't it I don't know what they're talking about
Anyway I hope you enjoyed it I got to stretch my legs a little bit this week little longer than 4 and 1/2 minutes everyone happy now
Thank you very much like I want to show how much time I have
Only have on the radio so
Maybe you'll be longer someday I kind of like it
The challenge
I hope you enjoyed it
I'm really Mars at 1% invisible
Take care and I'll talk to you next week
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Adad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
A movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com