99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Beethoven continue to write music in resumes best music
After he lost his hearing
So you couldn't hear his music at all
You can only hear the construction in his mind
As architects
We have all sorts of.
Different ways of
Experiencing art
Architecture
Both and it's built forum
And it's creation
Through
Scale drawings and models
Besides our own mental Construction
So Christian he asks me what's more preposterous
Composing music you can't hear
What is an architect
You can't see
My name is Chris Downey
In case you haven't guessed it yet he's a blind
Chris Downey lost his side about 3 years ago after being an architect for nearly two decades
Clearly there wasn't any book out there on how to be a blind architect so really the best thing to do it is just to get out there and
Try and once I did that
Quickly realize that there are ways to perceive and understand drawings and design both in two dimensional
Form and in three-dimensional form and their
Any number of ways to react
Advance Auto
Create it
Just like anybody else
He couldn't do ultimately with translate the physical models that he can make by hand in today.
That he can input into a computer design program
But hey
That's not all bad excuse not to
Reproduction guy and get past that and focus on
Where I could really deliver value it started falling together pretty well on
The key is finding the right tools
In this case
Computers at talking to me fast
So that's the following
I can't understand anything
I can slow it down
Am I being more
Easier to hear it
If you had to listen to that all day long that's how fast the
ATM machines are windows
Go and listen to those two have your non-visual access to it
And it takes
So long
To get to what you need to do
You got to be faster
Lightspeed Lansing
Another key tool is an embossing printer that makes a raised
Braille. Version of the architectural plans that he's working on
I'm like a sided architect that can get a bird's-eye view of an architectural plan
When Downey runs his fingers over the embossed printed page
He experiences the plan
More like
An actual person traveling through the building one
As a sequence of vignettes
When you do that
Then you have a better chance
The really putting yourself in that space
And think about everything that's happening when you move through there
The typical sensory
Experience of the environment around us
80% of it is visual
Brain is overloaded with the visual information the other 20% becomes a lot more important in this allows for a
New appreciation for
For certain buildings
Like for example a much
Heated old San Francisco
Bus terminal the transbay terminal is coming down
And that'll
Hbase
Once there
It was not a perfectly delightful place
Visually it was a horrific place
Olfactory experience with pretty miserable to
Appended to smell like urine
But I was lucky enough to have lost my sight and my smell
So
Didn't look bad and it didn't smell bad
And there are there alot of these that long
Ramps and
Inclined plane
If you're blind
Great because all the sudden you get directionality out of gravity
Regardless of whichever way you're going up or down here going uphill you can get a strong scent
Of going straight uphill as opposed to
Drake going off
On an angle
You coming down here
Make like a drop of water into
Just follow gravity
So those are actually kind of fun
Spaces so if you ever wondered what it would take to love the old transbay terminal
Being blind and having no sense of smell seems to do the trick
Something often talked about
The touch of the building where you actually
Reach Out
Grab
Building weather today
Door handle or a railing replace
Lean against
A place to sit down
If those places
Offer
The worms
But comfortable
Touched something that acknowledges
The presence of the body
Besides the agenda of the eyes
How can you think about the
The material or the Forum
In a way that
Give you that pension
Just like you
Give somebody a hand
Excommunicated
Through a handshake
It's a what
Sandshaker the building
What are you saying that
But no more about Christianity at 99% invisible. Org
Yeah
99% invisible is produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar it's a project of
Kalw the American Institute of
San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
I think a few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com