99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts in a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
You may not want to waste energy or burn fossil
Sophie Elizabeth
The deck is stacked
Against you
Everything is designed to just use more and more fuel as you'll see you Lisa Martinelli argues
Designed might not be the right word
But let's just say design
My name is Lisa margonelli
And I wrote
Avocado oil on the brain petroleum's long strange trip to your tank first
A metaphor
We are on a
A couple months ago I was at a tugboat race
And we're looking at an old Tugboat from when they used to be
Buy coal
And it was beautiful is shaped like a canoe on the bottom and the house on top was
Surrounded
Aerodynamic
Just like it is in the Popeye cartoon
Is gorgeous
It was all very streamlined to slip through the water in through the air on top
But there's also a newer diesel Tucker
The whole is
Relatively
Squarish I mean it's shape to go through the water but things are not
Scooped the way they were in the other one
And the top is just straight flat
Steel they don't even bother
30 shape them
They just
Skin pain all the corners and the reason is that
When you have a coal-fired tugboat
Every bit
A cold that you have to put on that tugboat
Master converter
Power and you want to reduce the amount of
With diesel fuel
It's very easy it's
Plentiful now
It's much easier to just design the
Tugboat to use more fuel
To waste fuel essentially
Ban
To shape the steel
And design that tugboat
To use less
So few lives are expended
And the whole world is designed as a big diesel
Square bottom
Tugboat to the biggest waste of energy is the wholesale
In the most wasteful component of that whole system in the US is the way we drive to and from work
The whole process
Selling mortgages and selling houses
Over the last
15 years or so is based on this
SEPTA drive to the koala
So you drove a
Best far out
You could stand
To the place where you could get a decent rate on a mortgage
House with a low enough
Payments and at the same time you get
Get like more Square
What supported the
Was that
Can you drive
Where to get into the city
To do your job
And then what supported that was that they were just
Countdown really big
Carso
If you'd been making that
Trip in a small car Emoji felt a little
But you could buy this
Palatial
And those big cars have horrible gas
Fidessa
Everything along the way app
To burn more gas
Apps just stopping at a
What is an enormous
Energy
What does the Ops
Even barreling down the highway at
Top speed is
No problem cars were tuned
3 most efficient around 50
55 to 6
That's the speed the government used to
The test for fuel efficient
So they were essentially designed to be
Less efficient at the speeds that we really
Because we really dry
Rm60
It's as if
Some Evil Genius designer system
That we will waste
Gasoline
How evil is this
It's more much more banal than evil
If someone sat down to Concha
Justly design this thing I don't know that they could do so
Of making a mess
Is the tyranny of the lack of design
The tragedy
Building a bad idea
On a thoughtless notion
On a careless
Plan another dumb thing piles onto another dumb saying and pretty soon we've got just a
Huge tangle
Find gasoline
Fairly cheaply
And speaking of buying gasoline
Chiefly there is something does
Actually design
To make you more
Comfortable
With all of this
When you buy gas
We don't like to be in gas stations refill
Dangerous and
We don't like to be paying money for gasoline to the oil companies and we always feel the gas is too expensive no matter what the price
SO gas pumps have been specifically designed to sort of diffuse that anger
So they did some market research and I found that people have warm feelings towards ATM machines
And they had bad feelings toward God
So they redesigned the
Gas pumps to look a little bit more like ATM machine so you felt like you were having sort of an intimate warm experience
When you were at the gas pump
As opposed to thinking about hitting the oil company because we want an experienced in tune with our values
Even if what we're doing
Is it
99percentinvisible is produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar it's a project of kalw.
American Institute of Architects
The Scout in the center for
Texture and Design
Find out more and 99% invisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com