99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Sustainability
Sustainability lighting for a lot of people to stand abilities and Abstract thing and it sucks
Hard to sort of an emotional level it's really needed the first thing
Thanks forward you want to inspire people rather than
Creating guilt trips
Making them look at numbers
My name is Anton Willis
I'm a designer
And part of the studio called Civil Twilight Civil Twilight Flagship project is lunar resident Street
Caesar street lights.
Sense and respond to ambient room lights
So they dim and brighten and respond
Solunar
When the moon is folded in done to save energy
It's about the way of saving energy
And creating a new Urban connection
The cycle of the moon
The project on the 2007 Metropolis
Generation design competition partly because
Took this huge design challenge of trying to
Curb energy use
Added
A bit of the poetic
Design that saves energy but also
Expires and reconnects urban dwellers
Was one of the fundamental
Cycles of nature
In most cities today the level of light pollution is so high that we're really not aware of
The stars are Moonlight at all
No no one knows what phase of the moon is on any given day, so we're looking for a way to really reconnect people to those kinds of Cycles
Each individual light is a very sensitive
The photo center
Pics of moonlight
Cloud cover app
Lynn Spirit condition
So on the scale of acidity you could actually have really interesting phenomenon
If a cloud passed over the moon youku
Sort of shimmering across the city reflecting the
REI Seattle
Pretty amazing way to
Makes it is a whole lot more
More responsive inserted for more Dynamic and more life
Turns out that
In the early years of Street lighting
Johnson Electric
Just electricity was really expensive so the only turn them on when they needed to
And they typically would not turn them on on the full Moonlight nights when it was clear at
People just had the understanding that that was enough
Light to see by Insidious and it was a waste of energy to the light on top of that
And that really change with the National Grid electric
Vacation in the 1930s when they actually needed a way to burn off excess energy at night when no one was
Would using electricity in their humps
And the street Light Grid actually be down as a way to do that as much
What is a way to
I sent that almost every city
To be illuminated
Very brightly
Twenty-four hours a day
The standards for lighting that are in place
That. So this is an effort to make
Beautiful energy efficient
Version of a thing
Designed and used historically to burn energy on purpose
I think we've gotten used to talking about sustainability in terms of a lot of metrics and numbers and less about
People's direct experience of it
So we're looking at ways
Is to really bring a
Tangible personal experience per level
We see ourselves as part of the stronger direction that the whole sustainability mooc
We'll go we believe in the coming years
So where's my friendly neighborhood Moon responsive street light
So far only exist
That's a prototype
So far
MIT labs are also prototyping a similar in
Spirit indoor adaptive lenses
Massive
Energy saving
Technology
But also is a way to make our working in my room
It's more comfortable productive
And please
Do you say more natural
The flight
I think the lot of the current design discussion is about how to
Make design more relevant how to make it part of this process
It's the really shaped the world
Economics
The government
I want to sort of processes that we don't think of being designs
Or having a relationship to design
Climate change is a design problem
National that is a design problem all of these things are our design problem two different ways
Expand the scope
How do you think about it a little bit
Art challenge
Best designers is related to expand that scope and to become part of the bigger discussion
99percentinvisible is produced by me Roman Mars
The support from lunar it's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects
The Scout in the center for
Texture and Design
Find out more at 99percentinvisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast
Dot-com