99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of autumn
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
Family ghosts
Is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view of the world
Each episode of Family ghost
Takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th
Between episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
An episode about uncovering the secrets scrolled in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode
It brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years
And more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
I'm sorry
But if you don't love Maps
I don't think we can be friends anymore
I think there are people nowadays who did admit that they don't love puppies and kittens and
Children
But nobody's going to say don't love Matt
Bats are awesome
As art as story as representation of Truth as representation of Lies really interesting visual information
Cancel it like a puzzle your solving it really engages your brain
Also is an invitation away nothing else has you know music somebody else's
It's a score for you to live your own life
Even if
What kind of map
Cycling with maps of my own neighborhood
And if your only experience with Matt.
AAA road atlas
And Rebecca solnit's new book for blow your mind
This is Rebecca solnit with infinite City a San Francisco at
That was exposed to a collection of maps and a proposition that any city is infinite
Because it can be described in infinite ways
No one map
Do everything
It's 22 maps that want to be beautiful and want to celebrate old fashioned map making
With paper with
Drawings with
Old cartography
With a sense of wonder and with
Is practical information you can ask
Which contain multitudes of maps
If I say to you there were 99 murders in San Francisco in 2008
Do you think it was deplorable for the three seconds before you completely
We forgot about it
But if I show you the actual map it makes you think this person died here and that one over there you see a pattern ECG
That most of them are in the east side of town
You don't become spray
Particular in specific it becomes places you could have been it could have been you you can go to them you could
Spring flowers
Enemy San Francisco infinite City Atlas these murder sites are represented on the city map
Red dots butt
Alongside them is a rave cream.
That represent
All of the living Monterey Cypress
Trees in the city
It's new ugly death
An old Beautiful Life side-by-side sharing a map
Because
Let me just because because you can make a meth do anything
My story is my story but instamap is also your story because you can literally enter what shown on the
The map you can go there you can walk it
Can you can be there
And so Maps
Give you a different sense they quanta
Define locate
An invite in a way that no other medium does
Would you like any
Weather maps
Show other guy
Sure
One of the infinite city maps
Treasure map
Panoply app
Treasured sites in Tampa
You know the Mission Dolores
Graveyard Monica rounds murals African Orthodox Church of St John
Coltrane some labyrinths
The nesting site of the great blue herons on Stow Lake we have treasure
And this is the map to help
You find it
The most curious feature about this map
The Scout is it
Depicted as bad
The little thumbnail at
End of the
Men's clothes thumb that it actually is
San Francisco is drawing
As an island
On the treasure map
San Francisco not only has the North Coast
East Coast and West Coast you all know one love it has a Southcoast the fictitious
Blue Ribbon of water just North of San Bruno Mountain
From the rest of the country ecologically geographically and culturally
Before the bridges
You basically came in and out of San Francisco bye-bye boats as though it was an island
And I just wanted to make that literal on the wonderful way Maps always are literal
Associates of the Cartographer been pieces wife
Shih Tzu sickle
Oblige Me by making San Francisco into an island
Maps are powerful objects that give direction they hide
Secret places
Support imperialism and oppression
A newly-designed map can create a nation
State
Represent a false sense
List of absolute truth
They changed the way we see the world
A joke
To some of my friends when is working on this project that
Owning race horses in castles there's nothing to commissioning Maps when it comes to a sensor
The power and luxury it's pretty
Amazing
99percentinvisible is produced by me Roman Mars
The support from lunar it's a project
Kalw the American Inn
YouTube architects
Sysco in the center for Ark
Texture and Design
Find out more at 99percentinvisible
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through
Treacherous
Annalise Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that guy
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there
Killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth Park
Dot-com