99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment in California and
Around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Amex special podcast edition of the show this week cuz I'm off the radio
Aaron repeat
February 4th
When season number 2 of 19
What starts up
How we have some funding to start up and
Getting more funding
Research
And recording more stories so
Look for new episodes
February
But in the meantime
I have
Probably what are going to be new stories to you unless you
Already listened to
Are the shows that I
I've worked on in the past
And this one is from one of those shows
Call Snapchat
The best new storytelling show out there
It's from NPR
TRX you should Def
Check it out
But this is a piece that I really love
That I did for them
For the Utopia epi
And if he has some design implications
So if you can bear with me
You know but otherwise it's a
Fun with Alyssa
I'm great
Stay with it
The tape the end
Destroyer
It's about
An online world
That was designed and created by EA Games and Thrift
Turned into a perfect little Utah
Copia by the
By the users themselves
But the problem was
Dagames
Didn't
Any money off
Supported anymore
So it's what happens when I created world
I hope you enjoy
A few months before the end of the world Paul Monaco posted this message
On YouTube
Hello everyone
Call Monaco here
Buddha palm
Do you know me as
Probably all heard the news
Online closing down
The world that was ending was called The Sims Online it was not online version the most popular computer game ever made
You've all been wonderful
Help me through a hard time in my life when I first got online but ironically
The online version of The Sims was not very popular
They ended up losing tons of subscribers and changing the name of the EA land
And then they finally
Thank you and please try to stay in touch
SmackDown
Whatever you choose to do and move on to
As you can probably hear real and was not a normal video
There are no monsters no killing
And although it had some competitive element
For many players competition wasn't the
The point at all
Unlike a lot of other games where you might be
Shooting people
Slaying dragons or something this is a game about socializing
That is Robert Ashley Ashley very popular internet radio show the creator of
A life well wasted a life well wasted it's about video games in the people who loves
Annie a land with a video game that a dedicated few absolutely
Love
The crowded attracted I think
We're people who just wanted to get together
Answer chat
Meet strangers it was a nice place over time it became a kind of intimate
Almost bar like the cheers of video games where everyone knows your name
Let the moment that Paul Monaco AKA Buddha Paul found EA land
It was exactly
What do you needed most
My wife from
A long-term illness she had blood transfusion she had hepatitis C
3 years of silver life were pretty
Yeah pretty much a challenge for a while for both of us
And after she passed away
I had absolutely no
Function of the new wake up go to work and go to sleep again
With with her illness I didn't get out of socialize much we know we
Weren't able to you know go out to the bars and meet up with friends and have dinner
I totally be socialized myself
And this game was, wait for me to just can't get back into into living you
It was pretty amazing
And Paul begin to live for real and you would play it for hours and hours with the first thing he did when he got home from work
Image feel really good it wasn't the real world his friends were real friends and virtue
Four worlds
Do you have an upside your race your car legal in Virginia all that can be totally in your truly
Judged on who you really are and how you present yourself
There's no no prejudices no preconceived
Anythink
Really taken at face value
People could really like break loose and envy themselves and have some fun
It just feels really good
The Paul's Utopia didn't last because he alien started hemorrhaging money
The writing was on the wall the server was about to go dark and this event
This virtual apocalypse
My only exist in the memory of the players if it weren't
4 dr. Henry lowood
I just stumbled across and this project by
Henry lowood who is this
Archival researcher at Stanford. I had a project called how they got game
Summit history of digital games and simulations
Saving video games for future
Generation Beyond 50 a hundred two hundred years from now are we going to say that history and like we got to save the video game
So doctor lowood and his colleagues preserve what happens inside video games no for single player game like
Pac-Man for example take the Atari cartridge out and you put it on a shelf but saving multi
3 player online games
Is not so simple
Saving the software alone is kind of a bearing exercise he said the code for Yale and turn it on hundred years now
You enter a world and nothing would be there
All the things that Paul Monaco and his friends love
Would be impossible to find you need to document what people are doing in these spaces
That situation is much more like what a historian on archivist would do when faced with the problem of document
The real world
Dr. Leatherwood caught wind of the alien shutting down here the opportunity to record something
Historian or archaeologist
Would die
To witness firsthand
In the real world
See what it would be like when an online world
Came to an end
What happens when a virtual world close
The end
I'm a culture what is it like to be there at the last minute and then when it shuts down
To the tape is rolling in the last few hours of Yale and are being recorded in the most dedicated DieHard users are there
Exchanging virtual hugs reminiscing
Players are typing messages which appear like comic book word bubbles in
You hear all these avatars
Crying and hearing all these
Cruise and moans in the gibberish language of the game
Simlish you know they said they sound like they're going to be bummed and
And everything but it's not like a big pity party but then
Toward the end of
Of the night
There's this radio station that you can listen to you in a game called Charmed radio
And they had
This TJ there
Names
Spike he is assertive The only voice that you and appearing at the end of the world
And as soon as
She starts talk
You understand what is
Being lost
Hey guys the last time you going to have me speak quote
Blossom 240SX exam
I just want to thank you it's been an amazing experience it ready has and
Private account
Stress enough how much you guys have been to me over the past
How many years has been
Already has been awesome ad
Some people don't touch nothing
But not when you make fake friends
Siri Hodge
Subway
Can you play the last song is Sarah Brightman and Andrea Bocelli
Time to Say Goodbye
Hopefully you guys relax in touch my Yahoo ID 16345
Ey
1 2 3 4 5
You looking like everybody and the
Best wishes
I love you all and that's been great knowing you
Play kygo
Rich's Automotive
If you have a nose ring supposed to toast the power that has been absolutely amazing cars that we could have done this without you. Thank you
To get this field
In like being on the deck of the Titanic
Very much invested in the game on an emotional level when they pulled the plug on the server bits and pieces of the world
Started disappearing
Environment began to disintegrate
The Textron the trees flicker
And all the people
And blinked out of existence
The actual ending was was
You're not with a bang but with a whimper and the last thing that they saw was basically just an error message a server.
Disconnect message
And then
The world ended
That was a game over
For sure I worked on called
Snap judgement
If you're not already a fan
Trust me in to download everything and listen to it you'll enjoy it
And also was a collaboration with Robert
Did the Internet radio show called a life well wasted I heard that
Do you have audio tape in the interview that
He dead
About this
Story
On his podcast
And
I asked him about it and we serve I interviewed him and can we arrange the parts and took little bits of it
It turned into
PC hurt so this is definitely a collaboration with Robert Ashley
The last episode of his show
Types of number 6 of a life well wasted
Is it working
It's just beautiful
So go look that up a life well wasted
Download it
That's the key for this week I have another one coming I think next week
Or in 2 weeks
Before that new show start on February 4th and really any ideas you have design stories anyting pitch me something
I respond really well.
So let me know
What you thinking about him what type of stories you'd like to hear on my neck
39% invisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Two days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had something
Nothing to do with it now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Every takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all five
Parts on the truth podcast.,