99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get support from UC Davis
Globally ranked universities
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
No quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Go hydrogen
Everybody recognizes
Certified as a castles with
Turrets lol
On the left and the right hand
Inside
There are some taller towers and then head
Queso dips in the middle
What's the periodic table of
Elsa the bricks of the Tower
Where are the individual Elliman
All of The 100
And 18 element
Science
Is snow exist
And the weather arranged on the table is
Bad element
Stead have very similar
Properties in
Characteristic
Similar properties like melting point
Similar chemical reactions with other elements are in the same vertical column on
I'm talking to is Sam Keen
The book is the disappearing spoon
And Other Two Tales of Madness love and
History of the world
Periodic Table of
The periodic table is a strange case of design duality
Design of both
Meme
Success
Just a little bit of failure
Let's do the failure fur
Different than other
A scientific I
It's hard to get
Take a look at it and get in
Information at a
Lance from it
Even though it probably hung in front of you every day that you went to school my guess is
Very little of its information really sunk in one of the bad design
It's not something that's
Intuitive
Until you've done a lot of work
But the bad part
The impenetrability is far outweighed by
Precision and predictive power and here's where we should introduce
The hero
Of the story
All the hero of the story is Dmitri Mendeleev Russian science
Mendeleev was the first to come up with a periodic system there were five others before him
Still periodic table Mac Daddy
He came up with the design and
Incorporated
More elements than the other scientist
He also knew enough to predict that there were
Pools on the periodic
You left gaps
That would be filled by later Elam
Discovered
I said he knew enough to be able to predict the properties of new elements
Based on
Where exactly the holes were at this was
Huge that's why he gets home
Credit
A scientist
I'm in the way of love his table but everyone else was about to discover how awesome it was
When the first gap of the table was filled in
What element newly-christened galleon
This was discovered in 1875 by a Frenchman
The Galleon filled in the Gap right below aluminum and because of that
Mendeleev said should have properties like aluminum for the French scientist who discovered and named gallon found at the melting point
Was different
Then what Mendeleev predicted using the table
Check your results
Which is pretty insulting to say to another scientist
I'm in the lab is not about Consulting anybody
And I after another year or so it turned out that Mendeleev was correct
And the Frenchman had to retract his results
The entire scientific world of chemistry was astounded
That Mendeleev sitting in his office in St Petersburg
For he knew nothing about the
But he had been able to see the properties of gallium more clearly than the person who would actually do
Discovered it in Paris who actually held it in his hand just because of the table because he knew exactly where it was on the table
And what
Properties it should have
That's when the periodic table
Stop to pee just a clever and nice looking arrangement of elements and really became a scientific
Tool that had real
Predictive power
But for most of us who know nothing of the Alamo
What's on the table
Most of us
It's Major Impact is as an object of Art
A scientific icon
Poster
Hang up between the Smiths and REM
The infographic
Apotheosis
This moment right now is especially
Intriguing you're looking at the design of the periodic
Table because last spring
Scientists announced the discovery of an element on the bottom row
What was element 117 whose temporary name is inceptia
Classic
Annette actually
Pleated
The seventh row of
The periodic table is sort of squared it off in the bottom right
Corner
And this is the only time
In history that we've ever had eight
Complete and full periodic
Tables the rest of the elements were discovered in pretty haphazard order
Asador always gaps or holes
But right now we have a
Full complete and Berry
Attractive.
So if you like your periodic table squared off in Thai tea
Well this is
The time to be alive my friend
And given the fact that the
Elements along the very bottom row
Are very fragile
Scientist don't know if they'll be able to
Plead the eighth row if that ever gets started to create one or more elements
To start a new row
Increase accuracy
The correct word because
Do you bake new elements
Are made by Smashing together other elements in a lab
The same King doubts that they'll be able to
Manufacture one that will fit into
Each and every column
So so right now is not only the only time we've ever had a complete
What it could be
The only real complete
Periodic table will ever
99% invisible with produced by Miro and Mars with support from lunar making a difference with creative
It's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco in the center for architecture and Design
Define amore
Go to 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com