99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Without other beeps without Sonic feedback all of your modern conveniences would be very
Hard to get
I mean try using your telephone without the
The beeps and it's
Really confusing
You're lost
Immediately
Play did I get it no I didn't get it the numbers there but if you hear it
Used to get it physically with the Rotary
Found this whole world is artificial
When I started I was working with this guy at the advanced product group at Apple
He had a case for a
Walkman I think and he opened it up and he closed it
Can you heard it
Click
And he said somebody work really hard to make that
Sound that way
That was an an acoustical element on a
Mechanical device in a lot of moving Parts in mechanical bits and today's devices but gimmicky still has to
To make him sound right my name is Jim McKee
And I have a company called earwax Productions we do sound for film radio
Internet and
Products Amazon
Quite simply a product sound designer looks at a product and thinks
What kind of sound should this thing make when it does a particular thing
So typically what I do is I create a bunch of button sounds he's our would-be buttons for a Yahoo widget
Say okay you guys tell me which ones are the closest and then you end up with
What 38 Sounds here
I love that
Like it wasn't about all day
Let's hear it again
Oh yeah
The best sounds are not completely synthesized they come from the everyday world my top drawer my dresser drawer
Over the years I've been collecting all these little things
Just I would like I would leave
Leave it there all out
How cool is his little tiny
Chinese ceramic bowl or no
Some kind of funky clip
And I realize that all these things are very kind of intimate to me very close to me but they make sounds
And the one cool and was dropping a
Small marble into this
China Bowl
And it has a dynamic to it which
Everybody's familiar with it bounces but then it
Let the marble sped up
Eq2 knows what all sorts of things
Actually the funniest one the one that everybody loved and it's seems to have stuck
More less across-the-board his
The sound of a
Vise grip
Opening up
Cuz it's got the click in the spring
And for some reason it just
It really works and
People
Like the way it sounds
I think you can hear
Almost the same sound when you plug in your iPhone
Ticket powered
You know that
Ono when you turn it on
Hear it
Is a device that sounds or design correctly it creates a special theater of the mind that you completely buy into
Electronic things
Fuel mechanical it's the feeling of movement texture in articulation
Where none exist
Jimmy Keys most recent phone project the sounds that work best with the ones you felt
Resonating quality of the sound in relationship
To the
Chassis itself is what sold it
I feel
That really feels like Sparta
And once you find those frequencies that resonate in a device you keep it
Flooring that space
Almost got to the point where I didn't even have to ask them which one they were going to select
Cuz I would give them
Typically it would give the
Doesn't
Wants to pick
Varying volume varying slightly and patch
And I go okay it's going to be 46
And they come back
I don't know why but that seems
How to work a lot better
You take any actor and put them in the room
And they're immediately going to find the size of the room with their voice
It's
Human Nature
And so why can't we expect the same thing out of our devices
It needs to feel like
What's indigenous to this
Pizza Plaza
99percentinvisible was produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar making a difference with creativity
Is a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects Tampa
Sysco in the center for architecture and Design
To find out more
Put it 99% invisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main got to know how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com