99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
Salute on cannabis vodka
Let me start with this
The invented language of Esperanto has a flag
And it kicks ass
Greenfield
White Canton in the upper left corner of the green five pointed star on it
I'm feeling bored
Because of the design of the flag alone
Seriously
I could March in the streets behind that flag
But that's not the Esperanto way at all
Esperanto
Is about hope
It was created in the 1880s by polish eye doctor
Ludwig salmon
He lived in this town Bialystok where there were holes
Choose
Germans in Russia
And they all spoke different languages and they all hated each I
So he had this
Idea that if everybody's
Common language they
Communicate
Each others
People and there wouldn't be any more racism or
Conflict which is a beautiful idea with the same green my name is Sam green I'm the director of
Utopia in
Four
One of the four movements of Sam greens live documentary is about zamenhof
Utopia of Esperanto
The 20th century
Certain
Flowering of utopian energy and
Ultimate winning
The end of the Sun
7 Hospital dream of peace to a shared second language never came to pass
According to estimates somewhere between 50000 and 2000000 people speak Esperanto
But that shouldn't
Suggested Esperanto is a failure
In the history of invented languages
Greatest success story ever
Guess number two
Erica Oak
My name is Erica ocrant and I'm the author of in the land of invented languages
Esperanto with a real product of the time
Early 20th century when nationalism was
Tearing Europe apart
All these old Empires were crumbling and the lines around which they fractured where linguistic ones
Tell me a lot of sense to say hey let's find a linguistic solution to our problem
The mantle of Esperanto as the king of invented languages also had to do with its design
As a language Esperanto was designed to
Have
As simple as
Possible a grammar all nouns end in o all adjectives end in a
Verb tenses indicated by regular endings and it never varies so there are no irregular verb
She learn a finite number of endings in a few root words
And you're up and running
After a few weeks
Woodstock commune
But it's other strength is that it's not
To engineer
Being over design is up
Fall of many other invented languages
Previous project
Tried to be so consistent and regular ants
Breakdown the entire world of
Concepts into their component pieces
Which letter would contain a part of meaning within it
Those hundred languages are impossible to use
Esperanto has nice
Floppy Middle Ground if it's a nice balance between system atticity and arbitrary sloppiness
And when it comes to language we need both
Of those things in our natural languages we need a way to get
Pacific Rim we need to with a we have
Stuff like legal jargon but it also lets us just sort of
Talk without
Necessarily knowing where we're going with it or no
Exactly what we mean
So Froyo language Adventures out there don't make it
Too Perfect
A little
Fuzziness is key
So is artistic
Expression from the beginning xiamen hofstrasse poetry and music
Esperanto
And there are unique aspect to the language
That make it especially Suited
To a kind of poetic word
With endings you can make any word into a verb so if you
You have blue eye meaning
Blue you can also have a verb
Blue eyes
Is bluing soap and Esperanto
Conseil not yellow
Estas blue eyes
Sky is blue
But nothing really wants to be in Sp
Save-A-Lot yellow
Blue waffle
The sky is Bluing
And that's a very
Esperanto way of expressing it
Anywhere can also be an adverb
Which is strange not many languages
Pandas
So you don't say
I go to the beach in the summer
USA
Summerly
I go to the beach
Some early I go to the
The beach
If you do not approve of that sentence
I don't want
How to live in your dark and joyless
Little world
What are the ultimate irony is of Esperanto is that
One of its most widespread uses in the US
Was during the Cold War
The US would do these war game
Against
Fictitious
Anime the maneuver enemy
Also known as the aggressor
And they'd have to have the enemies
Speaking a different language
And since they didn't want to ask
Send any other country they couldn't have them speaking Spanish or French
Russian even
They had them speaking
Esperanto
Esperanza was used by the US Army so it wouldn't possibly offend another country and cause some unnecessary,
So even in this
Think we American completely Twisted context
Esperanto achieved
Exactly
What it was designed to do
99% invisible with produce by me Roman Mars with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco and the center for architecture and Design
To find out more and see the flag of Esperanto which
Alicia do
Going to 99% invisible. Org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
Maven
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an act
Watch a movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com