99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore
Digging into unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of Love Letters
Asuna episode that brings you along to the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family
For 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
It's a big Majestic building on Nathan Phillips Square and this is my friend Sean Cole
In Toronto Ontario
New city hall
Its forms
Totally of concrete are these two towers that start
Curve like
Hands cupped around a
The clamshell to this was a big deal when it opened in 1965
The first
Modern concrete Civic building for Toronto inserted very prominently into the Victorian fabric
Master Cummins used to work in the city planning office in the east
Tower on floor 19
She's an architect building really
Explored and exploited
Possibilities
The concrete everything was about Concrete in Toronto back then
Play of a capacity versus
Transparency in everything
So that the furniture really picked up on that
Yes
Even the office furniture inside City Hall was made
In Paris
Of concrete
But let's back up
In the fifties
China decided that it needed a new city hall
So there was an International Conference
And in 58
There was
Define selected by finish
Architect Billy Oroville
But he wasn't satisfied with simply
Designing one of the most prominent buildings the city of ever seen
Know or go what you know
Proposed that he was also going to design the furniture he wanted to design the furniture
He had a vision
But it wasn't to be the decision I made was to commission the furniture thrift second competition
Summerville was very disappointed
Set this appointment of his life and he subsequently passed away
City Hall El Paso
Or at least they felt the weight of the responsibility
So where the competition
To someone who really understood and capture the spirit of the building so they gave it to a company called
Any was the only design
Used concrete
Craft desks
Coffee tables cabinets
They all had
Concrete legs
The mayor's desk was this sleek
Concrete and Polished wood stain
And all of this
Was really expensive
And there was immediate
Public outcry
About the furniture particularly from the people who were actually using it there were
Complaints about the desks are wobbly and that
Secretaries typed on them they weren't sturdy
Put it through the legs are concrete how could it not be sturdy it's hard to imagine you
Toronto Star Furniture Rouse on again
In my research how many articles from that time
With all kinds of really interesting headlines
Wobbly deaths at City Hall spark new furniture
Controversy
Various officials at City Hall were fighting over at the receiving one
The talked about somebody quitting Rusty George Bell went out as coordinator today after a blazing row with bordick
Control over secretary
Desks
Sixties and
Hemlines were starting to
Shorter than the shield of the secretaries knees
And the new desktop no drawers
But magic Hellman's has sat at that furniture
Used to work at one of those
And it didn't wobble
When she said it's hard to imagine because some of the complaints make no sense to her
And she has a theory
Once
Quite uncomfortable
People to
Internalized but this is really what the heck
Chosen
And perhaps there was a kind of anxiety about this new modernism in this new concrete that we were inserting into our traditional
So
Perhaps the furniture which was kind kind of mimetic
Of the building
Mimetic
Relating to characteristic of or exhibiting mimicry okay so perhaps the furniture which was mimetic of the building
Served as an outlet
For that anxiety
And perhaps this is why
The controversy
Didn't seem to me
How much time
Later of the complaint was that it was
Difficult to move and so on so of course you know actually holding on to update itself
Over the years
The furniture
Since it was not valued
It was it was lost just simply three replacement it was it was actually thrown away
But not all of it
It's kind of like a
A haunted house
Looking for them
They are here
In the late 80s the city's director of Urban Design at the time saw what was happening
This is a very subtle one
And put the word out to the rest of City Hall
If you replacing your concrete Furniture he said send it up
The 419
We like it
Which is why today
Whatever does were mean
Is
Still have wisdom in the Urban Design offices which are within the sea
City Planning Department there's a bit of it scattered elsewhere to the mayor still sets
Concrete desk
But mostly
Floor 19 is the Florida of retired Concord
Free furniture notice the concrete unless you really
Squat down
The concrete legs are curved and smooth the Cabinetry is a little worse for wear
It's kind of
Furniture only an urban designer could love
People like Robert Friedman who runs the urban planning office now
Is there a certain aspects of it that aren't that bad
What's really heavy if you want to rearrange your office
Call it
Tema people in to help you do it
And I think most of the Planters Inn
Urban designers Retin-A 19 at 7
Are you training right lyrics
Opposed to the
Different eras of design
On our staff that me.
Divisions in the city
This plant look at this pain
Do I have to say
The furniture really grew on me
Wow
That is actually very pretty
Rooting for its survival
Which is exactly what magic Cummins wants me to do
So the hope
Is that
Its actual value
As a rather important piece of uniquely Canadian
Furniture Design will be Rec
Organized and that that it will receive the the restoration and then
Ducks Unlimited
Do you miss it
No
This episode of 99% invisible was produced by Sean Cole and me Roman Mars
With support from the lunar making a difference with creativity
I think life is much bigger than my old office desk
It's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco and the center for architecture
Grand Design
A nice desk though
Agreed
To find out more go to 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com