99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
Keeping money in a savings account
Let's Pretend you've never been to a bank
Before
Douglas McGregor
It's going to be our guide
You walk through the door you see the red carpeting you see someone in a suit there may be greeting you
USC some ferns I know a nice robe
National looking people in suits
Behind the counter
You don't really see what it is they offer you look around you're not going to see a lot of service
Know what you want going in there or you have to talk with someone
Help you figure it out
You think about it
There's no menu on the door
And you walk inside and
Like instead of giving you a menu they ask go to what do you want and you
Italian
And and then you have a conversation about what they could provide and
17 different sauces they could offer
Pasta
Reasonable person might think I could become
Second grade is a journal
My name is Douglas McGregor I'm a fellow at the new America foundation and I'm the editor-in-chief of Papa
What magazine
In a couple of years ago he wrote a story about Check Cashers in payday lenders
Switch Lecrae is quick to point out these are different services
Does check cashing
Is when you have a check that's made out to you
You going to the check
If you leave
Midas at 3% fee or so
And PayDay lending is when you don't have any money
So you write the payday lender a check
Act 4
$350
And you get
$300
And they cash it
Weeks those are the much more problematic transactions if you
I happen to think charging 400% interest is bad for the Working Poor
But McCray found that For Better or Worse
You know I think it's mostly for
Or Worse these places are here to stay
What may surprise you though if you have the same visceral reaction that I used to have to them it is a person
They're going to think they're
It's at least check cashing stores even with their problems
The fees are too high I can't say that enough of the Seas read most of them are too high May teach Banks something about using design
To better serve a wider range of customers
The absence of the bank like trapping
Plush carpeting for
Desk suits
They're missing for a reason
When Doug macray went on a tour of a branch with Tom next to at the time was the owner of the largest chain of check cashing
Stores in Southern California
Dick's pointed out the design choices he made
He pointed out the linoleum floor
He said you know if you go into a bank you're going to see a carpet of
And say a guy is coming off of his construction shift he's in his work boots
He walks across the car
Floor
He's going to feel
Like a jerk
I don't know if he's right or wrong but it was an interesting
And it was a conscious choice you know they would they would not put down
Carpeting
Nick's also work really hard to make his places seem just like retail
It reminds me a lot of a corner store only instead of selling
Chips and soda and stuff like that it's financials
And everyone patronizes and is welcome at a corner store
Rich and poor
And you know what everything costs
One of the most important things may be the most important
If this chain of Check Cashes Neal see this a lot of them
There was a
Big list of prices
And
It was all really straightforward
In the prices for the most part the prices were too
But you weren't going to wonder what something was going
You weren't going to wonder what they could do
Am I talk to people who chose to go to check
A lot of them it had a bank at one point
They signed up for some free checking account but then all of a sudden they had
Would like read these statements that were pages long and they could
Couldn't figure out why they were getting charged but they were getting
Charged plus you are paralyzed by the vast
Number of options available to you
If you go to your bank at chances are
It'll have like five.
Still have five different checking accounts will have all these investment accounts will have college savings accounts University to research
I'm it's hard to figure out which one is right for
And I for one always seem to leave with
The feeling that I picked the wrong one
The check cashers and payday lenders
Don't have a bunch of different service
But there will only be one of
So
You can cash your checks
You can wire money to your family another country and
It's all designed to be really simple
Let's pretend that you've never been to a bank before
I think some banks are realizing
They're cookie-cutter Suburban Branch you know they can't drop it down and
You know it's one thing if you opened a bank account with your parents when you were eight years old and you've been going there forever and all the weirdness the bank
Prices in the pamphlets and the ferns and all the stuff
It's kind of strange about it
Think about it
It's just normal cuz that's what a bank is
Suppose if you don't know what I
If it's not normal
Olivia sui
99% invisible was produced by me Roman Mars with
Support from lunar
Making a difference
Creativity
It's a project of kalw the American Inn
Institute of Architects San Francisco and the center for architecture and Design
Define at Morganton 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who know how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com