99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
Family ghosts is a podcast explores all the unexpected ways our family structure and shape our view
Of the world
Each episode of Family ghosts takes a look at the story behind a different person's family lore digging into
Unanswered questions about their history
Season 2 Launches on May 15th featuring an episode where they take you inside the love Israel family called
So what about uncovering the secret scroll in a newly discovered stack of love letters and Moon episode that brings you alone
On the hunt for a container of missing Chinese food that's haunted a family for 25 years and more
Subscribe to family goes wherever you get your podcast and find out why they say
Every house is haunted
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food
Energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life for all living things find out more at 21st century.
Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible I'm Roman Mars
I'm not one of those people who romanticizes the edgier grittier New York but this park
Has been overrun with dogs and babies
And this is my friend Benjamin Walker reporting from New York City's Tompkins Square Park the first Tompkins Square riot
Took place in 1857
A bunch of unemployed immigrants
Try to set the park on fire
And then in 1863 the parks are more trouble when the ultraviolet draft riots in golf
City but it was the right of 1874 that made Tompkins Square Park famous over 7,000 workers
Battle 1600 police office
Some on Horseback swinging clubs
Early labor organizer Samuel Gompers describe the riot as an orgy of brutality
In 1936 Robert Moses redesign the park
It supposedly
He believes his design
Was Riot proof
Well I guess what we knew about that is
Chakrabarti is a professor of architecture and design at colombe
Peking university
And the late 80s he had a girlfriend who live in your tongue
Square Park
So he is
Experience the riots
The 1988
First hand
It was pretty extraordinary
You didn't want to wander around here too much
Set night time once again activist battled it out with
Cops on horseback
But the difference with this riot
If you can watch it on YouTube
In 1992 the park was redesigned again and there hasn't been another riot
Yes yes there does seem to be a little bit of a deliberate intent
Taft
Make it more of a places
Do the circulation
Places of
Repose
You know one can imagine crowd control happening in a different way now that there's all these for
Circulation pathway.
But no big
Lawns in which
Kongregate
The height of the fences scene
Growing
Chakrabarti recently wrote an essay on the architecture of public
Protest for the website Urban omnibus
He examined some of the protests
Unfolding in the Middle East
But he's interested
In the physical
Full site
Thousands and thousands of people are coming together
The traffic Circles of Bahrain
And the large and open
In space that is
Cairo's tahrir Square
I think one of the most
Extraordinary
Sites
When we looked at the protest run tires
Square where that
Was young and older children and they were
Clearly better off and clearly worse off
I don't think
Did actions like that are possible in C
Without broad swath
Space
Chakrabarti recently toured the Middle East
And he learned that some authoritarian regimes
Are still keeping the Robert Moses
Tompkins Square dream alive
Designing
Control
If you go to rehab
The capital of Saudi Arabia here is
The city of
4 million people is growing
And yet there are virtually no public spaces other than
Shopping mall
Actually that's not exact
Play true there is a giant public
What's square in Riyadh
Deera Square
But the only time the public is really allowed to
Kongregate
Is when there are B
Beheadings
That's why expat
Call it
There's a sore drain the diameter of a
Pizza
In order to evacuate the blood
Chakrabarti says the Saudi royalty doesn't need to build
Chop chop
Square or at the shopping malls
Cuz fear
Worx jawsaw
As well
Control
Doesn't need that much
Physical intervention
To be understood by the popular
There's a clear understanding that if you break the rules there are dire quoi
Now here in New York City's Tompkins Square Park
There is no pizza size
Blood drain
But there are fences
That keep people from coming together
The way they did in 90
You know a little gives a very tense time in New York serving history and a lot of
The more peaceful protesters were protesting about
Affordable housing
And I think those are very legitimate
Concern and actually I think it's really impacted policy
You know today the city of New York built
More affordable housing a year than the entire State of California
Bichon chakrabarti is not saying that open space necessarily lead
The social chain
But what do you want us to see
When we watch those giant crowds in the Middle East on
TV
Is this
One could argue
That
Nations actually may not be able to change without the
Kind of activities that happen
Pain in the public spaces
Of cities
99% invisible was produced this week by Benjamin Walker and me Roman Mars with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity it's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco in this
Center for architecture and Design
Devon at Morganton 99% invisible. Org
Hello 99 percentile it's me Roman Mars and I have a little bonus for the podcasters and website streamers
This week story is from my friend Benjamin Walker and he has his own program on WFMU call too much information
And if you do not listen to too much information you have basically resigned yourself to have one hour of your week
Suck
When it could actually
Be awesome
When I asked him to do a story for 99% invisible I told him to highlight something that was kind of hidden
Has some greater thought InDesign put into it
I said
Toy Story like that penis graffiti store you did 40 Mi but I can't use that one because I can't talk about genitalia for Foreman
Morning Edition
It's actually a really nice story about funny meaning when it seemed like the most
Artistic displays but
Still too many penises for 7:30 in the morning
But alas it's
Perfect
For the podcast so
Young Master Gilbert please check with your dad if it's okay but for the rest of you
This is Benjamin Walker
Again
Promise program
Too much information
Gaylon Smith lives in Brooklyn and works in Manhattan
And so he spends a lot of his time
Riding the subway
And waiting for
Living in New York
You know you see a lot of graffiti and in the
The time. Which I've lived here
Mike the Knight ESO now
It hasn't been real big
Classic 70s and 80s train mural
Send it hasn't really been that that famous New York style that really
Yeah got the ball rolling all around the world it's quick tags and quick
Throw ups
Nothing much
Pieces
The majority of these quicktags
End up
On the posters
On a Subway platter
You know dude
The are knocked out teeth
The zombie eyes like all the other the blacked out or cut out eye sockets
You know your mustaches all the way from
Chaplin Hitler
Over to El Salvador Dali Style
But you know I'm a graphic designer in overtime I got
I got past the initial feeling of
Blur
And then something really jumped out of made it in a way that most obvious things like their penis is growing
Almost on every single poster
Jaylon Smith is the author
New York DEC
A book
About to Subway penis
A Primitive little symbol to be sure
But one he believes
Is giving voice
To our true feelings
About our media landscape
These posters are are ubiquitous if you're if you're having traveled in New York you may not realize that there are
On practically all Subway platforms and there are dozens of them they're all over
The place they're in there in your stair literally in your space there about the height you are
Turn their large
Very unlike print ads in
Nothing like
Video types
And you're sort of bombarded with them
All the time and even if you don't think of your
Being bombarded
You're hanging with
A lot
And it can get really tedious
Especially if it's one you don't
But in this
Spec's in this country
Text you really can
Make your own counter argument your own counter state
And everyone knows what you mean
How is this different than
Say like
Conventional author
Graffiti tag
Glenn sings it makes it different in for me makes it really interesting is that it's
It's even more folklore
There's no
There's no authorship there's no getting famous
Well now you're not even really getting a lot of credit with your friends
I mean your friends may have been here giggling with you when you did it
But it's not really like your you know going all city with these things
No one's claiming a cigar
Everyone knows it's a little stupid
If there's something about
The idiocy
That is part of the
Part of why it works so well and
Like it in our culture way to show absolute disrespect
Is the draw this penis
But that's a very New Yorkie
Conversationalist how
New Yorkers like
Seether
Very aggressive
Moderately clever
And really thought of it
Disrespect
But honestly just
Respectful
The person drawing a penis didn't start the
Versation they didn't think they were winning and dominate
Communication
The Advertiser in the
System did
And so it's a way of
Putting some brakes on this
Is ramp
Concert
Getting over on one
Good advertising
Seems to feel that it's doing all right I like advertising okay I find it very interesting and away and so mad.
Really fun
But a lot of them aren't
Every time I see one of these penises now
I get
Kind of excited
It's like finally
Proof that there are tons of people
Who feel the same way I do
About our ever encroaching commercial world
Hunza people
And they're all saying the same thing
Screw
You
Really
It's awesome
This is actually happening now
Real people
Making real comments
I'm in a real space
And it's
More of a community than than you might realize
New York City subway stairs
The conjoining that conversation
Or you can just witness it and give that sort of
A little bit of charcoal the living
I'm not saying I agree but I
That's an excerpt from Benjamin Walker's too much information find a link at the 99% invisible website
That's 99percentinvisible. Org
That's it for me this week I'm Roman Mars
Take care
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life you know that sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked to play superhero and
Any movie or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind of thing a few days ago Wesley Stern
After that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had some
Nothing to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do what
Whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
What's on the truth podcast. Com