99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today at progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business it's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that on
When your message will resonate the most LinkedIn can help
Lincoln is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers
Weather in beijing every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure
Customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn builds trust a free $100
Burlington add Credit in launcher first campaign go to linkedin.com invisible up linkedin.com
Cam invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment in California and
Around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
This weekend radio audience got a rebroadcast of episode number 10 about Chris Downing the blind architect which is
Often cited as an audience favorite so you should go download it if you haven't heard it already that's episode number 10
Call 99% sound and feel
Poppy podcasters I'm pushing out a special
Never-before-released fees that served as the basis for episode number three
I'm 99percentinvisible but it's never aired in its full Glory until now think I meant to say
Slightly Theses shifted double length director's cut of episode number three
The story is about how a new technology in this case
The smartphone in the rjdj Adaptive music app
Can only change your consumption of music but can also
Change the very nature of Music itself
I think it's actually a pretty stunning development in The Evolution of Music and has even bigger implications than it seems on the surface
So
Check it out
San Francisco it doesn't years ago I stopped over in LA to visit my friend Max
And as he drove me around the Hollywood Hills the song screenwriter's Blues
Buy soul coughing came on the car stereo
Twisted like knots on the finger that seem to sync up
With everything in the world at that Mom
When the turn signal was flipped on
It always kept the beat
Headlights whizz by in concert with the bass flute
And the storm would Crescendo just as a new amazing Vista presented itself to the windshield
And you are with the name
If you have the Walkman generation
But the iPod generation
Or if you take a lot of drugs
You've probably had this happen to you
And Michael Brian bruker is a big fan of the sort of musical serendipity
That's for me was worse always very magical moments
That's one of the reasons he created rjdj
A musical iPhone app that tries to give you that
Feeling
Every time you put on your headphones
We are you know combining the world around you with your listening experience
So you know
The door closes and something really amazing acoustically could happen
Denim I'm always feeling like
I'm more in the in the movie
But basically take the movie away and put your life into it
And that talk to you too
Robert Thomas is one of our jdjs composer
I'll try TJ
Create swap wiko reactive music
What you sent me for my music which
Changes in Valatie
Into what you're doing
Rjdj is comprised of saints which are analogous to song
But they're more like instructions for songs
Tabata music
Kodi iPhone Zone built in synthesizer
Audio filters
And these are triggered by the user
According to the composers
Planned for the sea
Coolest Quantum composing
Think of all these different possible ways that they
I'm listen to you
Come up with lots of different ways that that will
Create something very interesting
Music
When the
Sound
Coming in from the field surrounding this is very loud because I place a really fine as kind of gun
Dudududu dudududu dudududu
Making a video
And when the
Sound of your surroundings he's pretty quiet
You could have ready simple kind of drones
Just make it really kind of
Quietsource am
You can have
All kinds of past changes in the music based on
Analysis of that behavior
Change the song but so does the accelerometer in the phone
Time spent listening to be a factor and even GPS data can be incorporated
It all these stimuli work in concert to create an augmented reality
Which is the kind of mind-blowing thing money
The way I see is it
It kind of feels like you're seeing some in a beauty and everything
And I think that's why
Weather really great scene
The people that made so far already what
Did the most famous One
Call Monica
Real estate
Add my wife may put in the patented white earbuds and check out one of the scenes for the first time
This one's called the orgasm
Tricare number
Do do do-do-do-do
It's what I steel girder would hear up a steel girder could hear
Kind of like being in a horror movie but not quite horrible
I know it definitely has a horror movie soundtrack body like something bad is coming but you haven't hit this
You know yet but now we have cookies
The most users report that the eargasm scene makes them hear the beauty in all things
An environment where my wife is listening she said It felt more like a horror movie
And that's kind of rjdj in a nutshell
It's almost as if we have been in the silent movie before and and now you're you're all of a sudden in the
In the movie that has the soundtrack
Possibilities are endless
If someone made The Bourne Identity Chase music into an endless reactive music scene
I swear
There is nothing the CIA could do to stop
Yeah you heard me Panetta
But the makers of rjdj aren't content simply changing your perception of reality
They're really looking to change music itself
To understand this wave
Consequences of
This advancement
Tea
Composition of music
Thank you kind of have to
Look at it over readyyy time scale
Antenna
And if I had some severe zakat music with something that
I guess pass between people
And it's a song was heard and replayed by someone else it changed
Constantly
Relatively weak
We've invented
Notation
Tries to record what that is
What piece of me
In some kind
Motif
And very recently
We got used to the idea that
Music can be recorded
Unfrozen in
To some form
Conceptual object
And the object
ICD
2 vinyl
A type of
An MP3 that Wilkins
And at this
Point a single version of a song that's like a performance of a song became
But song
And those thousands of years of mutability
Ended
But the technology of rjdj puts an end to that
The studio is actually inside
The iPhone
Manassas actually watch it
Tjs videos
Studio inside the knife
When
That happens when
Set delivery point
Music
It's actually a studio itself
Something very much
Because
It means that
That mixed and that way freezing music
Kantime
Recording
It's no longer really necessary
It means that you can have
Multiple pops
Simple ways of a
Experiencing a piece of meat
So it's kind of like
Worlds of music
The promise of rjdj is an unparalleled musical synchronicity with your surroundings
Rather than putting on a set of headphones to block out the rest of the world
Rjdj listeners.
Plug into a constantly changing unique soundscape that connects them to what they're doing and where they are in the world
I imagine
Walking around San Francisco
Listening to a mashed-up composition of punk and Hip-Hop
It gives me a history of the neighborhood I'm traveling through
And the GPS will trigger a sound clip from Alfred Hitchcock's vertigo when I pass through Nob Hill
Do I need to do spells this week
I'm having one right now
Music
In the tempo of speed up as I
Scary out of the way of an obnoxious bike messenger into the path of an unnoticed oncoming cable car
My sudden lack of all movement as I
Lion the pavement while listening
Using a harmonica
Drone from the iPhone earbuds
Which one makes beautiful
The Sirens from the paramedics
As they approached
Stop
Or you can choose your own adventure
Unless it's over this week I hope you enjoyed it
18 to the coming weeks because I have lots of stories from me as well as stories from some of the best radio producers in the world who
What happened to me
Friends of mine which is Rockin that they're doing pieces for 99percentinvisible I'm so happy about that
So stay tuned for that
And spread the word you guys have been so great
So Twitter and
Login Facebook and joined up on Facebook and unlike it on Facebook I would really appreciate
Appreciate it
I'm still trying to get funding for the back half the year so everything you can do
Spread the word helps us out
Alright thanks so much
Ticket
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius a five-part series from fellow radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm having I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of thing if you
Days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it now I need to
To clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com