99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time and connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers those relationships often
Turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin have the marking tools
Help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach you can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about which in turn
Turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
How to make a concrete silo
Voicemail
Habits of red hot in a blue gas play
Stop it in ice water
Abrasion has a cut
Cement and rock particles in concrete not yet hardened
Abstract
Concrete
I first found Nico by staring at the sidewalks vigil is a journalist from San Francisco one of my favorite things is
Going to get lost in San Francisco and stare at things that I normally might have looked past and then I saw his name written the sidewalk
I thought it was interesting and then the block later found his name again
Beach and I found another one you know I would find them not just to North Beach with Chinatown Russian Hill Telegraph Hill they were
References to the street name like me
Downtown
I'm just saying to myself
Dam Nico is everywhere
And then I looked down and it said
I know I felt like a dude and I remember thinking that I'd this is my duty to write the story and then
Coincidentally I'd run across
John doody
So Delphine decided to track Nico down and I want to know if this guy Ally Why did you do it was the first time I've ever felt like I was the one
Pay attention in class attack started in 1967 because I saw the date 1967 I figured you must have been about
12 years old
In some ways I got to watch him grow up because I felt like his personality kind of got a little more Boulder Through The Years earliest F Majesty
And later on you concept artist
I figured he went to school in the neighborhood so I went to the High School Galileo and I went to Francisco Middle School
And so I would start photocopying yearbook pictures from the 60s and 70s
And I would face this on guys who look like they just had that
Artful Dodger look in their eye
In this investigation went on through years of dead end
Knocking on Strangers doors
And getting nowhere live right now you're thinking I love this Nico kid He's My Hero 2
Wait for it
Here it comes
I was by the North Beach playground
I believe it was rainy day
And rainy days are always the best days
To read the
Because it washed away a lot
Could read things that on other days you probably couldn't see
And I saw this etching
That was the longest that I've ever seen it took over an entire sidewalk blah
It was like a paragraph
I think it said
Right now
Home by the Jews
First word begin with an n
I can actually say for sure I mean I can presume what it said
You probably can too but that those of those letters were actually washed away
Foot traffic
And then I found quite a few others and it was
Yeah I'm never talking 10 15 20
As far as I could tell from the and ride
I didn't want to believe it
Cuz it didn't go with
You know what identified with
I mean to some extent I wanted to identify as
Loner kid in the city 2 and this happened right before I go
Finally found it
One of the leads finally panned out
Can I prolong email Court
Delphine vigil grabbed his notebook and my
Microcassette
And Matt
Nico
How did unabomber get caught
I like Chinese shoes
Can I cure tiny shoes
I like you drop something
How many things you've done
At least it.
Neko describe all the places
Tagged in detail and Delphine believes the vast majority of them
From this one guy
My thoughts were that
If I do this really
Do it right
This stuff will last way in the future
The concert will be all washed away
It's kind of like any store you get into and you have a hunch about it a lot of
It was very close to
What I imagine a lot of it was completely different
He did have a very Artful Dodger lifestyle
His father was out of the picture
And
Barre bohemian
Upbringing
Kind of like a real Carefree parenting style he was just this
Kid who
We're sort of in some ways forgotten
And after a few meetings Delphine finally found the opportunity.
To ask the hard questions
I will see you abandon all none why
Stockton tunnel in nit
Hill news how about white race Consciousness keeping
The same block as
I I can pick out about 15 to 20
Same to me would be the same guy who didn't
But if I'm wrong
Can I was a kid growing up in the city
I'll talk a little kids Sunday
We would go to
March in Oakland for civil rights
Keysmart
On Monday
School
By the very people
That we were out
China sounds absurd now
When you get right down to it I was a boring Suburban kid rebelled against their parents they go to the opposite extreme.
Pirate's hat
Totally understand
PetSmart
And that explanation would sit better if the past wasn't written in concrete
I'm not reading my name and I've written his name
And what color
In fact that was the first
Line I wrote for the story was in the sidewalk
Walk up Montgomery Street to the Union Street steps and make a right at Green Street and
Right there unless it was double parked on top of
Sit still say
I found
99% invisible with produce this week by Stephanie Foo and me Roman Mars
A different version of the story was originally broadcast on the public radio program snap judgment which
I know you already subscribe to but if you don't
Do yourself a favor go find it in the iTunes and subscribe
You will love it
This program is made possible with support from lunar
Making a difference with creativity
It's a project of kalw the American Institute of Architects San Francisco in the center for architecture
Design
Define armoire
Including how you get your hands on Delphine vigils
Self-publish chapbook
All about the Neko story with beautiful illustrations and way more detail than I can go into ear
Go to our website
It's 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden 2 playlist
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action
Movie called Immortal cop was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine even worse the cops think that I had
Something to do with it now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com