99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay
Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match
Limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customer
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and ended
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com
Invisible
Beer free $100 at
Bad credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
As we are approaching on a 300th episode of the show The 99 guy crew took a couple days to go on a retreat at the coast
Listen to audio that inspires us and talk about the future of the show
Because of all the time it took to plan and execute the retreat
We have one of our rare rebroadcast this week and I'm happy to Revisited because this is a pivotal episode 4
9% invisible and one of my personal favorites
It was a really ambitious story for Avery at the time and we knew it was going to be important so
We commissioned an original score for the first time
Commercial real
Later came on staff to be our full-time composer if you haven't heard this episode
You're in for a real treat
Did you have
You should listen again because I think it gets better each time I stay to the end because we have a brand new interview with Sean that I
Conducted late last night on the foggy California coast
About the score for this episode in the process of composing music for nerds
To talk over
Here we go
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
All over New York City there are so many clothes or nude women
And they are so baked in architecture that we don't even see them
For example when you enter the New York Public Library on the left hand side there's a sculpture of a young woman leaning against a horse
On 59th and 5th
There's a statue of a woman holding a basket
107th Street and Broadway there's a woman reclining on a bed
That's former New Yorker Avery trufelman
100th and Riverside Drive
A stone woman sits
In a chair with a child
Very top of the New York Municipal Building
There's a golden woman holding a
Crown
And these women
Or actually
The same woman
Audrey Munson
Was the most famous artist model
In the United States
Over 30 statues at the Met are made in her likeness and she adores it doesn't the memorials and bridges and Regal
Buildings all over New York City
She basically was the equivalent of a supermodel at the time
This is Andrea Geyer
An artist herself and author of Queen of the artists studio
The story of Audrey Munson
Everybody knew who she was her picture was in the papers
And if one trust Legends I call every boy had a crush on her
She was a very desired
A young woman
In her lifetime
She would go on to decorate buildings and memorials all over the United States
Before becoming a movie star
And eventually getting embroiled in a sensational murder scandal
And although Audrey Munson's body has been immortalized in the iron and marble
Her name is mostly forgotten
But she was a prolific writer and pandas series of Articles telling her life in her own words
Sometimes and the third person
Where is she now
This model who was so beautiful
What has been her reward
Is she happy and prosperous
Arshi sad and forlorn
Her beauty gone
Leaving only memories in the way
Like so many supermodels that would come after her
Audrey Marie Munson was scouted on the streets of New York City
In 1906
Audrey's mother and father were divorced which was very unusual at the time and her mother decided to get a fresh start in the big sick
Audrey was 15
Enrolled in music school and one day
She was picked up on the street by a photographer
When she walked around with her mother this photographer gave Audrey his card and asked if she would pose for some portraits
Her mom was invited to so intentions were good
These photos were
Fully clothed
Audrey by chance was picked up as a model and then in the studio
Proof that she was somebody
Who was very good with the camera very good in creating a generating poses
Best photographer recommended that Audrey meet a friend of his the famous sculptor Isidore Conte
At first, he thought he didn't really need Audrey
But as Audrey herself later recalled
Suddenly he rose from the table walked about me asked me to stand and walk
And then said that he thought he could use me
Fedmyster Conte
You will have to pose in the altogether
Posing in the altogether mint posing naked
Audrey's mother consented
If they would have been wealthy people I don't think her mother would have let her pose in the nude
From that encounter the resulting sculpture was
The three muses
Three nude women with their arms around each
All three
Model
Dr. Audrey
For decades the sculpture was in the lobby of the hotel Astor
Audrey called this statue quote
A souvenir of my mother's consent
And this was the first of many sculptures that you would model for his Door County
Audrey began to work for many other famous artists in New York
As a reputation grew choose recommended from Studio 2
Studio and slowly
Her likeness appeared mostly naked or half-naked
All over the city
The New York Sun dubbed her Miss Manhattan
But Audrey is not always recognizable in sculpture
Her figure is different in different artist eyes
Sometimes she's lying
Sometimes she's Fuller
In sculpture the sculpture there are no obvious giveaway is that you're looking at Audrey's body
The clues are in her face
Expressions
Of the eyes and the mouth into nose
Like once you know how she looks you can see her everywhere
It's really fascinating I would like look at sculptures in the moment and be like
That looks like her and then research and be
Yeah be right that was her
Before it was easy for artists to snap a reference picture
Audrey could pose in a way that could invoke a mood
She must have been a very empathetic person she could really
Translate emotion
Fully into her body
Battery can hold the same pose for hours sometimes for an entire day
And she worked closely with the artist
Learning their temperament
Familiarizing yourself with their past work
She thought of herself as a collaborator
That she told the New York Herald in 1915
Study
Yes indeed I do
Every model who is a realtor
Success must study the work
What is a person
Cheese with
Audrey's unique set of skills earned her a decent salary
About $35 a week
Which today would be like $800 a week
She made enough to give a day's salary to the suffragist movement
Which was in full swing around her
Audrey with an independent
Confident Woman
Had a good time to be a
Because the architecture that was in Vogue in the United States from the end of the 19th century through World War
Was the Bozart Style
And this style required a lot of sculptures and detailed ornamentation
A great time in many ways
To be an artist
This is architectural historian Karen McNeil
Whether you an architect sculptor A Painter
Across person making lamps
Using Bozart style architecture
Virtually all state capitals are in this style
That image of an authoritative building with
Columns and statues all around maybe a big dome
That's bosarts the style is a cross between like
Stately Greek Parthenon and Flowery French Versailles
So a Bazaar building
It's a greek temple but then you do have the sculptures on it you do have the freeze work you do have all of this
Ornamental detail that is integral to the building and architecture and sculpture
Are we bound together in this movement
When you take a decorative elements off of a bozar building
It started looking weird the dimensions don't quite work anymore
Also the sculptures are signs of the buildings purple
The very overly representational
Like in a private home the statues are of domestic scenes
Sore on a market there of harvest and eating
Are government buildings
Say San Francisco City Hall it's all going to tell us about this is the seat of government in California so great
Fabulous and
But it's all going to be allegorical
In a government building you might find a statue of a woman holding an olive branch
Or the scales of Justice
Representing the state liberty
Truth
You name it just women placed on this
Pedestal
Virtue
Morality
Motherhood nurturing
Strength
Women decorated the seat of power
They didn't say that
Why's it gotta be a lady
Because women are pure
You know a woman with a spear
She would only use that
Spirit to really defend her kids
Right so it has two
And for several years is pure uncorrupt symbol of virtue in the US
Was Audrey Munson
She was everywhere
The World's Fair in 1915 held in San Francisco
Audrey posed for 3/4 the statues on the premises
Her face and body
Appeared
Everywhere throughout the grounds
What's Aaron Garcia of the California Historical Society
She curated an exhibit about the 1915 Panama Pacific Exposition in San Francisco
Where Audrey Munson was dubbed
The exposition girl
In a court of Four Seasons she was the seasons of the Fountain of energy
She was the Priestess of culture at the Palace of Fine Arts she posed for 91 figures meant to represent
At the stars
She was all over the place
What about 24 years old Miss Manhattan had won the West
And there was a new form of RN during the scene
Cinema
The obvious next stop for Audrey Munson was Hollywood
And Hollywood was
Unfortunately
The beginning of the end
Probably monsters
Cheers cast in a few films after the exposition but in every case she has cast
As a nude model
As an artist model and she appears nude
Body was actually the first leading woman in Hollywood to appear naked on film
Audrey may have been a good model
But she honestly wasn't much of an actress
If you've heard films she actually had an acting double
To basically do everything except the naked posing
In the movies and end up really being worth it for her financially she was paid very little
And none of them seem to have been critical successes
That might have been okay for her her career might have survived.
But then unfortunately she was involved in a murder
Scandal Audrey and her mother had an apartment in New York
The landlord doctor Wilkins
Fell in love with Audrey her landlord apparently became obsessed with her
And
Killed his wife
So that he could be with Audrey
Romance with Doctor Wilkins
She and her mother had actually moved out of the
Before this happened
But they were questioned they had to testify in court and they were sort of dragged through the mud in the Press
The so-called Wilkins case became a phenomenal media scandal
As Audrey told the daily Variety in 1920
The Wilkins case ruined my career
I'll never count for anything again
I'm loving and admiring me the public seems to have grown to hate me
Audrey couldn't find any work
In Fillmore in artist Studios for the decline of Audrey career wasn't just because of the Wilkins scandal
She was after all
Totally innocent
Noticed a lot of factors changing in the culture around her
I want the Bozart style wasn't very popular anymore the Bozart style came out of Europe
And there is this thing called World War 1
Where Western Europe kind of fell apart
And so there was a questioning
About whether or not
We want to be using
That kind of symbolism
Both European and American Architects were trending towards modernism
Away from the old world bosarts presidents
Also the economics of Bozart style wearing possible
It became increasingly expensive
To construct these buildings and pay for all of the artists and Artisans to design all of the elements of
The building and install it
The architectural world didn't need Audrey like it used to
And also at 30 she was aging out of the business career as an artist
Come to an end and her money starting to run out
She moves Upstate with her mother
You clean homes to support them both as they tried to carve out a place for themselves
In the small rural town
Of Mexico New York
It's not an
Kind of open easy going
Andrea Geyer went up there to talk to people about Audrey nobody was unfriendly to me but
There's something
About these close-knit Community Square as a stranger you don't
Feel welcomed
Audrey could not get used
It's a Small Town life
Her whole adulthood she been traveling around the country
Studying art
Working with artist engaging in intellectual discussion
And wearing fine clothes
Suddenly she lost it all
Well she still had the clothes
People told me that she
Very flamboyant
She
Like to
Dress up and colorful garments I mean I'm sure she had a pretty
Impressive wardrobes
Was very outlandish for a small community but it wasn't just Audrey style that set her up
She would dress up on that and then part of her
Workout routine in the city was roller skating so you know you can imagine a beautiful woman with
Long hair and a turban on her head
You know trying to roller skate on a country
Unpaved Country Road Douglas
Quite a scene
The town new Audrey as that crazy woman who used to get naked for money
Parents would close their Windows whenever she came roller skating by
The kids of course were totally fascinated with her
But there was a general consensus that she was crazy
Just because she was differ
So it's not hard to imagine why she
Would have fallen into a depression
And on May 27th 1922 Audrey Munson attempted suicide
By swallowing poison
I don't know how
Committed her suicide attempt was
Maybe it was just an expression of being some her at the end of her line
After her failed suicide attempt
Several years went by
And Audrey's mother was struggling to provide for her depressed daughter
Just couldn't do it anymore
40th birthday June 8th 1931
Her mother checked her into the state mental institution
At that time it was extremely common for families
To put
Relatives into these institutions
In moments of
A financial hardship where they felt
They couldn't care for a person
Body remained in the institution into her 90s
Then she was put in a nursing home
30 miles up the road but this home for the elderly will situated on this little four-lane Highway
The highway with a little strip mall
Which attabar
End
She was known
Sneak out of the home for the elderly and
Sneak across the four-lane highway
To spend her evenings at the bar
Ordering drinks and telling stories of
4 * as a model and isn't
They could not
Stop this 90 something elegant older woman
From running across four lanes of traffic to go to the bar
It sadly meant that they put her back into the mental and
Constitution worksheet
You know spent the rest of her life
Audrey Munson live just short of her 105th birthday
She died in 1996
This public body that once represented truth
Civic Fame memory
The universe and the Stars
But anyway
For nearly two-thirds of our life
But that 1/3
That glorious third immortalized her
In place or all over American cities
Perched High
Quietly out of sight
Staring down
I'm wondering if many of my readers have not stood before a masterpiece of lovely
Sculpture a remarkable painting of a young girl
And ask themselves a question
Where is she now
This model who was so Beauty
What has been herbivores
Is she happy and prosperous
Arshi sad and forlorn
Her beauty God
Leaving only memories in the way
An interview with 99percentinvisible composer
Sean real
But after this
Between the beats
Bongs and chatter of our devices
We're immersed in a cluttered world of man-made sound
If
I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis
Talking to me and my wife is in another room in a kid is another remembrall hearing that voice
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trap
Mets Joel Beckerman is a sound designer and composer
Who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights to 50
2%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding and some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural
Experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights
50%
We're presenting to special episodes from 99% invisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
About how are sounds gay
Is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Friday is May 17th and May 24th
Right here on the 9th 9 p.m.
We need to talk about something
Constipation abdominal pain and bloating yourself
It's not that bad you take laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine
But thinking about it all the time is frustrate
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again
And you don't know why and it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast
We can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God. Info / podcast
Oh my God
Black podcast
As I mentioned earlier Miss Manhattan was the first time we work with our composure Shawn real
And during our Retreat last weekend
I pulled
Sean out of a rousing game of Dixit
And ask them how that came about
I was in my car I was
Walking dogs as a job
And
She got a text from Avery that just said
Would you want to come
Compose music for the show
And I like had to pull over because I was so excited it was
It felt like a dream come true
Do you remember anything specific about the music from this episode The Audrey Munson
Episode in particular that you were
Really proud
One of the challenges I was having was
I really wanted
To get like the right textures for it because it felt
I felt like such a special story and it felt like
It was this architecture that was coming to life that like had life in it Audrey Munson personnel
Body that was like infused in the sculptures
And one of the things
But I felt really satisfied about
Was this one sound a guy.
When
I was trying to think like what is like
Stone and Marble and
Those kinds of things what kind of texture with
Feel
Representative of that and
Have this thing called the Glockenspiel it's like a little xylophone that's made of metal and it's more like a Chinese kind of a saint
Usually
Hit it here in a lot of indie folk bands and stuff
So I like Toca and
I'd like Dennis
Before
Just taking a bow like a cello bow and just seeing
What it does with
Pretty much anything
Cancel
So do you thinking of like those kinds of exercises
I took the cello bow and I
Put it on the glockenspiel
And it had a very kind of like
Coarse texture
2 Atwell still like maintaining it's like beautiful tone like it had like a very
Specific tone and so I like actually took two bows and I was able to like make harmonies
There's one specifically that
And the peace before the
Credits come up
Bap it is the screechy
Marbley Park
It's like probably one of the most Amorphis
Things I
Done for the show and it feels really
We could just think that like oh yeah that's the Audrey Munson piece that's like
The sound of Audrey Munson
What is the standard operating procedure for how
You work on the show and where you fit in
Structionsite
So it starts out with me talking with the producers about
The stories that they're working on
Are giving me life
Personalities of the people they're interviewing and
Bigger picture ideas of what they want to convey
And then when there's a first draft
I'm reading it and I'm kind of like
Writing
Music as I'm reading it and trying to like
Get an idea of pacing
But
It's really hard to
Lock that in
And iiii so I make sketches basically but it's hard to lock in like
The timing and stuff
Until we have
AR
Read through edit
Where we all
Set and we read through the script and play tape and then I record that and when I have that I can actually like
Do my recording
And
Make
Drafts of my songs Discord
A piece with
And then from there we like make a rough mix with music with the music drafts
And everybody gets notes on that
And then from there I like
Make any changes
That we want and
Do the final mixes
The pieces
Play doubt
The first time what is the most
Common teasel
That you
Get from
The producers of the show
But things are too busy
Is it
WhatsApp
I have a very
Dense sense of rhythm
It's just kind of the way that my head works I can't I can't do anything simply
And it's really helpful actually to sketch things out with midi because I can like
Just like
Do a cluster of notes
And then kind of just like go in and individually like pick this one out pick this one out pick this one out in like
Create a rhythm that like feels effectively the same but like isn't quite isn't going to be like
Grabbing for your attention,
People are talking and trying to
Explain
Things about working with
Musicians
Scoring is that
Some of the most interesting stuff that's going on the music
Is in the same Zone as The narrator's Voice
And you at the clinic
So that it
Doesn't
Peed
I feel like it's a lot like being in a band like
It's hard to listen to music when
Everything is like
Really active in competing and it's just
I think of it like
Whatever is happening in the story right now is
Delete instrument and I'm
There to support it the other instruments aren't less import
For not being like the center of attention
It's all working together
So we're going to end
What would be
Composition
Lights go out
Proud moment
From
Everything that happened from
So 200
Up to now it is we're getting very close.
Episode 300
Really wide spectrum the written so much music
One that I really
I feel really proud of is
The credits music for manzanar
It feels very
Sweet in this way that I
Don't always get to lock into
Quite quite the same way so
Tumi
Alright so we're going to go out and on manzanar credit
Sean real
Roman Mars
Recording from Dillon Beach
99% invisible retreat
Of 2018
Connecticut
99percentinvisible was produced this week by Avery truffelman
Music by genre
Katie mingle is our senior producer whole state is the digital director
Delaney Hall is the senior editor
The rest of Team includes reviews
Emmett Fitzgerald
Aaron Meza
And me Roman Mars
All Audrey Monson quotes unless otherwise noted were taken from a tell-all series called
Queen of the artists Studios
Munson wrote for the New York America in 1921
Audrey Munson was voice by Cara Rose Devon.
We are brothers 91.7 kalw in San Francisco and produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
We are part of radiotopia from PRX a collective the best most Innovative shows in all of pocket
We are supported by our listeners
Just like you
You can find the show and join discussions about the show on Facebook you can do to me at Roman Mars in the show at 99 Peoria
Run Instagram Tumblr and Reddit to
But we have more visual design stories and videos to
And 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from below radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a dark
Comic mystery
That whines through a
A treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
Or lose a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind
Nothing
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse
The cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 parts
Saint the truth podcast
Dot-com