99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
The new film green book
Is rolling out across the country
I have not seen the film so I can't speak to its merits or its shortcomings
The wall people are possibly being introduced to the concept of the green book for the first time
We thought we'd we released this story from a few years ago about the origin and significance of the green book
The Negro motorist travel guide to the segregated us
It's amazing story and one of my all-time favorite
Is a special bonus in this episode will also be playing a green book story from Nate dimeo of the Memory Palace
Native coincidentally written his Memory Palace episode called open road about the green book and we both release them without having her
Her the other
And I think hearing them one after another
Realtree
Highlights are shows
Similarities and differences in our approach to a subject
It makes me very happy to share them together today
Opelika
This is the American dream
Freedom on wheels
I know the movie Babe
Traveling on time-saving super highways
Futurama's the 1940s 50s and 60s were the Golden Age of road travel
Cars have become cheap and roomy enough to carry families comfortably for hundreds of miles
Racine highway system it started to connect the country smaller roads into a vast Nationwide Network
Finally Torres could make their way from New York to California with the windows down and the wind in there
We're here seeing the Grandeur of America along the way we have become
On Wheels with more motorized Mobility than ever dreamed of before
But of course this freedom and Mobility wasn't available to everyone
Splash of cold water Delaney Hall the year that Federal funding made the internet
State highway system possible Jim Crow was still the law of the land
Racial segregation was enforced by law
And had been since shortly after reconstruction
In many parts of the north the codes were enforced in practice
Cool road trip really complicated for black Travelers
How is this is that a good level it saw you picking me up well there
This is Curtis grave
Hey my name is Curtis Graves and I'll go in 1938 so I'm a little older than most of the people who listening to
Curtis would eventually become a Texas State representative
And then he go on to work at NASA
And then he'd become a photographer
What is a kid he grew up in the segregated South
And for many years
His parents tried to Shield him from that reality
I've often said that both my mother and father were the best Liars that I knew
For instance we sat in the back of the bus
Because it was cooler there
We rode in the front of the train because
Are you could get off quicker
I wish that upstairs in the movie because
You had better seats in the upstairs
Of course that ruse can laugh
And by the time Curtis with a college senior in Houston Texas in the mid-1950s
He was fully aware of what it meant to be a black person living under Jim Crow
There's one experience in particular that stands out in his mind
He was just 21 years old and getting ready to drive to a college meeting in Waco about 3 hours Northwest of Houston
Did agree to take a couple of acquaintances they happened to be white women but I said to myself
Might be in for some difficult times here
But you know I had to sold Yuan to get to Waco
Stretch of East Texas that was Notorious in those decades for racial violence oh yeah
Those communities were pretty bad around dusk The Travelers got hungry so they pulled over at a roadside
Thai Diner as soon as we got in the front door the guy said sorry but you can't come
And here we don't serve black people at all
So the three of them went back outside and Curtis devised a plan
They try another restaurant
Right across the street
I said to them the two of you go in get a table
And after you seated and the waiter or waitress comes up to you tell them that you have a boy that's
Driving you
And that you want to know whether he can you can bring him in to eat
So the women walked inside and they asked the waitress of Curtis could come inside to join them
Of course no problem at all
So as long as I was that boy
And their driver I could eat
With them at a table in a restaurant
But if I were equal to them I could not
This kind of humiliation on the road was routine and had been going on for decades
Many people wrote Into the NAACP around this time describing experiences
Just like curtis'
Don't make him CERN
Before starting my recent vacation trip to several eastern states
CP and an accord like to report an incident occurring on January 1st at a gulf service station in Macon
In Georgia
And I went to the restroom to refresh ourselves
Then found a vacant table
10 minutes past and no one came to service
He informed me that the restroom for the color was in the back
It seems to me dealers should not be permitted to sell gas and oil and not provide these comfort
Also
Some Travelers would drive all night instead of trying to find lodging in an unfamiliar and possibly dangerous
They talk picnic so they didn't have to stop for food
Some people would even carry portable toilets in the trunks of their cars
Knowing that there was a good chance they'd be turned away from roadside restrooms
But since 1936 a guy named Victor Hugo green I've been trying to help with some of these problems
Make life easier for thousands of black motorist
State-by-state deed in putting together a travel guide
Listings of restaurants hotels and service stations
That would welcome African American Travelers
He called it the Negro motorist green book
The green book for short
Victor green who died in 1968 lived in Harlem New York during the height of the Harlem Renaissance
His apartment was not far from Duke Ellington
His office would eventually be situated near small Paradise
A famous nightclub
Richard and have the most obvious background for starting a travel guide
He didn't work in tourism he wasn't a writer
He was a mailman in Hackensack New Jersey
But he kept hearing stories about discrimination on the road
So he would
Go do his route in Hackensack New Jersey come back home and work on the green book at night
Compiling these addresses typing them up and put them in a book for
This is Calvin Alexander Ramsey
Playwright author and filmmaker
And years ago
Calvin started researching the history of the green book
He learned that the green book wasn't really the first guy.
Science
In fact
Victor may have gotten the idea from Jewish Travelers
Because the Jewish Community was also having
Issues on the open road
A lot of places saying restricted
And it was a cold word for Gentiles only
When Victor published his first green book it just covered New York
And he heard around the country from other carriers and other people saying we really need this Nationwide
But it wasn't that easy together information from across the country back then long distance phone calls were expensive
And that Calvin says
Is when Victor green realized
That being a mailman
Was his secret superpower there were African-American let it carries all over United States
At this time we talked about 1936
And so he knew about you know
The relationship
That the mail men have with their
Homeowners or apartment dwellers
Delivering my mail so just like today the mailman is part of the community
So Calvin says Victor tapped into this network
Spreading the word about his guide through the National Alliance of postal and federal employees
A letter carrier Union
Calvin says postal workers across the country
Scouted potential Green Book locations and their cities and towns
He says it's some even asked families they delivered to
If they'd be open to hosting Travelers in their home
And if they agreed then
They will send the information to Victor Green in Harlem
Victor was able to get a feel for us
Of letter carriers who are all over the country
Acquire material and names and addresses and businesses for him black mailman
You got a green book salesman
For recruiter
Pretty quickly the green book caught on businesses many black-owned began getting in touch with Victor hope
Open to advertise and hoping to be listed
Black newspaper signed on as sponsors
Victor eventually retired from his job as a letter carrier and started working on the guy full-time
Keven opened unaffiliated travel agency
But hope Torres deranged traps
But still there was the challenge of distribution
How to get the Guide into the hands of Travelers who needed it
That happened in a few ways the United States travel Bureau signed on to help out
And then there would be more informal networks well churches
Pullman porters the Urban League NAACP
The Masonic lodges
There was a very wide varied distribution
Process in place for these Green books
And there was an important corporate sponsor to
A big one
Gas-X extra fine
SSO
Make
The Motoring
So also known as Standard Oil and now known as Exxon Mobil
Was one of the fuel oil companies back then then actively pursued Black customers they franchise their stations
Two African American operators
And he had a black representative on staff James billboard Jackson
Who helped plays Green books in many of those stations
As well as the White on Once
So may have done this out of a sense of fairness and equality
John D Rockefeller who founded Standard Oil in 1870
I married into a family of abolition
Who were part of the Underground Railroad
And he voted for Abraham Lincoln back in the day
But I probably did it for another reason to
Money honey
It has to do with money Curtis who had the crappy experience driving across East Texas
His dad operated one of the first black-owned Esso stations in New Orleans where Curtis was born and raised
It was called the Bootsy and Buddies
The economic logic of stocking the green book was pretty simple he says
If you want black people to buy your fuel
Why don't you give them an opportunity to see that they can travel and find places to stay
While they're on the road traveling
The Curtis's dad kept a shelf of Green books for
It's customers
You know if somebody came in and said no. Buddy I'm
I'm thinking about taking a trip to Chicago my dad would say well
Yep do you know where to stop between here and Chicago and other person would say no say what happened
The green book will tell you
And it gave you a sense of
Security
Into the green book came to cover listings in all 50 states and even some locations in Canada the Caribbean
CNN Mexico
They printed about 15000 copies a year
Wintergreen head change travel for thousands of African-American Torres
He wrote in a 1956 introduction to the guy
Now things are different
The Negro Travelers can depend on the green book for all the information he
This guy has made traveling more popular
Without encountering embarrassing situation
But as a civil rights struggle continued
Some people began to question the value of the green book
Black people many of them began to feel that this was accommodating to Jim Crow
Susan ruhe is a professor of history at Brigham Young University
And she says that the green book begin to seem a little out of step with the times
It really took on an overtly political town
Especially in its early days
And there were actually other black travel guides published around the same time the Dead
One called travel guide
Princeton
Travel guide
Listed where the NAACP chapters were
In each City
They were much
More attuned with civil rights
Much more political Town eventually the n-double-acp made it clear
An n-double-acp said
What we're striving for or striving for integration
That's their stand
Sheepey built out of their push for the 1964 Civil Rights Act which outlawed discrimination based
Sunrace and ended Jim Crow
Around this idea of total integration
In fact when the n-double-acp testified during the debate over the bill
They drew on all those letters they received about discrimination on the road
Fairfield to that vision of the iconic family road trip
The freedom to explore America by car
Roy Wilkins the executive secretary of the n-double-acp
Spoke before the Senate Commerce Committee
In 1963
As soon as Congress gets out they're all going to head into their station wagons and go back to their home just
Its July
In Washington
It's really hot
Will confess to send it to imagine what it might be like to travel as a black person
Would you like me to read what Roy Wilkins said
How far do you drive each day
Where what conditions can you and your family eat
Where can I use a restroom
Can you stop driving after reasonable day behind the wheel
I must you drive until you reach a city
We're relatives our friends will accommodate you and yours for the night
Will your children be denied a soft drink
Or ice cream cone because they are not white
Please appealing to them and at the most basic level of Their Own
Love for their own family
And Susan thinks this may have been one of the things that helped
Cast the bill
By Framing the narrative
Of civil rights as a family travel narrative
They were able to convince the Senators
Fallout 4 the Bell
In 1964 President Lyndon Johnson signed the bill into law
The Civil Rights struggle was not over then it's still not over today but Victor green it became clear at some
That is green book had a limited shelf-life
He wrote in the introduction to one of his guy
There will be a day sometime in the near future
This guy will not have to
Will be published
That is when we as a race
Equal opportunity
And privileges
United States
Ensure enough two years after the Civil Rights Act passed
The green book published its last Edition
Who actually could you just described where we
We're at the
Public Library downtown the central branch in Los Angeles
And I were down in the bowels
Force down Underground
And history and genealogy Department
And you have a stack
Of books are in front of you what are the who they are Green books
They're just little Jewels I mean I just buzzed with this kind of
Good energy that I just
I feel like all my God they're actually here
It's amazing it's amazing
Can Daisy Taylor is a photographer and a cultural documentarian
The guy she's holding her small maybe 8 in by 5 in
They have green covers each with a different destination featured
And there are pages and pages of listings inside
There were Beauty parlors barber shops
Taylors
Taverns or nightclubs
It was really a social network it was anything you might want to do in that town
And the resources that were available to you
Can they see has been traveling the country
Documenting old green book locations from California to Oklahoma to New Mexico
Many establishments are now run by people who don't know much if anything about the police's history
Some of the buildings are gone and what's left is just an empty lot or a patch of grass
Even either original copies of the guide are rare now
Smithsonian bought one at auction recently
For $22,500
Wow
Look in your if you're listening to
Can you know your parents you don't live during Jim Crow look in your attics and see you might have
Plus thousand-dollar
Can you do never know
$20,000 is a lot of money but back in 1936 when the green book first appeared in
Could be purchased for $0.25
Are the Travellers who needed it the most
It was arguably
Even more
Thanks to backstory with the American history guys for the recordings of the NAACP Red by Ali
Lisa Floyd
Steven Tolliver and Leslie Teleflora
And I'll letson
Who played the part of Victor green thanks also to Orlando Gonzalez at the National Association of letter carriers
And Jackie Moore at the National Alliance of postal and federal employees
We have another take on the green book from Nate dimeo The Memory Palace that you will not want to miss
Stay with us
Between the Beats bongs and chatter of our devices were immersed
In a cluttered World a man-made sound
If I'm in room listen to an Alexa interacting with Alexa not Alexis talking to me in my
Wife is in another room in a hearing.
Technology talk to us
It is a creation of Sonic trash
That's Joel Beckerman he's a sound designer and composer who studies how we can improve our interactions with technology
To make them more human
Turn the living room lights on
Okay
Dim the living room lights
50%
Okay
It's not exactly a thrilling conversation but taking away the fake human and adding in some thoughtful sound
Makes for a much more natural experience
Turn the living room lights on
Dim the living room lights to 50
80%
We're presenting two special episodes from 99percentinvisible and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation about how are sound
Landscape is impacting our health
And how we can humanize the sounds around us
Look for them Fridays May 17th and May 24th
Right here
NPI phase
We need to talk about something constipation abdominal pain and bloating you tell yourself it's not that bad you take
Laxatives modify your diet and exercise routine but thinking about it all the time is frustrating
It doesn't have to Define you if your constipation and abdominal symptoms come back again and again and you don't know why
Then it may be time to seek help
Go to oh my God. Info podcast we can learn more about your symptoms that's oh my God
. info / podcast oh my God
Dot and Bo
Black podcast
The Memory Palace is a longtime member of the radiotopia collected in a huge inspiration in the creation of 99%
Invisible if you don't already listen
You made a huge mistake my friend
You're about to hear why
Nate is the best writer in podcasting
Memory Palace
Is a gem
This is the Memory Palace
Niccaman
The couple on the cover ready for the road
Z Square job in strapping
She's pretty
Who carries both of their suitcases because it's 1948 and he's a gentleman
Maggie's dress like one
Tacos
Pocket square
Fedora hat at jaunty angle
She's got her hair done
Waves with curls beneath their Sunday Best hat
The couple picture they're on the cover of the 1948 edition of the Negro motorist green book
What a great picture of a particular kind of African-American aspiration at mid century
It's somewhere in those suitcases
Orion her clutch or in the glove box in the big old Asheville Pontiac for the Packard
Is a book
The slim paperback
3040 pages
A guide for African American Travelers
Pacifically for the lucky
The rare few who owned the car back then
In there they are on the cover
This handsome couple
Drawing in black and white
Walking off from their Suburban home to look for America
Comforted by that guy book
Published each year since 1936 by the victory green company of Harlem
In order to give it says the Negro Travelers
Information that will keep him from running into difficulties
Embarrassment
And other understatement
The couple will use it to navigate the post-war pre Highway United States
To keep himself safe and alive
In their own car
Free from the cruelties of segregated public transportation
Of colored only waiting rooms
The backs of buses
You'll be in the front seat of Their Own
Turn on gas pedal
Their own steering wheel
On the open road
The radio on
Searching for their song
Their music
Can you open air
You might catch a voice
Configure static
The Rhythm
Carried on invisible waves from some rooftop transmitter into
Decatur from Memphis
Falling away some Skyline
Disappears in the rearview
And then coming in clear and strong now
Is it come out of the trees
Is the road Rises through the alleghenies are around the bend in the air is warm Through the Windows
Warm under arms
In the light is warm
In Tangerine
Flashing on the surface of the Snake River
Definition of botanist
The Loxahatchee
Driving off
Nose
Grand Tetons
Liberty Hall
The Finger Lakes
Beale Street
Painted Desert
In their own car
Somewhere right there
Sal paradise and Dean Moriarty we're on the road
Somewhere right then
An ad man was showing an executive a pitch that would put a car in every garage
Some Auto Company lobbyist was showing some Senator just for the freeways would run one day
Through which unwanted neighborhoods
Telling him how those freeways would free us all
How weed road trip
See the USA in your Chevrolet
Look for adventure and whatever comes our way
Milwaukee to Minneapolis in 4 and 1/2 hours
Coast to coast in four and a half days
A nation transformed
People on the move
It's great cities
Natural wonders it's Amber Waves
Purple Majesty
All within reach
Unlimited possibilities be open road
Where the couple on the cover drove right then
Is the song hang low
Has their station started to fuss at the edges
The book said they could go to Oakland
Stay at the Warren hotel on 6th
Eat at the Crescent in Frederick Maryland
See the Grand Canyon
Get a drink Gill's Grill in Elizabethtown
But they shouldn't stop in Shelby Montana
There were no Negroes there
They should probably say they're delivering the car to its white owners if they get pulled over outside Lafayette
Should steer clear of whole cities all together
The Sundown town
They're all white
By Nightfall
There will be a day the Negro motorist green book says
In the near future
When it won't have to be published
But until that time
There was a bug
And a couple errands
As the sun goes down
In the road stretches out
In summer bugs flash white in the Headlights
In the signal fades
Probably out for good this
Need help with gas holdouts
Topeka
There's a place called powers
The green book says
Then get service there
And then I should be able to make it to Wichita
The Pact in a food they wouldn't have to risk
Stopping to eat
Might be better just
6th and Topeka
By the time you get there
Book says there's a hotel there were there should be okay
It might just be better
Who played Steve
Nikki Giovanni
In the moon Rose over an open fire
Another take on the green book
From The Memory Palace
Did you somehow neglected subscribing to the Memory Palace heretofore
I actually kind of into you
Because you have 134 episodes of short
Beautiful arresting history stories waiting for you
Take life changing child
This should be your Thanksgiving holiday entertainment
Shotgunning The Memory Palace episodes
A tomato has been making the Memory Palace
10 years and it represents the best of the medium so
Subscribe download all the episodes tell your friends
I love to see it reach
10 times as many people it deserves it
Badaling
In the show notes
99percentinvisible would produce this week by Delaney Hall
Recipe Ms senior producer Katie Mingle
Digital director Kurt Kolstad
Avery Chapman
Sharif Youssef
Emmett Fitzgerald Sean real Vivian Lee Joe Rosenberg Taryn Mazza and me Roman Mars
We are brother to 91.7 kalw in San Francisco who produced
On radio row
And beautiful
Downtown
Oakland California
99percentinvisible is a founding member of radiotopia from PRX a fiercely independent Collective of the most in a
Shows in all of podcasting
Aeon Mall
And radiotopia
Don FM
You can find the show and go instructions about the show on Facebook you can't we meet at Roman Mars in the show at 99p high orac run Instagram
Tumblr and Reddit to
But if you want over 300 other episodes of 99% invisible plus links and pictures of the green book
Look no further than our beautiful beautiful website it's a 99 pi
. org
Radio timoun
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
A five-part series from Bello radiotopia show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden to play like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest
I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes to find them
The final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com