99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progresso
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest professional network
LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers where they're engaging everyday when they're ready
Need to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads
Website traffic and higher brand awareness
And Linkedin have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Linkedin.com invisible
A free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions
Apply
We get support from UC Davis
Globally ranked universities
Working to solve the world's most pressing problems and food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe define transformational solution
No quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. UC Davis
. EDU
Mrs 99percentinvisible
I'm Roman Mars
And this is
Is Jeff Manor
My name is Jeff Maino architecture writer and blogger based in Los Angeles
For seven years he has written a website called building block
Which is about architectural conjecture
Urban speculation
And Landscape
I've always liked the sound of things
And the acoustic nature walking to the city or even just the sense that
When you're walking down the hall that has really rich
Lush
Wall coverings
The right side and sound totally different from the left side
I've just always been interested in those sorts of acoustic
Aspects of architectural space
Most Architects if a design for sound but they're actually designing to do is design for silence
Designing to keep sound out of the environments
They're designing to make sure that you don't hear the street sounds that are happening outside
Or that you're insulated from cars driving by or from the gravel plants up the road
So it's really an architecture silence that that people tend to be designing for but you know having said that there was an interesting project
A couple years ago by an architect named Joel Sanders
Mexican architectural design instead of standard glass windows that would use things like parabolic microphones
Kind of like those things that you see people holding on the sides of the football field during NFL games
These parabolic microphones would be pointed at the sky or they be pointed out into the woods nearby or you know they would capture the sounds
Airplanes flying overhead
Or birds in that in the forest or flat metal kids down the road it's very consciously and clearly brings a couch
Sticks into the architectural
Equation
There's an article in a British magazine called The Wire it was an article about
Generative sound so to speak it referred to it this idea of a quote-unquote Soundgarden
Rather than being the 1990s grunge band they were talking actually about the idea that you would deliberately plants
A certain species of flowering trees in the car thing in your back Garden so that you can sort of time in acoustic
Event over the course of the year
There certain species that when they
Bloom the seed pod opens up with an audible pop
It's going to be acoustic equivalent of the daisies coming up to the ground of the Tulips blooming
There's all kinds of other species that have particularly kind of silky leaves that
Brass against each other in the breeze so you can fall asleep at night too
The sound of this kind of
Really silken
Silvery
Serta tree brushing sound
That's one thing I think is really quite interesting that you can actually deliberately sort of build an acoustic ecosystem
You know you can easily imagine that sort of thing being added onto a kind of Botanic Garden
Said that you need to pay money to go literally listen to plant life
Desmond was also interested in
RKO
Good question
It's basically concerned with what two things not only how would a building have sounded or what would have been the acoustic
Effect of a certain building
When that building was standing
But then also what was the sort of sound culture of a given
Civilization or Village
Old Mayan temples were built
It's not just
Spaz spectacular mountain bike
Constructions
But specifically is a acoustic devices that would amplify
Not only the voice of the priest
But also the sounds of things like The Conch Shell that would be played to do ritualistic
Music internet service time
They building was actually physically designed to be as accurate as possible
The buildings themselves were like acoustic resonators or subwoofer so to speak
That were deliberately made to help induce a kind of almost like a psychedelic state in people
That's archaeoacoustics
Indiana Jones meets John Cage
I think Architects are too willing to sort of
Acoustics and sounds be taken care of by sound designers are taken up by other people
And I think it really would be interesting to see them think more in terms of
How to integrate their building into the soundscape of a city
There's a lot of talk with an architecture of how to build something that's contextually specific
And early response to its site
But the sight quote is almost always literally a question of sight it's an obstacle relationship the city
It would really be answering I should think about
Architects going out to sort of acoustically map
The city block where they're building is going to be in in figuring out a nice way to
Intervene in it and maybe reflect the sound back at the neighborhood
Too much silence is no more interesting than too much noise
99% invisible with produce this week by Nick Van der kolk
I'm your host Roman Mars
The program is made possible with support from lunar
Making a difference
The creativity
It's a project
The kalw the American Institute of Art
San Francisco
And the center for architecture and Design
Define Amor including links to Jeff menos building block which is
Essential readings
We go there
And nick vanderkolk love and radio which is
I program he does for both loe.org and it's
Stunning and Brilliant and Darkly fascinating and Nick is one of the
Sonic innovators in the field
Absolutely the best
I was going to clean that
At the end of this program but
Man that program
What is for adults
And I got I have 8th grade
Kids listening to
I can do
Anyway
You should absolutely check it out
If you're an adult
Do you love it
Set alarm radio. Org
And you finally do that
99 percent invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body Genie
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery
That whines through a
Treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath
Or put on 50lb all of a sudden to play like
A dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guy to know how to do that kind
I think
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now
I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast
Dot-com