99percentinvisible is brought to you by Progressive
One of the country's leading providers of auto insurance
With progressives Name Your Price tool
You can say what kind of coverage were looking for and how much you want to pay and Progressive will show you options that fit within your budget
Use the Name Your Price tool and start an online quote today
Progressive.com
Price in coverage match limited by state law
When it comes to marketing your business
It's all about reaching the Right audience at the right time
Connecting with that audience when your message will resonate the most
LinkedIn can help
LinkedIn is the world's largest Professional Network in LinkedIn marketing Solutions allow you to Target your customers were there
Engaging every day when they're ready to make a decision
When you advertise on LinkedIn you have the opportunity to build long-term relationships with their customers
Those relationships often turn into high-quality leads website traffic and higher brand awareness and Linkedin
Didn't have the marketing tools to help you target your customers with precision
Down to the job title company name and Industry
Because we can Target exactly who you want to reach
You can make sure your customers are getting a message that they care about
Which in turn builds Trust
To redeem a free $100 LinkedIn at credit and launch your first campaign go to linkedin.com
Isabel linkedin.com invisible Pier free $100 at credit
Terms and conditions apply
We get support from UC Davis globally ranked University working to solve the world's most pressing problems
Food energy health education and the environment
UC Davis researchers collaborate and innovate in California and around the globe Define transformational Solutions
Quality of life
For all living things
Find out more at 21st century. Ucdavis.edu
This is 99% invisible
I'm Roman Mars
In the middle of Sproul Plaza on the campus of UC Berkeley is this
Sculpture
Tall
But don't feel bad if you
You've never noticed
That I've had people you know, and look for it
I specifically and not find it
That makes me think well maybe I should have made it a little bigger or maybe that's just
The cost of making in the visit
Sculpture
PetSmart bressman Kemp
Is invisible sculpture is known to most
Free Speech Manya
It's actually it's called column A
Earth and Air
It's a 6 inch circle of
Soil in the column of air above it
Extending all the way to the limit of US controlled airspace
The column is marked by a 6
Black granite ring
Embedded flush
Into the concrete of the Plaza
Description of the outer edge read
This soil
And the airspace
Extending above it
Shall not be part of Any Nation
And shall not be subject
To any end
Jurisdiction
Use the traditional materials of wood clay or metal and instead
Uses jurisdiction laws in politics
It's kind of material to work with
The Free Speech Monument has both subtlety and Granger
And it's also
Bond and thought-provoking
A new way to consider jurisdictional space usually spaces of jurisdiction you enter into
You cross into a country you cross into
Estate you move into
Somebody private property and I thought it would be interesting to kind of inferred that and have a space that sort of move through your body
And when you stand next to it today
20 years after it was installed
You never see
Spect
The drama
That went on
To get this Granite Circle placed in the ground on University
The property I was kind of thrown into a little bit of a hornet's nest that I wasn't
Prepared for it all
Here's what happened
Free Speech Monument was born out of an open design competition
Memory at the 25th anniversary of
The start of the
Free Speech movement a bunch of professors ask professors they called themselves the Berkeley art from
Put this competition together separate from the University they did it as an autonomous group
Because they knew if they tried to go through the university to commemorate the
Which movement it would go nowhere
Because of the time
The university did not want to
Commemorate the free speech
Movement in any way shape
The Free Speech movement started in the fall of 1960
Before when students set up a
The table in Sproul Plaza to recruit for an off-campus Civil Rights group
This was against
School policy at the
And everything escalated from there
The following months
Wehrmacht by sit-ins
Strikes in a row
It was a pivotal moment
That defined
What we think of as the 6th
Monument seems appropriate
So anyway it's 1989
Calling out hundreds
Designs for consider
The 300
From all over the
They tweeted that down.
Define open.
Public discussion and voting that included
Publican
Art critics
All kinds of people outside of the Berkeley art project
That eventually selected Mark Pressman campins column of Earth and air as the Free Speech Monument
The Democracy doesn't always work with art thou
So I'm glad that it were
Work out this time
The people who would put the project together
Wanted to give the winning entry to the university as a gift
And then of course university did not want to accept it as a gift
And did everything that they could not do in the reason for the reluctance is that a lot of the Berkeley art project group
The once commissioned the monument
And the higher-ups at the University
We're the same people who are in the fight 25 years before and they were still very upset about it they still had
Very hurt feelings
So UC Berkeley did not want to memorialize the priest
Each movement in general and they hated this piece in particular
Yeah so
They did everything in their power
To not accepted
Which is kind of hard to do when still seem like a good guy
And after this big
Public selection process
They didn't have
Too much of a choice
So University decided to
SEPTA stop
Under one condition
They said okay will accept this commemoration to free speech as long as the press release that goes out
Does not contain
Any reference
To the Free Speech movement
That's right
Free Speech Monument
What sensor
And the unintended side of a
Is that it made
A piece of conceptual art
Conceptually better
Ironically it wasn't just the University Administration
Batman had a problem with
Column of Earth and Air
Probably early Free Speech movement leaders
Express their misgivings about the monument as well
I remember having a conversation with Mario Savio
He didn't like the peace at all
And not put words in his mouth but I did kind of get the impression that he wanted something that was a little bit more specific
Do the free speech
Movement
In the sixties
And I
Specifically didn't want to do that it seemed more relevant to me to use a
Real person
Speaking freely about something that they
Felt strongly about at that moment as a monument
Capri speech rather than a statue or something like that
The piece itself remains unfinished
The goal is to completely liberate this
Circle of soil
From any jurisdiction
And to do that it would have to go through all the jurisdictions you know the private property owners to the Board of Regents
The city of Berkeley County of Alameda the state there have to be an act of Congress
You also have to get International treaties because you don't want France coming in and taking that little piece of land so
You know it'll probably never be completely finished
After several attempts he made it only to the city jurisdiction level before getting bored
And now twenty years after it was installed
I'm standing in a noisy Sproul Plaza
If my breasts been camping
We run our hands
Through the column
Labare
And even though the Jurassic
Freezone westnet
Formula
I asked him if he
I feel something
Screw into
Baidu
I feel like I can feel the space
I grew up in Utah
And I
Would go to Southern Utah Lot in the four corners area that's the only place the United States where 4 States come together at
At one point
I remember very specifically
Jumping from state-to-state from Arizona to Colorado to Utah to New Mexico
It's also fun to lie down spread eagle in all four states at once
And really having a visceral feeling about that invisible line
Obviously
Psychological
But those spaces are very real I mean you commit
Certain acts in one space and you
You can do it you can make certain act in another space
And you might be killed so even though they're imaginary to certain extent they're very real
99percentinvisible was produced by me Roman Mars with support from lunar making a
The creative
The project
Kalw 91.7 in
San Francisco
American Institute of Architects
And the center for architecture and
You can find the show and like the show
On Facebook
I tweet
@roman Mars
What's my name
I just find the Show online
At 99% invisible
. org
Before we go I want to tell you about the body genius
Series from Bellow radio TV show the truth
The body genius is a Dark comic mystery that whines through a treacherous fictionalized Hollywood
We're looking the part
Might cost you your life
You know how sometimes a famous actor has to get really jacked play superhero in a movie
What is a ton of weight to play a prisoner or a psychopath or put on 50 pounds all of a sudden 2 playlist
Like a dad
I'm a Hollywood trainer and I specialize in that stuff
Actually if I'm being honest I'm one of the main guys who knows how to do that kind of
A few days ago Wesley Stern and actor that I was helping to get huge for an action movie called Immortal cop
Was found dead in my private gym
Crushed inside a high-tech weight machine
Even worse the cops think that I had something to do with it
Now I need to clear my name
Somebody out there killed Wesley and I'm going to do whatever it takes
To find them
Final episode of the body genius drops on May 30th Bend all 5 Parts on the truth podcast. Com